<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>“More moderate” developments do not prevent “optimistic” economic prospects</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/evolucao-mais-moderada-nao-impede-perspectivas-economicas-optimistas/</link><description>The Macau Monetary Authority maintains “broadly optimistic” perspectives regarding Macau’s economic growth this year. Despite anticipating a “more moderate” evolution, particularly due to “external headwinds”, the AMCM predicts “globally positive” growth for the Macao SAR, in accordance with the “Monetary and Financial Stability Review” of 2026
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
Macau's growth prospects for 2026 remain “broadly optimistic, driven by the stabilization of tourist demand and growing non-gaming investment”, according to the Macau Monetary Authority (AMCM). Despite the existence of “external headwinds”, AMCM expects Macau to maintain “globally positive” growth this year, albeit at a “more moderate” rate, resulting from the “normalization of base effects”.
In the first “Monetary and Financial Stability Review” report of 2026, analyzed by the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper, the organization points to the “continuous implementation of proactive fiscal measures and moderately accommodative monetary policies”, which have favored “a robust growing trajectory” of Mainland China, as the main causes of the improvement in consumer sentiment among Macau tourists.
At the same time, the synergy between “favorable travel policies, an enriched tourism infrastructure and the Government's continuous efforts in urban revitalization” reinforces the Macao SAR's growth momentum.
The AMCM Department of Studies and Statistics believes that, this year, inflationary pressures will remain “moderate” and projects a slight increase in the general average consumer price index, at the same time that labor market conditions “will remain stable”. The organization considers that the import of labor, intended to supplement the supply of local workers, will provide “sufficient slack for policy adjustments”.
AMCM argues that the modernization of financial services and regional integration can play “an increasingly vital role in advancing Macau’s adequate economic diversification agenda”. The authorities highlight the establishment of a Government industrial fund and a guiding fund, within the scope of channeling public and private resources for strategic projects related to the long-term development of the Macao SAR.
It is worth remembering that, on the 1st of this month, the new Investment Funds Law came into force, aimed at optimizing the business environment for the fund management sector and reinforcing the movement of capital in the financial sector.
Furthermore, “the improvement of institutions and infrastructure connecting Macau and the Deep Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin is expected to generate synergistic benefits, reinforcing growth momentum and fostering long-term prosperity for both regions”, the report reads.
 
Tourists and exports “charge” the economy
According to the AMCM, Macau's Gross Domestic Product (GDP) grew 5.5% in the second quarter of 2025, in annual terms, and accelerated to 8% growth in the third quarter, driven by “a strong impetus in the entry of tourists” and a “robust” increase in services exports. Overall in the first nine months of last year, supported by progress in the tourism sector and consumption, the economy grew 4.2%, compared to the same period in 2024, to 88.4% of the levels of the first three quarters of 2019.
It is worth remembering that, according to data published by the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Department, gross revenues from the gaming sector, in 2025, grew 9.09%, compared to the previous year, to 247.4 billion patacas. In the same period of time, VIP gaming revenues grew 24.14%, reaching 67.99 billion patacas, while gross revenues from the mass market, including tables and slots, rose 4.30%, reaching 179.42 billion.
The export of goods was the second largest contributing factor to Macau's GDP growth. In the first half of 2025, exports and imports of goods recorded annual drops of 6.7% and 6.1%, respectively. Between July and September, product exports recovered by 4.5%, while imports fell by 6.5%, resulting in a year-on-year contraction of 10% in the Macao SAR's trade deficit, to 23.6 billion patacas.
Although there was a more modest increase, consumption in the territory also grew, in annual terms, between January and September. According to AMCM, in the second quarter of 2025, private and public consumption increased by 1.7% and 0.9%, respectively, compared to the same period in 2024. In the following quarter, private consumption grew by 0.8%, while public consumption rose by 2.7%.
According to AMCM, moderate inflation in the consumer price index was due to “lower prices in transport and communications”. As this newspaper reported yesterday, with regard to transport, the price index fell by 1.15%, while in information and communication this indicator decreased by 2.82%, in 2025, compared to the previous year. Last year, Macau recorded an annual inflation rate of 0.33%, marking the third consecutive year of deceleration, according to data from the Statistics and Census Bureau.
Sales in the retail sector contracted by 5.4%, between January and September 2025, compared to the same period in 2024. In terms of product and goods categories, sales of household appliances fell by 16.1% and fuel sales by 11.6%, while pharmacies recorded growth of 7.9%.
Even so, “local business sentiment has shown improvements”, argues AMCM, taking into account the number of new companies incorporated. In year-on-year terms, and subtracting dissolved companies, the number of new businesses grew 1.2% to 824, in the second quarter of 2025, and 12.6% to 1,013, in the third quarter.
In the real estate sector, the number of residential units transacted rose 0.6%, to 2,510, in the first nine months of 2025. However, the average price per square meter fell 14.3% to 74,190 patacas in the third quarter of 2025, compared to the same period in 2024.
Between January and September 2025, the number of units purchased by non-residents increased by 59.4%, to a total of 247 units and with a combined value corresponding to 1.2 billion patacas. The proportion of non-resident owners rose from 6.6% to 9.7%, between the end of September 2024 and the same period in 2025.
Unemployment and underemployment rates stood at 1.7% and 1.5%, respectively, between the months of September and November. In fact, the unemployment rate was 0.6 percentage points below the 10-year average. At the end of November, 6,700 residents were without a job, while the number of people employed was 378,900 individuals, 0.1% below the value recorded in the same month of 2024.
However, salaries decreased, considering that the median monthly income amounted to 17 thousand patacas in the third quarter of last year, corresponding to an annual drop of 5.6%. In the particular case of residents, this decrease was milder, at 2.4%, setting the median income at 20 thousand patacas. In financial activities, the median income fell 9.1% to 20 thousand patacas, while in the gaming sector it remained at 20.5 thousand.
 
More savings and less investment
The Macao SAR's savings rate also registered an annual increase, of 4.6 percentage points, worth 59.5% of GDP in the first three quarters of 2025. Furthermore, this indicator remains substantially above the world average, of 26.2% in 2024, highlights the document.
Conversely, investment decreased in the territory, having been “the biggest brake on Macau's economic growth”. “Firstly, driven by a decrease in private and public construction projects, global investment expenditure, that is, the sum of gross fixed capital formation and changes in inventories, fell by 4.6% in the second quarter and 25.6% in the third quarter of 2025”, on a comparative basis with the same intervals in 2024.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Poor condition of statues in the Ruins requires “deep investigation”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mau-estado-das-estatuas-das-ruinas-requer-investigacao-profunda/</link><description>A specialist who is participating in the restoration of the facade of the Ruins of São Paulo and its bronze statues considers that the rehabilitation is “relatively complex”. Kin Hong Ip, a research assistant at the University of Macau, points out that the condition of the bronze dove is worse than that of the other sculptures. Therefore, he states that the restoration work “requires in-depth investigation carried out by experts in metallic materials”. The work should be completed by mid-February

VÍTOR REBELO
 
The restoration work on the façade of the Ruins of São Paulo and its bronze statues is facing difficulties, so the restoration is “complex”, according to the opinion of one of the experts involved in the rehabilitation of part of the monument, Macau’s ex-libris.
King Hong Ip, research professor at the University of Macau, said that the second phase of the recovery work is being finalized, which is proving to be “complex”, since the condition of the bronze dove, which symbolizes the Holy Spirit, surmounted by the cross, is worse than the other structures.
The expert, who was speaking on the sidelines of a symposium organized by the Center for Preservation and Transmission of Cultural Heritage of the Macau Palace Museum, highlighted that the dove is located in a high place and its condition is “relatively bad”. Therefore, he emphasizes that the restoration work not only requires the participation of specialists in cultural heritage, but also requires an assessment of public safety carried out by structural engineers.
Furthermore, he highlighted, “it requires an in-depth investigation by experts in metallic materials into the compatibility between the original materials and the restoration materials, in order to avoid secondary damage”.
As he explained, this restoration project involves collaboration between experts from different countries and different areas. Therefore, he states, “the team needs to deeply study the nature of the metal in this statue to define the restoration materials and how to avoid the impact on the viewing experience”.
Forecasts suggest that the work will be completed by mid-February.
On the other hand, the teacher considered that some mural paintings inside the chapel of Nossa Senhora das Neves are in a state of erosion, so those responsible will discuss with technicians from abroad to find plans, with the aim of “reducing the impact on the environment”.
The colloquium, held in the Art Museum Auditorium, brought together heritage conservation experts, who shared cutting-edge concepts, technologies and practical case studies from Mainland China and the international community.
The event facilitated the exchange of knowledge, taking as its starting point the revitalization of the Ruins of São Paulo. “The objective is to broaden the public's understanding of heritage restoration, strengthen exchange, collaboration and mutual learning on the topic, and inject vitality and new perspectives into the preservation of Macau's cultural heritage”, says a statement from the Cultural Institute (IC).
“By safeguarding this emblematic heritage, a centuries-old witness to the dialogue between East and West, the Center intends to promote the sharing of restoration techniques between tradition and modernity, giving a new contemporary meaning to the transmission of civilizations”, highlights the president of the IC, Leong Wai Man.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Xia Baolong demands joint defense of the predominance of executive power</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/xia-baolong-exige-defesa-conjunta-da-predominancia-poder-executivo/</link><description>Xia Baolong urged the Chief Executives and SAR Governments to materialize the predominance of executive power in all aspects of governance. As he argued, the persistence and improvement of the predominance of the executive power requires the active support and collaboration of the legislative and judicial bodies
 
The implementation of the predominance of executive power appears as an “institutional guarantee for the comprehensive and precise pursuit of ‘One Country, Two Systems’” and a “necessary requirement” to “safeguard the constitutional order of the SARs”, “guarantee the principles of ‘Hong Kong governed by its people’, ‘Macau governed by its people’ and a high degree of autonomy” and “realize efficient governance in the SARs, based on the reality of Hong Kong and Macau”, highlighted yesterday the director of the Hong Kong and Macau Affairs Office at the State Council. At this point, he praised the “successful practice” of the predominance of executive power in the SARs, saying that it demonstrates the “great vitality” and advantage of this principle.
The speech was given at a seminar on the “persistence and improvement of the predominance of executive power, and the promotion of good governance in the SARs”, held in Beijing by the Chinese Association of Hong Kong and Macau Studies. On the occasion, Xia Baolong also argued that the implementation of the predominance of executive power and the full use of the leadership role of the Chief Executives and Governments of the SARs contribute to improving the functions and efficiency of government bodies, joining forces from all sectors, responding flexibly to various risks and challenges and safeguarding the prosperity and stability of the SARs.
“Following the correct guidance of ‘One Country, Two Systems’, we must persist and improve the predominance of the executive branch and continuously improve the effectiveness of the governance of the SARs,” said Xia. In this regard, he demanded that the two regions “remain highly vigilant” regarding the ever-changing methods of “external forces” to oppose, destroy and disrupt the predominance of executive power, as well as clarify and correct “some ambiguous or even erroneous understandings”.
Specifically, the Chinese leader stressed that, in order to persist and improve the predominance of executive power, it is essential for Chiefs and Governments to reinforce the “sense of being the owner of the family” over Hong Kong and Macau and effectively assume the main responsibility for the governance of the SARs.
In this regard, Xia urged them to materialize the predominance of executive power in all aspects of governance and to strive to build an efficient and effective government. “All government services, under the leadership of the Chief Executives, should proactively reinforce high-level design and strategic planning for the development of the SARs, align with the 15th National Five-Year Plan and strengthen the forward-looking vision and initiative for the future development of Hong Kong and Macau”, stressed the Chinese leader.
Furthermore, he argued that SAR leaders and Executives must recognize, adapt and proactively seek change, innovate governance philosophy, improve governance methods and make good use of the powers granted by the Basic Law to promote reforms, break down the barriers of entrenched interests and resolve contradictions and deeply rooted problems in the development of SARs.
On the other hand, he emphasized that the persistence and improvement of the predominance of the executive power requires the active support and collaboration of the legislative and judicial bodies, to “form a powerful synergy in governance”, and the Legislative Assemblies (AL) and the courts “must defend the predominance of the executive power and respect this principle”. Furthermore, he highlighted that the support and participation of all sectors of society are also essential.
 
RAE AL urged to present “more constructive suggestions”
Regarding the AL, Xia Baolong demanded that they fulfill their duties and responsibilities, demonstrate a new image and fully support and collaborate with the governance in accordance with the law by the Chief Executives and Governments of the SARs, building “a good home” for Hong Kong and Macau.
Xia hopes that the LA will “consciously support the predominance of executive power.” Furthermore, he stressed that legislative bodies must “present more constructive suggestions to promote more scientific, fluidly executed and efficient government actions” and “not only express support verbally with regard to major political decisions and measures, but also take concrete actions”. This is to “strengthen research into policy implementation and provide more ideas, solutions and countermeasures, so as to make government policies and measures more operational and easier to implement effectively”.
They must also support Governments so that they do not neglect their responsibilities and monitor them so that they do not exceed limits, fostering a new atmosphere of responsibility, efficiency and pragmatism, and working with Governments to “explore a path of positive interaction between the executive and legislative powers under the capitalist system”.
To the deputies, Xia left five demands: cultivate a deep sense of patriotism, be courageous in assuming responsibilities, be enthusiastic in serving citizens, diligently participate and discuss political matters, and create a good image.
They were also urged to visit community neighborhoods more frequently and to listen to citizens and sectors, in order to try, as much as possible, to help resolve urgent problems and concerns.
Furthermore, he urged deputies to play an important role in the reform and development of the SARs. And in terms of fundamental principles, he highlighted that deputies must maintain a firm stance, be bold and resolutely combat external forces.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief granted license to Air Macau until 2046</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-concedeu-licenca-a-air-macau-ate-2046/</link><description>Air Macau will be able to carry out commercial air transport of passengers until 2046, in accordance with the license granted to the airline by the Chief Executive. Remember that the company now has to pay a deposit of 15 million patacas. The license takes effect from next Sunday, February 1st, in line with the entry into force of the new Civil Aviation Activity Law
 
CATARINA PEREIRA
 
The Chief Executive granted Companhia de Transportes Aéreos Air Macau, S.A. a license that gives it the right to carry out commercial air transport of passengers. Air Macau must begin licensed activity on February 1st, in line with the entry into force of the new Law on civil aviation activity, according to the order signed by Sam Hou Fai and published yesterday in the Official Bulletin.
The license granted to the Macao SAR flag company is valid “until January 31, 2046”, states the attached document, and can be renewed upon request to the Chief Executive up to two years before the expiration date. The renewal may, however, be refused, “taking into account the market development situation”, in which case “no compensation” is owed to the airline.
Air Macau must provide a deposit to the Civil Aviation Authority, which was also set by order of the Chief Executive at 15 million patacas. The deposit, according to article 44 of the law, serves to “guarantee compliance with the obligations assumed and the fines that may be due under the license”.
You also have to pay one million patacas for the granting of the license and an annual activity fee, which corresponds to 2% of the net profits recorded in the previous year.
Recorde-se que, no primeiro semestre de 2025, a Air Macau encerrou o exercício financeiro com prejuízos líquidos de 433,6 milhões de patacas, correspondendo a cerca de 67% do total das perdas verificadas ao longo de 2024, segundo a Air China, sua accionista maioritária. During this period, the Macao SAR flag carrier transported 43% of passengers who used Macau Airport.
With the license granted, Air Macau is obliged to comply with its five-year business plan accepted by the Chief Executive and to present, up to nine months before the beginning of the respective period, the business plan for the following five years.
Next Sunday, the new civil aviation law will come into force, which calls for the end of Air Macau's exclusive concession and introduces a licensing system, with the aim of gradually opening up the territory's civil aviation market.
In August last year, the Civil Aviation Authority told TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper that, at the time, it had not yet received “any formal license requests from new investors”. Yesterday, this newspaper asked the organization again about whether it had received requests and from which companies, however, until the close of this edition it was not possible to obtain a response.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Illegal work is more common in wholesale and retail trade</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/trabalho-ilegal-e-mais-frequente-comercio-por-grosso-retalho/</link><description>Chan Chon U, deputy director of Labor Affairs Services, said yesterday that most cases of illegal work occur in the wholesale and retail trade sector. As revealed, in the overall year 2025, 668 people were sanctioned for “illegal work”, an increase of 8.4% in annual terms. The total fines exceeded six million patacas
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
Most illegal labor cases are related to the wholesale and retail trade sector, said Chan Chon U, deputy director of the Labor Affairs Bureau (DSAL), yesterday. During a press conference, the official explained that cases of illegal work often boil down to “a lack of knowledge of the legislation”. Promising more interdepartmental collaboration and law enforcement efforts, Chan also called on citizens to report suspicious cases, assuring that DSAL will take reports “very seriously”.
Regarding complaints from citizens, the deputy director asked them to provide “the place, the time”. “In past cases, we had some difficulty, there was a lack of location data or even photographs”, he explained. "Citizens can provide more information. They can help a lot with this additional information", he asserted.
Yesterday, DSAL carried out an inspection, in which it identified 122 drivers. The authorities found two drivers suspected of carrying out activities other than those authorized, said Chan Chon U, adding that “DSAL will initiate the respective proceedings for illegal work, following current regulations”.
In 2025 overall, DSAL carried out 683 inspections, including 491 independent and 192 in cooperation with other entities. Of this universe, 62 inspections targeted drivers.
Overall, 668 people were sanctioned for “illegal work”, “other than the authorized”, “in a location” or “for an employer other than the authorized” or “self-employed by non-residents”, with a combined amount of fines exceeding six million patacas. Of the drivers inspected, 157 were sanctioned for “illegally exercising driver duties”, with a total fine of 982,500 patacas, according to Chan Chon U.
In 2024, of the 576 inspections carried out by DSAL, 65 involved drivers, with administrative sanctions being applied to 616 people for illegal work, which means that there was an increase of 8.4% in the last year. The total amount of fines was just over six million patacas, in 2024, similar to last year.
On the other hand, there were two fewer drivers sanctioned in 2025, compared to the 159 registered in the previous year. In 2024, the total value of fines imposed on these illegal drivers was more than 1.1 million patacas.
 
More publicity actions
Asked about job advertisements for fraudulent tour guides, Chan replied that DSAL has already “verified these cases on the platforms” and that “some preventive actions have been taken, for example, some legislative clarification sessions”. “We also issue reports and activities with more detailed information that will be continuously disseminated”, he promised.
The deputy director of DSAL urged “all sectors to act in strict accordance with the legislation, refraining from any expectation of impunity”. He also stated that “DSAL will continue to collaborate with the Public Security Police Corps to reinforce law enforcement, monitoring and combating all forms of illegal work”.
“If any illegal act is detected, the foreseen sanctions will be strictly applied, without any tolerance”, warned the person in charge.
Regarding public awareness and publicity activities, Chan Chon U stated that “53 information sessions have already been carried out on the illegal work of non-residents”. “We have been promoting some games with prizes on WeChat”, he said, adding that more activities related to legislation will be developed for the public to know.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Adjusted values ​​for outdoor venues</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ajustados-valores-local-de-espectaculos-ao-ar-livre/</link><description>Although the values ​​for each day of performance and rehearsals or assembly remain the same at the outdoor performance venue, at COTAI, interested parties can now request a refund of 25% of the fees paid. Furthermore, there are values ​​defined for entities that use the space for 30 consecutive days with at least two days of shows.
 
The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, has already defined the prices for using the outdoor performance venue, at COTAI, and, although the prices remain the same for use for just one day, there are now new prices for those who want to use that space for 30 consecutive days.
According to the order published yesterday in the Official Bulletin, and similar to what had been practiced, if the number of spectators per day for each show is equal to or greater than 30,000, the price for renting the space on the day of the show is 500,000 patacas, while on rehearsal or assembly days it is 250,000 patacas. If the number of spectators is less than 30,000 per day, space users will have to pay 350,000 patacas on the day of the show and 175,000 patacas on rehearsal or assembly days.
“After the actual performance of the show and the end of the period of use, a refund corresponding to 25% of the fees paid may be requested from the Cultural Institute”, it can be read.
On the other hand, until December 31st of this year, if the space is used for a period of 30 consecutive days and with a minimum of two days of shows, the usage fees are 3.6 million patacas, if the number of spectators is equal to or greater than 30,000, and 2.52 million patacas if less. If shows are held by the same entity for more than one day, “the fee corresponding to the largest capacity is charged”.
If the site is used for a period longer than 30 days, daily rates apply, adds Secretary O Lam.
It is recalled that the authorities announced that they will open a public tender for the management of the venue, with the tender process scheduled for the middle of this year.
The open-air entertainment area, which comes in line with the development strategy of adequate diversification of the “1+4” economy, aims to contribute to transforming Macau into a “City of Shows”.
It is located, temporarily, on State land with an area of ​​94 thousand square meters, with the project site facing North towards Rua de Ténis and Northeast towards Avenida do Aeroporto. The venue has the capacity to accommodate around 50 thousand spectators.
 
C.P.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Police will expand drone functions and update “Eyes in the Sky” system</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/policia-vai-expandir-funcoes-de-drones-actualizar-sistema-olhos-ceu/</link><description>The Office of the Secretary for Security revealed that the Police will expand the functions of drone equipment and applications in prevention, search and rescue patrols, in addition, it will begin updating the video surveillance application system of the “Eyes in the Sky” system. On the other hand, he said that the Police plans to introduce large AI models, intelligent analysis systems, AI assistance in handling complaints and intelligent answering service
 
Police authorities will optimize drone equipment and applications, expanding functions in prevention, search and rescue patrols, said the Office of the Secretary for Security, indicating that, simultaneously, work will begin on updating the “Eyes in the Sky” video surveillance application system.
In response to a written question from Wong Ka Lon, in which the nominated deputy called for improving the artificial intelligence (AI) crime response mechanism and strengthening police provision, Chan Tsz King's office also revealed that the Police plans to introduce large AI models, intelligent analysis systems, AI assistance in handling complaints, intelligent answering service, among others.
According to him, these systems will cover different scenarios, including combating money laundering, handling complaints, alerts, investigation and risk management.
Recalling that the Judiciary Police (PJ) has already introduced advanced level “Deepfake” detection instruments and electronic forensics instruments in advance, the response states that the PJ will continue to closely monitor the development of global AI security technologies, and promote the studies and work necessary for their implementation in a timely manner.
Regarding the training of qualified staff in the technological area, the office guaranteed that the various services in the security area actively promote continuous training.
 
Laws may “fail” to supervise Facebook and WeChat
On the other hand, the office noted that the PJ continuously monitors changes to legislative systems and regulatory situations regarding AI deep forgery and other forms of emerging crime around the world. Noting that, in Mainland China, current regulations focus on the supervision of service providers of deep synthesis and dissemination of information content on the network, the Security department admits that “local legislation may not be able to effectively supervise the companies in question”.
This is because, “according to local reality, whether it is deep synthesis service providers widely used by the public, such as OpenAI, Meta, Baidu or Tencent, or the main platforms for disseminating informative content on the network, such as Facebook, X (Twitter), WeChat or Xiaohongshu, none of these platforms has an operating entity established in Macau”.
Even so, the office assured that, given this reality, the PJ has already established expeditious communication mechanisms with those companies, allowing immediate notification and reporting of criminal situations related to them. Furthermore, he pointed out that, in terms of law enforcement, the PJ also actively acts through channels such as Interpol and judicial cooperation to investigate, collect evidence and combat these crimes.
In any case, he asserted that, although deep forgery through AI constitutes a new modus operandi, criminal acts such as fraud, insult and defamation, computer forgery and computer fraud, are already covered by the criminal legislation in force in Macau, namely in the Penal Code and the Law to combat computer crime.
“Therefore, nothing prevents the criminal responsibility of agents under current legislation”, highlighted the office, stating that the PJ will continue to closely monitor the evolution of this crime, improving law enforcement mechanisms. In this regard, he highlighted that, if the competent services develop legislative work related to AI, the PJ will proactively provide technical opinions in this area.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Recognized inclusion and creativity of Costa Nunes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/reconhecida-inclusao-criatividade-costa-nunes/</link><description>After a school evaluation process, in the academic years 2023/2024 and 2024/2025, carried out by DSEDJ, Jardim de Infância D. José da Costa Nunes saw recognition for its work within the scope of inclusive education and the development of creativity
 
The D. José da Costa Nunes Kindergarten, under the management of the Associação Promotora da Instrução dos Macaenses (APIM), participated in the global school assessment, carried out by the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ), “having been recognized for its work in the development of creativity and inclusive education”, according to a statement from the association. The process began with the school's self-evaluation in 2023/2024, followed, in 2024/2025, by the external evaluation carried out by a supervision team.
According to a press release, the team “gave a positive assessment to the Kindergarten’s educational orientation, recognizing in particular that its development planning is closely aligned with the educational mission”. “The commitment” to promoting the teaching of the Portuguese language “as a distinctive element”, in implementing the principles of inclusive education and in the application of information technologies to support teaching was also valued.
“The report also highlights that the priority areas defined (…) respond effectively to the learning needs of students and follow trends in educational development, with the broad recognition and support of those in charge of education”, adds APIM. DSEDJ also praised the organization of training activities in inclusive education, of a school nature, aimed at teaching staff.
In the planning of educational development, outlined by APIM, the Kindergarten “has been actively promoting innovation and quality of teaching”, and “attaches special importance” to stimulating the creative potential of students, “adopting playful activities as a basic learning method and seeking to develop children's artistic interest”.
“Looking to the future, APIM is attentive to the evolution of teaching and education perspectives in the Macao SAR and the D. José da Costa Nunes Kindergarten will actively respond to the improvement recommendations presented by DSEDJ, continually deepening the self-evaluation system based on the ‘planning – implementation – evaluation’ cycle, guided by data and evidence, in order to drive sustained progress”, he assures.
Furthermore, it guarantees that it will commit to strengthening the participation of teachers and guardians in planning school development, “together building a more prospective educational vision”.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Humanitarian mission goes to Mozambique to donate clothing and school supplies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/missao-humanitaria-vai-mocambique-doar-vestuario-material-escolar/</link><description>The Macau section of the international organization “Dress a Girl Around The World” will travel to Mozambique on a humanitarian mission, with the aim of donating clothes and school supplies to children in Maputo. Five resident women make up the delegation, which will remain in the Mozambican capital for around two weeks
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
A humanitarian mission will take children's clothing to Maputo, the capital of Mozambique, complemented by school and teaching materials, aiming to bring “some comfort and encouragement to children in vulnerable situations”, according to a statement from the promoters of the initiative. The trip is part of the “Dress a Girl Around The World” (DAGATW) project – Macau Section and will take place between the 7th and 21st of February.
To present the objectives and details of the charity action, DAGATW participated in a working meeting at the Consulate-General of Mozambique in Macau. At the meeting, the nature of the mission was explained, which has as its main objective the donation of clothes and school items, which should be delivered to the Central Hospital of Maputo, with a special focus on the Oncology and Pediatrics units, and to the IVERCA Association, an association of young students and tourism professionals that promotes cultural and environmental development in the country.
“In view of the recurring scourge of extreme weather events that affect Mozambique – such as severe droughts, floods and cyclones –, the initiative takes on an urgent character of concrete solidarity”, can be read in the note signed by the president of the Association of Friends of Mozambique (Macau), Ângelo Rafael.
The double institutional support that the mission has was also highlighted. In addition to the parent organization “Hope 4 Women International”, DAGATW has the institutional support of AAM and the President of the Regional Council of Asia and Oceania of the Council of Portuguese Communities, “strengthening its community framework and the region's commitment to cooperation actions with Mozambique”, highlights the document.
During the hearing, the collaboration of the Consulate General of Mozambique was formally requested to facilitate coordination with the competent authorities in Mozambican territory, “ensuring the success of the visit and the appropriate direction of donations”.
The delegation will be made up of five women, Isabel Marcelo, Fátima dos Remédios, Cristina Sá Carneiro, Madalena Cardoso and Ana Cristina Vilas.
“Dress a Girl Around The World” is a non-governmental organization founded in the USA in 2009, which works globally through volunteers to make and distribute free dresses and shorts to children in need, who live below the global poverty level, promoting their dignity, protection and hope. The organization, which relies on donations of materials, such as 100% cotton fabrics, threads, ribbons, elastics, provided by individuals, companies and other humanitarian groups, has already distributed around 600,000 pieces of women's clothing in 81 countries.
The Macao SAR section, created in 2017, has already made donations in places on the Asian continent such as Batangas, in the Philippines, and Chiang Mai, in Thailand.
As one of the group's members told the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, the project's collaborators “are volunteers, they produce and sell dolls, the proceeds of which are used to purchase clothing that is later delivered in this type of humanitarian missions”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Photographic competition focuses on the value of Portuguese-speaking customs</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/concurso-fotografico-foca-valor-dos-costumes-lusofonos/</link><description>The reality of Portuguese-speaking countries or regions will be the focus of the new photography competition promoted by Somos. “The Today of the Past” is the theme of the event, which aims to centralize “the ancient things that last in time”
 
“Somos! – Associação de Comunicação em Língua Portuguesa” (Somos – ACLP) launched the seventh edition of the “Somos Imagens da Lusofonia” Photography Competition, this year with the theme “O Hoje do Pastado”, running until February 28th. The objective, according to the promoter of the initiative, is for the competition to “focus on ancient things that last through time”, which still have a function and purpose in our societies and lives today, marking the cultural identity associated with a given geographic space.
“These days, with rapid socioeconomic and technological development, our focus tends to turn to what is more modern, evolved, to what is new”, emphasizes Somos in a statement, adding that “in a context of accelerated urban transformation, provinces, cities, and even towns and villages have undergone changes that lead them to lose some distinctive characteristics”.
However, he continues, “there are symbols, instruments, crafts, etc., that have defied time, new technologies and cultural homogenization”, some of which “may even be transversal to the Portuguese-speaking universe”.
In light of this theme, participants are invited to reflect on the realities of their countries/regions and to express, through photography, their point of view on the weight and value of ancient customs, practices and traditions in current societies in the Portuguese-speaking world.
“It will be a way of collectively rethinking the importance of the historical, artistic, ethnographic and intangible heritage of each geographic territory of Lusofonia, as well as the social value of culture and historical elements as vehicles of social connection, reinforcements of community identity and portals for evoking times past”, emphasizes the association.
The theme “The Today of the Past” will allow the presentation of works with artistic, historical and symbolic dimensions, which will serve as material testimonies of the interaction between the past and the present, highlighting that “the old may have a future”.
The competition, sponsored by the Cultural Development Fund, is aimed at all citizens of the countries and regions of Lusofonia or residents of the Macao SAR who have quality photographs, framed with the selected theme, taken in Angola, Brazil, Cape Verde, Guinea-Bissau, Equatorial Guinea, Macau, Mozambique, Portugal, São Tomé and Príncipe, Timor-Leste and Goa, Daman and Diu. The images submitted must be accompanied by a title and a brief descriptive caption to contextualize the reality represented.
The decision of the jury, composed of Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro (Macau), Lei Heong Ieong (Macau), Bruno Santos and Levi Bianco (Brazil), Luísa Nhantumbo (Mozambique) and César Mourão (Portugal), will be based on the criteria of creativity and originality, photographic composition, artistic quality, and relevance and quality in relation to the theme.
The three winning works will be awarded prizes worth 10,000, 7,000 and 5,000 patacas, and honorable mentions may also be awarded.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Entre Plástico” shows 19 works by local artists</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/entre-plastico-mostra-19-obras-de-artista-local/</link><description>Local artist Ng Sekha presents, from today, at Fundação Rui Cunha, until the 7th, a total of 19 works. The solo exhibition, entitled “Entre Plástico”, is curated by Guo Yun and academically supervised by Ung Vai Meng

























The solo art exhibition “Entre Plástico”, which will open today at Fundação Rui Cunha (FRC), at 6:30 pm, presents 19 works by Ng Sekha, a local painting, performance and installation artist. In recent years, Ng “has focused his work on the exploration of ‘plastic’ as a concept and as a material, reflecting this transversality in different artistic media and genres”, according to the note from the FRC, which co-organizes the exhibition with the Macau Youth Art Association and the Macau Fine Arts Artists Association.
There, the public will be able to enjoy almost two dozen works of oil and acrylic painting, sculpture and glass installation. The exhibition is curated by Guo Yun and academically supervised by Ung Vai Meng.
In “Entre Plástico”, the artist translates her previous performance works into easel painting, at the same time as she reintroduces plastic hemispheres into the pictorial field, as stated in the exhibition's preface. As an example, “transparent plastic is repeatedly inserted between painting, performance and installation”, and through its “semi-hidden, malleable and almost weightless materiality” it places “the body, the image and the act of seeing in a constant state of tension and instability”.
The idea can have multiple meanings, which Ng Sehka took advantage of in his creative process. “In the Western context, ‘plastic’ refers not only to the material itself, but also extends to plastic surgery, consumer culture and the social mechanisms through which the body is conceived, regulated and observed”, it can be read.
However, in the Chinese language “‘plastic’ means simultaneously molding, remodeling and regenerating, pointing to a state of incompleteness and continuous becoming”, highlights the note, and then adds: “It is within this semantic tension that Ng Sekha operates, transforming plastic into a method, and not into a singular medium – a method that mediates between perception and structure, and between individual experience and social mechanisms”.
With a degree in Fine Arts from the University of Massachusetts Dartmouth, in the USA, Ng Sekha is also a PhD student in Art History and Theory at the Faculty of Humanities and Arts of the Macau University of Science and Technology.
The works he has been producing include performance, installation and easel painting, focusing on the intersection between gender philosophy, identity and contemporary art. He has held solo and group exhibitions in Macau and abroad, namely at the Beijing Museum of Contemporary Art, the Shanghai Exhibition Center, Tank Shanghai, the Chengdu Biennale, the Guangzhou Art Museum, the Luohu Art Museum in Shenzhen, the Asia World-Expo in Hong Kong, the Gwangju International Biennial (South Korea), the Lisbon Biennale (Portugal), and other places.
The works will be on display until February 7th, with free entry.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CEM promotes ecology in school competition</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cem-promove-ecologia-em-concurso-escolar/</link><description>Seventeen secondary schools present two dozen ecological projects in an exhibition at the Macau Science Center until 31 January. The works were selected in the fourth edition of the “CEM Clean Energy City Competition”, which aims to awaken students' interest in clean energy and sustainability. The works can be visited at the Science Center from 10am to 6pm, “to learn more about the creative proposals for a more ecological Macau and vote for your favorite projects, with the opportunity to win an iPad or an Apple Watch”, according to a statement from the Macau Electricity Company. The 20 best works were chosen by a professional jury composed of representatives from the Science Center, Macau Science and Technology Promotion Association, Environmental Protection Services Department, Macau Association of Electrical Engineers, Macau Chinese Educators Association and CEM. The jury's assessment will represent 75% of the final score, the public vote 10% and the student vote 15%. The projects developed by students cover a wide spectrum, including smart playground areas, green campus, smart aviation system, smart building versus traditional building, wind and wave energy, low-carbon shared activity center, smart bus stations, integrated green hydrogen energy for smart cities, smart solar-powered waste container, smart photovoltaic system, among others.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>BRIEF</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2536/</link><description>Half-hour regime extended to five auto-silos
The self-silos in the Mong In, Mong Sin, Mong Tak Buildings and the car parks at the Mong-Ha Sports Center and the Traffic Affairs Services Directorate (DSAT) building will adopt the “half-hour billing” model. According to DSAT, from February 4th, parking rates in these parks will be three patacas, from 08:00 to 20:00 and 1.5 patacas, from 20:00 to 08:00, for light cars. For motorcycles and mopeds, daytime rates will be one pataca and 50 patacas during nighttime. The total number of parks with this charging system will thus increase to 32.
 
CC warns consumers against fraudulent tickets
The Consumer Council (CC) appealed to the population to prioritize purchasing tickets “through official channels” or “disclosed by the organizing entity”. The CC also emphasizes that “it is necessary to carefully check the sales platforms authorized by the organizing entity”, also warning of the risks of purchasing on “social networks or second-hand platforms”. When purchasing tickets from another region, consumers must pay attention to the withdrawal procedures, giving priority to electronic tickets and retaining proof of purchase. The organization also urged consumers to pay attention to change and refund policies.
 
Registration for ecological activities has opened
Registration for activities in the Ecological Zones is now open in February, organized by the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA). On the 7th and 28th of February, at 10am and again at 3pm, the “Open Day to the Public” activity will take place. The tour to the two Ecological Zones has a total of 50 places per session. At the same time, the workshop “Educational activity about Nature” will be held, aimed at children and parents. For each workshop session there are 12 places, with each pair of child and adult constituting a place. Until April, the monthly tour “Birdwatching in the wetlands” will also take place.
 
More than 5,300 in the public service access test
The written test for the integrated skills assessment competition referring to academic qualifications in complementary secondary education, essential for access to the public service, was attended by 5,370 candidates. The participation rate was 60%, as 9,019 candidates had been admitted to the competition. According to the Administration and Public Service Services, the competition jury will now carry out the evaluation work, which will be completed within a month. The validity period of the classification is five years.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>In Indonesia, faith and fun create controversy in the Islamic world</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/na-indonesia-fe-diversao-criam-polemica-mundo-islamico/</link><description>One song, one stage and one sensual dress were enough to spark a national debate about the limits between faith and fun.
In Banyuwangi, (East Java), a stage was set up to celebrate Isra’ Mi’raj, one of the holiest nights in Islam, which commemorates the Prophet Muhammad’s journey from Mecca to the Al-Aqsa Mosque in Jerusalem and his ascension to heaven. The place was intended for sermons and prayers.
On January 16, what followed the sermons and prayers was something completely different: a dangdut singer in a tight dress took the stage, her hips swaying to the lively rhythm of modern dance in the Osing dialect, and a man joined in to dance and tip her.
Someone filmed everything. Within hours, the video spread across social media, disturbing many people.
Isra’ Mi’raj is solemn, while dangdut performances thrive on physical proximity and interaction with the audience. For critics, the two worlds collided.
Organizers insisted there was no disrespect. Muhammad Hadiyanto, head of the local committee, said that before the music began, the religious program had ended and the clerics had left. The presentation, according to him, was only intended to entertain the members of the committee during the cleaning.
The apology did little to quell the outrage. Religious leaders considered it a moral failure.
“This incident is deeply regrettable,” said Sunandi Zubaidi, vice president of the Indonesian Ulema Council (MUI) of Banyuwangi. “The nobility of dakwah (Islamic preaching) has been tarnished by actions that do not reflect Islamic values.”
He warned that sacred events should not be mixed with acts that lead to immorality, including the exposure of the aurat (intimate parts of the body according to Islam), erotic dancing and ikhtilat (mixing between men and women). He even warned that such actions could constitute blasphemy.
Parliament echoed the concern. MP Singgih Januratmoko said the issue goes to the heart of how society protects the sanctity of religion. “The allegation that the entertainment took place after the main event does not resolve the issue in itself”, he stressed, arguing that, “from a religious point of view, the setting, symbols and context are inseparable”.
The police said that no crime was committed, but it was confirmed that the show was not included in the event license.
Organizers must understand the nature of an event and ensure presentations are aligned with its concept and audience. For religious occasions, this may mean selecting styles of “religious music,” such as percussion ensembles, modestly dressed singers or religious songs, Said noted.
"When a video goes viral, people only see what happens on stage. They don't see the preparation behind the scenes – the coordination, the briefings, the warnings. Yet the public's reaction is often: 'Why is dangdut like this?'" he added.
Dangdut, one of the most popular musical genres in Indonesia, is built on hypnotic rhythms, similar to tabla, and mixes Indian percussion, Malay melodies and Arabic phrases. It emerged in the 1930s and gained prominence in the 1950s during President Sukarno's anti-Western cultural campaign, which restricted Hollywood films but allowed Hindi cinema. In the 1960s, local singers began to appear, although the genre remained closely linked to villages and lower social classes.
In the 1970s, Indonesian Rhoma Irama, the “King of Dangdut”, electrified dangdut with guitars and rock influences, inspired by bands like Deep Purple, taking the genre beyond rural communities. He renamed his group, Soneta, as “The Voice of the Muslim”, fusing dangdut with Islamic themes, introduced the separation of genres on stage and replaced rock elements with religious-themed performances.
The first concerts were met with hostility, with stones and sandals thrown onto the stage. Initially, MUI (Municipal Indonesia University) declared singing verses from the Quran haram – prohibited by Islamic law – but later endorsed the work of the dangdut legend.
Like other Indonesian musical art forms such as jaipongan and campursari, dangdut has increasingly incorporated sexually suggestive lyrics and sensual dances, movements that test limits in the world's largest Muslim-majority nation.
"This art exists because there is an audience for it. The issue is not the taste, but the location. In a religious event, I would say that this type of performance is highly inappropriate, indecent and inappropriate" concluded ethnomusicologist Endo Suanda.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>