<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Kou Hoi In replaces António José de Freitas as president of the TDM Administration</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/kou-hoi-substitui-antonio-jose-de-freitas-como-presidente-da-administracao-da-tdm/</link><description>Kou Hoi In will assume the presidency of the Board of Directors of TDM, replacing António José de Freitas, according to Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU. Casimiro Pinto and Lei Chong Cheng will take the places of Inês Chan and Ma Kam Keong as directors at the public capital company
 
SERGIO TERRA
 
António José de Freitas will serve his last day today as chairman of the Board of Directors of TDM – Teledifusao de Macau S.A., a role he has held since August 4, 2021. In his place, the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, decided to appoint Kou Hoi In, former president of the Legislative Assembly (AL) of the Macao SAR and current member of the Standing Committee of the National People's Assembly (ANP) of the People's Republic of China, according to the report. TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper from a source familiar with the process.
The appointment of Kou Hoi In, 72 years old, takes effect from tomorrow, December 10th, and should last for a period of one year.
A member of the Legislative Assembly since 1991, Kou Hoi In was elected president of the Hemicycle on July 17, 2019, to succeed Ho Iat Seng, who resigned his mandate in order to run for the position of Chief Executive of the Macao SAR, in the elections held on August 25 of that year. Kou Hoi In, who also led the Macau Commercial Association, would leave the AL this year, after not seeking re-election in the legislative elections held on September 14th.
Kou Hoi In has already been awarded the Silver Lotus Medal of Honor and the Medal of Industrial and Commercial Merit by the Macao SAR in 2016 and 2007, respectively.
It is worth remembering that, in November, António José de Freitas was re-elected as provider of Santa Casa da Misericórdia for another two years, with the mandate beginning on January 1, 2026. “As far as the role of Provider is concerned, it will be another two years of intense activity, during which I will continue to dedicate myself to this cause, in order to maintain all the projects that we have implemented over these years, which means a lot of work ahead of me”, anticipated at the time, in statements to this newspaper.
In addition to the departure of António José de Freitas, the composition of the TDM Board of Directors will undergo two more changes among its members. Inês Chan Lou, former director of the Social Communication Office, and Ma Kam Keong, former administrator of the Institute for Municipal Affairs, will be replaced by Casimiro Pinto, former deputy secretary-general of the Permanent Secretariat of the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries, and Lei Chong Cheng, current president of the Board of the Workers' Federation.
In the case of Inês Chan, this is a mere officialization, as she had already ceased her role as administrator of TDM due to retirement. Ma Kam Keong will also no longer be part of the TDM Executive Committee, which has been chaired by Lorman Lo Song Man since September 2020, when he replaced Manuel Pires, who retired.
The new appointments of the Macao SAR leader will restore some “normality” to TDM's management structure, since, according to the portal of the Directorate of Supervision and Public Asset Management Services, the terms of office of all members of the Board of Directors and the Executive Committee of TDM officially ended on August 31st of this year.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Preferences for consumption on the Continent are based on “good value for money”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/preferencias-por-consumo-continente-assentam-bom-custo-beneficio/</link><description>A survey by the Macau Social and Behavioral Sciences Research Society, based on responses from 953 residents, found that 93.7% of respondents traveled to Mainland China in the last three months, with 46.8% crossing the border several times a month. Gastronomy, shopping and entertainment are the main reasons for consumption in Mainland China, associated with the “good value for money” factor. On the other hand, around 47% understand that, in a certain way, “they are already integrated into the society of Mainland China”
 
To analyze the behavior of residents when traveling to Mainland China in the context of the Macao SAR's integration into the Greater Bay Area, the Macau Social and Behavioral Sciences Research Society surveyed 953 residents between March and December this year. According to the study, 93.7% of respondents traveled to Mainland China in the last three months.
Specifically, 46.8% were in Mainland China several times a month. Respondents who made one trip per week to the Mainland represent 21.2% of the total.
Cited by Jornal do Cidadão, the association analyzed that the aforementioned data reflects that “traveling to Mainland China” has already become a common and frequent behavior of Macau citizens on a daily basis.
The study reveals that “restaurants and gastronomy” (27.5%), “shopping and consumption” (24.8%) and “leisure and entertainment” (21%) constitute the main reasons that take residents across the border, which “shows that consumption and experience are the main driving force”.
Among the reasons why residents prefer to consume on the other side of the border, instead of Macau, are “lower prices and good value for money” (82.3%), “more diversified products/services” (55.9%) and “the offer of services that cannot be found in Macau” (53.3%).
In the psychological and social aspects, the survey indicates that the majority of interviewees stated that they “are relatively accustomed” to life in Mainland China and around 47% consider that, in a certain way, “they are already integrated into the society of Mainland China”.
On the other hand, around 44.3% confessed that their concepts of consumption and lifestyle were “slightly influenced” by the experience of moving to Mainland China, while 15.9% consider the resulting changes to be “significant”.
Respondents with an academic degree higher than a bachelor's degree are those who spent more money on the Chinese mainland and also those who feel they are rarely treated differently on the other side of the border.
However, those interviewed over the age of 56 face clear language difficulties, while those in the 26 to 35 age group more easily feel “differentiated treatment” on the Mainland compared to the locals. In another aspect, male residents showed a higher level of adaptation and integration than women, however, they showed stronger linguistic obstacles.
Generally speaking, the association suggested improving policies and measures with a view to increasing the convenience of cross-border travel, promoting interconnection and mutual recognition of social security, medical services and educational resources between Guangdong and Macau. He also called for the creation of an “efficient and transparent” mechanism to guarantee cross-border consumption rights and conflict mediation.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief expects relations with Portugal to maintain a “solid foundation”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-espera-relacoes-portugal-mantenham-uma-base-solida/</link><description>Visiting Macau, a delegation from the Portuguese Assembly of the Republic carried out a series of visits to Portuguese-based associations and met with the Chief Executive. Sam Hou Fai said he hopes that friendly relations between Macau and Portugal “continue to advance on a solid basis”. At APOMAC, José Cesário, leader of the delegation, heard some concerns, one of which was related to the current national security context, having mentioned that relations between Portugal and China “must essentially be guided by respect”
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The Chief Executive considers that the “increasing” support from the Government in teaching the Portuguese language, in the transmission of culture and to the Portuguese community, “fully demonstrates Macau’s consolidated foundations in the coexistence of diverse cultures, and the importance and respect constantly given to the rights, interests, customs and traditions of the Portuguese community in Macau”.
Sam Hou Fai's words were delivered during a meeting he held with the delegation of the Parliamentary Committee on Foreign Affairs and Portuguese Communities, led by José Cesário, who was visiting the territory.
At the meeting held at Government Headquarters, Sam Hou Fai also said he hoped that “friendly relations between Macau and Portugal will continue to advance on a solid basis”. He also highlighted that the Sino-Lusophone cooperation platform is “in good working order”, with the number of students learning the Portuguese language “constantly growing”.
The Portuguese delegation, which included deputies from the three largest parties, visited several institutions, including the Fundação Oriente, Escola Portuguesa, Santa Casa da Misericórdia, Association of Retirees, Retirees and Pensioners of Macau (APOMAC) and the Public Service Workers' Association (ATFPM).
Jorge Fão, president of the general assembly of APOMAC, told TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper that the meeting served to discuss several topics, among which China's national security and the consequences for the Portuguese community residing here stood out.
“This issue is not just about China, Portugal also has it, as do other countries”, he began by saying, adding that “on our part we have been doing our part, fulfilling the requirements and requirements of China's national security”.
For this reason, he adds, “I took the opportunity to ask the deputies that when you talk to China, or when you have a relationship with China, before doing anything that is hostile, think about the Macau community, which is not small, there are around 140,000, whether or not they speak Portuguese”.
The APOMAC leader hopes that “Portugal will associate more with China, be more assertive in relation to its policies towards Beijing, because China today is an economic power and we cannot ignore that”. Portugal and its population “would only win if the policy towards China was more assertive and consensual”, he points out.
Regarding this relationship and the issue of national security, José Cesário was peremptory in stating that “Portugal does not forget Macau” and that relations between Portugal and China must be essentially guided by respect.
“A very great respect for China, as great as the one we ask China to have for Portugal, exactly the same”, he emphasized. Speaking to TDM, the Commission leader also highlighted the ancient culture of the two countries: “We have every reason to respect each other deeply, without forgetting one fundamental thing, which is that we have Portuguese in Macau and the rest of China, and that there are many Chinese in Portugal”.
In turn, José Pereira Coutinho, president of the ATFPM board, revealed to JTM that views were exchanged “on matters related to Caixa Geral de Depósitos, the Tax Authority, issues of residence and acquisition of nationality”.
During the conversation “we also discussed air connections between Macau, Portugal, Europe and Portuguese-speaking countries”, as well as “issues regarding closer sporting, educational, social and gastronomic cooperation”, he stated.
Regarding the trip to Santa Casa da Misericórdia, Ombudsman António José de Freitas told JTM that it was just “a courtesy visit”, in which the members of the delegation got to know the institution's projects.
The Parliamentary Committee went to Hong Kong yesterday, Monday. Timor-Leste will be the next stop, a country where he will remain for two days.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>USJ obtains 190 quotas for Mainland students</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/usj-consegue-190-quotas-para-alunos-continente/</link><description>The number of USJ quotas for students from Mainland China rose to 190, “a great achievement” for the institution. At least since 2023, the rector, Stephen Morgan, has been asking Beijing to be able to recruit more students from the Mainland
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The University of Saint Joseph (USJ) managed to increase the number of quotas for Chinese students from Mainland China, something that the rector, Stephen Morgan, had been asking for at least since 2023. Now, at the 2025 ceremony for awarding honorary and higher degrees, the institution's director announced, during his speech, that the Chinese Ministry of Education “has officially approved an annual recruitment quota of 190 Mainland Chinese students for USJ”.
The allocation, consisting of 160 master's and 30 doctoral places, “represents a great achievement for USJ, significantly expanding its ability to receive and cultivate outstanding academics from mainland China”, highlighted Stephen Morgan, quoted in a statement.
This “significant milestone” for the institution had already been on the rector's agenda for several years and resulted in a substantial increase in the number of students that USJ can recruit, as in previous years it was set at 30 for postgraduate and doctoral studies, according to information previously provided to this newspaper.
In November 2023, in an interview with TRIBUNA DE MACAU, Stephen Morgan revealed that he had asked Beijing to increase quotas, starting in 2024, but the objective ended up not being achieved. At the time, he did not reveal the number of quotas requested, only saying that it was “a substantial increase”.
At the ceremony that took place on Saturday, the achievements of 103 students were celebrated. One of the highlights was the award of the degree of Doctor Honoris Causa in Theology to Father Peter Stilwell, former rector of the USJ, and the degree of Doctor Honoris Causa in Business Administration to Lucas Lo, member of The Fellow of the Chancellor’s Court of Benefactors of the USJ.
According to a statement from the institution, the awarding of the degree to Peter Stilwell “recognizes his significant contributions to USJ and his profound impact on Catholic higher education in Macau and Portugal”. Stilwell was rector of USJ between 2012 and 2020, years marked by “academic reforms, campus development and improving the university’s reputation under his exemplary leadership”, according to what we can read.
The distinction also recognizes “the long-standing ecclesiastical contributions, both at USJ and at the Universidade Católica Portuguesa, the unwavering service to the Church and society in general and the lifelong commitment to promoting fruitful dialogue between Catholics, other Christians and non-Christians”.
The awarding of the title to Lucas Lo aims to recognize “exemplary philanthropic efforts and ethical business leadership, with special emphasis on his deep commitment to education”. The statement further notes that as a “consistent donor” to USJ and other institutions across China, Lo has “empowered countless students through financial support for scholarships and initiatives that promote Catholic higher education and community development.”</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Kenyan wins Marathon and breaks course record</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/queniano-vence-maratona-bate-recorde-percurso/</link><description>Victor Kipchirchir, from Kenya, won the Macau International Marathon and set a new course record. In the women's sector, Ethiopia occupied the entire podium, with Mastewal Senay's individual triumph. In Midfield, the Kenyan contingent dominated in both categories. Rosa Mota raced again in the Mini and was second placed



















VÍTOR REBELO
 
The good weather conditions that prevailed on Sunday morning, with sunshine and mild temperatures, ideal for a long-distance road athletics race, suggested a Macau International Marathon with fast times. In addition to this, a contingent of African athletes, with some quality, who traveled to the territory with the double objective of triumph and route record.
After the start, given at 6:00 am, the representatives of Kenya, Ethiopia and Rwanda, with the Chinese Bangliu Zhang in the middle, took the lead, remaining in a compact group during most of the journey, from the start at the Taipa Stadium Olympic Sports Center, until 10 km from the finish line.
Among the distance runners present, Kenyan Victor Kipchirchir, already a veteran (37 years old), was the one with the best time, with 2.05.43, achieved this year at the Barcelona Marathon, ending up beating all the competition in the Macao SAR competition, with a time that earned him the course record (2.09.27). He beat the best mark up to that point by 34 seconds, which had been in the possession of his compatriot Felix Kiptoo Kirwa, since 2017, collecting three checks: one for 40,000 US dollars for the victory and two more bonuses (15,000 dollars corresponding to the record and another 7,000 for the time under two hours and 14 minutes).
Victor Kipchirchir accelerated the pace in the final part and left the main opponents behind, especially Rwandan John Hakizimana, second placed, with 2.09.01, also an excellent mark, which becomes the second best ever. In third place was Ethiopian Barecha Tolosa Geleto, with 2.11.45, followed by two compatriots, Negusse Seboka Erre (2.12.31) and Bereket Yadete Kase (2.14.39).
The first non-African was the Chinese Bangliu Zhang, with 2.16.08, in sixth place, while the best in Macau would be Fong Ieng Wai, in 19th, with 2.40.56.
In the women's sector, absolute dominance belonged to Ethiopia, with Mastewal Birhanu Senay claiming the triumph, with a time of 2.31.37, ahead of Selam Fente Gebre (2.33.21) and Kolole Mekashu Tefera (2.34.10). Chinese Wei Li finished as the first non-African, in seventh place, and the fastest in the Macao SAR was Wu Yangyang, in 13th, with 3.11.31.
In the Half Marathon, the titles went to Ndungu Njenga (1:03:05), in the men's sector, and Lucy Ndambuki (1.12.36, course record), both from Kenya.
Highlighting the good results of long distance runners from Portuguese-speaking countries, invited by the Association of PLP Olympic Committees (ACOLOP). In the men, Samuel Varela, from Cape Verde, finished third, one place ahead of the Portuguese Fábio Oliveira and two in relation to the Mozambican Victor Cassecusse. As for Macau, Wong Chin Wa was ninth.
In women, Lucia Capingala, from Angola, finished third, followed by Portugal's Joana Ferreira. Mozambican Domingas Checane was 6th. Of the Macao SAR athletes, Hoi Long was the best, reaching sixth place.
Finally in the Mini-Marathon race, of around 4.5 km, Rosa Mota, 66 years old, Olympic champion of the Marathon at the Seoul Games, in South Korea, in 1998, was second in the absolute classification, 54 seconds behind the winner Kin I Chao, from Macau. In the men's sector, the triumph also belonged to local athlete Chi Lok Hong.
The three distances, which had a total of 12,000 athletes, were organized by the Macau Sports Institute and the Galaxy Entertainment group.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 850 admitted to the staff program</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-de-850-admitidos-programa-de-quadros/</link><description>In the first two phases of the program to recruit qualified staff, more than 850 candidates were admitted. The new phase runs until December next year and values ​​those who have studied at renowned higher education institutions in Portugal and Brazil
 
The Government admitted more than 850 candidates in the first two phases of the program to attract qualified personnel from abroad, including top athletes, members of the National Academy of Engineering of China and founders of publicly listed companies. At a meeting of the Qualified Staff Development Committee (CDQQ), Sam Hou Fai stated that the Macao SAR intends to optimize its policies, “in accordance with the concept of ‘gathering, cultivating, making good use of and retaining qualified staff’”.
The Chief Executive also explained that Macau will reinforce “close exchanges within the scope of work on qualified personnel with the Deep Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin and with the cities of the Greater Bay Area”, in order to “potentiate the advantages of resources and the synergy effects of the three regions”, according to a statement.
Além disso, Sam Hou Fai recordou que serão dados mais pontos a quadros com grau académico de instituições de ensino superior de renome de Portugal e Brasil. In addition, study or work experience in these countries also benefits. The new phase of the fundraising program runs until December 2026.
In turn, O Lam added that the Government “actively coordinated the different public services involved to promote work related to the integrated development of ‘education, science and technology and qualified personnel’”. The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture assured that, “in the future, Macau will continue to develop its unique advantage of connection with Portuguese-speaking countries, its ‘Macau + Hengqin’ positioning and its role as a ‘connection platform’”.
On the occasion, Kong Chi Meng, secretary general of CDQQ, presented the optimizations of the third phase of the recruitment program, whose elements “enrich the attraction of qualified international staff, the improvement of the functions of the Electronic Application Platform and the simplification of assessment and approval procedures”.
Wong Kin Mou, deputy secretary-general, reported on the status of the organization of the “3rd Greater Bay Area High-Quality Skilled Personnel Development Conference”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 400 companies awarded by DST</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-de-400-empresas-premiadas-pela-dst/</link><description>A total of 427 catering establishments, travel agencies and Certified Stores were awarded this year by the Tourism Services
 
The Tourism Services Directorate (DST) presented awards to more than 400 companies in the restaurant and travel agency sectors, under the 2025 Quality Tourism Services Assessment Program, which praised the establishments awarded this year for the first time and those that renewed the distinction. On the other hand, this year also Certified Stores were awarded.
Specifically, 327 companies in the restaurant sector were awarded the Quality Company Award, of which 170 were new companies competing or that re-applied, and 57 were awarded in the travel agency sector, including 26 new companies competing or that re-applied, says DST.
Among the award-winning companies in the restaurant sector, 20 were awarded the Special Theme Award and four were awarded the Quality Tourist Services Award. At the same time, three travel agencies were awarded the Special Theme Award and one the Quality Tourist Services Award.
On the other hand, in the retail sector in collaboration with the Consumer Council, DST awarded the Quality Company Award this year to 43 Certified Stores, whose awards ceremony takes place on Thursday.
The deputy director of DST, Jennifer Si Tou, said in a speech that the Quality Tourism Services Assessment Program aims to establish standards, raise quality and praise companies that provide excellent services in the tourism industry, to support tourism and related sectors to raise the quality of services.
“At the same time, the promotion of the Macau Courtesy Campaign continues, disseminating messages to various sectors and citizens about courtesy, so that front-line staff implement a courteous hospitality service, in order to extend the culture of quality services in the tourism sector to all sectors of society, consolidating Macau's status as a global tourism and leisure center”, added Jennifer Si Tou, quoted in a statement.
The Quality Tourism Services Assessment Programme, launched in 2014, has gradually expanded from catering to travel agencies and retail, now covering three sectors. This year, the limit on the number of applications for the restaurant sector and the travel agency sector was canceled, and all candidates who met the requirements were admitted and assessed, according to the DST statement.
At the same time, “the interconnection of information from the services responsible for licensing significantly simplified application procedures for companies, with a view to encouraging greater participation in this program”.
Since 2023, the program has launched several Special Theme Awards, including community and elderly care, operational innovation, green eating and food appreciation, promoting local character and this year's new honest operating award. By awarding these awards, DST intends to encourage tour operators to create a quality tourist service.
In a statement, DST points out that, in accordance with the development strategy of adequate diversification of the “1 + 4” economy, it has initiated several “important works, in keeping with the times, to transform integrated tourism and leisure into a sophisticated and robust industry, continuously enriching the content of Macau as a global tourism and leisure center”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Five years in prison for defrauding financial support</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cinco-anos-de-prisao-por-defraudar-apoios-financeiros/</link><description>A former worker from the former Directorate of Education and Youth Services was sentenced to five years in prison by the Court of Final Instance. Between 2017 and 2020, he used his position at DSEJ, falsifying computer data and documents in order to provide financial support to an association he had formed with other people
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
The Court of Final Instance (TUI) sentenced a former employee of the former Directorate of Education and Youth Services (DSEJ), currently the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services, to a sentence of five years in prison. The defendant was convicted of 18 crimes of fraud, one of document forgery, three of computer forgery and one of illegitimately obtaining computer data.
Between 2017 and 2020, he took advantage of his position at DSEJ to improperly obtain financial support for the benefit of an association he formed with other individuals. Despite never having been registered as a leader of the general assembly, or a member of the association's board of directors and supervision, the former public servant “effectively managed personal and financial affairs” and “the work of the aforementioned association”, according to the TUI.
More specifically, he used the association to apply for a series of financial support from the DSEJ, presenting false documents and causing the services to grant him “an amount that exceeded the amount actually available for financing”.
Furthermore, after the application deadline, he took advantage of his position to add and modify, without authorization, the annual financial support plan presented, having hidden from his superior the interests that existed between him and the association in question, failing to comply with the duty of impediment.
In 2021, the subunit's then division head asked his subordinates to review the association's application materials. O ex-trabalhador reproduziu os documentos e remeteu-os aos membros da associação, para fugir à investigação da DSEJ e do Comissariado Contra a Corrupção.
Accused by the Public Prosecutor's Office, in 2023, he was sentenced by the Criminal Court of the Base Judicial Court (TJB) to seven years in prison, for committing 18 crimes of fraud, 19 of document forgery, seven of abuse of power, two of forgery committed by an employee, three of computer forgery and one of illegitimate obtaining of computer data.
He decided to appeal to the Court of Second Instance (TSI), demanding the acquittal of the crimes of forgery and claiming that his conduct should not be “evaluated for a second time and be punished for two types of crime”. In the defendant's opinion, the crime of document forgery was a “necessary means” to carry out the fraud.
The TSI Collective Court decided to acquit the individual of the 18 crimes of document forgery and understood that the man should not be punished for two types of crime, but rather for the “crime of forgery committed by an employee”. Furthermore, in relation to the unauthorized alteration of application data, the Collective Court also considered that the defendant should only be punished for the crime of computer forgery, absolving him of the four crimes of abuse of power.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Gastronomy and culture combine at Taipa Market</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/gastronomia-cultura-aliam-se-mercado-da-taipa/</link><description>V's



With a new image, Mercado da Taipa now has 20 new stalls dedicated to gastronomy and cultural and creative products. These spaces are already operating on an experimental basis, and IAM hopes to “inject new vitality into the market, promoting its transformation and sustainable development”

Two dozen food stalls and cultural and creative items are already operating in the Taipa Market, on an experimental basis. According to the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM), the public has at their disposal “a variety of creative foods, coffee, tea and cultural and creative items”, in addition to the space also having indoor and outdoor dining areas.
The organization hopes, through the revitalization of the market, to introduce characteristic stalls, attracting young operators with innovative management ideas, to “inject new vitality into the market, promoting its transformation and sustainable development”.
The “gastronomy + cultural creativity” area of ​​Taipa Market is located on the 1st floor and on the terrace on the 2nd floor. The 1st floor has 19 gastronomy stalls and cultural and creative items and an indoor dining area; while the 2nd floor terrace has a terrace and an outdoor dining space. The ground floor, in turn, has traditional stalls selling fresh and live products and grocery stores.
The 20 stall operators have products such as dragon boat rice cakes, clay pot lo mein, cod waffles, Portuguese chorizo ​​waffles, flower-shaped dragon beard sweets, among others. “Some tenants also collaborated with local creative culture brands to bring a new approach to traditional sweets and snacks”, adds IAM. There were also operators that introduced technological elements to personalize creative postcards, or combined tourist cultural elements from various places to launch distinctive products.
As part of the revitalization of the Market, IAM globally optimized the facilities and the exterior appearance of the building, redefined the layout of the stalls, beautified the facades and added elements of Portuguese inspiration, “such as a decorative wall with Macau toponymic plaque elements at the entrance/exit of the area, the identification of several indoor dining points with street names and the decoration of the colored walls with different Portuguese-style window frames”, says a statement. The facade also has a new logo.
It is recalled that, in the public competition, IAM had received 437 applications for the 20 panels.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Loja Social helped almost 4,500 families in 2025</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/loja-social-ajudou-quase-4-500-familias-em-2025/</link><description>The campaign to distribute “food baskets” by Loja Social helped 4,476 families of low-income workers throughout this year, at a monthly average of around 370, announced the provider of Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macau. The total amount of financing amounted to 3.6 million patacas, and this month it was supported entirely by Santa Casa's own funds, involving around 300 thousand patacas, indicated António José de Freitas.



















The provider took advantage of the official conclusion of the 2025 campaign to “express its most sincere gratitude to all the sponsoring institutions, benefactors and, in particular, to all the volunteers from various sectors who helped monthly in the distribution of the ‘food baskets’”.
António José de Freitas also assured that, next year, Loja Social will continue to make efforts to distribute baskets to the “numerous” families of low-income workers, in order to alleviate their financial pressures. The same person in charge stressed that the success of this “significant” charity project is “intimately” linked to the rigorous process of monthly selection of families, carried out by the managers and staff of the Federation of Workers' Associations (FAOM) and União Geral das Associações dos Moradores (UGAMM), thus ensuring that households in difficulty receive adequate support.
Looking ahead to 2026, the provider expressed the desire to continue to count on the support of all sectors of society, so that the activity of distributing “food baskets” continues, “tirelessly” contributing to the construction of a “harmonious and inclusive society”.
On Saturday, the Social Store delivered hampers to 373 families. This month, the group of beneficiaries included 150 families nominated by UGAMM, 150 nominated by FAOM, 48 assisted by Santa Casa itself and 25 belonging to the Association of Family Carers for the Mentally Disabled.
The activity took place in the presence of António José de Freitas and the general secretary of Santa Casa, Gisela Nunes, among other officials. Santa Casa, UGAMM and FAOM sent around 20 volunteers to help with the distribution.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM opens Henry Fok Library</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/upm-inaugura-biblioteca-henry-fok/</link><description>The Macau Polytechnic University (UPM) opened the Henry Fok Ying Tung Library, in the Academic Building, next to the Guia Lighthouse. The new space constitutes “a comprehensive platform for learning, research, exchange and innovation” and aims to provide readers with “a comfortable learning environment”, “support scientific research and innovation” and “contribute to the construction of ‘Cultural Macau’”.
At the opening ceremony, which also marked UPM's 45th anniversary, rector Marcus Im highlighted that the institution's teaching and research “gained national and international recognition, and that its international ranking and reputation rose rapidly”.
Marcus Im added that UPM “will continue to optimize the distribution of educational resources, expand the international cooperation network in higher education and actively participate in the development of the Macau and Hengqin International Education University City”. In this context, it will also promote “the creation of the ‘international campus’ that focuses on higher education cooperation between China and Portugal and extends to other Portuguese-speaking countries”.
For his part, Chui Sai Cheong, president of the General Council and the Development Foundation of UPM, stated that “the great support from the Henry Fok Foundation represents a profound recognition of the educational concept and academic objectives” of the university. Furthermore, it serves “as a good example for the development of the Foundation” and plays “a major driving role in jointly driving academic progress, training qualified staff and providing services to the community”.
Ian Fok Chun-Wan, filho de Henry Fok, realçou o facto de a UPM ter vindo a formar “um grande número de talentos patrióticos para o País e para Macau”. Disse esperar que a nova biblioteca “possa prestar um forte apoio ao desenvolvimento de alto nível da UPM, promovendo o desenvolvimento integrado da educação, da ciência e tecnologia e dos quadros qualificados de Macau”.
The ceremony was presided over by O Lam, Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, in the presence of students, teachers and various representatives from different sectors of society.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Illuminate Macau” with a Portuguese artist’s “touch”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/iluminar-macau-toque-de-artista-portugues/</link><description>“Iluminar Macau” has already started, which runs until January 11th, and features local but also international installations, including by Portuguese artist Emanuel Barbosa. The event presents 28 sets of installations in nine locations around the city



















Portuguese artist Emanuel Barbosa designed one of the installations for the 11th edition of the “Iluminar Macau” festival, which runs until January 11th. According to the Tourism Services Directorate (DST), Barbosa created the work “Ark of Light” (‘Ark of Light’), in the shape of a ship, which was installed at the Nam Van Lake Nautical Center. The work “carries the spirit of different cultures” and includes four candles that, “like scrolls unfolded from space and time, project words” from several languages.
Professor and international coordinator of ESAD – Escola Superior de Artes e Design, Emanuel Barbosa is also a member of the board of directors of the Portuguese Cultural Association. He was one of four Portuguese invited, during the pandemic, to develop products for the Chinese air purifier brand Airhein, who were at Design Shanghai in 2020, one of the biggest events in Asia.
The designer also became creative director of the Chinese magazine Casa International, which dedicated an issue to Portuguese architecture in 2012, in Chinese and English.
This year's festival, under the theme “Landscape in Light – Horizon”, includes 28 sets of installations at nine points next to Nam Van Lake, in the North Zone and in the Outer Harbor Landfill Zone. The equipment was created by teams from Macau, Mainland China, Korea, Australia and the USA, as well as Portugal, in a display of “local creativity with an international vision”, as mentioned by DST.
Helena de Senna Fernandes highlighted that the initiative “is not just an event that shows the intersectoral integration of ‘tourism + events’ in Macau, it is also a large-scale event that aims to beautify the urban space and reinforce the cohesion of community areas”. The director of the organization hopes that “Iluminar Macau” can lead residents and tourists to consume in the neighborhoods, “further boosting community tourism and the night-time economy”.
This edition includes an original Macau creation, using 3D projection technology to present a 3D video mapping show “Macao Odyssey: The Story Unfolds” on the facade of the Grand Prix Museum. The show takes place every day, between 6pm and 10pm, with an exhibition every 15 minutes, lasting around six minutes.
Every Friday, Saturday, Sunday, and festive day, on which the event takes place, next to Rua de Luís Gonzaga Gomes, Rua de Xiamen and Rua de Nagasaki, 20 activities are organized under the theme of coffee and typical Macau cuisine. DST also cooperates with MPay to scan the QR code at newsstands and collect consumer coupons, with the number of vouchers to be distributed being limited and ending as soon as they run out.
The festival also includes a series of extension activities, such as workshops on reusing coffee grounds, coffee tasting, robots, a brilliant pickleball game and Portuguese tile workshops, along with several “flash mob” and live shows.
During “Iluminar Macau”, MGTO organizes the community activity “ZAPE Fantasia de Natal” between the streets of Guangzhou and Beijing. At the same time, the activities “Luminescent Night at Travessa do Armazém Velho” are taking place, on Rua dos Ervanários, Rua da Nossa Senhora do Amparo, Rua da Tercena and Beco de Chôn Sau, and the “Nothern Winter Market” in Praça dos Lótus in Bairro da Ilha Verde.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Two slopes at “high risk” of collapse</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dois-taludes-em-alto-risco-de-derrocada/</link><description>?????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????? ?????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????? ?????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????? ??????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????



Until October, 291 slopes were referenced at risk, corresponding to seven more than those recorded in 2024, according to the Directorate of Public Works Services and the Institute for Municipal Affairs. Of the slopes at risk, two were considered “high risk”, 79 “medium risk” and 210 “low risk”
 
Data from the Directorate of Public Works Services (DSOP) and the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) indicate that, until October this year, there were 291 embankments registered at risk of collapse, seven more than those recorded in 2024. The embankments on Estrada da Ponta da Cabrita da Taipa and near the São José de Ká-Hó School were classified as being “high risk”, having been monitored and treated by the entities competent.
Between January and October, personnel from both services together with the Macau Civil Engineering Laboratory carried out a total of 20 inspections of 135 slopes, maintaining 79 “medium risk” slopes and increasing the number of “low risk” slopes to 210. Of the “medium risk” slopes, 38 were located on the Macau Peninsula, 21 in Taipa and 20 in Coloane. Among the “low risk” slopes, 92 were in the Peninsula, 51 in Taipa and 67 in Coloane.
This year, DSOP completed three slope stabilization works, namely the work to reorder the slope on Estrada da Penha and the projects for the design and construction of the slopes at Escola Superior das Forças de Segurança and Avenida Padre Tomás Pereira.
In turn, IAM completed two slope stabilization works, which include the third phase of 2024 of slope reordering work and the first phase of 2024 of temporary slope protection work in municipal parks and cemeteries.
The interdepartmental services informed that the preparation of the project for the treatment work on the slope of the Government facilities in Penha is already underway and that the work to reorganize the slope on Rua dos Pescadores de Macau, adjacent to the Tin Hau Temple, will begin.
From April 2022 to October this year, authorities carried out 62 inspections of 337 slopes, including nine “high risk”, 128 “medium risk” and 200 “low risk”, with inspection rates of 100%, according to interdepartmental services.
The personnel responsible for assessing the safety of slopes will “continue to reinforce inspection work”, assured DSOP. The organization also added that citizens can find out about the updated status of slopes through the Slope Safety Information Network, available on the DSOP website.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Architect Frank Gehry, master of deconstructivism, has passed away</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/faleceu-arquiteto-frank-gehry-mestre-desconstrutivismo/</link><description>Architect Frank Gehry, considered the master of deconstructivism and author of a series of emblematic works, from the Guggenheim Museum in Bilbao to the Walt Disney Concert Hall in Los Angeles, died last weekend. He was 96 years old.

Gehry was perhaps the greatest among the so-called “starchitects” (an elite group that includes Renzo Piano, Rem Koolhaas and Norman Foster, among others) and, although he enjoyed fame, he hated this label.
“There are people who design buildings that are neither technically nor financially good, and others who do the same,” he told The Independent in 2009. “There are two categories, simple,” he added.
His artistic genius and boldness shone through in complex projects, such as the large glass “sails” at the Louis Vuitton Foundation in Paris.
Gehry popularized contemporary architecture and became such a well-known personality that he even appeared on the television series “The Simpsons”.
“I work with clients who respect the art of architecture”, he declared in 2014, according to his biographer Paul Goldberger.
Born Frank Owen Goldberg in Toronto on February 28, 1929, to a Jewish family who moved to the US in the late 1940s, he changed his surname to Gehry to avoid becoming a target of anti-Semitism.
He studied architecture at the University of Southern California in Los Angeles, where he graduated in 1954 before enlisting in the US Army. He then continued his studies in urban planning at Harvard University, although he did not complete the program.
Between 1952 and 1966, he was married to Anita Snyder, with whom he had two children. He married again in 1975 to Berta Isabel Aguilera and had two more children.
His career began in the office of architect Victor Gruen, a pioneer in the design of shopping centers in Los Angeles. Afterwards, he moved to Paris to work with André Remondet. Back in California, he opened his own studio in the early 1960s.
The 1970s and 1980s marked the beginning of a long series of bold and innovative architectural projects, many of them in Southern California.
Close to the Californian “funk” art scene, Gehry's deconstructivist and experimental style is difficult to categorize. Many of his works (irregular metal facades that may resemble crumpled paper) could only be built thanks to digital design tools, which he adopted in a pioneering way.
One of the best examples is the renovation of his own house in Santa Monica, from 1978, where he lived for a long time. Here, corrugated metal surrounds the original 1920s structure.
Gehry ended the 1980s with architecture's highest honor: the Pritzker Prize, awarded in 1989.
Almost a decade later, he presented what is perhaps his most iconic project: the Guggenheim Museum in Bilbao, which earned him international recognition and fame. The work of limestone and glass, with curved walls covered in titanium sheets, is easily identifiable as a creation by Gehry. The American architect Philip Johnson even described it as “the best building of our time”.
The museum helped revitalize the city's former industrial heart, attracting visitors from all over the world and giving rise to the expression “Bilbao effect”, used to explain how architectural beauty can transform a region.
Many of Gehry's projects required complex calculations, which he pushed to the limit. For a long time, architects avoided rounded or curved shapes, as they created difficulties for engineers and drastically increased construction costs.
Gehry went against this logic and used 3D modeling software similar to those used by the aerospace industry. In this way, he was able to create unique shapes and keep costs within what investors were willing to pay for more conventional buildings.
O Centro Lou Ruvo para a Saúde Cerebral, em Las Vegas – cujas paredes e janelas parecem ter derretido sob o calor do deserto – é um exemplo clássico de sua visão inovadora. “Eu adoro trabalhar. Adoro resolver problemas”, declarou ao The Guardian em 2019.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>