<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Young people tend to adopt “more conservative” expression forms</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jovens-tendem-adoptar-formas-de-expressao-mais-conservadoras/</link><description>The “Social Inquiry of Youth Indicators in Macao in 2024”, based on the responses of 2,350 young people, reveals that the patriotic sentiment of young people increased “significantly” compared to 2022. On the other hand, 80.6% of respondents prefer to discuss social issues with family or friends only, tending to “adopt more conservative expression forms” ”
 
Young people reveal a greater patriotic sentiment, at the same time presenting greater conservatism regarding the opinion on social affairs - these are some conclusions of the “social inquiry of youth indicators in Macao in 2024”. A total of 2,350 young people, aged 13 to 35 years, were asked last year, in a work developed by the Sheng Kung Hui Macau Coordinating Office of Social Services at the request of Youth Education and Development Services.
In general, and regarding expressing opinions on social matters, political and measures, 80.6% of respondents discuss these types of matters with family or friends only; Only 9.7% choose to transmit opinions to government services and 6.4% to the media. Also 26.8% discuss social issues on electronic platforms and 10.7% express opinions through associations.
“Young people in respondents tend to adopt more conservative forms of expression to express their opinions on social affairs,” says the report, analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, which is only in Chinese language. Given this scenario, the document warns that, in this way, opinions “may not be transmitted effectively to society”.
Still, it points out that young people from 19 to 24 are “relatively more active in the use of different channels of expression, highlighting a greater willingness to participate in the affairs of society”. Another conclusion is that 41.6% confessed that if they meet conditions, they will participate in the vote for legislative elections. On the other hand, 37.9% said they participate in associations.
Regarding social participation, the study concludes that it is located at a high level with 3.3 points, on a scale from zero to five, with female (3.37 points) more active than male (3.22 points).
The three main forms of social participation of young people are donation (38.3%), voluntary work (28.8%) and associative services (25.4%). It is also noted that 17.4% do something for environmental protection, 13.6% donate blood, while only 5.9% participate in consultation activities on government policies. On average, each interviewee uses 3.03 hours a month for social participation.
In this sense, the Sheng Kung Hui Macau Association suggested reinforcing civic education through diverse pedagogical methods and the creation of opportunities for the participation of young people in the organization of large events.
On the other hand, the inquiry highlights a high level of patriotic feeling, with 4.12 points, which means an increase compared to the result of the 2022 inquiry (3.99). "The patriotic feeling of young people increased significantly, registering the greatest climb in the group from 13 to 18 years," says the document.
Regarding the degree of participation of young people in national development, there is a high level trend, translated into 3.79 points), compared to 3.65 points in 2022. Young people are mainly interested in Chinese gastronomic culture (62.1%).
Regarding local culture items that arouse the most interest, the first five places are cuisine (67.5%), the characteristics of streets and crossings (45.2%), world heritage (42.3%), art (35.8%) and history (35.6%).
Looking at the situation of Macao, young people express a higher degree of satisfaction with public safety (3.84 points) and education (3.32 points). Both indicators rose in the evaluation of 2022. The satisfaction with the transport suffered a slight descent.
The study also concluded that young people from different cultural contexts do not present significant differences in terms of happiness, satisfaction with life and personal development conditions, which, for the inquiry promoters, reflects the “characteristics of Macao's diverse and inclusive society”. Still, the association proposed the continuation of the integration of multicultural content in education, including cultural elements of China, Lusophone countries and Southeast Asia.
 
Alcohol to deal with negative emotions deserves “attention”
In the area of physical and mental health, 76.4% of respondents said they had consumed alcohol, of which 21.9% were between 13 and 18 years old, a “significant descent” compared to 2022 (46.8%). “Family and Friends Meetings” (73.1%) constitute the main occasion of alcohol consumption, but 32.6% pointed out “work occasions” and 26.1% “poor” situations. About 11% confessed to having “daily habits” of drinking alcohol, including 37.4% are 30 to 35 years old.
"However, part of the respondents said they resorted to alcohol as a way of dealing with negative emotions. These young people have worse indicators of physical and mental health and less resilience… It is necessary to pay specific attention to this phenomenon among young people to resort to alcohol to deal with emotions," the report.
Generally speaking, the physical and mental quality of young people 13 to 18 is better than in other age groups.
On the other hand, the daily average sleep duration of the interviewees was 6.8 hours, approaching the recommended level (six to seven hours) by the US National Sleep Foundation. The quality of daily sleep of young people in general is 3.05 points, one medium level.
The average body mass index is 22.08 points, corresponding to normal weight. However, the percentage of overweight young people increases with age and this problem is higher in males.
Except for the range from 13 to 18 years, 40% of young people do not participate in beneficial recreational activities for physical health. In general, 55.3% participated in this type of activities in the last six months, a decrease meant to 2022 (73.7%). In addition, 20.9% of young people from 25 to 35 years old do no exercise per week.
Regarding mental health, the first three sources of stress are finances (3.15 points), work (3.13 points) and health (3.03 points). At the same time, resilience is of a medium-high level (3.55 points), similar to 2022.
In this chapter, the study warns that young parents, especially with young children, face relatively high pressure on family and work balance. Although the average confidence index in parental education of young parents heard is of a middle -high level (3.64 points) -higher than 3.55 points in 2022 -the study highlights that they need more support in moral formation, emotional management and safety of children.
 
30% dominate three languages
According to the investigation, 64% of young people reside in their own homes and 23.1% in leased fractions. In addition, 9% live in economic housing and 4.4% in social houses.
Last year, mostly earned a full -time monthly working income between 10,000 and 19,999 patacas (36.7%), while 36.3% earned between 20,000 and 29,999. Only 3.8% received less than 10,000 patacas. In 2022, the monthly income of the majority ranged from 20,000 to 29,999 patacas (38.2%).
The five main expenses are: food (80.3%), entertainment and fun (38.6%), housing (38.4%), transport (23.2%) and basic vital expenses (23%).
It is also noted that, in the six months prior to the inquiry, 11.2% of young people said they had participated in game activities, more than 2022 (9.1%). Mahjong (47.5%) and sports bets (31%) constitute the two main types of games.
In turn, the integrated skills of young people are tendency to middle and high levels. The overall tendency of the international view is mid-level (3.45 points), while, within the scope of communication capacity, a high level trend is recorded (3.81 points).
Already the percentage of young people who claim to dominate Chinese, Portuguese and English increased from 28% in 2022 to 30.2%. Alongside this, 68.1% dominate two languages and only 1.7% are monolingules. Notable progress were observed in the Cantonese language, in writing in Chinese and in the English language.
However, in speech and writing in Portuguese, young people - of which only 0.6% have Portuguese as a mother tongue - have only 1.41 and 1.36 points, respectively, “reflects a very low level of Portuguese competence among young people in respondents”.
However, at the level of self -confidence and willpower, they got 3.41 points. The boys (3.45 points) show better results than girls (3.37 points).</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Visitors rose 15% in the first half</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/visitantes-subiram-15-primeiro-semestre/</link><description>In the first half of this year, Macau received about 19.2 million visitors, an annual increase of 15%, while the hotels registered an occupancy rate of 91%, equivalent to that verified in 2019, said Helena de Senna Fernandes. According to the director of tourism services, Macau could register a daily average of 110,000 visitors during the summer holidays
 
The average daily number of visitors in Macau could reach 110,000 between July 1 and August 31, anticipated the Director of Tourism Services (STD). In addition, Helena de Senna Fernandes said that, according to provisional data, Macau registered about 19.22 million visitors in the first six months of this year, which translates into an annual increase of 15%.
In the first half of the year, the hotel occupancy rate reached 91%, equivalent to the level of 2019, said the official, adding that, still, the number of guests rose from 2019, since during the pandemic period they opened new establishments.
On the other hand, according to the Chinese language press, Helena de Senna Fernandes said that, under the fight against illegal guides, 15 illegal cases were detected and processed following 795 inspection actions, held from the beginning of the year until the 6th of this month.
He also said that the International Fire Competition could take place between the second week of September and the Golden Week of October, and preparations are underway. He said, 10 teams will be invited, like the last editions.
Senna Fernandes also highlighted the television program “Keep Running 13”, filmed in the territory last month, which features world heritage points and entered several neighborhoods little known to tourists. The official predicted that the program will attract more tourists.
In this respect, he said that the government is negotiating with the producing entity of another program to film in Macao and present, through various angles, characteristics of the different neighborhoods, in order to attract the attention of more fans to the territory.
 
Show “Charm” program of the
The television program “Keep Running 13” now debuts special episodes on the territory. The first one spent on Friday at Zhejiang Television, and the other will be shown on July 18. "These episodes intend to take the Chinese audiences to explore the neighborhoods of Macau, experience their multiculturalism and enjoy the charm of" Tourism +", contributing to the expansion of the interior of China tourist market," says STD, who supported the recording of the episodes.
During the recordings, several celebrities from the interior of China traveled iconic places in the city, such as Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro, Rua dos Penáráárás, Lotus Square in the Ilha Verde neighborhood and the Garden of the Municipal Market of Iao Hon. and the essence that defines the city, ”adds STD.
Production integrated the city's “emblematic” cultural and tourist elements, highlighting the value of the historic center and its “charm” as a creative city of gastronomy, reads the press release.
According to the body, until June 30, season 13 of the program accumulated more than 30,000 prominent topics on social networks, with over 13.5 billion publications, "consolidating itself as the most relevant variety program among those on display." "This popularity prepares the terrain for the special episodes of Macao," he said.
In line with the strategy of diversified and adequate development of the “1+4” economy, STD stresses that it is promoting with commitment to diversification of supply and sustainability of the Macao tourist industry. “In line with this vision, the special episodes of Macao from Keep Running 13 highlight different facets of 'Tourism +', with STD adopting varied and innovative promotional approaches,” he says.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Increase in game crimes results from a new law</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/aumento-de-crimes-de-jogo-resulta-de-nova-lei/</link><description>Game -related crimes increased in the first five months of the year in the homologous comparison. The director of the Judicial Police, Sit Chong Meng, clarified that this was due to the introduction of the new law to combat crimes associated with the game. On the other hand, since October last year, 481 “money exchange” were arrested and more than $ 60 million from Hong Kong. In general, criminal proceedings filed by PJ dropped 1.1% by the end of May
 
Pedro Milheirão
In the first five months of 2025, game -related crimes grew 62.9%compared to the same period last year, according to Sit Chong Meng, director of the Judicial Police (PJ). He explained, the increase was due to the entry into force of the new law to combat illicit play crimes. PJ has established 943 game -related crimes processes, with 204 cases of “illicit exchange exploration for the game”. There were also 251 cases of game -related burles, which translates into an increase of 93.1%.
In a speech under Judicial Police Day, Sit Chong Meng announced that between October 2024 and May this year, 323 cases were resolved, which resulted in the detention of 481 “money exchange burns” and the seizure of more than $ 60 million from Hong Kong, in cash and chips. Sit added that cases of illegal loans (83) and kidnappings (10) decrease 20.2% and 41.2%, respectively.
Between January and May, 5,843 criminal proceedings were filed, which means that there was a small descent (-1.1%) in terms of general crime. Of these, 2,858 were inquiry and complaint cases, which decreased 11.1%. The total number of proceedings completed was 6,379, of which 1,641 individuals were sent to the judicial agencies. In the same period last year, of the 5,099 cases completed, 1,395 people were sent to courts.
Severe crimes, such as homicides and kids, continue with low levels, which demonstrates that “public order and crime situation remain stable and under control”, according to the PJ director. Throughout the first five months of 2025, 16 cases of theft and 269 cases of theft were recorded. In annual terms, there was another case of theft and 100 of theft.
The telephone throws dropped 27%to 121 cases, and online schemes decreased 29%to 228. Online purchase cases “with illicit credit card use” decreased from 220 to 205. Until May, and in collaboration with telecommunications operators, 263 phishing sites were blocked. Conversely, in recent months, the mockery that simulates calls for online payment platforms have fired, according to PJ.
 
“Positive course” in cybersecurity
From January to May, the Cyberrsecurity Alert and Response Center (Caric) sent 97 warning messages to critical infrastructure operators, when in 2024 it was 110. The Caric also accompanied nine cases of cybersecurity incidents, one of which was a cyber attack. In comparative terms, last year there were 13 cases, showing that the “situation [if] kept stable and tended to a positive course,” said Sit.
In addition, in April, the first case of burla that involved artificial intelligence 'Deepfake' was also registered in Macao. Regarding the recovery of circumvents, PJ was able to prevent 131 payment cases, with the support of MSAR banks, involving an amount of over 25 million patacas. Police also reported 249 suspicious accounts to the banks themselves and detained 98 members of fraudulent groups.
In the context of combating drugs, PJ has established 22 trafficking processes and 10 consumption. Sit Chong Meng also highlighted the “resolution of the largest‘ Ice ”case” in the MSAR, as well as the dismantling of a case of “ephedrine” to mainland China, in a joint effort with customs services. It is recalled that the change in the Drug Fighting Law has been in force less than a month ago, in which 24 substances subject to control, such as “spatial oil” were added.
Over the past year, the PJ also "intensified the execution work in the context of fighting for espionage activities and external interference and alert to the fight against terrorism." The director reiterated that the body continues to defend “committed to national security and stability of masters”.
 
Children's Book on National Security
Last week, as a way to mark the “National Security Education Day” and to promote a greater understanding among young people, PJ launched “The Little Flag holder”, the first illustrated children's digital book.
The book addresses the “theme of political security, combining colorful illustrations and accessible text to integrate the comprehensive concept of maintaining political security”, read in the statement. It also includes a column that explains “the design elements and the legal status of the national flag, national emblem, national anthem, regional flag and regional emblem”</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Former President of ICBC Macau detained in the interior of China</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ex-presidente-icbc-macau-detido-interior-da-china/</link><description>Jiang Yisheng, former president of ICBC Macau, was arrested inside China for "serious violations of discipline and law." The detention will be related to loans for the construction of Windsor Arch, in the mud, linked to businessman NG Lap Seng
 
The former president of the China Industrial and Commercial Bank (ICBC) in Macau, Jiang Yisheng, was arrested by the interior authorities of China, suspected of “serious violations of discipline and law,” according to the China Central Disciplinary Inspection Commission, which announced the detention. The case will be related to loans for the construction of Windsor Arch, in the mud, linked to businessman NG Lap Seng and his family, according to the Chinese social media organ, which cites sources close to the process.
The same publication states that, earlier this year, ICBC Macau applied disciplinary sanctions to the former bank guard, due to the loan in question, whose value is unknown. The former president of the ICBC will now be the subject of a disciplinary review, according to the authorities, being under investigation of the Zhuhai Municipal Supervision Committee.
Jiang Yisheng was part of the ICBC Audit Division and chaired the bank's branch in Macau between 2018 and 2023. He held several heads of head in the ICBC and was known in the financial circles of Macao.
The Windsor Arch project is closely linked to NG Lap Seng, former president of Sun Kian IP Group, one of the promoters of Windsor Arch. NG's son, NG Kei Nin, was also director of the company that provided the land to the venture.
On June 18, the Base Judicial Court announced that the ICBC Macao had requested the freezing of assets belonging to NG Lap Seng and the son to recover outstanding debts. The court order includes almost 80 parking spaces, more than 40 offices, bank deposits and actions evaluated in more than 1.7 million patacas.
A prominent figure in the Macao Real Estate sector, NG Lap Seng faces legal problems since the 1990s, including a 2017 condemnation by bribe involving UN employees, who earned him a four -year prison sentence.
Ng orchestrated a scheme, between 2010 and 2015, to bribe two United Nations ambassadors, with hundreds of thousands of dollars in exchange for support for a construction project. The project could have paved the way for a UN conference center of several thousand millions of dollars in Macao.
In 2017, he was convicted by a US Federal Court for six charges, including bribery, money laundering and conspiracy. He was later sentenced to four years in prison, however, he left in 2021 for health reasons after complying with 34 months.
In Macao, the original 15-year-old was reduced to two and a half years after a long legal dispute over the role he had in a case of corruption and money laundering involving former public works in 2023.</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Bijagós and Maputo Park are world heritage</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/bijagos-parque-de-maputo-sao-patrimonio-mundial/</link><description>UNESCO yesterday enrolled Maputo National Park on the list of natural world heritage, as well as the Bijagós Islands in Guinea-Bissau, a country that debuts in this UNESCO classification. The decision was announced during the 47th meeting of the UNESCO World Heritage Committee, which runs until the 16th, at the organization's headquarters in Paris.

The registration of the bijagos on the list of world heritage sites comes over a decade after the first candidacy rejected by UNESCO. The archipelago is part of the marine and coastal territory of Guinea-Bissau, consisting of 88 islands and ishéus, with an extension of 2.6 square kilometers, where they live, in the 23-inhabited islands, about 33,000 of the two million inhabitants of the country.
The candidacy, now approved, of the “Marine and Coastal Ecosystem of the Bijagós-Omati Minhõ” archipelago is concentrated in the three natural parks, specifically the Natural Park of Orango Islands, the João Vieira and Poilão National Park and the Community Protected Marine Area of the Urok Islands and the connection between these three parks. It is the most relevant zone from the point of view of biodiversity in the islands and islets where turtles spawn, inhabit hippos and feed migratory birds.
The three natural parks covered are pointed out as "the central part of biodiversity", as "zones that allow for great productivity, which have beyond chordeling impacts." They serve as a “feeding zone for birds that come from afar, communities, fishing” and allow “the reproduction of an important cycle of threatened biodiversity, such as sea turtles, sharks and rays”. They are also on the Migratory Route of Birds of the East Atlantic.
The way of life and the culture of the Bijagós also distinguish these islands from the African Western coast.
Bijagós are also sought by beaches and fishing, with tourism still reduced to the expatriates of various organizations to work in the country and sports fishermen, especially from Francophone countries.
In the case of Maputo National Park, UNESCO pointed out that it "includes terrestrial ecosystems, coastal and marine, and houses almost 5,000 species." The park features “diverse habitats, including lakes, lagoons, mangroves and coral reefs”, including feature beaches, dunes, marshes, extensive moist zones, several herbs, providing a habitat for a range of South Africa marine species, also highlighting their longtime conservation.
It is linked to the Isimangaliso Humid Humid Zones Park in South Africa, which already has world heritage status, one of the places previously indicated as a “exceptional potential” for the World Heritage Statute by IUCN, an official advisory agency on the nature of the World Heritage Committee.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 20 countries at the gastronomic party</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-de-20-paises-na-festa-gastronomica/</link><description>The gastronomy party takes place at the fishermen's dock until the end of this week. The event brings together representatives of gastronomic cities from more than 20 countries
 
The “International Festival of the Cities of Gastronomy” takes place until next Sunday, in the Roman Coliseu Square and the Lelevard Legend Boulevard of the fishermen's dock. More than half of UNESCO's creative gastronomy cities participate in the activities, in an event that brings together representatives of 35 cities from 22 countries.
The Director of Tourism Services (STD), Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, said that “gastronomy is a language shared by everyone in the world” and highlighted “the singular gastronomic culture of Macao”. He also added that the event "takes advantage of Macau's advantages as an international exchange platform, committed to preserving and transmitting gastronomic culture."
Denise Bax, secretary of UNESCO's Creative Cities Network, said the initiative reinforces “The Cultural Ties” and promotes “sustainable growth”. According to Bax, there are also "many opportunities to deepen cooperation between UNESCO and Macau".
The party's three main highlights include the 105 newsstands of 15 cities, on International Gastronomy Avenue, the more than 60 chef demonstrations from 29 UNESCO's creative cities network, and the “International Gastronomy Forum”. On the avenue, visitors will be able to find 25 newsstands dedicated to the five cities in the interior of China, namely Chengdu, Shunde, Yangzhou, Huai'an and Chaozhou.
In addition to these, there are 10 other stalls from other Asian countries, such as Thailand, Saudi Arabia, Philippines and Iran, and 10 newsstands from four Brazilian cities. Macao's 54 newsstands offer macanese, western, local and singing dishes, among other delicacies. In turn, the newsstands of the six game operators feature Chinese, Western and Creative Fusion dishes.
The party has five thousand meal zones with a thousand places, so that visitors can “enjoy the delicacies with more comfort”. The animation program has “Portuguese folkloric dances, band performances, artistic rope jumps and street dances”. In addition, there are also a series of games for all ages and the interactive game “spice party” at STD Wechat. Services have also provided consumer discounts through MPay, BOC Macau and ICBC platforms.
The forum takes place today, between 09h00 and 13h00, at the Center for Convention and Exhibitions. It has 17 guests, two inaugural lectures of chefs Jordy Navarra and Varun Totlani and three theme panels, focused on the role of spices and herbs.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Air Macau plane returned for inspection after take off</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/aviao-da-air-macau-regressou-para-inspeccao-apos-descolar/</link><description>An Air Macao passenger transport plane, which departed from the territory on Thursday morning towards Tokyo, had to return to MSAR. According to the company, the flight was hit by lightning, so it had to return to inspection
 
Air Macau confirmed that the NX862 flight passenger transport aircraft, which departed from Macao to Tokyo on Thursday morning, had to return to the territory to submit to inspection as the flight was hit by lightning. Specifically, the airline stated, to “or Mun Tin Toi”, that the arrangement was taken according to the procedures, in order to ensure flight safety.
In addition, the local carrier said it had highlighted another plane to make the trip from Macau to Tokyo that day.
However, the Macao Airport Society (CAM) gave a distinct justification about the event. According to Cam to TDM, it was a “engine problem” of the Narita airport, which took off at 9:40.
In the same vein, on social networks, the group of “Macao bus enthusiasts and public transport” had revealed, before the official reactions that, after the Air Macao plane had cool, had registered an engine problem, and had to return to Macao while near Taichung, ending the plane to land safely.
In addition, the same Facebook page points out that the plane is an Airbus A320neo, and would use a “Pratt &amp; Whitney” engine. The page also describes that this type of engines "is affected by contamination of metal powder material and may be susceptible to metal fatigue, and currently, in the global level, needs to be dismantled and inspected to detect if there are small cracks."
On the other hand, Air Macao assured TDM that all Airbus A320neo with engines where manufacturing problems had been detected in safety tests. In addition, the carrier confirms to have in the fleet planes with “Pratt &amp; Whitney” engines, but says they went to the manufacturer's tests.</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ipor guides Portuguese classes at Club Lusitano de Hong Kong</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ipor-orienta-aulas-de-portugues-club-lusitano-de-hong-kong/</link><description>IPOR will help the Lusitano Club of Hong Kong raise the quality of Portuguese education, in the context of an agreement between the two institutions
 
The Portuguese Language Courses offered by the Lusitanian Club of Hong Kong will be guided by the Portuguese Institute of the Oriente (IPOR), thanks to an agreement signed in Macao, the two institutions told Lusa.
The Lusitanian Club of Hong Kong, with about 400 members, has been available Portuguese courses for about five years, but the initiative "is not official," the president said to the institution, Patrick Rozario, who now wants to bring more quality to the institution's offer. In this sense, Club Lusitano and Ipor signed, on Thursday, in Macao, an agreement that, among other purposes, wants to reinforce collaboration in teaching and learning Portuguese.
“In the future, the Portuguese classes we offer in the Club will be under the guidance and approval of IPOR. We will continue to do what we have done, but IPOR will help us with the material and program,” said the president of the largest institution in the Hong Kong Lusodescendant community, founded in 1866.
Rozario also expects in the future to make the courses available for non-member. For now, specifies, “members and friends” - including 'Visas Gold' - have resorted to the linguistic program.
"It seems that we have more and more people interested in attending Portuguese classes," said the Lusodescendent, noting that, in the last "four, five years", they passed there between 30 and 40 students.
The 'Visas Gold', also known as Residency Authorization for Investment Activity (Ari), are an investment program in Portugal that allows foreigners to get residence in exchange for investment in the country and attracted several people from China, including Hong Kong.
About this partnership will work, the director of IPOR explained to Lusa that the courses will be organized by IPOR - including teaching programs and methodology - and trainers guided by the institution. "When issuing a certificate of the learning of these courses, which are made at Club Lusitano, the seal of IPOR has been departed, and the seal of IPOR offers the quality," he said.
Still with regard to the protocol signed on Thursday, Patrícia Quaresma spoke of the intention of “strengthening collaboration in the cultural area and holding events” in Hong Kong.
"We are invited to participate in fairs or festivals (…) like the consulate [of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong] does not have a office [in Hong Kong], but only one person -and not every day -the Lusitano club will be support to develop these activities and promote Portuguese language and culture," he noticed.
IPOR, created in 1989 and based in Macao, has among the main missions the preservation and diffusion of Portuguese language and culture in the East and participation in support to communities of Portuguese cultural root.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UNESCO classification fostered cultural tourism</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/classificacao-da-unesco-fomentou-turismo-cultural/</link><description>Experts consider that the classification of the historic center of Macao by UNESCO, 20 years ago, boosted cultural tourism in the territory, supporting the diversification of an economy traditionally dependent on casinos, and warns of challenges in promoting heritage.
The Temple of Na Tcha, Chinese Sanctuary, and the ruins of Sao Paulo, facade of the former Catholic Church of the 17th century Madre God, are side by side in the historic center. Early in the morning, families pose to the chamber at the bottom of the iconic stone staircase of the ruins.
“I like the sidewalk [Portuguese], it's special,” says Lusa Alina Wang, a Shanghai tourist. The eight -year -old son York Xiong adds: "The buildings are beautiful." Not everyone in the family, however, knows the story behind Macao's "former libris", reduced to the facade after fires. The patriarch, I read Zijian, was going to swear that it had been destroyed during World War II.
Beside, another family, is from Xi'na, associates the image of ruins with a Japanese bombardment in the great war.
20 years ago, on July 15, 2005, the Historic Center of Macao, a set of 22 monuments that combines Portuguese and Chinese architecture, joined the UNESCO World Heritage list.
This milestone for the city's heritage, Lusa tells the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), brought more tourists to Macau, changing the profile of the visitor, who stopped crossing the border just to play. "This changed the image of Macao from a" city of the game "to a cultural destination, differentiating it in the Asia-Pacific region," said the STD.
Since 2005, the government department has added through email, the tourism sector has been developing at an “rapid pace”. Macao visitors arrived from 16.14 million in 2005 to 34.93 million in 2024.
A study of visitors conducted by STD this year reveals that 53.3%of tourists arrive in the territory to visit the heritage, surpassing those who want to shop (33.7%) and those most interested in gastronomy (18.5%).
For IP FEI, historian and former member of the Macao Cultural Heritage Council, the Statute of the United Nations Education, Science and Culture (UNESCO) has raised Macao's global profile. "The game has boosted the economy in the short term, culture should boost long -term growth," he told Lusa.
Macao's economy depends deeply on casinos, representing 80% of public revenues, and the government expects to collect 79.8 billion with the game tax this year.
But if, on the one hand, the inscription of heritage came to help diversify the tourist's profile, you have to think of those who live in the city daily, noticed Ka Nok Lo, vice president of the Macao Heritage Ambassadors Association. In an interview with Lusa, the official warned of the need not to turn Macau “into a Disneyland”, defending the balance between tourism and the needs of residents.
"Museums should serve the community, as are libraries, bookstores, not just tourists," he said.
Ka stressed, on the other hand, that the visitors still remain the narrative that unites the various places distinguished by UNESCO. "There is no story that turns on these monuments," he said.
The Macao government has as one of the main objectives to seek economic diversification, in order to reduce its dependence on the game industry through the development of new sectors. And these are integrated tourism and leisure, traditional Chinese and Big Health medicine, modern financial services, high and new technology, conventions, exhibitions, sports and commerce.
But the appeal of the casinos is unavoidable, such as the families of Shanghai and Xi'an have highlighted. The day after the Macao Historic Zone tour, the visit to the region would continue in the modern resorts of the game concentrated in the Cotai zone, highlighting the double role of Macao as a gaming destination and cultural heritage.
 
Stamps celebrate heritage
The “Itinerary with World Heritage Stamps” has already begun, organized by the Cultural Institute (IC), which runs by the end of the year. Participants are invited to collect “commemorative stamps from 22 emblematic places of the world heritage”, designed by local illustrator Yolanda Kog. The initiative is part of the celebrations of the 20th anniversary of the registration of the Historic Center in the UNESCO World Heritage list. Each location has a stamp available, and after collecting at least four, residents and tourists will be able to participate in a draw at Lou Kau's house, the Mandarin House, in the ruins of São Paulo, in the Fortaleza da Guia and at the Preservation and Transmission Center of the Cultural Heritage of the Palace Museum. Booklets can be raised for free at one of the drawn places. Kog's drawings present “the urban landscape with artistic lines” and arouse “the good memories of residents who grew up with heritage buildings”, highlights the IC.
 
*Jing Wu, from Lusa agency. Edited text</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Denied recruitment of volunteers for concerts by Eason Chan</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/negado-recrutamento-de-voluntarios-para-concertos-de-eason-chan/</link><description>The entertainment company “Unusual Productions (China)”, an organizing entity of the six concerts of the Hong Kong Eason Chan singer, scheduled for next month in Macao, warned that information that is circulating on social networks about the recruitment of personnel and volunteers for these concerts is false. Eason Chan will act at the Cotai Arena between August 1 and 10, and tickets are already sold out. The “Unusual Productions” issued a clarification, which stated that it had noted advertising information, not issued by the company, which recently emerged on various online platforms, claiming the recruitment of workers and volunteers to the site of concerts. The company stressed that it has never resorted or in charge social networking platforms to do so. In addition, he added that all the staff recruited for these shows, which are part of the international digression “Fear &amp; Dreams World Tour”, was directly hired by the company as the main organizing entity, and signed contracts that clearly establish responsibilities. The organizer of the concerts called on to the public so that she does not easily believe in false information on the internet, avoiding unnecessary losses. It is recalled that last month, Macao authorities detected illegal workers in the concert of South Korean singer G-Dragon in Macao, having opened a process to investigate 68 non-residents involved.</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Public account balance exceeds 11 billion</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/saldo-das-contas-publicas-supera-11-mil-milhoes/</link><description>The central account of the administration of the MSAR registered a positive balance of 11.39 billion patacas at the end of June, which represents an increase of 40.3% compared to the first six months of 2024, according to data published on the Electronic Page of the Board of Finance Services (DSF). The amount of the balance registered until June exceeds 4.56 billion the expected value for the economic year of 2025 (6.83 billion). Still, according to DSF data, MSAR current revenues retreated 0.9% to about 52.84 billion patacas in the first half, in annual terms, marking a budget execution rate of 46.5%. Taxes on the game accounted for 86.5% of current revenues, reaching 45.26 billion, plus 1% in the annual variation and 48.6% of the expected total for 2025. Including current and capital revenues, public coffers registered the entry of 52.74 billion patacas by the end of June, less 0.8% in annual terms and 45.4% of the budgeted amount to the general calculation. of the year. In turn, current expenses fell 12% to 31.59 billion patacas, ie 36% of the budget for the entire year. Integrating capital expenses, public spending dropped 8.2% to 41.36 billion of patacas within one year, reaching a budget execution rate of 37.8%. The Administration Development and Development Expenses Plan (PIDDA) generated spending of almost 8.78 billion between January and June, which represents an annual rise of 3% and 44.4% of the budget amount to 2025. It is recalled that the Legislative Assembly of the MSAR approved a government proposal to increase by 2.86 billion in budget expenses, to reinforce social support. The review includes the creation of a subsidy, totaling 54,000 patacas, for children up to three years old, to raise the lowest birth in the world.</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2431/</link><description>Found dead in a hotel in Cotai
A man was found dead in a hotel room in Cotai on Saturday afternoon, the Judiciary Police (PJ) said. According to the preliminary investigation, no injuries were found caused by acts of violence or criminals. According to PJ it was a man of mid-aged, non-resident. Authorities will continue to investigate.
 
Defrauded Philippines complained in the MP
Twelve victims of the alleged case of false employment recently reported by the TDM filed a complaint with the prosecutor. After months without salary and working more than 12 hours a day, the Philippine citizens with Blue Card expect the investigation to continue after leaving Macao. The Directorate of Services for Laboral Affairs told the public station that it received complaints about missing salaries.
 
China prohibits treatment available in Macau
The National Health Commission has prohibited treatment for people with Alzheimer's which is available at Kiang Wu Hospital, reported TDM's Macau channel. So far, nine people have been operated, with the hospital ensuring that none had complications. Despite being widely applied to Chinese province hospitals, surgery has never had international recognition. It has now been prohibited on the continent, with the authorities to say that proofs about the safety and effectiveness of treatment are lacking. Kiang Wu did not respond directly to TDM if it will continue with treatment, but assured being aware.
 
MSA athlete Defronta Compatriotic in the USA
Macao athlete Zhu Yuling, who for several years represented China on table tennis, was found for the “United States Smash” tournament, which is part of the International Circuit of the sport. In the tournament final, Zhu will face Chinese Chen Yi, 17th worldwide.
 
Wide Green Zones in Largo de Santo Agostinho
The Institute for Municipal Affairs is improving and expanding green areas by an old tree in Largo de Santo Agostinho, so that its roots have enough space to grow. During the works, tree protection measures will be taken. The term of the work is about 22 business days and may be prolonged, the AMI said.</description><pubDate>2025-07-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy will pay “disproportionate price” with the satellite casinos closure</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/economia-pagara-preco-desproporcional-fecho-dos-casinos-satelite/</link><description>Unemployment, impact on game recipes and small and medium-sized business, affected bank sector-these may be a consequences of the closure of the satellite casinos, from the perspective of António Félix Pontes. The economist anticipated the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that "adverse economic effects will be fundamentally the significant destruction of thousands of jobs, the reduction of operational capacity and the offer of companies linked to the game." In short, it admits that the economy, in the short term, “will pay a price too high and disproportionate to achieve objectives of greater regulatory control and transformation of the game model of the game in Macao”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The reflexes of the closure, by the end of the year, of the 11 satellite casinos in the territory may affect several sectors of the local economy, according to the opinion of António Félix Pontes. The economist told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that, in general terms, the closure “causes material and immediate costs”, with a special prominence in employment, the recipes of the game and the small and medium-sized sector, “whose life has been deteriorating since the time of the pandemic, without being unveiled actions of effective and realistic support to them”.
"In the short term, the economy will pay a price too high and disproportionate to achieve objectives of greater regulatory control and transformation of the game model of the game in Macao, which, we are pragmatic, it is only possible to realize in the medium and long deadlines," he argues.
The issue of casinos-satellite workers is another of the concerns. "In fact, of these 11 satellite casinos, two have already been integrated into the casino-prince of one of the concessionaires, assuming that all its workers have moved to the latter." However, he says, "this may not mean that it will be the general rule, nor is it imposed by law, and why" why "for such omission."
Regarding the remaining nine satellite casinos, whose labor force should be around 5,000 workers, points out that "the situation may be full of uncertainties," even admitting that "if the decision of these entities is different from what happened with the above integration, the path of workers involved will almost inevitably be unemployment."
The problem of labor force may not be exhausted in the workers of these casinos, as Félix bridges indicates, “insofar as it constitutes only direct labor. It should be remembered that,“ in the orbit of satellite casinos, it gravitates huge small and medium-sized companies in and outside the spaces where the satellite casinos-cleaning companies, diverse stores, hospitality, hospitality are operating, operating, hospitality operating. Restaurants…-whose workers represent the indirect labor, which should not forget, ”he warns.
Considering that families will also be affected, the economist speaks of "mystery", since "no one has dared to present any feasible solution" to get employment to thousands of workers, from various sectors, from cleaning employees to those serving in restaurants. "
António Félix Pontes notes that the "negative effects" are not limited to the labor market. "Companies that depend on the activity of the satellite casinos have made financial commitments of diverse order they will have to honor -such as bank loans, salary and rent payment of places where they work -but, of course, they will only be able to do so if they have revenues," he says. Therefore, it admits that the future for these companies is "very dark."
In short, the short-term adverse economic effects will be fundamentally “the significant destruction of thousands of jobs, the reduction of operational capacity and the offer of game-related companies, the loss of certain market niches (VIP players), the difficulties that are very dependent on the activity of casinos satellites, the negative economic impact on the zones where they are They operate and the reduction in the revenues of concessionaires and government (game tax) ”.
With regard to reflexes in the bank sector, the economist considers it to be “natural” that the “domino effect” makes it feel. With unemployment, workers “will be coar of their salary” and the affected entrepreneurs “will no longer earn revenues due to the closure of their companies, so they will have a hard time repaying loans”.
In this scenario, he says, "banks will have to be provisions for evil credit, whose current level is already worrying, in particular, for certain financial institutions."
 
Transition period was “short”
Analyzing the reasons that were the basis of the decision of closing the satellite casinos, it recalls the legal basis that derives from the law that alters the 'legal regime of the exploration of fortune or unlucky casino', in which a period of transition of three years to the satellites, which ends on December 31, 2025. Flexibility, meeting the behavior of the local economy, which grows, but little and to various rhythms, depending on economic sectors, ”he said.
As for reasons of another order, long -term realization, they believe that they radiate aspects such as “reinforcement of supervision and control plus the game sector, by the imposition of the central government, and the concentration of activity by operators of greater magnitude”.
It also lists “decreased financial risks related to the activity of satellite casinos and their possible contagion to the financial sector and promoting a more-oriented business model of family tourism and leisure, thus contributing to the long-awaited economic diversification of masters”.
In his opinion, there should have been a "greater weighting and common sense" in order to have sought "a balance between social costs, in the short term, that the measure implies with the intended purpose, in the medium and long term."
Assuming that decision making previously “a cost-effective study must have been done, or in other words, about the advantages and inconvenience of this measure, in the economic, financial and social aspects (employment)”, Felix Pontes understands that if it happened, “in the name of transparency”, it should be of public knowledge, “even to avoid any incorrections in analysis”.
In conclusion, it speaks of the challenge that dealers will face in the future, stressing that the main concern will be to recover and, “eventually, to overcome” the recipes that their satellite casinos have been providing them. "Will they, or not, have a capacity of it?"</description><pubDate>2025-07-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Case Epstein infuriates the foundations of Trump's Maga Movement</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/caso-epstein-enfurece-bases-movimento-maga-de-trump/</link><description>The basis of Donald Trump's Maga Movement is standing up after the government tried to discredit the dozens of conspiracy theories around Jeffrey Epstein, one of the most fervent followers of the US President.
Trump's Department of Justice and the FBI concluded, in a report published Monday by the American website Axios, which Epstein had no “customer list” and ruled out that the former financial financially accused of running a minor sex trafficking network, has blackmailed powerful figures. They also confirmed that Epstein committed suicide in a prison in New York, which dismantles one of the theories he maintains that he was murdered.
This report is the first done by the Trump administration about the case and the first that rejects the main conspiracy theories around the figure and death of the former financial, promoted by figures from the American right. The two highest -ranked FBI employees endorsed these theories before being appointed by Trump for the current positions.
The reaction was rapid and brutal by the foundations of his movement “Make America Great Again” (Maga, “Making America Big”), which promotes the theory that the “deep state” would be protecting prominent figures from all sectors - especially from the Democratic and Hollywood party - which would have bonds with Epstein.
"The next department of justice will say is," In fact, Jeffrey Epstein didn't even exist, "Alex Jones, Trump's faithful follower. “This is extremely unhealthy,” he continued.
Trump managed to channel part of the fury of his own base against FBI director Kash Patel and his deputy Dan Bongino.
Another quite affected figure was the Attorney General Pam Bondi, who had stated before the publication of the report that had the list of Epstein customers on his table and would publish the whole truth about the case. Statements that had the support of the White House.
Bondi was already in the sights of the Maga Movement after distributing tagged folders like “Epstein files” to influencers in the White House - folders that contained mostly public information and no new revelation.
"Trump should fire [Bondi] for lying to his base and being a dead weight for his administration," he published in X the influencer of far-right Laura Lomer. "She is a shame and does nothing to help Trump."
"This is what happens when you and the people around you become the same 'deep state' that they have been attacking," wrote CNN analyst Chris Cillizza in his bulletin in "Substack."
Epstein committed suicide in a prison of New York in 2019 after being accused of sexual trafficking.
Trump, who denies being in the mansion of the American virgin islands where, according to prosecutors, Epstein prostituted minors, said during the campaign that he would have no "problem" in making public the files related to the case public.
The president closed his face on Tuesday when a journalist asked him about the Epstein case during a meeting of his office. "Are you still talking about Jeffrey Epstein?… People still talk about this kind, disgusting? It's unbelievable," said Trump.
This is just one of the schisms that in recent hours seem to divide Trump's support base. Another is the republican's decision to resume the supply of weapons to Ukraine.
Maga's most isolation wing was already disappointed since the president's order to attack Iran and the announcement of softening operations against immigrants.
This new scam to the principles of the magician endangers some supports to Trump and feeds the path of the newly created party by billionaire Elon Musk, who from faithful squire began to rival the Republican because of federal spending.
At the height of the attack of attacks last month, Musk stated that Trump appears in the Epstein archives. "What time is it? Ah, see, it's time for no one to be arrested once again!," Musk wrote on Monday, accompanied by the image of a scoring scoring with the title "The Official Placard of Jeffrey Epstein pedophilia prisons."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-07-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>