<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Driver scarcity affects between 30 and 40 new black taxis</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/escassez-de-condutores-afecta-entre-30-40-novos-taxis-pretos/</link><description>Although the 500 new black taxis are in operation, between 30 and 40 of these vehicles cannot work fully due to the lack of drivers, said the director of the taxi driver mutual assistance association, pointing out that the sector will need dozens of taxi drivers to reverse this scenario. According to Tony Kuok, the situation is, among other factors, with the retirements of about 200 taxi drivers since the beginning of this year
 
All 500 new black taxis are already in operation. However, the number of taxi drivers to work with these vehicles “did not reach the 1,000”, a level considered reasonable. Consequently, between 30 and 40 new taxis have not been able to circulate at night or even for a few days, Tony Kuok, director of the Macao taxi conductors' mutual aid association, noted.
"The lack of taxi drivers is a problem that the sector has recently registered. Dozens of taxi drivers should be hired to satisfy the search," said Tony Kuok, in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao.
According to the associative leader, the problem derives, on the one hand, a vacancy of taxi drivers, especially drivers over 60, due to limited physical conditions. Since the beginning of this year, about 200 taxi drivers have been retired, Tony Kuok has revealed.
The associative leader said, on the other hand, that some young people tried to work in the sector only one or two days, however, they ended up giving up, considering that it is an inappropriate profession for them. "Young people care about the margin of profit in the sector, and the business situation is currently not very good. In addition, young drivers have many options, and can drive public buses, who already jobs to many of them, or work with dual or commercial vehicles," he described.
According to the same responsible, “a taxi driver can earn about 20,000 patacas per month if he works 10 hours daily with a day off a week”.
On the other hand, the association led by Tony Kuok plans to present to the public next month, a mobile application that will allow taxi drivers to accept customer orders and vice versa. However, the application only works in Chinese language, due to the issue of costs.
According to it, the Association will contact the management of services for traffic issues (DSAT), in order to ask the body for help to disclose the application, as well as for the connection of the “app” to the online payment system and other functions.
 
“Technological Solutions” to increase taxis occupation
However, in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Zheng Anting, DSAT has ruled out a direct relationship between the mileage traveled by taxis and the overall transportation capacity of the sector. According to DSAT, the reduction in the kilometer traveled by taxis is associated not only with changing residents' travel habits, but also to the tendency of the sector to privilege passengers waiting in taxi squares, in order to reduce unnecessary courses and, consequently, fuel costs, among other factors.
At this point, DSAT reported that, comparing the pandemic period in 2021 with the time of greatest affluence during this year's holidays and festivities, it is found that the number of taxis in operation was similar. At the same time, in the same temporal interval, the average mileage per vehicle rose about 35% and the average volume of transactions registered an increase in the order of 65%.
With the aim of increasing taxi occupancy rates and global transportation capacity, DSAT has ensured that “it will take as a reference to abroad experiences, studying the application of various technological solutions to support the sector in improving passenger transportation”. To this end, he also emphasized that "viable suggestions are welcome from the taxi and the public sector."
In the same answer, DSAT also stressed that, since the entry into force of the new taxi law in 2019, there was a significant reduction in the number of infringements compared to the period prior to the implementation of this diploma. In any case, it has ensured that it will continue to oversee the operation of companies in the legal terms, with a view to ensuring a quality taxi passenger transport service.
 
New Association of Taxi drivers promises to bet on training
The San Ieng Taxi Workers Association of Macau was recently created, whose objective is to “establish a professional service image” through training. According to it, the association will form black taxis drivers to be able to provide online marking services. After this stage, it will launch in the “Mass Plus” application a “exclusive access” to Taxis Black, with free immediate call services to about 400 vehicles. Currently, the association has 500 members, but aims to reach 2,000, including taxi drivers and other workers in the sector.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sands China profit fell 32% in the 1st quarter in annual terms</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lucro-da-sands-china-caiu-32-1o-trimestre-em-termos-anuais/</link><description>Between January and March, Sands China recorded net profits of 1.6 billion patacas, with revenues to decrease in homologous terms. "The results of the first trimester of Sands were undeniably weak in all aspects," noted the investment bank JP Morgan. Robert Goldstein, CEO of the Las Vegas Sands group, announced that Londoner's second phase of remodeling is ready, with rooms being already available and at a time when the operator prepares for the Golden Week of May
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Sands China ended the first quarter accounts with net profits of US $ 202 million (1.6 billion patacas to the current exchange rate), translating into a 32% break in annual terms. The data were announced yesterday by the majority shareholder, Las Vegas Sands.
Between January and March, results before interest, taxes, amortization and depreciation (EBITDA) also fell 12.3% annually to $ 535 million (4.3 billion patacas). "The low retention of mobile assets in Macao negatively impacted the adjusted EBITDA of properties by $ 10 million," the group said in a statement.
In the same line, the data also reveals that Sands China net revenues recorded a 5.7% decrease in the same period last year, having set $ 1.7 billion (13.5 billion).
"The results of the first trimester of Sands were undeniably weak in all respects, with a persistent loss of market share and low margins: in fact, the lowest in approximately two years," noted the investment bank JP Morgan.
Venetian Macau saw net revenues fall 17.3% to $ 638 million, including a 22.4% decrease in casino revenues to 495 million, with EBITDA adjusted to a break from 28.3% to 225 million. Nevertheless, the margin of Ebitda was 35.3%. Londoner's revenues, too, decreased from 5.9% to $ 529 million, while Sands Macao saw revenues retreat to $ 75 million. Parisian revenues remained stable (227 million), while The Plaza Macao and Four Seasons recorded a 46.5% increase in net revenues to $ 208 million.
“In Macao, although market growth has slowed down at the present juncture, our decades commitment to make investments that increase the attraction of Macao business and leisure tourism and support its development as a world center of business and leisure tourism positions us well for future growth,” said Robert Goldstein, president and CEO of Las Vegas Sands.
Goldstein also indicated that Londoner's second phase, with an investment of $ 1.2 billion, is practically completed. "Despite the challenging macro environment, The Londoner is now fully open," he said, adding that Sands is preparing for the approaching golden week of May. In total there are 2,405 rooms and suites. The weakened financial performance of the operator in the last 12 months was justified with the renewal being carried out.
Las Vegas Sands, which has operations in Macau and Singapore, closed the first three months of the year with global net profits of $ 352 million, 28.7% in homologous terms, but an increase of 8.6% in quarterly terms. Revenue has risen to 2.86 million, a 3.3% increase over the same period last year, but a 1.2% break in sequential terms.
In Singapore, net revenues increased by 0.4% in homologous terms to just over $ 1.16 billion. Adjusted EBITDA rose 1.3%, reaching 605 million. Casinos' revenues, in turn, fell 0.2%to 857 million.
However, Las Vegas Sands decided not to participate in a bidding process for up to three casino licenses in the south of the state of New York. The decision was announced by Patrick Dumont, president and director of operations of the group, following the announcement of the company's first quarter profits.
"We believe the best use of our capital in the short term is to buy Las Vegas Sands and Sands China actions," he said. "Consequently, Las Vegas Sands decided not to run for a casino license in New York," he added. It is recalled that Dumont will assume the position of president and CEO of Las Vegas Sands in March next year, as Goldstein will leave the current positions on March 1, 2026.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>EPM is still awaiting replacement of funds from the Portuguese government</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/epm-ainda-aguarda-reposicao-de-verba-governo-portugues/</link><description>Portugal's Minister of State and Foreign Affairs, Paulo Rangel (C), during the visit to the Portuguese School of Macau, in Macau, China, March 28, 2025. Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro/Lusa



The Portuguese School of Macao is still waiting for the Portuguese government to transfer the money it has decided to assign, as replacement of the amounts that had been cut before. The president of the EPM Foundation told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that “the school does not want to be rich”, but it is certain that the increase announced by Lisbon has not yet arrived. In a reaction to the decree-law approved by the Government of Portugal, which will extend the support to all teachers of basic and secondary education that teach in Portuguese public schools abroad, Jorge Neto Valente recalls that the EPM is not covered by these supports
 
Victor Rebelo*
 
The announcement of the replacement of the amounts attributed by the Government of Portugal to the Portuguese School of Macao (EPM), made when traveling to the territory of the Minister of Foreign Affairs, has not yet had practical effects. Under the Lisbon decision, EPM will take advantage of more than one million euros for the school's expenses, against the 776,000 it has received in recent years.
A month after this announcement made by Paulo Rangel on the visit to the MSAR, the money has not yet entered the coffers of the EPM Foundation. "The increase is no longer bad and the school does not want to be rich, the problem is that the minister approved in March an increase and so far I have not seen money," Jorge Neto Valente, the Jorge Neto Valente, told the Tribuna de Macao newspaper.
Holding 51% of the EPM Foundation's capital, the successive governments of Portugal reduced to 10% the contribution to the expenses of the school, from the time of the Troika, in 2014, a situation that caused some dissatisfaction in school leaders.
It is recalled that in statements to journalists, during a reception to the Portuguese community last March, the Minister of Foreign Affairs stated that funding is again “at legal levels”, which is the first time “after 11 years”, considering that there was no reason to have the cut.
However, commenting on the approval of a decree-law that widens the support to all teachers of basic and secondary education who, from next school year, teach in Portuguese schools abroad (EPE), Jorge Neto Valente stressed that this type of supports “does not apply to Macao”, since the EPM is completely different from others.
"The remaining schools abroad are fully supported by the Portuguese State Budget, which pays everything, including residence, travel, family subsidies, as if the teachers were employees in Portugal," he said, stressing, on the other hand, that those who support the EPM "are the students, with their bribes, the parents and the Macao government."
According to a statement issued at the end of the Council of Ministers, all teachers placed in the EPE next school year will receive support for installation and return, trip and return to the country where they are placed, at the beginning and cessation of functions, for the teacher and family aggregate, annual trip to the teacher and family aggregate, health insurance for their own household, support for the cost of residence, which will have the country where the teachers are in the country where the teachers are. placed ”.
Asked by Lusa, the Ministry of Education, Science and Innovation indicated that the measure aims to “ensure equity between basic and secondary education teachers who teach in the public school EPE”, since “there are currently very popular situations between teachers from different schools, since the supports provided for teachers in statutory mobility are not applied to teachers of the boards and contracted teachers”.
The changes, which come into force next school year, were subject to trade union negotiation, following the government's review of its proposal. Teachers who in the current school year have been placed in an EPE and who are maintained in their school next school will receive compensation equivalent to six months of support for the cost of the residence, by verifying changes in the cost of living.
The government approved supports and supplements to these teachers, such as support for installation and return, equivalent to double the value of the cost of the cost of the residence, paid with the first and last remuneration, health insurance for the teacher and their household, a permanence prize for four years of continuous functions, paid once, the following month to have completed the four years, equivalent to the base remuneration. The descendants of these teachers are now exempt from enrollment, bribes and other expenses due to school attendance.
A trip and return trip to the country to perform functions, at the beginning and cessation of functions, for the teacher and the members of their household, who can be made on different dates and a trip from first to Portugal and return to the country for the exercise of the functions, for each calendar year to perform functions in the beginning or the crashing of functions, for the members of their aggregate, which may be dates, which may be dates, which may be dates that may be in dates that may be distinct, were also contemplated.
Regarding support for the cost of the residence, paid 12 months, it varies depending on “the cost of living, the level of risk and unhealthiness”, being in Angola, Brazil and Mozambique of 2,700 euros (director), 2,200 euros (subdirector) and 1,850 euros (teaching staff). In Cape Verde and Timor-Leste the defined values ​​are 2,200 euros (director), 1,800 euros (subdirector) and 1,500 euros (teaching staff). In Sao Tome the director will receive 2,200 euros and the 1,800 euros subdirector, while teaching staff will receive 1,350 euros.
Regarding teachers placed in this school year, compensation will be 11,100 euros (Angola, Brazil and Mozambique), 9,000 euros (Cape Verde and Timor) and 8,100 euros (Sao Tome).
The government has defined that, to "ensure the commitment, continuity and return on public investment, teachers will have to work for two consecutive years at the school where they are placed." "Teachers who do not fulfill this obligation will have to return to school the paid funds, to date, to support the place of work at the workplace, except for reasons of force majeure or fact not attributable to the teacher. It still loses the right to payment of support for the return trip to Portugal, and to the members of their household," said the Ministry of Education, Science and Innovation.
The approved decree also determines that teachers placed in an EPE linked to the staff of schools, undressed school or pedagogical zone board, maintain their place of origin, for a period of four years.
 
*With Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Coloane protection work completed in 2027</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/obra-de-proteccao-contra-inundacoes-em-coloane-concluida-em-2027/</link><description>It is pointed out to August 2027 the completion of the flood protection and drainage work in the marginal zone on the west of Coloane, which includes the construction of 1,200 meter dikes
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The flood protection and drainage protection work in the west of Coloane west, including the dikes, which is in the hands of state company Nam Kwong Union Commercial and Industrial, limited, will be completed in August 2027. At least this is the forecast advanced by the Directorate of Public Works (DSOP).
The deadline for construction is 710 days of work, including a mandatory first goal of 90 days, being the second of 490 working days. The contract will cost about 566 million patacas.
Remember that this project has generated controversy and there were already those who opposed the construction of the 1,200 long dikes. Urbanist Lam Iek Chit has been afraid that construction can “violate the administrative regulation [classification of Lai Chi Vun shipyards as a site and fixation of their protection zone] and the cultural heritage safeguard law”, but there are also concerns about the possibility of impacting the animals that inhabit that marine area, specifically Chinese white dolphins.
DSOP's director, Lam Wai Hou, guaranteed, in response to an interpellation of Deputy Ron Lam, that, in the study and elaboration of the general plan of the protection work, “the opinions of the competent services and the urban planning council were consulted”. At the same time, the plan was presented to Coloane's residents and associations, as well as to the Islands Community Services Advisory Board and “opinions were collected”.
It also assured that environmental impact assessment works were developed, “including air assessment, noise, waste and marine environment and the elaboration of mitigation measures and the necessary inspection plan”. In this sense, it also mentioned that the environmental evaluation requirements are part of the documentation of the work competition, “in order to ensure strict compliance with the contractor's provisions in the execution”.
The work is located from the northern end of Lai Chi Vun Té to the downstream area of ​​the Tam Kong temple, covering the surroundings of Avenida de Outubroe de Coloane, Rua dos Navegantes, Coloane's pier and Lai Chi Vun Naval Shipyards. The work has already begun, which includes the construction of flood prevention dikes, floodgates for the passage of water and provisional watershed station.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Rome in “State of Site” for Pope Funeral</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/roma-em-estado-de-sitio-para-funeral-papa/</link><description>EPA12049866 Members of the Public Line Up To Pay Their respects to Late Pope Francis As He Lies in State Inside Saint Peter's Basilica, Vatican City, 23 April 2025. Faithful and Well-Wishers will be able to Pay Their Thes to Pope Francis, Who Died On 21 April 2025, AGED 88, Until His Funeral On 26 April in the Plaza in Front of the Basilica.  EPA/ALESSANDRO DI MEO



The city of Rome is on a state of alert due to Pope Francis' funeral, scheduled for tomorrow. Hundreds of thousands of faithful and political figures from around the world are expected in the eternal city for the last goodbye to the Argentine Pontiff, who died on Monday at the age of 88.
Known for its chaotic traffic and saturated infrastructure, the Italian capital faces weeks of intense activity that will extend to the conclave in May, in which the cardinals will choose the new Pope. The Logistic Security Challenge is colossal, as it is estimated to arrive in between 150 and 170 foreign delegations, including leaders such as US President Donald Trump, the leaders of Brazil and Argentina, Lula da Silva and Javier Milei, the kings of Spain and Belgium, as well as Prince William.
Since Wednesday, with the arrival of the coffin to the Basilica of St. Peter, the Italian authorities have completely closed access to the Vatican and adjacent streets, and implemented strict security controls. In total, about 2,000 agents are permanently highlighted in the area.
In addition, an air exclusion zone on Rome will operate 24 hours a day and anti-drug units have been imposed with signal interference systems to avoid suspicious activities. Combat aircraft are warned to intervene, if necessary, and elite shooters have been strategically positioned on roofs along the “Via Della Conciliazione” and the Gianicolo hill, while police helicopters constantly flee the historic center of Rome.
Italian civil protection also plays a crucial role in the operation. According to the agency, between 2,000 and 2,500 volunteers will be mobilized to help the faithful who go to St. Peter's Square. In addition, about 500 doctors and nurses, along with ambulances, will be available in the area thanks to the coordination with the Lazio region.
Although it is impossible to predict the exact number of participants, the authorities estimate the presence of at least 250,000 believers, similar to that of Pope Benedict XVI's funeral in 2023.
Between 11 am on Wednesday and 1 pm yesterday (19:00 in Macao), at least 61,000 people had already passed the central nave of the imposing Baroque Basilica to say goodbye to the Argentine Jesuit, according to the Vatican press.
 
Cardinal Zen authorized to go to the Vatican
Cardinal Joseph Zen, Bishop Emeritus of Hong Kong, was allowed to leave the territory to watch the Pope's funeral at the Vatican, the Associated Press said. 93-year-old Zen left Hong Kong on Wednesday night after filing a court order to recover his passport, his secretary told AP. Authorities confiscated their passport to Zen after being temporarily detained under the National Security Act. On Tuesday, Zen issued a criticism of the Vatican, questioning why pre-competition meetings began on that day.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Plan “An Event, Two Locations” promoted in Seoul and Tokyo</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/plano-um-evento-dois-locais-promovido-em-seul-toquio/</link><description>IPIM representatives moved to South Korea and Japan, on a trip to promote the convention and exhibition industry of MSAR and Hengqin
 
A team from the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM) visited South Korea and Japan, with the aim of capturing investments and promoting the advantages of Macao and Hengqin to hold conventions and exhibitions.
In Seoul, IPIM responsible presented the policies and advantages of conducting conventions and exhibitions in Macau and Hengqin to representatives of local companies. According to the institute, some participating organizations stated that “Macao has world -class convention and exhibition facilities” and showed interest in conducting “in the near future” academic seminars.
During the visit to Tokyo, the IPIM delegation met with the Chinese Commerce Chamber in Japan, the Japan franchise association and local companies, in an attempt to attract “conventions and exhibitions of different types for Macao and Hengqin” and promote proper diversification of the economy and the “synergotic development between the convention and exhibition sector and their industries”.
The “An Event, Two Locations” model from Macau and Hengqin has aroused the interest of some local companies representatives, who expect to visit Macau and Hengqin “to evaluate support hardware facilities” and “explore the viability of organizing convention and exhibition events”, according to IPIM.
Representatives of local companies also expressed “the hope of establishing a narrower partnership” with Macau and Hengqin, in order to achieve a “advantage complementarity” and “coordinated development”.
IPIM has visited several companies from Big Health, Commerce and Services, including some renowned local brands. According to the body, the head of a famous company stated that the IPIM's visit resulted in “deeper knowledge about the previous requirements for the realization of projects in Macau and Hengqin”, having clarified the technical issues faced by his company.
Citing the same responsible, the note also points out that “the clearest understanding of the relevant procedures involved in the operation and the latest commercial information in Macao” helps brands to accelerate the expansion of their business in Macau and Hengqin. The company in question even plans to “enjoy the Macao platform” to enter the interior markets of China and Lusophone countries.
In recent years, IPIM has visited countries such as Singapore, Germany, Saudi Arabia, among others, in order to promote the internationalization of the convention and exhibition industry and the advantages of the “an event, two locations” model, with industrial projects and quality companies.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Consumer Council makes a “bridge” between Shanghai and Lusophone countries</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/conselho-de-consumidores-faz-ponte-entre-xangai-paises-lusofonos/</link><description>Macao and the municipality of Shanghai will reinforce cooperation on consumer disputes, including connecting organizations from consumers from Portuguese -speaking countries. In addition, consumer advice from Macau and Shenzhen promised to join efforts to create a “consumer environment with honesty”
 
The Macao Consumer Council (CC) and the Shangoi Consumer Rights and Interest Board extended an agreement entered into in June 2020, with a view to intensifying cooperation in the treatment of consumer disputes and sharing information and resources. During an online meeting, the two organisms decided to expand the role of the CC as a platform for consumer conflict reemption between Shanghai consumer organizations and Lusophone countries, as well as creating a mechanism for transfronight mediation and arbitration cooperation, says a CC note.
Both parties will cooperate in the promotion of consumer “confidence symbols” and Macao and Shanghai companies, in order to encourage consumers to cultivate “green, low -carbon, and environmentally friendly concepts and habits”.
During the meeting, CC president Leong Pek San stressed that Macau and Shanghai have maintained a good collaboration in the protection of consumer rights and interests, and will “explore more innovative cooperation modes, raise the effectiveness of transpassioning rights and foster honesty in the exploitation of activities of commercial sectors”.
Recently, CC representatives also visited the Shenzhen Consumer Council to deepen cooperation in the creation of a “consumer environment with honesty” in the Great Bay. Like cooperation with consumer organizations in the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin and Zhuhai, through mechanisms such as the “certified store”, CC intends to cooperate with Shenzhen in the area of ​​“reliable consumption”. Future measures were discussed about strengthening work to protect the rights and interests of consumers of both regions, according to a press release.
In recent years, consumer organizations in Macau and Shenzhen have developed several joint projects, including “joint comparative tests of various products” or the organization of various “consumer experimentation activities” to offer more information to consumers.
The Cooperation Agreement with the Shenzhen Consumer Council, entered into in 2019, allowed to establish a “green pathway” with the intention of “facilitating the treatment of consumer conflicts that take place between the residents of these two places”, fostering exchange and collaboration in consumer rights defense work.
This year, works will be developed and will intensify the exchange between students of the two zones “Consumer Experimentation Activities”, said the CC, without advance details.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IPIM wants companies listed to increase 20% in the MSAR</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ipim-quer-empresas-listadas-aumentem-20-na-raem/</link><description>This year, IPIM will try to have the number of companies listed on the scholarship established in Macau to increase 20%, the body president pointed out, hoping that they will provide more than 1,000 job openings. On the other hand, according to the substitute president of the monetary authority, in the first quarter of this year, another 5.6 billion of Patacas were awarded by the banks in the context of “interest only, without the amortization of capital”
 
The Institute for Commerce and Investment Promotion (IPIM) will boost more companies listed on the scholarship and high quality to invest in Macau. The aim is that they increase 20% this year, and that they bring more than 1,000 job openings to the territory, said yesterday Vincent U, in a program of "or Mun Tin Toi".
In the context of conventions and exhibitions, the president of IPIM stressed that the body will seek to reach a 15% increase in the number of exhibitors and international commercial visitors. In addition, he stressed that, so far, 490 students have obtained professional exhibition certifications, while more than 330 people have enrolled for seven exhibition training programs that started this year.
The Chinese Language Radio Program was also attended by Henrietta Lau, Substitute President of the Monetary Authority Board (AMCM), who took the opportunity to reveal that, in the first quarter of this year, banks attributed more loans, in an amount of 5.6 billion patacas, as part of the “payment only, without capital amortization”. This measure was extended after negotiations between AMCM and the bank sector.
The same person said that a subsidy for obligations issuing costs will be studied, as well as the scope of the “Easy Transfer” services. He also highlighted the intention of optimizing the Macao Securities Deposit Center in phased, concluding the construction of the Central Digital Pataca System, as well as establishing a long -term training mechanism for financial talent.
In turn, Yau Yun Wah, director of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), said that, in general, the situation of Macao's economy remains stable. According to it, launched on April 14, the consumer draw for the activity “Flora Fête With Sanrio Characters” in the North Zone, generated an amount of consumption of over 50 million patacas in the first week and 3,100 gifts were offered.
On the other hand, the results of an inquiry related to this activity show that 82% of respondents extended the time of stay in the North Zone and 75% spent more money in that area. Arguing that this proves that it is feasible to promote the development of community neighborhoods through the intellectual property economy, Yau Yun Wah said that the government will make similar attempts to revitalize other community neighborhoods in the future.
In addition, he revealed that he will launch, in the second half of this year, a consumer program with discounts on community neighborhoods, intended for tourists who buy concert tickets on platforms in the interior of China. Also in the second semester, DSEDT will launch a subsidy to support local pharmaceutical companies to obtain a certificate of good medicine manufacturing practices.
 
Science and Technology with reinforced support
For its part, Che Weng Keong, president of the Fund for the Development of Science and Technology (FDCT), found that 90% of the fund's expenses are intended to support scientific investigations from higher education and staff institutions. He said, the amount approved to support science and technology companies registered a homologous increase of more than 70% last year.
The president of FDCT believes that the enthusiasm of the companies in scientific research "has increased significantly" in recent years, while the model of "research in Macao, transformation into hengqin" "has gained shape". About the current year, he stressed that the fund will increase funding for existing scientific research platforms and cooperation with abroad in science and technology, as well as support the establishment of new scientific research and research platforms.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Young people encouraged to convey spirit of May 4</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jovens-incentivados-transmitir-espirito-4-de-maio/</link><description>Youth education and development services are preparing a flag raising ceremony and a series of commemorative activities of the 106th anniversary of the May 4 movement
 
In celebration of the 106th anniversary of the May 4 movement, the Macao Polytechnic University Polydestive Pavilion (UPM) will host the “Ceremony of the National Flag Shipping by the Macao School Sector on Youth Day”, on the morning of the commemorative date. The Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) will organize the flag and a series of activities, in conjunction with over 90 associations.
The initiative aims to deepen “the understanding of young people and students about the historical significance and contemporary value of the May 4 movement,” according to DSEDJ. The flag raising will be in charge of a team with students from three higher education institutions and 36 MSAR secondary schools.
The work “Xian Xinghai and the Yellow River Song”, created by the Conservatory of Macao and the students of the Luso-Chinese technical-professional school, which combines theater, music and dance in celebration of Xian Xinghai's 120th anniversary, will be carried out. The Ilha Verde Secondary School of the Macao Commercial Association, in turn, will present the “Chinese Spirit” dance show, with the participation of representatives of Macao students and young people.
Experts, academics and sector personalities will also be guests to discuss “Macao Youth Mission and Future Development in the“ May 4 ”transmission and innovation process”, read in the statement.
As part of the festivities, there will be a postcard design and coloring contest, an online question and answers game, lectures on May 4 in various schools, visits to the cities of the Great Bay and Hengqin and activities on scientific exploitation and professional career, among others.
DSEDJ hopes that young people will “respond with actions” to President Xi Jinping's exhortation, in the transmission of the spirit of May 4 and “promoting the construction of a strong country and national rejuvenation”, contributing to “the performance of the role of good young people in the New Age” and to become a “vital force” in the construction of mashes and China.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mangais may be the solution to the bad-headed problem</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mangais-podem-ser-solucao-para-problema-mau-cheiro/</link><description>The direction of environmental protection services plans to take some measures to reduce the problem of Coloane's bads. One of the solutions may go through the mangrove plantation as a form of ecological recovery. On the other hand, the gradual publication of more environmental data will be studied and considered
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The odor treatment system of Coloane's wastewater treatment plant is being optimized during the modernization works, which began in March this year. At this stage, the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) plans to gradually enhance the situation of the intertidal zone (Mudflat) to improve the smell problem through ecological recovery measures such as mangroad planting.
According to DSPA, after the completion of the work, about 65,000 cubic meters of wastewater treated per day will fulfill the highest standard-level I-A-of the national standard “Standards of pollutant emission by wastewater treatment stations, in rustic and urban areas (GB 18918-2002)”. Part of the highly treated wastewater will be used in the medium and long term as a tributary of Coloane's recycled water station.
In a written interplies, Deputy Ron Lam had asked the government that, “taking into account recent public health incidents, increased torrential rainfall and increased environmental protection needs”, proceed with the revision of criteria related to drinking water quality, wastewater and torrential rainfall, “in order to meet the latest needs in public health, environmental protection and relief of climatic heating”.
DSPA ensures that it has been optimizing the infrastructures and equipment of the WWTP, "proceeding to modernize those that gather adequate conditions to raise the quality of the effluent to more demanding standards."
In the text signed by the director, IP Kuong Lam, the body states that it continues to oversee the operational data of environmental infrastructure, “in order to ensure that its operation corresponds to the established requirements”, as well as publishing the data through the Macao Environment Report and the Macau Geo-Environmental Information Page, “continually improving content published on the information platform”.
In the future, it also intends to “study and consider the gradual publication of more environmental data, periodically or in real time, depending on the development of relevant analysis technologies”.
Through the monitoring of the operation data of the Coloane WWTP, the sending of staff to inspect the facilities, the performance of effluent quality, as well as the renewal, replacement, repair and maintenance of obsolete equipment, DSPA ensures that the respective effluent corresponds to the needs of recycled water treatment facilities.
Addressing the Macao Peninsula WWTP, the response to Ron Lam points out that “chemically assisted primary treatment stations and retention plates in the biological aqual tank were successively installed, with a view to continuously improving the quality of the effluent”, adding that the land currently occupied by this WWTP construction will be reserved for the construction of pre-treatment installations. residuals, which will work in coordination with the new artificial island WWTP in the future. ”
On the other hand, and citing the direction of soil services and urban construction, DSPA indicates that “efforts are being taught” so that the revision of Macao's wastewater and drainage regulation is completed by 2025.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Caeal assures that civil servants will have time to vote</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/caeal-assegura-funcionarios-publicos-terao-tempo-para-votar/</link><description>Responding to the appeal made by the Macao Public Function Workers Association so that those responsible for services and companies facilitate employee participation in the September legislative elections, the Electoral Affairs Commission ensures that civil servants “will not have their voting rights harmed by the work”. CAEAL will appeal, “at the appropriate time”, recalling those responsible for public departments and companies the compliance with this legal provision
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Public officials wishing to vote in the elections for the Legislative Assembly “will not have their right to be harmed by work,” said the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal), in response to a letter delivered by the Macao Public Function Association (ATFPM).
Once an informative session on the candidacy procedures for the 8th Legislative Assembly elections, ATFPM members have appealed, through the massive, to be implemented “clear guidelines to ensure that civil servants (such as health professionals) and security forces voters have enough time (at least two hours) to vote on election day”.
The objective is, in the opinion of the ATFPM, "to allow all civil servants to also fulfill their civic duties, avoiding complaints about the impossibility of voting due to lack of time, as occurred in previous elections."
In the response, Caeal states that, according to article 96 of the Electoral Law for the Legislative Assembly, those responsible for the services and companies that have to be in activity on the day of the election "should make it easier to vote for their workers." To this end, “CAEAL will appeal, at the appropriate time, remembering those responsible for public departments and companies the compliance with this legal provision”.
According to the answer, civil servants will not have their voting rights harmed by the work. "All employees, especially those who are in service on election day, will be able to exercise their electoral right, addressing their respective voting places to fulfill their civic duty," said CAEAL, cited by ATFPM.
In the informative session, organized by Caeal, together with the commissioner against corruption, the electoral procedures of this edition were explained in detail, requiring all candidacy groups to campaign within the legality.
The elections for the Legislative Assembly will take place on September 14.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau coach takes Rangers to the title of under-23 in Hong Kong</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/treinador-de-macau-leva-rangers-ao-titulo-de-sub-22-em-hong-kong/</link><description>Paulo Conde, element of the Rangers coaching staff of the 1st Hong Kong division, became champion in the under-23 category. The former Elite League player is the first coach from Macau in Raehk's football history, having debuted in the season that now ends. The physical part of the club states that the sport in the neighboring territory is “many holes above Macao”, with “exceptional” conditions for the development of the sport



















Victor Rebelo
 
As with most countries or regions of the world, Hong Kong has been developing football with the introduction of a U22 championship, mandatory for clubs participating in the 1st Division, entitled “Premier League”. One of these teams, Rangers, has just become champion of that level, and one of the elements of the technical staff is from Macau.
Paulo Conde, specializing in the physical issue of athletes, works with the entire Rangers squad, including under 22 years. "The training is the same, but the U22 play midweek for their own and very competitive championship, while the main formation makes their challenges on Saturday or Sunday at the Premier League," he told the newspaper Tribuna Demacau.
At the age of 57, the "fitness coach" sees the reality of Hong Kong football at a level that "has nothing to do with Macau", regretting that the sirers are not able to implement what exists around the world, that is, a proof between B or Sub 22/23 formations.
"It is a pity that this does not happen in Macau, because only then is it possible to have a quality improvement of players and teams," says Paulo Conde, for whom the sport in the neighboring territory is "many holes above Macao", so "the creation of this U22 championship in the MSAR, since there are not enough fields".
Comparing the facilities on one side and the other, it states that "only for the U22 championship, Hong Kong has more than two dozen fields available, so a huge difference."
Speaking of its specific area, physical training, Paulo Conde stresses that "there is no athlete who can reach high levels of performance if he does not have adequate physical preparation," adding that "many famous coaches, such as Josep Guardiola, Carlo Ancelotti, among others, have said that the physical part assumes an importance of 80% in the performance of a player, while the technical question only 20%."
It gives as an example Cristiano Ronaldo, that "because of physical work over the years, he is still playing at a good level at 40 and, apparently, will renew for another two years with the Saudi Arabia Al-Nassr."
The part of nutrition is also considered by the coach as “fundamental” in the development of an athlete, “and it is this concern that I also have with my players, which has given good results,” he asserts.
Now that the U22 season has finished Rangers' main formation, which has three Brazilians, two Ghanais and one Israelite, points to the Hong Kong Cup final, playing against Eastern on May 31 at Mongkok Stadium. “It has been an excellent time, exceeding all expectations,” he concludes.
Paulo Conde, a Portuguese born in Angola, came to Macao for the first time in 2012, having been champion in several clubs, highlighting black red, Lam Pak and Ka I, as well as having represented the selection of the territory several times.
It is recalled that the coach has a daughter, Zara Matos, to also act in Hong Kong football at the same club, Rangers, and has been in view of the many goals she has scored throughout the time in the Women's Division Women's Championship.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Saxophone and piano in duet at the Military Club</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/saxofone-piano-em-dueto-clube-militar/</link><description>Christian Forshaw, in saxophone, and Jenny NG, to the piano, are the guest artists for another session of the Military Club's music journeys. The concert will take place this Friday
 
“On Fire: The Heart and Passion of the Saxophone” is the title of the classical music concert that will take place today at the Military Club of Macau (CMM), at 19h00. The interpretation is up to saxophonist Christian Forshaw and pianist Jenny NG. The show program includes works by composers such as Bach, Bartok, Ross Edwards, Piazzolla, Groblez, Debussy and Ravel.
According to CMM, Forshaw is a renowned saxophonist and composer whose distinct sound has won a global audience. Their performances and compositions have been presented by prestigious sets such as "Tenebrae" in "When Sleep Comes" and "Vocês8" in "Lux and Eventide."
The artist was hired by the “BBC Singers” to compose and arrange three new works for a performance at “Cadoganhall” in London in April 2024. He recorded six solo albums, most of which with their own compositions and arrangements.
"Your music is deeply influenced by the choral traditions of your education, as well as the Solionic Landscapes of Minimalism and Jazz," according to the finding of the Concert Organization.
In 2023, Forshaw's song was featured in Ridley Scott's movie “The Last Duel”, produced by “20th Century Fox” and starring Matt Damon.
Throughout his career, the saxophonist collaborated with an eclectic range of artists, including Brian Eno, Michael Nyman, Damon Albran, the "Chamber Orchestra of Europe" and Hugh Jackman. Since 2002, he has also been a saxophone teacher at the “Guildhall School of Music &amp; Drama” in London.
Jenny NG has been established as a collaborative artist since 2005. It is often requested for many recitals, festivals, contests, “masterclasses” and recordings in Asia and Europe.
His performances were made in places such as the "Queen Elizabeth Hall" in the "London Southbank Center", "York Minster", "Regent Hall", "SouthWark Cathedral", "Hong Kong City Hall", as well as at the Macao Cultural Center. Recent commitments included collaborations with Hong Kong Sinfonietta, “Panasia Symphony Orchestra”, “Hong Kong New Music Ensemble” and Macau's youth symphonic band.
Jenny NG has two piano -followed masters for “Guildhall School of Music and Drama”.
In addition to accompanying vocalists, the artist has also worked in close collaboration with various instrumental educators, including David Takeno and John Harle, and has established a long collaboration partnership in Duo and Trio with violinist Kitty Cheung and saxophonist Timothy Sun.
He received numerous awards in contests, including the "York Music Festival".
The concert of the Military Club, integrated in another edition of the “Musical Days”, will be held at the Stanley Ho Salon. Tickets to watch the show cost 120 patacas, including cocktail.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China intensifies restoration of relics</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/china-intensifica-restauro-de-reliquias/</link><description>In a workshop hidden in the historic forbidden city of Beijing, a restorative, leaning over a centenary statuette, uses a piece of cotton to gently clean the dusty cracks after years in a basement. Only a small part of the 1.86 million objects maintained at the Chinese capital palace museum is on display.
In the last decade, Chinese President Xi Jinping has requested to reinforce the protection of cultural heritage, motivating an intensification of efforts to preserve and restore the historical relics that will one day be exposed to the public.
In the forbidden city workshop, dozens of restorers with latex gloves work to restore lanterns, jade earrings or worn paintings to their lost glory. A restoration technique retoucks the head of a statue with a thin brush, while another applies a bright substance to an old Qing dynasty scroll.
"This restorer is repairing the edges of the assembly, specifically the floral penalties used in its decoration," he told AFP MA Yue, head of the museum's handwriting and painting section.
"This restoration is quite representative of our work, because we have to trust the original elements, be it the support, the materials, the color palette and even its aging," he added.
According to the Palace Museum, the inauguration of a new Cultural Center in Beijing, scheduled for October, will increase the number of restored and displayed objects annually.
Hundreds of tourists visit the museum complex, some dresses with traditional costumes. In sections open to the public, the work of the restoration teams is already visible.
Installed at the Imperial Palace of Ming and Qing Dynasties after the last Emperor PU Yi and his entourage were expelled, the forbidden city museum celebrates its centenary this year. The collection includes paintings, handwriting, bronze, gold, silver, ceramic and textiles, covering almost all forms of Chinese art, from prehistoric times to the modern era.
The pieces faced existential threats in various turbulent periods. Hundreds of thousands of pieces were removed from the museum in the 1930s to prevent them from falling into the hands of the Japanese invaders. Many others were taken to Taiwan by the nationalists after their defeat in the hands of the communists when they fled at the end of the Chinese civil war in 1949.
In 1952, the museum created a conservation team, with artisans descending from the Qing Dynasty imperial workshops. However, during the cultural revolution in the 1960s, valuable artifacts were damaged, destroyed or stolen by the red guards of Mao Zedong, brigades of young communists who violently attacked anything or person considered part of the bourgeoisie.
Chinese authorities also issued a circular with the aim of promoting advertising and the application of the Cultural relic protection law, the National Administration of Cultural Heritage said. According to the Xinhua agency, the circular stipulates that local governments should organize educational and promotional activities related to that cultural relics law, so that there is a “comprehensive, accurate and complete” understanding of the objectives and the main content of the diploma.
At the same time, China is holding a national census of cultural relics, which should extend by 2026.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Citizens of Seoul say that old age starts at 70</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/cidadaos-de-seul-dizem-velhice-comeca-aos-70/</link><description>Most residents of Seoul consider it 70 years of age as the beginning of old age, according to an inquiry released by the metropolitan government of the capital of South Korea.
The results of this inquiry, performed annually since 2003 with the purpose of monitoring public opinion on quality of life, social values ​​and urban life, concluded that citizens of Seoul believe that the average age in which a person becomes “elderly” is 70.2 years.
The inquiry was attended by about 20,000 households (involving total of 36,280 individuals), 5,000 citizens and 2,500 foreigners living in the capital of South Korea.
The perception of old age varies from generation to generation. Respondents 65 or older considered the limit in 72.3 years, while those under 65 identified him as 69.8. About half of all respondents stated to consider individuals aged between 70 and 74 as "elderly."
The inquiry also revealed that almost 88% of respondents support the increase in the official age of reform, reflecting changes in social attitudes in an aged city. Currently, the age of reform for public service positions in government agencies is set in 65 years.
When asked about post-reform life, respondents over 65 expressed a strong preference for hobbies or income-generating activities rather than traditional functions such as caring for grandchildren. About 65% of participants in the study stated that they preferred to live independently and close to their children instead of sharing a home with them.
Research has also revealed significant lifestyle trends. Notably, unipessal families now represent 39.3% of all families in the city; Two out of 10 homes have an animal of company; And 36% of family aggregates with animals are composed of one person.
Regarding transport habits, the results of the inquiry show that most seoul residents depend on buses for their daily travel, almost half refers a travel time from 30 minutes to one hour. Foreign residents, on the other hand, reported a more frequent use of the Metropolitan.
Among the foreigners living in Seoul, Gwanghwamun Square is the most recognized milestone in the city.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>