<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Elderly in the work force almost duplicated in 10 years</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/idosos-na-forca-laboral-quase-duplicaram-em-10-anos/</link><description>In a decade, the number of young people from 16 to 29 years old participating in the work force fell almost to half. Between 2014 and 2024, the number of active individuals in this age group went from 101 thousand to 54.6 thousand. In the same period, the 65 -year -old or older elderly activity rate
 
Pedro Milheirão
 
The proportion of active people in the MSAR has fallen six percentage points in a decade, according to official data from the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). The activity rate in 2024 was 67.8% (383.3 thousand people), and in 2014, the active population was 73.8% (394.7 thousand). The data consulted by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao also indicate that there are more elderly in the labor force.
In 2014, there were 35,600 young actives, aged 16 to 24, and 65,400 between 25 and 29 years. Last year, the work force had only 15,800 young people from 16 to 24 years and 38,800 aged between 25 and 29 years, translated into falls of 55.6% and 40.7%, respectively.
Conversely, the amount of active adults between 35 and 39 years grew 50.5%in the same period, from 43.6 thousand to 65.6 thousand individuals. Similarly, there was an increase of 6,500 elderly between 60 and 64 years, from 16.7 thousand to 23.2 thousand (+38.92%), from 2014 to 2024, respectively. The number of active people 65 years old or over almost doubled in the same period from seven thousand to 13,300 (+90%).
The phenomenon coincides with the aging of the general population. In 2014, individuals from 15 to 34 years represented 34% of the population (214,400 people), while in 2024 this age group represented 26% (181 thousand).
Another plausible reason would be the fact that younger people enrolled in higher education in 2024, compared to 2014. In fact, the number of students in degrees more than doubled in a decade. In 2014, higher education had 30,771 students enrolled, while ten years later the number was 62,463 (+103%). In addition, the master's students and doctoral students went from 1,262 and 100, respectively, to 5,940 and 966, between 2014 and 2024.
However, this climb is mainly due to the number of students from abroad. In 2014, there were only 12,213 students from outside, against 18,558 of resident students. In 2024, the number of resident students descended to 15,275 (-18%), while those abroad increased 286% (47,188).
In construction, the number of workers fell to about half, from 52.5 thousand, in 2014, to 26 thousand, in 2024, which translates into a 50.5%drop. Interestingly, the number of students of architecture and construction courses went from 325 in 2014 to 1,088 (+235%) in the last year. In the same period, engineering students went from 620 to 1,080 (+74%).
On the other hand, health services and social action registered an increase of 4,600 workers from 10.1 thousand in 2014 to 14,700 (+45.5%) in 2024. In education there was also a considerable increase. In 2014, the sector had 14,800 workers, while last year there were 23 thousand (+55.4%). Similarly, from 2014 to 2024, there was a substantial increase in students enrolled in social (+95%), health (270%) courses and education sciences (146%)
In terms of remuneration, monthly median income rose from 13,300 patacas to 18,000 (+35.3%) in ten years. By sector, the workers who earned the most in 2024 were in the Public Administration (48,500 patacas), education (28 thousand) and the games sector (21 thousand). On the other hand, housework and food have workers who earn the lowest salaries, with income of five thousand and 12,400 patacas, respectively.
 
Greater gender equality in labor participation
According to data on 2014, women's participation in labor force decreased significantly as they aged, compared to men, especially from the age of 55. From 25 to 49 years old, more than 80% of women were active, while the proportion of men was over 90%.
Between 50 and 54 years old, 72.5% of women participated in labor force, compared to 89.5% of men in the same year. From 55 to 59 years old, just over half of the women were participants (54.75%), compared to 85.1% of men. 35.7% of women between 60 and 64 years old participated in labor force, compared to 68.1% of men. Over 65 years old, only 6.1% of women were active, compared to 23.1% of men.
However, this disproportion has improved within a decade. In 2024, in the age group from 55 to 59, the proportion of active men dropped to 77.4% and that of women rose to 69%. The same trend is found in the following age groups. Last year, 42.2% of women between 60 and 64 years participated in work force, 6.5% more than in 2014. Men of the same age had a 58.5% activity rate, less 9.6% than a decade earlier. Last year, among the elderly over 65 years old, 10.2% of women and 18.1% of men were active, plus 4.1% and 5% less than in 2014, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Portugal returns and Brazil debuts at the fire festival</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/portugal-regressa-brasil-estreia-se-festival-de-fogo-de-artificio/</link><description>The presence of a pyrotechnic team from Brazil is the big news of this year's edition of the International Fire Fire Festival, which will take place for a month, between September 6 and October 6, with five nights of sky illuminated by 10 participating teams. Portugal repeats the presence, this time represented by Barbeita Pyrotechnics, Monção. The director of tourism services hopes that shows attract a number of people similar to last year, which was 720 thousand
 
Victor Rebelo
 
This year's edition of the International Fire Fire Festival will have as its main news the presence of a team from Brazil, which will act on the last day of the event, alongside the United Kingdom. The shows will take place in five nights, between September 6 and October 6, with two daily sessions, 20 minutes each, always at 21h00 and 21h40.
The event, which had its debut in 1989, again has a Portuguese representation, this time to the Pyrotechnics of Barbeita, Monção, Viana do Castelo. "The Heavenly Well" will be the theme to present, with the background "the stars reflecting the intensity of human desires, love and fragility of the world."
Portugal, which will act at 9:40 pm (after the Chinese formation) on October 1, the National Day of the Popular Republic of China, seeks the fourth victory in the contest after winning in 1991, 1996 and 2002.
The China team has chosen as the theme the “celebration of the 26th anniversary of MSAR” and will interpret classic melodies, “matching the perfect firefight”.
Moreover, the 33rd Festival brings to the Australia and South Africa territory (September 6), South Korea and Austria (13), Philippines and Japan (20), and United Kingdom and Brazil (October 6).
The details of the pyrotechnic event were released at a press conference, held yesterday morning at the Macao Tower facilities, in which the director of tourism services (STD) stressed that the participating teams were selected for “vast experience in contests and exhibitions, having already won awards in different fire events worldwide”.
In his speech, Helena de Senna Fernandes stressed that "Macau will have 10 high -level exhibitions, showing the charm of Macau's" Tourism + Events ", enriching night activities and boosting the community economy." He recalled that the festival period covers National RPC Day and the lunar bolus festival, “which reinforces the environment of the festivities”.
Regarding the forecast of expected visitors for the festival period, STD official said the estimate is similar to last year's edition, ie about 720,000 people. "It can even be slightly higher if the weather conditions allow it," he said.
Those who want to attend the shows of different perspectives have six places of observation advised by the organization, namely: Avenida Dr. Sun Yat-Sen, from the ecumenical center to the marginal leisure zone of the Kun Iam statue; Riverside tour of the Macau Science Center; Sagres Avenue (next to the East Mandarin Hotel); Anim'Arte Nam Van, on the marginal path of the lake (next to the Yoho Treasury Island Hotel), and Ocean Avenue in the mud.
For those who want to see on television, the sessions will all be broadcast live by channels or world and entertainment, while the Chinese channel of Radio Macau will broadcast, in real time, the music that serves as the backdrop to the fireworks.
Parallel to the exhibitions, the festival integrates other activities, highlighting the popular “Arraial do Fogo-Aartitio”, with gastronomy, shows and games, in a joint organization of STD and the General Union of Macao residents' associations. The same will take place on the days of the sessions, between 5:30 pm and 10:30 pm, on the riverside tour of the Macao Science Center.
In addition, it will once again be carried out photography and drawing contests for students so that they can develop their creativity. On the other hand, STD leads, for the first time, an artificial intelligence arts contest, so that “enthusiasts of the creation of this technology recall the beauty of fireworks, promote the development of macao science and art and intersectory integration of 'tourism + technology'”. There will also be interactive online games.
The total festival budget is 18.6 million patacas. The six dealers cover about 18 million. The rest is the responsibility of the government.
 
Break of visitors related to economy instability
The director of tourism services acknowledges that the breakdown of the number of visitors and expenses has to do with the current situation of the world economy. "The world is not in the best economic conditions, so we will try to endure and see in which areas and products we can bet on them to spend their money," said Helena de Senna Fernandes, on the sidelines of the presentation of the International Fire Fire Festival, adding that "it's a matter of time." "When the economy grows, Macau will see more spending from visitors," he said. Senna Fernandes also took stock of the event “Zape with flavors”, stating that for four days she received more than 36,000 visitors, a daily average of 9,100, having exceeded the initial expectation of 4,000 per day. "Traders who participated in the fair registered a total amount of gross revenues over 200,000 patacas, and some stands managed to earn more than 10,000 patacas a day, so the results are satisfactory," he noted. As for a possible extent of the event, he assumed that "for now, not."</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DSOP will start study on the impact of the east line on the guide headlight</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dsop-vai-iniciar-estudo-sobre-impacto-da-linha-leste-farol-da-guia/</link><description>The government will move forward with a study of the impact of the eastern east line on the Lagar da Guia landscape, the Cultural Institute said, a task that will be the direction of public works. Remember that this had been one of the requests made by the UNESCO World Heritage Center in July
 
Pedro Milheirão
 
The Directorate of Public Works Services (DSOP) will begin the “Evaluation of the Impact of the East Line of the Light Metro on the Landange of the Guide Lighthouse,” said Substitute President of the Cultural Institute (IC), Cheang Kai Meng. In July, it is recalled, the center of UNESCO World Heritage requested impact studies in relation to two projects, one of them precisely the east line of the slight metro, but also the viaduct between zones A and B of new landfills, as this newspaper reported.
The international agency also required the sending of an up -to -date report on the state of conservation of the Historic Center of Macau to the state administration of China's cultural heritage, to be sent until December 1, 2026.
In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Ron Lam, the Substitute President of the IC also indicates that the East Line - which will have about 7.7 kilometers long - will be built through a underground tunnel and will include six underground stations. "With the exception of access to stations, equipment rooms and emergency exits, which will surface, all other facilities will be located underground," he said.
Regarding the viaduct between zones A and B of new landfills, defined as “a relevant transport infrastructure” for the future connection between the peninsula and the new landfills, “presently, public works services are elaborating the respective project”. Cheang Kai Meng further assured that the mashed government "maintains an attitude open", taking into account the "concerns manifested by citizens as to the form of construction." According to said, the executive will proceed with the collection, organization and analysis, "broadly", of opinions, "in the sense of perfecting the project."
Stressing that “impact assessment on heritage” is a general mechanism for world heritage protection work, the same person adds that the government will continue to carry out this type of study “for programs that are needed, including evaluation on further programs under the requirements of the center of the world heritage”.
In this sense, it recalls that after the conclusion of the study of the “assessment of the patrimonial impact and urban conception of the area around Dr. Rodrigo Rodrigues Avenue”, the government submitted the “main content” of the study to the center of the World Heritage for appreciation. Also on this assessment UNESCO requested more details. "With regard to the information and data to be added after the decision, the Government of the MSAR is accompanied by the case according to the content of the decision," he added, no further details.
The government has periodically presented information on studies and reports to the center of the world heritage, with whom it will maintain a “narrow” communication and exchange, on any subject related to the preservation and management of the Macao World Heritage, the IC also guaranteed.
The body also recalls that the World Heritage Committee has settled with the content of the “Macao Historic Center Management and Management Plan” by gathering opinions from the International Council of Monuments and Sites and the Center of UNESCO World Heritage. According to Cheang, the plan is "a comprehensive framework and effective tools for the preservation and management of Macao's world heritage."</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sector asks measures to collect breaking the prices of houses</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sector-pede-medidas-para-colmatar-quebra-dos-precos-das-casas/</link><description>A report recently prepared and released by the General Association of Macao Real Estate Sector points to a 40% breach in the prices of Macao Houses registered since 2018, the “Pico Height”. On the other hand, the document observes the "continuous climb" of the stores' vacancy rate in residential areas. Given the scenario, the sector calls for solutions
 
Since the “peak height” in 2018, the prices of Macao houses “have fallen constantly” and have dropped more than 40% so far, and the pricing trend has “accentuated” this year “without any signs of stopping”, which “severely shook confidence in investment and consumption in Macao, as well as consumer power,” says a report by the General Association of Macao Real Estator, recently published, published, published, under the theme of “impact of prosperity and recession of the real estate market on the economy and society of Macao”.
In the report, the association notes that, although the government has suppressed, in 2024, all the main measures previously implemented to “cool” the real estate market, the market reactions “have been kept weak”.
According to the newspaper "or Mun", the report states that, in this context, many owners of housing fractions "suffer from a dilemma", which resulted in the "weakening of consumer power among residents" and "deterioration of the Macao business environment under a vicious cycle."
In addition, he mentions that an old T2 fraction in Rua do Campo, priced at 1.18 million patacas, did not attract any interested buyers after being put for sale. “Some fractions in old buildings have lower prices than parking spaces,” the report describes, regretting that the owners of old houses are mostly elderly, who also face the sales dilemma. "This frustrated the plan of some seniors to use their home to support old age," the document points out.
According to the association, between 2018 and 2024, nearly 40,000 real estate transactions were registered in Macao. However, decreased prices by 40% means that "tens of thousands of newcomers who have made an initial payment of 20% become the initial payment and contributions paid over the years to disappear", "most of them resident 40 to 50 years of age."
In addition, the document finds the “continuous climb” of stores unemployment rate in residential zones, as “houses prices continue to fall, resident revenues to decrease, consumption in the welfare of the population to leave abroad, and the business of traders in residential areas to constantly decrease”.
In this aspect, the report exemplifies that the eastern pearl zone has been one of the most affected residential areas by this problem, and the same is true of Rua da Barca, where “there are currently three dozen empty stores”, which “means, according to sector statistics, a 20%”.
As a solution, the General Association of the Real Estate sector asks the Government to take several measures, in terms of initial payment, taxes, interest bonus and imports of paintings, in order to stabilize the real estate market.
Suggesting the reduction of the minimum initial payment ratio to 15% and the resumption of the “credit bonus regime for the acquisition or financial housing lease”, ie the “4% bonus” measure, the association also proposes the collection of a 100 -rate seal tax for four million patacas, and a fixed rate of 1% for transactions exceeds four million.
In the field of import imports, the report proposes four types of people eligible to ask the right to residence in Macau and have been approved as long as they have worked or managed business in the territory for a number of years. "It may be the one who earns at least 1.5 million patacas a year, graduated from one of the 100 best universities in the world, has a master's or higher degree, or graduated by Macao Higher Education Institution and who has good academic performance," the report suggests.
In addition, the Association expects to be authorized to set residence for investors who have invested 10 million patacas in the purchase of housing house and 10 million in a store, office or industrial building, and lived at least seven years in Macao.
 
Payment of the seal tax can lead to “speculation”
The Directorate of Finance Services (DSF) considers that the resuming of the seal tax payment is an approach “likely to easily lead to speculative speculation or acts in the real estate market, which might not meet the expectations of society”. The position was shown in response to an interpellation of Deputy Chan Iek Lap on the optimization of real estate tax procedures. According to this measure suggested by the deputy, it is first paid, for example, 0.5% of the tax, being the remnant to be paid when the public deed of purchase and sale is celebrated. In the same response, DSF ensures that the executive will “closely monitor the changes in the fiscal policies of neighboring regions and timely review the respective tax measures, in conjunction with the actual situation of Macao”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Xi Jinping asks for unity in Tibet</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/xi-jinping-pede-unidade-tibete/</link><description>The Chinese president called for a unit in Lhasa, the capital of Tibet, where the 60th anniversary of the creation of the autonomous region was signaled, six years after the Dalai Lama exile in India, following a failed revolt.
Xi Jinping's unusual visit to Tibet is marked by political symbolism, when it occurs after the 14th Dalai Lama reaffirmed that only the Gaden Phodrang Foundation founded by him has the authority to recognize the future reincarnation of the spiritual leader. Beijing, for his part, insists that Dalai Lama's successor "must be sought inside China and receive the approval of the central government."
XI urged the authorities of the region to build a “united, prosperous, civilized, harmonious and beautiful” tibet, according to Xinhua, despite the persistent international criticism of the situation of human rights and religious freedom in this region of Himalayas.
Not to mention Dalai Lama directly, Xi added that “stability must be guaranteed” and “Tibetan Buddhism must be guided in its adaptation to socialist society”, stressing “the importance of maintaining the leadership of the Chinese Communist Party [CCP]” in the region.
However, China's main political counselor, Wang Huning, stressed yesterday in a commemorative ceremony, with the presence of Xi, that Tibeth entered the “best period of development”.
The official pointed to the "important national projects and policies that transformed the region", leading to "an improvement of life standards and a vibrant and modern socialist tibet." "This fully demonstrates the strong leadership of the CCP and the important political advantages of our socialist system," he added.
Xi arrived at Tibet on Wednesday, on the second visit as head of state, to attend commemorative events.
Images transmitted yesterday by state station CCTV showed dozens of people in Potala Palace Square to erect a giant Chinese flag, as well as the insignia of the CCP and XI portraits, which built a strong personality worship after taking over the Chinese presidency in 2013.
Xi Jinping's first visit to Tibet as president took place in 2021, on the occasion of the 70th anniversary of Beijing's so -called “peaceful liberation”, when, after the entry of the communist troops, the “17 points agreement” was signed, sealing the incorporation of the region in the Popular Republic of China.
The anniversary that is now celebrated commemorates the creation of the Tibet Autonomous Region in 1965. Beijing presents this statute as a mechanism designed to ensure the participation of ethnic minorities in politics and the preservation of their cultural identity, as Tibetan activists and human rights defense organizations accuse the Chinese government of repression, forced assimilation and restrictions on religious freedom.
On the other hand, the region remains of great strategic importance due to the border with India, a country with which China has territorial disputes and where Dalai Lama has lived since 1959.
The arrival of XI coincides with a visit this week from Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi, the New Delhi, where the two parties pledged to improve relationships after the 2020 border clashes.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mam displays 100 pieces of lok cheong in Tibet</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mam-exibe-100-pecas-de-lok-cheong-tibete/</link><description>An exhibition with more than 100 works by artist Lok Cheong was inaugurated at the Tibet Art Museum, patent until October. The show marks the 60 years of the autonomous region of Tibet and the three decades of “friendship” between the territory and the masters
 
The Tibet Art Museum (MAT) inaugurated the show “Tibet's Heart Ties” as a way to mark the 60th anniversary of the region's establishment, according to the Cultural Institute (IC). Lok Cheong's exhibition of works was co-organized by MAT and the Macao Art Museum (MAM) and will be evident until October 12, with free admission. Most of the items on display was provided by MAM, and the rest belongs to the Lok Cheong family and MAT.
The show features about a hundred masterpieces created over the more than half a century by Lok Cheong, who lived between 1923 and 2006, complemented with more than 70 sketches, archive materials and photographs, among other “priceless historical materials”. Organized in three themes, namely “Love to the Fatherland”, “capturing the character of Macao” and “portraits”, the exhibition offers “a systematic view of the author's artistic development”, read in a press release.
This is the first time that the manuscripts of Lok Cheong from Tibet are displayed publicly, accompanied by rare documents that report "their cultural exploitation of the heart of the homeland and the Tibet." The works “The mysterious palace Potala” and “a hidden path, shigatse” are “a tribute to the sacred landscapes of Tibet”, with “vibrant colors”.
The watercolors “witnesses of history”, in which trees intertwine branches in the Kun Iam Tong Temple, and “Octagonal Pavilion Library” capture the essence of the Macao scenario over the last fifty years with “dynamic brushstrokes”. In turn, the works “Technicians departing to serve the homeland” and “rice offer for the homeland” represent a tribute to the patriotism of the author's compatriots, according to the IC.
The representations of Tibet by Lok Cheong became "an eternal testimony of friendship between the two regions." Lok's participation in the “Painting Exhibition of Planalto Nevado”, which took place in Canton, began the “artistic exchange between Macau and Tibet”, in the early 1990s. Since then, the artist continued to “build a bridge of friendship between Tibet and Macau”, even organizing several visits by artists from Macau to the Tibetan region. It also promoted the creation of the first primary school, under the Esperança Project, in NAGQU, and Lok Cheong "continues to lead cultural integration between the two regions."
The IC and the Association of Fine Artists have organized this show to “honor Lok Cheong's pioneering efforts” in promoting cultural exchange between the two regions, which has been overriding more than three decades. The inaugural ceremony brought together more than a hundred figures of the cultural media of Tibet and Master in Lhasa.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Less than a fifth considers living old age on the continent</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/menos-de-um-quinto-considera-viver-velhice-continente/</link><description>Most residents over 45 have been experiencing a “normal” or “less good” economic situation, and one fifth needs government support to subsist. Only 18% would consider living the elderly in the interior of China
 
More than 60% of residents over 45 consider their economic situation “normal” or “less good”, according to an inquiry from the Macao Social Security Association, which was based on response from 1,000 residents. On the other hand, 33.5% of respondents depend on the salary to live, and 20.1% need government subsidies.
The study also revealed that only 18% of respondents would consider living in old age in the interior of China. The association said that the main concerns of residents are the “lack of connection” between Macao medical services with those of mainland China and the eventual absence of community ties, as well as the inaccucting transmission of information.
More than 60% of respondents said they went to the doctor regularly, but have shown a lack of confidence in the interior health system of China, relatively “to the language and reimbursement procedures”. The association noted that only less than 10% consider that knowing enough policies related to transfronical life for the elderly, which reflects a “lack of dissemination by the government”.
Almost half of respondents still live with their spouses, while about one fifth lives with their children. According to investigators, more than 80% of respondents prefer to live at home when they become elderly and about 20% live alone.
The association also considers that policies linked to the elderly are too focused on economic and medical issues and may be neglecting the influence of social participation on the quality of life of the elders.
According to the inquiry, 16.5% of respondents self-assessed their health as “less good”, 40.8% said they suffered occasionally from episodes of depression. In addition, more than a third of respondents never participated in social or volunteering activities.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>President of AL highlights 86 laws approval</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/presidente-da-al-destaca-aprovacao-de-86-leis/</link><description>In the last four years, the Legislative Assembly has approved a total of 86 laws. During a meeting on the work balance of the last legislature, the President of the Legislative Assembly, Kou Hoi In, highlighted the efforts made by the deputies of the industrial and commercial sectors
 
The 7th Legislative Assembly (AL) concluded a total of 86 bills, stressed Kou Hoi In during a meeting with deputies Chui Sai Peng, IP Sio Kai and Wang Sai Man, about the work balance done in the last legislature. The president of AL added that 1,337 interventions were held before the order of the day, 3,076 written and 341 oral interpeairs.
Over the years, industrial and commercial deputies “have actively struggled with the legitimate rights of the sector, worrying about the development of small and medium enterprises (SMEs)” and “helping employers solve their problems,” said Kou Hoi In.
In addition, Kou noted that the work of deputies “is always closely linked to social life and economic development”, and it is not limited to paying attention to the operational situation of SMEs, but also to Macao's business and investment environment, with “prospective” development planning.
The president of the legislature also recalled his 34 years as a deputy. Kou Hoi In is not part of the list of candidates from the industrial, commercial and financial sectors, for the indirect suffrage of the elections for al. However, it may also stay in the hemiciclo if appointed by Sam Hou Fai, chief executive.
On the other hand, Chui Sai Peng stressed that the laws passed in the last legislature created “a more solid base for development”, covering areas such as national security, social welfare and economy. IP Sio Kai, in turn, urged the government to create “more specific support programs” for SMEs, to help traders “transform, modernize and develop”.
IP Sio Kai took the opportunity to underline the “important role” of modern finances in the diversification of the economy. The deputy also said that he will continue to pay attention and promote the development of the financial sector in Macao, "fostering systems integration, prevention and risk control and talent formation."
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Legislation away to deal with statements online</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/afastada-legislacao-para-lidar-declaracoes-online/</link><description>Deputy Lei Chan U wanted the government to promote legislation on online public opinion and the creation of a rapid intervention mechanism in public opinion on the Internet, "in order to reduce the negative impact on social stability." However, the Substitute Director of the Communication Office (GCS), Wong Lok I, says that "although there is no specific law directed to online public opinion in the current legal system of Macau, there are provisions in different laws to deal with crimes involving online statements."
Remembering that “the Government of MSAR has been stressed, several times, that the internet is not a place without law,” Wong Lok I states, in response to the deputy's questioning, that the executive “will continue to proceed well to the work of disclosing official information on the Internet and pay attention to online public opinion”, as well as “respond proactively” to concerns within society. The goal, he said, is to prevent "misunderstandings and wrong interpretations."
In the replica, the GCS substitute director notes that, with the rapid development of computer technology and the popularity of social networks, online platforms and social networks have gradually become channels for the public to obtain and transmit information as well as express their opinions. Thus, the government has also been “expanding and taking advantage of” new media, publicizing official information on different platforms.
"Alongside the improvement of the information dissemination mechanism, the Government of MSAR has attributed high importance to online opinions, and proceeds to the systematic collection of public opinion through interdepartal cooperation mechanisms," explained Wong Lok I.
As for false information and online rumors involving the administration of the Government of MSAR or public interests, "competent services, after professional analysis and study, provide immediate clarifications in order to ensure the correct understanding of the facts, and contain the diffusion of false information," he added.
Wong Lok I then mentioned several laws that can be used when there are problems of this nature. For example, the legal regime of civil protection. "When sudden incidents of public nature occur, the authorities respond promptly and in accordance with the law to the diffusion of rumors inside and outside the internet, in order to reduce the negative impact on society," he continued.
He also spoke in the Computer Crime Law, adding that the Judiciary Police have already established cooperation mechanisms with internet service suppliers, social networking companies, among others, “in the sense of taking action to block and remove illegal content published on the network”.
It also recalled that the Penal Code stipulates crimes such as defamation, injury, advertising and slander, incitement to war, and incitement to genocide, while the law on the defense of state security provides for the crime of sedition and electoral laws provide for the crime of public incitement.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Pandas motivate agreement between Iam and Ocean Park</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pandas-motivam-acordo-entre-iam-ocean-park/</link><description>Giant pandas and wildlife conservation motivated the signing of an agreement between AMI and Hong Kong's Ocean Park. The idea is, among other aspects, to raise the quality of giant panda care and also reinforce public awareness of nature conservation
 
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) and Ocean Park de Hong Kong have signed a “memo of intention to cooperation and preservation”, in view of reinforcing the cooperation relationship related to giant pandas and wildlife conservation work.
Following the visit of representatives from the neighboring territory to AMI, both sides have set a memorandum, in which they agree to raise the quality of giant panda care, promote the conservation of wild animals and reinforce public awareness of nature conservation.
At the same time, “through exchange and personnel formation, medical knowledge and nursing experiences about wild animals were shared, building a technical cooperation platform,” according to an AMI statement. The idea is also to promote ecological education together and increase society's attention to wildlife conservation.
The meeting, followed by signing the agreement, was attended by Macao's side of the Chairman of the Board of Directors for Municipal Affairs of the IAM, Chao Wai Ieng, and the Board of Directors Administrator for Municipal Affairs, Tam Wai Fong, and by the Hong Kong entourage, the executive administrator of the company Ocean Park, Ivan Wong Chi Fai, and the Executive Director of Animals and Conservation, Howard Chuk.
The Ocean Park, which opened in 1977, is an animal theme park in Wong Chuk Hang, considered the largest of the genre in Hong Kong area.
Here, the Gigante Panda Pavilion features Jian Jian and Kang Kang, the first giant pandes born in Macao, as well as his parents, Xin Xin and Kai Kai. It is recalled that the Jornal Tribuna de Macao Aím said, not long ago, that this space registered last year 372,164 visitors, an increase of 189% compared to 128,508 visits verified in 2019.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC features “fado night”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/frc-apresenta-noite-de-fado/</link><description>On August 25, at 20h00, the Porto Medicine Fados Group, consisting of former university stresses, will act at the Rui Cunha Foundation, according to a press release. The “Fado Night” will be open to the public, with free admission. For years and generations, the group has been carrying the legacy of the “Student Song”, participating in monumental serenades, fado nights, birthday galls, among other events dedicated to music, according to the note. The musicians have visited Portuguese communities spread abroad, "with the aim of interacting with them in times of mutual sharing." In recent years, the group's digressions have brought him to Asia, the US and countries such as Switzerland, Luxembourg, Germany and France, among others. In 1992, a group of students from the University of Porto School of Medicine gathered to “enrich his academic experience, perpetuating the academic tradition and interpreting the most beautiful Portuguese music, the academic fado”. With melodies and chords that bring together values ​​of academic life, the group intends to celebrate the Fado de Coimbra and Portuguese music, as well as the “spirit that all those who find an expression of their identity”. The Porto Medicine Fados Group has since been one of the most historic landmarks of the Porto Academy.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2460/</link><description>3,000 illegal drugs seized in the North Zone
A mobile distribution point of illegally imported drugs was detected in the North Zone, having found a large amount of drugs inside a truck, including traditional Chinese and natural medicines. The Institute for Pharmaceutical Supervision and Administration (Isaf) and customs services (SA) inspected the products and seized more than 3,000 boxes of analgesic, traditional Chinese drugs for oral use, among others. The vehicle was parked in a parking lot and was discovered on the 18th. Isaf opened a process for investigation and the SA proceeded to the accusation against the offender regarding the violation of product imports by the commercial agency.
 
Hong Chan Kuan Temple will suffer repair works
From September 1, the Hong Chan Kuan Temple, located on 5 October Street, will be closed to the public, due to restoration works. It is estimated that the work is extended for 60 days. According to the “Hong-Chan-Kuan-Mio” Hong-Kuan-King Association, the temple was built 165 years ago and did not have great impact during the recent emission of the black signal of intense rain. The association revealed that the work will include the roof, which will cause the provisional closure of space. He adds that the Cultural Institute will assume about 70% of the expenses.
 
Patriotic Education Base for Young people opened in Beijing
Yesterday in Beijing was inaugurated the base of patriotic education for young people from Hong Kong and Macau, which was attended by the secretary for social affairs and culture, Lam. According to a statement, this is the first base of patriotic education created in China by the two special administrative regions. On the sidelines of the opening ceremony, Kong Chi Meng, director of Youth Education and Development Services, mentioned that preparations for the installation of a Macao Patriotic Education Exhibition Pavilion in Seac Pai Van, “is going well”, predicting that the room is expected to be inaugurated later this year.
 
Security and Technology among 373 job offers
The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) will organize four job pairing sessions in late August, offering 373 vacancies. Between the 27th and 29th, places will be available in sectors such as safety and cleaning (261), managers of IT products, operating and maintenance engineer (13), cooking and restoration, cooks, restaurant employee, bartender, beautician and hairdresser (74) and various jobs in the Macao Games society (25). Registrations will be open until noon of August 26.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Changed rules for choosing management and leadership positions</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/alteradas-regras-para-escolha-de-cargos-de-direccao-chefia/</link><description>Only holders of “immediately lower level positions” can be chosen for department leaders and heads, according to the new “fundamental provisions of the Board of Directors Statute”, which will come into force on 1 November. According to the spokesman for the executive board, André Cheong, a third entity will also be requested, to ensure the “legality and objectivity” of appointments
 
Pedro Milheirão
 
The recruitment of department leaders and heads should be made “by choosing the holders of immediately lower level positions,” according to the Executive Board. This is one of the new rules in the context of the “fundamental provisions of the Directorate and Head Statute”, since the current regulation stipulates that the recruitment for these positions is made by choice, “through curriculum appreciation, among individuals of recognized civic suitability”.
The new regulation - which comes into force on 1 November, together with the Law on the Fundamental Provisions of the Board of Directors Staff, which was approved in July at the Legislative Assembly - also determines that the choice for division heads is made between “staff who has completed, with use, the qualification course for the purpose”, whose pedagogical organization will be determined by the Executive Chief.
However, the Director of Administration and Public Services (SAFP), Leong Weng In, explained that, for the recruitment of leaders, there are some exceptional situations, such as choosing staff that performs functions of the same level, even in other services.
A “new request mechanism will also be introduced to a third part, according to which, the appointment of management or head personnel must be preceded by an opinion [of the SAFP],” said André Cheong, explaining that the intention is to “ensure the legality and objectivity of the appointment procedure”.
On the other hand, he added that "the guardianship, when the renewal of the management and head service commission, has to review again whether the staff in question continues to fulfill the requirements for the performance of duties, namely the necessary civic suitability and professional competence."
“We need to check if there is information about (…) disciplinary processes,” explained Leong Weng. In addition, in the event that the staff has a warning record during the service committee, the renewal order must be properly substantiated, André Cheong said.
Regarding the recruitment of division chiefs, the SAFP director said the objective is "better to organize and constitute the recruitment reserve for government positions."
According to Leong, the five editions of the Driver's Course were attended by 139 workers, with 30% of these already performing boss. The director also promised to “improve the content of the course”, taking into account the previous editions to “organize the curriculum plan”. Leong Weng In clarified that it will be enough to have completed the course once for a candidate to be able to join the recruitment reserve.</description><pubDate>2025-08-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Kneecap rapper appears in court for alleged support to Hezbollah</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/rapper-dos-kneecap-comparece-em-tribunal-por-alegado-apoio-ao-hezbollah/</link><description>Rapper Mo Chara, from the Northern Ireland Rap group Kneecap, accused of displaying a flag of the pro-Árião Islamist movement Hezbollah in a show in London, attended a British court on Wednesday, accused of "terrorist offense." Hundreds of protesters gathered to support the 27-year-old singer, whose real name is Liam O'Hanna at the Westminster Magistrates Court.
Some of his fans sang songs like “Freedom for Palestine,” while others raised Palestinian and Irish flags or posters that asked for the acquittal of Mo Chara.
After the hearing, the protesters applauded the rapper, who arrived at the scene with a Palestinian keffiyeh wrapped around his neck and left the court in freedom, as the judge postponed the verdict to 26 September after three hours of deliberations.
Mo Chara was accompanied by the two group members, who sat at the bottom of the court room.
"Thank you all for coming," said the rapper after the hearing. "This story is more important than me. It's more important than Kneecap," he added, considering that his group was "a distraction compared to the true story." "Keep talking about Palestine, keep saying it's genocide and that this is the true story. This is just another distraction," he said.
It also encouraged fans to continue to “talk about Palestine”. "We know that, unfortunately, this story will stop by the media, while Israel continues to commit genocide. Therefore, I ask you all to talk about Palestine and ask for the release of Palestine. Thanks to everyone for coming," he said.
The Northern Ireland group has appeared in the media in recent months for supporting the Palestinian cause.
In late June, the Kneecap took the Glastonbury Festival stage despite a request from British Prime Minister Keir Stmerer to be withdrawn from the event.
On May 21, Mo Chara was accused of showing a Hezbollah flag, considered as a terrorist in the United Kingdom during a show in London on November 21, 2024.
Both Hezbollah and Hamas are prohibited in the UK and it is a crime to express support for these armed groups.
A few weeks ago, the Hungarian government, very close to Israel, decided to ban the entry of the trio, which should be presented at a festival in that country.
Founded in 2017, the Kneecap Group defends Ireland's reunification and considers its language a "anti -colonialist" scream against British power.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>