<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Record of restaurants in the script of “June, month of Portugal”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/recorde-de-restaurantes-roteiro-de-junho-mes-de-portugal/</link><description>The gastronomic script, understood as an important vehicle for cultural dissemination, is again one of the strengths of the “June, Portugal month” program in Macao. The initiative “Eating and Drinking to the Portuguese” has this year with the adhesion of 29 restoration establishments, which constitutes a record of participation. Several events, a total of 32, will take place throughout the month, including exhibitions, cinema, workshops, releases and book performances, concerts, besides the camp, dance show and lectures. On June 10, there will be the usual rown to the Camões Cave and a reception open to the Portuguese community in the consular residence
 
Victor Rebelo
 
A month full of cultural activities fills the program of “June, Month of Portugal”, which this year has 32 diverse activities, including the bet, for the third consecutive year, in the dissemination of Lusa cuisine. The gastronomic script “Eating and Drinking to the Portuguese” will cover 29 restoration establishments, which is a record of adherent in the face of previous editions.
The promotion of typical Portuguese food in the cultural context of Macao, aims to “stage the places that serve it in the territory”, said Bernardo Pinho said during the press conference yesterday at the facilities of the Consulate General of Portugal in the mashes. The representative of AICEP - Agency for Investment and Foreign Trade of Portugal - considers that “having establishments of all segments present in Macau, is particularly relevant to a more challenging context for some small and medium -sized local businesses”.
As part of the gastronomic script, there will be an extensible offer throughout June, which could be a 10.6% discount (numbers alluding to the main date of celebrations) and a themed menu. At the end of the month and like last year, the organization will hold a draw where each of the adherent restaurants will offer a valid meal for two people.
At the same time, the National Bank Overseas (BNU) will draw a trip from two people to Portugal, for those who use the bank's credit card in the payment of lunches and dinners made at the adherent restaurants. “We have 70,000 credit card customers and so we find it interesting to carry out this integrated initiative in the gastronomic script,” said Carlos Álvares, chairman of the BNU Executive Committee.
 
Open Reception to the Lusa Community
Of course, June 10 will be the main day of the celebrations, including the raising of the flag (at 09:00) at the Consulate, followed by a romant to the Camões Cave, with the presence of students from the Portuguese School of Macao (EPM) and other educational institutions which declares, as traditional, some better known poems of the poet.
In the late afternoon, the Portuguese community will be able to participate in another commemorative reception. The meeting will take place at the consular residence, starting at 18:30 (the doors will open at 6:00 pm), being open to all, without the need for an invitation, even though Consul Alexandre Leitão asked interested parties to make a prior registration, “in the sense that we can manage the interior space for the case of much influx and even to prepare the events that we want to do on the various spaces of Bela Vista”.
The “June, Portugal Month” program features other events, including exhibitions, cinema, workshops, releases and books and concert presentations, in addition to the Arraial, dance show and lectures.
Among the events of the responsibility of Casa de Portugal, highlighting some exhibitions, one of them “quite original”, as said the president of the association, Amelia António, to take place in the Portuguese bookstore, called “Small Worlds in Solid state”, with works on stones, and another, collective, popular carris, to mark Santo António. In addition, the exhibition of images of Macau “yesterday and today” is scheduled, which is based on photographs by Francisco Ricarte, or selected by the artist.
Another of the initiatives of Casa de Portugal is the release of António Lobo Antunes' book “Treaty of the Soul”, presented by physician Shee Va, in a session that will talk about literature and gastronomy, since there are several novels of Portuguese writers who mention Portuguese food, such as Eça de Queirós and Camilo Castelo Branco. In the aforementioned novel, António Lobo Antunes describes a family dinner and the doctor from Macau will make these dishes for a gap after the conversation.
The Portuguese Matrix Association will also collaborate with the Oriente Foundation in a screening of puppets by artist Luísa Vilaça, at Casa Garden, where there will be preparation workshops for children and adults. It will happen on June 3.
 
JOANA ROLO FILM PROJECTION AND CONCERT
Cinema will also be in evidence. At Casa Garden, “the film cycle is organized with the support of the CUT Association,” said Catarina Cottinelli, representative of the Oriente Foundation in Macau.
As for initiatives of the responsibility of the Portuguese Institute of the East (IPOR), the program includes two concerts with Portuguese pianist Joana Rolo. One directed to children and will involve opera at the Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) and one more intimate at the Military Club, on June 6, at 19:30.
According to Patrícia Quaresma, director of IPOR, there will also be a representation, in a book, of the biography of Camões, made by Portuguese teacher Isabel Rio Novo, who will also present the publication in Beijing. The Institute will also promote the launch of a book by Sara Augusto, “The Vast Empire of the Heart”, which is an anthology of the presence of Camões in the literature of Macao, as well as the artistic exchange show between China and Portugal, played by the Portuguese company “Next Step”, in “T Theater Macau”.
Moreover, the program encompasses a live music concert by Bruno Pernadas, “Greatest Bay Area Tour 2025”, in the “None of Your Business” space. In addition, the “June, Portugal Month” will be at the Gallery Amagao with the Portuguese Art Exhibition “Creativity Dialogues”; in the FRC with the documentary “Metamorphosis”; In the Consulate Garden, with the “Diniz Caixapiz Release - Syllable Literary Games edition”, Educational and Literary Association; Also, at the consulate's facilities, with the inauguration of the exhibition of photographs “Cultural Heritage of Macau” and the view of the documentary “Heritople”, by the International Institute.
The Portuguese School (EPM) will receive the São João village, in two days, 13 and 14.
In addition, two seminars are planned. One about “Portugal-Macau Investment Opportunities”, promoted by the Macao Commercial Association Commission of Youth, with the facilities of the influential association. The other directed to the evolution of start-ups in the context of economic diversification, organized by the Association of Public Function Workers (ATFPM), which should have a hundred participants, including some businessmen from Dongguan, Guangdong Province City.
The Lusitano Club of Hong Kong will also associate with events, promoting a reception with the Portuguese community at Raehk on the 9th, as well as organizing a São João party.
“This program pursues an objective that is unavoidable for us, which is to continue working to publicize Portugal, language and culture with all the communities of Macau and those who visit us,” said consul Alexandre Leitão at the end of the press conference.
 
Visit by Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa pointed to after summer
The president of the Portuguese Republic is expected to visit Macau in the second half of this year, "specifically after summer," according to consul Alexandre Leitão. Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa had announced the intention of moving to Macau to celebrate June 10 with the local community, even though he did it at another time of the month, since he will be on that day in national celebrations in lakes, but the current political context in Portugal does not allow it. “When he comes, it will be another phase of the June, Portugal month,” said Alexandre Leitão.</description><pubDate>2025-05-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hundreds of faithful in the Virgin Mary procession in Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/centenas-de-fieis-na-procissao-da-virgem-maria-em-macau/</link><description>Several hundred devotes faithful to Our Lady of Fatima participated in the usual procession of May 13 in Macao, which signaled the day of appearances in the Cova da Iria would just over a century ago. The procession traveled several streets of the city, from the church from São Domingos to the Ermida da Penha. Bishop D. Stephen Lee made the route behind the Andor that carried the image of the Virgin Mary, accompanied by several priests of the diocese. Father Daniel Ribeiro told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that this religious act “serves as a bridge” to unite several communities. The Catholic Armindo Vaz, for his part, considers that “the admiration and love of the Diocese of Macao for the greeting to Our Lady of Fatima is an excellent example of her pluralism and tolerance”



































Victor Rebelo
 
First Mass, with the Church of St. Dominic Full of the faithful, and an hour later, at 18:30, the traditional procession to Our Lady of Fatima began her path through various arteries in the city center.
Several hundred devotees participated in the procession, who wanted to mark May 13, the date of the appearance of Our Lady of Fatima to the shepherds in the Cova da Iria in 1917. The event has been regularly held by the Macao Catholic community, with few interruptions, thus allowing the transmission and continuity of their religious and cultural values.
In addition to faithful from various local, mainly Portuguese and Chinese communities, also many Philippines, people from Hong Kong and a group expressly from Indonesia, accompanied the procession, which began in 1929 and is listed as Macao's intangible cultural heritage. The bishop of Macao, D. Stephen Lee, was just behind the Andor that carried the image of the Virgin Mary, flanked by priests representative of Macao parishes and many acolites and other church helpers, all wearing white clothes.
Ahead, after a long line of young students from Macao Catholic schools, such as the Salesian Institute and the School of Our Lady of Fatima, as well as an association of scouts, which opened the way to unfold quietly and slowly from the procession, was a group of children, including the three who symbolize the shepherds, Lucia, Jacinta and Francisco.
On its way, from the church from São Domingos to Ermida da Penha, where it arrived without daylight, the procession passed through Largo do Senado, Travessa do Roquete, Rua da Sé, Calçada de S. João, Avenida da Praia Grande, Praia do Bom Pertão, Avenida da República, Praia Calçada, Santa Sancha Road and D. João Paulino Road.
Father Daniel Ribeiro told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that “this is one of the best known and most experienced Marian devotions in the world.“ It is no coincidence that many people after baptized were named Fatima, ”he emphasized.
The parish vicar stressed that the act of faith “unites the Portuguese and Chinese communities and the different cultures of Macau, even serving as a bridge to the various Catholic cultures that exist here in the Diocese of Macao”, adding that “everyone has a great affection and much respect for devotion to Our Lady of Fatima”.
For all this, the priest believes that the new Pope, Leo XIV, "will surely visit the Sanctuary of Fatima, because he is a great devotee."
One of the Catholics who accompanied the procession was Armindo Vaz. The JTM stressed that the Catholic faith, and particularly devotion to the Virgin Mary, remain "a remarkable trait of the culture of Macao, with this procession being the best example of this Marian devotion."
He recalled some passages in history, noting that the three shepherds "witnessed the appearance of Our Lady, in which the Virgin Mary asked them to pray their third every day, for world peace and the conversion of sinners, and that they came back there on the 13th of the months."
Continuing, the Portuguese Catholic, resident for several years in Macao, recalled that Our Lady would appear at the three children again in 1917, on June 13, July 13, August 15 (“on August 13 the three shepherds were arrested by the administrator of the municipality of Vila Nova de Ourém”), September 13 and October 13.
In this last appearance, he mentions, would be between 50 and 70,000 people, "who were able to watch the so -called" Miracle of the Sun "where the rain stopped and saw the sun turns over itself for about 10 minutes, then Zigzag returns to its place and restrary there."
The admiration and love of the Diocese of Macau for the greeting Our Lady of Fatima is “an excellent example of her pluralism and tolerance,” concluded Armindo Vaz.</description><pubDate>2025-05-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Prepared” government to help staff and SME linked to satellite casinos</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-preparado-para-ajudar-pessoal-pme-ligados-casinos-satelite/</link><description>The secretary for the economy and finance yesterday assured that the government “is sufficiently prepared” to help the casinos-satellite workers and the commercial establishments operating in the immediate vicinity. According to Tai Kin IP, there are already response plans in this context
 
In response to the oral interpellations presented by deputies Leong Sun Iok, Jose Pereira Coutinho and Leong Hong Sa, the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP, yesterday that the government has already evaluated and prepared response plans for the problems that may come from the end of the satellite casinos.
"The government has made sufficient assessments, having evaluated the current operational situation of the satellite casinos, the number of commercial establishments in operation nearby, the satellite casinos workers and the classification of their jobs. The government knows all this data and is sufficiently prepared," said the secretary, revealing that they were considered several scenarios, depending on the size of the impact.
According to guaranteed, if workers are affected by changes in the operation of the satellite casinos, the direction of services to labor affairs (DSAL) will monitor under the law, in order to ensure the legitimate rights and interests of workers. In addition, it will take the initiative to seek to know the professional interests of local workers, as well as provide proper vocational training and relevant information.
The executive will “help workers as much as possible,” promised the secretary, highlighting that the executive is “experienced enough” in the direction of workers.
In the same line, Tai Kin IP assured that the government is also “sufficiently prepared” in relation to arrangements related to peripheral commercial establishments. "We know all the situations of small and medium enterprises (SMEs) in the surrounding area. What methods will be defined? If they have needs, the government will try to respond to them," he said, arguing that authorities also have "sufficient experience" in community revitalization.
Also within the scope of the game, the secretary for the economy and finance said that the government is still firm in maintaining the proportion of workers residing in medium and high levels of the six game operators at a level of more than 85%, which is worth encouraging them to continue hiring local workers. ” Segundo destacou, no final de Março deste ano, a percentagem real atingia 90%.
The secretary also indicated that the Government proceeded to evaluate the effectiveness of the game -related investment projects, and found that by 2023, it generated a total production of more than 30 billion patacas for the local economy.
 
TNR's “suitable” number serves “general interests”
On the other hand, confronted with the requests of several deputies to adjust the policy related to non -resident workers (TNR), Tai Kin Tip began to reiterate that the main premise is to guarantee priority for workers residing in employment and that their rights and labor interests are not affected.
However, the secretary stressed that, given that Macao is striving to build the World Tourism and Leisure Center and that economic activities focus on services, there is a great demand for human resources. In this context, the “proper importation of TNR to supply the insufficiency of the labor in Macau corresponds to the general interests of Macao,” he said.
As he said, at the end of March this year, there were 183,368 TNR, less 13,170 than at the end of December 2019, with different degrees of reduction for different jobs.
Note that the Gross Domestic Product of the MSAR has registered an expansion of nine times to 450 billion patacas since 2000, the secretary stressed that the demand for human resources increases as the economy grows. In this respect, he also recalled that the number of visitors in Macao in the recent Golden Week rose 40%, while other neighboring regions found only an annual increase of 20%. "It was necessary for all sectors, the whole city and the SMEs to participate in serving visitors. A large dimension of the economy requires a number of workers," he said.
In addition, SME operations face “very difficult conditions”, and the SMEs “need both local and TNR workers”.
"The Government of MSA will continue to promote the development of companies, in order to provide more jobs to residents," he said, stating that the authorities "attribute high importance" and will help unemployed residents who contributed to the recent increase in the unemployment rate at 0.2 percentage points.
DSAL Director Chan Un Tong stressed that, until this date, game operators employed 18,040 TNR, 4,500 less than in 2019. Still, the official stressed that, with economic recovery, it became necessary to add a basic or intensive workforce in this sector.
 
Schedules and facilities easier for residents
During the plenary meeting of the Legislative Assembly to respond to the oral interpeairs presented by the deputies, Tai Kin IP revealed that of the 451 residents who entered employment through the specific plan of “employment + training” in 2024, two saw their work relationship cease because they did not meet the demands of companies during the experimental period.
According to the secretary, DSAL is “fully committed” to creating an integrated vocational training platform, offering order training plans to help residents reach their employment and upward mobility objectives. This platform, he described, will provide training in places near the homes of the trainees and with easy hours for work and rest, including those who work for shifts. The objective is to allow “all the time” opportunities for training to residents and to add on this platform the training resources of the whole society.
In addition, Tai Kin IP said that the Technology Productivity and Transfer Center plans to create a place to perform international certification exams.
Already on a possible need to adjust the basic labor criteria taking into account the development of emerging industries, the secretary stressed that the government will first observe the situation of the market.
Regarding the needs of insurance for emerging sectors, such as delivery platforms, he pointed out that the monetary authority can play a facilitating role, promoting the establishment of contacts between companies interested in the purchase of insurance and the insurance sector, in which the latter proposes viable solutions, such as the implementation of collective accident insurance.
In addition, Kuok Cheong U, Deputy Director of Health Services (SSM), said he will reserve healthcare staff through training and hiring, with the aim of maintaining a stable and secure medical team. The official revealed that the health center in zone A of new landfills will go into operation in the second half of this year, while SSM adjusts the distribution of human resources to this new center according to the residential situation in this area, and may advance with hiring if necessary.
According to the Islands Hospital, in addition to being able to require a number of local health professionals in the future, he will create assistant physician vacancies for medical -graduated candidates and continue to perform, regularly training medical boarding schools, along with the SSM.
 
Thoughtful review of several issues in the work area
In addition to prioritizing studies on the revision of maternity leave and annual holidays, the government will review and consider, at the same time, other labor issues, said the secretary for the economy and finance. To this end, it will “proactively hear” the opinions of deputies and all sectors of society, conduct the analysis in conjunction with the actual situation of Macao, as well as compare local labor criteria with those of other regions, said Tai Kin IP. In general, it has ensured that the executive will develop, in an orderly manner, the works of revision and legislative production, giving priority to the subjects that most concern society.</description><pubDate>2025-05-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Seven Works” for the masters after Xia Baolong's visit</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sete-trabalhos-para-raem-apos-visita-de-xia-baolong/</link><description>After Xia Baolong completed his visit to Macau, Sam Hou Fai highlighted “seven works” to the government and the sectors of society to follow, including consciousness for “adversity in prosperous times”
 
Hong Kong and Macau's Office Director for the Council of State, Xia Baolong, ended his six -day inspection visit to the central government's connection office to hear a work report.
In the balance of the visit, the head of the Executive of the MSAR promised that the government will learn and profoundly implement the “important instructions” transmitted by Xia, distributing well to work tasks, to ensure their effective implementation. At a press conference, Sam Hou Fai highlighted “seven works” to the government and the sectors of society, starting to emphasize that they have to be aware of “preparing for adversity in prosperous times”, identifying, responding and seeking changes proactively as well as being committed to accelerating the development of economic diversification.
Secondly, the industrial and commercial sector needs to assume a greater role in the development of masters and the country, contributing effective actions to the proper diversification of the economy and the construction of hengqin, Sam Hou Fai pointed out.
The third work mentioned implies an accurate interpretation of the “Macau+Hengqin” position, in order to resolve the difficulties encountered in the construction of the in -depth cooperation zone, namely by reinforcing the interconnection of hardware, software and people between the two parts. On the other hand, Sam Hou Fai has linked the need to take advantage of the advantages of MSAR, expand opening, demonstrate greater achievements on the international stage, promote internal and external links, and “tell well” the stories of China and Macao to the world.
In addition, he said that the government will actively mobilize and channel resources to achieve the four important projects announced in the government lines. Sam Hou Fai also expects associations to continue to strengthen the central value of love for the homeland and Macau and reinforce the ability to participate in politics.
In addition, it continued, it is important to create favorable conditions for young people development, including support for studies, employment and entrepreneurship.
On the other hand, quoting Xia Baolong, Sam Hou Fai stressed that the government has to prepare well the elections for the VIII Legislature, so that they are elected in a fair and impartial manner who love the homeland and Macao.
Government secretaries also assured that they will have to consider the guidelines and demands transmitted by Xia Baolong. Raymond Tam, holder of the Transport and Public Works portfolio, has ensured that his protection will “adopt effective measures in the domains of maritime planning, infrastructure construction and regional cooperation, with the aim of promoting the city's orderly development and consolidating social stability through the improvement of population living conditions”. The Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, stated that the government must follow the demands presented by Xia, have “full awareness of the eventuality of seizures”, and “lead the various sectors of society in a total commitment to promoting the economy and improvement of development, remaining firm in defense of sovereignty, security and interests of the country's development and stability of Macau”.
The secretary O Lam considered, in turn, that Xia left “valuable guidelines on the various works of social and cultural spheres”. "The patriotic education of young people will continue to be consolidated, reinforced and deepened," he said, promising efforts to capture qualified paintings and raise the welfare of the population in general.
Already the president of the Legislative Assembly, Kou Hoi In, highlighted the need to promote the tradition of the “love for the homeland and Macau”, and firmly defend the nuclear interests of the country and the prosperity and stability of masters.
 
"Protected" game operators of China-Eua tensions
The Macao government leader guaranteed yesterday that he will protect US casinos operators in the region in case of worsening the trade war between Beijing and Washington. “The six game operators follow the Macao law. Since following the law, these operators develop their businesses, healthily, surely, they are certainly protected and supported by the government,” said Sam Hou Fai. "We always welcome from good foreign investment," including "US capital investments, they are all welcome," he said. On Monday, at a meeting with local entrepreneurs, the director of the Hong Kong and Macao affairs office, Xia Baolong appealed to the unit against “the increase in unilateralism and commercial protectionism in the US,” said the secretary for Economics and Finance of MSAR.</description><pubDate>2025-05-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China wishes to “join hands” with Latin America</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/china-deseja-unir-maos-a-america-latina/</link><description>EPA12095330 Chinese President XI Jinping (C-R, First Row), Brazil President Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva (R, First Row), Chile President President Gabriel Boric (L, First Row) And Colombia President Gustavo Petro (C-L, First Row) Attend A Group Photosion Before The Opening Ceremony for the China-Celac Forum Ministerial Meeting in Beijing, China, 13 May 2025. EPA / FLORENCE LO / POOL



The president of China yesterday proposed the narrowing of relations and cooperation with Latin America and the Caribbean in a period shaken by geopolitical tensions. "Confronted with the stream of geopolitical confrontation and blocks, the height of unilateralism and protectionism, China wants to join its hands with Latin America," said Xi Jinping at the opening of the China-Celac Forum (Latin American and Caribbean Community, which brings together 33 countries).
"Although China, Latin America and Caribbean are distant, both sides have a long history of friendly exchanges," he said. "Only through unity and cooperation can countries safeguard world peace and stability and promote development and prosperity around the world," said the Chinese leader, denouncing "intimidation and hegemony," in reference to the US.
XI has promised support to Celac countries to "reject external interference" and "follow a path of development aligned with their national conditions." "China supports the regional nations in defense of their national sovereignty and independence," he added.
The Chinese president has proposed several initiatives to “build a Sino-Latin American community with a shared future,” as a $ 9.2 billion fund in development credits. It also advocated the expansion of cooperation in areas such as infrastructure, agriculture, mining, digital economy or clean energy, the creation of training programs, as well as working with the region in counterattack and in the fight against organized crime.
Chinese foreign minister Wang Yi said, not expressly mentioning the US, that "certain world power" is "obsessed" with the law of the strongest. Wang encouraged Latin American countries to “act with hand” with Beijing to defend their rights to a power that “uses tariffs as a weapon to intimidate other countries”.
 
Lula praises partnership with China
Despite the 90-day truce in the trade war between China and the US announced on Monday, the issue was a prominence in the rulers' speeches in Beijing, including the Brazilian President, who criticized “the imposition of arbitrary tariffs” and the risk of “starting a new cold war”. Lula da Silva praised the importance of China as “Celac's second largest commercial partner” and “one of the most important direct investors in the region”. "The partnership with China is a dynamic element for the regional economy," he said.
“Free trade and just for the benefit of our peoples is the way for the progress and development of nations,” said Chilean President Gabriel Boric, who advocated “a quality leap” in the economic relationship with China.
Although without direct mentions, Colombian President Gustavo Petro was especially hard with the Trump government, with criticism of migratory politics, greed and negationism of climate change. Petro lamented that dialogue within the Americas “does not advance” and defended the importance of stimulating relations with regions such as Asia, Europe and Africa.
Dialogue with other regions "may be free from authoritarianism, imperialism," he said.
 
JTM with Lusa and International Agencies</description><pubDate>2025-05-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Myanmar thanks the medical team of Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/myanmar-agradece-ajuda-de-equipa-medica-de-macau/</link><description>Myanmar's National Natural Disaster Management Committee thanked and recognized the professional performance of the Emergency Medical team sent by Macau to participate in the rescue work, following the March 28 earthquake. The team also received praise from the World Health Organization
 
The five members of Macau's international emergency team “successfully completed” the mission in Myanmar, having returned to the territory last Friday, according to Health Services (SSM). Through a letter of thanks, Myanmar's National Natural Disaster Management Committee recognized the professional performance of the medical team, which was “highly praised” by the World Health Organization (WHO).
According to the SSM statement, China "fully demonstrated the spirit and responsibility of a great nation," it was one of the "first international powers" to reach the affected areas in Myanmar, following the land of March 28.
During the 14 days, the medical team visited the Embassy of the Popular Republic of China in Myanmar and the Consulate-General of Mandalay, where he held several work meetings with the Myanmar Ministry of Health's International Cooperation Department, the Myanmar Public Health Department and WHO representatives.
The parties involved exchanged "opinions on medical care, response to public health emergencies, and cooperation in epidemiological prevention in disaster -affected areas."
The team also attended at the Myanmar Ministry of Health Post-Sisma Coordination Meeting, where “post-desaster response strategies” were discussed with emergency medical teams and international organizations from various countries. Six more international teams have been developing continuous relief work.
The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, the LAM, and the advisor to the Study Study of the Policy of the Commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Popular Republic of China in Mashere, MA Naifang, expressed their “recognition and encouragement” to members of the Macao team.
In turn, the medical team presented the situation of the work in Myanmar, which allowed “accumulating valuable experiences for emergency medical work in Macao,” the SSM say.</description><pubDate>2025-05-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mand forms 19 Lusophone professionals in the "fintech" area</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-forma-19-profissionais-lusofonos-na-area-das-fintech/</link><description>For two weeks, 19 insurance supervisors from Macao and Lusophone countries will participate in an advanced training in the area of ​​financial services, which aims to bring local regulatory standards closer to international standards
 
Dezanove insurance supervisors will participate in the two weeks of the “Advanced Training and Study Visit for Supervisors of the Lusophone Insurance Supervisors Association”, co-organized by the Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM) and the Authority of Insurance and Pension Funds (ASF).
The trainees, from Angola, Brazil, Cape Verde, Mozambique, Portugal, Timor-Leste and Macau, participated in the inaugural seminar “Development and Supervision of Insurance to face the challenges of the New Age”. The event brought together leaders and experts in insurance supervision, from China and Portuguese -speaking countries (PLP), and financial and technological sectors for an exchange of “new perspectives and deep inspirations”.
Vong Lap Fong, AMCM administrator, considered that the seminar demonstrated “Macao's unique advantages” as a “financial services platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”. "International regulatory cooperation is increasingly important in view of the rapid development of digital transformation," continued Vong Lap Fong to reinforce the ability to "face the challenges placed by digitization" and promote "stable development of the insurance market."
In the same vein, Henrietta Lau Hang Kun, representing the Secretary for Economics and Finance, said Macau has taken "full advantage of the institutional advantages provided by the" one country, two systems "principle. According to AMCM Substitute President, MSAR has been actively engaged in the construction of the Sino-Lusophone platform in the area of ​​financial services.
This year the Macao's obligationary market has realized direct interconnection with the Hong Kong obligationist market, which created an accessible channel for an active participation of foreign investors, AMCM says.
The organization of this formation resulted from regulatory cooperation between Macao and Portugal, highlighted the chairman of the board of ASF, Margarida Corrêa de Aguiar, who stressed the need to adjust the regulatory framework in accordance with digital transformation, “in order to find a balance between technological innovation, financial stability and consumer protection”.
The same responsible also stressed "the importance of organizational cooperation and knowledge sharing in the face of the challenges of the New Age." The purpose of the initiative is to “reinforce the technical capabilities of the sector and facilitate the exchange of practical experiences in the insurance sector”.
According to AMCM, the regulatory framework of the area of ​​insurance “has been continually improved”, and the Government of MSAR has begun the study of “risk -based capital framework” in the sense of “aligning local standards with international regulatory standards” and reinforcing the supervision of solvency of insurance institutions.
 
“More attention” to the risks of interest and climate crisis
For its part, Xiao Yuanqi, a subdirector of the National Administration of Financial Regulation (NFR), said that "the worldwide insurance sector should pay more attention to the risk of interest rate and the risk of concentration and proactively respond to the challenges placed by climate change." He has warned, "insurance companies need to establish development strategies and business models that correspond to their resources and maintain flexibility in response to change circumstances," reinforcing the ability to deal with "operating uncertainty risks."
Xiao also stressed the need to develop “a healthy business culture of honesty, reliability, compliance with laws and regulations and sustainable development”.
In the same statement, AMCM advances that it will organize visits to cities of the continent to make known the “development of insurance technology in the interior of China”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Cultural essence” exalted on International Museum Day</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/essencia-cultural-exaltada-dia-internacional-dos-museus/</link><description>Next Sunday, a ceremony on access to the Fortaleza do Monte will mark the start of a set of activities organized by various Museums of the Museums, in celebration of International Museum Day and “Macao Cultural Essence”
 
More than 20 Macao museums will organize a series of activities within the International Museum Day, to highlight “the cultural essence of Macao” and create “an intensely cultural and festive environment for communities”. At 3:00 pm on Sunday, May 18, access to Fortaleza do Monte will have an opening ceremony, followed by “rich shows and activities”, according to the Cultural Institute (IC).
Under the theme “The future of museums in constantly evolving communities” will take place workshops, the “Museum Corridor” exhibition, the “Escaping Cosmos Museum” game and guided tours, which will depart from access to Mount Fortress and pass several museums “in a special course”. The exhibition, patent between May 18 and June 15 in access to Fortaleza do Monte, will allow visitors to obtain information about the exhibitions of the Macao Museological Institutions.
The activity “Set of Museum Seals” will also be launched, in which visitors will be able to raise blank postcards at the exhibition site and in selected museums, and complete a set of commemorative seals.
On Saturday and Sunday, the organization will also install free “mobile museums” in the North Zone, Central and Cotai, “in order to further promote museums in the community”.
On May 23rd, between 10:30 and 17:00, the Wu Yee Sun Library of the University of Macau will host the “Museum Development Exchange Conference in the Great Bay Zone”. Experts and academics from the International Museum Council, China Museum Association and the Great Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau Bay Museum Alliance will discuss the theme of this year's edition in depth.
According to the IC statement, guests will also share “their practical experiences and research results” on the development, innovation and cooperation of museums.
Registration for guided tours and the game are open until May 15th. There will be a limited number of places for registration on site, available in order of arrival. Interested parties can access the “Activities Registration” section in the single account.
International Museum Day, designated by the International Council of Museums in 1977, aims to “sensitize the public to the importance of museums and jointly promote the continuous development of the museum sector”.
Participating museum institutions and entities include the old Chong Sai Pharmacy, Sacred and Crypt Museum, Tung Sin Tong Historical Archive Gallery, the Heritage Space - A Traditional Pity House, Xian Xinghai Memorial Museum, Poly MGM Museum, Firefighters Museum, Maritime Museum, Museum of Communications, The Sacred Art Treasury de S. José, former residence of General Ye Ting, Museum of Taipa and Coloane History, Zheng Guanying Memorial Museum, Macao University Museum, Macao Grand Museum, House of Literature, Museum of Sovereignty, Memorial Lin Zexu Museum, Museum of Science, Museum of Art, Museum Taipa, Kiang Wu Historical Museum and the Jao Tsung-i Academy.</description><pubDate>2025-05-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Orchestra inspires young local musicians</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/orquestra-de-macau-inspira-jovens-musicos-locais/</link><description>Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment presented the event “Macau Orchestra Meet The Musicians” to “inspire the next generation” and offer young people and their families the opportunity to get involved with Macao orchestra musicians. Assistant conductor Tony Cheng-Te Ye, Timpanist David Burns and percussionists Chang Hio Man and Fung Chan Chi Wai shared professional experiences and knowledge with the public, in a “unique learning opportunity for all participants,” says Melco's statement. Clarence Chung, the company's administrator, said the "initiative shows Melco's efforts to strengthen Macao Statute as a Global Center for Performative Arts." Clarence Chung also highlighted Melco's support in the development of young talents in the arts “for the sustainable growth of the city”. Participants were students and teachers of the Macao Percussion Association, the Tamagnini Barbosa Community Center, the Macao Conservatory and the “Modern Player Music Promotion Association”. The event is part of Melco's initiatives, which aim to “provide inspiring opportunities to young people” and offer them exposure to world-class conductors in the areas of arts and innovation.</description><pubDate>2025-05-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief provides for visiting Portugal in July and admits to including Spain in the journey</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-preve-visitar-portugal-em-julho-admite-incluir-espanha-periplo/</link><description>The head of the Executive of the MSAR should visit Portugal in July, yesterday said Sam Hou Fai itself, also revealing that the trip to Europe could include a passage through Spain, "to find more development projects between Macao and these countries." According to it, it will be necessary to wait for the outcome of legislative elections in Portugal, anticipated for next Sunday, to define the calendar of the official visit. In any case, it has indicated that the Macao delegation will include local entrepreneurs from industrial, commercial and financial sectors and "even certain companies in the interior of China." At a press conference for a balance of Xia Baolong's visit, the Hong Kong and Macau's Office Director with the Council of State, the Chief Executive reiterated that the MSar wants to attract more foreign investors, including Portuguese and Spanish languages. "As long as they are in favor of economic diversification, they are always welcome," he added. Local entrepreneurs should “explore Spanish and Portuguese -speaking markets and Africa markets and the Middle East,” he said, stressing that it is “the role of Macao on the international stage”, attributed by the Chinese central government. "We have to know what our advantages are and promote our course of development abroad," he said. In a statement issued Monday night, Sam Hou Fai had already appealed to the industrial and commercial sector to "attract more investments from foreign capital and concentrate on Macao more resources [human] of high quality." Entrepreneurs should “take full advantage of the unique role and the unique advantages of Macao to“ actively explore priority markets, such as those of Portuguese -speaking countries, ”he added.</description><pubDate>2025-05-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2396/</link><description>Brief
Air Macau must resume flights for chongqing
Air Macau plans to restore the route between the Jiangbei International Airport and the largest of Chongqing, a mega Chinese municipality with about 32 million. According to the portal "Chongqing News", the flights should be resumed on July 2, with a frequency of three per week.
 
Telecommunications Day celebrates “gender equality”
Macao will hold on Saturday several activities to mark World Telecommunications Day and the Information Society, instituted by the International Union of Telecommunications. According to Post Office and Telecommunications Services (CTT), the program included a lecture on “gender equality in digital transformation” and free distribution of envelopes alluding to the date. The commemorative stamp service will also be available at CTT Central Station and the Communications Museum. Telecommunications operators will offer different promotions to their customers.
 
“Explanated” medicines in Macau's Single Account
In order to promote “intelligent medicine”, health services included the function of visualizing medicines prescribed in the “medicines in use” interface of the Macao Single Account. If you select a drug brand, users can consult information such as photographs, composition, form, dosages, common indications, possible side effects and drug dosage, among others. In addition, they can make a comparison between recently prescribed drugs and previously, with a view to reducing any doubts generated by differences in external packaging.
 
Tested fire response at the maritime terminal
Together with customs services, public safety police, firefighters and health services, the direction of maritime and water services (DSAMA) performed an exercise at the outdoor port maritime terminal, in order to reinforce the response capacity of infrastructure exploiting entities on evacuation procedures in case of fire. The simulacrum was attended by about 120 people from those organisms and service concessionaires at the terminal. According to Dsama, "the exercise took place without startles, and the planned objectives were implemented."
 
ELP military personnel donated blood for the 22nd time
About 130 officers and soldiers participated in the 22nd Blood Donation Activity of the Macao of the Chinese People's Liberation Army (ELP), recently performed in the mud, reported the health services. The head of the garrison security department, Zhang Chundong, stressed that this type of initiative demonstrates the heart of “home second” and genuine love of “blood to the water” Contribution, with concrete actions, to the public interest of Macau. This idea was also reinforced by the secretary for social affairs and culture, LAM, also present at the ceremony.</description><pubDate>2025-05-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Health services will extend medical support to unsubsidized homes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/servicos-de-saude-vao-estender-apoio-medico-lares-nao-subsidiados/</link><description>The medical support provided by health services in the elderly will be extended to other unsubsidized institutions. Proximity services, which already include home care to patients with reduced mobility, will be developed through the “medical cooperation” model ”model”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Macao health services (SSM) will extend medical support in the elderly homes in other non-subsidized senior spaces through the “medical cooperation model” model. In addition, SSM, in collaboration with non -profit medical institutions, reiterate the availability to continue to provide home care to patients with reduced mobility.
It is recalled that, currently, the proximity medical services cover all homes subsidized by the government and two rehabilitation centers and the residence for the elderly.
The information is included in response to an interpellation of Deputy José Pereira Coutinho, in which the SSM stresses that partnerships with non -profit medical institutions have been established in the provision of health care to the elderly or residents of Macao holders of the disability assessment card through financial support. At the same time, the health care reimbursement program provides subsidies to residents to travel to private clinics to optimize accessibility and convenience of access to health care.
In response to the deputy, the issue of accessibility in transport is also addressed. In this field, the Directorate of Traffic Affairs Services (DSAT) points out that a series of affordable transportation services and complementary measures to guarantee the mobility rights of disabled elderly have been implemented, including the exemption of tariffs in public bus holders for elderly and card holders for disabled people.
On the other hand, it reinforces the obligation that new acquired buses are equipped with accessibility devices (such as relegated flooring, wheelchair space and their fixing device, among others). According to data recorded until March this year, there were 974 buses equipped with relegated floor, representing about 99% of the total fleet in operation, and 883 buses with wheelchair fixation equipment, corresponding to about 90% of the fleet.
At the same time, DSAT asserts that it is also promoted to introduce accessible vehicles into taxi fleets. Currently, 12 accessible taxis and 10 with mechanical access equipment, available to people with reduced mobility or other specific needs, are in operation.
"DSAT will continue to pay attention to the use situation of these taxis, due to the timely assessing their number," says the body.
DSAT also recalls that the “General Planning of Traffic and Terrestrial Transport of Macao (2021-2030)” has incorporated the principle of improvement of barriers without barriers and measures, namely the “optimization of the pedestrian environment, the complementary equipment of the buses and taxi services, in order to achieve the government's goal of building a city without barriers”.
 
Expansion of careers for residence for the elderly
In response to another interpellation, now from Deputy Nick Lei, the president of the Institute of Social Action (IAS), Hon Wai, says, in turn, that DSAT is evaluating the possibility of expanding careers of public buses to include the terminal and nearby residence for the elderly. The evaluation is based on the calendar of inspection and reception of public roads and the Punching Terminal of Lot P, in the Black Sand, as well as the calendar of the entry into operation of the housing and installations of the respective lot.
The objective, emphasizes IAS, “is to promote, in a coordinated manner, the conduct of buses with buses and the introduction of public bus services in this lot, with the objective of facilitating the public travel”.
In order to facilitate access to the health care of the elderly of the residence, the president of IAS stresses that the health services have already launched the external consultation at a distance, having provided “One-Stop” services, namely online registration, video consult, revenue issuance, drug dismissal, among others. In addition, external medical services have already extended to the government's residence for the elderly.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Xia Baolong wants “high standard” cultural space in Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/xia-baolong-quer-espaco-cultural-de-alto-padrao-em-macau/</link><description>In the inspection visit to Macao, the director of the RAE affairs to the State Council stressed that, in addition to the preservation of cultural heritage, Macau must also advance with revitalization. In addition, Xia Baolong urged the creation of “a high standard cultural space” in the territory
 
On the fourth day of its official trip to Macau, Xia Baolong, director of the Hong Kong and Macau affairs office with the Council of State, visited several establishments of cultural interest. The Chinese leader took advantage of the occasion to urge the Government of Misreial to create “a high standard cultural space that has cultural value and contemporary atmosphere,” according to Lam, secretary for social affairs and culture.
For this goal to be achieved, Xia Baolong hopes that the local executive will study seriously, the strands of planning, construction and management, and proceed to several demonstrations, added Lam. According to the secretary, the director "expressed high attention to the situation of the planning of the" International Integrated Tourist and Cultural Neighborhood "and the development of the cultural industry in Macau.
LAM also stressed that the Chinese leader specifically expressed a "great interest" for the work dedicated to the protection of Macau's cultural heritage. In this chapter, he considered that, in addition to preservation, the territory must also "advance with revitalization."
In addition, Xia Baolong hopes that the government of the MSA will continue to make the most of the patriotic elements of the projects, such as the Lin Zexu Memorial Museum, Xian Xinghai Memorial Museum, the village of Mong-há and former residence of General Ye Ting, which visited that day, as well as the D. Pedro V Theater, in order to contribute to a good execution of the work of love for the Patria and Macao.
Regarding her guardianship, the secretary assured that she will, according to Xia Baolong's orientation opinions and under the leadership of the Chief Executive, intensify the union and collaboration, as well as interdepartal cooperation. LAM promised to strive to promote Macau as a “important high-level bridge in the country for opening abroad” and an “important door for exchange and mutual learning between Chinese and Western civilizations”, strengthen Macau's positioning as “a base”, and perform well the planning and construction of the “integrated tourist and cultural neighborhood”.
In addition, the ruler stressed that she will take advantage of tourist resources and further promote culture, in favor of developing the proper diversification of the economy.
 
Entrepreneurs heard appeals to the Union
Yesterday, a penultimate day of the visit, Xia Baolong met in the morning, for two hours, with representatives of the Macao Industrial and Commercial Sector in the Forum Complex. After the meeting, Tai Kin IP, secretary for the economy and finance, revealed that Xia praised Hong Kong and Macau entrepreneurs for their persistence in the tradition of love of the homeland and both sins, as well as taking responsibility and sharing the country's concerns at important times in national development, and their successes.
Xia Baolong concluded that this proves that the development of the RAE industrial and commercial sector and the country's development constitute a community of common destination.
According to Tai Kin IP, the director mentioned the current situation of international development as well as US unilateralism and commercial protectionism. In this sense, Xia Baolong pointed out that the industrial and commercial sector of the RAE should join and be on the same side of the homeland, warning that there would be no way out if they made concessions.
The Chinese leader also appealed to entrepreneurs' boldness, hoping that they are full of trust in economic development, invest in Hong Kong and Macao, take advantage of the advantages of the two regions and open even more abroad.
During the meeting, Xia Baolong listened to more than 20 representatives of the MSAR who presented proposals on the proper diversification of the economy, the current economic situation and the development of Macao.
Tai Kin IP has ensured that the team of its guardianship will, according to this year's governing lines, to implement the various works of economic development. At the same time, it will continue to hence opinions and suggestions from the various sectors of society, to study them deeply and to promote them.
He said, Xia Baolong urged the government, especially the protection of the economy and finance, to maintain communication with the industrial and commercial sector after this meeting to discuss issues by theme, in order to actively realize the expressed opinions.
Present at this meeting, Jia Tianbing, president of the Macao Banks Association and Boc Macau, stressed that the sector received "important signs." The official stressed that BOC Macau will take a number of measures to seek Macao's economic development, including future transfronist services related to Digital Pataca and a commercial and commercial service platform between China, Lusophone and Hispanic countries in Hengqin, which is already being created.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Centuries of cultural heritage destroyed by the earthquake in Myanmar</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/seculos-de-patrimonio-cultural-destruidos-pelo-sismo-em-myanmar/</link><description>A secular religious heritage was reduced to rubble when a strong earthquake hit Myanmar: the famous studies- Buddhist monuments of the Asian continent, usually used as mausoleum or place of devotion- Buddha statues, and the immaculate white temple where the elderly Khin Sein used to pray, everything fell.
The magnitude 7.7 earthquake on March 28 destroyed the Nagayon Temple in Central City of Mandalay, as well as many other historical places in Myanmar's last real capital.
"When the earthquake began, I screamed to pray that the Nagayon temple save me, but my son told me that the temple had already collapsed," said Khin Sein, 83.
“I don't think a bricklayer or architect could reconstruct it identically,” explains the woman with tears in her eyes as she walks around where she will pray for over half a century.
The landslide in the Sagaing failure line, which crosses Myanmar in the north-south direction, destroyed more than 3,000 monasteries and convents and at least 5,000 temples, the Military Junta said. Three quarters of the historic buildings listed in a “ancient cultural heritage zone” were damaged, according to the authorities.
Thu Nanda went there to visit what was left of the brick monastery naked, built in 1818. "Old things have the highest value," explains the 49 -year -old monk. "The loss of historical heritage starts our hearts."
“Even if we could notice it, people couldn't feel the same as they would feel if it was the original,” adds Thu Nanda. “I think the loss of our heritage will not only affect our country, but the whole world,” he laments.
The rains that approach the beginning of the monsoon station will complicate the search for human remains under the rubble, which is still the priority of the authorities.
The reconstruction of the damaged heritage is still under discussion.
Myanmar citizens are used to mass destruction, either by war or natural disasters. However, Thein Myint Ko says "never seeing a tragedy like this in 65 years of life." “I'm devastated,” he says.
However, in the middle of all the destruction, a monumental Buddha marble statue, eight meters high, was almost intact. Its golden edge was broken and the cracked base, but the master's serene expression is intact.
“No one was injured and Buddha's image survived,” says a man who cleanses the ruins at the foot of the statue. "This temple is really blessed," he added.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-05-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>