<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Detected two more medical errors in 11 skills</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/detectados-mais-dois-erros-medicos-em-11-pericias/</link><description>Among the end of February 2023 and the same month of 2024, medical errors were detected in two of the 11 cases evaluated. Since its inception in 2017 and until February 2024, the Medical Error Expertise Commission has classified 12 cases as a medical error, in a total of 71 processes completed
 
Pedro Milheirão
The Medical Error Expertise Commission registered two cases classified as a medical error in the 11 expertise that completed from February 26, 2023 and 25 February 2024. In addition to these proceedings, the expertise of a case was performed “under the terms of procedural law”, determined in court, according to the commission.
Considering the accumulated data between February 26, 2017, the date of the Commission's entry into operation, and February 25, 2024, the targeted health professionals were eventually unlawful in 83.1% of the investigated cases. In concrete, 12 cases of medical error were confirmed in a total of 71 skills performed over the course of these seven years.
In the period covered by the new annual report, and excluding the case whose expertise was determined by the Court, the percentage of cases of medical error against the number of expertise performed was set by 18.2%, thus less than half of the registered between February 2022 and the same month of 2023 (40%). On the other hand, it reached twice the annual term ended on February 25, 2022 (9.1%).
The committee chaired by Pang Heong Keong received 65 service records, 44 less compared to the previous year, and held 83 meetings compared to 81 held between February 26, 2022 and 25 February 2023.
In the preparation of reports of expert cases, the commission made two inspections on site, held 72 oral and one writing hearings and accessed 65 clinical processes of public and private hospitals, health centers and traditional Chinese and Western medicine clinics. The group also heard the opinions of three experts and five professional organizations and took 81 texts of professional documents.
Following “a detailed analysis and discussion”, the committee submitted 28 proposals for “prevention of similar medical errors or improving medical services”. Report recommendations include three items to strengthen specialized support and interdepartal cooperation, six to standardize the wording and management of medical records and reinforce medical communication, seven to protect the right to informed consent and nine to improve the guidelines and procedures for diagnosis and clinical treatment.
The commission received six complaints regarding the expert report, four of which were filed by patients and two by the medical part. Only five cases were appreciated, since one was rejected by exceeding the legal deadline, but the content and conclusions of the respective reports were maintained, says the agency, which did not receive any request for autopsy during the period under analysis.
The “internal norms” and “work processes” were also reviewed and optimized, and the “emergency treatment procedures” were also prepared, the activities report, without presenting additional details. The commission was also invited to share the problems observed in the expertise of medical error with health professionals, in order to promote an “improvement of the quality of Macao medical services”.
The Medical Error Expertise Commission has been chaired by Pang Heong Keong since 2023, whose appointment has been renewed for two years until February 2027, by the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai. The new members of the Commission are Liu Dayue, as effective, and Ieong Kin Mui, as alternate, both in the area of ​​medicine. Health professionals chan im kuan, goes Man Chi and Ma Hok Cheung remain as effective members, as well as jurists Chu Lam Lam and Lin Wei Qiang. Subsequent members Zhu Xian Lun Cannon of Medicine, and I am Kin Fong, from the law area, were also reappointed by the leader of the MSAR.
In order to integrate the committee, appointed members must have 10 years of experience in the “exercise of specialized technical functions” and an “proper deontological professional conduct”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cultural Institute is reviewing Heritage safeguarding</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/instituto-cultural-esta-rever-lei-de-salvaguarda-patrimonio/</link><description>The Heritage Settlement Law, in force since 2013, is being amended by the Cultural Institute. The body led by Leong Wai Man intends to simplify the request for works of works in secondary areas within the protection zones
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The Cultural Institute (IC) “is changing the law of safeguarding cultural heritage, reviewing the application of the legislation”. Among the points that will be the subject of review are "a reasonable simplification of the request for works of works in secondary areas within the protection zones." In addition, “the process of appreciation and approval will be optimized, in order to reinforce business dynamics in the old neighborhoods” - this with the aim of “better promoting the development of the six historical zones”. The law has been in force since 2013.
The information comes in response to a Wong Kit Cheng written interpellation about the revitalization plan of the six historical areas. The deputy showed concern about the “dispersion of private property rights verified in various zones and neighborhoods”, as well as “the situation in which the work of changing the purpose of buildings and beautification and maintenance are subject to the restrictions provided for in the legislation in force”. In this sense, he had questioned whether the executive intended to create a working group to review the diplomas concerned.
According to the IC revealed at the end of last year to this newspaper, over 10 years, 145 violations of the cultural heritage safeguard law, mostly committed by local residents and commercials, have been registered. At the time, the body also said that in a timely manner it would review the legislation.
Wong Kit Cheng's questions also arisen following the government's announcement that the revitalization of these zones will move from the authority of the Secretariat to Social Affairs and Culture to the Secretariat of Economics and Finance. The Substitute Director of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) said that to intensify the efforts to promote community economy and tourism development, "IC has expressed that it will actively collaborate with government objectives (…) deepening the historical and cultural characteristics of these areas."
In particular, he spoke in the restoration of historic buildings located there, improving existing facilities and providing technical support and assistance to the revitalization of these buildings. “IC will continue to coordinate with the zone development plan and explore in depth the cultural connotations of Macao, through the study of historical, tangible and non-heritage resources,” reads in the response signed by Chan Chou Weng.
Vinking that the development of these six areas “is a medium -term plan involving construction works, road reconstruction, restoration of historical buildings and improvement of the urban landscape,” the DSEDT subdirector added that the work is being done by phases. "Based on the experience of other countries and regions on community revitalization, the intersectory working group will perform their own advantages and coordination," he said.
In the same answer, it is said that the direction of soil services and urban construction (DSSCU) indicated that the six zones are mostly in the old neighborhoods and that, according to the directing plan, renewal and development “must have as its fundamental principles the increase in efficiency in the use of land and the preservation of community characteristics”. In this context, the body “will actively collaborate (…) in revitalization work, articulating, respect for planning conditions and established principles, the work of reconstruction, repair and beautification of buildings”.
He also stressed that the government is elaborating the detail plans of each zone, taking into account "the current situation and specific needs of each". The final intention is to “progressively improve the general disposition of space, sanitary and environmental conditions, afforestation, public facilities and the use of historical and cultural elements”, as well as improve the lives of residents and the commercial environment.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Angola closes contract with Huawei worth $ 110 million</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/angola-fecha-contrato-huawei-valor-de-110-milhoes-de-dolares/</link><description>The Minister of Energy and Águas de Angola was in Macau for the 16th International Forum and Investment Investment and Construction Exhibition, where he signed a memorandum with the Chinese company “Smeco”. Today, it will be in Shenzhen to sign a $ 110 million contract with Huawei to create a “closer connection” with the company. João Baptista Borges says that among Angola's priorities are access to financing, knowledge and technology
 
Pedro Milheirão
After being in Macao for the International Forum and Infrastructure Investment and Construction Exhibition, the Angola government, represented by the Minister of Energy and Waters of Angola, will be in Shenzhen today to sign an agreement with Huawei. According to João Baptista Borges yesterday, the contract will be worth $ 110 million. Objectives are to improve data communication and control systems and reinforce clientele management capacity, he explained.
The ruler spoke of the company's presence in the African country, highlighting the “confidence that Huawei deposits in our market, in our country”, and expressed the intention to create a “closer connection” with it. He also highlighted the fact that the technology has already built an infrastructure that "forms many local frames and also provides technology and equipment."
The minister reiterated that Angola already has "identified projects" and that access to financing, knowledge and technology are the "great priorities". Baptista Borges gave the example of Portugal, where Chinese companies acquired EDP assets. "State Grid owns the electric system in Portugal. In Brazil, there has also been the acquisition of assets and what we want is this form of investment in Angola." For the ruler, China's cooperation with African countries, as in the case of Angola, must “go from the traditional state financing solution to a direct investment” by Chinese companies. "We have great opportunities," he said.
The Angola government also signed a memorandum of understanding, with the Chinese “SMECO”, for the development of production and energy and water distribution infrastructures. "We need to expand the capabilities of water capture and treatment. We have many rivers, but we need water to be treated, to be distributed, which requires investment, the minister explained. He also recalled that the Government's goal is to be able to bring electricity to 60% of the population, until the end of the term. Currently, only 44% of the population has access to electricity.
In addition, João Baptista Borges stressed the need to expand the entire communications and fiber optic network, and to install clients management servers and systems. "Infrastructure projects are in fact relevant in what is the framework of our National Development Plan. The other activities, such as agriculture and industry, depend greatly on the availability of infrastructure and for this reason, we want to further deepen this cooperation for Chinese companies to continue to support and develop projects in Angola," he said.
As part of his second visit to Macau, within the Forum, Borges asserted that the collaboration between Angola and China has been notable in recent years. ” The day before yesterday, one of the themes of the event was the cooperation between China and the countries of Portuguese expression. The Angolan ruler stated that there was no meeting with the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, having expressed appreciation for the words that the leader of the masters addressed the representatives of Angola, on the first day of the event.
The African country subscribed to the initiative “a track, a route”, which has financed much of the infrastructure rehabilitation and development program in Angola. The Angolan minister praised the “substantial financial support of China” and highlighted the example of the Caculo Cabaça Hydroelectric Center, which has already generated “five thousand jobs”. Other projects with Chinese investment involving a water supply system and drought bars should “integrate more than 1,500 young people,” he said. "One of the major objectives of these infrastructure projects is to absorb the maximum workforce," he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Main names in Formula 4 will be invited to the GP Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/principais-nomes-da-formula-4-vao-ser-convidados-para-gp-macau/</link><description>The grids for the Formula 4 World Cups and the regional formula of this year's Macao Grand Prix will begin to take shape, as the International Automobile Federation has opened the registration period. The pilot selection will be made by invitation. Formula 4, which debuts as a World Cup in November at MSA, will feature young people in the various championships of the category, some of which will start this month. Names like English Freddie Slater, Japanese Slovan Nakmamura-Berta and Americans Bohra Akshay and Sebastian Wheldon are expected to be included in the list. The FIA ​​is currently performing its world council in Macau
 
Victor Rebelo
 
It is still early to be known the list of registrants for monolo canolings integrated in this year's Macao Grand Prix (GPM) program, but the grill will begin to define as soon as the registration period is over. The pilot selection for the two World Cup events, so supervising the International Automobile Federation (FIA), will be made by invitation, with priority for the names in the most prominent in the various regional and national championships that are competed in the continents.
The FIA ​​recently reported that there will be 20 competitors for Formula 4 (F4) and 23 for the Regional Formula (FR) and that registration, for the pre-selection phase, are open in both cases until 30 of July.
The highest expectation points to F4, which returns to the Guide Circuit, after four consecutive years (from 2020 to 2023), in a category, integrated in the Chinese Championship, which served as an alternative to the impossibility of having in Macao foreign pilots because of the pandemic.
Emanuele Pirro, chairman of the FIA ​​monuoligae Committee, said on the body's website that "the way to a remarkable edition of one of the most prestigious events of automobile sport begins here, with the opening of registrations for what will be a 72nd Macao Grand Macao Award."
In recent years, the FIA, the GPM Organizing Committee and the General Association of Macau-China Automobile (AAMC) have taken advantage of “the incredible inheritance of Macao, making the event the headquarters of our monolos world cups,” said the leader and ancient Italian driver. "With the lists of registrants to take shape in the FR, GT and, for the first time, in F4, the GPM Statute as the world's largest junior running talent is even more reinforced," he said.
Regarding names that may be on the F4 grid in Macao, everything points out that the main riders of the respective championships, including the European Center, move to the territory. They will probably be present at the asphalt of the pilots guide such as the English Freddie Slater (although it ran in the 2024 FR), Japanese Slovan Nakmamura-Berta, Austrian Oscar Wurz and Americans Bohra Akshay and Sebastian Wheldon. On another level, the Brazilian Gabriel Gomes, the English Martin Molná, Fionn McLaughlin and James Piszcyk, and the Chinese Yuhao Fu.
Meanwhile, the FIA ​​has confirmed that Pirelli will become the only tire supplier for FIA -certified regional formula championships, which will introduce the next generation of cars from 2026. As the remaining championships introduce the new vehicle the following time, they will also use Pirelli as an official tire supplier.
The Transalpina brand, which is also the Global Formula 1, Formula 2 and FI -FIA Championship Tire Partner, will provide 15 inch tires as part of the FR second generation updating package, which starts in 2026. These new high -performance tires were specifically designed for category requirements and will support greater technical relevance, a better racing and racing exhibition. Consistent patterns in the five regional championships, reinforcing the role of FR as a fundamental stage in the path of monologues.
In addition to the changes to 2026, it has also been confirmed that Pirelli will provide tires to the 2025 Fia FR World Cup and the Fia F4 Inaugural World Cup, which will take place on the streets of Macao from 13 to 16 November.
"This next phase of the FR reflects our ambition to create a truly modern, competitive and accessible platform for the development of pilots," said the FIA ​​president. Mohammed Ben Suulaym, who came to MSar to participate in the body's world council, added that "with technical innovation at its center, controlled costs and a clear route from regional series to the upper range of sport, we are investing in the future of global automobile sports."
Among some FIA ​​deliberations already taken to the World Council in Macao, highlighting the approval of the entry of the Madrid Grand Prix on the 2026 Formula 1 (F1) calendar and the continuity of Portugal at the Toda-Oterreno World Cup.
The Council also approved the use of 100% renewable fuels in F1 from next year, in which the introduction of new technical regulations and new teams will be registered.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Plane crash in India will not have left survivors</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/queda-de-aviao-na-india-nao-tera-deixado-sobreviventes/</link><description>EPA12171335 DEBRIS AT THE SITE OF A PLANSH NEAR SARLLABHBHAI PATEL INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT IN AHMEDABAD, GUJARAT, WESTERN INDIA, 12 June 2025. AIR INDIA FLIGHT AI171, BOUND FOR LONDON CARRYING 242 PASGERS AND CREW MEASURES ON BOEING 787-8 Aircraft, Crashed Minutes After Take-Off in the Meghaninar Area of ​​Ahmedabad.  EPA/SIDDHARAJ SOLANKI



Indian police admitted that there should be no survivors among the more than 240 people, including seven Luso-India, who were on the Air India plane who fired yesterday in a residential area of ​​Ahmedabad, still causing victims on land. "It seems that there are no survivors in the plane crash," said local police commissioner G.S. Malik, quoted by international agencies, at a time when 204 bodies had already been found.
The Indian channel NDTV reported that at least five people were died and several were injured after the flight AI171 was drew against a medical student residence. Deadly victims are four college students and a resident doctor of BJ Medical College.
The Boeing 787-8 Dreamliner, which would make the connection between Ahmedabad and London, carried 242 people, including 230 passengers, two pilots and 10 crew members. According to Air India, the list of passengers was part of 169 Indians, 53 British, seven Portuguese and one Canadian.
The Secretary of State for Portuguese Communities, Emídio Sousa, said that the seven Portuguese passengers will have double nationality. The Portuguese authorities consulted the passenger list and found that “the names are not of Portuguese origin, they are double nationality,” he said, addressing condolences to all relatives of the victims. The Portuguese Prime Minister, Luís Montenegro, also expressed “deep dismay” and expressed “votes for grief and deep solidarity with the victims' relatives”.
Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi classified the accident as a "desolate" tragedy, for which there is no words. British homologous, Keir Strmer, has solidated himself with the "passengers and their families at this painful moment."
The plane issued a rescue signal and “crashed shortly after offspring in Ahmedabad,” at 1:39 pm (15:39 in Macao), the India Civil Aviation authority said.
The 787 Dreamliner is a large twin -engine plane. This was the first accident of a Boeing 787, according to the Aviation Safety Network database.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IC will improve collaboration with game dealers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ic-vai-melhorar-colaboracao-concessionarias-jogo/</link><description>The cooperation process with game concessionaires for large -scale events has room for improvements, said the president of the Cultural Institute, asked about the content of the CCAC report on this article. Leong Wai Man has already given indications for the creation of a working group directed to the optimization of this process. On the other hand, he said that the body “has no competence” to oversee the organization of concerts on the responsibility of private entities
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Cultural Institute admits that “there is room to improve” within the cooperation process with the six game concessionaires to hold large -scale entertainment events. Instance to comment on the Commissioner's Report against Corruption (CCAC), which states that there was no written agreement in the financing of Christmas concerts and New Year's Eve of 2022 by the game dealers, the IC president took imperfections.
“I agree with the CCAC report, so there is room for breeding,” said Leong Wai Man, confirming the creation of a work team in this context. "And when the preparation of large -scale shows, we will follow these opinions of the Commissioner," he said.
Regarding public acquisition, “we will follow the whole process and, according to the real need, will establish contacts with these six dealers to clarify the responsibilities,” he said.
On the other hand, on the sidelines of the Advisory Board Meeting for Cultural Development, the IC leader stated that the body has no competence to make any supervision of non-resident workers who perform functions in the organization of concerts or other entertainment shows. "Our assignment is to select each proposal, so there are other public services responsible for this inspection," he said, when asked about the existence of illegal workers in the recent G-Dragon concert.
Regarding the organization of concerts by private entities, Leong Wai Man clarified that the only responsibility that IC has is to select, classify and evaluate. "If an association wants to perform the concert and the place does not belong to the IC, it will have to find the person responsible for that space," he noted.
On Sunday, June 15, the IC promotes a concert at the “Outdoor Concerts site” at Cotai, with Norwegian DJ and music producer Alan Walker, starting at 20h00. This is the first large -scale display in that space after the opening event in December last year. Six food and drink tents will be installed. "We had a contest and the result was very good, since we received many proposals," said the president of the IC.
 
Support for exhibition of works abroad
Six works were selected by the IC to join the project “Commissioning of Performative Arts Productions 2024-2026”, whose objective is to call groups or companies to present proposals for potential stage works.
With this initiative, the IC aims to “create more local artistic and cultural masterpieces”, to promote at the same time “the reenance of works”, prolong “their artistic life” and boost the development of the performative arts and cultural industries of Macau, according to the president of the body, at the end of the 3rd Ordinary Plenary meeting of the Advisory Board for cultural development.
The plan will assign 900,000 patacas to groups that display musical shows and 650,000 for theater, dance and children's programs. This financial support for production costs will be increased if companies perform acts abroad.
Following the project launched in June last year, whose applications closed in early September, IC collected proposals for unpublished, adapted and recreated productions, including music, theatrical, dance and children's programs, presented by valid Macao Identity Ticket holders or by associations or companies registered in the territory.
Between 35 proposals and after two evaluation rounds, six were selected, including the children's play “The Hamsters of the Chong Chong”, by the Rolling Puppet Alternative Theater, already scheduled for next month. Later, in November, will be displayed the dance piece "Selfish Selfie", by the group "Lam Dance Theater".
The remaining productions are theatrical pieces, one of which musical, from the “Stage Evolution Production LDA”, and another directed to babies, the cultural and creative Miracle Lab. There will also be performances by the PO art studio and “Dirks Theater Arts Association”. These four views have not yet been set for their debut, but will be presented to the public in 2026.
The IC will also facilitate the subsequent development of programs after debut and help them contact them with event organizers from other regions to look for resources to be reenacted, thus boosting the development of the Macao performative arts and cultural industries.
"Sometimes companies can only ensure a debut, or just an event, but with the support of this commissioning we can help these artistic and cultural groups to have more opportunities to present their work," said Ieng Weng Fat, a board member in the press conference question and answers that followed the meeting.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sands renews support to Fu Hong</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sands-renova-apoio-a-fu-hong/</link><description>A group of 200 volunteers, which includes members of the Macao Fu Hong Rehabilitation Association and “Sands Cares” ambassadors, joined 2,600 gift packages at the Association's Center Pou Law, in a commitment of “community service”. According to Sands China, those present were distributed by 66 local child and homes care institutions under Children's Day.
Sands also donated 259,750 patacas to Fu Hong as a complement to the “Fuhong Gift Pack Community Sharing Program”. The check was delivered by Catherine Kong, vice president of corporate communications and community affairs at Sands, to the association's director Jennifer Chau.
Wilfred Wong, vice president of the operator, said that "at Sands China, corporate social responsibility is a central philosophy." Since 2006, the company “stroked the lasting partnership with the Fu Hong rehabilitation association, which aims to serve its members and the community,” continued Wilfred Wong.
Sands China is dedicated to creating bridges for social inclusion of people with disabilities, offering job opportunities that, in turn, empower them in terms of self-esteem, the statement says. “Through Fuhong’s Gift Pack Community Sharing Program ', we are proactively distributing gift packages to 98,600 children to spread joy and affection for the community during the festivities,” added Sands vice president.
On behalf of the company, Wilfred Wong thanked Fuhong for his support and extended thanks to the ambassadors for volunteering. The leader of the Macao Fu Hong Rehabilitation Association, in turn, thanked Sands for the “21 years of constant support”. The partnership “not only provided job opportunities and income to members of the Pou Law Center, but also allowed them to give the community back through handmade gifts,” said Jennifer Chau.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>One hundred thousand participants in the “Reading Month”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cem-mil-participantes-mes-de-leitura/</link><description>Hundreds of “reading month” activities helped create “an atmosphere conducive to reading,” says the Cultural Institute. According to the balance of the initiatives, about 100 thousand participants were accounted for
 
About 100,000 participants joined the “joint reading month throughout the city of Macao”. With “diverse and rich” experiences, the approximately 550 activities “created an atmosphere conducive to reading with the public and contributed to the construction of the 'reading city',” according to the Cultural Institute (IC).
The IC also promoted “reading points” by the city, having obtained answers from more than 100 entities, for the organization of about 200 activities, in which approximately 45,000 people participated. In turn, the “World Book Day Creative Contest - Guangdong Province, Hong Kong and Macau” received about 1,400 registrations, of which 65 won prizes of excellence. The award -winning work will be displayed gradually and itinerantly in the public library and in local schools, the statement says.
More than 90 initiatives were held at Macau Cultural Center Square (CCM), and at the Center itself, for two days of the “Library Week”, which had over 25,000 participants. In addition to the “Book Exchange” and “Sale of Magazines”, workshops, story narration, lectures and musical performances were also held. Cultural and gastronomy stands, a sports challenges, outdoor photography facilities and film projections were also established.
As part of the “Reading x Sport” theme, the IC invited the Chinese athlete and director of the University of Jinan School of Physical Education, Su Bingtian, to give a lecture to the CCM small auditorium, which attracted a “large number of residents”. Su shared the journey of overcoming and winning the title of "Greatest Asia Sprite."
The “month of reading” was co-organized by the IC, by the preparatory cabinet for the organization of the Macao Competition Zone of the 15th edition of the National Games, the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services, the Institute of Social Action, by the Institute of Sport, for health services and also had the support of various local entities.
The IC states that it will continue to organize a "wide range of reading promotion activities to encourage residents of all ages to dedicate themselves to reading." Activities such as “switching one book for another”, “Pop-Up Library”, “Get to know the library” and “being a librarian for a day” will be released, ”the IC said.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Wutip” brings “strong showers”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/wutip-traz-aguaceiros-fortes/</link><description>Storm sign 3 was yesterday lifted, leading to the suspension of classes in children's, primary and special teachings; but in the afternoon it lowered to sign 1. SMG warn that the "wutip" will bring "strong showers" until Sunday
 
Due to the “Wutip” tropical storm, the classes of children's, primary and special teachings were suspended yesterday throughout the day, indicated the education and youth development services, still remembering that schools should keep their facilities open and staff at work, “welcoming students” that reached schools, until their return to home could be done safely. Although the Typhoon signal 3 early in the morning has been aveiled, the truth is that the consequences of "Wutip" have made little feel.
Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) warned that with the gradual weakening of the high pressure crest, the wind in Macau weakened, so signal 3 was replaced by 1 at 18:00 yesterday.
The body warned, however, that today, according to the forecast trajectory, the Wutip will "take a direction from the north to the northeast, approaching the west coast of Guangdong province." "The associated southwest air stream will affect Macau," he said, adding that the wind in the region could intensify.
The SMG also predicted “strong and thunder showers” ​​between the end of today and early Sunday. "Accumulated precipitation will be significant, and flooding may occur in low areas due to continuous rain," he said. Also due to the astronomical tide, indicated that slight floods may occur in interior port areas between today and tomorrow.
"Given that the trajectory of the tropical cyclone is still uncertain, it is advisable to the population to pay attention to the latest weather information and take precautionary measures against wind and floods," added SMG. Hong Kong kept the signal 1 yesterday, issued at dawn on Thursday.
Inside China, the meteorological authorities raised the emergency response yesterday to the “Wutip” typhoon, the first of the season, which is expected to reach southern China twice. The Chinese response system to weather disasters comprises four levels, level I being the most severe and level IV at least severe.
Activation of level III implies a broader mobilization of resources and reinforced coordination between local and national agencies to prevent and mitigate potential impacts of the phenomenon.
According to the Chinese national meteorological center, the Wutip was moving towards Northwest about 10 kilometers per hour and could play the Earth for the first time between dawn and today, in a coastal track between Lingshui and Ledong in Hainão. A second impact is scheduled for tomorrow, on the coast between the west of Guangdong and the Guangxi region.
Until tomorrow, southern China is expected to record “very strong or extremely strong” rains in certain areas, namely in the center of Haão, northern Guangdong and East Guangxi, according to the weather body.
The Central Observatory keeps an active a yellow typhoon alert, the third level on a four -color scale, where red represents the most serious situation. China's meteorological administration has appealed to the authorities to reinforce precautionary measures to the possible effects of strong winds, rainfall and landslides.
The "Wutip" is the first typhoon of the time in China, but training was registered with more than two months late in the usual start of the season, which usually occurs at the end of March. Experts attribute the delay to a system of undisputed subtropical pressure and the late arrival of the summer monsoon to the southern sea of ​​China, factors that inhibited the necessary tropical convection for the development of cyclones.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>A Symposium Organies on Biomedical Sciences</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/um-organiza-simposio-sobre-ciencias-biomedicas/</link><description>“Scientific Impact” is the theme of the 11th Symposium on Biomedical Sciences organized by the University of Macau. The initiative, which runs 20 and 21 this month, will be attended by 35 “renowned” academics of the area
 
The Faculty of Health Sciences of the University of Macau (one) will organize the 11th Macao Symposium on Biomedical Sciences, on June 20 and 21. According to the institution of higher education, the objective is to “reinforce collaboration in research and promote the innovation and development of biomedical sciences”.
Under the theme “Scientific Impact”, the Symposium will bring together 35 academics “renowned in the area of ​​the Biomedical Sciences around the world, which will present cutting -edge research and participate in discussions on academic innovation and future developments in the area.
In concrete, it will include a main session and several thematic sessions, in which academics will present topics such as tumor immunology and immunotherapy; Genomic biology; Neuroscience, aging and degenerative diseases; Stem cells, genetic and cellular therapy; microbiology; and biomaterials and nanomedicine.
Tang Ben-Zhong, academic at the Chinese Academy of Sciences and Rector of the Faculty of Science and Engineering at the Chinese University of Hong Kong, Shenzhen, will be the main speaker. During the lecture, entitled “Aiegenas: Biosondas conceptually new to visualize biostructures and monitor bioprocesses”, “will share your latest findings of research on added -induced emission luminogens (Aiegen),” explains UM.
Other speakers include Vojo Deretic, emeritus professor at the University of New Mexico; Huang He, Emeritus Professor at the University of Zhejiang; Feng Xinhua, professor at the University of Zhejiang; Lu Xin, professor at Oxford University; and Burkhard Ludewig, professor at Kantonspital St. Gallen, Switzerland. The Symposium will start at 09h00 of the 20th of this month.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>200 Chinese influencers on large -scale promotion</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/200-influenciadores-chineses-em-promocao-de-grande-escala/</link><description>About 200 influencers from the interior of China, some with tens of millions of followers, will participate this weekend in a major promotional tourism event in Macao. The purpose of tourism services is to attract young people to visit the territory during the summer
 
It is already this weekend that the promotional event “Enchanting Macao” will be launched, where 200 “popular influencers from the interior of China” will be present. The initiative is from the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), in collaboration with companies and local artistic and cultural associations.
"Through the attention generated online, the promotional action aims to attract young visitors to visit Macao to person during the summer holidays. Through the impact of influencers with thousands of followers, it is also intended to attract visitors to explore community neighborhoods and to promote the development of the tourist economy, with a view to further expanding the diverse market of visitors from the interior of China," the body explains.
Some of the influencers have dozens of millions of followers, such as Liu Yu, Xiamen Apo, Wulala, Amy, Guo Youcai, among others. With a total of over 300 million followers, the two hundred influencers will share tourist experiences with fans through short videos, focusing on younger visitors, STD says.
The initiative launch ceremony takes place tomorrow, at 2:30 pm, at the fishermen's dock. There will be “Star Stars”, “Star Fair” and “Star Parade”, with the participation of artists and artistic groups from Macao and local stores, as well as the influencers. The first segment will feature the action of several influencers, including songs and dances, and other stage views. Already in the "Star Parade" several influencers, animation groups and "Mak Mak" will parade.
On the other hand, the “Star Fair” will open to the public at 13h00 and extend until 18:30. In this context, several stands will be installed to bring together gastronomic specialties and cultural and creative products, integrating the elements of “Tourism + Gastronomy” and “Tourism + Culture and Creativity”.
“Three of the tents will have several digital influencers present, namely, cuisine tent, tent of idols and intangible cultural heritage tent, which will provide visitors with the possibility of interacting with the audience and fans,” explains STD. A zone for influencers and the audiences take pictures will also be installed on site.
Exchanges of memories in the tents of influencers are also scheduled, as well as fans tours in community zones. Under the “Open Line for Stars”, 100 people will be able to visit different zones of the peninsula, mud and coloane. The itinerary program includes the recently launched Popmart Travel with Popmart. On the other hand, guided tours were organized at some community sights to explain the culture to influencers and fans.
On Sunday, a “Star Salon” sharing session is scheduled, “inviting the main experts and influencers in related industries in China and Macau for exchange and sharing, where will be addressed the trends of short video and cultural tourism industries, so that local influencers and professionals from new media can deepen their knowledge”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Must Ipo and Shao Jiang in “duel” of candidates</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ipo-shao-jiang-em-duelo-de-candidatos/</link><description>The Macao Football Championship of the 1st Division entered the second phase of the season, with the top five teams of the first round to integrate the group that will discuss the title. The leadership belongs to Must IPO, guided by Japanese Yuki Masuda, who has not yet lost any game. At one point is the main revelation of the time, Shao Jiang, coming from the second level. The two rivals face each other next Sunday. Sporting and four other clubs are in the group that will decide who is and who goes down the division
 
The Macao Football Elite League entered the most important phase of the time, after a first round of one lap, in which the 10 teams played in the system of “all-continuousness”.
At the end of this initial phase of the championship, the clubs were divided into two groups of five, depending on the classification, having remained in the champion's determination series the formations of Must IPO, Shao Jiang, Benfica, University of Macao and Ching Fung. On the other hand, they will discuss the permanence or descent of Gala, Chiba, Hang Sai, Lun Lok and Sporting.
Must IPO closed the initial round of the championship in the lead, ahead of Shao Jiang and Benfica, starting the second phase of the league with a loose triumph (5-0) over the Benfiquista ensemble, throwing the "eagles" to a position in which they can hardly fight for the renewal of the title achieved in 2024. The current difference is already 10 points.
The first place in the Elite League should be girded by the “duel” between Must Ipo and Shao Jiang, separated by four points. However, Shao Jiang has a less challenge.
The two teams, who tied for two balls in the first phase of the championship in March, will face each other again on June 15, Sunday, at the Taipa stadium, in a match that will not be decisive, but in case of triumph of Must IPO, will put the Japanese Yuki Matsuda set well sent for the conquest of the sick.
“We are committed to being champions again, as well as winning the cup,” began the coach who took over the team just over a month ago after spending three and a half years in the Philippines, where he was the main coach. Before, he passed China, Taiwan and other places.
About the competitiveness of MSAR football, Yuki Matsuda recognizes that there is a large pit between four or five teams and the rest. "This difference is noted in the field and is reflected in the results," he says, adding that at this moment, in the face of the classification, "Must Ipo and Shao Jiang are the only teams to fight for first place."
In this “war” of the title, the Japanese recognizes that the main opponent will create difficulties. "They have, like us, a professional attitude in their structure, training three times a week, because only then can one reach a higher level," he said.
Also Shao Jian coach spoke to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, acknowledged that his team now has a great opportunity to reach the top of the table. "If we win, we will be up to us to go to the championship," he said, adding that "if this will reinforce the ambitions we left for this season."
Considering that the team started the time with “ambition and realism”, the coach, who guided teams from Mexico, Ecuador, USA, Venezuela and South Korea, wants to “play the game”, although acknowledging that the challenge of this journey may be of great importance in the decision of the title.
Shao Jiang bet strongly after being champion in the II Division, with seven foreign players, most of whom South Americans, from Venezuela, Colombia, Paraguay and Argentina, and also a US footballer.
Piñero's “Eleven” beat Ching Fung in the first round of the second phase, 4-0, thus redeems to the Desaire against this same opponent in the first round (1-0). In addition to this victory, the Ching Fung "stole" also two points to Must IPO, in a draw for two goals.
The old CPK must, now called Must IPO since the club's remodeling after former President Stephen Chow's departure, has been pointed out as the main favorite, even by the experience of his squad. Although this year did not have some players who have been a reference of the team over the course of several years, such as Diêgo Patriota and Niki Torrão, the club maintains the quality demonstrated in recent years.
In the table, Must IPO currently adds 29 points, against 25 from Shao Jiang and 19 from Macao University, Ching Fung and Benfica.
In the other group, which will define who goes down and who is in the Elite League, the lead is up to Chessman Chiba, followed by Gala is Hang Sai. Sporting is last, with defeats all the challenges made. “The“ lions ”were close to winning the first points, in the confrontation with the penultimate Lun Lok, but suffered the 3-2 already beyond regular time.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Artistic Book “Revelations” presented in Lisbon</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/livro-artistico-apocalipses-apresentado-em-lisboa/</link><description>The new edition of the artistic book “Revelations”, by the local duo and Polaca based in Berlin, Cheong Kin Man and Marta Stanisława Sala, was presented at an event of the Goethe-Institut (German Institute) of Lisbon.
Titled “Creating Connections”, the conversation with the duo and the German filmmaker Deborah Uhde was part of a parallel program of the exhibition “The Slazing and Curious Travel” of also couple in collaboration with UHDE, according to the Lisbon Cultural Agenda. The show is evident at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) in Lisbon until the end of August.
With a copy displayed at CCCM as an artistic object, '' apocalypses', in its current version, with the 550 additional logograms included, undoubtedly presents the recap of language time in the gesture, ”says Colombian curator Lorena Tabares Salamanca in her curatorial statement to the public.
Originally with 60 pages and entirely written in an invented language, the story of science fiction was commissioned by local curators Lam Sio Man and Pal Lok for Macao Biennial in 2023. He was also presented at the Singapore Art Museum and the World Culture House in Berlin.
Sponsored by the East Foundation, the present version of the work, with 720 pages, contains the ideographic work of Cheong and Room, exposed in the exhibition “De Copenhagen with Love”, which took place in the house of Krakow de Nuremberg in 2024.
“The mineral and liquid traces of the inscriptions created by room and cheong on the walls of an old medieval tower, at the facilities of the Cacovia Cultural Mission in Germany, become in this 'raw book', unpredictable logograms in their meanings,” continues Salamanca.
The first copy signed by the duo will integrate the collection of the António Alça Baptista Documentation Center of the East Museum in Lisbon. The limited edition has, totaling 25 copies, in contrast to the 100 pieces of the original version of 2023.
The presentation of the book in the cultural representation of Germany was intervention by its director, Jana Binder, and was supported by the Ministry of Culture and National Heritage and the Adam Mickiewicz Institute of Poland.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IBM prepares Computer Revolution with Commercial Quantum Computer</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/ibm-prepara-revolucao-informatica-computador-quantico-comercial/</link><description>IBM, the US technology giant, announced new advances with the aim of building the first commercial quantum computer, considered a computer revolution due to its unprecedented calculation power.
Current quantum computers are still experimental and face high error rates. Therefore, companies like IBM, Google and Microsoft are working to build more stable and scalable quantum systems.
IBM has ensured that it is close to solving these problems and can draw the script to a quantum system, which according to the company, would have applications to develop fuels, pharmaceutical products or even new elements.
The company based in New York intends to have, in 2026, its first quantum processor capable of storing information and performing logical operations. In addition, it bets on finishing in 2029 the Starling, the first commercial quantum computer, which is under development at its lab in Boukeepsie, in the Northeast of the USA. The company believes it will be able to perform 20,000 times more operations than current quantum computers.
Starling will be able to “solve concrete problems and open immense possibilities for companies,” said Arvind Krishna, CEO of IBM, quoted in a statement.
Quantum informatics is also designed to boost Artificial Intelligence (AI) for models more in tune with humans.
Mark Horvath, an analyst at consulting firm Gartner, praised IBM's “significant advancement”, however, pointed out that not all obstacles were overcome. In addition, the applications of real -world quantum systems continue to be "quite theoretical."
The challenge is considerable and motivates a frantic race among the great computer actors.
In December, Google presented a new quantum chip, called "Willow", which has a much lower error rate than those observed so far. In February, it estimated in five years the time required to finish its own quantum computer.
Microsoft then revealed its own quantum computer chip, “Majorana 1”, ensuring that it has made technology more reliable for use in the real world.
In late April, IBM, which was behind Microsoft, Amazon and Google in classic computing products in recent years, has been publicly committed to investing $ 150 billion in the US in five years, of which 30 will be destined for research and development.
The centenary American technology company says it has already generated more than 1 billion dollars in revenues thanks to quantum computer science, although current cases of use are limited.
In addition to 2029, IBM thinks of Blue Jay, expected for 2033 and 10 times more powerful than Starling.
For IBM Quantum Systems Director, the company is "redefining what will be computer in the future."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>