<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Public Hospital shortened waiting in urgency and external consultations</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/hospital-publico-encurtou-espera-na-urgencia-consultas-externas/</link><description>The average waiting time for adults at Conde de São Januário Hospital decreased in the first quarter of this year for about an hour. In the same line, the period when patients are waiting for the first external specialty consultation dropped to three weeks. Health services justify improvements with the introduction of an electronic system of patient referral monitoring
 
Victor Rebelo
 
In the first quarter of this year, the average waiting time at the Adult Emergency Service at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center was about an hour, and at the first external specialty consultation came down to about three weeks. The data are from Health Services (SSM), which attribute progress to some adopted measures, including the introduction of an electronic patient monitoring system, mobilizing, in due time, human resources and increasing the number of vacancies in external consultations, according to the needs of services.
In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Leong Hong Sai, the SSM say they currently have 1,300 nurses, and in recent years, the rate of detachment from the service and retirement of those health professionals has kept at a “relatively low” level, specifically in the order of 2%. “This reflects the stability of the nursing staff team,” says the body.
On the other hand, according to the director Alvis Lo, “to optimize the access of nursing staff, we will continue to develop access competition procedures according to the real work needs and the general plan for service development”.
The SSM also point out that in the last two years, access contests have been opened for nurse-Graduate and Chief Nurse. Regarding the nursing staff regime, "the health professionals' council will optimize the internship environment and raise its quality by increasing the number of advisors and the distribution of trainees by different services."
At the same time, the Council of Health Professionals “continues to collect opinions from all sectors of society and internship institutions, in order to optimize the internship regime of the 15 categories of health professionals, they underline.
Given the employment situation of local doctors, “the government follows the principle of giving priority to Macao residents in access to employment, so it only resorts to the recruitment of experts with vast professional and clinical experience abroad, when there is a lack of local professionals in some specialized health care services”.
Removing the situation of health professionals at Hospital das Ilhas, with the exception of staff highlighted by the “Peking Union Medical College Hospital”, “all acting doctors at the Macau Union medical center are residents of MSAR.
Following its official entry into operation, Hospital das Ilhas has been carrying out, “step by step”, the recruitment procedures of doctors. In addition, they clarify the SSM, “in order to attract the entry of more local healthcare courses, the creation of the position of 'Medical Assistant' in this context” was also planned.
At the same time, the body states that it will be promoted, in synergy, the training of qualified medical staff, ”as well as the“ progressive planning and development ”of the transformation of the Macau Union Medical Center“ in a high level formation in the territory ”. Thus, it is intended to “provide local health professionals a platform for continuous medical education of high quality and continuous professional development”.
In the future, it is also planned to send some doctors, nurses and clinical technicians to Beijing or other places, for the purpose of receiving different formations.
Referring to the opportunities that have been created so that local health professionals can exercise their activity in Hengqin, SSM and the direction of services for the subsistence issues of the in-depth cooperation zone "continue to deepen cooperation in the area of ​​medical services." The objective is to encourage MSAR doctors and nurses to obtain, under the law, the qualification for the profession in that area, and “support the health care providers of Macao in the installation of health institutions, in a capital capitals, mixed or in partnership, allowing them to take advantage of this opportunity to develop in the cooperation zone”, observe the SSM.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>"Bate Fado" team hopes to create "full connection" with the public</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/equipa-de-bate-fado-espera-criar-conexao-plena-publico/</link><description>The team of “Bate Fado” - a hybrid show between dance and the music concert, which “rescues” the dance known as “Fado Beatted”, which was extinguished in the twentieth century - will take the stage of the Cultural Center this Saturday, under the Macao Arts Festival. To the Jornal de Macao newspaper, the duo of creators of this work, Jonas &amp; Lander, explained that the public will have access to “a unique imagination that is impregnated with Portuguese culture, music and dance, but also linked to the world, Brazil, Africa and Asia”. Regarding the presentation of performance in the territory, they say they expect to create a “full connection” with the audience of Macau



















Catarina Pereira
 
"The rescue of the dance that fado has lost." This is described the show “Bate Fado” by those who do it. The Portuguese duo of choreographers Jonas &amp; Lander decided to “dig up” an ancient dance, extinct in the early twentieth century, known as “Fado Batada”, and bring it “to the present”, they explained to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. “Bate Fado” - a hybrid show between dance and music concert, designed for four dancers, four musicians and a fadista (dancer) - is one of the highlights of the Macao Arts Festival (FAM) and is scheduled for Saturday, May 17, at 7:45 pm, at the small auditorium of the Macau Cultural Center (CCM).
"The whole team is very excited to bring our culture to such a distant place, but with so many points of connection with our culture as is the case of Macau. This will certainly be a striking trip to the entire" Bate Fado "team, those experiences that are forever stored in memory," they said, in this time that artists move to the territory.
The work - which has been on a tour for more than three years “and has taken the public a little around the world” - will be presented as conceived, without any changes. “Even if the language is not understood, there is a dialogue in all the music and ancestry that hits Fado gives to the public,” he says, adding that one of the songs that the audience can listen to before the show is entitled “Rua do Capelão”, by Amália Rodrigues.
When artists take the stage, “people will have access to a unique imagination that is impregnated with Portuguese culture, music and dance, but also linked to the world, Brazil, Africa and Asia,” they won.
This choreographed staging premiered in 2021, and since then Portugal and other European destinations in digressions by France, Italy and Germany have also reached more distant stops such as Chile and South Korea. "All performances are unique and different, sometimes even when the show is made two in the same room in the same room," they said.
What about the territory, what expectations do you have? "What we expect is a full connection with the Macaense audience, who will certainly not have to understand a Portuguese word to connect with the show and travel with us around the world," they said.
"Turning a tradition into an unexpected form, he beats fado shakes the roots and history of the most emblematic music in Portugal, transposing them into the stage in an energetic artistic demonstration," he can read in the presentation of the work, adding that the cast "interprets a blend of guitar, voice and fadist soul with virtuous and sensual compassionaters".
On the CCM stage will be the dancers Catarina Campos, Melissa Sousa, Lewis Seivwright, Lander Patrick (also choreographer) and Jonas (also a fadista and choreographer), as well as Yami, bass, Helder Machado and Bernardo Romão (Portuguese guitar) and Tiago Valentim (fado viola). With an approximate duration of one hour and forty -five minutes, without break, the piece will be played in Portuguese, with subtitles in Chinese and English, according to the information provided by FAM.
The duo Jonas &amp; Lander was created in 2011. Since then, the Portuguese choreographers have undergone several national and international stages, and three years ago created “Bate Fado”, which was named by Expresso and the public as the best dance show of the year.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lace fall into stores and offices but continue to climb the homes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/rendas-caem-nas-lojas-escritorios-mas-continuam-subir-nas-casas/</link><description>Between January and March, the average income of housing fractions at MSAR rose 4.5% in annual terms and recorded the eighth consecutive quarterly increase. In the opposite direction, according to official data, the costs of the lease again decreased in fractions intended for stores, offices and industrial spaces
 
Sérgio Terra
 
The average income per square meter (useful area) of housing autonomous fractions in MSAR was headed at 138.4 patacas in the first quarter of this year, translating 0.4% and 4.5% increase over the previous three months and the 2024 same period, respectively, the direction of statistics and censuses (DSEC) (DSEC) reported yesterday. According to the official data analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, this was the eighth consecutive quarterly increase and the sixth followed in the annual comparison.
In the general calculation of last year, the rents of the houses had already bound 3.9% compared to 2023, marking the first rise since the start of the pandemic and equivalent to almost 84% of the level of 2019.
Data on the period between January and March 2025 show that the average income of housing fractions remains higher in Coloane (149 patacas), highlighting increases of 7.2% and 0.9% in one year and three months, respectively. In the mud, the average price set at 138 patacas, reflecting an annual growth of 3.8% and a quarterly rise of 1.2%. On the other hand, the average income on the peninsula (137 patacas) retreated 0.3% compared to the fourth quarter of 2024, but advanced 4.1% in the annual interval.
In the analysis by specific zones, DSEC highlights the cases of the “bass of the mud” (140 patacas), the “outer port landfill zone - Zape)” (120 patacas) and “Nape and landfills of Praia Grande Bay” (144 patacas), where average lace per square meter increased 1.1%, 0.8%and 0.7%, respectively, compared to the last quarter of the last quarter 2024. On the other hand, in the “new black sand landfills - Natap” dropped 1.5% to 163 patacas.
The most significant annual variation occurred in the area of ​​“Lamau's dock”, with the average income rising 12.2% to 150 patacas per square meter. Still, in this area, the quarterly increase was residual (+0.1%).
Compared to the fourth quarter of 2024, the average lace per square meter of the head -to -level surroundings between 50 and 99.9 square meters of payable area grew 0.5% to 138 patacas, however, that of the level of less than 50 square meters (166 patacas) retreated 0.9%.
 
Stores lace go down for nine months
In the remaining segments of the lease market, the trend continues to be descended, including in the income of the autonomous fractions for stores, which completed three consecutive quarters at low, after 1.1% between 2023 and 2024.
According to DSEC, the average square income of the spaces for stores reached 485 patacas between January and March, which corresponds to an annual break of 1.3% and a quarterly retreat of 0.9%, which the body associates with the fact that they were “added lower value lease contracts”.
When compared to the preceding three months, the average income of stores in “Baixa de Macao” (665 patacas), “Black Areia and Iao Hon” (452 ​​patacas) and “barge” (344 patacas) decreased 3.7%, 2.4%and 2.3%, respectively. On the other hand, in the “Nape and landfills of Praia Grande Bay” (623 patacas) rose 0.4%.
Official statistics also reveal that average offices of offices intended for offices (289.5 patacas) and industrial autonomous fractions (122.7 patacas) fell 1.3% and 0.2%, respectively, in quarterly terms. The annual comparison points to descents of 3.2% and 0.9%.
In offices, rents have always dropped in the last 16 quarters, while the average price of industrial units accumulates three consecutive quarterly declines. Between 2023 and 2024, the average income of offices and industrial autonomous fractions fell 2.8% and 0.1%, respectively.
Income statistics data comes from the Real Estate Declaration on which the building service is provided for. The statistical scope encompasses the leases of entire autonomous fractions, which have non -expired contracts, and whose owners are not the government government or philanthropic associations, among other situations.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>BNU net profit decreased 18% in the first quarter</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lucro-liquido-bnu-diminuiu-18-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>With the financial margin retreating 31.2 million patacas, BNU's net income decreased 18.4% to 133.2 million in the first quarter of this year, in homologous terms. The bank ensures that it maintains a “disciplined financial management” and a “solid risk control framework”
 
The National Bank Overseas Bank (BNU) closed the first quarter of this year with a net income of 133.2 million patacas, which reflects a decrease of 18.4% or 30 million compared to the same period of 2024.
In a statement released yesterday, BNU reveals that the net financial margin suffered a break of 11.8% or 31.2 million patacas in homologous terms, "mainly due to changes in the composition of deposits and the evolution of interest interest rates." According to the banking institution, this reduction was partially offset by an increase of 18.1% or 3.8 million patacas in liquid commissions, "reflecting greater economic activity and greater customer involvement."
On the other hand, impairment losses related to credit exhibitions and financial investments grew to 5.4 million patacas between January and March, compared to 1.3 million noted in the first three months of 2024, "in line with prudent practices of provisioning." "Despite this increase, the quality of BNU assets remains solid, supported by conservative credit practices and a robust level of provisions to respond to ongoing macroeconomic uncertainties," the bank underlines.
At the end of the first quarter, BNU's total capital ratio improved to 25.2%, which represents an annual increase of 1.3 percentage points. “This reinforcement, along with robust liquidity reserves, reflects the resilience of the bank's balance sheet, its disciplined financial management and a solid risk control framework,” the institution is convinced that “these pillars allow BNU successfully browsing complex economic contexts, maintaining support for its customers, communities and stakeholders”.
In the financial year ended on March 31 this year, operating expenses rose 1.1% in homologous terms, says the bank, noting that this variation illustrates "the effectiveness of cost optimization initiatives". “Efficiency gains resulting from process simplification and strategic service review have helped compensate added investments in digital transformation, talent development and brand reinforcement. These investments are aligned with BNU's strategic priorities to improve customer experience, reinforce operational agility and respond to rapid digital changes,” can read in the statement.
BNU reiterates that it continues to integrate ex -(environmental, social and governance) principles in all its operations, with the aim of promoting “sustainable growth that benefits communities and the environment”.
At the same time, the BNU branch in Hengqin continues to play a “strategic role” at the level of service to investors in Macau and Hong Kong, both individual and business, as the Great Bay and the Guangdong-Macau in-depth cooperation zone on mountain island “Strengthen integration”. “Functioning as a transionic financial hub, the branch supports economic collaboration between mainland China, Macao and Portuguese -speaking countries through the offer of personalized financial solutions and the promotion of a diverse business ecosystem” in the Great Bay, he underlins.
It is recalled that, in the general calculation of last year, net income after BNU taxes was 585.1 million patacas, marking a downward of 0.4% compared to the 587.3 million accounted for in 2023.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Promised reinforcement of technology in non -superior education</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/prometido-reforco-da-tecnologia-ensino-nao-superior/</link><description>The government will make an interspersed assessment this year on the planning of local non -higher education, with a view to creating an innovative technological support system, according to the secretary for social affairs and culture
 
In articulation with the “China Science and Technology Popularization Law” and the “Greeny Planning Lines for the Construction of a Great Educational Power (2024-2035)”, the Government of Mashere will perform an interleaved evaluation of the planning of not higher education, to build an innovative technological support system, the secretary revealed for social affairs and culture in the Legislative Assembly.
According to LAM, Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) intend to provide artificial intelligence content (AI) or linked to science and technology, with an average duration of 10 hours per year, computer teachers and six hours to other subjects. For this, it has more than 60 experts as advisors. In addition, it intends, in the school year 2026/2027, to make the service platform of “Intelligent Teaching” to all local secondary schools, with 25 have already participated in the respective Plano Piloto.
The goal is to develop AI teaching at all levels of education, as well as general education in this domain for the entire population. In regular education, the Science Center will provide extracurricular classrooms where students will have access to AI knowledge and techniques and a learning environment based on great AI scenarios, the director of the Science Center said.
Sio Hon Pan also pointed out that the Center for Science will focus on three dimensions to raise the literacy of AI residents, namely the breadth of cognition and AI recognition, the depth of AI logic and tool tools, and proficiency in the application of AI to solve real problems. The formative offer covers three levels: basic courses on cognition, recognition and safe application, designed especially for the elderly; General intermediate courses intended for residents to solve real problems, such as helping parents improve family interaction and deal with children's studies; and advanced courses for those looking for the development of their professional skills and companies.
The Science Center will also continue with the development of the “AI Forum”, inviting experts to lectures and interactive sharing sessions, as well as launching an extensive educational services program that allows the provision of AI equipment and didactic resources to the residence for the elderly, day centers and community homes.
The first stage involves the formation of sufficient advisors and the creation of scenarios favorable to the application of AI, stressed the responsible, asserting that the goal is "no one to be behind in the Age of AI".
On the other hand, according to the secretary, in the school year 2024/2025, 11 schools opened 28 courses of the “articulation between technical-professional and complementary secondary education” to 1,012 students from 54 classes.
The LAM also stated that, at the establishment of the University City in Hengqin, "the hypothesis of cooperating with national and international universities and top courses cannot be ruled out."
 
51 schools with inclusive education
In another scope, the secretary stressed that, currently 51 schools provide inclusive education, of which 21 teach kindergarten, primary and secondary education, with a number of “sufficient” vacancies. According to DSEDJ director Kong Chi Meng, schools with this teaching increased from two dozen 10 years ago to the current number, now absorbing 4.4% of the total students in Macao.
According to LAM, with a view to responding to demand, eight schools to be built in zone A of new landfills will provide inclusive education, of which one will have small classes of special education.
In addition, the secretary stressed the increase in the number of support teachers, from 209 to 265, and special education teachers, from 143 to 170, between the school years 2021/2022 and 2024/2025. It also noted that in 2023/2024, 94 inclusive education students graduated, and 79 entered the upper enino, meaning a rate of 84%.
Kong Chi Meng also assured that there are several measures to allow everyone's rise in this group of students for secondary education. According to the director of DSEDJ, in addition to free education, the government spends more than 200 million patacas per year in inclusive education and 50 million patacas in the acquisition of support services such as speech and occupational therapy.
In addition, LAM said that in the realization of the census on the elderly living alone and elderly couples, this year, the situation of elderly couples with children with intellectual disabilities will also be considered.
In turn, Alvis Lo, director of health services, revealed that the cloud platform for AI cognitive rehabilitation training has been used by 20,000 people/times, which shows that "certain results have been achieved."</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Instated AMCM to take action compared to the Malparado credit</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/amcm-instada-tomar-medidas-face-ao-credito-malparado/</link><description>The Macao Monetary Authority Supervisory Commission (AMCM) expressed concern about the level of misconduct in Macao banks after increasing 20 times in the last five years.
"Given that the Malpated Credit ratio grew from 3.9% to 5.5% for 12 consecutive months in 2024, which brought uncertainties to the stability of the financial system of Macau, the Surveillance Committee solemnly requests the necessary measures to ensure the stability of the financial system of Macao," says a opinion of the committee chaired by Leonel Alves over the 2024 report of the year and accounts. AMCM, yesterday published in the Official Bulletin of MSAR.
As this newspaper had already reported, the amount of “non -productive” or overdue credit (NPL, in the English acronym) in local banks reached 56.07 billion at the end of last year, translating an annual increase of 30.3% or 13.04 billion and establishing a new record in the territory, taking into account AMCM data that dates back to 1990. By the end of 2024, the backwards Contracted by clients not residents of customers were encrypted at 34.27 billion (61.1% of the total) and those of residents at 21.80 billion.
Considering loans with more than 90 days late, the NPL value was 56.1 billion patacas at the end of March this year, continuing to represent 5.5% of bank loans, ie 1.3 percentage points than in the same month of 2024. This percentage rises to 6.7% in the case of the credit assumed by institutions or non-residents.
In the annual report, AMCM states that the banking system of the banking system has increased “due to the joint influence of internal and external factors”, however, “the capital suitability ratio (RAC), consisting mainly of Tier 1 capitals, remained at a high level of 15.5%”. "In addition, the banking system had sufficient liquidity, demonstrating the stability of the bank sector of Macao," emphasizes the body.
“In 2024, global geopolitical tensions remained at a high level, creating numerous significant uncertainties in external economic and financial markets. Nevertheless, with the support of a series of Macao favorable measures, introduced by the central government, and the continuous implementation of policies related to the development of the economy's proper diversification and the guarantee of well-being by the government government, the economy, the economy. From Macau, he registered a stable recovery, ”he also indicates, on the other hand, that" Macao banks strictly fulfilled the prudent management principle, ensuring sufficient capital to stabilize the ability to resistance to risk. "
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Authorities insist on anti-covid vaccination</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/autoridades-insistem-na-vacinacao-anti-covid/</link><description>Despite the decline in the growth curve of the new type of coronaviruses in Macao, health services (SSM) have again appealed to residents to adopt preventive measures, especially vaccination. Highest groups, such as elderly and serious chronic patients, are advised to prioritize vaccination against the JN.1 variant, with the aim of reducing the risk of infection.
In the current year, Macau registered the peak of the sickness epidemic caused by the Sars-Cov-2 virus earlier than neighboring regions. According to laboratory surveillance data, the positivity rate of patients with flu -like symptoms, which were identified with the new type of coronaviruses in Macao, had a progressive increase since the second half of February.
In mid-March, the peak was reached, with 44.3% positivity rate in the 12th week, and then a gradual decrease. Positivity rates in the 17th, 18th and 19th weeks were 12%, 17%and 11%, respectively, “which indicates a slight recovery,” says the SSM.
In general terms, the new type of coronavirus in Macao has presented “a relatively high level of activity” in recent times. Currently, the variant of the new type of predominant coronavirus in the territory is the XDV variant related to the JN.1 variant, which is essentially identical to the variant of neighboring regions.
According to SSM, the latest data do not indicate that XDV can cause more serious illnesses than JN.1, XBB and its descendant genealogies. Thus, health authorities consider that the JN.1 vaccine, used in Macao, "continues to effectively reduce the infection caused by variants in prevalence and the risk of becoming a serious illness."
Regarding cases of collective infection of diseases with influenza symptoms, this year, 111 were recorded, of which 26 caused by the new type of coronaviruses, especially in homes. In accordance with the home support mechanism, the SSM has already provided adequate medical services to homes and prescribed antiviral drugs to applicable recipients.
To date, no severe or deadly cases were recorded caused by the new type of coronavirus in Macao. However, given the vulnerability of high -risk groups, the SSM appeals so that people complete vaccination as soon as possible.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Qualified Tables motivate new study</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/quadros-qualificados-motivam-novo-estudo/</link><description>The Qualified Table Development Commission will carry out a new study on the search for qualified frameworks. The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture yesterday advanced four focuses of this work
 
In articulation with the development needs of Macao and the country, the Commission for the Development of Qualified Tables (CDQQ) will again conduct a study on qualified frameworks, with a view to providing the public with a predictable trend of demand in the short, medium and long term, the secretary for social affairs and culture, LAM, said yesterday.
In response to an oral interpellation of Deputy Zheng Anting, the secretary said that the study will have four outbreaks, namely reflecting the requirements for employment candidates, including academic courses, to serve as a reference for students, and analyze in detail the information collected so that the general public and students can take them as a reference in planning their professional career. It also promised to continuously develop inquiries related to employment and studies of Macao graduates from higher education institutions, hoping, through the study, to guide students in the choice of university and the evaluation of university courses, and at the same time, to realize the degree of lack or excess in the market, and the collection of their data is ongoing and should take some time.
The fourth focus of the study, according to the secretary, is based on the search for different sectors by medium and high levels.
Recognizing that the “qualified frame database” should be periodically updated, even using artificial intelligence, LAM said that CDQQ will continuously make available information on professional accreditation, large bay policies and market dynamics, among other topics, to those registered abroad, through that base.
"In the future, with the development of professional qualification regimes in various domains, studies can be performed, involving all parties, to create better conditions for the return of qualified paintings," he said.
In addition, he mentioned that authorities will extend the coverage and number of vacancies of the participating institutions in the “Macao Youth Professional Development Plan”. In cooperation with services for labor affairs, the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) will elaborate another proposal for job advice for young people.
On the other hand, the secretary has emerged that the government will create conditions and support young doctors, retired elite athletes and teachers with a view to their promotion and registration.
Kong Chi Meng, director of DSEDJ, stressed that for the “Young Vacation Occupation 2025” program, in which young places can intern for six weeks in public services or local private entities, 500 vacancies will be maintained and online interviews available to residents in the interior of China or abroad. In addition, the number of vacancies of the “Internship Program in the interior of China for Macao Higher Education Students” will increase to 520.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Festive activities highlight children's rights and well-being</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/actividades-festivas-destacam-direitos-bem-estar-das-criancas/</link><description>In celebration of World Children's Day, several entities will organize various activities in the sense of “arousing the population's attention to the rights and well-being of children”. The program includes a village, gift distribution, a visit to the Military Headquarters of Taipa and an online game
 
The Organizing Committee of World Children's Day will organize a series of activities between May and June, to mark the commemorative date and “allow the population of Macau to enjoy the festive environment, indicates the Institute of Social Action (IAS). Subordinate to the theme“ Right to Life ”, and to“ arouse the attention of the population to the rights and well-being of children ”, the Activities Program, a visit to the Military Taipa headquarters, The distribution of gifts to hospitalized children and an online game game game with awards, among other initiatives.
The Arraial will be in charge of Caritas, Federation of Workers' Associations, General Association of Women and General Union of Macao Residents Associations. The organization invites all citizens to participate on May 25, between 14:00 and 17:30, at the Science Center.
On World Children's Day, between 09:30 and 12:30 and from 14:00 to 18:00, the camp will take place, respectively, in the field of workers of the General Association of Macao Workers and Tap Seac Square. From 1:00 pm to 5:00 pm on June 8, the camp will take place at the side space of Jardim da Cidade das Flores.
During May 25, the Organizing Committee will take about 600 students from primary education to the Military Headquarters of Taipa, to the “cultural and artistic representation of primary school students and the garrison in Macao from the Chinese people's liberation army”. According to IAS, there will be a moment of interaction between students and military, to allow students to “feel the festive atmosphere and celebrate the awareness of ethnicity and promote love for the homeland and Macao”.
On June 1, the organization, the work of mothers and other collaborators will distribute gifts to children in the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center and the Kiang Wu Hospital, as a way of conveying “the festive and best wishes”.
The online question of questions and answers will be available from 10:00 from May 20 until the end of World Children's Day, aiming to reinforce the knowledge and understanding of residents of the “Convention on Child Rights”. The activity is intended for any resident of Macao from 12 years.
The remaining activities include workshops on small rockets and illustrated books, on May 25, the “Children's Day with the Messenger Bear Guilherme”, between May 19 and June 27, and the offer of memories in the IC libraries, from May 26 to June 1.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Infrastructure Forum with reinforced ambitions</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/forum-de-infra-estruturas-ambicoes-reforcadas/</link><description>Macau will organize the Forum and International Exhibition on Investment and Construction of Infrastructure, in which international contractors and leading companies in the industrial chain will participate. Custom stands are estimated to represent more than 90% of the total
 
Companies of the 250 largest international contractors (ENR250) and leading companies in the industrial chain will be present at the 16th Forum and International Exhibition on Investment Investment and Construction (IIICF). The event, which will take place between June 10 and 12, at Cotai Expo do Venetian, will deal with the theme “Enhanced connectivity for mutually beneficial cooperation”.
This year's edition highlights the full expansion of the exhibition scale and the reinforcement of the synergy between conventions and exhibitions, “in order to expand the overall effectiveness of the event,” says a note from the Macao Commerce and Investment Institute (IPIM), which co-organizes the Forum, together with the China International Civil Constructors Association.
The IIICF reinforces the combination of exhibitions and conventions, with an exhibition area of ​​8,000 square meters. Custom stands are estimated to represent over 90% of the total, with more diverse exhibitors and richer content. According to IPIM, a ceremony of launching innovative results will be held for the first time, with the aim of supporting companies to take advantage of the opportunities of the “debut economy”.
In line with the latest trends of the sector, the Forum will offer several thematic activities, namely lectures, conferences, conventions, exhibitions, roadshows, contact scholarships, commercial negotiations and index report launches, the integration of elements related to Portuguese -speaking countries, the great hengqin cooperation zone and the construction of macau.
According to IPIM, the IIICF aims to encourage cooperation between China and countries covered by the initiative “a lane, a route” in the domain of infrastructure, “based on positioning and function of the Macao platform”. In addition, guided tours of community neighborhoods, organized during the event, "seek to extend the effects of the event to the local community."
By statistical data, the editions already held attracted the participation of more than 630 guests at the ministerial level and more than 30,000 elites of the sector. As a result, more than 220 cooperation projects were signed, with a total amount of over US $ 100 billion.
The projects concerned include areas such as transportation, housing construction, energy supply and electricity, industrial parks, engineering equipment, mineral exploration and the formation of qualified frames.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Explored more opportunities for cooperation with Brazil</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/exploradas-mais-oportunidades-de-cooperacao-brasil/</link><description>An IPIM delegation was present at the China-Brasil Business Seminar, held in Beijing, where cooperation opportunities were discussed in various areas
 
A team from the Institute of Commerce and Investment Promotion (IPIM) participated in the China-Brazil Business Seminar, held in Beijing during the visit of Brazilian President Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva to China. At the event, business leaders and experts discussed opportunities for cooperation in the areas of bilateral investment and financing, energy transition, sustainable development and food safety.
Through participation in this high-level event, IPIM, in addition to promoting the role and advantages of Macau as a Sino-Melidon Platform with the various representatives participating in the interior of China and Brazil, namely those of the Brazilian meat sector and companies of coffee brands in China, also presented the 2nd China-Paraíses Economic and Commercial Exhibition (PLP), planned to be held in October.
Similarly, it has released the “China-PLP Trade Conduct” service, which helps companies explore the market, “in order to encourage them to make the most of the role of Macao as an international window and the Sino-Lirpone economic and commercial cooperation resources” offered by IPIM. This service also promotes “the expansion of companies from the interior of China to the abroad”, through the Macao platform and the fundraising of Brazil to Greater China, “thus injecting a new dynamic in regional economic and commercial development,” he says.
During the stay in Beijing, the entourage visited the services of the municipality of the Chinese capital, taking the opportunity to promote C-Clpex to about 20 Beijing companies in the domains of state-of-the-art technology, infrastructure works and international trade. IPIM explained the unique advantages of Macao in terms of linguistic communication, legal articulation and commercial network, in order to encourage contact and partnership of companies in the interior of China, with the resources of the PLP market.
The commerce services of the Municipality of Beijing guaranteed that they will install a stand at the Macao Fair and organize the participation of companies at the event. The IPIM team also established contacts with several participating companies in the business seminar “to better know the registration procedure as professional buyers and explore PLP business opportunities through the Macao platform”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Trampoline gymnastics in Macau grows in number of athletes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ginastica-de-trampolim-em-macau-cresce-em-numero-de-atletas/</link><description>Trampoline gymnastics discipline has been growing in the MSAR, where there are almost half a thousand young people who practice the sport in clubs and schools. This weekend, 140 will participate in the Macao Trampoline Championship that will take place at the International School Pavilion. The organization is up to the Macao Trampoline and Acrobatic Sports Association, whose president of the Board, Nuno Fernandes, told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau that “with the conditions in Macau, such as lack of spaces and infrastructure, this trampoline discipline is the ideal gymnastics for young people to practice in the territory”






























Victor Rebelo
 
The adhesion of young people from Macau to the trampoline gymnastics has made significantly increasing the number of athletes involved in the sport, both at the level of competition and regarding initiation. In its entirety, “you can talk about half a thousand practitioners in the territory, distributed by clubs and schools,” Nuno Fernandes told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao.
The chairman of the Macao Association of Trampolins and Acrobatic Sports (Atdam), a former renowned gymnast with several representations by Portugal in international events, points out that “with the conditions existing in Macau, such as lack of spaces and infrastructure, this trampoline discipline is the ideal gymnastics for young people to practice in the territory”.
Since trampolins were introduced, at the individual level, at the Sydney Olympic Games, Australia, in 2000, “discipline has never stopped in terms of international growth, being one of the most important categories of the International Gymnastics Federation, which gives him great expression in many countries around the world,” says the leader and founder of Atdam.
Numo Fernandes was also responsible for the creation of the “Gymnastics Club”, together with his wife and also a Portuguese prestigious girl, Ana Conde. The collectivity is the most expression in Macao and so will present about 90 athletes, among 140 subscribers, in the Macau 2025 Trampoline Championship, which takes place this weekend, 17 and 18 May.
The tournament, which takes place for the sixth time and a consecutive fifth, will take place at the International School Pavilion (TIs), with the participation of four clubs or schools in Macau, namely Portuguese school, “Freestyle Acrobatic”, “Gymnastics Club” and “Union Acro Gymnastics”. Participants will be divided by four age levels: Children (9 and 10 years), initiates (11 and 12), Juvenis (13 and 14) and juniors (over 15 years).
On Saturday morning, May 17, between 9:00 am and 12:05 pm, is intended for the competition of the Tumbling category (Children), while in the afternoon, from 12:45 to 17:15, will take place the mini and children's trampoline tests, followed by the awards ceremony.
On Sunday, in the morning, from 9h00 to 12:30 pm, it is the turn of the performance of young people in the category of tumbling, initiates and youth. The awarding of awards is scheduled for 12:45. The afternoon program includes tumbling, juniors (from 2:15 pm to 2:50 pm, mini-tripolim, juveniles between 3:05 pm and 4:25 pm, and the juniors, from 4:25 pm to 5:05 pm, which will follow another trophy delivery ceremony.
In April, several of these athletes, representing the Gymnastics Club Macau, participated in an international trampoline tournament in Hong Kong, having won several medals. The competition also featured gymnasts from Taiwan, the continent and Raehk, in a total of two hundred.
Founded in 2013, the Gymnastics Club is currently close to 300 young people to practice the sport, many of which are an early age, still in the initial learning process.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Orchestra will present “seven worlds, a planet”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/orquestra-vai-apresentar-sete-mundos-um-planeta/</link><description>In July, the Broadway Theater will host the “Seven Worlds, a Planet” concert in a “audiovisual immersive experience”. The themes of the BBC television series, and the authorship of Hans Zimmer, Jacob Shea and Sia, will be interpreted by the Macao Orchestra, under the baton of conductor Vanessa Scammell, with live narration by Jason Chan
 
The Broadway Theater will host the “Seven Worlds, a Planet” concert on July 12 at 20:00. In a statement, the Cultural Institute (IC) points out that the Macao orchestra concert “will take the public in an immersive audiovisual experience through the wonderful landscapes of the seven continents”, designed on a giant LED screen narrated live.
Presented by the IC, the Macao Orchestra Society and the Galaxy Entertainment, the show will have “impressive excerpts” of the BBC's famous television series, and the award -winning composers Hans Zimmer and Jacob Shea, played live by the Macao Orchestra, conducted by Australian conductor Vanessa Scammell.
The themes played include the song “Out There”, by Zimmer's and the famous singer and songwriter Sai. According to the statement, the narration in English, by Hong Kong artist Jason Chan, will lead the audience in a "engaging sensory journey that intertwines music and image" and explore "The Stories of the Natural Wonders of the Seven Continents."
“Seven Worlds, a Planet” is “one of BBC's most popular natural history series”, taking four years to be produced and passed by 41 countries. The series, “widely acclaimed”, portrays “stunning natural landscapes on continents”, having hit the highest audience for documentaries at BBC One and won several awards.
Tickets for the show, about two hours and a quarter, are already available at the Macao online box office, priced at 150, 220 and 300 patacas.
The concert has the support of the “GEG Space Partnership Pilot Plan”. The 2024-25 orchestra concert season is co-organized by the IC, the Macao Orchestra Society and the six game operators.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New Cannes Clothing Code forces Halle Berry to change clothes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/novo-codigo-de-vestuario-de-cannes-obriga-halle-berry-trocar-de-roupa/</link><description>EPA12096429 JUY MEMBERS South Korean Director Hong Sang-Soo (L) and US ACTOR HALLE BERRY (R) ATTEND A Press Conference Ahead of the Opening of the 78th Annual Cannes Film Festival, In Cannes, France, 13 May 2025. The Film Festival Runes from 13 to 24 May 2025. EPA / TRISTAN Fewings / Pool *** Local Caption ***



Halle Berry, an Óscar-winning actress, was caught by surprise by the new Cannes Festival clothing code and had to change her choice of clothes at the last minute, told reporters on Tuesday.
According to the rules, nudity is not allowed on the red treadmill, and “bulky clothes, in particular those of Grande tail”, which block the way of other guests and complicate the places in the theater, are no longer allowed. The organizers warned that they could deny access to the red treadmill to those who did not respect the rules.
"I had an amazing Gupta dress to wear tonight, and I can't wear it because the tail is too big," Halle Berry, who is a member of the festival jury this year at a press conference.
"I had to change ideas. But I think the part of nudity is also a good rule," added the American star who won an Oscar for the 2001 movie Monster's Ball.
In recent years, guests and celebrities on the red treadmill have challenged the boundaries of the festival's clothing code with giant tails, transparent dresses and clothes that leave the nipples on display.
Kanye West and his wife, Bianca Censori, caused the Grammy Awards red treadmill in February, when Censori took a huge coat to reveal a transparent dress with nothing underneath.
 
Cinema stars denounce “silence” before “genocide” in Gaza
Several world film stars, including Pedro Almodóvar, Susan Sarandon and Richard Gere, denounced the "silence" of the world of culture in the face of "genocide" in Gaza, in a statement published in the French newspaper "Liberio", coinciding with the opening of the Cannes Film Festival. "We, artists and actors/actors of the cultural scope, we cannot remain silent while a genocide in Gaza is held," says the about 380 signatories of the text, which pays tribute to Fatima Hassouna, a deceased photojournalist in Israeli bombardment in April and protagonist of a documentary programmed in Cannes. The manifesto was published in printed version on the morning of opening the largest film festival in the world, a ceremony marked by the delivery of the Honorary Golden Palm to Robert de Niro, legend of the cinema and declared opponent of US President Donald Trump. Two filmmakers awarded the golden palm, Justine Triet and Ruben Östlund, as well as numerous actors and actors (Javier Bardem, Ralph Fiennes, etc.) signed the text. "What is our profession, if not to learn from history, from engaged movies, if we are not present to protect the oppressed voices?" Asks the signatories, who ask "in the name of all those who die in indifference."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>