<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>EPM operates changes in interior spaces</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/epm-opera-mudancas-nos-espacos-interiores/</link><description>The classrooms of the main building of the Portuguese School of Macau will not suffer any kind of works, unlike the gym zone, where yesterday, the planned remodeling has been due. The canteen and teacher room will change places. Inner space improvement work should be completed in July this year and will be mainly on weekends and holidays, so as not to disturb the normal functioning of classes. The school has already informed parents about the start of the works
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Some changes will be introduced into inner spaces of the Portuguese School of Macau (EPM), in a plan of works that started yesterday, but does not include any intervention in the classrooms of the main building. Improvement work should take place for about four months, with its completion expected to be completed next July.
Biggest interventions will cover the canteen/bar, which will change site, the resorts next to the gym and the teacher room. "These are necessary works, some of which should have already been done and others that it is important to do, and which are now finally pulling," the President of the Association of Parents and Parents of Education of the Educational Educational (APEP) are finally told the Journal of Macao.
Filipe Figueiredo revealed that a message was sent to all associates so that they become aware of the beginning and conclusion of the works, in which it is said that “despite the calendar of the works was done in order not to upset the normal functioning of the school, having place mostly outside the time and students in the facilities, on the weekends and during the academic interruptions, there will be any time, what will be extended, what will be extended, what will be extended, what will be long, cause some constraints. ”
In the same text, parents are informed that "the first works will take place in the gym resorts, a place that has currently reduced use, being intervened a resort at a time."
During the remodeling work, “there will always be a resort available to those who want to use it regardless of gender, obviously always under the supervision of school staff,” concludes the message, which appeals to “understanding of all members for this exceptional situation”, and is also asked that if they are aware of any problem throughout the works, contact the association.
According to Filipe Figueiredo, the classrooms themselves, which are located in the main building of the school, will not be moved. “Only two or three rooms in the gym area, which are being used, will be intervened, as are the bathrooms and the resorts,” says the APEP official.
Regarding the changes of spaces, the associative leader confirmed that the canteen will be transferred to the place where the teacher is currently located, which is in turn changed to the music room.
In the initial project, the canteen shift would be planned to the teacher's room, so near the school's entry atrium, but there will be some opposition, so the change solution to the music room was found, which will therefore have to be installed in another place.
Regarding other aspects of the school's operation, specifically anticipating the next school year, Filipe Figueiredo stated that at least one teacher will leave. "In what we were informed, of teachers who are teaching at school, in principle only one showed interest in abandoning, for personal reasons," he said.
The leader says that, however, the educational establishment is waiting for this to be confirmed, "so that a contest can be done for one or more teachers, as there may then be another kind of needs."</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Psychiatry services helped 5,000 children and adolescents</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/servicos-de-psiquiatria-ajudaram-5-000-criancas-adolescentes/</link><description>Child Sitting Alone in Living Room



A clinic of subspecialty of psychiatry services at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center provided services to more than 5,000 young people over the last year. Support is intended for children and adolescents, under the “Healthy Macao Action Plan”, aiming to follow the development of the physical and mental health of young people
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Macao health services (SSM), through a psychiatry subspecialty clinic that operates at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center (CHCSJ), accounted for more than 5,000 children and adolescents supported by that unit in 2024.
In addition, according to ChCSJ's deputy director, the public hospital highlights professional psychotherapists to provide mental health care in nine health centers, "as well as organizing teams of community psychiatry services, with external support to potential high -risk patients."
On the other hand, in relation to emerging cases, Tai Wa has stated that patients can use SSM psychiatry services, which operate 24 hours a day in the urgency of CHCSJ.
Emphasizing what is done in Macao in terms of psychiatric support, the official also stressed that “in order to increase the coverage of psychiatry services, since 2024 the public hospital began to perform systematic training for front line psychologists who work in health centers”.
He also recalled that, in 2021, the SSM created an interdepartal working group, responsible for monitoring the physical and mental health of young people and adolescents, "whose scope of participation has been constantly increasing." Currently, the group also encompasses educational associations, university students, pedagogical support institutions and youth associations, working to “continuously monitor the mental health of young people”.
Tai Wa Hou stressed that "in the context of the rapid evolution of society, young people have increasingly faced pressure and challenges, so depending only on the strength of a public service or a professional area, it would be difficult to deal effectively with the mental health of young people."
The statements of the Assistant Director of the CHCSJ are inserted in a statement by SSM, regarding an exchange meeting on the service models of youth psychology, assigned to “cross the border”. The event was organized with the aim of increasing the attention and knowledge of the public about the mental health of children and adolescents, and was attended by Macao and Continent Mental Health doctors, in a total of about a hundred people.
In the speech given during the meeting, Tai Wa has stressed that the government will implement the objectives and indicators set by the “healthy macao action plan”, following the development of physical and mental health of young people and adolescents. To this end, he stressed, "SSM will also cooperate with different public services and promote the wide participation of associations to their medical resources to extend to community neighborhoods and thus further improve the physical and mental health of residents."</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>21 Drone offenses in 2024 detected</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/detectadas-21-infraccoes-drones-em-2024/</link><description>The new requests for the drone operation rose 62% in 2024, but notifications of their activities were a small descent, in a year when unmanned air vehicle flights were prohibited for 15 days due to the holding of several events, namely in the context of the 25th anniversary celebrations. The civil aviation authority recorded 21 cases of infringements, three less than in 2023
 
Contrary to two consecutive years on the rise, the use of drones in the MSAR softened last year, as well as the number of cases of violations of the air navigation regulation. The Macao Civil Aviation Authority (AACM) received 7,748 notifications of non -manned air vehicle activities, less 31 or 0.4% than the 7,779 submitted in 2023, the year that a growth of 17.8% led to a new historical maximum.
In 2024, according to statistics by the aviation regulatory entity, 21 cases of drone offenses were detected, less than the previous year, which was also marked by a record in this domain by overcoming the 13 violations noted in 2019. After the AACM revision of the AACM, AACM accounted for a total of 100 cases of offenses.
On the other hand, the body received 1,010 new requests for drone operation, an increase of 387 or 62.1% compared to 2023. The number of approved orders rose 86% to 623 in the range of one year, corresponding to 61.7% of the total requirements.
According to the data analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, AACM has received 9,179 new requests since 2016 and approved 7,564. The percentage of authorizations was thus situated at 82.4%.
The restrictions imposed by the authorities for 15 days of 2024, due to the realization of various events, naturally contributed to the slight slowdown in drones use. It is recalled that flights with non-manned aircraft at Macao Airspace were banned between December 14 and 22, to ensure that the commemorative activities of the 25th anniversary of the establishment of the MGrear were “without startle and safe”. During this period, non -residents were even prevented from entering the territory with drones.
The flight embargo was also adopted on the Peninsula during the Macao Grand Prix (between November 14 and 17), as well as on October 13 in the area of ​​the Complex Complex for commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, due to government organized activities. On October 19, the same measure was implemented in Coloane for identical reasons.
The air navigation regulation stipulates fines between 2,000 and 20,000 patacas for violations involving drones. If the authorities consider that the activity concerned is a criminal act, the user is also subject to responsibilities enshrined in the Penal Code.
In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Leong Hong Sai, the president of AACM recently ensured that the body “strives to satisfy, as far as possible and ensure operational safety, the needs of use of unmanned aircraft in various sectors”. "For this purpose, after the evaluation of safety conditions, differentiated altitude restrictions were established and delimited flight areas for the operation of these aircraft in the limited Airspace of Macao," explained Pun Wa Kin.
In addition, according to the same responsible, “in order to facilitate government patrols and emergency relief operations, when considering authorization for unmanned aircraft activities, AACM makes a comprehensive assessment based on factors such as flight, time, model and weight of the aircraft, among others”. If the operational safety standards are gathered, the regulatory entity seeks to meet “the needs of the requesting entities, such as topographic and cartographic survey, registration of building construction and inspection works, among other works, in order to reduce pressure on human resources traditionally involved in patrolling, inspection and operation activities”.
 
11 cases of smokers aboard aircraft
Last year, the Macao Civil Aviation Authority accounted for 12 unlawful acts committed aboard aircraft, 11 of which related to the prohibition of smoking. The other case was the “disobedience to legitimate instructions of the aircraft commander,” the body said on its electronic page, without specifying the contours of the incident. In 2024, no cases of misuse of electronic devices were detected. The previous year, the body had recorded nine illicit acts, all involving smokers.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Work adjustment at Fai Chi Kei cost AMI over one million</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ajuste-de-obra-fai-chi-kei-custou-ao-iam-mais-de-um-milhao/</link><description>The institute for municipal affairs had to pay more than one million patacas to the contractor who was going to build the leisure zone at Fai Chi Kei, due to adjustments in the project. The modifications had to do with the requirements in the scope of flood prevention
 
CATARINA PEREIRA
 
The construction work of the northern bay leisure zone of Fai Chi Kei, on the street of Commander João Belo, which had to be adjusted because of an opinion in the scope of flood prevention requirements, cost to the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) over 1.085 million patacas. The amount covered the termination of the contract and compensation to the contractor, according to the explanation given by the body in the opinion of the report on the execution of the budget of 2023.
The award of that work was authorized in the 4th quarter of 2018, however, as explained by the AMI “in harmony with the flood prevention work”, and according to an opinion from the then direction of soil, public works and transport services, the leisure area had to be adjusted to “satisfy the flood prevention requirements and, to avoid the repetition of excavations and the congestion of the transit ”.
In this sense, “the contractor was agreed to terminate the contract, providing compensation for expenses already made”. The contractor had already had spending on exercise equipment and lighting, as well as administrative costs, among others not specified by AMI.
According to the opinion available on the Legislative Assembly page, the termination of the contract and compensation of the work were approved in mid -2023, and the compensation amount was paid in the same year.
According to the Cheng Pou newspaper, the full budget of the project's modified plan exceeded the amount originally awarded by more than 50%, that is, it was over 13.3 million patacas.
The leisure zone in the northern bay of Fai Chi Kei on Rua do Commander João Belo was completed and put in use earlier this year, and included the construction of 170 meters long boxes, involving the two works a total budget exceeding 45 million patacas.
According to the same newspaper, the compensation represented about 12% of the original cost of the project.
It is recalled that by 2023, the government abandoned the idea of ​​building a statue of Kun iam in HAC-Sá, budgeted at over 42 million patacas, after a wave of criticism. In November last year, the compensation process was still taking place, with the AMI not revealing details about the case. This newspaper tried to understand with AMI if there is already a decision, but did not get an answer until the closure of this edition.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Starting consumer plan with strong adhesion of elderly</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/arranque-plano-de-consumo-forte-adesao-de-idosos/</link><description>On the launch day of the “Great Award for Consumption in Community Zones”, the initiative attracted more than 9,000 elderly in the morning, according to the DSEDT director
 
The “Great Award for Consumption in Community Zones 2025” was launched yesterday, with many elderly people to appear to the service posts to obtain the immediate discount benefits of 300 Patacas by loading the new version of the Macau Pass card for the elderly.
According to the Chinese language press, Yau Yun Wah, director of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), said that until 10:30 yesterday more than 9,000 seniors completed the survey of immediate discount benefits. And before the program starts, about 10,000 requested the replacement of the new version of the Card for the elderly, of which 6,000 have already raised the new cards.
In addition, Yau Yun Wah said DSEDT and payment institutions have established an inspection mechanism, through which the act of canceling the order on platforms simply in order to obtain the opportunity to gain electronic discount coupons. The DSEDT director warned the public so as not to participate in the “great consumption award” award, warning that infrastors will be prohibited from gaining electronic discount coupons.
On the other hand, Yau Yun Wah revealed that, with the aim of giving even more impetus to the “great award for consumption” and stimulating consumption in the North Zone, DSEDT will launch, this Saturday, areas for large photographs, alluding to international -renowned brand characters, in the Ilha Verde neighborhood and in the IAO Hon market. North has reached a certain amount, the resident or tourist will be able to participate in a draw to receive a souvenir alluding to these characters.
Frederico MA, director of the Commercial Association, said that about 100 establishments plan to launch additional discounts, predicting the gradual climb of the number of stores that will adopt the same strategy.
For its part, Wong Kin Chong, president of the North Industrial and Commercial Association, found that many stores had prepared for the new consumer program, and many chose to intensify the purchase of products, especially supermarkets, pharmacies and frozen meat stores. In addition, he stressed that the association had already suggested to traders to launch more discounts, so as to redouble the effects of the “great consumption award”, attracting more people to consume in Macao.
According to DSEDT, the consumer program will take place until June 1 this year, lasting 10 weeks, and the obtained electronic discount coupons may be used in more than 20,000 physical stores.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>20 companies debut “Green” projects at MIECF</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/20-empresas-estreiam-projectos-verdes-miecf/</link><description>In this year's edition of the Forum and International Exhibition of Environmental Cooperation of Macau, 20 companies will present innovative technologies and projects, within the scope of the region's green transformation
 
About 20 companies will present new technologies and projects at the Macao's International Environmental Cooperation (MIECF) forum and Exhibition of Environmental Cooperation (MIECF) at March 27 and 29 at Cotai Expo do Venetian. “Innovation and Green Development - Solutions for the Construction of Beautiful Cities” is the theme of the event organized by the Government of MSA.
The first -time debut economy project exposure zone will bring together debut projects from various places, focusing on the “promotion” chain development mode, with the aim of boosting the green consumer market and green transformation.
According to the organization, presentations include green technology projects, intelligent energy, green AI management, carbon neutrality and circular economy. The robot dog B2, for environmental monitoring and resource exploration; A “highly efficient liquid -cooled superloading system for electric vehicles and carbon capture technology for interior spaces are some of the innovations that will be on display.
An exhibitor of the Hengqin cooperation zone intends to launch a new innovative biodegradable material with environmental application for consumers and companies. Already a Jiangsu company will present “an electric motorcycle with the automatic parking function that can be remotely controlled” through a mobile application. The product aims to improve the convenience of parking in tight spaces, according to the MIECF.
During the event, will also be presented the world's first system of “wireless loading solar energy for shared electric bicycles”. This new system, according to MIECF, “exceeds the limitations of traditional loading”, combining flexible high -efficiency flexible photovoltaic panels with wireless magnetic loading technology and aims to offer the public a convenient low carbon transportation.
MIECF will hold other initiatives such as the “debut economy @macau - launch of innovative contact scholarship session” to publicize debut projects and “ESG excellence premiums” to more than 30 Hong Kong and Macau's interior companies. These companies will be invited to the “Contact Scholarships session in the field of International Low Carbon International Development” in order to stimulate exchange and business cooperation.
In addition to exhibitions, professional environmental protection organizations will perform activities such as the Implementation Guide Conference on Carbon Neutrality for Conventions and Exhibitions and the Green Innovation Conference, within the Green Development of the Great Bay.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Deputy asks for more guarantees for workers on his own</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/deputado-pede-mais-garantias-para-trabalhadores-por-conta-propria/</link><description>Leong Sun Iok considers that, with the evolution of the "new sectoral ecology" in Macao, workers on their own and liberals should have access to more work guarantees, such as insurance. In this sense, the deputy urged the government to optimize the criteria provided for in the legislation
 
Given that many employers do not need to buy labor insurance for food delivery, taxi drivers, tourist bus drivers, among other workers on their own, Leong Sun Iok urged the government to try to discover cases of bosses that avoid the responsibilities and duties that they should take over labor relations, taking advantage of the form of “service contract”.
In a written interplies, the deputy suggested to the Executive that, according to the changes and the development of the “new sectoral ecology” in the territory, study ways to ensure work guarantees to workers on their own and liberal. In addition, he argued, he should boost the employer to provide work insurance to workers subject to service contract in order to reinforce labor guarantees in Macao.
Citing workers from the “new sectoral ecology”, Leong Sun Iok warned that while some platforms adopt the form of service contract, their time and work form does not differ from formally hired workers' situations, implying the nature of “working under the employer's authority”. "Macao, like a micro-economic, has a limited market, so many people can only choose this form of employment," he said.
In addition, the deputy emphasized that, subject to service contracts, workers on their own will have to bear risks and higher costs during work, including eventual health problems and work accidents. At this point, he noted that many food delivery platforms in the interior of China recently announced that they would start buying social insurance for their delivery, which, for the deputy, is a “positive sign” for the “new sectoral ecology”.
Noting that “many cities have already begun to discuss how to better protect workers from 'new sectoral ecology'”, the deputy linked to the Federation of Workers' Associations expects the authorities to study the criteria to define labor relations and their guarantees, provided for in the Labor Relations Law and in other relevant legal regimes.
In addition, Leong Sun Iok questioned the government about whether he has already collected statistical data to realize the number and types of workers on their own and liberals. It also suggested conducting a study related to jobs derived from the “new sectoral ecology” in order to protect the work and labor interests of the respective workers.
The deputy also understands that clear guidelines should be issued to clarify labor relations, and at the same time, reinforced awareness actions to prevent the violation of the respective legal provisions by employers.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IC Cancela concert scheduled for March</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ic-cancela-concerto-previsto-para-marco/</link><description>大型戶外演出場地



The upcoming musical show of great wingspan in the outdoor space located in Cotai will only happen in May. Another concert was scheduled for this month, but the Cultural Institute gave up organizing it, since the candidacies “could not collaborate with the authorities,” according to the body's president. For the two shows, the IC received about three dozen proposals
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The outdoor shows place in Cotai will only have a big concert in May again, but the details of the band that will act there are not yet known. Another show was scheduled for March, however, the candidacies presented did not correspond to what the organization required, and there was no “collaboration with the authorities, in relation to the time of the concert and the number of spectators,” according to the President of the Cultural Institute (IC).
Speaking to the Chinese press, Leong Wai Man stated that many requests were received, "about three dozen for both concerts together." However, for the March show “it was not possible to gather the best conditions for it to take place” and so the IC points to the next musical exhibition in May, whose details “will be released this week,” said the body's guardian.
The applications presented "are being appreciated," Leong Wai Man continued, who said he hopes that concerts will be "gradually promoted," that is, starting with shows for 20,000 spectators, "number that will increase later."
Regarding the balance of the Macao International Parade, which took place on Sunday afternoon, the president of the IC expressed satisfaction because the parade had "overcome the authorities' estimates," which were about 150,000 spectators along the way.
Although still without numbers of the 2025 edition, Leong Wai Man considered that "the assistance was certainly higher than that recorded in 2024," reflecting "the recovery of the flow of visitors from Macao."
The leader expressed, on the other hand, the hope that the parade contributed to strengthen the business of the traders who operate on the outskirts of the course. "Later, the IC will collect opinions with commercial associations and groups of residents regarding their activity and especially to know what were the positive effects raised by the parade," he said.
Asked if the government considers to extend the parade path to the northern part of the city, Leong Wai Man said the IC "has been pondering the realization of various activities in different community neighborhoods." Therefore, he said, "It will also ponder this orientation."
Still, Leong Wai Man pointed out that the parade requires a relatively wide space for the teams to be able to display and also implies traffic arrangements.
"Currently the procession starts in the ruins of São Paulo and ends in Praça do Lago Sai Van, where the space is relatively wide," he advocates. On the other hand, he concludes, "this route is popular for people, with many years of experience, so that, in the future, the IC will try to coordinate better with other public services, with regard to traffic during the stop."
The 2025 International Parade, which reached the 11th edition, brought Macao 23 foreign groups from 15 countries or regions, which came together about 60 local performance organizations and representative associations of the resident communities, such as Brazil, Philippines, India, among others. About 1,800 extras evolved along the way, in a display that attracted to the central streets of the territory a large crowd of people.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SJM and UTM open 70 vacancies for innovative program</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sjm-utm-abrem-70-vagas-para-programa-inovador/</link><description>In a joint effort, SJM Resorts and the University of Tourism of Macau launched the “Forge My Own Journey” program, with the purpose of offering young places an innovative training in the integrated tourism and leisure industry
 
SJM Resorts (SJM) and Macao University of Tourism (UTM) launched the “Forge My Own Journey” Development Program, at a ceremony that took place at Resort Grand Lisboa Palace.
In a statement, SJM stresses that the program “introduces an innovative approach to integrated learning and work experience, offering young places a unique opportunity that combines theoretical education with practical experience”.
Aligned with the Government's government policy to “build Macau through talent”, the initiative aims to cultivate tourism, leisure and hotel management specialists and offer internships in various SJM departments, such as hotel operations, food and beverage management, retail management or event planning, with monthly salaries and benefits.
Students who complete the program successfully, and get a degree in Hotel or Tourist Management from UTM, will receive the full value of the bribes for four years of training, sponsored by SJM. The program will be inaugurated this year, with 70 vacancies for secondary school finalists.
SJM administrator Daisy Ho said the operator “is committed to cultivating local talent” and that the project “aims to leverage the vast experience of SJM in the Integrated Tourism and Leisure industry, along with UTM's strong academic base to create a path for young professionals”.
In the same vein, Fanny Vong, rector of UTM, asserted that the program “aims to provide local students with comprehensive knowledge through theoretical learning and practical application”, allowing students to “quickly pursue professional paths within the integrated tourism and leisure industry”.
The SJM states that the initiative has received an “enthusiastic response” throughout the 30 informative sessions, with the participation of more than 2,000 students and the support of 26 secondary schools. The operator promises to continue to actively collaborate with local schools and educational institutions to develop high quality staff in the MSAR.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Studio City's “skatepark” is the first in a macao terrace</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/skatepark-studio-city-e-primeiro-num-terraco-de-macau/</link><description>Studio City opened the first skate park on a terrace on the territory, with the aim of contributing to the development of Macau as “City of Sport”
 
On the weekend, Studio City inaugurated "Sk8te Park", the first skate park on a terrace in Macau, which hosted the "Sk8tefest" festival and the "Fish Battle of the Champions" from "Melco Style". According to Studio City, this was the first international skate competition in the Great Bay.
The park was developed by “Hurricane Parks”, a renowned construction company of sports facilities worldwide. The project was built to combine Macau's urban landscape and a state -of -the -art skate park design, suitable for athletes of all levels, from beginners to professionals, with the only double -shaped bowl of 8 and the city's largest skate bowl.
The events brought together practitioners of the sport from around the world, including Kai Kishi, Nathaniel Wong and Jasper Dohrs. In addition to skate contests, demonstrations of BMX, DJ, Breakdance and Graffitis were held, which attracted many enthusiasts. The place of the competition had three zones, designed to highlight the mixture of Macao's cultural heritage.
The inauguration of the “Sk8te Park” reflects the dedication of the resort to strengthen the city as a “city of sport” and “further reinforce Macau's position as a world center of tourism and leisure”, bringing world-class sports facilities and major international sports events to the Senior and Director-General of Studio City, Kevin Benning, said that “ Melco has been committed to supporting the strategy of development of the Government of MSAR ”to diversify the economy and promote the transionic integration of“ Tourism+”.
According to Studio City's statement, the combination of “SK8Tefest” with “Fese Battle of the Champions” provided “an unforgettable experience for urban sports and radical sports enthusiasts” and helped establish Macao as an emerging destination for radical sports.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SMOKING AREAS IN THE RIGHTS AND SERCO DOORS</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/areas-para-fumar-nas-ruinas-portas-cerco-vistas-como-dificeis/</link><description>Although “residents are usually opposed to the conduct of smoking by walking”, the idea of ​​delimiting exclusive areas to smoke in the São Paulo ruins and the Siege Portas could imply difficulties in implementation, warned Chan U Iong, assistant coordinator of the North Zone Community Services Advisory Board. Quoted by the “or world tin toi”, Chan U Iong pointed out that the background measure means the widening of the scope of smoking, which will involve the execution of the law and accusations. Thus, the representative of the North Zone Advisory Board suggested the holding of a comprehensive inquiry and a public consultation on the matter. In addition, it considers that the government can intensify sensitization to “smoke in a well-educated way” so that an environment without smoke is fostered. In turn, Chan Kin Sun, director of the Association for Smoking and Health Protection, faces government orientation as "positive." However, it also predicted that the creation of smoking areas will be “very difficult”, since the high population density and the limited space of the territory oblige many factors to consider. From his perspective, another solution is the extent of the scope of prohibition of smoke to the immediate vicinity of schools and hospitals, having as reference the measures that are in force with the pounds of buses. In addition, the associative leader understands that, in the long run, it is necessary to create a “perfected and effective” interdepartal coordination mechanism, committed to the control of smoking, something that, in his opinion, will be equally “challenging”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Economic diversification of masters includes reinforcement of relations with the outside</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/diversificacao-economica-da-raem-inclui-reforco-das-relacoes-exterior/</link><description>The MSar will “strengthen and expand its relations with the abroad”, namely as regards the Spanish and Southeast Asia markets, “which will further promote the proper diversification of the local economy”, asserted the Chief Executive, in a meeting with China's deputy MINISTER OF Foreign Affairs, Hua Chunying, who thanked the support of Beijing. related to the outside ”. According to an official note, Sam Hou Fai also stressed that, due to his “great historical and cultural wealth”, Macau represents “a platform for communication and cooperation between the country and the abroad”. In addition, he reiterated, "with a prosperous, stable, peaceful and harmonious society," Macau "is a successful example of the implementation of" one country, two systems. " Present at the meeting were the Commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Popular Republic of China at MSAR, Liu Xianfa and the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2366/</link><description>Broadhouse cable hurt two women
Two women will have been injured by the metal cable of a broom, which was thrown from a building on the Hippodrome Avenue. The Fire Department revealed that the wounds, a 41-year-old resident and a 19-year-old saved-conduct holder, were transported to the conscious and stable state hospital, suffering bruises on the neck and on a shoulder. The case occurred at 8 pm on Sunday, when the broom cable fell near a bus stop. Police moved to the building concerned to ascertain the case.
 
271 economic houses have already been sold
Data from the Housing Institute indicate that 271 Economic Housing Fractions have already been sold under the 2019 competition. Currently, 2,632 candidates are waiting for the choice of home. According to the body, 80 T2 and 191 T3 typology apartments were sold, and 1,066 T3, 920 T2 and 760 T1 were still available. A substantial part (39%) of aggregates who have already chosen home is composed of three elements, in a total of 105 families; followed by 74 nuclei consisting of an element and 71 for four or more.
 
ATFPM approved reports for last year
At the General Assembly of the Macao Public Function Association (ATFPM), the partners “unanimously approved” the 2024 financial activities report and the annual activities of activities. According to the ATFPM, in the assembly "several members" pointed out that the economic uncertainty of Macao, affected by the international context, maintains many families in difficulty. They also talked about the “challenges” in young people's access to employment, housing problems, limited access to medical care, and lack of homes for the elderly.
 
Tickets for FAM are already on sale
Tickets for the 35th Arts Festival (FAM) shows are already on sale at the “Enjoy Macao” box office (Ticketing.enjoymacao.mo), through online box office services, by telephone and at points of sale. According to the Cultural Institute (IC), 30% discounts are available in early purchase of tickets, upon certain criteria, until March 30, and 20% from the next day, including card patients from various local banks. FAM also offers a 50% discount to people with special benefit cards for elderly or disability assessment, as well as a full -time student card.
 
Elderly challenged to participate in the sports games
Citizens born until 1974 will be able to participate in the “Sports Games for the Elderly of Macao”, which will take place on April 13, at the TAP Seac Pavilion, the Sports Institute (ID) said. Interested parties may move to ID, TAP SEAC Pavilion, Olympic Sports Center, General Union of Sports Associations of the Elderly, General Union of Residents Associations, Workers' Associations Federation, Macao Women's General Association and the Senior Citizen Academy of Polytechnic University to obtain the registration report or unload it online (www.sport.gov.mo).</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Japanese widow Aum Shinrikyo speaks 30 years after attack on the metro</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/viuva-culto-japones-aum-shinrikyo-fala-30-anos-apos-ataque-metro/</link><description>Just seven years after her marriage, Yuki Niimi first touched her husband-a morgue, where she collected her body after her execution, and kissed him in a coffin. Prior to that, a glass screen always separated her from her husband, Tomomitsu Niimi, a notorious member of the final judgment Aum Shinrikyo who for 30 years orchestrated an attack with a nervous agent in the capital of Japan.
On March 20, 1995, members of AME released Sarin in five Carriages of the Tokyo Metropolitan, killing 14 people and leaving thousands sick. "Until the end, he did not apologize to those who died. He did not regret what he did."
Yuki herself is a former member of an Aum's successor group that, despite her denials, has already been convicted of using intimidation to try to recruit an acquaintance for the sect. Given the magnitude of her husband's crimes, she believes that the death penalty was "inevitable" and that "paying refund" is the only way that the cultures of AM can do.
Under the domain of rebel -haired guru and almost blind Shoko Asahara, Aum's devotees believed that the Armageão was coming and saw the massacres as an altruistic way of raising souls to a superior kingdom.
Unhappy young people in Japan, including doctors and engineers who later manufactured toxins, found comfort in Asahara's doctrines. Among the most loyal pupils was Tomomitsu, which was behind bars when he met Yuki and when they got married in 2011.
His relationship consisted of letters and 15 to 30 minutes of conversation, almost every day, under the supervision of a guard. It all ended with its execution in the summer of 2018, along with 12 other AMA members, including Asahara.
After her death, the widow Yuki stroked the still hot body of Tomomitsu, whose neck was wrapped in a ligation to hide the mark left by the loop. He then spent the next three days, to the cremation, lying next to him at home. "He didn't seem to have suffered anything. He seemed to be sleeping," she said.
Tomomitsu, who died at the age of 54, is sometimes called Aum's “bloodiest” disciple - having helped perpetrate all seven deadly attacks on the group, including the previous strike of the meter in which he served as a driver.
The AUM cultists, who wasolated and were incommunicable in the pre-internet era, "believed in everything," Asahara said, and "honestly thought they were helping their act of salvation," Yuki said.
However, about a month before Tomomitsu's execution, she felt that her loyalty to the leader was finally crumbling. “He called him only 'Asahara'-this had never happened before in the 12 years or more we were together.
Then, in his diary, “in the last days of his life, he clearly expressed that 'I will not follow him anymore'” realizing that Asahara's teachings over Karma were a fallacy, Yuki said.
Also, despite Tomomitsu's lack of remorse, "I asked why Aum had performed the gas attack on the meter, and my husband clearly told me that the guru was sick, mentally ill," he added.
The poisoning in the metro shocked the world and led to an adjustment of accounts with extremism in Japan, with a repression of the Asahara Empire, which has had more than 10,000 followers.
Its successor groups continue to operate and recruit, with estimated numbers of 1,600 in the domestic market. Two of these groups, Aleph and Hikarinowa, openly operate in Japan, which, according to some experts, makes them easier to monitor.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>