<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>The persistence of “imbalances” in a year of growth</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/persistencia-dos-desequilibrios-num-ano-de-crescimentos/</link><description>In a year of growth, such as GDP or the number of visitors, the area of ​​the economy continued to be very marked by “imbalances”, with warnings from various parties about the decrease in domestic consumption and consequently the difficulties of small and medium-sized companies. The construction of the Deep Cooperation Zone in Hengqin was also on the agenda, with increasing efforts to develop that zone. In this year 2025, emphasis should also be placed on changes in the allocation of cash checks, the closure of satellite casinos and trends towards a decrease in birth rates and an increase in aging














































CATARINA PEREIRA
 
The year 2025 began with messages of hope from the new Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, who had taken office just a few weeks earlier. Stressing that Macau was in a “new phase of development”, the Macao SAR leader defended that the recovery would involve “high quality growth”, being optimistic that it would have “a promising future”. However, the truth is that throughout the year - and as the Chief Executive would recently recognize, as part of the presentation of the Government Action Lines for 2026 -, “some deep conflicts and long-lasting problems that are difficult to resolve” continued to persist: the imbalance in economic development, the lack of visible progress in the diversification of the economy and the slow progress in the revitalization of old neighborhoods.
In his New Year's message, Sam Hou Fai stressed that, in addition to making better use of the advantages of the “one country, two systems” principle, the Government should “know how to identify” problems”, “provide answers” and carry out “reforms with determination”. country's development situation.
Requests for support from the population would soon arrive. Days later, several associations, deputies of the Legislative Assembly and former deputies urged the authorities to launch new measures to encourage consumption. These requests were recurring throughout the year, as crossing the border to shop and eat meals in Zhuhai or Hengqin became increasingly common among the population.
Chinese New Year was seen by some as a good time for the Government to support residents and there were also those who called for another round of the “Grand Consumer Prize”. On the other hand, for the president of the Commercial Association, Frederico Ma, the Government should launch new activities to stimulate consumption after the Lunar New Year. The idea was also supported by Lei Cheok Kuan, president of the Federation of Industry and Commerce of Macau Central and Southern Districts, who also urged banks to extend the repayment deadlines for loans to small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs).
The Government would launch two initiatives to encourage consumption. The first “Grand Prize for consumption in community areas”, held between April and June, stimulated a turnover of 1.04 billion patacas. In this promotional activity, electronic benefits totaling 290 million patacas were issued, of which 250 million were used. In the second phase, which also took place over 13 weeks, but this time between September and November, electronic benefit coupons were awarded which boosted local consumption for a total value of around 1.645 million patacas. Specifically, the coupons awarded were around 462 million patacas.
At the same time, the prospects were quite encouraging within the game. The consultancy Seaport Research Partners considered that the sector should register “continuous growth” throughout 2025, which could culminate in an 8% increase in accounts compared to 2024. The projection specifically pointed to a global gross revenue close to 245 billion patacas, above the 240 billion patacas predicted by the Macao SAR Government in the Budget – a value that would later be revised downwards.
As for the flow of visitors expected for the year in Macau, the director of Tourism Services (DST), Helena de Senna Fernandes, indicated that it could reach between 38 and 39 million, values ​​that, if confirmed, would be very close to the level of 2019, before the pandemic.
In April, economists told this newspaper that Macau should not be immune to the trade conflict between the US and China, anticipating “direct or indirect risks” for the Macao SAR, arising from customs tariffs imposed by the Trump administration. Days later, the University of Macau (UM) adjusted its forecasts for the Macao SAR's GDP growth rate due to the changes observed in the global economy, generated by US tax policy. At the same time, Helena de Senna Fernandes assured that the impact of commercial disputes was not yet reflected in Macau's tourist flow.
The International Monetary Fund (IMF) again reduced its projections for Macau's economy in April, pointing to growth of 3.6% in 2025, half the estimate announced in October. On the other hand, forecasts for unemployment and inflation rates for this year were lowered to 1.7% and 0.9%, respectively. In October, however, the IMF would once again revise downwards its forecasts for the Macao SAR's GDP growth, pointing out that it should only grow by 2.6%. As for inflation, it pointed to 0.5% in 2025, while the forecast for the unemployment rate remained unchanged.
In June, the estimate for the game's gross revenue was revised downwards, with the Government pointing to 228 billion patacas instead of the 240 billion initially projected. As part of the amendment to the Budget for 2025, the authorities also announced an increase of 2.82 billion patacas so that the Government could comply with support for vulnerable groups and also to cover expenses with the construction of the University of Macau campus in Hengqin (1.75 billion) and with scientific and technological investment (340 million).
Despite this, by the end of November, gaming revenue reached 99.3% of the 228 billion forecast by the Government in the Budget review for the entire year. Specifically, in the first 11 months of 2025, gaming revenue totaled 226.52 billion patacas, reflecting an annual increase of 8.6% and corresponding to 84% of the value recorded between January and November 2019, according to data from the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Department (DICJ).
In November alone, gross gaming revenue amounted to around 21.09 billion, 14.4% more in annual terms and corresponding to 92.2% of the level reached in the same period of 2019, marking the highest recovery rate since the covid-19 pandemic.
Regarding the number of visitors, it grew 14.4% to 36.49 million in the first 11 months of 2025, in annual terms. In the month of November alone, the Macao SAR welcomed 3.34 million visitors (+18.1%), with those from Mainland China (2.40 million) rising 21.9% year-on-year. In turn, international visitor arrivals (around 274 thousand) rose 13.6% compared to November 2024.
Macau will end the year with an annual record number of visitors, guaranteed on the 27th, reaching 39.41 million, surpassing the final mark of 2019 (39.40 million).
 
O desaparecimento dos casinos-satélite
Also in June, the Executive began to move forward with plans regarding the closure of satellite casinos. Before the end of the year, the 11 spaces under the jurisdiction of SJM, Melco and Galaxy would close their doors – however, SJM intended to “rescue” two of these spaces, through the acquisition of the properties of the hotels where the Ponte 16 and Le Royal Arc casinos are located. The outcome would, however, be different: SJM ended up abdicating the Ponte 16 casino, aiming solely at L’Arc.
The closure of satellite casinos took place throughout the second half of the year, with the last of these spaces closing its doors on December 30th, and involved almost 6,000 jobs. With the disappearance of these gaming spaces, attention was also drawn to the impact it could have on SMEs and other surrounding businesses.
The Economic Association, in turn, anticipated that the Macao SAR economy would remain “stable” in the following months, but warned of several indicators that reflected “potential risks”, such as the “share price of gaming companies”, the “Chinese consumer confidence index” and the “ratio of loans and deposits of residents in local banks”. The association also warned of the “pressure” that the closure of satellite casinos could cause in surrounding areas.
Meanwhile, the Government announced that it would launch consumer coupon packages and install international intellectual property check-in points near satellite casinos, to support the stores. At the same time, the General Association of the Real Estate Sector highlighted the impact of the closure of satellite casinos on the ZAPE real estate market, particularly in relation to house prices and store rents, predicting that the situation will result in a “domino effect”, reaching a larger area.
In July, deputy Lo Choi In urged the Government to launch new consumption vouchers, “even if it is only for two or three thousand patacas”. The deputy observed that the economic situation continued to be “not optimistic” and that “citizens' incomes have decreased significantly and shopkeepers are suffering immensely”.
The Monetary Authority (AMCM), in turn, predicted that, until the end of this year, the Macao SAR economy should continue to show resilience and follow a “recovery trajectory”, albeit at a “weaker” pace due to “external challenges”. In the second “Review of Monetary and Financial Stability” report for 2025, the organization anticipated “moderate” inflationary pressures and “favorable” conditions in the labor market, and reiterated its optimism about the impact of economic diversification and measures to encourage consumption in old neighborhoods. On the other hand, despite some mixed signals in the sector, he highlighted that local banks had recorded “improvements” in terms of liquidity and profitability.
According to a study by members of the Research and Statistics Department of the Monetary Authority, in the last two years, the economic recovery driven by external demand “did not effectively spread to more than half of the sectors”. The gaming, hotel and restaurant sectors were those that “significantly benefited” from the arrival of more visitors to the territory. In this sense, they argued that “although efforts to boost external demand continue to be crucial, equal attention must be given to stimulating domestic demand” to guarantee “a balanced economic recovery”.
The latest data from the Statistics and Census Services on GDP show that, up to September, the MSAR's economy amounted to 301.33 billion patacas, reflecting a real increase of 4.2%, in annual terms, and corresponding to 88.4% of the economic volume of the same period in 2019. Macau's economy had advanced only 1.8% in the first half of this year, with a contraction of 1.3% between January and March, the first year-on-year decline since the end of 2022, to be offset by an increase of 5.1% in the second quarter.
The unemployment rate in Macau, in turn, did not undergo sequential changes between June and August, remaining at 2.0%, despite improvements in underemployment. However, this scenario of stability reflected in official statistics does not hide the fact that all employment indicators have worsened compared to last year, from the active population to the universe of unemployed and underemployed people.
In the months of August to October, the overall unemployment and resident unemployment rates fell by 0.1 percentage points, compared to the period from July to September, standing at 1.7% and 2.3%, respectively. This was the second consecutive sequential decline in unemployment overall.
This month, the Legislative Assembly unanimously approved, in particular, the proposal to review the universal minimum wage law. Thus, from January 1st, the minimum wage will increase from 34 patacas per hour to 35, from 7,072 per month to 7,280, from 272 to 280 per day and from 1,632 to 1,680 per week. The adjustment reflects an increase of 2.9% in all forms of calculation.
 
Change in the allocation of cash checks
It was at the beginning of the year that requests for the financial contribution plan also began to emerge, some of which would come to fruition. Pointing out that the financial contribution plays “a positive role in alleviating inequality between rich and poor”, Congresswoman Lo Choi In defended legislation to make the measure permanent. In order to ensure the reasonable use of public funds, it proposed a verification mechanism in relation to residents who have already emigrated, applying restrictions on their right to this benefit.
Lo Choi In was followed, two weeks later, by the then deputy Ron Lam, who also defended the end of the granting of checks to those living outside Macau. Later, Leong In Pong, deputy director of the social affairs committee of the General Union of Residents' Associations (“Kaifong”), shared the same opinion. Other people also defended changes to the rules, for example, the allocation of different amounts to different groups of the population, among other measures.
In March, the Chief Executive admitted that there could be changes in the value and form of distribution of cash checks, a matter that was not yet closed, however. "If there is room for improvement, how much and how to distribute, the public must give opinions, to further demonstrate fairness, precision and connection to the Macao SAR. And, in these aspects, we must consider more", said the leader of the Macao SAR.
As he said, it was necessary to take into account “the global economic environment”. "If you don't forget that the monthly gaming revenue worth 20 billion patacas was used as a base, there is a small surplus. But look at the month of December: there was only about 18 billion. The Government will consider this issue as a whole and will announce it to the public when a decision is made", he continued.
Admitting that the financial contribution plan benefits residents and creates expectations in society, Sam Hou Fai recalled that it was implemented in 2008, as a temporary measure, and whose objective was to share the result of economic development with the population, if there were conditions in the public coffers. The Macao SAR leader also recalled that, until then, 90 billion patacas had already been allocated in this context.
It was at the end of May that the news arrived. Macau residents who are living abroad will have to stay 183 days in the Macao SAR to be able to benefit from the financial contribution. Despite the change, several exceptions were established, such as being a student abroad or living in Mainland China. The measure affected hundreds of Portuguese people living abroad. After the change, the Chief Executive argued several times that the financial contribution plan was adjusted because there is “social consensus” in this regard.
As stated in the Government Action Lines, the new rules allowed the Government to raise 840 million patacas, money which, according to the Government, will be channeled towards social support.
 
Birth rate falling and aging rising
In the social sphere, the low birth rate and population aging continued to be a worrying trend in the territory. At a meeting to prepare for the elaboration of the Lines of Government Action, the Women's Association asked the Secretary for Economy and Finance to pay attention to reducing the birth rate in the territory. The president of the board pointed out that “it is essential for sustainable social development to launch measures to encourage birth rates” and also called for family-friendly measures. The birth rate issue was also on the agenda at a meeting between the Education Association and the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture.
At the beginning of the year, the deputy director of Health Services predicted that there should be less than 3,500 births in the territory this year, which, if it happens, would be the lowest since 2004.
Within the scope of the Governing Action Lines (LAG) for 2025, the Chief Executive announced policies to encourage birth rates and increase support for the elderly and people with disabilities. The “child care subsidy” provides for monthly support of 1,500 patacas, for a total of 18,000 patacas per year, to babies and permanent resident children under the age of three. According to Sam Hou Fai, in 2025 the subsidy should help 15 thousand children up to the age of three. In addition, the birth allowance, which was previously 5,418 patacas, increased to 6,500 patacas.
Despite this, in the first nine months of the year, 2,130 babies were born in Macau, a drop of 18.94% in annual terms, according to official statistics. Babies born in this period made up 59% of the total recorded throughout last year (3,607). Even so, the decline in birth rates was reversed in the third quarter, with 709 live births reflecting an increase of 5.6% compared to the previous three months.
In the first month of the year, there were only around five hundred vacancies in nursing homes, and the waiting list was quite long. As reported by the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, the vacant seats did not cover even a third of the people waiting to enter these spaces, which totaled around 1,800. The Social Action Institute then assured that it was working so that people could be admitted and indicated that, every month, more than 30 people entered subsidized homes.
In the case of the elderly, and within the scope of LAG, the subsidy increased from 9,000 to 10,000 patacas per year, while the pension increased from 3,740 to 3,900 patacas per month, for a total of 13 payments per year. Sam Hou Fai also said that work on identifying elderly people and single elderly couples would continue.
In May, this newspaper looked at precisely this issue. In view of the population aging trend, the academic specializing in Gerontology Jacky Ho and the general secretary of Caritas, Paul Pun, considered that “it is not an easy task” to identify the elderly alone and argued that “collaboration” was necessary between the different Government departments, in addition to the need to be aware of the most diverse social contexts.
For example, Jacky Ho said that public libraries and churches were places where social workers could be assigned to meet these elderly people. They also pointed out that the Government should create a home care services team, in addition to implementing policies to encourage professionals to dedicate themselves to this area.
 
The evolution of the Cooperation Zone
At the beginning of the year, in a meeting in Beijing with the Secretary for Administration and Justice of the Macao SAR, André Cheong, the director of the Hong Kong and Macau Work Office of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China and the Hong Kong and Macau Affairs Office of the State Council, Xia Baolong, argued that Macau should launch legal measures and invest “more resources” to promote the development of the Deep Cooperation Zone.
At the meeting, Xia Baolong said he hopes that the new Government of the Macao SAR “will continue to preserve the fundamental principles, be innovative and entrepreneurial, as well as understand, in depth, and put into practice, in an effective way, the spirit enshrined in the important speeches and instructions of President Xi Jinping, in order to create a new development situation for Macau”.
According to André Cheong's office, the visit "aimed at seeking the support of relevant ministries and commissions of the Central Government and listening to their guiding opinions, focusing on implementing the spirit enshrined in the important speeches given by President Xi Jinping during his visit to Macau and Hengqin, as well as accelerating the development of the Deep Cooperation Zone".
In February, the Secretary for Economy and Finance announced that Macau would allocate more financial resources to the development of the Deep Cooperation Zone in Hengqin, in addition to strengthening human resources. The message was transmitted to Xia Baolong, in a meeting that took place in the Cooperation Zone.
Tai Kin Ip afirmou igualmente que a tutela que dirige continuaria “a aperfeiçoar os trabalhos relativos à definição de medidas políticas sobre o desenvolvimento industrial” e a “optimizar o ambiente de negócios”, ao mesmo tempo que se iria empenhar na “captação de investimento e na prestação de serviços empresariais”. O “empenho total” de Macau na construção da Zona de Cooperação Aprofundada foi reiterado, tendo o governante sublinhado que a RAEM “manterá sempre em mente o objectivo inicial do desenvolvimento de Hengqin”.
O Instituto de Promoção do Comércio e do Investimento (IPIM) disse nesse mês que ajudou três empresas de capitais portugueses a estabelecer negócios em Hengqin, as quais estavam a operar em “áreas como a consultoria jurídica e a gestão de projectos”. As empresas de Macau com investimento estrangeiro, de Portugal, Alemanha, República Checa e Austrália, representavam cerca de 7% dos pedidos recebidos para registo em Hengqin.
Em Abril, no âmbito das Linhas de Acção Governativa, o Secretário para a Administração e Justiça, André Cheong, anunciou que Macau iria estabelecer um um Centro de Serviços para Países de Língua Portuguesa e Espanhola, na Zona de Cooperação Aprofundada em Hengqin. A ideia é proporcionar às empresas destes países serviços no “âmbito linguístico, jurídico, fiscal, de verificação da observância das normas, de formação, de arbitragem e de mediação”.
Até ao final do primeiro semestre do ano, mais de 28 mil residentes de Macau viviam e trabalhavam em Hengqin, revelou a Direcção dos Serviços de Assuntos Administrativos da Zona de Cooperação Aprofundada. Em termos anuais, os habitantes e trabalhadores da RAEM em Hengqin cresceram mais de 30% e 14%, respectivamente.
On the occasion of the 4th anniversary of the Cooperation Zone, the Hengqin authorities also indicated that, at the end of July, Hengqin had 7,303 companies with Macau capital, reflecting an increase of 57.5% since the creation of that zone. In addition, 306 items have already been defined in terms of the convergence of rules between Hengqin and Macau and reform and innovation. On the other hand, the same organization said that it has already started a preliminary study on the plan for a new Hengqin-Macau border access, and it will be possible to allow entry into Guangdong for vehicles with a single Macau license plate with authorization to circulate in the Cooperation Zone.
A new phase of the health integration process also emerged between Macau and Hengqin, as the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center and the Hengqin Branch of the No. 1 Affiliated Hospital of the Guangzhou University of Medicine inaugurated the “External Consultations of Associated Specialties between Hengqin and Macau” project. The initiative aims to promote the exchange of medical techniques, the training of talents and the innovation of scientific research.
On the other hand, four technological companies from Brazil have completed the procedures to start operations in Macau and Hengqin, more specifically, three will operate in the MSAR, while the fourth will be located in the Deep Cooperation Zone, the authorities announced.
Meanwhile, construction work has also begun on the new campus of the University of Macau, in Hengqin. With the new infrastructure, UM will have capacity for 25,000 students, in addition to several courses being planned in co-supervision with foreign universities. Completion of the work is scheduled for 2029, with a partial opening in 2028.
The Polytechnic University (UPM) and the Tourism University (UTM) each plan to occupy half of the same land in Hengqin, for the construction of their new campuses, which are expected to cost 9.5 billion patacas in total.
The Macau Foundation (FM) financed UM with 1.099 billion renminbi for the construction of the new campus across the border. In addition, it also helped UPM and UTM, in the amount of approximately 1.8 billion renminbis, equivalent to 2.05 billion patacas, intended to obtain land for educational purposes.
 
Slow advances in transport and infrastructure
In the year 2025, the area of ​​transport and infrastructure also saw some progress, although no large-scale project was completed. As of now, almost half of the construction project for the East Line of the Light Rail has been completed, including a kilometer of underwater tunnel between Taipa and the Peninsula, which will have a total length of three thousand meters. The idea is for the line to start operating in 2029.
Furthermore, the Secretary for Transport and Public Works announced that the Government intends to extend the Seac Pai Van Line to the town of Coloane, having promised that he will try to implement the plan as quickly as possible. Raymond Tam even considers the work to be “relatively easy”. The government official also gave details about the other lines proposed in a study on Light Rail development strategies and promised that a public consultation will be launched.
The other lines that the study proposes include the Taipa North Line, which could depart from the ES6 station, in Zone E, passing through Zones D and C of the New Landfills, and also through the Oceano station on the Taipa Line. The Southern Line will be able to connect the Macau border post at Ponte do Delta to the ES5 station in Zona A dos Novos Aterros, passing through NAPE, lot A9 in Nam Van, Sai Van and Barra; while the West Line will start at Doca do Lam Mau and end in Barra.
At the same time, expansion works at Macau International Airport continue at a good pace. After completion of the expansion, scheduled for 2030, the number of parking platforms will be increased from 36 to 56, while the capacity to receive passengers will increase from 10 million to 13 million per year. At the end of the contracts, the useful space of the infrastructure is expected to increase from 177 to 325 hectares.
 
The resolution on “one country, two systems”
In March, at the opening of the National People's Assembly (ANP), the Chinese Prime Minister reiterated the guarantee that the Central Government would support Hong Kong and Macau in economic development and improving the well-being of their populations. Li Qiang presented the Central Government's work report, with the document highlighting the duty of full, precise and unwavering pursuit of the “one country, two systems” guidelines and Hong Kong and Macau governed by their people, with a high degree of autonomy.
Another duty highlighted was based on defending the constitutional order of the SARs defined in the Constitution and Basic Laws, as well as implementing the principles of Hong Kong and Macau being governed by “patriots”. The Macao SAR leader, who was present at the opening of the ANP in Beijing, in turn, promised to transform the spirit of the “Two Sessions” into “concrete actions”.
Days later, the Chinese Vice Prime Minister, Ding Xuexiang, conveyed “three expectations” to Macau members. He said he hoped that the vowels “well convey” the spirit of the “Two Sessions”. Furthermore, he urged them to further support the Executive to govern in accordance with the law, as well as the Chief Executive and his team to “effectively” drive the development of the territory. On the other hand, he also hoped that the ANP deputies would unite Macau society to “carry out work for the stability and prosperity of the Macao SAR”.
At the end of the “Two Sessions”, the Chinese People's Political Consultative Conference (CPPCC) unanimously approved a political resolution that demanded the full, precise and unwavering pursuit of the guidelines “one country, two systems”, “Macau governed by its people”, “Hong Kong governed by its people” and with a high degree of autonomy. Furthermore, according to the resolution, it was necessary to “unswervingly advance the great cause of the reunification of the Fatherland and consolidate and develop the broadest possible united patriotic front.”
Also in Beijing, but already in December, the Macao SAR Chief Executive received yet another vote of confidence from Xi Jinping. “The Central Government fully recognizes the work of Sam Hou Fai and the Macao SAR Government”, said the Chinese President, in a meeting focused on presenting the Government's work in 2025 and the main points of the Government Action Lines for 2026.
Among other praises, Xi also said that Sam led the new Macao SAR Government in “firmly defending the country's security sovereignty, rights and development interests, with an entrepreneurial and pragmatic spirit”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Pereira Coutinho and André Cheong protagonists in legislative year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pereira-coutinho-andre-cheong-protagonistas-em-ano-de-legislativas/</link><description>The elections for the VIII Legislative Assembly brought 15 new faces to the Hemicycle, counting the direct and indirect votes, and the nominated deputies. In direct voting, the “Nova Esperança” list, by José Pereira Coutinho, was the big winner on election night, with more than 43 thousand votes. Among the deputies appointed by the Chief Executive, six made their debut in the role, including André Cheong, whose appointment triggered a series of changes in the Government itself. Wong Sio Chak took over as Secretary for Administration and Justice, leaving the Security portfolio to Chan Tsz King. In the run-up to the elections, 12 candidates from two lists, including Ron Lam, were disqualified due to alleged lack of loyalty to the Macao SAR.
 



































 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
On September 14th, more than 175 thousand people went to the polls to elect, by direct vote, 14 of the representatives of the VIII Legislative Assembly. List 2, “Nova Esperança”, led by José Pereira Coutinho, and list 1, “Associação dos Cidadãos Unidos”, whose list leader was Song Pek Kei, were the big winners on election night, having each secured three seats in the Hemicycle.
Nova Esperança received the most votes, electing Pereira Coutinho, Chan Hao Weng (new deputy) and Che Sai Wang. In the aftermath of the victory, the president of the Public Service Workers' Association described the results as “Nova Esperança's greatest victory”, stressing that, over the years, the list had always gained votes and never lost them. “I think many people were surprised by this result, because we were too”, he confessed at the time.
“It’s a historic landmark.” “As a citizen residing in Macau, with a Portuguese name, having this result is extremely satisfactory”, said Pereira Coutinho, also promising to “continue to fight for the rights of the Macanese and Portuguese community and all other communities in Macau”.
The group linked to the Fujian community re-elected deputies Song Pek Kei and Nick Lei, having also managed to find a place for a third candidate, newcomer Chan Lai Kei. For Song Pek Kei, the results demonstrated recognition from citizens.
This was followed by the “Union for Development”, list 5, which re-elected Ella Lei and Leong Sun Iok, similar to what had happened in the last legislative elections. List 3, “União Promotora para o Progresso”, linked to the Union of Residents' Associations of Macau (“Kaifong”), also managed to elect two deputies, keeping Leong Hong Sai and Ngan Iek Hang in the Hemicycle.
In turn, the results of the “Union of Macau-Guangdong”, list 4, allowed Joey Lao to return to the Legislative Assembly, this time as a deputy elected by direct suffrage and not appointed, alongside newcomer Lee Koi Ian. Reacting to the results, Joey Lao, whose list has connections to the Jiangmen community, left promises for the economy, the well-being of the population and young people.
In last position was the “Aliança de Bom Lar”, list 6, also with two seats in the Hemicycle. The list linked to the Macau General Women's Association managed to elect Wong Kit Cheng and Loi I Weng. After the vote, Wong Kit Cheng said that his re-election reflected “public recognition” of his work.
Initially, 5,987 direct votes were considered “blank” and 7,077 “null”, record values ​​in the history of the Macao SAR. Asked what the reason for the exponential increase in blank votes and invalid votes would be, the president of CAEAL, Seng Ioi Man, refused to comment. “In all data related to elections there are numbers rising or falling, there are many reasons, therefore, CAEAL will not comment”, he stated at the time.
After the final results were counted by the Legislative Assembly Electoral Affairs Commission (CAEAL), Cheong Kuok Chi announced that 24 votes previously considered invalid would be validated. After the recount, “Nova Esperança” ended the elections with 43,367 votes. The “Association of United Citizens” got 29,464 votes, the “Union for Development” 27,435, the “Promoting Union for Progress” 21,750, the “Union of Macau-Guangdong” 21,464 and the “Aliança de Bom Lar” 18,752 votes.
Regarding indirect suffrage, the four seats chosen by the electoral college for the industrial, commercial and financial sectors were already allocated to José Chui Sai Peng and Ip Sio Kai, Si Ka Lon and Kevin Ho, who was making his debut. Iau Teng Pio and newcomers Vong Hou Piu and Wong Chon Kit were chosen by the professional sector. The social services and educational sectors elected Ho Ion Sang, while the cultural and sports sectors chose Angela Leong and Ma Chi Seng.
The two candidate lists for the two seats in the labor sector would end up securing one deputy each. Lam Lon Wai remained, having obtained 484 votes, while Leong Pou U secured the other seat, debuting as deputy, with 578 votes.
 
New maximum number of voters
A total of 175,272 people voted, out of a total of 328,506 voters. At this point, a new maximum was reached, as there had never before been so many voters, as the number of voters was also higher.
The participation rate in the legislative elections was 53.35% in direct voting, an increase of almost 11 percentage points compared to 2021, when the highest abstention rate was recorded in the territory, after the disqualification of more than two dozen candidates by CAEAL. However, this year's voter turnout rate turned out to be the third worst since the creation of the Macao SAR.
In indirect suffrage, 6,645 of the more than 7,500 voters voted, corresponding to a participation rate of 88.12%, slightly higher than four years ago.
 
Secretary appointed to the Hemicycle
In an unprecedented political decision, André Cheong was one of seven deputies appointed by Sam Hou Fai to the VIII Legislative Assembly. For the first time in the history of the Macao SAR, a Secretary left the Government to join the Hemicycle. It was also the second time that a Secretary had left office, since 2006, when the then Secretary for Public Works, Ao Man Long, was arrested as part of a corruption scandal.
Upon a proposal from the Chief Executive, China's State Council appointed Wong Sio Chak, then Secretary for Security, to take charge of Administration and Justice in an equally unprecedented decision, in which a current Secretary assumed another portfolio in the same term. Chan Tsz King, Public Prosecutor, became the new Secretary for Security, eventually being replaced by the judge and president of the Court of Second Instance, Tong Hio Fong.
The remaining deputies nominated by Sam Hou Fai were Lei Wun Kong, Chao Ka Chong, Lam Fat Iam, Wong Ka Lon and Kou Ngon Seng, all debutants, with Kou Kam Fai being the only one renominated. In the first session of the new legislature, André Cheong was also unanimously elected president of the Legislative Assembly.
 
12 candidates disqualified
In the run-up to the elections, 12 candidates were disqualified, from two lists, including former deputy Ron Lam, who, remember, had been elected for the first time in 2021. It was also in that year that, after the first wave of disqualifications for the elections, the Macao SAR recorded the highest abstention rate, at 57.6%.
At stake were the lists “Power of Synergy” and “Strength of Popular Livelihood in Macau”. All candidates on the list headed by Ron Lam, namely Ian Heng Ut, Che I Kei, Sio Ieng Weng, Chan Chon Meng and Cheong Iek Chong were excluded from participating in the elections for the VIII Legislative Assembly.
The other list, which was running for the first time, also saw all of its candidates – Alberto Wong, Leong Sio Iok, Che Meng Lam, Chow Chi Fai, Ngai Ka Fong and Fong Kai Hou – being removed from the race for the Hemicycle. The seventh candidate on the list, Hong Wai I, had already withdrawn from the race.
Before the elections, the Commission for the Defense of State Security (CDSE) alleged that the candidates did not defend the Basic Law or were not loyal to the Macao SAR or the People's Republic of China. In this sense, CAEAL took the decision that “the individuals in question did not [have] the capacity to be candidates”.
Seng Ioi Man stressed at the time that “the opinion issued by the CDSE is binding, and the CAEAL's decision that a candidate does not have the capacity to be a candidate, taken based on the respective opinion, cannot be complained or appealed”.
Furthermore, Seng Ioi Man argued that the decision had been taken “taking into account the facts” and argued that “the authority and expertise” of the Commission should not be doubted, pointing out that the opinions issued “have a clear and sufficient legal basis”. “Data and information relating to their work must remain highly confidential, otherwise there could be risks to national security”, he stressed.
Asked how the population could know how not to violate the law, taking into account that the specific reasons were not explained, and asked to clarify which criteria or criteria motivated the decision, Seng Ioi Man once again mentioned the issue of “confidentiality” of work related to the CDSE. “CAEAL has no further information to provide,” he added.
After the announcement, the CDSE indicated, in a statement, that, when a candidate is excluded for not being patriotic, the remaining members of the list are also considered “not defenders of the Basic Law” or “not faithful to the Macao SAR”.
Shortly after the announcement about the disqualification of 12 candidates, the Macao SAR Government issued a statement demonstrating “strong support” for the CAEAL decision, taken based on the opinion of the CDSE. For the Executive, “it is a correct measure for the full implementation of the fundamental principle ‘Macau governed by patriots’”, read the statement from the Social Communication Office.
It was further said that “defending the Basic Law and being faithful to the Macao SAR of the People's Republic of China are the most fundamental legal duties and political ethics that deputies to the Legislative Assembly must observe”. “Under the constitutional order established in the Constitution of the PRC and the Basic Law, the people who make up the governance structure of the Macao SAR must be those who firmly love the Motherland and Macau”, stressed the Government.
The Liaison Office of the Central Government in the Macao SAR also commented on the decision, supporting it “firmly”, arguing that deputies “must be convinced patriots” and underlining that, according to the laws in force, these decisions “have absolute authority and are indisputable and indisputable”.
In a post on his Facebook page, Ron Lam thanked him for the “concern” and said he had not received any notification. “I only found out about the information when I saw the news broadcast live”, he stated, saying he was “calm” and had a “clear conscience”.
"My original intention regarding Macau will not change. I believe that the sun always comes after the wind and rain", added the then deputy, apologizing for not being able to continue serving the population. The deputy also thanked the partners who accompanied him and the supporters.
Similarly, Alberto Wong also appealed to Facebook, stating that he had not been notified about the decision. "My position of loving the country and loving Macau will not change. I will be faithful to the Macao SAR as in the beginning", he promised, apologizing to his supporters.
 
Vote appeal letters
In anticipation of the elections, remember, Sam Hou Fai had sent letters to public officials, saying that voting was a way of demonstrating “loyalty to the Macao SAR”. Entitled “letter to all workers in public services and entities”, the letter, which arrived from the Office of the Chief Executive, also pointed out that voting was a right, but also a duty. In this sense, the population should “actively” participate in the elections, especially public servants, appealed to the leader of the Macao SAR.
The letter stated that, “as part of the Macao SAR government team, workers in public services and entities must actively respond to CAEAL's call, diligently fulfill their duty to vote and encourage their family and friends to vote”.
The Macao SAR leader also asked public services to be flexible so that workers who were on duty could vote. As for employees who were not working that day, Sam Hou Fai left a message: “The remaining employees of public services and entities must plan in advance and actively participate on election day, going to the assigned polling station to vote in order to jointly elect representatives in the Macao SAR legislative body and offer their contribution to the stable and lasting implementation of the ‘one country, two systems’ principle”.
Furthermore, Sam Hou Fai met, even before the legislative elections, with the service directors and holders of senior positions, again calling for a vote. On that occasion, he argued that “leaders at management level must assume a liaison role between superiors and subordinates”, and must promote “fulfillment of accountability”.
Asked if he was satisfied with the participation rate and what he considered the main factor that led people to vote more strongly, Seng Ioi Man did not want to answer, saying only that it was necessary to do “some studies, some analyses”.
The Hong Kong and Macau Affairs Office of the State Council of China considered that the elections for the Legislative Assembly “fully demonstrated the healthy, positive and vibrant atmosphere of a high-quality democracy”. For the organization, the election marked “another milestone in the full implementation of the principle of ‘Macau governed by patriots’ by the Macao SAR and in the promotion of high-quality democracy in line with the real conditions in Macau”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau’s “cultural treasure” blew out 20 candles</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/tesouro-cultural-de-macau-soprou-20-velas/</link><description>This year marked the 20th anniversary of the inclusion of the Historic Center of Macau on the UNESCO World Heritage List. In order to mark the anniversary, the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper interviewed several relevant personalities in the sector, to take stock of the work and results achieved over the last 20 years. Leong Wei Man, president of the Cultural Institute, highlighted the social impact that the registration had on the population of Macau. Several local architects and urban planners pointed to the UNESCO classification as a turning point for the region, although some controversial cases still persist. It was also in 2025 that the Macao SAR officially included the Portuguese Folk Dance and the Making of Pastel de Nata on the Intangible Heritage List



































PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
On July 15th, the Macao SAR celebrated the 20th anniversary of the Historic Center's inscription on the UNESCO World Heritage List. Taking stock of the last two decades, Leong Wai Man told TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper that the inclusion of the Historic Center “reinforced the confidence and cultural pride of residents” and that the public began “to value even more the exploration and protection of their history and culture”.
In the opinion of the president of the Cultural Institute (IC), the Historic Center “continues to be the main environment that encompasses daily life, the economy and production, and the festivities and customs of residents”, having been mutually integrated with modern society throughout the city's development.
The continuous promotion of revitalization and the fact that most of the buildings, squares and squares maintain their original functions allow the Historic Center to remain “under the protection and sharing among the entire society” and radiate “a stronger dynamic and vitality”, pointed out the person in charge. On the other hand, Leong also described integrating safeguarding work into residents' daily lives as an “important and challenging” responsibility.
In response to this newspaper, to questions sent to the Office of the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, the IC explained that the inscription of the Historic Center on the World Heritage List “not only allowed Macau to gain its first international cultural visiting card, but also demonstrated to the world its exceptional position and contribution to cultural exchange between China and the West, increasing its confidence and cultural pride”.
Highlighting the “great progress” recorded in the last 20 years, the organization described the Historic Center as “a precious cultural treasure of humanity, whose extraordinary value has been recognized worldwide”.
“Macau’s unique multicultural identity is evidenced by the dynamic presence, side by side in the city, of Western and Chinese architectural heritage, and the same dynamics can often be found in the design of individual buildings, where Chinese-style elements also appear in Western-style buildings and vice versa, such as, for example, Chinese characters integrated into the decorative elements of the baroque facade of the Ruins of São Paulo”, he stressed.
With regard to public education, an aspect that is “an important part of the work to preserve World Heritage”, the president of the IC asserted that the organization has always given importance to the dissemination and promotion of World Heritage.
As he recalled, dissemination actions cover not only festivals, workshops, television broadcasting, publications and studies and community initiatives, for the general public, but also educational activities aimed at different age groups and different professional groups.
In this field, Leong Wai Man highlighted the training of local restoration talents, through cooperation with the Labor Affairs Bureau and local professional associations, within the scope of traditional Lingnan architecture. Furthermore, he highlighted the inauguration of the Cultural Heritage Preservation and Transmission Center of the Macau Palace Museum, last year, which also has educational and promotional functions.
 
Architects and urban planners unanimous on the importance of the Historic Center
Interviewed by this newspaper, architect Maria José de Freitas stated that the Center's inclusion on the UNESCO list gave Macau “a much more evident international projection”. “From then on, there was a commitment, from both the local Government and the Central Government, to maintain and preserve this heritage, because it is a heritage that belongs to everyone, it belongs to humanity”, he added.
Carlos Marreiros, in turn, said that the classification “contributed, on its scale, to tourist-cultural development” and “the value of collective memories”, which, in his opinion, help to “construct, substantiate and shape” Macau’s “own identity”.
On the other hand, the architect hopes to one day be able to see an “ambitious” museum of architecture and heritage, which would have “the pretext and main objective of Macau’s heritage”.
Urban planner Lam Iek Chit explained that both older generations and young people began to “attribute greater importance to Macau’s cultural heritage” since inscription. “Residents have come to realize that Macau is not just a small city, a fishing village or a fantastic tourist destination with resorts.”
"We have a history with a very profound influence. I think that the classification of the Historic Center as a World Heritage Site has a great influence, especially on young people, because it led them to create cultural confidence", he asserted.
Francisco Vizeu Pinheiro, in turn, highlighted the great benefits that occurred after 2005, with more protected buildings and more investments made by the Government. “We had more protected buildings, the Government also spent more money, because as there are more buildings there is more space, which means greater protection”. The architect said that the population of Macau itself feels “proud to have this heritage”, just like China “for having a rich heritage that ranges from churches, fortresses, libraries”.
Francisco Ricarte described the moment of inscription as “a decisive stage in the affirmation of Macau’s identity and its uniqueness in the regional and national context”. “In these 20 years, we have seen a clear assumption of the unique value of the city”, he observed, “in the political discourse and in the urban practice of the authorities”.
 
Pending controversial cases
In relation to the most controversial processes, such as those involving the Calçada do Gaio building and some buildings on Avenida do Doutor Rodrigo Rodrigues, which raised questions in relation to Farol da Guia, one of the classified monuments, Maria José de Freitas lamented the existence of “several cases”, noting that “they are specific situations, which were later somehow corrected”.
The architect recalled that, between 2002 and 2005, “the situation was still not very clear” and “in transition areas around the classified part, very tall buildings appeared, a lot was distorted, particularly in the NAPE area and the Praia Grande Bay closure”.
“Many buildings appeared at that time and, in some way, came to stifle the Historic Center, which is, so to speak, at the heart of the Peninsula”, he observed, a situation that was later “stopped”, with large complexes appearing in COTAI, “allowing the Historic Center to breathe where it could still breathe”.
“The visual corridor is an entire visual alignment that allows a monument to be seen from the surroundings, from the monument to the outside and from the outside to the inside, and this is what UNESCO appreciates”, explained the architect.
Lam Iek Chit, in turn, criticized the Government's “relatively slow” reaction to these cases. “20 years have passed, however, the Government's level of sensitivity to issues related to the safeguarding of World Heritage is still insufficient”, lamented the urban planner, referring to the safeguarding of the Guia Lighthouse, in 2008, the tall building on Calçada do Gaio and the controversy over the construction of a viaduct between Zones A and B of the New Landfills.
“There continue to be problems related to the landscapes around the Guia Lighthouse”. “So much time has passed and we have launched so many policies, but government services still have such a low level of sensitivity to the protection of landscapes adjacent to heritage sites,” Lam reiterated.
The urban planner suggested that the Government first clarify the limits imposed by current laws on planning and then move on to the projects, “instead of doing it first and only checking the requirements later and finding excuses to cover up mistakes”.
Furthermore, Lam Iek Chit argued that “it is very important to allow more citizens effective channels through which they can participate in the decision-making process regarding policies and measures for the protection of cultural heritage”. The Government should “define the visual corridors in more detail, including the concrete scope of the corridors and their relationship with each piece of land and each building next door, because this has a great impact”.
On the same topic, Francisco Vizeu Pinheiro highlighted that “Macau's problem is the buildings that are walls, which do not allow visual corridors, while the building, if expressed in height, leaves space for visual corridors to see the heritage, the mountain, the landscape”.
The architect continued, stressing that “limiting the height, but having a building that forms a wall, is a bit artificial, therefore, the most important thing is to create these visual corridors, which allow the heritage to be seen, even if the building has to be compromised at a higher height”.
For the future, Vizeu Pinheiro defended the existence of specialists for the maintenance of the Historic Center, since “things wear out over time, tiles are breaking, wooden structures need renovation”. “We really need experts who know how to work with stone and we need to bring someone from Portugal to do these things”, he concluded.
 
Portuguese manifestations in Intangible Cultural Heritage
This year, the Macao SAR Government included the 12 events proposed by the IC on the Intangible Heritage List, with emphasis on Portuguese Folk Dance and the Making of Pastel de Nata. The remaining manifestations also included the Dragon and Lion Dances and the Belief and Customs of Tou Tei. According to the IC, the 12 proposals met “around 70% or more agreement” in the public consultation, demonstrating broad social support.
“Portuguese folk dance has continuously acquired Macau characteristics, and currently involves artists from the Portuguese, Macanese and Chinese communities, among others”, explained the IC. For the organization, Portuguese dance “reflects the value of Macau's multiculturalism, as well as the integration and friendship between Chinese and Portuguese cultures, being a relevant cultural manifestation of the territory's typical culture”.
Regarding the making of Pastel de Nata, the IC recalled the “great success” of a bakery in Coloane that “started selling its own interpretation of characteristic egg tarts, based on the Portuguese recipe” and “with some influences from cooking techniques from Hong Kong and Macau.
“Nowadays, custard tarts have not only evolved to include new flavors, but have also led to the creation of other types of sweets”, with “characteristics specific to Macau” and a “deep cultural significance”, argued the organization.
Leong Wai Man highlighted that Portuguese-style intangible cultural heritage items are also an important part of Macau's World Heritage Site. The IC president recalled the protection work under the Cultural Heritage Safeguarding Law that the Government carried out over the last two decades.
Among the 70 local items included in the Inventory of Intangible Cultural Heritage are multiple festivities, cultures and customs of the Macanese community, such as the Theater in Patuá, Macanese Gastronomy, the Manufacturing and Painting of Portuguese Tiles, Portuguese Folk Dance, the Festa de São Martinho and Arraial de São João.
The president of the organization assured that “the IC has continuously monitored and recorded the protection situation of the respective items, and provides support in various aspects to the inheritance and dissemination of these items”. As he recalled, these efforts resulted in the inclusion of the Theater in Patuá and Macanese Gastronomy in the Representative List of National Intangible Cultural Heritage, promoting the inheritance and continuity of these items in society.
With regard to the Portuguese-speaking world, the official stressed that local authorities have deepened cultural ties between Macau and Portuguese-speaking Countries (PLP) and actively played the role of Macau's platform as a “Center for Cultural Exchange between China and the PLP”, giving the example of the Arts and Culture Festival between China and the PLP and the Lusophony Festival.
“The more than 400 years of unique history of exchange with foreign countries have resulted in the harmonious social and cultural connotation of Macau that exists today, established the development position as ‘A Base of Exchange and Cooperation for the Promotion of Multicultural Coexistence, with a Predominance of Chinese Culture’ and granted Macau an important historical mission in the ‘exchange and mutual learning between Chinese and Western civilizations’”, highlighted Leong Wai Man.
Looking to the future, the IC leader said she hopes that, “in the new phase”, Macau will make “good use of its own institutional advantages of ‘one country, two systems’”, reinforce “the two-way role of connectivity both with the Mainland and the rest of the world and the deep basis of humanistic exchange with the PLP”.
Highlighting Macau's role on the international scene, in terms of promoting “exchange and mutual learning between international civilizations”, the official argued that the Macao SAR should “further strengthen the fundamental role of the Historic Center of Macau in promoting exchange and mutual learning between international civilizations”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Storm signals broke annual record</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sinais-de-tempestade-bateram-recorde-anual/</link><description>2025 was a historic year in the climate field, with 14 storms hitting the territory, which set a new annual record for warnings since records began in 1968. Furthermore, 2025 was the only year in which Macau raised two storm signals, one of which was due to the super-typhoon “Ragasa”, in September. The first tropical storm signal was issued on June 11th and the last one was canceled on November 11th. In total, signal 8 was raised four times this year






























On the 11th of June, the passage of Typhoon “Wutip” led the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) to raise the first sign of a tropical storm in Macau in 2025. The warning signals were in force for five days, being canceled only on the afternoon of the 15th of June, but the Macao SAR ended up not being much affected, except for the suspension of classes in children's, primary and special education.
A few days later, on June 25th, the SMG issued tropical storm signal number 1 at 4:30 pm due to the influence of a tropical depression. The signal did not go up to nº3, but remained in force for 23 and a half hours.
Between the 4th and 6th of July, signal 1 was raised due to typhoon “Danas”, which left at least two dead and 500 injured in Taiwan.
On July 20th, typhoon “Wipha” forced the authorities to raise, at 12:30 pm, signal 10, the highest, something that had not happened for two years. According to data analyzed by the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper, the last signals 9 and 10 had been issued on the 1st and 2nd of September 2023, respectively, with the passage of typhoon “Saola”. On the other hand, since October 5, 2024, signal 8 had not been raised, at that time due to the “Yagi” storm.
“Wipha” caused five minor injuries and forced 139 people to resort to shelter centers. The authorities recorded 163 incidents, involving 98 cases of “removal of plaster, plaster, window, awning or other objects at risk of falling/knocking down” and 54 cases of “removing a building/lamp/tree at risk of falling/knocking down”.
As “Wipha” approached, authorities suspended public transport and closed public parking lots and border posts connecting the territory and Zhuhai.
Maritime connections were suspended and, with the raising of signal 9, the only connection between the Peninsula and Taipa – the lower deck of the Sai Van Bridge – was also closed. Thus, the four bridges connecting the two sides became impassable. Hundreds of flights were canceled and some people were stranded in the Macao SAR.
Despite the storm, the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Department kept the casinos open, justifying it with the need to “prevent potential risks arising from closure”.
Typhoon “Wipha” signal 10 became the earliest signal issued since there are records, in 1968. It was the fifth tropical cyclone since 2017 to trigger the highest tropical storm signal, according to the SMG.
In August, Macau was challenged by the tropical cyclone “Podul”, which led the city to experience intense showers on the afternoon of August 14th, as well as serious flooding in low-lying areas. Several streets were closed due to flooding. The SMGs also ended up emitting the black signal of intense rain for three hours and 48 minutes. This black signal was the longest since the implementation of the three-level Heavy Rain Signal System in Macau in September 2020.
Three days later, due to the influence of a low pressure area, tropical storm signal 3 was in effect for 11 hours, from noon.
Between the 23rd and 24th of the same month, typhoon “Kajiki”, which affected more than 100 thousand people on the island of Hainan, caused signal 1 to be raised in Macau over the course of 36 hours.
Still in August, a storm signal was issued at 7:00 pm on the 28th, which lasted until 4:30 pm on the 29th, due to a tropical depression.
September 2025 would become a landmark month in Macau, due to a century-old super typhoon. But, before that, the passage of cyclone “Tapah”, just 110 kilometers from Macau, forced the authorities to raise sign 8 for 18 hours, between the 7th and 8th of September. It was the 9th storm to affect Macau in 2025, something that had not happened since 1993, according to the SMG.
During the passage of “Tapah”, the Civil Protection Operations Center (COPC) recorded dozens of incidents and four injuries, as well as “light floods” in Taipa and the Porto Interior area. Classes were suspended and public services were closed.
This time, the Chief Executive, in a working meeting at the COPC, stated that, “due to the successive passage of tropical cyclones through Macau in recent months, the Civil Protection structure maintained its alert continuously and carried out numerous preparatory work for immediate reaction”. As he assured, “with the continuous improvement of the Civil Protection mechanism and installations against wind and floods, the accumulation of experience of services and institutions” allowed “maintaining a high level of alert”.
Another striking scenario during the passage of this tropical cyclone is that, for the first time, the circulation of vehicles on the Macau Bridge under signal 8 was tested. For this operation, the Public Works Services, DSAT and SMG deployed multiple vehicles and analysis technicians.
The tropical system “Mitag” led the authorities to raise signal 3, on the 19th and 20th of September, and to suspend classes. The “Mitag” would end up leaving Macau without causing any damage.
 
“Ragasa” affected casinos, supermarkets and…fish
On September 21, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) issued a statement assuring the public that the supply of fresh food was “sufficient” before the arrival of super typhoon “Ragasa”. On the 22nd, the supply of fresh food such as vegetables, fruits, meat, poultry and eggs increased by 50%, according to the IAM. Even so, the following day, in some supermarkets, there were no bottles of water and other products such as adhesive tape, as this newspaper found.
At 3 pm on the 22nd, signal 1 was raised. Under the impact of “Ragasa”, Macau entered a state of immediate prevention at 1pm on the 23rd. Two hours later, signal 8 was issued, which would be replaced by 9 at 4am on the 24th and 10 at 5:30am. All storm signals ended up being canceled at 6:00 am on the 25th.
The super-typhoon brought hurricane-force winds to the territory, knocking down trees, lamps, windows and other objects. Intense rains were also felt, and, due to the “storm surge”, the lower areas of the city were flooded, with the water height exceeding 1.5 meters. As a result, several streets were closed and left without electricity.
Signal 10 was raised for 10 and a half hours. The data also shows that 2025 was the only year, since 1968, in which Macau raised two storm signals.
With this super typhoon, there were eight injuries, 16 thousand houses and stores were affected by power cuts, 138 cases of falling windows and plaster, 62 cases of falling trees, lamps and others, as well as 145 flights cancelled, delayed and changed. This storm was considered the strongest of 2025 worldwide. In Hong Kong, more than six dozen people were injured, while at least 27 died in Taiwan and the Philippines.
Casinos suspended operations for 33 hours. The reopening of gaming establishments was authorized by the Chief Executive from 2:00 am on the 25th.
Several videos circulating on social media showed, for example, floods in the Porto Interior area, as well as in Coloane, where a large amount of rubbish was visible being washed away. Meanwhile, the rise in water levels in the low-lying areas of the city, which reached nearly two meters in height, led to the appearance of dozens of fish in the flooded areas, probably coming from aquariums in fishmongers or restaurants in the area.
After the first amateur photographs and videos appeared, published on social media, with a fish jumping in one of the arteries of Porto Interior, several people took to the streets, still with the 10 sign up, and sought their luck in an authentic open-air “market”. The situation, somewhat ridiculous, recorded not far from the Patane Market, even led the COPC to appeal to citizens and tourists to remain on alert and remain in closed and safe areas.
On September 25th, Macau began to return to normality, with public transport and education services resuming activity, with some exceptions, while cleaning work continued.
According to SMG, “Ragasa” set a number of records. It was the first time that the second signal 10 was emitted in a year, since 1968, and the signal was in effect for 10 hours and 30 minutes, the longest period recorded. Additionally, during the period that signal 10 was in effect, the duration of wind speeds that reached or exceeded signal 8 extended to 15 hours.
The insurance sector received more than 50 claims for compensation due to damage caused by “Ragasa”, including 39 relating to property insurance. Of these, four insurance policies are against major disasters for small and medium-sized companies (SMEs). Requests were submitted mainly by store owners in low-lying areas of the city.
In general, the Government made a positive assessment of the operations of different organizations, during prevention and cleaning work, in connection with the passage of this super typhoon. At least around 700 commercial establishments suffered losses due to “Ragasa”, but the sector recovered “relatively quickly”, in part due to “good preparation” for the storm, considered the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip.
 
Macau Bridge can now operate under signal 8
In October, the Macau Bridge operated for the first time under storm signal 8. In the early hours of October 5, this infrastructure, inaugurated in the same month of 2024, remained open during signal 8, with authorized vehicles and passenger cars able to circulate, during the passage of typhoon “Matmo”, the 12th storm to hit the Macao SAR in 2025.
According to historical data, signal 8 was emitted on four occasions in the same year for the fourth time. This had only occurred in 1993, 2008 and 2022.
In view of the passage of “Matmo”, signal 1 was issued at 11pm on October 3rd. Later, signal 8 remained in force for 11 hours, from 2:00 am until 1:00 pm on the 5th. At 9:00 pm on the same day, all signals were cancelled.
This time, the COPC recorded one minor injury and 16 incidents. The emergency reception centers received nine users. Meanwhile, the suspension of transport services led to large numbers of people traveling to the taxi zones at the Portas do Cerco border and the Hengqin Border Post, resulting in waiting times of more than an hour.
Still in the same month, due to the approach of “Fengshen”, which intensified into a severe tropical cyclone and entered a 500 km radius of Macau, signal 3 was raised at 7pm on 20 October, which ended up lasting 22 hours.
Due to the influence of “Fengshen”, the SMG issued the 13th storm signal in 2025, which set a new record for the highest number of warnings in a single year since records began in the territory. The previous record was 12 warnings, in 1974. But the updating of the record did not end, as a month later Macau raised the 14th signal of the year, following typhoon “Fung-wong”. It was also the fifth time in history that signal 3 was issued before 1.
A month later, the territory fell asleep on November 10th under signal 1, raised at 2 pm due to typhoon “Fung-wong”. After 31 hours, the alert was cancelled.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>National Games and NBA marked the sports calendar</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jogos-nacionais-nba-marcaram-calendario-desportivo/</link><description>The holding of the National Games in Macau and the presence of two NBA teams for pre-season challenges were the big news on the MSAR's sporting calendar in 2025. The event that brings together all the country's provinces brought to the territory the great Chinese table tennis stars and four other sports. As for the NBA, the Galaxy Arena was filled to see the “duels” between the Brooklyn Nets and Phoenix Suns

VÍTOR REBELO
 
Throughout 2025, Macau intensified its preparations to organize part of the National Games of the People's Republic of China, bearing the responsibility of hosting five sports, namely table tennis, amateur karate, 3×3 basketball, U18 basketball and women's volleyball.
With regard to results, highlights include five medals in karate, three gold and two bronze at the National Games, and a total of 145 trips to the podium, including 34 first places, at the National Games for People with Disabilities and the National Special Olympics Games.
In his speech at the end of the competition, Sam Hou Fai said that Macau “has accumulated invaluable experience in organizing sporting events and achieved its best results since joining the National Games”, representing a “reason of honor and pride for the territory”.
An unprecedented weekend in October, with two pre-season games of the NBA, the main basketball league in the USA, sold out the Venetian Arena, where the teams of the Brooklyn Nets and the Phoenix Suns faced each other. The matches marked the official return of the competition to China, which had not hosted competition games since 2019.
In the first meeting, the Nets won 132-127, after extra time, while in the next day's challenge, the Suns, from Arizona, won 111-109.
Table tennis was another highlight of the year, with two prestigious tournaments featuring the top players in the international rankings. The ITTF World Cup took place in April at the Galaxy Arena and was won by Brazilian Hugo Calderano, in the men's singles category. In women, the triumph went to Sun Yingsha, from China (PRC).
At the WTT Tournament in September, PRC representatives confirmed their credentials, with titles belonging to Wang Chiqin and Sun Yingsha.
 
Young French people win in GPM single-seaters
The Macau Grand Prix (GPM) reached its 72nd edition, marked by the holding of three FIA ​​World Cups, namely GT, Regional Formula (FR) and Formula 4 (F4), which was categorized for the first time.
The two monologue competitions were highlighted, with the FR winning the young 18-year-old Frenchman, Théophille Nael, ahead of the Spaniard Mari Boya. In Formula 4, the fastest would be Frenchman Jules Roussel.
In the FIA ​​GT, the Italian Antonio Fuoco had no rival and was in front from start to finish, while in the TCR the season's world champion title went to another driver from France, Yann Ehrlacher.
On two wheels, riders registered this year in the Motorcycle Grand Prix were able to enjoy the track, without any interruption. Victory for Englishman Davey Todd.
In the so-called GPM support events, the focus is on the Roadsport Challenge Cup, a rivalry between drivers from Macau and Hong Kong, which was decided at the secretariat. The official result, which awarded the victory to Leung Tsz Wa, from the HKSAR, was released hours after the end of the race, informing that the drivers who had crossed the finish line in the first three places, Lou Cheok In (Toyota), Jerónimo Badaraco (Toyota) and Leong Keng Hei (Subaru), as well as four other competitors, suffered a 30-second penalty for having overtaken when the “safety car” was still on the track. Leung Tsz Wa, who had been fourth to see the checkered flag, was declared the winner, ahead of compatriot Adrian Chung and Tsang Pak Yin from Macau, all in Toyota.
Also in motor sports, Macau hosted the final races of the Asian karting championships, in December, as part of the International Grand Prix. 330 pilots from 28 countries or regions participated.
In the first week, the highlight was the triumph, in Mini Rok, of the Hong Kong driver, Alexander Kwong, while in juniors, the fastest on the track was the North American Bruno Fu. In the senior final, victory went to Enoch Mi Hei, from Continente.
In the second week, the IAME finals took place. In particular, the victory of Thai Toby Brian Gale, just 14 years old, in the senior category. Australian Kip Samuel Foster won the Masters.
The year of karts also marked the presence of a driver from Macau in the FIA ​​Karting Arrive &amp; Drive World Cup, held in November in Malaysia. Chung Iam Iop, just 14 years old, came 19th in the Group B final.
 
Kenyans in focus in athletics and German more accurate in golf
In road athletics, Victor Kipchirchir, from Kenya, won the International Marathon and set a new course record, with a time of 2.09.27.
Rwandan John Hakizimana finished in second place, with 2.09.01, also an excellent time, which is the second best time ever in the Macau Marathon. In third place was the Ethiopian Barecha Tolosa Geleto.
In the women's sector, absolute dominance belonged to Ethiopia, with Mastewal Birhanu Senay claiming the triumph, ahead of compatriots Selam Fente Gebre and Kolole Mekashu Tefera.
In the Half Marathon, the titles went to Ndungu Njenga, in the men's sector, and Lucy Ndambuki, in the women's sector, both from Kenya. In the Mini, of around 4.5 km, Rosa Mota, 66 years old, Olympic champion of the Marathon at the Seoul Games, in South Korea, in 1998, was second in the absolute classification, 54 seconds behind the winner Kin I Chao, from Macau. In the men's sector, the triumph also belonged to local athlete Chi Lok Hong.
This year's edition of the Golf Open, held at the “Macau Golf &amp; Country Club”, in Coloane, was only decided through a play-off, with the triumph belonging to the German Dominic Foos, who beat the Taiwanese Wang Wei-Hsuan in a tiebreaker. The two players, who were outside the favorites, finished the fourth and final round of the tournament with a draw of 263 strokes.
 
China dominates dragon boats
The nautical disciplines had three competitions throughout 2025: Sailboat Regatta, Dragon Boats and Motosurf World Championship.
The sailboats took place in January in the waters in front of the Science Center, with the participation of 270 sailors from 22 countries or regions. The boats from “Canados Sailing Team” (Germany), “Muwu BBQ” (China) and “Tea Yacht Racing of Thailand” (Thailand) became champions, respectively in the Beneteau First 40.7 Macau Cup, the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau (IRC) Great Bay Cup Regatta and the Hobie 16 International Invitational Catamaran Regatta.
In the Dragon Boat races, which took place in June on Lake Nam Van, the Chinese rowers from the “Nanhai Jiujiang” team once again dominated, winning both men and women.
Motorsurfing was at Hac Sá, with the final round of the World Championship, where Czech Matyas Novotny repeated the title in the main Elite category, achieved in the previous edition. 80 motorbikesurfers from 19 countries or regions participated.
Finally football, a modality in which Must IPO revalidated the title in the Elite League, after losing, until the last round, with Shao Jiang. In the seven-a-side (Ball) variant, the first placed team was Kang San Tai Heng, who in the final defeated Ching Fung 3-0.
The year was marked by the departure, during the month of December, of main coach Kenneth Kwok, who decided not to renew the contract that linked him, for a year, to the Macau Football Association.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Music and fireworks at COTAI highlighted in the “New Year’s Eve” festivities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/musica-fogo-de-artificio-cotai-em-destaque-nas-festas-reveillon/</link><description>Sands is once again organizing a special New Year celebration program, with outdoor music at “Le Jardin” and a fireworks show. Tonight's “New Year's Eve” will also be celebrated in other places in the city and islands, with a highlight being a concert at Praça do Lago Sai Van, with the presence of Hong Kong vocalist Panther Chan and the rock band Dear Jane. Several hotels and bars in the territory organize special dinners to say goodbye to 2025 and “countdowns” to welcome 2026
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The welcome to 2026 will be marked in celebrations to be held in various locations around the city and islands, with emphasis on the fireworks show that, at midnight tonight, will light up the sky next to the replica of the Eiffel Tower at the Parisian. Before, at 9:30 pm, Sands presents the “New Year's Eve Countdown Extravaganza”, through an open-air party at “Le Jardin”, where local bands Penthaus and Blue Note will perform, as well as a DJ.
According to a statement from the tourism and leisure company, the countdown begins at 11:55 pm, with the Parisian tower “serving as a screen for a sensational sound and light show”, followed by an eight-minute pyrotechnic display in 360 degrees. The fireworks will start from several iconic locations across Sands China's developments, including the Venetian, Parisian and Londoner, “ensuring a memorable celebration for all participants”, underlines Sands.
Events at COTAI will result in special traffic measures, with road access limited from 10pm to 11pm and roads closed from 11pm to 1am. Transport services and parking arrangements will also be adjusted.
Meanwhile, the Cultural Institute (IC) organizes “New Year’s Eve” parties in two spaces. At Sai Van Lake Square, between 22:00 and 00:10, there will be performances by Hong Kong vocalists Panther Chan and Karen Tong, and the popular rock band Dear Jane, together with several singers and bands from Macau. The local cast will be Soler, Filipe Tou, KC Ao Ieong, winifai, Jenny, thetiredeyes and Initial B, who will “alternate to present a diverse range of music to celebrate a dazzling New Year's Eve”, says the IC, informing that there will be no fireworks.
The concert stage floor will feature an electronic screen combined with lighting and visual effects, providing an entirely new visual experience. “The entire performance will be presented in a theatrical format adapted to each session, which conveys, through narratives, the wishes for the coming year and reflects the exciting facets of the city”, highlights the organization.
According to IC vice-president, Cheang Kai Meng, the concert is expected to be attended by around 10 thousand spectators. The show counts, in addition to the IC, with the organization of the game's six concessionaires and the support of the Directorate of Tourism Services, Institute for Municipal Affairs and TDM – Macau Television.
The IC warned the public interested in attending the concert that it will be strictly prohibited to enter the concert with large items, glass, plastic or thermal bottles, canned goods, compressed gases or flammable substances, any offensive or dangerous items, long umbrellas, selfie sticks, luminous signs or posters that exceed the permitted dimensions.
 
Multicultural integration at Casas da Taipa
Casas da Taipa will also be the stage for celebrations marking the departure of 2025 and the entry into 2026, in a celebration dedicated to the theme of multicultural integration. The stage performances will feature local artists, namely FIDA, Tuna Macaense, Bossa Eva and João Gomes &amp; Band, culminating with a show by Karen Tong, who will perform a series of classic songs.
Furthermore, “to showcase the city’s diverse charm,” the event will include various modern and traditional music and dance performances by Victor Kumar and the Bollywood Dreams Group, Macau Bisdak Association Filipino dance groups and Macau Burmese and Vietnamese dance, as well as magic performances by magician Jason Fong.
Between 8:30 pm and 11:30 pm, in the same space, cultural exhibitors from the local communities of the Philippines, India, Myanmar and Vietnam will come into operation, promoting their cultures through traditional costumes, tourist information, snacks and drinks typical of their respective countries, “highlighting the Macau lifestyle characterized by the harmonious coexistence and integration of different cultures and peoples”, highlights the IC note. Entry is free to both events.
Lovers of “revelry” will also have other options for New Year's Eve, as several hotels and bars in the Peninsula, Taipa and Coloane offer programs consisting of special dinners and “countdown” parties.
Frites Macau, a Belgian brewery located in the Grande Lisboa Palace, organizes a masquerade ball, between 9pm and 1am. In the announcement of the event, it is said that “a night of mystery and charm, where elegant masks shine over chandeliers and emotional melodies, take you gracefully to 2026”. The bar will have live music performed by Mihi Matshingana and the Frites House Band. At a price of 375 patacas per person, revelers will have three hours of all-you-can-eat drinks, as well as savor gourmet delicacies.
Also the Roadhouse Macau, located on Broadway Food Street, known for being a meeting point with themes of rock 'n' roll, blues, motorcycles and sports, offers an extended night of festivities, from 9:30 pm until five in the morning, with no minimum consumption required. In terms of program, the bar presents “outdoor Rock Band” and “indoor DJ performance.” There are discounts on food and drinks.
 
In hotels there is “cabaret” and live bands
In terms of hotels, the Artyzen Grand Lapa will leave the “old year” behind and enter 2026 with a celebration that will last from 9pm until the early hours of the morning, including a live DJ performance. The ticket price is 150 patacas for adults and 100 for children.
At Sofitel, between 6pm and 10pm, the proposal is at dinner level, with a five-course menu at the Privé restaurant, priced at 888 patacas per person, and an international food buffet at Mistral for 488 patacas, half of which is for children between 4 and 12 years old.
In Coloane, at the Grand Coloane Resort, the party will have live music and will take place in the Panorama Lounge, starting at 10:30 pm. The price for adults is 298 patacas, while children will pay 148. Drinks are unlimited.
The Ritz Carlton Bar and Lounge, at Galaxy Macau, also joins the New Year's Eve party, presenting a French cabaret show with live music, while the Red House, at the Ascott hotel, offers a night of music from 9:30 pm, with a performance by the resident band, DJ and Chinese, English and Filipino singers.
Residents and tourists will be able to enjoy a special night, as is always the case on New Year's Eve, with several options available, both on the Peninsula and on the Islands. To know what to wear and what to expect in terms of weather, forecasts for today and the first day of 2026 point to temperatures between 16 and 22ºC. Saturday should be colder, with temperatures between 9 and 17ºC, rising slightly on Sunday and Monday to 11-20 and 12-20.
 
Buses and Metro reinforce services
With the aim of facilitating the travel of residents who will participate in the New Year celebrations, the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) coordinated with the two bus operators and the Light Rail Society to make temporary adjustments to public transport and contingency plans, including extending the timetable during today. The increase in the frequency of departures and the creation of special services on some bus routes are other measures designed to “help disperse the crowds”, indicated DSAT. Bus operators were also instructed to closely monitor the flow of passengers in each zone, in order to flexibly adjust the frequency of departures when necessary. The timetable of 21 daytime bus routes will be extended until 01:00 or 02:00 next morning and some night routes will also increase their frequency. The Metro will operate until 02:00 on New Year's Day.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>97% of secondary students have already used AI in their studies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/97-dos-alunos-secundario-ja-usaram-ia-nos-estudos/</link><description>A survey by FAOM and Escola Secundária Lou Hau reveals that 97% of secondary school students interviewed have already used artificial intelligence (AI) to support their studies. However, almost half admit that excessive dependence on AI can weaken independent thinking
 
To analyze the situation of personalized development of secondary school students in Macau, the Federation of Workers' Associations (FAOM) and Lou Hau Secondary School surveyed 2,000 local students and teachers this year and obtained 790 valid responses. The results of the survey, released yesterday, show that almost 97% of the students surveyed have already used artificial intelligence (AI) to support their studies, including with homework (more than 83%).
More than 50% of students interviewed recognized that the use of AI tools is beneficial for improving grades, positively evaluating the role of this technology as a form of inspiration. However, almost half considered that excessive dependence on AI could weaken independent thinking, while the teachers surveyed were generally concerned about students' “mental laziness” caused by AI.
Furthermore, according to the study, students “still have significant room for progress” in independent learning, long-term planning and capacity for innovation. On the other hand, students identified problems in the use of AI, such as the lack of precision in the content recommended by the AI ​​tools, asynchrony with the progress of the manuals, limited coverage of the resources provided and lack of interesting content.
Based on the survey results, the association suggested that the promotion of personalized learning among secondary school students be included in the overall planning for Macau's youth development and the construction of the Greater Bay Area. From their perspective, schools should start considering learning capacity, innovative thinking, problem solving, team cooperation and assuming responsibilities as indicators of essential skills.
“At the same time, curricular activities should integrate career planning, professional awareness and education for social responsibilities, to guide students in establishing correct values ​​and perspectives regarding work when using AI tools”, proposed FAOM.
He also suggested a systematic improvement in AI application capabilities among the teaching team, as well as an incentive mechanism that links AI literacy to teacher performance assessment.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Foundation will reward studies on Portuguese-Chinese ties through Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/fundacao-vai-premiar-estudos-sobre-lacos-luso-chineses-atraves-de-macau/</link><description>The last Portuguese governor of Macau, Vasco Rocha Vieira, during an interview with Lusa as part of the 20th anniversary of the handover of Macau's administration from Portugal to China, at Lusa's headquarters in Lisbon, December 6, 2019. The former governor of Macau, Vasco Rocha Vieira said, in an interview with Lusa, that 20 years after the transition of the administration of the territory to China, the most "important" thing remained, the continuity of the policy and "identity", fundamental aspects for its future. (FOLLOWS TEXT FROM DECEMBER 15, 2019). MÁRIO CRUZ/LUSA



The Jorge Álvares Foundation launched an annual prize, worth 25 thousand euros, to encourage the study and research of relations between Portugal and China, through Macau. With the “Fundação Jorge Álvares-General Vasco Rocha Vieira-Portugal-China Friendship Award”, it also intends to recognize “institutions that promote relevant initiatives in order to reinforce the rapprochement between the Portuguese, Chinese and Macanese communities”, it is stated on the foundation's website.
“It aims to honor and contribute to perpetuating the memory of the last governor of Macau, founder of the Jorge Álvares Foundation, its curator and first president, who passed away about a year ago”, wrote the current curator, Tiago Vasconcelos, on social media.
The prize will be awarded alternately to institutions, in even-numbered years and from 2026 onwards, and to research work, in odd-numbered years, with the latter being launched in 2027. In the first case, the award is open to any institution, national or foreign, rewarding “relevant actions that develop or deepen the relationship between the Portuguese, Chinese and Macanese communities”, in the fields of Portuguese, Chinese or Macanese culture and languages. patuá, science, education, philanthropy, among others.
With regard to research work, the award “is open to anyone without academic restrictions, nationality or otherwise”, and rewards “the quality of studies and written work on a topic, to be indicated for each edition, within the scope of relations between Portugal and China, particularly through Macau”.
“From the signing of the joint declaration to the transfer of the Portuguese administration of Macau” is, according to the regulations, the theme for the first edition of the award in the research category.
Rocha Vieira was the 138th and last Portuguese governor of Macau, a position he held until 1999, when the territory was transferred to China. He passed away on January 22, 2025, at the age of 85.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>BRIEF</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2521/</link><description>Jewelry involved in illegal exchange of 60 million
Two employees of a jewelry store located in a casino in COTAI were arrested on suspicion of illegally exchanging money. According to the Judiciary Police (PJ), since 2024, the jewelry store has been involved in illegal exchanges of 60 million HKD, having raised around one million. On Monday, the PJ red-handedly detected a player from Mainland China receiving 5,000 HKD after reading a QR code provided by female employees. The detainees, a 36-year-old resident and a 27-year-old mainland woman, admitted to engaging in illicit exchange, under instructions from their boss and in exchange for a monthly reward of 2,000 to 5,000 patacas per person. The PJ is investigating the owner of the jewelry store.
 
Statues of the Ruins undergoing new restoration
Between this Friday and February 9th, the Cultural Institute (IC) will carry out the second phase of restoration and maintenance work on the bronze statues in the Ruins of S. Paulo. The intervention will involve two statues located on the second level of the Ruins, as well as the bronze statue of Jesus Christ on the fourth level. During this period, scaffolding will be installed on the facade of the monument. At the same time, the Ruins of Colégio de São Paulo, including the Museum of Sacred Art and Crypt and the exhibition “Visiting the Ruins of São Paulo in Space and Time”, will be temporarily closed.
 
Hotel occupancy exceeded 90% in November
The average occupancy rate of hotel rooms in the Macao SAR stood at 90.2% in November, rising 0.7 percentage points year-on-year, announced the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC). Hotels welcomed 1,193,000 guests in November, an increase of 1.9%. Those in Hong Kong (141,000) rose 8.2% and those in Mainland China (859,000) fell 0.7%, reads a statement from DSEC, which also states that international numbers (125,000) increased 12.7%. In the first 11 months of the year, the number of guests grew 0.6% to 13.31 million and the occupancy rate increased 3.2 points to 89.3%.
 
61 thousand participated in the Sino-Lusophone festival
The “7th Meeting in Macau – Festival of Arts and Culture between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries”, took place “successfully”, attracting more than 61 thousand participants, according to the Cultural Institute (IC), which organized the event in conjunction with the “Festival da Lusofonia”, together with Galaxy Entertainment. This combination of efforts made it possible to carry out seven major series of programs between October and December, totaling around 80 shows and parallel activities.
 
Free Wi-Fi on the Metro from midnight
The Barra and Hengqin Light Rail stations will offer, on a trial basis, from midnight today, the free Wi-Fi service. Each user will be able to enjoy, free of charge, one hour of Wi-Fi connection per day. Sociedade do Metro Ligeiro assured that it will gradually expand the free Wi-Fi service to other stations, in order to “elevate passenger experience and provide a more convenient travel environment”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Exports with CEPA “seal” approach historic highs</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/exportacoes-selo-cepa-aproximam-se-de-maximo-historico/</link><description>Reaching a monthly average higher than the record recorded in 2022, Macau's exports of goods exempt from customs duties on the Chinese mainland increased by around 54% to more than 107 million patacas between January and November 2025, in annual terms, according to official statistics. Since 2004, 892 Macau service provider certificates have been issued under CEPA, mostly linked to the areas of health and logistical transport
 
SERGIO TERRA
 
The value of exports of goods from Macau that enjoy exemption from customs duties in the Mainland China market will record the second consecutive year of year-on-year growth in 2025, and could even reach a new absolute record. This projection, drawn up by the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, is based on the fact that exports covered by the Agreement on Strengthening Economic and Commercial Relations between Mainland China and Macau (CEPA) have increased in 12 of the last 14 months, in annual terms.
Between January and November this year, the total amount of exports with the CEPA “seal” amounted to 107.27 million patacas, marking an increase of 54.2% in relation to the 69.59 million recorded in the same period of 2024, according to provisional data from the Directorate of Economic and Technological Development Services (DSEDT). Overall for 2024, there was an annual increase of 12.8% to 79.82 million patacas, although with different developments in the two semesters, as the 34.9% increase in the second half of the year ended up offsetting the 13.4% drop between January and June.
In 2025, exports “protected” by CEPA reached the end of November with a monthly average of 9.75 million patacas, a value that exceeds the level of 2022, marked by an annual record of 115.33 million, at a monthly average of around 9.61 million. In other words, Macau will establish a new annual maximum if exports exceed 8.06 million in December, a value lower than that recorded in the same month of 2024 (10.23 million).
The results of the last six years were characterized by year-on-year fluctuations, with three drops (6.9% in 2019, 11.5% in 2020 and 38.5% in 2023) and three increases (32.6% in 2021, 10.2% in 2022 and 12.8% in 2024).
According to data from DSEDT analyzed by this newspaper, August was the month with the highest volume of exports in 2025, with 13.01 million patacas, despite reflecting a 5.8% drop in annual terms, followed by September, with 12.83 million (more than 166.8%), November, with 11.40 million (more 1,078%), and July, with 10.24 million (37.6% more). At the opposite pole come October, with 6.91 million, and January, with 6.95 million patacas, representing a drop of 7.1% and a growth of 64.3%, respectively.
In the remaining months, export values ​​totaled 9.96 million in March (plus 153.8%), 8.82 million in April (plus 59%), 7.41 million in May (plus 12%) and 8.38 million in June (plus 24%).
Since January 1, 2004, the date of implementation of trade in goods under CEPA, the accumulated amount of duty-free exports has exceeded 1.60 billion patacas.
Official statistics also indicate that, between the beginning of 2004 and June 2025, 892 Macau service provider certificates were issued, including eight in the first eight months of this year. The majority of certificates involve medical and dental services (340) and the transport sector (including freight forwarding, logistics, conservation and storage), with 309, which represented around 38% and 35% of the total, respectively.
The list also includes certificates for conventions and exhibitions (41), real estate (33), travel agencies and tour operators (28), banking and other financial services, excluding insurance companies (24), construction and engineering (16), hiring and placement of personnel (13), retail trade (nine), research and development in natural sciences (two) and “other” unspecified services (77).
On March 1st of this year, CEPA entered a new stage of expansion, with the removal of the requirement of at least three years of substantial commercial activity for Macao SAR service providers in most sectors. Furthermore, the implementation of pilot measures was announced to support MSAR-owned companies registered in the Greater Bay Area to choose Hong Kong or Macau as a place of arbitration, as well as the strengthening of liberalization in the “cutting-edge technology, financial, audiovisual and cultural services sectors”, with the aim of supporting Macau’s “1+4” economic diversification strategy.
Among other measures, the amendments to CEPA II also include the repeal of the requirement of five years of carrying out substantial commercial activity for Macau banks and the restriction on the total assets at the end of the year of foreign financial institutions for their shareholding in insurance companies. On the other hand, the limit on the proportion of local enterprises' share capital in providing Internet data center services in pilot areas has been abolished.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Works on the Guia Chapel begin in 2026</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/obras-na-capela-da-guia-arrancam-em-2026/</link><description>Starting next year, the Guia Chapel will be subject to restoration work, namely the restoration of the murals, which illustrate motifs of religious and mythological inspiration. The Cultural Institute revealed to the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU that the Center for Preservation and Transmission of Cultural Heritage of the Palace Museum will set up a team of Chinese and foreign experts to outline the restoration plan

Catarina Pereira
 
The Chapel of Nossa Senhora das Neves, next to the Guia Lighthouse, will be subject to restoration and recovery works starting next year, the Cultural Institute (IC) told TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper. “For this purpose, the IC hired professional institutions to carry out the study, inspection and analysis of the building and the murals”, can be read in the organization’s response.
The restoration work will be monitored by the Cultural Heritage Preservation and Transmission Center of the Macau Palace Museum, as the president of the IC, Leong Wai Man, had already announced in February this year, at the same time she announced that the bronze statues of the Ruins of São Paulo would be recovered.
Built around 1622, the also known as Capela da Guia was originally managed by Clarissa nuns. In 1998, during conservation work, mural paintings were discovered inside.
The frescoes illustrate both Western and Chinese themes, with motifs of religious and mythological inspiration “which are a perfect example of the multicultural dimension of Macau”, can be read on the World Heritage page. The Fortress of Nossa Senhora da Guia, the Chapel of Nossa Senhora das Neves and the Lighthouse are part of the Historic Center of Macau.
To this newspaper, the IC has now announced that the Center for Preservation and Transmission of Cultural Heritage at the Palace Museum will set up a team of “Chinese and foreign experts” to “develop a restoration plan based on the results of the report”.
“From 2026 onwards, the Center also plans to gradually carry out environmental improvement works in the Capela de N.ª Sr.ª das Neves building, as well as the reinforcement, recovery and safeguarding of the murals”, added the IC.
Featuring a simple facade, with a triangular pediment resting on pilasters painted yellow on a white background, the Guia Chapel has a sacristy on the left side and a small high choir above the entrance area.
In the Lines of Government Action for the next year under the supervision of Social Affairs and Culture, it had already been said that restoration projects such as the bronze statues and the facade of the Ruins of São Paulo, the frescoes of the Chapel of Nossa Senhoras das Neves in Fortaleza da Guia and the structural components of the Temple of A-Má will be prioritized.
The Center for the Preservation and Transmission of Cultural Heritage was created, it should be remembered, following a memorandum signed between the Macao SAR Government and the Ministry of Culture and Tourism, with the Palace Museum being responsible for providing professional advice and technical support for the restoration of the territory's cultural heritage.
Located on the ground floor of the Art Museum, it occupies approximately 900 square meters and is equipped with specialized laboratories, being prepared to carry out preservation and restoration work related to Macau's world heritage sites, immovable heritage assets and built heritage components. All of this through advanced technologies and the “strengthening of local talents in the area of ​​heritage conservation”, according to the IC on its website.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Melco will hire a company to explore Mocha rooms</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/melco-vai-contratar-sociedade-para-explorar-salas-mocha/</link><description>Melco closed the Mocha room at the Royal hotel, but was authorized to continue operating three slot machine spaces from January 1st. The game concessionaire will maintain the employment relationship established with the workers
 
The closure of the Mocha Hotel Royal, a gaming machine room belonging to Melco Resorts (Macau) took place in accordance with the established procedures, yesterday morning, December 29th. The closure was coordinated by the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ) in close interdepartmental collaboration, thus ensuring compliance with legal terms and the orderliness of the respective process.
After the closure, the organization suspended the operation of the gaming machines, having ensured coordination, with various services, to monitor the process of removal from the respective premises, among other aspects.
According to the DICJ, during the closure of the slot room, the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs sent staff to the site to provide clarifications to the workers in question, having provided them with information about an open line for further consultation. Furthermore, the Public Security Police Corps and the Judiciary Police preserved public order at the site and in its surroundings, “with the closure taking place in an “orderly manner”, adds the note.
On the other hand, taking into account that the three-year “transitional period” granted to “satellite casinos” ends at the end of this year, and after a comprehensive analysis and evaluation, the Government granted authorization to the request presented by Melco to operate the three existing Mocha rooms (Golden Dragon, Porto Interior and Hotel Sintra), by hiring a management company.
In this sense, Melco will continue to operate those spaces from January 1, 2026, maintaining the employment relationship established with the respective workers.
In the same statement, the DICJ reiterated that it will continue to ensure the coordination established with concessionaires operating games of chance and the competent services, “jointly promoting the healthy and orderly development of the gaming sector in Macau”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Drop in subsidies did not stunt the evolution of sport in the last decade</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/quebra-nos-subsidios-nao-atrofiou-evolucao-desporto-na-ultima-decada/</link><description>Subsidies for sport fell by 40% between 2014 and 2024 and, in that period, the number of sports clubs and associated athletes decreased. However, the proportion of affiliated women rose in the main modalities and, in general, the number of casual practitioners also grew. For Alice Lei, a sports professor at the University of Macau, these trends can be enhanced, while teaching can be reconfigured in favor of greater physical literacy

PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
In the space of a decade, subsidies granted by the Sports Institute (ID) fell by more than 40%, official data indicates. In 2014, the ID allocated 155 million patacas from the public treasury, while in 2024 this support totaled 91 million. During this decade, the number of associated athletes decreased by 9.6%, to a total of 35,787. Furthermore, at the end of 2024, there were 948 sports clubs, 195 fewer than a decade earlier.
Except for athletics, all sports categories received less subsidies last year, compared to 2014. In 2024, “ball sports” received 25 million patacas, corresponding to a 36% reduction. Similarly, last year, the Government allocated 23 million to “martial arts” (-24%) and 13 million to “water sports” (-43%). For “other” sports, 24 million patacas were allocated in support, less than half of 2014 (58 million). On the other hand, “athletics” received almost 5.9 million in 2024, compared to the 5 million allocated in 2014.
Despite the drop in funding, “martial arts” registered a considerable increase in affiliated athletes, going from 7,949 to 11 thousand (+39.2%). In “athletics”, the number of associated practitioners almost doubled, to a total of 1,478 athletes (+91.5%). Conversely, “water sports” and “ball sports” lost 534 and 4,194 affiliated athletes, respectively, registering 3,525 and 8,722 at the end of last year.
For Alice Lei, professor at the Faculty of Education at the University of Macau, and specialized in pedagogy and sports psychology, the growth of martial arts is linked to the fact that “it resonates culturally, due to the deep roots of Chinese heritage in Macau”. Furthermore, “support policies such as subsidies for free community classes” also contributed, Lei explained to the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper, and improved “accessibility in a densely populated urban environment”.
In turn, “athletics benefits from minimal entry barriers, not requiring special equipment and the presence of events that attract large crowds”. “Both modalities serve as effective responses to sedentary lifestyles in an economy dominated by gambling, contrasting with the resource-intensive need of water sports and the dependence of teams on ball sports”, noted the teacher.
 
Female athletes gain ground
Data from the Statistics and Census Services also reveal another trend. Between 2014 and 2024, the proportion of female athletes affiliated in “ball sports” and “athletics” rose by 12 percentage points, to 27% and 24%, respectively. In “martial arts” and “water sports”, this growth was more modest, with an increase of one and three percentage points, respectively, to 40% and 32%. Conversely, in “other” sports, the number of men increased.
Alice Lei recognizes that in general “the level of female athletes has improved, with particular progress in martial arts and athletics”. However, he admits that, “ball sports still remain largely behind due to a panorama traditionally dominated by men”.
The UM professor also highlighted that "women are more inclined to participate in sports that benefit from policies designed to promote inclusive curricula and aligned with traditional sports culture. Furthermore, post-pandemic events and media coverage played a crucial role in encouraging women's participation in sports, as many reports highlighted the benefits of physical activity for mental health."
However, “despite these advances, inequalities persist”. “Funding often prioritizes male ball sports and leadership positions remain disproportionately occupied by men”, lamented Alice Lei.
Last year, sports centers and halls had 7.8 million users, 52% more than in 2014. "As a sports psychologist, I see the recent boost in [physical] activity as a significant opportunity for public health. It aligns well with the guidelines of the World Health Organization and addresses the prevalent risks of a sedentary lifestyle in Macau, particularly those associated with prolonged periods of gaming", said Alice Lei.
"Overall, I see this phenomenon as a direct response to the growing well-being needs that followed the Covid-19 [pandemic], when many looked for ways to relieve stress and opportunities for social interaction through sports and group activities. To fully take advantage of this boost, it will be essential to incorporate mental health support on-site", argued the teacher.
For Lei, “this growth in physical activity could potentially reduce the incidence of cardiovascular problems while also fostering social connections that combat urban isolation”.
“However, the impact on the development of athletes is more complex”, he countered. "While this increase improves self-efficacy and encourages retention by providing better access and attracting casual exercisers to clubs, there is also a risk of overcrowding. This can lead to rushed training sessions that impede the development of deeper skills," he warned.
 
Curricula with “Physical Literacy”
School sports fields also registered a 135% increase in terms of participants, with 311 thousand in 2024. "I recognize progress in schools and universities. Yet, they often remain focused on performance-based models", contested Alice Lei.
“Physical Education classes tend to emphasize direct instructions, using exercises, competitions and quantifiable metrics such as speed”, he exemplified. “This instruction-based approach can neglect cognitive aspects, such as strategy, and affective components, such as fun, contributing to high dropout rates.”
Universities demonstrate some promising programs, such as mixed models of theory and practice, noted the professor. However, “a competitive environment persists”. To align physical education with “Physical Literacy”, one of Alice Lei’s areas of focus, sports teaching should be oriented towards “promoting autonomy”.
"Without a focus on building confidence and motivation, lifelong engagement in exercise is difficult. My observations indicate that low self-confidence can double the likelihood of quitting."
The UM professor suggested four key reforms. “Multidimensional curricula” would assess skills, knowledge and factors such as enjoyment and confidence, based on teaching games for learning. “Holistic assessments” would consist of self-assessments and peer assessments with consideration for the affective domain. The implementation of “workshops for educators” would serve to reduce competitive bias and, finally, “lifelong connections” between schools and local clubs would support the integration of former students.
At the same time, “starting with just one Physical Literacy module per semester, as I experienced, can significantly boost engagement, transforming physical education from an inflexible experience into an empowering journey”, concluded Alice Lei.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>The return of the South Korean presidency to the Blue House is more than a logistical change</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/regresso-da-presidencia-sul-coreana-a-casa-azul-e-mais-uma-mudanca-logistica/</link><description>The address of South Korea's presidential office is changing again, leaving Yongsan and returning to the Blue House after three years and seven months. The move triggered a series of other profound changes, including Ministry of Defense units displaced by the previous move.
However, President Lee Jae Myung's return to the Blue House, also known as Cheong Wa Dae, is more than a simple logistical change. This reignites the old, still unanswered question of whether the Blue House facilitates leadership or perpetuates isolation.
The change is already visibly underway. On the morning of December 22, the presidential office held its daily press conference with the press team at the Blue House (Cheong Wa Dae) complex for the first time since May 2022. At that time, Lee Kuan Yew's discredited predecessor, Yoon Hegde, led the office's move to Yongsan-gu in Seoul, 6 km south of the Blue House in Jongno-gu.
All presidential press conferences will be held in Chunchugwan from now on. The location is approximately 500 meters from the main hall, has a press room and seating for members of the presidential press team.
This is one of many changes in the relocation process that began on December 8, the day after Presidential Chief of Staff Kang Hoon-sik announced plans for President Lee and his secretaries to “return to where the President used to be and where the President should be.”
As announced, some Casa Azul employees had already left before the arrival of the presidential press. The entire process should be completed this week, but the Blue House has not yet confirmed when President Lee will begin working at the presidential complex.
According to the presidential office, the new President Lee's workspace will be both in the main hall of Cheong Wa Dae (Blue House) and in Yeomingwan. A Cheong Wa Dae official added that this will allow for closer communication between the president and his advisers – Kang, director of national security Wi Sung-lac and chief secretary for national policy Kim Yong-beom – as their offices will be in the same building.
The official residence in the Cheong Wa Dae complex, located east of the main hall, is still under renovation, and is expected to be moved from Hannam-dong in Yongsan-gu in the first half of 2026.
With great importance as the seat of the presidency in the modern history of South Korea since 1948, when the country's first President, Syngman Rhee, assumed power, the complex was renamed Cheong Wa Dae or Blue House, in 1960.
As it is difficult to access for ordinary citizens, there are those who argue that the location isolates the president from public life in a country that has experienced decades of dictatorship. This is how Yoon presented the plan to move the office to the former headquarters of the Ministry of National Defense and the official residence of the Minister of Foreign Affairs, both in Yongsan-gu, Seoul. However, he also faced criticism due to its high cost and lack of public consensus, given that the change took place just two months after he took office.
President Lee, who took office in June, two months after Yoon's dismissal due to his disastrous imposition of martial law, stated during the election campaign that he would return the presidency to the Blue House and the process is nearing full completion.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>