<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Protection of cultural heritage involves “about a tenth of Macau’s area”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/proteccao-patrimonio-cultural-envolve-cerca-de-um-decimo-da-area-de-macau/</link><description>In the year in which the 20th anniversary of the inscription of the Historic Center of Macau on the World Heritage List is celebrated, the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU interviewed the president of the Cultural Institute (IC), who highlighted the fact that around a tenth of the MSAR area is part of the scope of cultural heritage protection. Therefore, Leong Wai Man emphasizes that integrating World Heritage protection work into the daily lives of residents is an “important and challenging” task. On the other hand, he notes that the classification of the Historic Center by UNESCO contributed to the awareness of protecting cultural heritage “constantly growing” in Macau society in general. Looking to the “new phase”, the president of the IC promises that Macau will reinforce “the deep basis of humanistic exchange” with Portuguese-speaking countries and further strengthen the “fundamental role” of the Historic Center in “promoting exchange and mutual learning between international civilizations”



















Over the 20 years since the Historic Center of Macau has been inscribed on the UNESCO World Heritage List, “the Government, interested parties and the general public” have contributed “indispensable” support and participation to the protection of this legacy, considers the president of the Cultural Institute (IC), Leong Wai Man. In a written interview with the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, focused on this anniversary marked on the 15th of July, the president of the IC highlights although, currently, the protection of cultural heritage involves “around one tenth of Macau’s area”.
"The Historic Center continues to be the main environment that encompasses daily life, economy and production, and the festivities and customs of residents. Furthermore, the Historic Center has been mutually integrated with modern society, throughout constant urban development", highlights the president of the IC.
In the sphere of protecting the core value of the local World Heritage, which consists of its “dynamic state”, the IC leader concludes that, with the continuous promotion of revitalization and use, the majority of heritage buildings, squares and squares in the territory still maintain their original functions.
In this regard, it exemplifies that temples and churches continue to serve as places to celebrate traditional festivities and customs, and the Dom Pedro V Theater annually hosts the Festival of Arts and Culture between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries, the Macau Arts Festival, among other cultural events. Furthermore, it mentions the “harmonious integration” of Macau’s World Heritage Site with modern life, as well as the “organic combination” with Eastern and Western musical performances, virtual reality digital experience, the International Parade and the Macau International Art Biennial.
All of this “creates a beautiful cultural life for residents, allowing the Historic Center of Macau to be safeguarded and shared among the whole society, thus radiating stronger dynamics and vitality”, describes Leong Wai Man.
Taking into account that the scope of cultural heritage protection occupies a tenth of the territory's area, the president of the IC sees the integration of safeguarding work into the daily lives of residents as an “important and challenging” task.
 
Trust and cultural pride
On the other hand, from a spiritual perspective, Leong Wai Man believes that the inscription of the Historic Center on the World Heritage List “has strengthened the confidence and cultural pride of Macau residents”. “It also led the public to even more value the exploration and protection of its history and culture, causing Macau society in general to pay more and more attention to cultural heritage and the awareness of protection has grown constantly”, he highlighted.
From the perspective of the same person responsible, the “increased consensus and self-awareness of society in general, especially young people and adolescents, for the safeguarding of cultural heritage” is also associated with the definition and implementation of the Law on Safeguarding Cultural Heritage and the Plan for safeguarding and managing the “Historic Center of Macau”. The creation of the World Heritage Monitoring Center and the Cultural Heritage Preservation and Transmission Center of the Macau Palace Museum also contributed to this, which, according to Leong Wai Man, constitute “solid software and hardware” for the protection of the heritage legacy.
With regard to public education, an aspect that is “an important part of the work to preserve World Heritage”, the president of the IC asserts that the organization has always given importance to the dissemination and promotion of World Heritage. As he recalls, dissemination actions cover not only festivals, workshops, television broadcasting, publications and studies, and community initiatives, for the general public, but also educational activities aimed at different age groups and different professional groups.
In this area, it highlights the training of local restoration talents, through cooperation with the Directorate of Labor Affairs Services and local professional associations; holding workshops on the restoration of traditional Lingnan architecture, aimed at the public; and the inauguration of the Cultural Heritage Preservation and Transmission Center of the Macau Palace Museum last year, which also has educational and promotional functions.
In parallel, he emphasizes that awareness about the laws relating to cultural heritage has been intensified in the community, with a view to “constantly strengthening and expanding society's support and participation, transmitting and disseminating, with all its strength, the value and connotation of cultural heritage, and fostering an awareness of joint protection”.
Specifically, Leong Wai Man maintains that educating young people and teenagers about World Heritage “has achieved recognition in many aspects”. In addition to regularly carrying out different types of educational activities on World Heritage, the IC has been committed to promoting the participation of new generations in inheriting intangible cultural heritage, supporting them in exploring the meaning of World Heritage and intangible heritage, and stimulating enthusiasm among young generations for embracing innovation and cultural creation. At the same time, the organization continuously promotes youth exchange programs, with the aim of expanding, through multiple angles, historical and cultural horizons, fostering a sense of responsibility and mission among young generations in relation to the heritage of local culture, highlights Leong Wai Man.
 
Cultural ties with the PLP have been deepened
On the other hand, for the IC president, the 20th anniversary of the Historic Center's inscription on the World Heritage List symbolizes an important milestone for Macau's cultural cause. This is because the local World Heritage Site, marked by cultural fusion, constitutes the cultural essence of 400 years of exchange between East and West.
Leong Wai Man emphasizes that Portuguese-style heritage buildings and intangible cultural heritage items are an important part of Macau's World Heritage. Looking back at the last two decades, remember that the Macao SAR Government has carried out protection work in accordance with the Law on Safeguarding Cultural Heritage, for example, by monitoring the condition of heritage buildings and Portuguese-style intangible heritage items, providing support for their repair.
At the same time, within the scope of preserving the intangible cultural heritage of the Portuguese style, the IC leader highlights that, among the 70 local items included in the Inventory of Intangible Cultural Heritage, there are various festivities, cultures and customs of the Macanese community, such as the Theater in Patuá, Macanese Gastronomy, the Manufacturing and Painting of Portuguese Tiles, Folk Dance Portuguese, the Festa de São Martinho and the Arraial de São João.
“The IC has continuously monitored and recorded the protection situation of the respective items, and provides support in various aspects to the inheritance and dissemination of these items”, assures the president of the IC, pointing out that the inclusion of the Theater in Patuá and Macanese Gastronomy in the Representative List of the National Intangible Cultural Heritage was successfully promoted, which promoted the inheritance and continuity of these items in the society.
In terms of international exchange, Leong Wai Man believes that “Macau has continuously played the unique role of the local World Heritage Site in promoting exchange and mutual learning between international civilizations”. In this area, in addition to annually highlighting representatives from the Macao SAR to participate in the session of the World Heritage Committee, Macau maintains “close communication” with the UNESCO World Heritage Center, asserts Leong Wai Man. Furthermore, he recalls that, in 2020, Macau became part of the Organization of World Heritage Cities, having ceaselessly reinforced exchanges at international level.
Regarding the Portuguese-speaking world, the official highlights that local authorities have deepened cultural ties between Macau and Portuguese-speaking Countries (PLP) and actively played the role of Macau's platform as a “Center for Cultural Exchange between China and the PLP”, through the holding, in many consecutive years, of the Arts and Culture Festival between China and the PLP and the Lusophony Festival.
This year, on the occasion of the 20th anniversary of the Historic Center as a World Heritage Site, the Government will hold the International Cultural Forum for Mutual Learning between Civilizations under the theme of “protection of cultural heritage”. The IC plans to invite several experts linked to culture and cultural heritage, including some from Portuguese-speaking countries, to exchange opinions in Macau, so that the event serves as a window for exchange and mutual learning between civilizations.
Leong Wai Man hopes that this Forum will contribute to “transmitting the common values ​​of all humanity contemplated by cultural heritage, building a bridge of dialogue and communication between different civilizations and uninterruptedly expanding the circle of international friends, thus making Macau a ‘relevant high-level link for the country in opening up to the outside world’ and an important window for exchange and mutual learning between Chinese and Western civilizations”.
“More than 400 years of unique history of exchange with foreign countries have resulted in the harmonious social and cultural connotation of Macau that exists today, established the position of development as ‘A Base of Exchange and Cooperation for the Promotion of Multicultural Coexistence, with a Predominance of Chinese Culture’ and granted Macau an important historical mission in the ‘exchange and mutual learning between Chinese and Chinese civilizations. western’”, emphasizes Leong Wai Man.
“In the new phase, Macau will make good use of its own institutional advantages of ‘one country, two systems’, reinforce the two-way role of connectivity with both the Mainland and the rest of the world, and the deep foundation of humanistic exchange with the PLP, as well as further strengthen the fundamental role of the Historic Center of Macau in promoting exchange and mutual learning between international civilizations”, says the president of the IC.
 
World Heritage Museum “actively” promoted
With regard to improving the protection and management of World Heritage using digital technologies, the IC leader understands that the World Heritage Monitoring Center, ready in 2022, “has achieved the reinforcement of the management of World Heritage through digital technologies”. Furthermore, in recent years, IC has been actively introducing immersive and interactive digital technologies, such as virtual reality and augmented reality.
In this regard, he guarantees that, “currently, the IC is actively promoting the construction of the Macau World Heritage Museum, which will integrate more and diverse interactive digital experiences, in order to convey the cultural connotation of Macau's World Heritage to residents and tourists”.
On the other hand, Leong Wai Man notes that, for many years, in addition to providing support to heritage buildings in restoration works, the IC has continuously raised the level of management of World Heritage and its capacity to respond to natural disasters.
Within the scope of managing the flow of people in tourist attractions classified as World Heritage, it clarifies that the IC has taken management and control measures in accordance with the support capacity of heritage tourist attractions. Furthermore, it reinforced regulation by defining the Safeguarding and Management Plan for the Historic Center of Macau.
Regarding the response to natural disasters, the person responsible indicates that the IC has already defined the mechanism for responding to natural disasters involving cultural heritage, and intelligently monitors the situation of sites classified through the World Heritage Monitoring Center. At the same time, it has strengthened cooperation with professional institutions, in order to improve response measures to bad weather and natural disasters, concludes Leong Wai Man.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Average daily game revenue reached 1.1 billion at the beginning of October</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/media-diaria-das-receitas-jogo-atingiu-11-mil-milhoes-inicio-de-outubro/</link><description>Nos primeiros cinco dias deste mês, as receitas brutas do jogo foram de 5,5 mil milhões de patacas, representando o melhor início da “Semana Dourada” em mais de cinco anos, segundo analistas do JP Morgan. Os primeiros dias do período festivo também registaram o maior número de “high rollers” do ano com o valor da aposta média mais alto de 2025
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
Gaming concessionaires recorded gross revenues of 5.5 billion patacas in the first five days of October, translating into a daily average of 1.1 billion, according to a report by analysts at investment bank JP Morgan. For DS Kim, Selina Li and Lindsey Qian, it was the best start to “Golden Week” in “more than five years”. On the other hand, the 3% annual growth in the game's gross revenue was below the expectations of the JP Morgan team.
Analysts, however, said they were not worried about the fact that the holiday period would be “longer this year”, with one more day. Furthermore, the passage of Typhoon “Matmo” also had an impact on the numbers, as maritime transport and flights were suspended for half a day, they explained. According to preliminary data, the Macao SAR received 191 thousand visitors on Saturday, with this figure falling to 113 thousand on Sunday, the day sign 8 was erected.
In the same report, analysts maintained projections of 23 billion patacas for the month of October, which would correspond to an annual increase of between 11% and 13%, also expecting “sustained double-digit growth for the sector's gross revenues until the first quarter of 2026”.
Furthermore, the team continues to forecast that the gaming sector will record daily gross revenues of 750 million patacas, in the second week of October. This would mean a weekly decline of 30%, whereas, last year, the drop in gross revenue was 40% in the same time period.
 
Annual maximums of “high rollers” and average bets
A survey by Citigroup, carried out in the first days of “Golden Week” and before the passing of “Matmo”, indicates that the number of “high rollers” and the average bet of these players reached the “highest levels of the year”. Quoted by the portal “GGRAsia”, George Choi and Timothy Chau observed that there were 60 “whales” players, with an average bet of 176,583 Hong Kong dollars, an annual increase of 6%.
The term “whale” is given to players whose bets are 100,000 Hong Kong dollars or higher.
The “player of the month” was seen at the Venetian, for the second consecutive month, having bet 800 thousand Hong Kong dollars.
On the other hand, the average bet of “premium” mass players grew just 1%, in annual terms, to 28,466 Hong Kong dollars, values ​​close to the “Golden Week” in May. The average minimum bet was 2,432 Hong Kong dollars.
The banking group's analysts estimated an annual decrease of 15% in the number of “premium” mass players, to a total of 819, due to the fact that this year's festive week is eight days long. “We hope the additional day will translate into more visits in total, but it will likely dilute the daily average,” they argued.
Still, for George Choi and Timothy Chau, the quality of these players “continues to be golden”. “The new side bets are apparently becoming more popular”, observed the analysts, considering it “a good omen for a solid ‘Golden Week’”.
Citgroup also estimated that Sands China holds 27% of the market share of total bets from “premium” players, followed by Galaxy Entertainment, with 22%. “The 10 whales we found in the “Horizon” room at Galaxy Macau were the largest number we saw in any room,” they revealed.
 
128 thousand visitors on the 6th day of Golden Week
On Monday, the sixth day of Golden Week, which coincided with the Mooncake Festival, 128,890 visitors entered Macau. The previous day, despite the passage of Typhoon “Matmo”, Macau welcomed 113,051 visitors, according to data from the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP). Yesterday, until 5pm, another 113 thousand were registered. According to the CPSP, in the first five days of October, the borders registered around 3.57 million entries and exits, an annual increase of 2.1%, translating to a daily average of 716 thousand crossings. On the other hand, the CPSP detected, in those five days, four infractions committed by taxi drivers, including two cases of refusal to transport, one of fare negotiation and one that involved abusive charging and price negotiation with passengers. In addition, seven cases of lack of politeness in serving passengers were forwarded to the Traffic Affairs Services and five situations of carrying out transport services without due authorization were identified.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>85 drug addicts registered by June</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/registados-85-toxicodependentes-ate-junho/</link><description>Between January and June this year, 85 drug addicts were registered in Macau through the central registration system, which reflects an annual drop of 11.5%. Furthermore, in the same period of time, no drug addicts under 21 years of age were registered
 
Data from the Macau Central Drug Addict Registration System indicate that, in the first half of this year, 85 drug addicts were registered in the territory, which represents a reduction of 11.5% compared to the same period in 2024.
At the same time, there were no cases of drug addiction involving young people under 21 years of age, reported the Institute of Social Action (IAS), at a plenary meeting of the Commission for the Fight against Drugs. It is recalled that, in the first half of 2024, the Central Register included five drug addicts in the aforementioned age group.
Furthermore, the IAS revealed that, regarding the most abused types of drugs, “ice” represented the largest number of cases (22.7%) in the first half of the year, followed by heroin (9.1%) and marijuana (4.5%).
According to the organization, the Macao SAR Government is moving forward with the legislative process to add the six substances controlled in accordance with the Decisions of the 68th United Nations Commission on Narcotic Drugs to the control list.
On the other hand, the IAS highlighted that the Drug Enforcement Commission pays close attention to the trend of drug regulation and abuse emerging in neighboring regions. In this sense, it will continue to collect, evaluate and analyze the opinions of the members of the Commission and relevant entities, so that the Macao SAR remains in tune with the international community and neighboring regions, and increases the effectiveness of simultaneously preventing and combating drug-related crimes.
At the same meeting, the Commission also presented work plans for the next year, including the launch of several measures to improve detoxification services, the continued promotion of young people's participation in anti-drug issues and the improvement of the quality and level of detoxification services. In addition, the Commission announced the launch, in 2026, of the 2nd Macau International Youth Anti-Drug Ambassador Training Program and the Greater Bay Area Youth Anti-Drug Studies Program.
 
Drug addicts with an average age of 44.3 years
According to the summary of the report for the first half of 2025, the average age of drug addicts was 44.3 years old, with the youngest being 22 years old and the oldest being 78 years old. The proportion of female drug addicts registered in these six months was 27.1%, reflecting a slight increase compared to the same period last year.
Registered drug users live mainly in the North Zone (42.4% of the total), 31.8% were single and 60% have children. Another phenomenon observed is the increase in the proportion of drug addicts who are unemployed to 40%. Furthermore, the proportion of drug addicts with low education (primary education) rose to 21.2%. Furthermore, 29.4% have a past criminal record, representing an annual increase.
In relation to the average monthly cost for drug addicts, the value increased, in annual terms, from 2,172.7 to 2,359.4 patacas.
The place of consumption was mainly in Macau (81.7%) and only 4.3% chose to consume drugs in Mainland China. According to the same data, 58.4% consumed drugs in their homes and 14.2% in friends' homes, both rates being higher than in the same period of 2024.
The report reveals that “relieving stress” was the reason that led 43.4% of drug addicts to use drugs, a proportion equivalent to that seen in the first half of 2024.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New support launched for culling polluting motorcycles</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lancado-novo-apoio-para-abate-de-motociclos-poluidores/</link><description>The achievement of the national “Double Carbon Target” led the Government to launch a new phase of the plan to provide financial support for the scrapping of gasoline motorcycles and their replacement by electric vehicles
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The plan to provide financial support for the scrapping of gasoline motorcycles and their replacement with new electric motorcycles will have a new phase. The objective, according to the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA), is to “further improve air quality and guarantee the health of residents”, in line with the achievement of the national “Double Carbon Target”.
After being launched in two phases, in 2022 and 2023, the plan “contributed positively to the elimination of highly polluting motorcycles”, says DSPA. The percentage of citizens who chose to purchase electric motorcycles rose from around 2% recorded before the implementation of the plan, to 40.7%.
However, the organization considers that the proportion of electric motorcycles in relation to all two-wheeled vehicles “still remains low”, and that conventional fuel motorcycles “continue to emit high levels of pollutants, such as hydrocarbons and carbon monoxide”. Therefore, he emphasizes, “it is necessary to launch a new phase of financial support”.
The deadline for applying lasts five years, running from October 15th to October 14th, 2030. The scope of support has been extended to all petrol motorcycles and mopeds in Macau that have valid registration, excluding those whose registration has been/will be canceled on or after October 6th of this year and which are re-registered after cancellation, as well as owners of motorcycles that have debts to the Macao SAR.
If the request is submitted in the first year of the application deadline (that is, until October 14, 2026), the amount of financial support is 3,500 patacas, and in subsequent years, the amount will be gradually reduced. At the same time, exemption from fees for providing trial and registration plates will be granted for new electric motorcycles to be purchased, with financial support and fee exemption reaching up to 8,800 patacas.
Eligible individuals can go to the application submission location, with the necessary documents, to complete the respective formalities. Applications can also be made online through the “Single account for common access to Macao SAR public services”.
 
Six more silos adopt half-hour billing
From October 15th, six more public car parks will implement the half-hour charging model: those at Rotunda da Concordia, Estrada Flor de Lótus, Lok Kuan, Ip Heng and Koi Nga buildings. Daytime and nighttime parking for cars will be 3 and 1.5 patacas, respectively, for each period of half an hour or fraction thereof. For motorcycles and mopeds, the fare is 1 pataca during the day and 0.5 at night. Macau now has 15 public car parks charging for every half hour or fraction thereof.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM and Coimbra create laboratory on aging</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/upm-coimbra-criam-laboratorio-sobre-envelhecimento/</link><description>The University of Coimbra (UC) and the Polytechnic University of Macau (UPM) signed a cooperation agreement to create a laboratory dedicated to the study and development of solutions for aging. The partnership establishes the “Joint Artificial Intelligence Laboratory for Healthy Longevity”, with a research hub in Coimbra and another in Hengqin, the UC revealed yesterday, in a statement sent to the Lusa agency.
According to the Portuguese higher education institution, the central mission of the structure is “the development of innovative solutions that can slow down aging and improve the quality of life of the population, combining biomedical research with the potential of artificial intelligence”.
The laboratory reinforces the collaboration between UC and UPM, a partnership that has brought together several research teams in scientific projects, such as the Joint Laboratory in Advanced Technologies for Smart Cities, created in 2022.
During the ceremony that marked the launch of the new scientific structure, protocols were also signed to promote cooperation in teaching and mobility of students, teachers and researchers from the two academies.
For the rector of the UC, Amílcar Falcão, cited in the statement, the laboratory “means the internationalization of the knowledge of the University of Coimbra in the area of ​​aging”, with a global projection of the work developed by the UC in this area, through the Multidisciplinary Institute of Aging (MIA Portugal).
In turn, the rector of the Macau Polytechnic University, Im Sio Kei, highlighted the objective of working together in health, with a special focus on healthy longevity, “since the University of Coimbra is very strong in this area” and the MPU “is very strong in the area of ​​artificial intelligence”.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Security protection will reinforce investment in AI</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/tutela-da-seguranca-vai-reforcar-aposta-na-ia/</link><description>The Office of the Secretary for Security said that GIF will introduce the intelligent analysis system against money laundering, while the CPSP plans to launch the function of receiving complaints through Artificial Intelligence in the SAFP system
 
In the field of financial crime prevention, the Financial Information Office (GIF) of the Unitary Police Services (SPU) will introduce the intelligent analysis system against money laundering, to strengthen data collection and integration. Through the capital flow analysis function, it aims to identify hidden operation models that are difficult to detect by traditional means, said the Office of the Secretary for Security.
In response to a written question from deputy Ho Ion Sang who called for increased use of innovative technologies in law enforcement, the head of that office, Chang Cheong, also revealed that the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) plans to introduce, into the command and mobilization system of the Administration and Public Service Services (SAFP), the function of receiving complaints using artificial intelligence (AI).
Furthermore, he said that the Judiciary Police (PJ) and the Fire Department (CB), among other bodies, are studying the introduction of AI in their respective systems. In general, he noted that security services already have equipment and systems with intelligent analysis functions and have developed work on creating their own police application systems and integrating the respective data into the cloud police system, to combat new types of crimes more effectively.
On the other hand, he revealed that the Customs Service (SA) plans to create more automatic “airports” for drones in the coastal areas of Macau, and reinforce the drones' night vision equipment, with a view to expanding the patrol area and night surveillance capacity. According to him, the smart airports introduced recently can implement the automated patrolling model within a radius of four kilometers from the airports for drones.
As he explained, the PJ and the CPSP have already introduced the use of drones to support crime scene inspection, criminal investigation, control and security of large-scale activities and traffic control. The CB also has several drones equipped with a high-definition thermal imaging sensor, gas detector, among other instruments, in order to respond to rescue and search missions in different scenarios.
Regarding the future, the Office of the Secretary for Security said that security services will continue to optimize equipment, systems and functions related to drones according to real needs.
On the other hand, within the scope of “parallel trade”, the SA is studying and developing more modern intelligent police equipment in collaboration with the cities of the Greater Bay Area, in order to improve the effectiveness and management of security at a regional level. Currently, SAs use non-invasive scanner equipment and big data analysis.
Furthermore, he pointed out that the SPU plans to organize visits to the Greater Bay Area and other cities in Mainland China, with the aim of deepening exchanges with the competent services on data technology and intelligent policing, as well as studying the possibility of establishing various cooperation in this field.
In the same response, the Cabinet reiterated that the Hengqin Border Post has upgraded 64 existing automatic full inspection channels to intelligent channels with “facial recognition” function. And it will install another 46 automatic full inspection channels with this function in the passenger inspection room, in order to increase border crossing capacity.
Chang Cheong also assured that the security area has “actively promoted” the work related to the reserve of qualified personnel in the technological area. As he exemplified, the SPU collaborated with other services and organizations in organizing professional courses around intelligent policing, AI, big data and cybersecurity for police officers.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Studio City opened iRad hospital</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/studio-city-inaugurou-hospital-irad/</link><description>Studio City has opened a hospital with several advanced healthcare services. According to Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, the partnership with the “iRad” group represents “a historic achievement”
 
Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment recently opened “iRad Hospital”, described as Macau’s first resort-integrated healthcare facility with MRI and CT scanning facilities. Located in Studio City, the hospital offers cutting-edge health tourism experiences and constitutes a new step towards positioning the Macao SAR as “a privileged destination for health, rejuvenation and well-being”, says a statement from the gaming operator.
The new project integrates “world-class health screening, diagnostic imaging, aesthetic medicine, longevity treatments and medical concierge services”. At the same time, it “further enhances the city’s tourism infrastructure by introducing a robust medical and wellness ecosystem that strategically complements its existing world-class offerings.” The hospital represents “a historic achievement” and offers “an unparalleled fusion of healthcare, wellness and entertainment.”
With this venture, Melco and the “iRad” group intend to leverage “the growing global demand for high-quality medical services” as well as the “continuous increase in the number of tourists visiting Macau”. With a revolutionary healthcare concept, “the hospital aims to attract regional and foreign visitors, encouraging longer stays and higher spending”, both in Studio City and in Macau”, guaranteeing “recurrent and long-term guests”.
Lawrence Ho, president of Melco, explained that the aim of the project is “to offer guests world-class integrated entertainment and healthcare options”. Studio City “is now poised to become a leading health and wellness destination, establishing Macau as the region’s premier medical and wellness tourism hub.”
The group leader also believes that the local economy will be strengthened, with “invaluable employment opportunities for the community”. “This project is in line with the Government’s ‘1+4’ economic diversification strategy”, highlighted Lawrence Ho.
For his part, Dennis Tam, honorary president of the company 'iRad', stated that the Hong Kong group is confident that “a new benchmark of medical excellence will be established in Macau, attracting patients and visitors from across the region”. “At ‘iRad’, we are proud to present the first and largest hospital in the world to introduce MRI and CT equipment within an integrated resort.”
“With its large and growing tourism sector, projected to receive 38-39 million visitors annually, Macau offers an unparalleled opportunity to become the leading regional medical tourism destination”, concluded Dennis Tam.
Focused on “providing high-quality imaging services and exceptional care” to its patients, the group includes among its clients the HKSAR Government, other high-profile medical groups, corporations, private doctors and NGOs.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Young people dominate professional placement actions</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jovens-dominam-accoes-de-colocacao-profissional/</link><description>The Labor Affairs and Education and Youth Development Services placed more than half of the young people who participated in recruitment sessions co-held by the two organizations this summer. During a meeting of the Employment Promotion Coordination Working Group, Tai Kin Ip urged entities to prioritize residents when hiring workers. In addition, the Government opened applications for support for young people who want to work in Greater Bay Area
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
More than 1,700 young people up to the age of 35 were “successfully” placed by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), according to a statement from the Office of the Secretary for Economy and Finance. This value corresponds to 60% of candidates who participated in the three recruitment sessions co-held by DSAL and the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ), between June and August, showing an “increasing trend in the number of young people placed”.
During a meeting of the Working Group for the Coordination of Employment Promotion, Tai Kin Ip also called on employers to establish contact with DSAL, in order to “help residents who meet the conditions to integrate into the job market as quickly as possible”, referring to the priority of hiring local workers, in public works and services.
Furthermore, the Secretary for Economy and Finance assured that the Working Group will continue “to strengthen support for employment, helping young people to accumulate more practical experience in the workplace and integrate smoothly into the job market”.
Meanwhile, DSEDJ launched, in collaboration with DSAL, the “Financing Plan for Professional Careers of Young People in Macau in the Greater Bay Area”, with the aim of “promoting the professional development of young people in Macau and their proactive integration into the general context of the country's development”, it can be read.
The initiative aims to provide financial support “to young people from Macau interested in developing their careers in the diversified industries of the Greater Bay Area”, up to five thousand patacas per month, over a maximum cumulative period of 18 months. Cities covered by the program include Guangzhou, Shenzhen, Zhuhai, Foshan, Huizhou, Dongguan, Zhongshan, Jiangmen and Zhaoqing, as well as the Hengqin Deep Cooperation Zone.
Until September 2026, young people holding a Resident Identity Card, up to 35 years of age and with an associate degree or higher academic qualifications, will be able to apply. In addition, candidates must have contracted, in 2025, with an employer listed on the website “Financing Plan for Professional Careers of Young People in Macau in the Greater Bay Area” of DSEDJ, or on the “Guangdong Public Employment and Recruitment Services Platform of the ‘Human Resources and Social Security Department of Guangdong Province’”, and with a working schedule of at least 30 hours per week”.
Applications can be made on the DSEDJ website, or in person, presenting the application form, identity document, proof of academic qualifications and a copy of the employment contract. The organization will notify candidates of the result within 45 days, counting from the last day of the month in which the necessary documents were submitted. Support will be awarded in phases to eligible candidates, according to DSEDJ.
In turn, DSAL will continue to launch, until the end of the year, internship plans in Mainland China and Macau relating to the four main industries", for a total of 400 jobs. The organization will collect companies' recruitment intentions after completing the internship, as well as present the respective employment monitoring situation in subsequent meetings.
Until September, eight internship plans were launched in Mainland China, and since last month, the services have been developing the “Creating Better Job Perspectives” initiative.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Amagao presents posters of Pablo Picasso and Joan Miró</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/amagao-apresenta-cartazes-de-pablo-picasso-joan-miro/</link><description>Three dozen posters by famous Spanish artists Pablo Picasso and Joan Miró will be on display at Galeria Amagao starting this Thursday. The exhibition, part of Spain's National Day, exemplifies the interaction between art and graphic design

VÍTOR REBELO
 
Posters that reflect the artistic styles of Pablo Picasso and Joan Miró, mark another event promoted by Galeria Amagao, in an exhibition that will open on Thursday, October 9th, at 6:30 pm.
In the space located at the Artyzen Hotel, art lovers will be able to appreciate 30 posters, 18 by Miró and 12 by Picasso, which promote exhibitions by the two artists. The posters designed for Sala Gaspar, in Barcelona, ​​“exemplify the interaction between art and graphic design”, according to the exhibition’s introductory note.
Amagao highlights that these icons of modernism also used their creativity to promote artistic events, “reflecting their innovative visions”.
Joan Miró, with his surreal and playful style, “employs vibrant colors and organic shapes to create an evocative and dreamlike atmosphere”. Pablo Picasso, “with his bold cubist style, produces geometric shapes and strong colors, transforming advertisements into works of art”, highlights the promotional text for the exhibition, which will be open to the public until November 9th.
These artists, considered one of the biggest names in 20th century painting, promoted significant events, “strengthened the link between art and visual design and continue to be studied for their contributions to modern art”, highlights the curatorship of the exhibition, under the responsibility of Lina Ramadas, adding that “the works of Picasso and Miró show how art can transcend mere functionality, uniting aesthetics and message in a remarkable way”.
The exhibition of the works of the two icons who had a great influence and impact on the history of art, through canvas, was also designed as part of Spain's National Day, which is celebrated three days after the opening of the event, on October 12th, as a result of a partnership with a Barcelona gallery.
In essence, posters by visual artists refer to creations by the authors themselves to publicize works, exhibitions or events, or to pieces of art that are posters in themselves, such as graphic works of an artistic and collectible nature, which can be appreciated for their aesthetic value and not just for their informative function.
Over these three years, Galeria Amagao has exhibited works of art from different techniques and styles, such as drawing, painting, watercolor, engraving, screen printing, photography, digital art, sculpture and design.
“Macau is a small city and home to many graphic designers who have won awards in local and international competitions”, says the statement signed by Lina Barradas and Victor Hugo Marreiros, artists, co-founders and current owners of Amagao. “Soon, the gallery will be pleased to add local graphic design works to its list of exhibitions”, he adds.
Focusing on contemporary art and the cultural connection with the Portuguese-speaking world, Amagao, managed by Galeria 57, was founded in 2022, having held several exhibitions. One of this year's highlights was the exhibition “Portuguese Art – Dialogues of Creativity”, which included fifty works of painting and sculpture, produced by 24 Portuguese artists, in what was the first event integrated into the “June, Month of Portugal” program.
In addition, in 2025, it also launched “Bom momento”, with 32 authors from 12 different countries, including Brazil, China and Portugal, and “Year 3”, which marked the gallery's third anniversary, with works by 29 artists, many of them from Macau and with 30x30cm canvases.
Lina Ramadas told TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper that “two more exhibitions” will appear by the end of the year, the themes of which will be announced soon.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Pipe reserve tested on Rua dos Mercadores</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/reserva-de-tubagens-testada-na-rua-dos-mercadores/</link><description>The Rua dos Mercadores will close to car traffic in a phased manner from tomorrow, due to the pilot project to reserve connecting pipes. The first phase will take place from the 9th to the 26th of October, and the second from the 27th of October to the 7th of November.
Some sections of the streets of Camilo Pessanha and Estalagens will be converted to the opposite direction, thus ensuring access for vehicles for loading and unloading operations, picking up and dropping off passengers and entering and leaving the car park. According to the Road Works Coordination Group, the intervention will be carried out in three periods to minimize the impact of the works.
The third phase (from 8 to 27 November) will focus on internal roads in the area. Consequently, the streets of Mercadores, Estalagens and Camilo Pessanha, previously closed to traffic in the opposite direction, will be reopened on November 8th.
A statement from the CPSP, Traffic Affairs Services (DSAT) and Public Works Services states that “to increase efficiency”, work will take place from Monday to Saturday, between 8:00 am and 10:00 pm, and on Sundays and holidays, between 8:00 am and 8:00 pm. The Coordination Group demanded that the responsible contractors deploy more staff, ensure adequate management of the site and strictly monitor the progress of the works.
Regarding buses, route 18 (to Rua dos Currais) will not stop at the stops “Almeida Ribeiro/Tai Fung”, “Rua dos Mercadores”, “Rua das Estalagens” and “R. Cinco Outubro”, provisionally between 10am on the 9th of October and the 7th of November. During this period, passengers will be able to use the “Ponte 16” and “Rua do Tarrafeiro” stops as an alternative.
Several government entities, together with the contractors, organized information sessions and multiple site visits. These initiatives aimed to communicate and collect opinions from residents' associations, traders and vendors in the area, as well as coordinating the distribution of information leaflets. Additionally, temporary traffic measures and provisions were presented to the Central Zone Transit Advisory Board and Community Services Advisory Board.
This plan constitutes the first pilot project to reserve connecting pipes in Macau. In addition to piping and drainage connections for four new buildings, it includes the early installation of ducts for six future developments in the area. “This initiative will serve as a valuable reference for advanced planning of connection piping”, concludes the note.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Foshan Lion Dance won MGM tournament</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/danca-leao-de-foshan-venceu-torneio-da-mgm/</link><description>Twenty-one lion dance teams from 13 countries and regions participated in an international lion dance championship, promoted by MGM, setting a record in the history of the event. A team from Foshan finished first in the main freestyle event
 
The 12th edition of the International Lion Dance Championship – MGM Cup featured 21 teams, a record number since the competition was created in 2020. Thirteen countries and regions were represented, including Malaysia, Indonesia, Singapore, Thailand, Vietnam, Myanmar, Japan, Australia, Italy and Brunei, in addition to groups from Macao SAR, totaling around two hundreds and a half of athletes.
For the third consecutive year, the tournament promoted by MGM took place at Largo da Barra. However, on the second day, and due to Typhoon Matmo, which forced the raising of sign 8, the organization transferred the junior, youth and women's categories to the Macau Forum Pavilion. According to the operator, “the change of stage did not diminish the enthusiasm of the many fans” of this type of sport-spectacle.
The highlight, in competitive terms, was the Freestyle class, which included 14 groups, with the victory belonging to the “Foshan Nanhai Huangfeihong Zhonglian Cable Dragon and Lion Dance and Martial Arts Association”. In second and third place were the Yiwei Athletic Association of Singapore and the “Myanmar Long De Chuan Ren Dragon and Lion Dance Association”, respectively.
In the lower categories, aimed at promoting the sport among the new generation of practitioners, the “MGM Golden Lion Troupe” was crowned champion in juniors, ahead of a second team from the same operator. The third place would be occupied by Grupo Desportivo Chong Son, also from Macau.
In the youth division, Shenzhen Yidetang Dragon and Lion Dance Association received the highest score from the judges, followed by “Ou Kong Si San Kit Yee Tong” and Myanmar Long De Chuan Ren Dragon and Lion Dance Association.
The title in the women's championship went to the Mak Chi Leong Dragon and Lion Dance Association of Macau, with the Yiwei Athletic Association of Singapore and the Chinese Martial Arts and Dragon and Lion Dance Association of Hong Kong taking second and third place, respectively.
At the end of the competitions and awarding of prizes, the vice-president of the Macau General Wushu Association and veteran referee of the championship, considered that “this year's competition reached a new level, as the general technical level of the teams was exceptionally high, and the enthusiastic response from the live audience was the best proof of this”. Pun King Man stressed that “especially the organizers’ commitment to our cultural legacy, by creating dedicated divisions for junior, youth and female competitors, has provided a development roadmap for formations around the world, which is vital to this legacy of our culture.”
The entire event was again broadcast live via MGM's official Facebook page, long-shi.com Facebook and YouTube channels and 15 streaming platforms in mainland China, attracting nearly three million online and offline viewers.
The Lion Dance Festival, held simultaneously, included a special exhibition with the lion dance cultures of China, Japan and Korea, which will remain for public enjoyment at Naval Shipyards nº1 until October 12th. More than 100 people signed up to participate in the event's workshops and sharing sessions. The celebration extended to the community, with lion dance groups from the three countries performing a 'flash mob' in the Três Candeeiros area, interacting closely with the public.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Community tourism “lively” until the end of the month</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/turismo-comunitario-animado-ate-ao-final-mes/</link><description>After the celebrations for China's National Day and the Mooncake Festival are over, the Tourism Bureau continues with the cultural program for the rest of the month, with a variety of recreational activities

The Directorate of Tourism Services (DST) has planned a series of activities for the rest of October, within the scope of the thematic areas “Traveling around Macau”, “Flavors of Macau” and “Fun on the coast”. By the end of the month, DST hopes to attract more residents and tourists to community neighborhoods, with a series of initiatives such as shows, workshops and games, among others.
The “Festival of Rua Cinco de Outubro”, whose agenda included exhibitions, an interactive theater, fairs, live shows and games, ends today, in a celebration of the “stories of Macau” and the “characteristics of community areas”. Until the 12th, the “Carnival of Autumn Delights” will also take place at Largo Camões, where visitors will be able to taste typical Macau delicacies, watch shows and participate in gastronomic workshops.
Until the 26th, Rua dos Ervanários, Rua de Nossa Senhora do Amparo, Rua da Tercena and Beco de Chôn Sal will serve as fair spaces, with workshops and interactive games inserted into the “urban reality of the neighborhoods”. According to DST, this event “will help promote community brands in the Rua dos Ervanários and Armazém Velho area”, as well as “promote the exploration of the old neighborhoods by visitors”.
Every Saturday and Sunday, participants in the sea tour “Exploring Mysteries of the Gods by the Sea” will depart from Ponte-Cais da Barra, towards Coloane, on a visit to the Temple of Tam Kong and the Temple of Tin Hau, “to discover the legends of Macau's unique sea deities”.
There will also be a “video mapping” show, on the facade of the Na Tcha Temple, every night until the 30th, and a light projection alluding to the Na Tcha festivities, in Pátio do Espinho. Furthermore, on the 4th, 5th, 11th and 12th of October, in Pátio do Espinho and on the 18th, 19th, 24th and 25th of October, in front of the Na Tcha Temple, fairs will be held with local crafts, traditional gastronomy and cultural and creative products from Na Tcha, so that the public can experience “in an immersive way the unique charm of the National Intangible Cultural Heritage” and the “Beliefs and Customs of Na Tcha de Macau”.
Some activities require pre-registration and payment. DST guarantees that it “will continue to promote community tourism through the variety of activities brought by the Financial Support Program” to “further stimulate the community economy”.
The “National Day Fair – Mid-Autumn Lantern Night”, which took place at the entrance of Jardim Cidade das Flores, the “Macao Arts and Culture Fair and the Mid-Autumn Festival Romantic Walk”, which took place in Praça de Eduardo Marques, and the “2nd Macau Vegetarian Fair”, which took place in the Kun Iam Tong Garden area, concluded.
 
“PopMart” with more than 90 million views on social media
According to preliminary data from the Tourism Office, the “Pop Mart Tour in Macau” initiative attracted 723 thousand people to facilities throughout the city and around 45 thousand obtained limited edition postal tickets, between 6 June and 21 September. Partnerships were also made with influencers from Mainland China, accounting for more than 450 live broadcasts and publications, which resulted in a number of views exceeding 90 million. The installations featuring the characters “Baby Molly”, Crybaby”, “Dimoo” and “Labubu” attracted visitors to Calçada da Igreja de São Lázaro, Praça de Luís de Camões, Largo de Santo Agostinho and the Leisure Area on Rua do Pai Kok da Taipa.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Wynn recognized for its cultural role</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/wynn-reconhecida-pelo-seu-papel-cultural/</link><description>“Wynn Culture” was part of the “Summit Mechanism on Cultural and Artistic Cooperation in the Guangdong Greater Bay Area”, having been distinguished for its contributions to the region’s artistic and cultural scene
 
The “Wynn Culture” brand was selected to join the “Summit Mechanism on Cultural and Artistic Cooperation in the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area”. During the mechanism's annual conference, the brand was distinguished “for its efforts in boosting the development of culture and arts” and its commitment to “cultural and artistic exchange” in the region, according to a press release.
“Wynn Culture” is a new initiative by Wynn, “to support the strategic vision of Macau as a center of exchange and cooperation with roots in Chinese heritage and with diverse cultures thriving in harmony”. The brand aims to reinforce the Macao SAR's unique role as a “gateway between China and the world”, expanding the global reach of the country's culture through this “vibrant” city.
As a new member of the mechanism, the gaming operator intends to “fully leverage its strengths” in terms of cultural resources, international networks and innovation. Wynn promises to get involved with more cultural and artistic organizations in the Greater Bay Area and in co-curated projects “that encompass regional traits and a global vision”, in a contribution to “elevating the cultural power and international influence of Macau and the region”.
This year, the mechanism's conference was under the theme “Mutual Growth, Construction and Integration: Cultural and Artistic Innovation and Development of the Greater Bay Area in the New Era”. During the event, ideas such as establishing a collaborative mechanism for innovation, consolidating advantageous resources and developing a high-level talent hub between Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau were discussed.
Under the sponsorship of the Federation of Literary and Artistic Circles of China (CFLAC) and the Macao SAR Secretariat for Social Affairs and Culture, this year's edition was organized by the Federation of Cultural Sector Associations of Macau and the Federation of Literary and Artistic Circles of Guangdong. The event was attended by officials from government departments, cultural federations and cultural and artistic associations from cities in the Greater Bay Area.
The mechanism was co-founded, in 2021, by several cultural associations and federations from the nine cities of the Pearl River Delta, having driven “collaborative innovations” and “advances”, as well as launching around a dozen projects, such as an artistic innovation forum, cultural exchanges and cinematic art weeks, among other initiatives.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>'Unknown' work by Picasso presented at auction in Paris</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/obra-desconhecida-de-picasso-apresentada-em-leilao-em-paris/</link><description>A portrait by Spanish painter Pablo Picasso of his muse Dora Maar was presented at an auction house in Paris, a painting practically “unknown” to the general public, according to experts.
With the title “Bust of a Woman with a Flower Hat (Dora Maar)”, the painting was painted in July 1943 and remained with the owner family since 1944. The work is a painting “unknown” to the general public because it has never been exhibited, except in a private exhibition organized by the painter in his studio in the 1940s, explained auctioneer Christophe Lucien.
The canvas, cubist in style and full of colors, shows Dora Maar's face adorned with flowers and a sad expression.
“It is an exceptional work, which establishes a milestone in the history of art and that of Picasso”, highlighted Agnès Sevestre-Barbé, a Picasso specialist who presented the painting.
When he painted the painting, Picasso already knew who would be his new companion, Françoise Gilot. This could explain the look of sadness on Dora Maar's face, according to Sevestre-Barbé.
The artist often painted the muse, who was his partner for a decade. Until 1944, she did so with “very hard features”, but in this latest portrait, she is much “softer”, they emphasized. The vibrant colors are also exceptional, at a time when Picasso used dark tones.
The painting is almost a “raw” work, never varnished or restored, and is only protected by simple rods, explained Lucien enthusiastically.
The current owners inherited the work from their grandfather. It was acquired during the Nazi occupation, shortly before the liberation of Paris, between May and June 1944.
The painting, which will be auctioned on October 24th, is “valued at eight million euros”, according to Lucien, a low projection that “could skyrocket”, taking into account the amounts paid for other works by the author.
"A painting [by Picasso] and, moreover, a portrait of Dora Maar, is something unusual. It is even rarer to sell it in France, as happens on the market in general," Olivier Picasso, the painter's grandson, told AFP.
Several portraits of Dora Maar were sold mainly in the USA, in large English-speaking auction houses. In 2006, “Dora Maar with a Cat” earned $95 million in New York, after “Woman Sitting in the Garden” (1938), acquired in 1999 for $49 million.
The artist born in Málaga, who died more than half a century ago, has at least half a dozen paintings that have sold more than 100 million dollars, including “Woman with a Clock”, sold in November 2023 for 139.3 million dollars, one of the highest prices recorded for works by the painter.
Until now, experts in the Spanish master's work only knew about the portrait, authenticated by the Picasso Administration, in black and white, thanks to the official catalog of his works, according to the Drouot auction house. Some photographs by Brassaï, a friend of Picasso, taken in 1944 in the painter's Parisian studio, also attested to the existence of the painting.
The date of July 11, 1943 is on the back of the canvas, and the artist's signature appears on the front, in the upper left corner. Picasso used to sign his works when they left the studio, which is also the case with this one, since, in Brassaï's images, the canvas does not contain his name.
Dora Maar, whose real name was Henriette Théodora Markovic (1907-1997), was primarily a photographer and became known for her numerous portraits of Picasso.
Picasso made several paintings of her, such as “Woman Who Weeps”, which portrays her “profound nature”, he said. She also inspired him to create a series of paintings with the theme “Seated Women”.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>