<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Mandates shows “strong displeasure” before criticism of the EU report</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-mostra-forte-desagrado-perante-criticas-em-relatorio-da-ue/</link><description>The Macao government has expressed “strong displeasure” and “firm opposition” to the European Union annual report, according to which the space for “pluralist voices” in Macau is less and less in politics and society. For the executive, comments on the political and social development of the territory are “infactual and biased”. Already the Commissioner of Foreign Affairs of the Popular Republic of China stressed that "Macao affairs are totally internal affairs in China", and "any external interference, attack or defamation will certainly be useless"
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The European Union (EU) considers that the space for "pluralist voices" in Macau is less and less, pointing out that the legislative changes that intended to apply the "Macao Macao governed by patriots" principle came to introduce more restrictions on the territory. Moreover, he notes that freedoms and fundamental rights have been "deteriorating". Repairs are part of the 2024 annual report on the MSAR - a document that has been launched annually by the European Commission since the transfer. In the face of criticism -which Macau received with “strong displeasure” and “firm opposition” -the commissioner of Foreign Affairs of the People's Republic of China in the MSAR has asked the EU to “immediately to interfere, anyway, in the matters of Masters and in the internal affairs of China”.
In the report, analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the EU begins by remembering that it supports the principle “a country, two systems”, and its application in accordance with the Basic Law, pointing out that it aims to “ensure that the way of life, the rule of law and the protection of fundamental rights and freedoms in Macau are unchanged” for a period of 50 years.
Then he says that "from a political point of view, autonomy and freedoms and fundamental rights, which should be protected by at least 2049, continue to deteriorate." "The year was marked by two legislative changes to apply the" Macao Patriotas "doctrine, which further limit the space for pluralistic voices in Macao; and for the formation of the government of MSAR, in its sixth term, led by Sam Hou Fai, the first head of the born executive on the continent."
In particular, the EU refers to the amendment to the Electoral Law to the Legislative Assembly (AL), but also makes reference to the moved law on the occasion of the possession. From his perspective, "the new legislation further limits the space for pluralistic voices in both politics and society."
In this context, it recalls that under the Electoral Law the State Defense Security Commission (CSDE) now issues a binding opinion in order to determine whether candidates for elections defend the basic law and are faithful to masters. A decision that is not susceptible to judicial appeal. “The new system gives the central government a direct influence on the elections for Macao's Al”, points out the EU, since, it says, CSDE is chaired by the Chief Executive, being the director of the Advisor Connection Office for National Security Affairs and two other members of the National Security Technical Counselors. It is recalled that in 2021 and this year also disqualified several candidates for legislative elections.
On the other hand, in the document, the EU note that Sam Hou Fai became the first leader of the since born in the interior of China, "which raised questions regarding the maintenance of the validity of the Macao's" Administration for the Macao's Administration ". It also recalls that, for the election of the Chief Executive, only 6,265 people from a population of 686,600 could vote.
In the chapter of rights, freedoms and equal opportunities, the report states that "freedom of meeting continued under pressure," since for the fourth consecutive year the vigil was not allowed by the victims of Tiananmen's repression. Also "freedom of the press and freedom of expression remained under pressure." At this point, the EU exemplifies with the statements of the Macao Journalists Association, which last year asked the government to eliminate restrictions on journalistic work and also realized that some media were "urged to remove their articles due to political pressures."
In turn, "the space for the defense of the promotion of the rights of LGBTIQ+ persons continued to be limited." In this case, the report recalls the episode in which the Cultural Institute removed from the scene a show with transformists who was part of the Fringe festival. In the opposite direction, the EU also tells that "two groups of civil society were able to organize community activities during the month of pride in June."
 
Government says comments are “infactual and biased”
Following the publication of the report, the Macao government came to say that, in the document, the EU "makes some infractual and biased comments on the political and social development" of the territory, including "accusations without foundations" regarding the alteration of the electoral law to AL and others. "The government of the mandate manifests its strong displeasure and firm opposition for such an occurrence," can be read in a statement.
The executive later says that the masters "has strictly implemented" the principle "a country, two systems" and the basic law, as well as "achieved a rapid economic development, maintaining stability and social harmony." At the same time, the note says, the authorities have guaranteed residents, “broadly”, “their rights and freedoms of expression, the press, meeting and others”.
"The results obtained are notable, and widely recognized by the international community and with full and full agreement of MSAR residents, which constitutes fundamental facts that cannot be denied by the European Union," the government considers.
Regarding the electoral law and the law of oaths on the occasion of the act of inauguration, the Executive of the MSAR says that it has taken into account "the legal traditions and the social reality of Macao". "During the review process, the Government of the MSAR widely listened to the opinions of the population of Macao and the interested personalities," he said, also saying that, while the changes intend to realize the "Macao Patriotas" principle "have perfected the electoral systems and oath procedures, contributing to successful implementation and the stable and lasting practice of the principle, two, two country systems'.
"Macao affairs are China's internal affairs," the government said, saying that the annual publication of the report "constitutes an interference in the internal affairs of China and Masters, violating the fundamental principles of international law." "Being an important partnership of China and MSAR, the EU has expressed its support for the principle" a country, two systems "and its implementation in Macao. We hope that the EU fulfills its words, more actions that can benefit and promote the development of bilateral relations," he concluded.
In the same vein, the spokesman for the MNE of China's MNE in the MSA has expressed “strong discontent and firm opposition” to the report, arguing that “ignores the facts, it is full of prejudice, defama by bad faith the practice of 'a country, two systems' in Macao, the law and the situation of human rights in Macao and constitutes a rude interference in China affairs.”
It also says that "the freedom of expression of residents, freedom of the press and labor rights are fully guaranteed by law," this is "an undisputed fact and recognized by any impartial person." "Macao's matters are totally internal issues in China. Any external interference, attack or defamation will certainly be useless," said the MNE Commissioner.</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Civil servants questioned whether they think vote on the legislatures</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/funcionarios-publicos-questionados-sobre-se-pensam-votar-nas-legislativas/</link><description>Macao entities and public services questioned employees about whether they intend to vote in the elections for the Legislative Assembly on Sunday, and demanded justifications to those who said no, some of these workers revealed.
Five workers, who asked not to be identified for fearing reprisals, confirmed to Lusa that earlier this week they were questioned about the plans for the elections.
By September 1, the Chief Executive had already sent a circular to ask all civil servants to vote in the elections to prove their patriotism. All workers - including staff of at least two public universities - had to sign a document to confirm that they learned of the circular signed by Sam Hou Fai.
Regarding the intention of voting or not, the employees heard by Lusa said the question was not raised in writing, but orally, in some cases in seemingly informal conversations.
In cases where workers admitted not to have plans to vote, the superiors or administrative staff stated that it was necessary to justify the decision, in writing.
"When I said I couldn't vote ... My boss asked me why, saying he had to explain above," said one worker.
The five employees - some of whom with decades of service in Macao entities and public services - confirmed that this is the first time they have been questioned about whether or not to participate in elections.
"It's strange, because it never happened before," said one worker, who recalled that previous governments had, on the contrary, "traditionally appealed to civil servants to remain neutral."
At the circular of September 1, Sam Hou Fai recalled that the new civil service statute will require all workers to defend the basic law and loyalty to China. The revision of the Statute, which will only come into force on November 1, provides that civil servants, including those of Portuguese nationality, may be dismissed if they do “contrary acts” to the oath.
Sam Hou Fai argued that vote "is precisely a relevant demonstration of the defense of basic law and faithfulness to masters."
According to the new electoral law, passed in April 2024, "those who publicly incite voters not to vote, vote in white or null, are punished with prison up to three years."
But on 6 September, the chairman of the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly, Seng Ioi Man, assured that “the question of disciplinary responsibility” will not be placed on civil servants who do not vote.
Residents go to the polls on Sunday to elect, for direct suffrage, 14 of the 33 deputies of al. Another 12 are chosen by indirect suffrage through associations, and seven will be appointed by the government leader.
Five years ago, Macau registered the highest abstention ever (57.6%) and more than 5,200 people voted blank in a process marked by the exclusion by the Electoral Commission of five lists and 21 candidates, 15 of which pro-democracy.
This year, there are six lists for direct suffrage, eight less than in 2021 and the lowest number since 1988, when there were only five deputies chosen by direct vote.
The State Security Defense Commission excluded in July all 12 candidates from two lists, considering them “not defenders of the basic or non-faithful law”. One of them was the list of still deputy Ron Lam, one of the government's most critical voices in Parliament.
On August 26, Seng Ioi Man said public transport will be free on September 14, "to facilitate the exercise of voters' voting rights."
On the other hand, a resident of Macao who studies at the University of Beijing told Lusa that the public institution was made available to pay the plane trips to students wishing to return to the region to vote on Sunday. “Our university asked the leader of the Macau Cultural Association to contact us,” explained the student, who asked not to be identified by fears of reprisals.
"If we want to vote and only return to Beijing after September 14, the university will subsidize a plane ticket in the economic class from Macao to Beijing," he said.
"If we are already in Beijing, but we want to go back to Macau to vote, the university will subsidize a round trip," added the student.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cybersecurity rules will have “binding legal strength”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/normas-sobre-ciberseguranca-vao-ter-forca-legal-vinculativa/</link><description>According to Chao Tong Leong, head of the Secretary for Security Office, the government will give “binding legal force” to “technical guidelines for vulnerabilities,” by the end of the year. In August, Deputy Ho Ion Sang had urged the government to consider the creation of an exclusive “data security law” for Macau
 
Pedro Milheirão
The Government provides for “binding legal force” to the “technical guidelines for vulnerabilities management” from the Cyberrsecurity Alert and Response Center (Caric), “later this year,” said Chao Tong Leong, head of the Secretary for Security Office, in response to a written Ho Ion Sang. Last month, the deputy asked the government to evaluate the need and feasibility of an exclusive “data security law” for the MSAR and the creation of an audit mechanism for government data security.
Chao explained that since the cybersecurity law in 2019, the government has ensured “the security of networks, systems and computer data of critical infrastructure operators”. In addition, the State Secret Protection Law “also imposes rigorous demands,” he continued. "The Government of MSAR (…) has established a multiple protection system to safeguard the secret of state, network data and important personal data," he reiterated.
In addition, Chao Tong Leong also clarified that, under the Caric Guidelines issued in January last year, several cybersecurity tests were performed for operators. He also added that the respective operators will be required to "identify and correctly correct security vulnerabilities," in order to "reinforce the resilience of cybersecurity of critical infrastructure."
Another of the issues that Ho Ion Sang raised at the time was the need for more lectures, courses and formations with the population, in order to lead more residents to “fully know the important meaning of data security management”. For its part, Chao asserted that the Judiciary Police (PJ) "has carried out education work on data security, intended for the professional sector and the general public." PJ has even released online information on the prevention of cyber crimes and burlas, noted.
The Caric itself holds a cybersecurity forum annually with critical infrastructure operators with representatives of the Directorate of Personal Data Protection Services (DSPDP), experts and academics in the country, recalled the head of Wong Sio Chak's office. DSPDP has also been “promoted to disseminate the law of personal data protection to social service institutions, private companies and public services”, as well as organized lectures on “protection of privacy with intelligence”.</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Secretary Lam urges teachers to “embrace the Age of AI”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/secretaria-lam-insta-professores-abracar-era-da-ia/</link><description>On the occasion of Teacher's Day, the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture appealed to teachers to “embrace the age of artificial intelligence”, “guide students to be aware of cutting -edge technologies”, “try new methods and pedagogical means” and “actively participate in curriculum reform”.
 
In a “crucial phase of development” in which Macau “is facing opportunities and challenges resulting from changes in world education”, the secretary for social affairs and culture, LAM, expects teachers to “embrace the age of artificial intelligence (IA), constantly improving professional quality, guiding students to be aware of cutting -edge technologies, and encourages them to value and love science”, in order to cultivate more talent. High quality interdisciplinary.
Moreover, in a speech given in a commemorative activity of the teacher's day, organized by the Macao Education Association, the secretary urged teachers to “be brave to explore, to try new methods and pedagogical means, and to actively participate in curriculum reforms, teaching and the model of formation of staff”, in the sense of “making contributions to‘ the coordination and promotion of integrated development of education and technology and technology and technology. pictures'".
The ruler also expects teachers to guide students to develop a correct view of the world and life as well as adequate spiritual values. At the same time, teachers were urged to cultivate patriotism among students to ensure the continuity of the spirit of “love for the homeland and macao”.
Generally speaking, Lam appealed to teaching staff to “transmit the great spirit of the war of resistance and the glorious traditions of the educational sector”, forming more qualified pictures that love the homeland and Macao.
The secretary also takes the opportunity to reiterate that the government always attributes “high importance” to the growth and development of teachers. On the one hand, “provides opportunities for training and development space for teachers”, and on the other hand, “has continuously increased the conditions and position of teachers, striving to foster a good social atmosphere in which teachers are respected and education values ​​education”.
In addition, LAM has noted that more and more schools are part of the education of “Love to the Fatherland and Macao” in daily teaching, which contributes to “fully strengthening the feeling of identity and national pride of students”.
In general, he said that the government has defined a series of policies and plans, has constantly reinforcing investment in education, and is committed to raising the quality of education, optimizing the distribution of educational resources and promoting justice in education.</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Caipirinha to the sound of bossa nova at the Lusofonia Festival</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/caipirinha-ao-som-de-bossa-nova-festival-da-lusofonia/</link><description>BRAZILIAN MUSICAN JOAO GILBERTO, 77, ACKNOWLEDGES THE AUDIENCE DURING HIS PRESENTATION LATE AT NIGHT ON AUGUST 24, 2008 AT THE Municipal Theater in Rio de Janeiro. JOAO GILBERTO, CONSIDED THE "FATHER" OF THE BOSSA NEW HOLDING WITH TOM JOBIM AND VINICIUS OF MORAES, IS PRESENTING A SHOW TO CELEBRATE THE 50TH ANNIVERARY OF THE BOSSA NEW.  AFP Photo/Ari Versiani (Photo Credit Should Read Ar Versiani/AFP/Getty Images)



A musical theme returns to the Brazil tent for the Lusofonia Festival. Bossa Nova was chosen for this year. Jane Martins, the main responsible for organizing the tent, will bring Macao Old Discs in Vinyl, one of the main precursors of this genre of music, João Gilberto. The artist's house has been transformed into a museum and is a replica of this space that the public will be able to enjoy. Another of the associations involved that has already defined what it will present is Mozambique, with the dissemination of the coffee industry, which is in great growth in that African country
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Anyone who goes for a walk through the Lusofonia Festival stalls, along Avenida da Praia, where the Taipa Museum houses are located, will be able to drink a caipirinha in the tent of Brazil to the sound of bossa nova. The musical genre, which emerged in the late 1950s, in Rio de Janeiro, is the theme chosen by Casa do Brasil to mark another edition of the festival, a Lusophone culture celebration event, promoted with the aim of connecting peoples and communities through music, dance, art and gastronomy.
Carla Fellini, president of the Association, told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau that in space it will be possible to enjoy a replica of the house, now transformed into a museum, where she was born and lived one of the main precursors of that type of music, João Gilberto. “He is the father of Bossa Nova, so let's make him a tribute,” he says.
But more details have Jane Martins, formerly responsible for that association, who resided and worked at Mashes for tens of years, currently retired and living in her home country, in the city of Buzios. “28 years ago, since the launch of the first edition of the Lusophony Festival that I assume the main responsibility in organizing the Brazilian tent, always, of course, with the collaboration and participation of the other leaders of Casa do Brasil”, began by referring.
The introduction of Bossa Nova as a theme “It is an old dream”, he stresses, adding that, after the samba, already done earlier, as well as the anthology of Brazilian poetry, now Bossa Nova arises. “I really like this more cultural theme, but when I lived there in Macau I didn't always come to Brazil, so the options were more difficult,” he admits.
About the variety of themes, it states that the association has been concerned over the years not to repeat the decoration of the tent. “We always did it differently,” he says, recalling that two years ago it was the Brazilian coffee. "We offered coffee to people." Last year was shells. “It was more symbolic,” he reinforces.
Jane Martins will travel to the territory with “the possible luggage”, with records, books and photographs, mainly by João Gilberto. "Let's see if we can put to play, since we have to buy the turns," he says, ahead, in a typical Brazilian Portuguese, that "music will have anyway".
In a telephone conversation, he said that the tent will be based on the artist's house “which is now a museum in the bay”, in Juazeiro, the musician's homeland, called Bossa Nova Casa Memorial, painted blue. "It is this replica that we will show the public that pass through our tent, thus, throughout the day, listening to various songs from Bossa Nova and giving a dance foot," he notes.
In terms of decoration, and beyond the main part, consisting of the house-house, there will be other reasons, “all related to music, such as the placement of guitars, and several information about Bossa Nova musicians, such as Vinícius de Moraes, Carlos Jobim, Toquinho, beyond the main, João Gilberto”.
In his research, which “started a good six months ago,” Jane Martins found that there is a lot of Bossa Nova translated into Chinese in Mandarin. “It was very interesting to know that the Chinese sing and play this kind of music a lot in China,” he says.
Most of the material to the tent will be brought from Brazil. "In Taobao there is a lot, even João Gilberto vinyl records, but it is cheaper to take from Brazil, since they are more original, they have dedications."
Having moved to places like Porto Alegre and Florianópolis, “to see things to buy and take to Macao”, he realized that “people are buying old things, because it is in fashion, there are many stores that have antiques, not only music and books, but also CDs”, explains that “all this will be on display in our Lusophony festival tent, and if people are interested, people can buy, people It sells, ”he concludes.
For those who do not know much about Bossa Nova, it should be noted that the music was born from the transformation of samba, especially the "Samba de Raiz", and was strongly influenced by American jazz. The “different beat”, as it was known about 60 or 70 years ago, was defined by an innovative way to play the guitar and a smoother, colloquial and stripped-down song style.
The lyrics, often poetic, focused on themes such as Rio de Janeiro's life and the beauty of the city. Bossa Nova has a more complex harmony, unlike traditional samba, which brought it closer to the cool jazz of the time.
As main names and works that will be prominent in the Brazilian tent at the Lusofonia Festival, besides João Gilberto, there are composers of classics such as “Arriva de Saudade”, “The Happiness” and “Girl of Ipanema”.
 
Mozambique “Show” Café, Casa de Portugal makes secret
Among the other associations that will be once again involved in the festival, only Mozambique has announced to JTM what he intends to do in terms of decoration. This year the theme will be coffee. “This industry has been growing in recent years and so we will try to present something about coffee,” says Angelo Rafael.
The president of the Board of the Association of Friends of Mozambique recalled that the tent is still in preparation, "but we have already been able to bring some coffee from Mozambique." Now, it asserts, "we have to think how we are going to make the decoration, if we will have only coffee or something else."
Speaking of the product that is having a strong investment in the country, it points out that it is an industry that is usually linked to national parks, "but there is also a strong bet in this area." He said that last year "Mozambique historically beat the coffee sales record, therefore, in terms of export."
"It is a small industry compared to other countries, but it is growing in a faint growth," he concludes, considering that this presentation at the Lusophony Festival will also serve to "disseminate our coffee in Macao and Asia."
Also Casa de Portugal will participate, “as always, in the event”, although Amelia António, president of the Lusa Matrix Association, does not want to unravel the theme to present. "We usually do not disclose, so as not to spoil the surprise," he says.
For this year, the guardian admits that the house has “a bit big ambitions”. On the other hand, he notes that "we are a little disturbed by the labor, and therefore one more reason not to do so, do not go to the project to fail."
It is said that "everyone is working so that we can have an interesting, beautiful presence, worthy of the work that has been done over these years." Apart from the main secret, regarding the theme chosen for decoration, Casa de Portugal will feature the festival with artisans, food spaces and the usual traditional games, with awards, during the two weekends.
In addition to Portugal, Brazil and Mozambique, the remaining Lusophone communities will be represented at the event, namely Macau, Cape Verde, Angola, Guinea-Bissau, Sao Tome and Principe, Timor-Leste and Goa, Damão and IUD.
The festival will again feature 10, solo, band, or traditional dance and singing groups, representing the nine countries or regions of the Lusophony spectrum, divided into equal number by the two weekends, and there will be two “head-heads”, one for each period of the party, on Saturday night.
For this year's edition, there are some strong names on the table, which are being negotiated, but there is still no final decision by the main organizing entity, the Cultural Institute, which will have the support of the Tourism Services and the Institute for Municipal Affairs, and should also count on Galaxy as the official sponsor.</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>STD accepts proposals for three community tourism fronts</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dst-aceita-propostas-para-tres-frentes-turismo-comunitario/</link><description>Applications are open for the financial support of the Tourism Services Directorate, to assist the conduct of tourist projects next year. By October, interested local associations should propose activities that take advantage of cultural elements and encourage the community neighborhoods of Macau

Pedro Milheirão
Today starts the period of applications for the three financial support programs of the Tourism Services (STD) “Travel by Macao”, “Macao Flavors” and “amusements on the coastal edge”. The supports are intended for non-profit associations of Macao, which want to organize and develop “diverse activities and projects” under the “Tourism+”, throughout 2026. In a statement, STD said it will receive applications until 5:30 pm on October 3, and provides for a response to results in December.
The “Traveling for Macao” plan aims to take advantage of “the various tourist resources”, combining “cultural, sports, festive and entertainment elements”, in order to stimulate “the active participation of traders, guide tourism consumption in community neighborhoods and attract visitors from around the world”. The program's activities are divided into the categories “Tourism+” and “Combined Cultural and Tourist Activities”.
Regarding the support program “Flavors of Macao”, the proposals will be inserted in the category “gastronomic activities” or “major gastronomy festivals”. Projects should combine “tourism, gastronomy and creativity”, reflecting Macau's “unique” culinary culture and leading “visitors to 'taste' to the rich and diverse experiences and products” of the region.
STD expects to be presented “new ideas” to attract tourists from around the world to “boost the development of the Economics of Gastronomic and Nturnal Tourism” as “Creative City of Gastronomy”.
Regarding the support of the “amusement in the coastal edge” plan, the projects submitted should be “experiences of maritime tour itineraries”. Tourism activities or leisure experiences will have to take advantage of maritime and coastal areas, to “increase global tourist value” and boost the “economic development” of the coastal zone.
Candidates can submit proposals on the STD website through the “Platform for Companies and Associations”. Under the three support programs, STD organized a clarification session for representatives of interested associations. The body believes that “community tourism”, “gastronomic culture and“ leisure in the coastal edge ”can benefit and stimulate the economy of the neighborhoods.
 
Macao Week in Wuhan attracted 255 thousand visitors
Over the course of four days, STD promoted the MSAR, in Hubei province, having attracted about 255,000 visitors to the "Wuhan Customs House Square". According to the body, about 90 “wonderful” shows were presented, including a street dance performance from a group led by “Mak Mak”, the Mascot of the Masheries, and the “Light Show of the Yangtze River”, as well as Portuguese Folk Dance, Lion Dance performances, martial arts, dragon dance and live music. During the promotion, Macao tour operators presented offers such as airplane tickets, stays in hotels and gastronomic experiences, among others, in a joint value of 26 million Renminbis. Prior to the launch of the event, more than 120 tour operators participated in a contact scholarship session to explore business opportunities between Macau, Hubei and Hengqin. In turn, the Institute for Commerce and Investment Promotion (IPIM) organized a contact scholarship session between Hubei and Macau, in which almost 200 representatives of commercial associations and companies in the two regions participated.</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao athlete gives views on the WTT tournament on table tennis</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/atleta-de-macau-da-nas-vistas-torneio-wtt-em-tenis-de-mesa/</link><description>Macao secured the presence of a representative in the round of 16 of the WTT Champions Tournament in table tennis, thanks to the victory of Zhu Yuling, in singular women. The athlete, who occupies the seventh place in the world ranking, defeated Indiana Sreeja Akula. Chinese Lin Shidong and Sun Yingsha, main favorites in men and women, respectively, remain in test and today start participation in the second round. The competition takes place at Macau Dome until Sunday

Victor Rebelo
 
The Champions Tournament in Table Tennis, which brings together the East Asian Games Sports Ship (Macao Dome) the great figures of the sport, continues to have the presence of Zhu Yuling, which in the sixteenth-sized, the 3-0 Indian Sreeja Akula without great difficulty. The partials of 11/5, 11/1 and 11/6 let you notice the superiority of the player of the sabem, who resolved the match in just 18 minutes.
Supported by the house's audience, Zhu Yuling offered a good time of table tennis, especially on the second set, in which he did not give great hypotheses to the opponent, promising to go far in the competition.
Even though the Chinese delegation has brought to the territory a strong selection, which includes players of the world's top top, the representative of Macao, who occupies the seventh place on the international list, may constitute one of the surprises of the tournament. For this, you will have to surpass for now, in the round of 16, Bruna Takahashi. This Brazilian tablet qualified by winning the French of Chinese origin Jia Nan Yuan, with the result of 3-1.
It is recalled that the 30-year-old accredited player from Mianyang Chinese city in Sichuan's province requested the residence in Macao under the qualified staff law since July 2023, a process that was approved by the government last year.
From there, the player began to wear the mashed nightgown, after having represented China since 1995, having won several individual and collective titles. In 2017 it reached the first level of the world ranking. During this time of 2025, Zhu Yuling beat the United States WTT.
In the female sector of the competition that runs until Sunday in the Cotai enclosure, the Chinese Sun Yingsha confirms the number one-header status, having defeated, also in the sixteenth-grandson Anna Hursy, 3-1. The representative of the People's Republic of China faces today, on the night (8:50 pm), the Belgian Bernadette Szocs, from Romania, who beat Ana Godto do Egypt.
Moreover, Number Two, Wang Manyu, also Chinese, exceeded Taiwan's Cheng I-Ching and finds this afternoon ahead of Japanese Ina Hayata, in a scheduled match for 2:20 pm.
In this category, Macau lost one of his representatives, as Kuan Cheok Lam was defeated by Wang Yidi, from China, fifth pre-designed 3-0, partial 11/3, 11/2 and 11/3.
In the male condition, Macau also no longer has any athlete, after he Chan Fai was beaten by the French Simon Gauzy, 3-0 (11/4, 11/4 and 11/5).
Meanwhile, the Chinese entourage maintains in the world's number one, Lin Shidong, who learned to the round of 16 by overcoming Kao Cheng-Jui of Taiwan by 3-0. Today will face South Korean Oh Junsung, in a match scheduled for 2:55 pm.
It also follows in front of the Second Storage Head, Wang Chuqin (China), after beating Japanese Sora Matsushima 3-1.
Another favorites is Brazilian Hugo Calderano, who performs in Macao with the best room status in the world. He won in the first round of South Korea Jaehyun 3-0.
The Macao WTT Champions Tournament, sanctioned by the “World Table Tennis”, is organized together by the Sport Institute and the Galaxy, with the participation of 32 athletes in each of the categories, representing more than twenty countries and regions.
The race has a total monetary prize of 800,000 US dollars, about 6.4 million patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Electoral campaign ends today</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/campanha-eleitoral-termina-hoje/</link><description>The election campaign ends today and tomorrow is a day of reflection. On Sunday, the ballot boxes will be open between 09h00 and 9 pm, and citizens can vote to choose the deputies who will sit in the Legislative Assembly over the next four years. Public transport will be free on that day, having the authorities prepared a number of other transports to facilitate travel
 
The elections for the Legislative Assembly (AL) take place this Sunday, with the polls opening at 09h00 and ending at 21h00. However, the period for the election campaign ends today at 24h00, being tomorrow reflection day, so "no electoral propaganda activity is allowed," recalled the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal).
In this sense, until 24h00 today, the mandates of the candidates, candidates, mandates of the candidacy committee, as well as the persons responsible for posting or allowing the affixation, “must remove or eliminate all materials, messages or information”, including on the Internet, “that may attract the public's attention to one or more candidates and who, expressly or implicitly, suggested to voters to vote for these candidates”.
During the period of reflection and on election day, “no person, including candidates, candidates, support teams or the general public, should wear clothing or other objects in public places that display order numbers, names, abbreviations or symbols that clearly identify a candidate list, under penalty of constituting illegal propaganda”, warns Caeal.
For these elections, it is recalled, 328,611 unique voters are registered, according to the data advanced by Caeal President Seng Ioi Man, in August, but which may have undergone some change.
According to Caeal, more than 1,400 employees of nearly 60 public services were formed to be at the voting assemblies and respond to any arising situations. There will be 37 polling stations, where 38 voting assemblies will be available for direct suffrage and five for indirect suffrage.
To facilitate the displacement of citizens to voting assemblies, the authorities have decided that the light meter and bus careers will be free during the 14th, except for night careers, according to an order published in an official bulletin. In addition, there will be five special lines of buses purposely created for the electoral act.
These are the first legislative elections to be held since the Electoral Law for the Legislative Assembly was reviewed, which has reinforced the “Macao governed by patriots” principle. It should be noted that the incitement of abstention and white or null vote are infringered under the changes, subject to a maximum penalty of three years in prison.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Transfrontic arbitration resolves consumer conflict</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/arbitragem-transfronteirica-resolve-conflito-de-consumo/</link><description>A consumer conflict between Macao and Shenzhen was first resolved through transfronical arbitration. A video conferencing service, offered by the consumer councils on both sides, has charged the litigation, marking new progress in the context of cooperation between the two organisms
 
The Macao Consumer Council (CC), in cooperation with Shenzhen's homologous organism, offered for the first time a transfrontic arbitration service for a consumer of that Chinese city and a trade establishment of the MSAR. According to the CC, the consumer conflict in question was resolved by the two organizations, marking new progress in the scope of in -depth cooperation between Macao and Shenzhen consumer councils.
The case refers to a consumption made by a Shenzhen resident during a visit to Macao, where it filed a dispute with a commercial establishment. After receiving the respective complaint, the CC interfered with the conflict, tried to grant the litigating parts and recommended that they would submit the case to the Macao Consumer Conflict Mediation and Arbitration Center for a resolution.
After communication between the litigating parts, through a video conferencing session, a transaction agreement was reached.
According to the CC statement, with the implementation of the general planning lines for the development of the large bay, “the circulation of people and economic interaction in the region is increasingly frequent”, having made transfronist consumption “in a new normality”.
In this sense, he points out, the Macao Consumer Conflict Mediation and Arbitration Center has provided transfronting mediation and arbitration services, establishing a cooperation mechanism for online mediation and refereeing transfers with various consumer organizations from the large bay cities.
With the growing tendency between residents of Macao and the cities of the interior of China in consumer interaction, the CC stresses that it will “proactively advance the promotion of transfronheous mediation and arbitration services”, so as to extend the application of the successful model of cooperation-pilot projects with consumer organizations from the great cities of the great Chinese cities ”.
In addition, it will “explore” the establishment of any cooperation with consumer organizations from abroad.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>100 Years of Pirelli History to see at the GPM Museum</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/100-anos-de-historia-da-pirelli-para-ver-museu-gpm/</link><description>The Italian brand Pirelli shows 100 years of history in the manufacture of running tires in an exhibition at the Macao Grand Prix Museum. The thematic show allows visitors to know, from a different angle, the technical details of the Macau competition. The Pirelli director in Asia expects the exhibition to “encourage deep understanding and the love of tire technology, which is the pulse of the event”

In cooperation with the 100 -year -old Italian tire manufacturer, the Macau Grand Prix Museum (MGPM) has inaugurated the “Legenda da Pirelli” thematic exhibition, where they display various models of running tires, which will allow visitors to know GPM culture from different angles.
The show, patent to the public on the MGPM basement until March 2, 2026, features nine models, including a special version of dragon standard tires, offered to the Macao Grand Prix Organizing Committee last year, a Formula 1 tire and seven other ones used on the MSAR circuit.
In a note issued by the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), it can be read that the museum cooperates with Pirelli in organizing this exhibition, with the aim of “reinforcing the knowledge and love of society” by the Macao Grand Prix, conveying the culture of the event in the form of “education with fun”. It also points out that the products exposed “fully reveal the aesthetics of the technique behind the design of the tires, allowing fans to know more deeply the technical details of the great award”.
On the other hand, the special exhibition offers visitors, in video format, “the route of refined tires manufactured by the Pirelli factory in Milan, on a fast and fast trip to the guide circuit”.
At the opening ceremony, STD director Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes said that Pirelli “continues to pursue a technology of excellence and product innovation”, adding that this is an “effective form” of the Macao Grand Prix, “Unique International Brand”, to promote the territory and “deepen” the intersectoral integration of “Tourism + Sport”.
For its part, Pirelli's executive director for Asia-Pacific, Andrea Maganzani, stressed that the exhibition “is not just a demonstration of the Pirelli route in motorized races”, representing “a compliment to passion, innovation and sustainable development of a central piece for the future of motor sport”. Andrea Maganzani hopes that the exhibition "stimulates deep understanding and the love of tire technology, which is the pulse of the event."
Founded in 1872, Pirelli is today one of the leading tire manufacturers worldwide. Every year it participates in more than 350 cars and two -wheel motorcycles, including FIA tire partner supplier for Formula 1, 2 and 3 Formulas World Championships, and the European Regional and World GT Formula Championships. In addition, Pirelli participates in the most prestigious and legendary sports events in Asia-Pacific, including the Macao Grand Prix.
The Grand Prix Museum is open to the public from 10h00 to 18h00, ending on Tuesdays.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lisboeta presents Chef António Coelho Menu</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lisboeta-apresenta-menu-chef-antonio-coelho/</link><description>Portuguese chef António Coelho joined the “Angela’s Café and Lounge” at the Lisboeta Macau Hotel, to create a menu with “Macaense and Portuguese essence”. According to Lisboeta, the “a la carte” menu combines traditional Portuguese culinary techniques with innovative creations, to offer customers a “memorable” gastronomic experience and contribute to the progress of the “unique cultural identity of Macao”. Includes dishes like piglet in the style of Bairrada, Francesinha in the fashion of Porto and Octopus to Lagareiro, among others. António Coelho has four more decades of experience with Portuguese cuisine, including seeing his restaurant highlighted at the Michelin Guide from Hong Kong and Macau for 12 consecutive years. He also received the Merit Merit Medal of the Government of MSAR, in 2013, for its contributions to the promotion of Portuguese cuisine. In addition, it has won several international awards, such as the “International Quality Prize in Hotels and Restaurants” in Spain, “Quality and Best Commercial brand - Platinum Technology Award” in Italy, and the “Century Itm International Quality Era” Gold Award in Switzerland. António Coelho specializes in “combining unique ingredients from various regions of Portugal with traditional culinary techniques, continually incorporating influences from French cuisine”, in order to create different Portuguese dishes.</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>AMI launches two support plans for recreational activities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/iam-lanca-dois-planos-de-apoio-para-actividades-recreativas/</link><description>From September 15 to October 15, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) will accept applications for the “IAM Financial Support Plan” and the “Support Plan with subsidies for the operation of large -scale community facilities with various services”, according to a statement. For the first, elements such as “the content of the activities, their usefulness in fulfillment of the AMI functions and the reasonableness of budgetary expenses” will be evaluated. However, each qualified association may deliver a maximum of 25 requests, the body said. Regarding support for large -scale community operations, intended for cultural, recreational, sports and community services, there will be only one vacancy. For this plan, AMI will appreciate “the daily operation situation of the facilities, the size, the content of services, the reasonableness of budgetary expenses, among other factors”. Interested parties will be able to submit orders on the platform to companies and associations, send the documents by mail or deliver them personally to the service places to the AMI public. Forms can be discharged on the Institute's website, where more information about both plans is also available. Through these supports, AMI aims to “encourage and support society's organizations to perform special activities that enrich citizens' free time and promote the harmonious development of communities”.</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2471/</link><description>New Tomography Machines at the Islands Hospital
The islands hospital recently inaugurated a nuclear medicine exam service. In the first phase, the services will be destined to residents sent by health services. Pet-CT computed tomography machines, a “PET-MR” magnetic resonance scanner and a combined equipment for single photon emission and computed tomography. According to the hospital unit, these devices "can help significantly increase the accuracy and efficiency of the diagnosis of tumor -related diseases." It also provides that the functioning of these new machines will lead to the relief of the pressure felt in the public hospital in elevated class image exams.
 
Tamagnini Barbosa market will have a restoration center
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) plans to optimize the Tamagnini Barbosa market, informing that the work will not imply any demolition. According to the Chinese language press, the first floor of the building will open a food center, while the ground floor will be subject to a new planning depending on the current types of products sold. In addition, AMI revealed that, through this work, a space for the market connection to the sports park for citizens in the former Yat Yuen Canidgers will be reserved. It also indicated that preliminary preparations are being made for the work and then will evaluate if there are conditions to hold a public tender to assign stalls.
 
“Door to door” inspection due to chikungunya case
Health services were notified on September 7 on the third local case of Chikungunya. After an investigation and an evaluation, the Sio Fat building was classified as Rua do Padre Eugénio Taverna and near Rua da Vitória. In order to in a timely detect suspicious cases, the SSM performed a home inspection “door to door”, with the aim of sensitizing residents to the need for mosquito prevention and personally advise them to identify the place where they can easily accumulate stagnant water. Additionally, a temporary blood harvest post was installed in the area for further analysis of individuals with suspected chikungunya fever symptoms.
 
“Sacred Art Treasury” will end the public
The “Sacred Art Treasury of the S. José Seminary” will end the public from September 17. The exhibition, promoted by the Cultural Institute and the Diocese of Macao, can be revisited in virtual reality, through the Electronic page of the Diocesan Department of Historical Archives and Cultural Heritage. The show displays several religious relics, ecclesiastical documents, liturgical objects and related multimedia materials.</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea erases traces of Kim after meeting with Putin in Beijing</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/coreia-norte-apaga-vestigios-de-kim-apos-encontro-putin-em-pequim/</link><description>After North Korean leader Kim Jong-un reunited with Russian President Vladimir Putin in Beijing, those responsible North Koreans carefully cleaned the objects played by the country's supreme leader, when analysts say they are part of a set of security measures to fight foreign spies.
Even with the appearance of a growing friendship between Kim and Putin, the 3 September images showed the extraordinary measures of the North Korean state to hide any track over Kim's health.
In a publication on Telegram, Kremlin reporter Alexander Yunashev shared images of Kim's team to meticulously clean the room in the Chinese capital where Kim and Putin met for more than two hours.
The backrest and arms of the chair were rubbed, and a coffee table next to Kim's chair was also cleaned. Your glass has also been removed.
"After the end of the negotiations, the team accompanying the head of the RPDC carefully destroyed all the traces of Kim's presence," said the reporter. RPDC is the abbreviation of the official name of North Korea, Democratic People's Republic of Korea.
After conversations in the living room, Kim and Putin left for tea and said goodbye warmly.
As with previous trips to the foreigner, Kim took his own living house in a green train that took him to Beijing to hide information about his health, said the Japanese newspaper Nikkei, citing South Korean and Japanese information agencies.
Such measures have been the standard protocol since Kim's predecessor era, his father, Kim Jong-il, said Michael Madden, a US-based North Korean leadership expert.
"The special bathroom and the necessary garbage bags with debris, waste and cigarette tips are for a foreign intelligence agency, even friend, does not get a sample to test it," said Madden.
"This would provide information on any medical conditions that affect Kim Jong-un. This may include hair and skin marks."
In 2019, after a Hanoi summit with US President Donald Trump, Kim guards were seen blocking the floor of their hotel room to clean the room for hours and remove items, including a mattress.
Kim's team was also seen to clean items meticulously before he used them. During his meeting with then South Korean President Moon Jae-in, in 2018, North Korean security guard sprayed a chair and a disinfectant table and cleaned them before Kim sit down.
According to Reuters, in another Summit with Putin in 2023, Kim's security team cleaned the disinfectant chair in advance and vigorously checked if it was safe, with a security guard using a metal detector to scan the seat, as a video showed.
 
JTM with Western Agencies</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>