<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Survey of companies points to an average salary increase of 2.2%</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/inquerito-empresas-aponta-para-subida-salarial-media-de-22/</link><description>A survey carried out by the human resources agency “MSS Recruitment and Hello-jobs” reveals that 77% of a total of 99 Macau companies interviewed have plans to increase salaries this year, a percentage below the approximately 84% seen in 2025. On average, companies plan to adopt increases of 2.23% in 2026, an annual drop of 0.49 percentage points. At the same time, the percentage of companies that will give annual bonuses to workers this year has also fallen.
 
The human resources agency “MSS Recruitment and Hello-jobs” surveyed, in November, a total of 99 companies in Macau, with the aim of understanding trends in salary adjustments and the awarding of annual bonuses this year. According to the survey, on average, the companies interviewed plan to adopt salary increases of 2.23% in 2026, a drop of 0.49 percentage points compared to the increases planned for 2025.
The conclusions of this survey also indicate that the percentage of companies with salary increase plans decreased compared to the 83.87% recorded in 2025. Over the current year, 76.76% of the companies surveyed expressed a desire to adopt higher remunerations.
The questionnaire indicated that the percentage of companies intending to grant annual bonuses to workers this year also fell, to 83.84%, lower than the 90.32% recorded last year.
The companies surveyed pointed to an average annual bonus equivalent to 1.07 months of the monthly salary, which reflects an increase compared to the average of 1.01 months recorded in 2025. However, the human resources agency highlighted that this average was driven by two companies that decided to award bonuses equivalent to four months or more of the monthly salary. Without counting these two samples, the average size of bonuses in 2026 would be 1.01 months.
Tu Ji Ji, executive director of “MSS Recruitment and Hello-jobs”, analyzed that the drop in the level of salary increases and a size of annual bonuses similar to that seen last year correspond to forecasts. From his perspective, these decisions illustrate that Macau's economic environment is becoming cautious and normalized, and, despite the recovery of the main industries, following the stabilization of the growth rate, the margin for growth could come under pressure.
According to his observation, local companies have struggled to balance business recovery and cost control, so they will focus on maintaining the current state, rather than actively expanding. “In terms of remuneration and rewards for workers, employers will adopt a prudent strategy, preferring to retain staff with stable bonuses, while compressing the level of salary increases in order to control long-term fixed costs,” he continued.
The company leader also called on more companies to participate in similar surveys, in order to give “extensibility” to research data, making survey results more representative of the real market situation.</description><pubDate>2026-01-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UM moves towards restructuring by creating five science and technology faculties</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/um-avanca-para-reestruturacao-criando-cinco-faculdades-de-ciencia-tecnologia/</link><description>From August 1st, UM will have five new faculties operating at both the main campus and the new one in Hengqin. They are Medicine, Information and Computer Sciences, Engineering, Science and Design. The creation of these faculties comes as part of a restructuring announced by the institution's rector, Song Yonghua. The idea is that the number of students enrolled can reach 14,500
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The University of Macau (UM) will undergo restructuring, with the aim of creating five faculties of science and technology, revealed the institution's rector, Song Yonghua, after the approval of the project by the University Council. Adding that all faculties will officially begin operating on August 1st of this year, the rector also stressed that the idea is for the number of students enrolled in these areas to reach 14,500 in the future.
Song Yonghua stressed that "the initiative will significantly expand the scope and depth of UM's scientific and technological innovation capacity and provide strong support for its development as an internationally recognized university of excellence."
The faculties to be created by UM in the area of ​​science and technology include the Faculty of Medicine, the Faculty of Information and Computing Sciences, the Faculty of Engineering, the Faculty of Science and the Faculty of Design.
The Faculty of Medicine, the first in Macau, will be created through the integration and expansion of the current Faculty of Health Sciences. The intention is that it will become “a world-class medical school that integrates the training of high-level medical talents, advanced medical services and innovative medical research”.
Joining the departments of Biomedical Sciences, Pharmaceutical Sciences (which will be renamed the Department of Pharmacy and Pharmaceutical Sciences) and Public Health and Medical Administration, will be the departments of Clinical Medicine, Food and Nutritional Sciences and Dental Medicine. Various professional programs will also be offered, including a clinical medicine suite with the University of Lisbon. The Faculty of Medicine is expected to enroll approximately 4,000 students.
The Faculty of Information and Computing Sciences will be created based on the current Faculty of Science and Technology. The new faculty will be made up of the departments of Computer Science, Artificial Intelligence, Microelectronics, Robotics, Electronic and Communications Engineering and Financial Technology and Business Intelligence. It is estimated that around 4,000 students can enroll at this college, and UM says it will play a “leading role” in training talent in cutting-edge areas such as AI, microelectronics, financial technology and computer science.
The Faculty of Engineering, in turn, will also create new departments, including Materials Science and Engineering, Energy Science and Engineering, Chemical and Biological Engineering and Biomedical Engineering. With an expected enrollment of around 4,000 students, the college “will help meet the growing demand for talent in engineering and technological innovation in Macau and the Greater Bay Area”.
The creation of the Faculty of Sciences “is in line with the strategic needs of the country and the Macao SAR and will provide fundamental support in science for technological innovation in Macau and throughout the country”, says UM. It will be made up of the departments of Mathematics, Physics, Chemistry and Biological Sciences. In this case, 1,000 students are anticipated.
In turn, the new Faculty of Design will focus on the integration of AI and design, being made up of the Visual Communication Design, Architecture and Urban Design departments and the Industrial Design department. The aim is to contribute to the training of a new generation of design professionals and reinforce Macau's international influence in design education and creative industries. It is expected that 1,500 students will enroll in this area.
Song Yonghua stressed that the restructuring of the faculty “will also promote the optimization and integration of UM’s resources”. With the main campus and a new campus in the Cooperation Zone, UM will operate under a “dual campus” model.
In a statement, UM also indicates that it will operate under a “dual campus” model, with the new faculties operating both on the main campus and on the new campus in Hengqin. The Faculty of Medicine, Faculty of Information and Computer Sciences, Faculty of Engineering and Faculty of Design will offer programs on both campuses, with headquarters located on the Cooperation Zone campus. “This arrangement will strengthen collaboration between science and technology faculties and industry, and will facilitate the translation of research results into practical applications”, it can be read.
The rector stressed that this reform should increase UM's international competitiveness in cutting-edge scientific and technological innovation and that it will support the integrated development of Macau and Hengqin.</description><pubDate>2026-01-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MSAR wants more employees in Hengqin Executive Committee</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-quer-mais-funcionarios-na-comissao-executiva-de-hengqin/</link><description>The Government intends to increase the proportion of Macau public servants in the Executive Committee of the Deep Cooperation Zone, without changing the total number of workers, 893,
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Currently, the Executive Committee of the Hengqin Deep Cooperation Zone has nine work organizations and 893 workers, which the Macao SAR Government considers “sufficient to meet the development needs of the current stage”. However, subsequently, and keeping the total number of workers “unchanged”, the authorities intend to increase the proportion of employees in Macau.
“The Executive Committee will increase the proportion of workers in Macau's public services, recruit staff targeted at Macau residents and effectively coordinate the appointment of staff from Guangdong, aiming to better serve the long-term planning of the Cooperation Zone”, can be read in the response to a written question from deputy José Chui Sai Peng.
In the response, signed by the deputy head of the Office of the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Fong Peng Kit, it is also mentioned that, in order to better promote the Cooperation Zone, the Macao SAR Government concluded, in 2023 and 2025, the revisions of the Macau Public Administration Workers Statute and the respective legal diplomas, improving the provisions on the appointment of local public service workers to work in Hengqin.
“Thus, workers can be seconded, on an occasional service commission basis, to perform functions in the Cooperation Zone”, he adds. Furthermore, a special accumulation regime was created in Hengqin, “aiming to provide greater flexibility for Macao SAR public service workers to participate in all projects and construction work in the Cooperation Zone”, highlights Fong Peng Kit.
Citing the Administration and Public Service Services, the same official said that the Macao SAR Executive “is fully committed” to using this mechanism, and that, “in the short term”, it will deploy “more experienced workers” from different areas to the Cooperation Zone, under an eventual service commission regime.
Chui Sai Peng recalled that until September 1, 2025, 27 civil servants had been assigned, under occasional service commission, to perform full-time duties in the Executive Committee of the Cooperation Zone and its institutions. In addition, two recruitments were launched on a staff quota basis for Macau residents.
On the other hand, the number of Macau workers under the quota system was 84, representing 48% of the total under this system. Preparatory work has also begun to recruit an additional 50 workers under the Macau personnel quota system, “in the future, it is anticipated that a team of workers will gradually be built based on the employee quota system”.
Despite saying that it intends to increase the team of employees across the border, the Government has not indicated how many it intends to allocate.</description><pubDate>2026-01-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>130 couples eligible for medically assisted procreation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/130-casais-elegiveis-para-fazer-procriacao-medicamente-assistida/</link><description>Since the “Medical Assisted Procreation Treatment Participation Program” was introduced, just over a year ago, 480 couples have applied. The Health Services referred 352 to external infertility consultations and 130 are able to undergo treatment
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The Health Services (SSM) estimate that in the first half of this year all couples eligible to undergo medically assisted procreation treatment will be able to be assisted, according to the organization's director, Alvis Lo, in response to a written question from deputy Leong Sun Iok.
From the launch of the “Program for Participation in Medically Assisted Procreation Treatment”, in December 2024, until mid-November 2025, the SSM received 480 requests, of which 352 were referred to the External Infertility Consultation at Hospital das Ilhas. The rest did not meet the required conditions.
After the clinical evaluation, “it was found that around 130 couples are able to receive the services, namely the in vitro fertilization technique – first generation embryo transplantation or the second generation intracytoplasmic sperm injection technique”, highlighted Alvis Lo. He also said that, since last October, services have been available gradually, with the aim that “all eligible cases can be attended to within the first half” of 2026.
Regarding subsidies for the respective treatment, these cover the costs of oocyte retrieval and embryo transfer in two cycles (each cycle includes an oocyte retrieval surgery and an embryo transfer).
Taking into account that the program “is still in an initial phase of implementation, in the future, its effectiveness will be evaluated and reviewed, according to the real situation, in order to continue providing attention and support to residents who wish to have children”, he mentioned.
In another question asked by the deputy of the Legislative Assembly, about the reinforcement of specialized personnel in the medically assisted procreation program, the director of the SSM revealed that, to date, 16 workers have been allocated, including doctors, laboratory analysis technicians and nursing professionals. In this sense, “it is possible to further increase the capacity to provide services”, he assured.</description><pubDate>2026-01-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SJM sells debt to increase “financial flexibility”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sjm-vende-divida-para-aumentar-flexibilidade-financeira/</link><description>With the aim of extending the group's debt term, SJM will issue debt securities on Thursday with a total value equivalent to more than 4.3 billion patacas maturing in 2031
 
Next Thursday, January 15, SJM Holdings will issue corporate debt securities, in the form of senior bonds, worth 540 million US dollars (4.33 billion patacas at the current exchange rate), with annual interest of 6.5% and maturity in 2031. This operation will be carried out through SJM International.
Through this issuance, SJM “will extend the maturity period of the group's debt and increase its financial flexibility”, says the company in a statement sent to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange, adding that the gross proceeds from the bonds will also be used for general corporate purposes. Currently, there are 500 million dollars in circulation in bonds maturing on January 27th, which SJM will repurchase with “internal resources” and the bonds denominated in US dollars.
Sociedade de Turismo e Diversões de Macau (STDM), the majority shareholder of SJM Holdings, with 61.9% of the capital, agreed to subscribe to a “certain amount” of the bonds, through a subsidiary, the statement said, without providing details. In August 2022, during the pandemic, STDM had already lent two billion Hong Kong dollars to SJM, so that its subsidiary could fulfill one of the requirements associated with the game contest – having share capital of at least five billion patacas.
The commercial conditions of the new debt securities were established after negotiations between the company and the linked subscriber, “with the obligations not being guaranteed by the group's assets”, SJM Holdings further clarified. Therefore, he guaranteed, “the linked subscription is completely exempt from all disclosure, annual review, circular and shareholder approval requirements” under the rules of the Hong Kong Stock Exchange.
According to the GGRAsia portal, before the announcement of the issue values, the financial rating agencies Fitch Ratings and Moody’s Ratings assigned ratings below investment grade to the offer of SJM debt securities in US dollars, warning of the challenges faced by the gaming concessionaire, which closed all its satellite casinos with the exception of L’Arc, now operated directly.
 
Workers with bonuses at the end of the month
In line with the decision taken by four other gaming operators, SJM also announced that it will pay, on the 30th of this month, a “special discretionary bonus” equivalent to one month's salary to “all eligible workers”, according to an internal notice from the company to its employees. Galaxy, Melco, Wynn and MGM have also announced the same measure, but Sands has yet to make its decision public.
 
S.T.</description><pubDate>2026-01-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM will have 10% more students</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/upm-tera-mais-10-de-alunos/</link><description>The Macau Polytechnic University (UPM) predicts, for 2026/2027, an increase of 3,300 students, or 10% in new admissions, bringing the total number of students to 10,000. More than 8,000 students attend academic degree courses in the 2025/2026 academic year, which began in September.
Under the general coordination of the Government, in the first phase, UPM will install the temporary campus in Hengqin between August and September this year, to develop postgraduate pedagogical activities. The courses will cover areas such as big health, cutting-edge technology, Chinese and Portuguese languages, among others.
Admission work is already underway and the next phase will be the period of construction of the campus in the Cooperation Zone. All work is proceeding “in an orderly manner”, and construction is expected to begin in 2027, with completion scheduled for 2030. At that time, “UPM headquarters in Macau and its campus in Hengqin will embrace new opportunities for inter-regional, international teaching and regional collaboration”, said Vivian Lei, deputy dean, at the Open Day inauguration ceremony.
Evelina Maria de Souza, head of the Admissions, Enrollment and Enrollment Division at UPM, said, for her part, that the university's academic degree courses, “as they are closely linked to the development of society, register a satisfactory and growing demand”.
According to the institution, secondary school students present at the Open Day highlighted that the event allowed them to better understand the multicultural campus and university life at UPM. “The experimental activities provided them with an in-depth insight into development trends and career planning in the area of ​​‘Artificial Intelligence +’”, says the same note, adding that the event attracted more than 4,800 participants.
The Open Day took place on Saturday, with the participation of several entities, notably the representative of the Department of Education and Youth of the Liaison Office of the Central People's Government in the Macao SAR, Chu Zhiwen, the deputy director of the Education and Youth Development Services, Teng Sio Hong, and directors and representatives of more than 30 secondary schools.
The statement concludes that UPM's bachelor's, master's and doctoral courses for 2026/2027 “are highly sought after by local and international students, covering areas such as innovative technology, health and sports sciences, languages ​​and translation, arts and cultural creativity, human and social sciences, business management and finance”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2026-01-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Future Industrial Park generates “broad consensus”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/futuro-parque-industrial-gera-consenso-alargado/</link><description>The Government concluded the public consultation on the future Science and Technology R&amp;D Industrial Park, having collected more than 2,500 opinions. The Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services indicated that there was a “broad consensus” among participants
 
The Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) collected 2,546 opinions and suggestions on the planning and construction of the Science and Technology R&amp;D Industrial Park and, after a preliminary analysis, considered that there is a “broad consensus in society on the project”.
Between November 27th and December 26th, the seven sessions organized by the Government involved around 630 participants, including “members of the executive and legislative bodies, representatives of the scientific sector, academics and associations as well as two sessions open to the public and one dedicated to secondary school students”, having also received 247 written opinions.
According to DSEDT, “participants actively contributed with suggestions and proposals, addressing multiple aspects such as the positioning of the development of the Science and Technology Park, sectoral distribution, complementary infrastructures, training and talent attraction policies, coordination mechanisms between industry, academia and research, and cross-border cooperation models”.
Remember that the two possible locations for the Park are Wai Long Avenue and Zone E1 of the New Landfills. In the first, the lot occupies a strategic position of industry-university-research, with favorable accessibility and transport conditions. In this case, the Park would have 83 thousand square meters, including the slopes and the Taipa Grande Hill Tunnel. With the industrial ecosystem development chain as the main axis, the Park would be organized into functional zones to support research and development (R&amp;D) and production.
In Novos Aterros, the project would benefit from “privileged geographical conditions”, adopting a concept of an ecological and low-carbon coastal park. With 177 thousand square meters, it would consist of areas for digital technologies, integrated circuits, aerospace technologies, a data and computing center, an urban reception room, a public services pavilion and leisure spaces.
The Government assured that it will integrate “in a comprehensive way the diverse opinions collected, closely articulating the construction plan for the Greater Bay Area with the national development strategy” and “Macau's own advantages”, contributing to the development and diversification of the economy.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2026-01-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Robot operation marks a new stage at Hospital das Ilhas</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/operacao-robo-marca-nova-etapa-hospital-das-ilhas/</link><description>The latest and most advanced robotic orthopedic system, called Stryker Mako, was introduced for the first time in Macau, in a knee arthroplasty operation carried out at the Islands Health Care Complex – Macau Medical Center of Peking Union Medical College Hospital. A statement from the hospital unit states that the “success of the surgery marks a new stage in the development of intelligent medical technology in orthopedics in the territory”.
The intervention was carried out on an elderly patient who had great difficulties in walking due to severe flexion and varus deformity of the knee joint.
In more detailed terms, the operation used that world-first orthopedic robotic system to implement “three approaches with a single robot”. In the pre-operative period, the medical team carried out a computerized tomography to create a personalized three-dimensional model of the patient's bone structure, ensuring precise surgical planning.
During the procedure, the new method provided “real-time feedback” and allowed the performance of “osteotomy with submillimetre precision”, taking advantage of “haptic feedback technology to effectively protect essential nerves and blood vessels, which contributed to the substantial reinforcement of surgical safety”, adds Hospital das Ilhas.
At the same time, the use of this technology also makes it possible to dispense with the traditional surgery procedure of opening the medullary cavity of the femur, considerably reducing the risk of hemorrhage and blood transfusion.
“The patient had a positive postoperative recovery, being able to walk with the aid of a walker the day after surgery,” notes the hospital. In light of this, this case demonstrates “how robot-assisted surgery, through data analysis and intelligent planning, can increase the precision and controllability of the surgical procedure, optimize patients' prognosis and accelerate rehabilitation progress”, highlights the text.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2026-01-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>GCS revoked registration of six publications</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/gcs-revogou-registo-de-seis-publicacoes/</link><description>In 2025, the Social Communication Office (GCS) revoked the registration of six publications, in accordance with the Press Law and the Press Registration Regulation. On the other hand, it registered six new publications, including a weekly newspaper and five magazines (three monthly, one quarterly and one annual). In a statement, which does not specify the reasons for the revocations, the GCS indicates that the six publications whose registration was canceled in 2025 include “Jornal Skyscape” (weekly), “Líder de Comércio Internacional” (weekly), “Jornal Macau Jovem” (monthly), “All About Macau” (monthly), “Asian Heart Journal” (biannually) and “Play Zhu Ao” (annual). The number of cancellations represents almost half that of 2024 (11) and is the lowest since the creation of the Macao SAR, excluding the years 2000 and 2011, for which there are no references to similar processes. According to data available on the GCS website, since 1999, the registrations of 470 publications have been canceled, including 403 after the establishment of the Macao SAR. The record was set in 2013, with 45 revocations. In 2025, the most publicized case involved “All About Macau”, whose registration was canceled on October 10th. Days later, it announced the closure of its doors, citing “lack of resources, increasing external pressure” and the fact that some of its journalists had to deal with legal proceedings, after being prevented from covering official activities. It is recalled that, in April, reporters from the publication were prevented from entering the Legislative Assembly. Currently, 110 publications from different categories have valid registration with the GCS. Under the Press Law and the Regulation on the Organization and Operation of the Social Communication Office, the GCS is responsible for registering entities that own journalistic, editorial and news companies in the MSAR, correspondents and other forms of representation of OCS based outside Macau, and local periodical publications.</description><pubDate>2026-01-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>TJB REJECTS CONFISCATING 264 FRACTIONS OF THE WINDSOR ARCH COMPLEX</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/tjb-rejeita-confiscar-264-fraccoes-complexo-windsor-arch/</link><description>The Base Judicial Court (TJB) rejected the transfer of 264 housing units in Windsor Arch to the Macao SAR, as part of a corruption case involving two former directors of the former Land, Public Works and Transport Services (DSSOPT). According to TDM's Canal Macau, only one seized apartment will be declared lost and confiscated by the Macao SAR. Also according to the public broadcaster, the TJB decided that the convicts Ng Lap Seng, William Kuan and Ng Kei Nin will have to pay the Macao SAR a “corresponding monetary amount in lieu of confiscation” and that “the specific amounts will be determined at the time of execution and as soon as the Public Prosecutor's Office obtains the necessary information”. William Kuan e Ng Lap Seng foram condenados por terem subornado dois antigos directores da DSSOPT, Jaime Carion e Li Canfeng, para que estes aprovassem a construção de vários projectos, um dos quais o Windsor Arch. The 265 apartments in question were not included in the plan originally approved by the Government, making the units illegal. Li Canfeng chegou a admitir em tribunal ter aceitado uma das casas no complexo habitacional como forma de pagamento de serviços de consultadoria quando ainda não estava nas Obras Públicas.</description><pubDate>2026-01-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>TOURIST PRICES HAVE INCREASED FOR THE THIRD CONSECUTIVE YEAR</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/precos-turisticos-encareceram-pelo-terceiro-ano-consecutivo/</link><description>The average Tourist Price Index (IPT) increased by 1.71% in 2025, in annual terms, mainly due to increases in jewelry and entertainment and leisure, informed the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). Although more moderate, this was the third consecutive annual increase after the IPT advanced 21.53% in 2023 and 3.15% in 2024. According to DSEC, last year, the price indices for miscellaneous goods (including jewelry, watches and handicrafts) and entertainment and cultural activities increased by 13.46% and 8.20%, respectively, countering the drops in the accommodation (-2.88%) and medicines and personal use goods (-1.93%). In the fourth quarter, the IPT grew 4.95%, year-on-year, driven by the increase in the price of jewelry, hotel rooms and plane tickets. Between October and December, the highlights were the increases in the miscellaneous goods (+17.33%), accommodation (+7.33%) and transport and communications (+6.05%) sections. Official data also indicates that the IPT grew 9.30% in the last quarter of 2025 compared to the previous three months. In the quarterly interval, the accommodation price index increased by 34.86%, due to the holidays of the establishment of the People's Republic of China and the Grand Prix. The prices of miscellaneous goods (+7.77%), transport and communications (+4.86%) and clothing and footwear (+4.37%) also increased.</description><pubDate>2026-01-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>ELECTRONIC PAYMENTS RISE IN RESTAURANTS AND FALL IN RETAIL</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pagamentos-electronicos-sobem-na-restauracao-caem-retalho/</link><description>The volume of electronic payment transactions in the restaurant sector grew by 2.3% to 12.40 billion patacas between January and November 2025, in annual terms, revealed the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC). On the other hand, in retail trade there was a drop of 4.9% to 46.47 billion. Considering only November data, statistics indicate that electronic transactions grew 3.5% in restaurants (to 1.14 billion) and 3.7% in retail trade (4.50 billion) compared to the same month in 2024. In monthly terms there were drops of 2.1% and 4.0%, respectively, after the “disappearance of the effect of the holidays resulting from the implementation of the People's Republic of China”. According to DSEC, in November, the value of transactions in Western and fast food restaurants grew by 10.4% and 10.3%, respectively, compared to November 2024, however, Chinese restaurants recorded a decline of 2.7%. In retail, transactions in cosmetic and hygiene products, as well as those in pharmacies rose by 21.2% and 18.1%, respectively, in the annual variation, while that of warehouse goods and trinkets decreased by 8.8%. These statistics are provided by the main local institutions that receive electronic payment invoices (corresponding to around 95% of the total) and compiled after being integrated into DSEC data. According to DSEC, the volumes of electronic payments in restaurants and retail represent around 70% to 80% of the revenues of each branch.</description><pubDate>2026-01-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>BRIEF</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2525/</link><description>Another Nestlé batch suspected of contamination
Following an alert from Nestlé Hong Kong, another batch of powdered milk product for infants was added whose raw materials may be contaminated by Bacillus cereus microorganisms, indicated the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) and the Institute for Pharmaceutical Supervision and Administration (ISAF). The IAM and ISAF confirmed that this batch “was not imported to Macau”, however, they promised to continue to “closely monitor” the situation and called again for babies and young children to “immediately cease” the consumption of this affected product. If they experience discomfort after consuming the product, they should seek medical assistance.
 
Price index fell 0.1% in housing
The overall housing price index in the Macao SAR decreased by 0.1% between September and November, compared to the previous period (August to October), according to data from the Statistics and Census Services Directorate. As for the price index for built housing, that of the Peninsula decreased by 0.3% compared to the previous period, however, that of Taipa and Coloane increased by 0.5%. On the other hand, the price index for constructed housing fell by 0.1%, while that of houses under construction grew by 0.5%.
 
Lótus Metro Station will have its roof replaced
Today, the Light Rail Society will begin replacing the roofing system at the Lotus Station on the Taipa Line, which was damaged due to a typhoon. The work will be carried out in phases, maintaining the line's normal circulation frequency. The work will include the complete replacement of the station's covering system and the platform's false ceiling, among other works, within a period of 120 working days, to “improve the waiting environment”. To facilitate execution, parts of the platform will be closed in phases, and the Metro will run with a two-car train, and, during peak periods, the frequency will be increased. On the section of Estrada Flor de Lótus, traffic will be restricted, and the pedestrian crossing will be temporarily closed.
 
Authorities urge caution against telephone fraud
Authorities ask the population to be cautious, taking into account that complaints have been made about suspicious telephone calls. The Directorate of Personal Data Protection Services (DSPDP) received complaints from residents of Macau and neighboring regions about calls suspected of spoofing DSPDP telephone numbers or people pretending to be DSPDP employees. In these cases, personal data was revealed. The Tourism Services also received complaints from residents of neighboring regions who stated that they had received calls identifying themselves as DST employees, claiming that the number involved had sent messages about assistance in processing travel documents for third parties. The organization denies having made these calls. The PJ, in turn, also warned that fraudsters were once again sending messages pretending to be a bank.</description><pubDate>2026-01-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>House where David Bowie grew up will be opened to the public</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/casa-onde-cresceu-david-bowie-vai-ser-aberta-ao-publico/</link><description>The house where musician David Bowie grew up, in the suburbs of London, was acquired by an institution dedicated to rescuing and preserving historic buildings, which plans to make it accessible to the public. According to the Associated Press, the Heritage of London Trust, an independent charity, announced that the 19th century house, located in Bromley, south of London, will be restored with 1960s decor and opened to the public next year.

Visitors will be able to access the room, measuring 2.7 by three meters, where “a spark turned into a flame”.
David Bowie, born David Jones, lived in that house with his parents from 1955, when he was 8 years old, until 1967, the year in which he was already a young 20-year-old musician looking for fame.
The co-curator of the exhibition “David Bowie Is”, which was on display in 2013 at the Victoria &amp; Albert Museum, in London, said it was the house where “Bowie evolved from an ordinary suburban student to a musician at the beginning of an extraordinary international career”. "As he said: 'I spent so much time in my room, it was my whole world. I had my books, my music and my record player there,'" recalled Geoffrey Marsh, quoted by the "Associated Press".
Saturday marked a decade since the death of David Bowie, considered one of the most influential musicians in history, and recognized for his ability to reinvent himself in an innovative and provocative way. The artist died on January 10, 2016, two days after celebrating his 69th birthday with the release of an album, “Blackstar”.
From his home in Bromley, David Bowie set out on a creative journey that took him to Philadelphia and New York, in the USA, and Berlin, Germany, going through several changes in style and musical genres, from 'folk-rock' to 'glam', passing through soul, electronica and 'new wave'.
The English musician's repertoire includes songs such as “Space Oddity”, “Changes”, “Life on Mars”, “Starman”, “Young Americans” and “Heroes”.
The “Heritage of London Trust” decided to buy the house when it was put up for sale last year, but it was not revealed how much they paid for it. Other houses on the same street were recently sold for around 670 thousand euros, according to the “Associated Press”.
The house project, supported by David Bowie's representatives, received a donation of around 575 thousand euros and the “Heritage of London Trust” intends to raise another around 1.4 million euros in donations, with the aim of being able to open the space at the end of 2027 for visits and workshops for children.
David Bowie's collection has been on display and available for consultation since September at the V&amp;A East Storehouse museum, in London.
The David Bowie Center houses more than 90,000 pieces from the artist's private collection, including 414 costumes and accessories, around 150 musical instruments, amplifiers and other sound equipment, 187 awards, merchandise such as t-shirts and props and sets for concerts, films and theater. As an example, the collection includes suits designed by Freddie Burretti and Kansai Yamamoto for the “Ziggy Stardust” and “Aladdin Sane” tours, the coat with the British flag designed by Bowie himself for the cover of the album “Earthling” (1997), a key to the apartment where he lived in Berlin in the 1970s and a hat and scarf he wore in the film “Merry Christmas, Mr. Lawrence” (1983).
Some of the objects are displayed on a rotating and temporary basis in showcases, but visitors can reserve most of the pieces in advance for closer personal consultation.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>