<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Bankruptcy Situation in SMEs “has been very serious”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/situacao-de-falencias-nas-pme-tem-sido-muito-grave/</link><description>The president of the Board of the Small and Medium Enterprises Association considers that Macau has “lost competitiveness” due to the slowdown of the game market and warns that one of the biggest problems is the “wave of bankruptcy” in the territory. At a meeting with the Chief Executive on LAG, Stanley Au called on the improvement of the business environment
 
Stanley Au, president of the Board of the Macao Small and Medium Enterprises Association, considers that "the most urgent problem that needs to be resolved has to do with the business environment in Macao, because there is a wave of bankruptcy." The associative leader spoke to journalists after a meeting with the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, in the context of planning of the Governing Action Lines (LAG).
As stressed, the bankruptcy situation "has been very serious." “The fundamental reason for this is that Macau lost competitiveness” due to the slowdown of the game market. In this sense, it has suggested to the government to create a “fair, reasonable and encouraging investment environment”.
Stanley Au also defended the creation of a law to regulate incomes, in order to lock the problem of irrational increases in lace by owners with bad faith.
It also stated that in order to resolve difficulties in small and medium -sized companies (SMEs) it will be necessary to bet on sensitization with these companies to adapt to new social trends. In particular, he said that the government should stimulate SMEs to resort to computer technology and artificial intelligence to increase productivity and efficiently use human resources, as well as revitalize the economy of old neighborhoods and improving the level of science and technology and the professional education of higher education establishments.
He also suggested that the executive launch measures to create good job opportunities for residents. In particular, Stanley Au proposed that the government launch a number of measures to encourage commercial establishments to increase the hiring of local workers and improve their conditions.
On the other hand, and according to the Chinese language press, Stanley Au proposed the reduction of civil servants with overlapping functions, “in the sense of raising the efficiency of work” in the civil service. In this field, it also considers that it is necessary to “reinforce the fight against corruption”.
The other leaders of the association's leading bodies also expressed opinions on the opportunities of the low altitude economy, the construction of the qualified framework for formation, Big Health industry.
The head of the executive, in turn, stressed that "SMEs are an important force for the socioeconomic development of Macao and contribute significantly to the sustainable and healthy development of the local economy and the employment market." Underlining that there are numerous neighborhoods and streets “with a valuable historical and cultural context”, he has ensured that the government “will proceed, globally and integrated, to the work of revitalizing neighborhoods, giving constant impetus to the cultural and tourist economy, in order to ensure the business environment for SMEs and employment opportunities for the population of Macao”.
 
Patriotic politicians and technical-professional school in Hengqin
Also in the context of preparation of LAG, the chief executive met with the members of Macao in the National Committee of the Chinese Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC). According to an official note issued by the Social Communication Office, Lao NGA Wong suggested to the government to perfect "the Macao patriotic politicians formation system."
In addition, he argued that he should “strive to create a team of competent and high quality political workers with political morals and morals”, as well as “provide sufficient qualified political frames to support the stable and lasting implementation of the“ one country ”principle”.
Lao Nga Wong also suggested the creation of a background that focuses on diversified investments around five thematic sectors, including biological and health sciences, artificial and robotic intelligence, semiconductors and intelligent devices, digitization and modernization and transformation, and future and sustainable development.
Zhang Zongzhen considers that to support the construction of the in-depth cooperation zone “it is necessary to establish a technical-professional school in Hengqin, and thus form qualified frames” on Mountain Island, creating “a platform to improve workers' skills”. As for the courses, they should correspond to the development of Macao's “1+4” industries.
The low birth rate and population aging were also topics that were on the table, specifically taken by Ho Ion Sang. The deputy again insisted on the widening of the paid maternity leave and the paternity license, the increase in birth allowance, and the introduction of policies favorable to the family and housing.
The leader of the MSAR has ensured that the opinions will be taken into account in the preparation of LAG for this year.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Statues of the ruins and murals of the guide chapel will be restoring this year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/estatuas-das-ruinas-murais-da-capela-da-guia-serao-alvo-de-restauro-este-ano/</link><description>The Center for the Preservation and Transmission of Cultural Heritage will be dedicated to the restoration of the Murals of the Guide Chapel and the Bronze Statues of the Ruins of São Paulo, the president of the Cultural Institute revealed yesterday. The preservation works of these assets are part of the celebration of the 20th anniversary of the Macao Historic Center inscription on the World Heritage list. In this context, an international cultural forum is still scheduled and several workshops related to the subject

Catarina Pereira
 
In the year 20 years are celebrated on the registration of the Macao Historic Center on the UNESCO World Heritage list, the Cultural Institute (IC) will launch a series of activities, including an international forum and safeguarding and revitalizing works of cultural heritage. The body's president, Leong Wai Man, revealed yesterday that, in this context, items that are part of two well -known monuments of the territory will be recovered.
“Regarding revitalization, restoration, protection, as you know, the center for the preservation and transmission of the cultural heritage of the Macao Palace Museum recently entered into force. Therefore, let's take advantage of this center to recover some items, namely the bronze statues of the ruins of São Paulo and the murals of the Chapel of Our Lady of Guia, ”he said in response to journalists after the first meeting of the Cultural Heritage Council.
The president of the IC has not advanced details about what will be done specifically, nor the calendar for the beginning of these works. The center for the preservation and transmission of cultural heritage was created, there is, following a memorandum signed between the Government of MSAR and the Ministry of Culture and Tourism, being the Palace Museum responsible for professional advice and technical support for the restoration of the cultural heritage of the territory.
Located on the ground floor of the Art Museum, the Center occupies about 900 square meters and is equipped with specialized laboratories, being prepared to perform preservation and restoration work related to the Macao World Heritage Sites, with property of property and components of the built heritage. All this through advanced technologies and the “strengthening of local talents in the area of ​​heritage conservation”, according to the IC on the electronic page.
Regarding protection and safeguard work, he recalled that the work on the demonstrations to be inscribed in the Cultural Heritage List will be completed. There are 12 demonstrations to be inscribed, including Portuguese folk dance, the making of cream pastels, the spring festival, the belief and customs of Tou Tei, the Dragon Dance, the Lion Dance, among others.
In relation to the International Cultural Forum, Leong Wai Man said the details are still being thoughtful, but will be related to "safeguarding cultural or worldwide heritage." The idea, he continued, is to invite “international experts to come to Macau share opinions” on issues related to the theme. Also in this case, the body's leader said it will be disclosed later.
In addition to the International Forum, there are planned training workshops on cultural heritage and specific promotional activities in celebration of the historic center's registration on the World Heritage List, “among other initiatives”.
 
Revitalization of the six zones enters a new phase
Another aspect in which IC wants to continue betting is the revitalization of the six historical zones, together with the game operators, a work that will now come into a new phase. “In recent times, revitalization work has only been an initial phase. That is, we tried, through short term activities, during certain festivities, to promote local commerce and allow various sectors of the community or associations to develop their activities, as well as encouraged the participation of small and medium enterprises. Now, from now on, we enter a medium and long term phase, ”explained Leong Wai Man.
According to said, after the experience already acquired, this year will be launched "goals" regarding the revitalization of these historical zones, and the principles are maintained. The projects will be led by the government, to which the gamekeepers later join. "They have know-how, have resources and can, with their knowledge, attract visitors and develop activities that can promote not only trade, but also the community development of society, the well-being of the population, among other aspects," he said.
In this sense, Leong Wai Man stressed that these actions will be "optimized." "We hope that these historical areas in the future will interconnect with each other, that there is a synergy of cultural resources and a greater contribution to society," he added.
At the meeting of the Cultural Heritage Council was also discussed the exercise of the right of preference of three classified real estate, but, as usual, the president of the IC did not reveal that buildings are concerned.
In relation to the works of the Central Library, at Tap Seac, Leong Wai Man recalled that the foundations are being built and that a public tender will be launched for the next stage. Asked when it will be released, he said that the IC is still in communication with other organisms, namely public works, so there is no concrete calendar.
The new central library will be located on the ground between the intersection of Avenida de Sidónio Pais and Street Filipe O'Costa, in the former Hotel Estoril, in an area that covers about 2,960 square meters. According to the project, the library will have three floors, with a basement for storage. The gross construction area is 12,710 square meters. In addition to the main space for the library, there will be meeting rooms, a learning zone and a public reading zone.
 
Approved five requests to support historical buildings
Five requests received “green light” from the Culture Development Fund under the “Financial Support Plan for the Maintenance of Historical Buildings” of 2024, yesterday indicated the president of the Cultural Institute (IC), and the owners must now present a project, which should be prepared by a consulting company. "Then we have experts that will evaluate the viability of the project," added Leong Wai Man. The buildings are located at Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro, Largo do Senado and on the street of five October. As for the budget, a value was not advanced, which will only be known after the presentation of the project. This initiative aims to support the owners in the work of periodic structural verification or tests, both in classified buildings and of cultural interest, and perform the necessary recovery and maintenance works.
 
CPSP says filming team did not follow safe driving requirements
The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) said yesterday that the safe driving requirements were “not followed” by the filming team that was involved in a road accident, which caused 12 wounds, all extras. According to the authorities in the usual police conference of the police said, before filming there was an interdepartal meeting to coordinate the details, and the police "manifested themselves clearly against the filming mode proposed by the team, since the place concerned is a very narrow street and there is a sharp curve." Explaining that street conditions are not suitable for high speed driving, CPSP urged the team to perform the filming work according to the safe driving requirements, which will not have happened. The situation has already been reported to the Cultural Institute (IC), which authorized the shoot. The CPSP also said that filming activities cannot be considered illegal work precisely because there was “green light” of the IC. In the morning, after the meeting of the Heritage Council, Leong Wai Man had been asked about the accident, but said only that the investigation was still underway.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DSAT will study online taxis marking</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dsat-vai-estudar-marcacao-online-de-taxis/</link><description>In “Opposite Time”, services for traffic issues will develop studies on online taxi marking, guaranteed the body in a response to Deputy Leong Sun Iok, who defended this as a way of responding to the needs of residents and tourists, in line with the course followed by Hong Kong. On the other hand, DSAT indicated, without ahead of a calendar, which is “accelerating” preparations for a new public tender for the attribution of general licenses for taxis
 
Sérgio Terra
 
The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) “will remain attentive to legislative update and complementary work related to the provision of passenger transport services for online marking in neighboring regions, proceeding to the necessary studies in due time”. The guarantee was given by the director of the body, Lam Hin San, in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Leong Sun Iok, who urged the government to help black taxis provides such services, stressing that this “is a trend” and Hong Kong is already studying legal diplomas on marking over the internet.
"Society continues with difficulty taking taxi," warned the deputy, noting that, among more than 1,750 vehicles in operation, only 300 are radiotaxis and only a few black taxis can be called via the internet. "Given the traffic conditions of Macao and the protection of the taxi sector, I suggest to the government that promotes, first, the online taxi marking service and that elaborates a regulation, with a view to protecting the rights and interests of passengers and taxi drivers, as well as raising the level of services provided," said Leong Sun Iok.
Quoting data from Dsat herself, illustrating the “high demand”, the deputy stressed that, in the first nine months of 2024, about 30.39 million calls of special taxis were recorded, with “a response rate not exceeding 50%”. "At the same time, it is difficult for residents to catch black taxis in community zones, which demonstrates that taxis in Macau are in a greater demand situation than the offer," he said.
Asked about possible measures to collect these problems, including a possible increase in special licenses, DSAT said only that "it is studying, in many ways, the number of special taxis and ways to increase its response rate to the call." In this sense, it continues “to alert the opinions of society and to present suggestions”, expecting to “respond to the needs of residents and tourists”.
“Macao is a tourist city, so, starting from the point of view of social reality and the needs of residents, the promotion of online marking services for more than a thousand existing black taxis is undoubtedly a way out,” Leong Sun iok insisted that there is a “lack of correspondence between the zones where taxis and potential passengers are impossible for efficiency in terms of distance. and time ”.
The deputy also praised the fact that an award company of the last competition promised “making their taxis available on a cool taxis platform, so passengers could make previous marking through application”. "This is a measure that deserves our recognition and gives a positive signal for general taxis to be marked through the internet," he argued.
 
“Accelerated” preparations for new contest
On the other hand, in response to Leong Sun Iok and other interpellation of Deputy Ma Io Fong, DSAT's director asserted that, “taking into account the successive expiry” of some taxi permits in 2025, it is “accelerating the preparatory work” of the public tender to assign general licenses, which “will be announced in a timely manner”.
After distributing 10 general licenses to taxis between 2023 and 2024, with a period of eight years and involving a total of 500 vehicles, the body postponed the calendar of the new contest. According to Lam Hin San, the decision was the need to “further“ further ”the procedures by reviewing the administrative regulation on the assignment of licenses for the transportation of passengers in light rental cars.
In any case, the same person believes that the gradual entry into operation of the 500 vehicles "will allow compensation for the number of taxis (including normal/ special taxis) whose permit has expired."
The quality of taxi services is another issue that worries ma io fong. On this matter, DSAT clarifies that an academic institution is conducting another study, which includes the “future development tendency of the sector size”, as well as “the analysis of the impact and effectiveness of radiotaxis development on the functioning of urban traffic and the services provided”.
The study aims to contribute to “improving the calls of call and prior taxi marking”, providing “a solid reference and foundation for the elaboration of policies related to the sector and for the inspection work”, without prejudice to the “order of exploration of taxis” and “legitimate rights and interests of all parties”.
On the other hand, DSAT indicated that it does not plan to launch a program of “High Quality Taxi Services Awards”, thus removing one of the suggestions made by Ma Io Fong. Still, he promised that, together with the Public Security Police Corps, he will "intensify the fight against offenses and cooperate with the sector companies and associations in the periodic lectures for legal disclosure in this context, in order to improve the services provided."</description><pubDate>2025-02-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Airport updates information system</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/aeroporto-actualiza-sistema-de-informacao/</link><description>Macao Airport is replacing the “air transport services information processing system” with a more updated model. This process is expected to be completed in the second half of this year. Improvement will allow, according to the civil aviation authority, to increase the efficiency of the connection between the airport management systems of Macau and Hong Kong airports airports
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Civil Aviation Authority (AACM) is under substitution of the “Air Transport Services Information Processing System” at Macau International Airport by a more up -to -date model, whose conclusion is expected to the second half of 2025. With the improvement introduced, AACM believes that the efficiency of the connection between the air traffic management systems of Hong Kong and Macau airports will be increased.
In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Leong Hong Sai, directed to airport airspace and safety management issues, AACM President Pun Wa Kin says that work for the modernization of communication, navigation and surveillance systems is also in preparation, estimating that the public tender is launched this year. The new systems should gradually enter into operation between 2026 and 2027.
Other modernization projects should be implemented during the current year, and part of the commercial area previously occupied by French stores to expand the areas of security and departure inspection, “improving the efficiency of the security inspection procedure through the optimization of space and the introduction of technological modifications,” says AACM's response to the Legislative Assembly deputy.
Regarding airspace management, the body that guides, regulates, and inspecting the activities related to civil aviation in the Airspace of MSAR, recalls that the authorities of the interior sector of China, Hong Kong and Macau have created a tripartite cooperation mechanism. In this sense, “regular meetings are held to elaborate airspace management plans in the medium and long term of the Rio das Pearl Delta region and explore new technologies to optimize the use of airspace”.
Among other initiatives, the new technology called “Required Navigation Performance - Approval Required” was introduced, with the aim of improving failed approach or flight deviation due to meteorological factors, significantly reducing the number of unstable approaches and increasing operational safety.
Regarding the development of the “air taxis” service, mentioned in the interpellation of Leong Hong Sai, AACM says that it cannot only be considered the functioning of the commercial market, "it is also necessary to prioritize and ensure both aviation and public protection safety."
Already on the issue of unmanned aircraft (drones), the response to the deputy indicates that, to monitor the development of technology and its wide application, AACM “strives to satisfy, as far as possible and ensure operational safety, the needs of use of unmanned aircraft in various sectors”.
To this end, it underlines, “after evaluating safety conditions, differentiated altitude restrictions were established and flight areas delimited for the operation of these aircraft in the limited Airspace of Macao”.
On the other hand, in order to facilitate government patrols and emergency rescue operations, when considering authorization for unmanned aircraft activities, AACM makes a comprehensive assessment based on factors such as flight, time, model and weight of the aircraft, among others.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mandar reiterates commitment to women's rights</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-reitera-compromisso-pelos-direitos-das-mulheres/</link><description>Saying to be “well aware” that “many women still face various challenges and difficulties”, the chief executive reiterated the government's commitment to defend women's rights and equal opportunities
 
Executive head, Sam Hou Fai, reaffirmed yesterday the commitment of the Government of Mashell in defense of women's rights and equal opportunities for both sexes. At the commemorative reception of the International Women's Day and the inauguration of the 38th Directorate and the Fiscal Council of the General Association of Women, the leader of the MSAR said it was "well aware" that "many women still face various challenges and difficulties."
On the other hand, he also said that it is "inspiring to see that in Macao there are more and more women who exceed the limitations imposed by tradition, actively entering different sectors and branches of activities." They noticed that they take with them "thin and incessant commitment, as well as the ambition of being extraordinary women in their position," and they demonstrate "splendid talents and abilities, becoming an indispensable force for the development of economics and society."
Regarding the role of the government regarding the defense of equality and women's rights, Sam Hou Fai has ensured that the government will continue to unite all sectors of the community to safeguard the rights and welfare of women in Macao. "We will continue to promote faster and better development of women's affairs, support compatriots in building their professional careers, encouraging them to perform their aspirations of life and that develop their talents," he said during his speech.
"We hope that Macao women will continue to demonstrate their unique charisma, to gather strength and be brave, to contribute to their wisdom and ability in their professions, and to continue to use their advantages and unique roles in the construction of family civility," Sam Hou Fai continued.
The chief executive also said that women will expect a new boost in the practice of 'a country, two systems' with Macao characteristics and that they continue to gain new merits in the opening of a new conjuncture of Macao's high quality development, in the great cause of the country's strengthening and the rejuvenation of the Chinese nation.
As for the General Association of Women, he noted that over the past 75 years "he has always led to the beautiful tradition of patriotism, of love to Macau and the care of women and children", giving "contributions to the development and progress of women and children's affairs."
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SMG Optimize Meteorological Surveillance</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/smg-optimizam-vigilancia-meteorologica/</link><description>Manila received the 57th session of the Tuffons Committee, which is part of Macao, with the participation of about a hundred experts. At the meeting, the director of meteorological and geophysical services stressed that Macau has learned from the experiences of other regions, while promoting the development of surveillance, forecasting and alerting techniques
 
The Directorate of Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) participated in the 57th Session of the Tupuses Committee, held in Manila, the capital of the Philippines, during which the work was balanced in 2024. About 100 specialists in meteorology, hydrology and prevent and reduction of disasters from Asia-Pacific.
The meeting also served to elaborate and project the work plan for this year, having performed exchanges and presentations of technical reports.
During the session, which took place for four days, the director of the SMG, who led the delegation of the territory, said that, in conjunction with members of the Committee, he will strive to “promote the exchange and meteorological cooperation at international and regional level”, learning from the advanced experiences of other regions, while “constantly promoting the development of meteorological surveillance techniques and forecasting techniques. and Macao Meteorological Alert ”.
Leong Weng Kun also said that the 20th Seminar on the Integration of the Tuffan Committee will take place in Macao, in the fourth quarter of this year, and that it was honored to contribute to "establishing an important exchange and cooperation platform for meteorological technology for countries and cities in the Asia-Pacific region."
The delegation of Macau participated at various points in the Tuphin Committee agenda, sharing their experiences on tropical storm forecasting techniques and disaster prevention and reduction work. According to a statement, SMGs are committed to strengthening regional cooperation, "in order to better communicate and face the challenges brought by tropical storms, discussing the increase in monitoring capacity, forecasting and alerting tropical storms."
The Tuffan Committee was created in 1968 and has 14 national and regional members. Its objective is to reinforce cooperation in order to reduce the damage caused by taps and natural calamities.
The Tuphin Committee was set together by the United Nations Economic and Social Commission for Asia and the Pacific and the World Meteorological Organization.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Manders want to deepen cooperation with Asean</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-quer-aprofundar-cooperacao-asean/</link><description>The reinforcement of exchange with the countries of Southeast Asia was the main point of the SAM Hou Fai meeting with the President of the Association for the Promotion of China-Asean Industrial Cooperation and Development. The chief executive said that the government will take advantage of the strength and advantages of the overseas Chinese and their family members who returned to Macau
 
The executive chief received at the government headquarters the president of the Association for the Promotion of China-Asean Industrial Development and Industrial Development and a permanent member of the National Committee of the Chinese People's Political Conference, Chi Tat Cheong, in a meeting where impressions were exchanged for the reinforcement of exchange between sinhean and Southeast Asia (Asean).
Sam Hou Fai indicated that Macau has been striving to deepen relations with Asean nations, with the purpose of "expanding cooperation space and increasing exchange with all local sectors."
According to an official note, the same responsible said that Macau is "a city that is part of Chinese and Western cultures, with quality tourist and cultural resources, and their complementary facilities." Sam Hou Fai has assured that the government will enjoy the development position “a center, a platform and a base” and the favorable policies outlined by the country, and “actively perform the strength and advantages of the overseas Chinese and their families who returned to Macao”.
At the end of the meeting, Sam Hou Fai made votes for the association to boost the exchange and cooperation between Macao and Asean countries, participate and help “the joint and quality promotion of“ a track, a route ”, with the aim of contributing to“ building Macao as a higher -level opening platform ”.
Also at the meeting were the Secretary for Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP, the chief of staff of the Chief Executive, Chan Kak, the chairman of the Administrative Board of the Institute of Commerce and Investment Promotion, U U SANG, the executive president of the Association for the Promotion of China-Asean Industrial Development Cooperation and other responsible of the same Association.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Southeast Asian market took STD to the Indonesia Fair</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mercado-sudeste-asiatico-levou-dst-a-feira-da-indonesia/</link><description>The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) led a group of representatives of integrated tourism and leisure companies and Air Macau to participate in the Indonesian International Tourism Fair 2025 (“Astanding Travel Fair”). The Macao Pavilion promoted the diversity of “tourism +” offers of destination, aiming to explore the markets of Indonesian visitors and Southeast Asia.
During the event, STD held four tourist promotion sessions for interaction with the public, presented Lion Dance and Portuguese Folk Dance exhibitions and cooperated with operators in promoting Macao tourist products, “in the sense of encouraging visitors to visit the destination in person,” he said in a statement.
Between January 1 and 9 this year, in cooperation with Air Macao, STD had already invited 21 tour operators from Jakarta and Surabaia for a familiar visit to Macau. During the trip, a contact scholarship was organized with operators from both destinations, which attracted representatives of 42 travel agencies from Macao and helped boost cooperation between both sides.
The Macao Pavilion at “Astanding Travel Fair”, with 54 square meters, had as its main decoration a large model of the Mak Mak tourism mascot, along with tiles and floor on Portuguese sidewalk. The stand highlighted the intersection elements of sino-Portuguese crops, world heritage and development as a creative city of gastronomy, events, leisure tourism, among other elements, to show the dynamism of the environment and the Macao tourism offers.
Organized by the association of Indonesian travel agencies, this fair is one of the largest -wide tourism events for consumers, attracting the participation of large number of destinations, airlines and tour operators from around the world. After in the last two years participated in the editions of Jakarta and Surabaia, STD was invited again to this year's event.
STD states that "it continues to move efforts to expand the southeastern Asian visitors market." In addition to conducting promotions and participating in tourism fairs in several target markets to increase the dissemination of destination, it also organizes Macau visits to Macau to show new tourist attractions, hotel infrastructures, among others, “with a view to boosting operators on two sides to create directed tourist products”, the note stresses.
For this year, the body has planned promotions in South Korea, Japan, Singapore, Indonesia, Thailand and Malaysia, to "continue to explore greater diversity of visitor markets and drive tourism and the economy of Macao."
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Five Star Hotels contrary general pricing in January</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/hoteis-de-cinco-estrelas-contrariam-subida-geral-de-precos-em-janeiro/</link><description>The average price of the hotel rooms in Macau increased 1.5% in January, in annual terms, to 1,408 patacas, the highest month of the year since 2017. Still, according to data from the Macao Hotel Association, which brings together 46 local establishments, the average price in five -star hotels dropped 2.3% compared to the same month of 2024 to 1,550 patacas. On the other hand, the report, released by the Directorate of Tourism Services, revealed that the average occupancy rate of hotels in the territory rose 3.7 percentage points in January to 94.7%. With lower prices, five -star hotels in Macau had the highest rise in the occupancy rate (plus 4.5 percentage points to 90.7%), although the most full three -star establishments were full (97.5%). January included this year part of the Lunar New Year, a high time for tourism at MSAR. Macau received in January almost 3.65 million visitors, 27.4% more than in the same month of 2024 and the second highest value ever. The number of visitors was only exceeded in August, which recorded more than 3.65 million. However, according to the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), more than 59% of visitors (2.16 million) arrived at organized excursions and spent less than one day in Macao. Hotel establishments welcomed more than 14.4 million guests in 2024, establishing a new record. According to DSEC data, the number of guests in hotels and pensions rose 6.4% compared to 2023. The previous record, 14.1 million guests, had been fixed in 2019, before the pandemic, in a year that Macao ended with only 38,300 rooms in 122 hotel establishments. At the end of 2024 the territory had 146 hotels and pensions, four more than the previous year and the highest number since DSEC began compiling this data in 1997. However, the number of available rooms decreased by 7.8% compared to 2023 to about 43,000. With fewer rooms available for more guests, the average occupancy rate of hotel establishments rose 4.9 percentage points to 86.4%, the highest value since 2019.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-02-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Women encouraged to practice sports</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mulheres-incentivadas-praticar-desporto/</link><description>The “Macau 2025 Women's Sports Festival”, organized by the Institute of Sport (ID) and the Macao General Association of Women, will take place on March 22 and 23, aiming to make different sports. With this initiative, the ID also aims to encourage the female population to develop a healthy and sporty model of life throughout life, as well as “arouse the attention of the various sectors of society” to “physical and mental health”. The event will feature associations of women from the cities of the Great Bay. On the 22nd, at 15:00, the Senate Largo will be held the exhibition of the physical exercises of sports for all, presented by the participants and by coaches and students of the recreation and maintenance classes. On Sunday, at 9:00 am, Tap Seac Polydortive Pavilion receives the recreational and sports games, with women grouped according to the age group. On site, a health post will be installed to sensitize knowledge about the prevention of women's diseases. In addition, taking advantage of the arrival of the 15th edition of the National Games, the activities add the elements of these competitions, so that the public can know them better. Each collectivity or entity can enroll up to five groups and the maximum number of teams is 70. Registration, online, will take place until 12:00 pm on March 14th. Meanwhile, ID promoted the “Sports Day” in the leisure zone of the Morais Venceslau pardon. The event had a large participation of the population, especially children and their families, narrowing their relationship through physical activity.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Breves FSS calls for care with fraudulent messages</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-fss-pede-cuidado-mensagens-fraudulentas/</link><description>The Social Security Fund (FSS) has been the target of phishing fraud and clarifies that it has not sent any message about Electronic Verification of FSS accounts. The incident was reported to the Judicial Police, which appeals to residents not to believe or click suspicious links. The message in question was sent in the name of the “Social Security Center”, whose content mentioned the need to click on the electronic address, otherwise it would be canceled. The FSS states that it has not sent the message and no link was attached, alerting the residents to be aware.
 
Influenza cases tripled between December and January
Health services registered 2,529 cases of mandatory declaration diseases in January, including 2,190 influenza, a number that, on the one hand, translates an annual break of 30.9% and, on the other, corresponds to triple those noted in the previous month. As for scarletin, 97 cases were reported, 55.7% less annually and 12.8% plus a monthly variation. In turn, cases of norovirus infection (82) rose 241% in a year, but lowered 53.4% ​​in a month.
 
Sands China resumes dividend payment
Sands China's shareholders will receive a $ 0.25 dollar dividend from Hong Kong by action regarding the 2024 financial year, the company announced. This payment, the first in five years, will be made on June 20 for shareholders registered on May 30. Based on the actions issued on January 31, 2025, the total amount of dividend to distribute is estimated at about $ 2.02 billion from Hong Kong. Galaxy Entertainment, Wynn Macau and MGM China have also resumed the payment of dividends, which had interrupted during the pandemic.
 
Tigerair “Exchange” Routes between Taiwan and Macau
Tigerair Taiwan will cancel flights between Taipé and Macau from March 30. On the other hand, the low-cost airline announced that it will resume the Taichung-Macau route with two calls a week. The frequency of the Kaohsiung-Macau route will be kept with three weekly trips. With the implementation of the new operational plan, Tigerair will thus operate five mashed flights.
 
MGO and ZHUHAI reinforce airport interconnection
The Central Government connection office on the MSAR will support the strengthening of interconnection between the airports and ports of Macau and Zhuhai, as well as cooperation in the area of ​​Science and Technology. The warranty was given by Zheng Xincong, director of the connection office, visiting a delegation of the Zhuhai Chamber, led by Wu Zetong, president of the municipality, Edmund Ho, vice president of the Chinese people's Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC). The delegation also exchanged ideas with MSAR vowels in the Popular National Assembly and CCPPC, and Edmund Hor stressed that both sides should make full use of their advantages in the second phase of deepened cooperation zone, supporting more companies and young people to innovate and create business in Hengqin.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Public projects represent 74% of environmental impact reports</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/projectos-publicos-representam-74-dos-relatorios-de-impacto-ambiental/</link><description>DSPA received 14 environmental impact assessment reports in 2024, an annual increase of six that contradicts the decline recorded in 2022 and 2023. Since 2009, 191 reports have been presented, with public projects representing 74% of the total
 
Sérgio Terra
 
Throughout 2024, they entered the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) 14 Environmental Impact Assessment Reports (AIA), six more than the previous year. This increase interrupts a two -year break cycle, as this type of studies decreased from 17 by 2021 to 13 by 2022 and only eight by 2023.
According to official data published on the DSPA Electronic Page, between 2009 and the end of 2024, 191 projects for environmental impact assessment were submitted, representing an annual average of 11.9. Within 16 years, about 74% of the total environmental evaluations involved public entities, with the remaining 26% integrated into the private sphere, reveals the body, stressing that this scenario proves the “initiative” of public services to promote AIA studies in the projects they develop.
The lowest number of AIA dates back to 2009, with a total of five reports, before entering a phase of ups and downs: 14 in 2010, 11 in 2011, seven in 2012, 13 in 2013, eight in 2015, 12 in 2015 and six in 2016. This environmental protection tool gained a new momentum in 2017 (16 reports) and 2018 (18), eventually reaching peak in 2019 (22). However, in 2020, the first year of the pandemic, there was a break at just seven.
DSPA presented in 2011 a “exploratory text” for the creation of an environmental impact evaluation regime and, two years later, released a list of types of projects subject to AIA, which was tested on public projects. After a new review of the evaluation list, in 2017 the reports also started to cover private projects.
On January 1 this year new rules were adopted, in order to make the AIA list “more operational and closer to Macao's development situation”. According to DSPA, the new adjustments took into account the experiences of the interior of China and neighboring regions, as well as the opinions of public services, associations and related sectors.
By organizing a new relevant construction or remodeling plan for the existing project (including demolition, if applicable), the contract promoting entity will have to determine whether or not there is the need to prepare an environmental impact assessment report, in accordance with the AIA list. According to DSPA, relevant/expansion remodeling refers “to the demarcation of the area, plant or changes in the design of the project that may eventually cause significant environmental impacts in places with high ecological value”, or when, in the lack of mitigation measures, the emission of pollutants is likely to cause “serious adverse impacts on the environment”.
The new list is divided into three parts: projects of establishment (new buildings or large remodeling/expansions); demolition projects; and establishment projects in a given zone (which include new buildings or large remodeling/expansions). The projects contained in the first two parts are subject to the evaluation of the environmental impact, however, in the third part, "the promoter must first present a brief description and data from the project, for the competent authorities to determine whether or not there is the need to evaluate the environmental impact."
In general, the AIA report is "elaborated by an independent (third) entity, specialized and believed, in order to represent its independence and credibility." Technical evaluation should cover factors related to air and water quality, noise, ecology in general, solid waste and soil pollution.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Domestic workers expect government to “open the dialogue”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/trabalhadoras-domesticas-esperam-governo-se-abra-ao-dialogo/</link><description>Jassy Santos, president of the progressive union of domestic workers in Macau, expects the new government to hear the "voice" of domestic workers and can open to dialogue. This after sending a letter to DSAL with seven suggestions to improve the working conditions of maids and the government organism has said that rights and interests are already guaranteed by law
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The president of the progressive union of domestic workers in Macao, Jassy Santos, told the Tribuna de Macao newspaper that the new government, led by Sam Hou Fai, to “open the dialogue” - after almost the end of last year had received a non -response from the Directors for Labor Affairs (DSAL) after sending a letter with some suggestions to improve the conditions of these workers in the territory. Orders included, for example, that households can only work a maximum of 12 hours a day, a minimum wage of 5,500 patacas and compulsory medical insurance.
“With the new government, we liked to hear our voice and open to the dialogue. Our role is to suggest and we are looking forward to sitting with the authorities and discussing what is happening to domestic workers, ”said Jassy Santos, stressing that it would be important that his work be" recognized. " “We need social welfare. We hope this could happen in the near future, ”he added.
In the letter sent to the DSal released by “All About Macau” and to which this newspaper had access, the association also claimed standard and legal contractual conditions, as well as a housing, food and transportation allowance, in the amount of 1,000, 1,200 and 300 patacas, respectively. He also asked for at least four days off per month and the right to compulsory holidays and annual vacations.
In addition, it was asked that in the case of termination of a contract without just cause, article 70 of the Labor Relations Law, which provides for the calculation of compensation, and that the period of the written contract applicable to non -resident workers (TNR) was applied to domestic. This contract “must include a stipulation that workers must enjoy 13 months salary and that after the termination of the contract, the remuneration of domestic workers must be calculated in the same way provided for in article 70”, may be read.
In response, Dsal stated that domestic workers in Macau are already protected by law. Regarding working hours, the body said that employers and domestic workers may sign an agreement, but a 30 -minute rest of 30 minutes and a rest time of 10 consecutive hours or total time not less than 12 hours a day should be guaranteed. "If agreements are not signed, domestic workers should not work more than eight hours a day or more than 48 hours a week," he said.
Regarding the issue of dismissal without just cause, DSAL stated only that, according to the law, employers have an obligation to pay compensation. He concluded that, "in the future the government will listen carefully to opinions regarding the revision of the Labor Relations Law and will consider the issue in accordance with the real situations of society."
Given the answer, Jassy Santos said, quoted by the “All About Macau”, was “dissatisfied and disappointed”, understanding that the body only chose to repeat the legal provisions that are already known to the workers. He also noted that Dsal did not fully respond to seven suggestions.
Jassy Santos has lamented that, even if, according to the authorities, rights are guaranteed by law, the truth is that there are situations in which “the support provided by DSAL are not enough to solve the difficulties” of TNR. In this sense, he continued, workers "feel many times they were ignored."
To the Macao Tribune, Jassy Santos said that in January he met the Consulate General of the Philippines, having delivered the same letter with seven suggestions. “They said they are willing to help… but without promises,” said the associative leader.
Compared to this year, Jassy Santos says he will continue to fight for domestic workers of foreign nationality in Macau to be more recognized in society and have more legal guarantees. It will also strive to achieve the minimum wage and the maximum limit of working hours.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt announces the first discovery in 100 years of a pharaonic tomb</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/egipto-anuncia-primeira-descoberta-em-100-anos-de-um-tumulo-faraonico/</link><description>The Ministry of Antiquities of Egypt announced the discovery of the tomb of Tutmés II, the first ancient royal tomb found since Tutankamon's in 1922.
Tutmés II was the son of Tutmés I and his minor wife, Mutnofret, who was probably daughter of Ahmés I. He was therefore a minor son of Tutmés I and chose to marry his royal half sister, Hatchepsut, to ensure his royalty. As Mutnofret was a princess and Tutmés I was a commoner, they probably married only after Tutmés became king, so his son was born after his father's coronation, and probably after half sister Hatchepsut, who was Pharaoh's daughter with his primary wife.
This would mean that Tutmés II was in early adolescence when it became Pharaoh. Although successfully repressed rebellions in Nubia and the uprising and defeated a group of nomadic Bedouins, these campaigns were carried out specifically by the king's generals, not by Tutmés II himself which is often interpreted as evidence that Tutmés II was even a minor when he took over the throne. Tutmés II generated Neferure with Hatchepsut, and Tutmés III, with a smaller wife called ISET.
Some archaeologists believe that during the government of Tutmés II Hatchepsut was the true power behind the throne, due to the similar internal and external policies that were later adopted during his reign and because of his claim that he was his father's intended heiress. It is portrayed in several relief scenes from a Karnak portal dating from the reign of Tutmés II, both together with her husband and alone and later, became Pharaoh several years after the government of her husband's young successor, Tutmés III; This is confirmed by the fact that "the queen's agents have replaced the king's name in some places with his own."
Now, the tomb of Tutmés II was found near the Vale dos Reis in Luxor, southern Egypt, a few kilometers from its imposing funeral temple, erected on the west bank of the Nile.
It is “one of the most important archaeological discoveries of recent years,” celebrated the Ministry of Antiquities.
According to preliminary studies, the tomb, excavated by an Egyptian-British joint mission, was emptied in antiquity, leaving the tomb without royal mummy or the golden splendor associated with the discovery of Tutankamon.
Its entry was first located in 2022 in the mountains of Luxor, west of the Vale dos Reis, but the experts believed it led to the tomb of a royal wife.
The team then found “fragments of alabaster vessels with the name of Pharaoh Tutmés II, identified as the 'deceased king', as well as inscriptions with the name of his main royal wife, Queen Hatshepsut,” details the ministry.
Shortly after the king's burial, the water flooded the funeral chamber, damaging the interior and fragmenting a plaster coating decorated with extracts from the book of Amduat, an old funeral text over the beyond.
Also found in the grave were some funeral furniture that belonged to Tutmés II, the ministry said.
According to mission chief Piers Litherland, quoted by the Ministry of Antiquities, the team will continue their work in the region, hoping to find objects that were originally in the tomb.
This announcement occurs at a time when Egypt intensifies efforts to boost tourism, an essential source of foreign currency for the country's economy. Last year, Egypt received 15.7 million tourists and this year expects a visit of 18 million, especially thanks to the expected inauguration of the great Egyptian museum, at the foot of the Giza pyramids.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-02-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>