<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Game can exceed 23 billion for the first time since 2019</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jogo-pode-exceder-23-mil-milhoes-pela-primeira-vez-desde-2019/</link><description>The good performance of the gaming sector in recent months, reinforced by the “resilience” during the typhoon season, is expected to increase in October, with the “Golden Week” contributing to the best result in the last six years, predict analysts from JP Morgan and Seaport Research Partners. Forecasts point to a monthly turnover of more than MOP23 billion, reflecting an annual increase of around 13%
 
Sérgio Terra
 
Benefiting the tourist impulse of the “Golden Week” commemorative China's Day, the gross revenues of Macau casinos are expected to exceed 23 billion Patacas this month, illustrating homologous increases between 11 and 13% and the highest level in six years, although they remain far from 26.44 billion counted in October of the pre-pound year, according to the JP Morgan Investment Bank projections and Corretora Seaport Research Partners. The 23 billion bark could be overthrown for the first time since 2019, the year this brand was exceeded in nine months.
In the first five days of the “golden week”, celebrated between October 1 and 8, the daily average of revenues should exceed 1.1 billion Patacas, estimated the DS Kim, Selina Li and Lindsey Qian, JP Morgan, noting that it is an amount higher than the same period of 2024 (1.08 billion), “potentially equaling the level of 1.16 billion” reached in the era Pre-Covid. "The final demand is expected to be longer and stronger this year, probably generating between 750 and 750 million patacas a day in the second week (October 6-12), an increase of about 15% over last year's 643 million," they added.
According to the same forecasts, revenues will grow about 10% in the first two weeks of October, in the homologous variation, the result of a daily average of the 930 million Patacas, ie 84 million in annual terms.
With similar projections, Vitaly Umansky, an analyst at Seaport Research Partners, believes that growth in October should be "driven by increased marketing and, especially, by continuous ease of money exit", without forgetting the "robust emission of visas." Although it points out that any interruptions caused by tuffles may affect the results, the analyst also argues that the “continuous” holding of “entertainment events” and the realization of a trade agreement between the US and China should also contribute to strengthening “consumer confidence and the desire to spend and travel to Macao”.
For the 2025 general calculation, Umansky foresees an annual rise of 8.4% in the game market in Macao, including an increase of 12.4% in the fourth quarter. In addition, it expects a growth of 7% in 2026 and 2027, based on factors such as the high hotel occupation and the “strong” recovery of the base market base.
Despite having started the year “smoothly”, Macau continues to be “a secular market with long-term growth”, emphasizes the analyst.
In the first nine months of 2025, revenues rose 7.1% to 181.34 billion, compared to the same period in 2024, and reached 82.3% of the value recorded between January and September 2019, according to data from the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate. According to Umansky, the mass market was equivalent to 118% of the 2019 level by the end of September, while the recovery of the VIP segment reached 28%.
 
“Resilience”
In September, the game's revenues ciphed in “only” 18.29 billion Patacas, noting a monthly break of 17.5% and an annual rise of 6%. However, they were affected by the passage of the “Ragasa” super tuffon, which forced the closing of the casinos for 33 hours.
"We estimate that the typhoon reduced monthly gross revenues by between 5% and 10% - the equivalent of approximately three business days - which implies that September would have easily seen double-digit growth without the storm", said JP Morgan, in a report titled "Typhoon? What typhoon? Macau remains resilient".
As an example of this resilience, analysts point out that third trimester revenues (62.57 billion) increased 12.5% ​​and 2.4% in annual and quarterly terms, respectively, and already corresponded to 88.4% of the same period of 2019.
"The result reinforces our view that the search in Macau is in a cyclic cycle after reaching positive inflection in the second trimester of 2025, driven by a positive effect of wealth (for high standard Chinese) and wide liquidity in Hong Kong and China," said DS Kim, Selina Li and Lindsey Qian.
 
More than 190,000 visitors on the 4th day of the Golden Week
On Saturday, the fourth day of the “golden week”, Macau welcomed 191,176 visitors after registered 182,003 on the eve and 163,932 on Thursday, according to data from the Public Security Police (CPSP). Yesterday, until 5 pm, another 89,000 visitors entered. According to CPSP, in the first two days of October, the borders accounted for about 1.4 million inputs and exits, reflecting an annual climb of 6%. On average, the MSAR scored 705,000 border tickets per day. Also according to CPSP, at 23h00 of October 2 the accumulated number of visitors this year reached 30 million, this moment arriving 40 days earlier than in 2024.</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Bridge already worked with typhoon signal 8</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ponte-macau-ja-funcionou-sinal-8-de-tufao/</link><description>The Macao Bridge remained openly open, with sign 8, for the first time since it was inaugurated. The typhoon “Matmo” was the 12th storm to reach the MSAR in 2025, a record number in more than 50 years. In addition, it was the fourth time in history that signal 8 was raised for four occasions in the same year

PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
In the early hours of yesterday, the Macau bridge remained open during the 8th of Tropical Storm signal, for the first time since it was inaugurated in October 2024, with authorized vehicles and light passenger cars to be able to circulate on the bridge during the passage of the typhoon "maton". On Friday, an order from the chief executive who began to allow traffic, in a conditioned manner, on the Macau Bridge, with sign 8 in force, was published in an official bulletin. It is recalled that the authorities had performed a test on the circulation on the Macao Bridge about a month ago, during level 8, when the Tapah tropical storm passes.
The order also conferred to the Civil Protection Action Commander Wong Sio Chak, the power to suspend circulation, "if factors such as the intensity of tropical storms, the water level in the Storm Surge, precipitation and the strength of the wind are risks capable of undermining public safety."
This year, in addition to the “MATMO” being the 12th Tropical Storm to reach Macau, it was also the fourth time that Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) issued level 8. Signal 8 had only been raised four times in 1993, 2008 and 2022. It is also necessary to reassemble to 1974 to find a year with so many tropical storms since there are records.
According to a SMG balance, level 8 or higher winds persisted, in open areas and mashed bridges, even though the typhoon was held 300 kilometers from Macao, which led authorities to conclude that "the distance cannot be the only criterion to determine whether a signal should be ousted or not." The higher average speeds of the wind reached level 10, with high levels of level 12.
Signal 1 had been issued on Friday night, having been replaced by level 3 at 4pm on Saturday. At 02:00 yesterday, Sam Hou Fai declared a state of immediate prevention and the SMG raised signal 8. The Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services suspended early childhood, primary, secondary and special education classes throughout the day and transport services were also suspended. Signal 8 remained in force until 1:00 p.m., when it dropped to level 3, also ending the immediate prevention status.
 
One minor injury and 16 incidents
The Civil Protection Operations Center (COPC) recorded only one minor injury and 16 incidents, including 10 cases of removal of objects knocked down or at risk of falling, three incidents on construction sites and three incidents of falling from trees. The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) had to close traffic on several streets and on a viaduct in the Tamagnini Barbosa area, due to the possibility of scaffolding falling near the Dª Building. Julieta Nobre de Carvalho.
The Institute for Social Affairs' emergency reception centers received a total of nine users.
Some low-lying areas of Porto Interior recorded slight flooding. The COPC also issued a clarification regarding a video that circulated online, which claimed that there had been serious flooding in the Patane area, with the CPSP confirming on the spot that there was no flooding. According to civil protection, the video was filmed during the passage of “Ragasa.
The suspension of transport services led to large numbers of people traveling to taxi waiting areas at the Portas do Cerco border and the Hengqin Border Post, resulting in waiting times of more than an hour. At 10:30 am, 600 people were at the Workers' Field at Portas do Cerco, where 10 police officers were deployed, while another 280 people remained in the arrivals area of ​​the Hengqin Border Post. Around 408 regular taxis were operational.
According to the Civil Aviation Authority, as of 8am yesterday, 18 flights were cancelled, 26 were delayed and seven had changed schedules. Public bus, special taxi and Metro services gradually resumed from 1pm, with bus routes being adjusted due to road conditions. The connecting buses from the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macao Bridge border crossings to the HKSAR and the shuttle buses to Hong Kong Airport also resumed operations in the afternoon.
In anticipation of the passage of the “Matmo”, Wong Sio Chak chaired a meeting in the COPC, to hear the work of response to the typhoon by the members of the civil protection structure, highlighting the “close collaboration” between the authorities and the efforts to be made “to protect the safety from life and the goods of the population”.
Tourism services postponed the exhibitions of the UK and Brazil teams, which were scheduled for tonight, under the 33rd International Fire Competition.</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CLASS OF CASINOS-SATHELITE “threatens” pledge houses</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/fecho-de-casinos-satelite-ameaca-casas-de-penhores/</link><description>The streets of Nape and Zape are few residents and tourists circulating at night, Macao, October 2, 2025. The end of satellite casinos will bring problems for trade in general and pledge stores in Macao. (Accompanies Lusa Text of 05-10-2025) Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro/Lusa



Businesspeople told Lusa that the closure of Macau's satellite casinos threatens the survival of economic sectors that depend on them, such as pawnshops and high-end retail.
The streets of the ZAPE (Outer Harbor Landfill Zone) and NAPE (New Outer Harbor Landfill Zone) zones in Macau, once lively with players, are becoming deserted. The satellite casinos, which were the lifeblood of these parts of the city, are set to close by the end of the year, leaving pawnshops and high-end stores empty and their owners apprehensive about the future.
"The pledge houses in these areas will simply close or change. I see no other solution," said the president of the General Association of Penhoratrs of Macao, Alexander Wai Kai Leung.
Among the satellite casinos located in Zape and Nape are the Royal House, Fortune, Kam Pek, Landmark, Legend Palace and Waldo. Lusa tried to contact the hotels that houses these spaces, but none of its employees could indicate what the future of the place will be after closing. Grand Emperor serves as an example: the casino closed three years ago and the facilities remain empty.
"If the casinos close, the impact for us is significant. Our livelihood depends on the players", highlighted Leung, also expressing the hope that the satellite casinos will remain open.
In response to the impending closing, the Tourism Services Directorate (STD) told Lusa that “intends to attract visitors” to the Zape area to support local trade. Measurements for the doing include events, improvement of the urban landscape and the offer of special packages directed to concert spectators, which include 'vouchers' of purchases and museum tickets.
Authorities have already started testing this plan. In August, they organized a temporary market at ZAPE. More than 30 stalls were set up in the market, which promoted artisanal products and gastronomic offers, with the total number of visitors being around 36,000 in four days.
Businesspeople like Leong remain skeptical, however. The president of the pawnshops association questions these measures, considering them useless for the sector. "Our industry depends on players as its main customers. They can attract people to dine on the street, but I don't see how that benefits us," he said, adding that he feels that the sector has been "marginalized by the authorities, who consider the business 'high risk' for money laundering."
According to the association, there are about 25 pledge houses at Zape and Nape.
The threat extends beyond pawnshops. Store windows like the In Vo Chong Group display shark fins, ‘premium whiskey’ and Moutai, captivating a wealthy clientele.
Lok Chi Lai, Assistant Secretary-General of the Hong Kong and Macau Swallow Nests Association, recognizes the government's efforts to increase the influx of people other than the gaming space regulars. However, he noticed, these initiatives “cannot attract high range customers to consume”, only attract “young people to take photographs”, clarifying that there are more than 40 establishments of this kind in both areas of the city.
"Those who come to play are willing to buy luxury goods at higher prices to offer. Without these customers, the future doesn't look so bright," said Lok.
On the other hand, he added, promoting hotel offer at Zape and Nape is also ineffective because "the hotels here are old (…), and high -end customers prefer to stay in five -star hotels in Cotai."
Lok said he “absolutely disagrees” with the closure of the satellite casinos and criticized the government for not having adequately planned the transition in the two areas of the city where they will disappear during the three-year grace period that is now coming to an end.
Secretary for Economy and Finance Tai Kin Ip said in June that there are 320 stores located near satellite casinos, estimating that half would likely feel a “direct impact” from their closure.
In June, following the formal announcement of the closure of the satellite casinos, more than 70 ZAPE traders signed a petition demanding government intervention, asking for the satellite casinos to remain in operation.
According to a recent report by real estate consultant Jones Lang Lang Lang (JLL), the closure of satellite casinos is contributing to the drop in commercial properties in both areas of the city, Zape and Nape.
 
*Jing Wu, from Lusa agency. Edited text</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CPSP deputy commissioner suspected of abuse of power at borders</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/subcomissario-cpsp-suspeito-de-abuso-de-poder-nas-fronteiras/</link><description>Between 2020 and 2024, a CPSP subcommittee will have abused his power at the post of migration he headed for more than 100 times to get more easily into the MSAR, alone or with family members, announced the CCAC, which referred the case to the prosecutor. CPSP has already filed a disciplinary process
 
A deputy commissioner of the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) is suspected of having abused his power, on numerous occasions, to enter Macau with his family through the migration post under his command. According to the Commissioner against Corruption (CCAC), which detected the case, the deputy commissioner went through the internal channel intended for employees, requiring subordinates to handle border crossing formalities, in order to circumvent normal customs control procedures at the border post.
During the investigation, the CCAC learned that between 2020 and 2024, the suspect entered and left the territory, alone or with the family, for more than a hundred times through the migration post he headed, without passing the common channels to residents and tourists. According to CCAC, he took advantage of his police identification card to access the interdict's interdict employees, where formalities concerning the border passage were performed.
In addition, when entry into the MSAR, it avoided passing through the customs inspection zone, ignoring the respective formalities, the measures of migration control and the order of the border passage of the MSAR.
Considering that the deputy commissioner had committed the crime of abuse of power provided for and punished by the Penal Code, the CCAC forwarded the case to the Public Prosecutor's Office and reported the case to the CPSP. “The CCAC reiterates that public service workers, particularly law enforcement agents, must be more rigorous in their self-discipline and must not defy the law, in the hope of not being caught”, highlights the statement.
In turn, CPSP has announced the establishment of a disciplinary process and a review of internal procedures, to reinforce supervision mechanisms, promising to treat the case with seriousness and total cooperation with the investigation. CPSP also assured that it has always given great importance to the discipline and integrity of its agents.</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Macau Races On” wins award in London</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-races-on-vence-premio-em-londres/</link><description>On the fourth it was for good. After three nominations in previous editions of the International Motor Sport Film Awards, Macau achieved the much-desired trophy with the production “Macau Races On”. The director, Sérgio Perez, told TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper that the award represents “a reward” for everyone who “made our work possible over these years”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Macao won one of the categories of international motorized sports films, having presented the production “Macau Races on”, by director Sérgio Perez. The seven -minute film, which portrays the environment of the Macao Grand Prix (GPM) and is on display at the GPM Museum, won first place in “Best Event Film”.
The award ceremony for what are considered the “Oscars” of the motor film industry took place in London. To the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, the director said that “this award represents, in a way, a reward, not only for the entire team behind the Grand Prix videos, but also for everyone who believed in and made our work possible over these years”.
For success to have been achieved, he highlights the vast team that made the film's production possible, including the support of the Tourism Services, Sports Institute, GPM Commission, pilots and many other stakeholders. “It is an immense responsibility for me as a director, and for everyone on the team, to fairly represent this which is, without a doubt, the most emblematic event in the city, and which, above all, in its essence, reflects an immense soul and passion that exists in the people of Macau, something unique and special in the World of motor sport”, he highlighted.
The interim director of audiovisual content at DST, who has a group of professional collaborators in the field, points out that “every year we try to raise the level and quality of the Stories we tell around the event” and, “fortunately, the recognition is there”.
The “International Motor Film Awards” have been in existence for 12 years and the “Best Event”, won by Macao SAR, included productions from all over the world. This was the first time that Macau received an award of this type, but it was the fourth nomination, the first having occurred with the first film that the team made for the GPM Museum, “The Legend of the Macau Grand Prix”.
For the 2025 edition, “we were named two films, what we did from the 71st GPM, which we named‘ 71st Macau Grand Prix-The Film ’, and what they won, Macau Races On”, explains the 46-year-old director, who since 2004 has been part of STD. He adds that the 70th GPM filming was also made, "already with the idea that we would make this movie (Macau Races on), so it made the whole movie the whole impact it had."
The video was subjected to a contest by Sérgio Perez himself on an online platform, having been accepted after selection process, evaluated by several jury members, including former pilot Andy Wallace.
According to the director, the structure of the film is created through music. “It's a process that I use a lot in my creative process, creating the narrative first through a musical thread, which then serves to guide the image, and the music can eventually come out from the moment the film's narrative and rhythm require it”, he observes.
The script, musical selection and creation of the film's structure were made by him. “I followed the execution, with my long-time producer, Ho Man U, co-directing some segments that included animation elements and some direction of filming on FPV drones”, he explains.</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>The rise and fall of the plerians</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ascensao-queda-dos-penhoristas/</link><description>Veng Seng House of Pity, Macao, October 2, 2025. The end of satellite casinos will bring problems for trade in general and pledge stores in Macao. (Accompanies Lusa Text of 05-10-2025) Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro/Lusa



Alexander Wai Kai Leong, 39, fourth owner of Veng Seng Pawnshop, is a man whose story is told in gold and jade, and his first impression is remarkable, thanks to the jewelry he wears.
A shiny gold watch and a gold ring with a large bright green jade stone immediately draw the eye to the left hand. The right hand is equally adorned, with a golden dragon ring wrapped around the index finger and a gigantic ruby ​​sparkling on the ring finger. A string of wooden beads wraps around the right wrist, adding the finishing touch to the ensemble.
Leong's legacy began in 1940, when the family owned eight pawnshops in Hong Kong. At that time, during the Second Sino-Japanese War, pawnshops were experiencing a boom, fueled by refugees fleeing to Hong Kong and Macau in serious difficulties. “People pawned shoes, duvets and clothes in my grandfather’s time,” he told Lusa.
After 70 years in the stronghold of players, the store moved to a neighborhood inhabited by migrant workers. The change has led the Leong business to have as main customers workers in Southeast Asia countries, which meant "significantly lower profits." “A player customer is equivalent to 30 or 50 local or migrant workers,” he estimated, stressing that these workers often pledged jewelry for liquidity after sending most salaries to home countries.
Still, it does not regret change. "Good thing we moved. If we had not done it, it would have been terrible," said the businessman, who is also president of the Fiscal Council of the Macao Stress Traders Association.
The Leong family witnessed the entire cycle of expansion and contraction of the pledge industry, an intrinsically linked to the casino business. Shortly after the liberalization of the game in 2003, says Alexander, the number of pledge houses “increased dramatically” when compared to the period until the transfer of sovereignty. "Macao had so far no more than 40 or 50 establishments," he said.
“In the moments of peak of activity, around 2014, there were more than 200 pledge houses,” he said. This number has fallen in the meantime significantly, today is only 56, a number that has not been seen since the period prior to 1999, and the descent has not yet stained, given the new challenges that are announced.
The decline began in 2019. "The massive protests in Hong Kong impacted our industry in Macao. The [Chinese] tourists of the continent were afraid to come to Hong Kong and, as Macau is neighboring, they didn't travel here either," explained the attachment.
"Then, when the pandemic arrived, the business fell to the pike," he continued. After the end of borders, many pledge businesses, which previously operated 24 hours a day, had only daytime. "This forced the closing of numerous houses," he added.
The most recent challenge arises now, with the closure of satellite casinos until the end of the year, and the crisis in the sector “will deepen even further”, guarantees Leong. From now on, the law of the strongest must prevail, only the best businesses will survive, without the prospect of external help or other aid other than that based on the very nature of the activity.
Leong feels that the sector has been “marginalized by authorities, who consider pawnshops to be a ‘high risk’ business for money laundering”. But, he argues, even though the gambling industry is considered nuclear, “pawnshops have served a mutually beneficial purpose, both to themselves and to governing powers, for centuries.”
The pledge houses are a vital part of the ecosystem, he said, as a message: “not only generate tax revenue for the government and value the city that never sleeps, but also provide additional employment opportunities to Macao residents”.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>STD made new invested in the Japanese market</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dst-fez-nova-investida-mercado-japones/</link><description>The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), together with local tour operators, participated in the Japan Tourism Expo, with the aim of boosting the dissemination of Diversity of Macao's “Tourism +” offers, attracting more Japanese visitors and expanding sources of international tourists.
Considered the largest tourism fair in the country, “Tourism Expo Japan” was held for the first time in Aichi Prefecture, in the central region of Japan, attracting more than 1,300 exhibitors from companies and organizations from 82 countries and regions, and more than 120 thousand visitors.
The Macau Pavilion, with an area of ​​108 square meters, presented the theme “Feel Macau”, highlighting “the unique charm of the city, characterized by the fusion of Chinese and Western cultures”, according to DST. The stand showcased the Macao SAR's new tourist attractions, World Heritage Sites, typical cuisine and annual events, and included an interactive photography area and question and answer games with prizes, as well as the sale of Macau tourist products.
The space also served as a platform for exchanges and negotiations with tourist operators from around the world, especially from Japan, with a view to exploiting opportunities for cooperation and business.
During the event, a new travel guide for parents and children intended for the Japanese market was launched, “Journey to Experience Macao: Family Fun in Macao”, with information on hotels, restaurants, new facilities and family attractions. The guide recommends itineraries that combine education and leisure, “showing in all aspects Macao's friendly facilities and services to receive family visitors, further promoting the diverse development of the market”, stresses the same note.
STD considers that “Japan is a market of visitor from Northeast Asia with high potential for Macao”, recalling that there are regular direct flights between the two sides. The body is exploring, with various initiatives, the Japan market, in the sense of “continuing to raise the name of Macau at the international level”, as well as “attracting visitors to Japan to experience the charms and new tourist elements” of the MSAR.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau and Cape Verde expand financial cooperation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-cabo-verde-alargam-cooperacao-financeira/</link><description>The fight against money laundering and terrorist financing and staff training are some of the areas covered by a new cooperation agreement between the Macau Monetary Authority and the Bank of Cape Verde
 
The Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM) and the Cape Verde Bank signed a new cooperation agreement to deepen the exchange in matters related to financial supervision. Focused on the “prudential” aspect, this agreement, entered into during the 12th “Meeting of Governors of the Central Banks of Portuguese -Speaking Countries”, held in Cape Verde, “covers areas such as the combating laundering of capital and terrorism, technical cooperation, the formation of professional frameworks, as well as the supervision and interchange related to emerging financial services, with the purpose of jointly safeguarding security and to safeguard and to safeguard Stability of the respective financial systems, ”said AMCM in a statement.
“This initiative symbolizes a deepening of cooperation and exchange between the two institutions in the field of financial supervision”, summarizes the regulatory entity of Macao.
AMCM sealed the first cooperation and technical assistance agreement with the Cape Verde Bank in 1999, and the updated version was signed in September 2024 in Macao, on the 2nd “Conference of Central Banks Governors and Financial Tables between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”.
So far, AMCM has already signed bilateral cooperation agreements with 12 financial supervisory authorities from eight Portuguese-speaking countries. Looking to the future, the organization guarantees that it will “continue to deepen bilateral and multilateral cooperation with Portuguese-speaking countries in the financial sphere, actively promoting exchange and interaction” between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, in order to “fully play the role of Macau as a “Financial Services Platform between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries”.
The meeting of governors of the central banks of Portuguese-speaking countries includes interventions of representatives of Angola, Brazil, Cape Verde, Guinea-Bissau, Equatorial Guinea, Mozambique, Portugal, Sao Tome and Principe, and Timor-Leste, as well as the Central Bank of Western Africa States and the Bank of Central States.</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Opera Carmen opened Music Festival</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/opera-carmen-abriu-festival-de-musica/</link><description>Description



A dozen main shows and 14 extra activities fill this year's edition of the Macau International Music Festival (FIMM), an event that kicked off on Friday and brings together world-renowned artists and young talents. Dedicated to the theme “Vocal Waves”, FIMM offers the public a multiplicity of musical pieces at the autumn festival.
After the inaugural session, the public was able to watch the show Carmen – Opera in Four Acts by Georges Bizet, co-presented by SJM and FIMM, which gave the Festival “a powerful start”, as highlighted by the Cultural Institute (IC).
The event presents magnificent musical works that “result from the encounter between Eastern and Western civilizations”, among which the performance of fado singer Cuca Roseta stands out, together with the Macau Chinese Orchestra, on Saturday, October 11th, at 8:00 pm in the CCM Grand Auditorium. The artist will interpret the voice of the Portuguese soul and explore the themes of love, loss, longing and destiny, with the unique touch of the Portuguese guitar, in excerpts such as “Meu”, “Preto e Branco”, “Canção do Mar”, “Não sei Onde” and “Finamente”.
Another highlighted concert will be starred by accredited pianist Mikhail Pletnev and the Rachmaninoff International Orchestra, on the 25th and 26th, also at the CCM, presented by Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, in which the four piano concerts will be performed by Rachmaninoff.
It will also be in focus Thomas Hampson, a world -recognized baritone, to play several evocative Lieder, by Gustav Mahler. Meanwhile, violinist Daniel Hope alleges the Swiss gstaad festival orchestra to present two versions of The Four Stations in different Eras: Antonio Vivaldi's classic work and a recomposed minimalist version of British contemporary composer Max Richter. “This juxtaposition will create an impressive experimental sound landscape that intertwines representations of the original play and amazing reconstructions of the new version,” says IC.
To commemorate the 80th Anniversary of Victory in the Chinese People's War of Resistance against Japanese Aggression and the 120th Anniversary of the Birth of Xian
On the other hand, “Sheng in his best” will be presented by Wu Wei's renowned interpreter, violence Martin Stegner and double bassist Janne Saksala.
Tickets for the end are for sale at the “Enjoy Macao” ticket office and have several discounts.</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau represented at CCP meetings</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-representado-nas-reunioes-ccp/</link><description>The president of the Regional Council of Asia and Oceania of the Portuguese Communities Council (CCP) and secretary of the CCP Permanent Council will participate in a series of meetings of the CCP Permanent Council, which will take place in Lisbon from 13 to 16 October. According to Rui Marcelo, the agenda, “intense and comprehensive”, reflects “CCP's commitment to dialogue with the highest institutions of the Portuguese Republic and political agents”, with the central objective of “discussing and promoting public policies that recognize and value Portuguese communities abroad”. The program begins at the Independence Palace, with the public session “(re) to know and value the Portuguese communities abroad”, a joint organization of the CCP and the Historical Society of Independence of Portugal. The Macao Counselor will integrate the debate panel, subordinate to the theme “Communities How do we perceive them and what to do: an active, an asset or a piece of rhetoric?”, Sharing the perspective of the communities of Asia and Oceania. Over the next three days, more than 20 meetings will take place in the Assembly of the Republic and with other entities. Among the main points under discussion include the definition of strategic policy for communities and their state budget translation to 2026, the alteration of electoral legislation and the improvement of voting modalities for the Portuguese abroad. Hearings with presidential candidates are also scheduled, in which the main concerns of the Portuguese in the world will be presented.</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Contest on Events Visa PME and 'Startups'</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/concurso-sobre-eventos-visa-pme-startups/</link><description>With the support of the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM), Galaxy Entertainment and the Business Incubation Center for young people in Macau (MYEIC) will promote a contest on the "Made in Macau" event organization. Aimed at small and medium enterprises (SMEs) and young startups registered in Macao, applications are open until October 10. The winner will receive a contract in the amount of 200,000 Patacas and the opportunity to organize a “Made in Macao” market in the gamer's support areas, on November 27 and 28. Candidates must be residents of Macao aged 18 to 44 years. Each company may present, at most, a proposal with the theme “Made In Macau”, focusing on promoting local SMEs and products manufactured in Macau. The proposal should include between 10 and 14 stands, with a careful analysis of local layout, stage design, installation, decorative environment and traders recruitment. According to Galaxy, evaluations will be based on five criteria: “creativity and theme”, “functionality”, “quality of execution”, “sustainability” and “ability to support local SMEs and promote the Made in Macao principle”. "This competition aims to improve the competences of participants in event management, covering the whole process, from the development and planning of the concept to the implementation on site. It also serves as a platform for other places to present their products and expand business opportunities," says the Galaxy note.</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ruins welcome concert from the Fall Middle Festival</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ruinas-acolhem-concerto-festival-meio-outono/</link><description>Two sessions of “One Full Moon Night” will cheer up today the ruins of São Paulo. According to the Cultural Institute (IC), at 20h00 and 21h00, the Chinese orchestra of Macao and the singers Vivian Chan and Kane to Ieong will merge “traditional Chinese sounds with the beauty of the world heritage”, under the celebrations of the Fall Festival. The concert will be led by the resident conductor of the Chinese orchestra of Macao, Liao Yuan-Yu, who will interpret popular festive themes such as “colorful clouds chasing the moon”, “Full Moon and Flowers Blossing” and the work “Largo do Lilau”, in a representation of the “distinct characteristics of Macao”. Local musicians Vivian Chan and Kane to Ieong will interpret 'pop' themes as "red beans" and "The Moon represents my heart." As part of the 5th edition of the “Festival of Arts and Culture of the Great Guangdong-Hong Bay Kong-Macau”, the show will offer a repertoire that “joins tradition and modernity” and represents “The Cultural Charm of Macao”, indicates IC. Entry is free, and the public can also track the broadcaster through various channels, namely the different social networks of the IC and the Chinese orchestra of Macao, as well as on the website and mobile application of TDM. In the designated zone of the show, access control measures will be implemented and a maximum number of persons defined in order to ensure public safety. The CI warns that the concert is canceled, in the event of adverse weather situations.</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Proposed four more borders between Hengqin and Mand</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/propostos-mais-quatro-postos-fronteiricos-entre-hengqin-raem/</link><description>The proposal of the detail plan of the national spaces of the in -depth cooperation zone is subject to collecting opinions by the end of this month. The cooperation zone is expected to have less 300,000 inhabitants by 2035, the background, which advocates the opening of four more Hengqin-Macau border posts under the “one inspection” model. One of the new borders is pointed to the north of the International Financial Center of Hengqin. For this, space will be reserved to build a maritime passenger terminal, thus creating conditions to launch a new route between Hengqin and the inner port of Macau. In addition, the new borders will include a “smart” post on the new campus of the University of Macao in Hengqin and two land on “Lian to Lu” Street and the “Chang Long dao” road. The proposal indicates that it is necessary to accelerate the construction of the Cantão-Zhuhai (Macau) fast train, as well as planning and reserving a carril access between the masters and zhuhai. The public is also being consulted on the eventual sharing of public service facilities between Hengqin and Macau and the creation of community neighborhoods in the cooperation zone similar to those of MSAR. In these neighborhoods, Hengqin authorities want to foster a “5-10-15-minute circle of life” with their own characteristics. On the other hand, 56 secondary, primary and children's secondary schools are planned in Hengqin, where a “University City of International Education” will be built. The directing plan for national cooperation spaces (2021-2035) was approved for implementation at the end of last year.</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Taylor Swift enters new era with “The Life of a Showgirl”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/taylor-swift-entra-em-nova-era-the-life-showgirl/</link><description>What to expect from Taylor Swift's 12th album? The American singer released “The Life of a Showgirl” over the weekend after weeks of suspense fueled by cryptic clues for her fans. The most recent appear to be snippets of lyrics, like one that says, “Often, my life isn’t very glamorous.”
“The interesting thing about her latest albums (…) we didn't hear anything about music until midnight, when she started release day,” said Michael Kutek, 31, a fan interviewed by AFP at an album promotion event in New York.
To convey the essence of the album, the most heard artist on Spotify in 2024 revealed a series of photos with cabaret costumes. For the dominant color, he chose a bright orange.
“It's flashy, shrill,” said Kutek, who displayed the same tone in the nails. "I hope so much on the album, but in a positive way," he added. Her friend Sydney O'Shaughnessy, 28, played as a sign of "something very positive."
"The Life of A Showgirl", the most popular album in Spotify history, was presented by Swift as a backstage trip of her last year's world tour, which broke records and traveled all the "Eras" of her career.
The album, said the singer, “was born during the happiest, crazy and intense phase” of her life. “And this emotion is reflected” in the 12 tracks, including a duet with the rising star of Pop Sabrina Carpenter.
Producers are Swedes Max Martin and Shellback (Karl Johan Schuster), responsible for the Country Swift transition to Pop in “Red” (2012), “1989” (2014) and “Reputation” (2017).
American football player Travis Kelce, fiancé of the 35 -year -old artist, advanced dance tracks in the style of “22” and “Shake It Off”, created in partnership with the same duo.
Thus, the release signals a return to a more vibrant rhythm, after the folk albums “Folklore” and “Evermore” (2020) and the introspective “Midnights” (2022) and “The Tortured Poets Department” (2024).
As for the themes, which fans - the "swifties" - usually treat as pages of a personal diary, for now only the titles feed speculation: would it be "Elizabeth Taylor" a reflection on the actress? “Opalitis” a reference to Opal, Kelce's birth stone? And what ruined friendship inspired “Ruin ​​the Friendship”?
“This kind of narrative (…) transforms each launch into a collective hunting to the treasure,” said Robin Landa, professor of advertising and branding at the University of Kean.
"Fans don't just consume their art; they participate in it, which reinforces the bond with the artist," he explained. "Your theories and speculation on social networks turn the public into their promotion team."
Along with the release of the album, cinemas in around 50 countries will show special sessions, including music videos, making of videos and even a karaoke version of the album. According to the specialized website Deadline, the event is expected to raise between 30 and 50 million dollars in the USA.
Swift, who announced the album in August at Travis Kelce podcast, “is taking control of (…) every aspect of his music and how he introduces her to the public,” something “unique” in history, says Toby Koenigsberg, professor of the University of Oregon University Department of Music.
"She also understood the importance that her fan communities interact in person, not just online," he said about the film event.
But the teacher laments that they often "talk about their remarkable business view, fame and other things, and end up setting aside the essence of her: her talent as a songwriter."
Since her debut album in 2006, Swift “has proven herself capable of writing good songs consistently (…) in a way that almost no one else can”, he highlighted.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>