<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Economy and Employment “shake” consumer confidence</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/economia-emprego-abalam-confianca-dos-consumidores/</link><description>Between April and June, the general level of confidence of Macau consumers decreased 2.03% to 101.71 points, on a scale from zero to 200. Of the six parameters analyzed, five fell and only one recorded improvements. The “local economy” and the “employment situation” were the ones that contributed most to shake consumers' confidence, with almost 7%
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The general index of consumer confidence registered “a slight decrease” in the second quarter of this year, in sequential terms, according to the investigation carried out by the University of Science and Technology of Macao (UCTM). Of the six specific indices analyzed by the institution, five fell and only one registered a climb - the local economy and employment were the ones that most contributed to the reduction of confidence.
The analysis took into account interviews to 809 residents of Macao, 18 or more, during the first 10 days of June. On a scale from zero to 200, respondents attributed 101.71 points at the level of general confidence, which reflects a decrease of 2.03% compared to the 103.82 points obtained in the previous quarter.
The indexes of the “local economy” and “employment situation” have fallen “significantly”, showing “the softening of economic growth and the increase in pressure in the labor market” and marking the “lack of confidence” as they were below 100 points. Specifically, the economy-related subsidy received 93.61 points, 6.96% less compared to the first three months of the year (100.61), while employment had a score of 96.33, translating a drop of 6.83% (103.39).
A “moderate descent” was what was recorded in the “living level” parameters, which fell 1.13% to 107.8 points; “Purchase of housing”, which descended 0.9% to 99.29 points; and “price level”, which reached 97.74 points, marking a downward of 0.29%. Regarding the “housing purchase”, which was below 100 points, UCTM stresses that it “indicates greater caution in confidence” with regard to home acquisition.
In the opposite direction, the “investment in actions” sub-index rose, reaching 116.21 points in the second quarter of 2025, noting a 3.42% increase over the first three months of the year (112.37 points). This case demonstrates that there is an “increased optimism in the action market”, it can be read.
The investigators recalled that in the second quarter the external environment became “increasingly complex”, with the weakening of global economic growth and uncertainty worldwide. As for the economy of continental China, although it has presented "a positive trend," the truth is that "it still faces challenges and difficulties," such as "the insufficiency of internal demand, prices to remain low and frequent risks and threats."
"Although the confidence of Macao consumers remains optimistic in general, concerns arose in the areas of economics and employment, and policies are extremely necessary to pay attention to these issues to stabilize market expectations," UCTM researchers consider.
Given the “current complex and volatile economic environment”, analysts point out that the Government of MSAR and the different sectors of society need to work together and take “practical and effective measures” to deal with “potential risks”. "On the one hand, it is necessary to optimize the business environment, encourage innovation and entrepreneurship, stimulate market vitality and promote diversified development of the economy. On the other hand, it is necessary to reinforce the monitoring of the labor market, offer vocational training and improve the overall quality of labor, in order to respond calmly to the challenges of the labor market," they also argue.
At the same time, the welfare of the life of the population should not be neglected and reinforcing their trust in the future. "An active response and timely adjustments at the political level will help consolidate consumer confidence and promote the sustainable and healthy development of Macao's economy," they add.</description><pubDate>2025-07-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Secretary believes residents will increase labor competitiveness</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/secretario-acredita-residentes-vao-aumentar-competitividade-laboral/</link><description>Understanding that, currently, more than 60% of unemployed residents are out of work for a short time, between one and three months, the secretary for the economy and finance was convinced that the government will be able to help the local population increase their competitiveness in the work market
 
In another round of oral interpeação discussion in the Legislative Assembly (AL), several deputies appealed to the government to improve the measures of support for resident employment, ensure jobs and professional rise.
Reiterating the priority of priority hiring of residents, the secretary for the economy and finance said that, "for now, what the government can do is to develop, the best possible, and to accelerate job pairing." At this point, Tai Kin IP pointed out that, currently, residents who are unemployed for a period of between one and three months represent a “considerable percentage”, greater than 60%.
In response to the interpeairs of deputies Leong Sun Iok, Nick Law, Ngan Iek Hang and Ma Io Fong, the secretary has assured that the government "will continue to keep up with the employment needs of different social groups and provide them with adequate support services." “It is believed that, based on the good work already done, overlapping the advantages of the 'Working Group for the Coordination of Employment Promotion' and the 'Integrated Vocational Training Platform', residents will be helped to increase their employment competitiveness and improve their employment for fruit results,” said Tai Kin IP.
In addition, the ruler argued that the various actions developed by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) “have effectively promoted the development of the use of residents”.
This working group, created in May this year, has collected, so far, more than 1,000 job openings, which involve 300 jobs, covering integrated tourism and leisure sectors, hotel, information technology, banking and financial services, social services, among others.
According to the ruler, the unemployed are mainly looking for jobs linked to the construction sector, offices and retail for sale. In this sense, the Working Group is coordinating different public services to try to provide jobs to residents in public works and services, while Dsal analyzes jobs and the situation with large companies focused on these three areas, in order to channel residents for their jobs.
As for the training platform, DSAL Director Chan Un Tong said that it is in the conception and creation phase to be launched in the 4th quarter of this year.
 
Fixed proportions for residents and TNR
On the other hand, several deputies have requested the definition of fixed proportions for local and non -resident workers (TNR) at certain jobs. However, the secretary warned that the introduction of fixed percentages would "restrict market pairing" and "weaken the respective dynamism."
Tai Kin IP insisted that the executive expects, through a flexible adjustment mechanism, to dynamically evaluate the offer and search for different jobs to adjust, find local candidates for each post and recommend them to companies. "Fixing a proportion does not mean that it can resolve all employment conjunctions in all situations. The question deserves a deep weighting and the discussion for all of us, and needs enough arguments," he said.
In general, the ruler said he hopes to “meet more demands from all over”, through “dynamic TNR adjustments”.
In turn, the director of DSAL clarified that, by the end of May, the percentage of medium and local management staff in the six game operators reached 89.8% (10,407 people), with 1,187 non -resident paintings at these levels.
The secretary assured that he continues to demand at six companies a high percentage of medium and superiors of local management, continuing with the creation of conditions favorable to the exercise of these functions by residents. However, he suggested to the public to consider the issue "under more than a prism."
"It is pertinent to address all the fact that Macau is building" a center, a platform and a base ", characterized by a coexistence of multiple cultures, and that the presence of management frames of different cultural contexts in large companies contributes, to some extent, to cultural exchange and the increase of international competitiveness," argued Tai Kin IP.
He stressed, the government “pay attention” to the opportunities for professional ascension of competent residents, and will look for opportunities for ascension for competent residents, with international view and multiple cultures, but one must “find a balance”.
In relation to local workers employed in the satellite casinos, according to the director of DSAL, the body has already contacted 93% of the 4,800 workers directly hired by the game concessionaires and 43% of the 800 to the service of the satellite casinos themselves. Chan Un Tong explained that the rate of 43% is related to workers' working hours and arrangements taken by the owners of the satellite casinos.
Representative Angela Leong suggested to Dsal to accompany, in a minimum space of three years, the work situation of the croupiers over 55 years old transferred from the satellite casinos to the dealers. In response, the secretary promised a “proper inspection”, hoping that these workers will adapt to the new work environment, as well as the maintenance of negotiations with the three concessionaires involved in the issue, so that there is a good job transition.
 
Support for “first stores” and electronic sports
In the AL, the secretary also said that this quarter will be launched a plan that will support 20 to 30 companies from the Lusophone, Hispanic and Greater China countries at the opening of their “first store” in Macao, with a view to attracting leading companies from abroad to increase the urban characteristics of masters.
It also revealed that in the first half of this year, the “One-Stop” service to investors received 181 new investment projects, covering integrated tourism and leisure, 'Big Health' and modern finances, including 15 new projects from scholarship companies and market leaders, which “allowed the creation of a considerable number of jobs.
In another scope, Tai Kin IP has promised that the government will continue to encourage companies related to the activity of electronic sports to develop stablely, and to create favorable conditions to promote activities that can attract high purchasing power to attend competitions in this area, as well as study the possibility of better synergistic development with the relevant industries of the cooperation zone and the large bay.
On the other hand, it indicated that it can be implemented, from the end of this quarter, a measure to inject, with an innovative approach, new humanistic and historical elements in the six historical zones.
The secretary also assured that the government is creating a more favorable business environment for the development of the senior industry and related sectors.
 
Suggested Order of the Chief on Public Contracting Requirements of Residents
The Working Group for the Coordination of Employment Promotion proposes that, by order of the Chief Executive, the specific guidelines on establishing the requirements to ensure the use of resident workers and the definition of hiring measures such as “evaluation factors independent of evaluation criteria”. This, within the scope of public works and public services, authorizations for the exercise of activity under exclusive basis and procedures for the acquisition of works or services developed in the MSAR by public services and entities. In a note issued by the secretary's office for the economy, it is also said that the government has been prioritizing the policy of “employment stabilization” and will continue to carry out employment and promote professional ascension.</description><pubDate>2025-07-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Caeal received 13 complaints about electoral illegalities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/caeal-recebeu-13-queixas-sobre-ilegalidades-eleitorais/</link><description>The Electoral Affairs Commission of the Legislative Assembly received 13 complaints about apparent illegalities during the period in force of electoral prohibition. The president of Caeal says that one of the complaints has to do with advertising not allowed. "The cases are being seriously accompanied" and will have "proper treatment" if the illegalities are confirmed, said Seng Ioi Man. Announced, on the other hand, that this year there will be 770 polling stations, 80 more than in the previous edition. In addition, a slight change in voting sites will be registered for direct suffrage, which will be replaced by more appropriate spaces in the same area and with greater ease for voters
 
Victor Rebelo
 
With the period of prohibition of propaganda in force until August 29, the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) has so far registered 13 complaints about apparent rally to the electoral law. One case has to do with illegal advertising, according to the president of Caeal, at the end of another work meeting.
Seng Ioi Man said that "cases are being seriously accompanied" and will have "proper treatment" if the illegalities are confirmed. "We will give proper monitoring and will coordinate or cooperate closely with the competent authorities to follow up on these cases," he said.
Despite the complaints, he considered that, in general, "the candidacies and even the public, are acting according to what we have appealed, that is, in accordance with the law", hoping that the population "and our residents" can comply with "the entire electoral system".
Regarding the process of verification of the applications, CAEAL did not detect any procedural irregularity or unreadable candidates, “hence no application has to supply whatever it is,” he said, recalling that “regarding whether or not the candidates defend the basic law, or whether or not they are or not, it is up to the State Security Defense Commission to determine and verify the discomfort and issue. binding ”. Based on the opinion of that commission, Caeal will take, until July 15, the decision to verify the applications and disclose all the results.
On other aspects related to the elections that will take place on September 14, it was mentioned that this year there will be 80 more voting chambers than in the 2021 edition, now totaling 770. The goal is to accelerate the voting process and shorten the waiting time, thus creating better conditions and incentive for voters to go to the polls.
According to the president of Caeal, available to the venues of the voting assemblies is being properly conceived and planned, giving as an example the adoption of measures to optimize the waiting time of voters or outside the places where the assemblies are found, as well as the path they should travel. "Aspects such as the lifting of the voting report, the filling, the placement of the bulletin in the ballot box, including the number of ballot boxes in each voting assembly were discussed by us, in order to ensure that the vote process takes place in the best way," he said.
With regard to the 37 places where the 38 voting assemblies will be installed for direct suffrage, two will be at the Olympic Sports Center stadium. There will be five more assemblies for indirect suffrage. In this case, in addition to the Polytechnic University (UPM) multipurpose pavilion, already used in previous elections, the Kao Yip school was introduced in Nape, where two and three sectors will vote, respectively.
"As earlier, both spaces will make a vote available for direct suffrage, so that the voters of legal persons can also exercise their right in direct elections," he said, adding that in the past there was only one place of voting for indirect suffrage and this year will be the first time in two places. "The creation of another voting place for indirect suffrage will have a screening effect, reducing the waiting time," he said.
According to Seng Ioi Man, the voting places were defined after “a consideration” about the distribution of voters, the accessibility of the voting sites, their space, the facilities without barriers, among other factors. Most importantly, he pointed out, "was to create conditions to facilitate the displacement of voters to exercise their voting rights."
The voting spaces for direct suffrage "are practically the same as the previous elections, with minor adjustments in which we opted for other places in the same most appropriate area and which currently have better conditions," he said, adding that, as four years ago, there will also be a voting assembly for direct suffrage in Coloane's prison for prisoners to vote. In addition to the 38 polling stations, the Mong Sports Pavilion will be reserved if necessary.
 
Polling stores equipped to receive disabled
At the end of another meeting, followed by a press conference, Caeal said it will notify voters by mail. In addition, from August, several consultation platforms will be launched, one of which through the single account.
All assemblies will be equipped with voting chambers for people with disabilities and voting places will be improved or introduced equipment without electronic barriers so that people can vote without obstacles.
Regarding the computer equipment of the voting assemblies and other aspects, Caeal attributes “great importance”. In the sense of “ensuring the stability and supply of electricity”, there will be a reserve supply system. It is therefore expected that on election day, technical and specialized personnel be highlighted to oversee and keep the computer equipment, the internet and the supply of electricity.
In order to respond to any eventuality, a contingency plan has been made, which will be activated if the electronic system faces and the repair time is long. "For example," said the official, "the poll survey and the registration will be manual instead of electronic, so that the process can take place with normality, preventing voters from being retained there for a long time."
Seng Ioi Man also pointed out that, as regards materials to be used in the campaign, after the lists are definitely allowed, they must present a list of articles that will distribute to the public and in sessions or meetings, including the type of articles, the quantity and the cost. The guardian warns that these materials do not constitute benefit assignment.
About reports or news spread by the media organs in this period of prohibition of propaganda, only texts on matters of today may be published. However, the content of the news cannot involve electoral propaganda, for example, to address the political program or the principles of election application. "The journalist must consider if there will be no one who, with conditions and quality, can answer his questions, so that we can safeguard the electoral order," said Seng Ioi Man.</description><pubDate>2025-07-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Reduced 15% waiting for external specialty consultation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/reduziu-15-espera-para-consulta-externa-de-especialidade/</link><description>About 2.8 weeks is the waiting time for the first external specialty consultation at the Public Hospital, the secretary said for social and culture affairs, stressing that there was a 15% decrease compared to last year
 
The waiting time for the first external specialty consultation at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center (CHCSJ) reduced 15.1%between January and May this year to about 2.8 weeks, said the secretary for social affairs and culture, LAM, in the Legislative Assembly. The ruler recalled that in the same period last year, the waiting time was 3.3 weeks.
In response to an oral interpellation of Deputy Lei Chan U on the pressure felt by health professionals, Lam also reiterated that, “with the proper allocation of resources and consolidation of operation”, it is perspective that the Macau Union medical center will be able to take 25% of the load of São Januário medical services until the end of 2027. Distribution of resources and effective sorting of patients, reducing waiting time, ”he added.
The secretary also took a balance of the operation of the Islands Hospital, pointing out that it currently offers 47 types of external specialty consultations, giving priority to the most prolonged waiting lists in health services (SSM).
With the increase in the number of experts and the capacity of care, that health complex has provided, up to date, about 10,000 external specialty consultations. In May alone, 2,400 external specialty consultations were registered, representing an increase of over 300% compared to the 600 made in January.
As for the imaging services, about 9,000 exams have already been performed. In May, the volume of these exams reached approximately 1,900, an increase of about 170% over the approximately 700 exams performed in the first month of this year. "In addition, a specific unit for follow -up consultations of the first consultation was created in order to raise the effectiveness of screening," noted Lam.
"With a view to providing more convenient services to the population, the Macau Union Medical Center will continue to promote computerization of services in order to increase efficiency. The SSM implemented a unified electronic electronic system of cases that, following the principle of the shortest waiting time, forward the patients to follow up at CHCSJ or at the Macau Union medical center," he explained.
On the other hand, and with regard to human resources, the secretary said that tenders are being held for 35 general physician vacancies and 56 grade I nurse vacancies, which are in the phase of publication of the final classification list and in the completion phase of the knowledge tests, respectively. In addition, the SSM and the Macau Union Medical Center began the specialized medical formation of 57 doctors. As for the area of ​​community health care, 18 doctors will be reinforced.
 
One conducts a study on public-private cooperation
The LAM also indicated, in the plenary session, that the University of Macau “was responsible for conducting a study that aims to analyze the best cooperation model between public and private health sectors, to conceive a mechanism to maintain balance in the sharing of services between public and private sectors, perform an analysis of cost-benefit and elaborate planning for the training of health professionals, in order to promote sustainable development of the sector health ”.
According to the study, the study will involve interviews to stakeholders and data analysis. "It is expected that the preliminary report will be completed in the fourth quarter of this year, and that the final report is completed in the first half of 2026," he said.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-07-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Low birth and video surveillance "challenge" São José day care</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/baixa-natalidade-videovigilancia-desafiam-creche-de-sao-jose/</link><description>The decreasing birth rate is the main problem of São José International Nursery, according to Nair Cardoso. The director of the establishment provides that the number of registered next year is even lower than in 2024/2025. The installation of the CCTV system in day care centers is another of the concerns

























Pedro Milheirão
Nair Cardoso foresees a lower number of children in day care centers, a consequence of the descent of the birth rate in the MSAR. The director of the São José International Nursery told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau that they are registered between 110 and 120 children, for the school year of 2025/2026. In the year 2024/2025, the nursery had 168 children registered, the lowest number since 2020, the year of the opening of the institution.
In addition to the low birth in Macao, the other major challenge of day care is the installation of the CCTV system, which Nair Cardoso considers to be “the strong theme” of today. The São José Nursery was even one of those who requested the installation of the surveillance chambers in the rooms. "We are super honest, we have the doors open and windows everywhere. So another camera or less a camera, for us, does not affect us," he said, adding that it is also "another measure of protection" to the institution itself.
"However, there is one if not, in the way IAS [Institute for Social Affairs] wants to implement, where only they will have access to the chambers. We, institution, will not have access," he says, leaving some questions. "How will the use be done? Who will you evaluate if there is anything? Is it the day care center that will make the request to see the images? If there is a parent's complaint? Parents always come to day care before going to IAS?
The nursery is totally subsidized by IAS, and the director admits that the support is at the same time "sufficient and not sufficient." "We are very saved. We have the concept of recycling that helps us immense with art materials," in line with the slogan "Turning the Ordinary Into Extraordary" of "Reggio Emilia", notes the director.
Although IAS requires only one educator for every three rooms, the São José day care center has one in each. At the same time, the fact that it is open all year long and looking for people who speak three languages, or at least two, makes the process of hiring personnel difficult. However, Nair Cardoso considers that the project's balance sheet is “super positive. A miracle. (…) To do what has been done to this day and have qualified educators”.
The director also highlighted the fact that the institution was visited by several groups of foreign educators and curious to realize how the day care center can implement the regio Emilia model "with such a structured government" framework '. "We now have a Philippine university that wants to come to do a study. They are all very admired. And that was my main goal when I entered the day care."
The day care center also participates in an IAS program on children's social and emotional development, in response to the high number of suicides in Asia. IAS believes that “if we implement these social and emotional values ​​in the child since they were young, they can better solve problems in the future. We already do it,” explained the director.
Nair Cardoso has also announced that he will abandon the daycare direction for family reasons. At this time, his “biggest project” is to prepare Ricardo Rodrigues, future director of the institution, “because it is a lot of things to pass,” he says. The current director also revealed that she will move to Thailand to start a business, "a nursery, who knows." It also reiterated that today the day care is differentiated "by curriculum, pedagogy and by being international." "There are few day care centers that speak the three languages."
 
Exhibition of small artists
The São José International Nursery inaugurated the “Little Artists, Big Inspirations” exhibition on the staircase of its facilities. The gallery presents works created by the children, inspired by renowned artists and produced in a pedagogical environment of Reggio Emilia. The project reflects the institution's commitment to “fostering creativity, artistic expression and children's guided learning”.
Aged between one and three years, the youngest "replicated" artists like Wassily Kandinsky, Yayoi Kusama, Frida Kahlo, Jackson Pollock, Henri Matisse and Pablo Picasso. According to Sandra Monteiro, head of the day care center, the project lasted six weeks. This is the first time that the day care center has organized an exhibition on the staircase, according to Monteiro, who has highlighted the fact that the entire day care is decorated with children's work and recyclable materials.
The theme and the artist on which the children were based were attributed according to the age group. Children from both to three used bottle caps to recreate Yayoi Kusama's work, for example. The youngest, between one and two years, sought to recreate Kandinsky's paintings. "We present images, let's talk a little of the artists, in a basic way." The children had “complete freedom,” explained Monteiro. "We don't give our touch. Their work is as it is."</description><pubDate>2025-07-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Malparado resumed ascending curve in May</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/malparado-retomou-curva-ascendente-em-maio/</link><description>After two consecutive monthly descents, the amount of Macao's badly increased credit was increased, surpassing the 56 billion patacas in late May. At issue is 5.7% of total bank loans, according to official data
 
The amount of loans with more than 90 days late in MSAR bank institutions ascended to about 56.20 billion patacas in late May, marking a rise of 0.8% or 424.9 million compared to the previous month, according to data published by the Monetary Authority (AMCM) on its electronic page. The new data contradict a monthly descent of 2.7% and 0.6% recorded in March and April, respectively, but continue short of the 57.62 billion accounted for in February, which constitute the highest amount since AMCM began compiling these statistics in 1990.
According to AMCM statistics, non -productive or expired credit (NPL, in the English acronym) grew 16% or 7.74 billion compared to May 2024 and 20.3 times compared to 2.77 billion noted in late 2019, ie immediately before the pandemic.
At the end of May this year, the expired credit was 5.7% of the loans granted by banks, more 0.3 percentage points than in the previous month, and 1.3 points in the annual variation. The global value of NPL comprises 34.71 billion not resident clients (about 61.8% of the total) and 21.49 billion residents, corresponding to ratios of 7.0% and 4.3%, respectively.
The global climb of rally credit between April and May this year was due to non-resident customers, whose NPL grew 2.3% (plus 781 million patacas). On the other hand, in the case of residents, the expired credit dropped 1.6% or 356 million patacas within one month.
In the general calculation, internal loans to the private sector ciphed at 498.51 billion patacas in May, marked 1.4% and 6.8% in monthly and annual terms, respectively. In turn, foreign credit dropped 7.6% and 13.1% to 495.17 billion on the same comparative bases.
Thus, credit to the private sector descended 4.6%to 993.7 billion patacas between April and May, with the dollar loans of Hong Kong dollars maintained a dominant weight (43.8%), followed by PATACA (22.3%), US dollar (21.8%) and Renminbi (8.8%).
The same data show, on the other hand, that the public sector deposits in local banks set themselves at 216.08 billion, reflecting a monthly rise of 3.1% and an annual increase of 7.3%. Resident deposits (794.67 billion) grew by 1.3% in a month and 8.1% in one year, while non-residents (350.95 billion) increased 0.4% compared to April 2025 and 6.3% compared to May 2024.
As a result, deposits of bank activity rose 1.4%to 1,361.7 billion, compared to the preceding month.
 
Banks results almost a third
Macao banks exploration results totaled 5.81 billion patacas in late May, increasing 31.6% over the same month of 2024, according to data from the monetary authority. In the period under consideration, the results were driven by growth from 69.3% to 5.48 billion in bank service and operations benefits, while income from financial investments (611.8 million) rose 156.3%, offering a 4.7% break from profit margin (6.15 billion). On the other hand, bank operation costs rose 17.8% to 6.60 billion patacas. Overall 2024, the bank sector registered operational profits of 4.01 billion, which showed an annual decline of 21.3% and was the lowest since 2010. The results of 2024 marked the fourth consecutive break, after 12 years, including 10 successive records, starting in 2011.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-07-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Broadway filled six times for Jimmy Yang's shows</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/broadway-encheu-seis-vezes-para-shows-de-jimmy-yang/</link><description>The Broadway Theater, with a capacity of about 2,500 people, had a full house in the six shows that Jimmy O. Yang held in Macau from July 4 and 6, marking his debut in the territory. Initially three shows were planned, however, the organization duplicated the offer against the huge demand for tickets, namely from residents from Hong Kong, where he was born and lived until 2000, the year his family emigrated to Los Angeles, USA.
Despite leaving Hong Kong when he was only 13 years old, Jimmy O. Yang keeps strong memories of childhood, as he was keen to get his stand-up shows he starred in Broadway, with several humorous notes, which mixed English with the Cantonense. Between applause and laughs, he was also impressed by Macao's strong development and established parallels between local and Las Vegas casinos, noting the differences between the behavior of the "Croupiers" and the concentration of "uncles" and "aunts" with the tables when the gamblers live faster moments.
Jimmy O. Yang acted in Macao as part of his first tour of Asia after being exhausted tickets for five shows in Hong Kong, according to Galaxy Entertainment.
Having found inspiration at Dayo Wong, a famous Hong Kong comedian, Yang began his stand-up career with “intimate” places in the US. Since then, according to Galaxy, he has sculpted a unique comic voice, weaving sharp cultural observations, Asian American identity and immigrant experiences. ”
In the book “How to American”, it addresses his English learning experience through television, the fact that he became a DJ in dance clubs and the disappointment of his parents when he chose to pursue a career in comedy. In addition to his viral social networks, he also played various roles on television and movies, including in "Chinatown", "Love Hard", "Silicon Valley", "Space Force" and "Crazy Rich Asians."</description><pubDate>2025-07-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Casinos started July with a strong climb in gross recipes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/casinos-iniciaram-julho-forte-subida-nas-receitas-brutas/</link><description>The gross game recipes in Macao reached about 4.3 billion patacas in the first six days of this month, exceeding initial expectations, the citigroup said. In a report signed by analysts George Choi and Timothy Chau, the banking group points out that the daily average of 717 million patacas represents a 2.1% increase compared to June (702 million) and a 30% growth compared to the 2024 same period, thus continuing the rising curve of recent months. According to data from the Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate, June's invoicing ended with a registration of 21.06 billion patacas, which has become the second highest since the pandemic, illustrating an annual increase of 19%. Citigroup associates the strong early July with the impact of Jacky Cheung's last three concerts last weekend at the Galaxy Arena in Cotai. At the end of this month, Macau will also host concerts from Aaron Kwok and Sandy Lam, respectively at Studio City and Venetian arena, but analysts anticipate “some moderation” in the game's gross recipes after the Jacky Cheung series of shows. Still, Citigroup slightly raised its projection to July, from 19.5 billion to 20 billion, representing an annual increase of 7.6%, estimating an average daily average of 628 million for the rest of the month. Citing sources of the sector, the Citigroup team also indicates that in the first six days of July, the VIP segment of the game “remained practically stable” compared to the previous month, while gross revenues in the mass market rose between 2% and 4%. In the general calculation of the first six months of 2025, casinos' revenues totaled 118.77 billion patacas, translating an annual increase of 4.4% and equivalent to 79.4% of the amount accounted for in the first half of 2019.</description><pubDate>2025-07-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Center treats 76 cases of young people with internet addiction per year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/centro-trata-76-casos-de-jovens-vicio-da-internet-por-ano/</link><description>Since 2019, an average of 76 cases of young people with internet addiction have been accompanied per year, show data from the Institute of Social Action assigned to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau. Last year, 72 cases were treated, a climb compared to the 68 registered a year earlier. The young people accompanied by the Sheng Kung Hui Center played mainly "gamping" and used applications like Youtube, Instagram, Tik Tok and XiaoHongShu. The body led by Hon Wai also said that, for now, it is not foreseen to subsidize more support programs for young people addicts on the Internet
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The Coordinating Office of Social Services Sheng Kung Hui Macao follows, an average of 76 cases of young people with internet addiction. Under the one that is the only program of its kind in the territory, entitled “We-Connect’ Hidden and Internet Addiction Youth Service Project ”,“ comprehensive services ”are granted, which include prevention, development and counseling for young people and their guardians.
According to data from the Institute of Social Action (IAS) provided to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, last year, there was an increase in the number of cases compared to 2023, since there was an increase of 68 cases to 72 in 2024. The years when the most cases were treated 2022 and 2019 (87 cases each year), as well as 2021 (86 cases). In turn, in 2020 there were 57 cases.
The body led by Hon Wai pointed out that, "as some cases have been accompanied or reopened over the years, the sum of the referred numbers is not equal to the total number of people accompanied during these years." Asked what the total number of young people identified as having internet addiction and supported by Sheng Kung Hui, IAS did not respond.
As for age distribution, they are mostly young people with ages between 14 and 18 years old. However, according to data released by the center earlier, a tendency for the average age of help applicants was observed in Macao: the youngest were only six to eight years.
It was mainly the family and friends of the young people who sought help, but there were also cases where the people who work under the program were aware of young people with this problem, following the organization of activities.
These young people access the internet, especially through mobile phones: “They played mainly gaming and competitive, and mainly used social applications such as Youtube, Instagram, Tik Tok and XiaoHongShu,” IAS said.
There are “many” the factors that contribute to the “internet addiction”, with the government organism to enumerate “personality traits, low self-esteem, depression, low social support”. Regarding social workers, the biggest difficulties they encounter to deal with these cases are the “low sensitization of young people for internet addiction; lack of alternative activities; influence of family factors, such as the little family control over the use of the internet”.
According to IAS, social workers usually need “a lot of time” to establish a relationship of mutual trust with young people and understand the reasons for addiction, how family communication and relationships work works. Only after that can they "provide adequate support and suggestions for programs that lead to improving the situation of these young people."
Asked if you intend to finance more associations or institutions to carry out these programs, IAS has ensured that "it will continue to fund this program to help young people in need and their guardians," but said it was not currently planned to "finance other non -governmental organizations to promote related services."
In 2021, the program coordinator, Cabell Hoi, had said in an interview with this newspaper that there should be many more cases of young people with internet addiction than those who are registered. The same responsible explained that the government has indeed given important support, but admitted that the team could do more and reach more young people if there were more human and financial resources.
In the academic year 2025/2026, the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) will launch reference guidelines, so that schools and guardians are aware that mobile phones taken by students to schools must be subject to management measures. In addition, DSEDJ will provide a measure to support schools in the acquisition of centered mobile management equipment.</description><pubDate>2025-07-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau chosen to receive Asian minigp project</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-escolhido-para-receber-projecto-de-minigp-asiatico/</link><description>Coloane's karting track received, for the first time, a stage of the “World Series End Minigp”, which provides competition for young riders from 10 to 16, in a path that could lead them to the highest level of motorcycling, MotoGP. All three continental events in Southeast Asia will be held in Macau. The next will be in August. At the premiere were corridors of the continent, Hong Kong and Taiwan, as well as a local representative and one of the Philippines. The Chinese Huang Ting Nuo won the competition
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Dozen and a half of young pilots from east Asia and Southeast Asia, aged 10 to 16 years, participated in the debut of the “World Series MiniGP” in the coloane karting.
This is a project called MotoGP's “Road”, created by the International Motorcycle Federation (end), to provide experience for riders who want to embrace a professional career, with a view to participating in senior motorcycle-world competitions, MotoGP. To this end, he understood in order, the various continents are challenged to launch the newest runners in competitions seriously, and Macau joined the initiative, receiving all three rounds from the “Southeast Asia Series”, with pilots from this region, whose majority comes from the Popular Republic of China.
In the first of three rounds in the MSAR, the remaining two of which made in August, the karting - which has an international license and is therefore within the requirements of the end, especially with regard to safety - received eight pilots from the continent, three from Hong Kong, two from Taiwan, one of the Philippines and a representative of the MSAR.
On a very hot weekend, the right races were held on Saturday afternoon and Sunday, and the mornings were dedicated to free and qualification training.
In both events, with 14 laps to the circuit, the victory was up to Huang Ting Nuo, from the Popular Republic of China, ahead of his compatriot Chen Pin-Chi. Also Chinese Li Yuheng was third in the first race, while Cheung Yan Kit of Taiwan finished last in the second race podium. Mand's only driver Liam to Ieong Chi Him was not happy as he couldn't finish any proof.
The “Southeast Asia Series” debuted this year in the project, along with “Northeast Asia” and Turkey, to have 22 competitions throughout the time. Pilots participating in the 160 CC class are aged between 10 and 14, while the rest, until 16, compete in the category of 190 cc, but only after they have the experiment of at least one year in the lower displacement.
The president of the Macau-China General Association told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that this initiative serves to "support the development of our car sport, hoping to promote it with the citizens of Macao, so that they know that they can run by motorcycle since childhood." Roberto Osório adds that in Macau “there is a lack of motorcycle riders”, unlike Karting, who has had a larger projection. “In our gym we have already trained more than 44 Karting pilots,” he said.
Meanwhile, Jorge Viegas, president of the end, mentioned on the body's website that "this is the starting point that was missing at Road to MotoGP and will allow all talented riders to step on the" podium "with an extremely low budget."
The official stressed that "in addition, this joint initiative, between the end and the company Dorna Sports, puts national federations at the forefront of the system, as it is worth all the national series and choose their best in each country or region."
On the other hand, the Dorna Sports Executive Director stressed that “Road to MotoGP” is “very important”. Carmelo Ezpeleta says he feels "proud" to see "another initiative added to our talent promotion portfolio, in partnership with in the end", adding that the competition plays a relief role "in the standardization of competition for young riders around the world, helping their talent shine on equal circumstances and creating more opportunities than ever."
At the end of each of the continental championships, the first two classifieds will guarantee the presence in the "World Finals", to determine the champions, scheduled events for the valence track, from November 14 to 16, on the same weekend in which the great prize of that Spanish city, integrated into the calendar of the Motorcycling World Championship, where the Portuguese pilot Miguel is located.
The second stage in Macao of the “World Series Minigp” is scheduled for 9 and 10 August, followed by the third round, 30 and 31 of the same month.</description><pubDate>2025-07-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>GDP should reflect quarterly improvement</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pib-devera-reflectir-melhoria-trimestral/</link><description>The MSar GDP should record improvements in the second quarter compared to the first three months of the year, the president of the Economic Association anticipated. Despite proving to be optimistic, Lau Pun Lap recalled that changes in consumption pattern are bringing difficulties and questioned the effectiveness of the intellectual property promotion plan
 
The economic performance of MSAR in the second quarter of this year is expected to have a sequential improvement, anticipates the president of the Macao Economic Association, Lau Pun Lap. In an interview with the newspaper or Mun, quoted by Macau News Agency, the economist pointed out that the economic basis of the territory remains “quite stable,” however, persist concerns.
It is recalled that Macau's Gross Domestic Product (GDP) retreated 1.3% in annual and real terms in the first quarter of this year, with data released by statistical and censuses (DSEC) services to 99.78 billion patacas, equivalent to 85.2% of the first quarter of the first quarter of 2019. The amount also represented a decrease of 6.1% over the last three months 2024, marking the sixth consecutive quarter of deceleration.
Looking at Macao's economic performance in the first three months of the year, Lau Pun Lap was optimistic, pointing out that in the second quarter there was an increase in the number of tourists, especially in May and June, as well as stronger revenues in both game export and service. In this sense, it suggests that there will be an improvement compared to the first quarter.
However, it pointed out that the biggest challenge that the economy of the territory faces has to do with unequal development. Property prices continue to fall, affecting the assessment of mortgages for small and medium -sized businesses (SMEs), as well as their funding capacity, while reducing consumers' confidence among residents, he emphasized.
Lau Pun Lap continued, saying that small businesses are facing difficulties due to a change in tourist consumption patterns, leading to a trend of falling overall consumption.
Suggesting that the government collaborates with industrial and commercial associations, as well as local companies, to explore ways to improve tourist consumption experience in Macau, thus increasing the volume and quality of consumption, Lau Pun Lap also criticized the intellectual property promotion plan.
When asked about the effectiveness of this initiative, the economist admitted that the concept is valid, however, but questioned if enough attention had been paid to partnerships with community associations and companies. In concrete, he pointed out that tourists often visit these areas just to take photographs with thematic facilities and then leave, little contributing to boosting the local economy.
The homologous breakdown of GDP registered in the first quarter-the first in two years, as the latter was registered in late 2022-among other factors, based on relatively high comparison of the first quarter of the previous year and the change in the consumption pattern of visitors, ”DSEC said, and came after consecutive slowdown.</description><pubDate>2025-07-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Studied integration of metro works and flood prevention</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/estudada-integracao-de-obras-metro-de-prevencao-de-cheias/</link><description>The government will study the integration of the construction of the west of Metro with the flood prevention works, the secretary revealed for transport and public works. Raymond Tam also assured that a public consultation will be held for the subway line surrounding the artificial island
 
The Secretary for Transport and Public Works said yesterday that the Government will hire a specialized entity to conduct a study on the western line of the Light Metro, in which the possibility of integration with flood prevention works will be evaluated.
In response to an oral interpellation of Deputy Leong Hong Sai, the secretary also said that the government will consider how to increase the area of ​​the interior port, as the construction of the western Metro line, the flood prevention works and the revitalization of the inner port "are directly related to the increase of the interior port space."
In addition, the ruler highlighted the “narrow cooperation” with the Institute for Municipal Affairs, so that the rainwater pumping stations in the south and north of the interior port play the “essential role” of improving the flood situation on Almirante Sérgio Street.
According to the secretary, the government will continue to promote the revitalization of the interior port zone, and the conclusion of the quarter current of the structural restoration of the-country bridges 23 and 25.
Describing the overall optimization of the inner port as “a long -term process”, he stressed that the executive will continue to improve the general spatial provision of the zone, based on the directing plan and considering the current situation and development needs. At the same time, in an integrated way, traffic, disaster prevention, environmental protection and public spaces, with a view to reinforcing the vitality and resilience of the area will be considered.
Asked by Leong Hong, he goes on the idea of ​​building a pedestrian tunnel between Wanzai and the inner port, Raymond Tam clarified that Macao's part never mentioned this proposal. Currently, the government is studying, with the Hengqin authorities, the creation of a new access road between the two territories, whose developments will be timely.
On the other hand, the secretary said "to have confidence" to achieve the goals of completing the construction of the East Metro line in 2028 and start the operation in 2029.
With regard to another subway layout, Raymond Tam said it will be thoughtful as this line, from the artificial island, can pass through Zone A and Zape, and reach the city center and Barra. "This line will be very important for Macau and its construction may be faster than the West Line, because the conditions for doing works should be a little better. We will develop the respective studies and we will certainly consult the public when the choice of layout is ready," he said.
In addition, according to Raymond Tam, for the meter to be able to penetrate several areas of the MSAR, an inevitable solution that is already underway is building underground rails in some zones.
The secretary said, on the other hand, that, in the elaboration of the detail plan for northern zone I, the government will study the feasibility of a road corridor, with a connection between the West Zone of Lam Mau and Ilha Verde.
 
Adjustments to bus contracts
In addition, Raymond Tam pointed out that the revision of the concession contracts of the Bus Service is underway, and adjustments will be introduced, according to the requirements of social development and the progress of the construction of road networks and carril transportation. In particular, factors such as the departure of buses, the reorganization of careers and the way of distributing the front line workers will be considered.
Still in the area of ​​transport, it has ensured that the government will prepare in advance response to traffic traffic jams at San MA lo in the golden week of October, to divert tourists to different bus stops.
Raymond Tam also took the opportunity to point out that the government created more than 800 parking spaces for heavy vehicles on proper roads in the Cotai zone for the use of the transport sector.
 
Maritime protected zone will not be expanded
In another scope, in response to Deputy Lam Lon Wai, the secretary considered that the conditions for the expansion of the Macao Maritime Protected Zone are not gathered, taking into account the natural characteristics of the water and various factors. In this respect, he stressed that the delimitation of the area obtained the recognition of the Ministry of Ecology and Environment and the Ministry of Natural Resources of China.
In turn, the director of maritime and water affair has said that a local boat company plans to cooperate with Shenzhen so that a 70 meter -long boat type performs maritime tourism activities between the two cities. On the other hand, Susana Wong ruled out yacht lease, taking into account security management.
However, Ron Lam appealed to increased transparency of information on public works. The secretary stressed that, even if no plants of urban conditions are issued, the competent services request binding opinions to the direction of soil services and urban construction on public works. In this regard, he added that public works services have already proceeded to 34 public consultations in the first half of this year, asserting that their guardianship will not ignore the approach in the form of public consultation.
 
Exchange of economic fractions in study
Raymond Tam stated that the feasibility study is underway for the implementation of an economic housing exchange regime, which will allow the government to identify the real needs of the population, clarify the target audience and define the conditions applicable to this regime. As for the possibility of affecting economic fractions to the use of social housing, the secretary indicated that he will be analyzed with prudence, taking into account the concrete circumstances.</description><pubDate>2025-07-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CPSP's number of promotions grew</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cresceu-numero-de-promocoes-cpsp/</link><description>The Public Security Police Corps registered, last year, more promotions than the previous year, which were more visible in the class of agents. In concrete, and according to the annual report of the corporation, 50 became main guards, 30 were promoted to sub -chief and 17 ascended to first guards. In total, 119 rose in their career
 
Catarina Pereira
 
There were more promotions within the Public Security Police (CPSP) last year compared to the previous year. According to the corporation's annual report, a total of 119 professionals went up to 36 more than in 2023. Most promotions took place in the class of agents, although in the class of officers they were also registered.
According to the data consulted by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, 50 were promoted to the main guard and 30 to Deputy Chief, when the previous year no one had been promoted to these positions. Already the first guard ascended 17 professionals, and in 2023 they had been 34.
On the other hand, 10 became chiefs, against zero the previous year, while four were promoted to commissioners (against 12 in 2023), four to subtendents (compared to 12) and another four to intended (in the face of five).
Despite more promotions, the truth is that they have not yet reached the levels of 2020 and 2021, for example, years in which 213 and 219, respectively.
In general, the total number of security forces agents at the end of 2024 was 5,001 - most (4,735) belonging to the agent class. The data show that of these, 3,105 were guards, 898 performed the functions of main guards, 406 were first guards, and 326 were subsons.
Regarding the class of officers, the CPSP had 145 bosses, followed by subcommittees (45), commissioners (34), subfinals (22), interactive (9), superior bosses (7), superintendents (3) and a general superintendent. There are also 412 people in the context of civil personnel.
Regarding academic qualifications, of the total agents (5,001), about 84% or 4,186 are licensed or have bachelor's degree. Here are 514 agents with complementary secondary education, 159 with master's degree, 136 with general or lower secondary education, four with associated diploma and two with doctorate.
According to the report, over the last year, the corporation carried out 1,005 illegal work combat operations, a total of 2,968 places inspected. These actions resulted in the detection of 610 people, and 61 employers were processed.
In the context of the fight against prostitution, 148 operations were carried out and 193 people were detected, 16 of which were prosecuted criminally. It is also said that the number of victims totaled 22. As regards the anti -criminal operations (87), 3,823 people were investigated.
The document also references the records of repatriated individuals in the last five years. Last year, there were 22,275, a decrease of 7% annually (23,977), but still the second largest volume since at least 2020, precisely after 2023.
 
Fines were worth almost 190 million patacas
Throughout the year, the Public Security Police (CPSP) has awarded a total of 703,874 infringements, an increase of 9.11% in annual terms, with the amount of fines totaling 189.8 million patacas. Most of the fines were for illegal parking on public roads, non -payment in parking parks, alcohol research exam and disobedience to traffic signs.</description><pubDate>2025-07-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Egyptian curators give Tutancamon jewelry new</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/curadores-egipcios-dao-novo-brilho-as-joias-de-tutancamon/</link><description>In his teens, Eid Mertah spent the day reading books about Egyptian Pharaoh Tutancamon, drawing hieroglyphics and dreaming to have the monarch's gold mask in his hands.
“I studied Archeology for Tut,” Merrtah, 36, told AFP. "My dream was to work with his treasures, and this dream came true."
Mertah is one of more than 150 curators and 100 archaeologists who have worked silently for over a decade to restore thousands of artifacts from the Great Egyptian Museum (GME), a billing monthly project on the margins of Giza.
The inauguration was originally scheduled for July 3, but was reprogrammed for the last months of the year for safety reasons.
When finally opening, the GME will be the largest archaeological museum in the world dedicated to a single civilization. It will house more than 100,000 artifacts, half of them on display, and will include a living conservation laboratory.
Behind the glass walls, visitors will be able to see experts working to restore a 4,500 -year boat that has been buried near the Pharaoh Tomb Cheops to transport your soul to Ra, the sun god.
But the museum star will be the Tutancamon collection, with more than 5,000 objects, many of which will be shown together for the first time. Includes its Funeral Mask of Gold, Sarcophagos and Golden Amulets, Account Collars, Ceremonial Cars and two Mumified Fetuses believed to be their daughters born dead.
Many of these treasures have not been restored since they were discovered by British archaeologist Howard Carter in 1922.
The conservation methods used by Carter's team sought to protect objects, but more than a century later, their preservation is a challenge. Covering gold surfaces with wax, for example, "preserved objects in their time," curator Hind Bayoumi said "but hid the details that I wanted everyone to see."
For months, Bayoumi, 39, and her colleagues removed the wax applied by British chemist Alfred Lucas. Over the decades, this wax has captured dirt and opposed the brightness of gold.
The restoration was a joint effort between Egypt and Japan, which gave technical support and $ 800 million.
The golden sarcophagus of Tutancâmon, transported from the tomb in Luxor, was one of the most complex works. In the GME Wooden Laboratory, 34 -year -old curator Fatma Magdy used magnifying glasses and images to reassemble the delicate gold leaves. “It was like solving a gigantic puzzle,” he said. "The shape of the cut, the flow of hieroglyphics, every detail mattered."
 
Touch
Prior to restoration, Tutancamon's collection was recovered from several museums, deposits and tombs in Egypt. Some objects were slightly restored before their transportation to move them safely.
Before playing the objects, the teams conducted photographic documentation, X -ray analysis and material tests to understand the situation of each artifact. “We needed to understand the condition of each piece, the gold layers, the stickers, the wooden structure, all,” explained Mortah.
The team's philosophy has been the precaution. “The goal is always to make the least necessary and respect the history of the object,” said Mohamed Moustafa, a 36 -year -old restorer.
But beyond restoration work, the process has been an emotional journey to many of those involved. “I think we are more excited to see the museum than tourists,” admitted Moustafa. "When visitors walk through the museum, you will see the beauty of these artifacts. But for us, each piece is a reminder of the endless hours of work, debates, training," he said.
"Each piece tells a story."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-07-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>