<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>GDP DA</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pib-da-raem-registou-quebra-de-13-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>For the first time since the end of 2022, the GDP of the MGA retreated in annual terms. Preliminary data point to a 1.3%break between January and March, with GDP reaching 99.78 billion patacas. One of the justifications for the scenario is the “change in the consumption pattern of visitors”. Stressing that in the first quarter the recovery was based on “fluctuations”, statistics and census services still indicate that the economy of the territory “will not signal a cyclic recession, if there are no major changes in the internal and external context”. However, they recall the “volatility and challenges” of the international conjuncture and the growth of “uncertainties in Sino-American relations”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Macao Gross Domestic Product (GDP) retreated 1.3% in annual and real terms in the first quarter of this year, with preliminary data released by statistical and censuses (DSEC) to point to 99.78 billion patacas, equivalent to 85.2% of the first quarter of the first quarter of 2019. 2024 (given that it may be subject to review), marking the sixth consecutive quarter of slowdown.
The homologous break recorded in the first quarter-the first in two years, as the latter was registered in late 2022-among other factors, based on relatively high comparison of the first quarter of the previous year and the alteration of visitors consumption pattern, ”and appears after consecutive decelerations.
After an “accelerated recovery” in 2023, the territory economy gradually returned to normality last year. However, in 2024, the homologous growth in real terms progressively descended from 23.0% in the first quarter to 7.1% in the second, 3.8% in the third and 3.4% in the last quarter.
In the general calculation of 2024, the territory GDP increased by 8.8%, in annual and real terms, reaching 84.6%of the volume of 2019, however, it fell short of government projections, which had pointed to 10.3%.
According to DSEC preliminary data, between January and March 2025, global exports of services descended 3.8%, compared to the homologous quarter of 2024, notwithstanding the increase in the number of visitors. Until March, Macau received 9.86 million tourists, 11.1% more than in the same period last year.
According to the body's analysis, it was the change in the consumption pattern of visitors that led to “the fall in exports of other tourist services”. "The rapid changes in the consumption pattern of visitors, their preferences and consumer demographics" affected "the intention of consumption" of visitors, underlines DSEC, noting that "the expenses of visitors decreased, causing a certain impact on the development of the Macao Tourism sector."
In 2024, it should be recalled, the per capita expense of visitors was estimated at 2,157 patacas, 14.6% less than in 2023. Although it was maintained above the level of 2019 (1,626 patacas), the value represents the second consecutive annual break, after 20.8% to 2,525 patacas between 2022 and 2023.
In terms of internal demand, the main components were "relatively stable." The gross fixed capital formation rose 7.8% between January and March this year, while the government's final consumer consumption expense and private consumer expense grew by 1.0% and 0.6%, respectively, compared to the first quarter of 2024.
DSEC points out that “fluctuations” were found in the process of recovering the local economy in the first three months of the year. Nevertheless, "Macao's economy maintains the pace of recovery in global terms, public finances remain stable and local development is positive."
"In general, Macao's economy will not mark a cyclic recession if there are no major changes in the internal and external context, a continuous tendency for recovery, DSEC states. The body recalls, however, that since the beginning of the year, "the international conjuncture marks some volatility and challenges, the driving force of the growth of the global economy is not sufficient, and the uncertainties in Sino-American relations have grown."
In April, the International Monetary Fund again reduced projections on the economy of Macao, pointing to a 3.6% growth in 2025, half of the estimated announced in October, and a 3.5% rise in 2026. Expectations regarding the world economy also suffered a cut to 2.8% this year, with the IMF warning that the “rapid climbing of commercial tensions” and the high “political uncertainty” should have to have "A significant impact on global economic activity."
The data now released by DSEC are only preliminary, and the detailed and reviewed results of GDP will be known on May 16th. The body begins, from now on, to disclose preliminary data from GDP about 30 days after the end of the reference quarter.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>221 thousand visitors on May 2 marked a new record since 2019</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/221-mil-visitantes-dia-2-de-maio-marcaram-novo-recorde-desde-2019/</link><description>On May 2nd and 3rd, the daily number of visitors in Macau exceeded 200 thousand, and on the 2nd, more than 221 thousand entered a record since 2019. Until 17h00 yesterday, the last day of the Golden Week, the territory received more than 833,600 visitors
 
A new record has been established in terms of visitors since the pre-pound period. On May 2, 221,968 visitors entered Macao, a higher daily number since 2019, said the Public Security Police (CPSP). However, Macao scored 837,000 border tickets on the same day, which also established a record. Specifically, the Hengqin Border Post served more than 128 inputs and exits, marking the highest daily volume, while the siege door border registered more than 439,000 tickets, the highest since 2019.
Already on May 1st and 3rd, 176,921 and 204,078 visitors were accounted for. According to data from the Tourism Services Directorate (STD), in these three days, the total volume of visitors, greater than 602 thousand, represents an annual increase of 41.4%. In addition to the 60,000 Hong Kong visitors, which increased nearly 50% in annual terms, 507 thousand visitors from the interior of China (84.2% of the total) were recorded, which reflect an annual increase of almost 40%.
On the other hand, on the 4th, Macau received 154,462 visitors. In four consecutive days it was necessary to activate measures to control the flow of people on Rua de São Paulo. Given the crowds of people on Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro, several lanes between Central Street and the Institute for Municipal Affairs were closed to traffic, serving as provisional pedestrian walks.
Yesterday, the last day of the Golden Week, Macau registered 76,265 visitors until 17h00. It means that during the five days (until 17h00 yesterday), Macau received 833,694 visitors.
Regarding border movements, according to the CPSP, on May 1 and 2, there were more than 1.56 million border passages, which means an annual rise of 31.9%.
Also on the 2nd, Zhuhai's customs posts served 823,000 entries and exits (+32%), establishing a record. Gongbei's border has seen its border passage volume reach 439,000 that day, the highest in the last six years, while 13,000 Hong Kong or Macao vehicles have moved to Guangdong, which translates into an annual increase of 81%.
In turn, between the 1st and 3rd, borders on the Delta Bridge checked more than 283,000 tickets, an annual increase of 54.7%. On the other hand, between 1 and 4, about 64,000 RAE vehicles entered Guangdong by the Delta Bridge, equivalent to an annual climb of 60%.
Note that in the first two days of the golden week, CPSP detected a taxi offense involving the refusal of transport, and three cases of illegal provision of taxi services.
 
Hotel occupation surpassed 95% to 1 May
On the other hand, according to STD, the number of 176,921 visitors accounted for 1 illustrates an annual growth of 45%. According to the director of STD, this result was “encouraging”, with the hotel occupancy rate exceeded 95% on that day.
Helena de Senna Fernandes also revealed that STD will launch intellectual property cooperation projects in four community neighborhoods: one in the mud and the rest on the peninsula. In addition, STD will cooperate with local and foreign payment platforms to launch draw activities.
However, the authorities observed that, in the first four days of implementation of the temporary pedestrian zone in the old neighborhood of Taipa, it worked “well”, with the circulation of vehicles and people to remain “in good order”. On the other hand, STD conducted, during the golden week, “inspections to combat infringements, ensure the proper functioning of the industry, protect the rights and interests of visitors, and to make efforts to safeguard the image of Macau as a tourist city,” including the illegal accommodation measure.
Also in this period of holidays some incidents occurred in the city. On the 3rd, a four -year -old girl will have accidentally fallen from a three -meter -high location in Senate Largo. It was transported to the hospital, with injuries in various parts of the body.
On the same day, a 26 -year -old police will have been run over and injured by a public bus while guiding traffic on Conselheiro Ferreira de Almeida Avenue. Also due to the sudden braking of this bus, a 52 -year -old resident was injured. Both were transported to the hospital.
In turn, on the 4th, a passenger passed out shortly after entering a bus at the siege gates terminal. With the help of firefighters, he was able to recover consciousness and underwent more observations in the hospital.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ipim took 12 companies to the Lisbon Food Fair</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ipim-levou-12-empresas-feira-alimentar-de-lisboa/</link><description>To make the most of the advantages of the Macao Sino-Melidona platform was at the base of the trip to Lisbon of a delegation of local entrepreneurs, which participated in the “Farming Export Fair of Portugal”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
A dozen businessmen from MSAR has moved to Portugal to participate in the largest export fair of food products in Lisbon, as well as to perform for the first time in the Portuguese capital a “Roadshow” of the China-Paraís Economic and Commercial Exhibition of Portuguese Language (C-PLPEX). About 80 representatives of commercial associations and local businesses participated in the events, which sought to make the most of the unique advantages of the Macao Sino-Lusopone platform.
According to the Macao Commerce and Investment Institute (IPIM), some small and medium -sized local (SME) (SMEs) have established contacts with 10 companies from Portugal, reaching “cooperation intentions” with three companies during the “Portuguese flavors export fair”, covering products such as drinks, frozen foods and wines.
Among these, a first-time cider-made cash brand in Macao, “advancing the goal of making Macau as the premiere place for PLP products in the Great Bay market, helping to enrich and raise the contents of the Sino-Lirophone platform,” says IPIM in a statement.
In addition, some MSAR SMEs that participated for the first time considered that the results met their expectations, expanding not only the “circle of friends” but also deepening the function of the Macao PLP food product exposure center. Additionally, according to IPIM, Portuguese companies said they were “optimistic” about the prospects for the development of the Chinese market and “will take the opportunity to participate in the fair to explore business opportunities”.
The events took place for three days at the Lisbon International Fair (Fil), which attended about 400 Portuguese food companies, attracting more than 1,100 international buyers, which displayed agricultural products, food and alcohol, in the one that is the largest food export fair in the country.
During the visit to Portugal, IPIM took the opportunity to hold the Macao business environment and a C-PLPLPEX Roadshow at Macao Economic and Commercial Delegation in Lisbon, which attracted about 80 Portuguese businessmen.
 
Forum organized colloquium on cooperation in tourism
The Macao Forum Permanent Secretariat Training Center organized a colloquium on cooperation in the Tourism sector between China and Lusophone countries, with 18 representatives of Angola, Cape Verde, Guinea-Bissau, Equatorial Guinea, Mozambique, Portugal, Sao Tome and Principe and Timor-Leste. Among the graduates were representatives of government institutions, technicians and managers of specialty institutions. After the activities held between April 22 and May 6, participants received certificates. Discussions and lectures have dealt with the role of Macau as a sino-illusion platform, intelligent tourism, digital marketing, ecotourism and sustainable development. Participants were also at the International Tourism Exhibition and visited heritage sites, among others.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“The Chainsmokers” feature electropop music on venetian</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/the-chainsmokers-apresentam-musica-electropop-venetian/</link><description>The American duo of DJ's “The Chainsmokers” will act at the Venetian arena on June 28. Andrew Taggart and Alex Pall, winners of a Grammy, bring to Macau an Electropop show, which results from the mix of pop music, dance, indie, electronic and alt-rock. Tickets for the concert are already on sale
 
The Venetian Arena will host on June 28 at 20:00, a concert by the US DJ's duo “The Chainsmokers”, formed by musicians Andrew Taggart and Alex Pall. Winner of a Grammy in 2016 for better Dance recording, with the single “Don't Let Me Down”, the duo released the latest studio album “Summertime Friends” two years ago.
Taggart and Pall have been consistently raising popular music, breaking the boundaries between pop, dance, indie, electronic and alt-rock, featuring an electropop musical genre.
In doing so, “they marked the rhythm of culture and proved to be unavoidable, presenting some of the largest songs in the world, organizing a historic residence of several years in Las Vegas, filling enclosures on several continents, launching the first games of the gender in the metaveverse and selling tens of millions of singles,” says a note from the organization.
The Chainsmokers will act in Singapore the night before the arrival in Macao, then heading to the Japanese city of Chiba. In the MSAR show, they should play some of the most successful songs that have occupied tops of the tables over the years, such as "Don't Let Me Down" with Day, "Closer" with Halsey, "Something Just Like This" along with the Coldplay, "TakeAway" and "Lennon Stella", among others.
Territory fans can probably expect a mix of these iconic successes and more recent tracks from The Chainsmokers, namely "Hard Feelings" and "Summertime Friends."
The duo came in 2012 in New York. Both had a passion for electronic music and decided to unite talents to create a new artistic proposal.
With a career full of awards for international success, the two young men began with the creation of remixes and "mashups" of popular songs, gaining prominence in the electronic music scene when they released the first original productions, such as "The Rookie" and "It's All Started With A Whiscan."
Tickets for the show at Venetian are on sale at prices ranging from 699 to 1,399 patacas to sitting places. The standing places cost 1,299 patacas.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>The difference as Benfica and Sporting arrive</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/desporto/diferenca-como-benfica-sporting-chegam-empatados/</link><description>EPA12074081 Sporting's Eduardo Quaresma Scores A Goal Against Gil Vicente During the Portuguese First League Soccer Match, in Lisbon, Portugal, 04 May 2025. EPA/Filipe Amorim



With a knockout game next Saturday, Benfica and Sporting arrive in points at points, even though the lions have better “Goal Averag”. In this 32nd matchday, however, he stressed a great difference that can help understand the state of mind of both teams. On Saturday, Benfica, winning 2-1, ended the game trembling; On Sunday, Sporting to lose for much of the game, kept calm, tied and scored the goal of victory already in the final part of the discounts.
In more prominence:
 
Lent Savio Sporting at the reception to Gil Vicente
Eduardo Quaresma's goal, in compensation time, gave Sporting the victory at the reception of Gil Vicente. Felix Correia, in a penalty, on 26 minutes, inaugurated the marker. In the second part, Maxi Araújo, at 81, did the equality, and at 90-3, Lent made the turnaround that gave Sporting the triumph and that keeps him in the leadership of the I Liga, with 78 points, the same as Benfica, opponent in the next round.
If at the preview press conference, coach Rui Borges stated if Sporting had his head in the derby, could it be expensive to the team, the truth is that only after the 'captain' Hjulmand (alternate to not risk seeing the fifth yellow card) has entered the field to annihilate a cold Gil Vicente, cerebral and occupying the spaces well.
Even before the initial Fujimoto whistle, with a knee problem during the warming, he gave way to Santi Garcia.
Driven by a José Alvalade stadium practically sold out, (44,676 viewers), Sporting entered the game better with a more vertigo football, but was losing gas.
Gil Vicente, more paused and with great concern in the occupation of spaces, bet, when he could, in quick exits for the attack. In one of these initiatives, after 22 minutes, he saw Jonathan Mutombo be overthrown by St. Juste in the large Sporting area. After VAR intervention, Tiago Martins signaled a penalty that would be converted by Félix Correia.
Unable to penetrate the defensive wall mounted by César Peixoto, Sporting bet on the long balls, which were unsuccessful until the break.
In the second part and having to win, Rui Borges took the yellowish St. Juste -made debut to the axis of defense -Morita and Pedro Gonçalves and called the Hjulmand game, Geovany Quenda and Harder. With this, Sporting climbed the block-in possession of the ball the goalkeeper Rui Silva played by the midfield semicircle-, which pushed Gil Vicente to the last third of the terrain.
Without losing his mind, Sporting sought Gizar Gizar organized attacks, until Harder, with a shot at the entrance of the area, led the ball in an opponent with a townhouse for Maxi Araújo, who took advantage of the offer and, at 81 minutes, made the 1-1.
The Barcelos team accused the goal, opened spaces and saw Trincão, free of charge, 'take paint' from Andrew's goal at 87 minutes, who shortly after defended Harder's header.
When the nervousness had already taken over the benches to see that the draw would delay Sporting in the fight for the national title, here that Quaresma, who received the ball from Andrew, after a defense to fists following the collection of a corner kick, gave Sporting the trumpis, at 90+3, with a strong shot from outside the area.
At the celebrations, the 23 -year -old Central was "swallowed" by teammates and the public. In the images it was visible to see the player in tears and as a prize was considered the man of the game.
 
Benfica almost 'died' on Estoril beach
Benfica secured an important triumph on Estoril Praia visit 2-1, holding a last half-hour of much suffering.
Aursnes, after seven minutes, and Otamendi, at 35, seemed to refer the 'eagles' to a quiet triumph in the first half, but Vinícius Zanocelo reduced at 78, after Begraoui allowed Trubin's defense in a penalty at 66.
Bruno Lage changed only one element, with the entrance of Florentino to the departure of the punished Carreras, leaving Di María in the bench, while Pedro Carvalho and Orellana replaced the also suspended Wagner Pina and Holsgrove suspended.
The "Canarinhos" even started with more ball, but in the seven minutes Aursnes appeared in front of Joel Robles and did not faltered. Without forcing much, Benfica ended up increasing the advantage at 35, in a set ball charged by Dahl who discovered Otamendi at the heights, facing Pedro Álvaro's weak opposition and anticipating Joel Robles.
Bruno Lage's pupils reentry in the second half with authority and control of the ball, but this has been progressively fading throughout the match, a factor used by Estoril Praia to move forward.
Amdouni injured himself alone and was surrendered by Schjelderup at 57 at a time when Benfica was already totally 'dormant' and letting Estoril still dream, which could have happened at 66, a penalty. Otamendi knocked down Begraoui, but in the charge, Trubin sustained the Moroccan shot, with Vinicius Zanocelo hitting with a crash in the crossbar, in the recharge, allowing Benfica to hold the margin for a short time. At 78, ZanoCelo successfully responded to Guitane's cross and maintained the indecision until the end, but Benfica held a suffering triumph.
 
FC Porto returns to victories with Samu
FC Porto returned to the wins by beating Moreirense 3-1, with a twist on the marker, in the start of the journey, at the Dragon Stadium. Yan Lincoln advanced Moreirense on 30 minutes, but FC Porto would draw for Francisco Moura at 40, running the turnaround with a 'bis' of Samu at 70 and 77 minutes.
FC Porto, with Nehuén Pérex and Samu to return to 'Eleven', settled in Moreirense midfield since the initial whistle, but the low pace imposed by Eustáquio, more climbed, and Fábio Vieira, the first responsible for giving the portista game, and excessive bulletinas left the comfortable outsiders.
The defensive structure of the Vimaranense formation featured the reinforcement of the Early Spanish Teguia on the right side, in a line of five units that was controlling the timid actions of the places, in a register without beacons and that even motivated whistles of the demanding adept mass present in a dragon with the less completed benches.
The kick -off in the monotony belonged to the inevitable Rodrigo Mora, 30 minutes, in a shot that still "kissed" the post of the goal of Caio Secco, following a corner and a happy intervention by João Mário.
In response, the Moreirense, who had only passed the midfield with ball, was advanced by Yan Lincoln, with a cross shot from the right, after taking Nehúen Pérez from the front, in a move started in the goalkeeper, with several ball exchanges and the last pass of Alanzinho.
Moreirense did not, however, had a long time to capitalize on the advantage, the first in the history of clashes in the dragon, because Francisco Moura, at 40, tied, head, corresponding to a cross by Fábio Vieira, in a bid contested by the canons.
The game cheered up and in two moments the Moreirense could have passed again forward, but Claudio Ramos, at 43 and 45 minutes, avoided a new disadvantage, counting on one throw with the precious intervention of João Mário.
The portistas returned from the most expeditious resort to change the ball and saw their life easier when Gustavo Correia signaled a great penalty, for alleged hand to the ball of Maracás, on 68 minutes, with Samu converting their maximum punishment.
The back Frimpong, soon after, went up on the ground and still provided for an opportunity to reach the draw, in an approach that Moreirense would not repeat until the end, clearly slaughtered by the third portista, 79 minutes, noted by Samu, after delay work.
Caio Secco was injured in the final moments and left the Moreirense team reduced to 10 elements, being replaced in the goal by the striker Asué.
 
Braga and Santa Clara marks step in the goals
Sporting de Braga and Santa Clara drew 1-1, a result that penalizes the two teams in their respective objectives, the Minho in the fight for third place and the Azoreans for the fifth. Santa Clara marked first, for Ricardinho (six minutes), with Sporting de Braga tied at the beginning of the second half, by the inevitable Ricardo Horta (47).
The Minho were caught by FC Porto, now adding both 65 points, but with the 'dragons' with the advantage of goals. Already Santa Clara saw Vitória de Guimarães distance himself in the fifth post, now being three points from the Vimaranenses.
Without El Ouazzani, who was not even in the bank, Carlos Carvalhal only exchanged the punished Paulo Oliveira for Robson Bambu and, in Santa Clara, also registered one change, with Diogo Calila to return to ownership (Lucas Soares left).
Sporting de Braga even entered the match well and, just after 04 minutes, Gharbi shot the entrance of the area for the tight defense of Gabriel Batista.
It was, however, Santa Clara to advance on the marker after six minutes, with Ricardinho, served by Diogo Calila on the right, to get ready, discarded on the right, with the 'sleeping' Minho defense.
At 12 minutes, a quick counterattack conducted by Ricardinho ended with some precipitation of Gabriel Silva, who threw the figure of Hornicek.
Sporting de Braga then took over the game, but almost always in a very slow and predictable pace and only in the last minutes of the first half created danger with the opposing goal.
On 45 minutes, he drew a good offensive play on the right side that culminated in a Racic front shot still diverted by the opposite defense.
From the corner, a niakaté head was born that the Azorean guardian rejected with some difficulty (45+1).
The second part began practically with the goal of Braga, with Ricardo Horta to shot first, in the "heart" of the area, after assistance of Victor Gómez of the right - 11th goal in the Portuguese International Championship (15th in all competitions).
The coaches stirred the teams at 71 minutes, Carlos Carvalhal launching 'blood' new, with Roger and boss, and Vasco Matos refreshing midfield and attack with Pedro Ferreira and Vinícius.
Until the end, Sporting de Braga pressed more, but with little discretion in the definition, and Santa Clara, in counterattack, created more danger, with shots of Gabriel Silva (72), Diogo Calila (85) and Pedro Ferreira (90+4).
 
Vitória de Guimarães wins in Madeira
Vitória de Guimarães won Nacional 2-1 and remains in fifth place, the last of access to European competitions. At the Madeira Stadium, in Funchal, goals of Tiago Silva, 13 minutes, and Chucho Ramírez, at 64, secured the Minho team's triumph, with Fuki, at 73, reduced to the formation of the house.
Vitória adds 54 points, while Nacional is 11th, to the condition, with 33, on punctual equality with Arouca and Rio Ave, which have both less played.
 
Farense wins with goal in discounts
A goal from Spanish Darío Poveda, at 90+1 minutes, allowed Farense to win Famalicão at home 2-1 and win a new breath in the fight for maintenance. Poveda culminated the turnaround of the places, which began by Filipe Soares, at 45+4 minutes, ending a series of nine games in a row of the Algarve without winning at home, after Simon Elisor gives the outsiders advantage at 30.
The Farense rose, to the condition, from 18th to 17th place, with 24 points, the same as AVS, 16th, instead of play-off, in a table where Famalicão is seventh, with 44.
 
Arouca and Casa Pia draw at zero
Arouca and Casa Pia drew without goals in a game in which Lisbon formation played in numerical inferiority since 39 minutes, due to the expulsion of José Fonte. Casa Pia follows in the eighth position, with 42 points, equal to Estoril Praia, which is ninth, and two from Famalicão, seventh, while Arouca occupies the 11th place with 34.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Explore Macau” with workshops and guided tours</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/explorar-macau-workshops-visitas-guiadas/</link><description>Through the Financial Support Plan granted by the Directorate of Tourism Services, local associations will continue to be able to organize tourist projects in order to boost the community economy. During this month, the activity “Explore Macao” includes family adventures and visits to Chinese temples
 
Encouraging local associations to carry out activities or projects in the area of ​​tourism and culture, in view of the attraction of visitors to community zones, is the objective of another series of financial support for tourism services (STD).
During the month of May, the activity is launched with the theme “Explore Macao”, including the second edition of “Family Adventure at Macao Carnival” involving local commercial establishments, “Macau Fun!
The event dedicated to the family will take place until the 10th, Saturday, in the leisure zone of the Lok Yeung Fa Yuen building of the North Zone, presenting a fair of cultural and creative products, craft workshops, exhibitions and cultural shows, as well as interactive street views, among others.
In conjunction with 60 commercial establishments with local characteristics, the activity also offers different discounts to attract visitors to consume in community neighborhoods.
“Macao full of fun! Guided community tourism visits” is another of STD initiatives, which started last Sunday and extended until June 29. Includes 18 guided tours on nine consecutive Sundays.
Three scripts are made available: “Golden Years”, which leads participants to visit the East Foundation and the Protestant Cemetery, among others, exploring the development of Macao trade; “São Lourenço Memories”, with travel to the Church of St. Lourenço, and the building and church of the Seminary of St. Joseph; and “Tales of the Inner Harbor”, which allows you to “cross” the time to the Macao Industrial Era, with visits to the Kwong Hing Tai Panchões Factory and the No. 8 Bridge.
Each session has guided tours in Cantonense, Mandarin or English, as well as coffee, tea or incense preparation workshops, “enriching the participants' experience,” says a note from STD.
“Exploring Chinese temples of Macau 2025” will take place on Saturdays from May 17-25, with one session during the morning and another in the afternoon. On the 25th there will be guided tours in Chinese and English, the Peninsula's Chinese culture temples of Chinese culture, such as the old TCA temples, Fok Tak Chi from the Miter and Lu Ban District, which will allow us to get to know the history and culture through that heritage. Participants will also be able to create small objects with fragrances, bringing blessings home.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Banks Operational Profit grew 45%</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lucro-operacional-dos-bancos-cresceu-45/</link><description>Macao banks made operational profits of 3.76 billion patacas in the first quarter, 44.8% more than in the same period as 2024.
According to data from the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM), the main reason was banking services and operations, whose revenues increased 42.1% to 2.76 billion patacas.
Official data also reveal that financial investments yielded 528.6 million patacas to banks, more than 218.6% than in the first three months of last year.
In the opposite direction, the Macao banking fell from 3.1%to 3.75 billion patacas, on the interest margin, the difference between loan revenues and deposit expenses. This after the AMCM approved three descents of the main reference interest rate in the last three months of 2024, the last of which a 0.25 percentage points, introduced on December 19, following the US Federal Reserve.
Macao banks made a profit of 4.01 billion patacas by 2024, a drop of 21.3% and the lowest value since 2010, especially due to the fall of the interest margin.
The loans, the main source of revenue from the banking worldwide, decreased 4.7% in the last 12 months, settling in 1.02 billion of patacas in late March.
On the contrary, deposits with Macau banks increased by 10.3%to 1.36 billion of patacas, AMCM said.
Macau Banking Credit Credit fell 2.7% in March to 56.1 billion patacas after February had reached the highest amount since AMCM began compiling this data in 1990. In March, overdue loans represented 5.5% of Macao bank loans, more percentage points than in the same month as 2024. 6.7% in the case of credit to institutions or individuals outside the Chinese region.
The European Banking Authority, the EU regulatory agency, for example, considers that banks with at least 5% of bad loans have “high exposure” at risk and should establish a strategy to solve the problem.
Still, the percentage of bank credit overdue in Macau is far from the 25.3% record reached in mid -2001, in the middle of the world economic crisis caused by the outbreak of the speculative bubble of companies linked to the internet.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Spirit of “May 4” reinforced love for the homeland</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/espirito-4-de-maio-reforcou-amor-pela-patria/</link><description>The ceremony of the National Flag Hastear by the Macao School Sector pointed out the beginning of the commemorative series of the 106th anniversary of the “May 4 Movement”. The event was organized by the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services
 
In order to promote the spirit of “May 4” among young people, the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) organized, on the Youth Day, a “ceremony of the rainfall of the National Flag by the Macao School Sector”. At the same time, the DSEDJ promoted a youth forum, marking the beginning of the series of activities for the celebration of the 106th anniversary of the “May 4 Movement”.
The raising of the flag took place at the Macao Polytechnic University Polydestive Pavilion, having had the secretary's presence for social affairs and culture, LAM, as well as representatives of various entities, associations and universities.
The Hymn of the Popular Republic of China was played by the “Macau Youth Band” and a choir composed of students from various schools in the territory. Then, the show Xian Xinghai and the Yellow River song, created and interpreted by the students of the artistic course taught by the Conservatory of Macau and the Luso-Chinese Technical-Professional School, which incorporated the spirit of May 4 through diverse arts.
The Chinese Spirit Dance, presented by the students of the Ilha Verde Secondary School of the Macao Commercial Association, integrated elements such as the art of handwriting, boat tank top, martial arts, among other elements of Chinese culture.
On the same day, the “May 4” Youth Forum took place, at the auditorium of the Macao University of Tourism (Mong-Há Campus), under the theme “May 4 Legacy and Innovation: Macao Youth and the Future”. The guests shared their experiences in innovation and entrepreneurship and scientific and technological research.
The activities of the series of activities to celebrate the anniversary of the movement also include exchange visits to the cities of the Great Bay and the cooperation zone, career and scientific exploration activities, postcard design and coloring contest, online question and answers game, among others.
Between May and June, higher education institutions and primary and secondary schools will give several lectures and sharing sessions, “so that young students from Macau can know the history and meaning of the May 4 movement.
The objective, says DSEDJ, "is to respond to President Xi Jinping's council, given to young people in general, to defend their ideals and beliefs, the development of the sense of family and homeland and a working spirit and contributing to their youthful strength for national construction."</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SUSPENDED WORK AFTER WORKER OFF</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/obra-suspensa-apos-queda-de-trabalhador-ao-mar/</link><description>In a shipyard between zone A and the peninsula, a building machine and a worker fell into the sea, having been “slightly injured”. The work has already been suspended, and the causes of the incident to be investigated
 
An operator and a building machine fell into the sea due to the partial collapse of the provisional easel bridge at the A3 access road construction contract between the new landfills and the peninsula. The work was, however, suspended. The worker, who was “slightly injured”, left the sea by his own foot, having been transported to the hospital by the contractor.
According to the authorities, the operator, who was conscious after the succeed, will undergo a "detailed medical inspection." In addition, also a non -resident worker (TNR) was injured.
The public works (DSOP), maritime and water (DSAMA) and labor affairs (DSAL) services, which say they attribute “great importance” to the incident, issued a notice of suspension of work to the contractor, and ordered “the total suspension of the work”. In addition, “they will do the search and rescue work of the building machine and take the necessary measures for the maritime area, in order to avoid causing pollution during search work”.
As for TNR, Dsal has presented vows of rapid improvements and ensured that it will help monitor the indemnity process by the work incident.
DSOP also required the contractor and the supervisory entity to fully collaborate with the administration in the investigation of the causes of the incident, and the reports must be presented “in the short term”. "In the case of involvement in the act of infringement and work under the insecurity, responsibilities will be required," warns the bodies.
However, Dsama has already sent a boat and staff to inspect the site. In addition, it required the contractor to install oil containment barriers and signaling buoys.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Association gave up demonstration after “conversations” with the police</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/associacao-desistiu-de-manifestacao-apos-conversas-policia/</link><description>The “Macau People Power” association intended to organize a demonstration on Labor Day, so the president, Lam Weng Ioi, and another member warned police in mid -April about the intention. However, they eventually canceled the action, choosing to give a petition to the chief executive. Quoted by the “All About Macau”, Lam Weng Ioi said that, after warning the police, they were constantly contacted by agents through telephone calls and the Wechat. According to the associative leader, the agents wanted to understand the details of the demonstration, and they invited us three times to "talk" with agents in places outside the squad. In the "conversations", the agents addressed "the preparations for the manifestation, the circumstances possibly happening and several different consequences," said Lam Weng Ioi, recalling that they were suggested to think clearly, and it was still told that it was necessary to ensure that no chaotic situations would happen. "For example, if some protesters do not respect the discipline or someone takes the opportunity to cause problems ... Of course we said there would be a team to maintain the order, but repeatedly required that chaotic situations could not happen. Otherwise, organizers could risk solidarity responsibilities. They even mentioned the law of national security," he said. According to he confessed, they realized that it would be very difficult to meet police demands. Still, he stressed that the association has not yet given up expressing claims through demonstrations, stating that it will be more prepared in the future.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Collateral exhibition of “Art Macau” seeks proposals</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/exposicao-colateral-da-arte-macau-procura-propostas/</link><description>The Cultural Institute (IC) launched the contest of exhibition proposals within the collateral exhibition of “Macao Art: Macau International Art Biennial 2025”, inviting local individuals and organizations linked to the arts to respond. The aim is to “jointly promote the field of contemporary art, as well as build a platform for the exchange of international art, open and diverse, highlighting the results achieved in the local artistic formation and the creative energy of Macao”. The selected proposals will be promoted within the scope of “Art Macau 2025”, in synergy with other sections of the Biennial. Proposals are sought that reflect the “contemporary spirit”, with a period of exposure not less than two weeks, and should be evident between July 19 and October 12. With the place to choose the competitor and without limitations regarding the scale and the form of the exposure, it is mandatory to ensure compliance with security laws and standards, with the organization costs supported by the proponent. Proposals can be delivered until 5 pm on May 23. The selection will fit Feng Boyi, the main curator of “Art Macau 2025”, based on criteria such as curatorial concept, quality of the works, degree of adequacy to the theme, team qualifications, proposal's feasibility and place of the exhibition. With six sections -main exhibition, public art exhibition, city pavilion, special exhibition, local curatorship project and collateral exhibition -the event will be dedicated this summer to the theme “Hello, what do you do here?”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao obligations may be quoted in Luxembourg</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/obrigacoes-de-macau-poderao-ser-cotadas-luxemburgo/</link><description>The Secretary for Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP, led a delegation of MSAR for a visit to Europe to deepen cooperation in areas such as science, technology, economy, commerce and finance. France, Luxembourg and Monaco were the countries visited. In Luxembourg, the delegation participated in a lecture by local Chinese financial institutions and also had a meeting with “Luxembourg for Finance” and “Luxembourg Stock Exchange”. Tai Kin IP indicated that Macao's securities deposit center has completed direct interconnection with Hong Kong's The Central Moneymarkets Unit, and expressed hope that international cooperation will be extended to take advantage of Luxembourg's experiences. In addition, "both parties also negotiated about the quotation of Macau obligations on the Luxembourg Stock Exchange and the creation of conditions for the consequent transaction, as well as cooperation in the formation of financial qualified frames." In France, opportunities for cooperation were studied in the domains of transfrontic electronic trade, traditional Chinese medicine, technological innovation and formation of young qualified pictures. According to the press release, the hope is that, through Macau, a cooperation platform for cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, the development of industries in China, Macao and France, or even Europe, as well as "exploited cooperation spaces with Latin -speaking countries." Finally, in Monaco, the delegation was in a forum organized by the Prince Alberto II Foundation of Monaco and international energy companies.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2390/</link><description>Illegal immigrant sentenced to five months in prison
A 48 -year -old man from the interior of China, who had already been forbidden to enter Macao, was sentenced to five months in prison on suspicions of illegal entry. According to customs services, the defendant will have used a underwater propeller to illegally enter the territory. On the 1st, it was intercepted by Customs when he had headed to the coast in the vicinity of Cheoc Van beach.
 
Daily average passenger in the metro rose 5.7% in April
The daily average passenger in the light meter rose 5.7% in monthly terms to 25,900 in April, according to statistics from the Metro Society. The passenger volume was just short of the February (27,100), and it should be remembered that the Chinese New Year was celebrated this year between late January and the beginning of the following month. Recently, in the presentation of the government lines of action, the Secretary for Transport and Public Works announced that two more subway lines are being thought of on the peninsula, hoping that they can contribute to increase the number of passengers of this means of transport.
 
Guangdong circulation dispenses with vehicle certificate
From May 15, those interested in applying for “Macao vehicle circulation in Guangdong Province”, through mobile application or electronic page, no longer need to request the “certificate of information from the transionic vehicle”. Other updates produced by services to traffic issues include the addition of a warning of less than 60 days of the license in the warning of continuation, implementation of automatic cancellation mechanism for requirements that exceed the deadline, and make available the functionality of consulting “days of permanence accumulated inside China”.
 
Chinese manuals will be reviewed this year
Authorities will review this year the Chinese discipline manuals, the director of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) said. According to the Chinese language press, Kong Chi Meng said that schools and publishers have created a group to collect opinions from the guardians and have already begun to elaborate the new manuals. According to it, opinions focus mainly on optimizing the choice of words and the use of interesting methods in the presentation. As the discipline involves primary and secondary education, it is possible that new manuals will be gradually implemented in the next two school years.
 
36,000 have already become a national security exhibition
The eighth edition of the exhibition on National Security Education, co-organized by the government and the Central Government connecting office at MSAR, recorded, until May 1, more than 36,000 visitors and more than 92,727 navigations on the Electronic Page. The show, which can be visited at the Complex of the Commercial Cooperation Platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, runs until May 15.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Vatican installs chimney in the sistine chapel for the conclave</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/vaticano-instala-chamine-na-capela-sistina-para-conclave/</link><description>The Vatican installed, on the weekend, the chimney that will announce that the cardinals, confined to the Sistine Chapel from this week, elected the successor of Pope Francis.
A total of 133 cardinals will vote, starting on Wednesday, under Michelangelo frescoes to choose the new spiritual leader of the 1.4 billion Catholics. The so -called “Church Princes” will make four daily votes: two in the morning and two in the afternoon, except on the first day.
After voting, voting bulletins will be burned in a oven to announce the result to the world: black smoke if they cannot reach the necessary two -thirds majority; White smoke if "Habemus Papam".
Tens of thousands of people in St. Peter's Square and millions of people around the world who watch on television will be eyeing the narrow brown cylinder, waiting for the great announcement.
There is a “more spiritual,” AFP Diana Ispego, a Mexican resident in the US, told the AFP, pointing to the chimney.
The Sistine Chapel has two ovens linked to the same chimney, from which comes the only indication of what happens inside. In the oldest, voting bulletins and cardinals are burned. The second, more modern, is used to announce the result of the vote. From the latter, with the help of chemicals, comes the black smoke (if the cardinals do not reach an agreement) or white, when a new pope is elected.
The chimney was installed by a Firefighters from the Holy See, which climbed to the top of the roof of the majestic chapel. The work went unnoticed to most tourists present in St. Peter.
The installation coincided with the resumption of general congregations on Friday, where about 200 cardinals gathered to discuss the priorities for the future of this 2,000-year institution.
This meeting emphasized the spread of the Catholic faith, the need for unity, and the risk of “hiring”-problems such as sexual abuse and financial scandals-among other topics, said Vatican spokesman Matteo Bruni.
Bruni also reported that of the 133 cardinals able to vote for being under 80, only four left to arrive in Rome. He confirmed the absences of Spanish Antonio Cañizares and Kenyan John Njue.
Eighty percent of these voters were appointed by Francis. Many come from the “periphery” of the world, areas that for years have been marginalized by the Catholic Church. Most people are unknown and these meetings serve as a place to hear ideas and exchange views.
 
"There will be no Francis II"
Conclave is a meeting that dates back to the Middle Ages, when the idea of ​​electing a sovereign was a revolutionary idea.
The deliberations are kept strictly confidential, under penalty of instant excommunication. Mobile phones and any internet access are prohibited. Cardinals are not allowed to read newspapers, listen to radio or watch the television. Any contact with the outside world is prohibited.
"The world needs a completely coherent person," Cardinal Salvadoran Gregorio Rosa Chávez, 82, told reporters. "These people are not very common."
Many cardinals agree that the election will be short, but Vatican Marco Politi expert is skeptical.
"This is the first conclave in 50 years when there is a strong feeling of fracture within the church," explained the expert, who foresees a choice "between a decelected pope and another slowly advances."
“There will be no Francis II,” he predicts.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>