<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Half of those who have changed their jobs are young and want better salaries</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/metade-dos-mudaram-de-emprego-sao-jovens-querem-melhores-salarios/</link><description>There were more workers to change jobs last year, totaling 12,800, 50% were young. More than half of the people who took this step have made him motivated by the search for "better remuneration conditions." Overall, the change began, with the median monthly income growing 1,000 patacas - noting that men went to earn another 1,300 patacas, while women only got another 700. Still in the wage, and regarding full -time workers, almost 53,000 received 40,000 patacas or more, and this past is the sectoral level that
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The Macao Labor Market continued to give signs of dynamism last year, with unemployment and underemployment rates to decrease, and the population employed to rise. At the same time, there were also more people - especially young people - to change jobs, motivated by seeking better pay. As for this aspect, to note that there are more people to earn high wages.
The employment survey in 2024, prepared by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) and analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, reveals that 12,800 people changed their jobs, translating an increase of 8% in annual terms. The number is equivalent to 3.7% of the full -time population (plus 0.2 percentage points), whose numbers point to a total of 330,500 (plus 13,500 people).
The year 2024 thus marks the third consecutive growth of this phenomenon, since between 2018 and 2021, the number of people who exchanged work was decreasing from year to year, specifically 12,300 to 8,400 people. The situation was later reversed in 2022, a year much marked by the pandemic, when 10,300 people changed their jobs.
People aged 25 to 34 years were the ones that took the most step, representing 50.5% of the total (plus 7.4 percentage points in annual terms). Then follows the age group from 35 to 44, equivalent to 27.6% of this universe.
The main motive pointed out by 6,900 people to have done it was to “look for better remuneration conditions” (53.7% of the total and 5.2 percentage points). In general, this ambition was reached, since the median monthly income of people who changed jobs increased by 1,000 patacas or 7.1% in annual terms from 14,000 to 15,000 patacas.
However, it should be noted that differences between genres are observed. Men, whose median of monthly income was 15,000 patacas before the change of employment, went to earn another 1,300 patacas overall to 16,300 patacas. The women, who earned 12,300 monthly patacas, began to receive only 700 patacas after completing the exchange, raising a monthly median of 13,000 patacas.
The “end of temporary employment or termination of contract” and “extinction of the establishment or company/dismissal”, in turn, were pointed out as factors that contributed to the change of employment by 2,300 workers, equivalent to 18% (minus 6.7 percentage points). There were also 3,100 people who invoked “personal or family reasons” (plus 0.7 percentage points) to follow this path.
Still in the field of employment change, groups of people aged 45 to 54 years (11%), with 55 or older (5.5%) and from 16 to 24 years (5.4%).
The data also reveal that 6,700 people remained in the same branch of activity, while 6,100 completely changed work life. In addition, only about 1,100 had changed two or more work in the previous year, with most having done so only once.
Last year, the unemployed population raised 6,200 people looking for a new job (2.8%less) and 800 who tried to find their first job (less 0.1%). Unemployment who sought jobs for a period of less than four months equivalent to 53% of the total.
About 21%of unemployed people looking for a new employment previously worked in the game sector, surpassing areas such as retail trade (19%) and construction (14.1%).
In the analysis of the main causes of unemployment, the “personal or family reasons” prevailed again, presented by 2,400 individuals, ie 37.8% of the total. The “end of temporary employment or contract termination” was followed, which affected 1,100 people (17.8%) and the “extinction of establishment or company”, a factor that “weighed” 14% by leaving 900 in unemployment. DSEC also pointed out to 700 “dismissal” and 800 situations that pointed to “unsatisfactory working conditions”.
The problem of unemployment was more notorious in the age group from 25 to 34 years, involving about 2,000 people, followed by individuals 35 to 44 years old (1,600). In terms of academic qualifications, the unemployed population included about 3,300 people who completed higher education, 1,500 who completed the complementary secondary, 1,300 the general secondary and 700 primary education.
 
More people gaining 40,000 patacas or more
In the general calculation of 2024, the population employed consisted of 376,000 people, plus 11,100 compared to the last year, mainly due to the increase of non -resident workers. On the other hand, it should be recalled, unemployment rates set at 1.8% in general terms and 2.4% among residents, representing annual descents of 0.9 and 1.0 percentage points, respectively, while the discharge rate also decreased 0.3 points to 1.4%. In absolute terms, DSEC has accounted for 7,000 unemployed (less 3,000) and 5,300 underemployed (1,200 minus).
Under the population employed, the average monthly income was 18,000 patacas, plus 500 in annual terms, and the residents also increased by 500 patacas to 20,500. In the case of full-time workers, a group consisting of 330,500 people, the median monthly income settled in 19,000 patacas, ie another 1,000.
Regarding remuneration, statistics show that the number of full -time workers who earned 40,000 patacas or more totaled 52,500, equivalent to an increase of 18.8% or more 8,300 people in absolute terms. This sectoral echelon thus became the one that most people housed, followed by the remuneration between 20,000 and 24,999 patacas, with 51,100 (+2.7% or 1,400 people).
The DSEC inquiry also highlights that the number of workers who earned a yield between 8,000 and 11,999 patacas decreased to 41,200 people, a break of 4.5% or less 1,900 people. On the other hand, the salary segments from 12,000 to 15,999 Patacas and from 16,000 to 19,999 “received” more people, totaling 49,100 and 34,700, plus 900 people (+1.9%) and 1,600 (+4.5%), respectively.
In terms of academic qualifications, it was observed that 46% of the population employed, equivalent to 173,100 people, had higher education (plus 1.1 percentage points), and that 58,900 had overall secondary education (15.7% of the total and less 0.8 percentage points).
The number of workers due to others increased by 13,300 people to 351,600, but those of employers (12,200) and workers on their own (12,000) descended 1,900 and 600 people, respectively. Weekly, almost half of the population employed (47.3%) worked between 45 and 49 hours, with 12.5% ​​worked a total of 50 or more hours.
 
Almost 132,000 workers per shift
Employment inquiry data allow you to realize that the shift work system involved approximately 131,800 people in 2024, which is 37.5% of workers due to others (351,600), representing a 3.29% rise in annual terms. Most of the workers by shift were in the age groups from 35 to 44 years old (44,400) and 25 to 34 years old (34,900). This work model was adopted by about 62,500 gambling workers (77%of the total sector), 25,200 hotels (51.5%), 11,300 of the thick and retail trade (30.3%), 10,300 public administration and social security (33.6%) and 8,500 from the real estate and services provided to companies (29.6%).</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Animal mistreatment with 40 cases since 2016</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/maus-tratos-animais-40-casos-desde-2016/</link><description>Since the Animal Protection Act came into force in 2016, the Public Security Police (CPSP) body received, in total, 40 cases of abuse or animal cruelty. Last year, three cases were detected, equal to the accounted for in 2023. On the other hand, according to CPSP, 74 cases of discovery of animal corpses were reported over the past year last year

The Animal Protection Act came into force in Macao in July 2016. Until March 11 this year, the Public Security Police (CPSP) received a total of 40 cases of abuse or animal cruelty, mainly implying acts of cruelly beating in dogs or cats.
According to a response sent by CPSP to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, retreating last year, three cases of abuse or animal cruelty came to the police. Specifically, the perpetrators of the crime violently dealt with dogs or cats at home. In addition, a case was also detected in which a passerby kicked a dog's head several times while the animal was strolling.
The number was equivalent to that verified in 2023, the year in which three cases of the genre were also discovered by CPSP.
Regarding the current year, in the interval between January 1 and March 11, the corporation received a complaint related to abuse or cruelty against animals. However, the investigation eventually ruled out evidence of the crime of abuse provided by the Animal Protection Law.
According to CPSP, this case involved a cat that would have fallen accidentally and died while playing and ran on the porch of a fraction. The animal's body was discovered on a ride on Rua do Campo.
On the other hand, CPSP received, last year, 74 cases of discovery of animal corpses, including one of animal cruelty, 12 that involved road accidents, two in which the victims were attacked by other animals, and four falling in height. The causes of the remaining cases, about 74.3% of the total, were not cleared.
In addition, CPSP data show that, in the first two months of this year alone, the number of animal corpses discovered cases reached 22. According to police investigations, three cases involved road accidents, one involved attack by other animals, three occurred with the victims to fall at the height, and two were related to natural death, while in 59% of cases the cause of animal death is unknown.
Asked about the scheduled plans for this year in the sphere to combat animal abuse, in cooperation with the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI), CPSP indicated that it added, in the lectures on crime prevention, clarification on the contents of the animal protection law, including the legal consequences, law enforcement procedures and the forms of submission of allegations. The idea is that citizens can deepen knowledge about legal responsibilities for animal abuse.
In addition, CPSP said it will collaborate “actively” with AMI in taking the actions and promoting awareness activities, to encourage public knowledge about animal protection, so that it arouses “double effects” of warning and education.
 
Capture of stray dogs increased by 50%
On the other hand, following a 61 -year -old resident was attacked by a pack and bite by one of the Concórdia Marginal Street dogs in Coloane and transported to the hospital, AMI has issued a statement, ensuring that continuously reinforces patrol actions at critics most frequented by stray dogs.
In 2024, AMI captured 568 dogs, having the number rising almost 50% compared to 2023. In this respect, the body also linked that highlights employees to critical points where there are the most stray dogs, such as Concordia Industrial Park in Coloane, Avenida de Vale das Seac Pai Van, Vila de Coloane, Hac Ho-Hó Dam, how to reinforce the patrol.
In addition, AMI has highlighted “active cooperation” with animal protection associations in recent years to jointly promote the TNA measure (catch, sterilize and adopt in the English acronym), “striving” to reduce the number of stray animals.
 
80 veterinary activity licenses issued
About 80 establishments obtained provisional licenses under the “Veterinary Clinical Care Law and the commercial activity of animals”, according to which, until March 31, all establishments, regardless of whether or not they have this license, could work. According to the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI), 25 provisional licenses of veterinary clinical care and 59 commercial animal activity were issued, with a two -year expiration date. Specifically, they are in force between April 1 of this year and March 31, 2027. According to AMI, “two commercial animal activity establishments were unable to obtain the license, due to lack of delivery of all legal documents and not compliance with the requirements of transient provisions”. In this sense, the body required that they ensure the proper accommodation and care of animals in establishments, and AMI will send personnel to follow the situation.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Government exhorted to apply IA in economic policies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-exortado-aplicar-ia-nas-politicas-economicas/</link><description>The importance of artificial intelligence in the competitiveness of companies and the main challenges that Macao faces in areas such as education and the job market are themes underlined by José Pereira Coutinho in a written interpellation to the government. Among other questions, the deputy intends to know how effective the implementation of the Science and Technology Cooperation and Exchange Center between China and Portuguese -speaking countries in promoting technological initiatives and investment attraction
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Under the theme “Evaluation of Technological Companies in the MSAR: Methodologies and Criteria”, José Pereira Coutinho made a interpellation to the government, analyzing and questioning the technological innovation policies implemented in Macao in various areas. The deputy focuses on the challenge and the need to apply new technologies, and specifically Artificial Intelligence (AI), in order to create more jobs.
Considering it is important that digitization, automation and implementation of AI “are already reformulating the market in various areas, such as health, education, engineering and communication”, Pereira Coutinho understands that “local population aging and growing concern for environmental issues generate new requests, requirements and opportunities for qualified professionals in sustainable and health care”.
With advances in the areas of AI, biotechnology and sustainability, "many of the professions we know currently will go through a true revolution," he says, "while others, still nonexistent, will have to be created to satisfy the emerging needs of society." The deputy adds that "in a world that lives under pressure from innovations and profound economic, social and environmental transformations, it is essential that the Macao government understands these trends and anticipates to them, implementing policies that meet the professional and social needs of the population."
In this sense, Coutinho puts a series of questions, intending to know how the executive interprets the importance of AI in the competitiveness of Macao companies, and the ability of this technology to transform local economic sectors. On the other hand, Pereira Coutinho wants to know which quality teaching and training strategies that can be implemented in Macao schools and universities to prepare students for a job market increasingly influenced by artificial intelligence.
In other points of the question, the government is urged to disclose the evaluation made to the results achieved by the Business Certification Program, implemented in 2023 by the economy and technological development services and how this program contributed to the attraction and maintenance of companies in MSAR. On this article, the deputy asks the executive to explain the main scientific criteria and evaluation models used to classify and certify the technology companies that participated in the program.
Also alluding to the Center for Cooperation and Exchange of Science and Technology between China and Portuguese -speaking countries (PLP), Pereira Coutinho suggests the presentation of a balance on the efficacy of the center in promoting technological initiatives and attracting investment, as well as “how collaboration between Macau and the PLP has contributed to the strengthening of the local technological ecosystem and what concrete benefits have been observed so far”.
At the last point of a 24 -question questioning, the deputy intends to know what measures the government plans to implement to develop training courses in areas such as Artificial Intelligence Engineering, Data Science and Nanotechnology, in order to ensure the creation of quality jobs. In addition, the governance team questions the strategies that will be adopted to promote collaboration between higher education institutions and the business sector, "aiming at training professionals with technical and interpersonal skills necessary for emerging professions."
Pereira Coutinho ends the written interpelation by exhorting the government to clarify the support measures that will be made available to ensure that young career transitional young people have access to continuous training and updating skills in rapidly growing technological areas.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lift station will relieve floods in the mud</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/estacao-elevatoria-vai-aliviar-inundacoes-na-taipa/</link><description>???????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????? ???????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????? ???????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????? ?????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????



A new rainwater pumping station will be built in the mud, integrated into a drainage improvement plan in the old neighborhood. The objective is to relieve the situation of floods in the area during periods of intense rainfall
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) will build, at the intersection of East Asia Games Avenue with Rua Marginal with the same name, a rainwater elevatory station, occupying an area of ​​about 500 square meters.
The drainage improvement plan aims to relieve the situation of flooding in the old neighborhood of the mud during heavy rain. The station will also increase flow efficiency.
The first phase of the respective plan, which was recently presented to the Advisory Board for Municipal Affairs and the Advisory Board of Community Services, includes the contest for the construction work of the structure, composed of a set of bombs and accessories that enable the elevation of the water piezometric quota transported in public supply services.
In a statement, AMI states that the old district of Taipa is located in a low area and, although it has been maintaining and unclogging the sewers, when intense rainfall and tide levels are high, the entire stormwater box, from the Road of Nossa Senhora da Esperança Bay to the Avenida of East Asia Games, is full of water. Therefore, it is not possible to drain the rainwater effectively.
The lifting station has eight water pumps, with a capacity of 37.6 cubic meters per second, which is equivalent to the possibility of aspiring, in about 50 seconds, the volume of water from a standard pool.
"This will help improve the efficiency of rainwater drainage of the Box-Culvert from Nossa Senhora da Esperança Bay and the old neighborhood of Taipa during tall tides and intense rainfall," the AMI stresses, adding that the elevating station area does not involve or encompasses road roads and existing bike lanes, which means "a low impact on traffic during the period".
The contest for the construction work of this first phase has already been launched, knowing that the criteria for appreciation of proposals and respective weighting factors, announced in the official bulletin, are 55% for the overall price of the work, 15% for reasonable execution period, 10% experience in similar works and the same percentage for the quality of materials. Still in the statements stated, highlighting 5% in the hiring rate of local workers and the evaluation of the registration of the occupational safety and health situation.
The AMI stresses that as the plan advances, the next phase will be to build a small rainwater reinforcement pump station on a corner of the taipa stadium, “to alleviate the pressure of the EXISTING STATE in Father Kok and accelerate rainwater drainage”, predicting that the competition process will be launched through this year.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Myanmar Board announces temporary truce</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/junta-de-myanmar-anuncia-tregua-temporaria/</link><description>The Military Junta that rules Myanmar announced on Wednesday night a temporary truce in its fight against armed rebel groups, five days after a devastating earthquake that left more than three thousand dead in the country, where despair grows among the survivors. Second last balance of the military in power, the number of earthquake caused by the earthquake increased to 3,085, and 441 missing 341 was also accounted for.
The ceasefire will extend until April 22 “with the aim of accelerating the efforts of help and reconstruction, and maintain peace and stability,” the board said in a statement.
On Tuesday, the head of the Military Junta had rejected a truce offered by the Brotherhood Covenant, made up of three powerful ethnic guerrilla groups, to facilitate humanitarian aid efforts after the devastating magnitude 7,7. "We know that some armed ethnic groups are not currently fighting, but they are organizing and training for attacks, so the army will continue their defensive operations necessary," said General Min Aung Hlaing in the capital, Naypyidaw, in a speech quoted the next day by official press.
Despite giving in to the pressures for a ceasefire, the Board warned, in the same statement, that it will respond to any attack of its opponents, whether sabotage or "gathering, organization and expansion [control] of territory that can undermine peace."
Humanitarian organizations warned that the response to the earthquake was weakened by the combat between military and several rebel groups in the country. There were also reports of bombing of the Armed Forces against rebel positions after the earthquake.
The head of the military junta yesterday headed for Bangkok to participate in a summit of southern Asia countries, where it is expected to address the response to the earthquake, the largest to reach the country in decades.
"You can't ask for help with one hand and bombard with the other," said Joe Freeman, a myanmar expert at Amnesty International. The UN special envoy to Myanmar, Julie Bishop, asked all parties to "focus their efforts on civil protection, including humanitarian workers, and assistance."
In addition to the cost of human lives, the magnitude 7.7 earthquake caused wide destruction in this impoverished country, already punished for four years of civil war. Prior to the earthquake, the UN estimated that 3.5 million Burmese, from a population of 50 million, were displaced due to the internal conflict, many of them risking hunger.
AFP journalists have noted that hundreds of people clustered to receive help in Sagaing, the city closest to the earthquake's epicenter. “I had never made a queue like this to get food. I can't express how worried I am. I don't know what to say,” said Cho Cho Mar, 35, with his baby in his arms.
Rescue teams reported that one in three houses was destroyed in the city, according to the World Health Organization (WHO).
A few kilometers in Mandalay, the second largest city in the country, with 1.7 million inhabitants, the earthquake shook several houses, churches, hotels and large apartment condominiums. Medical facilities, with limited capacity and damaged by the earthquake, are “overloaded with a large number of patients,” and food, water and medicine supplies are running out, a WHO warned.

Beijing requires “security”
For humanitarian personnel
On Wednesday, China asked “all parts” in Myanmar to ensure the safety of humanitarian personnel, after the Burmese army fired on the air during the passage a Chinese Red Cross train without making victims. "Given this catastrophe, we hope that all parties to Myanmar prioritize help efforts, ensuring the safety of rescue and supply personnel in China and other countries, as well as ensuring unrestricted access to humanitarian transportation routes," said Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakun without providing details about the incident.
The military regime spokesman said the soldiers "fired three times to the air" after the army had unsuccessfully stopped a train of nine Chinese red cross vehicles that was heading from the state of Shan (border with China) to Mandalay. "We ask international help organizations to inform their operations and safety plans," he added.
"China and Myanmar are neighboring countries united by friendship. After the earthquake, China immediately activated its emergency response mechanism and mobilized all available resources for rescue operations," Guo recalled.

 JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>75% of exporting companies do not have enough personnel</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/75-das-empresas-exportadoras-nao-tem-pessoal-suficiente/</link><description>The percentage of exporting companies with a lack of labor rose to about 75% in the fourth quarter of 2024, according to the conjuncture survey to the sector. In general, entrepreneurs took “a prudent and observant attitude” about the business prospects for the first half of this year
 
The number of workers of the companies participating in the conjuncture survey to the industrial sector exporting in the fourth quarter of 2024 dropped 4.6% in quarterly terms, although it risen 1.9% in the annual variation. According to Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), 74.9%of respondents said they had faced a “worker insufficiency”, which exceeds percentages noted in the preceding quarter (62.4%) and the 2023 (69.5%) period.
On the other hand, 88.5% and 82.2% of entrepreneurs of the branches of “pharmaceutical products” and “clothing and clothing” reported “a relatively remarkable demand for workers”.
Regarding export activities, 55.7% of exporting companies pointed to the “most competitive prices abroad” as the biggest problem they were facing, while 28.8% mentioned “high prices of raw materials” and 28.7% to “workers' insufficiency”. As for the prospects for the next three months, 28.2% were concerned mainly about the "most competitive prices practiced abroad" and 24.3% with the "insufficient volume of orders".
Between October and December, the main exported goods of Macau were, in decreasing order, pharmaceuticals, electronic and electric equipment, alcoholic beverages and tobacco, clothing and clothing, and food products - memories.
The average monthly duration of the orders portfolio detained by the industrial entrepreneurs inquired reached 3.4 months in the quarter under analysis, reflecting a sequential increase of 1.1 months. The “Pharmaceutical Products” Orders Wallet has returned to the first place, with 5.4 months, followed by the sectors of “clothing and clothing” (3.5 months), “electronic and electric equipment” (3,4) and “other non-textile products” (2.1).
The Asia Pacific region stands out as the destination market for exports with “relatively better performance”, with a 21.0%rate, excluding data from the interior of China, Hong Kong and Japan. On the contrary, US market performance translated into a negative index of 19.9%.
According to DSEDT, industrial entrepreneurs expressed “a prudent and observant attitude regarding the export prospects” for the first semester of this year. Inquiry conclusions indicate that 23% inquired anticipated “an optimistic perspective”, representing a 25 -point descent against the previous quarter, and all expected a “slight growth”.
Entrepreneurs who predicted “a less favorable evolution”, specifically “a slight decrease”, accounted for 23.1% of the total, 4.1 points than in the previous three months. The percentage of those who anticipated a “similar” situation was fixed at 53.9%, plus 29.1 points in quarterly terms.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Academics enhance Macao's role in China-Brazil Relations</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/academicos-realcam-papel-de-macau-nas-relacoes-china-brasil/</link><description>The Annual Covenant Conference for the Teaching of the Portuguese Language in the Great Bay took place at Macao Polytechnic University, to discuss, among other topics, the role of masters as a communication channel in relations between China and Brazil. The debate was attended by more than a hundred teachers and students
 
Under the theme “Potentiation of the Great Bay: Innovation and Development in Sino-Brazilian Trade under the New Silk Route”, the Portuguese Alliance Annual Conference for Teaching the Great Bay gathered at Macao Polytechnic University (UPM) more than a hundred teachers and students, including Guangdong experts and academics, Hong Kong, Macau and Brazil. According to the UPM, the debate explored the opportunities generated by the innovative development of China-Brazil trade, in order to promote academic exchanges of the Portuguese language in the Great Bay and boost the new pattern of cooperation and development of “one track, a route”.
Several speakers exposed their points of view, focused on the strategic, innovative and guiding role of China-Brazil relations.
Marcus im, rector of UPM, said during the meeting that, based on the great bay, that educational institution develops a platform for cooperation between the two countries, in areas such as education, science, technologies and culture. At the same time, it promotes narrower cooperation in the field of higher education, "in order to create a new pattern of advantageous cooperation for both parties and common prosperity."
In turn, the Permanent Director of the University of Hong Kong Professional and Continuous School, presented the history of trade between China and Brazil and the role of Macao in cooperation between the two countries. Macao as a platform between China and the PLP “constituted a communication channel to establish China-Brazil relations and became one of the connection bridges,” said Sonny Lo.
Raehk's representative spoke on the theme “Bilateral Relations between China and Brazil and the role of Macao”, stating that the development of the in -depth cooperation zone “creates more trade possibilities for Brazil”, as well as trade, investment and technology cooperation in the Great Bay and Hengqin “opens new opportunities for commercial development between China and Brazil”.
The rector of the University of Foreign Studies of Guangdong, Yan Xiangbin, stressed the desire to explore, together with the alliance partners, “new ways for cooperation in education”, expressing the interest in the formation of more qualified frames for the promotion of exchange between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries (PLP). Thus, he maintained, “a new future for commercial development” can be created and opened “a new chapter of cooperation between China and PLP, strengthening relations between China and Brazil”.
Meanwhile, the director of the Institute of Economics of the State University of Campinas of Brazil, presented at the Conference of the Alliance the academic and scientific research results of the Brazil-China Study Group of the State University of Campinas, the Cass-Unicamp Center for Studies on China and the Confucius Institute. Célio Hiratuka has revealed that the University of Campinas is in the process of creating a Brazil-China Interdisciplinary Studies Center, which will integrate academic resources for research in five areas, namely society, culture and languages, economics, public policies and international relations, science, technologies and innovation, environment, energy transition and sustainable development and health and life sciences. Thus, the Brazilian University intends to “contribute to the promotion of diversified cooperation between the two countries”, he expressed.
The Portuguese Language Teaching Alliance in the Great Bay was created in 2020 through cooperation between the UPM, the University of Foreign Studies of Guangdong and the University of Hong Kong University School of Professional and Continuous Education. It aims to develop the role of Macau as a platform between China and PLP, reinforce the exchange of teachers and students between Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau and, through joint academic seminars, academic competitions, scientific cooperation projects, among others, promote integration, innovation, sharing and development of Portuguese language education in three regions.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Works with mineral pigments will be exposed in Ká-Hó</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/obras-pigmentos-minerais-vao-estar-expostas-em-ka-ho/</link><description>The “Hold on To Hope” project of the Macao Toxicode Rehabilitation Association, and “Questionmark Workshop” will open next Saturday, at 16h00, an exhibition aimed at promoting the traditional art form of mineral pigments. “China Academy of Arts - Exhibition of Instructors of the Research and Creation Class in Painting with Natural Pigments” has the participation of eight influential teachers from China and Japan in this area, who present unique creations in Rock Color Painting. The works disclose a fusion of this ancestral technique with modern art.

This type of painting works with mineral pigments, as an important expressive technique in traditional Chinese painting, is known for its rich colors and unique methods.
"The exhibition highlights not only the individual styles of the artists, but also reflects their deep understanding and innovative exploitation of rock color techniques," can be read in a note released by "Hold on To Hope", which adds that each work "carries a single narrative and emotion, aiming to provoke the reassessment and contemplation of the public about rock color."
Generally speaking, pigments are the main constituents of the paints used in painting, being responsible for the color that appears in the paints in the form of small particles linked to each other by the binding (oil, egg, according to the painting technique). In the strict sense, they are insoluble materials used in the form of very thin powder, which are suspended in the binding. Today, paints are usually bought in stores, but in the 15th, 16th and 17th centuries, it was common for the painters' helpers to prepare the paints, grinding the pigments on a stone with oil or water.
Since 30,000 years ago, natural pigments have been used in paintings, characterized by joint use of natural and artificial pigments. The natural, obtained directly from nature and subjects only to physical purification processes, have as prominent elements in the history of overseas blue painting, cinábar, azuritis and malaquitis, green earth and the oceres, while the artificial, transformed, result from chemical reactions.
The show will be evident until April 27 in the “Hold on To Hope” gallery, in the village of Our Lady of Ká-Hó.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Four installments of land included in the public domain</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/quatro-parcelas-de-terrenos-incluidas-dominio-publico/</link><description>Two plots of land located on the peninsula, next to Dr. Sun Yat-Sen Avenue, with areas of 59,729 square meters and 254 square meters, were integrated into the state's public domain. According to the plant issued by the Board of Cartography and Registration Services, the land is located next to the Coastal Maritime Zone and near Rua da Torre de Macau. This is what can be read in a order signed by the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, who also had two other plots of land in the State. Both are “next to East Asia Games Avenue, in the landfill zone between the islands of Coloane and Taipa (Cotai),” according to the official bulletin. According to Raymond Tam's order, the installments have the areas of 936 square meters and 267 square meters. In concrete, and also according to the plant provided by cartography and registration services, the two plots of land are on the Marginal Street of the East Aria Games. If the government intends to use these land or its purpose, it is not yet known. Many have been the voices to ask for disapproved land to be used for sports and leisure fields or parking parks, however, the government has shown some containment regarding the use of lots in reserve.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Rae formed 80 workers in Brazil about combating corruption</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/rae-formaram-80-trabalhadores-brasil-sobre-combate-a-corrupcao/</link><description>At the invitation of the Independent Commission against Hong Kong (ICAC) corruption, the Macao Commissioner against Corruption (CCAC) went to Brasilia to jointly teach the “Capacity Building Program for the Office of the Union together jointly. The training, which took place over three days, was attended by more than 80 workers from institutions to combat corruption and execution of the Brazilian Law. Tong Leong Law, head of the 2nd CCAC Research Department, presented the history of the fight against corruption in Macao, the functions of the commissioner and the legislation, as well as some cases and investigation measures adopted, under the theme “The Progression of Combating Corruption in Macao - from hope to perseverance”. The Minister-Conselheiro of the Embassy of the Popular Republic of China in Brazil, Jin Hongjun, was present as guest and attributed the certificates of completion of the course to graduates. The representatives of CCAC and ICAC also visited the Federal Prosecutor of Brazil and the Federal Police, among other entities. In a statement, the CCAC states that the trip contributed “to demonstrate abroad the success of the implementation of the principle of 'a country, two systems' in the MSAR” and widen contacts and exchange with institutions to combat corruption of Portuguese -speaking countries.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Wynn presents unpublished “feiyi” clothing</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/wynn-apresenta-pecas-de-roupa-feiyi-ineditas/</link><description>Under the “Tradition With a Modern Twist-Feiyi Pop-Up” series, Wynn will collaborate with Chinese luxury brands and present “pop-up” retail experiments with marks inspired by China's intangible cultural heritage or “Feiyi”, starting this month. Wynn Palace welcomes the first collaboration, with a boutique healed by the “Chinese Arts &amp; Crafts Hong Kong” (Cachk), until May 31st, where Xiang Yun silk fashion pieces will be presented, Suzhou embroidery, drill weaving, zhang wool fabric, we floral and brocade song. Throughout the year, partnerships will run every two months with the aim of offering guests “dynamic, engaging and immersive experiences”, safeguarding “China's Intangible Cultural Heritage”. According to Wynn, brands will present limited edition designs never seen and "enriched with significant feiyi elements." The operator aims to revive old crafts and Chinese traditions, which are undergoing “a strong rebirth among younger consumers”, interested in exploring China's handcrafted heritage, says the statement. For the company, feiyi handicrafts gives cultural heritage a feeling of lasting value and prestige and the partnership is an opportunity for Chinese luxury brands to gain global recognition.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Game sector guarantees neutrality in the electoral period</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sector-jogo-garante-neutralidade-periodo-eleitoral/</link><description>Macao game concessionaires promised to fully fulfill the requirements of the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) to maintain “neutrality and impartiality” during the period of the elections that will take place in September. According to a note from the Social Communication Office, representatives of the six casino operators and the Macao Games and Entertainment Association also ensured that they will “constantly warn their workers to respect, in a“ rigorous way ”, their provisions, and reinforce the inspection work in this context. The guarantees were given at a meeting co-organized by Caeal and the direction of inspection and coordination of games, organisms that underlined the importance of jointly ensuring a “lawful, fair, impartial and whole environment” surrounding the electoral process. According to CAEAL President Seng Ioi Man, the Electoral Law for the Legislative Assembly states that, like public entities, the organs of the game concessionaires and companies or businessmen who exploit fortune games for contracts with the operators cannot do acts that somehow favor or impair an application or advantage of others. In addition, the respective workers, in the exercise of functions, have to observe “rigorous neutrality”, not being able to display symbols, stickers or other elements of electoral propaganda at the workplace, including in canteens and rest rooms. If the entity verifies an infringement situation, it should communicate as soon as possible to Caeal or DICJ. Caeal also clarified that operators can provide transportation for the travel of workers to voting places, as long as it does not involve electoral propaganda.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2373/</link><description>Overseas Chinese support Myanmar
Macau's General Chinese Association Doou and sent an emergency supply batch to Myanmar to support areas hit by the earthquake on Friday. According to the association, the goods sent include electricity generators, portable solar lights, mosquito nets, disinfection materials, mineral water and food.
 
“MPay” can be used on buses and subway in Canton
Since yesterday, MPay users have been able to make payments on Metro, buses and ferries in the city of Cantão, right in the meter of Foshan. According to Macau Pass, after activating the “Canton Metro” service on “MPay”, the user will have a QR code to use, and payments are settled in Patacas. In addition, MPay users can enjoy preferred rates in Canton, namely a 20% discount for those who spend more than 80 Renminbis per month on transport and 50% if tariffs exceed 200 Renminbis within a month.
 
Injured driver after collision near the Delta Bridge post
A 34 -year -old man was transported to the hospital, with injuries on a shoulder and in his hands following a collision between the car he was driving and another light car, in a strip of arrivals at the Macao border post on the Delta Bridge. According to the firefighters, the case occurred yesterday at noon, and one of the cars overturned after the collision. The injured is in a stable state. The cause of the accident is being investigated.
 
10 treadmills will be improved on the islands
The Directorate of Traffic Affairs Services (DSAT) plans to improve this year 10 islands located on the islands. At a meeting of the Island Community Services Advisory Board, DSAT indicated that the roads involved include, for example, ocean gardens, East Asia, Wai Long, and the airport. Improvement measures consist of installing stainless steel anti-collision pillars with reflective adhesives, alert signs for the presence of treadmills, longitudinal deceleration markings, among others.
 
New neighborhood station integrates network of infectious diseases
The Macao's new neighborhood health center in Hengqin is already included in the infectious diseases monitoring network in the in -depth cooperation zone, according to China's Law on Prevention and Treatment of Infectious Diseases. This means that the information of cases diagnosed by this health post has already been officially declared to the National System for Monitoring Infectious Diseases. Monitoring covers the MSAR residents that remain in hengqin and people with transfronic movements.
 
Health Inquiry involved 170 residents
There were recently four sessions of the healthcare inquiry on health, with the participation of 170 residents. According to health services, the various physical examinations and health questionnaires had a response rate of 85%. The inquiry consists of three parts: analysis of blood and urine samples, body mediation and interview with health questionnaire.</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourists and local inhabitants take advantage of Tokyo cherry flowers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/turistas-habitantes-locais-aproveitam-efemeras-flores-de-cerejeira-de-toquio/</link><description>Japanese tourists and residents marveling at the Tokyo cherry trees on Monday, at the height of the annual flowering time, which traditionally represents new beginnings, but also the passing impermanence of life.
Crowds were crowded in the main places of the city to take pictures and picnic under elegant dark branches full of pink and white flowers, known as "Sakura" in Japanese.
"Honestly, it's an amazing feeling to be here. Honestly, it's better than we expected. And this only happens from time to time and for a short time," Christian Sioting, a Philippine tourist, told AFP.
"It is an ephemeral experience and we are very happy to have a state here and to witness this in full flowering."
The Japanese Meteorological Agency (JMA) declared on March 30 that the country's most common and popular cherry variety, the “Somei Yoshino” was in full flowering in Tokyo.
Although the 2025 flowering dates are close to the average, JMA says climate change and the effect of urban heat island are making the Sakura flourish approximately 1.2 days earlier from 10 to 10 years.
“Seeing photographs is something else, but being here, (to) to really see Sakura in your eyes… It's really amazing,” said Ralf NG, from Hong Kong.
Iene weak is attracting more visitors than ever to Japan, with national tourism figures released in January to show a record of about 36.8 million arrivals in 2024.
Kayoko Yoshihara, resident in the 69 -year -old Japanese capital, organizes annual picnics to observe flowers with his friends, including one held last week, when cherry trees began to flourish.
"After supporting the cold winter, cherry flowers flourish and this makes you feel motivated to head to summer," she told AFP.
Nurse Nanami Kobayashi, 31, said the peak of the flower time left her speechless.
"When the trees are in full flowering, it's so beautiful that you are speechless," she said.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>