<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Obesity among basic students descends to the 2000 level</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/obesidade-entre-alunos-basico-desce-para-nivel-de-2000/</link><description>Exams performed to first -year primary school students for the 2023/2024 school year reveal that the obesity rate decreased in annual terms, and even returned to the level recorded in 1999/2000. According to health services, the number of children between six and seven years of overweight dropped to 9.1%, when in previous years it had ranged between 12.4% and 15.6%
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The rate of obesity among students of the first year of basic education has been quite high in recent school years - as had happened in other periods since 1997/1998, with the prevalence of obesity to reach the maximum of 16.4%, in 2009/2010 - but in the school year 2023/2024, the incidence of overweight between children from six to seven years of age dropped to the 1999/2000 level, Reveal the data from the Health Services (SSM) analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao.
Authorities take as reference the growth curve currently used by the Hong Kong Health Department as a measurement indicator, considering obesity when the weight is greater than 120% of the median of height and weight loss when weight is less than 80% of the median.
Statistics show that in 2023/2024, the obesity rate of first -year primary students dropped to 9.1% annually (by 2022/2023 had been 12.4%), a level that had only been registered in 1999/2000. The lowest incidence rate of overweight among these students was a year later, in 2000/2001, and was 7.4%.
However, in the first year of pandemic, 2019/2020, the obesity rate among these children rose to 15.6% in annual terms, when in the previous period it was 11.5%.
The issue of overweight has been a government concern, which in April warned that the obesity rate could continue to rise in the coming years between the local population, constituting a risk factor for chronic diseases such as hypertension, hyperglycemia and hyperlipidemia.
It is recalled that in the academic year of 2022/2023, the excess weight and obesity rate among young people was 21.7%, a slight increase of 0.5% compared to the data obtained in 2017, according to the results of the “health behavior of macao student health behavior”, performed every five years.
The latest SSM data are based on regular medical examinations conducted by health professionals to students of the first year of basic education. In the 2023/2024 school year, 5,781 valid samples were taken into account, equivalent to a 94.9%coverage rate. Most (51.5%) were boys.
The boys were those with a higher excess rate of 10% over 8.1% among girls. A trend that has been maintained over the years. In 2022/2023, the obesity rate was 13.2% among boys and 11.5% among girls.
 
Light improvement in vision
On the other hand, as regards the situation of vision among these children, SSM use the ophthalmological table to evaluate the degree of vision of each eye. It is considered normal when it is 0.7 or more, and below this value means that there is a “low visual acuity”.
In the school year 2023/2024, the prevalence rate of low visual acuity in students of the first level of education was 27.2%, a break from 30.1% recorded in the previous school year.
The latest SSM data show that girls were the ones that had the most vision problems, with a rate of 28.9%, while the boys was 25.7%.
Despite the decrease verified that year, the truth is that the vision of students six to seven years of age has worsened over the years. In 2012/2013, for example, the rate of low visual acuity was 14.7%, having risen to 19.7% in 2015/2016 and 29.1% 2019/2020, the first year of the pandemic.</description><pubDate>2025-09-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mandates returns to normal after super tuffon who broke record</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-retorna-a-normalidade-apos-super-tufao-bateu-recordes/</link><description>Macau began to return to normal, after enduring the passage of the “Ragasa” super tuffon, which established a series of new records, according to the meteorological and geophysical services. With some exceptions, public transportation and education services resumed activity throughout yesterday, while part of the city continued with cleaning work



















Pedro Milheirão
The passage of the “Ragasa” super tuft through the territory broke several records, according to the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG). First of all, and as this newspaper had already reported, it was the first time that the second sign was issued 10 in a year, since 1968, and the signal has been in force for 10 hours and 30 minutes, the longest registered period. In addition, during the period when sign 10 was in force, the duration of the wind speeds that hit or exceeded signal 8 extended for 15 hours.
On the other hand, this was the 11th tropical storm to affect Macao, marking the “second year with the most tropical storms since there are records”.
In a balance of the passage of this storm, the SMG also state that the 10 -minute sustained winds that were registered in all Macao areas reached “force 12”, with gusts of “force 14”.
According to the authorities, the "Ragasa" even formed a "double wall of the eye" in its center. This phenomenon occurs when a cyclone reaches a certain intensity during which the external rainfalls form a new wall, while the inner wall dissipates gradually.
The maximum sign of tropical cyclone would eventually replaced by level 8 to 16h00 on Wednesday, and the SMG has dropped the signal to level 3 to 23h00. At 6 am yesterday, the meteorological services canceled all signs.
In combination with the high tide period, the passage of the super tuffer resulted in a “significant elevation of 'Storm Surge'”, causing “widespread and serious floods in the territory,” SMG observed. The maximum flood height registered in the interior port area was 1.51 meters, and the red warning of “Storm Surge” was issued.
The Macao Electricity Company was able to restore energy supply to all customers affected by the suspension of electricity at 2:35 am yesterday. It is recalled that about 16,000 dwellings were left without electricity following the flood caused by the storm.
In turn, the chief executive authorized the reopening of the casinos to reopen from 2 am yesterday, after 33 hours of suspension of operations.
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI), however, highlighted 26 garbage trucks and 16 compacting crashes for the city's cleaning work, according to a press release. Yesterday, AMI advanced that almost 700 tons of garbage had already been collected, a 70% value above the usual. The body maintained 90% of parks and recreational areas closed to the public, giving priority to obstructed traffic roads.
 
Schools without “significant” damage
With the exception of a special education establishment, students from all schools returned to classes, between morning and yesterday afternoon, after the direction of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) considered that the traffic situation would resume “normality in an orderly manner”, in coordination with the AMI, the direction of services for traffic affairs (DSAT) and the Public Security Police.
Kong Chi Meng and Wong Ka Ki, DSEDJ's director and subdirector, respectively, visited several schools “to inspect and understand the situation of the resuming operating”, especially in low -filled low areas. The DSEDJ reported that most educational establishments "have not suffered significant impacts," except "flooding and equipment damage."
Public transport services had already returned to operate at 11 pm on Wednesday, as soon as Sign 3 was lifted, with some bus itineraries conditioned by road conditions, when the state of immediate prevention ended.
For its part, passenger maritime transport operators also resumed crossings between Macau and Hong Kong yesterday morning, while Macao's calls with Zhuhai and Shenzhen remained suspended. The Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs Services also ended the Maritime Museum, until next Saturday, for cleaning and repairing work.
Despite being kept in operation, Macao International Airport canceled a total of 206 flights. In a statement, the airport reported that scheduled flights began to normalize yesterday.
DSAT reported that vehicles with reservations for 'circulation of Macao vehicles in Guangdong province' on September 22, 23, 24 and 25 and did not make the ticket, would not be considered as 'non-comparnce' or accounted for the number of markings used this month. In addition, owners of vehicles with periodic or marking inspection term on September 23rd and 24th may schedule a new inspection by October 11, the services have announced.
In turn, the direction of services for labor affairs urged the contractors of the construction shipyards to “evaluate the occupational safety and health conditions” and to “take the appropriate doctors” of inspection and inspection before the restoration of the works.
With the gradual removal of the “Ragasa” typhoon, the SMG asked the population to remain a relatively “risk of torrential rain”. Beginning yesterday afternoon, the black sign of strong winds of monsoon was still in force. The body also foresees that the next tropical storm "Bualoi", which will enter the Southern Sea of ​​China by the end of the week, keep "a considerable distance from Macao."
 
22 claims for compensation due to damage caused by the “Ragasa”
The insurance sector received, until yesterday afternoon, 22 requests for compensation related to general insurance due to the damage caused by the “Ragasa” typhoon, of which three are requests related to the “property insurance against large disasters for small and medium enterprises”, said the Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM). To accelerate the payment process of compensation claims, insurers activated “Via Verde”, coordinating with notaries for conducting on -site surveys, with the aim of simplifying and streamlining complaint procedures, helping citizens and traders affected to obtain compensation as soon as possible, the body added. AMCM also indicated that all financial institutions resumed normal operations. He also recalled that he mobilized a team of about 20 people to support the cleaning work on Almirante Sérgio Street, Ponte and Horta and Barra Square.</description><pubDate>2025-09-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese stars confirmed at Macau's golf Open</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/estrelas-chinesas-confirmadas-open-de-golfe-de-macau/</link><description>Shanghai, China - April 20: Haotong Li of China Reacts Before Teeing Off on the 1st Hole on Day Four of the Volvo China Open 2025 at Enhance Anting Golf Club on April 20, 2025 in Shanghai, China. (Photo by Lintao Zhang/Getty Images)



The best golfer in China of the current, Li Haotong, and the Gold Medal at Hong Kong Asian Games, Taichi Kho, will join the list of players present in this year's edition of Macao's golf Open, which will take place from October 16 to 19

Victor Rebelo
 
The list of participants in this year's edition of Macao's Open Golf is practically completed, just over 20 days from the beginning of the tournament. To the players who had previously been announced by the organization, including English Lee Westwood and Thai Rattanon Wannasrichan, other renowned practitioners, China and Hong Kong.
One of them is Taichi Kho, who won a historic gold medal at the 2022 Asian Games in Hangzhou, in the individual men's race, ahead of Sungjae Im, South Korean star and also participating in the next Macao Open. He spent his professional in 2023, the year he became the first golfer in the neighboring territory to win at the "World City Championship" Asian Tour.
Present at the Press Conference for more accredited athletes who will be on the pitch of Coloane's “Macau Golf &amp; Country Club”, from 16 to 19 October, Taichi Ko, current 359th in the world ranking, recalled that in the past edition ended tied in sixth place. "I feel that this field adapts very well to my game and, as I have been very recently, I hope to get some rounds below the pair to discuss the title," he believes.
Another prominent player in the race is Li Haotong, number one of the Popular Republic of China. Canton's 30 -year -old athlete, whose main career moments include eight tournament titles and a third place in “The Open Championship” in 2017, enters the “SJM Macau Open 2025” motivated after beating Qatar Masters earlier this season.
"I am very happy to return to Macao, after being here in 2023, prepared to feel again the vibration and energy of the city," he said. He says he is having “an excellent season so far”, and expects to “play well” to secure the second title in 2025.
There are other Chinese players who come to Macao to try to occupy the first places in the classification, including two veterans: Liang Wengchong, 37, and Zhang Lianwei, 60. The latter won the Macao Open twice in 2001 and 2002, becoming the first player to successfully defend his title.
Lianwei, a native of Zhuhai, who guided Liang Wenchong in his transition from amateur to professional, has been an “unconditional supporter” from Open de Macao since the first edition in 1998, the organization stresses in a statement. His titles at MSAR are among the 22 wins in professional tournaments in a career that began in 1994.
Respected as a pioneer of golf in China, he is responsible for many "first times" for Chinese golfers, including being the first to win at the European Tour and the first to reach the top 100 in the official golf ranking.
“I consider SJM Macau Open my homemade tournament and I've played here many times, so Macau will always be in my heart,” said Zhang Lianwei at the SJM session, sponsor and organizer of the tournament, along with the Sports Institute and IMG, with the support of “Asian Tour” and the Macau Golf Association.
The Chinese contingent will join the former world leader, Englishman Lee Westwood, to South Korean Sungjae IM, twice winner of the Macao Open PGA, Thai Rattanon Wannasrichan. Also guaranteed the participation of Kelvin Si Ngai, from Macao, who will take advantage of the competition to prepare for the national games.
The tournament, which has a total monetary prize of one million US dollars, will be attended by 144 golfers. Over the past two decades, the race has received a series of important tournament champions such as Ernie Els, Nick Faldo, Fred Couples, Padraig Harrington and Vijay Singh.</description><pubDate>2025-09-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong “loses” voters for the fourth consecutive year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/actual/hong-kong-perde-eleitores-pelo-quarto-ano-consecutivo/</link><description>Hong Kong's electoral record announced yesterday a new break in the number of census voters, the fourth consecutive, within the elections for the Legislative Council, scheduled for December 7. This year's final data include 4,138,992 voters registered in geographical electoral circles, the only category subject to direct universal suffrage, a lower number of about 330,000 to the peak of 4.47 million reached in 2021. In functional electoral circles, which group economic and professional sectors and elect 30 seats, the number of voters lowered from 198.157 to 2024 for 2024 to 193,674 this year. This will be the second legislative election after the broad electoral reform approved in March 2021 by the China National Assembly of Popular, which introduced a filtering mechanism to ensure that the region is “governed by patriots”. The change has reduced the number of elected places directly from 35 to 20 on an extended 90 members, where 40 are appointed by an electoral committee of 1,500 members and the remaining 30 by these functional colleges. The reform, implemented after the 2019 Pro-Democracy Protests and the entry into force of the National Security Act in 2020, included a review panel composed of security agencies and the Electoral Commission itself. In the legislative elections of 2021, already under these rules, participation descended to 30.2%, the lowest since the transfer of sovereignty in 1997. Of the 90 elected legislators, only one did not aligned in the pro-System field. The electoral census process takes place throughout the year and allows permanent residents over 18 to register for free through the official mobile application, by mail or in person.</description><pubDate>2025-09-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Rogério Santos, former director of health services died</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/faleceu-rogerio-santos-antigo-director-dos-servicos-de-saude/</link><description>Rogério Artur dos Santos, former director of health services in Macau (SSM) and the Conde São Januário Hospital Center (CHCSJ), died yesterday morning in Macau at the age of 89. The doctor took over the SSM board in October 1999, two years after starting roles as the maximum responsible of the CHCSJ. Previously, he had held the position of subdirector of the same hospital unit, where he was responsible for the area of ​​widespread health care. At that time, clear width, equally deceased, was the number one of the SSM.
Rogério Santos, Portuguese based in the territory 61 years ago, graduated from the University of Shanghai University of Medicine, and a local board since 1987, was also a member of the CHCSJ Installation Committee, having directed the SSM Technical School between 1988 and 1996. He had previously held the position of President of the then Leal Senate, between 1974 and 1983, as well as being an advisor and head of the former governor of Carvalho.
The provider of the Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macao was one of those who deprived closely with Rogério Santos, considering him “a friend and an excellent professional”. António José de Freitas recalled that Rogério Santos was a brother of the Holy House and that soon after retiring, at 65, went to work for the home of Our Lady of Mercy, managed by the institution, collaborating as a doctor for 19 years, specifically between 2001 and 2020.
“I remember him as a person who didn't like to be still and so he came to take care of our elderly,” said the provider, in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao.
In turn, Jorge Neto Valente told this newspaper that he lost a friend of over 50 years. "A good, generous man of great sensitivity, with whom I had the opportunity to work and live over many years," said the lawyer, adding that Rogério Santos served Macau "with discretion and competence, and did a lot for the community in the various functions he performed and in his positions."
As a doctor, "he was always available to those who were looking for him, and for everyone had words of comfort and tranquility," he said, adding that his thinking goes to family members, who accompanies "with solidarity and a lot of sadness."
To the bereaved family, JTM presents senses condolences.
 
Victor Rebelo</description><pubDate>2025-09-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DSAT Attentive to Careers next to the residence for the elderly</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dsat-atenta-as-carreiras-junto-a-residencia-para-idosos/</link><description>Given the change of residents to the residence to the elderly, Deputy Ella Lei has reported that the number of careers and their frequency to places such as hospitals in the territory is “insufficient”. DSAT says it is “attentive” to the needs and indicated that stops will be installed on the section with the Lok Koi building and “extended existing careers” to facilitate the mobility of those people
 
The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) says it remains “attentive” to the “travel needs” of residents of the residence for the elderly, “in order to order in an orderly public bus services based on the use of public roads in the vicinity of Lot P”. In response to an interpellation of Ella Law, the body indicated that, in the first phase, "bus stops will be installed next to the Lok Koi building and extended existing careers to facilitate the mobility of residence residents for the elderly."
At the same time, DSAT ensures that "it will continue to evaluate and balance the resources of public buses and the needs of travel from all parties, with a view to improving bus connecting services."
In the written interpellation, the deputy had pointed to the “insufficiency of careers and the frequency of buses that connect between the North Zone, the Conde de S. Januario Hospital Center and the Kiang Wu Hospital”, which, he said, became “increasingly evident” as residents moved to those facilities.
“With the occupation of residence fractions for the elderly, the increased dwelling in the Plado Plack Lot and the impending occupation of dwellings in the new landfills, it is indispensable to accelerate the comprehensive planning of the above -mentioned bus itineraries, including the continuous improvement of accessibility and ease of use of self -timing services, in particular, public transport options for the elderly. or vulnerable groups of these zones when traveling to hospitals, ”said Ella Law. In this context, the deputy recalled that there was a break in the number of deducted and wheelchair space buses.
In this regard, DSAT pointed out that “bus operators proceed to the gradual renewal of the fleet in accordance with the contractual provisions in force, which stipulate that, with the exception of small vehicles, the number of vehicles in operation with a wheelchair parking vehicle can not be less than 80% of the total fleet”.
Currently, according to the body, the proportion of relegated floor buses and vehicles with a wheelchair parking vehicles remains above 90% of the fleet in operation. Until August, 974 relegated floor buses were in operation, corresponding to about 99% of the total fleet, and 883 vehicles with a spacechair reserved for wheelchairs, equivalent to about 90%. "DSAT will continue to require operators to use relegated floor vehicles with a wheelchair parking space in the provision of bus services," he concluded.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-09-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Evaluation and treatment center with four -week waiting time</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/centro-de-avaliacao-tratamento-da-demencia-tempo-de-espera-de-quatro-semanas/</link><description>Health services were renamed about 600 elderly to be treated at the Dementia Evaluation and Treatment Center. According to SSM, waiting time for new patients is on average about four weeks. The Government has organized multiple activities within the “Alzheimer's World Month”
 
This year, Health Services (SSM) evaluated the cognitive function of more than two thousand elderly, and refered about 600 for treatment in memory consultation of the Dementia Evaluation and Treatment Center. For new cases, the average waiting time is approximately four weeks, the SSM revealed in a statement.
Throughout this month, health authorities have organized several activities to mark the “World Alzheimer's Month” and raise awareness of the population regarding the dementia of the elderly. In this sense, the body also invited more than 200 local associations to join the “great friendly covenant” to build “a friendly community environment for people with dementia”.
Together with the Institute of Social Action, the Macao Alzheimer Disease Association and the Kiang Wu Nursing Institute of Macao, the SSM organized the “Memory Walk activity”. Through promotional videos and infographics about “how to communicate with dementia patients,” the body sought to disseminate information related to the prevention and treatment of the disease.
In addition, the Dementia Evaluation and Treatment Center also recently invited more than 60 elderly people, sick with dementia, as well as their families, to participate in a community activity. The SSM hope that, "through the continuous motivation of community forces," it can be achieved "a social consensus on the care of patients, and support for their family members and caregivers."
The various initiatives are aligned with the general objectives and indicators of the “Healthy Macao Action Plan” and with the promotion of the “Healthy Community” program of the Government of Masters, in an attempt to decentralize health care for community neighborhoods.
Given the great importance that the Government attributes to the health of residents, MSar has established a systematic support network in the area of ​​dementia prevention and treatment. To provide proper medical and social care, the Executive created the Dementia Evaluation and Treatment Center and the Dementia Support Center, the statement says.
SSM recall that dementia is a common chronic disease among the elderly, also affecting the family of the sick, as well as constituting a charge for the global development of society. The body made more information available on the “Friendly Community of People Community with Macao dementia” from its site.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-09-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>EPM former student shows film on Porto Big Show</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ex-aluna-da-epm-mostra-filme-big-show-porto/</link><description>Rita Variz, who made her entire pre-university academic course at the Portuguese school, produced a short film that will be presented today in Porto, in the third edition of “Big Show”. Among the many works of digital art and multimedia produced by recent students, the young woman saw “your lucid abyss” be one of the works selected for the event

Victor Rebelo
 
A small solo film by Rita Variz, former student of the Portuguese School of Macau (EPM), will be one of the highlights of the event “Big Show”, in the city of Porto, which annually gives visibility to work performed by newcomers from Portuguese colleges.
In a screening that will take place at 3:15 pm this Friday (Portuguese time), at the iconic cinema Batalha, the young resident of the mashes will present a short film, entitled "Your lucid Abyss" and dedicated to her maternal grandmother, sick of Alzeihmer.
Rita Variz told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau that she did everything "practically alone" and that the end product makes her "enthusiastic" to follow up a possible career in the multimedia area.
"This is a final undergraduate project and I could have done it together, but the teachers themselves encouraged me to accomplish alone, as it was a very personal idea," said EPM's former school, a pre-university academic course, from primary to 12 year.
The short film, just less than three minutes long, which includes a quick filming in Macao, in a plane carried out next to the traffic light that connects Jorge Álvares Square to the “New Yaohan” shopping center, is basically made of archive images, with the author worked the part of the edition, with her own narration, and the part of the analog animation in the videos.
The short film produced, held and edited by the newly Licensed School of Arts and Design (ESAD), in Porto, addresses the early mourning in everyday life, around the issue of memory and its gradual loss.
When she was a 13 -year -old Rita, now 23, she saw her maternal grandmother (Aurelina Lobo), with whom she had a strong relationship, “slowly disappearing” because of Alzheimer's disease. Then came the idea to the story of the movie, in honor, "Since the theme of the project was" time and memory, so I decided to touch this subject that was very personal, "he said.
During the film, in “voice-off”, the aspiring being a day of digital art and multimedia reads a text of his own, which emphasizes strong, emotional phrases, like these: “Grandma… this grief accompanies me and comes with me with the hurt. It is not a mourning that comes from a sudden cruel end, nor a cold hug from the certainty of death. loss before loss ”.
Born in Porto, he accompanied his parents on the adventure of Macau when he was a baby under one year old. He left the territory in 2018 to study architecture for two years, but soon found that "it was not what he wanted."
It was then to ESAD, “where the course was quite comprehensive, encompassing administration, animation, video and photography, and as I always liked the part of the photograph and the drawing, the useful was joined with the pleasant,” he emphasizes.
Now, with the undergraduate degree and this “first serious project”, he says he liked, in the future, to continue in the multimedia area. “I like digital art, even the most analogous part of things, drawing, because it's more familiar to me, but also the video editing is interesting and I'm pleased to do it,” he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-09-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Narrative of five women marks exhibition in Zhuhai</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/narrativa-de-cinco-mulheres-assinala-exposicao-em-zhuhai/</link><description>A feminist look at identity, resistance and cultural transformation are topics of the exhibition “Other Ports - Other Looks”, which will be inaugurated today in Zhuhai, as part of a tour of the great bay. The show brings together a visual narrative of photographic works by five women artists from Macau, Portugal and China Continental






























The photography exhibition “Other ports - other looks” arrives today to Zhuhai, integrated into a tour of the great bay. The show brings together a visual narrative of photographic works by five women artists from Macao, Portugal and Continental China: Mine Ao, Margarida Gouveia, Ting Song, Xing Danwen and Zhang.
"Each one brings a visual approach to its own to reflect on the role of women in society and culture, exploring topics such as identity, resistance and transformation within contemporary feminist thinking," according to a note of introduction of the event.
Curated by Clara Brito (Macau and Portugal) and Gu Zhenqing (Beijing), the exhibition proposes a “intense and diverse” visual narrative, built through documentary records, personal reflection and cultural criticism. “The artists involved question fixed ideas about what it is to be a woman and challenge the prevailing speeches in their societies,” read the presentation text.
Among the prominent artists, Ting Song stands out as a pioneer in digital art. He was the first cryptortalist to join the collection of a national museum in China and created the first Chinese works with artificial intelligence and auctioned NFT. His work “The Counter-Cyborg Cathedral and Bazaar” marked the first Asian collaboration between humans and blockchain-based artificial intelligence. Recognized by Forbes 30 Under 30 and Gen.T Asia, Ting Song also participated in Chanel's “Dare” campaign. His work combines state -of -the -art technology with traditional aesthetics to explore digital femininity and the construction of identity, bringing to the exhibition “a bold, innovative and deeply current voice”.
Xing Danwen, Mina Ao and Daisy Gouveia address forms of “symbolic and material violence”, offering deeply personal reflections on autonomy and identity. Zhang documents the legacy of adoption policies in China, focusing on the lives of over 55,000 Chinese girls adopted by American families, "raising moving questions about belonging, cultural exchange and female identity."
During the inauguration, scheduled for 6.30 pm, a round table with questions and answers session, moderate by Clara Brito and with the participation of guest curators and artists of the exhibition.
The show, which will be patent until November 17, at The Moment Art Space Gallery, located at 4 Hongqi Street, Xiangzhou district, has an organization of the +853 Cultural Association and Tomorrow’s Heritage, with the support of the Macao Cultural Development Fund.
The +853 Cultural Association was founded in 2006 and has been developing creative and cultural projects annually in the MSAR. Since 2010, the Association has been in -depth cultural and creative collaborations with Portugal. In 2015, he made his debut at the internationalization of Macao's historical-cultural heritage, taking him to the most relevant cities of the Rio das Pérola Delta.
In his portfolio, he highlights the festival “This is My City”, with 15 years of history, and the photographic exhibition “Language France”, held in 2019 in partnership with the Cultural Institute. The following year, he also organized the exhibition “Other Ports - Other Looks” in the Maus Habites Gallery, in the city of Porto.
“Tomorrow’s Heritage” is a project co-developed by that association, based on an intercultural view that questions the utopian possibilities of future legacies, while crossing secular cultural heritages of two distinct regions: the great bay and Portuguese-speaking countries.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-09-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MGM e UCTM lançam programa de literacia financeira</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mgm-uctm-lancam-programa-de-literacia-financeira/</link><description>A memorandum of understanding was signed between MGM and UCTM, with a view to launching a literacy program on campus, which focuses on “improving the financial education of university students” and warning of the game responsible for the game.
 
MGM and the Macao University of Science and Technology (UCTM) have signed a memorandum of understanding to officially launch the Healthy Financial Literacy Promotion Program, a three -year initiative “intended to improve the financial education of university students,” explains the gambling operator in a statement. "The program is part of MGM's experience in the responsible game sector with UCTM academic strengths to offer structured financial education," the statement adds.
The main components include the “University Life” Financial Education Seminar, “Creative Financial Welfare Competition”, among others, “all aimed at helping students develop adequate financial values ​​and decision-making skills before entering the job market”. In concrete, the first theme will incorporate special modules on healthy financial management and responsible entertainment. The competition “will focus on the presentation of short videos, encouraging students to combine popular culture with creative narratives to broaden the scope and relevance of financial education”.
Tian Han, executive vice president of MGM, said the company "conceives educational initiatives adapted to different age groups, integrating concepts of financial literacy and responsible game in everyday life, from campuses to communities."
On the same day, MGM also organized the release and public presentation ceremony of the third edition of the “MGM Financial Education School Tour 2025 - Gen Z Earth Cup”. Guided by the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services and carried out by Dream Theater Association, Turé has reached more than 40 schools and almost 8,000 students in the last two years.
This year's production adopts a theme of generation Z, using dynamic narratives and interactive elements to convey messages about responsible entertainment and intelligent financial habits. The tour will visit more than 20 schools, and must reach more than 3,500 students.
"These two events exemplify our continuous efforts to promote the game responsible through collaboration with academic institutions, community organizations and professional groups. In the future, we will continue to deepen the public's understanding of these values ​​through intersectoral partnerships, creative content and active social involvement, working together to build a healthier and better macao," said Tian Han, quoted in a statement.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-09-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Job sessions provide 148 more vacancies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sessoes-de-emprego-disponibilizam-mais-148-vagas/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), in collaboration with the Federation of Workers' Associations (Faom), will hold three more employment conjugation sessions for specific sectors, with a total of 148 vacancies. Registration is open until 12:00 today. On the afternoon of the 29th, 52 offers will be available for restoration functions, specifically for assistant manager, supervisor, stage director and entertainment equipment, kitchen deputy chief, tea expert and table employee. The next morning a pairing action will be performed for the Information Technology sector, having as participating companies the “Boardware Information System Limited”, “HMN Smart (Macau) Information System Technologies” and “Anmai Artificial Intelligence Technology”, with 38 vacancies for System Research and Development Manager, Safety Service Provision Manager, quality engineer and security, transport and maintenance staff, computer technician and seller. In the afternoon, the areas covered are safety and cleaning, directed to the International Cleaning Services Company, Insect Control Company and Yongan Environment Administration, Imperial Security Services Society, Macao Security and Administration Agency and Gold Court Property Services Company, for 58 work offers for customer service assistant places, safety, cleaners, exterminators, among others.</description><pubDate>2025-09-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau issued this year two signals 10 for the first time since 1968</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-emitiu-este-ano-dois-sinais-10-pela-primeira-vez-desde-1968/</link><description>The “Ragasa” super tuffon brought winds with the strength of hurricane to the territory, having toppled trees, lamps, windows and other objects. Intense rains were also felt, and due to the “Storm emerge”, the low areas of the city were flooded, with the height of the water exceeding 1.5 meters. As a result, several streets were cut and were without electricity. Sign 10, the maximum alert level, was raised for 10 and a half hours, according to information on the meteorological and geophysical services. The data also indicate that 2025 was the only year, since 1968, in which Macao lifted two 10 signs 10 - the first of this year was the passage of "Wipha". With this super tuffon, eight injured and more than two hundred occurrences were recorded. This storm was considered the strongest of this year in the world



















Catarina Pereira and Pedro Milheirão
 
Strong, very strong winds made themselves feel in the territory due to the passage of the "Ragasa" super tuffon, considered the strongest of this year around the world, according to the China National Meteorological Center, and comparable to "Hato", which devastated Macao in 2017, and the "mangkhut", which passed the territory a year later. Also intense rains were brought by this super tuffon, which left eight injured. The city's low areas were flooded, a scenario already foreseen by the authorities, and, as a result, there were energy and road cuts. The strength of the storm also caused the overthrow of trees, lamps, windows, motorcycles and other objects.
Although the destruction in the territory was not similar to that of the "Hato", the truth is that this super tuffon came to break with the relatively calm tapper registered this season, having led the meteorological and geophysical services (SMG) to make the sign 10 of tropical storm-this year, had been emitted once, when the "Wipha" passage, but not so long. This time, the maximum alert was in force for 10 hours and 30 minutes.
According to the SMG data analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macau, 2025 marks the first year, since 1968, in which Macau has lifted two signs 10 of tropical storm.
Macau went into immediate prevention at 1 pm on Tuesday, when signal 3 was still in force. At 17h00, signal 8 was issued, which was replaced by 9 at 04h00 yesterday and 10 at 05:30. Throughout the day, the sign 10, which then descended to 8 am to 4 pm and 3 am to 11 pm.
According to the SMG, the winds brought by the "Ragasa" reached level 12, "which corresponds to the level of hurricane, or higher." As for the maximum wind in the center of the super tuffon, it reached 195km/h yesterday morning.
This storm was less than 100km away from Macao, and in the afternoon yesterday afternoon, the super tuft weakened to "Severus Typhoon" and continued to move and gradually move away from the territory. The sons, however, was still under the influence of the “Ragasa” circulation nucleus, with strong winds, water and thunderstorm to affect the city.
According to the Civil Protection Operations Center, until 5 pm 241 occurrences had been registered, more precisely 138 cases of plaster removal, claim, window, awning or other objects with risk of falling or overthrowing; 62 Construction/lamp removal cases/tree with risk of falling or overthrowing; 23 fires; 11 retention cases in the elevator; Six scaffolding removal situations or other facilities at risk -risk or overthrowing workshoars; and a case of “other incidents that occurred on public roads”.
As for the emergency host centers of the Social Action Institute, at 20h00 there were 152 users to use these shelter spaces. In total, 705 people had to resort to the shelter centers.
Yesterday at 21h00, the border posts of the doors of the Serco, Qingmao and the Industrial Transfrontic Zone resumed their normal functioning. On the other hand, according to the Macao Civil Aviation Authority, 131 flights had been canceled due to the typhoon, and 12 that suffered delays and two whose times were changed.
 
Floods led to the power cut
The warning for flooding in the low zones had already been given by the authorities days before the passage of "Ragasa", a scenario that was confirmed, and the SMG activated the red warning of "Storm". Several videos circulating on social networks realized, for example, flooding in the inner port, as well as in Coloane, in the latter case, a large amount of waste to be carried by water was visible.
Once a “significant increase” occurred of water due to the Storm, overlapping the maximum level of the astronomical tides, several zones recorded floods.
On the peninsula was where there were more affected streets: Rua do Visconde Paço de Arcos, Avenida de Demétrio Cinatti, Dr. Lourenço Pereira Marques Street, Ribeira do Patane Street, Almirante Sérgio Street, Avenida da Amizira Lacerda/ João de Araújo Street, Rua das Lorchas, Rua de Almeida Ribeiro Rest, next to Cinema Alegria and Street of Estlagen. According to the authorities, in the interior port, the height of the water exceeded 1.5 meters.
Already on the islands, it was Coloane who suffered the most, specifically: Largo Tam Kong Mil, Largo do Cais and Avenida de Cinco de Outubro. According to the SMG, at St. Francis Xavier station in Coloane, a flood of about one meter was registered.
The streets were closed and the Macao Electricity Company (CEM) suspended the power supply in various areas, such as safety, specifically in the interior port, Ponte and Horta, Barra and Patane square. According to one hundred, the power cut has affected about 16,000 residential and commercial units in the low areas.
Hours later, the hundred announced that it would not advance to a second phase of the power cut, as the water had begun to go down; At the same time, electricity began to be restored in some areas, with the company indicating that it would use remote control equipment.
Still, it warned that due to the temporary suspension of electricity in certain zones, the telecommunications network began to operate using emergency generators, so if the suspension extended and the energy reserves were exhausted, the telecommunications services of these zones would be "inevitably affected." Storm's warning was canceled at 19h00.
 
More than six dozen injured in Hong Kong
The passage of the “Ragasa” super tuft also forced Hong Kong's observatory to lift sign 10 at dawn yesterday. This is the first time that the maximum signal has been lifted in Raehk twice in the same year, since 1964. Level 10 has been in force for 10 hours and 40 minutes, until 1:20 pm, corresponding to the second longer period. This is only surpassed by the signal issued in 1999, when the “York” typhoon passed for 11 hours.
The super tuffon rode 120 kilometers from Hong Kong, with the 212-kilometer-hour gust registered per hour in Ngong Ping. Water levels reached four meters in Tseung Kwan O, said Christine Fong, advisor to Sai Kung district, quoted by RTHK station. The official also said that repair work could take up to about a month.
Until early afternoon, 62 people had been treated in public hospitals, while Hong Kong authorities reported 437 reports of fallen trees, 15 floods and one landslide. In fact, several cables from the metro lines were hit by tree falls, slowing down the resuming of transportation services. Airport operations were also suspended, with about a thousand flights affected.
Benjamin Horton, a professor at the University of Hong Kong, said Raehk "was spared the worst when" Ragasa "deviated south of the region instead of having a direct impact." Speaking to the television station, the academic also greeted the authorities' evacuation plans because they were executed in time.
However, and despite considering Hong Kong “one of the most prepared and resilient cities,” Horton still believes preventive measures can be improved. "The future is climate change. The weather conditions we have experienced in 2024 or 2025 will only get worse in 2026 and 2027, and later," warned the teacher.
Three members of a family were rescued from the sea on Tuesday afternoon in Hong Kong. According to RTHK, a five -year -old mother and child decided to go to see the waves in Chai Wan, and both ended up falling into the sea. The father then plunged in an attempt to save them. The man eventually had to be removed from the water by the firefighters, while the wife and son of the couple were rescued by a Sampan. Yesterday afternoon, the mother and the boy remained unconscious, hospitalized in the intensive care of the "Eastern Hospital".
Fok Chun-Mon, Department of Fire Department, appealed to Raehk's population to "not underestimate the strength of nature." "Even if we can carry out a rescue operation in a short period of time, the power of nature is immense," he reiterated.
At the “Fullerton Ocean Park” hotel, the pressure exerted by the flood destroyed the glass doors of the establishment and flooded the lobby, with the water stream dragged at least one employee. However, a staff member clarified Hong Kong television station that were not registered injured. In addition, he also said that more staff were highlighted to help with post-tuff work and ensure guest safety and comfort.
Quoted by RTHK, the drainage services department confirmed that the occurrence was one of several floods caused by the super tuffer, explaining that water levels in the city's coastal zone "had risen significantly."
On the other hand, nearly 1.9 million people were resolved in Guangdong province, CCTV state television said.
 
At least 27 people died in Taiwan and the Philippines
The “Ragasa” super tuffer caused at least 27 deaths in Taiwan and the Philippines. Specifically, in Taiwan were at least 17 deaths and 32 injured, and 17 people were missing only in Guangfu, while 135 residents were rescued alive in the last few hours of yesterday, the Formosa disasters responded, quoted by EFE agency. A torrent of water and mud flooded the city of Guangfu, as a result of the intense rains caused by the storm. Already in the Philippines, the "Ragasa" caused destruction and caused death to at least 10 people, due to flooding and landslides. According to the National Council for Reduction and Risk Management of disasters, seven fishermen drowned after a boat turned, because of the high waves and strong winds, off the city of Santa Ana, in the northern province of Cagayan. Provincial authorities reported the existence of five other missing fishermen. Almost 700,000 people were affected by the storm on Luzon Island, including 25,000 who protected themselves in emergency shelters.
 
FISH RACE IN THE INTERNAL PORTO
The rise in water level in the city's low areas, which reached close to two meters high, led to the appearance of dozens of fish in the flooded areas, probably from existing aquariums in fishfish or restaurants in the area. After the first amateur photographs and videos, published on social networks, have emerged with a fish jumping in one of the arteries of the inner port, several popular came to the street, still with the 10 -storm signal, and sought their luck on an authentic open "market". Shortly thereafter, early yesterday afternoon, several videos showed people to sport the "trophies", by the way of large size, and others to desperately try to ensure the capture of living animals that served in an attempt to escape. The situation, something caricatured, not far from the Patane market, led the Civil Protection Operations Center to issue a note, appealing to citizens and tourists to stay on alert and remain in closed and safe enclosures, as weather conditions were still unstable and there were still risk factors on public roads.
 
V.R.
“Bualoi” could be the next tropical cyclone
Still poorly refined of the “Ragasa” super tuffon, Macau will be able to enter the next few days within the radius of action of the “bualoi” tropical cyclone, which goes to the Philippines, where it is expected to arrive tomorrow. Bualoi was yesterday at the beginning of the night about 800 kilometers northeast of Mindanau Island, in the south of the Filipinas Sea, with gusts up to 105 km/hour. The weather agency of the archipelago, Pagasa, said the cyclone will continue to intensify and could reach the Typhoon Statute before reaching the Bicol region on tomorrow afternoon. After crossing the archipelago, the cyclone should head towards the capital, Manila. For now the Philippines authorities issued only the minimum warning for strong winds in central Visayas.
 
Typhoon “Ragasa” in numbers
Wounded: 8
 
Flood height: greater than 1.5 meters
 
Houses and stores affected by the power cut: 16 thousand
 
Canceled, late and altered flights: 145
 
Window fall and plaster: 138 cases
 
Falling trees, lamps and others: 62 cases</description><pubDate>2025-09-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Supermarkets without hands to measure before the typhoon</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/supermercados-sem-maos-medir-antes-tufao/</link><description>Population is up to the supermarkets to guarantee essential assets for two days of the passage of Super Tufão Ragasa, Macau, China, September 22, 2025. The chief executive of Macao, Sam Hou Fai, warned today for the possibility of Typhoon Ragasa, which approaches the region, causing the water level to reach "about five meters tall". Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro/Lusa



Macao supermarkets were filled on Monday with people in search of essential goods, anticipating the passage of the "Ragasa" super tuffon in the region and following the recommendations of the authorities, which warned of the possibility of causing large floods.

Police appealed to the population on Sunday to “make provisions in advance” of enough water and food for three days. In supermarkets such as "San Mil" and "Royal" in the city center, some shelves were partially empty, with employees working permanently to replenish them with the stocks.
“We have seniors and children at home, I come to fuel to prepare for the typhoon,” she told Lusa Kitty Ma, a 40-year-old teacher, with her eyes on a shelf with limited options for instant noodles. "I've chosen a lot of vegetables, now I'm going to buy noodles, canned food and frozen meat," he added, with the basket already full of groceries, enough for two or three days.
An employee of the same supermarket, who continually refracted the noodles section, said the client movement is typical when a typhoon approaches. "People always come to buy pasta, bread and instant food, and the line in the box is always long," he said, noting that I saw nothing this time "unusual".
In the rival supermarket, "San Miu", the movement was more intense, but Lusa did not observe any empty shelf.
Not everyone there was specifically because of the typhoon. A 30 -year -old, surname, surname, who was choosing vegetables, said his presence there was not related to the storm and had "no intention to fill the food pantry."
"I'm buying food as on normal days. It's just two or three days. Then everything will be back to normal," he said, also admitting that he had stored five bottles of water at home.
Mandy Chan, a 35 -year -old employee who had just left his job, shared a similar opinion as he passed the corridor of the fish preserves.
"I buy what I would buy normally. I buy bread, eggs and preserves of fish," he said. Still, in the basket of purchases, it was already a sufficient amount of food for both or three days advised by the authorities.
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) announced on Friday, through a statement, that the supply of fresh food was "abundant" in Macao, recognizing that the demand continued to increase as the "Ragasa" approached. "The AMI continues to coordinate and maintain close communication with food importers in Macau to ensure the quality, safety and stable supply of agricultural products such as vegetables and meat, as well as fresh foods," he said.
"The transport of fresh food to Macau is still unchanged, with sufficient amounts provided to maintain the stability of the daily life of Macao residents," he added.
Already on Tuesday, the Consumer Council and the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services reinforced inspection actions, to “ensure globally the stability of the supply” of the first need, “appealing to sectors to replace the goods on the shelves as quickly as possible”. According to the two organisms, then the swallowed water stocks were "enough" for supply throughout the sinters for "more than 10 days", while essential and non -essential food products, such as cereals, oils and instant pasta, arrived for "more than 20 days".
 
JTM com Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-09-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>The 10 -month Calvary of a Malay in a Burlas Center in Myanmar</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/calvario-de-10-meses-de-um-malaio-num-centro-de-burlas-em-myanmar/</link><description>The Scam Center in Myanmar's Myawaddy Region Which is Still Operating.



In Myanmar, Gan Jiea Jie, a young Malay, was trained to write faster and use Artificial Intelligence (AI) to create profiles or videos, while learning ways to talk to random people on social networks. In short, he was trained to become a burlon.
Gan's unpleasant “career” began in February 2024, when he was attracted to a job offer that would allegedly pay him weekly 80,000 Ringgits (about 152,000 patacas) helping to transport gold from a Thailand dealer to Golden Stores in Malaysia. He eventually became a victim of human trafficking, being smuggled from Thailand to Myanmar, where he received an intensive one -month training on how to apply scams.
During his 10 months in Myanmar, Gan has learned to improve typing capabilities, talk to strangers online and gain their trust by talking about their favorite things, families, friends, and hopes for the future.
"We try to isolate the person from their loved ones, so that it does not talk about it with friends or family until we can get them as much money as possible," he said.
Gan received a manual on how to deal with various situations and ways to go through banking or police to scare the victims. "We need to explore people's emotions. A good way is to instill their fear of losing all their money or going to prison."
According to Gan, the Burla centers were well organized and were led by foreigners who managed them as corporate offices, with an executive director, general directors, supervisors and team heads. These centers had personal data, including dwellings and identity numbers, from countless people, had access to dozens of "mule" accounts and immediately transferred money from the local coin to US dollars.
The “mule” accounts are opened by an individual who gives access to online banking services or debit cards to a union, who then pays to the account holder between 500 and 1,000 Ringgits per month. Gan said the burns also access dating applications to attack the targets, using IA to create fake profiles or videos with police uniformed to convince victims during the VideoChamadas.
“We also produce legal documents or fake letters to freeze the accounts of people involved in the bleaching of capital,” to intimidate the usually elderly victims, he added.
He explained that his work involved four "layers." Union members played different roles: to know the target, to pass by an employee, transfer the money to fake accounts, and finally persuade the victim to pay even more money.
Those who performed investment schemes asked the victim to use the company's platform to buy cryptocurrencies and convince her to invest more to get profitable returns.
A foreigner even lost millions of dollars to the union. "The burlon that reached the feat received a huge bonus, an immediate wage increase, drink and even women," he said.
Over 10 months in captivity, Gan had to work up to 18 hours a day. He was beaten, handcuffed and electrocuted with a taser for not reaching the monthly quota, he said, showing many bruises on his back.
Its “KPI” (key performance indicator) was to reach about 30 people a month. Every day I should send messages saying, "Good morning. How are you today?"
And when the victim answered "I'm fine," Gan was forced to have a long conversation with him.
The bosses considered him useless because he could not fool anyone, despite sending calls and messages daily. "I was terrible to deceive people. I was always punished. They sold me at least three times to different call center unions," he said.
"They also said they needed to pay 50,000 USD if he wanted to go home. Otherwise, he would have to continue to work for them to pay this amount."
Criminal groups used social networks and messaging platforms like Telegram to publish rewards news for those who tried to escape, which was difficult. All the burla centers were located in large complexes, guarded by people armed with Kayin (Myanmar).
His opportunity for freedom came in February, when Thailand cut off the supply of electricity, internet and fuel to five border zones in Myanmar. The bosses gave him the option of moving to another blow center in Cambodia, and from there he fled one morning when he was buying breakfast.
On the way back to Malaysia sought shelter in a social assistance group to avoid the provisions of those who had borrowed money before leaving for Thailand in search of a “lucrative job”. He is grateful to social worker Joyce Hwang Qi Hui, whom he called “older sister” for raising 2,000 RM to finance his return to Malaysia.
The Malaysian embassy, ​​especially an employee named Buhari, other supporters and a church were also fundamental to his release, Gan said.
Now it is determined to restore the bonds with the family, which reneged him. It has three younger brothers, aged 9 to 13 years.
Gan admitted to being a tracker in childhood. "I had a lot of bad habits. I even went to a gang. It was missing to school," he recalled. "Now, I want to try to correct all the mistakes of my life. I hope to complete my fifth year, because I haven't done the exams." I regret all my wrong decisions, but I hope to do something useful with my life going forward. "
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-09-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>