<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Residents have “greatest concern” with areas linked to well-being</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/residentes-tem-maior-preocupacao-areas-ligadas-ao-bem-estar/</link><description>_cuva



Usina de Ideias dos Cidadãos Unidos surveyed 981 residents to understand the “Well-being Index of Macau’s population”. The association considers that the study results reflect that “residents have higher expectations and greater concern with areas related to well-being”. As he warned, discrepancies were observed between subjective assessments and objective data. As an example, in terms of objective indices, “employment and income” obtained 9.05 points, on a scale of zero to 10, but only achieved 3.77 points in the subjective assessment. The association understands that residents' current perceptions result from adaptation pressures motivated by the transformation of the economic structure
 
“Residents have higher expectations and greater concern about areas related to well-being”, indicates Usina de Ideias dos Cidadãos Unidos, based on a survey developed together with the City University of Macau, on the “Macau population well-being index 2024”.
Among all areas linked to the well-being of the population evaluated by a total of 981 residents, “security” obtained the highest subjective score in 2024, and the association does not explain the meaning of this evaluation parameter.
However, respondents showed “special attention” to areas related to the economy and quality of life, such as “employment and income” and “housing conditions”. According to the association, discrepancies were observed between subjective assessments and objective data, which reflects the “increased demands” of residents for the stability of guarantees for their well-being and the sustainability of economic development during the current period of economic transformation.
Representatives of the association revealed that, in terms of objective indices, “performance in general was excellent”, with “employment and income”, “level of education” and “quality of the environment” occupying the first three places, with 9.05, 8.75 and 8.27 points, respectively, on a scale of zero to 10. For the association, the aforementioned data illustrate that Macau has achieved “significant achievements” in macroeconomic data, investment in education and environmental infrastructures.
In relation to subjective indices, “safety” obtained 6.34 points, occupying the first position, followed by “level of education” (4.94 points) and “quality of the environment” (4.9 points).
The association highlighted that, although “employment and income” obtained a higher score in the objective assessment, it only achieved 3.77 points in the subjective analysis. In the same vein, interviewees gave only 3.64 points when subjectively evaluating “housing conditions”, making this the area that received the fewest points among all those analyzed in the study.
Chan Peng Peng, director of the United Citizens Idea Plant, pointed out that, compared to international standards, the overall employment situation of Macau residents has remained in a good state, with the unemployment rate constantly decreasing. According to him, residents' current perceptions result mainly from adaptation pressures caused by the transformation of the economic structure.
Based on the conclusions of the survey, the association suggested that the Government improve the adjustment regimes regarding the value of social risk and subsidies, taking into account the real costs of families and changes in the burden of people's well-being, in addition to continuing to take price changes as a reference.
Furthermore, the association linked to the Aliança de Povo de Instituição hopes that the authorities will expand the acquisition of medical services, provide more parking spaces for motorcycles, find solutions to the noise problem and create an economic support system that covers the population from zero to three years old.</description><pubDate>2025-12-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Public space thought of in six different ways</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/espaco-publico-pensado-em-seis-formas-diferentes/</link><description>The IN SITU Placemaking Biennial began yesterday and runs until Sunday. Six locations have six installations – and several activities – designed by local and international artists. In this article, we get to know each of the projects
 



































Catarina Pereira
 
Several artists thought of different concepts to use public space in six locations in Macau as part of the IN SITU Placemaking Biennial, organized by the Center for Architecture and Urbanism (CURB), which kicked off yesterday and runs until Sunday. The inauguration ceremony of the initiative took place yesterday at 4 pm, at Ponte 9 – Creative Platform, in Porto Interior.
Pátio da Claridade is one of these places and hosts the project “Where Time Crystallizes”, by six local artists: Lora Lei Mei Ian, Wang Shumeng, Jiang Xintong and Xu Huiyao. To the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, Lora Lei Mei Ian explained that the idea came about because “Pátio da Claridade was once a vibrant community” and now “the buildings are empty”.
The installation is composed of nine mirrored crystalline shapes and an undulating carpet. “Each crystal contains photographs, video fragments and everyday objects, collected in Jason Lei's documentation about the neighborhood, before the residents left”, says the description. The mirrored exteriors reflect the current street and passersby, while the enclosed interiors invite viewers to peek at traces of the past, he explained.
“With the exception of old doors and walls, it is difficult to find any sign of past life, so we wanted to show the ‘inside’ and ‘outside’ of time in the same space”, pointed out the artist. “When we looked at the photos taken before the residents left, we understood what life was like there and we transformed that feeling into our project,” he added.
"During the research, we interviewed former residents. They told us many interesting stories", said Lora, giving an example: "In the past, there was a well where people washed clothes, cooled watermelons and children took baths. The walls were red for many years and only recently changed to yellow".
He also said that some families raised chickens and dogs there and “in the same house, behind a single door, two or three families lived”. In the 1960s and 70s, there was even a small store on the corner that sold boiled water, he added.
In addition to the installation, there will be a sharing session today between 10:30 am and 11:00 am, followed by the “Time Crystal Lab” activity. Participants are invited to write or draw on small cards, which will then be attached to a red string.
“Through this installation and activity, we hope that visitors can feel the deep stories and history of Pátio da Claridade, observing the contrast between the past and the present (…) And we hope that this group of ancient buildings can be well preserved in the future”, concluded the team, who are studying for a master's degree in Communication Design at the Faculty of Humanities and Arts of the Macau University of Science and Technology, in the words of Lora Lei Mei Ian.
 
Revive lost tradition
Largo do Aquino, in turn, gains new life with “Furniture Where Life Begins”, by Lo Wing Hei, master in Architecture from the Chinese University of Hong Kong. The choice of this space came from the observation that, “despite its central location, in the heart of dense residential blocks, it has lost almost all traces of the inherited community spirit”, as he explained to this newspaper.
Stressing that squares are spaces that are intended to function as “urban living rooms”, the local artist points out that, despite their accessibility, many “remain surprisingly empty and underused”. “I observed this pattern repeatedly throughout the city, and it became the central problem I wanted to address.”
For Lo Wing Hei, “what makes the emptiness even more impressive is the cultural weight that the word ‘Largo’ itself carries.” "In Macau, a Largo is much more than a generic square; it is a distinct typology of public space born from the fusion of Chinese and Portuguese traditions. The Portuguese originally designed them as open squares in front of churches for religious ceremonies and processions, but over the centuries they have evolved to become the city's most vibrant social centers – places to chat, exchange gossip and cool off in the evening breeze," he described.
Being an exception that proves the rule, when choosing Largo do Aquino, Lo Wing Hei wanted to understand why some “urban living rooms” thrive while others are forgotten.
With “Furniture Where Life Begins” the idea is to “revive the lost tradition” of these public spaces being once filled with furniture brought by citizens from their homes. "I designed simple chairs, tables and shelves that invite residents to use and paint them together in the square. Through collective creation, everyday objects become carriers of shared stories," he said.
After the event, people can adopt a piece and take it home: “What they take with them is no longer just furniture, but a living fragment of the community (…) In this way, the spirit of Largo travels from the empty square to the homes, silently uniting public and private life”.
Activities are scheduled for Sunday. At 10:30 am there is a sharing session, followed by “Love Me? Destroy Me!”, between 11:00 am and 12:00 pm. The “adoption” of the pieces is scheduled for 6:30 pm.
 
Echoes and reverberations
Also local artists Joseph Lau and Lawrence Liu created “Resonatorium”, inspired by “the echoes and reverberations inside churches, as well as the historical image of the wooden chapel that once stood on the site of the Church of São Lourenço”. This work thus builds “a resonance belonging exclusively to the past and present of the site”.
The installation is composed of wooden sound modules, forming a semi-open architectural space, in which the structure itself becomes a resonant body, says the project description. “When wind and environmental sounds enter the work, they are filtered and amplified through resonance tubes at different frequencies, intertwining to create spontaneous and fluid sound fragments.”
According to the authors, each resonance tube is oriented towards a reference point or area of ​​symbolic significance, such as the Church of São Lourenço, the Porto Interior pier, the Largo de Santo Agostinho neighborhood, Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro. Furthermore, there is a tube directed towards the sea.
The resonant frequency of each tube corresponds directly to the physical distance between the installation and the reference site, except in the case of the sea. The installation is on display next to Praça Ponte e Horta.
 
Dating platform
In turn, “UnPlan”, designed to offer a new perspective on public space, “landed” in Largo de Santo Agostinho. The creators are Portuguese Hugo Reis and Filipa Frois Almeida. “This piece is completely designed for this Macau context”, said Hugo Reis, explaining that they both know the territory.
"The project understands public space not as a void waiting for construction, but as a living platform for meetings, relationships and cultural expression. Placed as if it had landed there by chance, 'UnPlan' embraces contingency and encourages spontaneous interactions", says the description.
Specifically, it is a platform created with different bamboo elements. "Part platform, part backdrop, part sign, it adapts to its surroundings while subtly transforming it. The gentle curve, shaped by gravity and time, becomes the most distinctive feature – a visible marker of temporality and vulnerability", it can be read. “The surface becomes a shared terrain, where authorship belongs to the place and meaning emerges from individual and collective use”.
Asked what the biggest difficulties were, Hugo Reis explained that the design itself was easy, especially because they have already been carrying out these experiments in different locations. “The biggest challenge is the reaction that this type of project may provoke, but at the same time it is our greatest encouragement”, he stated.
“Macau has a highly designed, highly planned, highly codified public space, ruled in the sense that each function occupies its place, each object has an assigned function, and in some way the opening of spaces to transformation is very conditioned by the logic of prior planning”, he noted, adding that the idea is “to be able to try to deconstruct the idea and perception we have about things”.
Visiting professor at the Department of Architecture and Design at the University of São José, Hugo Reis admitted to being expectant about the reactions.
 
Letters to Macau
Still on an international level, architects Kruti Shah (India) and Sebastián Trujillo-Torres (Spain) present “Letters to Macau”. The installation “reinterprets the city’s traditional mailbox as an urban device for reflection, correspondence and civic imagination.”
Visitors are invited to write letters addressed to the city, sharing memories, wishes or proposals for renewal. Each letter is deposited in the structure, accumulating throughout the Biennale and gradually transforming the installation into a collective civic archive.
Constructed from 10 plywood panels, the structure is finished “in a matte red with discreet white accents, the object evokes Macau’s postal heritage, operating on an architectural scale”. “‘Letters to Macau’ functions simultaneously as an artefact and an instrument: a modest but precise space to write, gather and reimagine the city.”
On Sunday, from 3:30 pm there will be a sharing session with the artists, at the intersection between Travessa do Aterro Novo and Rua dos Mercadores, where the installation will also be located. Between 4pm and 5pm, a collective reading session is scheduled.
 
Space experience
A spatial experience in response to urban change: this is what artist Yik Sze Wong, from Hong Kong, proposes for Largo do Lilau. "How can we question and renew established models of public spaces? And how can we encourage the public to participate more actively in the construction and practice of these spaces?"
The central question of the “Multi-place” project lies in exploring how public spaces can respond effectively to dynamic changes in urban activities and the needs of their use.
Specifically, he created a modular device, built with plywood panels and mounted on multidirectional wheels, allowing “flexible spatial configurations and easy maintenance”. The idea is to “stimulate community interaction, reinforce social cohesion and, thus, build a more inclusive and adaptable public domain”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>88 million reverted to the coffers due to checks not collected</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/88-milhoes-reverteram-para-os-cofres-devido-aos-cheques-nao-levantados/</link><description>The opinion on the proposal for the “Budget Law of 2026”, which has already been signed, reveals that 87.94 million patacas were returned to the Macao SAR coffers, resulting from cash checks that exceeded the three-year deadline for withdrawal. The Government predicted a significant reduction in these situations of funds being returned to the Treasury, with the implementation of changes to the allocation conditions. On the other hand, accepting the opinion of the Legislative Assembly, the Executive began to allow both spouses to enjoy exemption from stamp duty when purchasing a housing unit up to the amount of six million patacas, regardless of the property regime they adopt.
 
The 2nd Permanent Committee of the Legislative Assembly (AL) has already signed the opinion on the proposal for the “2026 Budget Law”. According to the document, in the “Replacements of payments made in previous years”, the revenues from the Cash Contribution Plan that exceeded the three-year withdrawal period returned to the Macao SAR coffers a value of 87.94 million patacas.
According to the Government, there are several reasons for the return of funds from that Plan: the failure to collect checks during the respective period of validity, the failure to present proof of life or the subsequent verification that the beneficiary did not meet the requirements, after the allocation of the amount of the financial contribution.
Committee members paid attention to the possibility of these funds being reduced. The Government explained that, due to changes in the allocation requirements, it is believed that the prior verification of the requirement to stay in Macau, already carried out by the competent services before the distribution of the amounts, will contribute to a significant reduction in these instances of funds being returned to the Treasury.
On the other hand, the opinion of the 2nd AL Permanent Commission indicates that the budgeted expenditure for the “Individual accounts of the non-mandatory central pension scheme” is 3.68 billion patacas, involving an annual increase of 12.4%. According to the Government, the number of complaints about the central pension scheme increased significantly this year, and, up to 30 November, in a period of five and a half months, around 32 thousand complaints were received, more than double the same period in 2024. On the other hand, since the extraordinary distribution of budget balances of this scheme has a limitation period of three years, in 2026 complaints will still be received regarding the 2024 funds. and 2025, making it necessary to carry out a budget increase.
The document also indicates that, in 2026, the budgeted revenue from the “Professional Tax”, one of the main sources of revenue, amounts to 3.25 billion, an increase of 7.8% compared to 2025. The actual revenue from the professional tax in the first half of this year increased compared to the budget estimate, which, according to the Government, happened because the level in terms of general employment and wages is “relatively stable”, in addition to “the wages in some sectors were even increased.”
The budgeted revenue from the “Supplementary Income Tax” stands at 7.39 billion in 2026, an increase of 8.1% in annual terms. Noting that the banking sector is always an important source of Supplementary Income Tax revenue, the Executive explained that, due to the expected improvement in the economic environment, the banking sector's provisioning expenses for non-performing loans will be relatively reduced, at the same time that bank profits are expected to increase, thus leading to an increase in revenue from this tax.
On the other hand, the president of the 2nd Committee, Ip Sio Kai, revealed that the Government accepted the opinion of the members, allowing both spouses to benefit from the exemption from stamp duty on transfers of assets up to the value of six million patacas, in the acquisition of autonomous housing units by residents of legal age, regardless of whether a regime of general community of assets or separation of assets is adopted between the two.
 
Hospital das Ilhas will hire 167 workers in 2026
Furthermore, the document reveals that, until October 31st of this year, Hospital das Ilhas had 686 workers and 28 trainees from the “Medical Residency Program”, in a total of 714 elements. Among these, 483 were health professionals, representing 67% of the total, with 137 doctors and 175 nurses standing out.
The Government promised that, in 2026, Hospital das Ilhas “will actively contribute to alleviating pressure on the public health system, through the expansion of the various health care services – such as taking over the operation of the Ilhas Emergency Center and optimizing the service models of the Dialysis Center – reinforcing service capacity, increasing the number of inpatient beds in the wards and expanding the size of diagnostic and treatment services”.
At the same time, the “orderly development” of the International Medical Center’s private services is also planned, promoting the advancement of the big health industry.
Given the need to expand multiple medical services, the authorities understand that it is “indispensable” to continually hire more human resources in the areas of healthcare and logistical support, to cope with the increased volume of work. In this sense, Hospital das Ilhas will gradually recruit around 167 workers in total over the next year.
 
FM supports UPM and UTM for land in Hengqin
Also according to the opinion, by order of the Chief Executive, the allocation of financial support by the Macau Foundation (FM) was authorized, through a “cooperation agreement”, to the Polytechnic University (UPM) and the Tourism University (UTM), in the amount of approximately 1.8 billion renminbis, equivalent to 2.05 billion patacas, aimed at obtaining land for educational purposes in Hengqin.
Furthermore, to finance the acquisition of land by the University of Macau (UM) for the construction of the new campus in Hengqin, FM spent 1.099 billion renminbi.
In relation to UPM, this institution predicted that the number of students will increase by around 600 next year, while approximately 200 postgraduate students will take classes at the teaching center on a provisional basis in Hengqin in 2026. In this sense, in conjunction with the construction of the campus in the Deep Cooperation Zone, the expansion of courses, the increase in scientific research projects and the increase in the number of students, as well as to fill staff vacancies due to termination of duties and retirement, the institution “considers it essential to recruit more teachers and researchers” and “it is necessary to increase the number of non-teaching staff accordingly”.
As for UM, in addition to creating 29 places for teaching staff on the main campus, it plans to allocate 31 teaching staff places in 2026 for the construction of the campus in Hengqin, with the aim of supporting the implementation of the Faculties of Medicine, Information and Computer Science, Engineering and Design, providing specialized support for construction and development work. It is estimated that these new positions will be filled by August 2026.
In addition to recruiting 20 new administrative workers for the main campus, UM plans to allocate 15 new administrative staff positions in 2026, to ensure that preparatory work at the Hengqin campus proceeds in an orderly manner. These new positions will be filled progressively in the second half of 2026.</description><pubDate>2025-12-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Accelerates the digitalization of Financial Services</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/acelera-digitalizacao-dos-servicos-das-financas/</link><description>Electronic documents related to public accounts procedures will now have the same legal obligation as paper documents, Wong Sio Chak announced yesterday. The spokesperson for the Executive Council also said that administrative processes related to requests for funds from public entities with administrative autonomy will be simplified
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
Payment orders and electronic requests related to public finances will now have “the same legal effects” as paper documents, as announced yesterday by the spokesperson for the Executive Council (EC), Wong Sio Chak. Recently, the EC concluded the discussion on the amendment to the Regulation of the Budgetary Framework Law, which aims to realize the vision of a “smart city”.
According to the Secretary for Administration and Justice, the measure aims to maximize “to its fullest extent, the operational efficiency of the system and electronic management”, removing the restrictions previously imposed on the digital form.
According to Ho Silvestre In Mui, deputy director of the Financial Services (DSF), this intelligent system will be “very convenient”. To pay for services, companies will only have to register with the bank, allowing the banking entity to transfer the service provider's data to the DSF. Subsequently, the DSF will coordinate with the bank and, when it is necessary to pay a company, the online channels will allow the funds to be transferred directly to the company.
“Currently, the DSF has to issue a check and then contact the company, informing them that it is now available. Afterwards, “the company has to go to the bank to collect the check”, pointed out the deputy director. “This electronic payment can be more convenient”, she reiterated.
In the same vein, the Executive also intends to simplify administrative procedures, reducing the “examination and authorization phases that prove to be unnecessary” for “requests for funding allocations from services with administrative autonomy. For Wong Sio Chak, this measure will allow for a “shortening of treatment time”, an “optimization of the use of resources” and an “increase in administrative efficiency”.
This new administrative regulation also includes the “updating of the denominations and expressions of printed matter in current legislation”, since “there are still denominations of printed matter on paper that prove to be incompatible with operational reality”, explained Wong.
The regulation will come into force on January 1, 2026.
 
First Group of Movable Assets divided into 24 typologies
The Government defined 24 categories for the 400 pieces or sets covered by the administrative regulation of the “Classification of the 1st Group of Movable Goods”. These include “archaeological species, cult pieces, religious objects, porcelain, ceramics, enamelware, drawings, engravings, calligraphy, sculptures, stone inscriptions, textiles, furniture, decorative components, recreational materials, means of transport, valuable manuscripts, rare books, maps, printed materials, official documents, letters, photographic records and handmade fans”, said Wong Sio Chak yesterday. The change to the regulation takes effect from today. Leong Wai Man, president of the Cultural Institute, also stated that the organization will begin work and contact other public services with properties with potential “high historical values”, with a view to creating the classification of a second group.
 
Government considers easing regulation of some activities and events
The Chief Executive decided to launch a public consultation on the elaboration of the “Regime for the regulation of certain activities and events”, to be held in the first half of next year, in agreement with the Executive Council (EC). According to Wong Sio Chak, the new regime will allow some sectors to be exempt from certain regulations, without adding details. According to the EC spokesperson, the idea is to simplify administration and decentralize powers and optimize services, increasing the efficiency of interdepartmental coordination, in favor of “an environment conducive to trade and a market order that is ‘fair, transparent and predictable’”. The legislation has “great significance for optimizing the business environment and socio-economic development of Macau”, reiterated Wong, and “represents a major political change”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Strike in Portugal hit transport, schools and hospitals</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/greve-em-portugal-atingiu-transportes-escolas-hospitais/</link><description>Portugal was hit yesterday by a general strike, the first in 12 years, which considerably paralyzed air and rail connections, as well as the operation of schools and hospitals, in protest against the labor reforms proposed by the government. Lisbon's main train station was deserted, with most trips canceled, and TAP suspended almost two thirds of its usual 250 flights.
According to the unions, garbage collection was interrupted and hospital units that deal with non-urgent cases also suspended their activities. Speaking to SIC, José Feliciano Costa, general secretary of the National Federation of Teachers, highlighted that “large hundreds of schools” had closed across the country, with teacher participation being around “90 to 100%” in some establishments.
In the area of ​​Health, adherence levels exceeded 90%, asserted the National Federation of Doctors, highlighting the closure of most hospital operating rooms and the strong constraints on scheduled appointments.
In the early hours of the day, the secretary general of the General Confederation of Portuguese Workers (CGTP) stated that the strike was registering “high participation” in both the public and private sectors, translating into a “success”. In an assessment at the beginning of the afternoon, Tiago Oliveira highlighted that the data collected up to that point indicated that more than three million workers joined the strike, but the numbers were expected to increase, because there was still “a lot of fighting to be done”.
The Minister of the Presidency, António Leitão Amaro, stated that “the vast majority of Portuguese people are working” and this “looks like another public service strike, a partial strike in some sectors of the public service”. “The level of adherence throughout the country to the general strike is insignificant, particularly in the private and social sector”, he argued.
According to the minister, financial, commercial and economic activity registered a reduction of 7% compared to the normal period, while traffic on bridges south of Lisbon decreased by 5%. “In the private and social sectors, reports point to a strike adherence rate of between 0 and 10%,” he said, to minimize the impact of the strike.
“We respect the right to strike, we respect those who have already gone on strike and those who are currently on strike in Portugal”, he highlighted, reiterating that the government remains open to negotiations with the unions to try to reach an agreement on labor reform.
Confronted with the minister's statements, the CGTP general secretary stated that “it is a government that is completely out of touch with the reality of the country, that does not want to understand the justice that today leads workers to fight, for this great general strike that is taking place throughout the country”.
 
JTM with agencies and Portuguese press</description><pubDate>2025-12-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>AMCM follows US and Hong Kong and lowers basic interest rate</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/amcm-segue-eua-hong-kong-baixa-taxa-de-juro-basica/</link><description>Following the decision taken by the North American central bank, the regulators of the financial systems of Macau and Hong Kong yesterday reduced their basic interest rates by 0.25 percentage points. This is the third cut adopted this year
 
The Macau Monetary Authority (AMCM) yesterday lowered its basic interest rate by 0.25 percentage points, following the cut announced by the North American Federal Reserve (Fed) and consequently by the Hong Kong Monetary Authority. AMCM thus set the rediscount rate at 4.00%, the amount charged to banks for short-term capital injections, with immediate effect.
Taking into account the exchange rate indexation regime – from the pataca to the Hong Kong dollar and from there to the US dollar – the rediscount rate in the Macao SAR is “consistent” with that of Hong Kong, standing 0.50 percentage points above the minimum limit of the Fed's indicator interest rate, reiterated the AMCM. The same applies to the averages of the last five days and the interbank offer interest rates practiced overnight and in the last month in Hong Kong, depending on which value is higher, the organization pointed out in a brief note published on its website.
With the new cut, the third this year, after the cuts announced in September and October, the Fed placed its rates in a range between 3.50% and 3.75%.
The statement issued at the end of the two-day meeting of the Federal Open Market Committee (FOMC) indicates that three of the 12 members voted against the decision. Two of them opposed any reduction in interest rates and another defended a broader reduction, of half a percentage point.
Kansas City Fed President Jeffrey Schmid had already opposed an interest rate cut at the previous meeting, which took place at the end of October. This time he was accompanied by Chicago Fed President Austan Goolsbee.
In favor of a deeper cut, Governor Stephen Miran, recently appointed by President Donald Trump, declared himself a staunch supporter of steeper interest rate cuts.
According to updated forecasts by Federal Reserve officials, who are more optimistic regarding economic growth and inflation in the USA, it may be necessary to reduce interest rates just once next year. According to these projections, the US could see annual Gross Domestic Product (GDP) growth of 2.3% in 2026 (compared to a previous estimate of 1.8%).
Inflation may also be lower than expected (2.4% versus 2.6%). Unemployment could remain at its current level (4.4%).
In the final statement, the Fed added some words that, according to AFP, will not go unnoticed by the markets, considering that “the magnitude and timing” of possible additional adjustments in interest rates will depend on the way the economy evolves.
The interest rate cut was decided on the second and last day of the FOMC meeting, made up of the seven members of the Federal Reserve System's board of governors, the president of the Federal Reserve Bank of New York and four of the remaining 11 presidents of the Reserve Bank, who serve one-year terms on a rotating basis.
Federal Reserve Chairman Jerome Powell will step down next spring. Donald Trump's economic advisor, Kevin Hassett, is currently considered the favorite to succeed him.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Platform launched to assist guardians</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lancada-plataforma-para-auxiliar-encarregados-de-educacao/</link><description>The Government launched the educational platform “Classes for parents”, in an attempt to “support guardians in all stages of their students’ development”. Several members of the Education Council and the Youth Council welcomed the initiative, anticipating a “positive impact on social stability”
 
In an attempt to improve policy planning regarding non-higher education, the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ), the Health Services and the Institute of Social Action launched the information and training platform “Classes for parents”. According to a statement, this mechanism aims to “support guardians in all stages of their students’ development”.
This platform is part of a series of efforts by the Government to improve the educational environment in the territory. During a conference held at the Official Luso-Chinese Primary School “Sir Robert Ho Tung”, chaired by O Lam, Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, several members of the Education Council and the Youth Council “placed hope in the new ‘Class for Parents’ initiative”, trusting that it “will promote greater family harmony” and a “positive impact on social stability”.
In this context, DSEDJ has also optimized counseling work to promote the physical and mental health of students, with some members suggesting the use of scientific equipment to monitor students' physical and mental health data and the reinforcement, “from a young age”, of “building their psychological resilience”.
Furthermore, several stakeholders agreed on professional career planning already in complementary primary education, proposing measures to support youth employment and their integration in the development of the Greater Bay Area.
On the other hand, other members expressed some concern “about the impact of the low birth rate on the educational system”, asking that “high quality and equity in education” continue to be guaranteed.
With regard to higher education, DSEDJ stated that it has focused on optimizing the administration of the various institutions and disciplinary planning, in addition to promoting the implementation of the pedagogical extension model to the Cooperation Zone, with priority given to public higher education institutions in the construction of the Macau International Education University City in Hengqin.
DSEDJ also highlighted the optimization of Youth Policy action plans, within the scope of interdepartmental cooperation in supporting learning and employment for young people, as well as the “Community Esplanade for young people” sessions, which provide more avenues of expression to improve the formulation of government policies.
The organization also stressed that the development of quality at the various levels of education will also involve strengthening the development of courses and teaching materials and the construction of Macau's artificial intelligence teaching system.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-12-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Insurance companies cover 35 thousand lifetime annuities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/seguradoras-cobrem-35-mil-rendas-vitalicias/</link><description>In the first 10 months of the year as a whole, the Labor Affairs Bureau managed to find jobs for 134 elderly residents, according to Chan Un Tong, director of the organization. Furthermore, as of the end of October, there were 35,177 individual life annuity policies in the Macao SAR
 
From January to October this year, the Directorate of Labor Affairs Services (DSAL) placed 134 residents aged 65 and over in jobs. In response to a written question from Deputy Lam Lon Wai, the director of DSAL, Chan Un Tong, also clarified that, at the end of the third quarter of 2025, there were 35,177 individual life insurance policies, corresponding to 10.4 billion patacas and 6.8% of the total volume of life insurance business in force.
For Chan Un Tong, the life annuity products available on the Macao SAR market demonstrate “a considerable degree of flexibility and diversity”, with different modalities and guarantees such as death rights or guaranteed annuity payment periods.
The director also assured that the Macau Monetary Authority “will continue to encourage the insurance sector to launch more life annuity products and reinforce corresponding dissemination and education actions.
The Fund for the Development of Science and Technology (FDCT) has also intensively supported higher education institutions and companies in Macau, noted the person responsible, “in the development of R&amp;D projects in the area of ​​‘big health’, including the areas of health maintenance and smart care for the elderly, through various financial support programs”.
Furthermore, there are initiatives aimed at the needs of groups of elderly people in the community, argued the director. These “integrate technologies such as artificial intelligence and robotics to research and develop a small intelligent traditional Chinese medicine pharmacy”, in order to “seamlessly” articulate medical prescription and prescription filling systems.
Chan also pointed out the Macau Youth Innovation and Entrepreneurship Competition of the Economic and Technological Development Services Bureau, which actively promotes the application of innovative technology products and services from 'big health' and smart technology projects to the living needs of the elderly.
The director of DSAL also added that a methodology based on eye tracking technology with artificial intelligence was developed to assess the cognitive capacity of the elderly, helping with early intervention and treatment.
At the same time, the Health Services are monitoring the legislative work on the “Law on the activity of private institutions providing health care” which regulates day hospitals and defines a legal basis for telemedicine, proximity medical services and advanced therapy.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-12-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>International Forum promotes exchange between civilizations</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/forum-internacional-promove-intercambio-entre-civilizacoes/</link><description>The first edition of the International Civilization Exchange Forum will promote humanistic and cultural exchange and narrate the historical paths of China and Macau. Under the theme “Mutual Learning between Civilizations, Heritage and Development”, the event will take place on the 16th and 17th of December and includes two parallel seminars and several academic meetings
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
Representatives of government departments from various countries and regions, international organizations, as well as renowned experts and academics, both national and foreign, will participate in the first International Civilization Exchange Forum.
At the event, which will take place on the 16th and 17th of December, around 20 thematic sessions will be held, debating topics such as civilizational inclusion, cultural innovation and the development of cooperation. The main objective of the event, organized by the Cultural Institute (IC) and supported by the Academy of History of the Chinese Academy of Social Sciences, is to promote humanistic and cultural exchange at an international level and narrate the historical paths of China and the Macao SAR.
The Forum will serve to “establish Macau as a relevant high-level link for the country in opening up to the outside world and an important window for exchange and mutual learning between Chinese and Western civilizations”, says a statement from the IC.
This year's theme is “Mutual Learning between Civilizations, Heritage and Development” and includes two parallel forums: “Mutual Learning between Civilizations and Diverse Coexistence” and “Conservation and Sustainable Development of Cultural Heritage”, in addition to several academic meetings.
Macau will be the main focus of the debates, highlighting the convergence between Chinese and Western cultures. “Over more than four centuries, different ethnic groups have taken root and prospered here, learning from each other and integrating, which has given rise to a unique cultural landscape and a rich cultural heritage”, highlights the IC.
The introduction to the Forum further highlights that “the roots of Chinese civilization and the harmonious coexistence of diverse cultures have jointly shaped Macao's open and diverse urban DNA, which embodies the pioneering and inclusive spirit of Chinese culture and vividly constitutes the dynamic practice of mutual learning between Chinese and Western civilizations”.
He adds that holding the seminar “is precisely a concrete action by Macau to actively engage in global dialogue between civilizations, demonstrating the unique charm of ‘Cultural Macau’ and contributing to the construction of a community with a shared future for humanity”.
In this sense, the Forum intends to establish a “platform for dialogue and academic exchange” with international influence, promote “mutual understanding and respect between different civilizations” and convey the “vision of an era” in which cultural integration drives human development.
In this way, “it aims to inject new impetus into the deepening of international cooperation and the promotion of global exchange between civilizations, valuing Macau’s contribution to the construction of a community with a shared future for humanity”, indicates the body responsible for the organization.
The debate program begins with the opening ceremony, on December 16th, at 11 am, in the Events Hall of the JW Marriot Hotel.
The following day, at the Galaxy International Convention Center, starting at 9 am, the academic meetings will debate topics such as “The Contemporary Value of the Practice of ‘One Country, Two Systems’ and Mutual Learning between Civilizations”, and “From the Perspective of Macau: New Approaches to the Protection of World Cultural Heritage”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>USJ shares smart culture and tourism ecosystem</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/usj-partilha-ecossistema-inteligente-de-cultura-turismo/</link><description>The University of São José and the Tourcon B2B platform have created a new ecosystem to promote data integration and artificial intelligence innovation in Macau's cultural and tourism sectors. The initiative will seek to address issues such as data fragmentation, limited digital resources within the industry and the need for more efficient cross-border tourism services
 
Jointly promoting data integration and innovation in artificial intelligence (AI) in Macau's cultural and tourism sectors is the central objective of a memorandum of understanding signed by the Institute of Engineering and Data Science of the University of São José (USJ) and the Tourcon B2B platform. “The agreement marks an important step towards strengthening the city’s digital capabilities and increasing its competitiveness as an international tourist center,” says a USJ statement.
As part of the partnership, both parties will collaborate on data analysis, the development of AI-based products and smart tourism applications. The initiative aims to address long-standing issues such as data fragmentation, limited digital resources within the industry and the need for more efficient cross-border tourism services.
The cooperation will support tourism supply chain insights, policy decision-making and scenario-based smart tourism applications, helping Macau improve the quality of inbound and outbound travel and deepen tourism cooperation in the Greater Bay Area.
After signing the memorandum, George Du, director of the USJ Data Science and Engineering Institute, stated that “companies, on their own, often do not have the capacity to carry out a complete digital transformation”. Hence, the partnership allows “to integrate the strengths of academic research”, such as machine learning, multimodal models, traveler behavior prediction and intelligent recommendation algorithms, with Tourcon's market-oriented platform.
This collaboration “will not only improve technical capabilities in the short term, but will also create technological advantages in the long term”, helping the industry to avoid “technological homogenization” and develop differentiated tourist services. These innovations will accelerate the development of Macau as “a model city for global smart tourism”, he stressed.
In turn, Phoebe Cao, director of “Tourcon B2B Platform”, highlighted that, despite the progress brought by the Macau-Hengqin integration policy, “the local industry still faces difficulties with data silos and dispersed information systems”, noting that this collaboration “fills a critical gap” and will reinforce the “soft power” of the industry, allowing companies to adopt AI-based tools and data-driven decision making.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-12-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>António Aresta pays tribute to Monsignor Manuel Teixeira</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/antonio-aresta-presta-tributo-monsenhor-manuel-teixeira/</link><description>The vast bibliography of Monsignor Manuel Teixeira is highlighted by researcher António Aresta in a study published in the magazine of Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Braga
 
The figure of Monsignor Manuel Teixeira, emeritus historian of Macau, is once again evoked by António Aresta, professor and researcher of the territory's cultural history, this time in the magazine of Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Braga. Composed of 515 pages, issue 21 of the magazine will, in fact, be presented by António Aresta himself, a former teacher in Macau and a regular collaborator of JTM for decades, in a session scheduled for this Saturday, December 13th, at 3:30 pm (Portuguese time), at Palácio do Raio, one of the 'ex-libris' of the city of Braga.
In this study, António Aresta seeks to group Monsignor Manuel Teixeira's vast bibliography into 16 topics, including education/teaching; Luís de Camões; medicine; military history; international relations; toponymy; Macau and its diocese; biographies; Chinese temples; history of Macau; press; anthology; interviews; literature; collaboration in the press. “Through this bibliographical glance, we can assess the magnitude and complexity of the history of Portuguese presence in Macau and the Far East”, highlights the researcher.
For António Aresta, the figure of Manuel Teixeira “calls to mind the image of a medieval sage who, in the dusty silence of the Scriptorium, surrounded by paper icons, gradually studied and read, wrote and meditated, publishing books after books”. “The constancy of his intellectual work, the kaleidoscopic theme of subjects he wrote about and his tenacious love for causes and values ​​that he never tired of defending and propagating is impressive”, he emphasizes, evoking “the committed priest, the scheming polemicist, the mischievous eye, the tireless journalist, the very fruitful writer, the conversationalist with broad horizons where the glass and fork participated in an almost liturgical aesthetic”.
"Were it not for his extraordinary donation to History, especially to the history of Macau, the Church and the Portuguese presence in extreme Asia, saving, collecting, reproducing and interpreting documents and sources, the degree of knowledge we would possess about our history in eastern parts would be unimaginable. We owe him a good part of our memory filled with affections, people, stories, things, greatness and miseries", can be read in the article, remembering that the 76 years of Manuel Teixeira's works include 61 in Macau and 15 in Singapore and Malacca.
Manuel Teixeira was born on April 15, 1912, in Freixo de Espada à Cinta, and headed to Macau, aged 12, on September 16, 1924, on the D’Artagnan liner of the “Messageries Maritimes” Company, arriving in Hong Kong on October 27 of that year. Ten years later he received priestly ordination from the hands of Bishop D. José da Costa Nunes and was the parish priest of the Church of S. Lourenço between 1934 and 1947, being then appointed superior and vicar general of the Portuguese Missions of Singapore and Malacca, from 1948 to 1962.
Throughout the article, António Aresta addresses the different facets of Manuel Teixeira, who ended up returning definitively to Portugal on May 15, 2001, staying at Casa de Santa Marta, in Chaves, a work he helped found. He died on September 15, 2003, at the age of 91, and was buried in the Chaves Cemetery.
"Conservative, nationalist, passionate about History and the imperial vocation of Portugal, Monsignor Manuel Teixeira accumulated works, distinctions and friendships, without losing the coherence in his convictions, the fraternal rudeness of a native Trás-os-Montes and the true simplicity in his way of being. We may disagree with his research methodology or the ideological contours he gave to the narratives, but we recognize the greatness and indispensability of the work he bequeathed to us", he highlights António Aresta, observing that the religious man “searched the history of Macau and the history of the Portuguese presence in the Far East from end to end, saving documentary sources, outlining biographies, accepting legacies and manuscripts, reconstituting documents, collecting photographs, interviewing protagonists or accumulating an enormous epistolary”.
“No one will study Macau and the history of the Portuguese presence in the Far East without going through his work”, argues the researcher.</description><pubDate>2025-12-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>PhD student from Macau in Coimbra creates AI model to optimize drugs</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/doutoranda-de-macau-em-coimbra-cria-modelo-de-ia-para-optimizar-farmacos/</link><description>A Macau student at the University of Coimbra (UC) developed an artificial intelligence (AI) model to discover and optimize drugs, which open up new clinical perspectives, within the scope of a doctoral program. The work of Yanan Tian, ​​a student in the Joint Doctoral Program between the UC Faculty of Science and Technology and the Macau Polytechnic University (UPM), promises a new approach to designing drugs with greater selectivity and clinical efficacy.
“This work proposes the MMCLKin model, a structure based on advanced AI methods, designed to predict with high precision and interpretability the activity and selectivity of kinase inhibitors, significantly accelerating the process of discovery and optimization of new targeted drugs”, explained Yanan Tian, ​​in a statement from the Faculty of Science and Technology sent to the Lusa agency.
According to the note, protein kinases constitute one of the most relevant classes of therapeutic targets in biomedical research, whose potential results from the central role they play in the regulation of multiple cellular processes, including proliferation, differentiation and cell death.
“However, the development of highly selective inhibitors continues to be a challenge, due to the strong structural conservation between kinases and the high cost of experimental tests”, he said.
The results of the research carried out under the guidance of professors Joel P. Arrais, from the Department of Computer Engineering at FCTUC, and Huanxiang Liu, from MPU, “demonstrate that the model outperforms existing methods in predicting the affinity and selectivity of inhibitors, even in cases involving unknown structures or mutated kinases”.
De acordo com os autores do estudo, os ensaios validaram o poder preditivo do modelo, demonstrando que cinco compostos sugeridos pelo MMCLKin inibem de forma eficaz uma mutação associada a doenças neurodegenerativas, sendo quatro deles activos em concentrações nanomolares.
“These results reinforce the potential of MMCLKin as a tool to accelerate the development of targeted therapies, opening new perspectives for the rational design of drugs with greater selectivity and clinical efficacy”, reads the statement.
According to the researchers, the proposed approach represents an advance in the application of AI to drug discovery, demonstrating how new generation computational models can reproduce 'in silico' complex biological processes that, experimentally, can take years or even decades. This capability allows for the rapid identification of promising therapeutic candidates, significantly reducing the time and cost of pharmaceutical research.
In addition to its immediate impact, it opens up new directions of research in the field of kinase modeling by providing a unified framework for analyzing structural, mutational and functional patterns across the entire family of human kinases.
“This type of approach can evolve into generalist models capable of anticipating the behavior of new kinases – including those without an identified structure – and supporting the rational design of selective and personalized therapies in diverse areas, from cancer to neurodegenerative diseases.”
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Recycled water for 9,000 households in Seac Pai Van and UM</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/agua-reciclada-para-9-000-agregados-em-seac-pai-van-na-um/</link><description>The construction work on the first phase of the Coloane Recycled Water Station has basically been completed, with tests on various systems currently taking place, the director of the Maritime and Water Affairs Services (DSAMA) said yesterday. As revealed, according to the current assessment, the objective is for recycled water to begin to be supplied from March 1st next year to around 9,000 households in public housing in Seac Pai Van and at the University of Macau (UM). Susana Wong also stated that, starting next month, the organization will install publicity posts and distribute pamphlets in the respective areas. Regarding the prices of this type of water, the director of DSAMA said that the authorities continue to evaluate the issue with interested parties and will publish the values ​​in due time. Reiterating that recycled water will be slightly cheaper than tap water, Susana Wong indicated that prices will also have two categories, namely one for domestic use and the other for commercial use. Also on the sidelines of a meeting with the 12th Customer Liaison Group of Macau Water, Kuan Sio Peng, executive director of the company, predicted that water consumption in the territory could rise by 3% in 2026, justifying this possible situation by the successive reception of residents in public housing in Zone A of Novos Aterros and in housing in lot P in Areia Preta, and by the opening of new hotels in COTAI.</description><pubDate>2025-12-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Muscular young women from Japan seek to break the usual beauty standards</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/jovens-musculadas-japao-procuram-quebrar-os-padroes-de-beleza-habitual/</link><description>Hitomi Harigae, 38, manager of Muscle Girls, a fitness-themed bar, flexes during a dance performance in Tokyo, Japan, July 25, 2025. "I remember to this day when I first realized that I was fine just as I was, and how my self-esteem shot up," Harigae said of her early days in the bar. REUTERS/Kim Kyung-Hoon

SEARCH "KYUNG-HOON MUSCLE GIRLS" FOR THIS STORY. SEARCH "WIDER IMAGE" FOR ALL STORIES. TPX IMAGES OF THE DAY



A dozen women in sporty tops and tight shorts stood behind a U-shaped counter in an underground bar in a busy Tokyo neighborhood, showing off their statuesque bodies as they crushed grapefruits in unison with their bare hands.
Music played loudly and neon lights flashed against a hot pink background as patrons of the Muscle Girls fitness-themed bar screamed and cheered, jockeying for space to record the ritual on their smartphones.
“Most people in Japan generally consider women with small breasts, slender backs and slender legs to be attractive,” said Hitomi Harigae, manager of the bar, which features only female artists. “The customers who come here are different,” he explains.
Challenging conventional ideals of female beauty in Japan, the bar, which opened in mid-2020, attracts an average of around 100 customers a day, mostly foreign tourists, and has gone viral on social media.
A fee of 6,000 yen (almost 310 patacas) for 80 minutes includes a protein shake and all-you-can-eat drinks, while staff, showing off their muscular physiques, put on a show on stage, and others, in leopard-print bikinis, smile as they do push-ups and pole dances. Customers can also pay for extras, such as being slapped hard in the face or being lifted by the thighs.
“Femininity can be muscular and doesn’t have to be defined by delicacy, smallness, silence and not taking up space,” said Aubrey Lee, a tourist from Los Angeles.
Among major developed nations, Japan has the highest proportion of underweight adult women, around 9%, or nearly five times higher than its peers in the US and Germany in terms of body mass index, according to the OECD.
This year, a Japanese panel of doctors and academics who study obesity warned that the convention of equating female thinness with beauty leads to malnutrition and other health problems that need to be addressed. But this “norm” is challenged by the approximately 30 women who work at Muscle Girls, who are passionate about bodybuilding and CrossFit, some of whom sport defined abs that would shame many men.
“I still remember to this day when I realized I was fine as I was and how my self-esteem soared,” Harigae, 38, said of his first days at the bar.
For her, Muscle Girls is a gift that fosters a sense of sisterhood as the women exchange diet and training tips. Even on her days off, Harigae goes to rotations and nail salons with her colleagues.
Women's bodybuilding has gained popularity in Japan in recent years, with competitions held in many cities. But outside this circle, old conventions still prevail.
“When I talk to friends from school, I still notice that they are very stuck in these fixed ideas – they want to be thin,” said Harigae.
However, these views, partly derived from gender stereotypes, may be changing, albeit slowly. A 2023 poll by think tank Dentsu Soken showed that 38.2% of respondents said “men should be masculine and women should be feminine”, a drop from 43.7% in 2021.
“Female beauty is not limited to thinness,” said Yuka Moriya, who joined the bar in 2023 and is inspired by colleagues who are passionate about bodybuilding, pole dancing or simply physical activities.
“I wish more people appreciated the beauty of muscles,” added Moriya, a bodybuilder who aspires to win competitions and eventually become the best in Japan.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-12-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>