<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Caeal appeals to candidacies to prepare campaign</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/caeal-apela-as-candidaturas-para-prepararem-campanha/</link><description>20 days from the beginning of the campaign for legislative elections, the Electoral Affairs Committee launches the refers to the candidacies to prepare that period, which starts on the 30th. On the other hand, Caeal announced that about 116,000 people visited or consulted the various information channels about the legislatives. "We see an increase in the number of people, who pay more attention to this year's elections," said the president
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The visit to the information sites made available to update the procedures for elections to the 14 September Legislative Assembly seems to reflect an increase in interest to this year, to evaluate the rise in the number of research and consultations, considered the chairman of the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal).
Judge Seng Ioi Man indicated yesterday at a press conference that, until the 11th, about 116,000 people visited the various channels to find out where they will vote. "We see an increase in the number of people, who pay more attention to this year's elections," said Seng Ioi Man, reiterating that "people are more aware of the information that is released." Among the research sites, highlight the single account, the Caeal website and the telephone system made available to residents.
It is recalled that in the last electoral act, in 2021, when 21 candidates were disqualified by “not defending the basic law or not being faithful to MSAR”, Macau then recorded the highest abstention rate of 57.6%.
The official said, on the other hand, to expect the applications to “take good time to plan and prepare the bests to be” the government's channels and advertising platforms. In addition, "in conjunction with other means of propaganda to be made with their own resources, candidacies may, within 14 campaign days, expose and present their political programs, to raise voters support on election day."
In other aspects related to Caeal's work, it was reported that, as regards the designation of the candidacy lists, pursuant to the electoral law, each is entitled to designate, for each voting assembly, an effective delegate and another substitute.
To supervise voting activities, these delegates “must have active electoral capacity,” according to the committee, which adds that “these delegates can only represent a list of candidacy and exercise the right of delegate in only one voting assembly”.
The representatives must present, between August 16 and 25, the list of delegates so that Caeal can issue the appropriate certificative documents, which must be raised by the agent up to two days before the date of elections at the service counter.
The body that oversees the act that will elect the new team of deputies for the AL recalls that during the voting period, each application can only be present a delegate in a single vote assembly. If the effective delegate is not present, this can be replaced by the designated alternate.
With the objective of facilitating the inspection work and the exercise of the right of vote of the delegates themselves, Caeal has deliberated that they will vote in the voting assembly for which they were highlighted. "Thus, on the one hand, they can do their inspection work in this vote meeting, and on the other hand to exercise the right to vote in the same meeting," said Seng Ioi Man.
 
Accompanied activities outside Macau
About illegalities committed until this time, the official said they remain in 18.
Asked if he is aware of activities that are being developed by associations abroad of Macao, number one of the Commission said that “our electoral law does not apply only to MSAR, so there are mechanisms of cooperation with not only local authorities, but as well as the law enforcement and execution authorities will also follow if there are such activities outside”.
In order to deepen voters' knowledge about how to vote and the vote secret, CAEAL has produced two videos to “simply and lively” the voting procedures and some observations. The opening period of the voting assemblies will be between 9h00 and 21h00.
The second video addresses the secret of voting, noting that the entire electoral process is confidential, with no form of identification of the respective bulletin. There are no surveillance appliances in the areas of the voting assembly, nor in the booths.
Under the terms of the electoral law, up to a certain area outside the voting assembly, the voter cannot reveal his voting intention, and the use of mobile phones or other communication equipment, as well as the capture of images. "At the time of the vote, the voter cannot be filmed under penalty of violating the electoral law," said Seng Ioi Man. The videos will be available from today.
Regarding the antenna time, he confirmed that he was increased, explaining the reason: "We took into account the spending, costs and the need for advertising, based on these issues that the decision was made."
"The procedures have been successfully completed, which means that all applications have a good base to perform, under the law, electoral propaganda during the campaign period," he said, thanking the support and cooperation of the various lists that participated in the respective draw of antenna times.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CTT had a positive balance exceeding 100 million in 2024</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ctt-tiveram-saldo-positivo-superior-100-milhoes-em-2024/</link><description>Among revenues and expenses, Post and Telecommunications services ended 2024 with a positive balance of 106.7 million patacas, an increase of 123% in annual terms. Already Caixa Económica Postal made profits of 47.7 million patacas, an increase of 28%. On the other hand, local correspondence and international correspondence suffered breaks - only the sending of letters by air showed results in the opposite direction, with a 22%rise. In the same line, orders sent and received also recorded decreases. Derby Lau has stained that in the last five years, "CTT have been confronted with various tests and challenges," but they are still committed to "developing their work with commitment and based on the accumulated experiences over more than a century."
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Last year, Macau's Post Office and Telecommunications (CTT) registered a positive balance of 106.7 million patacas, including income and expenses, excluding the postal Economic Caixa accounts. A result that represents a 123% rise in annual terms or 58.8 million patacas.
According to the annual report, total revenues rose to 605.9 million patacas, an increase of 16% compared to 2023. The climb was driven mainly by the extraordinary benefits and gains, which grew more than eight times to 61.8 million, representing 10.2% of the total.
The document analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macau shows that the provision of services (postcards and telecommunications) accounted for 55% of revenues, generating 333.5 million patacas, an annual increase of 4.6%. Sales were the second fastest growing segment within one year, although they were responsible for only 5.3% of revenues, a total of 32.3 million patacas (+11.8% in annual terms).
Financial income and gains - including real estate income, interest obtained and capital participation, among others - exceeded 151 million patacas (+8.6%), equivalent to 25.1% of total revenue. In the same vein, supplementary profits also grew by 3.9% to 26.3 million, representing 4.4% of the gains.
In turn, the sale of philatelic products yielded 32 million patacas (+10%) to CTT, which launched 13 philatelic emissions. In this field, highlighting the emissions of the “Lunar Year of the Dragon”, “150th anniversary of the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center - Lunar Year of the Dragon”, “140th anniversary of the Macao Post and Telecommunications”, “50th anniversary of the inauguration of the Nobre Carvalho Governador Bridge”, “25th anniversary of the establishment of the macao of the Macao de Liberation of the Army of the Army of Army of Army of Army of Army of Army of Army of Army of Army of Army de Liberation of Army of Army de Liberation of the Army of Army of Army of Army of Army of Army de Liberation from Chinese ”.
As for expenses, the global amount was 499.2 million patacas, with a increase of 5.6% or 26.6 million in annual terms. Personnel costs represented the highest expenses, totaling 372.7 million (+5%), corresponding to 74.7% of the total.
External supplies and services, in turn, “weighed” 14.8% in the expenditure structure, having grown slightly (0.4%). This category encompasses the operating costs of the WiFi GO wireless broadband system, the Internet Information Center, the maintenance and repair of CTT facilities, the expenses paid to other postal and airline administrations to operate the postal service and the expenses necessary to maintain daily CTT operations.
Other CTT expenses were related to goods sold and consumed materials (8.4 million), other operating costs (1.8 million), year -on -year amortizations (36.6 million), among others.
CAIXA ECONOMIC POSTAL (CEP), CTT department that is managed by an administrative commission and has its own budget and accounting, noted profits of 47.7 million patacas, plus 28% or 10.5 million compared to the previous year.
At the end of 2024, the total of deposits captured by CEP fell 3% to 812 million patacas, in annual terms, but the amount of new loans (186 million) - granted to civil servants and workers from organizations and companies with which they have agreed - rose about 6%, revealed the report, while the outstanding balance, reduced 3% to 163 million.
The financial margin and the results of services and commissions were, respectively, about 61 million and 8 million patacas, with the exploration costs of 31 million.
On the other hand, the report states that the number of transactions made through the electronic payment platform was 90 thousand, still representing a reduction of about 50%. Currently, 14 government departments use the electronic payment platform as a payment method, covering about 40 online payment services.
In the opposite direction, and as the tourism sector “performed”, the volume of transactions of the exchange service increased about 15% over the previous year.
 
Falls in orders and correspondence
The report also reveals that the local correspondence volume dropped 11%, while international correspondence suffered a 15%break in the total surface, while by air rose 22%. Already the correspondence received from abroad registered a decrease of 2% by air.
"Due to the higher frequency of travel and transfronist purchases by the citizens of Macao, there is a significant decrease in the volume of rapid post office objects (EMS) and postal orders, issued and received, compared to the year 2023," the body denotes.
In concrete, last year, the volume of objects issued and received recorded a drop of 19% and 15%. The main destinations were the interior of China, Hong Kong, Taiwan, the United States and Japan, while the objects received came mainly from Japan, inland China, Taiwan, Hong Kong and Canada. The service covers about 200 countries and regions.
In a message, CTT director Derby Lau notes that in the last five years, "CTT have been confronted with various tests and challenges." "During the pandemic period, when successive interruptions in the global logistics chain were having a serious impact on the normal functioning of the services provided, we were able to create new postal routes through cooperation with different partners; and while transportation costs were constant, we insisted on maintaining our prices and unchanged fees," he recalled.
Derby Lau also reaffirmed the intention of the CTT "continuing to develop their work with commitment and based on the accumulated experiences over more than a century." "We will assume as a mission to improve the well-being of citizens and exercise all activities with usual professionalism, opening a new chapter of our history," he said.
By stressing that CTT continues to “optimize” their postal infrastructure, expanding the postal network and striving to provide “more diverse” postal services, the report states that, by the end of last year, the Macao Postal Network was made up of the central station, 13 Postal Stations, a filately store, a store in the Museum of Communications, a Centro and Central Service Post and Central Station Self-service postcard.
 
More than 32,500 entries to the Communications Museum
The Museum of Communications accounted for in 2024 a total of 32,519 entries, “with most belonging to school groups and organizations with prior visit to visit,” CTT indicates in the annual work report. Of the total of 406 scheduled visits throughout the year, 74% were guided tours, workshops or electronics courses, and 26% were services to the air and in school context. While “space of experimental and interactive nature”, the museum organized in the Post Office/Filatelia and Telecommunications areas, 26 thematic guided tours, seven scientific demonstrations, 27 work workshops and five electronics courses by marking.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy made profits of five billion by June</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/galaxy-obteve-lucros-de-cinco-mil-milhoes-ate-junho/</link><description>In the first six months of the year, the Galaxy Entertainment Group made net profits of $ 5.2 billion from Hong Kong, a 19% rise compared to the results presented in the same period of 2024
 
Pedro Milheirão
 
Galaxy Entertainment Group (GEG) registered net profits of $ 5.2 billion from Hong Kong, in the first half of this year, representing a 19% increase in the same period of 2024. Until June, EBITDA (results before interest, taxes, amortization and depreciation) was 6.9 billion, 14% above the first half of last year.
In the first half of the year, the company's net revenues were over $ 23.2 billion from Hong Kong, an increase of 8.2% compared to the 2024 same period, and the game's operations contributed with 18.58 billion, according to data released by the group.
The gross revenues resulting from the game reached almost $ 23 billion from Hong Kong between January and June. Mass market tables reached 17 billion, 5.88% more than in the first half of last year. The VIP segment recorded gains of 4.4 billion (+63.2%, in annual terms) and the 1.5 billion electronic games (+19.05%).
During the first half, Galaxy Macau, GEG's main venture, obtained net revenues of Hong Kong's $ 19.1 billion, translated into an annual rise of 13%, and Ebitda gains of 6.3 billion (+18%). Starworld Macao had net revenues of 2.4 billion, 10% less than last year, and EBITDA gains of 653 million (-21%). At the end of June, cash money and net investments were 30.7 billion, with debts worth 0.4 billion.
Francis Lui, president of GEG, said the company continues to “leverage the competitive advantage” of the Galaxy Arena and its facilities for Conventions and Exhibitions (MICE). "In the last two years, it has been proven that entertainment shows and events have played a key role in conducting new and recurring clients to Macau," he said in a statement.
"During the first half of 2025, we held a total of approximately 190 entertainment events, sports and MICE, and experienced an annual increase of 65% traffic at Galaxy Macao," he said. "We remain optimistic about the mega tourist mega for the second half of the year," he added.
According to Francis Lui, the company entered a new development phase, which includes unpublished hotel brands in Macao, an amphitheater of about five thousand seats, a casino and restaurants, among other enterprises. "We continue to evaluate development opportunities in the great bay and in foreign markets," he said. "As always, GEG keeps totally committed to leaving a positive contribution to the Macao Tourism and Leisure industry," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Banks received 2,000 loans since April</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/bancos-receberam-2-000-pedidos-de-emprestimos-desde-abril/</link><description>The president of the Banks Association, IP Sio Kai, revealed that since the launch of the Bank Credit Interest Bonus Plan for SMEs in mid -April, banks received 2,000 loan requirements, including 80% involving new loans. According to it, if all these requirements receive “green light”, they will involve more than three billion of Patacas
 
Since mid -April this year, when the Bank Credit Bottle Plan was launched for Small and Medium Enterprises (SME), Macao banks have received about 2,000 loan requirements, of which 80% requested new loans and 20% are related to “request for new loans to reimburse old loans,” said IP Sio Kai, president of the Banks Association of Banks Macau (ABM).
Quoted by the newspaper “or Mun”, IP Sio Kai said that if all requirements are approved, they will result in more than three billion. In addition, he noticed that more than half of the quotas is still available for requests from companies.
It is recalled that qualified SMEs may require the bonus of credit interest through banks. The maximum amount of credits to be granted to each commercial entrepreneur is five million Patacas, with a maximum bonus period of three years and the maximum limit of the annual bonus rate of 4%. The maximum limit of the total amount of the credits to be bonus is 10 billion patacas.
According to IP Sio Kai, the 2,000 loans are concentrated on traditional sectors, such as restoration, retail sale, thick sale, construction, representing more than 70% of requirements. In addition, Big Health, High Technology, Culture, Sport and Entertainment industries were also received.
For the president of ABM, the fact that requests for new loans occupy 80% reflects the confidence of companies in continuous operation, while the existence of requirements related to “reimbursement of old loans through new ones” is in line with the government's guidance to support the development of SMEs.
The deputy also believes that the interest bonus plan provides support for companies to develop emerging sectors, following a transformation plan. In addition, it can help some companies solve urgent problems.
According to the associative leader, banking institutions will continue to publicize this plan to the industrial and commercial sector, hoping to be able to bring to the respective plan, especially to Big Health, high -tech companies, among other emerging industries.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing calls for “fair” agreement on Ukraine</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/pequim-pede-acordo-justo-sobre-ucrania/</link><description>China yesterday expressed satisfaction for contacts between the United States and Russia before Friday's summit in Alaska, and asked “all stakeholders” to participate in peace negotiations over Ukraine at the appropriate time.
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian said Beijing “is pleased to see Russia and the United States maintain contact, improve their relations and advance in the process of political solution” of the crisis.
In a statement quoted by EFE agency, he also indicated that Beijing hopes that the conversations will lead “as soon as possible” to a “fair, lasting and binding” agreement on Ukraine, acceptable to all parties involved.
Asked about the absence of Ukraine and the European Union at the meeting, Lin did not comment on the validity of any agreements reached without these parts and merely said that Beijing “awaits” his participation “at the proper time” in the conversation process.
The meeting between US presidents Donald Trump and Russia, Vladimir Putin, is scheduled for Friday, August 15, in Alaska, with the war in Ukraine as a central theme.
Donald Trump said on Monday that Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky "could" attend the meeting with Russian leader in Alaska, but expressed skepticism about whether such a peace agreement would be cleared.
"[Zelensky] is not part. I would say he could go, but has been in many meetings. He knows, he has been there for three and a half years. Nothing happened," Trump told reporters at the White House.
"We will have a meeting with Vladimir Putin and, at the end of this meeting, probably in the first two minutes, I will know exactly whether an agreement can be closed or not," Trump added.
Recently, several European leaders have warned that "the path to peace in Ukraine cannot be decided without Ukraine," while the United Kingdom stressed that it will support contacts, but stressed that "one cannot trust at all" in Putin.
India, in turn, supported the realization of the summit, considering it an opportunity to advance towards a ceasefire, despite its own commercial frictions with Washington.
Putin, however, has maintained in recent days telephone conversations with his main allies-including leaders of China, India and Brazil-to inform them about summit plans and raise support for their positions before the meeting with Trump.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 100 operated to the Falls at the Islands Hospital</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-de-100-operados-as-cataratas-hospital-das-ilhas/</link><description>The “Peking Union Medical College Hospital” outpatient surgery model was implemented at the Islands Hospital. The new system will allow a more convenient treatment for elderly patients with vision problems. Within a month, this hospital unit performed surgeries to cataracts to more than 100 patients
 
For the sake of the needs of the inhabitants, under the organization of health services, the Ilhas Hospital and the Conde de São Januário Hospital Ophthalmology Service have maintained a narrow collaboration. Since mid-July, three surgeons from both hospitals have been operating at the Cataracts at the Islands Hospital daily, and so far, interventions have been performed in more than 100 patients, helping them recover their vision.
The Islands Hospital adopted the outpatient surgery model, in force for several years in the department of ophthalmology of the “Peking Union Medical College Hospital”. The implementation of the new system will allow, on the day of operation, eligible patients may be admitted, operated and receive discharge within a maximum of three hours, according to a statement from the island hospital. Exceptionally, patients who cannot be discharged on the same day may be admitted and, after a new consultation with the responsible surgeon, have discharged the next day.
The hospital states that the new service model aims to offer convenience to the elderly who need surgery. For cases of surgery to the most complex Falls, the hospital unit will be supported by experts from “Peking Union Medical College Hospital”, reinforcing cooperation between Beijing and Macau in the treatment of ophthalmological health. The “expert group with extensive experience” will ensure “the quality and medical security of the Islands Hospital”.
The continuous optimization of the Cataract Surgery Service and the gradual integration of personnel from all departments will allow the islands hospital to serve a growing number of patients with cataracts, with “real benefits for Macao residents”. Currently, the aging of the MSAR population is increasingly evident and many people over 60 begin to have vision problems.
 
Open registrations for course on physical and mental health
As part of the establishment of the Family Medicine Training Base, which is intended to form qualified conditions in the health area, health services (SSM) announced that the “Physical and Mental Health Training Course in Community Health Care” runs until April 2026. With 10 modules and trainers of the Hong Kong Family Family College, the course is directed to local health professionals, being the participation, being the participation, being participation free. Trainees who complete eight or more course modules will receive a certificate issued by the SSM. The activity has already been included in the continuous professional development program, and participation is free. Registration takes place until August 20, and the vacancies are limited.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Southeast Asian flavors arrive at Zape</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sabores-sudeste-asiatico-chegam-ao-zape/</link><description>The initiative “Zape with Flavors” begins at the end of this week, which will extend until the 24th of this month. Under the theme “Flavors of Street Food on Food Truck”, visitors will have rulots and dozens of newsstands with food from Southeast Asia
 
The gastronomic fair “Zape with Flavors” starts this Friday, with more than 30 newsstands and six rulots of food from Southeast Asia, in the pedestrian zones of Cantão Street and Shanghai Street, according to the Tourism Services Directorate (STD). Until August 24, between 3:30 pm and 10 pm, the event will bring together local traders under the theme "Flavors of Street Food in Food Truck".
In addition to a hundred meals places, the fair will also have performances, contests, promotions and photograph facilities, including “a large claw machine”. For every 100 patacas spent on purchases, visitors will be able to participate “in a claw game to take toys”, the higher the consumption value, the greater the number of offers.
Throughout the event, local artists and associations will present dances and songs, “providing visitors and residents diverse experiences of‘ Tourism + Gastronomy + Consumption ’and fostering the flow of people and consumption in the area”, says the statement. The fair will combine “diversified gastronomy” and cultural and creative elements, taking advantage of the space of the outer port landfills (Zape), “to show the community of Macau”.
During the fair days, the promotion will be made through an excursion to the area, which will include digital influencers from the interior of China and foreigners to publicize the event. At the same time, STD will collaborate with “large scale” Chinese tourism platforms, create a theme page about Macao Tourism and launch exclusive promotions.
STD expects residents and tourists to “experience accommodation in hotels and consumption in community neighborhoods, promote the night economy, stimulate the community economy and streamline tourism in Zape”. The government intends to stimulate the flow of people in the area, introducing international intellectual property, extending the economic benefits of concerts, maximizing the space for activities and optimizing the environment of the area, according to STD.
Tourism authorities and the General Association of Overseas Chinese of Macao, co-organizers of the fair, maintain communication and cooperation with the community, taking into account the life of the population and the surrounding environment “as important factors”.
Recently, the organization has held a meeting with local trade associations "to explain the content of this activity and collect opinions, continuing to maintain full communication with the stakeholders of the area." The objective was "to ensure the undertaken of the activity and minimize the impact caused to neighboring residents."
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“The astonishing and curious travel” in CCCM</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/as-espantosas-curiosas-viagens-patente-cccm/</link><description>The exhibition “The Slazing and Curious Travel”, evident at the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) in Lisbon, extending until August 17, according to the newspaper or Mun. The Chinese language diary highlights the words of CCCM president Carmen Mendes, at the inauguration, stressing that the initiative is in line with the mission of the Portuguese institution to promote cultural ties between Portugal and China, with Macao as a meeting point.
The duo formed by local visual anthropologist Cheong Kin Man and Cracovian artist Marta Stanisława Sala presents seven joint works, five of which unpublished, the result of four years of collaborative work on translingism. The exhibition includes various supports, such as textile, video and graphic work, advocating sustainability and collective memory through the reuse of fabric remains.
The “Entrevista, MięDzy-Widzenie, Roz-Mowa, Despositivation” With automatic subtitles in various languages, generated by artificial intelligence and with purposeful errors, the work is accompanied by a book of artists. In the form of a Portuguese dictionary for Polaco, the volume presents, a photographer the photogram and word The Word, an interview excerpt held in 2009, in Rio de Janeiro, by Cheong and Flora Fong Pui Wa to the Iana and Ísis D'Assumpção sisters.
Unpublished material was sponsored by the Cultural Institute, the International Institute of Macau and Fred Martins Ltda, having the logistical support of the Macaense Memory Project, by Rogério P. D. Luz.
The show interconnects geographies and languages, crossing personal and collective memories, with connection points between Macau, Poland, Portugal, Brazil, Germany and Colombia. One of the featured works is “The Utopia compass”, a textile installation and bamboo structure inspired by the verses of local poet Sin Iok Cheng (Xian Yuqing, 1895-1965).
The work uses six chromatic maps to represent the six shades of the singing, intertwining the clandestine arrival of Cheong's parents in the 1970s and 1980s with illustrations by the Jesuit Polaco Jesuit Miguel Boym and narratives of adventurer Conde Benyowsky.
The curatorship is in charge of Colombian researcher Lorena Tabares Salamanca, who proposes an “immersive” experience, where the public is invited to cross layers of memory, travel and imagination.
At the invitation of Duo Cheong and Sala, the exhibition also includes works by German director Deborah Uhde, who dialogue with the show's central themes.
The exhibition has the institutional support of the Poland and Colombia embassies in Lisbon, with the partners the Ministry of Culture and National Heritage of Poland, the Goethe Institute of Portugal, the Krakow City Council, the Boym Institute of Poland and the Babel Cultural Association of Macao.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Economist suggests non -permanent BIR for imported paintings</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/economista-sugere-bir-nao-permanente-para-quadros-importados/</link><description>Given that the government will launch this year the 3rd edition of the Qualified Board Capture Program, economist Samuel Tong argued that authorities must implement painting plans at different levels to respond to the demand for Sreight, Medium and Long Term Economic Development. Quoted by the Citizen Journal, also president of the Macau Management Institute proposed, in this context, a program of capturing specialized elite staff with permanent residence permit in Macao, with a view to meeting the needs of short and medium -term economic development and, on the other, relieving the financial charges of the executive derived from the social benefits he will have to pay. This is because if there is a plan of the genre, the government will not need to support the whole set of social benefits enjoyed by permanent residents. In your opinion, as MSAR is a micro-economic, it requires more dynamic and accurate models for capturing qualified frames, not being able to import a large number of talents such as practice in many other regions. On the other hand, Samuel Tong praised the government's decision to create two interdepartmental working groups, in order to “capture, use well and retain pictures”. From their perspective, the two groups can provide staff support services, helping them to better know the “1+4” industries in the territory and the updated policies of MSAR, as well as deal with housing and educational issues for their children, so that frames can focus on work.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“M Plus” with English football rights</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/m-plus-direitos-de-transmissao-de-futebol-ingles/</link><description>The "M Plus Sports Media Company" guaranteed the exclusive rights of transmission of the "Premier League" and the England Cup, for the seasons 2025/2026 to 2027/2028, according to a statement. Over the next three seasons, “M Plus” will broadcast English league games and live Cup live, through its application and on the 34, 35, 36 and 37 channels of Macao television. In addition to matches, with comments in English or Cantonese, magazine programs, real-time news, post-game analysis and other support programs will be available. The games calendar is available on the company's website, where interested parties can also unload the application. The “M Plus Sports Media Company” is the only provider of live broadcast platform services for sports events at MSAR. According to the statement, "the company will continue to boost technological innovation and actively introduce more high -level international sports events, providing the high -level immersive visualization experiences anytime, anywhere." In addition to English football, the company conveys a variety of sporting events and original programs for the public in Macao and neighboring regions.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM features “innovative” model to create new medicines</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/upm-apresenta-modelo-inovador-para-criar-novos-medicamentos/</link><description>The team at the Drug Discovery Center driven by Artificial Intelligence from the Macao Polytechnic University (UPM) presented an innovative method for the intelligent conception of medicines. The group, which is part of teachers Liu Huanxiang and Yao Xiaojun and doctoral student Yang Yuwei, developed the “DIFFMC-Gen” model, which integrates deep learning technology and molecular generation technology, UPM said. The investigation was presented in the article “DIFFMC-GEN: a double-eliminated noise elimination model for the multicondondial molecular generation”, published in Advanced Science, and provides new ideas for “promoting the new generation of artificial intelligence-driven drug discovery”. AI is used “to improve the ability to design and optimize molecules,” explains the university. At an early stage of drug development, there are several factors to take into account, such as “the affinity of the molecule to the target, the structural novelty, the similarity of drugs and synthetic viability”. The “DIFFMC-GEN” model consists of a “more stable molecular generation process” and optimization of evaluation criteria such as drug similarity, synthetic viability and the risk of toxicity, among others.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Industrial Park location will be the target of public consultation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/localizacao-de-parque-industrial-sera-alvo-de-consulta-publica/</link><description>A public consultation on the location and direction of the development of the construction project of the Macao Sciences and Technologies Industrial Park of Research and Development is planned, the secretary said for the economy and finance, in a meeting of the working group. Quoted in a statement, Tai Kin IP stressed that the park "will constitute a key engine to support the proper diversification of Macao's economy, being, currently being intensified of previous studies and logistics arrangements." In particular, he said, it is being focused on “continuous improvement of processes” and “simplification of expendable administrative procedures”, among other matters. Presided by the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, this was the first meeting of the group, and issues related to the promotion of planning and the construction of the park was discussed. Sam Hou Fai stressed that the park is an “important project to optimize the technological innovation environment” and added that it is up to the various public services to “promote, proactively and pragmatically, the planning and preparation of the park”. At the same time, during the park preparation phase, “one should study and formulate a general legal system, providing support and supports, to provide systematic support to technological companies that settle in the park,” said the leader of the MSAR. At the meeting were present, among others, the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, and the chairman of the Administrative Council of the Institute for Commerce and Investment Promotion, Che Weng Keong.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2453/</link><description>Detained for assaulting, stealing and taking illicit photographs
A 34 -year -old man from the interior of China was arrested by the Judiciary Police (PJ), following threatening a casino player, having taken naked and stolen photographs 69,000 Renminbis. According to the PJ, the suspect and the victim met in a casino in Cotai, at dawn yesterday. Later, the two met in a hotel room, having been assaulted and injured with a knife. The man was sent to the prosecutor accused of theft, unjustified use of weapon and other instruments, recordings and illicit photographs, and the wanton of private life.
 
Smallest found dead in the southern street of Patane
A minor resident was found dead Monday night on the platform of a building in Southern Patane Street. According to the Judicial Police (PJ), the young woman will have fallen from a high place, which has caused her death. The PJ stated that no injuries were found caused by acts of violence or criminal origin.
 
DSAT studies viability of tours widening
The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) is currently studying the feasibility of progressive widening of the tours near Avenida da República and Street of S. Tiago da Barra. At the same time, it performs coordination with the competent services for the joint optimization of the pedestrian environment in this area. In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Lo Choi In, DSAT reports that the works are included in the General Traffic Planning and Macao Land Transport (2021-2030) related to the construction of a network intended for pedestrians only, "continuing with the continuous improvement of the pedestrian environment."</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Medieval trip took to the fair 70 thousand in one day and had a thousand inhabitants to act</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/viagem-medieval-levou-a-feira-70-mil-num-so-dia-teve-mil-habitantes-actuar/</link><description>The “Medieval Travel”, which ended Sunday in Santa Maria da Feira, after a 13 -day edition, received 70,000 visitors in a single journey and involved more than 1,000 inhabitants of the county in its 96 shows.
The organization of the historical recreation that involves a budget of 2.3 million euros by the said Aveiro district autarchy and Porto Metropolitan Area highlights, in the initiative balance, the greatest breakdown and fluidity of the city's traffic, even on the highest days, thanks to the availability of about 10,000 parking spaces next to the different entrances.
"The medieval trip maintained an average daily influx of 40,000 to 60,000 visitors and on the second Saturday more than 70,000 people visited the event. Final numbers similar to previous editions and the excess of heat in a few days penalized the afternoons, but every night were strong," said the mayor of the fair, Amadeu Albergaria.
The mayor also pointed out that of the 60 entities that ensure the different areas of activity of the event, about 40 are from the fair and this meant that, among protagonists and extras, "over 1,000 feirenses participated in shows and performances in this edition."
In the list of the most demanded shows are included, according to the mayor, “the last crusader” for its “technical and aesthetic dimension, impact and spectacularity”; “The Count of the Fair”, for the “lightness and empathy that generated in the public and families”; “Once upon a time… D. Afonso V”, which celebrated “10 years of continuous participation on the trip”; and “The Great Tournament”, with French acrobatic cavalry that “led the audience to the red in numerous sold out”.
As for thematic areas, part of which requiring paid entry beyond the general access ticket to the enclosure, Amadeu Albergaria highlighted Lusa three: the Convent of Loios Museum with its various activities, which reached growth of more than 50% compared to the previous year; The baths of São Jorge, where there was an increase of more than 12% in the number of visitors and a “growing search for massage” besides the base circuit; and “The Granja dos Animals”, with “an affluence largely higher than last year”, especially from the first Saturday of the event.
Dates for the 2026 trip is not yet, but the mayor ensures that the edition that will mark the 30th anniversary of the event will again have the special and voluntary participation of the so -called “children of the trip”, that is, all people born in Santa Maria da Feira since 1996.
“The exciting way as this year's medieval journey began, with the participation of the children of the trip in a contemporary opening show, will be forever in memory and played all those who were part of this production,” argues Amadeu Albergaria.
According to data from the organization in July, the budget of 2.3 million euros for the 2025 edition represented a reinforcement of 600,000 compared to 2024 and should be “fully paid for the recipes generated by the event”, namely bracelets and entrance tickets, space rentals, sponsorship and merchandising.
Last year, when the budget was 1.9 million euros, the trip faced 2.2 million, which contributed more than 650,000 entries, an average of 50,000 visitors per day. This year, the municipality did not make available the requested invoicing data.
 
JTM/LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>