<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Expecting associations to keep in contact with Marcelo on the visit to</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/associacoes-expectantes-para-manter-contacto-marcelo-na-visita-a-raem/</link><description>The President of the Republic, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa (D) Conversation with local sellers during a walk from foot from Leal Senate to the ruins of the São Paulo Church, this morning in Macao, China 1 May 2019. The President. da República, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa is from April 26 to May 1 on a state visit to the Popular Republic of China. Miguel A. Lopes/Lusa



The trip to Macao of the President of the Portuguese Republic, at the time of the celebrations of Portugal Day, Camões and the Portuguese communities, was received with great satisfaction. Associations want to take advantage of Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa's time to stay in the territory to maintain contacts and address the real situation of the community. The Portuguese head of state will not be present at the ceremonies to be held on June 10, and should be moved immediately before or after that date
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Six years after he was in Macao, a two-day stop towards Beijing, inserted on a state visit to the Popular Republic of China, at the invitation of Xi Jinping, Portuguese President Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa again traveling again to the territory. The objective of this time is the participation in the celebrations of Portugal, Camões and the Portuguese communities, which takes place on 10 June.
According to news released by the Presidency's Office, the dates of the visit are still unknown, and may be immediately before or after June 10, since precisely on this day Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa will be presiding over the official celebrations, which this year will be held this year in the Algarve city of Lagos.
The novelty of travel to the territory was well received by responsible from some Portuguese matrix associations or entities linked to the Lusa community.
The Portuguese Consul General in Macao and Hong Kong told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that it is “an honor that the president decided this year to associate the Portuguese community of Macao with the June 10th celebration program”. For Alexandre Leitão, the choice of territory "is a huge joy for a career diplomat and it is always a great honor to work on the visit of a head of state."
The maximum representative of Portugal at Mashes is sure that the move of Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa will be seen by the Portuguese community as “a moment of recognition of its dimension, its relevance”. "That's why I think it's a very positive moment," he added.
About the program, the ambassador did not want to advance details, "because this will have to be worked with the embassy in Beijing and the Civil House of the President of the Republic, in the composition of the visit." As the president will come before or after, from June 10, it is possible that the reception to the Portuguese community will take place “by the time Marcelo meets in Macao,” says Alexandre Leitão.
The expectation of direct contact with Portuguese matrix associations is mirrored by Amelia António, president of the House of Portugal in Macau. The leader told JTM that “June, Portugal's month” has been systematically celebrated in Macao “with great commitment from the associations and the consulate, among others”, and is therefore the opinion that the coming of the Portuguese president “is A reinforcement and way of giving credibility, strength and encouragement to an effort that has been done to make the work developed more visible to highlight the presence of culture in Macao. ”
Amelia António considers that the Portuguese president's direct contact with the associations is very important. "This will be fundamental for him to realize the real situation, because in Portugal there is often little the notion of reality," he noted. "Perhaps because Macau is far away, we have had evidence of the lack of knowledge that reveals itself in many attitudes by the Portuguese government and the lack of support for many important things," he lamented.
On the other hand, it states that Sam Hou Fai's visit to Portugal would be “a very important step, because with some of the measures that were taken, in the previous two years, I think it was essential to replace and highlight the importance of the Portuguese in the area of Knowing, culture, teaching, a number of things that are missing Macao and that a trip to Portugal may help to replace a certain balance that is being missed. ”
In turn, Jorge Fão, president of the General Assembly of the Association of Retirees, Reformed and Pensioners of Macao (Apomac), says he is “very good for Macau” and expects the Portuguese president, “who will also reform”,, also Go this time to Apomac. “Never has it been there and I think our around 800 associates deserve it, since it is a community that is not small,” he says.
 
Expected “synergies”
Miguel de Senna Fernandes, president of the Macanese Instruction Promoter Association, speaks of “development of synergies”, relating the trip of the Portuguese head of state to a territory led by someone who speaks the language of Camões. "It may be symbolic, but the fact that there is a maximum leader, who appears at a fantastic time to Macao, after the complicated years of the pandemic, to communicate in Portuguese, that is a very large breath," he says. "From then on synergies develop and this is important."
António José de Freitas also told JTM that Marcelo's visit is “a very special meaning”, recalling the passage of the Portuguese President in Macau in 2019. “It was a visit from which I keep intense memories, having had the honor of The The Honor Receive as a provider at the Host Casa da Misericórdia building, ”he recalled. At that time, it goes on, "we have signed its presence on the time of the 450th anniversary of our institution, with the unveiling of a commemorative tombstone."
In this second visit, “we will have the immense honor of receiving President Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, if he provided herself,” he continued, talking about an “old friend of Santa Casa and Macau, with a relationship with our city that dates from 1980s of the last century, when he taught law at the University of Macao (then designated University of East Asia) ”.
The provider considers that “we are facing winds so will be favorable to reinforce the deeply rooted relations between Macau and Portugal and, in general, for the ties between Portugal and the Popular Republic of China, which celebrate, for these days, the 46th anniversary of the establishment of diplomatic relations, ”he concludes.
 
Evident sign of the relationship between Portugal and China
Paulo Canelas Castro, president of the Macao European Studies Institute, says it is this visit by Marcelo “a very significant act and a sign of the recognition of the community's role in maintaining the multisecular relationship between Portugal and China, centered on Macau, with more 500 years old, and which continues to deserve the dedication of the Portuguese community through history, even after the creation of the MSAR, ”he said.
The official of the Institute recalls that when Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa moved to Macau in 2019, said that he was always well informed about what is happening here. “He said he would go back here, which is interesting, so I say it's a symbolically very loaded act,” acknowledges Paulo Canelas Castro.
José Luís Sales Marques, chairman of the Organizing Committee of the Meeting of Macanese Communities, considers the visit “important to reinforce relations between Macao and Portugal and also at this particular moment between Portugal and China in an international context of very fast change and many uncertainties” . The economist points out that "the multisecular connection between the two sides has always been permanent, strong and stable, hence it is important to reinforce these links."</description><pubDate>2025-02-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Per capita spending of visitors suffered a new annual break</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/gastos-per-capita-dos-visitantes-sofreram-nova-quebra-anual/</link><description>The 'per capita' expense of visitors in Macao descended almost 15% between 2023 and 2024, suffering the second consecutive annual break, reveal official data, which highlight those of Singapore as the most spent and the only ones among the main markets. In absolute terms, excluding the game, the total expense exceeded 75 billion patacas, an increase of about 6% that derives from the increase in the number of visitors
 
In the general calculation of last year, the 'per capita' expense of visitors was estimated at 2,157 patacas, 14.6% less than in 2023, the Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) services reported. Despite being kept above the level of 2019 (1,626 patacas), that value represents the second consecutive annual break, after 20.8% to 2,525 patacas between 2022 and 2023.
In 2024, the trend for savings was more notorious among the excursionists, whose 'per capita' expense dropped 12.7% to 691 patacas, in annual terms. In the case of tourists, it fell 8.2% to 3,884 patacas.
According to official statistics, excluding game expenses, “purchases” absorbed 45.4% of visitors' per capita expenses, followed by “accommodation” (25.5%) and “food ”(20.9%). The 'per capita' expenses of those who came to attend shows or competitions (5,076 patacas) and participate in conventions or exhibitions (4,323 patacas) were the highest in 2024.
Among the international visitors, the 'per capita' expense reached 2,140 patacas, indicated the DSEC, without specifying the annual variation in this tourist segment. Considering the main origins of visitors only was an increase in the spending of tourists of Singapore, who even led, with 2,834 patacas, 6.6% more than in 2023.
On the other hand, the 'per capita' expenses of visitors from the interior of China (2,503 patacas), Hong Kong (1,009) and Taiwan (1,952) decreased 18.1%, 13%and 8.8%, respectively. With regard to the Chinese continent, visitors from Shanghai were the most spent, with an average of 5,572 patacas (less 17%).
In Northeast Asia, the 33.8% descents were highlighted in South Koreans (2,405 patacas) and 1.4% of the Japanese (2,093). In the southeastern Asia there were declines of 22.7% and 15% in the markets of Thailand (2,598) and Malaysia (1,992), respectively.
In absolute terms, after rising 292.2% in 2023, the total expense of visitors was headquartered by 75.36 billion patacas by 2024, an annual growth of 5.8% that derives from the increase of 23.8% increase of the number of entries in Macao (34.9 million) and that returned to exceed the amount of 2019 (64.1 billion patacas). The tours spent 13.05 billion patacas (plus 17.9%) and tourists 62.31 billion (plus 3.5%).
However, in the last quarter of 2024 the total expense decreased 0.2% to 19.15 billion patacas, in annual terms, including 16.28 billion of tourists (less 0.7%) and 2.87 billion of the excursionists (plus 2.8%). In turn, the 'per capita' expense of visitors (2,126 patacas) descended 8.2% in the annual variation, but advanced 6.2% over the previous quarter.
 
STD will promote tourism at Dubai, Riade and Berlin
By the end of this month, the teams of the Tourism Services Directorate (STD) will move to Dubai and Riade to hold Macao Tourism Promotion sessions, the STD Director said, adding that, early in March, the Body will participate in a tourism exhibition in Berlin. In addition, between April and June, STD will organize street promotions in Japan, South Korea and Southeast Asia, to attract international tourists and to the number of visitors to return to the highest registered before the pandemic. According to the Chinese language press, Helena de Senna Fernandes mentioned that tourist discounts will be released from March, including plane tickets. In addition, the government intends to adjust discounts on bus and boat tickets to be intended for international tourists. On the other hand, he revealed that they will begin to be launched, from next month, four dozen subsidized plans for community activities.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Proposed subsidy for employees who dominate Portuguese and Chinese</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/proposto-subsidio-para-funcionarios-dominem-portugues-chines/</link><description>At a meeting with André Cheong as part of the preparation of LAG, ATFPM suggested the attribution of a subsidy to public officials who dominate Portuguese and Chinese. The salary increase was another aspects addressed, along with adjustments in the various subsidies, increased transparency in the appointment of bosses and hiring doctors to São Januário and personnel to the Institute for Municipal Affairs
 
Catarina Pereira
 
There are more than two dozen suggestions that the Association of Macao Public Function Workers (ATFPM) made in the context of the administration and justice -government lines, between the adjustment of wages in the civil service, optimization and career fusion, changes, changes to subsidies, transparency in appointments to positions of leadership and promotion of the Portuguese language. The meeting with André Cheong, who took place yesterday, lasted more than an hour, said José Pereira Coutinho to this newspaper.
In a note sent to the newsrooms, the association stresses that one of the claims it has been presenting over the years "is the creation of a special subsidy for public officials who dominate both official languages." The goal, he says, "is to encourage employees whose mother tongue is Chinese to learn Portuguese, and employees whose mother tongue is the Portuguese to learn Chinese," recommending that "the promotion of the use of the two official languages ​​begins in public departments" .
The adjustment of compensation in the civil service was another of the points discussed. "We consider that the government should adjust the salaries of civil service workers in a timely manner, proposing the increase in the current 94 patacas for each index of the Indiciary Table to 97 Patacas in 2025," suggested the ATFPM, pointing, among other things, that the “Increased prices of first-need goods” led workers, “especially basic levels”, to lose purchasing power, moving to the interior of China, whether it is there to live or shop.
ATFPM also suggested the adjustment of residence, family and seniority subsidies, “due to the increase in housing, rent and cost of living” prices, and that this allowance will continue to be granted to retirees in the pension regime. On the other hand, it defended the creation of a special subsidy for security forces professionals and an annual subsidy equivalent to 100 points for grassroots employees, as well as the increase in the proportion of survival pensions from 50% to 70%.
As for retirees who transferred pensions to the Caixa Geral de Retirement in Portugal, he asked for a lifestyle, "because they all worked for a single government of Macao." In addition, the ATFPM leaders have transmitted André Cheong that “many employees wish to retire in advance, but are prevented”, so they have argued that those who have 20 years of service, enrolled in the retirement regime, be able to apply for retirement voluntary.
 
Transparency in appointments to leadership positions
In another scope, the secretary has been told that in recent years they have received "many complaints from grassroots employees about the lack of transparency in the nominations for leadership and leadership positions." In this context, ATFPM proposed the creation of an independent committee, “responsible for recruitment and promotion issues in government departments, to evaluate the qualifications of candidates in a highly transparent way and clearly explain to the public the reasons for their transfer to other departments as leaders and bosses ”.
In addition, he suggested that internal promotion be prioritized, instead of reservations of employees from other departments when leaderships appear. "We propose that, for the choice of leaders and bosses, people with professional experience and years of service in the performance of specific works of their services be named."
At the meeting, the hiring of workers was also requested to fill vacancies. In particular, it was said that “the institute for municipal affairs and health services face staff scarcity, but have not hired new employees, resulting in other colleagues to take additional functions, especially in the case of drivers”, a situation that extends to security forces.
“Considering the importance of maintaining stable human resources in health services, especially at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center (CHCSJ), it is urgent to implement a stable replacement system for medical specialists, nurses and other essential professionals who reform, resign, death or leave office for other reasons. The current system of accumulation of functions has severely impaired the quality of medical services, both in terms of time and workload and infrastructure, ”said ATFPM.
In this field, it required the career adjustment of general clinic doctors and nurses. “Due to long waiting times at CHCSJ, many citizens choose consultations at health centers, increasing workload and pressure on general practitioners. However, the starting salary of these doctors is 560 points, increasing only to 600 points after years of service, ”he said. As for nurses, vertical progression was suggested without the need for additional exams or courses.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Game below the projects in the Chinese New Year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jogo-aquem-das-projeccoes-ano-novo-chines/</link><description>Macao casinos invoiced about 6.2 billion Patacas on Chinese New Year's holidays, a lower value than official expectations, according to consultant Seport Research Partners
 
Gross Macao's gross revenues totaled about 6.24 billion patacas during Lunar New Year's Golden Week, at a daily average of 780 million, Seaport Research Partners said. The result achieved between January 28 and February 4 was “weaker than originally planned,” says the consultant, in a report signed by Vitaly Umansky.
The daily average of revenues will have descended 1% compared to the Chinese New Year of 2024 and 8% compared to the same festive season of 2019, the expert notes. Considering the same time intervals, Umansky also points out that the daily average of visitors in Macao decreased about 4% and 5%, respectively.
On the other hand, Seaport notes that, despite growing 3% to $ 593 compared to the golden week of 2024, the value of the average gross revenue of the game by visitor fell 3% compared to the Chinese New Year 2019. , the 'per capita' expense in the casinos is “a little deceiving, since Macau probably received many non -players during the holidays,” says the analyst, adding to having received information that points to a “slightly better” invoice in the "premium" game than in the "base pasta" market.
Although Casinos' performance in the new year is “an important driver of the feeling” of investors about Macao operators, Vitaly Umnsky insists that it is important to take into account the frequent “mixed” signs associated with this golden week. He stressed, the Chinese New Year accounted for 2.7% of the game's total gross revenues in 2024 and only 2% in the year before the pandemic.
Seaport Research Partners believes the Chinese New Year will be able to contribute this year with about 2.6% of global revenue. In absolute terms, it maintains the forecast of 242 billion patacas for the general calculation of 2025.
February is expected to be “slightly better than January,” anticipates Umansky, reaffirming the forecast of 18.5 billion patacas. This amount would represent an annual increase of 0.1% and a monthly growth of 1.3%.
"Our estimate assumes that, in the rest of the month, gross game revenues will have a daily average of 609 million patacas (3% above January average), which should be achievable," wrote the analyst.
If this scenario is confirmed, the casinos will be a 2.8% break in the first two months of 2025, compared to the same period last year.
In January, the game's revenues ciphed at 18.25 billion patacas, reflecting an annual descent of 5.6% and corresponding to 73.2% of the level reached in the same period of 2019, according to data released by the Board of Inspection and coordination of games.
In general, most consultants and investment homes believe that the game's gross revenues can record annual growth of about 8% to 245 billion patacas by 2025, exceeding 240 billion referenced by the government government to budget to The current year. In 2024, revenues reached almost 226.8 billion, marking an annual increase of 23.9% and equivalent to 77.5% of the result of 2019.
 
Melco's debut at Sri Lanka pointed to the third quarter
The opening of the “City of Dreams Sri Lanka” casino, which will be operated by Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, is scheduled for the third quarter of this year, announced Krishan Balendra, president of John Keells Holdings, a partner of Macao operator in this project evaluated in More than 1 billion US dollars (about eight billion patacas to the current exchange rate). Located in the capital of Sri Lanka, Colombo, the venture, so far operated under the "Cinnamon Life Integrated Resort" brand, was rebuked with the promise of "revolutionizing the luxury hotel, entertainment and leisure" in the country, according to the two companies announced the two companies in April last year. The casino zone will receive an initial investment estimated at $ 125 million (billion) and will be operated by a Singlea subsidiary fully detained by Melco, who received a license from the Sri Lanka government to explore the activity of the game for 20 years . In his company's last financial report, Krishan Balendra reiterated that a 687 -room hotel, along with restaurants and banquet rooms, began operating on 15 October last year under the "Cinnamon Life" brand.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mand will allocate more financial resources for hengqin</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/raem-vai-alocar-mais-recursos-financeiros-para-hengqin/</link><description>Macao will allocate more financial resources for the development of the in -depth cooperation zone in Hengqin, the secretary said to the economy and finance, as well as reinforcing human resources. The message was broadcast to Xia Baolong, director of Hong Kong's work office and Macao of the China Communist Party Central Committee, Xia Baolong, at a meeting that took place in the cooperation zone.
Tai Kin IP also stated that the guardianship he directs will continue to “improve the work on the definition of political measures on industrial development” and “optimize the business environment”, while committing to “capturing investment and In the provision of business services, exploring and proactively adopting more innovative and guiding economic policies. ”
Macao's “total commitment” in the construction of the in -depth cooperation zone has been reiterated, and the ruler underlined that the Mand will always keep in mind the initial objective of hengqin development ”. That is, the MSAR will promote “gradually economic synergy and articulated planning between Macau and Hengqin, with a view to raising the facilitation level of the regional circulation of elements such as qualified frames, capital, logistics and data”.
The secretary also stated that the guardianship he directs will have "a more open mindset" and "more realistic measures" in the scope of the diversification of the economy.
In addition, it also ensured that proactivity in alignment with “important national strategies” is also reinforced, namely the construction of the great bay, cooperation between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries and implementation of “expand abroad” and “attract foreign investment". Thus, Tai Kin IP pointed out, "the promotion of bilateral opening, strengthening international cooperation and economic and commercial exchange, and better playing the role of Macao at the opening of the country abroad."
At the meeting, Xia Baolong, also director of the Hong Kong and Macao affairs office with the State Council, stressed the “important speeches of President XI Jinping”, so “manders must understand their spirit” and their spirit ”and “The Chinese leader's aspirations of the best”.
 
Boss betting on strengthening cooperation with Heilongjiang
In the visit to the city of Harbin, Province of Heilongjiang, the chief executive met with the secretary of the PCC Provincial Committee, Xu Qin, and addressed the reinforcement of bilateral cooperation. Sam Hou Fai began for thanking the invitation to watch the opening of the 9th edition of the Winter Asian Games, pointing out that the opening "demonstrated to the world the organization's ability to organize major international sports events." He also stressed the “determination” of MSar to take advantage of his own platform role between China and Portuguese -speaking countries to help Heilongjiang reinforce cooperation with Lusophone countries. The leader of the MSAR intends that the two parts "further reinforce collaboration in the areas of education, tourism, sports training and traditional Chinese medical industry."</description><pubDate>2025-02-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hospital das Ilhas generates complaints</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/hospital-das-ilhas-gera-queixas/</link><description>Representative Leong Hong says he has received complaints from residents due to the “lack of specialized services” and the “long waiting time” at Hospital das Ilhas
 
Residents complained about the “lack of specialized outpatient services” and “long waiting time” at the islands hospital, Leong Hong said in written interpellation. The deputy recalled that the authorities had already revealed plans such as the opening of more specialized outpatient services and the formation of more paintings by the public hospital and health services, thus asking the progress of these work. In addition, he asked about the point of situation of acquiring “medical hardware” for the same hospital.
On the other hand, Leong Hong said that the creation of Hospital das Ilhas aims to boost the development of medical education, promoting the transformation of scientific research results into medicine, as well as “making Macau's 'golden business card brighter' brighter brilliant while 'city of medicine'. In this sense, the government urged to explain how it will make the hospital at the “Best Regional Medical Center of the Great Bay”, in accordance with Big Health + Tourism industry development orientation.
Specifically, he asked what the policies and measures to optimize the protection of medical guarantees and the privacy of international clients at Hospital das Islands, with a view to providing more timely and appropriate treatments and services.
In the same question, he questioned the situation of aesthetic medicine and vaccination services, including vaccines for pneumonia and for the prevention of cervical cancer.
Pointing out that South Korea and Thailand promote health tourism with plastic surgery and sex change surgery, argued that the islands hospital should define, in the legal regime, criteria and principles related to the aesthetic medicine services, in sense of “ensuring reasonable rights and interests of buyers and salespeople”. It also intends to know if there has already been any advance in the optimization of legal regimes in the health tourism.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Defended restrictions on “highly polluting” vehicles</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/defendidas-restricoes-para-veiculos-altamente-poluentes/</link><description>The 45% target fixed inside China for new sales of electric vehicles by 2027 would be unfeasible in Macao, considers environmentalist Joe Chan, stressing the need to restrict the circulation of more polluting vehicles and define deadlines for their progressive elimination
 
Environmentalist Joe Chan Chon Meng told Lusa that it is “absolutely impossible” Macau to follow the goal for mainland electric vehicles from 45% of new sales by 2027.
In early January, the Chinese government released a list of environmental objectives, which includes a raised review of the previous goal for electric vehicles, which was 20% to 2025. In the second half of last year, the tramons have already represented more than Half sales of new vehicles, according to data from the China Passenger Automobile Association.
In the MSAR, 31.4% of the new vehicles recorded in 2024 were electric, according to official data.
But the president of “Macau Green Student Union” stressed that fossil -powered vehicles “continue to represent a great proportion” of the territory park. At the end of December, Macau had a total of 253,182 vehicles, of which 12,302 vehicles (4.8%) were existing electric, according to the direction of services for traffic affairs (DSAT).
Still, Joe Chan stressed that in recent years, the government has implemented several measures to promote less polluting transportation, including the creation of more loading spaces for electric vehicles.
At the end of 2023, Macao had 2,100 electric charging places for light cars and 500 for motorcycles, indicated the direction of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) on its portal.
Authorities launched in 2023 a financial support plan for the slaughter of obsolete motorcycles and replacement with new electrical motorcycles, a maximum of eight thousand patacas. According to DSAT, in 2024 Macao had 128,542 motorcycles, and only 3.5% were electric, an increase of 1.4 percentage points over the previous year.
Joe Chan suggested that authorities start by restricting heavy goods from goods, namely those used in construction, and public transport, "since Zhuhai and border zones use natural gas and electricity."
On Wednesday, DSAT officials told Macau's Chinese channel that there are 929 new energy buses in operation, representing more than 92% of the total, while the proportion of more polluting buses descended to about 3%. As for taxis, there are only 210 electrical in circulation, representing about 11.9% of the total number, while hybrid taxis represent about 86.2% of the total.
"However, when it comes to highly polluting vehicles, such as trucks and heavy motorcycles, authorities have not yet defined a very clear calendar and deadline for their progressive elimination, so pollution [they cause] is high." , lamented the environmentalist.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-02-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More “golden” holidays at the airport</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/feriados-mais-dourados-aeroporto/</link><description>Contrary to the slight break in the total flow of visitors in the MSAR, the airport registered homologous increases of 5.4% in the number of passengers and 6.7% in the aircraft movement, according to Cam data
 
Macau airport received more than 170,000 passengers and accounted for 1,265 flights during Chinese New Year holidays, specifically between January 29 and February 4. The figures released by the Macao International Airport Society (CAM) represent 5.4% increase in passengers and 6.7% on flights compared to the same period of 2024, and illustrate a recovery of 80%, in both cases, Compared to the Chinese New Year in 2019, that is, before the pandemic.
The airport thus contradicted the break recorded in the total of visitors in Macao during the holidays of the year of the serpent. According to preliminary statistics revealed by the Directorate of Tourism Services, which encompass another day (January 28), the sinners welcomed 1.31 million visitors in the golden week, with the daily average down 3.5% to near 164,000 compared to the same festive time of 2024.
The peak in passenger flow occurred on the fifth and sixth day of the Chinese New Year (February 2 and 3), with the daily figures to reach about 6,000 and 25,000, respectively, reflecting 4% and 12% increase over the same period last year.
According to CAM, the routes of mainland China represented 50%of the total passenger volume, surpassing international connections (33%) and Taiwan (17%). Shanghai, Taipei and Bangkok stood out among the “frequent destinations”.
On the other hand, the airport management company stresses that the number of passengers grew 15.1% to almost 680,000 in January, in annual terms. Aircraft movements rose 8.2% to 5,261 on the same comparison base.
During the Chinese New Year period, the airport established “active” coordination with various departments and units in order to ensure “quiet” management of passenger flow and air traffic, the cam statement says, reiterating that they will continue to be launched "preferred policies to encourage airlines to increase the number of international passengers and to introduce new international routes."
 
Maritime transport with fewer passengers
During the Lunar New Year period, the volume of transfringe transport passengers recorded a slight break due to the decrease of passengers from the Shenzhen-Macau route following the opening of the “Shenzhen-Zhongshan Corridor,” said Susana Wong, director of the Services for maritime and water affairs. In the opposite direction, the number of passengers on the Wanzai-Porto Route interior rose slightly. At “peak”, that is, January 31 and February 1, the boats carried 49,000 passengers per day, and the trips between Macau and Shekou saw the daily passenger volume (about 7,400) fall 30% in Annual terms, between the 3rd and 5th day of the lunar calendar. As for the links between the RAE, Susana Wong pointed out that passenger volume was equivalent to that in the same year's same year, while the frequency of boat exits rose between 30% and 40%.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>International 10k Race again receives 10,000 athletes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/corrida-internacional-de-10k-volta-receber-10-000-atletas/</link><description>International athletes are expected to return to Macau to participate in the fifth edition of the 10 -kilometer race in athletics, promoted by the Sports Institute and sponsored by Sands China. The event, which will take place on March 16, is already open for the main test and Fun Run, about half the route. 10,000 vacancies are available, and 7,000 will be for the program-ride of the program
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Evaluating by the strong presence of Chinese, African and other regions in last year's edition, the Macau 2025 International Race should again have a strong contingent of founders, who will move to the territory to try to ease the fence award 80,000 patacas.
The event will take place on March 16, starting at Praça do Lago Sai Van, at 7 am, while the start of athletes enrolled in “Fun Run” will be given at 7:45 am. The 10K route will pass the Sai Van Bridge and the Cotai strip, ending at the Olympic Sports Center stadium.
Registration is open and will end as soon as the existing vacancies are filled. Anyone interested can apply through the Electronic Page of the Event (www.macao10k.com) or the “Macao 10k” mobile application. All individuals should have an online personal account.
Participants will be able to lift the dorsal, timing chip and notes to participants at the Olympic Sports Center - pavilion covered between March 12 and 15, upon presentation of the respective registration receipt and identification document.
The main race, wins in 2024 by Kenyans David Bett and Betty Sigei, respectively in men and ladies, who hit the record of the route, offers the winners a check of 10,000 US dollars.
Although not a high award, the competition has attracted from the beginning athletes from various countries or regions, and the places represented in the 2024 edition. This said at the press conference of presentation the president of the Institute of Sport (ID), an entity that organizes the competition in conjunction with the Athletics Association, with the sponsorship of Sands China.
Luís Gomes said the race has been welcomed “with enormous support and enthusiasm since its creation”, having expressed the hope that this event could “further boost the development of the local sports sector, involve all quadrants of society and encourage them residents and tourists to participate in events related to sport. ”
Wilfred Wong, Executive Vice President of Sands China, said the 10K International Race became a “big wingspan” sports event, always long awaited in March. Through the continuation of this race, he expects to promote “health awareness Public and widen the range of local sports events, inviting tourists from different countries and regions to experience the charm of Macao as a world center of tourism and leisure and raising the statute and international influence of mashes. ”
Chan Pou Sin, President of Agam, said that background running events cover a wide range of distances, suitable for different sports enthusiasts, believing that this competition will rely on the participation of a larger number of road running practitioners again and will “further expand the range of health -related city events”.
The popular “The Funkiest Costume Award” will continue to be held this year, being open to the participants of the two categories. Dedicated to the “Ocean Run” theme, the prize encourages athletes to incorporate oceanic elements. The objective is, according to ID, "motivating athletes to contribute to the protection of the marine environment and biodiversity."
Participants will be able to compete by introducing their data in the mobile phone application and sending a photograph of them with a fantasy, along with the respective dorsal number, from 9 am from 15 March to 9h00 the next day. To be eligible for the prize, subscribers must complete the race with their fantasies.
After the test, ten winners will be selected, which will receive several awards, including restoration coupons.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Photographic contest proposes reflection on religions in Lusophony</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/concurso-fotografico-propoe-reflexao-sobre-religioes-na-lusofonia/</link><description>The 6th edition of Somos's Photographic Contest! - Portuguese Language Communication Association (Somos - ACLP) wants to contribute to a “greater understanding of the different ideologies and creeds” between the regions where Portuguese is spoken, the organization said. “The question of understanding is closely related to ignorance that persists between the various ideologies and creeds in the countries and regions of Lusophony. Through photography, we intend to explore this cultural and religious diversity, ”said the association's president, Marta Pereira.
Under the theme “Man and the Divine”, the contest, which starts today and takes place until March 10, wants to “promote coexisting dialogue between religions or traditional local beliefs,” he noticed. "The images must capture the essence of devotion, contemplation and the profound connection between humanity and the divine or the transcendent," said the official, adding that "it is fundamental" that the works "allow a historical contextualization, reflecting the various influences cultural and religious that shape spiritual experiences in different regions ”.
Marta Pereira recalled that, in Macao, "the most practiced 'religion' is Buddhism, often associated with elements of other traditional Chinese beliefs and philosophies, such as Confucianism and Taoism." There is also a strong presence of "Christianity, brought to Macao by Catholic and Protestant missionaries."
“If we look at Brazil, candomblé, a religion of African origin, is based on the worship of nature and its soul, and is therefore considered soul. In Timor-Leste, the population still remains rooted in the cult of ancestors and belief in spirits, ”he exemplified.
The competition, defines the regulation, is intended “to all citizens of the countries and regions of Lusophony or residents of Macau” with work done in Angola, Brazil, Cape Verde, Guinea-Bissau, Macao, Mozambique, Portugal, Sao Tome and Prince, Timor-Leste and Goa, Damão and Diu.
The assessment of the works is up to a jury chaired by the Portuguese photojournalist based in Macau Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro and also featuring António Leong (Macau), Samba M. Baldé (Guinea-Bissau) and José Sena Goulão, Reinaldo Rodrigues and Alexandre Coelho Lima ( Portugal).
The three winning images will be awarded prizes worth ten thousand patacas, seven thousand patacas and five thousand patacas, and honorable mentions can be conferred. In addition to the pecuniary prize, the first place will be contemplated with the trip and stay in Macao -if not reside in the territory -to participate in the opening ceremony of the usual exhibition, to be organized later this year, and in workshops.
In addition to the winning images, the exhibition completes other photographs selected by the jury “for its relevance or value” for the theme of the contest and “the purpose of the association of projecting the cultural dimension of Lusophony, as well as the role of Macao as a platform that unites China and the countries/regions of Portuguese language ”read in a statement. The regulation can be consulted on the Association page (https://somosportgues.com/).
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-02-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Flu caused death of two residents</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/gripe-causou-morte-de-duas-residentes/</link><description>Two residents died due to flu, health services (SSM) indicated. One case concerns a 35 -year -old woman from the high -risk flu group and was not vaccinated this year. On January 31, the patient expressed symptoms of fever and cough, but did not resort to doctors. Subsequently, on February 3, Emergency Service of the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center (CHCSJ) due to the persistence of symptoms, where the flu was diagnosed. Days later, he went to the same service, having been diagnosed with influenza A and acute pericarditis, having been hospitalized. His condition got worse, and was administered to intubation, with a fan assisted in the breath. It was also transferred to therapy at the Intensive Care Unit, but eventually died. The other case refers to a 69 -year -old woman with various chronic diseases, who was not vaccinated either. He eventually died with flu and pneumonia, according to the SSM. This year, seven serious cases of influenza were registered in Macao, of which two were deadly, with the body appealed to vaccination. According to official data, on the 8th and 9th of this month, more than 5,400 residents were vaccinated, of which about 2,100 (40%) had been previously tagged for the administration of the vaccine and about 3,300 (60%) without appointment.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Vincent U integrates China's Board of Directors in Association of Mice</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/vincent-integra-conselho-directivo-da-china-em-associacao-mice/</link><description>Vincent U, president of the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment (IPIM), was appointed member of the China Board of the International Exhibition and Event Association (IAEE, in the English acronym) to 2025, being the only representative of Hong institutions Kong and Macao. Founded in 1928, IAEE is one of the Mice Sector Reference Organizations, says a note from IPIM, stressing that more than 20,000 exhibition organizers and commercial fairs are members of the Association, representing more than 12,000 industry professionals and offering business support and training in more than 50 countries and regions. “The Association expects, with the creation of the China Board of Directors, further deepening cooperation with China's exhibition industry partners, promoting best practices and vocational training of international exhibitions, and boosting sustainable development and the greatest success of industry, ”says the statement. According to IPIM, the China Exhibition Certificate Professional Training Program under the guidance of IAEE has already trained more than 1,600 professionals, including hundreds of Macao, providing “important support to build a team of qualified frames at Local Convention and Exhibition Area ”. In May 2023, IPIM received the “IEAE International Excellence Award”. In addition to leading the IPIM, Vincent U is secretary general of the Commission for the Development of MSAR Conventions and Exhibitions, and since 2022 is a member of the Board of Directors of the Global Exhibition Industry Association (UFI).</description><pubDate>2025-02-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao beaten by India at winter games</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-batido-pela-india-nos-jogos-de-inverno/</link><description>Macau's ice hockey selection lost again in the tournament included in the Winter Asian Games, which are taking place in Harbin's Chinese city. The MSAR team discussed the match against India, which ended group C of the competition, but was defeated 4-2. The goals of the formation of the territory were both scored by Edison Sou. In the previous challenges, Macau, oriented by Ho Chon Nin, had conceded many goals against Hong Kong (26-1) and Turquemenistan (26-0). Macao today performs, at 9:00, his ultimate challenge, this one of the penultimate and last places of the overall classification of the race. The Macao entourage is made up of 21 players, who participated in the opening ceremony of the Winter Asian Games, carrying the Flag of the Masters. The Macao delegation enters for the third time at the event, always in the ice hockey mode, after 2007 and 2017. The games are part of 11 modalities and a total of 64 subjects, unfolding until February 14. The Harbin tests, known as the “city of“ ice ”, feature two records: the participation of countries or regions, 34, against 32 of the 2017 Games in Sapporo and Obihiro, Japan; and number of athletes, which is 1,275, against 1,145 of the previous edition. This is the second time Harbin has received the games. In terms of medals already assigned, by the end of yesterday afternoon, the Popular Republic of China had won 21, against 19 from South Korea, seven from Japan and three from Kazakhstan. The host entourage, China, has 170 athletes, five of whom have won gold medals in the last 2022 Winter Olympic games in Beijing.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>"Anora" surprises in the "Critics Choice" prizes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/anora-surpreende-nos-premios-critics-choice-ana-rita-guerra/</link><description>Ana Rita Guerra*
The big surprise of the 30th edition of the Critics Choice Awards, which took place at dawn on Saturday in Los Angeles, was the victory of "Anora" in the most coveted category of best film, surpassing the favorites who won more statuettes in the ceremony. The independent film made by Sean Baker and starring Mikey Madison passed ahead of "The Substance", "Wicked" and "Emilia Pérez", the most awarded films by critics with three statuettes each.
"We made this little movie with six million dollars, a micro budget," Baker said in Vitória's speech. “We filmed roll, filmed in New York and put all dollars on the big screen,” he continued, stressing that “Anora” was made to be seen in the cinema.
"It was in the movie theaters that we all fell in love with movies, we lost many during Covid, but that's how we should watch movies - in local rooms," he said.
The coronation of “Anora” was surprising because the film had lost in other categories. A huge highlight was “The Substance”, which took home three statuettes, including better original argument and best actress for Demi Moore. "This argument is very personal," said the Conductor and director Coralie Fargeat, who used the film to express his fears and the way the world faces older women.
“When I started to get close to 50 I had this idea that I was going to disappear and wanted to show the world that we are not here, and ask them to look at us for whom we are and not for what we want to be,” said Fargeat.
Demi Moore, the protagonist of "The Substance," echoed this feeling. The 62 -year -old actress is receiving the first career interpretation prizes and was even named after Oscars.
"This has been such a crazy journey," said the actress. "The recognition not only of me, but what is this movie, what is wanting to show, is almost like an elixir, a cure for the problem that the movie points out." "The Substance" also won better characterization, a category in which they competed titles such as "Nosferatu" and "Wicked."
But the one who was one of the most viewed 2024 films did not go out to shake. “Wicked” gave Jon M. Chu the best achievement statuette, a surprising victory because he was not named for the Oscars and won here that were, such as Brady Corbet (“The Brutalist”) and Jacques Audiard (“Emilia Pérez ).
“I love to accomplish. We live in telling stories. It was all I wanted, making movies with my friends, ”said Jon M.chu, feeling“ privileged ”to be there. "America is the best place in the world where dreams come true," he said, remembering how he dreamed of doing movies while doing homework at his parents' restaurant.
"Wicked" was also awarded better art direction and best wardrobe.
The other movie that took home three awards was "Emilia Pérez" - critics voted before the scandal that slaughtered on the Netflix production because of the "tweets" by protagonist Karla Sofia Gasco.
Zoe Saldaña won the best secondary actress and, in the speech, praised the route of the “little movie” that managed to get far, saying expecting their impact to make people more open with each other. “Emilia Pérez” was still considered the best foreign film, beating the Brazilian “I'm still here”, and took the prize for best song with “El Mal”.
The night was also good for "Conclave", which took two statuettes: best cast, award received by protagonist Ralph Fiennes, and best adapted argument, handed over to Peter Straughn.
Adrien Brody cmented the place as a favorite of the season by winning best actor for "the brutalist," although the film has not won in any other category. Kieran Culkin was the best secondary actor for "The True Pain" and Maisy Stella, in "My Old Ass", had the best young interpretation. “Robot Selvagem” was the best animation movie, “Nosferatu” won best photography and “Challengers” got better edition and best band (Trent Reznor and Atticus Ross).
On television, highlighting “Shōgun”: It was the best drama series, gave Hiroyuki re -remedied the best actor prize, best secondary actress for Moka Hoshi and best secondary actor for Tadanobu Asano. "Hacks", with Jean Smart and Hannah Einbinder, won in the comedy, while "The Penguin" was highlighted in the miniseries.
 
*From the Lusa Agency</description><pubDate>2025-02-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>