<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Doctors specializing in hospitals grew in a year to 636</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/medicos-especialistas-nos-hospitais-cresceram-num-ano-para-636/</link><description>Within a year, the number of doctors specializing in the five hospitals of Macau increased 6% to a total of 636, reveal health statistics for 2024. “Internal medicine” were in greater numbers, followed by “general surgery” and “pediatric/neonatology”; As for experts of “psychiatry, it should be noted that they represented only 2.7% of the total, equivalent to about 17 professionals. At the end of last year, Macau had 2,030 doctors and 3,058 nurses. At the same time there were more people to be attended to external consultations and more sick hospitalized, they were also less hospitalization beds.
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Macao's five hospitals had, in late 2024, with 636 specialist doctors, an increase of 6% compared to the same period last year, indicating official data yesterday published. Analyzing by specialty, information on Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) reports that the number of medical specialists of “internal medicine” (117) was the highest, representing 18.4%of the total, followed by “general surgery” (85 doctors or 13.4%) and “pediatric/neonatology” (41 or 6.4%).
At a time when mental health has been on the agenda, it should be noted that experts in “psychiatry” in territory hospitals represented only 2.7% of the total, ie only about 17. Also doctors in the area of ​​“otorhinolaryngology” and “dermatology” were less, corresponding to 2.8% and 2.4% of the total, respectively.
There were also 36 experts in “Imagiology/Radiology”, 35 anesthetists, 34 from “gynecology/obstetrics”, 30 cardiologists, 30 other specialists in “hematology/oncology”, 25 doctors of “ophthalmology” and about 23 in the area of ​​“orthopedics and traumatology”.
In the general calculation, the MSAR had 2,030 doctors, another 50 in annual terms. In concrete, there were 2.9 doctors per thousand inhabitants, like 2023.
In hospitals, 928 doctors worked, while in primary health care establishments (including government health facilities, such as health centers, as well as private offices) worked 1,009. There were also 93 other doctors to practice in other health-related places, such as the case of senior homes.
There were also 732 doctors of traditional Chinese medicine/Masters of traditional Chinese medicine (four more), a total of 1.1 per thousand inhabitants; and 304 dentists/dentists (two minus), in this case, 0.4 per thousand inhabitants.
As for nurses, they totaled 3,058, 78 more than the previous year, of which 1,985 were in hospitals and 620 in primary health care establishments. There were also 453 nurses working in other locations not linked to health. At the end of the last year, there were 4.4 nurses per thousand inhabitants, also in the similarity of 2023.
 
More hospitalized and less hospital beds
In total, 63,016 patients were admitted last year, a 4.1% rise in annual terms, according to DSEC. Looking at the age of people who were hospitalized, 41.7% were between 15 and 64 years old, 38.7% were elderly and 19.6% were under 15 years old.
Analyzing by specialty, it was observed that the numbers of patients admitted to “pediatrics/neonatology” (10,765) and “general surgery” (9,374) were the highest, representing 17.1% and 14.9% of the total, respectively. The areas of “internal medicine” and “gynecology/obstetrics” in turn corresponded to 12.9% and 11.5% of the total.
The number of hospitalization beds was 1,779 at the end of the year under analysis, 103, in annual terms, "mainly due to the transfer of beds to sick." The rate of use of hospitalization beds set at 71.5%, with a homologous decrease of 2.3 percentage points.
At the end of 2024, there were 2.6 hospital beds per 1,000 inhabitants, less 0.2, compared to 2023. Most were general hospitalization beds (1,616), with 80 berths, 35 beds in intensive care units and 48 beds.
Regarding beds not intended for hospitalization (such as emergency and daytime health care), the number increased by 97 to a total of 379, in relation to 2023. The number of beds in operating rooms (45), labor rooms and rehabilitation (243) remained stable.
In operative services, 20,464 individuals were also served, an increase of 8.1% compared to the previous year. The number of people operated in the scope of “general surgery” (5,329) was the highest, representing 26% of the total, followed by the number of individuals met in “ophthalmology” operative services (4,715), which corresponded to 23%. In third position was “Gynecology/Obstetrics”, which represented 19.1% of the total operations.
 
More people attended to external consultations
On the other hand, in external consultations in hospitals, 1,998,551 people (+2.1%, compared to 2023) were treated, which means that each macao inhabitant was attended on average 2.9 times. Almost 60% of people who went to external consultations were between 15 and 64 years old, while the elderly accounted for 27.8% of the total.
In this context, it is noteworthy that the number of individuals attended to external consultations of “traditional Chinese medicine” (265,736) was the highest, making 13.3% of the total, followed by the number of people attended to external “physical medicine and rehabilitation” consultations (252,054 or 12.6% of the total) and by the “internal medicine” (239.825 or 12.825 or 12%).
Urgent services, in turn, arrived 463,446 individuals, with a slight growth of 0.5%, compared to 2023. The main cause of admission to the emergency services was “illness, fever)”, totaling 448,673 people, representing 96.8% of the total, followed by “pregnancy/postpartum/postpartum” (7.162) and by “road accident” (2,990).
Regarding the age group, people aged 15 to 64 who most resorted to emergency services, representing 53.6%of the total, followed by children under 15 (25.9%) and the elderly (20.5%). The DSEC also indicates that the Peninsula's emergency services served 348,666 individuals (+3.7%, in annual terms) and those of islands 114,780 (-7.9%).
In the reference year, the number of users of hospital services (external consultations, emergency services, hospitalization services and operative services) was 2,545,000, plus 1.9%, in annual terms.
 
Each inhabitant was served 5.7 times at health centers and private clinics
Health statistics released yesterday by Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) show that at the end of 2024 there were 733 primary health care establishments (such as health centers and private offices). In particular, there were 720 private offices, of which 63.1% were polyclinic. In these primary care establishments, 3,925,424 individuals (+3.6%in annual terms) were served, that is, each macao inhabitant was met on average 5.7 times. DSEC stressed that the number of people attended in private offices (3,012,223) and individuals treated in government health facilities (913.201) also increased 3.3% and 4.6%, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Decline of birth does not decrease adherence to the Santa Casa nursery</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/declinio-da-natalidade-nao-faz-diminuir-adesao-a-creche-da-santa-casa/</link><description>The superb birth rate, scheduled for this and for the next few years in Macao, will not affect the number of children that the Santa Casa da Misericórdia nursery will receive next academic year, which starts on the first day of September. After the registration is over, the nursery will keep close to 185 children, divided by 11 rooms. The space located in Nape will receive a new group of children, about two and a half children, increasing the frequency of the day care for just more than 210. "This is a number that surprised us, meeting the poor birth, so we are very pleased to maintain last year's level of adhesion at the beginning of the next year," the Journal Tribuna de Macau, Isabel told the newspaper Marreiros.

Victor Rebelo
 
Maintaining the number of children for the next school year in Nape da Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macao is the objective achieved, although birth rates are even lower in 2025 than before. After completing the deadline for registration, the nursery will count to 2025/2026 with the same number of babies and children, around 185, at the beginning of the academic year, scheduled for September 1.
However, according to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau, the director of the day care center, these values ​​“should grow close to 210, because there are parents who have already contacted us to put their children to the Chinese New Year, since (…) at the beginning of the year, there are parents who are afraid, because their children are still very small”.
Isabel Marreiros was pleased that there was no decrease compared to last year, as had happened in 2023/2024: "This is a number that surprised us, meeting the poor birth, and so we are very pleased to maintain last year's level of adhesion early in the next school year."
"We were afraid that the numbers could decrease again, because the birth has worsened," he says, adding that "there were many efforts, such as the organization of an open day, to draw the attention of the population and parents, to the good conditions we can offer in our space."
The Santa Casa nursery has 11 large rooms, which allows you to have a frequency simultaneously, by class, between 18 and 22 children, “which can work very well with these groups, because there is better conditions to take care of children and babies and we are all happier,” he assumes.
As with other Portuguese matrix schools, this infantary subsidized by the government has a majority of Chinese ethnic groups, currently representing more than 80% of the total. “When we opened, 23 years ago, the [Portuguese] percentage was greater, nowadays our larger component is Chinese, because there are also less Portuguese living in Macau,” he explains, saying that the basic formation is in Portuguese, something that “parents like”.
In Nape also works an English language room, "which is always full", because the choice is "very large". This giving some parents "are already thinking of putting their children in kindergarten and going to an international school, intending to start speaking English," albeit at the director's perspective "it's not just about the kindergarten or kindergarten, but you need to talk home."
“So, in the future, we will have one more English room, because there are many Chinese parents to ask, but also Portuguese. It's funny that I have Portuguese children who choose Chinese, which I understand, because it's another language they learn,” he emphasizes. Most of the Nape day care rooms are Chinese language, both in Cantonense and Mandarin. “Our educators dominate these two languages,” he says.
Isabel Marreiros praises the people who work in space, who were always faithful to the day care, "corresponding to the conditions they always had." During the pandemic, the Holy House did not dismiss anyone, "always fulfilled with its duties." “That's why they feel right here, with a good environment, working like us, with the heart,” he says.
The Nape Nursery currently has 12 childhood educators and two full -time nurses, which join 39 employees for various services, such as room assistance, kitchen, laundry, among others. They are total 53, a number that is not small.
"That's why Santa Casa loses money every month," says the director, adding: "We receive the tuition allowance, but also Santa Casa gives practically the same, or more, than this government support, so that the day care center has a good work environment."
Regarding the commonly due activities, "throughout the year parents are called to interact with their children, as the younger ones are still very small to travel abroad," he says. For the elders, there are a few exits for visits, such as firefighters and Pandas Park, said Isabel Marreiros.
 
Costa Nunes will have two less classes
Meanwhile, D. José da Costa Nunes kindergarten will have fewer students in the next school year. There will be two less classes. The information was allowed to the Macao channel of TDM by the president of the Macanese Instruction Promoting Association (Apim).
Miguel de Senna Fernandes confirmed that the number of students will go from current 220 to 180, reducing at least two classes. "It is a direct consequence of the sharp decrease of the birth rate in Macao, so we are already reducing classes," he said.
The kindergarten director addressed the situation, noting that there are several factors for the decrease. "After 82 students have been left, because they are finalists, there are only 47 registrations until last year, 61 were registered," said Felizbina Gomes.
For the next school year, the official predicts that there are 10 classes, nine in regular education and one of the special education.
Regarding the last three years, the new registrations have fallen 47% and the total of students about 27%, because at the beginning of this school year 12 classes were opened after 61 new registrations, totaling 230 children. In 2023/2024 there were Nunes 13 classes on Costa Nunes and a total of 250 students and 89 new registrations.
Although the scenario translates into fewer subsidies, it is no longer for the intentions of reducing the people who work at school. The solutions are being studied in collaboration with education services, according to Miguel de Senna Fernandes and Felizbina Gomes. Currently, there are 23 educators in the children's garden, nine teaching agents and 12 assistants.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Illegal works continue to decrease</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/obras-ilegais-continuam-diminuir/</link><description>In the first quarter of this year, soil services and urban construction established 190 processes related to illegal works, a number that reflects a breach trend. Between January and March, there were 41 cases of voluntary demolition
 
The Directorate of Soil Services and Urban Construction (DSSCU) opened 190 processes related to illegal works in the first quarter of this year, which represents a monthly average of 63.3. Data published on the DSSCU website illustrate a break trend when compared to the 844 processes instituted in the 2024 general calculation to a monthly average of 70.3.
Since 2019, the annual number of processes filed only between 2022 and 2023, from 723 to 1,114. The recent breaks will be associated largely with the impact of the legal regime of urban construction, which entered into force on 17 August 2022, aggravating fines and expanding the means for the execution of the law, including the introduction of criminal liability, registration with the provision of water supply and electricity.
Official statistics also indicate that between January and March 2025, 41 cases of voluntary demolition of illegal works were reported. The monthly average of 13.7 cases also fell short of 19.8 noted in 2024, the year that ended with a total of 238 voluntary demolitions.
In the first three months of this year, 16 cases were also filed, including demolition actions made by DSSCU and at the initiative of infrastructors. In the 12 months of last year, the body applied fines of about 1.5 million patacas due to illegal works and filed 102 processes, according to data previously revealed.
The legal regime of urban construction advocates pecuniary sanctions, both for the execution of illegal works and by breach of the order of demolition. If the demolition is made by the administration of the MSAR, the payment of the resulting expenses will have to be assumed by the offender or owner.
According to DSSCU, authorities have given priority to combat new cases of illegal works, renewal and ruin constructions that undermine fire safety and affect sanitary conditions.
Under the Urban Construction Law, usually the inner remodeling works of stores on the ground floor and repair and maintenance of buildings lack prior communication with the DSSU or the submission of the work project, so they can only be started after the issuance of the respective license. If the work is performed without that authorization or license, the owner of the contract will be sanctioned with a fine and may not be dispensed with payment even if the project is eventually legalized.
On the other hand, if the offender requires voluntary demolition within the deadline set by DSSCU, the fine is half reduced, a benefit that can only be applied once. In cases of recurrence, if the offender again violates the law in the following five years, the minimum limit of the fine is aggravated by 25%.
 
Bad state buildings motivate 68 cases in three months
Between January and March, soil services and urban construction opened 68 processes on repair works in private buildings due to poor condition and sent 59 notifications to the owners to “urgent” to these works. In the general 2024 calculation, 213 proceedings were filed and 248 notifications in the same scope were made. Data from the first quarter of 2025 also include 86 inspections on poor buildings and four private real estate surveys.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Salaries rose 2.7% in the financial sector</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/salarios-subiram-27-sector-financeiro/</link><description>Financial activities employed about 8,500 individuals in the first quarter of this year, during which time the average remuneration in the sector increased by almost 3% to 32,000 patacas, official data reveals official data
 
The sector of financial activities had a total of 8,484 full -time workers at the end of March, less 81 or 0.9% than in the same period of 2024, of which 58.5% were female and 84.8% worked on banks, according to data released yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC).
In the period under analysis, banks had 7,193 full -time people (less 0.7%), including 742 counter employees, and insurers employed 821 (plus 1.1%). The rest of the sector was linked to activities related to financial intermediation (216), such as exchange houses and rapid delivery companies in cash, among others.
Statistics also show that the average remuneration (excluding the irregular remuneration) of full-time workers in financial activities was 32,020 patacas in March, translating an annual rise of 2.7%. The average remuneration of resident workers equivalent to 30,630 patacas and non-residents settled at 41.050.
Average remuneration in banks (32,160 patacas), insurers (34,480) and “other financial intermediation” (30,270) - for example, payment services and financial lease institutions - grew 2.3%, 3.3%and 5.5%, respectively, within one year.
On the other hand, there were 266 job vacancies in financial activities, less one in annual terms, including 202 in banks (eight minus) and 41 in the insurance business (seven more).
With regard to recruitment requirements, higher education was required in all sector vacancies and the mandarin and English domain in most cases. Mandarin and English were required at 95.0% and 89.6% of banks, respectively, and 87.8% and 100% of the stations for filling in insurers.
In addition, professional certification was required in 23.8% of banks and 70.7% of insurance vacancies.
Between January and March, banks recruited 180 workers (14 less in the annual variation) and saw 234 (less five). Vacancy rates (2.7%), recruitment (2.5%) and workers' turnover (3.2%) dropped 0.1, 0.2 and 0.1 percentage points, respectively, in annual terms.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Screen Generation” in debate at the Rui Cunha Foundation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/geracao-dos-ecras-em-debate-na-fundacao-rui-cunha/</link><description>The excessive time that young people spend on the internet will deserve discussion in a scheduled lecture for May 28 at the Rui Cunha Foundation. “Screen Generation: Navigating Without Limits” launches the debate on a theme of current in society. The guest speaker is jack ho
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The internet and the time that especially the younger ones spend on its use will be topics to be addressed in a scheduled lecture for the 28th, at the Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC), at 18:30. With the title “Screen Generation: Navigating Without Limits”, it will address the impact of navigation, without limitations, digital screens, especially in mobile phones, and new technologies.
The session, organized together by the Association of Young Macanese (AJM), University of St. Joseph (USJ) and the FRC, will focus on “in the way excessive time in digital scraps can affect health and well-being, especially the younger generation, and how it can affect the educational system in Macao,” says an AJM note.
Participants will also analyze "what can be done to balance and manage time (with or without screen), including the introduction of artificial intelligence into our near future."
Jacky Ho, director of the Faculty of Health Sciences and the Macao Social Development Observatory of the University of São José, is the guest speaker for the moderate session by Jerusa Antunes, vice president of AJM.
Professor Jacky Ho, which specializes in Gerontology, Dementia and Sleep Sciences, is also a dean of the Faculty of Health Sciences, co-director of the USJ-Kong Hon Academy for Nutrition and Cell Health, having been appointed member of the Committee of the UN-China UN-UN-UN Sustainability Center and Sustainability Research.
He created the Innovative Social Labor Department and the Healthy Lifestyle Research Center of Macao, having been appointed department director during his service at the University of Macao. Its research interests include “aging and health”, “hypertension and cardiovascular disease”, “chronic disease prevention and management”, “dementia and social support”, “physical activity”, “physiology and sleep pathology” and “health and professional risks”.
Its current study focuses on establishing a community-based and chronic disease management model in Macao and in the Great Bay area. It has published articles in international magazines, including the "American Journal of Hypertension", "Asia Pacific Journal of Public Health", "Journal of Women's Health" and "Steroid Biochemistry and Molecular Biology." At the same time, he has often been invited as the lead speaker at international conferences and symposiums and was a specialist member of the Macao Social Assistant Registration and Professional Licensing Commission.
He participated and served as consultant and board member in several Macao organizations, including the Social Worker Association, the Registered Psychotherapist Society, the Hypertension Alliance, the Alzheimer's Association of Alzheimer's and the Hung Wing Sports Association, as well as a lifetime member of the Golden Key International Honor Society and Academic Counselor of the Macao United Nations Promotion Association.
The session, open to the public and led in English, will be moderated by Jerusa Antunes, Vice President of AJM.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Otcosonic” gives life to five pages of the bishop's Bible</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ottosonic-da-vida-cinco-paginas-da-biblia-bispo/</link><description>The exhibition “The 1568 Bishop's Bible” will be evident at the University of São José Library until June 20th. The public will be able to know the legacy of the Bible and the translation process, through “five distinct pages” and a “miraculous” sound landscape

The exhibition “The 1568 Bishop's Bible” is evident at the University of São José (USJ) library, where five distinct pages of an edition of the 1568 Bible are presented and one of the first Bibles to be recognized by Tudor's house. USJ states that visitors will have the opportunity to explore the context of the period, the translation process and the lasting legacy of the Bible.
Printed in folio size and with a dedication to Queen Elizabeth, the 1568 edition was produced under the direction of Matthew Parker, which served as a Cantering Archbishop. This edition represents, according to USJ, "a crucial development in the history of scriptures in English," having influenced other translations, including the "King James" version.
For USJ Rector Stephen Morgan, the pages are a "testimony of a commitment to translate the Holy Scriptures so that the Word of God can be understood by all in all languages." During the inauguration speech, Morgan also mentioned St. Jerónimo, who first translated the Bible into Latin at the end of the fourth century.
The rector also praised the "Ottosonic", responsible for the sound landscape of the exhibition, which "miraculously brings back an ancient voice of modern English," can be read in the university statement.
The teacher and head of the Department of History and Heritage at USJ Faculty of Letters and Human Sciences, Priscilla Roberts, participated in the production of the soundtrack and explained that she was very careful in preparing the script and reproducing the sound of old texts, since some of the words printed in the texts are no longer used today.
In turn, Antonio Wong, curator of the exhibition, said it was an "extraordinary occasion," in which participants may experience "what the psalmist says about the goodness of the Lord."
The exhibition will be evident at the USJ Library by June 20, with free admission.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>115 jobs offered at three sectors</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/oferecidos-115-postos-de-trabalho-em-tres-sectores/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) and the Federation of Macao Workers Associations (Faom) will co-perform three employment conjugation sessions on May 29, for the branches of restoration and transport, and the next day, to the education sector, with a total of 115 vacancies. On the morning of the 29th, “Macao Fisherman’s Wharf” and the Menya Restoration Company will offer 66 vacancies to Chinese cook chief team, receptionist, ramen master, restoration services and cook help. In the afternoon, AA Turismo, Li Heng Automobile Services, the International Travel Agency Cheong Fai and the Macau International Travel Agency will make 37 places available to driver, tourist bus driver, senior station head and foreign language tourist guide. The next day, the Yuet In Explanation Center and the Siu I Dee San Educational Development will offer 12 vacancies for explaining explanators and assistants. Registration for all sessions is open until the 28th. On the other hand, Dsal and Sands will launch the “Sands China Hotel Development Plan”, with 32 job offers, and half are for stages such as hotel supervisor and the remaining for supervisor trainees of the Housekeeping department. According to DSAL, the plan, whose registration stems until the 29th, covers theoretical concepts on hotel exploration and interdepportional practical training actions in integrated resorts.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Seized 13,000 cigarettes in two Nape stores</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/apreendidos-13-mil-cigarros-em-duas-lojas-nape/</link><description>Customs services seized a total of 651 cigarette packages at two convenience stores at Zape, following a complaint received by the prevention and control of smoking and alcoholism of health services. According to a statement of health services, the 159 packages of one of the stores, with a total of 3,180 cigarettes, and the 492 of the other establishment, with 9.840 Cigarettes, they did not contain the labels required by law or their import documents. Health services have stressed that the follow -up procedures will begin and if the offense is confirmed, the illegal objects will be confiscated and destroyed and the store may be fined up to 200 thousand patacas. In the same statement, the body states that "the law of Macau rigorously regulates the circulation of tobacco products" and appeals to traders "not to risk luck or challenge the law", at the risk of being "severely punished".</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MGM has 100 Junior Leão Dance vacancies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mgm-tem-100-vagas-para-danca-leao-junior/</link><description>Under the Lion Dance Championship “Annual Spectacle”, MGM is organizing several activities, which will take place between May and October. According to a statement from the game operator, the 11th edition of the MGM Junior Leão Summer Dance Course will take place between July 7 and August 22, and the registrations will be open until June 5th. The program has 100 vacancies for children from five to eight years. For the first time, the training will be held in the Barra area, offering children a unique opportunity to learn traditional lion dance techniques in a “culturally rich environment”, according to MGM. The course covers the “History of Lion Dance, Basic Movements, Beginning Posture Training and understanding of the use of various props and instruments”. According to the operator, the activity for young people help participants develop physical fitness and instill discipline, nourishing “the next generation of talents” and opening a “new chapter in the lion dance inheritance”. Trainees show “exceptional performance” and are approved in the evaluation will be eligible to participate in the MGM Lion Dance Training program. Over the past decade, the initiative has covered more than 640 young people, almost 200 became athletes. On October 4th and 5th, the 12th Lion International Dance Championship will be held in conjunction with the Leão Dance Festival, designed to “promote community involvement and interaction,” says MGM.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2403/</link><description>Detected 80 illegal workers
Throughout April, 80 suspects of illegal work were detected, according to data from the Public Security Police (CPSP). In total, CPSP, the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs and other services have supervised 411 locations, including construction shipyards, private buildings and commercial and industrial establishments, among others.
 
DSSA Alert for insolation risks
The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) has called for workers that they are close to heat sources in interior spaces or who work outdoors to take preventive measures against sunstroke. Dsal has made available on its website promotional plans of “Anti-Calor clothing and sunscreen security helmet”, “waist portable fans” and “safety guidelines for tropical storm, heavy rain and adverse weather conditions”.
 
Heat motivates the opening of the shelter center
Following the yellow alert, issued by the Directorate of Meteorological and Geophysical Services, the Summer Shelter Center of the Institute of Social Action (IAS) is open "until the temperature is lowered again." The IAS appeals to take heat prevention measures, carefully to the elderly who live alone, chronicle sick and weak individuals.
 
World Environment Day celebrated with activities
In response to World Environment Day, which is celebrated on June 5, the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) will organize a series of activities. From the outset, the “Festival to commemorate World Environment Day between Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau” will be held at Friendship Square on the afternoon of May 31st. Also scheduled are the initiatives “turn off the lights for 1 hour” at 8:30 pm on June 5, and “Informal Summer Clothing - Let's all conserve energy!”, Between June 1 and August 31. In addition, there will also be a draw of the activity “Energy Savings - Conservation Action of 5% Energy”, which will take place between July and October.
 
Workshop addressed aviation security control
The Civil Aviation Authority (AACM) organized, between May 12 and 16, the “Workshop Quality Control Workshop on the Aviation Safety Development Program in the Asia-Pacific Region”, focused on articles such as risk management in analysis, auditing programming, inspections, tests and investigations. AACM invited 11 Macao Civil Aviation representatives and nine Laos, Malaysia, Philippines, Singapore and Sri Lanka aircraft operations operators. The workshop was given by the coordinator of the Asia-Pacific Aeronautical Security Cooperation Program, Tony Blackston, and Lita Lee, head of program training and development development.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CTM already dominates more than half of the mobile market</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ctm-ja-domina-mais-de-metade-mercado-movel/</link><description>With the number of 5G users reaching nearly 760,000, CTM expanded dominance on MSAR mobile telecommunications by 2024, controlling more than half of the market, highlights the annual report of the Citic Group, which owns 99% of the local operator. Sales and services revenues rose about 10% to more than $ 2.6 billion from Hong Kong
 
Sérgio Terra
 
The Macao Telecommunications Company (CTM) strengthened the leadership in the mobile telecommunications sector last year by winning more than half of customers. At the end of 2024, the CTM quota in the Macao mobile market increased to 53.3%, after reaching 48.3% in the previous year and 45.7% in 2022, indicates the annual report of the Citic Telecom International Holdings group, which has 99% of local operator capital, which also has 1% of Macau Post and Telecommunications (CTT).
CTM currently has a competitor in 5G (China Telecom) and three services on the 4G network (China Telecom, Hutchison and Smartone). The four 4G operators also explore the 3G network, whose licenses will expire on June 4th.
In the annual report, Citic Telecom stresses that the CTM "realized the potential value through the strong penetration of 5G and explored new scenarios for applications in vertical industries." The number of 5G users of the CTM ascended to almost 760,000 at the end of 2024, plus 260,000 within one year, corresponding to 98.4% of the company's mobile customers, against a penetration rate of 75% by 2023.
In July 2024, CTM launched 5.5g commercial services, making Macao in one of the first cities with this segment of telecommunications worldwide, highlights Citic Telecom. On the other hand, it collaborated “actively” with the main operators of the Great Bay to make available '5g SA) 5G Roaming, thus promoting integrated and “high quality” telecommunications services in Macau, Hong Kong and Guangdong.
“In addition, CTM actively enables customers to achieve digital transformation in various sectors, including government issues, companies, education, health care and finance,” says the mother company, giving “Dr. Easy” launches, an intelligent solution in the domain of health, and an application of “intelligent care” to Macao Tourism clients, in association with the direction of tourism services.
Over 2024, CTM sales revenues increased 9.8% in homologous terms to about $ 2.62 billion from Hong Kong, including mobile devices, equipment and services. Only mobile service revenues grew 12.7%to $ 1.09 billion from Hong Kong, compared to the previous year, due to the increase in the number of mobile customers and mobile markets, as well as the 5G penetration rate.
The business scale has also grown in the internet chapter, driven by “intelligent updates in technology and services”. On December 31, 2024, CTM owned 96.8% of the Macao broadband market.
Overall, Citic Telecom ended last year's financial year with net $ 910 million profits from Hong Kong, which reflects a decline of 26.1% compared to gains of 1.23 billion in 2023. In the interval of one year, the group's total revenues fell 4.1% to 9.57 billion.
"In 2024, we continued to face complexity and uncertainty in the macroeconomic landscape," said Luo Xicheng, president of Citic Telecom, referring, on the other hand, that the group accelerated the transformation process "towards digitization and intelligence, to" increase the proportion of new business. "
Considering that the Information and Communication sector "is entering a new growth cycle," Luo Xicheng said that the group "will strengthen their global business and take advantage of opportunities in the foreign market." “With a special focus on foreign countries or regions, such as the Range and Route initiative and the BRICS countries, we will leverage the Citic Group's brand influence as a trusted partner for national companies seeking international expansion,” he said, still promising to consolidate the “advantageous leadership position in the deeper efforts to explore segments such as mobile communications, broadband services and solutions and solutions. business, among others ”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Manders presents in the national games the largest delegation ever</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-apresenta-nos-jogos-nacionais-maior-delegacao-de-sempre/</link><description>The MSar delegation that will be present in this year's edition of China's National Games will feature the largest number of athletes ever, in a total of 350. The entourage of the territory will participate in 31 modalities, including collective sports such as football, handball, basketball and dragon boats, and other individuals, highlighting table sneakers, Karaté and Badminton. Some competitions will take place in the territory and the remaining in Hong Kong and Canton, during the next month of November
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Macau will feature a record delegation to the National Games of the Popular Republic of China, which will take place in November this year, with some of the modalities to take place in the territory, which happens for the first time in the history of the race.
According to the President of the Institute of Sport (ID), the delegation of the MGA will integrate 350 athletes. “This will be the largest entourage ever,” said Luís Gomes, in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau.
Local athletes will be distributed to 31 modalities. Dezanove are considered “competition sports”, namely swimming, athletics, martial arts, Badminton, basketball, boxing, canoeing, cycling, fencing, football, golf, judo, arc shooting, taekwondo, tennis, triathlon, volleyball and handball. The remaining 12, entitled “Main Group Modalities” integrate Karate, Dragon Boats, Weiqi, Chinese Chess, Bowling, Guidance, Modeling (Aviation), Jianzi, Football, Gateball, Dragon and Lion and Qigong.
The dissemination of the sports in which Macau will be present came after the plenary meeting of the Sports Council, chaired by the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM, which were presented, among other topics of local sports, preparations for the organization of the Macao Competition Zone of National Games.
To reinforce the support for the preparation of athletes who also participate in the special Olympics for the disabled, the ID, through the “Special Olympic Games Glory Program for Disabled”, will provide a set of complementary support to athletes, “with a view to preparing and participation in the events”.
In a statement, ID clarifies that the chosen modalities were defined for the purpose of “ensuring that Macao athletes participating in the games have a certain degree of competitiveness, after analyzing different factors and taking into account the opinions of sports associations”.
The body will make available to the various modalities its facilities, to be used as training sites and competition, specifically the TAP Seac Polydestive Pavilion, the Macao Forum, the East Asia Games Sports ship and the Sports Pavilion of the Olympic Sports Center, “having already started several benefit works of their respective enclosures,” according to ID.
At the same time, the Games Glory Program and the International Sports Technical Officers Plan will be launched, and “optimizations” are planned in the scope of financial support to improve athletes training and competition competition, in order to “promote the development of high performance sport”, adds the document released after the Sports Council meeting.
Regarding advertising, information and relevant elements will be introduced in major international sports events and sports activities for all organized by the Sports Institute, as well as their sports facilities, in order to publicize the national games and the special Olympic Games for the disabled.
 
Training Actions for Referees
In addition, with the aim of promoting the participation of local sports agents in international affairs and reinforcing the professionalism of local referees, “encouraging them to participate in the work of arbitration of more large sports sports events and increasing the influence of the Macao International Sports panorama”, ID stresses that it will take the initiative to “regularly collect with sports associations, the lists of personnel members Assume positions in the international sports federations and the referees in beyond border events, providing them with training and fully supporting the corresponding expenses ”.
It is recalled that MSar will receive some modalities in the 2025 edition of the National Games, namely Table Tennis and 3 × 3 Basketball, as well as the Five Men's Under-18 Basketball competition and the women's volleyball tournament. Macau will also organize an amateur karate tournament, open to the entire population.
In addition, the territory will welcome two Badminton competitions for people with physical or hearing disabilities and for practitioners with intellectual disabilities, under the China Special Olympic Games, which take place between December 8 and 15.
The 15th edition of the National Games will take place between November 9th and 21st. Regarding the overlap with the realization of the Macao Grand Prix, the ID's head assured that the authorities have planned their preparation and coordination.
Luís Gomes said at the end of the Chinese press meeting that the National Games tests will take place in the mud during the Grand Prix period, "hoping to reach a synergistic effect, so that residents and tourists can feel the sports atmosphere of races of the great prize and national games at the same time."
 
Medal made history four years ago
The latest national games have taken place in the province of Shaanxi, in the northeast of the country, in September 2021, involving more than 12,000 athletes in 35 modalities, and ended with 12 new world records.
The race has been held since 1959, therefore, 66 years ago, with many of the main athletes in the country, some of which are Olympic sportsmen who contributed medals. Earlier, between 1910 (launched during the Qing Dynasty) and 1948 the competition had the designation of Chinese national games.
It has been the second time that Guangdong province has been responsible for the organization, but in 2011 it has done it alone, contrary to what will happen this year, which will be in conjunction with Macau and Hong Kong.
For a few years and at the intervals of these national games, China organized the all-china games between 2000 and 2010, but in this case intended for modalities that do not usually part of the Olympic Games program.
Regarding Macau's participation in the latest edition in Shaanxi four years ago, the delegation of the territory was a total of 102 elements, including athletes, coaches and leaders, being involved in 17 modalities. For the first time in the history of his appearances at the Chinese multi -sports event, an athlete from MSA has reached a medal. It was thanks to the performance of Kuok Kin Hang in men's karate, having obtained third place in individual kata, raising the bronze.
It was the first time that a representative of the territory was on the podium of the games, after having already sought in the Games of East Asia in 2013, with the conquest of the gold medal.</description><pubDate>2025-05-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Found Bust of Jim Morrison stolen 37 years ago of Paris Cemetery</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/encontrado-busto-de-jim-morrison-roubado-ha-37-anos-de-cemiterio-de-paris/</link><description>The bust of singer Jim Morrison, iconic figure of The Doors, stolen 37 years ago from the famous Parisian cemetery Père Lachaise, was accidentally discovered during a police operation.

Paris police announced on Monday through social networks, the discovery of the sculpture, created by Croatian artist Mladen Mikulin, who was stolen at night, with no clues about the criminals.
Jim Morrison was a American singer, songwriter and poet who was the lead singer and lyricist of, also iconic rock band The Doors, with huge success since she was founded in 1965.
Due to his charismatic personality, poetic letters, striking voice and unpredictable performances, beyond the dramatic circumstances that surrounded his life and premature death, Jim Morrison is considered by musical critics and fans as one of the most influential vocalists in rock history.
According to Wikipedia, since his death, in 1971 his fame lasted as one of the main rebel icons and often displayed from popular culture, representing the difference of generations and young counterculture.
Although his death was officially attributed to a cardiac arrest in his Beautreillis Street apartment, several witnesses later suggested an overdose in a disco that would have been hidden by authorities and friends.
Jim Morrison's tomb is one of the most famous in Père Lachaise's cemetery, despite being home to many great figures, such as Oscar Wilde, Frédéric Chopin, Yves Montand and Sarah Bernhardt.
The bust was placed in 1981 to celebrate the tenth anniversary of the musician's death, however, only seven years later, was stolen.
According to Lusa, the police search, conducted by the Paris Police Financial Brigade and Anti -Corruption found the bust at the Parisian house of an executive from an company under investigation for falsifying accounting documents.
Authorities have not yet clarified whether the bust will be returned to their original place, but Jim Morrison fans, certainly they will press to go to the Père Lachaise cemetery pay their honors to a mythical 60's figure, missing in the flower of age…
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>