<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Firefighters develop specific contingency plan for large fires</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/bombeiros-elaboram-plano-de-contingencia-especifico-para-grandes-incendios/</link><description>The Government is investing heavily in prevention and inspection actions to prevent fires from having serious repercussions. In this sense, inspections of construction sites where scaffolding and protective nets are installed have increased. At the same time, the Fire Department, in addition to purchasing rescue vehicles, is developing “a specific contingency plan for large fires”
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
Inspection of construction sites where scaffolding and protective nets are erected has been at the forefront of the Government's inspection actions to combat fires, as a way of preventing tragedies such as the one that occurred in a residential complex in Hong Kong at the end of last November.
There are several departments that work together towards the same objective, which is prevention through inspection and awareness. The Fire Department (CB) is joined by, among others, the Directorate of Public Works Services (DSOP), the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) and the Directorate of Land and Urban Construction Services (DSSCU), which have collaborated in various actions with priority on works under construction.
The CB, in addition to suggesting to the Executive the creation of an interdepartmental working mechanism, so that the competent services can agree and clarify the division of competences, responsibilities and tasks in the future, acquired several small rescue vehicles, specially designed to operate in narrow streets such as those in the old areas of the city. The reinforcement of resources includes vehicles with small water pumps, ladders with 18 and 20 meter water pumps, fire-fighting motorcycles, medical emergency motorcycles, among others.
On the other hand, the Fire Department prepared intervention plans for different types of main buildings and carried out regular inspections of the condition of hydrants on public roads.
In response to a question from deputy Nick Lei on fire prevention, a topic that gained another dimension after the tragedy in Hong Kong, which killed at least 161 people, the Office of the Secretary for Security states that the CB “draws up temporary work guidelines or emergency plans according to the nature of the activities, and at the same time, under the coordination of the Unitary Police Services, it is putting into practice a specific contingency plan for large fires”.
Furthermore, through the simulation of different accident scenarios, training and rescue exercises have been carried out on different models.
The Executive guarantees that the CB “continuously” monitors the international development of rescue vehicles and equipment. “Taking into account the urban development of the Macao SAR, appropriate equipment and vehicles have been introduced in a timely manner”, he highlights.
He also adds that, in addition to the vehicles already mentioned to operate in narrow streets, in recent years, the Fire Department has acquired vehicles with high-jet articulated arms and other rescue equipment, including more than 20 drones of different models that have infrared thermal imaging cameras, portable speakers, LED spotlight lighting and gas detectors. This equipment, he reinforces, “can be used to provide assistance in fires or rescue scenarios, in order to improve rescue efficiency and reduce personnel safety risks”.
In the response to the deputy, signed by the head of Secretary Chan Tsz King's office, DSOP “expressly required supervisory entities and contractors to effectively comply with safety rules relating to the management of access to the construction site, the use and inspection of scaffolding, as well as the carrying out of hot work, among others”. At the same time, DSOP will continue to “deepen” the permanent inspection mechanism through the rigorous assessment of execution projects regarding the assembly of scaffolding, the reinforcement of random inspections of materials, as well as the optimization of their storage and management, adopting multiple measures aimed at raising the level of safety on construction sites.
The Secretary's office guarantees that it will also send personnel to inspect the shipyards under its supervision and, if any infraction is found, warnings will be issued or sanctions will be applied in accordance with the law, and, in serious situations, the suspension of works and their rectification may be ordered.
Furthermore, DSAL, within the scope of its responsibilities, “continues to reinforce fire safety on construction sites in Macau, periodically carrying out, with other services, specific inspections of the flame retardant effect of nets and scaffolding”, it further states.
During these inspections, contractors are required to present the quality certificate for the scaffolding and nets, and samples are collected to be sent to third-party laboratories for testing.
DSAL organized 1,472 training courses and seminars on occupational health and safety, with the participation of around 46,000 people.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Real estate predicts an increase of up to 20% in home sales in 2026</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/imobiliaria-preve-subida-ate-20-nas-vendas-de-casas-em-2026/</link><description>The real estate agency Centaline, which has a strong presence in the Greater Bay Area, predicts that the residential market will see an increase of between 10 and 20% in the volume of transactions this year compared to 2025, in a context of stable prices. The company considers that the Federal Reserve's interest rate cuts and Macau's gradual economic recovery, along with other measures, should improve the market outlook
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The removal of measures to cool down the real estate market, interest rate cuts by the US Federal Reserve, the gradual economic recovery and residents' savings deposits, which exceed 800 billion patacas, are considered favorable factors for an upward trajectory of the housing market in the Macao SAR in 2026. “The key is whether market confidence can be restored”, according to officials from Centaline in Macau, Zhuhai and Hengqin, gathered at a press conference to take stock of the 2025 real estate market and outline prospects for 2026.
At the time, they estimated that the volume of housing transactions in Macau should grow this year by between 10 and 20% compared to 2025, with stable prices.
The real estate agency noted that the Hong Kong and Macau markets have fallen by around 30% on average since their peak in 2019, with an estimated 6% annual decline in home sales in 2025. Residential transaction volumes and prices in Hong Kong have even reached their lowest level in 2025.
Regarding the sector in the Macao SAR, since January 1st this year, residents of legal age began to benefit from exemption from stamp duty on transfers of goods up to the value of six million patacas when purchasing autonomous housing units, a measure that, according to the real estate agency, “should gradually release the accumulated purchasing power”. “This new policy is more aggressive than that of Hong Kong, and relaxing mortgage limits to 80% will help improve market sentiment,” said Pun Chi Ming, general manager of Centaline in Macau and Hengqin.
However, admits Centaline, smaller units should only recover when interest rates fall again or the economic recovery becomes more pronounced, leading tenants to realize that purchasing their own home is more profitable than renting.
Analyzing the residential market in 2025 in the Macao SAR, the agency indicates that data from the Financial Services points to 2,153 transactions in the first nine months of the year. “Although visits to properties recovered significantly after the announcement of the new stamp duty policy, transactions remained slow, as buyers postponed signing contracts and paying deposits until the formal implementation of the policy”, he points out, calculating that around 700 transactions were carried out between October and December, leading the year to end with a drop of 6.6% compared to 2024.
In turn, Lee Chau-cheng, Centaline's regional director for industrial and commercial properties in Macau, stated that, in this segment, around 346 transactions were carried out last year, marking a year-on-year decline of 4%. For 2026, he predicted an increase in commercial transactions and the “stability” of prices, due to “favorable” factors, such as the continued growth of tourism.
Sales of units intended for offices also continued to decline, with the agency indicating that there were only “around 10” in the fourth quarter of last year.
Industrial properties also lack investment momentum. According to the Centaline database, average sales and rental prices for industrial units fell by 16% and more than 20% in the last quarter of 2025, respectively, in annual terms, with the volume of transactions falling by more than 30% to just 41.
With regard to stores, the company said that preliminary estimates indicate that the total number of transactions will have decreased by 4% to 346 throughout 2025, including 96 sales in the last three months.
“With vacancy rates on prime streets in tourist areas approaching zero, demand for properties on secondary streets will be stimulated”, anticipates the real estate group, predicting that the vacancy situation will gradually improve in all areas, with Nam Van, NAPE and Taipa outperforming other property categories in terms of appreciation.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Restructuring of the Public Service already has plans until 2028</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/reestruturacao-da-funcao-publica-ja-tem-planos-ate-2028/</link><description>The Government has already drawn up plans to restructure public services for the current year, 2027 and 2028, said the Secretary for Administration and Justice. This matter will involve the Audit Commissioner, who will evaluate the restructuring plans for some services, presenting opinions, said Wong Sio Chak
 
The Secretary for Administration and Justice revealed yesterday that the Government already has Civil Service restructuring plans for 2026, 2027 and 2028. According to Wong Sio Chak, not all proposals will necessarily be implemented, and will have to be discussed with different public services and the Audit Commissioner (CA), which will evaluate the restructuring plans for some services, presenting opinions.
In response to an oral question from deputy Chui Sai Peng, the Secretary reiterated that the readjustment of public services will not result in layoffs nor will it affect the remuneration, benefits and professional advancement of public servants.
“Through a series of reforms, we hope to achieve the objectives of protecting the team well, doing more work with fewer people, improving team spirit and increasing the efficiency and effectiveness of government actions”, highlighted Wong Sio Chak.
In this sense, he called for a global vision on the part of employees, to “obey and serve the general situation”.
Furthermore, the Secretary highlighted that the Government has paid attention to the physical and mental health and cultural training of employees through the continuous organization of various types of recreational and sporting activities. At the same time, in 2025, it carried out 30 training courses in the field of stress and emotion management, positive psychology, conflict and crisis management and frontline conflict handling, with the participation of 1,010 employees.
 
SAFP will evaluate career simplification
In turn, the director of Administration and Public Service Services (SAFP) revealed that the organization will evaluate the simplification of careers in the Public Service, since, with the evolution of society, some positions have undergone changes. As an example, he indicated that some functions were replaced by electronization.
Leong Weng In warned that changes in careers must be balanced with the Legal Regime of the Civil Service, so the matter must be studied with caution.
Wong Sio Chak clarified that, in order to encourage employee commitment, the SAFP is “promoting the study of the access regime between careers, which encompasses a clear definition of qualification requirements and fair and transparent access procedures, and also in conjunction with the necessary training”.
Furthermore, the Secretary ruled out conditions for staff mobility between assistant technicians, technicians and senior technicians, ruling out an integration plan for these careers, due to the “very distinct differences” between the three careers, both in the specifics of the functions and functional content, as well as in the academic qualification requirements for entry.
According to what he pointed out, between 2024 and 2025, 119 employees in full employment were promoted between careers through public recruitment competitions, accounting for 32.2% of the total of those who entered the higher education and technical careers. Among them, 38 assistant coaches and 35 technicians managed to enter the senior coaching career.
The government official also highlighted the objective of controlling the size of the staff team and maximizing the use of existing human resources, giving priority to the redistribution of work, internal mobility of staff, optimization of procedures and promotion of the use of electronic means.
Even so, he guaranteed that, if there are real needs for human resources due to the volume of work, the services will meet them through the opening of recruitment competitions. In this context, he assured, recruitment competitions have been promoted on a scheduled basis and according to needs.
On the other hand, Wong Sio Chak found that some experienced employees take a stance of inaction, not looking for career advancement. The Secretary stressed that directors and bosses have the responsibility to manage the team well, assign tasks to those subordinates and apply disciplinary procedures to those who do not fulfill tasks.
As he added, the CA also carries out evaluations of senior technicians. And if there are indeed cases of inaction on the part of these employees, the number of senior technicians will be reduced.
Furthermore, it revealed that, from March 2023 until the end of November 2025, 330 transfers and secondments were carried out within the framework of the new mobility regime, involving 58 services and organizations from different areas.
Regarding the creation of a platform to register services with human resources needs and interested employees, the Government will be able to hear more opinions and carry out a more detailed study, said the Secretary.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Planned cinema services center</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/planeado-centro-de-servicos-cinematograficos/</link><description>The Macao SAR will have a cinematographic services center, said Secretary O Lam, adding that a monthly transfer mechanism for the Performance Venue will soon be launched, which will also host sporting activities
 
The Government will create a cinematographic services center, the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture announced yesterday. This center will operate in the areas of the film and television industries, through consultation and presentations.
“It is also intended to promote the integration of industries and the exploration of new markets, in order to speed up exchanges and cooperation between the film industry in Macau and Mainland China”, said O Lam, in response to an oral question from Ngan Iek Hang.
In response to the development trend of short films, the Government wants to intensify efforts in four areas. Thus, the Culture Development Fund will optimize the “Subsidy Plan for the Dissemination and Distribution of Cinematographic and Television Works with Elements of Macau” and the “Subsidy Plan for Cinematographic and Television Filming”, granting specific support, for example, to micro-series with elements characteristic of Macau and Hengqin.
In addition, support for films from Mainland China aims to encourage the use of the Macao SAR as a distribution base for Portuguese-speaking countries, highlighted the Secretary.
The Cultural Affairs Bureau (IC) will also organize exchange visits to the micro-series filming and internationalization base in Hengqin. At the same time, adequate assistance will continue to be provided for applications for filming licenses for Macao and Hengqin micro-series projects.
The Secretary also guaranteed that the Government will maintain the “Macau – The Power of Image” program to train and support more talents in the area of ​​short films. In addition, IC will explore products on new cultural and film tourism routes and launch a “Thematic Page for Macau’s Film and Television Sector”.
Lam highlighted that, in the last three years, more than 110 talents have been trained in the sector, including directors, screenwriters, producers, professionals in cinematographic arts and audiovisual design. “It is expected that in the near future more invitations will be sent to cinema professionals from the Greater Bay Area so that they can create mentorships and transmit professional knowledge and hold courses or masterclasses for different areas of the film industry”, he said.
On the other hand, he revealed that the Government wants to improve the advantages of the Performance Venue, including through the launch, soon, of a monthly space transfer mechanism. In between concerts, the venue can also host 3×3 basketball courts and family sporting activities.
In another sphere, a financial support plan will be launched this year for the acquisition of technological rehabilitation equipment by qualified facilities, be they accommodation providers or day centers, to meet the needs resulting from the aging of service users. This plan is expected to involve 26 rehabilitation equipment and a cost of around 2.6 million patacas.
The official also indicated that, in November, Macau had 557 speech, occupational and physical therapists, an increase of 70.3% compared to 2020.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing repudiates Trump's pressure on Venezuela and Greenland</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/pequim-repudia-pressoes-de-trump-sobre-venezuela-gronelandia/</link><description>The Chinese Government yesterday considered the alleged US demand for Venezuela to break economic relations with Beijing as an act of “intimidation”. Questioned at a press conference about the information provided by the North American television channel ABC News, the spokesperson for the Ministry of Foreign Affairs (MNE) Mao Ning declared that Venezuela “is a sovereign country and enjoys full and permanent sovereignty over its natural resources and all economic activities in its territory”.
According to ABC News, the Trump Administration demanded that the Venezuelan interim president, Delcy Rodríguez, end ties with China, Russia, Iran and Cuba as a precondition for restarting the production and sale of crude oil. US Secretary of State Marco Rubio reportedly said in private sessions with lawmakers that the US believes it can put pressure on Caracas because its oil storage tanks are full and warned that Venezuela could go into financial insolvency in a few weeks if it fails to sell its reserves.
Senator Roger Wicker confirmed in an interview with ABC that the plan is based on controlling Venezuelan oil exports and stated that it is not part of the US intention to send US troops.
Mao described the alleged pressure as a “brazen use of force” and stated that the attempt to condition access to Venezuelan energy resources to an “USA first” logic constitutes a “typical case of intimidation” that “seriously violates international law, seriously infringes on Venezuela’s sovereignty” and “harms the rights of the Venezuelan people.” He also stressed that the “legitimate rights and interests” of China and other countries with economic relations with Venezuela “must be protected”.
The spokesperson reiterated that Beijing defends economic cooperation between sovereign states and highlighted that China “has always developed exchanges and cooperation with other countries based on mutual respect, equality and reciprocal benefit”.
The statements come in a context of growing international tension following the capture of Venezuelan leader Nicolás Maduro by US forces and in the midst of an intense diplomatic debate over the legality of the use of force and control of Venezuela's energy resources.
 
Respect the UN Charter
On the other hand, China defended that relations between countries must respect UN principles, after the US renewed its intention to take control of Greenland. The spokesperson for the Chinese MNE said that Beijing's position has been consistent in defending that relations between States must be managed in accordance with the objectives and principles of the UN Charter, without commenting further on the case.
Washington has once again suggested the possibility of using military means in its strategy to acquire or influence control of Greenland, an issue that has generated opposition from European countries and the Danish government, which claim that the territory can only decide its future sovereignly.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DSAL created “International Skills School”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dsal-criou-escola-internacional-de-aptidoes/</link><description>Strengthening exchanges and cooperation with international experts is the central objective of the program of activities and training actions entitled “International Skills School”, launched by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL). According to the organization, the initiative falls within the scope of the Government's strategic plan for the construction of “One Center”, “One Platform” and “One Base”, and is “in line with the needs for the development of adequate diversification of Macau's industries and the training of qualified local staff with an international perspective”.
In this sense, DSAL intends to collaborate with educational and professional training institutions, both in Macau and “reference international institutions”, to “expand the international horizon of local qualified professionals”, by carrying out various activities, including workshops, training courses and certifications.
The first activity of the “International Skills School”, entitled “International Exchange Camp for the Hotel Reception category of the 48th edition of the World Professional Skills Competition”, took place at the “Macao Integrated Training Base” located in the Deep Cooperation Zone. This month, a “Workshop with Star Chefs from the Le Cordon Bleu School” is also scheduled to begin, followed by training activities in the financial and tourism areas.
“In addition, given the needs for adequate diversification of industries, DSAL will continue to develop training programs and exams with international certification, in the areas of financial planning, management, languages, facilities management, food safety, among others”, states the same statement.
DSAL also indicated that the “Macao Base – Branch of the Ou Tao Health Management Society (Hengqin)”, at the Angsana Hotel, was approved by the Chinese organizing committee of the 48th edition of the World Vocational Aptitude Competition as one of China's preparation bases for this competition. “The designation of the Macau Base as China's preparation base is the result of innovative cooperation in planning, construction, administration and joint use between Guangdong and Macau, representing a significant recognition of talent training in Macau and Hengqin”, highlights DSAL.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau and Hong Kong discuss water conservation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-hong-kong-discutem-conservacao-de-agua/</link><description>The exploration of unconventional water resources and water conservation policies were topics discussed in a meeting between officials from the Macau Department of Maritime and Water Affairs (DSAMA) and the Hong Kong Water Supply Department. At the meeting, DSAMA presented the various projects and constructions that the Government is promoting in the use of recycled water, as well as increasing the autonomy of water consumption in Macau.
In turn, the organization from the neighboring region shared the experience and results of the water recycling system in several districts of Hong Kong, and the supply of locally recycled water. “Both parties exchanged views on the development of the use of unconventional waters, the promotion of education on water saving and technical training, among other aspects”, says a statement from DSAMA.
The two parties are participating in the process of drafting the “Greater Bay Common Water Criteria” and the “Greater Bay Common Drinking Water Quality Criteria”, promoted by the Pearl River Water Resources Commission of the Ministry of Water Resources. The objective is to jointly define the “Greater Bay Criteria”.
Wong Soi Man, director of DSAMA, said that the two special administrative regions, as cities in the Greater Bay Area, are facing many similar challenges in managing water resources.
After the meeting, in which, among others, the deputy general manager of Macao Water, Chu Wai Man, also participated, representatives from Kong Kong visited the Coloane Recycled Water Station Phase I, to learn more about the infrastructure construction project for recycled water to be launched soon in Macau, underlines the DSAMA note, highlighting that the Hong Kong Water Supply Department and Macao Water have maintained good communication and interaction.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Five major Codes reviewed by priorities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cinco-grandes-codigos-revistos-por-prioridades/</link><description>Wong Sio Chak stated that the five major Codes will be reviewed depending on priorities. The process will begin with the Administrative Procedure Code
 
In order to promote the modernization of Macau's legal system, the Government has been gradually carrying out work to review the major Codes and study the respective changes, said the Secretary for Administration and Justice. In this process, priority will be given to reviewing and amending the Code of Administrative Procedure (CPA), the revision proposal for which will be submitted to the Legislative Assembly this year.
In response to an oral interpellation by Lei Wun Kong, Wong Sio Chak also announced the completion of basic studies relating to the Civil Procedure Code (CPC) and the start, in 2026, of the respective consultation work. As for the Contentious Administrative Procedure Code (CPAC), preliminary basic studies have already been completed, and the respective revision should progress gradually, in conjunction with that of the CPC. Finally, regarding the Penal Code (CP) and the Code of Criminal Procedure, it is expected that the corresponding basic studies will be completed this year.
According to the Secretary, the order of the review was defined according to priorities, the needs of citizens and the development of society. On the other hand, he highlighted that, to guarantee the specialization and effectiveness of the review work, the Government created several specialized monitoring groups for the Codes, made up of magistrates, lawyers and personnel from the Government's legal area, among others.
The CPA deserved priority, because it is closely linked to the functioning and increasing the administrative efficiency of the Government, explained Wong Sio Chak. The CPC and CPAC are also seen as priorities as they involve the efficiency of processes, given that civil processes tend to be very long and complex, he noted.
Finally, the Secretary recalled that the CP has already been subject to several changes in recent years. Some crimes may be included in the CP, but certain emerging crimes, with frequent changes, such as technological crimes, may not apply to this approach, especially because the constant review of the CP would be unfavorable to its stability, he argued.
The Government will, “based on the results of the basic studies, sufficiently consider the articulation between the different codes, between the codes and other legal provisions, as well as their harmonization in order to define the guidelines for the revision of the codes, including the study on the introduction, in the procedural codes, of provisions relating to procedural electronicization and procedural simplification, with the aim of improving the current procedural system, taking as a reference the experiences and practices of other countries and regions, adapted to the reality of Macau”, he stated.
 
Marriage registration for non-resident couples discarded
In another oral interpellation, Si Ka Lon suggested that the authorities allow marriage registration in Macau, regardless of the bride and groom's place of residence, to boost the “wedding tourism” market, as in Las Vegas.
This hypothesis was discarded by Wong Sio Chak, who warned that Macau's marriage registration regime is interconnected with the provisions enshrined in Family Law of the Civil Code. This gives rise to other legal effects linked to marital relations, particularly with regard to the property regime, conjugal rights and duties, kinship and even succession effects.
For the Secretary, even if the bride and groom register their marriage elsewhere, they can take advantage of the local landscapes and restaurants to hold wedding ceremonies. On the other hand, he stressed that marriage registration is “serious and solemn”, appearing as a legal contract that entails a series of legal consequences.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mendes and Seguro with agents in Macao and Ventura without local representative</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mendes-seguro-mandatarios-na-raem-ventura-sem-representante-local/</link><description>At a time when the campaign for the presidential elections is underway in Portugal, only two candidates nominated representatives for Macau, with António José Seguro and Luís Marques Mendes being represented in the territory by Jorge Neto Valente and António Bessa Almeida. The rest opted for national and district representatives and coordinators
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
So far only Luís Marques Mendes and António José Seguro, two of the candidates for the presidential elections in Portugal, have appointed representatives for the Macao SAR, with António Bessa Almeida and Jorge Neto Valente, respectively, being the liaison elements.
In a published manifesto, Bessa Almeida states that, “in the candidacy debates and the personal contact we had with the candidate, we learned better about the political capacity and the requirements necessary to hold a high position in the Nation”. Mendes' representative for Macau, and also for Hong Kong, highlights that there has always been “concern” about everything related to Portugal and “much more so at this time where political changes at a global level are sudden and unexpected”.
Therefore, he says, “we need a visionary president, experienced and thoughtful in guiding the destinies of Portugal, of Portuguese people born and living outside the country”. He also states that, in the debates, “Luís Marques Mendes stood out among all the candidates, demonstrating uninterrupted political experience and the capacity for dialogue to find consensus with all social sectors”.
In the opinion of the representative, who is linked to the local PSD section, “the President of the Republic, above all, must have the ability to aggregate and not divide”. From this perspective, he understands that Marques Mendes is the only candidate who “brings together all the attributes”.
In a reference to Portuguese people living abroad, the campaign manifesto emphasizes that Mendes promised to “closely monitor all diaspora matters”, including in Macau and Hong Kong.
It is worth remembering that Jorge Fão, António José Seguro's campaign director, also highlighted, through a letter, the reason for his support for the candidate, recalling that he has been following the current political situation in Portugal, a subject that deserves concern and attention, “because we are all Portuguese, even if born far from the country”. For Fão, Seguro represents a candidacy of “maturity, responsibility and historical vision, and is therefore not an ornamental, confrontational or spectacular presidency”.
Regarding the candidacy of André Ventura, leader of Chega, the third most voted party in Macau in the last elections for the Assembly of the Republic, behind the Socialist Party (second) and Democratic Alliance (first), he decided not to have any representative outside of mainland Portugal and the Islands, but only at national and district level. “Since there are no constituencies in these elections, only the national representative, Pedro Tinoco de Faria, was appointed,” a source linked to Chega told Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU.
The official campaign for the January 18 elections officially kicked off last Sunday, with 11 candidates, a record number. Seven have party support. In addition to the names already mentioned, the others are Henrique Gouveia e Melo, João Cotrim de Figueiredo, Catarina Martins, António Filipe, Jorge Pinto, Manuel João Vieira, André Pestana and Humberto Correia.
There were supposed to be 14 competitors, but three (Joana Amaral Dias, José Cardoso and Ricardo Sousa) were unable to meet all the conditions to formalize the race for president. However, their names will appear on the ballot paper.
The National Elections Commission said that it was no longer possible to remove the three names from the ballots, since the printing process “had already started” so that they could be sent in time for early voting, which takes place on different dates (5th and 8th for voters unable to travel, 6th, 7th and 8th abroad and 11th January for mobile voting within the national territory).</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Open Day launches celebrations of UM’s 45th anniversary</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dia-aberto-lanca-comemoracoes-45o-aniversario-da-um/</link><description>The University of Macau (UM) will hold an “Open Day” next Sunday, January 11, marking the beginning of its 45th anniversary celebrations. By 5pm, three locations will be open to the public: the main campus, UM's Scientific and Technological Research Institute in Zhuhai, in the Youth Entrepreneurship Valley in Hengqin, and, for the first time, its Research and Transitional Education Center in Yuxin Tower, in the Deep Cooperation Zone.
Encompassing various in-person activities and live online broadcasts, the event will showcase UM's latest developments and achievements in teaching, research and community service. According to the higher education institution, around 250 initiatives will be developed on the main campus, including lectures on admission, academic and research activities.
Students and parents will be able to attend admissions talks and visit information desks at colleges and research institutes to speak directly with professors about academic programs and planning. The program also includes lectures on science and other subjects, guided tours and the possibility of exploring UM's sports facilities.
For families, several faculties, student residences and laboratories will organize interactive games on stands, scientific experiments, workshops and knowledge challenges. In addition, “cultural and audiovisual presentations will offer a vibrant view of campus culture”, says the UM statement, adding that several restaurants and stores on campus will offer special discounts during the “Open Day”.
Meanwhile, UM's Hengqin Research and Transitional Education Center and Zhuhai Scientific and Technological Research Institute will host admission lectures, research seminars, alumni sharing sessions and interactive activities.
Currently, UM offers more than 100 bachelor's, master's and doctoral programs in diverse areas, including literature, languages, business management, marketing, accounting, finance, integrated resort management, science, education, biomedical sciences, law, history, economics, psychology, sociology, communication, engineering, computer science and traditional Chinese medicine. The application deadlines for the undergraduate (joint admission exam) and postgraduate programs are extended until January 16th and March 13th, respectively.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Historic Center with online route</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/centro-historico-percurso-online/</link><description>The Cultural Institute (IC) added the “Track through the Historic Center of Macau” to the themed website “Macau Cultural Heritage Trails” (www.culturalheritage.mo/pt/plans), so that residents and tourists can explore UNESCO-listed sites more conveniently. The “Routing through the Historic Center of Macau” has the World Heritage Site as its central core, connecting 22 historic buildings and 8 squares, including the Temple of A-Má and the Ruins of São Paulo. “Along the area’s undulating terrain and winding streets, the public will be able to explore its profound historical legacy, architectural features and urban landscapes, thus getting to know Macau’s vibrant diversity as a meeting point between Eastern and Western cultures,” highlighted the IC. In addition to various information and images, the themed website includes video guides, audio guides and interactive maps. In addition to the new route, the website also proposes two other thematic routes: the “Track of Historic Sites on the Macau Maritime Silk Road” and the “Tour of Historic Buildings with Educational Functions in East-West Cultural Exchange”. The IC assured that it will continue to explore Macau's historical resources, gradually launching new thematic routes and enriching the content of the website, in order to encourage the public to learn about and experience the history and culture of the territory.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>ORDERED WITHDRAWAL OF 21 LOTS OF MILK POWDER FROM NESTLÉ</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ordenada-retirada-de-21-lotes-de-leite-em-po-da-nestle/</link><description>baby milk bottle isolated on white background



The Institute for Pharmaceutical Supervision and Administration (ISAF) and the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) ordered the withdrawal from the Macau market of six batches of powdered milk for infants from the Nestlé Nan brand and 15 from Wyeth Nutrition, on suspicion of being contaminated with a bacteria (“bacillus cereus”). Hong Kong authorities also adopted the same preventive measure. In a joint statement, ISAF and IAM stated that they were “extremely concerned about the incident”, and therefore took “immediate measures”, issuing a food safety alert and “requiring the removal of products from shelves, their collection and the suspension of sales of the affected lots”. The two organizations also sent personnel to inspect the market and contact the main importers, having confirmed that some of the products were imported to Macau. As a precautionary measure, regardless of how the products were purchased, babies “should not consume” powdered milk from the affected batches, the statement highlights, adding that if this happens “they should immediately seek medical assistance”. ISAF and IAM guarantee that they will continue to monitor the incident to prevent the circulation of affected products on the MSAR market. In another statement, Nestlé highlighted that the collection of batches, including from cross-border e-commerce platforms, is a “precautionary” measure, ensuring that it has not received reports of any illness associated with the consumption of the products in question. Even so, “out of extreme caution, Nestlé Nutrition decided to carry out this voluntary recall of products, in accordance with our strict quality and safety protocols”, says the note. The batches in question were imported from Germany and Switzerland.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2524/</link><description>Pedestrian crossings in Zone A will cost more than 20 million
The Public Works Services Department admitted the 15 proposals submitted to the public tender for the design and construction of an overpass for pedestrians between Lots A1 and A4 of Zone A of the New Urban Landfills, whose prices vary between more than 22 million and 23 million patacas. Execution times vary between 342 and 360 working days. The start of work is scheduled for the second quarter of this year. Approximately 37 meters long and three meters wide, the passage will cross Avenida Doutor Ma Man Kei, connecting the buildings on both sides of the road, and will provide, in each lot, access equipped with an elevator, escalator and accessible facilities.
 
Three job sessions offer more than 220 vacancies
The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) and the Federation of Workers' Associations will co-organize three job matching sessions between January 14th and 16th, offering a total of 227 job vacancies for residents. On the 14th, Nova Galaxy Entretenimento 2006 Companhia Limitada will offer 40 vacancies in the hotel and restaurant sectors, followed the following day by SJM Resorts, with 22 vacancies. Job matching sessions are scheduled for the 16th for Companhia de Hotel Roosevelt Macau Limitada, offering a total of 165 vacancies. Registration is open until noon on the 13th.
 
Melco supports health project in Jiangxi province
Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment donated three million Hong Kong dollars for the construction and relocation of the Health Center in Hangkou City, Xiushui County, Jiangxi Province. Through this support, the gaming operator aims to contribute to rural revitalization efforts in Xiushui County, together with the Macao SAR Government and the Central Government Liaison Office. According to the company, the project will benefit around 100,000 people in Hangkou and neighboring cities, with an outpatient care volume of approximately 40,000 patients and an inpatient flow of around 2,500. "Melco is honored to support the country's rural revitalization goals. We recognize that high-quality healthcare is the foundation of sustainable social development. By contributing to this modernized facility, we aim to provide the local community and residents of the surrounding industrial zones with quality medical resources," said Lawrence Ho, president and CEO of the company.
 
Health Services warn of low temperatures
The Meteorological and Geophysical Services Department has issued a yellow warning for low temperatures, predicting that the weather in Macau will remain cold in the coming days, with minimum temperatures equal to or below 12º C. Therefore, the Health Services (SSM) warn citizens to take precautionary measures against hypothermia, keeping themselves properly dressed. In particular, the elderly, people with chronic illnesses, their caregivers and institutions “must adopt appropriate preventive measures to protect their health”, highlights a statement from the SSM.
 
Third phase of support for scrapping diesel vehicles launched
The Environmental Protection Services Directorate has started accepting applications for the third phase of the “Financial support plan for the scrapping of old diesel-powered vehicles”. This two-year plan is aimed at owners of old diesel vehicles registered and registered until December 31, 2019, excluding those whose registrations were canceled on December 15, 2025, or on a later date, and who are re-registered. The application deadline in the first year runs until January 4, 2027 and the amount of financial support varies between 25 thousand and 155 thousand patacas. For the second year, applications can be submitted between January 5, 2027 and January 4, 2028 and the amount of support varies between 15 thousand and 93 thousand patacas.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Changi Airport handled almost 70 million in 2025</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/aeroporto-de-changi-movimentou-quase-70-milhoes-em-2025/</link><description>Changi Airport handled about 70 million passengers in 2025, surpassing pre-Covid-19 levels, said Acting Transport Minister Jeffrey Siow. Passenger numbers hit an all-time high, eclipsing the previous record of 68.3 million in 2019, before the pandemic grounded flights and devastated air travel. In 2024, Changi Airport will handle 67.7 million passengers.
The strong recovery of international aviation after the pandemic demonstrates that the Government made the right decision in continuing construction plans for the airport's Terminal 5, which were interrupted during the pandemic, said Siow at the opening of a new exhibition on the future mega terminal. Stressing that the decision to build T5 was based on confidence in Singapore's future and the conviction of the country's ability to secure its place in a competitive world, he said that this confidence was shaken when global aviation demand collapsed during the pandemic.
"For a while, we weren't sure what the future of aviation held. And we deeply reconsidered whether we should continue with T5," he said, but the government decided to move forward and the future now looks bright – global air traffic is expected to double by 2050, with the Asia-Pacific region leading this growth.
With Terminal 5 representing the future of aviation for Singapore, it was designed to be highly technological, driven by automation and artificial intelligence (AI), he highlighted. For example, autonomous vehicles and robotics are already being tested in labor-intensive processes such as baggage and cargo handling.
The new mega terminal – scheduled to open in the mid-2030s – will show the way to aviation sustainability, promoting the use of sustainable aviation fuel and being fully electrified, he said.
It was designed to be customer-first, with ideas from passengers, airlines and airport tenants incorporated into the layout of the lounges and the design of the commercial spaces, Siow said.
Terminal 5 will increase Changi Airport's annual passenger capacity by more than 55% to 140 million.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>