<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Wynn Macau plans investments of six billion in two years</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/wynn-macau-planeia-investimentos-de-seis-mil-milhoes-em-dois-anos/</link><description>The Wynn Macau Investment Program will gain a new momentum by the end of next year, with the channeling of about six billion patacas for the implementation of commitments made in the concession contract, including the construction of a new Cotai event center. Entertainment is boosting the tourist flow in Macao, observed Wynn CEO, admitting that the company has benefited from the impact of the concerts performed on Venetian and Galaxy. Still, the results of the second quarter were short of expectations
 
Sérgio Terra
 
Among mashed modernization and expansion projects, Wynn Macau plans to invest around US $ 750 million (six billion to the current exchange rate) by the end of 2026, especially the construction of a large Event Center at Wynn Palace in Cotai. This project is part of the set of commitments made in the concession agreement, which entered into force on 1 January 2023 and is valid for 10 years.
Expected to be concluded for the beginning of 2028, a period of course subject to government approvals, the “Wynn Palace Entertainment and Entertainment Center” will be erected on a land located at the northern end of the resort, according to Craig Billings, executive director of the Wynn Resorts Group, in the presentation of financial fiscal year results in the second quarter of 2025.
"It is absolutely true that entertainment has driven visitors and demand," said Billings, admitting that Wynn has benefited from the impact of the concerts recently performed on Galaxy Macao and Venetian. “We also recognize that we need the ability to boost entertainment, so the largest component of our commitment to the concession [in Macau] is an event center, and we are well referred to the project's engineering and design”, promising to offer “high quality” shows.
The investment strategy is part of a context of growing competitiveness in the Macao market. “It's a daily ways to be melee for the market share and we adjust and modulate our reinvestment up or down every day, time, week or month, depending on the objectives we seek to achieve,” said Wynn Resorts CEO, asserting having a “very clear view” about the volume of reinvestment required for Wynn Macau to keep “competitive” and “profit”.
The game operator allocated between 200 and 250 million dollars (between 1.6 billion and two billion patacas) for investments in 2025, including the expansion of the game of "Chairman's Club" in Wynn Palace and the renewal of rooms at the Wynn Macau hotel. For 2026, the budget rises to a range between $ 450 and 500 million (between 3.6 billion and four billion patacas).
In the context of the concession contract, Wynn Macao has committed to execute an initial investment plan of 17.7 billion patacas over the 10 years of the license, of which 16.5 billion (93.1% of the total) in non-game elements. However, the channeled value for projects without game will have to be reinforced by 20%, a requirement for the case of Macau casinos to make 180 billion of patacas in any of the first five years of the new concessions, which occurred in 2023. The game's annual gross revenue target will be valid in the second half of the percentage of licenses, but the extra investment percentage will decrease to 16% by 2028 And it will continue to lower four points a year, until it is annulled by 2032.
 
Operational gains below forecasts
Wynn Macau's operating results ciphed at $ 128.3 million (1.04 billion patacas) in the second quarter of 2025 and $ 255.4 million (2.1 billion patacas) in the first half, which represents annual descents of 20.8% and 30.6%, respectively. According to data released by Wynn Resorts, based on US accounting standards, EBITDA (results before interest, taxes, amortization and depreciation) reflected gains of 253.7 million in the second quarter (2.1 billion patacas) and 505.8 million in the semester (4.1 billion patacas), noting 9.5% homologous breaks of homologists and 18.4%, failing the average projections that, according to Banco Morgan Stanley, pointed to $ 274 million between April and June.
In annual terms, operating revenues went down 0.2% to $ 883.5 million (7.1 billion patacas) in the second quarter and 7.1% to $ 1.7 billion (14.1 billion patacas) between January and June. The two Wynn Macau casinos generated almost 84% of the company's total operating revenues, contributing to $ 741.7 million in the second quarter (six billion patacas) and $ 1.5 billion in the first half (11.8 billion patacas), which translate, respectively, a 2.2% increase in 5.4% in the annual comparisons.
After all, Craig Billings was pleased with the results in Macau. "Although the retention of the VIP game negatively impacted the results, we have generated a healthy market quota and a significant free cash flow, supporting our continuous investment in the properties of Macau and our dividend program," he said in a statement.
Between April and June, Wynn Palace registered operating revenues of $ 539.6 million, or 4.4 billion patacas (1.5% in the annual variation), and ebitda gains of $ 157.2 million (1.3 billion patacas) at 14.8%. On the other hand, on the peninsula, revenues rose 1.9% to $ 343.8 million (2.8 billion patacas), while Ebitda remained stable at $ 96.5 million (780.2 million patacas).
Globally, the Wynn Resorts group ended the first semester with net profits of $ 138.9 million (1.1 billion patacas), including 66.2 million (535.3 million patacas) in the second quarter, thus suffering homologous breaks of 10.9% and 40.8% respectively. In turn, Ebitda fell 3.4% to $ 552.4 million (4.5 billion patacas) between April and June and 10.9% to $ 1.1 billion (8.8 billion patacas) in the first six months of 2025.
"The results of the second quarter evidenced the continuous strength of our business and were marked by a new record in the second trimester of ebitdar adjusted from the properties in Las Vegas," said Craig Billings, again in a more positive record.
In the teleconference with analysts, the group's CEO revealed that the construction of Wynn Al Marjan Island, a resort developed in the United Arab Emirates in partnership with two local companies, has already reached the 61st floor, predicting that the works are completed in 2025. He added.
During the second quarter of 2025, Wynn contributed $ 58.2 million (470 million patacas) to the joint venture that is building the venture in the United Arab Emirates, from which it has 40% of capital, raising total investment to $ 741.1 million (about six billion patacas). The inauguration of Wynn Al Marjan Island is scheduled for 2027.</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>'Per capita' expense of visitors is already less than 2,000 patacas</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/despesa-per-capita-dos-visitantes-ja-e-inferior-2-000-patacas/</link><description>Completing two and a half years of decline, the 'per capita' expense of visitors in Macao, excluding game -related expenses, decreased about 13% in the first half of 2025, in homologous terms. The largest break occurred among international visitors
 
The 'per capita' expense of visitors, not related to the game, continues to fall into Macao, already below 2,000 patacas. Official data show that between April and June, spending dropped by the eighth consecutive quarter and only climbed once after the end of the pandemic, specifically in the second trimester of 2023. Sequential comparisons also illustrate the ninth break in the last 10 quarters.
After retreating 14.6% to 2,157 patacas at the general calculation of 2024, compared to 2023, the 'per capita' expense was estimated at 1,970 patacas in the first six months of this year. According to the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), it is a 12.8% decrease compared to the first half of 2024 (2,260 patacas), including 14.9% cuts in the expense of tour (702 patacas) and 4% in tourists (3,735).
Between January and June, the 'per capita' expenses of visitors from the interior of China (2,253 patacas), Hong Kong (940) and Taiwan (1,940) decreased by 14.4%, 13.4%and 7.4%, respectively, within one year. In the case of international visitors, there was a decrease from 16.9% to 1,885 patacas.
The 'per capita' data reveal that 43.7%of spending involved purchases, followed by accommodation (24.3%) and food (22.9%). The expenses of visitors who came to participate in conventions or exhibitions (4,232 patacas) and watch shows or competitions (4,161) were again the highest in the first half.
In absolute terms, due to the increase in the number of entries in the territory, the total expense of visitors not related to the game rose 0.2%to 37.86 billion of patacas compared to the first half of 2024, including 30.01 billion of tourists (less 1.4%) and 7.85 billion of tourists (plus 7%).
Considering only the second quarter, total expenses grew 4.6% to 18.25 billion in the homologous variation, and those of tourists (14.64 billion) and tour (3.61 billion) increased 4.4% and 5.5%, respectively. However, between April and June, the per capita spending of visitors retreated 12.3% to 1,950 patacas in the annual range, with a decrease of 19.3% among the excursionists (673 patacas) to overcome the 2.1% break in tourist expenditure (3,663).
In the second quarter, savings was most evident among visitors to mainland China (2,203 patacas) and international (2,134 patacas), with 15% and 10.2% breaks in per capita expenses. Visitors from Hong Kong and Taiwan reduced expenses by 9.1% and 5.1% to 1,000 and 2,031 patacas.
Among the exceptions include visitors from Singapore (3.201 Patacas) Japan (2,274) and Malaysia (1,799), with growth of 22%, 18.5%and 6.1%.
 
Electronic payments go up on restoration and fall into the retail
In the first six months of 2025, the volume of electronic payment transactions rose 3.1% in the restoration business, to 6.75 billion patacas, but went down 10.2% to 25.05 billion in retail trade, compared to the same period of 2024, reveals data from statistics and census services. The trend remained in June, with an annual increase of 2.2% in restoration (1.06 billion) and a 1.5% decrease in retail trade. These statistics take into account the data provided by the main Macao institutions that receive electronic payment invoices, corresponding to about 95% of the total.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More residents in construction despite lower wages</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-residentes-na-construcao-apesar-de-salarios-mais-baixos/</link><description>Despite losing more than three thousand workers, between the first half of 2024 and the same period this year, the construction sector was able to employ another 1,500 residents in this time interval. There are also more women and people over 55 years old, reveal official data
 
Pedro Milheirão
Within a year, MSAR residents compensated almost half of the workers' losses in the construction sector, according to data from the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services. In the first half of 2024, the general population of Macao had 26,300 workers in the sector, 14 thousand were residents. In this year's homologous period, the construction was 23,000 (-12.55%), which included 15,500 residents (+10.71). In terms of salaries, and between the two periods under analysis, the median monthly income remained the same for the set of resident and non-resident workers, settling in the 15,000 patacas. On the other hand, in the particular case of residents the value fell from 17 thousand to 16,800 patacas.
In addition, 1,100 of the 7,300 unemployed residents (26.19%) belonged to the construction sector until June this year. These were only surpassed by the 1,300 unemployed retail area, which represented 30.95% of the 4,200 residents without employment. The construction was also the area of activity with more underemployed residents, with 1,700 out of a total of 5,800, of different activities. Even underemployed women increased 27.78%from 1,800 to 2,300, between the first half of 2024 and the same temporal interval this year. In the first half of the year, there were also 1,600 underemployed residents over 55, more than any other age group.
Transport, storage and communications were other sectors where the number of residents grew. In the first half of 2024, they represented 17,600 of the workers of these activities, between 21,100. In the first six months of 2025, it was already 19,200 (+9.09%) out of a total of 20,700.
In the branches of real estate and hospitality, residents recorded the highest losses in terms of salaries, analyzing the same period. In real estate, the average monthly income went from 16,000 to 13,000 (-18.75%). In “hotels and the like”, workers began to earn 18,000 patacas (-10%).
Until June, 65,600 of the 70,200 workers (93%) in the game sector were residents. In the first six months of 2024, the 70,300 branch workers included 65,100 residents. Considering the wages of the general population in the main branches, the median monthly income “in the lottery and other betting games” was the one that fell the most, from 23,000 to 21 thousand patacas (-8.7%).
Financial services lost 15.33% of their work force, from 15,000 employees to 12,700, within one year.
The employed population went from 376,400 people between January and June 2024 to 372,700, in the same period of 2025. The age group over 65 years was the fastest growing, from 12,600 employees to 13,800 (+9.52%). The age group from 16 to 34 was the one that recorded the highest losses in number of workers, from 111,100 to 102,500 (-7.74%).
Considering only the residents, the 3,300 individuals from 16 to 34 represented almost half (45.21%) of the 7,300 unemployed. These data coincide with the fact that the number of unemployed residents looking for the first job increased from 500 to 800 (+60%), compared to the first half of 2024.
From the population employed, 29,816 people had primary education, 57,396 completed the secondary general, 104,729 the complementary secondary, 174,424 had a higher education formation and 6,336 another type of training in the first half of the year. Among the main professions of the population employed, 53,700 were technicians and intermediate level professionals (14.41%), 90,000 administrative employees (24.15%), 73,000 worked in services or were sellers (19.59%), 21,300 were workers of industrial production and artisans (5.72%) and 62,600 had no qualifications (16.8%).
Between January and June, 23,700 full -time workers earned less than six thousand patacas (6.36%), 19,600 earned between six thousand to 7,999 (5.26%), 43,600 had remuneration of eight thousand to 11,999 (11.70%), 47,800 earned between 12 thousand and 15,999 (12.83%) and 31,800 received between 16 thousand and received 19,999 (8.53%). The 20,000 to 24,999 Patacas level had 51,000 employees (13.68%), 22,100 workers received a salary of 25,000 to 29,999 (5.93%), 28,600 people earned between 30 thousand and 39,999 (7.67%) and 47,300 had monthly income of over 40,000 patacas (12.69%).
During the same period, among residents with full -time contract, 3,900 earned less than eight thousand patacas (1.38%), 18,000 earned between eight thousand and 11,999 (6.39%), 34,000 received between 12,000 and 15,999 patacas (12.07%) and 29,300 had salaries of 16,000 to 19,999 (10.4%). In addition to these, 48,500 residents received between 20 thousand and 24,999 patacas (17.22%), 20 thousand earned 25 thousand to 29,999 patacas (7.10%), 27,200 earned between 30 thousand and 39,999 patacas (9.66%) and 45,300 received more than 40 thousand (16.09%).</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sun Yat-Sen “Revisited” at the Macau Museum</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sun-yat-sen-revisitado-museu-de-macau/</link><description>About 100 pieces and collections of historical images, documents and relics fill a patent exhibition until October 12 at the Macau Museum to mark the centenary of the death of Sun Yat-sen

The Macao Museum inaugurated on Friday a commemorative exhibition of the centenary of the death of Sun Yat-Sen, the first president of Post-imperial China and considered the "father" of the modern era of the country, in order to pay tribute to his "noble spirit" in the "search for the revitalization of the nation." Organized together by the Macao IC Cultural Institute), Hong Kong Cultural and Leisure Services Department and Zhongshan Department of Culture, Radio, Television and Tourism, the exhibition of “Dr. Sun Yat-Sen's Salvation Cure in Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau” is evident to the public until October 12 this year.
The exhibition features about 100 pieces/collections of historical images, documents and valuable historical relics of Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macao, divided into four sections: “The Cradle of Nation's Salvation,” “The Cradle of Revolution”, “The National Regions of the Family” and “Memorials for the Great Spirit”. According to the IC, the show highlights “systematically the deep links of Dr. Sun Yat-Sen and members of his family with Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau, as well as his fighter and indomitable spirit and his revolutionary career, revealing the process of rejuvenation of the Chinese nation in the modern era and the importance of national reunification and progress”.
Based on the theme of this show, the Macau Museum will also launch an online virtual reality exhibition through its electronic page.
On its website, the Macau Museum underlines that Sun Yat-sen was "a great national hero, a great patriot and a great pioneer of China's democratic revolution", "determined to save his country and his people." Guangdong, where Sun was born and began his studies, Hong Kong, where he did secondary studies and attended medicine, and Macau, where he began to exercise medicine, "were the main bases for his revolutionary activities," he emphasizes that "it was in these places that Dr. Sun used medical practice as" form of entry into the world ".
"Most of the armed revolts they planned were organized and directed from Canton and Hong Kong and, after the Republic of China, went to the south and established revolutionary governments in Canton on three occasions, to protect the newborn republic and seek national reunification," he says.
It is recalled that Sun Yat-Sen's family resided until 1952 in a building on Silva Mendes Street, which is part of the list of real estate classified as Macao's cultural heritage. In 1958 housing was transformed into an exposure space, which remains in operation.
The Macao Museum is open daily from 10:00 to 18:00 hours, ending on Monday. Admission is free for people with Macau BIR and, on Tuesday and the 15th of each month, to the general public.</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New subsidy supports projects on intangible heritage</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/novo-subsidio-apoia-projectos-sobre-patrimonio-intangivel/</link><description>The Culture Development Fund will launch in 2026 for the first time a subsidy to promote intangible heritage. In addition, it will also support other activities and cultural projects. Registrations open the day after
 
For the first time, the Culture Development Fund (FDC) will launch the “Financial Support Plan to the Intangible Cultural Heritage Projects of 2026”. The initiative aims to encourage entities that are dedicated to safeguarding intangible cultural heritage, local associations or foundations to present projects “in order to promote community participation in transmission, awareness, study and dissemination of intangible cultural heritage”.
According to the FDC, the scope of financial support is limited to projects already included in the list and inventory of intangible cultural heritage, “including applications whose content is entirely made up of Cantonense opera prominent”. Other related musical art projects may apply for the “financial support plan for cultural activities/projects”. The modality of financial support for this plan is for subsidies, with the period of financial support of one year.
The “Financial Support Plan for Activities/Cultural Projects of 2026” aims to support local associations or foundations in the creation and promotion of activities and exchanges in cultural and artistic areas, “also promoting the conservation of local history and culture”.
It covers various artistic and cultural areas, including visual arts, literary creation, music, musical art (including musical dialogue) and recreational activities (classic and popular songs), theater, dance, tangible cultural heritage, fashion, design, cinema and television, animation. In this case, the financial support period may be one or two years.
To improve the effectiveness of the use of public resources, all applications must be evaluated by the “Activities and Project Evaluation Committee”, according to the defined criteria, “in order to support, through the selection modality, projects and activities with quality content, proper planning, reasonable budget and contribute to the cultural and artistic development or to safeguard the intangible cultural heritage of Macau, whose candidates, and whose candidates have good execution capacity. ”
Both application periods will take place from August 13 to September 8, 2025. The FDC will hold a clarification session on the two financial support plans, on August 22, at 2:30 pm, at the Center for Science Convention Hall.</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mandar reinforces cooperation with Shanghai in nine areas</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-reforca-cooperacao-xangai-em-nove-areas/</link><description>Macao and Shanghai reinforced cooperation in nine areas, from finance and conventions and exhibitions to education, social action and technology. For Sam Hou Fai, “the level and effectiveness of cooperation have gradually improved” between the two parts
 
The chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, met with the mayor of Shanghai, Gong Zheng, at the government's headquarters, where they spoke about “important projects” for the new Pragmatic Cooperation round between Shanghai and Macao, according to a statement issued by the Social Communication Office. After the meeting, Macau and Shanghai signed a series of cooperation agreements.
First of all, they signed the memorandum of understanding within a new round of cooperation between the two parties, as well as a “memo about the deepening of financial cooperation”. A letter of intent was also signed on “the reinforcement of cooperation in the convention and exhibition sector” between Shanghai and Macao.
In turn, the Shanghai Institutes for International Studies and the University of Macao (one) signed an agreement on academic exchange and cooperation. One also signed a cooperation agreement on scientific research in summer with the Faculty of Medicine of Shanghai Jiao Tong University. Cooperation in scientific and technological innovation was also the target of a memo of cooperation between the parties.
The Institute of Social Action also signed a memo of cooperation with the Department of Social Affairs of the CCP Municipal Shangoi Committee, while the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services reinforced exchange and cooperation in the area of Education with the Shanghai Municipal Education Commission.
Another of the agreements signed was between the Qualified Table Development Commission and the Shanghai Municipal Qualified Work Department.
The GCS statement did not detail, however, that actions will be taken in practice to reinforce cooperation in different areas.
During the meeting with Gong Zheng, the leader of MSA stressed that “the level and effectiveness of cooperation has gradually improved” between Macau and Shanghai, “forming a new scenario of continuous and in -depth development in various areas”, especially in finance, scientific and technological innovation, culture and tourism, conventions and exhibitions, youth and education.
In an interview with Jiefang Daily, the CCP's Shanghai Official Journal, Sam Hou Fai said this month will visit the Yangtzé River Delta region, hoping to be able to walk in Shanghai.
Asked if he is concerned about the attractiveness of Macao, given that tourists from the interior of China have started to have more options to travel, Sam Hou Fai said that according to the search for youth tourism, "Macao is considering how he can make the old areas in the most sought after by backpackers."
"If you can explore Macau's connotation in terms of a base of exchange and cooperation for the promotion of multicultural coexistence with a predominance of Chinese culture, I am not concerned with the decrease of young tourists' will to travel Macau," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau will have a pavilion at Food Expo in Raehk</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-tera-pavilhao-na-food-expo-na-raehk/</link><description>To support the expansion of Macao to abroad companies and the proper diversification of the economy, the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM) and the Macau Industrial Association will coordinate the installation of the Macao Pavilion, for the first time, at the 35th Hong Kong Gastronomy Fair (HKTDC Food Expo), which is held between 14 and 18 this month.
According to IPIM, 10 small and medium -sized Macao (SME) will also participate for the first time at the fair, specifically displaying and selling, along with about 500,000 professional traders and visitors, a total of 100 Macau Big Health products, “Macao Brands”, in which local products are recognized for the Macau Product Quality Certification Program. In addition, more than half are Halal certification holders. Some exhibitors intend to take advantage of the event to launch new products.
The Macao Pavilion will be divided into three zones: company standards, convention standards and exhibitions of an economic and commercial nature of Macau and Hengqin and promotion of the Sino-Lusophone platform, with animated check-in points and exchange promotion zones. Specifically, IPIM said that local SMEs carry products such as healthy foods, typical memories and pasta, alcohol and tea, among others. On the other hand, during the fair, digital influencers will visit the stands of companies.
Organized by the Hong Kong Trade Development Council, the 35th HKTDC, with an exhibition area of 32,000 square meters, will take place at the Hong Kong Convention and Exhibition Center. The event will feature 900 exhibitors from the interior of China, Japan, South Korea and Thailand, among others, to display typical gastronomies and inherent products of various locations in one space, indicates IPIM.
At the same time, six promotion and exchange sessions and 12 contact bag sessions are scheduled.</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Group that supports social store for 13 consecutive year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/grupo-wu-apoia-loja-social-pelo-13-ano-consecutivo/</link><description>The Wu Group donated 300,000 Patacas to the Santa Casa da Misericórdia Social Store of Macao (SCMM), to support the institution's operating expenses this month. Through the distribution of comic book with first -need goods, the project benefits 372 low -income families this month, including 300 nominated by the General Union of Residents Associations (Kaifong ') and Federation of Workers Associations (Faom), 47 families assisted by Santa Casa and 25 by the Macao Mental Mental Association. The president of the WU group, António Ferreira Wu, handed the check to the Santa Casa provider António José de Freitas, in a ceremony that was attended by NG Sio Lai, president of Kaifong, and Leong IOK VA, Faom consultant. At the time, António Ferreira Wu again praised the social store, in operation since 2013, for his commitment to the community, calling for more entities to associate with this cause. In turn, António José de Freitas thanked the sponsorship, highlighted the continuous support of the WU group over 13 years and reaffirmed Santa Casa's mission to help the needy.</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>USJ reinforces partnerships with institutions in Portugal</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/usj-reforca-parcerias-instituicoes-em-portugal/</link><description>The University of São José (USJ) strengthened partnerships in Portugal by signing a series of agreements with schools and associations. The dean of the higher education institution, Stephen Morgan, recently visited Portugal to establish partnerships with local educational institutions. The visit included meetings with leaders of the Portuguese Association of Catholic Schools (APEC), Brave Generation Academy (BGA) and Sharing Foundation. According to a USJ note, at a meeting with deacon teacher Fernando Magalhães, a memorandum of understanding was signed “to reinforce collaboration with the Catholic schools in Portugal”. This agreement “aims to create enriching experiences for students and teachers in various academic and cultural activities”. Already with BGA, in Cascais, Stephen Morgan met with the founders, Timothy and Lidia Vieira, having signed another agreement, in this case “focused on the development of essential skills for adolescents through personalized learning and innovation”. Finally, the rector of USJ met with Sílvio Santos and Miguel Santos of the Sharing Foundation at the International School of Oeiras, where a third memorandum of understanding was signed to promote collaboration in multicultural education. “These agreements contribute to the continuous expansion of the internationalization of USJ and the provision of valuable opportunities for your community,” read the statement.</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Renewed Children's Zone in the Garden of the City of Flores</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/renovada-zona-infantil-jardim-da-cidade-das-flores/</link><description>The Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) has completed the optimization works of the children's fun zone in the city of Flores, Taipa, as well as public toilets, in order to provide a “more comfortable” leisure space. In this area of children's fun, which occupied an area of 490 square meters, the facilities and the floor rugs were already “aged,” said AMI, explaining that “optimized, reordered and provided appropriate fun facilities for children with ages between the two and the 12 years”, including climbing and balanced devices, slips and bloods, among others. At the same time, the project included the installation of “a seamless safety rug”, a children's washbasin and a barriers access to connect the children's fun zone and the garden of the city of Flores.</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2451/</link><description>Replaced nutritional supplement for pregnant women
Health services (SSM) are replacing the nutritional supplement for pregnant “PRENATAL VITAMIN DHA Softgels”, giving priority to 1,367 residents to whom the drug was prescribed by the body. The measure arises after two lots of the drug were collected by the Institute for Pharmaceutical Supervision and Administration, because they were found "black spots in the capsules". Pregnant women heard by “or world tin toi” have asked the SSM to reveal what impacts discovered changes in the medicine can have on health. In turn, the SSM assured that they did not receive notifications about cases of side effects related to the take of this medicine.
 
Found lifeless two women
A middle-aged resident was found dead in the parking lot of a building on Nova da Areia Preta Street after falling from a high place. According to PJ, no criminal injuries were found or caused by acts of violence. On the other hand, a non-resident middle-aged woman was discovered at sea in front of the fishermen's dock and subjected to first aid, but the death was eventually confirmed by the hospital. Suspected injuries were also discarded in this case.
 
Four in the hospital after inhaling carbon monoxide
Four male residents, aged 31 to 58 years, were transported to the hospital after inhales carbon monoxide, while performing drainage work in an oil separation room from a hotel located on Dr. Sun Yat-Sen Avenue. According to health services, the four patients are in a stable state, and the case was caused by the accumulation of harmful gas in an environment with poor ventilation while using combustion equipment. The operation of the hotel area was suspended. However, services for labor matters were notified for the case.
 
MGM pays 1.2 billion in dividends
MGM China provides to spend about $ 1.19 billion from Hong Kong with the payment of dividends to shareholders, related to the first half of 2025. According to a statement sent to the Hong Kong scholarship, the MGM Board of Directors approved the payment of provisional dividends worth 0.313 hkd per action on September 3. The measure fits the company's new policy, which perspective the payment of a regular dividend of up to 50% of net profits. Between January and June, MGM registered net profits of 2.38 billion HKD, less 11.3% in annual terms.
 
IH listens to opinions on exchange of economic houses
Until September 30, the Housing Institute will hold a random telephone inquiry to collect the opinions of Macao residents and the residents of economic houses on the economic housing exchange regime. In the first phase, the organism took care of an institution to study the opinions of the members of the Council for public housing and social associations.
 
PJ looking for fugitive in case of loan for game
The PJ has detained two individuals from the interior of China -a 25 -year -old man and a 44 -year -old woman who will have committed illicit loan for play. PJ also looks for an accomplice on the run. According to he said, a non -resident was convinced by the detainee to deliver to the trio 148,000 HKD to be able to play in a casino with 296,000 HKD, on the condition of paying “interest” equivalent to 20% of the amount of the bet for each baccará round that won. If I lost, I would have to return all the money within a month. However, the player found that the number of game sheets he had received did not correspond to the agreed, so he had verbal conflicts with the suspects, which caught the attention of security guards of the casino, who decided to alert the police. In possession of the player, police found and seized 285 thousand HKD. The case was referred to the prosecutor.
 
Confiscados 358 kilos of shark fins
A cross -border truck was intercepted at the Zhuhai Delta Bridal Border Post, suspected of smuggling 358 pounds of shark fins on extinction. According to the gongbei customs, blue shark products were not declared to the authorities.
 
Air Macau Alert for Fake Cheap Airplane Tickets
Air Macao has called on to the public to be vigilant about misleading information in which false local travel agencies will disclose the offer of alleged cheap Air Macau tickets, hoping that citizens will not fall into this type of scam. According to the carrier, fake information try to instigate people to fill in personal data, which also affects the company's brand image. Air Macau has appealed to the public to resort to official channels and called for caution with the purchase of tourist products with advance payment or transfer of money to a private account.
 
Illegal crossing generated 187 cases in seven days
Between July 28 and August 3, the Public Security Police body detected 187 illegal crossing cases. The corporation also revealed a case of illegal crossing in which a 50 -year -old tourist from China was hit by a public bus on Luís Gonzaga Gomes Street. The woman was referred to the hospital. The bus driver passed the alcohol test, having been accused.
 
Price index remains low in housing
The global housing pricing rate dropped 3.1% to 196.1 in the second quarter of 2025 compared to the previous three months, with a 3.7% break in fractions built to counteract the 2.7% increase in houses under construction, the statistics and census services said. Compared to the period between April and June 2024, the General Housing Price Index decreased 10.4%, and the decline was higher in the mud and coloane islands (less 11.6%) than on the Macau Peninsula (10.1%minus).</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Food Bank has already supported more than 2,800 residents this year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/banco-alimentar-ja-apoiou-mais-de-2-800-residentes-este-ano/</link><description>In the first seven months of this year, Caritas de Macau accepted requests from 2,841 residents to receive support from the food bank. According to Paul Pun, secretary general of Caritas, on average, about 900 residents raise food attributed under the weekly food bank. On the other hand, the institution continues to make a temporary food supply service available to foreign citizens in Macao, and has been distributing bread to approximately 250 per week
 
Between January and July this year, 2,841 residents successfully requested the support of Caritas de Macao under the food bank, a number similar to the same period of 2024 (2,848 accepted requests), Paul Pun, Secretary General of the Institution, told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau.
In terms of a weekly average, about 900 residents receive food at food bank service stations, being sufficiently raised for an entire week, Paul Pun said. The weekly number is equivalent to the accounted for in the same period of last year.
The beneficiaries of the food bank are residents or local families of low income, not included in the subsidies network of the Institute of Social Action.
The short-term goal is to help alleviate the difficulties of these residents in life and make them physically and mentally more resilient. In the long run, the institution expects that, through the Food Bank project, the public provides more attention to the problem of poverty in local society and demonstrates more solidarity with others.
As for foreign citizens in the territory, Caritas also provides a temporary food supply service from pandemic. According to Paul Pun, the institution has received new food donations in the last two months, but as the amount is not very large, it has ceased to distribute them to foreign citizens on Sunday. However, it maintains the distribution of bread on weekdays, having served about 250 foreigners per week.
 
Home service for elderly with “remarkable” results
On the other hand, Caritas will organize the “Charity Race” at the University of Macao, on September 28, waiting for 2,000 participants. Paul Pun clarified that the funds raised through the race will be used to cover the expenses of the “We Connect” project, a new service launched by Caritas in March to provide support to the elderly at home or in designated places.
The “We Connect” service currently works with five helpers, all non -resident workers, and featured about 140 users in July. Currently, monitoring in the medical appointment and at night are the most sought after types of support by the We Connect users.
"This service has already begun to give very remarkable results. Some family members of the elderly want our support a lot. But on the other hand, the service costs 100 patacas per hour while that similar government subsidized only 100 patacas for eight hours of service. So we need to gradually broaden users of this new service," Paul Pun acknowledged.
In this sense, funds raised through race will help partially subsidize some users who actually require a longer duration of this service, but have been restricted by financial limitations.
"Some seniors have money deposited on the bank, but they don't want to get it up, because they only keep this money for use after you die. And there are others unable to raise money, which may also be some of our home support users," Paul Pun noted.
In general, the Secretary General of Caritas stressed that an amount of 300,000 Patacas, equal to the range of last year's race, will not be sufficient to support the respective service for a long time, because the management of this company by residents, the necessary means of transportation to travel to the hospital, among many operational details imply costs. On the other hand, he found, most people needed in this context continues to preference to the government's subsidized service, so the reinforcement of the disclosure will be one of the institution's important tasks.
Earlier next year, Caritas may need to increase the “We Connect” assistant team. Usually a helper can provide service to three seniors, and the five workers currently assume 50% of normal working volume. When they are not working, helpers are subject to training and other psychological works.
 
New home should take “a lot of time”
Already on the new elderly home of Caritas, with 40 beds, which will be located on Coronel Mesquita Avenue, Paul Pun revealed that the cultural institute “verbally” agreed with the design of the project. However, as there are divergent opinions between various government services, the project “may face many problems” and “it should take a long time”.
Regarding the institution's clinic, in Areia Preta, whose opening was scheduled for July 2024, the secretary general of Caritas revealed that the direction of soil services and urban construction recently approved the project project. After obtaining another document from this organism, Caritas may already require license from health services, and license issuance usually takes a few months. After this stage you can start recruiting doctors.
Maintaining the plan of three consultation rooms and three Western Medicine doctors, including a dentist, as well as the non -profit nature of the clinic, Caritas has supported an income for the occupation of space. “The preparation took a long time,” lamented the official, hoping that the procedures around the clinic will gain speed.
In addition, the Caritas Bakery, in the São Lázaro neighborhood, also did not go into operation according to the scheduled calendar - in April this year. Paul Pun explained that he has already obtained a license and the decoration was completed, and the institution was acquiring clothing equipment. Despite having resorted to different channels, Caritas has not yet been able to find a advisor, who, besides needing to make bread and cakes, must be “a loving person”. At the same time, it is necessary to seek sponsorship.
Four or five people with disabilities are intended to work at the bakery per day, each one or two hours a day. Bread sales will start when the master is found. On the other hand, Caritas intends, through the bakery, to offer birthday cakes to children.
 
Inclusive Travel Agency in “Stable Development”
In turn, Caritas Travel Agency Kin Hang, which promotes inclusive excursions, dedicated to people with mobility difficulties, “has maintained a stable development”, although it has not organized a high number of excursions. "People with disabilities still do not have a strong motivation to participate in paid tourist excursions," said Paul Pun.
Still, the official emphasized that the travel agency has the main objective "to give one more option to the disabled to leave home" and provide "an opportunity to their families to show affection". Normally, the agency serves families with members with disabilities or social groups that seek to promote a different way of social inclusion, through the organization of tours or sponsoring excursion rates.
According to Paul Pun, the agency's next excursion will depart in October with at least a dozen visually impaired tour, and can spend a night in the interior of China.</description><pubDate>2025-08-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Defended pedestrian areas in Zape</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/defendidas-areas-pedonais-zape/</link><description>Like several restoration traders at Zape, Leong Chon Kit, a vowel of the Central Zone Community Services Advisory Board, suggested pedestrian zones in that area of the city. In turn, another member of the Advisory Body, Lao Sio Cheok, proposed the regular holding of cream and “Bubble-Tea” pastel festivals at Zape
 
At a plenary meeting of the Central Zone Community Services Advisory Board, vowel Leong Chon Kit suggested the creation of “own characteristics” pedestrian zones at Zape. In the same vein, some traders who operate restaurants in Zape also proposed the transformation of some streets in this part of the city into pedestrian areas to improve the overall image of Zape.
Listened to the newspaper “or Mun”, traders appealed to the government to enjoy the gastronomic, cultural and creative fair, which will start on Zape on the 15th, to transform, for example, Beijing Street into one of the pedestrian zones. The idea has as reference the projects of community revitalization of Shanghai and Hong Kong.
Assuming that they will support and collaborate with the gastronomic fair, through the launch of discounts for consumers, retailers argued that any pedestrian zones could facilitate the displacement of residents and visitors to Zape, make young tourists more familiar with the area and enrich gastronomic elements through the attraction of different types of restaurants. According to the traders, the lack of cooking diversity in Zape has been the subject of comments among the public.
For vowel Leong Chon Kit, it would be advisable to create incentives for Zape restaurants to require Esplanade licenses to promote the transformation of commercial establishments. In addition, it expects community facilities to be perfected in the area, namely awnings, adjusted to the distribution of parking spaces and bus careers to become “more reasonable”.
Leong Chon Kit also requested a health center, spectacles and sports at Zape, as well as long -term community dissemination actions, with the aim of seeking sustainable development and the economic transformation of that part of the territory.
In turn, another member of the Advisory Board, Lao Sio Cheok, asked that new scenarios of cultural and tourist consumption will be fostered at Zape. In concrete, he suggested regularly holding a “cream festival” and a “Bubble-Tea Festival” at Zape, with a view to stimulating consumption.
Alongside this, this vowel proposed the “deep exploration” of the connotation of Flor de Lotus Square and the Kun Iam Ecumenical Center, and the integration of the respective elements into intellectual property brands, Chinese fashion and tourist activities of immersive experience.
On the other hand, Lao Sio Cheok has suggested to the government that “officially recommended” tourist tour of tourist tour and careers of free tourists to tourists, in order to bring more visitors to Zape, promoting sustainable development.</description><pubDate>2025-08-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Adult pacifiers are already a trend in China and South Korea</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/chupetas-para-adultos-ja-sao-uma-tendencia-na-china-na-coreia-sul/</link><description>Adult pacifiers, unlike babies, seem to have multiple uses: they are a tool for relieving stress, promoting better sleep and helping smokers stop smoking, according to retailers and advocates.
However, prolonged use of pacifiers - which has become a trend in recent times in China and other parts of the world, such as South Korea and the US - can cause jaw stiffness, teeth displacement and, when used during sleep, choking, warns medical professionals.
Some retailers are selling more than 2,000 adult pacifiers a month, according to news in the Asian countries press.
The pacifiers, which resemble those made for babies, but are larger, cost between 10 yuans and 500 yuans each on electronic trade platforms such as TAOBAO and JD.com.
Adult pacifier evaluations have been generally positive on social networks.
At Tiktok, several users from around the world have shared that adult pacifiers help them control anxiety and sleep better. A buyer described the product as “high quality” and stressed that it was comfortable to use without affecting his breathing.
"When I am under pressure at work, I feel a sense of childhood security," said a Chinese buyer.
Some have even ensured that pacifiers are useful for dealing with some symptoms of hyperactivity care deficit disturbance, such as restlessness, impulsivity and difficulty concentration.
"I only use an adult pacifier, it doesn't move with your teeth, I have been using it for four years," said a Tiktok user. Another confessed, "I'm so embarrassed, I'm addicted for 23 years, all my life."
However, some medical professionals warn against the use of adult pacifiers. According to dental doctors in cities in China, prolonged use of these pacifiers can cause jaw stiffness, pain when chewing and displacement of teeth if used for more than three hours a day.
Tang Caomin, a dentist in Sichuan, warned that "sleeping with a pacifier in the mouth can interfere with breathing and, in the worst case, there is a risk of asphyxiation." The doctor also warned that prolonged use can harm the bite, force the jaw and even interrupt sleep.
Zhang Mo, a Chengdu psychologist, noted that the popularity of these products may reflect deeper emotional needs. The expert also warns that the response to these problems is not intended to use children's comforts, but to face their own problems directly.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>