<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Minimum wage expected to increase to 7,280 patacas per month</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/salario-minimo-devera-aumentar-para-7-280-patacas-por-mes/</link><description>From January 1st next year, the minimum wage is expected to rise from 7,072 patacas per month to 7,280 patacas per month. At least, that is the intention of the Government, which will submit the proposed law to the Legislative Assembly as quickly as possible. Authorities estimate that the measure will benefit around 18,200 people, excluding domestic workers
 
Catarina Pereira*
 
The Government intends to raise the minimum wage to 35 patacas per hour, representing an increase of one pataca per hour, announced the spokesperson of the Executive Council, Wong Sio Chak. Since the idea is for the proposed law to come into force on January 1, 2026, the Secretary for Administration and Justice also indicated that the Government will “immediately submit it” to the Legislative Assembly for consideration.
The diploma proposes that the universal minimum wage be increased from the current 34 patacas per hour to 35 and from 7,072 patacas per month to 7,280 patacas, as well as from 272 to 280 patacas per day and 1,632 to 1,680 patacas per week. The increase is 2.9% in all forms of calculation.
The decision was taken after hearing the opinions of employers and workers within the Permanent Council for Social Coordination (CPCS), “and comprehensively considering the macroeconomy, the labor market, workers' remuneration and the operational situation of employers” during the implementation of the minimum wage between November 1, 2022 and October 31, 2024.
Remember that, before this decision, the expectation was that the minimum wage could increase to between 35 and 37 patacas per hour. The option for the minimum value was justified by the “current economic conditions” in the territory.
When this issue was discussed at the CPCS, employers rejected a possible increase in the minimum wage, arguing that the Executive should launch even more measures to support small and medium-sized companies.
For Vong Kuok Seng, vice-president of the board of the Macau Commercial Association and representative of employers, it would not be favorable to increase the minimum wage, since “the current business environment in Macau is not very optimistic”, he argued at the time. “Companies face many operational difficulties and the desire and form of consumption have also changed”, he explained.
The labor part asked for 37 patacas. Choi Kam Fu, vice-president of the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau and workers' representative, also defending an update of the review mechanism as it is “long overdue”.
According to Wong Sio Chak, the Government estimates that this increase will benefit around 18,200 workers, representing 4.4% of the total, “excluding domestic workers”. The main beneficiary groups will be workers in the building administration and cleaning services sectors.
 
Domestic workers are excluded again
The legal revision once again excludes domestic employees. At the press conference to present the proposal, the director of Labor Affairs Services (DSAL) defended the exclusion of domestic workers. “When the law was established, the main premise was the ‘unique nature’ of domestic work and the need for the worker to ‘integrate’ into the employer’s family life,” said Chan Un Tong.
“However, even if this legislation does not apply to them, this does not mean that their rights are not protected,” he added. For new contracts for domestic workers, signed from July 2024, the minimum remuneration set by DSAL is 3,200 patacas.
Chan Un Tong mentioned, however, that the median salary for these hires is around 3,800 patacas, a value that, in the director's opinion, “demonstrates that, even excluded from the general regime, there are mechanisms that guarantee a reasonable remuneration”.
It is recalled that, in 2022, the UN Human Rights Committee questioned Macau “why non-resident domestic workers are treated differently” and, unlike other workers, are not covered by the minimum wage.
“What measures is DSAL taking to protect the lives of migrant domestic workers, who are particularly vulnerable to illegal and abusive treatment by employers”, asked committee member Shuichi Furuya.
When explaining why domestic workers are not entitled to the minimum wage, DSAL responded to the committee that this group of workers is “a special case” and that “employers are providing employment without a profit motive”.
 
*With Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More public at the start of the Lusofonia Festival</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-publico-arranque-festival-da-lusofonia/</link><description>For some volunteers and visitors to the Lusofonia Festival, the start of this edition brought more people to Casas Museu da Taipa, compared to last year, as they told TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper. The event brought communities together again, in what is described as an “incredible opportunity” to “get to know various cultures of Portuguese-speaking countries”














































PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
The first days of the Lusofonia Festival brought more public to Casas Museu da Taipa, compared to last year's edition, according to some exhibitors and visitors that Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU spoke to. The general consensus of those interviewed is that the event got off to a good start and that many more people will visit the venue by the end of next weekend.
On Saturday afternoon, while some stalls and organizers were still finalizing preparations for the festivities, the first visitors were mainly concentrated at the foosball tables, the traditional Portuguese games area and the drawing, painting and crafts tables for the youngest.
Tristan, 24 years old and originally from Macau, said he was “very excited to participate as a volunteer for the first time, after many years as a visitor”. As he noted, the first days “attracted more people than previous years”, adding that the “general feeling is that many more people will visit the festival this year”.
Similarly, Peyton, a local student and volunteer for several years, also had “the feeling that there were more people”, despite “not remembering last year very well”, he confessed. Peyton also took the opportunity to highlight the cultural importance of the event. “It’s an incredible opportunity to get to know different cultures from Portuguese-speaking countries.”
Zoe and Matilde, Portuguese students, who “grew up with the festival”, also consider that “more visitors came than in recent years, especially since the pandemic”, in addition to having noticed “more tourists”. Regarding expectations for the rest of the festival, Zoe confessed that “they are always the same”. "It's always fun, we always meet people we know. It's really good. And it's a way to create bonds with friends too", he concluded, as they waited for the Calema duo's concert, close to the stage.
For Carlos and Adélia, natives of Mozambique and participants for the third consecutive year, “the event has gone well, with a lot of movement and a lot of support for the Banca de Moçambique”. Through the country's cultural products, such as drawings representing the Mozambican people, wooden and blackwood objects, sandalwood, capulanas and key chains, both explained that they intended to represent “not only Mozambique, but all of Africa”, while anticipating the Calema concert and the performance of the Tafika dance group.
The party continued yesterday at Casas Museu da Taipa and returns next weekend for three more days of entertainment, gastronomy, traditional games, crafts, among others.
Marisa Liz's concert is scheduled for November 1st, at the amphitheater, at 9:30 pm. Known mainly for being the lead singer of the band Amor Electro, with which she released successful albums and won several awards, Marisa Liz began a solo career in 2022 with the album “Girassóis e Tempestades”, and also stood out as a mentor in several editions of the television program “The Voice Portugal”.
 
Six major events until December
Until the end of next weekend, and with the promotion of Angolan culture as a highlight, the Festival da Lusofonia agenda will feature performances by groups from a total of 10 Lusophone regions and countries and more than 40 local artists.
The event is part of the program of the 7th Meeting in Macau – Festival of Arts and Culture between China and Portuguese-Speaking Countries, which runs until December. The remaining events of the Meeting in Macau include the Spiritual Narrative – Annual Arts Exhibition between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries, the Exhibition of Illustrated Books in Chinese and Portuguese, Traditional Music and Dance Shows in the Community, the 7th Film Festival between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries, the Vanessa da Mata Concert with the Macau Chinese Orchestra and the Chinese Tasting Workshop and Portuguese.</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Inflation in 2025 will mark third consecutive decline</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/inflacao-em-2025-vai-marcar-terceira-descida-consecutiva/</link><description>Macau is preparing to end 2025 with the lowest inflation rate in four years. Until the end of September, accumulated inflation stood at 0.24%, reflecting 15 successive months of slowdown, according to official data
 
SERGIO TERRA
 
The annual inflation rate in the Macao SAR will reach its lowest level after 2021 in 2025, culminating three consecutive years of deceleration, if the trend of the last 18 months does not undergo a major and unlikely reversal. Data from the Statistics and Census Services Department (DSEC) analyzed by the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper show that, in September this year, inflation accumulated in 12 months was the lowest since May 2024, following 15 consecutive months of slowdown.
According to DSEC, the general average consumer price index (IPC) rose just 0.24% in the annual cycle ending in September compared to the 12 months immediately previous (between October 2023 and September 2024). In this comparative basis, used by governments and economists to measure the annual inflation rate, the highlights, on the one hand, were the increases in the price indices of the “miscellaneous products and services” (+2.07%), “leisure, recreation, sport and culture” (+1.47%) and “education” (+1.08%) sections and, on the other, the drops in “information and communication” (-2.32%) and in “transport” (-2.24%).
Considering also the annual chain comparison until September, it appears that the IPC increased 0.19% in bracket A, which covers around half of households with average monthly expenses between 11,000 and 35,999 patacas, and 0.27% in bracket B, which encompasses 30% of families with average monthly expenses between 36,000 and 71,999 patacas.
It should be remembered that Macau recorded negative price variations between 2000 and 2003, with deflation rates of 1.61%, 1.99%, 2.64% and 1.56%, respectively, with this phenomenon resurfacing 18 years later, between March and November 2021. Even so, the accumulated rate in 2021 ended up marking a return to inflation, albeit residual. (0.03%), followed by an increase in 2022 (1.04%) and slowdowns in 2023 (0.94%) and 2024 (0.74%), in any case far from the record in the Macao SAR era, set in 2008 at 8.61%.
The updated data also indicates that the general CPI grew 0.47% compared to September 2024, again driven by the “leisure, recreation, sport and culture” section (+2.81%). The price indices for “food products and non-alcoholic drinks” and “housing and fuel” rose 0.56% and 0.37%, respectively, mainly due to the increase in the cost of meals purchased outside the home and “take-away” and household rent. Conversely, the “information and communication” (-2.94%) and “clothing and footwear” (-1.43%) indexes fell in annual terms.
On the other hand, the IPC rose 0.11% compared to August this year, illustrating increases in the indices of “education” (+0.94%), “miscellaneous products and services” (+0.74%) – including personal care, insurance, jewelry, goldsmithing and watches – and “food products and non-alcoholic drinks” (+0.23%). On the other hand, there were drops of 0.64% in the “leisure, recreation, sport and culture” sections and 0.56% in “transport”, thanks to the decrease in prices for excursions, hotel rooms and plane tickets after the summer holidays.
In year-on-year terms, the average general CPI increased by 0.22% in the first nine months of this year and 0.29% in the third quarter.
The expenses with the highest weights in the inflation calculation are those of the “housing and fuel”, “food products and non-alcoholic beverages” and “transport” sections, with weights of 34.47, 29.47 and 8.33, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 140 agreements signed at the three fairs</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/selados-mais-de-140-acordos-nas-tres-feiras/</link><description>The three fairs promoted by the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment attracted more than 85 thousand people over the four days, representing an annual increase of 30%. The Macau International Fair, China-Portuguese-Speaking Countries Economic and Trade Exhibition and Franchise Exhibition resulted in more than 140 commercial agreements

More than 85 thousand visitors attended the 2nd China-Portuguese Speaking Countries Economic and Commercial Exhibition, the 30th Macau International Fair and the Franchise Exhibition, representing an annual increase of 30%, with some of the residents describing the events as “rich and interesting”, according to the Trade and Investment Promotion Institute (IPIM). Of the total visitors, 15 thousand were professional traders. Over four days, nine thematic exchange sessions were held, resulting in more than a thousand commercial meetings and more than 140 agreements signed, an annual increase of more than 30%. Of these pacts, 15% involved Portuguese-speaking countries.
IPIM presented the opportunities and advantages of Macau to more than 350 companies, with at least 68 companies, from countries and regions such as Portugal, Brazil and Indonesia, signing declarations of intent, corresponding to an increase of 70% in annual terms. Of these, 24 started or completed the formation of new companies, in sectors such as “high technology, ‘big health’, conventions and exhibitions, cultural and creative industries, as well as Sino-Lusophone trade”.
In an area of ​​almost 30 thousand square meters, more than 1.1 thousand exhibitors from 30 countries filled 19 exhibition areas. More than 30% of exhibitors were foreigners and covered sectors such as “agricultural industry chains, new energies, blue economy, smart technology and ‘big health’”.
Under the themes “China-Portuguese Speaking Countries”, “first-time economy” and “technology”, more than 80 activities were carried out, including meetings, forums, thematic contact exchanges, new product launches and other initiatives under the “One Event, Two Places” model. More than 40 products were debuted in the areas of 'big health', traditional Chinese medicine, smart technology, cultural and creative industries, artificial intelligence robotics, construction and new trending items and toys.
Furthermore, more than 600 businesspeople from Portuguese-speaking countries, Southeast Asia and Mainland China visited the Cooperation Zone, to learn about “the advantages of the ‘Macau + Hengqin’ model”. The organization also scheduled guided tours of tourist attractions and local neighborhoods to promote “the charm of Macau as a tourist, convention and exhibition city”.
In support of participating companies, broadcast studios conducted 30 sessions for more than 200 exhibitors, publicizing and promoting more than 800 products. Over the four days, these broadcasts accumulated more than 5.6 million views. According to IPIM, a local souvenir company stated that the initiative contributed “to improving the company's brand image and expanding product sales channels”. For this company, the combined sales of banking and those generated by broadcasting reached a six-figure sum, “significant growth compared to usual values”.
In turn, exhibitors from Mainland China welcomed the “high level of internationalization and professionalism” of the events. A representative of a company from the Continent's new energy sector praised the organization and said that it had received cooperation intentions from at least six companies. This “fruitful result” allowed the company to “vividly realize Macau’s strategic advantage” as a Sino-Lusophone bridge. An Angolan company in the same sector revealed that the presentation of a new product resulted in eight cooperation consultations, an effect “that exceeded its expectations”.
In the same sense, some exhibitors from Portuguese-speaking countries expressed confidence in identifying new partners and exploring “new business paths”. They also mentioned that the experience “provided a greater understanding of cutting-edge technological advances and opportunities for transformation” in the Greater Bay Area.
A Serbian businessman pointed out that the Macao SAR facilitates “efficient participation in exhibitions”. And he expressed his intention to return in the future “to participate in more commercial activities and develop his business”.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Visitors grow in all markets</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/visitantes-crescem-em-todos-os-mercados/</link><description>Visitors to Macau grew 14.5% to around 29.7 million in the first nine months of this year, with progress in all tourism markets. Even so, visitors from Mainland China increased their weight to almost 73% of the total, increasing 18.4%, surpassing the 12.4% increase in international markets
 
Between January and September this year, Macau welcomed 29.67 million visitors, a number that represents a year-on-year increase of 14.5% and includes 17.28 million day-trippers (+24.9%) and 12.39 million tourists (+2.5%), reported the Statistics and Census Service (DSEC), whose data points to increases in all tourist markets referenced by the authorities. The average length of stay for visitors reached 1.1 days, 0.1 days less than in the same period in 2024, due to the increase in the proportion of day-trippers.
The average length of stay for day trippers (0.2 days) and tourists (2.3 days) did not change within a year.
According to DSEC data, visitors from Mainland China increased by 18.4% to 21.58 million year on year, of which 11.50 million were individual visa holders (+24.3%). With this growth exceeding the general average, the weight of visitors to the Mainland rose to 72.7% of the total, 2.4 percentage points more than in the first nine months of last year.
This Mainland group also includes visitors with visas for “one entry per week” (1.44 million), “multiple entries” (444,326) and “group entries and exits” (118,120), within the framework of the latest measures launched by the Central Government to support the tourism sector in Macau.
Hong Kong remained the second largest visitor market in the Macao SAR, with almost 5.48 million, an increase of 1.4% in total variation and 18.5% of the total, followed by Taiwan, with 727,062 (+16.5%), a number corresponding to 2.5% of the total.
In turn, international visitors increased by 12.4% to 1.88 million, representing 6.3% of total arrivals in the first nine months of 2025. In Southeast and South Asia, visitors from the Philippines (382,851), Indonesia (146,490), Malaysia (121,409), Thailand (114,933) and India (80,917) grew by 10.8%, 14.6%, 3.1%, 20.8% and 5%, compared to the same period last year.
In Northeast Asia, visitors from South Korea (382,494) and Japan (116,224) stand out, with increases of 12% and 25%, respectively. In relation to long-distance markets, the number of visitors from the USA (112,330) rose 8.7%, continuing well above those from Portugal (8,674), which grew 35.4%.
Official statistics also indicate that visitor arrivals by land (24.53 million) increased by 19.5% and were equivalent to 82.7% of the total, in contrast to sea (2.91 million) and air (2.22 million), which fell by 5.4% and 3.5%, respectively.
In September alone, total visitors rose 9.8% to 2.77 million, year on year, the highest number ever for this month, including 1.56 million day trippers (+19.4%) and 1.21 million tourists (-0.5%). The average length of stay for visitors was 1.2 days, 0.1 days less than in September 2024.</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Inflow of foreign capital rose 55%</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/entrada-de-capitais-externos-subiu-55/</link><description>Last year, Macau had 4,358 companies that had direct investment from abroad, 236 more than in 2023. According to official data, the inflow of foreign capital grew 55% to almost 14 billion patacas, partly due to increased reinvestment by some companies in the financial sector
 
The flow of foreign direct investment (FDI) in Macau amounted to 13.76 billion patacas in 2024, representing an annual growth of 54.9%, revealed the Statistics and Census Service (DSEC). According to the organization, this significant increase derives mainly from “some companies involved in financial activities having increased the value of their profits for reinvestment, and some companies in this sector having taken out more loans from direct investors from abroad”.
Last year, the Macao SAR had 4,358 companies with FDI, that is, 236 more than in 2023. Among these investors, 1,880 companies with investments from Mainland China, 1,879 from Hong Kong and 366 from the British Virgin Islands stand out.
According to the same data, the values ​​of FDI channeled to the transport, storage and communications sector (2.69 billion patacas) and the banking sector (3.07 billion) increased by 4.18 billion and 2.88 billion, respectively, in annual terms. Flows applied to the insurance sectors (6.89 billion) and wholesale and retail trade (2.91 billion) fell by 189 million and 2.95 billion, respectively.
On the other hand, the flow of FDI in the gaming industry (-476 million) once again recorded a negative value, but much less volume than in 2023 (-2.47 billion). DSEC attributes this variation essentially to the decrease in loans repaid by some gaming companies to foreign partners or interconnected companies outside the Macao SAR.
Regarding the direct source of investment, the flow of FDI from Mainland China increased by 102.3% to 6.30 billion patacas year-on-year, driven by financial activities, while that from Hong Kong decreased by 519 million to 6.18 billion. The amount from the Cayman Islands went from a negative value in 2023 to a positive level of 2.97 billion in 2024, due to the reduction in the amount of loans repaid by some gaming companies.
In the year under review, FDI income stood at 53.92 billion patacas, 1.9% more than in 2023. At the end of 2024, the stock of direct investment from abroad stood at 395.36 billion, corresponding to an annual increase of 4.5%.
Official statistics also show that the income from FDI applied to the gaming sector reached 30.83 billion patacas, surpassing financial activities (8.17 billion) and wholesale and retail trade (7.95 billion).
In terms of economic sectors, DSEC highlights that FDI stocks invested in financial activities (143.00 billion) and in the development, rental and sale of properties (23.96 billion) grew by 9.2% and 5.5%, respectively, in annual terms. On the other hand, in the gaming sector it fell 0.1% to 142.35 billion.
The stocks of investment from Mainland China (95.95 billion) and the HKSAR (108.58 billion) rose by 9.6% and 7.6%, respectively, in annual terms, but that from the British Virgin Islands (79.13 billion) fell by 1.0%.
In turn, Macao SAR companies made direct investments abroad worth 3.74 billion patacas, including 1.93 billion in Mainland China (+26.6%), obtaining income of 1.11 billion (+91.4%) and reaching a total stock of 110.02 billion (+2.0%).
In 2024, 1,705 companies in the Macao SAR had direct investment abroad, showing an annual increase of 69.
The stock of FDI made in Mainland China amounted to 82.91 billion (+0.5%), with 68.81 billion invested in the cities of the Greater Bay Area (+1.5%). At the same time, the stock of direct investment made in the HKSAR grew by 14.4% to 8.59 billion.</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Information Technologies “give” better salary to recent graduates</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/tecnologias-da-informacao-dao-melhor-salario-recem-licenciados/</link><description>Close-up Focus on Person's Hands Typing on the Desktop Computer Backlit Keyboard. Screens Show Coding Language User Interface. Software Engineer Create Innovative e-Commerce App. Program Development



Jobs related to Information Technology (IT) are the ones that offered the best salaries to recent graduates in Macau last year, according to a survey carried out by associations and higher education institutions in Hong Kong, Macau and Guangdong. The idea is to understand the salary scenario and projections for next year in the Greater Bay Area.
In Macau, the co-organizers of the survey are the Faculty of Business Management of the University of Macau and the Macau Greater Bay Area Human Resources Association. According to the results relating to the Macao SAR, IT graduates were the ones who, in 2025, achieved better salaries after leaving college, an average of 19,000 patacas per month.
This was followed by graduates in Engineering, who received, on average, 18,000 patacas per month, and in Research and Development, with 16,500 patacas monthly. Graduates in the areas of Sales, Finance and Human Resources achieved salaries in the order of 15,500 patacas.
39 companies participated in the survey, according to which, between July 2024 and June 2025, the global average salary increase was 1.6% overall. Additionally, 24 reported salary freezes. After excluding these, the real average salary increase for the remainder was 3.4%.
As for the forecast for 2026, six companies said that the projected increase is 3%, with the remaining 33 “not yet deciding” on the matter, according to what can be read in the conclusions. In the overall ranking of salary review criteria, “overall organizational performance” came first for all levels of employees, followed by “individual performance”.
In Hong Kong, 33.3% of the 78 participating companies said they expect a 2.8% salary increase next year, while 51 have not yet decided. In Guangdong, 141 companies were interviewed, of which 38.3% foresee a salary increase of 3.7% in 2026, with some foreseeing a salary freeze. Removing the latter, the prospects for the remaining companies are for an increase of around 4.1%.
Survey results showed different benefits offered to different levels of employees, including leave, education and housing. This year, around 40% of participating companies gave employees a day of “birthday leave” with full pay.
Regarding turnover, the average percentage, in general, varied between 5.7% and 9.8%, with frontline/operational staff registering the highest turnover. “Career/promotion prospects” and “pay” were ranked as the top two reasons for employee turnover. However, among the 39 companies, 17 reported “involuntary turnover”.
The research data also shows that around 40% of participating companies said they were “available” to provide compensatory time to employees, while more than 45% said they had “almost no availability” to offer work-from-home options.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief promises to “seize” opportunities in the 15th Five-Year Plan</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-promete-agarrar-oportunidades-15o-plano-quinquenal/</link><description>The Chief Executive promised measures to “seize” the opportunities arising from the 15th National Five-Year Plan. At the same time, he highlighted the importance of Xi Jinping's speeches at the fourth plenary session of the 20th CPC Central Committee
 
After the fourth plenary session of the 20th Central Committee of the Communist Party of China (CCP), which took place over four days in Beijing, the Chief Executive stressed that the Macao SAR Government “will unite and lead the various sectors in learning and implementing the spirit enshrined in the fourth plenary session, in order to contribute to the strength of Macau to promote modernization with Chinese characteristics”.
In a statement issued by the Social Communications Office, Sam Hou Fai said that General Secretary Xi Jinping delivered “important speeches” during the session. Furthermore, “the ‘proposals of the PCC Central Committee for the formulation of the 15th Five-Year Plan for national economic and social development’ were deliberated and approved, which define the principles that must be fulfilled and the main objectives for economic and social development”.
At the same time, “the importance of maintaining the long-term prosperity and stability of Hong Kong and Macau, promoting the peaceful development of cross-strait relations, advancing national reunification and building a community with a shared future for humanity was also highlighted,” he listed.
In the press release, the Macao SAR leader highlighted that the Government “will study ways to fulfill the spirit of the fourth plenary session, take a series of measures with pragmatism, constantly increase the effectiveness of governance, unite and lead the different sectors of Macau”, as well as “seize the new opportunities” arising from the “15th National Five-Year Plan”. He also assured that “he will also continue to implement, fully, precisely and unwaveringly, the principle of ‘one country, two systems’, firmly defending the sovereignty, security and development interests of the State”.
Sam Hou Fai also stressed that the MSAR “will further take advantage of the institutional advantages of the aforementioned principle and the particular role as a platform for international cooperation, in order to boost the development of Macau with high quality in all areas, and make a greater contribution to beginning the new horizon of fully building a strong country and rejuvenating the Chinese nation through modernization with Chinese characteristics”.
On the other hand, the Chief underlined that the Government plans to coordinate the four major projects relevant to development, in the long term, closely articulating with the new positioning of “Macau + Hengqin”, and to “reasonably” increase investment in the Deep Cooperation Zone, in order to boost the tasks foreseen in the second phase. “At the same time, it will consolidate and reinforce Macau’s unique role and advantages and deepen international exchanges, in order to show greater performance on the international stage, integrating and better serving the context of national development”, he stressed, quoted in a statement.
He also indicated that the Government is taking stock of the implementation of the “2nd Five-Year Plan” and the work to prepare the “3rd Five-Year Plan”, and defining a longer-term plan for the diversification of Macau’s economy, “in line with national development strategies, depending on domestic and foreign market demand and development trends”. The idea is to combine this plan with local development conditions, “with the purpose of injecting a new dynamic into future development, contributing to providing new advantages, achieving new progress and opening new horizons”, it can be read.</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Portuguese center detects signs of “opening” of the Chinese market</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/centro-portugues-detecta-sinais-de-abertura-mercado-chines/</link><description>The Portuguese center Fibrenamics – Institute for Innovation in Fibrous and Composite Materials told Lusa that there are “positive signs of opening up” of the Chinese market to collaboration with foreign countries in cutting-edge technology. “This exhibition is proof of that”, said the marketing director of Fibrenamics, during the third day of the second edition of the China-Portuguese Speaking Countries Economic and Commercial Exhibition.
“Without a doubt, there are already very interesting signs here about the opening of the Chinese market,” said the executive, before traveling to Guangzhou, capital of Guangdong province.
“It's a company that approached us and asked us to go and talk to them, with the aim of innovating a little, improving quality or performance or added value to the market”, he explained. “We want to be on that front line, we want to feel the pulse of this opening, this new mentality”, added the marketing director.
Fibrenamics, which has the University of Minho among its partners, is a technology and innovation center that studies solutions for architecture, construction, sport, medicine, protection and transport.
“Our focus is clearly international”, said Pedro Pacheco, who pointed to Macau as “an ideal point” to approach China, “also because of this cultural proximity, the language issue”.
The Institute for Innovation in Fibrous and Composite Materials has already developed personal protective equipment for the Portuguese Army and collaborated with US universities.
The director of business innovation at Fibrenamics, Eduardo Bacelar Pinto, admitted that “the logics that we can call geopolitical” can complicate international cooperation. But the researcher from the University of Minho stressed that “knowledge is intangible, it does not pass through customs, nor does it have to be transported”.
The innovation developed at Fibrenamics currently allows “business values ​​to be shared” with concern for environmental protection, added Bacelar Pinto.
The executive expressed interest in using Macau or Hengqin as a base to explore the Mainland China market. “We need to have some local opportunities and partnerships, because alone I think it is very difficult”, admitted Bacelar Pinto.
The same person in charge said he saw desire and interest in possible partnerships with universities, research institutions or private companies.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Arrested suspected of stealing statues from temples</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/detida-suspeita-de-furtar-estatuas-de-templos/</link><description>Four temples located in Coloane and Taipa discovered that nine statues of Gods had been stolen in recent days. Three of these statues were reportedly stolen by a 38-year-old local woman, who was arrested on Thursday
 
The Judiciary Police (PJ) arrested, on Thursday, a 38-year-old resident, allegedly unemployed, who allegedly stole three statues of the God of the Earth, belonging to temples in Coloane and Taipa. The three statues were found in the suspect's house and car. However, representatives of four temples in Coloane and Taipa alerted the police to the theft of a total of nine statues, used for worship.
On the other hand, in the suspect's house, the PJ found another 50 statues of Gods. According to him, the possibility that they were all stolen has not been ruled out. The case will continue to be investigated.
The complaints were made to the police between 21 and 23 October. According to temple representatives, the value of the stolen statues varies between hundreds and 3,000 patacas. Although the suspect refused to collaborate with the police, the investigation indicates that the woman, one night, drove to the temples in question and wandered around for some time before going to the temples on foot to commit the crime.
Due to suspicion of qualified theft, the suspect was referred to the Public Prosecutor's Office. Meanwhile, the PJ appealed to representatives of temples and citizens to contact the police as quickly as possible if they discover stolen statues of Gods.
The case also aroused the “high concern” of the Cultural Institute (IC), which, in a statement, appealed to the public to “value and respect culture and religious traditions in Macau, refraining from practices likely to cause damage to the value of cultural assets, thus avoiding breaking the law”.
Specifically, it stated that removing, on one's own initiative, important objects or components in public spaces open to worship, both in temples and churches, will constitute a violation of the provisions of the Law on the Protection of Cultural Heritage and the Penal Code.
Furthermore, the IC warned that temples with their respective customs and beliefs constitute an important cultural heritage for Macau, with statues, horizontal plaques with inscriptions and other components forming an integral part of this heritage.
“The IC has been carrying out regular inspections at several local temples, maintaining direct and constant communication with those responsible, and continuously recording the state of conservation of buildings and relevant objects”, added the organization.</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Powerful speakers” at “CreatorWeek”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/oradores-de-peso-na-creatorweek/</link><description>Today and tomorrow, the “CreatorWeek Conference” and the “CreatorWeek Academy” will take place at the Grand Lisboa Palace. The two activities of “CreatorWeek Macao” will feature “important speakers”, according to the Tourism Services Department (DST).
The conference will take place over two days, from 10am to 6pm, and will focus on “cultural integration of Chinese and Western social media and platform trends, the current situation and the future of the creator economy”. Topics include “The CreatorWeek Portal to China”, “China Export Plan: Scaling Eastern Creators to the Global Stage”, “Taking Asia to the World”, “The State of the Creative Economy 2026” and “Scaling Success: The Strategy Behind the World's Largest Creator Businesses”.
Speakers include Ben Wong, director of Marketing Operations for Google in Greater China, Evan DeFilippis, vice president of strategy for YouTube channel “MrBeast”, and Benny Chu, director of Greater China Industry at Meta, among others.
Between 2:00 pm and 5:00 pm, the academy will feature “the participation of talents from the sector and leaders from the main platforms”, to talk about “the secrets of quality content”, the “establishment of a stable base of followers and partnerships with brands” and the combination of “the characteristics of Chinese and Western cultures in Macau in the practical creation of content”. “Giving a Local Voice to Global Influence”, “Creating a Community with Snapchat” and “Scaling your Creative Brand” will be some of the topics presented.
Both activities aim to “create a platform for content creators, companies and local groups producing new media and social media leaders that provides commercial value”, indicates the statement.
“Branded” and DST also prepared opportunities for social interaction, to “promote an in-depth exchange between participants and mutual inspiration” and to “jointly explore the future of the creator economy and its countless opportunities for cooperation”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Angolan writer's work translated into Mandarin released</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lancada-obra-de-escritor-angolano-traduzida-para-mandarim/</link><description>The first edition of a work by Angolan writer João Melo translated into Mandarin, “Será Este Livro Um Romance?”, was launched on Friday in Macau, with simultaneous publication in Mainland China. The translation, carried out by Chen Qian, was sponsored by the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries (Macau Forum).

The objective was, “through literature, to build a spiritual bridge between Sino-Lusophone cultures and promote exchange between different civilizations”, said the secretary-general of Forum Macau, Ji Xianzheng.
The founder of the publishing house “Os Macaenses Publicações”, which published the book in Macau, lamented that Angolan literature “remains an unexplored territory” by Chinese readers. Cyan Cheong In Cheng said he hopes that the launch of João Melo's work “will be the beginning of a cultural dialogue” between China and Portuguese-speaking countries.
In addition to the edition in traditional Chinese characters presented in Macau, the edition in simplified characters was also launched in Mainland China.
The editor-in-chief of the Chinese publisher “Lijiang Publishing”, Zhang Qian, said she hopes that João Melo's work “injects new dynamism into the study of African Lusophone literature” in China.
In a video message sent for the occasion, the Angolan writer congratulated Forum Macau for the “initiative to publish writers in Portuguese” in the Chinese market. João Melo lamented that African Lusophone literatures are “still little publicized internationally”.
However, on the sidelines of the ceremony, Ji Xianzheng admitted to Lusa that “Is This Book A Novel?” It should be the only book translated under the auspices of the Macau Forum. None of the other Portuguese-speaking countries responded to the organization's request to choose a work of their national literature in Portuguese to be the next to be translated, lamented the leader.
Even so, Ji assured that the Macau Forum will continue to look for “other ways to promote cultural exchanges” between China and Portuguese-speaking countries.
According to a note from the Forum, João Melo “tries to explore the struggles and reflections inherent in his creation, in a humorous and profound tone, authentically portraying the realities and emotions of Angola and, by extension, of all of Africa, with the aim of, through literature, building a spiritual bridge between Sino-Lusophone cultures and promoting exchange between different civilizations”.
The launch of the translation of “Será This Livro Um Romance?” took place within the scope of the 17th edition of the China-Portuguese Speaking Countries Cultural Week, which kicked off on September 26th. The Cultural Week has been organized since 2008 by Forum Macau, with the support of associations from Portuguese-speaking countries in the Macao SAR.
This was the first year that the event took Portuguese-speaking cultural and artistic groups beyond the territory, to the neighboring city of Zhongshan and the Chinese capital, Beijing, recalled the organization's secretary-general.
Ji Xianzheng was speaking during the opening of an exhibition that brings together 27 painting and photography works by 23 Portuguese-speaking artists, until November 18, at the Gallery of the Institute for Municipal Affairs, with free entry (closes on Monday). The leader revealed that more than 70 thousand people visited the same exhibition while it was on display at the Xiangshan Commercial Culture Museum, in Zhongshan, between September 29th and October 12th.
Nesta mostra de artes plásticas foi ainda incorporada a “Exibição Colectiva de Obras Audiovisuais da China e dos PLP 2025”, permitindo a exibição offline e três filmes chineses de alta qualidade.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Smoking ban in four daycare centers and schools</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/proibicao-de-fumar-junto-quatro-creches-escolas/</link><description>On an experimental basis, smoking-free areas will be implemented next to four schools and daycare centers. On the other hand, also according to the SSM, the issue of completely banning the possession of electronic cigarettes could enter the legislative process in 2026
 
The Government intends to begin implementing, on an experimental basis, no-smoking areas at the entrance and exit points of four schools and daycare centers, within one to two months, said Lam Chong, director of the Office for the Prevention and Control of Smoking and Alcoholism of the Health Services (SSM).
Quoted by the Chinese-language press, Lam Chong also revealed that he had completed the internal consultation regarding the idea of ​​a total ban on the possession of electronic cigarettes. According to him, all public services were in favor of the measure.
After that, the Government will consult, “in a timely manner”, the relevant associations on the issue, and if consensus is reached, it is expected that the issue will be able to enter the legislative process next year, continued the person in charge.
On the other hand, according to Lam Chong, an increase in illegal smoking situations is expected as the number of visitors to Macau increases, so the authorities will continually carry out various awareness-raising efforts.
At this point, the person in charge mentioned that, in recent days, two cases of sale of illegally imported cigarettes had been detected, highlighting that the authorities were able to discover cases of this kind thanks to complaints made by citizens.
 
Illegal import of cigarettes and smuggling of electronic cigarettes
Specifically, according to the SSM, after receiving a complaint on Thursday, the organization and the Customs Services (SA) intercepted, in the leisure area in Praça de Luís de Camões, a woman suspected of illegally importing a total of 900 cigarettes in 45 packs. The cigarettes were seized by the SA, which, together with the SSM, will monitor this case in accordance with the Foreign Trade Law and the Tobacco Prevention and Control Regime.
On the other hand, on the 22nd of this month, the SA found, at Macau International Airport, a total of 138 thousand electronic cigarette cartridges in the luggage of five individuals from Mainland China coming from a flight from Japan. Customs revealed that the individuals tried to smuggle the electronic cigarettes to Macau, and the SA will forward the cases to the SSM.</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Bengaluru's experience in the face of urban chaos</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/experiencia-de-bengaluru-perante-caos-urbano/</link><description>Anger is a common emotion on the roads and byways of Bengaluru, also known as Bengalore. India's so-called “Silicon Valley” has been an administrative disaster for years, with companies like digital transportation giant BlackBuck threatening to leave the city because of persistent potholes that prevent employees from getting to work on time.
The 14 million inhabitants spend half the day stuck in traffic jams. The city occupies the third worst position globally in a traffic index compiled by the Dutch navigation service TomTom.
Every summer, the water dries up. Every monsoon, the city's poshest suburbs flood. The lakes are filled with toxic sewage. Garbage accumulates for days. Uncontrolled real estate development blocks stormwater drains, cuts down trees and builds over lakes without any permission.
"What is Bengaluru's biggest problem? Many agencies work 'in a bubble', so one builds a road and the other digs to lay cables the next day," said activist Srinivas Alavilli who works on sustainable cities and transport at WRI India, a research organization.
The blame for Bengaluru's dysfunction lies in the semi-independent functioning of at least a dozen organizations controlled by the state government or parastatals, in addition to the municipal corporation. These agencies responsible for water and electricity supply, sewage management, garbage collection, buses, subways and roads follow their own plans, rarely communicating with each other.
This results in new Metro stations with no connections to bus routes, residential areas designed without drainage plans and traffic police struggling to deal with traffic jams caused by unannounced road repairs.
The city is now experiencing a new governance structure. In 2025, it divided the municipal corporation into five mini-corporations, or zonals, under the Greater Bengaluru Authority (GBA), a coordinating agency chaired by the state's chief minister. It is the first Indian city to do so. Each zonal corporation will be headed by a bureaucrat and a mayor.
The transition will be complete after the election, at the beginning of 2026, of 368 district governors, who in turn will choose the mayors of each zone.
Bengaluru is testing “political decentralization and administrative centralization”, explained urban planner V. Ravichandar, one of the architects of the GBA, which has been under construction since 2014.
If the new system works, Bengaluru could be a model for other rapidly expanding Indian metropolises, where at least half of the country's 1.4 billion people live. Cities contribute the vast majority of direct taxes and at least 60% of India's Gross Domestic Product. However, municipal authorities largely depend on state and central government funds, and city presidents are mere figureheads.
“The formation of the GBA addresses the problem of lack of communication between different agencies because it will manage all parastatals,” said the activist.
The GBA's financing model, still under development, will be a combination of state and central allocations, to be distributed equally among the five companies. Enterprises will collect their own revenues, obtain financial disbursements as determined by state and central financial commissions, and receive state subsidies based on their revenues and capital needs.
Having five smaller companies means they each have individual budgets. Each company will be motivated to maximize revenue collection through property taxes, parking fees or advertising – “and they would keep all of that, and not hand it over to a central company (like they had to do before),” Alavilli said.
For some, however, there is a flaw in the conception: at the top of the pyramid is the chief minister of the state, who is also the president of the GBA. The vice-president is the deputy chief minister, who is also the minister of Bengaluru.
Not all activists believe this structure is effective – or even legal. Vijayan Menon, president of the Citizens' Action Forum, an activist group, believes it is a bad idea to have the chief minister and deputy chief minister at the head of the GBA. "The new structure pushes Bengaluru towards greater state control instead of municipal-led governance. It is not citizen-centric because it weakens the step that is closest to the people," he said.
Alavilli agrees: "If there are incidents like flooding due to poor quality sewage within the city limits, the chief minister cannot really be held responsible because he is running for election in a rural district. It makes more sense for one of the five mayors to be elected as a GBA representative."
City governance is complex because “their electoral influence is often small compared to the disproportionate influence they exert on the economy”, he added.
The state government has ruled Bengaluru for nearly a decade, finding excuses to postpone local elections to keep the city in the hands of lawmakers. With this “political reality”, Ravichandar believes that making the chief minister the head of the city's highest body is a pragmatic solution.
“The new framework formally brings state involvement to the fore, rather than letting it do so in the shadows without any accountability,” he said.
The details of the governance structure would raise “a yawn from the average Bengali citizen”, he admitted, as most of them “just want the city to function”.
The biggest test for the new structure will be whether trash will be collected, whether craters in the roads will disappear and whether the city's wheels will turn instead of sitting still for hours.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>