<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Bank profits rose 43% to eight billion by November</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lucro-dos-bancos-subiu-43-para-oito-mil-milhoes-ate-novembro/</link><description>Macau banks' operating earnings amounted to around eight billion patacas in the first 11 months of last year, marking a year-on-year increase of almost 43%, according to the Monetary Authority. On the other hand, at the end of November, bad credit exceeded 55.5 billion, corresponding to 5.5% of bank loans
 
SERGIO TERRA
 
The operating results of the Macao SAR banking sector amounted to around 7.96 billion patacas between January and November 2025, reflecting an increase of 42.8% compared to the 5.57 billion registered in the same period of the previous year, according to data from the Monetary Authority (AMCM), referring to operations in the territory. Including branches abroad, earnings amounted to 8.12 billion, 33.8% more year-on-year.
In the final accounts for 2025, banks are expected to surpass by a large margin the gains recorded in the 2024 general report, when they fell 22.5% to 3.81 billion patacas in the annual comparison, considering only local operations. This was the fourth successive crash, after 12 years of growth, including 10 consecutive records.
Also accounting for branches abroad, the banking sector's results in 2024 reached 4.02 billion, 24.8% less than in the previous annual year.
In the first 11 months of last year, the value derived from the profit margin grew 8.7% to 15.33 billion patacas in annual terms, excluding activities abroad, with income from active operations (74.42 billion) and costs from passive operations (59.09 billion) falling by 15.2% and 19.8%, respectively. Income from banking services and operations (8.64 billion) grew 21.5%, offsetting the 2.5% decline in income from financial investments (940 million).
On the other hand, financing costs increased by 2.7% to 17.47 billion patacas. In this chapter, highlights include increases of 2.2% in appropriations for provisions (6.86 billion), 5.7% in personnel costs (4.30 billion) and 6.5% in third-party supplies and services (2.92 billion).
AMCM data analyzed by the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper also reveals that loans from banking activity totaled 1,001.4 billion patacas at the end of November, equivalent to a monthly drop of 1.9% and an annual drop of 0.9%. Credit granted in Hong Kong dollars continues to prevail (43.7% of the total), compared to that denominated in patacas (22.3%), US dollars (18.7%) and renminbis (11.3%).
Domestic loans to the private sector (495.51 billion) decreased by 0.5% compared to the previous month and 4.5% in the space of one year. In turn, the value of foreign credit (505.89 billion) decreased by 3.2% in the monthly variation, but increased by 2.8% compared to November 2024.
 
55.5 billion bad debts
At the end of November, the total amount of loan installments overdue at banks for more than 90 days stood at 55.51 billion patacas, marking a monthly increase of 0.3% and an annual growth of 1.2% or 635 million patacas. “Non-productive” or overdue credit (NPL) “skyrocketed” 20 times when compared to the 2.77 billion recorded at the end of 2019, the pre-pandemic year.
Remember that, in February last year, the NPL reached the highest value since AMCM began compiling this data, in 1990, reaching 57.62 billion patacas.
In the period under analysis, non-performing loans were equivalent to 5.5% of bank loans, 0.1 percentage points more than in October 2025 and November 2024. The NPL data included 32.50 billion patacas from non-resident customers (58.6% of the total) and 23.01 billion from residents, reflecting ratios of 6.4% and 4.6%.
In general, deposits from banking activity totaled 1,392 billion patacas, 0.2% more than in the previous month and 9.7% more than in the same period of 2024. Deposits from residents (810.16 billion) decreased by 0.7% in one month and rose by 6.8% on an annual basis, while those from non-residents (349.41 billion) increased by 2.6% and 12.4% in the same time windows.
Public sector deposits in banks (232.86 billion) fell 0.1% and grew 16.3% in monthly and annual terms, respectively.
The resident loan/deposit ratio stood at 47.5% at the end of November, remaining well below the level of non-resident customers (71.9%).</description><pubDate>2026-01-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mavericks and Rockets at Venetian for pre-season games in October</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mavericks-rockets-venetian-para-jogos-de-pre-epoca-em-outubro/</link><description>Between October 9th and 11th this year, the Venetian Arena will once again host two pre-season challenges from the North American professional basketball league. This time the Houston Rockets and Dallas Mavericks teams will play in Macau, which is controlled by the Adelson family. In addition to the games, and as happened in 2025, fan interaction events are scheduled

VÍTOR REBELO
 
After the success, with a full house at the Venetian Arena, of the NBA pre-season games in Macau in October 2025, Sands China and the North American professional basketball league will once again organize two matches this year, this time featuring the Dallas Mavericks and Houston Rockets teams.
Included in the “NBA China Games 2026”, the event scheduled for the period between the 9th and 11th of October, will also include interaction actions with fans, including the “NBA House” and “NBA Fan Day” presented by “Alibaba Cloud”, youth basketball clinics and a “Community Impact Week” promoted within the scope of the “NBA Cares” and “Sands Cares” programs, with social impact programming focused on health, well-being and sustainability.
The arrival of the Dallas Mavericks is of special significance. In December 2023, the NBA approved the sale of Mark Cuban's majority stake in the Dallas Mavericks to the family of Miriam Adelson, the largest shareholder of Las Vegas Sands (LVS) – the group that controls Sands China -, and Sivan and Patrick Dumont, in a deal valued at 3.5 billion US dollars. The widow of Sheldon Adelson, founder of LVS, and a fund in his name hold almost 57% of the casino operator's capital.
At the same time, the position of administrator of the Dallas Mavericks was held by Patrick Dumont, son-in-law of Sheldon Adelson and current director of operations at LVS. The North American executive is also expected to take over leadership of Las Vegas Sands in March this year.
Quoted in a statement released yesterday by Sands China, Dumont stressed that it is “a great honor” for Sands to host the games at the Venetian Arena next autumn. “I couldn’t be more proud to have the Mavericks in Macau and for the team to experience the incredible hospitality that Sands’ ventures offer,” he mentioned.
Patrick Dumont also considered that the success of 2025 “demonstrated the strength of the NBA in creating fan engagement and exciting experiences around the world”. From his perspective, “NBA China 2026” will be another “great opportunity to showcase the league, its world-class athletes and the excitement it brings”.
In turn, Patrick Fertitta, deputy administrator of the Houston Rockets, said that his team is “an iconic brand” with worldwide support. “We are honored to have been selected alongside the Dallas Mavericks to take a game the size of Texas to Macau,” he said.
The same official noted that since Yao Ming was selected as a Hall of Famer as the first overall pick in 2002, the club has received “overwhelming love” from basketball lovers in China and built “several cherished memories playing abroad”.
In the same vein, Mark Tatum, NBA deputy commissioner and director of operations, highlighted that “the games in Macau earlier this season showed how passionate and excited fans in China and across Asia are about the competition”. The NBA “is looking forward to seeing the Mavericks and Rockets in Macau and, once again, engaging fans, aspiring players and the local community through games and related events”, he highlighted.
Grant Chum, president and executive director of Sands China, also recalled the success of the games in 2025 and was “enthusiastic” about the program being planned for this year's event. “We are confident and ready to welcome teams, players, legends and fans from around the world to Macau for another incredible NBA week, full of unforgettable sports, entertainment and community experiences,” he said.
Tickets for both games will go on sale on a date to be announced, the NBA said.</description><pubDate>2026-01-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Education Services plans AI platform for teachers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/servicos-de-educacao-planeiam-plataforma-de-ia-para-professores/</link><description>Relieving teachers' workload is the objective of launching, in the next academic year, a localized service platform, within the scope of artificial intelligence teaching. The program includes a database of smart questions and other functions. In the current academic year, the Education Services Department has already made around 3,000 training places available to teachers in the information technology discipline
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The Directorate of Education Services (DSEDJ) will launch a localized service platform, within the scope of artificial intelligence (AI) teaching, in the 2026/2027 academic year, which includes the knowledge map of 11 subjects linked to the “Basic Academic Skills Requirements”. The aim is to alleviate the workload of teachers.
O programa inclui uma base de dados de perguntas inteligentes, a composição de enunciados inteligente, a correcção inteligente e outras funções, com vista a reduzir a carga de trabalho dos docentes, desde a preparação das aulas até à avaliação.
On the other hand, for 2026-2027, DSEDJ also intends to launch complementary teaching materials for AI teaching, developed with higher education institutions in Mainland China, suitable for use in Macau.
In response to a question from deputy Ella Lei, DSEDJ states that teacher training, related to AI, was integrated into the core courses of professional development activities.
“Through three aspects, namely, specialized training in cutting-edge technologies in the field of AI, itinerant thematic workshops at higher education institutions and training carried out by schools, training opportunities of at least 10 hours are made available each academic year for teachers of the information technology discipline and at least six hours for teachers of other subjects”, highlights the document signed by the director of DSEDJ, Kong Chi Meng.
On the other hand, the organization highlights that around 3,000 training places and more than 51,800 teaching hours were made available to teachers who teach information technologies and around 9,000 places and more than 355,000 hours to those teaching other subjects.
DSEDJ emphasizes that teachers assume the important responsibility of training qualified staff for the country and for Macau. In this sense, “the Government attaches great importance to creating a good pedagogical environment” and promotes a reduction in the number of non-pedagogical work to be carried out by teaching staff.
This is done “through the establishment of legal systems, the promotion of intelligent education, funding for schools to recruit specialized staff and other measures, in order to allow teachers to dedicate themselves to teaching and training students, achieving the fundamental mission of reinforcing moral education and cultivating literacy”, indicate the response to the deputy.
In coordination with the “Requirements for Basic Academic Skills in Information Technologies”, revised in 2024, the DSEDJ emphasizes that it simultaneously updated the “Curriculum Guidelines for Information Technologies”, enriching the pedagogical cases covered, in addition to having been articulated, in 2025, with the State's Smart Education Public Services Platform, the pioneering creation of the “Zone of Macau”, which allows local teachers and students to benefit from quality educational resources from across the country.</description><pubDate>2026-01-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Social housing in Zone A will welcome tenants later this year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/habitacao-social-na-zona-acolhera-inquilinos-ainda-este-ano/</link><description>The Secretary for Transport and Public Works said that the Government expects the first group of a total of 1,800 applicants for social housing to receive the keys to the houses in Zone A of the New Landfills later this year, and that the waiting list will disappear in 2027. According to Raymond Tam, in addition to affordable housing in Zone A, more units of this kind will be put up for sale in the future
 
In response to an oral question from Leong Hong Sai, the Secretary for Transport and Public Works promised that the Government will accelerate construction and ensure that the first group of the total 1,800 social housing applicants on the waiting list receive the keys to Zone A of the New Landfills before the end of this year.
Announcing that even more social houses will be ready in 2027, Raymond Tam stressed the objective of allowing all candidates on this list to occupy social houses next year. In total, in Zone A, there will be 4,088 fractions.
Currently, applicants for social housing have to wait around a year and a half. For the Secretary, compared to other companies, the current regime in Macau is already “relatively advanced” and this waiting time “is not very long”.
Regarding the viability of the affordable housing exchange scheme, a matter that is being studied, Raymond Tam indicated that the opinions of citizens and affordable housing residents were collected. The results of the study show that this regime “has a high degree of acceptance in society”, he stressed.
Based on the results of the study, the Government will carry out a “scientific assessment” of the exchange conditions, the price fixing mechanism, the restrictions on implementation and the types of viable houses for application, he explained.
As long as the supply is sufficient, the implementation of a permanent application mechanism will be discussed, said the Secretary, ensuring that, in addition to economic housing in Zone A, more units of this type will be put up for sale in the future.
Another study on the optimization of housing policy indicates that the number of social and economic housing units in Macau will be sufficient to meet needs over the next five years, with no strong demand for intermediate housing expected, argued Raymond Tam.
In this sense, the Government will listen to the public to redefine the intermediate housing project originally planned for the lot on the north side of the Son Lei Building, in Iao Hon, so that it “serves to create more favorable conditions for the reconstruction of the seven buildings in the Iao Hon neighborhood”, said the official, adding that, so far, only foundation work is underway on this lot.
Raymond Tam also said that the Government will carry out new studies and continue to consult society, to define the guidelines for future housing policies.
With regard to exchange housing, he maintained that residents waiting for reconstruction projects should be priority recipients. In the long term, he highlighted the need for there to be sufficient consensus for the implementation of the respective policies.
Furthermore, he stated that the Government takes a cautious and optimistic attitude towards promoting urban renewal. According to what was found, the owners initially preferred reconstruction, but later began to consider exchange, and may have overlooked that exchange also requires expenses. In any case, the Secretary believes that, once there is a concrete plan and the owners clearly understand the costs, they will be able to make an appropriate choice.
Raymond Tam also indicated that there are currently 2,800 housing units for temporary accommodation, the rents for which are still under discussion. On the other hand, the definitive number of exchange homes not purchased will be known on the 30th of this month. Subsequently, the authorities will follow up on unpurchased fractions.
The Secretary also highlighted that the Government has been promoting, in a phased and orderly manner, the preparation of detailed plans for the various areas. Detail plans for the North-1, Outer Harbor-1 and Central Taipa-2 zones are in progress. In these plans, the needs to support urban renewal have already been considered, namely through the integration of urban spaces and the optimization of land buildability conditions, including increasing the maximum permitted building height and reducing the land occupation rate, with a view to reducing the density of urban construction and reserving more space for green areas along public roads and for community parks.
In this area, he revealed that the Government is optimizing the areas of Praia do Manduco, Praça de Ponte e Horta and Porto Interior. As these parts of the city are old and with little land available for use, the authorities are considering building facilities integrated with commercial elements, including a multi-storey car park, on the lot adjacent to the Barra Piloting School where there is currently a temporary open-air public car park.
In addition, work will be carried out on the revitalization of Ponte-Cais nº 11. In addition to considering the increase and optimization of the facilities at the Porto Interior Maritime Terminal, the Government will also study the use of the remaining spaces in Praça de Ponte and Horta, indicated the Secretary.
As part of the provisional use of the nine plots of land, Raymond Tam pointed out that two lots, on Estrada do Repouso and Rua do Volong, are intended for the construction of the Alegria Environmental Center, with the design expected to be completed in the first half of this year.
Recognizing the “unsatisfactory” state of some lands without definitive purposes, the Secretary recognized that his guardianship has the responsibility to manage the respective lots well. He also promised a comprehensive assessment to try to define provisional purposes for the lands that meet the conditions.
 
Airport will have check-in center in Hengqin
In another area, Pun Wa Kin, president of the Civil Aviation Authority (AACM), revealed that the Macau International Airport Society (CAM) is moving forward with a check-in service center in Hengqin. The idea aims to attract more passengers from the Greater Bay Area to use Macau Airport.
The local airport's cargo volume reached 109 thousand tons in 2025, a slight increase compared to 2024, but in the last two years it has grown more than 1.5 times compared to the pre-pandemic period.
Raymond Tam pointed out that the AACM is reviewing the air transport agreements in force and taking the initiative to negotiate with the contracting parties, with a view to expanding Macau's traffic rights. Currently, airlines from Qatar, Türkiye and Malaysia already operate, under the Fifth Freedom of the Air, exclusively cargo transport routes with connections to Macau.
With a view to improving Macau Airport's regional connectivity, CAM is carrying out a comprehensive review of current incentive measures, with the aim of encouraging existing airlines to strengthen routes to Mainland China, Southeast Asia and Northeast Asia.
On the other hand, the Secretary revealed that the Government will begin, in the second half of this month, collecting public opinions on the planning of the Taipa South, West and North Lines of the Light Metro and the extension of the Seac Pai Van Line to the edge of Vila de Coloane.
As he said, the remodeling of the existing Metro carriages will also be promoted, in order to allow interconnection between them. New carriages to be purchased will be required to have this functionality, which aims to increase transport capacity and improve the passenger experience.
At the same time, the restructuring of the Public Bus Management System, which has been in operation for more than a decade, is in the planning phase. In the future, public buses will be equipped with a passenger counting system, the data from which will be made available in the “Macao Smart Go” application. Also according to the Secretary, bus routes will be reorganized and the launch of “point to point” buses during holidays will be studied.
With regard to taxis, Raymond Tam hopes that the review of legislation on the sector will be completed this year, to create prerequisites for the introduction of the hailing service via online platforms. According to him, the vehicle calling service via online platforms will only be promoted later, and this will depend on the results of the aforementioned measure.</description><pubDate>2026-01-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Electric super charging stations start in the middle of the year in COTAI</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/postos-de-super-carregamento-electrico-arrancam-em-meados-ano-cotai/</link><description>Battery electric vehicle.



At Rua da Patinagem do COTAI, the Government will try to launch, in the middle of this year, super charging stations for electric, light and heavy vehicles, revealed Secretary Raymond Tam. Furthermore, he added that another incentive to be launched soon involves the adjustment of tariffs for using charging points
 
The Secretary for Transport and Public Works announced yesterday that super charging stations for light and heavy electric vehicles will be launched at Rua da Patinagem do COTAI, promising to make efforts to have these facilities come into operation in the middle of this year.
In response to an oral question from deputy Iau Teng Pio, Raymond Tam revealed that at these stations there will be four charging points for light vehicles and three for heavy vehicles. As he explained, the installations will allow light vehicles to travel 300 to 400 kilometers after charging for five to 10 minutes.
Explaining that the location was chosen because it houses a Macau Electricity Company substation, the Secretary stated that, if the pilot plan is well received by the public, motivating a high demand, the authorities will install similar charging stations in other suitable locations.
Furthermore, he stated that a study is being developed to assess whether the city lacks fast charging facilities. At the same time, authorities are gradually changing existing service stations in public parking lots to fast-charging ones, with the aim of meeting demand.
On the other hand, tariffs for using charging points will soon be adjusted, said Raymond Tam, highlighting the objective of increasing incentives.
Faced with the suggestions of some deputies, the Secretary assumed that he will study ways to compensate, reduce or exempt parking fees for the use of charging points.
A preliminary study is also underway on the feasibility of introducing hydrogen energy to the Macao SAR. Regarding the application of this energy in vehicles, the Secretary defended caution regarding the possibility of building hydrogen filling stations in the city.
 
Gradual measures to control vehicles
"In the long term, the Government needs to control vehicles, through many methods, including economic incentives and restrictions. Under the premise of facilitating the use of citizens, vehicle control measures will be taken little by little," said Raymond Tam, ensuring an adequate increase in charging facilities.
As he noted, installations of this kind in Macau are “sufficient” given the current number of electric vehicles. But, on the other hand, he acknowledged that the movement of vehicles to Guangdong led to a change in demand for charging.
For the Secretary, in the long term, operational vehicles could serve as a “pilot point” for battery changes. In this regard, he highlighted that exchange stations require relatively little space and the respective technologies have already matured in Mainland China, so the Government will consider introducing some brands to the territory.
In another oral interpellation, Leong Sun Iok urged the Government to support residents in the islands' old neighborhoods in resolving the lack of electricity and water. In response, the Secretary stressed that the public supply of water and electricity throughout the territory is currently assured. The Government, he stressed, has guaranteed the basic supply of electricity and water to the aforementioned homes, with the power currently available being sufficient to meet the daily needs of a typical T2 home.
Furthermore, he indicated, the Water Supply Society continues to provide services to these buildings under the terms of the conditions originally established, in order to guarantee the living needs of the residents. Also according to the Secretary, in the absence of illegal works, the original residents of shacks in the old neighborhoods of the Islands, built on land without title proving the right of use, can submit requests to carry out maintenance and conservation works, as long as they meet the legal requirements.
Assuring that the Government is attentive to the daily needs of these residents, Tam promised an open attitude on the matter. However, he argued that a precedent cannot be hastily created that allows illegal cases to request water and electricity.</description><pubDate>2026-01-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Guaranteed stable increase in specialist doctors</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/garantido-aumento-estavel-de-medicos-especialistas/</link><description>The Health Services ensure that the number of specialist doctors will increase steadily, satisfying, in the long term, society's needs in this field. Until October, there were 770 specialist doctors in the territory
 
In response to the needs for human resources and specialist medical services, the Health Services (SSM) are carrying out a medical training course, with around 160 participants, with a view to ensuring that, in the future, the number of these professionals increases steadily.
In this sense, the SSM emphasize in response to a question from Congresswoman Song Pek Kei, cooperation with various institutions has been reinforced, “gradually increasing the number of specialized training places from an annual average of around 40 in the past to more than 60 per edition in the last two years”.
Until last October, Macau had 770 specialists, representing 37% of the total of 2,038 doctors.
The SSM is also preparing the “Professional Training Program for Young Doctors of Macau in the Greater Bay Area”, through cooperation with medical institutions in Mainland China, providing training opportunities, “which contributes to increasing their professional technical capacity”, highlights the response signed by deputy director Cheang Seng Ip.
Registration for this program opened on December 19, 2025, with implementation expected in the first quarter of this year.
Furthermore, SSM emphasize, Hospital das Ilhas “has been progressively developing as a high-level training institution in Macau, thus contributing to providing local healthcare professionals with a platform for high-quality continuing medical education and ongoing professional development”.
According to the organization, Hospital das Ilhas is promoting the “training of qualified medical staff in Macau in three areas, that is, graduates of health courses, general practitioners and specialist doctors”. In relation to graduates of health courses, “internships will be available for certain professionals, including doctors”.
At the same time, the position of medical assistant was created, with eight hired in 2025. Future recruitment in this area is also planned, depending on real operational needs. With regard to general practitioners, the SSM state that three rounds of public recruitment have already been carried out.
On the other hand, as part of the pre-entry training program for specialist doctors, Hospital das Ilhas now offers new hires “a wider range of in-service training modalities”, guarantee the SSM.
Furthermore, “eligible people are also given opportunities for improvement and learning. Through these actions, the COTAI medical unit “continuously promotes the development of health professionals”, they conclude.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2026-01-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>AMCM launched exchange rate swap in renminbis</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/amcm-lancou-swap-cambial-em-renminbis/</link><description>The Macau Monetary Authority has improved bond buyback measures and introduced a specialized renminbi currency swap project to optimize “liquidity management” in the financial sector
 
Taking into account the expansion, to 50 billion renminbis or 57 billion patacas, of the scale defined in the “Permanent RMB/MOP Swap Agreement” signed with the People's Bank of China, the Macau Monetary Authority (AMCM) launched on January 2nd new measures with the aim of fully taking advantage of the support granted by the Central Government and promoting the “effective” use, by the sector, of the exchange rate swap mechanism and exchange instruments. fund management, in order to “optimize your liquidity management”.
In a statement, AMCM recalls that, at the beginning of 2023, it implemented bond repurchase measures, to allow the “supply of liquidity” in patacas and renminbis to local banks, using qualified bonds as the object of repurchase. In order to support the development of local money and bond markets, a relatively long-term “RMB Fund Facilitation Mechanism” has now been introduced within the framework of bond buyback measures.
Furthermore, as explained by the regulatory entity, local banks can use qualified bonds under the direct link mechanism between the “Macau Securities Deposit Center” (CSD) and the “Central Moneymarkets Unit” (CMU) of Hong Kong to carry out repurchase operations, “even better enhancing the effects of synergy and development of collaboration between the two regions”.
On the other hand, with the aim of diversifying the channels for obtaining funds in RMB by Macao SAR banks, AMCM implemented a specialized exchange rate swap project in RMB carried out against Hong Kong or American dollars. The organization thus intends to “improve liquidity” in offshore renminbis in the local market, in order to support the stable development of activities denominated in RMB in the local financial sector.
AMCM and the “Macao Securities Deposit and Settlement Center Sociedade Unipessoal Limitada” (MCSD) recently held an online information session on the “Bond buyback measures and specialized RMB currency swap project”, with the participation of more than 30 local banks.
Looking to the future, AMCM promises to continue carrying out money market operations through various instruments, “thus maintaining the stability of Macau's monetary and financial system and promoting the development of a quality modern financial industry”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Operation Dragon” evoked in Poland</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/operacao-dragao-evocada-na-polonia/</link><description>Marta Stanisława Sala, a Polish artist, and Cheong Kin Man, a visual anthropologist from Macau, evoked “Operation Dragon” in a “podcast” about migrations at the “Five Flavors” Asian Film Festival in Warsaw, released on the Spotify platform on December 22nd.
Asked about his own diasporic experience in artistic creation, the doctoral student in anthropology at Universidade Nova de Lisboa and ISCTE–Instituto Universitário de Lisboa recalled how Mário Soares' visit to Macau, in 1989, resulted in the regularization of illegal workers and their families. “So my family, like thousands of other illegal immigrants, obtained legal status,” he recalled.
This historic episode served as the basis for the duo's exhibition, entitled “Flora Macanensis”, presented in January and February last year in Katowice, in southern Poland. According to a note released by the Camões Institute in Warsaw, the exhibition tells the story of how the amnesty “changed life in Macau”.
“I was born a foreigner and, in a way, I still am, wherever I live”, said the former holder of a Portuguese foreign citizen identity card. “As artists and visual anthropologists who work with language, we function within a multilingual and transcultural organism,” highlighted Cheong Kin Man.
In turn, Sala, who has projected Macau's name on the Polish art scene, stated that, by “creating situations in which, through this reconfiguration of language, inventing a new language, through deconstruction, we seek to return to the human instincts of mutual understanding and the acceptance of misunderstanding”.
Invited to talk about migration in art and cinema by the Arteria Art Foundation (Fundacja Sztuki Arteria) in Warsaw, the entity that manages the festival, Sala and Cheong made a point of analyzing the French-Argentine film “Elder Son”, by Cecilia Kang, awarded “Best Emerging Director” in Locarno this year, as well as “Manta Ray”, by Phuttiphong Aroonpheng, a French-Sino-Thai co-production premiered at the Venice Film Festival in 2018.
The program, recorded in Polish and moderated by Łukasz Mańkowski, director of “Cinco Sabores”, followed another debate held in November at the Museum of Modern Art in Warsaw, between the duo of artists and Polish researchers Paweł Kaczmarczyk and Krzysztof Kardaszewicz, whose recording was also published.
According to Cheong Kin Man, the ongoing research project by the duo based in Berlin and Cascais will be integrated into the series of traveling exhibitions “As Espantosas e Curiosas Viagens”, to be held, through negotiations, in Mealhada, as well as in a new work at the Cricoteka-Museu Tadeusz Kantor, in Kraków, in 2026.</description><pubDate>2026-01-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DELTA BRIDGE EXCEEDS 100 MILLION TRIPS</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ponte-delta-supera-100-milhoes-de-viagens/</link><description>The Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge, the largest sea bridge in the world, has recorded more than 100 million passenger crossings since its inauguration in 2018, reflecting “advances in regional connectivity and integration”, reported the Chinese state news agency Xinhua, citing data on entries and exits at the land port of Zhuhai. With the end of the Covid-19 pandemic and the greater opening of the infrastructure to private cars, the volume of traffic accelerated dramatically, highlighted the head of the Border Inspection Station at the bridge post. "It took more than five years for passenger traffic at the border post to surpass the first 50 million trips, while the second 50 million was reached in just one year and eight months," Chen Faqiu said. Open to traffic since October 2018, the bridge has a total length of around 55 kilometers, which includes an underwater tunnel of almost seven kilometers between two artificial islands, built to facilitate navigation in the Pearl River Delta. Residents of Hong Kong and Macau represent 58.7% of total passenger volume, with more than 58.7 million crossings recorded. In 2025 alone, around 18 million trips were made by residents traveling to and from mainland China, almost three times more than in 2019. Vehicle traffic has also soared. More than 8.4 million vehicles registered in Hong Kong and Macau with cross-border circulation authorization were inspected. “Driving to Mainland China via the bridge has become part of the daily lives of Hong Kong and Macau residents,” highlighted Xinhua. On the other hand, the bridge has already recorded an accumulated total of 39.4 million trips by citizens from Mainland China to Macau and Hong Kong. More than 12.6 million of these trips occurred in 2025, setting an all-time record. Construction of the bridge began in 2009, but was affected by delays, the death of more than 20 workers and budget overruns. The final cost of the infrastructure is estimated at US$16.4 billion, 25% more than initially forecast. The infrastructure reduced travel time between Macau and Hong Kong by around half. In June, the Macau Public Security Police Corps announced that tourists from 82 countries, including Portugal, Brazil and Cape Verde, can enter the region through the bridge, without needing to leave the vehicle. The aim is to “promote international cultural exchange and help Macau become a platform open to the outside world (…) and an important window for exchange between Chinese and Western civilizations”, said the police.</description><pubDate>2026-01-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Foreign visitors rose 14% in 2025</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/visitantes-estrangeiros-subiram-14-em-2025/</link><description>The flow of international visitors who traveled to Macau through the various border posts in 2025 translated into more than 2.75 million entries, an annual increase of almost 14%, according to the Public Security Police Corps
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
In 2025, the entry of foreign visitors to the Macao SAR recorded an annual increase of 13.7% to 2.75 million, who used the nine border posts, according to data from the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP).
Visitors from Mainland China naturally constituted the largest group, with more than 29 million, an increase of 18.5% compared to 2024. From Hong Kong came 7.31 million (+1.7%) and from Taiwan 996 thousand (+19.4%). In total, 40.06 million people visited Macau in 2025, 14.7% more than in the previous year.
Furthermore, during the New Year holiday period, that is, between December 31st and January 4th, authorities recorded a total of 766,240 visitors. On Sunday alone there were 99,631 visitors.
Statistics from 2025 indicate that all border posts registered 235 million crossings, an annual increase of 9.8% and a daily average of 640 thousand. Passages through land stations represented 93% of the total, while entries and exits through sea and air stations accounted for 7%.
On the other hand, border crossings by residents rose 10.1% to 85.78 million, year-on-year.
Also according to CPSP data, the policies of “one visa for multiple entries” for residents of the Deep Cooperation Zone and “one entry per week” for residents of Zhuhai led to almost six million tickets over the last year. The average daily number of tickets under the “one visa for multiple entries” policy was approximately 4,200, while the average under the “one entry per week” policy was around 11 thousand.
The CPSP assured that, in response to the growing demand for border crossings, it will collaborate with relevant services to explore more innovative crossing models, thus increasing the capacity of border posts and improving the crossing experience for visitors.
Since the implementation of iris recognition swiping, 329,000 residents have registered with the service. In 2025, this method represented approximately 42.6% of passes, totaling almost 17.5 million entries and exits, while the fingerprint system constituted 57.4%, with approximately 23.57 million movements.
Hong Kong residents have been able to register for the iris recognition ticket since June 11 last year. Around 394 thousand people in the HKSAR have already subscribed to this service.
Meanwhile, the Hengqin Border Port's “single inspection” system introduced facial recognition on November 5, 2025. Around 167,000 people registered and carried out 1.1 million passes with facial recognition, representing 26.7% of the total.
The authorities also highlighted that on January 1st this year, the “Macao Vehicle Circulation in Guangdong” policy celebrated its third anniversary. Over the past three years, Gongbei Customs has supervised 4.393 million Macau unique vehicle registration passes through the Delta Bridge checkpoint. In 2025 alone, the number reached 1.741 million vehicles/times, 14.1% more compared to the previous year.</description><pubDate>2026-01-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UTM PHOTO…. UTM will recruit 1,300 students in the next academic year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/foto-utm-utm-recrutara-1-300-alunos-proximo-ano-lectivo/</link><description>In the next academic year, UTM will continue to increase the number of new students to a total of 1,300, said rector Fanny Vong. The institution plans to launch, also in 2026/2027, two courses: one for a master's degree in business management and the other for a degree in science in management and data science
 
In recent years, the Macau Tourism University (UTM) has increased the number of new students, having admitted a total of 952 students in the 2025/2026 academic year, said Fanny Vong, rector of the institution. According to him, UTM intends to admit, in the next academic year, around 1,300, including students who will take classes at the institution's temporary campus in Hengqin.
Quoted by the Chinese-language press reiterating that UTM's temporary campus in Hengqin will focus on master's programs, the dean predicted that there will be many international students interested in the respective courses.
Furthermore, Fanny Vong revealed that UTM plans to launch master's degrees in business management and bachelor's degrees in management and data science in the next academic year, with the aim of training interdisciplinary talents, equipped with business acumen and data-based skills, to face the new challenges of the era of smart tourism.
At the 2026 Open Day of the UTM Taipa Campus, held on Sunday, the rector highlighted, in a speech, that the Macao SAR Government is vigorously promoting major projects, including the “Macao International Integrated Tourism and Culture Zone” and the “Macao-Hengqin International University City”. According to him, UTM will make the most of these political opportunities, expanding its educational reach in Hengqin, innovating its programs and strengthening international collaboration to train “tourism+” professionals with a global vision and social responsibility.
According to the institution, during the Open Day activities, students, parents and the general public were able to learn the latest information about the admission process and course characteristics, as well as experience university life and campus culture.
“Some secondary school students reported having experienced the richness and diversity of degree courses and life on the UTM campus during the event, which helped them make important decisions about their future studies”, highlighted the university.</description><pubDate>2026-01-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Construction of drainage systems worries residents of Coloane</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/construcao-de-sistemas-de-drenagem-preocupa-moradores-de-coloane/</link><description>Dike construction work in Coloane, as a means of preventing floods, is generating some concern among residents near the Coloane Pier Bridge, fearing that the project could obstruct existing sea views and affect the coastal landscape. For the president of the Son I Charitable Association, the current construction is “closer to the coast than expected”
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
Residents of the area where works are being carried out, near the Coloane Pier Bridge, to build flood prevention equipment and reorganize water drainage systems in the dikes and the Shizimen canal, are concerned that the project could obstruct sea views and affect the coastal landscape.
The warning is given by the Son I de Coloane Charitable Association, whose president states that the current construction is closer to the coast than expected, “which actually affects the landscape”. In this sense, Yeong Keng Hoi intends to contact the competent authorities in the near future, in order to discuss and convey these concerns.
Quoted by Jornal do Cidadão, the association leader states that the initial plan proposed raising existing dikes to improve resilience to floods, but this “was rejected due to its serious impact on the coastal landscape”.
He adds that, “after extensive discussions”, the current “two lakes proposal” was finally adopted. “This involves the construction of new dikes that seek to balance the needs of flood control with the preservation of the landscape”, he points out, adding that “this optimized approach has obtained preliminary recognition from several interested parties”.
However, “as the project enters its preliminary phase and the initial construction takes shape, new concerns have emerged”, warns the president of the Associação de Beneficência dos Son I, for whom there are discrepancies between the current construction site and the project representations, with the actual location “closer to the coast than anticipated”.
Yeong Keng Hoi believes that if the dike is built in its current position, areas such as Avenida de Cinco de Outubro “will lose the view of the sea, significantly affecting the original coastal landscape”. On the other hand, it recognizes that the dike will be open to pedestrians after its completion, offering “potentially different views”.
The same official said that he will present suggestions to the Public Works Services Department on improving the landscape, such as the incorporation of recreational and fitness facilities in the dike area. The objective is, he notes, “to create a new landscape that combines practical functions of defense against floods and typhoons with aesthetic appeal”.
Furthermore, the association leader expressed the hope that stakeholders will consider public views during implementation, “meticulously optimizing landscape design while ensuring defenses against floods and typhoons, thus achieving the dual objectives of the “Two Lakes proposal”.
The same publication also heard from the owner of a café in the area, who expressed support for the flood prevention project in general, considering it to be “vital for the subsistence of riverside communities”, and maintaining that, in relation to the landscape aspect, it is premature to judge before completion. The cafe owner, surnamed Cheong, also noted that the dike “could offer new panoramic views, once accessible to pedestrians and cyclists”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Alice Costa presents paintings that combine the natural and abstract</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/alice-costa-apresenta-pinturas-combinam-natural-abstracto/</link><description>Former judge Alice Costa will exhibit solo for the first time, presenting more than three dozen works of abstract paintings, oil and acrylic on canvas. The works, according to the author, combine “the organic beauty of the natural world with the freedom and expressiveness of abstraction”. The exhibition will take place at Creative, with the opening scheduled for January 8th
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
An exhibition by Alice Costa will open on the 8th, Thursday, between 6:30 pm and 8:30 pm, at the Gallery of the Center for Creative Industries of Macau – Creative, in which the former presiding judge of the Courts of First Instance will present around 30 painting works.
The works consist of abstract paintings, oil and acrylic on canvas, and also “mixed media”, where the artist uses various materials such as clay, sand or pigments, to create textures.
Speaking to the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, Alice Costa explained that she uses abstract paintings of a “captivating genre”, combining “the organic beauty of the natural world with the freedom and expressiveness of abstraction”. He is inspired by landscapes, flora, fauna and natural phenomena, such as forests, oceans, mountains, sun or storms, and reinterprets them “through non-representational forms”.
The painter points out that she created the “Flow” series, making “organic shapes and fluid lines that flow into irregular shapes, imitating the spontaneity of nature”. He says he likes using textured and surface techniques, such as impasto, splashes or layers, which create “tactile depth, suggesting natural textures”.
According to the exhibition manifesto, a deep creative vocation led the artist to painting three years ago, where she now dedicates herself entirely to abstraction. “His work is a dialogue between the structured and the organic, translating the rhythms of the natural world, such as forests, oceans, storms and light, into non-representational forms”, can be read in the introduction to the event.
Ultimately, he adds, “Alice Costa’s paintings are sensory experiences”, asking the viewer, not to recognize, but to feel, with the aim of “connecting with the invisible emotions and primitive rhythms within the chaos and serenity of nature”.
For the exhibition's curator, the author's cultural and professional diversity gives her art a unique perspective. “She transmutes the precision of her legal training into the free expression of abstract painting” and her work “oscillates between chaos and calm, creating a dialogue between discipline and liberation”.
Menn Chow adds that the “Flow” series perfectly captures this balance, reflecting the “unpredictability of nature”, while also offering a peaceful space for meditation. Therefore, says the curator, Creative invites the public to “immerse themselves in this artistic current”, where art becomes “a channel for emotion, a witness to the invisible rhythms of nature and a record of creative transformation”.
The exhibition, the proceeds of which will be donated to ORBIS Macau, can be seen until January 31st.
Graduated in Law from the University of Macau in 1994, Alice Costa was appointed judge of the Court of First Instance in 1997. She left the service in 2017 for retirement purposes.
For this year, the artist is already preparing another exhibition of painting works, which will take place in March at the famous white horse temple in LuoYang, in Henan province.</description><pubDate>2026-01-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Writer Oníssimo Teotónio Almeida distinguished with Graça Moura Prize</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/escritor-onesimo-teotonio-almeida-distinguido-premio-graca-moura/</link><description>The writer and university professor Oníssimo Teotónio Almeida was honored this year with the Vasco Graça Moura Prize – Cultural Citizenship for his contribution to “the affirmation of the culture of the Portuguese language in the world”, it has now been announced.
“As a scholar and essayist, he has contributed decisively to the affirmation of the culture of the Portuguese language in the world, thus affirming cultural citizenship as an exemplary factor of expansion and development”, highlighted the jury, chaired by former minister Guilherme d’Oliveira Martins.
The jury justified the choice of Oníssimo Teotónio de Almeida “due to his persistent action as a prestigious professor and researcher with proven experience in the fields of study and consolidation of the Portuguese language, literature and culture, especially those of the United States of America”.
The author of “Na Senda de Fernão Mendes” (2013) has lived in the United States since 1972, where he went as a postgraduate student at Brown University and where he continues to teach, having helped create the Center for Portuguese and Brazilian Studies, currently a department at that university, which he directed from 1991 to 2003.
Onesimo Teotónio Almeida was born 79 years ago in Pico da Pedra, on the island of São Miguel, in the Azores, having studied at the Angra do Heroísmo Seminary and completed his bachelor's degree at the Catholic University of Lisbon.
As an author he has published in different genres – chronicle, short story, theater, poems and essays. His works include “José Enes – Filósofo, Pedagogue e Mestre” (2025), “Diálogos Lusitanos” (2024), “O Século dos Prodígios” (2018), “A Obsessão da Portugalidade” (2017), and “Despenteando Pararágrafos” (2015).
In a statement sent to the Lusa agency, Estoril Sol – organizer of the prize – highlights that “Oníssimo Teotónio Almeida is one of the greatest thinkers and prose writers, having more than a hundred essays and texts published in Portugal and abroad, namely in the United States, Brazil, France and England”.
The Vasco Graça Moura Prize – Cultural Citizenship, worth 20,000 euros, was awarded for the first time in 2016 to essayist Eduardo Lourenço. Since then, journalist José Carlos Vasconcelos, writer and researcher Vítor Aguiar e Silva, actress Maria do Céu Guerra, fado singer Carlos do Carmo, manager and jurist Emílio Rui Vilar, book publisher Zeferino Coelho, painter Graça Morais, historian José Pacheco Pereira and writer and researcher Helder Macedo have been distinguished.
In addition to Guilherme d’Oliveira Martins, the jury was made up of Maria Carlos Gil Loureiro, from the General Directorate of Books, Archives and Libraries, José Manuel Mendes, president of the Portuguese Writers Association, Manuel Frias Martins, president of the Portuguese Association of Literary Critics, Ana Paula Laborinho, director in Portugal of the Organization of Ibero-American States for Education, Science and Culture, by journalist José Carlos de Vasconcelos, and, also, by Dinis de Abreu, at the invitation of Estoril Sol.
The award winner was announced on the day that writer Vasco Graça Moura would have turned 84 years old. The award ceremony “will be announced in due course”.
 
JTM/Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>