<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Government will hear population about maternity leave and annual holidays</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-vai-ouvir-populacao-sobre-licenca-de-maternidade-ferias-anuais/</link><description>PREGNANT WOMAN WORKING ON LAPTOP. Cropped image of pregnant businesswoman type Something on laptop while sitting at her Working place in office



A calendar was not advanced, but after the government concluded the study on the increase in maternity leave, annual holidays and family -friendly measures, the article will be the subject of public consultation. The information was advanced yesterday at the Legislative Assembly, as part of the presentation of the government and finance portfolio of the folder and finance
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The government will study the increase in maternity and annual holidays license days -this is one of the points set forth in the government lines for 2025. Yesterday, in the presentation of the economy and finance folder measures, led by Tai Kin IP -and despite the warnings for the low birth rate -the secretary argued that it is necessary to “pay attention” to the difficulties of local companies. Throughout the debate, the questions were more than the answers in this context, but it was known that public consultations will be launched.
Ella Law was one of the first to address the subject. It questioned, in particular, whether the government's plans have already been submitted to the Permanent Council for Social Concertation. The deputy also argued that not only the number of days of maternity leave and annual holidays should be increased, but there are also other aspects of the labor relations law that lack revision.
In the replica, the secretary assured that the government will “work” on this subject. “We understand that society is concerned about labor rights and interests, but we have to pay attention to local companies, especially small and medium -sized businesses (SME), because we are facing enough changes,” said Tai Kin IP, adding that we need to hear the opinions of society to make “full planning” on the issue of motherhood.
The new Director of Labor Affairs Services (DSAL), Chan Un Tong, stressed that “the government will follow the legal procedures to complete the work” regarding this aspect. He then added: "After completing the work, it will launch public consultations to hear the opinions, namely the labor and employer parts." Chan Un Tong also linked that it will all depend on the “concrete situation of the market”, but there was no point in a calendar to auscultate society.
Wong Kit Cheng has lamented that the government has "taken too long" to increase maternity leave to 70 days, hoping that this time, it can advance with work quickly. " In this field, the deputy warned of the low birth rate, noting that there are numerous families in which the spouses are both workers. "Can the government subsidize companies to pay paid compensation during maternity leave? And can I encourage companies to launch hours for breastfeeding?" He also asked "family friendly measures."
Chan Hou Seng pointed out that the reduced number of births in the MSAR "has to do with various factors, for example, low yields, high costs in everyday life, and the number of license days is lower than in the interior of China and Hong Kong." Regarding the costs of increasing license and annual holidays, the deputy said that "the government must study whether they will be fully paid by the SMEs", taking into account the difficulties they go through, admitting, however, that "if they are totally paid by the government is also very much."
 
10 Repealed Employment Authorizations
In the context of the Labor Relations Law, Deputy Leong Sun IOK also defended mechanisms to resolve labor conflicts and to ensure local workers' access to employment. There were also those who asked the “dynamic adjustment of the number of non -resident workers (TNR)”, as was the case of Ella Law.
The DSal's director stated that TNR have “supplying the insufficiency of local human resources”, and is always given priority to residents in access to employment. "We will proceed with a review to reach a balance between locations and non -residents," he said, stressing that "TNR import is necessary and corresponds to the demands of Macao's development."
Regarding illegal work, Chan Un Tong revealed that since the beginning of last year and until March this year 741 inspections have been made that led to the application of administrative sanctions to 738 people and the revocation of 10 employment authorizations.
 
Granted 440 thousand patacas in the new round of the complementary subsidy to maternity
The Director of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), Chan Un Tong, revealed yesterday that, in the new round of the “Plan of the Supplementary Subsidy attributed to employers for the remuneration paid in the maternity leave”, launched in October last year, 45 orders were received, which were approved, in a total amount of 440 thousand patacas. Employers who fulfill the requirements, after paid, under the law, the 70 days of remuneration in the maternity leave to the workers residing in the delivery that will take place until December 31, 2025, may submit the application with DSAL. Chan Un Tong responded to questions from deputies Wong Kit Cheng and Chan Hou Seng.</description><pubDate>2025-04-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Prudente attitude” before trade war</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/atitude-prudente-perante-guerra-comercial/</link><description>Given the world scenario, the Government of MSAR is adopting a “prudent attitude,” said the secretary to the economy and finance. Although there is no signs of a slowdown in tourist visits to the territory following the trade war, Tai Kin IP has ensured that plans are being created to “face unforeseen events”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The Secretary for Economics and Finance said yesterday, in the Legislative Assembly, that the Government of MSAR has been aware - and will continue to be - changes in the international environment, following the tariffs imposed on several countries, including China, by the United States. Noting that the impact on the territory is not visible, Tai Kin IP has ensured that the authorities are preparing for any consequences.
"The United States have recently taken many measures, reinforcing protectionism. We are always aware and make evaluations," said the ruler, after being questioned by Deputy Ho Ion Sang about if there was already an impact on consumption and coming from visitors to the trade war.
In the replica, Tai Kin IP said that no direct impacts were observed, but pointed out that there was already impacts on the stock market and obligations, as well as "affecting people's confidence in the market." "The measurements are always oscillating. We look at the number of tourist entries and it seems that nothing is still felt, but we have a prudent attitude," he said.
The secretary also said that the government is "defining preparatory plans to cope with unforeseen situations." "We are always working on this," he added.
At the beginning of the presentation session of the government and finance portfolio lines, the secretary stressed that the world scenario "is undergoing unprecedented accelerated changes," which "gives rise to various instabilities and uncertainties in terms of perspectives in the world economy." Once again, he said that Macao "being a microeconomic-oriented-oriented microeconomics, he can hardly isolate out of external impacts."
Tai Kin IP also reiterated what he had already stated: in the first quarter of this year, the game's gross recipes remained virtually equal in annual terms, "financial revenues could not be as optimistic as expected."
It also pointed out that, for this year, the main axis of the folder that leads is to “reinforce the economy, promote diversification, improve the quality of life of the population and seek development”, having as main priorities the “promotion of the development of the proper diversification of the economy”, “support for the qualitative development of companies and residents” and “integration in the large conjuncture of national development”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New IMF low review foresees 3.6% growth in Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/nova-revisao-em-baixa-fmi-preve-crescimento-de-36-em-macau/</link><description>The International Monetary Fund has again reduced projections on Macao's economy, now pointing to a growth of 3.6% in 2025, half of the estimate announced in October, and a 3.5% rise next year. On the other hand, predictions on unemployment and inflation rates for this year dropped to 1.7% and 0.9%, respectively. Expectations regarding the world economy have also suffered a cut to 2.8% this year, with the IMF warning that the “rapid climbing of commercial tensions” and the high “political uncertainty” should have “a significant impact on global economic activity”
 
Sérgio Terra*
 
Macao Gross Domestic Product (GDP) is expected to grow 3.6% by 2025 and 3.5% in 2026, in annual terms, anticipates the International Monetary Fund (IMF) in the new report on “world economic perspectives”. The estimate for this year represents a new overhaul, after the institution expected an increase of 7.3% in October last year, a percentage that, in turn, already reflected another cut of 9.6% announced five months earlier.
In 2024, according to data from the Macao Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC), the territory GDP increased by 8.8%, in annual and real terms, reaching 84.6%of the volume of 2019, however, it fell short of government projections, which pointed to 10.3%, and from the IMF itself, which began a growth of 13.9%, later reviewed to 10.6%. After growing 75.1% in 2023, the local economy went into deceleration in a cycle of five consecutive quarters, mainly due to the relatively high comparative bases and the slowdown or stabilization of the game's revenues.
Nonetheless, according to the report now released, under the spring meetings of the Washington-based institution, the growth of Macau GDP will remain above the average of the “advanced economies” of Pacific Asia, which should advance 1.2% this year and 1.4% in 2026. Estimates for 2025 put the masks ahead of Taiwan (+2.9%), Singapore, Singapore (+2.0%), Australia (+1.6%), Hong Kong (+1.5%), New Zealand (+1.4%), South Korea (+1.0%) and Japan (+0.6%).
In Asia's general calculation, including large emerging economies such as China and India, IMF predicts 3.9% this year and 4.0% in 2026. For China, it foresees a 4.0% growth in 2025 and next year, which represents the lowest progress since 1990. Beijing has set the GDP growth target for “about 5%” to the current year.
On the other hand, the IMF is increasingly optimistic about the labor market in Macau. After reaching 2.7% in 2023 and 1.8% in 2024, the unemployment rate could retreat to 1.7% both this year and next. In October, the projection was 1.8% for 2025.
The low review was even more significant in the inflation chapter, with the IMF now predicting a rate of 0.9% in 2025, against the estimated 2.0% in October, and from 1.3% in 2026. According to DSEC, the consumer price index retreated from 0.94% by 2023 to 0.74% by 2024.
With regard to the mashed balance balance in a percentage of GDP, the institution led by Bulgarian economist Kristalina Georgieva anticipates positive results in 2025 (30.0%) and next year (28.9%). In 2024, the exercise ended with a positive balance of 31.7%.
 
Commercial tensions and political uncertainty
The International Monetary Fund has reduced the forecast of the growth of the world economy, to 2.8% this year, compared to the 3.3% it pointed out in January. For 2026, IMF estimates a growth of 3%, less than 3.3% indicated in January.
"The rapid climbing of commercial tensions and extremely high levels of political uncertainty should have a significant impact on world economic activity," he said in the report.
According to the fund, "the volatility of financial markets in the markets of actions, currencies and obligations increased markedly," and the "reaction of other countries further increased uncertainties." Thus, and "in the face of the high asset price volatility," the worldwide financial stability report "evaluates that risks to world financial stability have increased significantly, mainly due to a greater restriction of world financial conditions."
The IMF projects that growth in advanced economies is 1.4% by 2025, estimating that “growth in the US recovers to 1.8%”, less 0.9 points than that projected in January update, due to “higher political uncertainty, commercial tensions and the lowest demand dynamics”.
Growth in the euro area of ​​0.8% by 2025 and 1.2% in 2026 should slow down 0.2 percentage points compared to January calculations. "The euro zone has been recovering cyclic, but internal demand has been weak and, with the exception of Germany, the contribution of consumption growth may have reached its maximum point in its greatest economies," said the IMF, highlighting the "weak feeling of consumers and the high uncertainty", which "increased savings by precaution."
Germany stands out for its stagnation scheduled for this year (0%) and an estimated 0.9% growth for 2026. France GDP is expected to grow by 0.6% this year and 1% in 2026. Growing up a higher pace this year are the countries of southern Europe, including Spain (2.5%), Portugal and Greece, both with 2%.
In emerging and developing markets, it should “slow down to 3.7% in 2025 and 3.9% in 2026, with significant descents for countries most affected by recent commercial measures such as China,” he warned.
Since February, the US has announced several waves of tariffs against business partners and rivals, some of which have responded with contracted. The IMF took into account the evolution of tariffs until April 4, but not reprisal measures between Beijing and Washington.
"We are entering a time when the global economic system we have known for 80 years has been restarting," Pierre-Olivier Gourinchas, chief economist of the IMF, told journalists.
As an example of the significant impact of customs tariffs, the fund highlights a data: the trade in goods and services should only grow 1.7% this year, instead of the 3.2% expected three months ago.
The uncertainty caused by US President Donald Trump's trade policy is “a great weight to the world economy” and should be eliminated “as soon as possible, for all,” IMF chief economist to AFP told. "Tariffs are weighing on worldwide growth, but" uncertainty about how commercial policy in the future will be in a week, in a month or six months, it also weighs a lot, "said Gourchas during an interview between the financial institution's annual meetings in the US capital.
For gourchas, the US should focus, for example, in "policies that allow us to resolve so-called internal imbalances." In the case of China, it is about “guiding the economy for domestic consumption”, which would be “good” to the country “and therefore to the world”.
According to the expert, "the Chinese economy had a weak demand for some time, due to the crisis in the real estate sector and a production -oriented economy."
In the case of the US, the growth forecast fell, compared to the “significant increase in inflation”, which could reach 3%, although initially should return to the long -term goal of 2% established by the Federal Reserve (Fed, Central Bank). "This has implications for future Central Bank actions. If the inflationary effects are persistent, we can expect it to delay" the next cuts in interest rates, the expert explained.
The European Union registers a less sharp drop in perspectives than other places, as tariffs “are less impactful” as they are currently limited to 10%. The European bloc also benefits from Germany infrastructure expenses and the flexibility of Berlin tax rules, as well as increasing military spending throughout Europe.
 
MSAR FINANCIAL RESERVATION surpasses 623 billion
The value of the capital's financial reserve capital reached about 623.4 billion patacas in late February this year, translating a monthly rise of 0.3% or 1.9 billion, according to data from the Monetary Authority (AMCM) published in the official bulletin. According to the synopsis of the active and passive amounts released by AMCM, the basic reserve remained around 164.2 billion, and the extraordinary rose 0.4% to 459.2 billion. Compared to the end of 2024, the financial reserve grew 1.2% or 7.2 billion, but still remains far from the record of 663.56 billion reached in February 2021. The basic reserve is equivalent to 150% of the appropriations of the core services, while the extraordinary corresponds to the remaining balances of the financial reserve after the satisfaction of the basic, and can be taken to be able to provide financial support to an eventual support to an eventual support to an eventual support to an eventual support to an eventual support to an eventual support to an eventual support to an eventual support to a possible support MSAR budgetary as well as the necessary financial resources to favor socioeconomic development.
 
*With Lusa and International Agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Dinner and concert are high points of the celebrations of April 25</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jantar-concerto-sao-pontos-altos-das-comemoracoes-25-de-abril/</link><description>The usual dinner at the Military Club on the night of April 25, Friday, will join other initiatives to celebrate in Macau the 51 years of the Carnation Revolution. On the 26th, Casa de Portugal brings to the territory the musical show “The Guitar inspired by the walls”, presented by Paulo Soares, at the D. Pedro V Theater, a concert that serves as a tribute to Carlos Paredes in the centenary of his birth. The Portuguese school will also join the History date, inaugurating on the 28th an exhibition of visual and digital arts, subordinate to the theme “and after April…”, by students from some classes from the 6th grade. Two days later, in the inner atrium of the educational establishment, it will be the turn of “Songs of April”, with the participation of Tuna da EPM

Victor Rebelo
 
Several events will mark in Macau the 51th anniversary since April 25, 1974, highlighting, on the day of the celebration of the historic date, tomorrow, at 7:30 pm, the usual conviviality organized by the Military Club, which continues to count on the support of Casa de Portugal and several friends.
The dinner, scheduled for the Ho Yin Commander Hall, will be preceded by a cocktail at the club's pub at 6:30 pm. Entries have been coordinated by four responsible for organizing the conviviality, Manuel Geraldes, Pedro Vale de Gato, Lurdes de Sousa and Carlos Wilson.
The price is 280 adults for adults and 160 patacas for young people up to 16 years old.
Manuel Geraldes, responsible for the restoration of the Military Club, stresses that “this dinner is a tradition maintained for several years”, promoted with the aim of “gathering people and annually marking the values ​​of April 25, which is very important to all of us”.
At the same time a photography exhibition will be inaugurated, entitled “Lisbon, April 25, 1974”, with works by Álvaro and José Tavares.
The next day, Saturday, at 20h00, with free admission, the D. Pedro V Theater will be the scene of a concert of tribute to Carlos Paredes in the centenary of his birth, promoted by Casa de Portugal.
According to the general coordinator, Diana Soeiro, the musical show “The Guitar inspired by the walls” is presented by Paulo Soares, on the Portuguese guitar, accompanied by Rui Ferreira on the classical guitar, being the program composed of songs by Carlos Paredes, Octávio Sérgio and Paulo Soares.
Paulo Soares is considered one of the most versatile and generous artists ever of the Portuguese guitar. The musician has been studying and investigating the instrument for over 40 years, seeking the excellence of sound and musical discourse. "It is possibly the deepest knowledge of Carlos Paredes's guitar," according to a note from Casa de Portugal, adding that "its innovative synthesis of techniques and intentions of the traditional guitars of Coimbra and Lisbon are the foundation for its enormous musical and guitarist versatility, full of enthusiasm and depth."
Throughout his interesting career, Paulo Soares has interpreted not only the traditional repertoire, but also pieces of his own, from the most varied guitarists his contemporary, of classical composers and others. It has the experience of numerous performances around the world and collaborations with some of the most striking artists of Portuguese music, as well as the inclusion of guitar with various musical groupings.
Paulo Soares has been accompanied by fados, guitar recitals such as soloist, duos, trios, guitar sextet, wide guitar grouping, stringed quartet, saxophone quartets, jazz quintet, popular music, soleist with various classic orchestras, debut of countless pieces and arrangements of his own and other national and foreign composers. “As a soloist, he has always been present in the most important Portuguese guitar festivals,” says the presentation note of the Luso guitarist.
As a pedagogue and driver of the Portuguese guitar, Paulo Soares's work is undoubtedly the most important. He is the author and editor of the Portuguese Guitar Method, a reference work in the learning of the instrument.
“It has consistently taught other teachers and generously shared several transcripts of their own, being one of the biggest drivers of our guitar's modern development,” concludes Casa de Portugal at the launch of the concert scheduled for Saturday.
 
Exhibition and Musical Session at EPM
The Portuguese School of Macao (EPM) will also celebrate April 25, but this year will do so after the date itself, as students are on vacation from Easter until April 28.
On this day, an exhibition of visual and digital arts will be inaugurated. The director of the educational establishment, Acácio de Brito, told JTM that the EPM “will once again mark the historical date”, informing that the exhibition is subordinate to the theme “And after April…” and will be evident to the public at the school atrium until May 2. The works are by students from classes from 6th to 9th grade and 12th B.
On the 30th, at 12:40 pm, the classes of 5ºA and B and 8º A and B, accompanied by Tuna da EPM, will present some “April songs”, in a session guided by music teacher Marco Antunes and where they will certainly not lack the best known “Portuguese revolutionary songs”, by musicians such as Zeca Afonso (Grândola Vila Morena) and other interpretes.
Regarding the importance of being marked April 25 at EPM, Jorge Neto Valente, president of the school foundation, told our newspaper that "it is essential that students know the meaning of April 25 and not just that it is a holiday day at school."
It is recalled that, starting next year, the day will no longer be a holiday at EPM, although in 2026 coincided with a Saturday and 2027 with a Sunday.
Professor Bernardo Silva, coordinator of the EPM Department of Social Sciences, an element responsible for organizing the April 25 activities, stressed that “students have been increasingly interested in 25 April”. And in the future, not being a holiday at school, and especially when it takes a week on weekdays, "this will allow another kind of celebrations, and there may be more time for these date -related activities."
For Bernardo Silva, "it is always important to reinforce the values ​​of April 25 and now perhaps even more than in previous years, in the face of all the changes that have been happening worldwide." For all this, he points out, "we need to revive these issues."
 
“Quiz nights” at “Bookand” celebrate “Freedom”
In celebration of the 51th anniversary of April 25, “None of Your Business” organizes a special edition of Quiz nights this Thursday, at 8:30 pm, at Bookand, for which he promises “a night of knowledge, fun and celebration of freedom”. This time, participants will be challenged with 30 questions and two “guillotines” dedicated to April 25 and contemporary themes at the historical date. The 16th edition of Quiz will be presented in Portuguese as usually, played by teams of two to four elements and with several awards for the best classifieds. Participation has a cost of 20 patacas per person. Quiz nights have been held biweekly since August last year, and have had 550 enthusiasts and several partnerships with local brands, according to the press release. Bookand, located in São Lourenço, has been the “house” of Quiz nights and “has consolidated its place as a reference cultural space in Macau, with a diverse and regular programming”, says the organization.</description><pubDate>2025-04-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Bet on generation Z to streamline tourism</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/apostar-na-geracao-para-dinamizar-turismo/</link><description>To streamline tourism and respond to the younger visitors group, the government intends to launch promotions for generation Z. Authorities will also analyze the feasibility of organizing large -scale international events dedicated to digital influencers in the MSAR.
 
The government intends to bet on generation Z to streamline tourism, namely launching promotions for this specific group. In the presentation of the Governing Lines (LAG) of the protection of the economy and finance, Secretary Tai Kin IP argued that “it is necessary to take into account the needs of generation Z”. The idea is to “prioritize the expansion of collaboration with the most used social networks” by these young people, “, taking advantage of new innovative technologies and establishing partnerships with digital brands and influencers appreciated by this target group”.
“Promotional campaigns and specific offers will be conceived to attract this segment, taking advantage of the vast features of Macao 'Tourism+',” says the LAG report. At the same time, the feasibility of organizing major international events dedicated to digital influencers will be analyzed, “with the aim of forging the city's image as an international metropolis for digital content creators, thus increasing the global notoriety of destination and promoting the Z generation fan savings.”
In the same line, and because more and more young people use digital wallets to make payments, the secretary argued that small and medium -sized business (SME) should accelerate digital transformation, thus maintaining competitiveness. "As for the elevation of SME's ability, the government has done a lot of work. But we will also launch short -term measures, for example consumer awards in community zones to raise its ability and so that they can articulate with digitization," he said.
The secretary also announced plans for the “reconversion and appreciation of the restoration sector”. It is recalled that the government will support stores with its own characteristics of community neighborhoods in reinforcing competitiveness and reputation. In line with the years of operation and the characteristics of the spaces, a three -level support plan will be launched.
On the other hand, he argued that it is necessary to bet on the idea of ​​“multiostins” to attract more international visitors. "We can't look just for a city, we have to take into account resources from neighboring areas and enjoy them. For long-range visitors, we will develop a trip with various destinations," he said, stressing that it is necessary to "integrate the resources of Macau and Hengqin."
Tai Kin IP also pointed out that tourism has to walk aligned with technology. In this sense, he indicated that the government will “introduce many technological measures, filming through drones, work with various services” to work on the image of Macau as a tourist city.
In the hemiciclo, he also spoke of the need to create a “honest city” by optimizing electronic services related to the presentation of orders to obtain the quality of a certified store. “The certified stores dispersed in all areas of Macao to residents and visitors will be promoted by diversified means, increasing consumers' confidence in consuming the community and promoting the image of Macao as an honest city,” read the lag report.
 
Evaluation of the revitalization of historical zones is to the protection of the economy and finance
The initiatives and results of game dealers in the context of revitalizing the six historical zones will be evaluated by a group created by the protection of the economy and finance, with the support of the protection of social and culture matters, announced yesterday Tai Kin IP. After a review of the work already carried out, “a new positioning” will be defined to “explore the resources of each historic zone”. The areas concerned, it is recalled, are the shipyards of Lai Chi Vun, the Barra Zone, the Interior Porto and the Monte Fortress, the Almeida Ribeiro Avenue and the Rua da Felicidade, as well as the Panchões Iec Long factory.
 
Expected mechanism for response to incidents in casinos
According to the government -action line report, the government intends to maintain the “rigorous monitoring” of “healthy and ordered” development of the game sector, so “it will be sent uninterrupted personal to make the on -site inspection of casinos operations”. In addition, "a sudden incident response mechanism will be created in casinos." On the other hand, studies “on the enrichment of the modalities of fortune or unlucky games will be performed and the diversification of the elements of the game, meeting the different requirements of foreign visitors”.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-04-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mand will take Chinese companies to Lusophone countries</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-levara-empresas-chinesas-paises-lusofonos/</link><description>Macao will help Continental China companies to look for opportunities this year at Equatorial Guinea, Cape Verde, Portugal and Brazil. The secretary for the economy and finance has promised that the territory will reinforce the role of “accurate interlocutor” between China and Portuguese -speaking countries (PLP).
In the presentation of the Governing Action Lines (LAG), Tai Kin IP pointed as priorities “cooperation in the commercial, cultural, financial, technological and tax scientific areas”. According to the LAG report, Macau will join efforts with "the economic and commercial coordination authorities and the business sectors of the interior of China."
The priority target will be the meeting of entrepreneurs for economic and commercial cooperation between China and the PLP, which will take place in July at Equatorial Guinea. Macao will, in 2025, make a visit to Cape Verde, “for trade exchanges”, and visits to Portugal and Brazil to participate in “large food -related thematic fairs”.
Tai Kin IP also promised to “explore more cooperation spaces with Portuguese -speaking countries and Spanish -speaking countries”. Remember that it will be created in Hengqin a center for economic services between China and Lusophone and Hispanic countries.
As for the China and PLP cooperation fund, the secretary said authorities have already “downloaded some requirements” to promote Chinese investment in Lusophone countries, but stressed that it “works according to the market situation”. Still, it is in view of the execution of projects in areas such as infrastructure and environmental protection.
 
Precious PLP Stones Transformation
On the other hand, it has been revealed that a company will transform, in the MSAR, precious stones from PLP, targeting the mainland China market. The Director of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) stressed that the company will be able to export precious stones to the other side of the border through the Cepa agreement.
According to Yau Yun Wah, since October 2019, DSEDT has already issued operating license for raw diamond activities to 17 companies, and 37 import certified and 26 for export. He also added that they have already passed Macau Diamonds in Gross with a total amount of $ 180 million.
 
FDCT Budget rises 88%
The Secretary for Economics and Finance revealed that the Fund Budget for Science and Technology Development (FDCT) will rise this year 88%, better supporting the development of local scientific research. In the sectoral debate of the government lines, Tai Kin IP also promised that, through the FDCT, Macau will “boost cooperation with Portuguese -speaking countries and the international community”.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-04-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Studied expansion of the TAP Seac Health Center</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/estudada-ampliacao-centro-de-saude-tap-seac/</link><description>Health services will study the feasibility project of optimization or expansion of the TAP Seac Health Center. On the other hand, they plan, among other measures, to increase the number of vacancies in the subsidized services of non -profit medical institutions, aiming at the realization of the concept of “effective treatment where prevention is privileged”.
 
The capacity to provide health care to the population of Macau will increase with the realization of the feasibility project of optimization or expansion of the TAP Seac Health Center.
In response to a written interpellation presented to the Government by Deputy Leong Sun IOK, Health Services (SSM) indicated that, currently, the scope of the provision of services of the TAP Seac Health Center already covers the majority of the areas of the Outdoor Portfills (Zape). In any case, the body will continue to examine the resident population at Zape and the services provided by that health center.
On the other hand, in the response signed by the director, Alvis Lo, the SSM emphasizes that, “in collaboration with non -profit and private medical institutions, they have provided free or low -cost health care services to all residents of Macao, through the financing and acquisition of services, the health care program, satisfying people's needs”.
The “Action Plan for Healthy Macao”, released by the SSM, integrates the health elements in public policies, taking as main political guidelines the “change of paradigm, decentralization of resources and change of mindset”. Recently, the “Healthy Community” program was launched, with the aim of “deepening cooperation between government and associations”, and in the future “reinforcing work such as chronic diseases, health management and weight control of Macao residents”.
At the same time, the response to the interpellation of Leong Sun IOK underlines, “the increase in the number of vacancies in the subsidized services of non -profit medical institutions, the implementation of additional private health support measures and the promotion of the development of community health care services, will be planned to achieve the concept of 'effective treatment where prevention'.
The SSM remember that Macau has nine centers and three health posts, with a response capacity that allows residents to access, in 15 or 20 minutes, "enjoying free, affordable and high quality community health care services."
 
Pathology Service receives international accreditation
The Pathology Service of the Conde de São Januário Hospital (CHCSJ) was evaluated by experts from the ISO15189 Medical Laboratory, during the third quarter of 2024, having received international accreditation, health services reported. The evaluation of the group of experts led to the approval of all 47 laboratory tests performed. With the accreditation, the ChCSJ Pathology Service became the Macao Medical Laboratory with the largest number of certified exams through this international standard. This accreditation is “a complete statement of the Pathology Service Quality Management System, which means that the management level and technical capacity of CHCSJ laboratories have achieved standardization and internationalization”, the SSM stress.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-04-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SINO-LUSOPHONE TRADE PROMOTED IN BRAZIL</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/comercio-sino-lusofono-promovido-brasil/</link><description>The Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment organized a delegation consisting of entrepreneurs from the interior of China and Macau, to hold business exchange meetings with associations, companies and government entities in Brazil
 
The Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment (IPIM) sent a delegation of 16 entrepreneurs from the interior of China and Macau to three cities in Brazil, to “promote the achievement of the results of the“ China Trade Conduct- Portuguese-speaking countries (PLP) ”.
Initially, the entourage was in Cuiabá and Manaus, to foster the “import” of Brazilian agricultural products of intensive consumer consumer for the Chinese market and support the companies in China and Macau to “expand abroad”, through the establishment of factories in Brazil, according to IPIM.
In Cuiabá, the delegation performed an exchange with commercial associations of local agricultural products. The first 10 companies in the country's national cereal and oil ranking and Macao companies signed two memories of cooperation with the Cuiabá government and agricultural commercial associations, to bring high quality Brazilian agricultural products to the large bay.
Part of the delegation, consisting of leaders of China's construction and domestic furniture materials, moved to Manaus and explored the viability of investment and factories construction in Brazil. Entrepreneurs learned of tax exemption policies, logistics facilities and business environment, “increasing confidence in the Brazilian market,” according to IPIM.
The group of representatives of intensive consumer trade, manufacture of construction materials, bank finances and electronic trade has also traveled to São Paulo for official conversations, industrial meetings of contact scholarships and promotion sessions, aiming to “create more cooperation scenarios between China and Brazil and deepen international interactions”.
The purpose of investing in Brazil is to fully use PLP resources “to establish the industrial chain in South America” and expand products to South American markets.
IPIM recalled that it has provided “China-PLP trade conduct”, oriented to help companies, institutions and individuals interested in exploring markets in the interior of China and PLP. According to the body, more than 160 companies have benefited from services since 2024, and last month had been a connection with the Angola Ministry of Industry and Trade and local trade associations about the installation of a factory in the country, whose production is expected to start in mid -year.</description><pubDate>2025-04-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Visitors grew 11% in the first quarter</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/visitantes-cresceram-11-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>Between January and March, the MSar received almost 9.9 million visitors, a number that represents an annual rise of 11% and the second best quarter ever
 
Macau received 9.86 million visitors between January and March, 11.1% more than in the same period of 2024 and the second highest amount ever for a year start, was announced yesterday. According to official data, the number of visitors was only exceeded in the first quarter of 2019 -before the COVID -19 pandemic -during which it recorded almost 10.4 million.
However, according to the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), about 59% of visitors (5.82 million) arrived at organized excursions and spent less than one day in the city, reflecting an annual increase of 21.5%. The number of tourists decreased by 1.1% to just over four million.
The average period of permanence of visitors was 1.1 days, less 0.1 days than in the first quarter of 2024, due to the increase in the proportion of tour over the total of visitors.
According to DSEC, the number of visitors in the interior of China grew 14.5 to 7.2 million in annual terms, including four million with individual visa (plus 15.6%). Visitors with “one entrance per week”, “multiple entries” and “group outputs and groups” corresponded to 381,172, 97,957 and 28,671, respectively.
In the quarter under analysis, visitors from Taiwan (221,146) increased by 21.6%, compared to the same period of 2024, however, the Hong Kong (1.7 million) decreased 3.6%.
On the other hand, international visitors totaled 682,442, illustrating an annual rise of 16.9% and a 20.3% drop from the same period of 2019. In Southeast Asian markets, DSEC highlights visitors of the Philippines (126,559), Indonesia (53,643), Malaysia (47,094) and Singapore and Singapore (26,356), which increased 10.4%, 36.5%, 18.2%and 2.8%, respectively, in contrast to a 9.2%break from Thailand (35,073).
Among the remaining Asian markets, the visitors of South Korea (172,255) and that of Japan (44,663), which increased 33% and 23.6%, respectively, stand out. Visitors from India (19,135) lowered 3.4%when compared to the first three months of the year.
With regard to long -range markets, the number of US visitors (36,629) entries had a 9.7%homologous increase.
This month, the director of Macau Tourism Services (STD), Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, reiterated that in 2025 the priority will continue to “capture international tourists”, participating in fairs abroad and organizing activities on the territory.
The STD director recalled that Macau will host in June the semi -semi -sectional meeting of the European Confederation of Travel Agency Associations and Tourist Operators and, in December, the Annual Congress of the Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies (APAVT). APAVT is still organizing a European delegation, with “about 20 people”, which will participate in the 13th International Tourism Expo (Industry) of Macau (Mite), between tomorrow and Sunday, Senna Fernandes said.
Macau received last year 34.9 million visitors, 23.8% more than the previous year, but still far from the 39.4 million record set in 2019, before the pandemic.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-04-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Crafts, food and music again cheer up tap seac</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/artesanato-comida-musica-voltam-animar-tap-seac/</link><description>The TAP Seac Craft Fair will have another edition starting today, featuring 200 stands, 65 handicraft workshops and 47 musical performances
 
Between today and Sunday and from May 1-4, Tap Seac Square will host the Spring Craft Fair, organized by the Cultural Institute (IC). This year's edition will feature more than 200 craft and gastronomy stands and professionals from the cultural and creative sector in the interior of China, Hong Kong, Macau and Taiwan, Malaysia, Thailand, South Korea and Japan.
In a statement, the IC points out that “a wide range of original cultural and creative products” will be displayed, such as daily use articles, clothing, accessories, handicrafts, natural and food products.
The event will also have 65 Creative Craft Workshops sessions. The IC warns that participants selected by draw must attend the indicated time, at the risk of losing their vacancy without return of paid fees or distribution of material package.
In the absence of previously selected candidates, vacancies will be filled by participants in the waiting list, in order of arrival, upon registration on site and paying a rate of 50 patacas per workshop.
47 performances of musicians from Macau, Hong Kong and the interior of China are also scheduled, including the inaugural ceremony of the “Hi-Fi Queen”, Lily Chan. The artist of “GG Ties” and “Hero de Armor” has played in more than 20 concerts in Hong Kong, Macau and Canton, among other places, having released several solo albums since 2007.
The inauguration ceremony is scheduled for 18:00 today, and the fair runs from 5:00 to 22:00, Thursdays and Fridays, and from 15:00 to 22:00 to the weekend.</description><pubDate>2025-04-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Acolop Congress discusses the return of the Lusofonia Games</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/congresso-da-acolop-discute-regresso-dos-jogos-da-lusofonia/</link><description>Macao will be represented at the Lusofonia Olympic Congress that takes place today and tomorrow in the Cape Verdean capital, organized by the Association of Olympic Committees of Portuguese Official Language. One of the highlights of the work schedule is the discussion of the Lusophony games, suspended since 2014, which will be able to return in 2026
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The return of the Lusophony Games, which has been suspended for over 10 years, will be able to receive green light as early as 2026. This issue will be discussed at the 4th Lusophony Olympic Congress, which takes place in the city of Praia, Cape Verde capital, with the organization of the Cape Verde Olympic Olympic Olympic Olympic Committee.
Today, Thursday, will be dedicated to Congress itself, while tomorrow will be the turn of the General Assembly of Acolop. The two meetings will be attended by a representative of the MSAR, appointed by the Macau-China Olympic Committee, as happened at the last General Assembly of Acolop held last year in Cascais, Portugal.
The likely realization of the Lusophony Games in 2026, after being interrupted in 2024, will be one of the main points of the work schedule, and details of the return of the competition should be discussed.
Following the Colop General Assembly of 2024, the current president of the body, Filomena Fortes, said the Lusophony games could have a different format from the past. "The idea is to try to take the test with beach modalities in 2026, although the same name can be maintained, that is, Lusophony games," the Cape Verdean leader told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, expressing the desire to be a reality during his mandate ahead of Acolop.
The fact of the countries or regions that are part of the body has a coastal edge, may be decisive for the final decision, which may even appear during these two sessions in Cape Verde.
It is recalled that the start of the Lusophony Games took place in Macao in 2006, with the presence of 12 countries or regions and a total of about 700 athletes. Eight modalities were played (soccer, basketball, athletics, futsal, taekwondo, table tennis, volleyball and beach volleyball).
The organizations of Portugal followed in 2009 in Lisbon, and five years later in Goa. Because mainly of high investment, Mozambique canceled the 2017 Games and Angola did not confirm the candidacy for 2021.
The Congress, which starts this morning, has as a motto “for a joint approach to development through sports”, and will bring together delegations from the National Olympic Committees members of Acolop and many other international international organizations in sports.
The objective is to “reinforce the bonds of cooperation, promote sports development and align strategic actions for the future of the organization,” as can be read in a note sent to our wording by the Colop Communication Office, Susana Duarte.
The first day will address four fundamental strategic axes: the international recognition of Acolop, the strengthening of Lusophony games, the development of consortium -based programs and international funding, and the improvement of services provided to the Member Olympic Committees.
The statement states that Congress "reinforces Aconlap's commitment to the strengthening of the Portuguese language as a common identity element and the increase in cooperation between its members." In addition, he points out, “the event will be a unique opportunity to reflect on sport as a strategic instrument for sustainable and inclusive development in the Lusophone space”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Suspected violation in pre -trial detention</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/suspeito-de-violacao-em-prisao-preventiva/</link><description>Under the promotion of the Public Prosecution Service (MP), the Criminal Instruction Judge decided to apply the pre -trial detention measure to a local businessman who had violated a worker who had hired. After the first judicial interrogation made to the suspect, the judge understood that there are strong evidence of the crime of violation. According to the MP, the application of the pre -trial detention measure took into account the illegality, gravity and degree of intentionality of criminal acts, as well as the risk of escape, the possibility of continuing to commit crimes of the same nature, among other factors. In addition, he said, during the interrogation, the suspect's statements were inconsistent. The conclusions of the preliminary investigation indicate that, in the middle of this month, the 33-year-old suspect urged the drunk victim to accompany him back to the office to help at work, having eventually committed the violation there. Under the Code of Criminal Procedure, the MP will continue to direct the further investigation procedure. In the statement, the MP also stressed that it has severely fought sexual crimes, which, in addition to severely infringing the individual's freedom and self-determination, constitute a serious threat to public order and social tranquility. In this sense, the body has again appealed to citizens to immediately report any criminal cases to the police or MP, with the aim of creating a safe social environment.</description><pubDate>2025-04-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China is expected to launch Shenzhou-20</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/china-devera-lancar-hoje-missao-shenzhou-20/</link><description>EPA12048077 Austronauts of the Shenzhou-20 Space Mission (L-R) Wang Jie, Chen Dong and Chen Zhongrui, Attend A Press Conference at the Jiuquan Satellite Launch Center Near Jiuquan, China, 23 April 2025.  EPA/ANDRES MARTINEZ CASARES



China's manned space agency (CMSA) presented yesterday the astronauts of the Shenzhou-20 mission, which will transport them to Tiangong space station, with the launch scheduled for Thursday.
The astronaut team is part of Chen Dong, Chen Zhongrui and Wang Jie, with the first to perform the duties of commander, the agency reported at a press conference held at the Jiuquan Satellites Launch Center in the northwest of the country. Chen Dong has already participated in the Shenzhou-11 and Shenzhou-14 missions, while this will be the space debut of Chen Zhongrui and Wang Jie.
At the meeting with the media, the commander expressed his "confidence" in the team. "We have passed a long training period together, we know well and have a good mutual understanding," said Chen Dong, adding that "they learn with each other" and "improve each other through training and coexistence."
In turn, Wang explained, according to state broadcaster CCTV, that, as a flight engineer, it is “responsible for maintaining the platform, maintenance and repair of equipment and resolution of emergency problems, as well as new technologies that protect against the absence of gravity”.
Already Chen Zhongrui admitted that he felt "nervous and stressed" when he started training with his colleagues, but now guarantees that the integration of the team is "total". The team “will learn with humility” from their predecessors, who await them aboard Tiangong, he asserted.
Shenzhou-20 is expected to take a flight at 5:17 pm today from the Jiuquan satellite launch center, said Chinese space program.
This Tuesday, the final tests were completed before launch, after which the authorities considered that "the equipment is in a stable state." In addition, they evaluated that "the staff is ready and the facilities have completed all the preparations for takeoff."
Shenzhou-20 will transport the new Tiangong crew, which includes three astronauts who arrived at the station under the previous mission, Shenzhou-19 in October last year. The new crew will become the ninth group to inhabit the Chinese space station, where they should remain until the end of October this year.
Tiangong's current crew, composed of astronauts Cai Xuzhe, Wang Haoze and Song Lingdong, arrived at the space station on October 30. During its stay of approximately six months, the group performed three extra -veicular missions, as well as conducting a series of scientific experiences and technical tests in the space.
Tiangong will operate for about 10 years and could become one of the main orbital platforms in operation, especially since the International Space Station-an initiative led by the US, of which China is prohibited due to military ties with its space program-approaches its reform scheduled for 2030.
China strongly invested in its space program and was successfully landing the Chang'e 4 probe on the hidden side of the moon-the first time it was achieved-and arrived in Mars for the first time, becoming the third country-after the US and the former Soviet Union-landing on the red planet. The Asian giant also plans to build a base of scientific exploration with Russia and other countries at the southern hub of the moon.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Social networks help boost the growing sex tourism in Japan</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/redes-sociais-ajudam-impulsionar-crescente-turismo-sexual-japao/</link><description>Young women distractedly stopped in a park in western Tokyo suggest that a giant Godzilla statue is not the only attraction to a record number of foreign tourists.
With the faces illuminated by the cold shine of their mobile phones, women aligned in Park Okubo are the evidence that sex tourism has developed as an obscure side of Kabukicho's busy night life neighborhood.
There are no official data, but evidence suggests that a growing number of foreign men are migrating to the area after watching videos on social networks.
One of the women said that the area near Kabukicho, where Godzilla roars and spits smoke on a cinema, has become a "true tourist attraction", and that about half of its customers are foreigners.
“Since they can't communicate in Japanese, they write 'how much does it cost?' In their mobile phones,” using an automatic translator, Ria said, who didn't use his real name.
The men who go to Park Okubo are mainly from South Korea, China or Taiwan, but also from North America and Europe.
Consciousness abroad has grown in part because of videos on social networking platforms such as Tiktok or Chinese Bilibili. Videos are usually recorded without consent, sometimes live, and some clips accumulate hundreds of thousands of views.
Ria and others say they are autonomous, without the involvement of proximity. They take their customers to “love hotels” nearby.
The average price is between 15,000 and 30,000 yen (860 and 1,700 patacas), but women are under pressure to charge less and less, Ria said 26.
This is because “the cost of living and the decline of purchasing power” are making many Japanese men demand a lower price, he said. "Foreigners tend not to negotiate the price and usually give us more," she said.
Azu, 19, who is sitting next to him at Rescue Hub, a shelter created by a non -profit group, he agrees. "At best, I can charge a customer 20,000 yen, per hour, with a condom, sometimes a little more," said Azu.
Financial concerns are among the problems that lead more and more women to become sex professionals, said Rescue Hub director Arata Sakamoto.
It was not very common, a decade ago, Japanese women have been sex professionals on the streets, said Arata. However, especially since the COVID-19 pandemic, "young women started selling sex at low prices." "I think this is one of the reasons why the number of foreign customers has increased," he said.
About 10 women were relaxing in the cozy rescue hub apartment on a recent night, taking something to eat and carrying their mobile phones.
They are safe there, but Arata said women face "risks to their physical and mental health, the spread of sexually transmitted diseases, unwanted pregnancies, abortions and unwanted births."
"Some women are victims of abuse, or their actions can be filmed without their consent," he said. "They may also not receive payment for your services or your money is stolen."
Japan, a socially conservative country, received a record of 36.8 million tourists in 2024, in part thanks to the weak yen.
Tokyo police have not responded to requests for information about increasing foreign clients visiting sex professionals. However, they said that since December there were more police patrols in the area. This only had the effect of dispersing sex workers throughout the area.
"It has become safer to choose foreign customers instead of Japanese, because at least we can be sure they are not undercover police," Ria said as he drank a sip of tea.
Only sexual services “with penetration” are prohibited in Japan, and they are sex workers who face fines, or even prison sentences, not customers.
Arata Sakamoto said that “establishing legal consequences for customers” would help to lock demand, including foreigners.
"The authorities should also run awareness campaigns in various languages ​​at airports, hotels and tourist areas," he said.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>