<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>All employment indicators worsened this year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/todos-os-indicadores-emprego-pioraram-este-ano/</link><description>The unemployment rate in Macao has not undergone sequential changes between June and August, remaining at 2.0%, despite improvements in the sub-unemployment chapter. However, this scenario of stability mirrored in official statistics does not hide the fact that all employment indicators have worsened compared to last year, from the active population to the universe of unemployed and undereased
 
Sérgio Terra
 
Between June and August 2025, the general unemployment rate and the unemployment rate of the residents settled at 2.0% and 2.6%, respectively, maintaining the levels of the previous period (May to July), the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) announced. On the other hand, the global sub -unemployment rate (1.5%) and residents' subfather rate (1.9%), which encompass cases of unpaid licenses, both 0.2 percentage points in the same temporal interval retreated.
However, this panorama of relative sequential stability in the labor market does not find the same correspondence in homologous and annual terms. On the contrary, according to the official statistics analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, comparisons with 2024 invariably point out in the opposite direction, reflecting the weakening of all major employment indicators, despite the efforts of the management of work to propel professional placement services.
First of all, general unemployment and resident rates are above levels reached between July and August last year (1.7% and 2.3%, respectively) and in the general calculation of 2024 (1.8% and 2.4%). The increases extend to the Domain of Sub-Camp, whose rate reached 1.2% a year before and 1.4% in the general set of 2024, and 1.4% and 1.8% in the case of residents.
In the period between June and August this year, 7,600 residents were unemployed, 14.5% of which sought their first job, a percentage that, according to DSEC, rose 0.8 percentage points in sequential terms “due to the graduation season”. On the other hand, most of those looking for a new job worked previously in the branches of retail and construction trade.
The universe of unemployed was residual increase (+0.4%) compared to the period between May and July. However, it points out 13.4% and 8.6% increase compared to the same period of 2024 (about 6,700 people) and all last year (7,000), respectively.
DSEC data also point to the existence of 5,600 undereased residents between June and August, ie 8.8% less than in the quarterly cycle ended in July, and most belonged to construction sectors, real estate activities and services provided to companies. In the opposite direction, the number of underemployed residents rose 7.7% compared to a total of 2024 and 36.6% compared to the same year's same year period.
The sub -unemployment category includes individuals who, in the seven days prior to employment survey, regardless of the situation in the profession, worked less than 35 hours for involuntary reasons and were available to accept additional work. This accounting also includes people who, 30 days earlier, sought extra work.
In turn, the number of employees (371,600) grew about a hundred in sequential variation, including 280,800 residents (less about 100). Comparisons with last year's homologous period illustrate down 1.4% in general terms and 1.8% among residents. Considering the entire year of 2024 there were decreases of about 1.2% and 1.9%, respectively.
The scenario repeats itself in the active population, which was part of 379,200 people in the last job survey, marking an annual decrease of 1.1%. Thus, the activity rate dropped from 67.8% to 66.4% within one year.
According to official statistics, cultural and recreational activities, lottery and other services absorbed 26.3%of the population employed between June and August, surpassing the thick and retail trade (13.7%), public administration and social security (11.1%) and hotels, restaurants and similar establishments (9.9%). Here are the real estate and services provided to companies (7.2%), transport, storage and communications (7.0%), education (6.8%), construction (5.7%), health and social action (5.0%) and financial activities (4.6%).
Employment survey excluded residents and non -residents who, although they work in Macao, live abroad, and whose average number was calculated at about 108,100 in the period under analysis. Including this group, the total labor encompassed 487,300 people.</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Number of visitors can reach 1.2 million in the golden week</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/numero-de-visitantes-pode-atingir-12-milhoes-na-semana-dourada/</link><description>The STD director predicted a total of 1.2 million visitors in Macao in the golden week of October, representing a daily flow of 150,000, exceeding an average of 140,000 registered in the same year's same year. Regarding hotels, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes anticipated a “satisfactory” occupation rate

In the commemorative gold week of China National Day, ie, between October 1 and 8, Macau could receive about 150 thousand visitors per day, which means a total volume of 1.2 million, anticipated the Director of Tourism Services (STD).
In the same year period of last year, Macau registered a daily average of visitors of 140 thousand, recalled Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, analyzing that, in addition to the longer duration of this festive period, the beneficial visa policies for Macao appear as another factor that should motivate the increase in entries in the territory.
On the other hand, according to the Chinese language press, the STD director pointed out that, since the beginning of this year, the hotel occupancy rate reached almost 90%, a level that was even exceeded in August. About the golden week of October, the same responsible did not risk a concrete number, but predicted that the hotel sector will register a “satisfactory” occupation rate.
Considering that hotel room prices have been “rational” in recent years, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes has stated that they have climbed some holidays, but at a “reasonable level”.
He stressed, currently, the Hotel Units of the MSAR offers about 47,000 rooms, at a time when new hotels opening doors in Hengqin. In the future, he expects that, in addition to increasing the offer of hotel rooms, Macau can reinforce cooperation with the in -depth cooperation zone and the large bay in tourist service.
In turn, the president of the Macao Tourist Industry Association, described the authorities' forecasts as "conservatives." Andy Wu believes that with the increase in the effects of individual visa policies, in the golden week, the number of visitors will be "even more satisfactory" than official projections.
On the other hand, Andy Wu found that Macao's tourist care capacity has already become “much stronger” compared to the pre-pound period, but expects authorities to pay more attention to the response capacity of public buses. In this regard, he recalled that in the previous golden weeks, many visitors in the community neighborhoods and the tourist areas had to play well -crowded buses.
In addition, Andy Wu warned of the lack of taxis in the tourist areas and old neighborhoods, which “affects the experience of tourists”, especially those in the interior of China that, being used to online taxi markings, are more demanding with their services. In this sense, he called on to the government to accelerate the law on the subject to collect the deficiency of taxis.
 
Two temporary pedestrian zones
In this time with the largest number of visitors, the Government of MSar will create temporary pedestrian zones in the old neighborhood of Taipa and Rua de Nossa Senhora do Amparo, from October 1 and 7, daily from 12h00 to 19h00. Thus, it intends to “offer a more comfortable and safe trip environment” to the old neighborhood of Taipa and the surrounding areas of the ruins of São Paulo.
According to the government, the scope of the pedestrian zone in the mud will be located in the area between the intersection of Rua de Fernão Mendes Pinto with Rua do Suci and the intersection of Rua Correia da Silva with Rua Governador Tamagnini Barbosa, covering the section between the sidewalk of the barracks and Carlos da Maia Avenue. Already the pedestrian zone in the peninsula will cover the entire street of Nossa Senhora do Amparo, located in the central and southern Macao.
The director of Economics and Technological Development Services, Yau Yun Wah, ensured that the creation of the pedestrian zone “obtained broad recognition and support from residents and tourists”. Thus, after visiting civil and commercial associations and schools and heard and analyzed the opinions of all parties, the government, based on the continuation of the creation of the pedestrian zone in the old neighborhood of Taipa, decided to add one more during the golden week.
In three designated locations in the old neighborhood of Taipa, special bus services will be provided to residents with reduced mobility. At the same time, with a view to minimizing the impact of pedestrian implementation on commercial establishments operations, the official Chun Su Mei terrain will continue to be used as a temporary load and unloading of goods.
In addition, during the pedestrian implementation period, several bus careers will be adjusted in the old neighborhood of Taipa. The careers that serve the areas adjacent to the pedestrian zone on Rua de Nossa Senhora do Amparo will maintain their normal functioning.
On the other hand, the government plans to place, in pedestrian zones, check-in devices that have the themes of national games and retro style. A fair with special features, several shows and sports games for parents and children on Fernão Mendes Pinto Street, near the entrance of the old Panchões IEC Leong factory, from 1 to 7 October, daily from 1 pm to 6 pm. Also at the intersection between Largo do Pagoda do Bazar and Rua de Outubro, there will be the Night Market of the Bazaar pagoda, which will operate from October 1 to 5, from 16h00 to 22h00.
In addition, according to the Cultural Institute, the opening hours of the Panchões IEC Long factory will be extended until 21h00. In parallel, the former Panchões factory will host the artistic installation “Philip Colbert Art Tour in Macao” by the recognized British pop artist Philip Colbert.
 
STD celebrated World Tourism Day
The Director of Tourism Services (STD), Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, received on Saturday morning at Macao airport, “the Felizardo World Tourism Visitor”, a South Korean who visited the territory for the fifth time, who offered memories and an electronic consumer card to encourage the community. To mark World Tourism Day, STD also again organized the traditional “trays”, with 178 participants from 32 Macao hotels and restaurants, and tourist information counters distributed memories to visitors throughout the day. This year, World Tourism Day was subordinate to the theme “Tourism and Sustainable Transformation”, aiming to highlight the transformative potential of industry as an agent of positive change.</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hospital das Islands created “good synergistic effect” on health</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/hospital-das-ilhas-criou-bom-efeito-sinergico-na-saude/</link><description>After officially in operation, a year ago, the Ilhas Hospital now provides about 10% of public health services and aims to increase to 25% by the end of 2027. Collaboration “created a good synergistic effect through the mobilization of health professionals, the sharing of equipment and space resources,” the secretary said at the commemorative ceremony of the hospital's anniversary. In the 12 -month space, this unit registered an increase in specialty consultations and decreased its waiting times, performed 500 surgical interventions and discharged 400 patients, and created a therapy center that can cover all types of tumors
 
Victor Rebelo
 
After a year of official operation, the Macao Medical Center of the “Peking Union Medical College Hospital” islands Complex (Hospital das Islands), the number of specialty consultations provided to 52. At the same time, and according to the director of “Peking Union College”, rose to 1.5 times, in annual terms, the registration of patients in Macao has already served, while the unit has served, while the unit has served, while the unit has served, while the unit has served, while the unit has served, while the unit has served, while significantly reduced the waiting time in specialty consultations and medical examinations.
During a ceremony that marked the beginning of the Academic Week to celebrate the first anniversary of the Islands Hospital, Zhang Yuyang also said that it will take advantage of Peking Union resources to "consolidate the medical base of Macao." The idea, he said, is "to adopt innovative thoughts" to boost the industrial update of the "Big Health" sector of MSAR, in order to "inject a new impetus in the development of the proper diversification of Macao's economy."
In turn, Wu Wenming, director of the Islands Hospital, reported that, within a year, they discharged over 400 people, including patients who received clinical medicine consultations and surgical medical consultations. At the same time, he said that, in the five operating rooms of the unit, more than 500 interventions have already been performed and the largest tumor radiotherapy center was created in Macao, "which can cover all types of tumors."
At the inaugural session of the Academic Week, the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, and the Secretary for Social Affairs, were present. In her speech, the health official acknowledged that the Islands Hospital, guided by her three main missions - “optimizing public health, exploiting high quality medicine and forming local frames” - moved from the initial phase to a growth phase, “achieving many positive results”.
The secretary stressed that the mechanisms of collaboration between the two centers (São Januário and the islands) have been reinforced, "creating a good synergistic effect through the mobilization of health professionals, the sharing of equipment and space resources."
Currently, he said, the Islands Hospital "already assumes about 10% of the load of public health services", ensuring that the goal points out "to assume 25% of Macao's public health services by the end of 2027".
 
Initiates preparations to obtain international accreditation
In order to achieve the general objectives and indicators defined in the “Healthy Macao Action Plan”, and to optimize the Macao Medical and Health Services System, the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, the Kiang Wu Hospital and the preparatory work officially began to obtain international accreditation according to national standards. CHCSJ's goal is to get certification by 2026.
In a speech given at an inaugural meeting on the process, the director of health services, Alvis Lo, stressed that this accreditation will allow “align the medical institutions of Macao with the standards of the Great Bay and promote integration in national development”.
The session was attended by more than 140 professionals and included a detailed explanation of the criteria by a “Shenzhen Hospital Accreditation Research Center” (Sharc) expert.
These criteria, organized in three chapters and 186 articles, cover hospital functions, patient safety and quality management. Accreditation is reassessed every four years. Until 2025, seven hospitals in the interior of China and Hong Kong obtained this certification.</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Government satisfied with response to “Ragasa”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-satisfeito-resposta-ao-ragasa/</link><description>The government took a positive balance on the operations of the different organisms, during the prevention and cleaning work of the various departments, regarding the passage of the “Ragasa” super tuffon. Security Secretary Wong Sio Chak considered that the response mechanism, led by Sam Hou Fai, was implemented "successfully." Civil protection also considered that the works ran “positively”
 
Pedro Milheirão
During a balance of the work response to the passage of the “Ragasa” super tuffon, Wong Sio Chak, Secretary for Security, considered that operations related to warning and reply planning under the leadership of the chief executive were performed “successfully”. In turn, Sam Hou Fai thanked all the employees who made efforts on the operations performed. Similarly, the Civil Protection Operations Center (COPC) concluded that “everything went positively”.
According to a COPC statement, “there was no record of serious occurrences” and normal was restored “in a short time”. The high awareness of crisis and the strong capacity for cooperation “allowed to jointly safeguard the safety of life and goods of residents and tourists.
Eight cases of injuries caused by the Super Tuffon, of which seven light and one severe, which needed to be hospitalized. In addition, the COPC recorded 259 occurrences, including 147 cases of treatment of objects with risk of falling, 71 tree fall and other objects, six fall situations in construction shipyards, 23 fire and 11 retained people.
In addition, COPC has made security inspections to all Macao roads and removed obstacles with the help of the Macao Construction Machine Owners Association and China's Engineering and Construction Company to safeguard “the travel of citizens and tourists safely”.
Through an interdepartal collaboration, the authorities evacuated about 9,070 dwellings, with removed 3,236 people, under the “Low Zone Evacuation Plan in situations of Storm during the Typhoon Passage”. In articulation with evacuation operations, the 17 emergency reception centers and the four places of permanence of the Institute for social affairs were open and welcomed 705 people.
 
Box 1 more than 50 claims of compensation
Macao insurers received more than 50 claims for compensation, including 39 insurance of assets, according to Radio Macau. Of these, four insurance are against large disasters for small and medium enterprises. The requests were mainly submitted by store owners in low areas of the city, according to Chan Kuan I, director of the monetary authority insurance supervision department. The owner of an electrodomestics store on Rua das Estlagês predicted losses of around 300,000 Patacas. TDM also reported that private insurers do not contract with low -areas entrepreneurs, such as Porto Interior, the São Domingos market and Ponte 16, Taipa Velha and some areas of Coloane, for flooding “easily” every year. Speaking to the radio, a sector agent stated that most of the companies he knows in the low areas do not have active insurance, except those that are mandatory, for workers and occupational accidents.
 
Safe world heritage despite some “light damage”
The Cultural Institute (IC) highlighted personnel to ascertain the general condition of world heritage infrastructures, following the passage of the “Ragasa” typhoon. Following a preliminary inspection, the IC determined that “a small number of heritage buildings has suffered slight damage”, however, ensuring that churches and temples continue to be safe. The windows of the Fortress of Our Lady of the Guide were loose and were found broken branches and trees fallen into the Protestant cemetery, the São José seminary and the temple of Kun Iam Tong. However, “no building has been damaged,” says the IC press release. The inspection works also revealed infiltrations and water accumulation in the TAC temple, the Church of St. Augustine and the Church of St. Lourenço. Anticipating the arrival of the Super Tuffon, the IC had made a “comprehensive inspection” of the world heritage sites and repeatedly remembered those responsible for the “to take all prevention measures” buildings. In the same note, the body said that it will “coordinate and monitor the restoration and support work”, having appealed “to the owners of private cultural heritage buildings to monitor and treat damage based on inspection results”.</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Documentaries explore Xi Jinping's thinking</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/documentarios-exploram-pensamento-de-xi-jinping/</link><description>The series “Passion of Xi Jinping for Culture” and “Presentation and Interpretation of Xi Jinping's economic thinking” were presented yesterday in Macao. The two documentaries, in episodic format, focus on the cultural and economic views of the China leader
 
Yesterday, the documentary series “Passion of Xi Jinping for Culture” and “Presentation and Interpretation of the Economic Thought of Xi Jinping” were presented in the complex of the commercial cooperation platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries. The first is a 10-episode “micro-district” series and will be released on TDM and Cabo Macau TV from October 13th. The second, with 14 episodes, began to be broadcast yesterday by TDM, and will be aired until November 9, according to a statement from the Communication Office (GCS).
The “Passion of Xi Jinping for Culture” represents “the essence of Xi Jinping's thinking about the culture and the deep cultural foundations contained therein”, reported through “authentic stories of valorization and commitment” by Xi “with the transmission of cultural heritage and its development”. The "presentation and interpretation of the economic thinking of Xi Jinping" is an analysis of the main speeches of the Chinese leader and "historical transformations and achievements achieved under his orientation."
Both series have a theoretical study, released by the media, to help the public “to understand, in a comprehensive, precise and deep way”, Xi Jinping's thinking about economics and culture. For Sam Hou Fai, "present well the history of China, promote international exchange and continue to expand the circle of friends." The head of the Executive of MSAR also said that these two productions could "encourage the involvement, understanding and implementation" of Xi Jinping's ideas, between "the compatriots in Macao and the peoples around the world," regarding "socialism with Chinese characteristics for a new age."
"Since the 18th National Congress, the Chinese Communist Party (…) has led the Chinese people to be united and to have a fighter spirit, have adopted a number of strategic initiatives, driven innovative practices and realized revolutionary advances, which culminated in historical victories," said the leader of the MSc. "This represents the invaluable spiritual richness of our nation and constitutes an innovative theory of global importance," he said.
Sam also recalled that President XI has expressed "his burning expectation that Macao becomes a relevant connection of high level, at the opening of the country abroad and an important window for exchange and mutual learning between Chinese and Western civilizations." The chief executive also reiterated that "in the immediate and close future, the Government of MSAR will unite and lead all sectors of society, leading Macao to create a broader view with insight, embrace diversity and inclusion with an open mind" and "advance with determination."
At the time, Sam Hou Fai announced that the Government of MSar will soon sign a series of strategic and professional cooperation agreements with the "China Media Group", whom he took the opportunity to thank "for the unconditional support and broad coverage" of Macao. The Chief Executive believes this partnership will help Mand to be "constantly driven to improve its external communication capabilities." Following the launch ceremony, representatives of the “China Media Group” and the MSAR exchanged five framework agreements.
The documentaries will also be broadcast in early October on the platforms of the newspapers "Macau Daily", "Tai Chung Pou Journal", "Jornal do Cidadão", "Hou Kong Daily" and "Lotus Times", according to GCS.
In addition to Sam Hou Fai, the event was attended by Lam, secretary for Social and Culture Affairs, Shen Haixong, president and chief editor of “China Media Group”, and Zheng Xincong, director of the central government's connection cabinet at MSAR, among other guests.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Inflation completes 14 months of softening</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/inflacao-completa-14-meses-de-abrandamento/</link><description>The annual inflation rate dropped again in Macao, settling at 0.25% in August. According to official data, the chain variation reflects 14 consecutive months of slowdown
 
The Consumer Average General Index (IPC) at MSAR rose 0.25% in the annual cycle ending in August compared to the immediately preceding 12 months (between September 2023 and August 2024), the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) announced. The analysis of the historical data of this comparative interval, the most used by economists to calculate the annual inflation rate, show that the IPC has been slowing for 14 consecutive months, approaching a deflation scenario.
In August, the annual inflation rate also reflected the lowest value of the last 17 months, with the variation in chain to slow since May 2024. Since then, it has not only descended between June and July last year, months when the rate remained at 1.02%, ending inflation because it is estimated at 0.74% in the general calculation of 2024.
The last period of negative price variation in Macau dates back to 2021 (between March and November), interrupting 18 years of inflation. Between 2000 and 2003, the CPI also showed deflation rates of 1.61%, 1.99%, 2.64%and 1.56%, respectively.
According to DSEC, in the annual chain cycle ended in August 2025, the CPI rose 0.21% in level A, which includes about 50% of family aggregates with monthly expenses between 11,000 and 35,999 Patacas, and 0.27% in level B, which concentrates 30% of families with average spending between 36,000 and 71,999 Patacas. Generally speaking, the price rates of the sections of “transport” and “information and communication” lowered 2.09%and 2.57%, respectively, contrary to increases in “various products and services” (+2.20%), “leisure, recreation, sport and culture” (+1.38%) and “health” (+1.02%).
Official data also reveal that the General IPC advanced 0.27% over August 2024, with the highest growth to focus on the “Leisure, Recreation, Sport and Culture” section (+2.45%). Price rates of “food products and non-alcoholic beverages” and “housing and fuels” rose 0.44% and 0.33%, respectively, stimulated above all by the increase of meals acquired away from home and “Take-Away” and home lace. In contrast, the indices of “Information and Communication” and “clothing and shoes” retreated 3.00% and 2.09%, respectively.
On the other hand, the IPC advanced 0.11%in the monthly variation, with DSEC to highlight the high evolution of “food products and non -alcoholic beverages” (+0.05%) and “transport” (+0.87%). In the opposite direction, the declines of 0.47% in the “clothing and footwear” (-0.47%) and 0.11% in “various products and services” have stood out, including personal care, insurance, jewelery, goldsmiths and watches.
In the first eight months of this year, the average IPC advanced 0.19%, compared to the same period of 2024, driven by the section of “food products and non -alcoholic beverages” (+0.46%).
Expenses with higher weights in the calculation of inflation are those of the sections of “housing and fuels”, “food products and non -alcoholic beverages” and “transport”, with considerations of 34.47, 29.47 and 8.33, respectively.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More education and fines to avoid deaths during typhoons</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-educacao-multas-para-evitar-mortes-durante-tufoes/</link><description>EPA12401104 A Man Watches Waves Crash Ashore During Typhoon Ragasa, Signal 10, In Hong Kong, China, 24 Sepncer 2025. EPA/May James



In addition to educating the population more, it may also be necessary to impose fines to prevent hazardous behaviors during the passage of tufts through Macau and Hong Kong, admitted experts heard by Lusa agency.
A woman and five -year -old son were intensive care of a Hong Kong hospital after being taken by waves in Chai Wan, a riverside area in the city. According to the firefighters, the family decided to go to see the sea when the authorities had already recommended to the population to seek shelter, due to the passage of the "Ragasa" super tuft, the most powerful storm registered on the planet in 2025.
"When a disaster happens, such as tuffons or tsunamis, if people are alerted, the hypothesis of injuries is very reduced or minimal," said Faith Chan Ka Shun. "Unless we are talking about crazy people, who will still surf or for the beach to take a look, there are a risk," added the professor at the University of Nottingham Ningbo.
Yau Yung, a professor at Lingnan University in Hong Kong, argued that it is necessary to "educate people to really be aware and deal with these extreme climate."
"At the current moment, the formation of the population is not enough, in Hong Kong and also in Macao," lamented the urban planning expert, who pointed to Japan as a good reference.
Japan is located in the fire ring, one of the world's most active seismic zones, and suffers tremors relatively frequency, so infrastructure in the country have been specially designed to resist on these occasions.
In addition, it stressed Yau, public schools in Japan include, since primary education, education on "importance and how they should respond to this type of emergency situations." For the sustainability expert, betting on children's education can generate "a kind of virtuous cycle," because they "can actually teach adults."
In Macao, videos of people were shared on social networks on flooded streets, fish that had escaped nurseries and aquariums in stores and restaurants, at a time when the maximum warning of typhoon was still in force.
"Of course it is possible to laugh at the situation and say that it really depends on people, if they want to die to be able to see the waves climbing," admitted Faith Chan, an academic born in Hong Kong. But the environmental science professor recalled that dangerous behaviors during those can also lead to the death of firefighters or police officers if a rescue operation is required.
Following the passage of “Ragasa”, Hong Kong police detained four people on suspicion of children's negligence because they took children to see the waves by the coast when the warning sign had already been issued. A 54 -year -old man was also allegedly fined swimming on a closed public beach when signal 10 was in force.
On Thursday, Hong Kong Security Secretary Chris Tang Ping-Kung promised to consider the promulgation of a new law after dozens of residents ignored the alerts.
Faith Chan admitted that it may be necessary to punish dangerous behaviors and gave as an example Shenzhen, where police applied fines from two thousand yuans to those who did not stay home. "It can be criticized, but if the [China] government continental is not strict, some people will end up paying for the offense with their own lives," Chan warned.
 
Infrastructures to mitigate the impact of floods
The two experts consider that Macau and Hong Kong have to learn to live in a world of constant floods and extreme climate.
The “Ragasa” forced the two Chinese special administrative regions to maintain the maximum typhoon alert - level 10 - for more than 10 hours, a new historical record. Authorities had warned that this super tuffon could bring conditions comparable to the mangkhut, which in September 2018 caused estimated damage to $ 4.6 billion from Hong Kong in the former British colony, and the "Hato", considered the worst typhoon in over 50 years to hit Macau, which in 2017 caused 10 dead and 240 injured in the territory.
During the passage of “Ragasa” in Hong Kong there were about 100 people injured, 1,220 fallen trees and more than a thousand canceled flights. In Macao, the floods reached 1.51 meters, but only seven injured were recorded. Yau Yung argues that it was no luck, but "structural adaptation."
Faith Chan Ka Shun, a professor at the University of Nottingham Ningbo, says the absence of deaths was “a victory”, which is due to improvements in the alert system and the preparation of civil protection. “This time they prepared very early, more than 12 hours [before the Ragasa's passage]. People could decide to lose money because they stopped work, schools and everything else,” he said.
In Macao, the authorities ended the casinos for 33 hours. Operators will have lost 880 million patacas in revenues, almost 5% of the expected of September, estimated Jeffrey Kiang, analyst at Consultant CLSA, quoted by the portal "Gggrasia".
Even before the passage of “Ragasa”, the leader of the government of Macao already showed optimism, pointing to the implementation of evacuation plans for the low zones and the annual exercise of exercise. Sam Hou Fai also underlined the entry into operation of rainwater lifting stations and sewage projects, which “significantly improved” the ability to drain and flood prevention.
Yau Yung admitted that it would be possible to "really project a city to make it the flood test," building "large-scale infrastructures," like the rails that protect the Italian city of Venice. But with much of Macau practically at sea level, a large -scale system “may not be effective or economically viable,” warned the urban planning expert.
On the other hand, it stressed Faith Chan, would make it harder for the population to enjoy the sea, part of the history and culture of both cities.
The Professor of Environmental Sciences recalled that there are areas of Macau and Hong Kong where floods are chronic during the rainy season between May and September, even without typhoons. Therefore, he argued that it makes more sense to build infrastructures to mitigate the impact of floods, namely underground tanks to store rainwater.
The sustainable flood management expert has given the example of the Netherlands, where parking parks are designed with space to divert rainwater.
Yau Yung argued that including rainwater tanks should be “a mandatory requirement” for any building to be built in Macau and Hong Kong. "Of course it would cost some money, but in fact, the benefits can compensate for the investment in the medium term. I would say it's a good deal," added the expert in inclusive cities.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Crafts and gastronomy animates fishermen's dock</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/artesanato-gastronomia-animam-doca-dos-pescadores/</link><description>Offering a “vibrant cultural mosaic” is the objective of the Craft Fair and the Gastronomic Show of the Lusophone Countries of the China Cultural Week and Portuguese -speaking countries, in the fishermen's dock



















The fishermen's dock hosts the handicraft fair since Saturday, one of the highlights of the 17th Cultural Week of China and Portuguese -speaking countries. This edition of the event brings together an “exceptional cast of masters artisans”, underlines a note from the Permanent Secretariat of the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries (Macau), highlighting the participation of two “Higher Level Cultural Heritage heirs” of Zhejiang Province, who promise to enchant the public with demonstrations of sublime clipping techniques Pujiang and the embroidery “Cross Point”.
The fair also has the presence of artisans from nine Portuguese -speaking countries, bringing to the fishermen's dock “a stunning show of ceramic, weaving, sculpture and visual arts, displayed in newsstands overflowing authenticity and creativity”. Also noteworthy is for the participation of artisans from Macao, highlighting “the singular charm of the identity of Macao”.
At the same time, the gastronomic exhibition of Portuguese -speaking countries was inaugurated, another activity of the cultural week. Until October 2, this gastronomic festival brings together renowned chefs from five Lusophone countries, namely Brazil, Cape Verde, Equatorial Guinea, Guinea-Bissau and Mozambique, who, in collaboration with a local restaurant, in the fishermen's dock, will create a special menu characterized by the confluence of Lusophone flavors.
In addition, on today's afternoons and October 1, the heads of Brazil, Equatorial Guinea and Mozambique will hold culinary demonstration sessions at the Legend Boulevard of the fishermen's dock, making live traditional dishes that carry the flavors Lusophone directly to the public taste. In addition, during tomorrow, the two heads of Guinea-Bissau and Cape Verde will hold Lusophone cooking workshops at the University of Science and Technology of Macao, to share culinary experiences and the charms of gastronomic culture with participants.</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>French synologist work opened audiovisual exhibition</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/trabalho-de-sinologo-frances-abriu-exibicao-audiovisual/</link><description>A collective exhibition of audiovisual works, inserted under the Sino-Lusophone mechanism, includes the presentation of three Chinese documentaries. The inaugural session of the event highlighted an investigation made in the Great Bay for a French synologist
 
Three Chinese documentaries are part of the program of the second edition of the “Collective Exhibition of Audiovisual Works of China and Portuguese -speaking countries (PLP) 2025”, organized by the Permanent Secretariat of the Macao Forum and the International Cooperation Department of the National Radio and Television Administration of the Popular Republic of China.
The inaugural session, which took place at Macao University of Science and Technology (UCTM), featured the presentation of the film “Inspiration-Great Bay-an investigation from southern China”, followed by a meeting with the production team. About 200 guests attended, including teachers and UCTM students.
The documentary offers a vivid perspective of culture, society and development of southern China, in particular of the Great Bay. This work portrays a “dynamic panorama, full of opportunities and hope, combining deep intercultural observation with humanistic sensitivity,” according to the Forum.
The director Tang Lina and the author of the book, the synologist David Gosset, interacted with the public, providing copies of the book. Audiovisual works will be exhibited at the Institute's Gallery for Municipal Affairs and in several schools in Macao, as well as offered for broadcast by PLP Language Television stations. In addition, they will still be available on the Forum Electronic page for the promotion, through documentary format, of “mutual learning” between China and PLP civilizations ”.
The “collective exhibition of audiovisual works”, held under the audiovisual cooperation mechanism between China and PLP, includes even two Chinese documentaries, namely “where the sea turtles” and “Ice Kingdom” go.
According to the Forum, the dissemination of the works aims to reinforce Macao's “irradiator role” as “a center, a platform, a base”, promoting “cooperation in the audiovisual domain between China and PLP and deepening Sino-Lusophone cultural exchange”.
The exhibition takes place on the sidelines of the 17th Cultural Week of China and PLP.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>I was going to cross with the dance in “Selfie”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ia-cruza-se-danca-em-selfie/</link><description>The frenzy of social networks inspired the dance group Lam Lam to create the play “Selfie”, which will be presented in November at the Macao Cultural Center. This project is part of the “Commissioning of Performative Arts Productions” Program
 
Between November 14 and 16 (Friday to Sunday), Studio II of the Macao Cultural Center (CCM) will host five shows of the “Selfie” dance-theater play. Selected under the program “Commissioning of Performative Arts Productions 2024-2026”, this piece directed by Alexis Kam and produced by the Dance-Theater Group Lam “explores a sphere where Artificial Intelligence (AI) intersects with dance”, said the Cultural Institute (IC).
Using “an innovative theatrical sensation” in collaboration with Dynamic Wang, Beijing -based artist, and betting on a local cast of recognized actors and dancers, Alexis Kam “invites the audience to enter a sometimes absurd narcissistic world that portrays the distortion and rebirth of diverse personas”. "The show challenges the audience to discern the reality of virtuality in an era dominated by the frenzy of social networks, in which individuals constantly rehearse idealized versions of themselves, seeking attention and affirmation," says the IC note.
Created in Macao, Alexis Kam is a “emerging” choreographer and dancer who attended the Macau Conservatory Dance School and joined the “Beijing Dance/LDTX” group. His works have already been presented internationally at the Israel Festival, Lodz Ballet Festival (Poland), Suzanne Dellal Dance and Theater Center, in Telavive (Israel), Chemnitz Municipal Theater (Germany) and at the Macao Arts Festival.
Kam established an artistic residency in the "Dance Base Yokohama 2024", having been the first resident artist of the program "Plateau/Dance Beyond Borders".
Tickets for CCM shows are already on sale on “Enjoy Macao”, “Damai” and “Maoyan” platforms, with several discounts available.
 
Launched “Hush! 300 Seconds” Video Contest
The Cultural Institute will accept, until 12:00 on October 8, registrations for the “Hush! 300 second” video shorts contest, focused on musical performances or vocal interpretations. Awards will be awarded in the categories “Music in Sport”, “Music and Jam”, “Creative and Fun”, “Enthusiasm”, “Spirit of Participation” and “More Popular”. The awards are sponsored by MGM, Air Macao and Tai Fung, ICBC, BNU and OCBC seats. The regulation and application form can be consulted and discharged on the IC electronic page. Organized by the Cultural Institute, the event “Hush! Concerts on the Beach” will take place between 11 and 19 October at Hac Sá Beach, Barra Zone and community neighborhoods.</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao away from Futsal Asian</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-afastado-asiatico-de-futsal/</link><description>Macao de Futsal's selection ended the participation in the finding phase for the Futsal Asia Championship with a defeat against Cambodia 11-2. In the previous challenges of Group C, the formation of the MSA had suffered two more goals, against host Tajiquistan and in the face of Japan
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Acquiring competition routine and trying to avoid major thrashing were the realistic objectives of the participation of the Macao de Futsal team in the qualification phase for the Asia Championship, which will take place next Anona Indonesia. One of the goals, gaining experience, has been achieved, but something heavy defeat was not possible to avoid, since, at the outset, it was known that the opponents have more traquejo in these international wanderings.
Even so, on the final journey of Group C, it was expected that the training guided by Chiang Ka Cho, assisted by Eduardo Farm could balance a little more against Cambodia, a selection that occupies the 126th place in the world ranking, while Macau was, at the departure for the competition, 115th.
On the court, in the indoor hall of Dushanbe, the capital of Tajiquistan, where all the challenges of the tournament took place, this difference was reversed, as the Cambodians have superiorized over the 40 minutes of the meeting, winning by comfortable margin, 11-2, 4-0 at the break. In the second half, Macao consented seven more goals, although he was able to score twice through Leong Hou In (32 minutes) and Fong Chi wa (at 35).
The set of mashes ended with the third displacement throughout the race, after in previous games was also surpassed by Tajiquistan, 10-2, with both goals of Macao to be obtained by Fong Chi Wa, and the strongest opponent, Japan, 13-0. The final balance of Macau's performance is 34 goals conceded and four scored.
Thus were confirmed the weaknesses of the territory's futsal selection, which, in addition to this qualification for the Asian, has not much more chances of gaining competition routine throughout the year. The players, some of whom also play eleven football, participate in the local futsal championship for about four months.
Fong Chi Wa, which aligns at Marvel, was the most evidence element, having scored the four goals of the team.
Coach Chiang Ka Chon told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that "the team fully embraced performance in this Asian qualification and the results of the first two games (Tajiquistan and Japan), facing very strong, combining the defense with counterattacks to score goals, which was achieved."
The coach added that, in the third match, "the resistance decreased and some players acted with injuries, which eventually determined an unexpected result."
The group was won, as was expected by the Japanese, thirteenth parties of the international ranking, who won all the challenges, having in the last, who decided the first place, overtaken the home team, Tajiquistan, 3-1. The Tajique Formation is 46th in the world.
In the remaining groups, Australia and Kuwait secured their presence in the final phase (Group A), as well as Thailand and South Korea (B), Vietname and Lebanon (and here with China in third and Hong Kong in bedroom), Kirguistan and Uzbekistan (F, in this Timor-Leste series won the 5-4 and closed in third), Iran and Malasia (G) (G) and Afghanistan and Myanmar (H).
With regard to Asian ranking, Iran occupies the first position, ahead of Thailand and Japan. Already in the world, the Iranians are fifth, the thirteenth Thai and the thirteenth third party, in a smooth led by Brazil, ahead of Portugal, Spain and Argentina.
It is recalled that Macau organized the final phase of the futsal Asian in 2004 at the current Polytechnic University pavilion, where he won the Philippines in his group 7-3, then attended in almost all championships, and in the final phase and in the investigation, with two exceptions, 2016 and 2022.
The best participation took place in 2008 in Japan, where the mashes surpassed Indonesia 4-2 and drew against Kuwait to three balls.</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MGM Alert for “Deepfake” video with pansy ho</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mgm-alerta-para-video-deepfake-pansy-ho/</link><description>MGM China denounced a fraudulent scheme involving the creation and dissemination of a video “Deepfake” generated by Artificial Intelligence (IA), which illegally embodied Pansy Ho, president and executive director of the company. The video “falsely promotes a fictitious investment plan, with unfounded promises of 100 times higher returns,” warned the game operator in a statement, emphasizing that “such content is totally fraudulent and has no connection” with the company or pansy ho. "MGM China vehemently condemns these acts of falsification of identity and misrepresentation and reserves all legal rights against the parties involved, in order to protect our rights and interests," the statement can be read. MGM China also urges the public and the media to maintain “maximum vigilance” and verify information through official channels, noting that the dissemination of fraudulent content can have legal and financial consequences. “All commercial updates are communicated exclusively through the company's official platforms,” he adds.</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Placed for sale tickets for national games</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/colocados-a-venda-bilhetes-para-os-jogos-nacionais/</link><description>The Macao Competition Zone Organizing Committee of the National Games has put for sale the first tickets to access the tests that will take place in November, including volleyball (female adults), karate and table tennis. Interested parties will have to register with the real name before purchasing the tickets. Meanwhile, the test competitions of all modalities were “successful” and “preparatory work have been developed in full and orderly,” said the secretary for social matters and culture. LAM, who is also the chairman of the committee, attended a meeting, along with other officials, including the coordinator, Pun Weng Kun, in which the work already performed, including the organization of competitions, the preparation of the enclosures, the promotional activities and the service of volunteers. Until the start of the games, the Macao competition zone will host several events, including the 30 -day decreasing count ceremonies and volunteer commitment, the torch transmission activity. During the meeting, representatives of the public services of the Organizing Committee presented the situation of preparatory work, including safety, border passage, food security, dissemination and promotion, medical assistance and transportation, and exchanged opinions in various areas.</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Centenary doctor in Japan still exerts medicine with no intention of reforming</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/medica-centenaria-japao-ainda-exerce-medicina-sem-intencao-de-se-reformar/</link><description>A woman over 100 years old from Wakayama province in Japan continues to exercise medicine to support the health of local residents. Dr. Teru Kasamatsu, a doctor at Kasamatsu Hospital in Kainan, serves external patients three days a week, especially ordinary patients.
At the hospital facing Wakayama Bay, Kasamatsu wore a white gap and talked to patients with a kind smile while checking their medical records. "Your blood pressure is a little high," he told a patient. "Please bring your medicine registration book the next time."
The hospital was founded in 1909, and Kasamatsu examines and treats residents as a doctor for almost 80 years. Your belief as a doctor is very clear. "The best thing to do is hear what the sick means," he said.
Now, his second son, Dr. Satoshi, 68, is the director of the hospital, and his wife, Dr. Hitomi, 61, heads the Nursing Department. Kasamatsu has a great confidence of both.
Satoshi said, "She's great to create an atmosphere where it's easy to talk. Patients trust her."
Dr. Kasamatsu was born in 1925 where Kinokawa is today in Wakayama province, as the youngest of five brothers. He chose to become a doctor because the war intensified while still attending female secondary education. Seeing many women lose their husbands in the war, his father recommended that he learned to sustain himself, Kasamatsu said.
He studied a lot and became a doctor in 1948. He married Shigeru, an orthopedic surgeon at the age of 24. When Shigeru took over her father's Kasamatsu Hospital, she began working at the hospital unit with her husband.
The couple managed the hospital together as they raised three children. She said she sometimes served 120 patients a day. As the hospital used to receive urgent patients, it was not uncommon to stay up all night to attend surgeries.
“I did everything from examining the patients to dispense with medicines and accounting,” he recalled. When the hospital began to accept more hospitalized sick and needed a cook to provide meals, he decided to do so alone and got a cook license when he was over 30 years old.
Despite his busy and busy days, he continued to work with energy, even though he was hospitalized for cancer treatment. Dr. Kasamatsu states that the secret of his longevity and health is in his diet.
"Eat a lot of vegetables, such as spinach, broccoli, kale and okra. Eating vegetables helps keep blood sugar levels low, so it's good."
Shigero died in 2012 at the age of 91, and Kasamatsu is currently alone in the house, which is next to the hospital. Even at 100, it is still without cane. It receives support from people around it, however, remains healthy both physically and mentally.
Its daily routine is to resolve numerical puzzles, which, according to itself, is a way of preventing dementia. Spends one to two hours a day to solve them to keep the mind active.
Kasamatsu's hobby is the piano, which started playing at age 70, inspired by Shigeru, who had already begun to learn before her. Plays with skill as it traputes pieces like Moon River. It also has weekly classes and endeavored to dominate Für Elise, from Beethoven, even performing in a recital alongside young people.
It also tries to update your medical knowledge by reading medical association materials whenever you have time. She has no intention of reforming herself. “I'm not feeling bad,” he says.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>