<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Electoral campaign started “orderly”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/campanha-eleitoral-arrancou-de-forma-ordenada/</link><description>Macau is in the middle of the election campaign, which will extend for 14 days. The six candidacies for direct suffrage and the six for the indirect began the promotion of political programs at the early hours of Saturday, participating throughout the day at a ceremony in Tap Seac Square. The event attracted several people, who were able to have a first contact with the candidates. The chairman of the Electoral Affairs Commission indicated that the campaign period started “orderly”. Seng Ioi Man also asked the lists to engage in the “proactive and full transmission” of his ideas to serve Macau and encouraged the electorate to vote on September 14

Victor Rebelo
 
Candidate lists for the elections of the Legislative Assembly (AL), six for direct suffrage and six for the indirect, are already in full period of electoral propaganda, trying, with the presentation of political programs, to ensure the voters' vote for the act that will take place on September 14.
Thus, it will be 14 intense days of election campaign for lists, either with street actions, favoring narrow contact with citizens, either through other initiatives, including the dissemination of ideas for the future of Macao in periods equitable in a “antenna time” on television and radio.
The start of the campaign, which will take place until midnight on September 12, had an official opening ceremony in Tap Seac Square, which brought together several dozens of people, mostly supporters of the lists, despite the rain that fell over a morning. However, in the afternoon, with the sun shining, the number of citizens was thickening.
During the event, in addition to the dissemination of political programs, on stages and stalls installed for this purpose by the Legislative Assembly Electoral Affairs Commission (Caeal), there were also interactive elements, where it was possible to simulate the vote or mark with the commemorative stamp of the elections, among others.
The ceremony was chaired by Caeal's head, Seng Ioi Man, by the corruption, Ieong Seong, five members of the Commission and the Director of Post and Telecommunications Services, Derby Lau.
In his speech, the president of Caeal said he hopes that all lists will perform campaign activities according to the law, “striving in the transmission, proactive and full of the respective political programs, ideas and vision of serving Macao, through exchange and interaction, with the aim of gaining the support of voters”.
He also pointed out that Caeal “invites the entire electorate to participate and monitor the activities of the electoral campaign (…) and to go to the 14th of September to the polling station attributed to support with his vote the list of his preference”. "With our vote, we will contribute together to the formation of the new Legislative Assembly, ensuring the stable and lasting implementation of the principle" a country, two systems "and better implementation of the" Macao Macao governed by patriots "principle," said Judge Seng Ioi Man.
On the other hand, he indicated that, so far, “the electoral process has elapsed in an orderly and legal way”, noting that “with this well -consolidated basis, Caeal expects everyone to continue to work together to maintain the electoral order, to comply with the provisions of the electoral law and the instructions of Caeal (…)”. "Together, we will ensure that these elections are successfully carried out in a fair, impartial and integral environment," he said.
On the sidelines of the event, Seng Ioi Man stated that the electoral campaign has elapsed in an “orderly way”, hoping that the lists and support teams will continue to maintain a “positive atmosphere” to ensure “impartiality, equity and integrity in elections”. On the other hand, it ensured that Caeal "will continue to closely oversee the situation of the election campaign together with the competent authorities."
The president of Caeal was pleased to have seen "numerous voters and residents" to participate in the rally held the day before and also in Saturday's event, "demonstrating an active participation in the elections."
 
CCAC received 80 complaints in the electoral process
The commissioner against corruption, Ieong Seong, said the body “has maintained the frequency and intensity of monitoring and patrolling work”, since the beginning of the advertising prohibition period. In addition, it revealed that since the beginning of the period of the constitution of the proposal so far, more than 80 complaints have been received, mostly done online, having been established 22 processes, all related to irregular campaign behaviors.
Regarding campaign activities and benefit nature actions, the commissioner indicated that all collective associations and candidates have already made statements in accordance with stipulations. The CCAC received 52 statements filed by candidates, involving 114 benefit activities. On the other hand, it registered 67 declarations of legal persons, involving 356 benefit actions, for which "will trigger inspection and supervision."
 
Disqualifications can ward off voters
Political commentator Sonny Lo told Lusa that "the middle -class liberals, younger voters (…), may be frustrated by the disqualification of relatively liberal and moderate candidates." It is recalled that the State Security Defense Commission has excluded all 12 candidates from two lists, considering them “not defenders of the basic or non-faithful law”. One of them was still deputy Ron Lam, one of the government's most critical voices in Al over the past four years. "On social networks - Facebook, Twitter - many voters and young people question why they were disqualified," he said. The disqualification was “a little surprising” and “the younger middle class may not be willing to vote,” he predicted. On the contrary, Lou Shenghua, Professor of Political Science at Macao Polytechnic University, believes that "the rate of abstention in this election is not higher than the last election." On the other hand, Sonny Lo said the opposition can survive disqualification but have to adapt. “Liberals seem to repeat some of the palmatory mistakes,” he laments. The analyst believes that exclusion may be linked to the “red lines” of the CCP, including contacts with Taiwan or comments about the 1989 protests at Tiananmen Square in Beijing. In his view, the opposition needs more caution when giving interviews or talking to the foreign press. In addition, it should "adapt to the new political environment, focusing on more-centered on Macao, such as [population] subsistence and less external matters." "Macao's democratic space is limited. But within this limited space, it is necessary to look for spaces where it is possible to boost change," says Sonny Lo.
 
JTM and Electoral Act
In accordance with the electoral law, the Jornal Tribuna de Macao begins today the coverage of the campaign for the legislative elections on September 14. Like previous years, we will adopt a model that aims to inform our readers about the ideas defended by the various candidacies, under the premise of granting the same journalistic treatment to all competing lists in direct suffrage. Without prejudice to any general reports on the elections, never focused on specific lists, we will present interviews with the different candidacy teams, which will be entitled to a page until the campaign is closed, naturally without any charges for the lists, as a way to provide a public interest service to readers.
In this sense, we sent a fixed set of questions to all applications, whose answers will be published over the next few days, in increasing order of the number of the lists in the voting newsletters, among those we have received until the day of production of the edition.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-09-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>ALS guarantees to have “rigorously” appreciate each proposal of law</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/al-garante-ter-apreciado-de-forma-rigorosa-cada-proposta-de-lei/</link><description>Regarding the legislative session 2024/2025, the president of AL observes “new progress and success in all work”, despite “challenges and pressure”. In the Activities Report, Kou Hoi In points out that the Hemiciclo ensured “a rigorous and meticulous appreciation of each bill” in the last legislative session
 
In the 4th and last legislative session of the VII Legislative Assembly (AL), which began on October 16, 2024 and will end on October 15 this year, the Al held 28 plenary sessions (average attendance rate of 97%) and 100 Committee meetings (average assiduity rate of 96%). In addition, it “accelerated the progress of production and legislative reviews”, under the “assumption of ensuring legislative quality”, having appreciated and approved 22 laws and two resolutions, “with an attitude of rigor, meticulosity, pragmatism and rationality”, concludes the report of activities related to legislative session 2024/2025.
"Despite the challenges and pressure, in particular, the lack of time, the high volume of work and the accelerated rhythm," AL has achieved, "with joint efforts, new progress and success in all work," says Kou Hoi In, president of the legislative body, noting that al "played an important supervisory role in the consideration of legislative initiatives and the budget proposal presented by the government."
Kou Hoi in stresses that the Al provides “a strong institutional support” to “the full realization of the Macao principle governed by patriots, the rise in governance capacity, the promotion of industrial diversification, the impetus of hengqin-Macau integration, and the guarantee of the population's welfare”.
According to the legislature, in the legislature, the Hemiciclo has observed the institutional provision enshrined in the Basic Law on the power of legislative initiative and repeatedly discussed with the Executive the issues related to the bills at different levels, "which, from the initial version to the final version, also need to go through various work texts, thus ensuring a rigorous and meticulous appreciation of each law."
Regarding the inspection, the AL “fulfills its legal attributions, persisting in exercising the supervision under the law, correctly and effectively, in respect for the legal competences of the Chief Executive and the Executive Body, and supporting the government in effective governance and under the law,” he asserts.
In addition, it recalls that six monitoring reports on land policies, public finances and work and employment matters were prepared, as well as 782 written and oral interpeairs on government action, and 257 interventions in the period before the age of day (IAOD) on the most diverse issues related to the life of the population and development. In addition, it recalls that AL has made more than 100 calls related to letters, phone calls, visits and petitions, having managed to “supervise the good use of the public purse, and exhort the government to constantly improve and effectively implement the various policies and benefit measures for the population”.
For Kou Hoi In, these results “were achieved thanks to the fulfillment of the functions and responsibilities of all deputies to serve the population, professionalism, efficiency and dedication of workers from Al, coordination and close collaboration between the legislative and executive bodies, and the strong support and dissemination of AL”.
Generally speaking, he concludes that the al has fulfilled, "always and scrupulously," the predominance of the executive branch whose core is the chief executive. On the other hand, he recalls that the members of the Al Table made a visit to the Chief Executive, having exchanging opinions on the creation of a more effective communication mechanism and the improvement of the legislative coordination mechanism.
Specifically, the report notes that, in legislative production, AL has been able to play “its fundamental role of legislative body regarding the expression, balance and coordination of society's interests”, “increasing the well-being of the population and ensuring impartiality and justice in society”. Moreover, during the process of appreciation of law proposals, he points out that both the Al and the government "maintained a narrow collaboration and positive interaction."
According to the report, the “in-depth discussions” “result in laws that better satisfy social development and correspond to the interests of the population, effectively increasing the quality of legislative work”.
“Al has persisted in scientifically and democratically legislating, promoting development and ensuring good governance through good right, and widely listening to the opinions and suggestions of all quadrants, using the most diverse channels to research and understand the actual situation, and to perform, if necessary, consultations with specific bodies and professional associations,” says the document.
In the last legislative session, AL appreciated 23 legislative initiatives, of which 22 were approved in the specialty (14 definition of laws and eight of law change). The only one that was not approved was the proposal of the road traffic law.
On the other hand, Al Reviu the Regiment and the Statute of the Deputies, “in order to significantly strengthen the regimental constitution itself, consolidate the basis for the exercise of the functions of the Legislative body of the MSAR and to prepare a propitious land for the beginning without the new legislature,” says the report.
Moreover, the document points to the “efficient management” of assets and human resources, a “rational control over the increase in the number of workers and the total amount of expenses” of AL, as well as increasing the quality, professional capacity and level of service of human resources.
As for staff formation, national security and Portuguese learning courses were mentioned. It should also be noted that Hemiciclo has recorded a reduction in the burden of translators and an increase in the effectiveness of their work through the use of the “Portuguese/Portuguese-Chinese Chinese Translation Auxiliary System of Official Documents”.
 
Five deputies were the most present and interventive
Deputies Leong Sun Iok, Leong Hong Sai, Ngan Iek Hang, Ma Io Fong and Nick Lei were the most presence at the AL 28 plenary meetings and in all committees to which they belong), as well as those who presented the most interpeairs (all submitted 44 writings, four orals and 11 IAOD), in legislative session 2024/2025, shows the report.
Regarding attendance, Vong Hin Fai, Angela Leong, Zheng Anting, Ella Law and Chan Hou Seng also had a rate of 100%. In contrast, Chui Sai Peng and Pang Chuan were the ones who were absent in more meetings - Chui Sai Peng absent in six plenary and 10 meetings of the 1st Permanent Commission, and Pang Chuan absent in three plenary and five meetings of the 2nd Permanent Commission.
Regarding the interventions, in addition to the five deputies mentioned above, Wong Kit Cheng, Che Sai Wang and Ron Lam also made 44 written interpeairs, four oral and 11 IAOD.
Except for AL, Chan Chak Mo was the only one who did not intervene or interpeairs. In turn, Chui Sai Cheong, Al vice president of AL, did not submit interpeairs, and was a subscriber of only one IAOD. Among the deputies who have not challenged the government, are also all seven nominees -MA Chi Seng, Iau Teng Pio, Eddie Wu, Pang Chuan, Chan Hou Seng, Kou Kam Fai and Cheung Kin Chung -as well as Vong Hin Fai, elected by indirect suffrage.
 
Kou Hoi In Want New Pragmatic and Responsible Deputies
The president of the AL shows the conviction that the deputies of the new legislature "will undoubtedly continue the good tradition of love for the country and Macau". Vinking the desire that they comply with the oath through concrete actions and make efforts to work well, it hopes that, with pragmatism and a responsible attitude, they will take the initiative to adapt to the developmental trend and the requirements of the time to “actively respond to the new expectations of the population in relation to a better life and promote a better integration of Macao in the conjuncture of national development”. In addition, he believes that "with greater wisdom and political courage," they will play well "the role of practitioners, taxpayers, promoters and defenders of the cause" a country, two systems "," without defrauding the new mission conferred by the New Age. " And “they will strive to advance the works of AL,” he stresses.</description><pubDate>2025-09-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Unemployment rises with the entry of newborns in the market</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/desemprego-sobe-entrada-de-recem-graduados-mercado/</link><description>Between May and July, there were 300 more unemployed residents than in the quarter of April to June, according to the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services. In addition, the number of young people looking for the first job and the number of part -time workers also grew
 
Pedro Milheirão
Unemployment rose slightly from May to July, and a total of 7,600 unemployed residents was registered, more 300 (+3.5%) than in the quarter from April to June, according to the employment investigation released by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). The global unemployment rate increased by 0.1 percentage points to 2%, and the percentage of unemployment residents rose from 2.5%to 2.6%.
DSEC points out that the scenario was due to “the number of unemployed people looking for the first job to have increased at the time of graduation”. According to the data, of the total of unemployed residents, 13.7% were looking for the first job, corresponding to an increase of 2.7 percentage points, compared to the previous period, "thanks to some new graduates have entered the job market."
In addition to these, most unemployed residents looking for a new job were previously in the branches of construction, retail trade and bullies and other betting games.
On the other hand, the sub -unemployment rate has also grown 0.1 percentage points to 1.7%, and there was an increase of 200 people underemployed to a total of 6,300.
Between May and July, the active population decreased to 379.1 thousand, with the number of persons employed from 372.7 thousand to 371.5 thousand, in relation to the preceding period. The labor force of the MSAR still represented two thirds of the population (66.4%), corresponding to a loss of 0.2 percentage points, in quarterly terms.
Among the residents, 288,500 were active, 400 less than in the quarter of April to June. In addition, the underemployment between residents grew more than in the general population. There were 6,100 part -time residents between May and July, 300 more than in the preceding period. In addition, 280.9 thousand residents were employed, a reduction of 700 workers.
In annual terms, global unemployment rose 0.3 percentage points at a rate of 1.7%, such as unemployment between residents, at a rate of 2.3% from May to July last year. The global activity rate fell 1.4 points, from 67.8% to 66.4%, in homologous terms. The percentage of active residents was 62.4%, in the same interval as last year, translating a decrease of 1.3 points to 61.1%.
 
Largest quota of workers in leisure and public function
From May to July, “Cultural and Recreational Activities, Bullies and other services” employed more than a quarter of the population (26%), corresponding to an annual increase of four percentage points. “Public Administration and Social Security”, on the other hand, employed 10.9% of labor force, translating a three percentage point growth.
The “thick trade and retail” grew 2.3 percentage points, from 11.8%to 14.1%, while “transport, storage and communications” rose 1.4 points to 6.7%, in homologous terms. The sector of “health and social action” employed 5.1% of workers, corresponding to an annual increase of 0.9 percentage points, and “education” represented 6.8% of the population employed, plus 0.5 percentage points.
On the other hand, the population employed in “hotels, restaurants and the like” decreased by 3.5 percentage points, representing 10% of the total of employees, between May and July this year compared to the same quarter of 2024. The “construction” branch was responsible for 6% of employment but 1.1 percentage points.
 
Orders more opportunities for residents and young people
During a working group meeting to coordinate employment promotion, Tai Kin IP asked members to commit to balance between supply and job demand, instructing services to demand suppliers the increase of “resident workers' proportion,” according to a statement by the secretary's office for the economy and finance. Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) will also create a recruitment platform “to create more job opportunities,” you can read. During the meeting, the representative of education services drew attention to the “newly graded youth employment needs”, asking the group to support measures. Since the beginning of the year, Dsal has helped 7,471 residents to find work, and half were young people under 35.</description><pubDate>2025-09-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Bamboo made macau and not even in modernity the metal will impose</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/bambu-fez-macau-nem-na-modernidade-metal-se-vai-impor/</link><description>Yoyo Leung (D), CEO of Wuyi Scaffolding Engineering poses for photography in the company of one of his partners, at the company's headquarters in Macao, China, April 16, 2025. Manifestation "of the Deserk" and the willingness to build quickly, the traditional technique of bamboo scaffolding assembly is still adjusted to modern mesh macao today. Urban. Total transition to metal would have socioeconomic impact. (Accompanies Lusa text on August 31, 2025). Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro/Lusa



Manifestation of “DESARCAR” and the desire to build quickly, the traditional technique of assembly of bamboo scaffolding still adjusts today to the modern macao of dense urban network. The total transition to metal would have socioeconomic impact.
Yoyo Leong belongs to an empire. And to realize this, just go through the businesswoman's land in the center of the mud, where is located Wiyu, the scaffolding business that inherited from the father.
He assumes himself as the only woman in the management of a gender company, and it is not difficult to believe: Yoyo circulates between warehouses, metal scaffolding, a world with men orbit around this entrepreneur.
“Where are the bamboo?” Asks an employee. The man follows us by our side, points to where gigantic canvas blankets protect the rain canas, the sun. Exposure can limit the lifetime of the plant.
“At first, I was not used to going to the work. I had to overcome many obstacles, dirt, hard work, a trip to the bathroom, the weight of the shoes and safety helmet,” he recalls.
It was in Zhuhai, across the border, that his father launched himself in the business of metal scaffolding. The bamboo came later, in the start of the century, when they moved to Macau. Of these early days, Yoyo recalls the act of mooring.
"It is necessary to have technique to tie bamboo, because if it is not very tight, it is loose and this affects the entire structure of the scaffolding. The technique is very important and it is necessary to use the feet too," he explains.
At one end of the ground is the Wuyi office, in a prefabricated structure. The façade does not denounce the interior: there is the traditional table of serving tea, a tank with carp-lucky symbol and fortune in Chinese culture-a pagoda fig tree to cross the ceiling to the outside and even the model of a rocket decorated with the Chinese flag and more than two meters.
On the walls, photographs of Yoyo's father alongside former leaders of the local government. Also images that testify some projects of the company, such as the Macao Science Center, the MGM-Casino Hotel and, more recently, the Londoner Integrated Resort. The company's interventions in these three works were carried out with metal scaffolding.
Despite this, says Yoyo Leong, metal and bamboo are used in equal proportion in Macau. The six residential towers that Wuyi is now working in Zone A, where public housing will be born, grow in parallel with bamboo scaffolding.
The debate on this old construction technique has returned to the agenda since neighboring authorities Hong Kong announced in March that they will “promote a broader adoption of metal scaffolding in public works”. They claimed security issues, with 23 deaths involving bamboo scaffolding since 2018.
In Macau, four people have died in serious work accidents with bamboo scaffolding since 2018, according to data provided in April by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, "being the cause of accidents mainly to human fall."
But for now, there are no plans to lower the reeds in the city, where the assembly of scaffolding with this material has been registered since 2017 in the inventory of the local cultural intangible heritage. In a response to Lusa, the authorities say they are aware of the development of the sector, “having an open attitude” in the face of the use of metal.
In the case of Macau, architect Nuno Soares notes that the obligation of metal may have socioeconomic impact in the region: “We are talking about an economy where we have many companies that are small and medium. Civil construction has hundreds of companies and if we make it mandatory to use metal scaffolding, we are transforming this type of economy.”
Still on metal scaffolding, the architect says, they can be “more resistant, but also heavier and more expensive”, as well as “demanding specialized machinery and large companies”.
But safety is also categorical element of the bamboo alternative, a flexible material that grows fast, abounds in the region and is cheap. In periods of strong winds or tropical storms, explains Nuno Soares, "the bamboo structure is lighter and more redundancy, that is, it is linked to the structure of buildings in more points, faster than part."
In addition, in a town with a dense urban mesh like Macau, with narrow streets, the metal scaffold will occupy a larger base, and it can make it difficult, while bamboo “have a very small 'footprint', increasing as it rises at height”.
And in this discussion, of course, it is still the future of local artisans, who will hardly find a new generation willing to fuck the bamboo chess. “Like all very physical work, it has less adherence from the new generation, but there is also an opportunity, because, again, it has an economic value that is still significant,” says Soares.
Bamboo, he says, is not only past. And in Macau we must continue to value this local technique, instead of “importing only other traditions”. "This vernacular technique, this technique of developing and building quickly is intrinsically linked to the construction in Macao and is regulated. Bamboo did Macau," he says.
 
Catarina Domingues, journalist at Lusa Agency (text edited)</description><pubDate>2025-09-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Su tong highlights Saramago's world influence</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/su-tong-destaca-influencia-mundial-de-saramago/</link><description>Chinese author Su Tong, winner of the Man Asian Literary Prize, who received a 'Honoris Cause' doctorate in Macau, highlighted Lusa the impact of José Saramago, “writers revered” worldwide. “In the Portuguese-language world, there is a revered and honorable figure by writers around the world: José Saramago. His influence extends all over the planet,” said Su Tong.
"I am also among your admirers," added the 62 -year -old writer after a lecture on his literary career at Macau University (UCM). UCM distinguished with a doctorate 'Honoris Causa' Su Tong, author of seven novels and more than 200 short stories, some of which are translated into Portuguese, such as “my life as emperor” and “wives and concubines”. “Wives and Concubinas” was adapted to the cinema by director Zhang Yimou in 1991 and was prohibited in mainland China.
During the lecture, Su Tong noted that his literary journey began when he was young, hearing stories. "In the early 1970s, when people's spiritual life was arid, the fascination with tales became increasingly intense," he recalled. To continue a story that had not heard until the end, Su Tong tried to write the outcome of the plot, thus embarking on his writing career.
The author considers that it was precisely the time he lived that forged his connection to literary creation. The 1980s made China enter an age of literary fervor, which further lit its creative passion, he explained.
Su Tong is one of the best -known contemporary Chinese novelists residing in China and won the Man Asian Literary Prize in 2009, with the Asian version of Man Booker Prize, with the book “The Boat for Redemption,” a novel passed during the Cultural Revolution.
All writers are spokespersons of their time, and the time, "like the Egyptian sphinx, reveals different aspects when seen from different times and angles," he said in the lecture.
To Lusa, Su Tong said that the writers of this era share a feeling of "weightless absence," "this feeling of being drifting." "Consequently, they become more attuned to the relationship between humanity and reality, and between the writer and the world," he explained.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-09-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>The architect who wants to see the bamboo challenge the weather</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/arquitecto-quer-ver-bambu-desafiar-tempo/</link><description>Catarina Domingues*

To study and work for bamboo for over 20 years, Nuno Soares has seen future for permanent buildings with this material in Macao, where he has tradition and associated economic value, but lack regulation.
For Nuno Soares, the versatility of bamboo is not exhausted in temporary construction. Neither in the usual scaffolding that cope skyscrapers in progression, nor on Pads of Cantonense opera erected at festivities, or giant sculptures, thought by students or artists, or even moments that would be unlikely-and that did not dispense with contestation-such as the end of the Portuguese administration, when a bamboo square was improvised in the center of Macao.
Portuguese architect and academic distinguish “a potential that is not yet fully explored”: the use of this material, rooted in the city's tradition and economic fabric, to give life to bamboo structures with no demolition date. There is regulation only for temporary projects.
“We cannot be fundamentalists and defend only what we know and are used to,” the architect says in an interview with Lusa. There is a disciplinary obligation of the field of architecture and the construction of creating better products “from the point of view of sustainability, resistance and aesthetics”, he argues.
Soares, a native of Lisbon but living in Macau since 2003, crossed for the first time with the potential of this “beautiful material” in construction when he visited Macau in 1997. And what is such a routine element for those who live the region's daily life was for Portuguese, with a vision used to another urban landscape, the beginning of a trip.
At the Center for Architecture and Urbanism (Curb), which founded with designer Filipa Simões in 2014, has conducted investigation in this field, with work done with bamboo artisans.
Also at the University of São José (USJ), where he is at the head of the Department of Architecture and Design, Portuguese guides annually, in collaboration with industry, the construction of a bamboo pavilion - with material used in the assembly of scaffolding and that, in the end, will serve that same purpose again.
“An architecture that is very innovative, very challenging, which uses parametric design of the most sophisticated worldwide and then builds with a handcrafted technique,” ​​says the project, noting that only specialized companies and technicians are allowed to build bamboo for public safety reasons.
In the field of permanent construction, USJ is developing in partnership with Thailand's Assumption University, a project that foresees the building of a structure, “and then monitoring over the life period” and performance of the building and being able to draw conclusions.
Despite being a degraded material, there are techniques to deal with permanent bamboo construction that differ from the options for limited time works. “We should not prevent evolution,” he argues.
In addition to Thailand, where there is a code that allows the building of bamboo permanent buildings, without the term architecture is common in several other geographies of the region, such as Indonesia, being the Green School, in Bali, a private school, a prominent work.
"Bamboo, as a permanent construction, enters a classification of materials that are those that are the light structures, such as some metal structures. It is important that we use the materials that are suitable. In Macau we have so much experience and tradition of using bamboo, which it is already part of the urban landscape," he reflects.
It is necessary to realize where these bamboo structures can be useful: "namely in buildings in buildings that exist, terraces buildings, because they are structures that are light naturally, which carry little weight to the existing structure."
“Bamboo has legs to walk and things to do in the future, and we have already seen that there is a cutting-edge industry that is also working with bamboo, doing bamboo clusters,” he says, referring to the creation of compound products produced from this material.

*Journalist of Agency Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-09-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Melco reaches “balanced growth”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/melco-alcanca-crescimento-equilibrado/</link><description>In the first six months of the year, Melco registered profits of Hong Kong's $ 350.8 million, and last year it had signaled losses of 253.2 million. Net revenue rose 12.4% in annual terms, and the "house of Dancing Water" boosted the group's non-game gains. Lawrence Ho speaks of a “balanced growth” of the group
 
Melco Resorts and Entertainment recorded Hong Kong's $ 350.8 million profits in the first half of this year, “reaching a balanced growth,” according to a company statement. It is recalled that, in the same year period, Melco had signaled a loss of 253.2 million.
On the other hand, between January and June, the group's net revenue was 19.96 billion, an increase of 12.4% compared to the 17.77 billion noted in the same period of 2024, with the increase to be attributed to the “best performance” in game -related general operations, but also with non -playing elements.
Lawrence Ho, president of the group and CEO of Melco International, said the group "demonstrated resilient performance throughout its integrated resort portfolio", having achieved "balanced growth, optimizing operating expenses and investing in premium property improvements and experiences for customers." In the background, he stressed in a statement, "our adaptability to market dynamics has strengthened the basis for sustainable growth throughout our diverse portfolio."
Specifically in relation to Macao, he noted that he was driven to operational efficiency, "through strategic improvements in our real estate." Regarding the relaunch of the show "House of Dancing Water" in May this year, Lawrence Ho pointed out that "it provided a strong impulse" to the game not related to the game, "reaffirming the position of Macao as an entertainment destination."
On the other hand, the group generated an EBITDA (results before interest, taxes, amortization and depreciation) of 5.37 billion by the end of June, compared to 4.49 billion registered in the same period last year.
"In Philippines, City of Dreams Manila has shown agility to implement prudent cost optimization measures in response to the intensification of competition in the market. In Cyprus, the City of Dreams Mediterranean and satellite casinos showed solid results, despite the events in the Middle East," said the company's CEO.
Lawrence Ho also recalled that the City of Dreams Sri Lanka, opened in August, was the first resort integrated in Sri Lanka and southern Asia. "This project demonstrates the group's mild capital strategy, which aims to maximize returns while mitigating investment risks, and will serve as a model for future expansions in high -growth emerging markets," he continued.
Looking to the future, Melco is "optimistic" about long -term prospects. “Through an unshakable commitment to excellence and innovation, we will continue to improve our offerings, strategically seeking emerging opportunities. This approach consolidates our market leadership and drives sustained growth and success,” said Lawrence Ho in a statement.</description><pubDate>2025-09-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>July with the largest number of guests and less excursions</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/julho-maior-numero-de-hospedes-menos-excursoes/</link><description>The hotel sector recorded the largest number of guests this year in July, with more than 1.28 million tourists being housed in Macao. On the other hand, the entrances of visitors in excursions fell 18.4%, in annual terms, given the most ease of obtaining individual visas by the continent's residents
 
In July, the Hotel Establishments of the MSAR hosted more than 1.28 million people, the highest value of the year and corresponding to an annual increase of 4%, compared to the same month of 2024, according to official data. On the other hand, Macao has only 145,000 visitors entries at excursions, minus 18.4% in annual terms. Although international tourists in excursions increased by 15.1%to 15,000, those from mainland China fell 24.1%to 124,000. The Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) explains that this was due to the fact that more visitors on the continent entered with an individual visa, benefiting from a “greater degree of convenience” at the entry into the masters.
Of the visitors who were staying in the territory, 958 thousand came from the interior of China (+3.9%) and 82 thousand from abroad (+7.3%). Visitors from Thailand increased 41.7% to six thousand, and tourists from the US grew 16.1% to a total of five thousand in homologous terms. South Korea's 25,000 visitors represent an annual increase of 5.5%, while the four thousand Indonesia correspond to an increase of 3.4%.
On the other hand, in the same month, fewer people from Japan, India and Malaysia were housed in the territory, with annual breaks of 3.1%, 7.9%and 2.9%, respectively. From Japan only six thousand guests arrived, while from India and Malaysia only four thousand were housed for each country, according to DSEC. The average stay period was 1.6 nights, the same as in July last year.
The occupancy rate of the sector was 91%, representing an increase of 1.9 percentage points, in relation to the same month of 2024. Five star hotels recorded the highest rate of 94.2%, corresponding to a growth of 2.3 percentage points. Four -star hotels marked the largest increase of 2.6 percentage points for an occupancy rate of 86.4%. Three -star hotels, in turn, had a break of 0.2 percentage points for a rate of 86.3%.
During the first seven months of 2025, the average occupancy rate of hotel stations guests corresponded to 89.4%, an annual climb of 4.7 percentage points. Hotel establishments hosted more than 8.4 million individuals, translating a decrease of 0.3% in homologous terms, with an average permanence period of 1.7 nights.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-09-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Detained for threatening wife with kitchen knife</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/detido-por-ameacar-esposa-faca-de-cozinha/</link><description>A case of domestic violence, with physical aggression and threatens with a kitchen knife, led to the detention of a 35 -year -old resident in the North Zone
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Trivian domestic issues will have led a 35-year-old resident to assault his wife and threaten her with a kitchen knife. The man was eventually detained. According to the police investigation, the individual left for the aggression for being dissatisfied with the willingness of household items in a residence in the northern part of the city.
According to the authorities, on the afternoon of July 27, the suspect will have pushed the woman, while threatening her with a kitchen knife, requiring inspecting her mobile phone and other items.
The victim obeyed her husband's instructions and, after calming down the next morning, fled the scene and reported the incident to the authorities. The forensic exam confirmed that the victim suffered minor injuries.
The individual was arrested where the couple - who has a minor child - resided, having been seized a kitchen knife with a blade of 17.5 cm. Sent to the Public Prosecution Service, the perpetrator is accused of domestic violence, the use of prohibited weapons or related items, intimidation and severe coercion.
In another case, a 20-year-old local hairdresser is suspected of attracting teenagers to his salon, located next to the Olympic Sports Center in the mud, and then inducting them to consume cartridges of electronic cigarettes containing synthetic cannabinoids. Subsequently, I sold these cartridges to young people for 500 patacas each.
The PJ said that since January this year, the barber had bought drugs with drugs from a 37 -year -old filipino worker by 1,500 patacas the bottle, which could be divided into five cartridges.
Meanwhile, the PJ, in collaboration with Zhuhai's authorities, dismantled a transfronist group of illegal exchange rate, holding two men and two women in Macao. The case involved transactions of approximately $ 7.26 million from Hong Kong.
Investigations revealed that those responsible for two pledge stores acted in collishes with clandestine loans in Zhuhai, settling the data from more than 80 exchange clients together.
Police forces from both jurisdictions launched coordinated operations on July 28, having seized approximately one million dollars in illicit cash and documents from all financial and tax operations in the stores implicated and at the residence of the owner of the pledge store. The PJ believes the criminal organization has generated illegal profits of 500 hkd for every 10,000 exchanged, accumulating more than $ 363,000 since October last year.
However, Zhuhai police dismantled two clandestine exchange groups, holding nine individuals and seizing approximately 500,000 hkd.</description><pubDate>2025-09-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Books of the middle launches translation of the writings of Master Xun</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/livros-meio-lanca-traducao-dos-escritos-mestre-xun/</link><description>The first full translation of Chinese to Portuguese from the full work of philosopher Xun Kuang, better known as Xun Zzi, will be launched on the 10th of September by the Books do Meio Publishing, in a co-editing with the Macau Foundation. “Master Xun Writings” integrates 32 Chapters of the Confucian philosopher.
The translation of the publication is “a cornerstone of Chinese philosophical thinking finally accessible to the Lusophone reader in definitive edition and fills a crucial gap in the philosophical and synological studies in Portuguese,” says the text of publicity.
The work has extensive explanatory notes, critical comments and a comprehensive introduction that sites xun Zi in the context of the period of combatant kingdoms and traces its influence throughout history.
Unlike his contemporary Mencius, “who believed in the innate goodness of the human being,” Xun Zi argued that “human nature is originally bad (xing ER)”, and that goodness is acquired through “conscious effort, ritualized education (LI) and the orientation of wise and a just government,” the note adds.
The work addresses aspects such as ethics, politics, education, language and cosmology, "offering surprisingly modern perspectives on the nature of society."
Xun Zi is characterized as an “intellectual giant,” whose thinking is fundamental to understanding not only Confucianism, but the whole Chinese intellectual history. Publishing his complete works in Portuguese is a “editorial framework and a gift for students, academics and all readers who seek to understand the foundations of Chinese civilization,” says the book's launch statement.
The publisher Books do Meio says that, after having recently published the last of the four books, makes this classic accessible to Portuguese -speaking readers. "Translating Xun Zi was a journey of several years," he stresses, adding that "the rationalism of the Chinese philosopher, his defense of culture as an antidote to chaos and his language analysis resonate in a powerful way today."
Our biggest concern, concludes the introductory document of the event, "was also capturing the accuracy and argumentative strength of its text, allowing the Portuguese -speaking reader to face, for the first time its extent, one of the most lucid and challenging thinkers of humanity."
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-09-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MSAR PAYMENTS BALANCE WITH SUPERAVIT OF 144.3 billion</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/balanca-de-pagamentos-da-raem-superavit-de-1443-mil-milhoes/</link><description>The MSAR PAYMENTS BALANCE registered a surplus of 144.3 billion patacas in 2024, and increased by 28.8 billion compared to 115.4 billion noted in 2023, the monetary authority (AMCM) reported, based on preliminary estimates, pointing out that “the surplus observed in the commerce of services, as well as the net outputs Primary and Secondary Income ”. Composed of the checking account, capital account and financial account, the balance of payments is an integrated statistical record that presents the results of external transactions between an economic system and the whole world. Goods exports and imports of goods decreased 12.1% and 6.1% in annual terms. The deficit recorded in the goods account decreased 3.3 billion to 94.4 billion between 2023 and 2024. The total amount of service account exports grew 10.1% in 2024, “mainly due to the increase in tourist service exports”, while service imports ascended 9.3%. Therefore, the SUPERAVIT registered in the Services Account rose from 247.9 billion by 2023 to 273.2 billion PATACAs in the last year. The non -reserving financial assets registered a net outlet of 161.2 billion patacas, corresponding to an increase of 84.7 billion compared to 2023. AMCM points out that direct investment continued to register a net entry, which decreased from 9.3 billion by 2023 to 4.6 billion in 2024. On the other hand, the net output from the investment portfolio rose from 150.2 billion to 185.7 billion last year, "due to the increase in the external investment portfolio of Macao residents." At the same time, the financial derivatives recorded a net outlet of 0.4 billion last year.</description><pubDate>2025-09-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Studied prohibition of possession of electronic cigarettes in the</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/estudada-proibicao-de-posse-de-cigarros-electronicos-na-raem/</link><description>Health services (SSM) are studying the prohibition of possession of electronic cigarettes, and the idea is that punishment for this type of behavior will be referenced by the legal provisions in the regime for prevention and control of smoking. The information was advanced by Lam Chong, director of the Office for prevention and control of smoking and alcoholism, which, in statements to the Chinese language press, said that although Macao prohibits the manufacture, sale and import and export of electronic cigarettes, citizens can easily buy this type of products in neighboring regions. " They received opinions from society, hoping to further reinforce the regulation imposed on electronic cigarettes. ”On the other hand, the authorities will review the law to control water pipes and herbal tobacco. Lam Chong said the government intends to create areas of designated smoking, namely in the gates of siege and in the ruins of São Paulo, among other places with a large flow of people, in the sense of“ dealing with conduct Smoking when people walk. ”Preliminarily, he adds,“ the idea is to find a busy place to serve as a pilot point where the implementation of the designated smoke will be the subject of opinion in one year. ”And in this aspect, he will focus on disclosure and only later will take the penalty measure. "It is still being discussed, and the respective information may be released to the public when there is news," he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-09-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2465/</link><description>Registered 11th Imported Case of Chikungunya
Macau registered the 11th imported case of chikungunya fever. This is a 37-year-old resident living in a General Galhardo Street building. The woman was in the city of Jiangmen and is now hospitalized, being in a stable state. Kong Chi Meng, Director of Youth Education and Development Services, revealed that all schools have requested financial support from the body to acquire mosquito elimination equipment. He also said that the body will send the equipment, "according to the size of the geographical environment of schools."
 
28 “euros” for Badminton's Paralympic tests
The president of the preparatory cabinet for the organization of the Macao Competition Zone of the National Games, Pun Weng Kun, revealed that 28 gold medals will be awarded in Badminton's Paralympic competitions during a Canton press conference. In addition, he explained that these tests will be divided into two groups, one intended for athletes with physical disabilities and another reserved for sportsmen with hearing impaired. Badminton Paralympic tests will also be divided into four age groups.
 
UCM welcomes more than 4,000 new students
Almost 4,200 new students were at the opening ceremony of the new school year of the University of Macao. The institution's dean, Liu Jun, encouraged students to focus on “consolidating the academic base, learning to think of multiple disciplines, and resorting to new technologies and new tools to exploit with audacity, as well as form a global view and actively participate in social practice”.
 
Gongbei tickets rose 25% in July
Since July 1, the Gongbei Border Post has registered more than 20 million cross -border passages, and more than 4.4 million were performed by tourists. The total volume of tickets means an increase of 25%compared to the registered in the same year's same year period, which means this was the summer with the highest number of transfronist tourist movements in the last five years.
 
Available list of scholars who will study in Portugal
Preliminary lists of candidates admitted to the assignment of scholarships to study in Portugal in the school year of 2025/2026 are available, the direction of Youth Education and Development Services said. The body also indicated that the admitted candidates "must deliver, by September 12, 2025, the respective documents" in order to prove that the candidacy "fulfills the requirements". The selection test lists and the final results of the applications will be published, respectively, on October 17 and December 15.</description><pubDate>2025-09-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Set of filming of the nanjing massacre becomes a tourist spot on school holidays</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/set-de-filmagens-massacre-de-nanquim-torna-se-ponto-turistico-nas-ferias-escolares/</link><description>The sound of machine gun shots echoed by collapsed buildings while children eagerly exploited the devastated streets of the 1930s, enchanted by visiting the set of a Chinese blockbuster on a historical massacre.
Produced with mastery and full of stars, "Dead to Rights" takes place in Nanjing, then China's capital, for six weeks of mass murders, violations and looting by the Japanese army in 1937, which killed hundreds of thousands.
Like other films about the massacre, "Dead to Rights" does not hesitate to portray atrocities, but that didn't demotivate viewers. The film has been at the top of the Chinese box office since late July and is on display in Singapore's theaters.
Its set, in a movie park in the Shanghai suburbs, is now open to the public and was full of enthusiastic fans - many of them children, when AFP visited him this week.
A huge mural of the former Chinese leader, Chiang Kai-Shek, a bullet-kiced, contemplated from a bombarded building, while the visitors entered, taking selfies and broadcasting lively.
The film caused strong emotions. "It's a deep pain that comes from within, a feeling of deep hatred," said a woman in a nickname he, describing her feelings about Japan. "The story is something that cannot be erased from the heart, what happens in the future."
One man told AFP that he traveled almost 2,000 km since the north of Ningxia with his five -year -old son to watch the movie.
Another boy, with a Chinese flag, made a triumphant pose on a corded bunch of rubble and pieces of glass, while his parents took photographs against the blue summer sky.
The plot of the film revolves around a group of inhabitants of Nanquim, hidden in a photographic studio, which are required to reveal Japanese photographs as "memories" of war crimes.
“Dead to Rights” is one of several summer releases about the war with Japan, which killed millions of Chinese and for which many believe Tokyo never exhibited properly.
The country prepares for a large military parade next week to mark the 80th anniversary of Japan's defeat and the end of World War II.
The poster of "Dead to Rights" says, "No Chinese will ever forget."
"I don't think (films like this) represent hatred. It's because we need to restore the story," said Jiang Xiang, a 37-year-old visitor, adding that consciousness of China's suffering must be transmitted from generation to generation-to teach that "we need to trust ourselves, continue to strengthen."
The death toll in the massacre - the Chinese estimated 300,000 - remains a cause for debate, and some Japanese ultra conservatives have denied that it has occurred despite the overwhelming international evidence.
In the set studio on the set, a book of visits was completely full of patriotic and profane comments. “Japan is the stupid country in the world,” said one of them with child calligraphy.
Almost all the parents AFP found said their children saw the movie, with a mother of Nanjing claiming that the school encouraged them.
China does not have a movie indicative classification system, and it is not uncommon for children to watch content that, elsewhere, can be considered excessively violent.
“Look, that's where the head was hanging (in the movie)!” A child laughed at a friend as they passed a wooden pole.
The goal is to help "children understand the story - not to make them hate or anything."
Li Xinyi primary school student said she found the Japanese "antipathic", but warned against bitterness. "Even if we have done many cruel things, we still need to respect them, because now we should focus on peace."</description><pubDate>2025-09-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>