<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Procession of the Lord of Passos is preparing to receive thousands of faithful</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/procissao-senhor-dos-passos-prepara-se-para-receber-milhares-de-fieis/</link><description>After three months of preparations, he is ready to return to the street one of the greatest religious manifestations of the Catholic community of Macao. The procession of Our Lord Bom Jesus dos Passos takes place on the first weekend of Lent, and this year the two processions will be held on March 8 and 9. The Jornal Tribuna de Macao, Carlos Anok, President of the Brotherhood of Our Lord Bom Jesus dos Passos, said that the legend of a miracle that put the image of return to the Church of St. Augustine led to the realization of the two processions. Father Daniel Ribeiro, who will give the sermon in Portuguese, stressed, in a first message, that this length presents “the meaning of showing that our life is a walk of direction to God”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Registered on the list of intangible cultural heritage, the procession of our Lord Bom Jesus dos Passos has a place annually on the first Saturday and Sunday of Lent and is part of the “Catholic novena and the feast in honor of the Lord Bom Jesus dos Passos”. This year, the manifestation of faith of the Catholic community of the territory will take place on March 8 and 9.
With a long history in Macao, dating back to 1708, being a characteristic and representative religious event of the city, the procession consists of two stages. The first is the trip to the Cathedral, and the second will return to your residence in the Church of St. Augustine.
Asked about the reason for both acts on the same weekend, Carlos Anok, substitute president of the Brotherhood of Our Lord Bom Jesus dos Passos, told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that "there is a legend, with several versions," to justify this fact. “In times gone, the image was placed in the Cathedral, but miraculously always returned to St. Augustine, hence the return to his church is now assured,” says Carlos Anok.
The Sabbath procession then begins in the Church of St. Augustine, descends the sidewalk of the Old Trunk, passes through the loyal Senate atrium and climbs the Roquete Platter towards the Cathedral.
On the morning of that day, the five wound mass will be celebrated, which means the Lord's wounds, in both hands and feet and also the marks of the spear that was spotted on the body. The mass starts at 8 am in Chinese and Portuguese, being celebrated by the Bishop of Macau, D. Stephen Lee.
Later, at 16h00, the Via-Sacra will take place in Chinese and at 5 pm will be the turn of an early mass in Chinese and Portuguese, followed by Via-Sacra in Portuguese. At 6.30 pm the sermon of the garden in Chinese is held and at 7 pm the procession will come out, known as the “candle procession” or “procession of the cross”, which will take just over half a hour.
The next day, Sunday, at 4 pm, the Pretorio sermon is held in Chinese language, followed by 16:30, the second procession, which will have a reverse route to the first but longer.
At the sound of the Public Security Police Band, the image of Senhor dos Passos, transported by the brothers of the Brotherhood, will depart from the Church of the Cathedral and pass the door of the Consulate General of Portugal, before going down to Praia Grande and ending in the Church of St. Augustine.
In the middle, the seven seasons of the Way of the Way will be held, in each of which the chaplain prays for prayer, Veronica chants the responsibility, in Latin, and the faithful respond with a song. After arrival at the Church of St. Augustine, there will be the sermon of Calvary in Portuguese and the blessing of the Holy Cruz.
Preserve origins to reinforce heritage
Carlos Anok underlines that the choice of the person who interprets the figure of Veronica is mainly made according to the voice. The Veronica is dressed in white, also in a veil of the same color in the head and takes the so -called “sacred face”, which is a handkerchief that represents his gesture of when he cleaned the face of the Lord.
These are original characteristics of the procession “which we have to preserve almost totally from the time it started in 2017, the process of entry to Macao's intangible heritage list, published by the Cultural Institute”, stresses the Substitute President of the Brotherhood.
Carlos Anok points out that this image has been the third since the Diocese of Macao was created, about 450 years ago. Currently, only the heads, hands and feet, which are in the Museum of Sacred Art of the Church of St. Dominic.
"It was cut because the Lord was very heavy, hence the chaplain has given order to do so, and this new version is already over 150 years old," explains the brother of the Brotherhood, indicating that the procession is prepared in advance so that all details are fulfilled when the image of the Lord leaves the streets of the territory.
This religious manifestation of great significance has in recent years has counted on the faithful of various stops. “In addition to the local Catholic community, many Hong Kong faithful, inland China and even the Philippines come to participate in the procession,” notes the main responsible for the organization.
 
Penance period invites to reflection
Father Daniel Ribeiro, parish priest of the Diocese of Mand, who also participates in the procession, highlights the importance of the act of faith. "The meaning of the procession is to start Lent, that is, it is the 40 days that Jesus passed in the desert, which is a period of penance, a period of reflection, conversion," he says, adding that "through this procession it is intended to remember every Catholic, every Christian, of the importance of preparing well to celebrate Easter."
The priest recalls that the Hebrew people spent 40 years in the desert to prepare, to convert to entering the Promised Land. “Therefore, we want to live 40 days of conversion, reflection and life change,” he says.
The main message of the Calvary Sermon that the missionary will give points to the meaning of the suffering of our life. "Suffering is not a punishment of God, but to remember that our life here on earth is not our definitive address yet."
"Suffering and difficulties, all of this helps us strengthen, approach God and change our behavior to live what He expects from each of us," expresses the priest, considering in his message that faith, even though it is part of the daily lives of Catholics, needs to be "always renewed."
For this, he argues, "we need to have mercy, have devotion, and to live life always as a novelty," because "God has not created the human being to finish his days here on earth in a cemetery, but to live forever with him."
The procession of the Lord of the Steps “also has this sense of showing that our life is a procession, a walk of direction to God,” he reinforces.
For Father Daniel Ribeiro, adherence to this manifestation of the Christian religion has grown mainly since 2023 and "as part of Macao culture is to grow more and more." Beyond those who purposely move to watch, “there are always many tourists from mainland China and these people always follow the procession with great taste and interest,” he concludes.
The procession of Our Lord Bom Jesus of the Passos was introduced into Macao by the priests of the Order of St. Augustine. When they reached the territory they founded the convent with the same name and the annexed church dedicated to Our Lady of Grace, now known only by the Church of St. Augustine.
Since the procession took place for the first time, that is, shortly after the arrival of the Augustinians in 1586, the cult of the Lord of the Steps has grown very specially among the inhabitants of Macao, and began to constitute the most significant public manifestation of piety and devotion.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Salary freezing may be the option of non -tourism sectors</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/congelamento-salarial-podera-ser-opcao-de-sectores-nao-ligados-ao-turismo/</link><description>Based on the information gathered, the Macao Human Resources Association anticipated that there will be a “significant demand” by both local and non-resident labor in the “sectors directly linked to tourism”, such as the concerts, conventions and exhibitions industry, tourism, game and transport. In addition, the association's president provided for a salary of 2% to 3% in these sectors, while in areas not linked to tourism, salary freezes can be adopted. On the other hand, Choi Chin Man anticipated that game operators “can focus” on the strategy of “hunting rivals talents”
 
The Macao Human Resources Association predicts that there is a “significant demand” for human resources, both places and non -residents, verified this year in the “sectors directly linked to tourism”. At stake are the industries of concerts, conventions and exhibitions, tourism, game and transport, Choi Chin Man, president of the association. The estimate is made based on the information gathered by the association.
Heard by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the associative leader anticipated the possibility of this year a salary increase of 2% to 3% in the above sectors. Under these circumstances, it estimated that the average monthly income in Macao, both local (20,500 patacas in the 4th quarter of 2024) as a global (18,000 patacas), will also register an increase ranging from 2% to 3%.
However, the president of the Human Resources Association noted that some sectors may have a relatively reduced labor demand, such as the financial. This is because, "in addition to having a decrease in profits last year, bank institutions will continue to deal with the expansion of electronic payment, which naturally weaken the demand for human resources," he said.
Regarding the remuneration, Choi Chin Man found that "there is still no intention to raise wages in other sectors [not related to tourism]." "The respective companies have not yet announced the salary freezing, but I believe they also do not intend to lower their remuneration," he noted. In this sense, the Association predicted that most companies operating in community neighborhoods will choose to freeze salaries, including keeping the salary of 60 to 70 patacas for part -time work scheme.
“Such a solution will be adopted in order to maintain the most basic operations. In this context, the revitalization of the community economy would be essential to counteract this scenario, ”he emphasized.
In addition, the associative leader added that sales workers whose compensation is based on commissions may also face salary freezes, which "is due to the phenomena of modification of the tourist structure, especially the weakening of the consumer power of tourists."
On the other hand, Choi Chin Man pointed to the emergence of bankruptcy in residential areas, which led to "many human resources to flow to the tourist areas."
 
“Hunting rivals talents”
Regarding the requirements adopted regarding job candidates, Choi Chin Man noted that, last year, "employers began to give greater importance to the work experience," a situation that "constituted a major challenge for candidates, especially for newcomers."
“Currently, many newcomers have two academic diplomas. However, they focus too much on the gym, but have little work experience. We think that, given the current panorama, college students should participate more in economic activities, which can be internships, part -time work or even voluntary activities, ”he said.
Regarding the remuneration, the president of the Human Resources Association said that, as in 2023 and at the end of 2022, a newly graduate can earn about 13,000 patacas monthly in the early stages of his career. For the associative leader, this value is likely to remain unchanged this year. “Companies do not want to raise compensation for newborns. For example, integrated tourism and leisure companies may give preference to the most experienced candidates, although this means a higher price, ”he continued.
In another aspect of this phenomenon, Choi Chin Man stated that the strategy of “hunting rivals talents” has been most often used in the Macao job market, particularly among tourism and integrated leisure companies. “For example, a game operator may want to 'hunt' experienced workers from other companies, because they have already left the worst scenario and stopped worrying about the issue of salaries… We just got into the year 2025 and consider that these companies could focus on this guidance on hiring,” he predicted.
In addition, Choi Chin Man described that, in general, Macao young people are still "not very interested in Hengqin." “We have found many situations where a Macao company opened a branch in Hengqin and naturally highlighted some local workers there. However, this does not mean the constitution of Macao Human Resources in that area and will only be beneficial to the economy of the short -term deepened cooperation zone, rather than being able to represent a great help to the long -term hengqin economy, ”he said.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Xia Baolong installs vowels at CCPPC to accelerate economic diversification</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/xia-baolong-insta-vogais-na-ccppc-acelerar-diversificacao-economica/</link><description>Hong Kong and Macao's affairs office director Xia Baolong visited Rae vowels at CCPPC, installing them to scrupulously fulfill the functions to accelerate the proper diversification of Macau's economy
 
On the occasion of the “two sessions”, Xia Baolong, director of the Hong Kong and Macau Affairs Office with the Council of State, visited in Beijing the vowels of Raehk and MSAR at the 14th Chinese Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC). According to this cabinet, Xia Baolong hopes that vowels will scrupulously fulfill their functions and responsibilities, actively participate and discuss political affairs, as well as perform, in a better way, the “double positive role”.
The same responsible also urged these vowels to implement full and precisely “a country, two systems”, and to fully support governance, according to the law, the heads of the executive and the governments of the two RAE. In order to accelerate Hong Kong's evolution from stability to prosperity and the proper diversification of Macau's economy, thus making a greater contribution to maintaining RAE's lasting prosperity and stability, the construction of a strong country and the revitalization of the nation.
On the other hand, the 3rd Session of the CCPPC began yesterday in the Chinese capital, being the Chinese President Xi Jinping present at the opening ceremony.
Wang Huning, president of CCPPC, presented the work report of the CCPPC Permanent Committee. Regarding the RAE, the report recalls that, over the last year, the CCPPC Permanent Committee implemented the Hong Kong and Macau vowel visiting system, organized visits with a view to promoting exchange and cooperation between RAE and the interior of China, as well as supporting 75 Briefing sessions on the national situation of RAE, in the form of “entering campus”.
However, 33 CCPPC vowels received the “best performance award”, one of which was Ho Ion Sang.
 
ANP will make thematic inquiries about large bay
On the other hand, the opening ceremony of the 3rd session of the 14th Popular National Assembly (ANP) will take place at the People's Hall this morning, and will take place until March 11.
At ANP's press conference, spokesman Lou Qinjian revealed that the ANP permanent committee will be carried out this year, inquiries of themed research, with the aim of boosting, in building the large bay, a better combination between the base of “one country”, the advantages of “two systems” and the strengths of the three regions.
In addition, Lou Qinjian pointed out that, with full support from the central government to build the Great Bay, the interconnection of infrastructure, rules and mechanisms, and residents of Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macao at the spiritual level has constantly reinforced.
The spokesman also noted that, over five years, the total economic volume of the large bay has increased to over 14 billion Renminbis, while the flow of goods, capital and people between the three regions has become easier, and the “one-hour life cycle” is already a reality. In addition, it pointed out that the opening of the Islands Hospital contributed to increase the offer of medical resources.
In addition, at the ANP preparatory meeting, members of the “Presidium” and secretary general of the 3rd session of the 14th ANP were elected. The "Presidium" integrates, as last year, Kou Hoi In, Lao Ngai Leong and the director of the Central Government's connection office in MSAR, Zheng Xincong. After the meeting, Chui Sai Peng, a spokesman for the Macao delegation, stated that these members can "sufficiently express the voices of Macao."
 
Sam Hou Fai praised in Beijing
In Beijing, Xia Baolong met with the leader of the mashes. According to an official statement, Xia Baolong said that since the inauguration, the team led by Sam Hou Fai "has resolutely implemented the spirit of President Xi Jinping's speech and central government decisions." He also argued that the chief executive "has been bold and done many beneficial innovative works for Macao." The director of the RAE affairs to the State Council said he also believed that the new government will be able to lead all sectors of Macao society to implement and precisely “a country, two systems” and promote the proper diversification of the economy, especially the construction of Hengqin. In turn, Sam Hou Fai pointed out that the government has “widely” the opinions and suggestions of society to elaborate the lines of governing action.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hospital das Ilhas expands medical aesthetic services</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/hospital-das-ilhas-expande-servicos-de-estetica-medica/</link><description>Hospital das Ilhas is gradually introducing more medical care services and, in a short term, will activate the Health Management Center. It will also be promoted to expand the supply of aesthetic medicine projects, with the possibility of surgeries, and vaccination services. Through advantages in the field of state -of -the -art professional technologies, the hospital intends to reinforce the development of medical tourism and the industry of “Big Health”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Several private medical services have been introduced by Hospital das Ilhas since the health unit officially entered operation on 16 September last year. Briefly will be activated the Health Management Center, at a time when the aesthetic medicine service and external vaccine consultations are already available.
On the one hand, regarding medical aesthetic services, the initial focus lies in facial rejuvenation, so they are launched, using the most advanced equipment of Hong Kong and Macau, 16 therapeutic projects, including Picosure Laser (Picosure) and Radiofrequency Microagulhing, according to the director of Health Services (SSM), Alvis Lo Iek Long, in response to An interpellation of Deputy Leong Hong Sai.
On the other hand, in terms of vaccination services, a total of five types of inoculations are made available to users, including the Nanavalent Vaccine against Human Papillomavirus (HPV), the Herpes Zoster vaccine and the pneumococcal vaccine.
For the future, the Islands Hospital aims to expand the supply of aesthetic medicine projects and vaccination services, as well as introducing new types of services, including medical aesthetic surgeries, private wards and distance consultations.
Taking advantage of the advantages brought by the domain of state -of -the -art professional technologies, the willingness of sophisticated equipment and competitive prices within the region, the hospital stresses that it “will further reinforce the development of medical tourism and the Big Health industry”.
In parallel, following the attraction of more tourists who move to Macau with the aim of receiving health care and health care, the direction of tourism services “will be articulated with the launch of relevant offers in the health tourism”.
The objective, observe the SSM, is to promote in conjunction with the tourist sector and the integrated tourism and leisure companies, “the creation of thematic tourist products deeds for medical and health care, well-being and food therapy”.
The SSM director also states that the hospital will also introduce several special accommodation offers, "in order to strengthen the promotion and dissemination of these services in the target markets."
Between March 2024 and January this year, about 6,900 transferred users took advantage of external external consultations and imaging examinations, under the provision of services to residents sent by the SSM, involving 28 specialty services.
Until last January, the average waiting time for the first appointment, sent by the SSM at the Islands Hospital was about 1.7 weeks.
 
The registration of organ donors increased
The number of people registered for organ donation rose 6.6% to 6,380 in 2024, in annual terms, with 4,420 completed formalities (plus 2.8%). On the other hand, according to Health Services (SSM) in response to an interpellation of Deputy Ron Lam, the number of associations that joined the Organ Donation Advertising Charter grew to 30, having performed about 42 activities and promotional lectures. SSM will add an organ donation registration function to the “single account” to further increase the will and convenience of registration of residents.
 
Gastroenteritis cases record significant climb
Cases of rotavirus infection, which causes acute gastroenteritis, have recorded a significant increase in recent days. According to health services, the average number of patients who resorted to consultations at Conde São Januário and Kiang Wu hospitals rose from about 925 a week in January 2025 to 1,271 in mid -February. Norovirus infection was the main disease contracted in January, while there was an increase by rotaviruses in February, with the average cases a week to rise from about two in January to 20 in the middle of the following month.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Poetry dominates Festival Rota das Letras</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/poesia-domina-festival-rota-das-letras/</link><description>20240308lpo and pe session



The strong presence of the poetic component and the performance of the Portuguese Lisbon Poetry Orchestra are some of the main news of the Literary Festival Rota das Letras that starts on the 21st. The event returns to Barra da Barra, in Porto Interior, and presents, over 10 days, two dozen lectures, three exhibitions, a movie cycle and a concert, as well as visits to schools and photography workshops and writing creative

Victor Rebelo
 
The Rota das Letras festival will bring to the territory the Lisbon Poetry Orchestra, which will present the show “The Surrealists”, accompanied by the vocalist of Radio Macau, Xana. The concert is one of the news of this year's event, which will take place between 21 and 30 March.
The orchestra from the Portuguese capital is a multidisciplinary group formed by musicians and poets who invite other artists to celebrate and interpret poetry on a unique trip to the discovery and reinvention of the word said.
In the first part of the concert will act the band Poetry &amp; Music, by Anthony Tao, formerly the organization of the Beijing Literary Festival. The theme of the performance will be “the myth of writing”.
Among the Chinese poets that will be present at Rota das Letras 2025, stands out the name of the young Xu Jinjin, an interdisciplinary artist who divides his time between Shanghai and New York. They join, among other poets: Valério Romão, from Portugal, Zang Di and Jia Wei, from Beijing, Chan Ka Long and Wang Shanshan, from Macau. Poetry recites, presentation of new books, lectures and workshops will take place at the building of the former Municipal Slaughterhouse.
The Society of Arts and Letters and the Prail Editions, co-organizers of the event, celebrate the 100th anniversary of the publication of “Lin-Tchi-Fá, Flor de Lotus”, book of poems by Maria Anna Acciaioli Tamagnini, with the unprecedented release of translations for Chinese and English.
This year's Route of Letters also marks the passage of the 50th anniversary of the Independence of Portuguese -speaking African countries through an exhibition of the photojournalist Alfredo Cunha, who covered these historical events.
The theme of the end of the colonial war and the process of decolonization that followed is also present in the novel of João Ricardo Pedro “Your face will be the last”, which Luís Filipe Rocha adapted to the cinema. The director returns to Macao after, in the late 1980s, here he directed the programming of TDM and filmed “Love and Fores de Fé”, an adaptation of Henrique de Senna Fernandes's namesake novel.
Still around the same theme, António Costa Silva, writer, poet and essayist, and Portuguese Minister of Economy and Sea between 2022 and 2024, makes the presentation in Macao of the novel “Disconsigured Angola”, over a period lived half a century ago, when in the middle of a fratricidal war, the Angolan nation was sought to build.
Non-fiction literature has the English language this year as the main vehicle. British writer Paul French brings his last two works to the Route of Letters. Meanwhile, the books for the youngest will be taken to schools by Chen Shige and André Letria, an illustrator and Portuguese editor who already has several of his works published in Chinese language.
On the eve of the festival's opening, Wang Zhengping, one of the great masters of Chinese photography, inaugurates in the TAP Seac Gallery the exhibition “The Wind blows on the prairie”, a poetic look at the Mongolia in the interior and who inhabits them. Rao Yongxia shows his work days later at the Holy Holy Gallery of the Holy House of Mercy.
Over the course of ten days, Rota das Letras, sponsored by MGM, with the support of the Culture Development Fund, offers a program with two dozen lectures, three exhibitions, a movie cycle and a concert, visits to schools and photography and creative writing workshops.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>GAME WORKERS complain of disqualification without cause</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/trabalhadores-de-jogo-queixam-se-de-despedimentos-sem-justa-causa/</link><description>Some local workers from various departments of a game operator sought help from Deputy Ron Lam, after being dismissed without cause, accusing the government to tacitly approve this practice in the six game dealers, according to Macau News Agency, citing a deputy publication on social networks.
Although Ron Lam did not reveal the name of the game operator concerned, the deputy reported that workers contacted him this week after being notified of the dismissal on February 28. "The employment contracts were immediately terminated without reasonable justification and no reason for termination or alternative employment options were presented," he said.
"Several workers from different departments [of the game operator] were suddenly dismissed without any irregularity [pointed] or explanation," he added. The deputy even said that the workers "also said that, earlier this year, there were already rumors in the sector that the government had" given green light "to the operators of the game to dismiss staff."
According to employees, cited by Ron Lam, five of the six dealers have already begun to dismiss local workers. On the part of the government there was not yet a reaction.
The Jornal Tribuna de Macao contacted the management of services to work matters to find out if it received complaints regarding these cases and how many workers are involved, however, until the closing of this edition did not get an answer.
The latest official data show that about 71,600 people were employed in the game industry in the fourth quarter of 2024. There was an increase of 6.2% annually, but the value is still 15.9% below the pre-pound level when there was 85,100.
"With the economy of Macao still completely recovering, only game operators recovered quickly and returned to profitability, employing more than 27,000 workers not residing in June 2024," said Ron Lam.
"Given this scenario, if the six actively terminate local workers contracts without reasonable justification, it will not only be unacceptable to the community, but it will also open a dangerous precedent," he said.
The deputy urged the government to “take proactive measures to investigate this issue and end this practice”, noting that one of the main obligations of the six operators, under the new contracts, is the safeguarding of labor rights. "The government has to clarify why game operators are being allowed to dismiss local workers without providing any employment alternatives," he added.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Changes” in the consumer model “bring new challenges”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mudancas-modelo-de-consumo-trazem-novos-desafios/</link><description>The Chief Executive listened to several economists and academics, in the context of the elaboration of the government lines
 
The new economic cycle and the “changes” recorded around the consumer model and the class of consumers “bring new challenges”, noted the chief executive a meeting with economics academics within the scope of the Lagas of Governive Action (LAG). Sam Hou Fai stated, according to an official statement, that "the Government of MSAR has to face and properly deal with the problem of unbalanced development of the internal economy."
In this context, he argued, the executive should “promote industrial diversification and help sustainable development of small and medium -sized businesses (SMEs), as well as develop, in the best way, the exploration of hengqin under the cooperation between Guangdong and Macao”. He also said that it is necessary to promote the transformation of high quality of universities scientific research and inject dynamics into the sustainable development of the economy through the deep integration of industry-university-investigation, but also boosting the cultural and tourist economy, improving the business environment of SMEs and creating more employment opportunities for the population.
At the meeting, several economists and academics gave their opinions. Associate professor at the Faculty of Business Management at the University of Macao (one) Siu Chi Sen indicated that Macau can reinforce the development of the local economy and support the technological transformation of SMEs, take advantage of unique tourist resources to increase the benefits of tourism. In addition, he argued that Mand must "prepare well for the uncertainties of the financial market and organize the government budget more reasonably and prudently."
In turn, Lei Chun Kwok, an associate chief of the department of the same college, argued that the government should help SMEs increase business capacity and provide business diagnostic service. Also vice president of the Board of the Macau Economic Association also suggested that investments are captured and committed more efforts to attract technological companies.
Loi Hoi Ngan, Assistant Professor at the Center for Political, Economic and Social Studies at Macao Polytechnic University, said policy elaboration should have the principle to consolidate the foundations and boost innovation, as well as “increase the number of PME acquisitions”. In addition, it should unlock the “data islands”, take advantage of the data to develop precise policies, and continue to deepen the cooperation between Guangdong and Macao, the vice president of the Directorate of the Strategic Research Center for the Development of Macao has linked.
The vice-rector of the University of Science and Technology of Macao and Rector of the Graduate School, Pang Chuan, suggested to the government to invest more in the background for the development of science and technology, and create a mechanism for capturing international qualified pictures.
In turn, the president of the Macao Management Institute and president of the Directorate of the Political Economy Study Association, Samuel Tong, considers that authorities should “create a mechanism for accumulation of human capital, boost the enhancement and comprehensive conversion of traditional industries and accelerate the second phase of the in -depth cooperation zone”.
However, the director of UMA's Continuous Education Center and professor at the Faculty of Business Management, Liu Ting Chi, stressed that the government should “enjoy” the advantages of “one country, two systems” and attract international companies to Hengqin. The also member of the Economic Development Council also suggested that the disapproved land is used “efficiently” while being introduced international capitals in the competitions.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Fire caused burns in three people</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/incendio-provocou-queimaduras-em-tres-pessoas/</link><description>Two children and a maid suffered 3 or 2nd degree burns after a fire that took place the night a day before yesterday in a fraction of the Jardim Cidade building in the Tamagnini Barbosa area. In total, five people were injured. According to IAS, about 30 residents affected by the fire were resting in a center of faom
 
A fire that launched in the Jardim Cidade building in the Tamagnini Barbosa area, caused five injuries, said the Fire Department (CB) - a two -year -old boy and an eight girl suffered a 3rd grade burns at 20% and 25% of the body, respectively, while a 53 -year -old vietnamese maid had 2nd degree burns in 35% of the body. The injured were transported to the hospital, conscious, but to need first aid.
The case happened in a 19th floor fraction of Block 2, the night of the day before yesterday, and reached another fraction on the same floor, where a 66 -year -old woman felt cursed after inhaling thick smoke. On the other hand, a 20 -year -old passenger was injured by an object of the building concerned. Both wounds were transported to the hospital.
In addition, the fire led to 300 residents of 100 aggregates from the building to be prohibited some parts of the Pou Chjon Rua and several bus careers.
According to the CB, the case was caused by oil gas leakage. In the rescue action, 67 firefighters and 19 ambulances were mobilized.
After becoming aware of the fire, the Institute of Social Action (IAS) sent social workers to the site to provide necessary support to affected families.
According to IAS, the Lok Chon Center of the General Union of Residents' Associations is supporting the affected people, while the Community Center of Tamagnini Barbosa of the Federation of Workers Associations (Faom) is open to residents in need of temporary shelter. Yesterday, about 30 affected residents were resting in this center, with employees trying to understand their needs.
In addition, IAS states that the Ilha Verde's wirearm center can also provide temporary reception services and make basic life equipment available to needy.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Healthy Campus” arrives at universities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/campus-saudavel-chega-as-universidades/</link><description>More than 66,000 students and teachers will benefit from integrated measures in the “Healthy Campus” program, which will reach the 10 Higher Education Institutions
 
Health Services (SSM) and the Directorate of Education Services and
Youth Development (DSEDJ), in collaboration with 10 higher education institutions, launched the “Healthy Campus” program, intended for more than 66,000 students and teachers. The program aims to promote the health and well-being of students and teachers, focusing on the implementation of healthy policies, creating health-favorable environments and activities that encourage a healthy lifestyle, within the scope of the “Healthy City Macau 2030” goal.
The director of SSM, Alvis Lo, highlighted the importance of public health for the stability of society and for the development of the country. According to since 2004, the Government of MSAR has been fulfilled the “Healthy Campus” program that reaches approximately 90,000 students from 76 primary and secondary schools. In a statement, it is also said that Alvis Lo mentioned the government's intention to deepen the cooperation between departments, perform various activities and support policies for a healthy lifestyle between teachers and students.
DSEDJ Director Kong Chi Meng, in turn, thanked the contribution of higher education institutions to the implementation of the program that can help achieve better physical and mental quality of students and teachers, stimulate learning and contribute to a healthy campus.
On the other hand, the head of the Health Promotion Division of the SSM Disease Prevention and Control Center, Wong Weng Man, detailed the “Healthy Campus in the various higher education institutions” program that is based on five essential points. First of all, the definition and implementation of appropriate policies for health promotion by higher education institutions and the creation of a healthy environment through the availability of healthy eating options and physical exercise and disease tracking equipment.
The initiative is also based on improving health quality through periodic dissemination of information on healthy behaviors; In the promotion of a healthy school culture, performing activities that encourage students and teachers to take care of each other; And in reinforcing the exchange between higher education institutions, SSM and DSEDJ through a cooperation platform that simultaneously benefits academic and medical communities.
In addition to Alvis Lo, Kong Chi Meng and Wong Weng Man were present more than 200 leaders of a dozen higher education institutions in the territory.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Pollution on the coast is not only resolved with ETAR and “optimization of techniques”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/poluicao-na-costa-nao-se-resolve-apenas-etar-optimizacao-de-tecnicas/</link><description>Last year, DSPA received 14 cases related to bad smell on the coast, mainly caused by the wrong connection of sewage, unit collector extravasation and illegal discharges. The body argues that the problem of pollution in coastal waters is not only solved by the “optimization of techniques” and the construction of new WWTP with greater capacity
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Pollution in coastal waters and bad smells have been serious problems in Macao, but over the last few years, they have been improving, as mentioned in the Macao Environment Report on 2023. The document, however, realized that some indicators of water quality treated in the peninsula's WWTP have exceeded the limit. In the last year, and according to the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA), 14 cases related to odors detected along the coast were received.
"After investigation, the main reasons were the wrong connection of sewers, the extravasation of the unit collector and the illegal discharges, among other situations, which led to wastewater to have been discharged in the coastal waters, through the rainwater collectors, causing bad smells," says the director of the body, IP Kuong Lam, in response to an interplies of it. Reason, continues, "the problem of coastal water pollution is not simply resolved by optimizing treatment techniques or building new treatment stations."
According to IP Kuong Lam, after the problems detected, "DSPA contacted the competent services through the existing mechanism, to coordinate, track and jointly improve problems as soon as possible."
Regarding the modernization project of Coloane's WWTP, he stressed that he will start in the first quarter of this year, “being also developed efforts to conclude, as much as possible”, the works of adjudication of the project of the artificial island in the zone of Ponte do Delta border, in order to launch conception and construction.
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) stressed that it continues to combat the situation of illegal discharges of wastewater. The deputy specifically questioned what is the point of situation of the study on the legislation regarding illegal discharges of wastewater and what were the results of the execution of the law to combat illegal discharges of wastewater in recent years.
In the replica, the body reported only that, in 2024, he performed more than 1,180 inspections to the fat and beverage stores and more than 720 inspections to the form of drainage in the works of works, and respectively, 132 and 37 news records.
Noting that Macau's public drainage network is more than 527 kilometers long, with about 75% of sewage to have the sectional separation of wastewater separation, DSPA indicates that the main reason for the existence of unit collectors in the old neighborhoods is “to the narrowing of the available underground space and the problems that any traffic deviations and road traffic lights are reason for works can cause ”. This happens, for example in the San Kio neighborhood and Rua da Manduco Praia.
"AMI will continue to analyze community development and coordinate with public works services to perform sewage reordering works in order to gradually improve the public sewage system system," reads.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Gastronomy, arts and tours drive community economy</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/gastronomia-artes-passeios-impulsionam-economia-comunitaria/</link><description>Experiences centered on gastronomy and arts, as well as visits to museums and coloane tours, will fill this month the program of STD -subsidized activities with Macao Associations. The objective of diversified initiatives is to explore culture and boost the economy of community zones
 
Through its Financial Support Program, the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) continues to encourage Macao associations to carry out diversified activities or tourist projects, with a view to boosting the community economy. For this month several initiatives are also prepared.
Every Saturday, from March 1st and until April 19, Chef Michelin, Justin Paul, will conduct visits to buy ingredients in local markets and cook with participants typical Macao. During the tour, participants will be able to taste the traditional red bean cake and enjoy herbs tea in a centenary store, as well as “feel the characteristic environment and the intangible cultural heritage of Macao”, according to a STD statement.
On the other hand, between March 7 and 30, from Friday to Sunday, from 17h00 to 21h00, the Bazaar Pagoda Largo will become an arts market, with cultural and creative stands for the sale of handcrafted products, free swolk of pastel candles, large flower devices to take photographs and intermittent animation shows.
The “historical and nostalgic walk in coloane tours will take place on Saturdays and Sundays between 8 and 16 of this month. One of the activities, oriented in Cantonese, Mandarin and English, is a guided tour with tea meeting and documentary display on Lai Chi Vun's shipbuilding culture.
The Event Program also includes the making and design of the NATA and Sanbayaki Pastel Packaging, held in cooperation with Fong Seng Law Lai Memories and Hamo Yaki. The “Happy Macao Tour 7” will take place between the 9th and 22nd.
Antonieta Mannhão (granddaughter), award -winning chef, will lead every Saturday and Sundays between March 22 and April 20 an exploration for the essence of macanese cuisine. The cook will teach the secrets of making authentic dishes, at the same time will share stories about their people, to give residents and visitors the uniqueness of the history of crossing gastronomic cultures.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Art Museum inaugurates “Above Zobeida”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/museu-de-arte-inaugura-acima-de-zobeida/</link><description>The show “Above Zobeida”, presented by Wong Weng Cheong and Chang Chan at the 60th International Art Exhibition of the Venice Biennial, will be available to the public from Friday at the Museum of Art. The Cultural Institute explains that visitors will be part of the exhibition, which addresses topics such as spatial alienation and foreign identity

The Macao Art Museum will open on Friday the exhibition “Above Zobeida”. Artist Wong Weng Cheong and curator Chang Chan presented the artistic project at the 60th International Art Exhibition of the Venice Biennial-it was the ninth time Macau participated in the international show. Cheong and Chan will display the same work, in full, to the public of the territory, providing “a unique opportunity to experience contemporary art”, says the Cultural Institute (IC).
The exhibition addresses topics such as contemporary artistic practice and the anxieties of the new generation of Macao artists, through regional narratives as well as global themes, representing a reflection of local society and dynamics. The ideas of spatial alienation and foreign identity are also explored and are in line with the one that was the central theme of the Venice Biennial during last year: "foreigners everywhere."
Wong Weng Cheong resorts to digital images and immersive artistic techniques for recreating a post-apocalyptic world imagined by Zobeida, a fictional character from Italo Calvino's Italian romance “As Invisible Cities”. According to the IC, the public becomes an integral part of the Dystopian scenario recreated by Cheong, where security cameras watches every corner of a deserted city inhabited by mutant beings and the boundaries between reality and fiction are lavished, creating an engaging atmosphere that causes reflection.
In Macau's latest participation in the International Art Exhibition of the Venice Biennial, Wong Weng Cheong and Chang Chan was able to attract about 77,000 visitors, according to the body led by Leong Wai Man.
Interested parties will be able to visit the city of Zobeida from 6.30 pm on Friday, being free admission. The Museum of Art is open between 10 am and 19h00, from Tuesday to Sunday and holidays, "providing a unique experience for visitors seeking immersion in the most diverse forms of contemporary art."</description><pubDate>2025-03-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>LAW IAT PO shows Porcelain at the Rui Cunha Foundation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lei-iat-po-mostra-porcelanas-na-fundacao-rui-cunha/</link><description>A porcelain exhibition from Macao and Canton, called “Return to Navigation”, was inaugurated yesterday in the Rui Cunha Foundation gallery. The show of artist Lei Iat PO, presents a set of about 40 colorful pieces from the Cantão region.
Porcelain is a traditional industry originating from the Qing dynasty and developed mainly for export, which has gained popularity between European courts and western aristocracy, promoting Chinese culture abroad from the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.
According to the text of the exhibition, the Porcelain of Canton -also known as Guangcai -is famous for the strong and vibrant colors, the complex and intricate patterns, and the gold -painted golden and richly decorated applications.
“Being a typical southern China industry, it also gained vitality in Hong Kong and Macau in the past twentieth century, namely from the 1930s invasions and the political instability of the continent,” says the introductory document, adding that “many factories moved to the two autonomous territories and production shot here in the 1950s, with the international demand of these oriental exoticism in the recovery of the recovery postwar ”.
Canton's porcelain has been a successful example of a fusion between the east and the West over the centuries, contributing to the advantageous cultural exchange. In Macao, at the height of the 1960s, there were dozens of factories, but two decades later the production returned to the continent, much more competitive in labor and costs, in the aftermath of the cultural revolution.
Law Iat PO was born in Macao in 1954. His interest in the art of color porcelain is due to the family business, influenced since his father's childhood, who produced and exported pieces to European and American markets. The artist worked at his father's Guangcai wooden bases and, later, at the Guangcai Colorful Porcelain factory. Under the parent's guidance, he followed the famous Master Zhao Zhuo to learn burn control technology in the oven. Later, I would learn about artisanal painting techniques and porcelain color.
Curated by Margareth Lei Siu Heng, the collection presents invaluable pieces of value, for the quality and degree of complexity in execution, revealing the years of improvement and dedication to this centenary technique by the artist, who intends to continue to disseminate his art and preserve the important historical past.
The works will be exhibited until March 14.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-03-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>First auction at Christie's of works created with Ia Roils artists</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/primeiro-leilao-na-christies-de-obras-criadas-ia-enfurece-artistas/</link><description>Casa Christie’s launched an auction dedicated to artificial intelligence (AI) artificial works of art, surfing the wave of the revolution of this technology, an initiative that enraged some artists. Baptized with increased intelligence, the auction has about 20 pieces and takes place online until Wednesday.

Like its competitor Sotheby’s, Chriie’s has already offered AI works, but had never dedicated a whole auction to this technology.
"AI has become more prolific in everyone's daily life," said House's Digital Art Director Nicole Giles. "More people understand the process and the technology behind AI, so they are better able to appreciate the AI ​​also in creative fields," he argued.
The use of algorithms in the art world is almost as old as modern computing itself. Christie’s offers a work by American artist Charles Csuri (1922-2022) dating from 1966. Pioneer of computational art, he stood out for using software to distort one of his hand-drawn sketches.
"All artists in the field of Fine Arts, in particular those who participated in this auction, use AI to complement their practices," explained Nicole Giles. The collection includes paintings, sculptures, photographs and giant screens that show totally digital works.
The sale was not well-made by all. An online petition requesting its cancellation gathered more than 6,300 signatures.
Many of the works presented "were created using AI models that were known to have been trained with copyright -protected works," says the petition, according to which the auction contributes to "the mass theft of the work of human artists."
In 2023, several artists filed legal actions against new Generative AI companies, including Midjourney and Stability AI platforms, which accuse the violating intellectual property laws.
The “heavy weight” of Digital Refik Anadol, which participates in the event with an animated creation, claimed on social network X that “most project artists are specifically promoting and using their own data sets plus their own models”.
Illustrator Reid Southern, who signed the petition, said that at least, parts that do not use the artist's own software or data, which perhaps, may perhaps a third of sales, he said.
“I am not a lawyer specializing in copyright, so I cannot comment on legality in particular, but the idea that artists used previous artists as an influence on their current work is not new. Each new artistic movement generates controversy and criticism, ”said Nicole Giles.
"There is so much information available [out there] that you cannot infringe individual copyright," said Turkish artist Sarp Yavuz, who participates in the auction. Reid Southern reacted: “Basically, it means arguing that it is wrong to steal one or two people, but no problem stealing millions of people. Right? ”He stressed.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-03-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>