<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Fall to nine candidacies for direct suffrage in AL</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/caem-para-nove-candidaturas-para-sufragio-directo-na-al/</link><description>The number of lists candidates for direct suffrage for the Legislative Assembly not only fell from 2021, the year five lists were disqualified, but the lowest ever since the creation of the MSAR. According to the Electoral Affairs Committee, nine requests were received for the constitution of a direct election committee - seven of which currently have representation in the Hemiciclo - and six for indirect suffrage. The State Security Defense Commission will now determine if the candidates “defend the basic law and are faithful to the MSAR”, and the decision is disclosed to the late 15 July. On September 14, 333,391 people may exercise the right to vote. Academics told this newspaper that the scenario could result from the “background censorship” verified in the last electoral act, as well as the “feeling of impotence of citizens”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Applications for elections for the Legislative Assembly (AL), scheduled for September 14, fell to less than half compared to those submitted in 2021. On Friday, the time he ended the deadline for the request for recognition of the Candidacy Committee, the Al (Caeal) Commission of Electoral Affairs (Caeal) revealed that he received a total of 15 orders-nine for direct suffrage and six for the suffrage.
Four years ago, the body had received 19 application for direct suffrage; These requests that were then reduced to 14, with the disqualification of five lists and 21 candidates (15 of which pro-democracy), by, according to the authorities, “not defending the basic law” and “not being faithful to the masters”.
This number of candidacies for direct suffrage not only decreased by 2021, but also the lowest since it is registered. According to CAEAL data consulted by the Jornal Tribuna de Macau, between 2001 and 2021, the candidate lists have always been close to two dozen or above that. For example, in 2017 there was the largest number of applications to AL, totaling 25, while in 2001 there were 15-this counting only the lists for direct suffrage.
Speaking to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, academic Leon Ieong recalled that Caeal's decision "implied background censorship in 2021", so "all candidates must take this factor in account before they decide to run for elections."
Asked if he anticipates that in the future there may be even fewer candidacies, the professor at the University of Macao Faculty of Social Sciences said that "it is likely," adding: "This would not change the standard of distribution of places, would only make public opinion less diverse."
Leon Ieong argued that "it can currently be considered that the Legislative Assembly is closer to the National Popular Assembly in Continental China."
Also in statements to this newspaper, an academic, who asked not to be identified, considered that "reducing the number of candidates groups reflects that the public is very aware that organizations that do not have visibility and resources are simply unable to compete with traditional, pro-government organizations." “This may also be the feeling of impotence of the citizens of Macau. Knowing that these organizations will be elected, what is the meaning of participating in the elections?” He asked.
The same academic said it also believed that this year the voting rate "could reach a new minimum." "Young people, in particular, have no motivation to participate," he said. In 2021, the influx rate to the direct suffrage, reached 42.38%, representing the lower percentage since the establishment of the MSAR. That year, 137,279 people voted in a universe of 323,907.
As this newspaper reported in January, at the end of 2024 9,759 new singular voters, well below the 2016 (-61%) and 2020 (-39%) records, which preceded equally years of legislatures were counted. For former deputy Agnes Lam, the decrease may be associated with demographic factors, but also with the disqualification of deputies in 2021.
"The phenomenon of the disqualification of political candidates in Macao probably played a role in reducing the vigor of electoral competition. When potential voters realize that the range of candidates does not fully represent their political opinions, particularly those of opposition, this can lead to shutdown," he said. In general, Macau has 333,391 people qualified to vote.
Caeal explained that the “verification process to follow the eligibility of the candidates now begins, and if the information presented is according to the regulations”. It is incumbent upon the MSar State Security Defense Commission to determine whether the candidates "defend the basic law and are faithful to MSAR", in which they are the first elections under the new electoral law, "which aims at a greater implementation of the" Macao Macau ruled by patriots "principle.
The commission will give Caeal an opinion, and from the decision that a candidate “does not have the ability to be a candidate (…) there is no complaint or litigation”. The decision will be announced, until late, until July 15.
 
Seven lists remain in the hemiciclo race
Of the nine candidates for direct suffrage, seven are linked to deputies with a seat in Hemiciclo. From the outset, the list “Macao Citizens Association” linked to the Fujian community, which in the last elections won three seats (Si Ka Lon, Song Pek Kei and Nick Law); as well as the “Union for Development”, of the Federation of Workers' Associations (Ella Law and Leong Sun Iok).
Also the “New Hope”, linked to the Association of Public Function Workers and which currently has deputies José Pereira Coutinho and Che Sai Wang, continues in the race. In the presentation of the application for candidacy, Coutinho said he is confident that he will not be disqualified: "The fact that being critical does not mean that I am not a patriot, I am also a patriot." Despite not having revealed the composition of the list, he guaranteed the presence of Rita Santos, who requested in October the suspension of the mandate of advisor to the Portuguese communities.
The “Macau-Guangdong Union”, linked to the province of Jiangmen (Zheng Anting and Lo Choi In), has also reappointed, like the “Promoting Union for Progress” list, which elected Leong Hong Sai and Ngan Iek Hang in 2021, which is linked to the general union of residents' associations.
The “Good Home Alliance”, linked to the Women's Association, which has reached two places for four years (Wong Kit Cheng and Ma Io Fong), advances again for direct suffrage. And the same is true of the “Synergy Power” list of the Synergy Association, whose only elected deputy was Ron Lam.
However, it is not yet known if the current deputies will remain in the race, or what are the priorities of each of the lists. Both the composition of the lists and the political program must be presented until the 26th of this month.
There are also two new lists: “Mutual Help Grassroots”, which should have as a head-cloak Wong Wai Man, who is running for the second time; And the list linked to the Citizens and Economy Life Promotion Association, which competes for the first time, and has as number one Tim Wong, linked to the Myanmar community.
A total of 33 deputies are part of AL, 14 of which are elected by direct suffrage, 12 by indirect suffrage, through associations, and seven appointed later by the Chief Executive.
In the case of indirect suffrage, Caeal received six application, more than in 2021, for the five sectors: industrial, commercial and financial; workers; Liberal professionals; social and educational services; and cultural and sports.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Formulas 4 and Regional are part of the Grand Prix Program</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/formulas-4-regional-integram-programa-grande-premio/</link><description>Less than six months from another edition of the Macao Grand Prix, the organization has confirmed seven races on the program. The main novelty is Formula 4, which will thus join the other monoloar test, the regional formula. FIA President Mohammed Ben Suulayem was yesterday in the territory to inaugurate the exhibition of another car at the Grand Prix Museum, the winner of the last year's regional formula, the American Ugo Ugochwu

Victor Rebelo
 
The Macao Great Prize (GPM) 2025 program is defined, consisting of seven races, the same number as the previous edition. However, there is a change in relation to the categories that will evolve in the guide circuit, returning to Formula 4 (F4), now with the name Cup of the International Automobile Federation (FIA), to the detriment of one of the support races, RoadSport - Establishment Cup of MSAR.
The presence of young F4 riders thus raises to two monoloar competitions, always pleasing the spectators, joining the Regional Formula (FR) test, also supervised by the FIA.
The F4 World Cup returns to the guide asphalt, certainly bringing the best pilots from various continents, as well as you can open some vacancies to representatives of the territory. It is recalled that in 2023 Macao took Charles Leong to second place, behind British Arvid Lindald, in a year when another house pilot, Tiago Rodrigues, ended in sixth.
At this time there are 13 national F4 championships, where all competitors will have to use Mygale M21-F4 singlesuar, recently renamed Ligier JS F422. This will be the fourth time the category will run in the MSAR, after 2020 to 2023.
Already the FR comes to the territory for the second consecutive year. The triumph in 2024 was reached by Ugo Ugochukwu, from the United States, ahead of the German damage Oliver Goethe and the Mexican Noel Léon. The driver of Macau Tiago Rodrigues was 33rd in the qualification race and did not qualify in the main race.
In short, this year's program will have four FIA World Cups, as in addition to the monologes, the GT and TCR World Tour (Guide Race) Cup are included.
Moreover, the GPM, which will take place from 13 to 16 November, will feature, in terms of car racing, with the usual fight between Macao and Hong Kong riders in Roadsport Challenge. The Big Motorcycle Award also integrates the program of the 72nd edition of the event.
The news was announced yesterday afternoon, at a press conference held at the Grand Prix Museum, by the President of the Institute of Sport (ID), which is also the coordinator of the organizing committee.
By his side the president of the FIA, Mohammed Ben Suulaym, Luís Gomes said that the event “has been taking place with innovations and incorporating new elements in the events, being confident that this year the races“ can attract the attention of fans from around the world ”, adding that“ the success of the GPM depends a lot on the confidence and long time support for the sectors and support for the sectors of the sectors and support. society".
The ID official also said that "in this edition we continue to cooperate with the FIA ​​in the organization of world class events, in order to continue to show on the international sports stage the high position of the event."
Luís Gomes stressed that the GPM annually attracts “huge visitors from the abroad of Macao and the interior of China, taking advantage of the promotion of economics and tourism and stimulating the development of markets such as hotels, transport, restoration and retail”. Therefore, it reinforced the event "not only contributes to itself, but also benefits society and the economy."
Thus, the government will “oppose” the organization of the event continuously, by increasing the quality of the evidence, the reinforcement of the promotions carried out in the neighboring regions and the organization of various related activities, “in order to increase the effect of the brightness of the great award”.
Meanwhile, the FIA ​​president defended the coming to Macau of the FR World Cup and praised the history of the competition.
Mohammed Ben Suulayem then watched the inauguration of a new car that will be evident to the public at the Grand Prix Museum. This is the monoligue of the 2024 FR winner, the American Ugo Ugochukwu.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Guinea-Bissau wants to attract Macau's investment</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/guine-bissau-quer-atrair-investimento-de-macau/</link><description>The president of Guinea-Bissau moved to Macao on an official visit and met with the chief executive. During the meeting, Sam Hou Fai and Umro Sissoco Embaló exchanged impressions on how to better enjoy the role of Macao as a sino-illusophone platform, and boost bilateral economic and commercial cooperation. Attracting investment to the African country was another goal assumed by Embaló
 
Victor Rebelo
 
In a meeting of about an hour, the head of the Executive of the MSAR and the president of Guinea-Bissau gathered at the Government headquarters, in the one that was the first point of the agenda of Umaro Sissoco Embaló in the short visit to the territory. Among other topics, dialogue focused on bilateral economic and commercial cooperation and the better use of the role of Macao as a sino-illusophone platform.
Sam Hou Fai stressed that China and Guinea-Bissau maintain a good relationship and highlighted the establishment of the strategic partnership last year, noting that the Macao Forum Ministerial Conference, held in 2024, contributed to a broader and higher and high level cooperation perspective between China and all Portuguese-speaking countries (PLP).
According to an official statement, the chief executive assured that the MSar will continue to “perform its advantages” of “a center, a platform and a base”, providing help to Guinea-Bissau “in full use” of the commercial cooperation platform between China and PLP, promoting and supporting companies on both sides to reinforce mutual investment and cooperation. This in the sense of "helping Guinea-Bissau transforms its potential to the level of resources into a development engine."
In addition, he argued that Macau and Guinea-Bissau can deepen exchange and cooperation in the domains of health, education and youth.
Later, Umro Embaló held a meeting with guardians from the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment, Associations and Entrepreneurs, during which he said that Guinea-Bissau offers many advantages. "Our currency is open and we have parity with the euro, which is very important and facilitates commercial transactions," said the Chief of Staff of the African country, in statements that were reproduced by Radio Macau.
Umro Embaló, who was accompanied by the other members of the entourage, including the Minister of Economy, Plan and Regional Integration, Soares Sambú, and the Secretary of State for International Cooperation, Fatumata Jau, appealed to entrepreneurs to bet on Guinea-Bissau. "We will create conditions to facilitate your business," he said, adding that his country "may be the gateway to Macao investors on the African continent, particularly in the economic community of West African states that have over 300 million inhabitants."
In this meeting were also present, among others, the commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Popular Republic of China at MSAR, Liu Xianfa, and the secretary for Macao Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP.
On Friday night, Umro Embaló received about three dozen elements of the Guinesse community, mostly students. In his speech, the head of state encouraged students in Macao to dedicate themselves solely to studies, leaving aside politics.
On the other hand, it emphasized that Guinea-Bissau will bet on scholarships in areas where the country needs the most, such as agronomy and some technologies.
According to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the president of the Association of Naturals and Friends of Guinea-Bissau, Graziela Lopes, the students reported some problems they face in the MSAR, such as integration issues and the value of the scholarship, while other elements of the community spoke of the difficulty in bringing Macao artisans and cooks.
The president of Guinea-Bissau ended a visit to the territory at noon on Friday, having proceeded to Hong Kong, where he was a few hours before traveling to Washington. Today, Umaro Sissoco Umaló should be received by US President Donald Trump.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Malparado in the board registers second consecutive descent</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/malparado-na-banca-regista-segunda-descida-consecutiva/</link><description>Contrary to a long trend in the rise, Macao's badly raised credit came down in April for the second consecutive month, although it remains at a high level, above 55 billion patacas. The expired credit ratio retreated to 5.4%
 
At the end of April, loans with more than 90 days late in Macao banks totaled about 55.78 billion Patacas, which represents a drop of 0.6% or 314.6 million compared to the previous month, according to data published by the Monetary Authority (AMCM). After reaching 57.62 billion in February -the highest value since AMCM began compiling this data in 1990 -the “non -productive” or overdue credit (NPL, in the English acronym) thus recorded the second consecutive decrease as it had already dropped 2.7% in March.
On the other hand, the badly raised credit increased by 21.2% or 9.77 billion compared to the end of April 2024. Since the end of 2019, when it has been encrypted by 2.77 billion, the NPL has grown 20 times.
In April this year, the expired credit accounted for 5.4% of local banks loans, less percentage points than in the previous month, and 1.1 points more than in the same period of 2024. The global delayed amount includes 33.93 billion not resident clients (60.8% of the total) and 21.85 billion residents, translating into racings of 6.3% and 4.3%, respectively.
Official data also show that internal loans to the private sector reached 505.3 billion patacas in April, noting decreases of 1.2% and 5.1% in monthly and annual terms, respectively. Foreign credit (535.80 billion) grew 4.5% in a month, but decreased by 2.5% compared to April 2024.
In general, the credit granted to the private sector increased by 1.7% to 1,041.1 billion patacas between March and April. Hong Kong dollar loans maintained a dominant weight (42.2%), followed by pataca (21.4%), US dollar (21.2%) and Renminbi (12.1%).
Already the deposits of the public sector in local banks totaled 209.59 billion, illustrating a monthly descent of 0.8% and an annual increase of 4.3%. Resident deposits (784.12 billion) decreased 0.6% in a month, but advanced 8.1% in the annual range, while non-residents (349.66 billion) dropped 2.9% and rose 6.8% on the same comparative bases.
As a result, bank activity deposits fell 1.2%to 1,343.3 billion compared to March this year.
 
Bank sector profit rose 44% until April
Macao banks exploration results increased 44.2% to 3.71 billion levels at the end of April, compared to the 2024 homologous period, according to data from the monetary authority, which point to a 25.3% increase in bank service and operations (3.37 billion) and an increase of 329.8% in the income of financial investments (558.3 ​​million). On the other hand, banks suffered a 1.7% break in interest margin (4.97 billion). It is recalled that banks closed 2024 with operational profits of 4.01 billion, which reflected an annual decrease of 21.3% and was the lowest since 2010. The 2024 profits marked the fourth consecutive descent after 12 years, including 10 successive records, starting in 2011.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Seminar left clues about mental health of young people</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/seminario-deixou-pistas-sobre-saude-mental-dos-jovens/</link><description>The challenges and strategies to face the mental health of young people in the context of the internet were approached in a seminar on the mental and psychological health of children and adolescents. In its intervention, the Deputy Director of Health Services said it is “essential to reinforce communication”
 
Experts and academics, in a total of 180, participated in a seminar on mental and psychological health of children and adolescents, which took place at the Center of Health of the Areia Preta. Through dialogues and interdisciplinary sharing, the debates provided multidimensional ideas and strategies of response to the protection of the mental and psychological health of children and adolescents in the age of the internet.
In the opening speech, Kuok Cheong U, Deputy Director of Health Services (SSM), said that the government attributes great importance to the problems and challenges that children and young people face in the scope of mental and psychological health. "Given the rapid change in the social environment, it is understood that, in addition to being concerned with the physical health of children and adolescents, it is essential to reinforce communication, to follow more children and young people, guiding them to create good emotional management since childhood," he said, according to a note from SSM.
The lectures promoted by the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center (CHCSJ), with the collaboration of Macao Pediatric Society, included several thematic sessions, covering areas such as Clinical Medicine, Psychological Intervention and Social Phenomena, analyzed from different perspectives.
The head of the ChCSJ Pediatric Service mentioned that current adolescents - the first generation of digital natives - "have behaviors and difficulties whose analysis through traditional development theories prove insufficient, creating challenges in the elaboration of adequate intervention strategies." Exemplifying, Wong Fong stressed that "when doctors, in external consultations, stress that children have to do 60 minutes of physical exercise a day, many of them are immersed on electronic devices, such as short or mobile videos, clinging to the screens until high hours, although they are advised to guarantee nine hours of sleep per night."
The same responsible said that, in the internet age, "the pressure of peers goes from the physical field to social networking groups," cyberbullying "gets worse with the anonymization mechanism, even emotional expression becomes a competition for" likes "." These phenomena, they emphasize, reflect "the characteristics of the mental and psychological changes of young people today, as well as the unique challenges of the time they are in."
Cheang Sut Ieng, Wong Wai Kei and Pang Weng SI, SSM psychotherapists, discussed topics such as “Children's Psychological Health series: Alert Signal Identification-Causes Analysis-Intervention Techniques” and combined clinical cases of Macau with Statistical Data on Emotional Welfare of Hong Kong and Macau students, to detail the early signs of problems. psychological in children.
The experts and academics of the two RAE also discussed “healthy lifestyle”, “family influence”, “role of school and community”, “labeling effect”, among others, considering that the growth of children and young people is a “highly complex development process that involves various physical, psychological and social factors”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Border passages have already exceeded 100 million</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/passagens-fronteiricas-ja-superaram-100-milhoes/</link><description>The number of border passages spent 100 million 18 days earlier than last year, ”said the Public Security Police Corps, which continues to“ continually innovate the border passing model through 'technological training' ”and to reinforce collaboration with the interior authorities of China and Hong Kong
 
This year, the number of entries and exits of people at the various border stations of Macao “remains at a high level”, having repeatedly beaten new records of the volume of tickets, noted the Public Security Police (CPSP). Until 2 pm on June 7, the total number of this year's entries and exits exceeded 100 million, "which occurred 18 days earlier than last year."
In this sense, it was beaten once again a shorter record time to reach 100 million border passages, with a daily average of 0.6 million inputs and exits of macao, representing an increase of 10.8% over the same period last year, indicated that it was possible under the impetus of policies “one entry per week”, “a visa of multiple inputs” and “circulation of macao vehicles in the province of the province in the province Guangdong ”.
According to the data available, 33.9 million were visitors (33.9%of the total), 36.2 million residents of Macau (36.2%) and 25.9 million non -resident workers (25.9%). Already the students accounted for 3.6% of the total, with 3.6 million, and “others”, unidentified, occupied 0.3% of the total (0.3 million).
Most (92.8%) went through the terrestrial border stations, with the doors of the siege occupied it more than half of the total, having passed there, 52.7 million. According to CPSP, the passenger/ticket volume at the Cerco doors border post exceeded 50 million on May 30.
Already the border posts of Hengqin and the Delta Bridge reached the annual flow of 10 million tickets on May 7 and 9, respectively, "earlier than the previous year."
"Given the growing border -passing needs and the opportunities of integrated regional development, CPSP will follow the executive's chief executive's philosophy of governance to" work with an entrepreneurial spirit and move together, persist on the right track and bet on innovation, "the corporation said, saying that it will reinforce collaboration with the competent services of Macau, the interior of China and Hong Kong.
In addition, he promised to “continually innovate the border passage model through 'technological training' and persist in the spirit of 'based on the population' to improve the border passage experience, all in order to promote the exchange of people, contributing to the integrated development of Macao, Hong Kong and other cities of the great bay”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Social Store and Galaxy delivered Kabcks to 372 families</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/loja-social-galaxy-entregaram-cabazes-372-familias/</link><description>With the sponsorship of Galaxy Entertainment, the Santa Casa Social Store distributed Cabazes with first -need goods to more than 370 needy families
 
The Santa Casa da Misericórdia Social Store of Macao (SCMM) held on Saturday its monthly distribution activity of cabazes with primary needs to a total of 372 low -income household aggregates. The initiative was supported by Galaxy Entertainment Group (GEG), which donated 300,000 patacas to regular social store operations in June.
The donation's officialization ceremony was attended by Philip Cheng, administrator of GEG, who handed the check to the SCMM provider António José de Freitas. Also present were Ricardo das Neves, president of the SCMM Fiscal Council, Ho Ion Sang, vice president of the General Union of Residents Associations (Ugamm), and Leong IOK VA, consultant of the General Union of Residents Associations (Ugamm). About 40 game operator volunteers, including several children, helped distribute the kitchen.
During the ceremony, António José de Freitas thanked Galaxy for the continuous support over 13 years, noting that the group "never stopped worrying about the needy, even while expanding their business." In turn, Philip Cheng reiterated that GEG follows the principle of “returning to society what it receives”, encouraging employees to participate in social actions with their children, in order to convey “the spirit of solidarity through example”.
In addition to material support, the game operator has promoted initiatives such as the visit of 20 users of the Santa Casa Blind Rehabilitation Center to the exhibition “Pictoric Universe” in the “Galaxy Art” gallery, with audio description and tactile experiences to make art accessible to the center's invisuals. On the other hand, it also regularly invites the elderly and needy groups for cultural events and shows.
GEG reiterated its commitment to continue to support social causes in a proactive way. According to SCMM, the social store project reinforces the collaboration between the business sector and social solidarity institutions in relieving the difficulties of Macao's most vulnerable families.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Boss expects young people to follow “The Rhythm of the New Age”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-espera-os-jovens-sigam-o-ritmo-da-nova-era/</link><description>More than 6,300 undergraduate students from the University of Science and Technology received undergraduate diplomas. At the ceremony, the chief executive emphasized the need for Macau to continue to promote prosperity through education and aiming at the formation of talents
 
The University of Science and Technology (UCTM) has attributed the degree of degree course to 6,300 students at a ceremony in which the Chief Executive was present. In his speech, Sam Hou Fai said that the government will continue to strategically develop the implementation of “promoting the prosperity of Macao through education” and “building macao through talent formation”, as well as “coordinatingly boosting the integrated development of education, science and technology and qualified frames”.
On the other hand, he guaranteed the promotion of the city's orderly (university) construction of the city of Macao and Hengqin, as well as accelerating the creation of macao of high -level qualified staff, to “equip 'fleets' and provide a strong base to constantly open new horizons” of “one country, two systems”.
In collaboration with all sectors of society, Macau will “provide more opportunities, a larger stage and a more favorable environment for students and the young generation develop their talents, work, create their own businesses and realize their aspirations”.
Considering that students are the group “most energetic, entrepreneurial and fighter for their dreams, bearers of the hope of the nation and the future of the homeland,” Sam Hou Fai said all students “follow the pace of the new age, will have inspirations and grandiose dreams, assume responsibilities and take action with courage, reinforce solidarity and cooperation, perform their own personal development”.
Keeping focus directed to students who had just received their degree diplomas, the Chief Executive spoke of the “new circumstances and new requirements”, noting that “in the course of the integration of Macao at the conjuncture of national development and the exploitation of internal and external bonds, you have affections with Macau, have skills, knowledge and advantages to apply what they have learned and give full use to yours talents'.
This, he said, "will help deepen the exchanges and cooperation between Macao and the interior of China and contribute to the high quality development of the large-basket and to the high quality construction of 'a track, a route'."
Sam Hou Fai praised UCTM, stating that the university has been focused on “increasing the number and quality of its students, developing investigations with characteristics and special advantages, and has achieved remarkable results in cultivating qualified staff, academic investigation, building macao and providing services to the country”.
Diplomas delivered to students included graduation from the first UCTM Medical and Surgery course. The Higher Education Establishment, classified among the 300 best in the Times ranking, celebrates this year the 25th anniversary.
Prior to the undergraduate ceremony, Sam Hou Fai visited the State Reference Laboratory for Lunar and Planetary Science, the Macao Satellite Science and Application Center and the State Reference Laboratory for Quality Research in Chinese Medicine at UCTM.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lecture addresses Nepal's “neglected” architecture</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/palestra-aborda-arquitectura-negligenciada-nepal/</link><description>Architect Jharna Joshi will talk about the challenges of documentation of modernist buildings in Nepal, at 6.30 pm on the 16th. The lecture aims to promote dialogue and value a “neglected” era of Nepalese architecture
 
At the invitation of the Docomomo Research Center, teacher and architect Jharna Joshi will participate in the lecture “Modern Encounters in Architecture: Documentation Challenges for Modernist Buildings in Nepal”, moderated by architect João Nuno Marques. The event will take place at the Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC), on June 16, at 18:30. In the lecture will be presented the initial conclusions of a recent initiative of the Kathmandu Institute to document modern buildings, built between 1945 and 1985, in order to promote the dialogue and the valorization of a “neglected” era of Nepalesa architecture.
Jharna Joshi has over 20 years of experience in architecture, conservation, cultural landscapes, tourism and teaching, having worked at Nepal, mainland China, Hong Kong, US, Vietnam, Greece and New Zealand. According to Docomomo, he led restoration and adaptive reuse projects in Nepal, focused on “local materials, traditional knowledge and creative reuse”.
In Nepal, architectural discourse has centered on heritage buildings, whose official recognition is attributed only when they reach 100 years. The initial modern architecture of the structures built between 1945 and 1985, “remains undervalued, unocumentated and vulnerable to demolition or abandonment”, according to the same note. “The absence of a consolidated tradition of archiving of architectural materials makes it even more difficult to understand and teach this period,” which leaves students and teachers “with few resources”.
The constructions of this period symbolize “the impulse of the modernization of the nepal”, during which agricultural zones were urbanized. According to the statement, accelerated development and marketing put them at risk of disappearing. The collection of documentation about this period was hampered by the scarcity of files and the diversity of formats, from pencil sketches to photographs.
Jharna Joshi collaborates with professionals in project architecture and conservation projects and teaches, as a guest teacher, on urban conservation, vernacular architecture, callings and cultural landscapes. Architect from the University of Tsinghua, Beijing, is also specializing in historical conservation from the University of Pennsylvania, and cultural landscapes from Jean Monnet University.
In addition, he is a doctorate in management, in tourism, Victoria University of Wellington. His dissertation, entitled “Aesthetics of Landscape, Tourism and Change: Case Studies in Nepal”, analyzes how “residents and tourists perceive the aesthetic changes of the landscape in Ghandruk, Bandipur and Sauraha”.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau loses and tied in an internship in Taiwan</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-perde-empata-em-estagio-em-taiwan/</link><description>A defeat and a draw is the balance of the Macao's main football stage in Taiwan. The Kenneth Kwok-oriented team faced the main formation of the nationalist island, with whom he lost 2-0, followed by an equality to two balls with Taichung Futuro
 
Taking advantage of the elite league break, the MSar selection performed a one -week internship in Taiwan, where he played two matches, held at the closed door. In the first, the "eleven" guided by Kenneth Kwok was beaten by the main formation of the nationalist island, 2-0, 1-0 at the break.
The only Portuguese player who participated in the internship, Nuno Pereira, although he had not played for recovering from an injury, told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that the team of masters, "felt physical difficulties, allowing the ascendant of the opponent." So, he stresses, "the game didn't go very well for us, since we weren't able to circulate the ball."
Despite the Desaire, the challenge served the coach's goals, to give the team's competitive pace and “provide more international games,” as Kwok said when, at the end of last year, he took command, replacing Luso-Angolan Lázaro Oliveira.
Macao's team was much better in the second game, in which it faced, also in Taipé, the Taichung Futuro, classified in the second position of Taiwan's “Premier League” last season.
At the break, the two teams were tied to a ball. They marked for the formation of the MSAR, Fischer and Him, with the second goal to be achieved in the last minute of the match.
Local selection players will now resume preparation in their clubs, at a time when the Elite League resumes its normal calendar, with games divided by two groups, the champion's determination and the permanence or descent.
The championship returns on the 12th and, three days later, there is a game that can start defining the title between leader Must IPO and the second positioned Shao Jiang.
 
Women eliminated in national games
The MGI's female football team was also involved in international clashes, having played the qualifiers for the National Games of the Popular Republic of China, which took place in Zhuhai for four days. The formation of the territory lost the two challenges performed, 2-0 before Shanghai and 6-0 against Beijing.
Sara Fonseca, the only Portuguese summoned for these meetings, told this newspaper that she “missed luck in the first game, played in climacteric bad conditions”. Even so, he admits the athlete, "Macao has no big chance of making much better face of these teams with more experience."
The MSAR selection is currently guided by a continent coach, Mong Mong. “The Chinese team-selector is very renowned in China and has a very high level, which has provided great improvements to the team, noting the difference since it started training,” says 32-year-old Sara Fonseca, who since 2014 has been representing the mashed selection.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Accounts in accommodation and trips to attract Thai</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/descontos-em-alojamento-viagens-para-atrair-tailandeses/</link><description>Yesterday ended the large -scale street promotion “Feeling Macau” in Bangkok. Under the concept “Macao Wonder”, the promotion showed the intersectory integration of Macao “Tourism +”, inviting Thai residents to travel to the site to experience Macao's culture, entertainment and gastronomy, indicated the direction of Tourism Services (STD). At the time, several discounts were released to attract the Thai to the territory.

In his speech, STD subdirector Cheng Wai Tong stressed that “Macau is a very popular tourist destination for Thai visitors”, hoping that they could get better informed during street promotion. In addition, he indicated that through cooperation with a Thailand electronic payment platform, they can now enjoy immediate discounts on tourist consumption in Macao.
Online and face -to -face travel agencies, along with airlines and the six game operators participated in the promotion. Examples of available offers included 50% discounts or plane tickets from 199 Bahts, 50% of the Agoda in accommodation, among others, to encourage promotion visitors to buy on site.
The promotion also included a tourist sales stand, a stage zone, a gastronomy zone, an artificial intelligence photographs zone, an installation to take photographs, a chainsman workshop with recorded stones of Macao, among others, as a variety of interactive games, with Macao tourist products with special offers.
The six consumers with the highest consumer value each day of the promotion were able to get free hotel accommodation prizes, meal coupons, tickets for sights and models of the limited edition of the popular character “Mega Space Molly” in Macao Nata Pastel, among other awards, STD said.
A seminar on the new products of “Tourism + Conventions and Exhibitions” from Macau and Contact Stock Exhibitions was also held. The event was attended by 185 representatives of the Macao and Thailand tourist industry, among others. According to STD, the parties negotiated, "with a view to jointly expanding potential sources of tourism visitors and the convention and exhibition sector."
STD also had a meeting with the Sino-Tailandesan Trade Chamber to exchange impressions with leaders of the Chinese diaspora on tourism, conventions and exhibitions, and trade between Macao and Thailand.
This was the first major street promotion of STD organized this year in Southeast Asia. Engfa Waraha, a popular star of Thailand, was the guest of honor to act in the opening show of street promotion, and present the festivals and gastronomy of Macao. Already the female group "Pixxie" and the men's "Perth" group shared their travel experiences to Macau and recommended sights.
 
“Popular characters” invade the city
The “Pop Mart Macao Citywalk” cultural tourism program has already inaugurated, in an organization of the Tourism Services Directorate (STD) and Pop Mart. Thus, installations of the popular characters from pop Mart, Baby Molly, Crybaby, Dimoo and Labubu, are on the sidewalk of São Lázaro church, Luís de Camões Square, Largo de Santo Agostinho and leisure zone on Pai Kok da Taipa Street. The idea, says STD, is to encourage visitors, especially younger ones, to travel to community neighborhoods during the summer to have fun and consume in Macau, "helping to promote the economy of community tourism." There will be a series of raffles in four phases, between June and September.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Game operators offer almost 700 job openings</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/operadoras-de-jogo-oferecem-quase-700-vagas-de-emprego/</link><description>In collaboration with the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), the six game operators will hold at least six employment conjugation sessions in June, providing a total of 686 vacancies. According to DSAL, these sessions aim to "relieve the pressure felt by companies in the search for human resources and, at the same time, to provide jobs to Macao residents with employment needs." Until June 24, residents interested in applying can apply through the DSSA Electronic page or the “Local Employment Offers” Single Account. The vacancies in question involve various departments of the front line and the logistics of hotels and restoration establishments of integrated tourism and leisure companies, and the jobs are distributed in three areas, namely in the "restoration", "rooms and cleaning" and "front line operations", representing about 75% of the total offer. According to Dsal, these pairing sessions also involve some management and professional technique stations, such as purchasing manager, customer development manager, shift manager, security supervisor and food hygiene, cooking chief and chief cook of different cuisines, among others. Upon admission of the application, interviews will be scheduled by the company with candidates who meet the requirements. The first labor conjugation sessions are scheduled for June 17 (Melco), 20 (Galaxy and SJM), 24 (MGM), 26 (sands) and 30 (Wynn).</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Maritime tour revives fishing culture</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/passeio-maritimo-reaviva-cultura-piscatoria/</link><description>The maritime tour in the fishing period is back in the waters of Macao, indicated the direction of maritime and water (DSAMA) services, remaining until July 20. The vessel used is a traditional wooden fishing vessel with a length of about 31 meters, which part of the Green Island dock, towards the waters near Shizimen and returns to the Green Island Doca. According to Dsama, this itinerary allows to appreciate the landscape of the inner port, bridges and modernization of the Shizimen commercial zone. “On board the vessel are displayed several fisheries and fishing equipment, as well as fishing vessels and display vessels. During the trip, fishermen will demonstrate traditional weaving techniques and sharing stories of their lives on fishing vessels, so that citizens can know the fishing industry and the unique fishing culture of Macau,” says the body. Three sea trips are operated for the public on Saturdays and on Sundays, starting at 10:30 am, at 2:30 pm and 4:30 pm. The tour lasts about 1 hour and 30 minutes, with the maximum number of passengers on each trip set at 26. Each person can buy at most four tickets, each has a cost of 40 patacas. The initiative is organized by the Mutual Fisherman Association, and supported by Dsama, Galaxy, Melco, MGM and SJM.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ana de Armas is better to kill than to dance in “Ballerina”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/ana-de-armas-e-melhor-matar-dancar-em-bailarina/</link><description>JOCELYN NOVECK*
You begin to think that everyone is a killer. The type of newspaper bank, the street musician, the passenger of the metro, that friendly neighbor in the elevator - relentless salary killers, all.
So, maybe it's not that surprising that in “from John Wick's world: dancer,” the latest movie in the Wickian universe, come to the logical end: a city where each inhabitant is a killer. Yes, it is a snowy and picturesque winter landscape in Austria, where everyone wears wool caps and very beautiful nightgowns. But they also wield a relentless launcher, and school-age children have a mandatory shooting training.
The initial scenes in this crazy place on top of the mountains are the best part of “The Ballerina” - they really contain ingenious surprises and even a touch of humor, which we would hardly expect from a John Wick movie. (Have you ever seen the type smile?) Seeing our energy star Ana de Armas, participating in a competition to leave dishes with a sweet table maid that has become a cruel murderer reminds us that the action can be intelligent, even though most scenes in this series become inevitably numbing as bodies count stretch.
Before we go on, some clarifications about where this movie fits the timeline. Let's forget (for now) that there was a John Wick 4, because the events of "The Ballerina" happen during the third movie. Thus, erase from your mind any striking and transformative event that may or may not have happened in the last movie. Right?
For Ana de Arma, Keanu Reeves colleague for 10 years and once again, “The Ballerina” is a pirouette.
Eagle -eyed spectators may recall a brief scene in the third movie in which a dancer tries to make a series of Fouettés, those one -legged whip curves that are a big attraction in “The Swan Lake”. The same scene returns to "The Ballerina", with the character of Armai, Eve, trying to stubbornly master them in training. Why does it continue to fall - every time, after years and years of classes - it's a mystery.
We do not seek total realism in action movies, guys, but we can suggest that falling to the floor with the tips sneakers each time a curve looks like a much harder stunt than anything else in “The Ballerina” - including annihilating a horde of inhabitants of the city. This also demonstrates a worrying lack of coordination, a definitive problem for a killer.
Anyway! In fact, we first met Eve as a child, living alone with his dear father in a wind residence swept by the wind. Suddenly a team of black killers arrived by the sea, aiming at the father. It can protect Eve, but dies as a result of the injuries.
Soon, Eve, now orphan, is approached by Winston (Ian McShane, return), owner of the continental hotel. Winston says he can take her to his father's family. He takes her to the director (the arrogant Anjelica Huston), who welcomes the aspiring dancer in what appears to be an elite ballet gym, but is also the Ruska Roma training field, the criminal organization where Wick himself learned his craft.
The years pass. Eve is now a young woman determined to walk her own way, although she still has difficulty completing a Fouetté's return. Fortunately, she shows more aptitude with firearms. And this is important because its main objective is to avenge the death of the father. So when Wick himself (Keanu Reeves, of course, appearing in some important scenes) makes a crucial stop at the gym, Eve looks at him and asks, "How do I leave here?"
“The front door is unlocked,” says Wick - a speech that deserved applause in the exhibition I was in, but also just about everything Wick said or did. "No, how do I start doing what you do?" Asks Eve. Wick says she can still leave - has the option of rejecting a killer's life. The sad subtext: he is not.
But while Wick wants to leave - always - Eve wants to come in. Otherwise, we would not have a movie. And so, her search for revenge takes her, the dangerous track (and against the strict orders of the director), to Hallstatt's snow village. Then the fearsome chancellor (Gabriel Byrne, properly cold) leads a bunch of killers - all who want to kill her. Oh, and more: the chancellor killed his father.
And then Eve has to fight, using all the training and mill that has accumulated. A lesson she must learn from a trust teacher: "Fight like a girl."
In this case, as you might imagine, this is not a derogatory phrase. What it means is to use your strengths-you will not overcome a man by brute force, the teacher told him, but with intelligence and inventiveness.
This means using increasingly interesting weapons to kill an infinite supply of people (it must be said, the applause of viewers are, as always, disconcerting). And in the end, you can be quite comfortable with a flames.
 
*Journalist of the Associated Press specializing in culture and gender, as well as film critic.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>