<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Mentor of the theater in Patuá appointed “heir” of the national heritage</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mentor-teatro-em-patua-nomeado-herdeiro-patrimonio-nacional/</link><description>At a time when the Dóci Papiaçá Di Macao prepare another theater show in Patuá, included in this year's edition of the Art Festival, the group's great mentor, Miguel de Senna Fernandes, was selected as “heir representative of intangible heritage at national level”. The China Ministry of Culture and Tourism also appointed John Lo as ambassador to Tou Tei's belief and customs. Miguel de Senna Fernandes told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that this distinction is a “recognition of work” developed by Dóci Papioca. The title attributed to the person responsible for the item listed in 2021 as China's intangible cultural heritage, also gives “greater relevance to the Macanese culture and community,” he says. Given the growing projection of the shows in Patuá, the official intends to take the group to Portugal in 2026 and hold sessions in the diaspora
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Theater in Patuá has just received another honorable distinction from the cultural entities of the Popular Republic of China, this time in the person of its great mentor. Miguel de Senna Fernandes was appointed “heir representative of intangible heritage at national level”, in a nomination released by the China Ministry of Culture and Tourism, which also indicated John Lo as ambassador to belief and Toumi customs. The sixth list of national heritage representatives, which integrates 942 people, raised to nine the total of MSAR ambassadors.
In the case of the theater in Patuá, whose members are already in great bustle in preparations to present another show at the Macao Arts Festival, Miguel de Senna Fernandes considers that the title is “the recognition of the work that has been done”. It also arises following the integration of the theater in Patuá into the list of China's intangible cultural heritage in June 2021.
“This distinction is very honored,” says the head of the Dóci Papiaçá Di Macau group, noting that the appointment has to do with the confirmation of the person behind the items appointed by China for intangible heritage. “In this case, it is me the human element that represents the theater in Patuá,” says Miguel de Senna Fernandes.
Regarding what may result from here, Macaense says that at least the guarantee that there will always be theater in Patuá. "Chinese entities give great importance to this kind of distinctions, which can also be interpreted as an important hub, at a time when it comes to the exchange between the West and the East and now more specifically between China and, for example, Portuguese -speaking countries."
For Miguel de Senna Fernandes, the recognition now bound by the Ministry of Culture and Tourism of China, "must be understood in this aspect and gives relevance to the Macanese community and culture."
Recognizing that the Macanese community is small, compared to the general population, understands that “it remains relevant in dialogue between China and other Portuguese -speaking countries”, something that “is also good for the Portuguese community itself”.
Certainly motivated by another reference to the theater in Patuá, Miguel de Senna Fernandes talks about the “need for the group to have more mobility” and, therefore, wants to see the third trip to Portugal already realized.
"We will bet on this presence in Lisbon year, after we have performed there in 1996 and 1999 and last year we made our choir shift," says the official.
 
Present the theater in the diaspora
In addition to Portugal, the idea is for the theater to be shown in other places. "In the diaspora, for example, what is also important, following the various requests made by members of the houses of Macao scattered around the world," he says.
The Chinese continent may also be contemplated. “Then the strategy would be different, since the show will have to diverge from what we usually do, because we have to be careful with the vehicle language and other aspects,” assumes Miguel de Senna Fernandes.
It is recalled that the display of the Dóci Papiaçá di Macau was close to happening at Expo Shanghai in 2008.
The theater in Patuá was, as we mentioned, accompanied by the belief and customs of Tou Tei in the new listing of heirs of representatives of items belonging to China's intangible cultural heritage, with John Lo Chung Seng receiving the title. Toumi is a Chinese god responsible for earthly affairs.
In the newspaper "or Mun", the leader of the Cheok Chai Un Fok Tak Chi Tou Mio Lei Wui de Macao Association, stated that it was very difficult to include the beliefs and customs of Tou Tei, in the list of national immaterial heritage and now, as heir to this project, feels that there is an important mission ahead. “As a heir, I will reinforce cooperation with the other times of Tou Tei in Macao, with the aim of campaigning this good belief and leading more young people to pay attention to Tou Tei's party,” said John Lo.
Tou's belief and customs ambassador hopes to continue the support of the government and different sectors, to be able to integrate the elements of the Tou Feast in Community Tourism.
John Lo also intends to combine more cultures about the temples of Macao, with cultural and artistic products, in the sense that the history of the festive event is publicized. "We want this heritage to gain greater vitality in the new era," he said.
The associative leader states that, for this national recognition, the support of the respective Chinese ministry and the protection of Macao's social affairs and culture, including the Cultural Institute, was indispensable.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Launched Transfrontic Ambulance Service</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lancado-servico-de-ambulancias-transfronteiricas/</link><description>The service of transionic ambulances, which travel between hospitals from Zhuhai and Macau, has been officially launched. For the authorities, “not only symbolizes a realization of deepening health cooperation in the Great Bay, but also a new step in cooperation” between the two cities. In Macao, the public hospital integrates this service, while in Zhuhai there are four those who are part of the agreement
 
The Transfrontic Transfer Service has already been inaugurated point to point “hospital-hospital” between Zhuhai and Macau, after in January the governments of both cities signed a memo about the administrative departments that make up this service. "After several meetings, both parties defined the traffic procedures and the facilitation mechanism of the border passage, and the conditions are gathered to start the transmitter transport service of patients between Zhuhai and Macau," said the Unit Police Services (SPU) in a statement.
The service arises to respond to the “increase in the displacements of the large bay residents”, with the authorities to provide for “an increase in the demand for transionic health care”.
To activate the transfrontic ambulance mechanism, it is necessary to exist a prior agreement between the issuing hospital and the receptor hospital, “taking into account the needs, safety and interests of patients,” the SPU says.
In this context, a mechanism was also established to prevent “abusive situations”, which will work in parallel with the old “ambulance-ablemaker” model, according to which patients have to change ambulance in border-controlled areas. Thus, certain patients who “do not gather the conditions” for direct transfringe transportation of ambulance have to use the old “Ambulance-Ambulance” model.
For the authorities, “the transfrontic ambulance service between Zhuhai and Macau does not only symbolize a realization of deepening health cooperation in the Great Bay, but also a new step in health cooperation between Zhuhai and Macau, injecting a new dynamic in the integrated development of regional health services”. At the same time, it constitutes “a solid basis” for the transfronical rescue work between the two cities.
“With the official launch of the Transfrontic Ambulance Service between Zhuhai and Macau, the degree of satisfaction and well-being of residents of both regions could increase, reflecting the importance and attention provided by the governments of the two regions for the general well-being of the population,” read the SPU note.
The opening ceremony of the service, meeting room of the main building of the popular government of Zhuhai, was witnessed by the vice president of the popular government of Zhuhai, Huang Zhenqiu, and the commander General of SPU, Leong Man Cheong. Present was also the director of the Zhuhai Municipal Health Directorate, Zhu Ziqin, who assigned a hospital identification plaque designated to the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center.
From Macao, the director of health services, Alvis Lo, attributed identification signs to the popular hospital of the city of Zhuhai, the fifth affiliate hospital at Sun Yat-sen University, the Zhuhai Hospital of the Guangdong Traditional Medicine Hospital and the Chinese and Western Traditional Medicine Hospital of Zhuhai.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Number of junkets fixed in 24</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/numero-de-junkets-fixado-em-24/</link><description>There are currently 24 junkets licensed to exercise in the territory, according to the list updated by the Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate. The number of game promoters does not even reach half of the total of these authorized professionals for this year, a total of 50
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The universe of Junkets in Macao was fixed in 24 for this year, according to the list updated yesterday on the page of the Directorate of Inspection and Coordination of Games (DICJ). Regarding the beginning of last year, when 18 game promoters were allowed to exercise in the territory -the lowest number since 2006 -the increase was 33.3%. Regarding the latest update on the list, dated mid -December last year, only one more was added.
The number is not even half of the total "junkets" authorized for this year - half a hundred, according to a June 2024 order of the then Secretary for Economics and Finance, Law Wai Nong.
In the relationship published on the DICJ page, Venetian Macau and SJM Resorts continue to stand out as the concessionaires who can cooperate with the largest number of game promoters (12), followed by MGM Grand Paradise and Melco Resorts (eight), and Galaxy Casino and Wynn Resorts (five). Game prosecutors will have to sign a contract with one of six dealers.
This year 2025 there seems to be a reversal in the tendency to decrease game promoters. But in recent years this type of professionals have been decreasing: according to official data, in 2013 there were 235 junkets licensed to operate in Macao.
On the other hand, for this year, DICJ also maintained the maximum limit of junkets in 250. According to the last update, from mid -December last year, 14 employees of game promoters were licensed in Macao.
The new game of the game, which came into force in January 2023, has defined that “each game promoter can only exercise game promotion activity in a dealership” and prohibit “junkets” to “shares - in any form or agreement - with concessionaires, revenues from casinos, or exclusive exploitation of casinos reserved for contract”.
In addition, the "junkets" were prohibited from issuing credit to players, passing the game dealers to be excluded exclusively, further strengthening their radius of action.
The Government of MSAR estimated, late last year, that by 2025 it would raise 100 million PATACA in taxes on the commissions paid by casinos to the "junkets", representing a 233.3% increase compared to 30 million patacas that predicted in fiscal year 2024. The information is found in the budget report for this year, which, however, did not include justification for the increase of taxes on taxes game commissions.
By 2023, the executive charged 62.58 million patacas on taxes paid by casinos to junkets, an increase of almost 526% over the 10 million estimate for this fiscal year.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Caeal follows case of “pressure” in the subscription collection</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/caeal-acompanha-caso-de-pressao-na-recolha-de-assinaturas/</link><description>Aware of the comments on the Internet that aim to obtain voter support to constitute commissions of application for the elections for AL, Caeal is following a case in which a person, who “is part of an association”, felt “pressure” because he was “instated” to deliver a certain number of voters signatures
 
From the 6th of this month until yesterday noon, nine people raised the “request for recognition of the Constitution of Candidacy Commission” to the elections for the Legislative Assembly (AL), but no request has not yet been submitted, the Chairman of the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) said yesterday.
At a press conference, Seng Ioi Man revealed that, in addition to following the comments and "posts" on the Internet to get voter support for the constitution of candidacy committees, Caeal is following a situation where an association was "pressure" because it was "instated" by the association to deliver a certain number of voter signatures. Conduct, this person provided little information to the commission, which has not yet received “officially any complaint”.
Seng Ioi Man stressed that both voters and people who help to obtain voter support to the constitution of candidacy committees must sign in the bulletin or voluntarily provide help, clearly knowing the situation. In addition, he stressed that the law prohibits and considers as a crime the act of resorting to coercion, fraud, professional coercion, promise to make profits, among other means, to make signatures or develop application work, in order to lead to the constitution or not of candidacy commissions, or to influence voting intentions.
Appealing to people who are coerced or defrauded to sign in the candidacy report that submit a complaint to Caeal or the Commissioner against corruption and provide detailed information, Seng Ioi Man asserted that the commission will follow all cases seriously to ensure that the elections are legally, impartial, fair and intact.
In addition, CAEAL is following a situation where some elderly people have been asked for associations responsible for helping to replace the elderly cards to leave signatures in the candidacy report. Despite having resorted to several channels, the commission has not yet been able to obtain concrete information about the case, which made the follow-up difficult, recognized Seng Ioi Man, stressing that he will continue to accompany him. At this point, it also clarified that, according to the government, staff cannot develop, during the exchange of elderly cards, works not linked to this task.
On the other hand, Seng Ioi Man was asked about the words of an alleged teacher, expressed on social networks. The person in question said he was instated by the school to help collect signatures for the constitution of a candidacy committee. Seng Ioi Man stressed that if the authenticity of the situation is confirmed, the application proposal bulletin will be considered invalid.
 
Meetings with schools and game operators
In addition to a clarification session on election participation procedures, scheduled for the 26th of this month at the Science Center, CAEAL will hold, on April 7, a session in which it will explain with school representatives to law and voter procedures, so that schools sensitize students for fair, impartial and whole elections.
Also in early April, together with the Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate, Caeal will make an appointment with representatives of the game operators, to explain that concessionaires have to maintain neutrality and impartiality throughout the elections. In addition, its workers must also be neutral in the exercise of functions and cannot display objects related to the candidacy.
In addition, Seng Ioi Man reiterated that people considered “non -defenders of the basic law” and “not faithful to mashes” in the 2021 elections cannot apply for elections scheduled for September 14 this year, as “only four years” and the electoral law stipulates five years of prohibition for the re -candidacy. "Currently, the person responsible for this assessment is the State Security Commission, whose decision does not provide an appeal," he recalled.
At the conference, the official also pointed out that the “request for recognition” must be filled and submitted before June 6, and June 26 is the deadline to deliver the list of candidates or political program.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China's interior leads preferences for trips at Easter time</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/interior-da-china-lidera-preferencias-para-viagens-na-epoca-da-pascoa/</link><description>Cherry Blossoms in Wuhan



Residents are more inclined to travel to the interior of China during Easter, Andy Wu indicated, pointing out that Japan and South Korea are no longer the favorite destinations - at least, taking into account the breakdown of tour marking for those countries at this time. The associative leader also said that during Cheng Ming the hotel occupancy rate could reach 90%
 
Japan and South Korea used to be the favorite destinations of Macao residents for a walk at Easter time, but “this year began to give more preference to tourist destinations in the interior of China,” said the president of the Macao Tourist Industry Association. Andy Wu pointed out that "many" marked excursions to travel from fast train to Wuhan, in Hubei province, to see the cherry trees in flower.
"However, the number of registrants for Japan excursions at Easter time registered an annual break of 20 to 30%," the same said, in a joint interview with the newspaper "or Mun" and the Chinese radio "or Mun Tin Toi". In the opinion of the Macao Tourist Industry Association leader, this decline must be related to the rising price of airplane tickets to Japan and increasing excursions rates for that country, so many residents prefer to choose another time to travel there.
On the other hand, due to the political instability installed in South Correia since the beginning of the year and issues related to air safety, the willingness of many residents of traveling to this country "was shaken." As a result, the number of registered for southern Korea excursions registered a 50%annual break.
The same associative leader also noted that, in February and March, the volume of visitors has been stable in the territory, and also noted that the number of tour.
For Cheng Ming holidays, Andy Wu predicted that hotel occupation in Macau could reach 90%, and at this time visitors should come mainly from neighboring Hong Kong.
Already Cheung Kin Chung, president of the Macao Hotelers Association, told the same Chinese communication bodies that, after the Chinese New Year, the territory hotels have recorded occupation rates over 80% "thanks to the new visas measures launched at the beginning of the year."
He also said that, given that the national games are scheduled for November, the tourist and hotel sector is committed to launching new “Tourism + Sport” packages, “thus fostering an atmosphere of tourism city”. On the other hand, Cheung Kin Chung stressed that in the next phase several measures will be taken to increase Macao's integrated tourist competitiveness to respond to the government's objective to extend the tourist market of Portuguese -speaking and Spanish -speaking countries.
The president of the Macau Hotelers Association believes that at a later stage, authorities should begin to further improve the traffic network and create facilities in terms of basic tourist facilities. Regarding medium and long distance tourists, Cheung Kin Chung noted that the sector has been trying to diversify the tour packages of "a trip, various destinations."</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Club Rotarium appeals to young people to donate blood</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/clube-rotario-apela-aos-jovens-para-fazerem-doacao-de-sangue/</link><description>In a context where there are fewer and fewer blood donors in the territory, the Macao Rotary Club appeals to this layer of the population to participate in the campaign that will take place this Saturday afternoon, in “Nova Mall”, in Taipa. The group, which has organized the initiative since 2001, warns that the decrease in the participation of lower age groups "may lead to future shortages in blood supply" on thecep
 
There are fewer and young people to donate blood in the territory, so this year's Rotary Club Donation Campaign launches precisely “special appeal” to this layer of the population. The event, scheduled for the afternoon of next Saturday, will take place on “Nova Mall”, at Taipa.
The latest data from the blood transfusions center show that the percentage of blood donors who do so for the first time “has been decreasing from year to year” from 30% in 2018 to 21.1% in 2024. “This decline is mainly a decrease in the number of blood donors between university students and secondary education,” explains Rotary.
According to the organization, which cites official data, the number of high school students who donate blood has recorded “a decreasing trend” since 2019, maintaining the “low level” of about 2%. Looking at 2015, for example, 9% of blood donors were high school students.
The available figures indicate that, last year, a total of 13,740 people donated blood, and a homologous decrease of 3.2%was registered. The number of blood gifts was 20,587, and 2,899 were donors for the first time, a break of 13.6%. The data also reveal that the number of university students who donated blood over 2024 also “decreased significantly” compared to previous years, falling 3.5%.
"The decrease in the participation of young people in the blood of blood can lead to a future shortage of blood supply in Macao," the organization warns, thus, "Macao young people actively participate in the blood of blood, contributing to a sustainable blood supply to needy patients."
Rotary Club's Blood Donation Day is organized by the eight existing Rotary Clubs in the territory and co-organized by the Health Services Blood Transfusions Center. In the last 25 years, the organization is the objective of this project “has been the promotion of the awareness and the need for blood to ensure sufficient supply of blood reserves in the city”, underlining that health is one of the areas. of group action.
Rotary understands that the event in “Nova Mall” will help to reach “key demographic groups”, including young people and middle-aged residents of various cultural and ethnic origins. Started in 2001 by former Macau Rotary Club President Alfredo Ritchie, Rotary's Blood Donation Day became a project of all Rotary Clubs in the Territory, in a joint work with health authorities.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Shared poems to preserve “linguistic and cultural diversity”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/poemas-partilhados-para-preservar-diversidade-linguistica-cultural/</link><description>A session of shared poems, in Portuguese or Chinese: this is the suggestion of the Rui Cunha Foundation for a will be on World Poetry Day, which is celebrated on Friday. The idea is to “enrich the common experience” by reading special poems for participants
 
To commemorate World Poetry Day, the Rui Cunha Foundation presents this Friday a special session entitled “Give Life to a Poem”. In the form of gathering, the public is invited to pass the FRC gallery and bring a poem of their choice, in Portuguese or Chinese, to share with the other participants, "in a will be with the purpose of enriching the common experience."
Co-organized by the Book Friends Association in Macao and the Jardim da Flora Friends Poetry Association, the meeting is seen as “an opportunity to encourage reading, support poets and preserve linguistic and cultural diversity through the written and spoken word”. The session starts at 6:30 pm.
World Poetry Day was instituted by UNESCO at the 30th General Conference in Paris in 1999 to honor the poetic expression and its cultural importance in societies worldwide. “Poetry, with its ability to thrill, provoke reflections and convey feelings, crosses centuries and civilizations, being one of the pillars of literary art,” says the organization.
More than a simple set of verses, poetry is a manifestation of the human soul, which can be lyrical, epic, social, philosophical or experimental, adapting to different eras and styles, he adds. “From Camões's sonnets and Liu Yong's classic poems to the free verses of contemporary poetry, this literary genre has been a powerful means of communication and resistance,” reads.
This session of shared poems will be conducted by the doctor and writer Shee Va, representing the Association of Friends of the Book, who will invite participants to reveal poems with special meaning in their lives. The conversation will be held in Portuguese and Chinese, according to the suggested readings. The entrance is free.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Teresa Leong addresses law themes at the FrC</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/teresa-leong-aborda-temas-de-direito-na-frc/</link><description>Topics related to the area of ​​law will join a series of four lectures in the Rui Cunha Foundation gallery, under the responsibility of Teresa Leong. Debates take place on Wednesdays and Thursdays in two consecutive weeks. The first session takes place today
 
The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) will organize four lectures on law topics, on the “vicissitudes of the case (i)”, which aims to identify possible incidents in court proceedings and address the respective regimes.
The sessions in the FRC gallery will take place on Wednesdays and Thursdays, for two consecutive weeks and start today, continuing the next day, always at 18:30. 26 and 27 of this month will take place the other two events.
The conferences, the responsibility of Teresa Leong, will be guided in Portuguese, in the first week, and Chinese, in the second.
Organized by CRED-DM-Center for Reflection, Study and Dissemination of the FRC Macao Law, the cycle aims to address, in a practical and explanatory way, relevant themes of the daily life of all Macao judicial operators. "This is a project started in previous years with great interest and adhesion by the class," according to a FRC statement.
In the introduction of the event, Teresa Leong states that the judicial process "begins with the dispute" and ends with the "decision to end this dispute". If the process follows its normal course, without major startles, “justice is naturally served without disorder,” he says.
The note also indicates that "incidents of the most varied order make this desiderate, sometimes difficult to achieve" and these incidents, "in addition to causing some inconvenience to the ongoing process, may even in question the acts laboriously practiced, including the final decision itself."
With “process vicissitudes (i)” begins this approach with the “analysis of the circumstances in which it can, or has to modify the subjects of a judicial process and their implications for the ongoing process”, adds the speaker.
The free lectures are organized by themes. The first session will deal with the “subjective modification: subjective substitution vs. subjective cumulation” and “third parties intervention: main intervention”. In the second, a week later, it will be the turn of the “Third Party Intervention: Accessory Intervention and Opposition”. The entrance is free.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Support plan celebrates 80 years of victory over Japan</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/plano-de-apoio-comemora-80-anos-da-vitoria-sobre-japao/</link><description>To commemorate the “80th anniversary of the Chinese people's victory in the war against Japan and the world victory against fascism”, a financial support plan for cultural and artistic activities will be launched. Registration starts on Friday, and projects can be supported up to 500 thousand patacas
 
The Culture Development Fund (FDC) will launch a financial support plan to commemorate the “80th anniversary of the Chinese people's victory in the war against Japan and the world victory against fascism”. The idea is to support non -profit associations and foundations in the realization of various cultural activities, "in order to promote the spirit of the War of Resistance, to foster patriotism and reinforce the feeling of identification and pride of Macao residents with national history."
Applications are accepted between March 21 and April 22, and the projects must belong to the area of ​​Arts and Culture, and be held in Macau, to the public or accessible to the public. They must also be cultural and artistic performances and performances, exhibitions or fairs, contests, audiovisual production, film production and television or animation production, lectures, workshops, seminars, book publications and journals.
According to the FDC, candidates must be non -profit associations or foundations, legally constituted until December 31, 2023, and are organizing entities of candidates and content. Each candidate can only present a project, warns the fund, adding that the amount financed maximum varies, depending on the type of activity, between 150 thousand and 500 thousand patacas, "being given priority to projects with higher scores".
The financial support period extends from March 21 to December 31, 2025, without extension-that is, the projects must be completed by December 31 of this year.
The evaluation will be made by the Activities and Project Evaluation Committee, taking into account the various criteria: quality and improvement of content planning, budget rationality, candidate execution capacity and scale and influence of activity. Additional score will be awarded for the projects that were funded by the China National Arts Fund or extended projects.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Face -to -face vote for legislatures in Portugal must be communicated today</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/voto-presencial-para-legislativas-em-portugal-deve-ser-comunicado-hoje/</link><description>Following the marking of legislative elections in Portugal to May 18, the Portuguese Consulate-General in Macau and Hong Kong warned yesterday that co-active voters abroad can exercise the right to vote by post or in person. If they intend to vote in person, citizens must express this intention - if they have not done so in a previous election to the Assembly of the Republic - with the census Commission of the area of ​​residence. In the case of Macao, it is then with the consulate, and the request must be made ahead of tomorrow, March 20. If they choose not to exercise the right in person, citizens will receive at the address in the electoral census the documentation to do it by post. Remember that in the last legislative elections, about a year ago, just over two hundred people were registered in Macau to vote in person. At the time, the Consul General, Alexandre Leitão, made an appeal, in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, so that people altered the voting mode, taking into account the problems that are often verified in the delivery of bulletins via mail. "It is a little paradoxical that there are only 213 people registered to vote in person and 49 thousand by post," said Alexandre Leitão. In the legislatures last year, and according to a study published by the National Commission of Elections, irregularities in the inclusion of the copy of the Citizen Card resulted in the annulment of most postal votes of the Portuguese abroad.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2362/</link><description>Eight detainees in illegal game
An illegal game operation was discovered by the Judicial Police (PJ) in a fraction in Zape, where two suspicious operators, seven players and one person watching the game, all residents of Macao were arrested. In the action, the PJ found two game tables, a large amount of chips and some poker card boxes. According to police, an online group will have recruited the gamblers, while one of the operators will be the source of hiring people to distribute the letters, with a daily salary of 500 patacas. Each bet involved an amount between 1,000 and 1,500 patacas. Those responsible for the illegal game will have made profits of about 400,000 patacas.
 
Burned gray deposits in a cemetery
Seventeen human gray deposit places were set on fire at the Nossa Senhora da Piedade Cemetery in the Mong-Há area. The Judiciary Police are investigating the case as being of fire, having found components left after the burning of candles, which will have been at the origin of the fire. The incident happened in the afternoon in the day before yesterday and there were no injuries. The Institute for Municipal Affairs says that, in addition to collaborating with the investigation, it is contacting family members of the spaces concerned.
 
Filming with “more concrete and clear” guidelines
The president of the Cultural Institute (IC) revealed that “more concrete and clear” guidelines will be released for filming in Macao, and if a team wants to develop a complex project, for example involving traffic, will be urged to deliver more detailed clarification and filming plan. According to Leong Wai Man, the IC will consult opinions from other government services to ensure a safe environment in filming. About the team that caused an accident, it did not rule out the possibility of abolishing the authorization for filming. In 2024, more than 300 teams from abroad asked to film in Macao, reaching a record.
 
Suggested review of AI -related laws
Given that the authorities in the interior of China will force, from 1 September, that all content generated by Artificial Intelligence (IA) have a symbol to inform from this, local lawyer Andreia Lao suggested that the masters take this experience to improve legal regimes regarding this domain. In turn, Lam Chi Wa, director of the Macao Informatics Academy Association, considers that the new measure of the continent can guarantee citizens' safety at the level of daily life, information and privacy.
 
One and public housing will receive recycled water
From the beginning of 2026, water recycled to 8,000 aggregates in the public housing of Seac Pai Van and on the University of Macao campus, buildings that are equipped with double conduct of water, said the director of maritime and water services. Although it is yet to be disclosed, the price of recycled water will be “certainly lower” than that of tap water, said Susana Wong, predicting that, after the entry into operation, the recycled water rate will lower.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Almost 1,700 wait for social houses</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/quase-1-700-esperam-por-casas-sociais/</link><description>A total of 1,675 candidates are waiting for social housing, and the Housing Institute has 1,166 houses available, which covers about 70% of the waiting list. According to data from the body, 275 apartments are suffering repair works
 
Catarina Pereira
 
There are just over 1,600 household aggregates in a waiting list to receive social housing, and the Housing Institute (IH) has houses available for the vast majority. The scenario of a year ago, when the waiting list exceeded 13 times the available social houses, now gives signs of inversion.
The latest data reveal that 1,166 social houses are available for a total of 1,675 family nuclei, which means that the ready -to -handed fractions cover about 70% of candidates on hold. Applications statistics report to the period from August 20, 2020 until yesterday, March 17, and the data related to the available fractions are referred to until March 14.
Most (890), they are aggregates composed of only one element, but T1 typology apartments are available only 88. Family nuclei with two members (567) are followed, and T2 are free 957; and the families of three people (203). There are also 12 aggregates made up of four people and three formed by five or more elements. As for T3 and T4, IH has 121 houses.
Regarding the age group, candidates stand out between 23 and 44 years old, totaling 679 (41%), and aged 45 to 64 years, totaling 677 (40%). In addition, there are still 312 with 65 years or over and seven aged 18 to 22 years.
There are still 275 repair fractions. Of these, 128 are T1, a total of 133 are of T2 typology and only 14 are T3 or T4. The works to which they are being subjected include “painting, replacement of doors and windows, repair of electricity and supply facilities and water drainage,” says IH. When these jobs are ready, the truth is that the waiting list as it exists will now be greatly reduced, with just over two hundred aggregates. However, it should be noted that the candidacy for social housing is a permanent mechanism, so new requests are always emerging.
But most social housing fractions, in a total of 4,088, are still under construction. They are all in zone A of the new landfills: 1,736 in lot A5; 1,064 in Zone A6; 728 in lot A10; and 560 in zone A11.
Most candidates on the waiting list (1,444 of the 1,675) have not yet been notified for the presentation of the documents for assessment before the home assignment, so only 231 have already received the notification to move forward with these procedures.
According to official data, IH number 8,510 applications with all documents delivered, of which 5,978 were admitted. Regarding the appreciation phase, 1,574 were rejected for breach of the requirements, 265 gave up, 91 are undergoing legal procedure and 602 are under consideration.
Regarding the admitted candidacies, much (4,303) has seen the treatment is completed, and the 3,467 candidates were assigned, 414 were excluded because they did not meet the requirements and 422 eventually gave up.
 
13 cases on suspicions of misuse of houses
According to IH, there are currently 17,548 social housing fractions in the territory. The January data this year point out that 14,817 tenants increased income not exceeding the maximum limit, while 653 received yield not exceeding double the fixed ceiling. On the other hand, only six tenants were calculated in accordance with Decree-Law 1/91/m, which defines the payment regime of houses attributed by the territory to public administration workers.
The tenants total 15,476, and 10,797 have a family aggregate composed of one to two people, followed by the family nuclei consisting of three to four elements (4,047). But there is also counting tenants whose families have five to six members (595) and seven or more people (37).
Statistics regarding the period between January 1 of last year and January 24 of this year indicate that 13 proceedings have been instructed because there are suspicions that beneficiaries are not using social housing as permanent residence or by allowing them to live in the contract. There was also a case of voluntary return of social housing in the scope of the administrative sanctioning procedure. On the other hand, there is no one to report any case related to violation of the building's regulation by the lessee.
On the other hand, about the administration of social housing, between January and March this year there was only one case suspected of not doing the work of administration in accordance with the contractual terms, having begun the application of sanctions.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UTM will reduce duration of tour guides courses</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/utm-vai-reduzir-duracao-dos-cursos-de-guias-turisticos/</link><description>The University of Tourism of Macao has been conducting a plan to optimize the courses for the formation of tour guides and, after the study, will reduce their total duration to about three quarters. The objective, according to the educational institution, is to improve the efficiency of global training
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Tour guides training courses, provided by the University of Tourism of Macau (UTM), are being the subject of an optimization plan, involving dialogue with different stakeholders. The information is contained in a response from Tourism Services (STD) to an interpellation of Deputy Ron Lam, noting that, after study and planning, UTM will adjust the method of articulation of the courses, reducing the total duration of the program from about four to about three quarters.
The goal, he points out is "to improve the efficiency of global formation and, at the same time, to allow students to organize their learning according to their own pace."
The two courses, “Certificate in History and Tourism of Macao” and “Certificate of Tour Guide”, are independent and their conception covers several areas, including roles of tour guides, cultural knowledge, tourist care techniques and ability to respond to unforeseen situations, among others.
In response to the market search for less spoken language tour guides last year, UTM states that it tried to organize programs in language such as Korean, Thai, and Japanese. However, due to insufficient registration number, most courses could not be performed.
Macao had at the end of October last year with 1,821 tour guide card holders, including 809 proficient in Cantonese and 1,207 in Mandarin, according to Chan Chak Mo, president of the 2nd Permanent Commission of the Legislative Assembly, citing updated data provided by the government.
Excluding the Chinese, the panorama was not very positive, since only 156 guides were fluent in English, representing 8.6% of the total, 75 in Japanese (4.2% of the total) and 23 in other “minority” languages, not specified (1.3%).
In the future, adds the text now signed by STD director, Helena de Senna Fernandes, UTM will offer “more flexible linguistic training methods such as mixed online and face -to -face teaching modalities to support the learning of tourist guides”. Regarding language evaluation, in addition to annual tests in April, August and December, "an exam system will be implemented with the registration at any time."
With regard to guided tours activities, STD stresses that the Cultural Institute has promoted a variety of cultural and promotion actions, including guided tour services, for certain sites of heritage, as well as the launch of local activities “Cultural Guided Visits”, “Cultural Tour” and “Visits to World Heritage”, all in collaboration with tourist guides Macao tour guide card.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Dream of painting Eusebius in Mafalala takes French artist from Paris to Maputo</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/sonho-de-pintar-eusebio-na-mafalala-leva-artista-frances-de-paris-maputo/</link><description>French artist Glass (2-d) poses for photography in the company of children next to the mural who is painting in the neighborhood of Mafalala in honor of the late footballer Eusébio, Maputo, Mozambique, February 27, 2025. With some spray cans in his luggage and a dream, the French artist Glasson made the more than 12,000 kilometers that separate Paris from Maputo to paint eusébio In the neighborhood where the “Black Panther” was born, Mafalala. (Accompanies Lusa text on March 15, 2025). Luísa Nhantumbo/Lusa



Stephen Chavisso*
With some cans of spray in the luggage and a dream, the French artist Glass made the more than 12 thousand kilometers that separate Paris from Maputo to paint Eusébio in the neighborhood where the “Black Panther” was born, Mafalala.
"It was a special moment: painting Eusébio where he was born," Lusa, Brian Diegues, 28, told Lusa, minutes after giving the "last touches" to the mural in the middle of Mafalala, a historic peripheral neighborhood in the Mozambican capital.
Eusébio's new painting is really at “Campinho da Mafalala”, where the legend discovered his passion for football.
For many, this space, a few meters from the Mafalala Museum, is the heart of a peripheral neighborhood with historical importance in Maputo.
These are alleys and alleys that separate precarious building houses that carry the weight of having housed personalities who named Mozambique to the world, including writers such as José Craveirinha and Noémia de Sousa, besides Eusébio himself, an icon of football.
There are about 20,000 people from almost all over the country who share daily the neighborhood of an informal zinc urbanization, but which for many was the “center of cultural resistance” to the Portuguese colonial administration in Maputo.
“I wanted to paint even in this neighborhood, not even knowing that it was called Mafalala. So, still in Paris, I prepared a painting (…) and came with suitable material to paint Eusébio,” explains the artist.
In the new mural, Eusébio boasts Benfica's jersey, his "heart club" and of which glaçon is also adept at "heredity".
“My father gave me Benfica as a club (…). I am a benfiquista and, being a benfiquista, could not forget the history of Eusebius in Benfica,” explains the artist, who even worked as a guide at Estádio da Luz during a time when he lived in Portugal.
“I lived and grew up in Paris, but I decided to leave my Parisian life to work at the [Do] Sport Lisboa and Benfica (…) stadium. I worked for over a year as a guide,” he added.
From a deceased Portuguese father, born in Mozambican territory before independence, Glass's relationship with Mozambique and Portugal is “emotional”.
"It is always difficult to talk about someone who was born in Mozambique before June 25, 1975. I always considered my Portuguese father, but because he was born in Mozambique, I also considered him always Mozambican," he added.
It is this connection that gives glaçon the ambition to return to the African country to give color to other murals, highlighting the importance of other historical figures in the country, including Mario Column, another reference in Portuguese football born in Mozambique.
"I like to tell stories and then Samora Machel [First President of Mozambique], Eduardo Mondlane [founder of the Mozambique Liberation Front] and Mario column are my next goals," he said.
For many a symbol of Portuguese sport, national champion for Benfica 11 times and winner of the 1962 Champions Cup, Eusébio da Silva Ferreira died on January 5, 2014, 71 years old.
Eusébio won in 1965 the Golden Ball, which then distinguished the best European footballer to play in Europe, and twice won the gold boot (1967/68 and 1972/73), award for the best scorer of European national championships.
In the 1966 World Cup, played in England, he was one of the most outstanding players of the competition and the best scorer, contributing nine goals to third place in Portugal.
 
*From the Lusa Agency</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>