<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>IAM is negotiating with IC Camões Bust</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/iam-esta-negociar-ic-reparacao-busto-de-camoes/</link><description>Already issued by the Cultural Institute, technical opinions for the work of repairing the bust of Camões, which is in the cave with the name of the poet. However, the Institute for Municipal Affairs did not indicate to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao a date for the beginning of the work, saying only that it is “negotiating the plan and demands” of the statue's repair
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau to be “in contact” with the Cultural Institute (IC) “to negotiate the plan and repair requirements of Luís de Camões bust in Jardim de Luís de Camões” . The answer came after the IC informed this newspaper that it has already issued technical opinions about the repair works, by AMI.
As for the procedures to be adopted in the work, neither the body led by Leong Wai Man, nor the body directed by Chao Wai Ieng advanced details. AMI had already said that after having the opinions of the IC would start the work, however, no date has not been indicated to start. The statue, it is noted, is in the area of ​​a classified property and has historical value, as the IC has already stressed.
The third stanza of “Os Lusíadas” on the back of the pedestal where Luís Vaz de Camões bust is practically unreadable. It is the number 81 of singing VI: “And yet, nymphs of mine, it was not enough/ that such misery would surround me,/ but those that I singing walked/ such a prize of my verses made me:/ the change of the rests I expected,/ From the bay chapels that honored me,/ works never used invented me,/ with which in such a hard state they lay me down. ”
Faced with this situation in July last year, AMI had told JTM that “it had already found that the registration is disappearing” and that it was “accompanying”, having added that maintenance work would be performed.
It should be noted that the first two excerpts in the stone pedestal in the Camões cave can still read. They concern the stanza 95 of singing VI and the resort 42 of singing VIII.
The garden of Luis de Camões, one of the oldest in Macao, was created in the mid -eighteenth century. In the cave, consisting of three large faceted rocks, there is then the bust of Camões, by sculptor Manuel Maria Bordalo Pinheiro.
It is said that in the mid-16th century, Camões (1524-1580) lived in Macao for two years, where he will have finished, in the cave that has its name today, the work "The Lusíadas". “With the sponsorship of 600 francs from a rich Portuguese merchant from Macao, Lourenço Marques, son -in -law of Manuel Pereira, the cave was renewed in 1849, and there was a bust of the poet. A pavilion on the cave was also erected, which no longer exists. The last restoration of the group dates from 1866 and the poet's bust was refused in bronze, ”can be read on the Macao Cultural Heritage page.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Suggested reorganization of the public transport system</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sugerida-reorganizacao-sistema-de-transportes-publicos/</link><description>Several deputies made suggestions on public buses and the slight meter. Leong Sun Iok called on the reorganization of the public transport system when the bus contracts end and the acceleration of the construction of the West Metro line. Nick Law wants to achieve discounts on the transfer between buses and the meter after the end of these contracts. On the other hand, Ngan Iek Hang expects both to play a better role in relieving traffic pressure while performing concerts
 
Deputy Leong Sun Iok considers that the end of public business contracts at the end of next year is an opportunity for the government to reorganize Macao's public transport system to raise its efficiency. In particular, the government entered the optimize bus career and lightweight lines, adjusting the operational times of the two public transport means and increasing the ease of transfer between buses and the subway.
From its perspective, according to a preliminary analysis, it will be difficult to reach the target of a daily volume of 137,000 passengers in the meter by 2030. Remembering that services for traffic issues do not yet have a detail plan relative to the west line, He stressed that, given the constant increase in the number of visitors, the government should start as soon as possible to work related to this line, shorten the construction cycle of the metro network, and transform it into a Ring format.
For the deputy, in a context where the transportation capacity of public buses "has already reached the limit" and it will be difficult to have more careers, the extension of the metro network will provide a new solution.
In addition, Leong Sun Iok lamented the lack of diversity of the electronic payment means in the Metro, so it urged to improve the payment system. On the other hand, it suggested measures aimed at raising the subway's ability to divert people while holding events in the city.
Regarding buses, the deputy proposed that, taking the metro network as the core of the public transport system, companies reinforce the “intelligent buses” as well as differentiate and adjust the careers of buses through played.
In turn, Deputy Nick Law anticipated the increase in the demand for the service of Metro with the implementation of new visa policies. Thus, it defended, in a written interplies, the updating of the electronic payment function of the input and exit access channels in the metro stations, so that the equipment corresponds to the habits of payment of the population.
As for the automatic metro selling machines, Nick Lei understands that the payment function with code code should be added. After this step, it expects electronic tickets to be launched and a mobile application to reduce the time to purchase metro tickets.
In addition, the deputy once again urged the executive to make discounts on the transfer between buses and the meter, so that more people want to use this means of transport and to maximize their effectiveness. It concretely argued that authorities should take advantage of the termination of bus contracts to advance with this work.
 
Exclusive bus careers for concerts
On the other hand, Ngan Iek Hang has proposed careers of exclusive buses that circulate between border stations and concert places. It also suggested the extension of the operational time of the subway, in order to relieve pressure on traffic in general and on the border passages.
The deputy also requested, in written interplies, more analysis of the flow of people during large -scale shows, using the authorities, for the authorities to warn visitors in advance about the traffic situation. In your opinion, during “special periods”, more manual ways should be opened at the borders and accelerated the launch of roads of border passage directed exclusively to residents.
In the same vein, Che Fok Sang, director of the Macao Federal Commercial Association of the Convention and Exhibition Industry, also proposed “Shuttle-Bus” that transport directly and free spectators from concert site for old zones. Alongside this, the executive director of the "Chessman Entertainment Production" suggested tourist scripts "concert + cultural experience" in order to stimulate the recovery of commercial establishments in ancient areas.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>21 years in prison for assistant prosecutor Kong Chi</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/21-anos-de-prisao-para-procurador-adjunto-kong-chi/</link><description>The last court aggravated from 17 to 21 years in prison the penalty applied to the deputy prosecutor Kong Chi, understanding that he also committed the crime of association or secret society
 
Kong Chi, deputy prosecutor of the suspended mandate, was sentenced yesterday by the last court (TUI) to a single sentence of 21 years in prison, in legal entity. This sentence represents an aggravation of the 17 -year sentence imposed by the Court of Second Instance (TSI) in January 2024 in a process where Kong was accused of helping people escape the court in 30 cases. At the time, it was considered guilty of dozens of crimes of passive corruption for illicit act, abuse of power, prevarication and violation of secrecy of justice.
Tui now considered that Kong Chi is also guilty of the crime of association or secret society, validating the prosecutor's thesis (MP). According to the prosecution, the main defendant will have received bribes, in collusion with the couple of entrepreneurs Choi Sao Ieng and NG Wai Chu, to interfere in several cases of criminal investigation, illegally file the proceedings and raise the property seized.
Choi and NG's penalties were also aggravated by Tui, from 14 to 16 years and six to 10 years in prison, respectively.
The MP and the three defendants filed appeals with the last instance, raising issues such as “the nullity of the decision, proof of facts, the assessment of the evidence, the prescription of criminal proceedings, the application of the law, and the measure of the penalty”, Among others, according to a note from the Tui President's office.
The appeals were partially judged in some aspects, translating namely in the prescription of a crime of passive corruption for illicit act committed by Kong and three of prevarication imputed to the three defendants. In addition, the convictions for some crimes were revoked and the typology of others were revoked.
On the other hand, TUI decided to condemn Kong for the crime of management or head of association or secret society, and the couple of entrepreneurs for participation in association or secret society. Kong was also considered guilty of two inaccuracy crimes of the elements.
The remaining decision of the TSI remained unchanged. It is recalled that the TSI also determined the loss, in favor of the MSAR, of assets arrested by the deputy prosecutor in the amount of 14 million patacas, considering them as “of unknown origin”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Suicide cases have reached peak from the last 11 years</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/casos-de-suicidio-atingiram-pico-dos-ultimos-11-anos/</link><description>There were 90 people who, last year, ended life in Macao, according to the health services monitoring data compiled by this newspaper. The number not only represents a 2.3% increase over the previous year, but also the highest, at least in the last 11 years. Only between October and December 2024, there were 25 people who died this way, a 19% rise in quarterly terms
 
Catarina Pereira
 
A total of 90 people ended life in Macao last year - this is the highest number at least in the last 11 years reveal the data on the monitoring of health services (SSM) compiled by this newspaper. The causes of suicide “are complex”, underlines the government organism, adding that “often involve mental illness, psychological, socioeconomic, family, human relations and biological genetic factors”.
The nine dozens of cases recorded in 2024 represent a 2.3% increase compared to 2023, when 88 people ended life. Retracting to 2018, we can observe a number not far from this: there were 81 people who committed suicide. Moreover, since 2013 the number of these cases has always been around six or seven dozen per year. Looking at the latest years, 80 people died this way in 2022, in 2021 had been 60, in 2020, 76 and in 2019, a pre-pound year, were 66.
The body led by Alvis Lo yesterday made public statistics of the fourth quarter of last year, with the data to realize that, in the last three months of 2024, 25 suicides were committed. There were four more cases or an increase of 19% over the previous quarter, when 21. Between January and March, 22 cases of suicide were reported, and between April and June were 22.
Of the 25 people who committed suicide in the last months of the year, 17 were men and eight women, aged 13 to 75. Of these, most (20) were residents of Macau (80%) and five were tourists. Unlike previous quarters, in this case there was no reference to cases of non -residents.
According to the authorities' analysis, the possible causes of suicides recorded between October and December were “mainly resulting from mental illness and emotional, financial or game-related problems”, read the press release.
According to the World Health Organization, more than 720,000 people around the world die every year for suicide, which is the third leading cause of death among young people from 15 to 29 years old.
SSM warns that effective suicide prevention requires everyone's attention. "To reduce the incidence of suicide, residents should contact, communicate and worry more about the people around them, their daily lives and encourage those who have emotional problems to actively seek professional help," they advise.
It is also said that SSM "have attributed more resources to continuously improve accessibility to mental health services." With the entry into operation of the Mental Health Service at the Inner Porto Health Center, residents can make the prior marking at TAP Seac Health Centers, Fai Chi Kei, Sand Black, Green Island, Ocean Gardens , from Nossa Senhora do Carmo - Lake, Manduco Beach, Seac Pai Van and Porto Interior, without the need for a transfer letter.
Authorities also underline that they grant financial and technical support to associations such as the General Union of residents' associations and the General Association of Women to create community psychological counseling entities, “being committed to promoting and deepening defenders to prevent suicide. In the community, in order to improve the early identification of the risk of suicide by the public. ”
In addition, they reiterate that they “reinforce the formation of community health doctors about mental health knowledge and diagnostic and treatment techniques, in order to integrate specialized mental health services in the community health system”.
The SSM appeals to all those who are “emotionally distressed and desperate” to call the open line “Life of Caritas” (28525222) to obtain emotional counseling services.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy Arena receives Andrea Bocelli in March</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/arena-galaxy-recebe-andrea-bocelli-em-marco/</link><description>Andrea Bocelli, one of the most famous tenores in the world, will give a concert at the Galaxy Macau arena on March 29 at 20:00, the Galaxy Entertainment announced yesterday. The Italian singer will be returned to Macau almost nine years after acting in the opening gala of Wynn Palace in August 2016.
With over 90 million albums sold and over 16 billion streams, 66 -year -old Andrea Bocelli is the most selling artist in the classic genre, stressed the Galaxy, recalling that Celine Dion even classified Tenor as “ Voice of God ”. Over the course of 30 years of career, Andrea Bocelli stood out for her ability to mix Italian, opera and pop folk music, and has achieved great international success, including her unforgettable duet with Sarah Brightman in “Time to Say Goodbye”, which led to German singles table for an impressive 14 weeks. His talent was also very evident when he collaborated with Celine Dion in "The Prayer" and "Vivo Per Lei."
True Italian culture ambassador, Bocelli attracted worldwide attention in 2020 with his event “Music For Hope”, which became one of the biggest live musical performances, also participating in the “Lady Gaga's One World: Together at Home” concert. , along with stars like Lady Gaga, Celine Dion, Lang Lang and John Legend to spread messages of love and hope during the challenging times of the covid-19 pandemic. In addition to numerous concerts, including iconic monuments, he acted in major events, including the opening ceremony of the 2020 European Football Championship at the Beijing 2022 Winter Olympics, and at the inauguration of the “World Expo” in 2010, 2015 and 2021. In 2021, he was also invited to the CCTV New Year gala.
Tickets for the concert “will be available soon,” said the Galaxy, without advance prices. The concert is organized by NGE Arts &amp; Culture Company Limited.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourist itineraries contest attracted 186 works</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/concurso-de-itinerarios-turisticos-atraiu-186-trabalhos/</link><description>“Visiting and Learning” was the name chosen by tourism services for a contest on the conception of itineraries. The initiative received a total of 186 proposals, having been selected 10 in each of the two groups, addressed to students and candidates in general
 
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) launched last year the contest for conception of itineraries “Visit and Learning” intended to encourage students and the general public to create scripts, taking advantage of the tourist resources of Macao, capable of enriching knowledge and Experiences in a format of “teaching and learning with tour”.
In order to boost the development of “Tourism + Education”, the contest received a total of 186 proposals, including 69 in the category of students and 117 of the general group. 20 works were awarded, divided by a dozen in each of the categories, including gold, silver and bronze awards, and attributed seven honorable mentions.
The jury, consisting of representatives of STD and co-organizing entities, evaluated projects according to the theme, creativity, learning and viability. In the first phase the work was classified based on the information of the proposals presented by the participants, in which it resulted the selection of the 10 works with the highest score of each group.
Competitors found for the second phase also made a brief presentation and explanation of the proposals, to allow the jury a further and comprehensive assessment. Upon completion of the second phase, the winners of gold, silver and bronze were selected, and seven honorable mentions of each category.
In the student group, the gold prize receives 10,000 patacas, while silver and bronze are contemplated with 7,500 and 5,000 patacas respectively. As for honorable mentions, they are distinguished with the 3,000 patacas prize.
In the general group, 20,000 patacas is the amount attributed to the winner, followed by 15,000 and 10,000 patacas for silver and bronze, respectively. Honorable mentions receive 6,000 patacas.
The awards ceremony will be held during the 13th International Tourism Expo (Industry) of Macao, in April. The list of selected is available on the STD page.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Strain “supports” mashed integration in the country</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cepa-apoia-integracao-da-raem-pais/</link><description>Tai Kin IP considers that the new version of the Cepa agreement “demonstrates the continuous widening of the degree of liberalization from the interior of China to the MSAR, constituting a concrete practice of the country in promoting the opening to the high level outside”
 
The secretary for the economy and finances defended yesterday that the change to the agreement on trade in cepha II between the interior of China and Macau “demonstrates the continuous widening of the degree of liberalization from the interior of China to the masters, constituting a concrete practice from the country in promoting high -level opening. ” For Tai Kin IP, it also represents "a significant measured measure to support the integration of masters in the conjuncture of national development."
In a clarification session on the subject, the ruler said the agreement "contains many prominent points", including the reduction of access requirements for Macao service providers and the elimination of the exercise requirement at least three years of Substantial commercial activity in the territory, “so that startups can benefit as soon as possible from the preferential treatment provided for in the strain”. He also noted supports the choice of Macao capital companies that registered in the pilot cities of the Great Bay, the law of Macao as an applicable contractual law, thus creating even broader spaces for the development of legal professionals.
On the other hand, he stressed that “new liberalization measures are added to the sectors of state, financial, audiovisual and cultural technology services, among others”. In the view of Tai Kin IP, the measures "not only will provide new opportunities and spaces for the development of the proper diversification of the economy of Macao." They will offer greater facilities for professionals in the areas of construction, accounting, medical treatment, education to develop careers in the interior of China, which will provide “more favorable conditions for the integration of the various sectors of the Macao community at the large conjuncture of national development” .
The Change II Agreement II will come into force on 1 March. The secretary assured that the Executive of the MSAR will continue to maintain a “close communication and cooperation” with the Ministries and Commissions of the State, “congregating the efforts of all social sectors for use Effective preferential measures granted by the central government to Macau, including the strain. ”
At the clarification session, which was attended by more than 380 people, the department director for the matters of Taiwan, Hong Kong and Macao of the RPC Ministry of Commerce, Fan Shijie, was present. According to an official note, he said that the country has been “relieving restrictions on access to the Macao market, reinforcing the articulation of the rules of both territories, in order to boost economic and commercial cooperation for a new level”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More elderly people receive in March keys from the residence</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-idosos-recebem-em-marco-chaves-da-residencia/</link><description>Next month, the elderly will receive the keys of the apartment in the residence for the elderly, indicated yesterday Hon Wai, adding that, after this stage, the number of residents in that space will increase to about nine hundreds
 
More elderly people who applied for the government's residence in the first phase will receive the keys of the apartments in March, yesterday indicated the president of the Institute of Social Action (IAS). According to Hon Wai, after the Chinese New Year there were more elderly people who moved to the residence, so, after the Chaves' assignment stage next month, the number of users of that building will rise to about 900.
The second round of applications ended on the 14th of this month, with Hon Wai indicating that 483 applications were received, involving about 600 elderly people. The president of IAS said that the body will evaluate the data presented and verify the self -care capacity, providing to complete these works "in a short term".
Hon Wai said he already communicated with the condominium management company and residents to develop fire simulations, among other safety work. According to the Chinese language press, he also guaranteed that so far IAS has no longer received complaints related to the stench problem by the northern avenue of the Hippodrome.
Even so, he continued, some residents insist on requesting the exchange of fraction due to family concerns or factors. For this reason, said Hon Wai, IAS will follow the situations and "will try to collaborate as much as possible with the will of residents." The president of IAS also stressed that these cases "represent a minority."
In relation to the special subsidy within the “Inclusion and Harmony Program in the Community”, he pointed out that the presentation of applications ended yesterday. At each stage, about 5,000 families ask for this support and more than 11,000 people benefit from it. It also added that if the beneficiary family moves to the “new Macao neighborhood of Hengqin” could submit a request to the authorities to be subject to a new assessment.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Game disorder motivated 208 requests for help</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/disturbio-jogo-motivou-208-pedidos-de-ajuda/</link><description>The number of requests for aid from the game addiction has reached peak since 2011. Last year, IAS accounted for 208 individuals, a 23% rise in annual terms. The data provided by the House of Firm Will show that the serious and moderate cases have grown, unlike those of light degree
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Requests for gaming addiction help seem to give signs of growth. In 2024, the disorders caused by the game originated 208 requests for help from the Institute of Social Action (IAS), a 23% increase over the previous year. The number not only represents an annual climb but also the highest since there are records.
The data, released by the House of Firm will based on the central registration system of individuals affected by this disturbance, trace the scenario of the problem in the territory since 2011.
Statistics show that, in the period under analysis, there was an increase in cases considered serious and moderate. Almost half of the individuals (about 47%) signaled by IAS suffered from moderate game addiction, a rise of more than three percentage points.
Those who had a serious level of addiction to the game accounted for 34% of the total, almost two more percentage points than a year earlier. The slight degree thus affected almost 13% of people who resorted to the government organism to ask for help, denoting a break of more than five percentage points.
But what led these people to play? The reasons can be varied, and a person can be led to play for one or more conjugated reasons. According to the data now published, the “resolution of financial difficulties” was the most pointed out (24%), as in the previous year, despite a break. The “entertainment” (20%) and “disagreeing” (19%) followed.
The volume of debt players suffered a break from more than five percentage points to about 72%. Regarding the amount of debt, the cases in which it is between 100 and 250 thousand patacas descended from 24% to 19%, a trend equally verified in cases of debts of more than 250 thousand and less than 500 thousand patacas. In this case, they descended from about 15% to 11%. Also in the lowest value debts (between 50 thousand and 100 thousand patacas) registered a break, from 11% to approximately 9%.
The most popular choice among players continued to fall on Bachará, with 49% pointing him as the most played. Note that the proportion of players who played “SIC PO CUSSEC” grew from about 5%to 6%, while those who bet on soccer and basketball games remained about 7%. On the other hand, the poker/mocha machines were less used, having descended from about 8% to 5%.
 
The player's profile
Most players affected by addiction and recorded over the past year were BIR. In the same line of previous years, men continued to be the most affected by this problem (80%), with the average ages to be set in 40 years.
The game's disorder affected single and married single ones in the same proportion, with the former to feel the problem more. In addition, 56% said they had family members who usually bet.
Regarding the work situation, a large part (72%) was employed, and there was a descent compared to 2023. Of those who said they had work, about 2% were Croupiers, while 4% had work related to game industry. In addition, 17% said they work for shifts.
In the opposite direction, the cases of student, domestic or retired students have increased, representing 16% of the total. Looking at 2023, they didn't reach 12%. As for the unemployed, which made 13% last year, there was also a rise compared to the 11% of the previous year.
The firm willpower was created in late 2005 to provide advice to individuals affected by the problems of game addiction and their families and, through community prevention actions, reduce the possible consequences they caused.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Discussed impact of national security on legal practice</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/discutido-impacto-da-seguranca-nacional-na-pratica-juridica/</link><description>The Faculty of Law of the University of Macao brought together 40 legal experts on the continent, for a seminar on the “evolution and impact of the National Security Act: interaction between the legal systems in the interior of China, Hong Kong and Macao”. The event aimed to analyze the evolution of the National Security Law and its importance for legal practice in the Great Bay. The debate was divided into three thematic sessions, featuring presentations of guardians from various universities, namely Gansu, Tsinghua Zhongnan, Wuhan, Shenzhen and Sun Yat-Sen. Experts spoke, among other matters, of the evolution of the China National Security Law and the application of the certificate system for cases related to that diploma. The event also included lectures on the relationship between the Hong Kong National Security Act and the Basic Law, as well as the rule of law in an international context. One of the MSAR representatives, Xue Wechao, from the University of Science and Technology, explored the interaction between the criminal provisions of the Macao National Security Act and criminal law in general, while Lok Wai Kin, emeritus professor at the University of Macao, did A presentation on systematic education in the domain of national security in the territory. At the closing session, Li Juqian, director of the Hong Kong, Macau and Taiwan Cabinet at China University of Political Sciences and Law, stressed that the seminar represented “an important academic support for the strengthening of the rule of law in Grande Bay".</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Banks increased international assets</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/bancos-aumentaram-activos-internacionais/</link><description>The percentage of financial investments in international markets in the total active of the Macao banking system reached 83.4% in late December, plus 0.1 points in three months. International responsibilities in the total liability of the banking system rose from 80.5% to 80.9%, according to data from the Monetary Authority (AMCM). At the end of December, the total of the international assets of local banks grew 0.4% to 2,010.4 billion patacas for the previous quarter. AMCM highlights the 3.5% growth in offices on the outside (1,499.2 billion) and a decrease of 7.6% in local assets in foreign currencies (511.2 billion). Loans of non-banking entities on the outside, which constituted most international assets, increased by 18.8%, setting by 536.9 billion patacas. The total international responsibilities of the bank sector reached 1,952.1 billion patacas, signaling an increase of 0.8% compared to the registered rate three months earlier. In turn, the responsibilities of abroad reached 1,013.1 billion (plus 3.9%), while internal responsibilities in foreign currencies recorded a break from 2.2% to 939 billion in the same time. Deposits in foreign residents' foreign currencies in local banks represent the largest component in the total of international responsibilities, rising 3% to 722.6 billion. According to AMCM, Macao International Bank Activity continues to distribute it mainly through Asia. At the end of 2024, the quotas of the Macao banking system availability in the interior of China and Hong Kong equivalent to 39.5% and 24.2%, respectively, in the total of exterior assets. The quotas of availability in Lusophone countries and nations integrated in the initiative “One Range, a Route” occupied 0.6% and 12.1%.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2346/</link><description>Chief creates working groups to raise public management level
The head of the Executive of the MSAR signed an internal order with a view to creating two “leadership groups” on the reform of public administration and the promotion of the construction of the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin, which will be headed by Sam Hou Fai himself. In addition, the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, will lead two coordination groups, one of the Public Administration reform and another for the legal area, and a working group on embellishment and urban cleaning. These five working groups will “intensify intersectory and interdepportal collaboration, striving to raise the capacity and level of public management of MSAR”, as well as “promote the leadership and coordination mechanism of public administration reform”, according to Refers to a statement issued by the Social Communication Office. In addition, they will focus on “coordination and planning of legislative production and the improvement of the legal system”, and foster a “positive interaction between administration and the legislative body”. The Chief Executive also intends that the working groups will take full advantage of the country's support policies to promote the high quality achievement of the objective and a task defined for the second phase of the construction of the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin With innovative and proactive spirit and thinking, and improve the system and regime of guaranteeing and improving social welfare ”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Retreat at the Ká-Hó Church served as a test for the restoration of activities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/retiro-na-igreja-de-ka-ho-serviu-de-teste-para-reinicio-de-actividades-2/</link><description>The Church of Our Lady of Sorrows, in Ká-Hó, will reactivate its religious and pastoral activities as early as March, after a period of little dynamism. On the weekend, Friday, Saturday and Sunday, will take place three masses, whose times are not yet defined. In addition, the Diocese of Macau will highlight a priest to daily serve the faithful for confessions and guide the worship of the Blessed Sacrament. The first experience of revitalizing the chapel and the surrounding area was done through a retreat that had more than 70 people. Some participants consider that the site has all the conditions to become a kind of "sanctuary" and a reflection space. Father Daniel Ribeiro stressed to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau that “formerly Ká-Hó took care of sick with leprosy and physical problems”, and “now will work the soul of people”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The first experience by the Diocese of Macao to revitalize religious and pastoral activities in the Church of Our Lady of Sorrows in Ká-Hó, Coloane, was considered a success. The retreat, in Portuguese, held last Saturday, from morning until late afternoon, brought together more than 70 faithful, many of which belonging to the Congregation of Our Lady of Sorrows, who participated in a mass presided by Father Daniel.
In addition to the religious act, which took place at 16h00, the retreat had periods of formation, prayer, via sacred and worship of the Blessed Sacrament. One of the objectives was also to provide healthy conviviality among the people who responded to the diocese's call to mark the restart of activities, beyond a Christian reflection that was associated with him, on a day of spirituality.
From mid -March, the revitalization of events in the church and the surrounding area will be a reality. The activities will take place every day, with the presence of a priest-still named by D. Stephen Lee, bishop of the Diocese-who will receive every morning the faithful who want to confess from Monday to Friday, so How will the worship of the Blessed Sacrament guide.
On the weekend, from Friday to Sunday, three masses will be held, one of which may be in Chinese language, with times that will be defined by the end of February.
“We are studying the best times, that is, those who can have more people,” Father Daniel Ribeiro told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau.
In addition, pastoral activities will be organized in the nearby institutions, both at the Rehabilitation Hospital and at the Santa Ana Sisters Convent, or at the Hold on To Hope. “In the latter case we have not yet failed with the Macao toxicode dependent Rehabilitation Association), but it is one of our ideas for making events more often, which will have the responsibility of the congregation of the Fathers of the Sacred Heart of Jesus (Dehonians), ”says the priest.
However, remodeling works are being done in the house adjacent to the church, which should end at the end of March. In this housing, essentially oriented activities will be developed.
 
Some emotions
among the faithful
Father Daniel Ribeiro recalls that "formerly Ká-Hó took care of sick with leprosy and physical problems and now it will be a place where the soul of people will work," those who have depression, fear, who feel alone. " Therefore, “the place will be open all day,” he reinforces.
About the retreat, the vicar considers it to have been very positive, with good adherence from people, and states that "Ká-Hó is a very pleasant place where Macao people have a very large respect and consideration." In this context, he notes, "many of those who were thrilled there."
The ecclesiastical believes that this revitalization of activities, especially the presence of a priest every day and the accomplishment of masses to the weekend, will constitute "a source of blessing for many people in Macau".
One of the faithful who participated in the retreat confided to JTM that the space of Ká-Hó “has all the conditions to become a kind of sanctuary and reflection”, since it is in a quiet zone, involved in nature.
Another similar retreat is already scheduled for March 15th.
 
Dedicated church
to the protector of the sick
The history of the Church of Our Lady of Sorrows is indissolibly linked to the lepers who lived in Ká-Hó and Father Gaetano Nicosia, rising on the slope of the Ká-Hó hill on Coloane Island.
Built in 1966, during the bishopric of Dom Paulo José Tavares and was supported by Pope Paul VI, the government of Macao and the local diocese, it was intended to serve the religious needs of the village of Ká-Hó, where, at that time, They lived the families of healed lepers and some new patients with this terrible illness. Hence, the Church was dedicated to Our Lady of Sorrows, the protector of the sick.
The Nossa Senhora das Dores Church was the first projected in Macao according to the new concepts of religious architecture introduced after the Second Vatican Council (1961-65), so its inner space reflects the changes of the liturgy implemented during this Council , being conceived as a large hall, with the high altar positioned to the center of the assembly and focused on the faithful, as an amphitheater, establishing a closer relationship between these and the priest.
It has the shape of a great tent and, by the desire of Father Nicosia, has 13 doors that symbolize Jesus Christ and his twelve apostles. Its conception, in a modernist style, was by Italian engineer and sculptor Francisco Messina, and also had the contribution of Leopoldo Goffredo Acenci, another transalpino sculptor and his construction of contractor Oso Acconci.
As it turned out before, your altar is not placed in the back of the church, but on one side, so that it had seven doors on one side and six on the other. It is therefore known as the 'odd -doors church'.
In turn, the coverage consists of eight sets of diagonal beams that, in addition to structural function, symbolically divide the Church into seven sections, evoking the 'Seven Pain of Our Lady of Sorrows'. Outside his north door has a magnificent bronze crucifix, by Francisco Messina, who also conceived the church's bronze bell.
Construction is an authentic logistics challenge. In fact, the materials had to be transported by boat to Coloane, as there were no terrestrial roads that made the connection with the Macau Peninsula and, in addition, the church zone was separated from the village, because the workers, many of which They lived in Ká-Hó during the construction, were afraid that the lepers approach.
The church is classified by the Macao government as a building of architectural interest.
 
Father Nicosia improved
THE LIFE OF LEPEROS
About Father Gaetano Nicosia, undoubtedly one of the great workers of the work done at Ká-Hó leprosy, the ecclesiastical began his mission in Hong Kong in 1935 when he was only 20 years old. Eleven years later, he was ordained a priest at the São José Seminary Church in Macao, joining the Society of St. Francis of Sales (Salesians). He began to preach in China, but wanted his mission to be among the poorest, including lepers, as he had promised Jesus Christ when he was young.
His superior Salesian then intended to send him to a leproseria in Colombia, when the bishop of Macao asked for help from the leper colony on Coloane's island.
He definitely moved to Macao in 1958, having lived in the village and Ká-Hó between 1963 and 2011. Under the proposal of Gaetano Nicosia, the place of leprosaria was called the 'village of Our Lady'.
When he arrived at the leper colony in Ká-Hó, the priest came across a catastrophic situation. Due to the serious illness that they suffered and the almost total abandonment they were targeted, the suicide rate among the lepers was high, there was no drinking water or electricity, hygiene was virtually nonexistent, only from time to time received a visit from a visit Doctor and the foods were few.
The Italian developed all efforts to improve the living conditions of the lepers of Ká-Hó and, thanks to their long and continuous work for 48 years, has achieved many of them recovered and reinstated in society, despite the associated social stigma To this disease, having become known as the 'Angel of the Leperstos'.
In Macao, the lepers were welcomed in a hospice in the São Lazarus neighborhood (Macau), built by Bishop Dom Belchior Carneiro, in the mid -16th century and was funded by the Holy House of Mercy of Macao.
Already in the late nineteenth century, in view of the expansion of the city of Macao, a separation of lepers was made, and men were taken to a 'leper deposit' in Pac Sá Lan, on the island of São João (today , Mountain Island or Hengqin), initially being in very fragile dwellings that were destroyed by a typhoon in 1883, and then, more solid houses were built to your welcome.
Despite the stigma of leprosy, this was not an impediment for the sick to be a frequent target of pirate attacks that stole their little belongings, such as rice and coins.
 
Disease separated
Men of women
In 1885, women with leprosy were placed in the five homes that were part of the Ká-Hó hospice. It was neither a simple nor peaceful process, and the authorities changed their plans several times, as the places chosen, both on the island of macao and in the Macau Peninsula (near the siege doors), were rejected by the populations of these places.
Even the Portuguese authorities of the time referred to leprosy as 'that disgusting disease' and, on behalf of public hygiene, direct medical care to lepers was very limited. In the 1930s, the doctor only visited Ká-Hó once a week and even less frequent were the medical visits to Pac Sá Lan.
The treatment of leprosy wounds was left in the hands of the smartest and most polite patients, and the construction of a building on the Macau peninsula for the treatment of some of the patients has even happened, but this never happened.
In 1929, the government began the expansion of the Ká-Hó leprosy. The new buildings, including five pavilions and a chapel designed in an eclectic architectural style, were completed in 1930, defining a road on the slope facing the sea. The pavilions were characterized by large, classic, large -inspired balconies that opened on the landscape.
The new leproseria had a capacity of 90 patients and received weekly visits from medical teams, as well as the assistance of religious organizations, including the Canossian charity sisters who settled here to provide care to the sick, as well as the inhabitants of Vila de Ká -Hó.
In 1950, men with leprosy who were in Pac Sá Lan were also taken to Ká-Hó, since there was an intention to expand the village on the island of São João, but this did not occur, because the builder of Work also contracted leprosy and disappeared to never being seen again.
The couples were not allowed to cohabitation, but, of course, the members of the couples exchanged correspondence between them. The leper community cultivated vegetables, thus being autonomous. He also received food from Macao that was left in a small beach located in the area.
Apart from these sporadic trips, they were not visited by anyone else, being the leper treated as animals and chained for fear of contagion. In the leprosy of Ká-Hó then lived about 100 lepers, abandoned to their luck and urgently need medical care.
The situation only changed with the arrival in Macao do Father Nicosia in 1958. This, with a boundless dedication, never refused to deal with these sick, despite the high risk of contagion. From there, the lepers began to receive more frequent medical assistance and the village was slowly free from leprosy.
In 2011, all inhabitants of the leprosy colony were declared healed and many of them returned to work as teachers, workers or exercising activity as independent professionals.</description><pubDate>2025-02-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Emilia Pérez’ wins the best movie bafta not English</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/emilia-perez-ganha-bafta-de-melhor-filme-em-lingua-nao-inglesa/</link><description>The Franco-Belga film “Emilia Pérez” has won the best non-English language movie statuette on the Bapta Cinematography Academy BAFTA awards, beating “I'm still here”, two weeks from the Oscars. “Emilia Pérez”, made by Jacques Audiard, a film that tells the story of a Mexican drug trafficker who undergoes gender change surgery, surpassed the feature film of Brazilian Walter Salles, set at the time of the military dictatorship (1964- 1985).
French director Jacques Audiard received the prize, saying "thrilled" and adding that "it was for all who worked tirelessly in this movie."
Audiard paid tribute to the other films nominated in the category, such as the Irish "Kneecap" and the Brazilian "I'm still here".
The French director noted that he would like to “thank the wonderful talents” who participate in the movie, citing his “dear zoe” Saldaña and Selena Gómez.
The filmmaker also mentioned the Spanish actress Karla Sofa Gasco, calling her "dear." Gascon was not present at the ceremony due to the controversy by tweets xenophobes he wrote in the past.
Moments after the award, Zoe Saldaña, 46, was awarded the best secondary actress bafta.
“It became a special character for me,” said Saldaña, adding that the fact that the film was shot in Spanish, his mother tongue, allowed him to “call me with my culture, with my art. It was significant to me, ”said the actress, of Dominican origin.
The two other named for the best non -English language film were the Indian "All We Imagine AS Light" and the Iranian "The Seed of the Sacred Fig."
The American actor Adrien Brody got the best actor of Bafta's award for his work on “The Bruly”, which tells the story of an architect who survived the Holocaust and seeks to reach the American dream.
The Best Actress Award was also American Mikey Madison for the role of a stripper in "Anora."
“I'm still here”, which has already been awarded the Best Sleeping Award at the Venice Film Festival and the Golden Globe Best Actress for Fernanda Torres, as well as the reward for best Ibero-American movie in Goya Spanish, a week ago , he left empty hands in the bafta.
The film tells the story of Eunice Paiva (played by Fernanda Torres), widow of Deputy Rubens Paiva, missing during the military dictatorship, and the couple's five children. Kidnapped by state agents in 1971, Rubens Paiva was killed in jail, but his body never appeared.
Brazil never tried the crimes of the dictatorship that, according to official figures left 202 dead, 232 missing and thousands of victims of torture and illegal arrests.
The Amnesty Law, passed in 1979 by the military regime, prevented the punishment of the culprits, although the National Truth Commission elucidated in 2012 that the state was responsible.
The film competes for Oscars, on March 2, in three categories: best film (the first Brazilian production with this appointment), best international film and best actress for Fernanda Torres.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>