<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>“Most common” electronic means in the transfer of illicit funds</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/meios-electronicos-mais-comuns-na-transferencia-de-fundos-ilicitos/</link><description>Although the “exchange of cards without/with reduced game activity” leads for the second year in a row the top of the suspicious transaction reports table, the truth is that the “use of online banks/Internet-related transactions” was the one that recorded “a more significant increase” in 2024, according to the financial information office, and 555 cases were verified. The body says it is a sign that "the transfer of illicit funds is increasingly common through electronic technology." In the general calculation, a total of 5,245 STR arrived, reflecting an annual increase of 13.7% and 78.3% compared to the pre-pound period
 
Pedro Milheirão
 
The “change of cards without/with reduced game activity” again led for the second year consecutive reports of suspicious transactions (STR, in the English acronym), totaling 1,569 cases, a 24% increase compared to 1,282 registered in 2023. According to the report of the financial information office (GIF) for 2024, the rise is proportional to the “significant increase in the number of cases of suspicious transactions in the game sector in the last two years ”.
Despite being first, it was the “use of online banks/internet -related transactions” that recorded “a more significant increase”, as the body stresses. 555 cases were counted, however, it is not possible to make a comparison with 2023, as this year this type of cases was included in the "others", along with other characteristics, such as "possible correspondence with the" Watch-List "screening system or other black lists," transactions with unknown provenance funds "and" tried, but failed transactions. "
According to the GIF, this feature was common in the STR reported by financial institutions, "reflecting that, currently, the transfer of illicit funds through electronic technology is increasingly common."
“Background transfers through check, promising notes or bank transfer,” in turn rose 29% to 599, while “suspicious electronic transfers” also rose, in this case 16% to 411. “The“ cash deposits of high amounts of origin ”increased 10 to 796.
During the last year, there were also 141 cases related “with other crimes” (+20%), ascending a total of 843. In addition, 100 cases of “use of multibanco, telephone board, cash deposits” (633) were reported than the previous year, representing an increase of 19%. In 2024, the GIF also reported 2,723 cases of “other” activities, 337 more than the previous year (2,386).
Overall, throughout the year the GIF received 5,245 STR, reflecting an annual increase of 13.7%. The increase was even more visible compared to 2019, as there was a 78.3%increase. Chu Un, GIF coordinator, an organism that is now integrated into the Unit Police Services, says in the report that the data “reflects the challenges of supervision resulting from the dynamism of Macao economic activities and demonstrate the high degree of confidence of reporting institutions in the professional capacity of GIF”.
“Despite adjusting the GIF structure, the number of suspicious transactions participations continued to grow two digits, demonstrating that the operators of the different Macau sectors have been reinforcing their awareness of the risk and sensitivity to the risk,” says Chu Un.
In particular, the number of STR from the financial sector rose 23.7% to 1,097, according to the GIF report, which considered it to be a "significant increase." The financial industry was responsible for about one fifth of reports (21%) and other institutions by 311 (5.9%).
However, most STR continued to be reported by the game industry, in a set of 3,837 (73%). In 2024, the GIF received another 406 reports from game operators (12%) than the previous year (3,431).
In 2024, a total of 142 reports were re -enhanced to the Public Prosecution Service, a 22% rise in annual terms. The GIF suspects that "some cases are related to the crime of slopping", with "the possibility that their illicit funds are transferred and bleached through the Macao financial system."
STR's main form of participation in 2024 was online, with 91% of reports (4,794) to be digitally submitted. The concessionaires submitted all their reports by this means, while the financial sector institutions sent 957 (87%).
Last year, the GIF continued to promote global optimization of the computer system and the construction of cybersecurity, “with the aim of raising the effectiveness of the analysis of financial information and responding effectively to increasingly complex security challenges”, can read in the report. Main work included, among others, the “updating of the STR online participation system”.
Perspective this year, the coordinator, Chu Un, stresses that the GIF will “build a high and solid defense line against capital bleaching [as well as] establish and improve the financial risk prevention and resolution mechanism in order to create a secure financial barrier”.
 
Information sharing and international collaboration
"Capital bleaching phenomena, terrorism financing and financing the proliferation of weapons of massive destruction are not only in a jurisdiction. Capital flows often involve various regions," the report says. According to the recommendations of the Financial Action Group (GAFI), "different jurisdictions, in addition to identifying and evaluating the risks (…) should also update them regularly to maintain the risk assessment updated."
The GIF claims to have continued “to fulfill its member duties in international organizations against capital laundering”, such as the Asia-Pacific group against capital laundering and the Egmont Group. The cabinet also believes it has established "a long -term solid base for the construction of a more efficient international financial security network."
On the other hand, and according to Gafi reviews, an intergovernmental organization that investigates capital whites and organized crime, updated in July, the MSAR is still poorly effective in the investigation, seizure of revenues and sanctions on money laundering crimes, requiring “fundamental improvements”.
Regarding the combat of money laundering associated with terrorism, reporting suspicious transactions and the application of preventive measures by financial institutions, “non -financial companies and designated professions” (DNFBP, English acronym) and “virtual asset service suppliers” (VASP), performance is moderate and the gafaf indicates that “great improvements” are needed.
By the end of the last year, the GIF has signed 33 memorandums of understanding with other financial information units from various countries and jurisdictions, including Portugal. “Cooperation mechanisms in the exchange of information” were also established, “in order to reinforce the effectiveness of preventing and combating the crime of laundering capital and related crimes,” the report says. Throughout 2024, the GIF received 48 requests for information and made 60, having received 19 occasions and made available on 17, within the scope of international cooperation.
Created in 2006, GIF is an administrative financial information unit, responsible for participating in the prevention and combating criminal activities related to capital laundering, terrorism financing and financing the proliferation of weapons of massive destruction.</description><pubDate>2025-08-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Part of the Portuguese sidewalk can be replaced in the alley of Lilau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/parte-da-calcada-portuguesa-podera-ser-substituida-beco-lilau/</link><description>The AMI is negotiating with residents and the condominium management company about a work to replace the Portuguese sidewalk pavement in Beco do Lilau with non -slip granite, with the contract with an area of ​​about 12 square meters. According to AMI, the IC has already been consulted on this proposal for optimization. To be completed, the work also requires “consensus”, presentation of the request to DSAT and “Light Verde” of the “Road Works Coordination Group”, noted the body
 
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) is planning to extend the granite floor used on the Lilau Beco Ramp to the Lancil do Passeio, linked to Rua da Barra - which means that the existing Portuguese sidewalk may disappear. The work involves an area of ​​12 square meters, and the body said that the idea is that the materials remain consistent throughout the ramp. To the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the body said that their materials already take into account the harmonization with the surrounding landscape, and at the same time allow a better non -slip effect for this street section that is going down.
According to the perspective plant sent by AMI to this newspaper, the area of ​​the work is currently fully paved with Portuguese sidewalk, and the contract then consists of replacing the Portuguese sidewalk pavement with granite. As for the Portuguese sidewalk in Largo do Lilau, AMI assured that the work will not cause any change.
It is recalled that Lilau's square and alley are part of the historic center, classified as a UNESCO World Heritage Site. For this reason, AMI stated that it had already consulted the opinion of the Cultural Institute (IC) regarding the respective optimization proposal.
When consulting another AMI plant, it is clear that, in the area of ​​the work, except a small part of the Portuguese sidewalk (not linked to Rua da Barra) that will be preserved, most of the sidewalk will be replaced by gray granite and non-slip red granite, as well as red brick that is currently being used on the side of the alley. According to AMI, all stone materials will comply with the size and colors of the existing materials there.
In this respect, he recalled, there were residents who pointed to the possibility of the vehicles skidded in rain time on the floor in the alley of Lilau, linked to Rua da Barra. Ensuring that it has been following this subject continuously - including through the use of non -slip ink for some years to improve the situation - the AMI has lamented, however, that this measure has “limited effect”.
Since the holding of the street section pavement contract involved will be an impact on the entries and exits of residents' vehicles, AMI indicated that it is currently “communicating actively” with the condominium management company and residents, to coordinate the proposal to execute the work, in order to reduce the impact on those who inhabit.
"When there is consensus, AMI will submit a request to the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT). Only after approval at the Road Works Coordination Group meeting can the concrete plans for execution of the work be implemented," said AMI.
On the same subject, in turn, the IC stated that “actively collaborates” with the respective work of IAM and had already expressed opinions in the scope of protection of cultural heritage in relation to the proposal in question. To the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the IC also indicated that, later,, along with the AMI, to proceed to further evaluate the conditions on site, studying the feasibility of the proposal of optimization.</description><pubDate>2025-08-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief exalts “spirit of resistance against Japanese aggression”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-exalta-espirito-da-resistencia-contra-agressao-japonesa/</link><description>Until September 24, the forum complex hosts a photographic exhibition about the 80th anniversary of China's victory in the Japanese aggression resistance war. At the inauguration ceremony, the chief executive argued that "we need to guide ourselves by the spirit of resistance against Japanese aggression, strengthen our belief in patriotism and love Macao", as well as "to have the wisdom of daring to change." Sam Hou Fai also highlighted the role of Macao's “compatriots” in the war. Already the director of the connecting cabinet urged all communities of Macao to “focus on boosting the economy”
 
The “Exhibition of the 80th Anniversary of the victory in the Chinese people's resistance to Japanese aggression and the anti -fascist World War” was inaugurated yesterday, organized by the Government of MSAR and patent in the complex of the Commercial Cooperation Platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries until September 24.
Prior to the visit of the exhibition guests of honor, an inauguration ceremony took place. At the time, the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, began stressing that, in the 14 years of resistance against Japanese aggression, "the Macao compatriots, permanently sharing the destination of the country, played an irreplaceable and unique role, made contributions that will be to history and wrote their own resistance epic against Japanese aggression."
In the speech, the leader of the MSAR recalled that they “reacted positively” ahead defended by the Communist Party of China, having, early in the incident of 18 September, created “enthusiastically” groups of patriotic salvation to raise funds and promote the resistance war.
Specifically, he stressed that, after the occupation of Canton and Hong Kong, despite Macau was surrounded and almost coming to an “isolated island”, thanks to his unique position and the joint efforts of all spheres of society, he became a port of shelter for hundreds of thousands of compatriots and refugees that arrived from neighboring areas and also an important channel to rescue cultural celebrities and patriots arrested in Hong. Kong, which "demonstrates the national spirit that is to face together the national crisis and remain united in good and bad times."
"The macao compatriots, consistent with the 'rise and fall of the nation to say respect to all', have become an indispensable force in the torrent of resistance," he said.
In this sense, he stressed that the realization of the exhibition aims to “remember history and pay tribute to the martyrs”, also serving as “a solemn commitment to value peace and create a great future”.
Stressing that the victory in the war was "an important turning point for the Chinese nation, from suffering to rejuvenation," Sam Hou Fai also describes victory as "an important spiritual strength for us today, in the new journey of building a large country and national revitalization."
“Given the great changes, unprecedented in the last 100 years, we need to guide ourselves by the spirit of resistance against Japanese aggression, strengthen our belief in patriotism and love Macau, inspire mission and responsibility in the New Age, have the courage to face challenges and difficulties, as well as to dare to change and be good in innovation,” he defended.
In this sense, the leader of the Macao audience for the defense of the “a country” principle and taking advantage of “two systems” to “create a new conjuncture in the midst of change and further contributing to Macao's force to national development, mutual learning between civilizations and world peace”.
Noting that the cause “a country, two systems” in Macau is entering a new phase of development, the boss assured that the celebration of the 80th anniversary of the victory in the war will be used to widely promote the national spirit, with patriotism as a core. In this respect, and citing President XI Jinping, he stressed that "the story is the best textbook and the best reflection agent."
“We will continue to perform a series of commemorative activities for the Macao compatriots, especially the younger generation, to remember the suffering and glory of the nation, remember the dedication and sacrifice of our ancestors and transform historical memory into spiritual strength to our contemporaries, inspiring the whole society to remember history and to transmit it alive from generation to generation, to join new chapters of practice. "One country, two systems" in Macao and making new contributions to national revitalization, "he said.
 
Inherit “the red genes”
In turn, the director of the Central Government's connection office in the MSAR, Zheng Xincong, pointed out that Macau was “never absent” in the War of Resistance, with “Macao compatriots” to strive “with all his heart” in national salvation, which “constitutes a vivid interpretation of patriotic sentiment and national justice”.
Zheng Xincong found that since the beginning of the year, all sectors have “actively organized” a series of activities to commemorate the ephemeris.
According to example, the exhibition encompasses the war of representative figures such as Ye Ting, Ke Lin and Xian Xinghai, the “precious collections” such as the “Special Edition of Aid” edited by the Macao's four sectors, as well as the old photographs showing participation in the war effort of groups such as the Chinese youth ambulances body, support for Macao, support for the support for the support for the support for Macao, Rescue of cultural and patriotic figures such as Fan Changjiang and Xia Yan, and the aid to the anti-Japanese activities of the Dong Jiang Column Corps, "all historical testimonies that Macao shared the joys and sufferings with the homeland."
In the same line, it also emphasized that the current and future period is “crucial” to advance the construction of a strong country and the cause of the great revitalization of the Chinese nation through modernization, arguing that performing a better development of Macao and contributing more to the construction of a strong country is an important mission of practice “one country, two systems”.
“All communities of Macao are expected to profoundly learn the spirit consecrated in President Xi Jinping's important speeches, inherit and develop the great spirit of resistance against aggression, take advantage of the 'one country, two systems' system, maintain firmly the national security and stability of Macao, focus on boosting the economy, promoting development, and constantly opening a new panorama of high quality development for the cause Country, two systems', ”said Zheng Xincong.
In addition, he added that young people are "the hope and future of Macao" and "the living force to build Macao and the nation." In this sense, it expects young locals to “inherit the red genes”, “perpetuate red blood”, firmly establish the great aspiration of participating in the strengthening of the Chinese nation, whether the builders and successors of the cause “a country, two systems”, and “let the youth shine in the construction of a strong country in the vast space of a beautiful Macao”.
Noting that the show “is not only a deep retrospective of the extraordinary times of the past, but also an aspiration and adherence to peace”, Zheng Xincong called on the public to, learning from history and looking into the future, implementing the “country, two systems” principle, to safeguard the environment of peace and development “conquered with such effort”, and “writing a new chapter in the realm of the dream together” together Chinese of great revitalization of the Chinese nation. ”
Yesterday there was also a ceremony of delivery of commemorative medals of the 80th anniversary of the ephemeris.</description><pubDate>2025-08-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Community neighborhoods will host artists from the Lusofonia Festival</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/bairros-comunitarios-vao-receber-artistas-festival-da-lusofonia/</link><description>There are still no names of invited artists for the musical activities of the Lusophony Festival, but there is a certainty of two "headwaters" for each of the Lusofonia weekends, one of which should come from Portugal again. The success of the bet on two weekends made in the 2024 edition leads to the organization to keep the event model for this year. The popular party will take place in two periods, from October 24 to 26, and from October 31 to November 2. In parallel, the Cultural Institute also organizes the meeting in Macau - Festival of Arts and Culture between China and Portuguese -speaking countries ”, which will feature a first“ show in the community ”on October 23rd, in the IAO Hon neighborhood
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The 28th edition of the Lusofonia Festival returns this year for six days, on two consecutive weekends, after the 2024 experience was considered positive by the organization of the event, in charge of the Cultural Institute (IC). The first period of the popular party will take place between October 24 and 26, and the second between October 31 and November 2, always on Friday, Saturday and Sunday, on the beach Avenue where the Taipa Museum houses are located.
Therefore, six days of celebration will be, where there will be no lack of music, popular games and matraquilhas, as well as food and drink and stands with handicrafts and other articles representing countries or regions of Lusophone expression.
The names of the artists invited to the musical shows, which constitute one of the most important parts of the festival program, have not yet been released, which should only happen at the press conference, scheduled for September.
Moreover, the associations that usually participate in the festivity already know some points of the program, after a first meeting that kept with the IC, also having details about the other event that is again promoted in parallel with the Festival of Lusofonia, which is the “Meeting in Macao - Festival of Arts and Culture between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”, also under the same Session of the IC and will be released in the same presentation. Lusophony Festival.
According to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau, the model of the two events remains virtually unchanged compared to previous years, varying only the names of artists who will participate in the musical shows. The budget will be equally similar to the past edition.
For Lusophony, there will be 10 solo interpreters, in band, or traditional dance and singing groups, divided into the same number by the two weekends, and there will be two “head of carta”, one for each party period, on Saturday night, and one of them must come from Portugal, as has happened usually. In 2024 came Fernando Daniel and 2023 Carlão, with the expectation of being able to come in 2025 a singer.
JTM knows that there are some strong names on the table, which are being negotiated, but there is no final decision yet. It should be noted that the artists who will come abroad will join several musicians from Macau, many of whom, with a lot of experience, have added quality to the festival's musical shows program.
In addition to Portugal and Macao, nine more countries or Lusophone regions will be represented in the shows to take place at the amphitheater of houses in the museum, in the afternoon and evening. They are: Brazil, Angola, Mozambique, Cape Verde, Guinea Bissau, Equatorial Guinea, Sao Tome and Principe, East Timor and Goa Damão and Diu. Some of these groups will be made up of bands.
Following the same system of previous years, IC will take advantage of the presence in Macao of artists invited to the Lusophony Festival, to also monetize them in the “Traditional Music and Dance Shows in the community”, integrated into the “Meeting between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”.
Thus, four of those who will come to the first period of the festivity, except for the “headlof”, as this will only give a concert, will be displayed in places of the already chosen city. One of these stages will be installed in the Iao Hon neighborhood, with the first scheduled performance for the eve of the Lusophony festival, October 23, between 18:30 and 21h00.
A group of traditional dances from China, Guangdong Province, will accompany the other artists in the 23rd show, repeating the performance on 30 October, as will be present at the opening ceremony of the Lusophony Festival and the meeting, on the 24th, Friday, at 19h00, at Taipa Museum Houses.
For the remaining exhibitions in the community, the organization has also decided the places where the public can watch the events: Leisure Zone of the Lok Yeong Fa Yuen Building, next to Lam Mau, and in the side spaces of Jardim Cidade das Flores, in Taipa. Last year, the places went to the Carmo Fair and the ruins of São Paulo.
Regarding the programming of the meeting, several activities are planned, beyond the musical shows, such as exhibitions, cinema and a book fair.</description><pubDate>2025-08-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 100,000 affected by “Kajiki” in Haião</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/mais-de-100-mil-afectados-pelo-kajiki-em-hainao/</link><description>Typhoon Kajiki, the 13th climate phenomenon of this type this year, affected more than 100,000 people when hitting the island of Haião, the local press reported yesterday.
The typhoon crossed the coastal zone of Sanya's tourist city on Sunday, in the southern region of the island, and then headed towards the center of Haião, affecting 102,500 people, according to a provisional balance released by Chinese state news agency Xinhua.
The firefighters performed rescues, removed objects and trees, and performed cleaning work in various areas following rain and strong winds.
According to the media, there are no reports of tuft victims, which caused damage to roads, water supply systems, electrical and communication installations in various cities, as well as falling trees and floods in some zones.
In addition to mobilizing 10,000 military personnel, police units and fire -fighting teams, Chinese provincial authorities have sent more than 770,000 emergency lots to support flood control efforts and clean roads in severely affected areas.
In Lingshui County and in the city of Sansha, fallen trees and matches blocked road sections for part of the day.
According to Xinhua, the province was resuming public transportation, with Sanya Phoenix International Airport to return to normal operations, as well as the three main ports of Haikou, the province's capital.
The city suspended classes, work, public transport and maritime trips, and ordered the closure of some tourist destinations, following the warning issued by the Chinese national meteorological center, which included the withdrawal of more than 20,000 residents.
 
More than 30 thousand taken from home in Vietname
The typhoon then headed towards the central and northern coastal regions of Vietname, from where tens of thousands of inhabitants were removed yesterday as the typhoon “Kajiki” was preparing to reach the center of the country, with winds of about 160 kilometers per hour.
About 325,500 people from five coastal provinces would be to be removed for temporary shelters in schools and public buildings, authorities said.
The center of Vinh, a coastal city in the center of the country, was flooded at night. In the morning, the streets were practically deserted and most shops and restaurants were closed, with traders and residents protected them with sandbags.
At dawn, about 30,000 people had been removed from the region and 16,000 military personnel were mobilized. Two domestic airports were closed and all fishing boats were on the Typhoon's path were called back to Porto.
In Vietnam, more than 100 people have died or are missing due to natural disasters in the first seven months of 2025, according to the Ministry of Agriculture. Economic losses were estimated at more than $ 21 million.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-08-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 30,000 joined the promotion of national games</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-de-30-000-aderiram-a-promocao-dos-jogos-nacionais/</link><description>Performing the activity “National Games at Your Door” for the preparatory cabinet for the organization of the Macao Competition Zone of the 15th edition of the National Games and Special Olympic Games for the disabled.



The release of the national games had another series of activities, which attracted about 30,000 citizens and tourists. The objective of the organization's organizing committee is to create a “vibrant” environment throughout the city
 
Several places from Macau received another event promoting the National Games of the Popular Republic of China, a competition that will have some events in the territory this year next December.
In order to “deepen the attention and knowledge of the public, increase the participation and support of all citizens and tourists, creating a sports city atmosphere for the entire population”, the preparatory cabinet for the organization of the Macao Competition Zone of the 15th edition of the National Games, the 12th edition of the National Games with disabilities and 9th edition of the special national Olympic Games. community zones.
The events had the platform of the Mong Tak building, the Jardim da Areia Preta, the leisure zone of the northern Fai Chi Kei, the Macao Science Center, the Rotound of Carlos da Maia and the roundabout of the Taipa Stadium.
In those places, game stalls were installed, allowing the public to try different sports. In addition, children and adults had the opportunity to take photographs, “so they can keep good memories,” according to the text widespread by the preparatory cabinet.
The Promotional Action Program also included the presence in the city center of the “Xiyangyang and“ Lerongrong ”mascots, which interacted with citizens.
Since its first achievement, in June of this year, the activity “Together in the National Games - National Games at its Door” has attracted the participation of more than 30,000 citizens and tourists, corresponding to the slogan “National Games, we will all participate” to create “a vibrant environment” for the entire city and welcome the great sporting event that will take place at the end of the year.
The 2025 National Games will take place for the first time in three different regions, Macau, Hong Kong and Guangdong. The organization of five modalities, namely table tennis, three basketball, five (U-18 male), volleyball (female adults) and karate, as well as two Badminton competitions in the special Olympics for the disabled.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-08-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Macao Week” brings tourist offer to Wuhan</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/semana-de-macau-leva-oferta-turistica-wuhan/</link><description>Jianghan Guan Wuhan Square (photo file)



Under the great promotion of the “Macao Week in Wuhan, Hubei”, which will take place between September 5 and 8, STD will promote a series of activities to show the “rich elements” of “Tourism+” from Macao, including tourist promotions of more than 26 million Patacas presented by tourist operators, themed maping video lighting, macaense -theme buffet, macaense showers and Portuguese and Contact Stock Exchange between Hubei and Macau
 
Between September 5 and 8, the great promotion of “Macao Week in Wuhan, Hubei” will take place at Jianghan Guan Square in Wubei, the capital of Hubei province. According to the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), the event aims to promote the “rich elements” of “Tourism+” of Macau with residents of that city to “attract visitors from the interior of China to visit and consume in Macau, to experience the diversity of festivals and events, to promote the tourism economy”.
It is recalled that since 2020, the “Macao Week” face-to-face tourist promotion event has been held in 10 cities, including Beijing, Shanghai, Tianjin and Xi'an. According to STD, the events “Macao Week” attracted the participation of a total of about six million people. On the other hand, the body noted that last year, Hubei's number of visitors increased by 11%in annual terms, "demonstrating the potential of the market." In addition, he noted that the direct flight between Wuhan and Macau and the "convenient transport" through the high -speed railway to Zhuhai contribute to "the deepest development of bilateral cooperation in the areas of tourism, economy and commerce."
He said, the “Macao Week in Wuhan” has the participation of various public services from MSAR, six game operators, tour operators and commercial associations, among others.
On September 5, the opening ceremony will take place, with the presentation of a major street promotion in Jianghan Guan Square, which will take place for four consecutive days. One of the highlights is that tourist operators will present tourist promotions of the total value of more than 26 million Renminbis, including “tourist products with their own characteristics”, such as airplane tickets, hotel accommodation, restoration, among others, on street promotion stand and through “precision marketing” on online travel agencies.
At the same time, the event will feature different thematic zones, with a “rich range” of tourism, commerce, cultural and creative industries, sport and entertainment, indicates that, at the event site, an activity will also be organized to take photographs, through which the public can take photographs to collect stamps and look for a “colorful egg” in an installation with a guide headlal design installation. “Lucky Lighthouse” to exchange for memories.
On the other hand, between September 2 and 8, will be projected on the four banks of the two laughs (Yangtze River and Han River), which cross Wuhan, thematic lighting shows, taking advantage of the “Yangtze River Light Show”, the most emblematic of Wuhan, to attract the attention of residents and visitors.
At the same time, during the event, a 3D Mapping Video Show will be offered at Jianghan Guan Square, with three -dimensional projection in the building structure, to “show the synergy between Macau and Wuhan, UNESCO creative cities in the area of ​​gastronomy and design,” said STD.
Another highlight is the gastronomic promotion, and this time, STD, in cooperation with SJM, organizes a culinary program. Between September 5 and October 8, at Hotel Wanda Reign Wuhan, a macanese and Portuguese themed buffet will be served to invite Wuhan's residents to “feel Macao for the taste buds”.
On September 4, a special session for the media and a gastronomic dinner is held in advance, which has the participation of renowned cooking chiefs. These will preside over to the Macaense and Portuguese Food Thematic Dinner and will present culinary demonstrations, “actively spreading Macau's profile as UNESCO Creative City in Gastronomy”.
In addition, taking advantage of the opportunity, there will be a Macao Tourism Promotion Seminar, Contact Scholarship between Hubei and Macau, and convention and exhibition session between Macau and Hengqin (Wuhan Stop) in 2025, among other activities, to “further promote cooperation between Macau, Hubei and Hengqin, deepening the pragmatic exchange in tourism, conventions and conventions, and convention Exhibitions, Economics and Commerce, among others ”, presents the STD, also referring that the event will be held in conjunction with online promotions on various fronts.</description><pubDate>2025-08-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Mirra Urbana” presents 20 works by Leong Kit Man</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mirra-urbana-apresenta-20-obras-de-leong-kit-man/</link><description>Spices: Schisandra Chinensis



An exhibition of Gongbi painting “Mirra Urbana”, by artist Leong Kit Man, will be inaugurated tomorrow at the Rui Cunha Foundation. The show features 20 pieces from an art known for the detail the thorough brush, including the “Spices of Soul” series, inspired by the Rota da Rota Trade of Rota da
 
Two dozen gongbi painting pieces, art known for the detail The thorough brush, created by Leong Kit between 2024 and 2025, will be exhibited at the Rui Cunha Foundation Gallery (FRC) from tomorrow. The opening is scheduled for 18:30.
Named “Urban Mirra”, the show includes three sets of work, one of which is “Spices of Soul”, inspired by the Rota da Seda spices, which gives life to branches, shoots and fruits full of vitality and painted in silk.
“Innemost”, which recently gained recognition in various art fairs and collections, addresses the oppressive emotions of urban life, with the aim of nourishing the souls of city through small works of art.

Spices: Cinnamon

The other series, "Daily Apps", focuses on the reflection on the electronic decline of urban life, portraying "Scroll" and usual navigation driven by muscle memory. In this case, “fingers often manipulate electronic applications icons and symbolize toxic addiction that drains personal contemplation”, read in the HRA text.
According to the artist, these Gongbi creations reflect from “personal feelings to complex images, as well as the thoughts about life and the challenges of living in an agitated urban environment”. Through art, the author wants to "achieve a calm mind like water and reach a state of serenity."
Leong Kit Man has a degree in Fine Arts from the National Academy of Arts of China and currently performs the position of Assistant Professor of Fine Arts (and advisor of Master and Doctoral Students) at the Faculty of Humanities and Arts of the University of Science and Technology of Macao.
It has a vast experience in the creation of oriental supports, art teaching, exhibition planning, artistic projects and speakers' formation, “always dedicated to research and reflection on the essence and form of artistic creation,” says the FrC.
Over years of creative practice, Leong Kit Man not only inherited the techniques of Gongbi painting, but also continually developed a characteristic visual language. His key work, “Embrace of Love”, was highlighted as a project funded by the Young Talent Support Program of Artistic Creation of the 2024 National Arts Fund.
Among other distinctions, his works include selected pieces, three times in a row, for the China National Art Exhibition, and for the “Ten Best Excellent Works” at Macao's Annual Exhibition of Visual Arts on three occasions. The artist was also curator of numerous exhibitions.
The show “Mirra Urban”, which is curated by the artist Julia Lam, is co-organized by the Macao Artists Society and the Macao Young Artists Association. It can be visited until September 13.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-08-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Manda is the best destination for conventions in Asia since 2023</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-e-melhor-destino-para-convencoes-na-asia-desde-2023/</link><description>Macao received, for the third consecutive year, the distinction of “Best Convention Destination in Asia” during the “M&amp;C Asia Stella Awards” ceremony in Banguecoque. Macau was represented by the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM), which organized the participation of the Macao and Hengqin Convention and Exhibition Sector (MICE) at the event. IPIM also took advantage of the presence in Thailand to meet with more than 20 companies, to capture events and investments, having held “one-to-one” contact scholarships, with the aim of promoting the advantages of conventions and exhibitions and the cooperation zone business environment, according to a statement. In partnership with 10 institutions and companies, IPIM conducted more than 220 contacts with international entrepreneurs, which included hotels, convention and exhibition institutions, destinations management companies and other event organization. Some companies in Macau-Hengqin participated for the first time and said that "the event increased the attractiveness of the area to hold exhibitions." In addition, they received demonstrations of interest to cooperation by representatives from Southeast Asia. A MICE representative in particular expressed his intention to cooperate with Macau-Hengqin companies to raise "the standard and vision of local companies in the international context."</description><pubDate>2025-08-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>TDM issues reports on Cape Verde</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/tdm-emite-reportagens-sobre-cabo-verde/</link><description>The Portuguese, radio and television channels, and TDM digital platforms, have been issuing from yesterday and until August 29, a series of interviews and reports about Cape Verde. A TDM team has moved to that African country of Portuguese expression to know the economic, social and political reality, and make the point of the situation of cooperation between Cape Verde and China and Macau, looking at the new development bets. The TDM report spoke the main Cape Verdean political figures, especially the President of the Republic, José Maria Neves, a piece that was issued yesterday, Prime Minister, Ulisses Correia e Silva (Friday), former presidents Jorge Carlos Fonseca and Pedro Pires and the rector of the University of Cape Verde, Arlindo Barreto. The “The Hug of China on the Islands of Morabeza” also includes reports about China's presence in Cape Verde, the balance and future of cooperation between the two countries and the relations between Cape Verde and Macao. TDM will also address the Cape Verde challenges it faces in the coming years and statements of elements of the Cape Verdean community of Macao. The main attractions of the islands of Sal and São Vicente will also be in focus, as are the 50th anniversary of the country's independence. The interviews will be issued on the same days at Radio Macau at 10:30 am and reports at 17h00. “China's hug to the islands of Morabeza” is part of the company's strategy of “closer approach to Portuguese-speaking countries”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2462/</link><description>17 people bumped into a total of 3.4 million
Between the 22nd and 24th of this month, the Judicial Police (PJ) received complaints made by 16 residents and a citizen of the interior of China, aged 18 to 70, who will have been circumvented at 3.4 million Patacas in total, following believed in burns who were passed by client support employees. According to the PJ, the burns began by warning the victims about the “expiration of the deadline” of an alleged “payment safety guarantee insurance”, ending those injured by seeing funds in their diverted bank accounts and stolen credit card data.
 
Government imposes more restrictions on the use of plastic
The government will prohibit the importation of cotton swabs, balloons, and uncomplainable plastic sticks from January 1 next year, as read by the executive head of the executive. According to the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services, “extensive analysis of the real situation of Macao” was performed, which considered the offer of alternative products, the experiences of neighboring regions and consulted “the relevant sectors”. The government has progressively implemented restrictive measures to the use of plastic, "in order to better ensure the quality of the Macao environment."
 
Fire in the black sand for 60 people from home
A 50-year-old non-resident worker felt damaged to inhale thick smoke, caused by a fire that launched in his fraction, located in a building in Rua da Areia Preta. He was transported to the hospital and is in a stable state. According to the Fire Department, following the accident, which happened at dawn last Sunday, 60 residents momentarily left their homes. The preliminary investigation indicates that the fire was caused by the damage of a portable charger placed inside the housing.
 
Suspended blood donation vehicle for two days
In order to coordinate the activities of disclosure of the elections for the Legislative Assembly, the blood donation services in the vehicle will be suspended for two days, the health services indicated. On the 26th, will be suspended from 13h00 to 18h00, at Rua Nova da Areia Preta, specifically in the pedestrian zone next to the RAEM service center; Already on September 9, will be affected the vehicle in the pedestrian zone next to the Garden of the City of Flores, in Taipa, during the same time.
 
CTT launch stamp of the beginning of the election campaign
The Directorate of Post and Telecommunications Services (CTT) will open, on August 30, a temporary post office, with the commemorative stamp “Day of the Electoral Campaign for the Elections of the Legislative Assembly 2025”, installed at Tap Seac Square, from 9:45 am to 12:45 pm. The CTT report that, in the event of adverse weather conditions, the post will be located inside the TAP Seac multi -sports pavilion. Commemorative envelopes of this event will be distributed to the public, and posts for sale philatelic products from Macau Post.</description><pubDate>2025-08-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Malpated SME credit grew 14% in a year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/credito-malparado-das-pme-cresceu-14-num-ano/</link><description>The debt loans are still growing unpaid by small and medium enterprises, having already reached 5.64 billion patacas at the end of the first half of this year. Malpated credit has risen 14% in a year and about 27 times since the same period of 2019, according to official data, which is the highest amount since there are records. AMCM recalls that it has been encouraging the banking sector to negotiate “flexible refund plans, under the principle of prudent risk management”, to provide support to customers with “liquidity difficulties”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Debt loans not paid by the Small and Medium Enterprises (SMEs) of the territory cipher at 5.64 billion patacas at the end of the first half of this year, noting an increase of 14.4% or almost 705,000 patacas within one year. When compared to the end of the second half of last year, the bad SME credit rose 5.6% or about 302,000 patacas, according to data released by the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM).
Unpaid loans, involving interest and/or capital payments with delays of more than three months, thus performed two and a half years of consecutive climbs, having recorded the ninth semester increase since 2020. Official data show that liquidation debts grew 26.8 times, or 5.43 billion patacas, compared to the end of 2019. It is the highest value since 2008.
“Due mainly to the drop in the balance of debt loans granted to SMEs”, the non -paid debt ratio - proportion of loans with delay in relation to the total credit granted to the SMEs - advanced to 7.6% at the end of June 2025. This percentage represents a semiannual rise of 0.8 percentage points, an annual increase of 1.4 points and a growth of 7.4 points to the period Pre-Covid.
According to AMCM, in the first six months of this year, the new limit of banks approved by 47.7% to 4.93 billion, in relation to the previous six months, and rose 11.8% in annual terms. The warranty ratio, which illustrates the proportion of credit limit with promised body assets, set at 62.2%, corresponding to a decrease of 14.5 percentage points compared to the last semester of 2024 and a 15.4 points in annual terms.
Regarding the balance used of the loans granted to SMEs (74.34 billion patacas) suffered a semiannual decrease of 4.7% and an annual break of 7.2%. Between January and June this year, loans to the “Transport, Storage and Communications” sector increased by 14.1%, while attributed to “Grosso and Retail Trade” and “construction” decreased by 9.9%and 2.8%, respectively.
The use rate, defined as the proportion of the balanced balance sheet for the approved credit limit, grew 1.2 percentage points to 84.8%, when compared to the rate registered at the end of 2024. In addition, it increased by 3.8 points compared to the end of June 2024.
In a statement, AMCM recalls that "encourages the banking sector to negotiate with Flexible Reimbursement PMEs, under the principle of prudent risk management and in accordance with their own credit policies, continuing to provide credit support to customers with liquidity difficulties."
Recently, the president of the Macao Banks Association, IP Sio Kai, revealed that since the launch of the Bank Credit Bottle Plan for SMEs in mid -April, banks received 2,000 loan requirements, including 80% involving new loans. According to it, if all these requirements receive “green light”, they will involve more than three billion patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New consumer plan launched on September 1</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/novo-plano-de-consumo-lancado-1-de-setembro/</link><description>Between September 1 and November 30 this year, the Government and the Commercial Association will release the great award for consumption again, in order to “revitalize the confidence of the consumer market”. This time, the total amount to be assigned in the form of consumer benefits rose to 485 million patacas
 
The big consumption award will be held back in Macao, between September 1 and November 30, with a duration of 13 weeks and a total amount of 485 million patacas to be attributed to consumer benefits, "in order to give an injection of the community economy," the Macao Commercial Association (ACM), organizers of the initiative, announced.
At a press conference to announce the activity, entitled “Strength of National Games - major consumption award in community zones”, the objectives were highlighted: “boosting the continuous and stable recovery of Macao's economy during the usual tourist season about to arrive”, “responding to the enthusiastic environment of national games” and “revitalizing the confidence of the consumer market”.
The president of the ACM board, Frederico MA, said that in this edition, the association will continue to sponsor pecuniary awards expecting to increase attractiveness. He pointed out, all the promotional activities organized by the ACM and the government "were effective in attracting client flow and expanding clientele to small and medium local traders, encouraging residents to consume in Macao, increasing the confidence of the commercial sector and establishing a solid base for this initiative."
The director of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), Yau Yun Wah, said that the edition promoted between March and May “obtained remarkable successes”, pointing out that an inquiry shows that residents and commercial establishments expressed satisfaction with the initiative model, considering that it produced a positive effect on the encouragement of local consumption.
According to the Chinese language press, the official noted that the initiative budget was elevated from 295 million to 485 million patacas, representing an increase of 65%. In addition, he stated that he took into account the government's “cautious” analysis and consideration of Macao's current economic situation.
At this point, Yau Yun Wah said the government has noticed that some traders continue to face economic pressure, needing more time to adapt. "Budget reinforcement fully reflects the government's determination to actively respond to society's needs in the current economic environment, and support the local economy," he said.
The attribution of electronic benefits through mobile payments will maintain the usual model.
Throughout the activity, from Monday to Friday, when the electronic portfolio user, with real name authentication, make a mobile payment in the eligible stores in the amount of not less than 50 patacas for each transaction, can get three opportunities to earn discount coupons, which expire at midnight immediately.
Cups (with value of 10, 20, 50, 50, 100 and 200 patacas) should be used on Saturday and Sunday immediately following more than 20 physical stores, and the amount actually paid in each transaction should be equal to or higher than triple of the nominal value of the coupon. If you have several coupons in the same electronic wallet, they will be “exchanged” automatically in a single transaction as long as the requirement of “triple the value of the coupon” is satisfied.
In addition, on Saturdays and Sundays, beneficiary consumers can automatically participate in the luck. We will be drawn weekly three winners who can receive 8,000 patacas each in cash.
Organizers encourage and appeal to the most merchants to launch additional offers.
However, the initiative involves two perfected aspects, according to the government. The first is the increase in the value of the “immediate discount for the elderly” to 500 patacas, while the second is the assignment of a “social care card” with 500 patacas for immediate discount benefits to the holders of the Disability Evaluation Registration Card (CRAD).
According to DSEDT, 50% of the purchase value will be deducted directly from the amount of discount awarded (equivalent to 50% off), while the remaining 50% will be charged. In practical terms, holders of both types of cards may purchase goods or services in the total amount of 1,000 patacas using only 500 patacas of their money.
All 65-year-olds until November 28 may travel to more than 100 service posts designated to obtain the benefits by loading the Macau Pass card to the elderly. On the other hand, since yesterday, more than 40 institutions coordinated by the Institute of Social Action (IAS) began notifying and assisting users in surveying the social care card. The other CRD holders will be able to raise this card from September 1 in the five social action centers at the IAS General Rehabilitation Evaluation Center.
This group of beneficiaries covers individuals who have requested CRD until August 21 and approve by November 28. According to DSEDT, it is not possible to enjoy the two types of benefit simultaneously.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Korea bets on culture in search of impulse for growth</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/coreia-aposta-na-cultura-em-busca-de-impulso-para-crescimento/</link><description>South Korean entertainment companies, which “surf” in the Korean wave, or Hallyu, are striving to widen global range, while Asia's fourth largest economy is betting on cultural exports at a time of growing protection barriers to traditional manufacturers.
Although it is growing rapidly from a low base, thanks to the substantial support of the government and the high visibility in the world landscape with some recent successes, the sector's contribution to the economy is still just a fraction of the transforming industry.
The Samsung and Hyundai Industry Giants House is delighting in the success of Boys Band BTS, the winning movie of a Oscar, “Parasite”, from the “Round 6” series “The Vegetarian”, whose author Han Kang won the Nobel Prize for Literature in 2024, and, more recently, the musical Maybe Happy Ending.
India, Latin America and the Middle East, in particular, are new promising markets for Korean cultural products that have been revealed global hits, said executives from major producers in interviews with Reuters.
"The Latin America region, recognized as the cradle of Latin music, is a key focus area," said Jason Jaesang Lee, executive director of the K-Pop Hybe agency, who manages BTS, featured his return planned for the next spring.
The agency is also holding auditions in Latin America to release another boys Band, after the US -based Katseye group debut last year, whose six members come from four countries.
"It's time to re -examine Hallyu's definition," Lee said. "If the content is created abroad, but produced by a Korean company, or even by a foreign entity with Korean capital, I believe it should still be considered part of Hallyu."
Still, cultural exports are unlikely to replace the traditional transforming industry in the near future.
South Korea Intellectual Property Exports (PI), from music and movies to games, more than tripled over the past decade, reaching $ 9.85 billion by 2024, but representing only a fraction of goods exports, which increased 13%, reaching $ 696.2 billion, according to Central Bank data.
Another company that is expanding the global business this year is CJ ENM, producer of “parasite”, which began to provide K-Damas for the Middle East and North Africa through a partnership with a regional streaming platform in June.
In the case of the Middle East, “we see this market as a promising long term, because Hallyu's popularity is high among the youngest generation,” said Sean Cho, executive vice president of the global business division.
In the main markets in Japan, Southeast Asia and the United States, the company is widening partnerships, more recently with Amazon Prime Video, to offer joint productions that combine Korean elements with local culture, Cho added.
For the game industry, a source of income that represents more than half of South Korea's intellectual exports and is famous for Krafton's award-winning PUBG: Battlegrounds, India promises to be the next growing market, although it represents only a tenth of the South Korean market.
"The India Game Market is still early in comparison with other advanced countries," said Sean Hyunil Sohn, executive director of Game Editor Kraftton India, which plans to explore growth potential, adding new genres and types of games.
President Lee Jae Myung has promised support and investment to make South Korea in a “great cultural power,” with the aim of expanding the market to 300 billion wons in value and exports to 50 billion wons by 2030.
"But we can't leave it in the hands of individual companies," he said in a recent talk show. "The government will play the role of establishing a solid foundation, and it begins now."
Big Five refer to music categories, dramas, webtoons, beauty and food products, which are key elements in President Lee's efforts to reposition South Korea as a cultural power.
For long -term success, sector experts and even the Central Bank have appealed to legislative structures to help national companies compete with global giants such as Netflix.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-08-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>