<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Government urged to review work import policy</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-instado-rever-politica-de-importacao-laboral/</link><description>In the period before the agenda, in the Legislative Assembly, several deputies addressed the scarcity of employment for the residents of Macao, asking the government to review the labor import regime and make adjustments to the number of TNR, especially in large companies, such as players
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Because “the issue of employment remains the one that most concerned the population” were several deputies who yesterday took advantage of the period before the agenda, in the Legislative Assembly, to install the government to take action in this field. Since the revision of the labor import regime and adjusting the number of non-resident workers (TNR) in the game companies to create a “updating fund”, there were several suggestions from the various stands.
"With the new conjuncture and the adjustment of the labor market, the jobs with good condition are very looking for, the technical requirements are increasingly high, and this adds the impacts caused by the importation of TNR," said Leong Sun Iok. For the deputy "it is still necessary to review, globally and systematically, the regime of importation of labor, reinforcing the supervision of the appreciation of requests, in order to guarantee the use of local workers."
Also Song Pek Kei pointed out that TNR's import policy was implemented "for over 20 years." And "in the face of adjusting and changing economic structure, it can no longer respond to social needs," he continued, asking the executive to review and perfect the mechanism, "defining a maximum limit for the proportion of TNR as the search for each sector."
In addition, Leong Sun Iok considers that large companies, game operators, banks and public interest entities “the requirement to hire locations” should be imposed on large companies. The deputy stated that until April this year, the number of specialized TNR reached 5,905 - "therefore, the government has the responsibility to evaluate the current situation and to manage the number of TNR."
He also asked the Executive to “reinforce the inspection”, preventing companies from “hiring part -time sites and then they can require TNR quotas”, asserting that “the government must improve the appreciation mechanism” for labor imports, namely introducing “more transparent assessment standards about the reasonableness of remuneration, to prevent companies from taking advantage of salaries and making it believe them Local workers who are not willing to work and then may request TNR quotas. ”
Song Pek Kei considers, on the other hand, that it takes a “limit” for job operators for the first line or base level jobs, noting that there is only one measure that ensures the proportion of local and higher -level local workers not less than 85%.
Leong Hong Sai approached the same theme. "Some jobs are busy by many TNR," he noted, asking the authorities to evaluate the issue "rationally and based on scientific criteria" and that "adjust the labor import mechanism."
According to the intervention, some residents who work in the satellite casinos said it was “very difficult” to change their jobs in middle age. Given this situation, the deputy suggested the creation of a “funding fund” so that those for middle-aged workers who change employment can have financial support in obtaining certification for emerging industries.
In the same line, and remembering the case of the end of the satellite casinos, law chan u stressed that "employment is the pillar in people's lives and the" rice bowl "of residents." In this sense, he said he hoped the authorities “closely follow the situation of employment in general, including that of the casinos-satellite workers” and “attribute an active role to the working group to coordinate employment promotion, which should gather proper jobs and create quality job opportunities for residents.” A request, by the way, also made by Leong Hong Sai.
Nick Law foresees “a large-scale unemployment situation” with the satellite casinos closure and the launch of the voluntary dismissal program promoted by large companies. "The government must supervise the companies in question, (…), reducing the impact of unemployment. At the same time, I propose to the government to a continuous assessment of TNR's hiring situation," he said.
 
Young unemployment
Zheng Anting, in turn, expressed concern for young unemployment. According to data from the first quarter of this year, which he mentioned, "the number of unemployed higher education increased over the previous quarter, reaching about 50% of the total." And in the approaching undergraduate period, there will be more than 8,000 graduates, he added, noting that there is “weak willingness to hire by companies”.
Stressing that according to many newly graded “the pressure to have employment is great”, the deputy noted that the search for labor in traditional industries and sectors such as tourism and the game “is shrinking”, while “for emerging industries, such as financial technology and macrosaúde, there are no corresponding courses in Macao Higher Education Institutions”.
In your opinion it is necessary, then, to “optimize” the internship plan. Zheng Anting also considers that it is necessary to perceive the difficulties of employment and entrepreneurship that affect young people in the deepened cooperation zone.
 
On the deputies' agenda
Childhood subsidy
Lo Choi in proposed to extend the childhood assistance subsidy up to six years to support families and increase birth. During an intervention in the period before the agenda, the deputy appealed to the government to "adopt more comprehensive policies and measures." He also suggested a revision of the “Labor Relations Law”, a better use of the social security fund's financial support and an increase in maternity licenses to 90 days, and paternity to seven. He also asserted that workers' holidays should be increased, "to promote harmony and family stability."
 
Environment without barriers
Deputy Ho Ion Sang asked the Executive to define a “clear calendar” for the environmental legislation without barriers. In this sense, it argued that communication and the exchange of opinions with the public should be reinforced, disabled associations and rehabilitation organizations, in order to ensure that “the law really satisfies the real needs of society”. Ho Ion Sang also proposed that a collaboration between platforms such as “Amap” and “Baidu Map” was studied to develop “intelligent” and “barriers” navigation for disabled people, residents with needs and visitors.
 
Cyberliteracy
Ella Lei asked the government to advance with cyberliteracy education and to pay more attention to the situation of web use by young people, reinforcing their guidance for a “correct use of the internet”. The deputy also suggested promoting a "filtering function" through telecommunications operators, in order to block the "bad content". According to the deputy, support to the 390 counseling agents for students should also be reinforced, explaining that it is necessary to have human resources in adequate proportion to provide support ”to students.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New Law feeds hopes for airline expansion</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/nova-lei-alimenta-esperancas-sobre-expansao-de-rotas-aereas/</link><description>It was approved yesterday, in the specialty, the proposal of the Civil Aviation Activity Law. The Secretary for Transport and Public Works stressed that the Government will preference to strategies to create conditions for the gradual increase in the number of passenger air transport licenses. Raymond Tam expects that “through proper and healthy competition between airlines, more airlines are opened”
 
The Legislative Assembly (AL) approved yesterday, in the specialty, the proposal of the Civil Aviation Activity Act, which advocates the end of the exclusive concession of Air Macau and introduces a license system, in order to gradually open the civil aviation market of the territory. This diploma will come into force on February 1 of next year.
During the discussion phase, Raymond Tam, Secretary for Transport and Public Works, stressed that, in the passenger transport segment, the government will consider priority to ensure security in aviation and market stability. He stressed, preference will be given to “step -by -step” strategies to create conditions for the gradual increase in the number of passenger air transport licenses, under the premise of not having a negative impact on the current market structure.
In addition, the secretary said that the government will prepare, “with all the commitment”, the respective complementary regulations, among other preliminary preparations, insisting that passenger air transport services will be promoted gradually according to the actual situation and will have to contemplate the market situation.
"The Government of the MSAR always hopes to open the sky. Through the proposal of law, it will introduce competition properly under the premise of maintaining market stability, in order to improve the restrictive market environment, create even more space necessary for the civil aviation sector and satisfy the demand for residents and tourists for better quality air services," said Raymond Tam.
"At the same time, the government expects that, through proper and healthy competition between airlines, more airlines will be opened, and extended to the Macao Aviation Network," the secretary continued.
In this respect, Raymond Tam also mentioned that the gradual promotion of the market does not mean an inction or slowdown of their work, but a stable and gradual pace, to meet the needs of the Macao market, whose size is very small.
In addition, Pun Wa Kin, president of the Macao Civil Aviation Authority (AACM), explained that “openness” means that the authorities expect to see a diversification of the market, and will not protect only local companies.
The same responsible also assured that the government assumes an open attitude in negotiations with different countries, trying not to restrict between both sides regarding air connections, the number of flights and passenger volume, and allows airlines from other countries and regions to operate in Macao.
Regarding traffic rights, Pun Wa Kin said he hoped the other sides will allow more than a Macao airline. The government has already begun to prepare an administrative regulation on the management, distribution and supervision of traffic rights to find a “reasonable and balanced” solution, the president of AACM said, indicating that these rules will be adopted when there are new airlines in Macao in the future.
On the other hand, Raymond Tam said that if Air Macau intends to continue operating, he could submit the request provided it satisfies the stipulations. The government follows the operational situation of Air Macau and “actively promotes a series of improvement measures,” said the secretary.
 
“Total Opening” for air load services
Raymond Tam also stressed that the “total opening” for the air load segment may be realized “very quickly”. This means that there will be no restrictions on the number of air load licenses, he said, noting that, provided they correspond to the civil aviation law and international civil aviation rules, companies that make this service available may obtain air operations certifications to settle in the territory.
According to the secretary, some cargo companies that have a certain dimension have already expressed interested in operating in Macau. The ruler believes that, with the approval of the civil aviation activity law, more capacity operators will join the local market, which will be positive for the Macao cargo transportation sector, which has a “relatively broad space for expansion”.
Also in the discussion, Deputy Ron Lam urged the government to lower the restrictions on drones in order to boost the development of this sector.
In response, Raymond Tam stressed that the government actively promotes the use of drones. According to explained, as Macau is small and faces more wind restrictions than other regions, the Executive will elaborate a complementary regulation that aims to promote drone activities, taking into account this situation and the guarantee of aviation safety.
In addition, the president of AACM also highlighted the authorities' opening attitude regarding helicopter operations, ensuring that their operations may be free as long as they meet the requirements on both sides.
He added, if the border posts in the interior of China are available to accept this type of operations, have heliports and correspond to customs requirements, AACM may approve the respective routes, and the body adopts “flexible forms of approval”. The official considers that if the market provides conditions, the airlines will be “all very interested”.
In addition, Pun Wa Kin assured that Macau has “absolute” opening to the executive aviation sector.
 
Approved Law of Travel and Guide Agencies
Also approved, in the specialty, the proposal of the Law of Travel Agencies and the Tour Guide profession, which will also be effective on February 1, 2026. The law stipulates that travel agencies have to provide security and perform professional liability insurance.
According to the Director of Tourism Services (STD), this requirement will cause excursion rates to increase, but not substantially. In addition, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes noted that, in relation to neighboring regions, there are few excursions in Macao, so it is not appropriate to deal with their expenses through a compensation fund, such as Hong Kong, because otherwise it could have to be removed an amount that represents a very high percentage with each excursion with the end of warranty.
The diploma does not apply to tourist travel organized by associations. However, according to the director of STD, this will not affect the acquisition of tour guide services for this type of excursions.
On the other hand, the law clarifies that, up to 12 hours before arriving at the attendees of tourist trips within Macao, the travel agency has to introduce STD database the information regarding these visitors and the itinerary, as well as the name of the guide.
The STD director clarified that this requirement serves to supervise the authorities, to, for example, to identify the guide and to verify that the excursion has deviated from the itinerary. However, the excursionist data will not have to involve personal information, and it is sufficient to introduce the province of origin to meet the inspection requirements, said Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Background with 650 million to support SMEs and typical stores</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/fundo-mais-650-milhoes-para-apoiar-pme-lojas-tipicas/</link><description>To launch a project to support SME digitization and the other focused on the companion and launch of specific programs for typical stores, the government intends to increase the budget of the industrial development and marketing fund by 650 million patacas. The 2nd commission of AL will urge the government to advance more details
 
The government intends to raise the budget of the Industrial Development and Marketing Fund (FDIC) on 650 million patacas, due to two projects, which motivated the attention of the 2nd Permanent Commission of the Legislative Assembly (AL). This is what Chan Chak Mo, chairman of the commission, indicated after a meeting held yesterday for the first discussion, in the specialty, of the proposal to change the Budget Law of 2025.
Quoting the government, Chan Chak Mo revealed that one of the projects has in view to support the digitization of small and medium enterprises (SME), whose number of vacancies was not explained. The other is centered on the campaign and launch of specific programs for typical stores.
According to the Chinese language press, Chan Chak Mo said the commission expects the government to clarify whether the two projects have already raised a budget of more than 600 million patacas.
In addition, the commission is aware of the budget of the 3rd phase of expansion of the Solid Waste Incineration Center, from 90 million to about 200 million patacas, which translates into an increase from 1.14 times. According to Chan Chak Mo, deputies expect to obtain an explanation from the government next week.
In addition, the Commission also follows two projects, whose total budgets exceed 150 million Patacas, both related to administration and civil service services. Specifically, one, 110 million patacas involves the preparation of software and hardware of a cloud computing disasters center, while the other, budgeted at 40 million, concerns the construction of this center. However, the calendars are unknown for the beginning of the projects.
According to the deputy, in general, for the economic year of 2025, the government's financial income decreased 3.8%, while expenses increased by 2.5%, and the positive jump of public finances reduced significantly from 7.7 billion to 290 million patacas. By the end of March this year, the total amount of the MSAR financial reserve was 630.7 billion patacas.
 
Pidda with execution of 22.8% in the 1st quarter
On the other hand, according to the ALS Form Monitoring Committee, the initial budget of the Administration Development Investment and Development Plan (PIDDA) for this year was 19.78 billion Patacas, equal to the one that was approved until the first quarter of this year.
During this period, the government's effective expenses were 4.52 billion patacas, which means a budgetary rate of 22.8% and a budget use rate of 81%.
In addition, the commission signed the opinion of the “PIDDA budgetary execution report of the 3rd quarter of the 2024 economic year”, according to which budget execution and budget utilization rates were 70.5% and 93.4%, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Provisional use of lots includes auto-silos and sports fields</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/uso-provisorio-de-lotes-inclui-auto-silos-campos-desportivos/</link><description>The creation of parking parks in various locations of the city and islands, with electric charging, is one of the government's priorities regarding the provisional use of unoccupied land. In addition, it is planned to create sports rooms, namely a soccer in new landfills, with synthetic floor and lighting. Two more lots, in Nam Wan and in the mud, will provide sports and leisure spaces
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Several provisional facilities, such as parking parks and sports spaces and leisure activities, will be created by the government on state land that are currently unoccupied and should be available to the population from the second half of 2026.
One of the most widened projects will be a soccer field, capable of hosting games from the 11 -playing variant, with a size similar to the canid drive field. The construction of the soccer field is only possible in lot B13 due to the available area of ​​the land, which is 15,000 square meters. "It will be a normal enclosure for soccer of eleven, having a synthetic floor, lighting posts and resorts," said the chairman of the Land Follow -up Committee and public concessions of the Legislative Assembly at the end of a meeting, in which the Secretary for Public Works and Transport, Raymond Tam was present.
Chui Sai Peng said that, in addition to this “mini-stadium”, which will help solve some problems with training fields for training, that zone will have sports facilities designed for modalities such as Badminton, Volleyball, Basketball, Athletics, among others.
The land located in the new landfills is one of those that have a government planning for provisional use, and in lots C8, in Nam Van, with an area of ​​4,422 square meters, and B7, in the mud, with 3,700 square meters, will also emerge facilities for sports and recreation.
On the other hand, the lot next to Kwong Tung Avenue, in the mud, will be attached to another adjoining, to house a underground parking park, beyond the outdoor leisure zone. The spaces are in an area composed of five lots between the Nam San and Nova Taipa buildings.
Two were up to auction, but only the BT 9a aroused interest from potential buyers, planned for this place the construction of residential buildings.
Sports and leisure spaces should not allow use over 24 hours, as “when they are situated in residential areas, they can produce noise, affecting the life of the population,” noted the committee chairman.
The designated “free fields” are intended for the population, in general terms, but with particular priority for schools. However, the secretary was urged to take into account "the needs of physical exercise for the elderly and middle-aged people, so the facilities should serve such residents," said Chui Sai Peng, adding that deputies suggest that in those sporting spaces, "luxury" equipment will be installed.
Another priority is the creation of more parking parks, so the three referenced lots will have self-siles, with electric charging. "Increasingly the government is aware of low carbon policy and environmental work and these loading posts, so it is possible to encourage and stimulate our environmental policy," he said.
One of the parks of parking will emerge in Barra, near the piloting school, but also in a second phase of the demolition works of the D. Juliet building, near the doors of the siege, and can make available close to 30 or 40 seats. There are also provisional self-siles in the old “Flying Eagle” field in Coloane, and can receive between 60 to 70 light and motorcycle vehicles, and on Rua da Skating, also on Coloane Island.
The works should start briefly. As for the budgets, “only after the useful services elaborate the respective conception projects,” said the chairman of the commission, adding that the management of provisional spaces will be done by the corresponding services.
In addition to the sports facilities and parking parks, considered priority, there is also the intention of taking advantage of the unoccupied land and installing joy environmental centers, as it should happen in a lot near the Kiang Wu hospital, which has a smaller area.
Chui Sai Peng said that all projects intended for the use of dismissed terrain "will not be performed if residents of the respective areas do not agree." Therefore, it reinforces, "you need to find land and make the design projects well."</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Arts Festival for Children with lower budget</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/festival-de-artes-para-criancas-orcamento-mais-baixo/</link><description>The International Children's Arts Festival will have an investment from the 20 million Patacas Cultural Institute, a value below the edition of last year, the president, Leong Wai Man. The body announced several activities intended for the youngest, which will take place between July and August
 
Pedro Milheirão
The Budget of the Cultural Institute (IC) for the 2nd International Arts Festival for Children of Macao will be 20 million Patacas, about nine million less compared to the previous edition, said the president of the body. Leong Wai Man justified the reduction with their own choice of programs and not having an exhibition with an “as large as last year” wingspan, but also due to the fact that partner players take a larger part of the costs. The leader, who was talking at a press conference about the initiative, was no use, however, which amount invested by the concessionaires.
During this year's edition, the IC will present a total of 49 activities and more than a thousand sessions, including international level performing arts, a large -scale musical, exhibitions, artistic camps and a fair, among others. The play “Bebeethoven” of the full moon Theater of Portugal, intended for babies until two years old, will take place in CCM studio I, from July 18 to 20 and, again, between 22 and 25. The tickets will cost 200 patacas for two people and 300 for three.
The first Chinese music camp, for children from five to 10, will be organized by the Chinese music orchestra and will allow younger ones to enter “in contact with Chinese musical instruments”, encouraging them to increase “interest in traditional culture”. During the four days of the “Small Chinese Music Group” camp, games and interactive performances will be performed based on the theme “The Journey to the West”.
The camp will also include a “mini instrument diy workshop and a sharing session. In addition to art workshops and a visit to the museum, the “creative camp for children” and the “family artistic camp” will also be released, providing the opportunity to camp at CCM.
The artistic fair, co-organized by the IC and Sands China, will also return, with “large-scale inflatable facilities, sprinkles and highlights for photographs” with “Micaf”, the festival's mascot. Throughout July, there will also be weekend parties, with collective games, within the spirit of the National Games. In addition, Sands will present the musical “Disney - The Magic Caixa”, a selection of classic Disney composers that combine “magnificent dance, exquisite puppets and stunning visual effects, to tell well -known aspect stories”.
Together with MGM, the IC will present the exhibition “Magic of the Lines: The Wonderful World of Serge Bloch Illustrated Books”, a “space of innocence and freedom” with “vibrant features and rich colors”. Combining educational and artistic elements, the show will guide “children to experience art and creativity through the change of lines”, exploring “beautiful moments of life”.
During the two months of the festival, the CCM's “Artmusing” room will welcome the “Children's Bookstore”, which will be open to the weekends, in a pop-up modality. "More than 400 types of illustrated books, books for young readers, books with images, booklets and other cultural and creative products", in which "small and large can enjoy reading together."
The “Children's Artistic Adventure - Thematic Exhibition of Books of Public Library Collections” will be held at the Macao Central Library and the Taipa Library, among others. A “Book Collection that encompasses topics such as the history of Ballet symphony, puppet theater, western and oriental music will be displayed, as well as the dialogue between music and literature, children and music, artistic therapy”. The exhibition will allow readers to “experience the integration of art and reading into daily life”.
In the last two weekends of August, the “Micaf Fun Day” will take place, which will include the “Foam Festival”, the “aquatic fun party”, shows, food stands, handicraft workshops and game stands.
Tickets for the shows are available at the points of sale of the “Enjoy Macao” ticket office, and tickets for the International Film Festival for children are for sale at Cinemateca Paixão and on the online reserve platform. Registration for workshops can be made in the single account.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More prizes to improve tourist services</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-premios-para-melhorar-servicos-turisticos/</link><description>The Quality Tourist Services Evaluation Program will include new evaluation criteria and more prizes
 
Launched by the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) in 2014, the Quality Tourist Services Evaluation Program will know this year new adjustments in the appreciation system, as well as cover more awards. In a clarification session on the evaluation criteria, Jennifer Si Tou, a subdirector of STD, said she was "pleased to see the tourist industry constantly seek improvements in the quality of services provided and customer experience."
As part of STD quality tourism assessment programs and consumer council certified stores, the two bodies launched this year for the first time the “Good Practice Prize in integrity, with the aim of encouraging companies to provide quality services and put into practice trusted business management models”.
In addition, the evaluation system of the quality tourist service assessment program was simplified, including “adjustments in the form of travel agencies assessment and the number of evaluations per client mystery of the restoration sector”. According to STD, the 176 new qualified candidacies and companies that have returned to the restoration sector prize will submit to two assessments per mystery client and a general evaluation of the service management system.
The travel agency sector has 27 new qualified competitors, who will submit to three service assessments to mystery clients and a general evaluation of the service management system. On the other hand, 31 commercial establishments that are in the supervision phase, will be evaluated twice by the mystery customer service, according to the award renewal mechanism.
This year, for the restoration sector was added the “good practices prize” to the “special theme awards”, raising the total to five, along with the “sustainable food” prizes, “community care services”, “local feature” and “operational innovation”.
In the business agencies, there will be, for the first time, three “special theme prizes”, namely “good practices in integrity”, “courtesy company” and “team training quality”. "The awards intend to praise commercial establishments that distinguish themselves by their excellent performance in the areas of honest management, label in the provision of services and formation of their workers," says STD.
Awarded establishments will have priority in the recommendation to participate in promotions and activities, and admission to training courses organized by STD.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Experts address “inclusion” over two days</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/especialistas-abordam-inclusao-ao-longo-de-dois-dias/</link><description>Topics such as “dementia-friendly communities, clinical strategies for autism and sex education for young people with special needs” will be addressed throughout Monday and Tuesday, under the “Inclusion Conference &amp; Festival”. The initiative of the Macau Business magazine's Beneficência Charity Association intends to “promote the experience dialogue”, explained José Carlos Matias to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, stiving that there is still a way to go to these issues
 
The “Inclusion Conference &amp; Festival” will address, over two days, topics such as “dementia -friendly communities, clinical strategies for autism and sex education for young people with special needs”. This is described as “one of the main regional forums dedicated to neurodiversity, inclusive education and family -centered care” is organized by the Macau Business magazine's charity association, and supported by Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment and MGM, taking place on the first day at the Anglican College of Macao, and second at MGM Cotai.
"It is a very special event for us, who has been growing over the years, always with an international climate. It is very important to talk about these topics. It has to be acknowledged that over the years they have gained space on the public discussion agenda in Macau, but we are still short," said José Carlos Matias in statement to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau.
From its perspective, the conference comes to “promote the dialogue of exchange of experiences”. "Hopefully Macau can have as reference and inspiration the experiences and what is best done a little everywhere and will be brought here," he added.
The event will bring together international experts in the areas of autism, psychology and inclusive education, as well as policy formulators, educators and defenders of the cause. During the initiative, “moving stories of family resilience, educational transformation and community inclusion will be told,” the organization says in a statement.
“Reflecting its growing depth and regional impact, the 2025 edition will feature a cast of speakers, especially from the People's Republic of China and the Great Bay (Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau Province). His participation promises to create a much deeper social impact, encouraging hundreds of local and regional NGOs to engage in actively, to face experiences, face challenges and face challenges, and they Establish new collaborations, ”read the event.
Some sessions highlighted in this year's edition title “Empowering parents with information on the journey of autism” by Carmen Li (Hong Kong), “Developing Macai as a friendly community of dementia”, by Bill Wen Zeng (Macau) and “Sar-Reassessment of Sexual Attitudes for Macao,” Angus Yuk Lam (Hong Kong) communication. Also noteworthy is the session “Sexuality and Intellectual Disabilities” (Angus Yuk Kit LAM). The sessions will be conducted in traditional Chinese and English.
In addition, this year's festival will host "several international workshops supervisors and art, music and sports specialists, ensuring that the spirit of collaboration, creativity and inclusion continues to flourish." As for workshops, they are scheduled for the period between 23 and 27 this month, including a golf tournament for people with intellectual disabilities.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Biennial will have renowned curator</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/bienal-de-macau-tera-curador-de-renome/</link><description>Feng Boyi, an international notoriety artist, will be the main curator of this year's International Art Biennial edition of Macao. According to the Cultural Institute, the event will explore the history and memory of the territory, as well as its participation in the globalization process
 
The curatorship of the Macau 2025 International Art Biennial will be led by Feng Boyi, “one of China's independent and most active critics”, and researcher at the Institute of Art Sociology at Sichuan Academy of Fine Arts, the Cultural Institute (IC) announced. Feng has already assumed the functions of artistic director at the He Xiangning Art Museum and the Suzhou Jinji Lake Art Museum, and was distinguished as curator of the year of “Art Power List” (in 2010 and 2016) and “AAC Art China” (2017 and 2018).
According to an IC statement, Feng Boyi “focuses on marginal and alternative artists and groups, as well as the existence and artistic creation of new generation artists”, favoring the “experimental nature, criticism and practice of contemporary Chinese art”. In addition to being the author of various theses and criticisms, he was curator of hundreds of major contemporary art exhibitions, including the first triennial of contemporary art in Guangzhou, China today - the reincarnation of Chinese contemporary art (in Vienna and the Netherlands), five artistic exchange programs between the two margins and Xu Bing: ideas and methods.
Subordinated to the theme “Hello, what do you do here?”, The Biennial is an artistic event that “covers the whole city”, in which “the government of Masters joins forces with various sectors to give broader to global creativity”, underlines the IC. The Biennial, which will extend between summer and autumn, “explores and narrates the history and memory of the territory, as well as its current situation in globalization”, emphasizes the body.
Over the course of three months, the event will be divided into six sections, namely the “main exhibition”, the “Public Art Exhibition”, the “City Pavilion”, the “Special Exhibition”, the “Local Curator Project” and the “Collateral Exhibition”, articulating with about 30 exhibitions throughout the city. Bringing together avant-garde artists from more than 10 countries and regions, such as Xu Bing, Ann Hamilton, Gregor Schneider, Bart Hess, Kasia Molga, Chan Hung-Lu and other contemporary figures, the biennial aims to “renew artistic narratives, revitalize historical places, interact with community fabric and boost the spirit of humanity”.
Under the secretary's sponsorship for the social and cultural affairs of the Government of MSA, the Art Biennial has the co-organization of the Directorate of Tourism Services and the six game operators.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Parallel Monolingism” in Lisbon and Porto</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/monolinguismos-paralelos-em-lisboa-porto/</link><description>The series of “BPM” cultural events, an initiative of the Small City Experimental Theater Group, known internationally as “Macau Experimental Theater” - arrives in Portugal this Sunday, promising to challenge the conventional notions of multilingualism.
O “bpM” propõe um mergulho nos “monolinguismos paralelos”, conforme salienta uma nota curatorial de Cheong Kin Man, artista e antropólogo de Macau sediado em Berlim. Criada a partir da “complexa” herança cultural de Macau, esta plataforma de experimentação translingue “procura construir pontes e desmantelar barreiras”, segundo um comunicado da associação local.
The Portuguese public is invited to recite with the artists. The entrance will be marked by a physical book that combines with the theme of the day, calling on the “exploration of the limits of language and the hearing of voices from within and somewhere”.
Under the theme “Monologue”, the first night of literary and musical improvisation will start at Atelier Artery, on the Benfica Road in Lisbon, in a session starting at 20:00 Sunday (Portuguese time), with the action of Japanese musician Akitsugu Fukushima, resident in Macao, and the Venezuelan artist Max Provenzano, inhabitant of Lisbon.
The second half of this night, starting an hour later in the same place, will be starring the young and award -winning poet Li I, also from Macau, in the company of Portuguese musician Gonçalo Antunes, ensuring a “unique sensory immersion”.
Next Tuesday, the 24th, si tou chi ü, author of Macau born in 2000, will declare his verses Cantoneses along with the song Coimbrã de Gonçalo Pinto, in a session in the Hangar-Artistic Research Center, at 20:00, around the theme "Silence", followed by 21:00 a session with musician Lisboeta Alcides Miranda. Max Provenzano will also offer, at this meeting, a performative and multimedial recital.
The next day, at 18:15, in the Garden of Goethe-Institut Lisbon, the two authors of Macau gather with José Joaquim Monteiro Júnior, before a "jam" with the song of Miranda and Pinto, scheduled for 19:00. Addressing the theme “dialogue”, linguistic diversity will be celebrated through the recital of the verses of J.J. Monteiro by his son José Joaquim Monteiro Júnior, and the reading of poems by Li and Si Tou. Inspired by the experiences of Berlin and Macao, the curatorial concept of “Translingism” will be a highlight in the event to be held in the cultural representation of Germany in the Portuguese capital.
The delegation of the artists will then head to Porto. The last event, with the topic of “Other Languages”, will take place on the 28th, at 16:00, in the Camelli Garden of the Soares dos Reis National Museum. Si tou chi ü e li i, both awarded by the Macau Foundation's literary prizes, will present their literary work in a set of improvisation with artist Maria João Almeida and the music Raquel Ribeiro.
In pair with Marta Stanisława Sala, Polish textile artist, Cheong Kin Man will read excerpts from his artist book “Revelation”, and present a roll of fabric as part of the scenography of the events, according to the municipality of Krakow.
The initiative is curated by Cheong Kin Man, Kathine Cheong Weng Lam and Tam Chi Chün. It has the support of the Fund for the Development of MSAR CULTURE.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Checks motivated 5,000 orders on the first day</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cheques-motivaram-5-000-pedidos-primeiro-dia/</link><description>The government registered on Wednesday, the first day for the reception of requests, about 5,000 requirements to assign the pecuniary reimbursement plan in economic development for 2025, the Social Communication Office (GCS) said. Macao residents who, in principle, do not gather the assignment requirements may submit their application through the “single account” or personally at government service centers, among other methods. According to the GCS, until 18:00 on Wednesday, more than 3,720 requests were submitted to the “Single Account” and more than 1,180 in the service centers. The highest influx was registered at the Sand Black Services Center, leading the Executive to open all reserve counters, refers to the same note, ensuring that, in general, the process took place with fluidity and “proper functioning”. Still, in order to further shorten the waiting time, the government appealed to residents who intend to present the requests in person to opt for the other four service centers, and to make a previous marking with the “single account”. Residents gathering the requirements will begin to receive the amounts provided for in the monetary reimbursement plan from July 15, through bank transfer or check. On the other hand, until 12 noon yesterday, the “single account” and the service counters received about 1,300 requirements.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ho Ion Sang is a single candidate for the social and educational sector</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ho-ion-sang-e-candidato-unico-sector-social-educacional/</link><description>Deputy Ho Ion Sang is a sole candidate for the seat of the Social and Educational Services sector in the Legislative Assembly (AL), under the September 14 elections. Yesterday, the team of the Social Work and Education Promotion Association handed over to the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) the list of candidates and the political program. To the Chinese language press, Ho Ion Sang said that the political program focuses on promoting social services, diversification of education and creation of a proper city to live and “happy”. In concrete, he promised to press the government to achieve measures to respond to society's aging and improve social benefits, "in order to protect the legal rights and interests of the elderly, people with disabilities and other vulnerable groups." He also pointed out that he will seek to “promote a fair and diverse educational system”, following the impact of the low birth rate. Ho Ion Sang said he intends to "increase the professional level of teachers and improve the conditions of teachers." Employment stabilization, measures to improve housing, transport and urban renewal are some of the priorities, as well as the price issue, environmental protection, culture and sport. The only candidacy in the indirect suffrage of this area obtained 140 nominations out of a total of 162 voter legal persons.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Legal matters discussed by Macau, Zhuhai and Hengqin</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/assuntos-juridicos-discutidos-por-macau-zhuhai-hengqin/</link><description>In a joint meeting on close cooperation in legal affairs between Macau, Zhuhai and Hengqin, “exchange and cooperation in the legislation between the three regions, cooperation in legal disclosure, the mechanism of sharing and exchange of legal information, the articulation of the rules and mechanisms between Macau and Hengqin, within the scope of the second phase of development of the deepened cooperation zone. According to a statement from the Directorate of Justice Services (DSAJ), they addressed “innovative paths”, namely “the creation of the cooperation mechanism for the formation of qualified frames in the foreign legal area between Macao, Zhuhai and Hengqin, and cooperation in notarial affairs between the three regions”. At the same time, it says DSAJ, the interaction and exchange between volunteer groups for the legal disclosure of the three regions will be reinforced, in order to increase, together, the effectiveness of the release work of the State of Regional Law. In the future, it can be read, “together, an innovative path to the articulation of rules and mechanisms, promoting high quality integration between Macau and Hengqin and the construction of the rule of law of the great bay”. The meeting was held by DSAJ in conjunction with the Zhuhai Justice Department and the Directorate of Legal Affairs Services in the Deepened Cooperation Zone.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>27% of the elderly suffer from light cognitive deficit</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/27-dos-idosos-sofrem-de-defice-cognitivo-ligeiro/</link><description>AGU OHER 79798798



Lau Veng Seng, director of the Kiang Wu Charity Association, said that more than 27% of Macau's elderly suffer from light cognitive deficit. Given this situation, the hospital considers that it is "urgent to create a system of systematic brain health protection that covers all phases of the disease." The director also mentioned that hospital representatives participated in Beijing in an exclusive study on the disease, with the purpose of bringing to Macao "the results of the most advanced scientific research in the country." The objective will combine the data with the reality of Macao, making scientific information more effective and appropriate for the sire's patients. Lau also revealed that the hospital began to develop a treatment plan on cognitive deficit consisting of introducing “intelligent treatment methods” for the disease. The intention is to increase the scraping rate of light cognitive deficit screening through artificial intelligence techniques. At the same time, Kiang Wu Hospital organized several academic teams in the creation of a cognitive evaluation center, to create a tracking service system on the cognitive deficit “in the early stage”, through interdisciplinary treatments and the extension of their home services, Lau explained.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Baby box in South Korea is the last refuge for single mothers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/caixa-para-bebe-na-coreia-sul-e-ultimo-refugio-para-maes-solteiras/</link><description>"I just gave birth to a baby," a woman said on the phone when Mrs. Hwang Min-Sook was about to leave work on a winter day. Hwang insisted that he would call 119, the medical emergency line, but she replied, "I can't do that." Then Hwang told him to catch a taxi and find it at Babybox Korea in Gwanak -gu, Seoul.
A few hours later, the woman arrived with the newborn. The staff suggested that he spent there at night and went to the hospital the next morning, but she insisted on leaving and did not take the baby. He said he needed to clean the blood and other signs of delivery before vacating a rented room the next day.
A month later, she turned on. He explained that the room was in an urbanization zone where residents had changed. He was dusty and had no electricity, and she rented the space temporarily to give birth.
It was then that Hwang understood what could have caused the newborn's infection.
After this call, the mother never came into contact. As soon as the health of the baby was restored, it was transferred to a children's care center.
Not everyone can imagine what this mother has gone through. But Hwang said, "Many give birth to their own and leave their babies. Baby Box is their last refuge."
A baby box is a place that allows mothers to leave their babies safe in a protected environment.
Currently, in South Korea, there are two facilities of this type: the one in front of the Jusarang Church, which manages Babybox Korea, is the first of its kind.
The babies box was founded by church pastor Lee Jong-rak. On a winter night of 2007, he received a call around three o'clock in the morning. A man said he had left a baby in front of the church.
Pastor Lee ran abroad and found a baby with Down syndrome lying in a smelled fish box. The news spread that he was taking care of a child with disabilities, and soon more babies with various conditions began to appear in front of the church at night.
Fearing that someone could die of cold, built a box where parents could leave the babies safely.
The box was later modernized with a sensor that fires an alarm when a baby is placed inside. The team, which works 24 hours a day per shifts, responds immediately. Whenever possible, it also offers counseling to mothers.
The concept is not unique to South Korea. Baby boxes - with the same name or with different names - exist in at least 20 countries, including US, Germany, Czech Republic, Poland and Japan.
Since Pastor Lee installed the Caixa in front of his church, 2,181 babies were delivered until March 2025.
When a baby is born, the institution's team takes care of the child until six months, so that local authorities then determine their future. Of the 2,181 babies, 1,693 were sent to day care centers, 167 were adopted and 311 returned to their mothers. In the remaining 10 cases, the records are not available.
Mrs. Hwang said that when the alarm fires, the institution usually takes the mother to counseling and offers all the necessary support. "The main objective of counseling is to encourage mothers to create babies alone," he added, noting that the center offers support for three years, including babies kits, medical expenses, legal assistance and housing, as well as subsistence expenses. All of this is funded by donations.
"The saddest is when mothers disappear or do not give up guard. If mothers do not abdicate the guard, babies cannot be adopted."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>