<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Chief warns of “old problems” and “new challenges”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-alerta-para-velhos-problemas-novos-desafios-economicos/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai warned yesterday that the "old problems" that affect the economy of Macau should "persist" for a while, while "new challenges". The chief executive pointed to the risks that Macao faces, given the “international strategy of the new US government and the uncertainty of policies in relation to China”, as well as internal difficulties in Macao and the country

Catarina Pereira
 
The chief executive warned yesterday to the “old problems” existing in the economy of the territory and the “new challenges” that are fired. At this year's first plenary meeting of the Council for Economic Development, Sam Hou Fai discussed the internal and external environment of Macau's development, pointing out that “it has suffered and will continue to undergo profound and complex changes” - now, he said, the economy of Territory is in a “crucial phase of transition”.
From the point of view of the international environment, the leader of the MSAR has noted that, in recent years, "unilateralism and protectionism have aggravated significantly," so "many unstable and uncertain factors" are imposed on global economic development. “Macao, as a highly open micro-economic to the outside, cannot be immune. At the same time, the international competition that the main sector of Macau is facing tends to get worse, so the inherent risks and challenges cannot be ignored, ”he said during the speech.
Looking at the home environment, he said that "the support conditions and the basic tendency to the positive and long -term development of the interior economy of China have maintained unchanged." However, “in the short term, we should be aware that as the US increases customs rates on imports this month, the international strategy of the new US government and the uncertainty of policies in relation to China bring us a new Negative impact, ”he said.
Pointing out that China's economic functioning “continues to face many difficulties and challenges”, facing pressure on the insufficiency of domestic demand, the difficulties of production and exploitation of some companies, employment and increased resident performance, Sam Hou Fai Defend that it takes "extra attention and proper answer." Especially because "the economy of Macao has to pillar the integrated tourism and leisure industry and is highly dependent on the market of visitors in the interior of China."
 
Pillar sector, resources and sources of tourists
In the internal level, the chief executive predicts that, at the economic level, "the structural problem of 'exclusive development of the game sector as a single sector of the economy' is still difficult to change substantially over a certain period of time." In addition, he continued, "old problems such as scarcity of resources, a unique structure of tourist sources, imbalance of financial revenue and insufficient innovation ability to resolve more effectively." At the same time, the new economic cycle and changes verified around the consumer model and class of consumers “also bring new challenges,” says Sam Hou Fai.
“How can we properly deal with the problem of insufficient development and imbalance of Macao's internal economy during the process of economic recovery; With conflicts derived from the development of industrial diversification not to live up to the expectations of society, as well as with the common difficulties and pressing that the small and medium companies of Macau are facing? And how can we better develop hengqin exploration under the cooperation between Guangdong and Macau, so that it can effectively contribute to the economic development of Macao? ”He asked.
"Regardless of being urgent solutions or long -term plans, these old problems and new challenges cannot be avoided, and we must find concrete solutions together," he replied. He also recalled the “four hopes” left by the Chinese president, when his visit to the territory in December last year, stressing that it is necessary to “unite efforts and persist, with confidence and determination, in the reform, assuming all responsibilities, in order to not defraud the expectations of President Xi Jinping and the Central Government. ”
 
Development of “high quality”
"Macao's economy is currently in a crucial phase of transition from a recovery development to high quality development," he said. In this sense, it argued that it is necessary to “consolidate consensus and form synergies”, as well as insist “in a mindset of economy facing the market and promoting the entrepreneurial spirit, in order to effectively balance the relationship between the consideration of the current situation and the planning of the future ”.
Sam Hou Fai said it is equally necessary to face difficulties and reinforce trust, have an efficient market and proactive government, revitalize the existing and increase quality and quantity, develop the economy and improve the well-being of the population, and also achieve a “High quality development and high level safety”.
Pointing out that 2025 marks the beginning of the government's mandate that directs, reiterated that the effective coordination and execution of the work for the present year regarding the social and economic development of Macao ”is" crucial.
“With a spirit of facing challenges without fear and reformist innovation, we will keep a precautionary and searching mindset for excellence, adopting new forms of reasoning, more effective methods and greater determination to achieve new advances in the development of the economy and the construction of the area deepened cooperation, increasing the sense of participation and realization of sectors and residents, ”he said.
Sam Hou Fai also stated that “aligned with the position of Macau as 'a center, a platform, a base', we will strive to build a highly attractive territory for high-level international qualified frames, preparing and enhancing the enabling Macao economy for long -term development through internal and external connections. ”</description><pubDate>2025-02-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Anima focused on managing 700 animals in overcrowded facilities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/anima-focada-em-gerir-700-animais-em-instalacoes-sobrelotadas/</link><description>The financial situation of Macao Animal Protective Society - animates little or nothing has changed in recent times and 2025 will bring back great worries. The year is still in the beginning and the first two months have already caused debts of 1.1 million patacas. One of the boards of salvation remains the support, through subsidies, from the Macau Foundation, which made available in January a first tranche, of 1.93 million patacas. The budget scheduled for this year is over 8 million. "The biggest problems are the debts contracted and not yet paid, which makes the situation increasingly complicated," the Journal of Macau told the Association's executive committee chairman. The anima currently welcomes 400 dogs and 300 cats
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Macao Animal Protective Society - Anima continues to face significant financial restrictions, a situation that has been dragging on for several years, increasingly with more accumulated debt. The association transported to this year a debt of 400,000 patacas and has accumulated, in just two months, January and February, plus 1.1 million, which makes a total of 1.5 million patacas.
"Last year, at its worst moment, Estimated Anima's debt was about 2.3 million patacas," the Association's president of the Association's executive committee told the Jornal de Macao, adding that "although some funds have been received And used to settle part of the outstanding debt, the financial situation remains difficult and there is little or no money for operating expenses. ”
Zoe Tang confirms that anima saw approved last January a Macau Foundation allowance that totaled about 4.8 million patacas for this year, paid in four installments. The first Tronche, worth 1.93 million patacas, “has already been used to pay previous debts,” says the leader, for whom “the biggest problems are the debts contracted and not yet paid, which makes the situation each time more complicated ”.
Regarding non -official support, that is, private individuals and private entities, the association continues to conduct multiple campaigns and knock on various doors. “We have not stopped asking for support from the community and companies,” says Zoe Tang. However, he stresses, "due to current economic difficulties, many companies are also in trouble." Nevertheless, he attests, "five casinos (MGM, Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment Limited, Sands Macao, Galaxy Macau and Wynn Macau) donated an 80,000 patacas last year to help anima."
Regarding the requests for financial support with the game operators in Macao, number one in the direction of the Association underlines that constant appeals have been made to the casinos, through their annual letter, requesting donations.
The animal budget for 2025 is approximately 8.3 million patacas, “to maintain operations throughout the year,” explains Zoe Tang.
Due to financial restrictions, anima has not been able to hire new employees. “We strongly depend on volunteers, but it is difficult to find consistent and long-term people who can commit to the opening hours of our organization,” which opens at 09h00 and ends at 6 pm, Zoe Tang explained.
 
“There is no ability to expand”
From year to year, the number of animals that the anima welcomes in its shelters has increased, which leads to overcrowding. “In fact, many of our shelters are already full, not having diminished the wandering animal population,” those found on the public road not accompanied by its owner, unidentified or with indications of abandonment.
This problem has gained even greater dimension because, says Zoe Tang, “there has been no update, or signs of implementation, in discussions that have been ongoing with the government, about the Trap-Neter-Return Program (T.N.R)”, which In Portuguese it means "to capture, sterilize and return to the place of origin."
The system, implemented in many countries, may prevent, for example, that cats give birth and multiply, knowing that they are highly fertile. Because cats have high reproductive power, animal protection societies believe that T.N.R can reduce the birth of cats through sterilization surgery, reducing their slaughter.
The chairman of the animal executive committee is peremptory when referring to the short space available to host the animals. "We no longer have enough facilities to welcome more animals, dogs or cats, due to the lack of space and resources." It also clarifies that existing dogs, many of which are older, need prolonged care.
The anima welcomes about 300 cats and 400 dogs, six hamsters and about 25 turtles. Zoe Tang states that "as space is extremely limited, there is no ability to expand." For the person responsible, "the main objective at this time is to manage existing animals, ensuring that they receive medical care, food and proper shelter."
It also makes an effort to work with volunteers to sterilize stray dogs, covering transportation costs and medical procedures while volunteers deal with capture and care.
According to the statistics provided by the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI), last year were slaughtered in the Municipal Kennel 430 Animals - 119 cats and 311 dogs. An increase of almost 20% over the previous year, when 360 animals died.
While slaughtering increased, also rose the number of animal adoptions and complaints, show the data released by AMI. In the year that ended, 614 animals were adopted or claimed - 373 cats and 241 dogs. This number reflects an increase of about 16% compared to 2023, when 528 animals - 327 cats and 201 dogs were adopted.
The anima underlines that it will maintain a close collaboration with AMI, also promoting monthly stands and animal -related events.
On the other hand, Zoe Tang admitted that there are other pending issues: “We also have to solve the problem of our sewers because the direction of soil services and urban construction requires that we call our sewage to public sewers, and it is not allowed to use the truck Pump to collect fecal waters, otherwise our land renewal will not be approved. ”
Since 2003, the association has been dedicated to creating adequate conditions and veterinary care to abandoned and mistreated animals, will continue this year to organize monthly adoption campaigns, activities that allow the public to interact with animals and know the work of the organization.
In less than a year and a half, more specifically in July 2026, the anima will have elections for its managing bodies.</description><pubDate>2025-02-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Pugilist convicted of negligence homicide</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pugilista-condenado-por-homicidio-por-negligencia/</link><description>The second instance court sentenced to a year and three months in prison, suspended in execution, a boxer who a few years ago participated in a friendly boxing combat that would eventually lead to a man's death. Considered that the athlete was negligent
 
Catarina Pereira
 
A boxer who four years ago was involved in a friendly fight with another fighter, who died, was convicted of negligent murder in material authorship and in a consummate form. After being acquitted by the Base Judicial Court (TJB), the man will have to serve a year and three months in prison, suspended in execution for two years, and pay compensation to the victim's family in the amount of nearly 750,000 patacas, according to the decision of the Court of Second Instance (TSI).
The two friends, with several years experience in boxing, combined a friendly boxing match, which was attended by a licensed combat coach. They also woke up that they would not wear a helmet during the dispute. The first two rounds were between attacks and defenses on both parties, indicates the official note, adding that one of the fighters then reached the other “with vigorous punches”, having the colleague on the floor. It was at this time that the referee declared suspension of the match.
The died fighter got up, talked to his colleagues and went down from the ring voluntarily to rest. He eventually fainted and falling to the floor, having hit his head on an iron rod. He was transported to the hospital and would die days later.
The deceased's wife and daughter asked Muay Thai athlete and the referee, but the TJB acquitted the murder fighter for serious offenses to physical integrity, and rejected the claim for compensation. Disagreeing, they resorted to the TSI.
The court stressed that the rules of common experience teach that the head is one of the vital parts of the human body, pointing out that in a boxing combat not using helmet puts the brain "at risk of serious irreversible injuries." In this sense, he considered the agreement “invalid”.
Saying that the friendly match aimed to foster the technical mastery of both parties, and that neither intended to hurt the opponent, the TSI states, however, that Muay Thai athlete should know that in a confrontation without enough security measures, “ Dangerousness intensifies significantly, which could cause physical injuries. ”
Since the added risk "is no longer within the measure allowed for a match whose safety is sufficiently guaranteed", the boxer "did not stop committing a negligent crime and must assume criminal liability for negligence murder, given the death caused" . As for compensation, TSI understands that it should be reduced, since the victim participated in the boxing departure on their own and agreed that they would not wear helmets.
The prison sentence will then be, according to TSI, one year and three months in prison, suspended in execution. On the other hand, you will have to pay 378,260 patacas to the deceased's wife and 371,400 patacas to his daughter, as compensation.</description><pubDate>2025-02-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Water ateves 3% rise in water consumption</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-water-anteve-subida-de-3-consumo-de-agua/</link><description>After the total water supply in Macau has risen 5.6% to 100 million cubic meters by 2024, water consumption could record a 3% increase this year, predicted Kuan Sio Peng, Macau Water's executive director. On the other hand, the official said the company decided to extend the “Financial Support Plan to repair the water supply facilities for low buildings” for a period of three years
 
Last year, the total water supply in Macau increased by 5.6% (about five million cubic meters) compared to 2023, reaching a record of 100 million cubic meters. The climb was mainly driven by the general recovery of the integrated tourism sector and related economic activities, said Kuan Sio Peng, Macau Water's executive director, at a spring lunch offered to the media. Specifically, it revealed that the islands registered a more notorious increase in water consumption by 2024.
Looking at this year, Macau Water's head anticipated that, with the gradual conclusion of various construction projects in zone A of new landfills and new government buildings, as well as the city's economic development, water supply in Macau may increase about 3%.
On the sidelines of lunch, Kuan Sio Peng also revealed that the company decided to extend the term of the “financial support plan to repair the water supply facilities for low buildings” for three years. The plan should end in March this year, but after an internal evaluation of the company, it was concluded that the initiative was effective in helping participants solve the hygiene problem in low buildings and contributed to reduce the water loss rate on networks of tubing.
According to the plan, the plan has about 700 participating buildings, which represent 20% to 30% of the total low buildings in the territory. The company expects to widen the coverage of the plan through inspections and information revealed by citizens.
Given that residents' consciousness has increased for water conservation and condominium repair, the official believes that the number of participating buildings will record an increase between 20% and 30% after the extension of the plan.
On the other hand, Kuan Sio Peng said that Macau Water is able to provide water for hengqin if there is this need. "Our ability is sufficient to fulfill this commitment," he added.
In a speech given before lunch, the Macau Water Executive Director also recalled that last year to support the Ká-Hó Dam expansion venture, the company completed the installation of equipment and water conducts in the surrounding area, increasing the total effective capacity of local reservoirs to 2.64 million cubic meters, equivalent to 10 days of water consumption in Macao, and “actually enhancing the guarantee capacity of the local water supply system ”.
This year, the company will continue to cooperate with the work of building water supply and underground conducts shared in Zone A.
On the other hand, he stressed that Macau Water continued to promote two scientific research projects with the University of Tsinghua and the University of Sun Yat-sen, as well as cooperation in the industrial, academic and research sectors with various educational institutions Superior from Macao and the interior of China, continually providing internship opportunities for students of these institutions.
Last year, the company established an internship base in collaboration with the University of Tsinghua Shenzhen Research Institute. For the future, Macau Water hopes to further promote the deep integration of the three sectors and the formation of talent in the water supply sector.
Regarding the conservation of water, the official pointed out that the open day of the Ilha Verde Water Treatment Station had, last year, with a record of 2,000 visitors.
Yesterday Macau Water also organized the opening ceremony of the celebrations of its 90th anniversary. Kuan Sio Peng noted that the company expanded its operating scale, moving from a small water treatment plant to four major modern stations, and evolving into a digitized water production process, whose quality has been improving and already fulfills the standards of Macao, China, the European Union and the World Health Organization.
To commemorate the date, the company is planning and organizing a series of events, including technical water supply seminars, the open day of the water treatment plant, the Wechat campaign and a game of questions and answers online, with the aim to sensitize the public for the conservation and rationalization of water resources.
On the other hand, Kuan Sio Peng has stressed that Macau Water “will work in full articulation with the country's policies and objectives and the Government of the Masters and will be more actively in global national development, also exploring the application of innovative technologies. In the area of ​​water supply, along with counterparts in the Great Bay, with a view to boosting the development of intelligent water services. ”</description><pubDate>2025-02-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>STD intends to “consolidate” Hong Kong Market</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dst-pretende-consolidar-mercado-de-hong-kong/</link><description>About a hundred representatives of Hong Kong's tourist industry participated in a lunch offered by Macao tourism services, which served to open the cloth of this year's promotions, directed to the neighboring territory market. Helena de Senna Fernandes expects to reinforce cooperation “at different levels” to boost the sustainable development of the tourist industry on both sides
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) organized a spring lunch in Hong Kong, which was attended by more than 100 representatives of the tourist industry in the neighboring territory. The conviviality opened the cloth of this year's promotions directed to the Hong Kong market, which STD aims to continue to explore in accordance with the promotional plan drawn.
The objective is “to proceed with the consolidation of Macao's second largest visitors market,” as read in a statement from STD, a body that recalls the figures recorded in 2024, which pointed to Raehk's 7.1 million tourists.
Based on this reality, Helena de Senna Fernandes, who headed the Macao delegation, said in her speech that the tourism of the MSAR expects, “in conjunction with the homologous services and partners of the tourist industry of the neighboring region, that cooperation is reinforced in different levels to boost the sustainable development of the tourist industry on both sides. ”
The STD director stressed that the body that guardians will continue to make promotions on “different fronts” to the Hong Kong market, including through online platforms, social networks and online and face -to -face activities, and according to the needs of different groups of Hong Kong market visitors, “discover more points of interest in Macau”.
At the same time, the representation of STD in Hong Kong “will strengthen communication and cooperation with the tourist industry”, regularly conducting product presentation sessions, thematic familiarization visits, joint and consumer promotions, among others, in the sense of ““ I consolidate the visitors market even more, ”said Senna Fernandes.
To collaborate in the dissemination of Lunar New Year's commemorative activities in Macao, STD invited more than 20 micro influencers, and also cooperated with the generalist press and renowned tourism and leisure newspapers, in order to increase the number of reports and of Macao exhibition.
On the other hand, during “Holiday &amp; Travel Expo 2025”, which will take place in Hong Kong between today and Saturday, STD will especially launch the “Experience Macao” Mega Sale campaign, in which, together with several Territory Travel Agencies Neighbor, will sell discount attractive tour packages to attract more residents of Hong Kong to visit Macau, injecting new vitality into the tourist economy of Macao.
STD points out that in 2025 it will continue to hold online and face -to -face promotions at national and abroad, organize various events and promote community tourism, as well as boosting the development of Macau as a creative city of gastronomy.</description><pubDate>2025-02-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ipim helped three Portuguese companies enter Hengqin</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ipim-ajudou-tres-empresas-lusas-entrar-em-hengqin/</link><description>Three Portuguese capital companies had the support of IPIM to get trade licenses in Hengqin, where they are operating in areas such as Legal Consulting and Project Management
 
The Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment (IPIM) of Macau told Lusa that it helped three Portuguese capital companies to establish business in Hengqin. "Currently, there are three cases of Portuguese investors who have obtained commercial licenses in the cooperation zone [in -depth between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin]," Ipim added.
In response to questions sent by Lusa, the body revealed that the three Portuguese capital companies are operating in “areas such as legal consultancy and project management”.
IPIM said the companies in Macao with foreign investment from Portugal, Germany, Czech Republic and Australia represent about 7% of requests received for registration in Hengqin.
On February 6, the IPIM indicated, in a statement, that it had received 100 requests from Macao companies, through a trade registration transformer service in the Special Economic Zone, with almost 90 already approved.
The institute told Lusa that the remaining processes have not yet been passed because "they include cases in follow -up, waiting for additional documents or where there were adjustments made by the applicants themselves."
Macao companies with foreign capital “are optimistic” about taking advantage of the special economic zone for expansion in the interior market of China, Ipim said in the statement issued in early February.
More than 40% of Macao companies that have already bet on Hengqin are involved in integrated tourism and leisure industries, health and well-being, modern finances, cutting-edge technologies, conventions and exhibitions, commerce, culture and sport, added the body.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-02-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Airlines ensure helping to transport deadly victims from Taichung</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/companhias-aereas-garantem-ajudar-transportar-vitimas-mortais-de-taichung/</link><description>Both Air Macau and Starlux have ensured that they will provide help in transporting the remains of Macau residents who were victimized by the explosion in Taichung, denying the refusal of transportation
 
Following the explosion in a shopping center in Taichung, Taiwan, which caused two residents of Macao, Taiwan press reported that “as airlines rejected transporting deadly, the victims' relatives decided to believe the bodies in Taiwan to Later bring the ashes to Macau. ” However, to the Macao press in Chinese language, the two carriers who operate Taichung-Macau flights have stressed that they will provide help in transporting the remains.
On the one hand, Air Macau said it has measures and preparations for this type of situation. Regarding the case in question, the Flag Air Company stressed that it has kept contact with several parts, being "available at any time to provide support and assistance." He also stressed that he had not refused to transport the remains.
In turn, the “Starlux” airline has also denied that there has been a problem of refusal to transport remains, ensuring that the company has done, over many years, a standardized operation of this type of transport. According to “Starlux”, whenever the passenger submits this request, the company will surely help to deal with the situation.
Regarding the two -year -old Macao girl, seriously injured in the explosion, Taichung Hospital revealed that the child's vital signs have been stable and her brain pressure began to decrease. Temperature control treatment has also been completed. According to the hospital, the medical team will treat and continually observe this patient.</description><pubDate>2025-02-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Participation in the games will “reinforce” influence on “sports arena”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/participacao-nos-jogos-reforcara-influencia-na-arena-desportiva/</link><description>The Macao Competition Zone Organizing Committee of the National Games, the National Games for People with Disabilities and the National Special Olympic Games met under the presidency of the committee's head and Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, Lam. , representatives of various public services made the point of the situation regarding the preparations of the games, discussed and exchanged points of view on, among other aspects, sports facilities, transit provisions, passage TRANSFORNING, FOOD SAFETY AND MEDICAL SERVICES. The preparatory office of competitions, which will be held in the territory in November and December, said in a statement that “it will continue to fully take advantage of the connecting effects between public services and social entities to jointly take the work of preparation of the games. ”. The secretary O Lam, in turn, said that the participation of the masters in the organization of the event “will not only further reinforce Macau's influence on the sports arena, but will also promote in -depth cooperation between the cities of the great bay in several domains, such such as sport, tourism and culture, injecting a new vitality in the development of the proper diversification of the economy. ” He also stressed that the games, "besides having a great responsibility in promoting the development of the sports industry, also allow us to show the nation's overall capacity, being a platform that promotes exchange and cooperation between regions." Cabinet coordinator Pun Weng Kun presented the emblem, slogan and mascot of the tests, as well as the works related to the Macao competition zone, including dates and facilities, volunteer program and test competitions, among others.</description><pubDate>2025-02-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>280,000 watched the firefight and the stop</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/280-000-assistiram-ao-fogo-de-artificio-a-parada/</link><description>The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) took stock of the activities performed during the festive period of the Lunar New Year, highlighting the number of viewers who witnessed the fireworks show and the celebration parade. The first event, which had three exhibitions, attracted close to 210,000 people, while the second, with two parades of floats, had assistance calculated by almost 78,000. The body also launched the “Happy Chinese New Year - Golden Stars” hobby in the “interactive STD zone” on Wechat, with the interactive games “Bricks of Fortune” and “Year of Snake”. During the promotion period, a total of 108,438 people participated in the games and 67,203 entered the raffles. In a note released yesterday, STD states that it collected the opinions of residents and visitors about the activities performed, through inquiries and different means, with the aim of “knowing the evaluation of residents and visitors about events and their benefits”. The statement points out, on the other hand, that the integration of the three activities, namely the Giant Dragon Dragon parade, the celebration parade and the fireworks, at the cultural exchange brand event with the outside, which is The “Happy Chinese New Year” celebration staff of the RPC Ministry of Culture and Tourism reflects the capacity and attraction of Macao's “Tourism+Events”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>500 non -residents repatriated within one month</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/500-nao-residentes-repatriados-espaco-de-um-mes/</link><description>Between January and February, authorities submitted 500 non -residents to the Public Security Police Border Control Department, so that the repatriation process began, Unit Police Services (SPU) indicated. In this “Winter Preventive Operation”, 8,598 agents and 45 patrol vessels were mobilized in the performance of 651 police operations, having identified 41,953 individuals. Of these, 1,140 were taken to the police for involvement in 365 cases, namely related to drugs, theft, sloping, theft, provision of illegal immigration, illicit loan, exploration of illicit exchange rate, among others. Among the detainees, 464 were sent to the judiciary, 345 being subject to coercion or conviction measures, while 22 were arrested preventively. In addition, 18 were intercepted in compliance with warrants of capture and detention issued by the judicial bodies, including 13 were sent to the prison establishment for immediate penalty, the SPU indicated. On the other hand, customs services triggered actions to combat smuggling, illegal immigration and counterfeiting. Regarding activities related to parallel trade, 305 people were administratively accused in accordance with the “Foreign Trade Law”. In the course of the actions were seized tobacco, electronic cigarettes, alcohol, cosmetic products, fresh and living food, electronic products, extinction plants, among others. In a balance of the “winter operation”, the authorities considered that “fully achieved the expected results, having contributed to the maintenance of the security and stability of the social order of Macao”. With the increase in the number of tourists, the SPU have guaranteed that they will remain “attentive to the situation of security” in the territory, adjusting the police strategies and triggering preventive operations in order to maintain a stable and safe environment in the region.</description><pubDate>2025-02-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IAM is negotiating with IC Camões Bust</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/iam-esta-negociar-ic-reparacao-busto-de-camoes/</link><description>Already issued by the Cultural Institute, technical opinions for the work of repairing the bust of Camões, which is in the cave with the name of the poet. However, the Institute for Municipal Affairs did not indicate to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao a date for the beginning of the work, saying only that it is “negotiating the plan and demands” of the statue's repair
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau to be “in contact” with the Cultural Institute (IC) “to negotiate the plan and repair requirements of Luís de Camões bust in Jardim de Luís de Camões” . The answer came after the IC informed this newspaper that it has already issued technical opinions about the repair works, by AMI.
As for the procedures to be adopted in the work, neither the body led by Leong Wai Man, nor the body directed by Chao Wai Ieng advanced details. AMI had already said that after having the opinions of the IC would start the work, however, no date has not been indicated to start. The statue, it is noted, is in the area of ​​a classified property and has historical value, as the IC has already stressed.
The third stanza of “Os Lusíadas” on the back of the pedestal where Luís Vaz de Camões bust is practically unreadable. It is the number 81 of singing VI: “And yet, nymphs of mine, it was not enough/ that such misery would surround me,/ but those that I singing walked/ such a prize of my verses made me:/ the change of the rests I expected,/ From the bay chapels that honored me,/ works never used invented me,/ with which in such a hard state they lay me down. ”
Faced with this situation in July last year, AMI had told JTM that “it had already found that the registration is disappearing” and that it was “accompanying”, having added that maintenance work would be performed.
It should be noted that the first two excerpts in the stone pedestal in the Camões cave can still read. They concern the stanza 95 of singing VI and the resort 42 of singing VIII.
The garden of Luis de Camões, one of the oldest in Macao, was created in the mid -eighteenth century. In the cave, consisting of three large faceted rocks, there is then the bust of Camões, by sculptor Manuel Maria Bordalo Pinheiro.
It is said that in the mid-16th century, Camões (1524-1580) lived in Macao for two years, where he will have finished, in the cave that has its name today, the work "The Lusíadas". “With the sponsorship of 600 francs from a rich Portuguese merchant from Macao, Lourenço Marques, son -in -law of Manuel Pereira, the cave was renewed in 1849, and there was a bust of the poet. A pavilion on the cave was also erected, which no longer exists. The last restoration of the group dates from 1866 and the poet's bust was refused in bronze, ”can be read on the Macao Cultural Heritage page.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Suggested reorganization of the public transport system</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sugerida-reorganizacao-sistema-de-transportes-publicos/</link><description>Several deputies made suggestions on public buses and the slight meter. Leong Sun Iok called on the reorganization of the public transport system when the bus contracts end and the acceleration of the construction of the West Metro line. Nick Law wants to achieve discounts on the transfer between buses and the meter after the end of these contracts. On the other hand, Ngan Iek Hang expects both to play a better role in relieving traffic pressure while performing concerts
 
Deputy Leong Sun Iok considers that the end of public business contracts at the end of next year is an opportunity for the government to reorganize Macao's public transport system to raise its efficiency. In particular, the government entered the optimize bus career and lightweight lines, adjusting the operational times of the two public transport means and increasing the ease of transfer between buses and the subway.
From its perspective, according to a preliminary analysis, it will be difficult to reach the target of a daily volume of 137,000 passengers in the meter by 2030. Remembering that services for traffic issues do not yet have a detail plan relative to the west line, He stressed that, given the constant increase in the number of visitors, the government should start as soon as possible to work related to this line, shorten the construction cycle of the metro network, and transform it into a Ring format.
For the deputy, in a context where the transportation capacity of public buses "has already reached the limit" and it will be difficult to have more careers, the extension of the metro network will provide a new solution.
In addition, Leong Sun Iok lamented the lack of diversity of the electronic payment means in the Metro, so it urged to improve the payment system. On the other hand, it suggested measures aimed at raising the subway's ability to divert people while holding events in the city.
Regarding buses, the deputy proposed that, taking the metro network as the core of the public transport system, companies reinforce the “intelligent buses” as well as differentiate and adjust the careers of buses through played.
In turn, Deputy Nick Law anticipated the increase in the demand for the service of Metro with the implementation of new visa policies. Thus, it defended, in a written interplies, the updating of the electronic payment function of the input and exit access channels in the metro stations, so that the equipment corresponds to the habits of payment of the population.
As for the automatic metro selling machines, Nick Lei understands that the payment function with code code should be added. After this step, it expects electronic tickets to be launched and a mobile application to reduce the time to purchase metro tickets.
In addition, the deputy once again urged the executive to make discounts on the transfer between buses and the meter, so that more people want to use this means of transport and to maximize their effectiveness. It concretely argued that authorities should take advantage of the termination of bus contracts to advance with this work.
 
Exclusive bus careers for concerts
On the other hand, Ngan Iek Hang has proposed careers of exclusive buses that circulate between border stations and concert places. It also suggested the extension of the operational time of the subway, in order to relieve pressure on traffic in general and on the border passages.
The deputy also requested, in written interplies, more analysis of the flow of people during large -scale shows, using the authorities, for the authorities to warn visitors in advance about the traffic situation. In your opinion, during “special periods”, more manual ways should be opened at the borders and accelerated the launch of roads of border passage directed exclusively to residents.
In the same vein, Che Fok Sang, director of the Macao Federal Commercial Association of the Convention and Exhibition Industry, also proposed “Shuttle-Bus” that transport directly and free spectators from concert site for old zones. Alongside this, the executive director of the "Chessman Entertainment Production" suggested tourist scripts "concert + cultural experience" in order to stimulate the recovery of commercial establishments in ancient areas.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>21 years in prison for assistant prosecutor Kong Chi</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/21-anos-de-prisao-para-procurador-adjunto-kong-chi/</link><description>The last court aggravated from 17 to 21 years in prison the penalty applied to the assistant prosecutor Kong Chi, because he also committed the crime of association or secret society
 
Kong Chi, deputy prosecutor of the suspended mandate, was sentenced yesterday by the last court (TUI) to a single sentence of 21 years in prison, in legal entity. This sentence represents an aggravation of the 17 -year sentence imposed by the Court of Second Instance (TSI) in January 2024 in a process where Kong was accused of helping people escape the court in 30 cases. At the time, it was considered guilty of dozens of crimes of passive corruption for illicit act, abuse of power, prevarication and violation of secrecy of justice.
Tui now considered that Kong Chi is also guilty of the crime of association or secret society, validating the prosecutor's thesis (MP). According to the prosecution, the main defendant will have received bribes, in collusion with the couple of entrepreneurs Choi Sao Ieng and NG Wai Chu, to interfere in several cases of criminal investigation, illegally file the proceedings and raise the property seized.
Choi and NG's penalties were also aggravated by Tui, from 14 to 16 years and six to 10 years in prison, respectively.
The MP and the three defendants filed appeals with the last instance, raising issues such as “the nullity of the decision, proof of facts, the assessment of the evidence, the prescription of criminal proceedings, the application of the law, and the measure of the penalty”, Among others, according to a note from the Tui President's office.
The appeals were partially judged in some aspects, translating namely in the prescription of a crime of passive corruption for illicit act committed by Kong and three of prevarication imputed to the three defendants. In addition, the convictions for some crimes were revoked and the typology of others were revoked.
On the other hand, TUI decided to condemn Kong for the crime of management or head of association or secret society, and the couple of entrepreneurs for participation in association or secret society. Kong was also considered guilty of two inaccuracy crimes of the elements.
The remaining decision of the TSI remained unchanged. It is recalled that the TSI also determined the loss, in favor of the MSAR, of assets arrested by the deputy prosecutor in the amount of 14 million patacas, considering them as “of unknown origin”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>From Auschwitz to Tiktok, as young people learn about the Holocaust</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/de-auschwitz-ao-tiktok-como-os-jovens-aprendem-sobre-holocausto/</link><description>He was a teenager like them. “I arrived here on September 2, 1943”, begins in the extermination field of Auschwitz-Birkenau the French survivor Esther Senot for high school students. A first person testimony that will soon be possible.
About 100 young people hear the former deportionate who, at almost 97, still made a point of traveling to explain the horror of Auschwitz, 80 years after his release by the Red Army in January 1945.
“We slept 18 people per bed. Around five in the morning, the head of the block made us force out, hitting a stick. We took those who died at night to tell them… ”.
“I had a fixed idea: I can't die at age 15,” he continued, reporting how he rediscovered his 17 -year -old sister in the countryside, so malnourished that she barely recognized her. “She said to me,‘ I won't live long. You are young, promise me that if you turn, you will tell our story so that we are not forgotten by the story.
Built in occupied Poland, Auschwitz-Birkenau is the symbol of genocide perpetrated by Nazi Germany, which resulted in the deaths of six million Jews, including about one million murdered in the field between 1940 and 1945.
For the teenagers, who saw the bags, utensils and hair that the deported had to leave before their execution, the barracks surrounded by barbed wire, the gas chambers and the crematorium, the impact was direct.
“We have told us about numbers in class, but only here, we realized what people really lived,” explains Charlotte, 16, student at Saint Jean Hulst College in Versailles, near Paris, where the 15 students who participated in Travel shared their impressions some time later.
The preparation work was long, happening every Thursday mornings: “We can't simply take them, we need to prepare them,” explains Camille de Hillerin, pedagogical responsible for Austchwitz.
Readings, visit the synagogue and the Holocaust memorial in Paris, presentation of video testimonies and classes on the growth of anti-Semitism in Europe. “We focused on our work on the transmission of testimonies and the idea of ​​fraternity, which was destroyed by the fields,” he adds.
Before leaving the dark shed, Esther Senot exhorted the young people around him: "If we, at our age, devote time to alert them, it is hoping that this will not be repeated."
This is the purpose of taking young people today to Auschwitz, explains Haïm Korsia, a great rabbi of France, who has organized these trips from memory for over 20 years: “They become witnesses to witnesses.”
But soon the last survivors will disappear. “We need to reflect on how to continue transmitting this whole story to younger generations, which have a different way to listen,” says Alexandre Barycki, president of the “Mémoire du Convoi 6 et des Camps du Loiret” Association (“Comboio Memory 6 and of the fields of Loiret ”).”
The project allows you to enrich incomplete files - on train 6, by which 928 people were deported, but also makes it possible to understand the Holocaust's exterminating character. Sometimes “they find almost nothing. We say, "Do you understand what Nazis wanted to do by trying to erase all the traces of these people?"
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-02-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>