<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Monjardino regrets Portugal’s “lack of will” to resolve EPM problems</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/monjardino-lamenta-falta-de-vontade-de-portugal-para-resolver-problemas-da-epm/</link><description>The president of the East Foundation is again in Macao and will meet tomorrow with the secretary for social affairs and culture, revealed in an interview with the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. At the meeting with Lam, Carlos Monjardino will address, among other topics, the need for greater support to the Portuguese Institute of the East by the territory executive. The leader of the East Foundation considers that the role of IPOR is "very important in the work that has been done in terms of teaching from Portuguese to Chinese." About the Portuguese School of Macao, it stresses that the government of Portugal has not shown as much “will” as it wanted to solve “pending problems” in the educational establishment
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The work developed by the Portuguese Institute of the East (IPOR) in Macau, regarding the teaching of the Portuguese language, “will have to be more supported by the government of the territory,” says the chairman of the Board of Directors of the East Foundation.
In one more visit to MSA, before Ruma to Goa, where he will participate in the 30th anniversary of the East Foundation's installation in that former Lusa Colony, Carlos Monjardino insists on the need for greater help to IPOR, an issue that had already emphasized about a year ago when he moved to the territory.
As he did then, the president of Fundação Oriente will once again draw the Macao SAR Government's attention to this matter, through a meeting scheduled for tomorrow, with the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam.
“I will sensitize it to the need for greater help to the work that has been developed by IPOR in the teaching of the Portuguese language, and not Portuguese or other nationalities,” said Carlos Monjardino, by stressing that “IPOR It has a major role that deserved greater support from MSAR entities. ”
In an interview with the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the leader of the Oriente Foundation also addressed the issue of the lack of teachers that the Portuguese School of Macau (EPM) has felt in recent times.
Carlos Monjardino considers that “there must be good will from the Government of Portugal to resolve the problems that are pending”. Until now, “this desire has not existed, or at least it has not been as good as would be expected for a school that plays a fundamental role in teaching Portuguese outside of Portugal”, he lamented.
"The Portuguese school should be more cherished and the problems solved faster," said the official of the East Foundation, an institution whose departure from the EPM management structure was made official in September 2015, at a time when it no longer contributed to the establishment's budget teaching. At the time, with the formalization of the new statutes, the permanent change to Macao of the headquarters of the Portuguese School was also established.
Regarding the old question of the facilities of the Portuguese School building, the president of the Oriente Foundation regretted that this had not been resolved for years. The place where the former Hotel Estoril was even pointed out as a hypothesis for a possible change of facilities, among several possibilities explored over several years, including the sale of the land to the Macao Tourism Society (STDM ).
“The building was right next to the casino [Grand Lisboa] and it didn’t make sense to have a school so close to the casino”, recalls Carlos Monjardino. Probably, “it would be useful for STDM and we would look for money to then install the EPM in another location”, he added.
Asked about the factors that prevented these plans from being implemented, the director of Fundação Oriente said he had no idea why. “That is beyond me, it was outside my reign, so to speak,” he said, confirming that, at the time, the Foundation allocated a sum, which was not reciprocated due to the fact that there was no change of facilities. “At the time, there was certainly a reaction on my part, but the budget wasn’t that large either, from what I remember”, he observed, without indicating a specific amount.
In April 2014, the then Minister of Education and Science of Portugal ended the EPM 'dossier', formally announcing that the institution would remain in the premises where it continues to work currently. The decision took into account two aspects: the stability of the place and students and teachers and the duration of the chosen location, according to Nuno Crato.
Regarding the allocation of the funds granted by the Macau Games Society, owned by Stanley Ho, to the Fundação Escola Portuguesa de Macau, of around 65 million patacas, for the change of EPM facilities – which did not take place – the minister then attested that “there is, in fact, a donation”, deposited in the Foundation’s accounts, so “there is a process of dialogue that the foundation will now have to start with SJM, because part of that donation was guaranteed for the operation of the school.”
In an interview he gave to JTM in April 2023, Carlos Monjardino said that there would have to be a solution to the issue of EPM's facilities, however, he noted: “Quite frankly, I also see no reason to greatly increase the facilities at the Portuguese School , because the demand is relatively small, it is that which is and will grow little. Because it is the children of expatriates who want to take courses in Lisbon…”. Faced with the reality of the growth in the number of Chinese mother tongue students entering the School, Monjardino insisted, even so, that the increase in demand for teaching at the Portuguese School or for teaching Portuguese here would be “little”. “If I’m wrong, that’s great,” he added.
 
Works at Casa Garden finished in May
Regarding works at Casa Garden, Carlos Monjardino - who also held the position of substitute governor of the Macao government between 1986 and 1987 - wants the conclusion to be a reality in April. "But, delegate Catarina Cottinelli told me that perhaps only in late May," he said.
This historical building, located in the historic center of Macao and classified as UNESCO World Heritage, is considered a significant milestone in the region's cultural heritage. Built in the late eighteenth century, Casa Garden has been a space for cultural and social exchange, as well as being the headquarters of the Oriente Foundation, whose mission is to serve the local community and promote culture.
The works, which began in December, include the restoration of the exterior, the consolidation of the roof structure and facades, as well as the restoration of the architectural elements that make up the facade, such as the shutters and other decorative details.
The endeavor will be subsidized by the Cultural Institute, to whom the East Foundation thanked the “fundamental support” and the “contribution to the implementation of the Macao Historical Heritage Settlement Plan,” according to the body.
"This collaboration is vital to ensure that Casa Garden not only maintains its structural integrity, but it also remains an active space for culture and dialogue," said the Oriente Foundation. He also stressed that renewal is a source of enthusiasm, and once the works are completed, the East Foundation hopes to restart cultural activities, "which are essential for the community of Macao."</description><pubDate>2025-01-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Road accidents rose 14% to more than 15,500 in 2024</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/acidentes-de-viacao-subiram-14-para-mais-de-15-500-em-2024/</link><description>Last year, more than 15,500 road accidents were counted on the roads of Macao, a 14% rise in annual terms. Data from the Public Security Police Corps also reveal that the occurrences of illegal road crossing roads increased by almost 60% to a total of 7,460. The offenses practiced by taxi drivers also registered growth last year
 
CATARINA PEREIRA
 
Many of the offenses and parameters analyzed in traffic registered climbs last year. But the cases of pawns that cross the road without complying with the rules have stood out. According to statistics from the Public Security Police (CPSP), during 2024, there were 7,460 pawns that crossed the roads without complying with the traffic rules, translating a growth of 58.55% in annual terms, ie , 2,755 cases than those registered in the previous year.
Overall, authorities recorded 15,510 road accidents, an increase of 14.36% year-on-year, which caused 5,341 injuries (+12.94%), of which only 76 were admitted to hospital. However, fatal accidents decreased from eight to five. According to the data available, the fatal victims were all drivers.
Road accidents involving pedestrians also increased by 6.69% to 510 cases. Between January and December last year, there were 541 cases in which priority was not given at pedestrian crossings (+32.92%) and 882 in which traffic signs or rules were not followed (+5.76%) .
Cases of disobeying traffic signs rose sharply (+80.22%) to a total of 32,693. There were also 498 situations in which there was a “lack of care when overtaking” (+0.61%). Conversely, red light crossings fell by 11.04% to 4,529 occurrences. Also registering declines are cases of overtaking the continuous line between two lanes (-21.45% for 846) and stopping at the yellow mark in the lane entrance area (-41.05% for 270).
As for non -use of the seat belt during driving, the cases also rose, 23.21% for a total of 929. The use of mobile phones behind the wheel was a practice that also increased, with CPSP accounting for 1,999 cases ( +3.41%), and car drivers are the most infringing the law (1,828).
In the period under analysis, 170 alcohol research tests +20.18%were performed), both during Stop operations and in road accidents. During Stop operations, of the 32,079 people examined, 0.27% did not pass, while in the road accidents of the 8,642 tested 0.95% "splashed". There are also a record of two cases where drivers were guiding under the influence of souls or psychotropic substances.
In general, CPSP registered 703,874 infringements related to the road traffic law and the Road Code regulation, a slight rise of 0.40%. The value of the fines, in turn, ascended over 189.78 million patacas (+9.12%).
 
Taxi drivers committed more irregularities
Official statistics also account for the irregularities practiced by taxi drivers. In this field, there were 870 offenses, a significant climb of 47.96%. In concrete, 274 cases of “refusal of transport” (+15.61%), 571 “other irregularities” (+70.45%) and 25 of “abusive collection” (+56.25%) were reported.
Authorities also account for 618,260 illegal parking lots, a break of 2.38%. On public roads were carried out 2,226 vehicle blocks (+24.50%), while in the parking parks were made 5,085 (-45.24%). On the other hand, the authorities reported 895 cases of vehicle removal on public roads (+34.99%).
According to CPSP, there were 1,076 cases where people did not have the circulation tax, a 4.87%rise, in homologous terms.
Also noteworthy is the cases of illegal vehicle modification. The CPSP reported 1,186 cases, more 24.58% of the 952 registered between January and December 2023. In this field, 522 cases have been respecting “driving with the lights/light model not according to the authorized”, an increase of 10.36%; Following the cases related to the “registration model not according to the authorized” (502), which registered a growth of 67.33%; and “interception of vehicles suspected of illegal changes” (291), an increase of 27.07%.
On the other hand, in relation to the launch of polluting smoke, the authorities examined 450 vehicles (-11.59%), and verified 97 infractions (+2.11%). Of these almost one hundred irregularities, 48 ​​were committed by cars, 41 by motorcycles and eight by heavy vehicles.</description><pubDate>2025-01-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>186 illegal pensions last year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/seladas-186-pensoes-ilegais-ano-passado/</link><description>The Tourism Services Directorate sealed 186 illegal guesthouses in 2024, and this year it has already applied the same measure to six fractions suspected of illicit accommodation
 
Over the past year, the Tourism Services Directorate (DST) inspected 493 housing units/times as part of the fight against illegal provision of accommodation. In total, the organization sealed 186 units suspected of illicit accommodation in 2024.
Furthermore, between January 1st and 12th of this year, six illegal guesthouses were sealed and those suspected of illegally providing accommodation were identified, including controllers and operators of the respective units.
On the other hand, also last year, the DST and the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) filed reports against 17 individuals suspected of illegally exercising the profession of tourist guide in Macau.
The figures for 2024 also indicate that STD conducted 2,742 inspections to services and establishments and 1,615 with border posts and points of tourist interest.
Regarding the eight -day Chinese New Year period, the body has ensured that, together with CPSP, random inspections for boundary stations, sights and shopping places, in order to combat illegal guides. At the same time, it will continue to make joint inspections with CPSP to suppress illegal accommodation situations.
In addition to inspecting shopping locations to maintain order in the tourism and retail sector, DST will also work together with the Customs Service to combat smuggling activities involving excursions. The organization urged the six integrated tourism and leisure companies and associations linked to the hotel industry to mobilize human resources to optimize service in hotels and reinforce the monitoring of online platforms, so that hotel room prices remain at reasonable levels.
With regard to strategies for 2025, STD stressed that “it will continue to consolidate the markets of visitors in Greater China and Southeast Asia”, to “deepen” the Asian Northeast, to “reactivate” the markets of Europe, USA and India, and to “explore” those of the Middle East.
In addition to online and in -person promotions at national and abroad, organization of various events and promoting community tourism and the role of Macau as a creative city of gastronomy, STD promised to continue to provide training to tour operators, to oversee and promote Quality tourism. At the same time, it will accompany the second phase of the General Plan of the Development of the Macao Tourism Industry, and will deepen the intersectoral integration of “Tourism+”.
As revealed, the Grand Prix Museum attracted more than 156 thousand visitors in 2024, a year in which DST also financed 41 tourist activities in community neighborhoods, which attracted 1.34 million people/times and 2,100 commercial establishments/times . Furthermore, DST has already opened 28 promotional accounts, with 9.23 million followers, which represents an increase of more than 45% compared to 2023.</description><pubDate>2025-01-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Associations ask for “relief” of “economic pressure”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/associacoes-pedem-alivio-da-pressao-economica/</link><description>Faom and Fukien's countrymen made several suggestions to the Secretary for Economics and Finance, asking, in particular, the “relief” of “economic pressure” and the “improvement of the pecuniary reimbursement plan”
 
In another meeting within the scope of the elaboration of the Lines of Government Action (LAG), the Secretary for Economy and Finance met with the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau (FAOM), which made a series of suggestions related to the good -being of the population. From the outset, he asked the Government to “optimize measures that benefit the population, alleviate their economic pressure and reinforce their feeling of happiness”.
The use of the most disadvantaged and the community economy were thus topics that were on the table at the meeting between the parties. Faom leaders understand that “various measures” should be taken to revitalize the community economy and follow the evolution of times. The continuous improvement of the legal regime of labor rights was other of the proposals, along with “optimizing employment training plans and raising the high quality use of residents”.
In an official note, it is also said that Faom has ordered Tai Kin IP to “improve job policies for young people and support professional career development”. On the other hand, the association, represented by its president, Ho Sut Heng, and the chairman of the board, Lee Chong Cheng, required changes to industrial structure and increased efforts to form local qualified frames. He also proposed that incentive measures are studied to help the population of Macao articulate with employment in the in -depth cooperation zone.
Similar subjects were addressed between Tai Kin IP and the Fukien General Association of countrymen. At the meeting, where the association's president, Chan Meng Kam, and the vice-president, Nick Law, among other representatives, were given to the ruler suggestions on the incentive for consumption, financial support measures to micro, small and medium companies and improve the business and consumer environment.
Fukien's fellow countrymen also called for “the improvement of the financial contribution plan”, in addition to promoting the role of the commercial cooperation platform between China and Portuguese-speaking countries and the training of tourist guides.
In the replica, Tai Kin IP indicated that the Government of MSAR “will continue to support SME through a variety of measures” and stressed that it will take into account the favorable suggestions for sustainable development, “seeking its implementation more speeding whenever conditions allow it ”.</description><pubDate>2025-01-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Thailand records first gay weddings</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/tailandia-regista-primeiros-casamentos-gay/</link><description>epaselect epa11846432 Thai same-sex couple Sumalee Sudsaynet (R) and Tanaphon Chokkhoksung (L) hold their marriage certificate after the Marriage Equality bill came into effect at Bang Rak district office in Bangkok, Thailand, 23 January 2025. Thai same-sex couples applied to officially register their marriages at district offices nationwide after the Marriage Equality law came into effect on 23 January, recognizing and allowing same-sex couples to legally marry, making Thailand the first Southeast Asian country and the third Asian nation to legalize same-sex marriage.  EPA/RUNGROJ YONGRIT



Thailand celebrated its first LGBTQ+ weddings yesterday with the entry into force of a law authorizing same-sex unions, a first in Southeast Asia. Hundreds of couples “tied the knot” in various locations across Thailand, including in the capital, Bangkok, where a mass wedding took place in a celebratory atmosphere supported by the government of Prime Minister Paetongtarn Shinawatra.
Thailand thus joins Nepal and Taiwan on the short list of leading Asian countries or territories in terms of LGBTI rights, while in nations like India and Japan the legalization of same-sex marriages is blocked in the political and in the courts. On the other hand, the gay community continues to face stigma and persecution in countries such as Malaysia, Indonesia or Brunei.
Two well-known Thai actors, Apiwat “Porsch” Apiwatsayree, 49, and Sappanyoo “Arm” Panatkool, 38, received their marriage certificate at a Bangkok registry office, while two women, Sumalee Sudsaynet, 64, and Thanaphon Chokhongsung, 59, they made their union official in another neighborhood of the capital. “We are very happy, we have waited 10 years for this day”, declared Thanaphon, quoted by the AFP agency.
Meanwhile, dozens of LGBTQ+ couples dressed in traditional and contemporary wedding attire flocked to a large hall in a shopping center for a collective ceremony organized by 'Bangkok Pride' and city authorities. There, rows of staff at tables helped couples fill out marriage forms before receiving their certificates.
Ariya “Jin” Milintanapa, transgender, said she was “excited” about this day, after two decades of waiting. “This day is important not only for us, but for our children. Our family will finally be one,” he said.
The marriage equality law was passed in June and ratified in September by King Maha Vajiralongkorn. The legislation uses gender-neutral terms instead of “men”, “women”, “husbands” and “wives”, and grants adoption and inheritance rights to same-sex couples.
Prime Minister Paetongtarn Shinawatra stated last week that, regardless of the genre, "love has no limits or expectations." "Everyone will be protected by the same laws," he said.
Thailand has an international reputation for tolerance towards the LGBTQIA+ community and surveys published by local media reveal broad support for equal marriage. However, much of this majority-Buddhist kingdom maintains traditional and conservative values, and sexually diverse people say they face obstacles and discrimination in everyday life.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-01-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Firefighters went out more often to fires</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/bombeiros-sairam-mais-vezes-para-incendios/</link><description>Last year, firefighters went out more often for fires. These occurrences rose 5.5% to 882, according to official data
 
The Fire Department (CB) responded to 882 fires last year, which corresponded to an increase of 5.5% or 46 cases compared to 2023, Commander Leong Iok Sam said yesterday, in a review of the work. The reasons for the fire were essentially forgetting to turn off the stoves, not leaving the flames completely extinguished, burning incense and candles/votive papers, and mechanical/equipment failures, with 586 cases, representing 66.44% of the total number of exits. for fires.
In the fire area, 15,924 investigations and inspections were carried out. For cases in which situations have not been corrected despite repeated warnings or in which situations are serious, 49 cases of the administrative sanctioning procedure have already been concluded. Since the new law came into force, 83 cases have been closed, which were essentially due to the placement of various objects, shoe racks and motorcycles on the evacuation paths, and in 16 cases administrative sanctioning procedures have already been developed.
In general, CB ambulances responded to 45,236 requests, an increase of 5.06% or 2,177 cases. The climb “was mainly due to the increase in cases of mild dizziness and headache”. General medical emergency cases are mainly dizziness, abdominal pain, fever, bruise, among others.
The number of occurrences recorded by CB totaled 54,133, translating a climb of 2.75% or 1,448 cases. In the opposite direction, the corporation was involved in 1,792 rescue operations, a break of 30 cases; and in 6,223 special services, 745 cases than the previous year.
The CB said that it continuously develops all the awareness work, having organized 628 disclosure activities, distributed 61,366 informative pamphlets and held 138 lectures, which had 13,492 participants.
Regarding the development of actions in the Greater Bay Area and the Deep Cooperation Zone, the CB has already registered three ambulances to be used in the “Experimental Cross-Border Ambulance Transport Plan between Hong Kong and Macau”. In parallel, it planned eight emergency vehicles that have dual registration licenses from Guangdong and Macau (five ambulances and three fire engines). In addition, it has several drivers who have driving qualifications from the interior of China, “whose respective tasks are being promoted in an orderly manner”.</description><pubDate>2025-01-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hotels accommodated 14.4 million guests</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/hoteis-alojaram-144-milhoes-de-hospedes/</link><description>Last year, hotel establishments hosted more than 14.4 million people, a growth of 6.4% compared to 2023. Visitors who arrived on tours rose 63.8% to 2,103,000, official data indicates
 
Macau hotels accommodated 14,433,000 individuals in 2024, an increase of 6.4% year-on-year, according to the Statistics and Census Bureau (DSEC). A scenario that resulted in the average occupancy rate of hotel rooms at 86.4% (+4.9 percentage points compared to 2023). The average length of stay for guests remained at 1.7 nights.
The number of international guests (1,108,000) increased by 57.4% in annual terms, highlighting the 100.8% increase in the South Korean market (321,000). Official data also shows that the number of guests from Malaysia increased by 53.4% ​​to 87,000; from Japan there were 81,000 individuals (+49.1%); followed by India, with a total of 73,000 (+97.2%) and Singapore, 68,000 (+24.1%).
At the end of the year under analysis, 146 hotel establishments provided public accommodation services (four more, compared to the end of 2023), providing 43,000 rooms (-7.8%). According to DSEC, the occupancy rate of five -star, four -star (82.3%) and three star (83.8%) hotels (88.6%) increased 6.1; 3.1 and 3 percentage points, respectively.
Isolating the month of December, the average room occupancy rate was 89.9%, an increase of 4.2 points in annual terms. That month, hotels hosted 1,194,000 people, 9.6% less than the annual variation, with the average length of stay being 1.6 nights.
On the other hand, in 2024, the number of visitors from visitors who arrived at excursions to Macau corresponded to 2,103,000 (+63.8%, compared to 2023), including 1,867,000 from the interior of China (+57.1 %) and 204,000 international (+157%). The DSEC points out that the entries of visitors in South Korea (91,000) and India (24,000) excursions rose 226.4% and 302.2%, respectively.
The number of Macau residents who purchased services to travel abroad at agencies reached 583,000, an increase of 39.1% in annual terms. Among these residents, 215,000 traveled on tours (+87%), 193,000 of which traveled to Mainland China.
In the last month of the last year, the number of visitors from visitors that arrived at excursions equivalent to 189,000 (+13.1%), of which 163,000 were from the Chinese continent (+9.5%) and 22,000 were international (+50% ). Also here there was an increase of 86.5% to 11,000 of visitors' entrances at excursions from South Korea and Thailand, which rose 83.4% to 3,000.
For its turn, the number of Macao residents who purchased travels abroad at 10.4% to 59,000, 23,000 of which traveled on excursions (+4.8%).</description><pubDate>2025-01-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Boom and Bloom” transforms GalaxyArt into a Chinese garden</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/boom-bloom-transforma-galaxyart-em-jardim-chines/</link><description>The “Boom and Bloom” exhibition highlights at GalaxyArt the creativity of a new generation of artists from Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau, and celebrates the Lunar New Year

Victor Rebelo
 
Ray Chan, from Shenzhen, and Sanchia Lau, from Macau, are the protagonists of an exhibition at the GalaxyArt gallery, which is curated by Gary Mok, a famous Hong Kong art promoter.
The “Boom and Bloom” exhibition, which showcases creations by Greater Bay Area artists and represents one of the highlights of the Chinese New Year celebrations at Galaxy Macau, combines creativity with Chinese cultural traditions, “offering blessings of prosperity and joy to the festive season”, according to a text promoting the event.
On the day of the inauguration, the artists organized a workshop with local college students, sharing their creative concepts and inspirations.
Gary Mok transformed GalaxyArt's 6,500 square feet into a traditional Chinese garden, with distinctive architectural elements, vibrant plants and colorful flowers. The “serene, winding landscape” serves as the backdrop for the debut collaboration between Sanchia Lau’s “Wishing Doll” and Ray Chan’s “Shake Money Tree.”
“Shake Money Tree”, designed as a “spinning toy”, inspires young people to maintain a positive mindset and embrace hope and aspirations in life. It is a work that revolves around a pine tree that attracts fortune, symbolizing the harmonious coexistence between wealth and nature and highlighting the importance of financial management.
In turn, “Wishing Doll” reflects a deep understanding of the pursuit of dreams. Together, Sanchia Lau's works fuse auspicious Chinese symbols with modern design, creating a dialogue between tradition and contemporary art “that resonates deeply with younger audiences”, highlights Galaxy.
The exhibition features three themed works specially ordered in Macao, along with five creations from the “Shake Money Tree” series, which comes to life with the interactive installation “Boom and Bloom”.
The three exclusive designs, known for their intricate craftsmanship and auspicious symbolism, are particularly noteworthy. “Joy and Glory” is inspired by jewelry and precious metals, showcasing large, shiny “pearls” and sparkling “gold ingots” that symbolize opulence and blessings for a prosperous year. Meanwhile, “A Propicious Omen” incorporates the concepts of love and prosperity, with the lotus – the symbol of Macau – giving a unique touch and representing fortune and harmony for the new year.
At the opening ceremony, Ray Chan shared the underlying vision to her collaboration, mixing pop art with popular tendencies among young people to reinterpret the traditional Blessings of the Chinese New Year. "This is not just a visual and artistic banquet, being also a journey through cultural heritage," said the artist, who is based on Macau.
Sanchia Lau presents a new series of blessings of blessings, explaining that "the combination of the tree of money and the desire doll represents love and wealth." Gary Mok, in turn, said that the exhibition "offers both visual attraction and entertainment, benefiting both artists and art enthusiasts."
The exhibition has free admission and will be patent until March 9 at Galaxyart, on the first floor of the Galaxy Promenade, and can be visited between 10:00 and 22:00.</description><pubDate>2025-01-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Pianist Tra Nguyen performs tonight at Clube Militar</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pianista-tra-nguyen-actua-esta-noite-clube-militar/</link><description>Tra Nguyen, an artist born in Vietname and naturalized British, will give a solo piano concert tonight in Macau. The show is included in the Military Club's music journeys and the music will play compositions by Frederic Chopin, Nimrod Borenstein and Evelyn Chang
 
A Chinese New Year celebration concert will take place today, at 7pm, at Clube Militar, with a performance by British-Vietnamese pianist Tra Nguyen. The artist will perform excerpts from three composers, Frederic Chopin, Nimrod Borenstein and Evely Chang.
The Vietnam-born pianist in a family of musicians gave the first major concert when he was only 10 years old at the Grand Opera House of Hanoi, followed shortly afterwards the debut with the conservatory orchestra of the same city, playing Mozart. Since then, it has performed in rooms around the world, including Queen Elizabeth Hall, Cadogan Hall, Wigmore Hall, Tokyo Opera City, Hong Kong City Hall and Ho Chi Minh City Opera House.
Its imaginative and acclaimed programming balances the core repertoire with lesser-known works, with the most recent concerts exploring Schubert's complete piano sonatas, Liszt's Grandes études, S.137 and a large number of piano concertos.
As a chamber music, Trai Nguyen collaborated with Baritone Benjamin APPL and clarinetist Sabine Grofmeier. Currently, he works with British-Franco-Israelite composer Nimrod Borenstein in solo recordings and interpretations of his works.
The artist's discography, which has been broadcast on the main classical music radio stations around the world, also includes many international premiere recordings of neglected pieces. His series of recordings of Raff's piano music, released on Grand Piano, has received widespread critical acclaim, being named “Album of the Week” by The Independent.
Nguyen studied with Lev Naumov at the Conservatory of Moscow and Christopher Elton at the Royal Academy of Music, where he received the top prize for his final recital. He was named Associate of the Royal Academy of Music in 2013.
Those interested in attending only the concert at the beginning of this evening, in the Stanley Ho Hall of Clube Militar, will have to pay 180 patacas, with cocktail included, while those who also want to have dinner at the club's restaurant, will have to spend 320 patacas.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-01-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Master Plan for land in Hengqin published</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/publicado-plano-director-sobre-terrenos-em-hengqin/</link><description>The Executive Committee of the Deepened Cooperation Zone officially published the Directing Plan for the State Lands, tracing the directors related to spatial and ecological standards, industrial and housing spaces and the urban image of Hengqin until 2035. According to the Director Plan, the zone of In-depth cooperation should include the urban functions of the North Zone of Macao and articulate with the spatial structure of green leisure in southern masters, thus constituting a spatial structure: “city in the north, nature in the south and coexistence of differences” in hengqin. In addition, three main areas are defined (central area of ​​Hengqin-Macau vitality; Intelligent and Innovative Industrial Area; and Ecology, Health and Leisure Area) and Three Centers (Hengqin-Macau Vitality Center; Financial Center; and Centro of scientific and technological innovation of the Tianmu River). With regard to ecological patterns, the Director Plan advocates the hengqin connection to the Zhuhai ecological protection pattern and the Macao Nature Reserve area. In terms of industrial space, for the next decade, Hengqin will be subject to the principles of “promoting science and technology, improving manufacturing, strengthening culture and tourism, and optimizing trade” to correspond to the economic diversification strategy “1 +4 ”from the sons. In the field of housing space, the authorities intend to establish a housing supply system that “focuses on warranty housing, has the private market as a supplementary supply channel and promotes lease and purchase simultaneously”. On the other hand, the plan points to the reinforcement of the landscape coordination between the two sides of the Shizimen Canal and connecting to the Macao urban conception requirements.</description><pubDate>2025-01-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao SAR will promote “convergence” of judicial systems in the Greater Bay Area</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-promovera-convergencia-dos-sistemas-judiciarios-na-grande-baia/</link><description>The Government of the MSAR will “fully” support cooperation and judicial exchange between the interior of China and Macau, as well as “will jointly promote the convergence of judicial systems in the Great Bay”, said the chief executive, in a meeting with the deputy President of the Supreme Popular Court, Mao Zhonghua. According to an official note, Sam Hou Fai also stressed his intention to contribute to the rule of law to reach “a new level”, both in the interior of China and Macao. The ruler also took the opportunity to thank the Supreme Court for the "strong support for the judicial work of MSA during his term as president of the last court."</description><pubDate>2025-01-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>BRIEF</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2332/</link><description>Young man run over by bus on the treadmill
A 20-year-old woman was hit by a TCM bus while crossing a treadmill at Nape on Wednesday night. According to police, the 60 -year -old bus driver was accused of not having respect the priority for pedestrians. The victim was injured in various parts of the body, being conscious and stable when sent to the hospital. On the other hand, on the afternoon of the same day, a 60 -year -old driver was out of vital signs when he was driven to the hospital by firefighters after his vehicle crashed into the sidewalk of the guide. The causes of the accident are still being investigated.
 
Valentine couple will have trafficked drugs
A loving couple, of Indonesian nationality, aged 45 and 39, were arrested on suspicion of drug trafficking and consumption. In his fraction, located in the Três Candeeiros area, 105 grams of cocaine and 0.73 grams of “ice” were found, the value of which was estimated at around 210 thousand patacas. The detainees tested positive in the toxicological test. The Judiciary Police found that the suspects began trafficking drugs in Macau two weeks ago, with compatriots as “clients”.
 
“Aomi” records drop in food deliveries
The food delivery platform “Aomi” recorded a drop of 5% to 8% in the volume of transactions related to restaurants, said the company's president. Quoted by the newspaper “Ou Mun”, Acen Jiang Hai Tao also said that, faced with operational pressures, some restaurants in residential areas chose to “trigger a price war”. To “help restaurants reduce operating costs”, “Aomi” plans to promote more activities this year, he indicated, also warning of the decrease in motorcyclists delivering food after the end of the pandemic. In this sense, he suggested to the Government that, without prejudice to the premise of guaranteeing employment for residents, it consider authorizing non-resident motorcyclists, to make delivery services cheaper.
 
Flights with high search in the Chinese New Year
With the Year of the Snake approaching, the booking rate for plane tickets related to Macau has already exceeded 90%, revealed the Macau Airport Society (CAM), adding that, to meet the growing demand, 58 regular flights were added and charter during the festive season, involving destinations in Mainland China, Taiwan, Vietnam, Japan, South Korea and Malaysia. On the other hand, between tomorrow and February 7th, CAM will offer special parking discounts to Airport passengers. Passengers departing from the airport can enjoy a 50% discount on parking for a maximum of five consecutive days. The offer is applicable to the airport's south and north car parks.</description><pubDate>2025-01-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Rocha Vieira, the last Governor, who had “Macau in his heart” has died</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/morreu-rocha-vieira-ultimo-governador-tinha-macau-coracao/</link><description>Vasco Rocha Vieira died at the age of 85 in Portugal. The last governor of Macao will be forever in the memory of many, with the Portuguese flag on his chest, within hours of sovereignty transfer in 1999. In the last visit to the territory, the general said he had “Macao in the heart” and It was “optimistic” as to the future of the territory. To the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, several personalities praised their role in the transition process and remembered him as a man who "dedicated a lot from his life to Macao." They said they had lost “a great friend”



















Catarina Pereira and Vítor Rebelo
 
The image of General Vasco Rocha Vieira with the Portuguese flag next to the heart on December 19, 1999, a few hours from the transfer of Macau to the Popular Republic of China, will be forever in the memory of many. “I felt it wasn't me who was there. There were many generations. I felt that it was a moment that represented centuries of history. Which represented the effort and life of generations and generations of Portuguese, ”he described in the book“ All the ports I arrived ”. In memory, there are also the nine years that Rocha Vieira was at the head of the Praia Grande Palace, in a decisive period for the territory. Macau's last governor died yesterday in Portugal at the age of 85. He leaves his wife, Leonor Rocha Vieira, with whom he married in Lisbon in 1976, and three children.
Born in Lagoa, Portugal, on August 16, 1939, Vasco Joaquim Rocha Vieira was the son of João da Silva Vieira and Maria Vieira Rocha. He spent most of his childhood beyond borders: With a year, he went to Mozambique, where he remained until 10. He then went to Portugal, having been a student at the Military College in Lisbon.
He held many positions throughout his career, until, in 1991, he was appointed Governor of Macau by President Mário Soares, having been confirmed in the position in 1996, after the election of the new President, Jorge Sampaio. Rocha Vieira took office as Governor on April 23, 1991. Macau, a place in the East where he had already been on commission in the 1970s, became his home.
As governor, he was responsible for a vast program that was intended to reinforce Macau's own identity, the consolidation of his autonomy and the promotion of territory as a regional platform, with a specific role, at that time and for the future, in the relations of the China with the outside. Under his administration, Macao has watched, in recent years, to reinforce the local political system and the rule of law, namely through the consolidation of the judicial system, the reform of the education system, the formation of staff, the modernization and extension of the systems of health and assistance.
Three days of the transfer of Macao, in an interview with RTP, when asked what it was like to be the last governor, Rocha Vieira said he had the feeling that he played the role “at a historical moment”, but described only as “the interpreter of the sovereignty bodies of the territory ”and the“ interpreter of fulfillment of the obligations that Portugal assumed in the joint statement ”. "I see it naturally," he said then.
It claimed to be convinced that Portugal managed the territory "in a unique way." And that, she watched, saw the way the Chinese said goodbye to the Portuguese: "They come with us, hug us, want to take photographs, say they will miss us." "I think Portugal has fulfilled over the centuries ... I think we left a good work here, we can be proud of," he argued.
“There is no future if there is no history if there is no memory. And this story is fundamentally linked to the presence of Portugal and the Portuguese here in Macau, ”he continued, adding that in the territory they were“ very things ”from Portugal. From the outset, a political system based on the separation of powers, the laws, the judicial instructions, an administrative culture, listed.
Asked if the Deng Xiaoping formula “A Country, Two Systems” gave some security in the rights, freedoms and guarantees in the future of Macau under the sovereignty of the Popular Republic of China, Rocha Vieira said: “I think when he signed and wrote What he wrote, and when he wrote in Basic Law the chapter of fundamental rights, did so in a sincere and responsible way. Then I think the future authorities of MSA share the same values, the same principles as we share, the Portuguese Administration. ”
As for his relationship with China while he served as Governor, he said it was “always good”. “I managed to have a very frank, cooperative, very open relationship with the Chinese. Naturally, we had many disagreements (…) But this understanding, in a context that has always been favorable, of friendship, which is traditional and historical between the Portuguese and the Chinese, helped a lot. And I think that disagreements never led to rupture situations.”
On Portugal's side, the relationship was also “always good”, as he said at the time, but he stressed: “Of course, Macau and Portugal are physically separated, but they were always together through affection, solidarity and the sense of responsibility that the governing bodies sovereignty they always had before Macau”.
For the future, the last Governor asked for attention to the territory. “Portugal must continue to pay attention to Macau and I think the international community must pay attention to Macau, naturally without interfering with Chinese sovereignty, which must exercise it. But it must follow this process, because the Joint Declaration is an international treaty, signed by two countries”.
Regarding the criticism that Portugal could have been “submissive” in relation to the People's Republic of China, Rocha Vieira said, days before the transfer, that he no longer heard these types of accusations. “Today people realized that we took good advantage – in the good sense of the term ‘taking advantage’ – of good relations with China to defend our interests in the best way possible. Because having good relationships, speaking frankly, being friends, having a sense of the future, being serious in your goals is not incompatible with being firm, determined. On the contrary. We took advantage of this climate to be able to be very determined and very firm, say what we thought and fight for the interests that we believe to be the interests of Macau”, he concluded, in the same interview.
On the night of the transfer, after the official ceremony, the presidents of each country, Jorge Sampaio and Jiang Zemin, exchanged formal greetings, but they were not the only ones. Among the various greetings, special mention goes to Vasco Rocha Vieira, who was finishing his position, and Edmund Ho, his successor and first Chief Executive of the Macao SAR.
If it is true that the last governor was cherished by many, and his role in transfer negotiations was recognized “in the country and within the international community”, it is also certain that Rocha Vieira was the target of much criticism. Especially within the Case Jorge Álvares Foundation, which caused controversy, either in the first month of Chinese administration in the territory and in Portugal.
Formalized on December 18, 1999, the eve of the departure of the Portuguese administration from Macau, the Foundation had an initial allocation of 100 million patacas coming, in equal parts, from the Macau Tourism and Entertainment Society and the Foundation for Cooperation and Development, based in the territory and fed by local public funds. The president of the Board of Trustees of this latter foundation was Rocha Vieira himself at the time it was decided to transfer 50 million patacas to the newly constituted Jorge Álvares Foundation.
Over the years after the transfer, the General sporadically returned to Macau. The last time he was in the territory, at least as far as is publicly known, was in March 2023. He came to receive an honorary doctorate in Social Sciences, awarded by the Macau University of Science and Technology. “Returning to Macau is always very pleasant. All the people who were, lived and worked here have Macau in their hearts, as I do, so returning here under these circumstances is very pleasant”, he then told journalists, stating that he was still optimistic about the future of the territory.
Rocha Vieira was Chief of Staff of the Army and, inherently, member of the Council of the Revolution between 1976 and 1978. In 2015, he was awarded the Grand Cross of the Military Order of the Tower and Sword by former President Cavaco Silva. Previously, he was decorated with the Grand Cross of the Order of Infante D. Henrique (1986), awarded by General Ramalho Eanes, with the Grand Cross of the Order of Christ (1996), awarded by Mário Soares, and with the Grand Collar of Order of Infante D. Henrique (2001), awarded by Jorge Sampaio, a decoration awarded exceptionally, as it is normally intended for heads of State.
 
“A huge loss”
"Deholate", thus reacted Anabela Ritchie to the death of the last governor. “I was very dismayed. I knew him seriously sick, but we are never prepared. I am not, ”he said in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. He deprived closely with Rocha Vieira, as president of the Legislative Assembly, and ensures that, besides the work relationship, they eventually created a friendship.
“I had with the governor an excellent working relationship. A relationship of great solidarity, also much determined by the fact that we were aware that we were in the transitional period. And we had a lot of work ahead of us, ”he recalled. "It was possible to make us friends," he added.
Anabela Ritchie points out that she always felt that she “could speak at ease” with Rocha Vieira. “I can say I had a very good relationship. Sometimes we agreed, sometimes we disagreed. But there was room to explain our way of thinking, the meaning as we were seeing things. ” The goal was always to "find solutions."
Stressing that she enjoyed working with the Governor, Anabela Ritchie also praised the “important figure” he was for the transition: “I really admired the determination with which he did things, his competence and dedication”.
He also recalled that Rocha Vieira “listened to others and allowed them to speak,” heard different opinions from the most varied people. "It was a facet that I admired a lot," he noted, also saying that he was a "calm, serene" man.
In turn, Jorge Rangel said it was “a huge honor” to serve Portugal alongside Rocha Vieira, “in the government of Macao, integrating his governance team, and in civil society institutions, such as the Historical Society of Independence of Portugal, Military Associations, foundations linked to Macau and the Scientific and Cultural Center of Macau in Lisbon that he was the founder. ”
"I highlight its sense of state, attachment to fulfill the mission, intelligence, leadership and accomplishment, dignity, responsibility, dedication to the family and causes and love to Portugal," said the former secretary For the administration, education and youth of the Government of Macao, adding that it will always remember "with respect and admiration for the example of life that went to how many worked with it and somehow collaborated."
"It was a privilege to get to know him closely, to accompany him in multiple and diverse journeys at the service of Portugal and Macau, with him to live in the civil society institutions and deserve his confidence and friendship," he said.
José Luís de Sales Marques worked directly with Rocha Vieira for about eight and a half years during the transition period, as president of Leal Senate and also as a member of the governor advisory board. Subsequently, the economist continued to work with the general within the Portuguese school.
"It is a huge loss, in terms of the importance of the figure that was General Rocha Vieira, its importance in the history of Macau as the last governor, but not only for this, because it actually worked the transition from Macao," he said.
“At the same time that infrastructures were being built and the material conditions were being prepared for the transfer of administration to China, this was also done through his wisdom, his diplomacy and the vision he had of things”, he continued.
For Sales Marques, the former governor has always been careful to maintain Macao's stability and prosperity. "It is known its role in the transition process and its role even of moderator under certain circumstances of what has happened, and so it is an unavoidable figure," he told this newspaper.
 
“He dedicated a lot to Macau”
Meanwhile, Jorge Neto Valente stared that he lost a friend and recalls the last governor of Macao as a "man who is in history, not at the footer, in the center of history." The lawyer considers that "Macau was due to him a lot." For Neto Valente, Rocha Vieira was very important in the transition period, "that he accompanied until the end, as we know, and left Macao with all his dignity."
After returning to Portugal, recalls the lawyer, “the General continued to be interested in things in Macau and contributing to the good of Macau”. Rocha Vieira returned to the territory a few times and on one of his last visits he received an Honoris Causa doctorate from the University of Macau.
The lawyer reinforces that the former Governor “did what he had to do and was a person who dedicated a lot of his life to Macau”, having been in the territory long before that, in the 1970s, as a troop engineer.
“I met him at that time,” says Jorge Neto Valente, to add that Rocha Vieira returned to be governor “by the hand of Mario Soares, after not running well the experience of civil governors from the point of view of Portugal, from the point Politically, and Mario Soares went to the Azores. ”
After remembering that Rocha Vieira was a member of the Board of Trustees of the Fundação Escola Portuguesa de Macau, an educational establishment founded during his mandate in 1998, agreed in the Liaison Office, Neto Valente points out that the former highest representative of Portugal in Macau left many things that are still valid today.
"He and the people who chose to accompany him in governance in recent years have faced a very difficult time, hard work and only really people with a lot of desire and love Macau and Portugal could do what he did," he said. After leaving Macao, he finishes his statement, "the general has always remained linked to the territory."
José Rocha Diniz, co-founder of JTM, also mourned the death of Rocha Vieira. “I'm very sorry, but it was something that didn't surprise me, because I followed the last few months, in which he was hospitalized, seriously”, he said, adding: “I was with him at a dinner after the tribute to Dr. António Aresta at the Cultural and Scientific from Macau, in Lisbon”.
Recalling that the last governor “managed to mobilize the majority of Macau's population during the last years of the transition”, Rocha Diniz pointed out that he had a “great advantage”. “I knew the Territory very well, because I had already been deputy secretary, I knew the two diverse communities and also the way the Chinese understand power, so I had a great advantage over previous governors,” he said.
“Man of the 25th of April and the 25th of November,” continues Rocha Diniz, “nowadays, when we talk about General Rocha Vieira Portugal, almost everyone highlights the way he placed the Portuguese flag on his chest” at the time of the transfer . “In Portugal, the full complexity of the transition process is unknown, in which Macau was not called to the negotiations, which were between Portugal and China, but Macau, however, had numerous fundamental issues to be resolved, ‘on the spot’”.
“Rocha Vieira was very creative and firm in the way he always kept Macau's positions, sometimes even against Portuguese institutions,” he recalled, adding that “contrary to what some people may think, he was a dialogue man with a deep spirit Mission of the interests of Portugal and the Portuguese who lived in Macao, but always recognizing that it was in a decisive moment to solve a 'problem inherited from history', where Portugal had to do well. ”
“The Portuguese administration left Macau, but the Portuguese remain here, continuing to contribute to its progress and development”. Rocha Diniz concluded with a word of deep condolences, in this hour of pain, “to Dr. Leonor Rocha Vieira and her children”.
In turn, António José de Freitas began by stating: “More than the last Governor of Macau, I lost a great friend”. Then, he remembered that three months ago he had spoken to Rocha Vieira on the phone.
The provider also recalled that Rocha Vieira came to Macau annually, being part of the curators of the Portuguese School Foundation, and in 2019 came at the invitation of Santa Casa, on the 450th anniversary of the institution. "At the time, he was proclaimed meritorious from Santa Casa," he said, reiterating that he lost "a great friend."
“For me, he was the best Governor of Macau”, continued António José de Freitas, adding that they always had a lot of contact.
Antonio Félix Pontes, an economist and former administrator of the monetary authority, said that Rocha Vieira "was a good governor, loved and respected by the entire population of Macao, and that honored Portugal at a historical phase of this territory."
“I owe him the appointment as deputy to the Legislative Assembly of Macau, from 1991 to 1999, having never interfered in my political activities in that role”, he also recalled, regretting having lost “a great friend”.
 
“It fulfilled”, but it was not “to everyone’s liking”
Jorge Fão said he was also saddened by the news, which was given to him through JTM. On the mandate of the former governor, the president of the General Assembly of the Association of Retirees, Reformed and Pensioners of Macao points out that “complied with what he had to fulfill, but was not totally the liking of public administration workers”.
However, Jorge Fão says General Rocha Vieira pleased the general population and also to entrepreneurs. "I think there was fine."
Regarding public service workers, “he wasn't that worried, but in the end we had a happy outcome, let's say, since the entire public administration achieved what it wanted, that is, what it was fighting for: for a pension, for a transfer of his functions to Portugal”.
Fão says he has no person in person. "I had a lot of contacts with him due to his function outside the civil service, but I was affectionate to the Association of Public Service, having dialogued a lot with him, although these dialogues were not very satisfactory," he acknowledges.
Despite everything, he points out, the association “happily managed to achieve the desired results, also because we traveled to Portugal and had several meetings with Mário Soares and Cavaco Silva and were in Beijing to talk about our desires and concerns”.
Jorge Fão concludes stressing that the former governor of Macao, as the highest representative of Portugal in the territory, "fulfilled the mission that was given to him, even if, I repeat, it was not the liking of all."
The Association of Public Function Workers, directed by José Pereira Coutinho, also regretted the loss of Rocha Vieira and left him a thank you “for resolving, during the transition phase, many issues of the civil service workers, the Macaenses and those Portuguese who chose to continue to provide services in the MSAR ”. In a message, Coutinho also recalls that the use of the current headquarters of the association was authorized by Rocha Vieira.
 
PR and PM recall “sense of State”
The President of the Republic expressed “deep grief” for the death of Vasco Rocha Vieira, praising his “marked patriotism” and recalling him as “one of the most illustrious officers of the Portuguese army in the transition to democracy and the first decades of his statement” . “Always closely linked to commands, it has also performed political functions such as those of Minister of the Republic for the Autonomous Region of the Azores,” says the note published in the official site of the Presidency of the Republic. Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa also points out that Rocha Vieira was “very close to President António Ramalho Eanes”, having been “designated chancellor of the old military orders”. "The symbolism of the moment of transferring the Portuguese administration to the Chinese will remain in the memory of many Portuguese as an example of meaning, meaning of the public cause and marked patriotism," can be read. The President of the Republic, who claims to have followed “closely the last months” of Rocha Vieira's life, “presents to his family, and, much in particular, to his widow and children, the testimony of gratitude of Portugal, with very longing friendship". Also the Prime Minister recalled Rocha Vieira as "one of the most brilliant military personnel to give body to the patriotic meaning of being Portuguese", highlighting his "historical and striking and macau" connection. “General Vasco Rocha Vieira was one of the brightest military personnel to give body to the patriotic sense of being Portuguese, with special services in the consolidation of our democracy and in the historical and striking connection to Macao, where he was the last governor,” wrote Luís Montenegro, In a publication on the social network X. He also presented condolences to family and friends and said to keep from Rocha Vieira “gestures of kindness and words of civic and political responsibility”.
 
Eanes remembers “extraordinary man”
“General Rocha Vieira was an exceptional man for his excellent actions and his assumed social responsibility, deserving, rightly, to be considered 'one of the best of our greatest'”, wrote former President of the Republic Ramalho Eanes in a note sent to Lusa. He remembers him as “an extraordinary man”, especially “on three levels: for his distinctive personality, for his relevant military performance and for the services he provided to the country at a political level”. On a personal level, he “possessed superior qualities of spirit”, had “exceptional intelligence”, “a good temperament” and “had a strong personality”. At the military level, “he was one of the most distinguished of his generation, providing relevant services to the Army, in difficult times, namely, in the throes of the political regime prior to the 25th of April, during the 25th of April and, even, in the 25th of November, having also played an important role as a representative of the Portuguese Armed Forces within NATO”. Regarding the political level, he had an activity of “great quality and great importance for the country, both as minister of the Republic for the Azores, and also as governor of Macau, putting all his commitment into the design and successful execution of a policy of successful transformation of Macau, also participating, with the success that is known, in the transfer of the administration of the territory of Macau to the People's Republic of China”.
 
Army praises “patriotism” and “legacy of service”
The Army expressed its regret over the death of Lieutenant General Vasco Rocha Vieira and praised his “legacy of service and patriotism”, hoping that he “continues to inspire future generations”. In a note, the Army states that “it is in mourning, having lost one of its most notable soldiers”. “His life and legacy justify profound recognition and enduring respect for his memory, and constitute a factor of motivation and pride for all who serve in this centuries-old institution. May his legacy of service and patriotism continue to inspire future generations”, he highlights. According to a note, the wake will take place today, between 5:00 pm and 10:00 pm (Lisbon time), at the Military Academy Chapel, in Lisbon. Tomorrow, the wake will resume at 10:00, followed by a mass before lunch. After the ceremonies in Lisbon, the procession will head to the Algarve, where the funeral will take place at the Lagoa Municipal Cemetery.
 
“Dignified” Portuguese presence in the East
Former President of the Republic Aníbal Cavaco Silva lamented the death of Rocha Vieira, “Figure Figure” whose legacy dignifies the last years of the Portuguese presence in the East. “We keep from General Rocha Vieira the solemn image and worthy of the domestic flag in Macau, now 25 years old. More important than this image, it is the work of Rocha Vieira as the last governor of Macao, dignifying the last years of our presence in the East, allowing us to leave the territory reconciled with our history and proud of the work we left, ”he said, in a note of condolences sent to Lusa. Cavaco Silva expressed “deep sadness” for the death of Rocha Vieira, “a remarkable figure” of the recent history, with whom he kept “narrow bonds of friendship”. He also stressed the “importance of the high military functions he performed, as head of the army's staff, in a critical period of consolidation” of Portuguese democracy, between 1976 and 1978. “their exceptional qualities of command, their firmness, integrity of Character, and their ethical and military formation helped replenish hierarchical authority and discipline in the Armed Forces in a troubled period of the country's life, ”he said.
 
“One of the best interpreters of the importance” of Macau
The PS expressed regret for the death of Rocha Vieira, praising a life “entirely dedicated to the service of Portugal”. Noting that “his life was forever linked to Macau”, for the PS this “was one of the best interpreters of the importance” of that territory “for the relationship between Portugal and the Popular Republic of China”, as well as the uniqueness of RAE. “The last years of the Portuguese administration of the territory of Macao, under the leadership of General Rocha Vieira, are marked by the realization of several important infrastructural public works to support the subsequent development of Macao, as well as management reforms for its preparation For the subsequent period, ”he praises. The socialists also refer to the transfer ceremony, in which it was undeniable the way Rocha Vieira "embodied and symbolized dignity and tribute to the Portuguese presence over the centuries in Macao." "And marked the friendship and respect that the Portuguese maintain with Macao and the Popular Republic of China, and which allows, after 25 years of transition, to preserve the uniqueness of Macao that remains a meeting point between cultures," He added. The PS thus gives "public note of its deep respect for services to the country" and "addresses to your family and your friends your most felt condolences."
 
Performed public functions “always with dignity”
The president of the Government of the Azores, José Manuel Bolieiro, lamented the death of Vasco Rocha Vieira, recalling that the lieutenant general “always performed his public duties with dignity”. “I pay tribute to a man who, throughout his career, always performed his public duties with dignity, a sense of duty and a deep commitment to the public interest”, he stated, quoted in a press release. He also adds that he “leaves a legacy of service to the country, which will be remembered with respect and gratitude”, expressing “deep regret at the death of the lieutenant general”, who “performed relevant functions in the service of Portugal”. Rocha Vieira, who was minister of the Republic for the Azores between 1986 and 1991, “stood out for the integrity and responsible way in which he held his position, contributing to the strengthening of relations between the Autonomous Region of the Azores and the State, always with respect for regional autonomy and the specificities of the Azores”. The Azorean executive also refers to his performance in the role of Governor of Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Young Chinese accelerate savings due to increased economic risks</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/jovens-chineses-aceleram-poupanca-por-aumento-dos-riscos-economicos/</link><description>The frugal tendency that began in China during the economic crisis caused by the COVID-19 pandemic and has deepened in the midst of the real estate crisis is intensifying as generation Z rejects government appeals to spend and redoubles savings .
In XiaohongShu, similar to China's Instagram, or Rednot, as it is known in the West, many under 30 are exchanging notes on how to spend less on lunch and making cheap shopping.
Influencers are also sharing tips on how to turn financial discipline into a lifestyle. Posts about how to save money total more than 1.5 million, with more than 130 million views.
“I feel like the economy is really bad and it seems like it's hard for everyone to make money, so I think it's important to protect my own wallet,” said Ava Su, who joined Alibaba after graduating just over a year ago. six months and earns a relatively comfortable salary.
Ms Su, 26, who sees the Internet industry as "unstable", said she cut expenses on impulse and has a long-term plan to save two million yuan - 100 times her monthly salary.
According to Yu'e Bao data, a popular online monetary market fund in Alipay payment application, users born after 2000 made an average of 20 deposits per month at the end of 2024, twice the number of May.
The May number was 10% higher than the previous year. Yu'e Bao also said that the funds in each person's account this month were nearly 3,000 yuan, 50% more than in the same month last year.
Some economists warn that rooted savings can empty the search, at a time when political decision makers are having domestic consumption to boost China's Gross Domestic Product (GDP). Pessimism, which has already led to falling consumer prices, also impairs the long -term potential of the second largest economy in the world.
The situation is strongly contrasting with the excessive spending attitudes of the so -called "Moonlight" generation, a term used to describe those born in the 1980s and 1990s.
“They only saw expanding job opportunities, increasing incomes, and a quality of life that continued to improve,” said Ho-fung Hung, a professor of political economy at Johns Hopkins University, and were known to spend their entire monthly salary.
Covid-19 and the economic slowdown have made today's young people feel they need to prepare for the worst, he added, "a loss of optimism that is the first since the start of (China's) market reform in 1978." , said Professor Hung.
Pessimism means that many young people seek “iron” jobs in government departments or state-owned companies that they believe offer more job security. Ava Su said that she planned to take the civil service exam at some point in the future.
Unemployment between the approximately 100 million Chinese aged between 16 and 24 has remained high in the last two years. The unemployment rate among young people reached the 21.3% historical record in June 2023, leading the authorities to interrupt the disclosure of the data series and “reevaluate” how the numbers are compiled. The young unemployment rate recalibrated was 15.7% in December 2024.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-01-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>