<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Nine days of play in Macau exceed a month in Las Vegas</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/nove-dias-de-jogo-em-macau-superam-um-mes-em-las-vegas/</link><description>Macao reinforced the status of the world's largest market in the first half of this year, registering 84 billion more patacas in gross revenues than the Las Vegas strip casinos, which is more than triple. Between January and June, the invoicing in Macao reached almost double the amount accounted for throughout the state of Nevada. In average terms, according to official data analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, nine days in the 30 local casinos yielded more than a month in the 60s game spaces in the celebrated Las Vegas area
 
Sérgio Terra
 
In the first six months of this year, the Macao game market consolidated the world leadership, a statute it first won in 2006 and only gave in 2022 to Las Vegas 'strip' due to the strong impact of the Covid-19 pandemic. Between January and June 2025, the two jurisdictions had different annual variations, with a 4.4% growth in the contrast with a 0.7% break in Las Vegas, according to statistics from the Macao Games and the Nevada State Game Control Committee.
According to the official data analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the gross revenues of the 30 casinos in the territory rose to 118.77 billion patacas, which represents $ 3.34 billion ($ 35.07 billion to the current exchange rates) for about 60 Las Vegas Strip Spaces. It should be noted that the number of casinos considered by the regulatory entity of Nevada suffers monthly fluctuations, and in June it was fixed in 57.
Despite increasing 62.2% compared to 2019, the pre-pound year, the billing in Las Vegas in the first half of this year only reached 29.5% of the amount recorded in Macao, reflecting a difference of about 84 billion between the two largest markets in the world. On the other hand, in the MSAR, revenues are still short of the pre-pound level, corresponding to 79.4% of the first six months of 2019.
Between January and June, the daily averages of revenues ciphed at 656.20 million patacas in Macao and 193.77 million in Las Vegas. Thus, nine days in local casinos yielded more than an entire month in the old "Mecca do Game."
In the period under analysis, Macau also exceeded the total raised by the nearly 440 casinos in the state of Nevada, which closed the semester with gross revenues of $ 7.79 billion (62.99 billion patacas), at a daily average of approximately 348 million patacas. This value reflects a 0.4% homologous rise and equals 53% of Macao level.
Using the daily averages again, it appears that 16 days in Macau were enough to match a month of revenues in Nevada.
In the general calculation of last year, the revenues of Las Vegas 'strip' (about 71.25 billion patacas) and the state of Nevada (126.18 billion patacas) dropped 1% and 0.5% compared to 2023, respectively, and accounted for 31.4% and 55.6% of the Macao market, which grew 23.9% to 226.78 billion.
Already in 2023, although they established a new annual record, the revenues in the iconic Las Vegas zone also did not reach half the value generated by the Casinos of the MSAR, which were still in the early phase of the Postcovid resum. Official statistics show that by 2023, Las Vegas and the state of Nevada registered revenues of 71.97 billion and 125.50 billion patacas, ie 39.3% and 68.6% of 183.06 billion in Macao.
In 2022, the situation was quite distinct, with strong travel restrictions motivating an annual break from 51.4% to 42.20 billion patacas in Macao, a value far below Nevada results (119.67 billion patacas) and Las Vegas 'strip' (66.82 billion). In turn, the 2021 accounts illustrated a difference of 30.1 billion patacas, with Las Vegas casinos reaching 65.3% of the level of the MSAR. In 2020 and 2019, Macao had generated twice and more from the member of the revenues, respectively.
 
Las Vegas faces tourism decline
In response to the latest indicators, both in tourism and in the game, Macau casinos should continue to expand the advantage over Las Vegas during the second half of this year. After July have marked a postpande record in the game, several analysts were already rising the projections to 2025, animated by the growing flow of visitors, which rose 14.9% to 19.22 million between January and June, in annual terms.
In Las Vegas, the perspectives are much less laughing, and do not show signs of improvement during summer. According to data from the convention and visitors authority (LVCVA), the number of tourists fell 11.3% to 3.09 million in June and 7.3% to 19.5 million in the first half. With the city losing 1.5 million visitors since the beginning of 2025, the hotel occupancy rate retreated 6.5 points to 78.7% in June and 2.1 points to 82% in the set of six months.
In the analysis of June data, LVCVA maintained that the decline in tourism reflects “the broader scenario of persistent economic uncertainty” and the weakening of consumer confidence, in a “slower” month in the convention sector, where the participating public dropped 10.7% to 375,000 people. At Harry Reid International Airport, passengers dropped 6.3% in June to 4.7 million and 4.1% to 27.6 million in the first half.
Still, by presenting the financial results of the second quarter, executives of MGM Resorts International and Caesars Entertainment anticipated that Las Vegas will recover in the coming months, with an intense calendar of events, namely conventions, at the end of this fall and in 2026. "I want to take advantage of this opportunity to emphasize that Las Vegas continues to be fundamentally solid," said CEO of MGM, Bill, Bill, Bill, Bill Hornbuckle, highlighting the strong business volumes in the group's ventures.
However, new national immigration and visas policies are also affecting Las Vegas's tourist perspectives. The announced imposition of a $ 250 visa fee on all non -immigrant foreign visitors may discourage international tourism, while reinforcing immigration inspection and doubts around workers protection originate operational challenges and foster work instability in the local hotel sector.
These concerns are not unfair, given the strong weight of tourism in the Las Vegas economy, where travel -related branches of activity ensure more than one fifth of jobs and hotels and casinos absorb more than 13% of work force. Restaurants, transportation services, space spaces and stretch trade establishments now face times of uncertainty, which in some strands have a national dimension.
A report from the World Travel and Tourism Council estimated that the US will be able to lose $ 12.5 billion in spending on international visitors throughout this year. "While other nations extend the welcome rug, the US government puts the 'closed' sign," said Julia Simpson, chairman of the board, in a statement.
The report cited March air reserve data, which signaled breaks between 15% and 20% on expected trips from large tourist markets, including the United Kingdom, Germany and Canada.
Visitors from Canada and Mexico represented more than half of international tourists in Las Vegas in 2024, according to LVCVA. However, the ambition of US President Donald Trump of making Canada in the 51st US state and its decision to impose tariffs on Canada will have removed many travelers from the neighboring country. In addition, the media have reported several cases of refusal and bizarre arrests at US border stations.</description><pubDate>2025-08-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>"Podul" caused serious flooding in the low areas of Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/podul-causou-inundacoes-serias-nas-zonas-baixas-de-macau/</link><description>Due to the “Podul” tropical cyclone, Macau registered intense sweeteners yesterday afternoon, as well as serious flooding in the low areas. The black signal of heavy rain was issued for the second time this year. Several streets were closed due to floods. In the mud and in coloane there was a rainfall volume of 110 millimeters per hour. Authorities received at least 54 requests for help
 

Photo: Jornal “or Mun”

The “Podul” tropical cyclone gradually moved away from Macao yesterday afternoon. However, according to Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG), under the influence of the circulation of “Podul”, there were intense flackets and serious floods in the low areas, which led to the heavy black signal of rain for the second time this year. The highest level of alert for heavy rain was issued at 2:02 pm yesterday, having been replaced by yellow in the late afternoon. At the same time, signal 1 of tropical storm has extended for much of the day, having been canceled at 18h00.
Due to the emission of the heavy rain signal, children's, primary, secondary, and special teachings were suspended in the afternoon, and schools were entered to organize staff to welcome students to the educational institutions until their return home could be safe.
According to the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP), several streets were provisionally closed to traffic due to floods, including the underground lanes of the Auto-Silo Ferreira do Amaral Square, Rua do Porto, Rua de Fernão Mendes Pinto, Wai Long Avenue and Rotunda Ouvidor Arriaga, as well as the coloane central central.

Photo: Jornal “or Mun”

Monitoring data show that at 5 pm, the maximum total precipitation recorded in several zones of the peninsula was 135.8 mm, while in the mud reached 253.8 mm and in Coloane was even higher, with 269 mm. According to the SMG, during the period of the Intense Rain Notice, the highest accumulated precipitation was 110 millimeters at Ká-Hó station.
As for the highest water level registered by the stations, it was 0.92 meters at the Caminho das Márto das Torta station, 0.55 meters at IEC Long Station, and 0.34 meters at Rua da Ponte Negra Station and Seac Pai Van station.
Also due to strong sweater, according to the direction of services for traffic affairs, several roads in the mud and coloane were highly congested yesterday afternoon. Several photographs and videos that were circulating on social networks showed the floods in the mud and cotai, with the water reaching the knee of pedestrians. The cars were also struggling to circulate due to the huge amount of waters on the roads.

Photo: Jornal “or Mun”

On the other hand, five airlines canceled a total of 16 flights, linked to Taiwan and the city of Quanzhou from Fujian province, Macao International Airport said.
However, the Civil Protection Operations Center has launched appeals to residents and tourists to be sheltered in a safe and covered place, avoid damage caused by heavy rain, and taking preventive measures such as drowning from low areas, flooded areas, ramps and streams, and avoiding remaining underground places or spaces without exit alternatives.
Until 5:30 pm yesterday, the Fire Department received 25 requests for help -related help, including cases where people were trapped in certain spaces, removing objects that had fallen, treatment of infiltration, landslides and falling trees. None of these situations caused injured, reported the corporation, ensuring that you have mobilized more firefighters to deal with requests for help.
The Public Security Police Corps received 29 requests for help, namely from people arrested in vehicles, detachment of buildings and landlords.</description><pubDate>2025-08-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Law without barriers will be careful people with multiple disabilities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lei-sem-barreiras-tera-em-atencao-pessoas-deficiencia-multipla/</link><description>IAS has ensured that the legislation for the creation of conditions without barriers will take into account the needs of people with different types of disabilities and people with multiple disabilities. The body will hear opinions from stakeholders and associations. On the other hand, IAS recalled that census work and registration on isolated elderly are underway to create a database from different parishes
 
Legislative works for the creation of accessibility conditions in Macao have deserved “close attention” of the government, ensured the Institute of Social Action (IAS), noting that this legislative task will be included in the new “planning of MSAR rehabilitation services for the next decay”.
In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Ho Ion Sang, IAS highlighted the plan to improve legislative work, taking into account, within the scope of the “universal design” principle, the needs of people with different types of disabilities and people with multiple disabilities. Thus, the Government “will closely collect the opinions of stakeholders and the individualities of the Commission's company for rehabilitation matters, service organizations for people with disabilities and rehabilitation services institutions,” he said.
According to IAS, currently, in order to provide rehabilitation services and other services to people with disabilities, including multiple disabilities, IAS will evaluate the general evaluation and prepare the individualized training plan to service users, according to service needs.
In addition, he promised that "regularly review the services of services and adjusts the content of services according to progress and change of needs, in order to ensure that users can constantly and properly use services in the same installation."
On the other hand, in the same answer, IAS stated that, this year, gradually develops the work of censuses and registration of the elderly living alone and families with elderly couples in different parishes. In concrete, it is proceeding, by phases, research work and data collection, gradually creating a database from different parishes, in order to optimize the placement of home support services to the elderly, including the “Peng On Tong” service service.
IAS also stressed that it will continue to review data change from various social services, in order to improve, in a timely manner, service provisions and financial support conditions, to gradually realize intelligent work and the digitization of social equipment. At the same time, it expects to promote “the development of high quality and accuracy of Macao social services” by observing the current situation about the needs of various social services.
Regarding the application of intelligent technologies, IAS recalled that it launched the “Financial Support Plan for the Application of Gerontechnology”, which supports social equipment in the acquisition, rent and experimental use of Gerontechnology equipment. In this context, IAS indicated that, in the future, it will support more in the development of technologies by social equipment, according to the degree of acceptance of the application of intelligent technologies of social equipment and the government's financial situation.</description><pubDate>2025-08-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MSA and China reject US accusations of human rights</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-china-rejeitam-acusacoes-dos-eua-sobre-direitos-humanos/</link><description>The United States has again included Macau in the human rights report in the world, accusing the sinters, for example, of restricting freedom of expression and press freedom through censorship, among other aspects. In response, the Macao government and China's Ministry of Foreign Ministry Commissioner in the MSAR rejected the “unfounded accusations”
 
Pedro Milheirão
 
Macao is again targeted in the annual report on the world of human rights in the world of the US State Department. Washington says there are "credible reports of serious restrictions on freedom of expression and press freedom, including censorship." In addition, it states that the masters "does not fully fulfill the minimum rules for eliminating trafficking in persons."
In response, the Government of MSAR criticized "unfounded accusations of the human rights situation in Macao", adding that "they do not correspond to the facts and are full of prejudice." For its part, China's Foreign Ministry (MNE) commissioner at MSA accused the US of interfering "openly on Macao affairs and China's internal affairs."
Saying that there was no "significant changes" in the situation of Macao, the document, points out that "the law provides for freedom of expression, including to members of the press and other media, but the government has restricted this right." "Mandre imposed restrictions on press freedom and encouraged the media to align with government positions. There have been reports of self-censorship by bodies and journalists," they can read.
Washington speaks, for example, of the “various criticisms” of the Macao Journalists Association about “the gravity of censorship” to the media.
Regarding workers' rights, Washington criticizes the fact that the law prohibits "workers of certain professions, such as security forces, unions, protesting or strike." In addition, from the US optics, the Macao government and "employers do not respect collective bargaining, having influence on associations and the choice of its leaders."
As for “refugees protection”, the State Department criticizes the MSAR for not granting refugee status to those who asked for asylum.
Following the criticism, the Government of the MSAR, in turn, said that "residents enjoy, under the law, broad rights and freedom of expression, the press, meeting and parade, among others, being also the labor rights guaranteed by law." "All sectors of society join efforts to safeguard the sovereignty, security and interests of the country's development," he said.
A spokesman for the MNE Commissioner argued that "since the return of Macao to the country, the practice of the" one country, two systems "principle has achieved great recognized achievements worldwide." "The democratic system was perfected, the economy registered a historic leap," having freedom of expression, freedom of the press and workers' rights was "fully guaranteed according to the law," he said.
In the same vein, the Macao government stated that "society has maintained long -term harmony and stability" and that the quality of life of the population "continues to improve and achieve comprehensive progress in human rights." He also assured that "these successes are remarkable and cannot be erased by the so -called US report."
The executive headed by Sam Hou Fai expects "the US to be impartially attempted to the huge successes achieved by Macau" and "respect the facts and stop the situation of human rights in the Mance." The MNE Commissioner of China in the MSAR, in turn, urged the US to respect the "objective facts" and to immediately cease to "deny and defame the situation of human rights in Macao."</description><pubDate>2025-08-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Fair in Dili wants to capture macau investment</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/feira-em-dili-quer-captar-investimento-de-macau/</link><description>Dili's first international exhibition wants to capture investment from the large bay, including Macau, with businesses between the two parts, in areas such as infrastructure development or coffee, was announced yesterday.
The Dili 2025 International Exhibition, which runs between August 28 and September 1, “intends to attract more investors from the Great Baia (…), entrepreneurs from all sectors, from trade, service, financial institutions and bank”, reads in a statement signed by the Timor-Leste delegate to the Permanent Secretariat for the Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and the Portuguese-speaking countries (Macao), António Ramos da Silva.
From Macau, the note, the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM) will send 19 entrepreneurs from various sectors.
Among the planned businesses, Macau will buy more coffee to Timor-Leste, with distributor Timor Global signing an agreement of 808,800 dollars with Macau Café Limited company. Also the company Água Nova de Timor (Macau) will do business with the Ministry of Education Timorese for the installation of drinking water machines in public schools in the country, reads in the note.
In the statement, other protocols are also referred to, namely the participation of the Top Builder groups from Macao and Huafa from Zhuhai in the area of infrastructure development in Timor-Leste. Another planned investment is the Chinese group Caizi in partnership with the Zhuhai Daguang Electronic Products Factory group in “Integrated Development”.
Representatives of the China-Parais Cooperation and Development Fund will also be present. This fund, created in June 2013 by the China Development Bank and the Macao Industrial and Commercial Development Fund, has a total capital of $ 1,000 million.
During the “First International Exhibition Organized in Timor-Leste by the Ministry of Commerce and Industry”, it refers to the note, companies from Macao and the Chinese province of Guangdong will sign “protocols of cooperation and sales and purchase contracts with their counterparts of Timor-Leste”.
The Caizi Group, also refers, signed in January this year a pre-agreement with the Macao Forum's Timor-Leste Secretariat for an investment of about $ 1 billion, which includes the construction of integrated resorts, from a factory for construction and other industries.
According to the Timor-Leste government website, the purpose of this fair is to “bring together countries, small and medium businesses, business, NGO and government organizations” to present “their successes, demonstrate the latest innovations in culture and technology and promote collaboration between various sectors”.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-08-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Extended mosquito elimination team</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/alargada-equipa-de-eliminacao-de-mosquitos/</link><description>Currently with 15 employees exclusively responsible for combating mosquitoes, health services mobilized internally 60 workers, to participate in a “training in the application of mosquito elimination technologies” and thus serve as a reserve
 
Given “the trend of increasing dengue fever and chikungunya fever in neighboring regions” and frequent displacements of transfronist personnel, “it is possible that cases imported from the two types of fever increases in Macau” and “the risk of community transmission outbreak,” health services (SSM) yesterday.
Therefore, the body emphasized the need to “actively prepare prevention, control and response work”, especially with regard to resources for the prevention and elimination of mosquitoes and reinforcing response capacity. According to this purpose, the SSM called the sectors of society, including public services, schools, companies and the condominium management sector, to create and expand their mosquito elimination teams.
In a statement, the SSM noted that 15 of their employees are responsible exclusively for the elimination of mosquitoes. In addition, the body revealed that it has just mobilized more internally 60 employees, who participated in a course of “training in the application of mosquito elimination technologies”. According to the formation, this group of employees has exceeded the techniques of chemical elimination of mosquitoes and will serve as a reserve of human resources from SSM in this area.
Alvis Lo, director of SSM, and Leong Iek Hou, director of the Center for Disease Prevention and Control, also attended this training action to learn to work with these technologies.
Alvis Lo stressed that, taking into account the situation of chikungunya fever in neighboring regions, Macau needs even more to prepare in advance. According to SSM, the SSM has been driving the sectors of society to develop autonomous mosquito skills. The objective is, through the formation of personnel, the improvement of equipment and the reserve of materials, to strengthen Macau's ability in terms of mosquito eradication, explained Alvis Lo.
Thus, if a community transmission occurs, the sectors of society will be able to gather resources and personnel in the shortest possible time, to quickly extend mosquito uninsectization teams and proceed with their work, reducing the density of adult mosquitoes, and protecting community safety and population health.</description><pubDate>2025-08-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 2,500 accused of smoking in forbidden places</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-de-2-500-acusados-de-fumar-em-locais-proibidos/</link><description>During the first six months of this year, more than 2,500 people were accused of smoking in forbidden places. Casinos continue to record most cases. 127 cases of electronic cigarette transport were also detected. Regarding the consumption of alcoholic beverages, there were three sales situations to under 18
 
Victor Rebelo
 
In the first half of this year, the Smoking Control Law Supervisory Agents detected a total of 2,748 infringements. According to data provided by health services (SSM), more than 123,000 inspections were made to establishments, which makes an average of 680 per day.
Regarding tobacco, between January 1 and June 30, 2025, the SSM, Fire Department, Public Security Police Corps, Municipal Affairs Institute, Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ) and Customs Services detected 2,529 illegal tobacco cases and 127 Electronic Cigarette Transport for Macao entry and exit.
There were also 81 occurrences suspected of breach of other provisions of the smoking prevention and control regime, namely the non -posting of smoking prohibition, in the places provided for in the law, and the non -posting of the sale of sale of tobacco products to children under 18 in the places of sale.
Regarding the type of establishment with the largest number of cases of people to smoke in forbidden places, casinos registered in a total of 480 cases (19.0%), followed by restoration spaces, with 368 (14.6%) and parks, gardens and leisure zones, with 229 (9.1%). The DICJ, in collaboration with the SSM made 429 inspections to places of play in the territory.
Regarding the control of alcohol consumption, the first six months of this year registered 11 suspected occurrences of violation of the prevention and control of alcohol consumption by minors, three of which involved the sale or availability to young people under 18 years.
The other eight cases are related to several establishments that did not affix the sales for sale or availability of alcoholic beverages to minors, approved by order of the Chief Executive. "The respective cases have already been instructed for proper follow -up," says a text released by the SSM.
On the other hand, it is stated that some retailers have taken the opportunity to boost promotional activities, including tobacco products, and perform their promotional disclosure and advertising on the online platform. These acts were suspected of violating one of the articles of the smoking prevention and control regime, in which all forms of publicity and promotion to tobacco, their products and electronic cigarettes are prohibited.
In the past, some retailers were also accused of not respecting the law of sale of cakes or desserts in the form of cigars or cigarettes, where the manufacture and marketing of games, toys, electronic games, foods or treats in the form of tobacco products or a distinctive object products are prohibited. The violation of the above provisions is sanctioned with a fine of 20,000 to 200,000 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-08-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>One received 5,600 new students</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/um-recebeu-5-600-novos-alunos/</link><description>In the school year 2025/2026, an account with 5,600 new students, who were received yesterday by the Rector of the institution. Yonghua Song highlighted the university's “multicultural and international environment”
 
The University of Macao (one) yesterday held the welcome ceremony of the 2025/2026 school year, where there were more than 5,600 new students. At the time, Uma Rector Yonghua Song said that “the university's multicultural and international environment provides an important platform for students to widen their horizons and develop their collaboration with others,” according to an institution.
In concrete, more than 2,100 are undergraduate students and more than 3,500 are postgraduate students. During the event, one also granted scholarships and research scholarships to over 800 new students.
In his speech, Yonghua Song recalled that Macau is developing the university city in Hengqin, starting with the creation of the one in the in -depth cooperation zone. He also noticed that since he has moved to the Hengqin campus, one has recorded significant development.
The rector also added that "integration between Macau and Hengqin is accelerating, opening even more opportunities for the community." "One will continue to form high -level talent for Macao and the country, and ensure that their students are well prepared for both local and global success," he said.
In line with the political guidelines of the Government of MSAR, and to support the development of new quality productive forces and to satisfy the demand for society for different types of talents, one launched four new postgraduate programs for the new school year, including the doctorate in cognitive and brain sciences, the PhD in visual communication design, the master's design and the masters in fire safety and response Catastrophes.
Yesterday, a lecture was also held, in which Yonghua Song was the speaker. The dean spoke about the challenges of the transition to the university and encouraged students to “use UM UM Learning resources”, to participate in sports activities and exchange programs to “expand horizons” and “respect the differences in language, religion and culture”.
To graduate students, Song pointed out that the transition requires higher levels of analytical capacity, responsibility and self-sufficiency, and should “cultivate interdisciplinary innovation, break disciplinary barriers, expand their contact networks, build a good relationship with colleagues and teachers, and explore their potential and strengths”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Launched reputed to the capture of images for “collective memory”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lancado-repto-a-captacao-de-imagens-para-memoria-colectiva/</link><description>Rua de Fernão Mendes Pinto



The Macau Foundation's “Memory of Macao” cultural and historical website, which celebrates the sixth birthday, has launched a new image sharing program, inviting all residents to publicize their life memories. The idea is to reinforce the vitality and creativity of the platform and at the same time provide the dissemination of personal experiences in the city
 
Victor Rebelo
 
To celebrate the sixth anniversary of the “Memory of Macao” website, reinforce the platform's vitality and creativity and allow more residents to find their own history on this land, the Macau Foundation (FM) electronic site has launched a new photograph collection project.
The “My Memory of Macao” Image Sharing Program aims to encourage people to capture, through their perspective, “precious moments of life, subtle and moving moments, integrating their personal experiences in the city's collective memory, thus becoming an important part of Macau's cultural memory,” according to a Macau Foundation release.
The contest is open to all MSar residents interested in participating, professional or amateur photographers, whose content to be submitted for Macau. Works may include urban landscapes, art and culture, popular customs, historical development, among others, without restrictions on the location or date of capture of photographs, whether they are emotional moments of everyday, or are historical testimonies of transformation of the city.
Through this long -term collection plan, FM expects to encourage more residents to pay attention to the “details around it”, explore and share “moments and memories of life”, transforming individual stories into a common file of Macao and achieving the goal of collective participation.
In order to encourage the sharing of great excellence work, the website will annually make a selection of the images submitted, evaluating criteria such as historical significance, characteristics of content, rarity and image description. For this year, will be selected up to 250 images, and each will be awarded with the assignment of 300 patacas.
In addition, all works received and acceptances will be included in the Annual Plan of “Friends of Memory” points and the Honor Star Program of the “Memory of Macao” website. The points will be credited automatically, the following year, in the participants' accounts after disclosure of the results.
The submission period takes place until December 31, 2025, and participation is limited to a maximum of 50 photographs per person.
The Cultural and Historical website “Memory of Macau”, created by FM, has been dedicated, since its launch, to establish a intersectoral and multichannel collaboration platform, working with schools, government departments, private companies, national and international collections institutions, photographers and artists in order to progressively enrich the content of the platform.
The FM points out in the text that the annual image collection campaign “has gained wide participation of residents, becoming an important social platform for registration, sharing and regular dissemination of information about the history and culture of Macao”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM teachers and students visited Huawei's laboratory</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/docentes-alunos-da-upm-visitaram-laboratorio-da-huawei/</link><description>The Faculty of Health and Sport Sciences of the Polytechnic University of Macau took teachers and students of the Master and Physical Education course for an exchange visit to the “Huawei Health and Sports Laboratory” in Dongguan, Guangdong Province. The visit “aimed to deepen participants' knowledge about intelligent wearable technology, sports data analysis and scientific and technological preparations for the Olympic Games, exploring deep integration between sports sciences and intelligent technologies,” says a statement from the local higher education institution. During the exchange, teachers and students participated in discussions with laboratory experts on the theme “Intelligent Vestible Devices and Trends of Sports Technology”. During the visit, China's General Sports Administration researcher Li Xiangchen indicated that the laboratory promotes technology transfer and preparation to the Olympic Games. According to the statement, through the use of Huawei intelligent vestable equipment, "students can monitor, in real time, their electrocardiograms, blood oxygen levels, among other indicators." By 2023, the platform has served 320 million users worldwide and is collaborating with more than 60 institutions, including China's Popular Liberation Army Hospital, developing health risk assessment algorithms.</description><pubDate>2025-08-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy of the “essential” phase of transformation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/economia-da-raem-em-fase-essencial-de-transformacao/</link><description>A study by the Macao Economic Association indicates that between August and October this year, the “economic perspective index” of the region will be between the 5.9 and the six points, on a scale from zero to 10. The authors warned that the economy of the MSAR is in a “essential phase of transformation and development” and predict that, in the second half of the year, the macroeconomic context of the territory remains “embarrassed and insufficient”. The association has appealed to the government and the market to strive to improve the business environment, raise the integrated competitiveness of Macao, and achieve sustainable development. He also recalled that the number of visitor to the MSAR registered a break in June, with a daily average of 96.4 thousand. Still the hotel occupancy rate was 88.4%. The authors also observed that the performance of gross game revenues remained at a “stable” level with “satisfactory results”. However, in June, the consumer confidence rate of the interior of China remained “low”, reflecting external demand and a weak desire for consumption. In June and July, the Macao Economic Perspective Index obtained 5.8 and six points, respectively, which mean a “stable” level. In the second half of this year, the Association foresees Macau to continue to face many "external factors of uncertainty and instability." The authors say that real estate investors have assumed a cautious attitude, with the prices of houses and the volume of transactions being at a "less good" level.</description><pubDate>2025-08-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2455/</link><description>Jardim Zone 1 in the Canidrome will cost up to 1.36 billion
17 proposals were received and accepted for the public tender of the Sports Jardim Zone 1 construction work for citizens in the Lot of the former Yat Yuen Canid, whose area is 40,425 square meters. According to the management of public works services, the proposed prices range from more than 1.27 billion and more than 1.36 billion patacas and the proposed deadlines range from 913 to 973 working days. The works will be executed in two zones. In the so -called zone 1, the work consists of the demolition of existing buildings, the construction of pavilions 1, 2 and 3 and the Cave Parking Park. Already the work of zone 2-which includes the Pavilion for Children, the outdoor athletics field and the Cave Parking Park-will be started following the completion and entry into operation of the zone 1 pavilions. It is expected that the venture of zone 1 will begin in the 1st quarter of 2026.
 
Two more residents found lifeless
A resident was found killed by the Judicial Police (PJ) inside a fraction located in Rua do Capão. His death would eventually be confirmed in the hospital. The case happened on Wednesday night. According to PJ, no criminal injuries were found or caused by acts of violence. In another occurrence, on the afternoon of the same day, a middle -aged resident man was found lifeless on the platform of a building located on northern avenue of the Hippodrome. The PJ revealed that the individual will have fallen from a high place, which will probably have caused his death. Also in this case suspicious injuries were discarded.
 
Discovered eight cases of irregularities in vehicles
As part of the “Thunderstorm Operation”, which took place between Tuesday and Wednesday, the Public Security Police (CPSP) body inscribed a total of 63 vehicles, having detected eight irregular cases, including three mobile phone use and two related to vehicle irregularities. In another type of operations, CPSP has supervised several pensions in various areas of the city and investigated 771 people in certain locations, not having discovered any illegal conduct.
 
Extended deadline for cross -border taxis quotas
Macao and Hong Kong agreed, after negotiations, the extension, for another three years, of the deadline for exploiting the quotas attributed to the transfronheous taxis aimed at providing a passenger transport service in light cars between both territories. The drastic reduction in the number of passengers of this type of transport during the pandemic period led to the suspension of its operation for almost three years. Currently, the quota attributed to this service is 100 (60 for Hong Kong and 40 for Macau). The quotas remain in operation, being the validity deadlines successively expired from 2028.</description><pubDate>2025-08-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Required Acceleration of Esplanade Licenses</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pedida-aceleracao-da-emissao-de-licencas-de-esplanada/</link><description>The union of the associations of the owners of restoration and beverage establishments indicated that the government has expressed its intention to move forward with the resumption of Esplanade licenses, suspended work since 2009. The association expects, after retaining, the government accelerates the appreciation and approval of requirements for this type of license and prolong the operational hours of these spaces.
 
The resumption of the issuance of Esplanade licenses was discussed at a meeting between the Union of Associations of Restoration and Beverage Owners and the Institute for Municipal Affairs, said Association President Chak Mo, at a press conference held yesterday.
According to Chan Chak Mo, the government revealed its intention to boost this work. For the Association, as the number of visitors Macau has been rising and tourists are increasingly valuing the tourist experience, it will be positive if the authorities re -accept requirements for the Esplanade license. At the same time, he called for the restoration sector to “exercise self -discipline”, collaborating with the authorities regarding the hygiene and design of the terraces, as well as in the integration of terraces with the street.
In this regard, according to the Chinese language press, Chan Chak MO has called for the government to accelerate the pace of appreciation and approval of requests for the Esplanade license to receive in the future and determine clear instructions. Specifically, the associative leader has proposed to prioritize, with priority, the requirements for opening terraces in front of the establishments where the spaces are vast, for example, in the Cotai, in the sense of helping the development of the sector, but also reduce the discomfort in the lives of residents.
Remembering that these types of licenses are no longer awarded since 2009, Chan Chak MO found that there are currently only about 20 macao licensed terraces.
In turn, Fong Kin Fu, the association's subdirector, pointed out that many local customers want to enrich meal experiences and are “anxious” by European -style outdoors. For this associative leader, the existence of terraces is “adequate” for Macau, the city of coexistence of cultures. Under the premise of not causing uncomfortable residents, Fong Kin Fu expects the operating time of the terraces to be extended to allow the sector to exceed this “difficult operational phase”.
On the other hand, regarding the issue of pets on the terraces, Yeong Keng Hoi, vice president of the association, pointed out that there are currently no restrictions on the entry of pets in restaurants, and the establishments themselves decide whether or not to authorize this behavior.
Chan Chak Mo added that today many residents have a habit of having pets. In addition, he argued that if there are more terraces in Macao, the sector can count on more local customers.</description><pubDate>2025-08-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China uses robot antelope in Tibet to monitor real herds</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/china-utiliza-antilope-robo-tibete-para-monitorizar-rebanhos-reais/</link><description>For the Tibet wolves, China's first “robot antelope” may seem as appetizing as the royal herds that wandered through the rugged tundra. But the "creature" is part of Beijing's growing vigilance, which now reaches the most remote places.
His doe eyes and his thick brown coat make the robotic ruminant almost indistinguishable from the royal antelope, while the 5G impostor and integrated artificial intelligence digitizes the Hoh Xil plateau with his sensors, show images of the Chinese state news agency Xinhua.
This is the first time that a robotic antelope has been used in the heart of Hoh Xil, which is more than 4,600 meters above sea level and where there is usually strong winds and cold temperatures. Hoh Xil is often called “no one land” due to extreme conditions. Nevertheless, it is a biodiversity hotspot known as the "kingdom of animals."
The robot to operate on rugged terrain, including steep slopes, muddy marshes and rocky soil. It can work up to two kilometers away from the control point in open areas.
Developed for Xinhua, the Chinese Academy of Sciences and Deep Robotics, based in Hangzhou, the Robot Antilope is equipped with 5G connectivity and artificial intelligence systems, allowing real-time monitoring of migration behaviors, feeding and mating of the endemic species of Tibet.
China is offering its robotic tens of thousands of millions in subsidies and has been host of the 2025 World Robotics Conference, which ended on August 12. 5G arrived at Tibet in 2019, according to Chinese government documents, and the southwest region reached 1 million users in 2022.
With the completion of a 5G base station in the city of Gogmo in late 2023, all Tibet districts were covered, the state press said.
In addition to transmitting direct images and tracking data on rare anthylopian species, Tibet's 5G infrastructure now supports a growing range of artificial intelligence applications, from small drones that can operate in areas impenetrable to telemedicine consultations and intelligent rainfall technologies, according to reports from Chinese state media.
China has invested strongly in Tibet, boosting the role of the region, in President Xi Jinping's main infrastructure initiative, “a track and a route”, reinforcing its commercial ties with Central Asia, while intensifying internal control and extends Beijing's digital presence to neighboring India, its rival.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-08-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>