<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Air Macau’s “survival” depends on “restructuring strategy”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sobrevivencia-da-air-macau-depende-de-estrategia-de-reestruturacao/</link><description>Given the “difficult” economic and financial situation in which Air Macau finds itself, the “survival” of the airline will depend “on the successful combination of implementing a restructuring strategy with government support and support from its strategic partner, and also on a repositioning in the market”, considers economist António Félix Pontes. Commander Vicente Serafim argues that one of the biggest problems, along with regional competition, are “low-cost” companies, which Air Macau is “systematically” trying to combat. On the other hand, he says that expanding routes is a way forward. Vicente Serafim also highlights that the new civil aviation law is “very vague” in some aspects, while deputy Leong Hong Sai foresees a series of challenges for the Macao SAR flag company with the entry into force of the new regime in February next year



















CATARINA PEREIRA
 
In a “difficult” economic and financial situation and with some external factors contributing to a more vulnerable operation, Air Macau faces some challenges, according to experts interviewed by Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU. Furthermore, in February 2026, the new civil aviation law will come into force, which calls for the end of Air Macau's exclusive concession and introduces a licensing system, with the aim of gradually opening up the territory's civil aviation market – some consider that the entry of the new law into force will bring more obstacles for Air Macau, while others do not foresee any major difficulties.
At the end of 2024, Air Macau's net assets totaled 209,142,539 patacas, representing only 24.8% of the share capital (842,042,000 patacas). Since it was less than half of the share capital, the airline now ran the risk of being dissolved at the request of any partner, shareholder or creditor, under article 206 of the Commercial Code. For this reason, the share capital was reduced from 842 million patacas to 200 million patacas and, on the same date, an increase was made to 2.38 billion patacas, a value that “translates a substantial financial reinforcement for Air Macau”, according to the analysis of economist António Félix Pontes.
Currently, the China National Aviation Corporation (CNAC) – the state-owned group that makes up Air China – holds 74.94% of Air Macau's share capital, while the Macao SAR's share now represents 24%. In turn, STDM now has 0.97263% of the share capital of the Macao SAR flag company. Previously, distribution was carried out under the following terms: CNAC (66.9%); MSAR (21.5%) and STDM (11.57%).
As explained by Félix Pontes to the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, with the reduction in capital to 200 million, “the percentage shares of all shareholders became ‘indexed’ to that value, so, in the particular case of STDM, its share became 23,142,800 patacas”. “As this amount did not change after the increase in Air Macau's share capital to 2.4 billion patacas, it can be assumed that STDM did not sell its share, nor did it follow the financial reinforcement of the airline carried out by the two main shareholders, thus explaining that its shareholding is currently 0.97263%”, he clarified.
Having been accumulating losses since 2020, “the Macao SAR's flagship aviation company faces a series of challenges and constraints, for which its survival will depend on the successful combination of implementing a restructuring strategy with government support and support from its strategic partner, and also on a repositioning in the market”, considers the economist.
António Félix Pontes immediately points out that there is a “great dynamic and strong and growing competitiveness of the airlines that operate in the neighboring airports of Hong Kong, Guangzhou and Shenzhen”, which offer more attractive prices and a very wide range of options for connections with international flights. Furthermore, there is “the abysmal difference in the size of the local airport” compared to those. “All this is reflected in the situation of Air Macau”, he points out.
Por outro lado, o economista fala em outros três factores: “os encargos financeiros resultantes dos empréstimos bancários à Air Macau; a sua grande dependência do mercado do Continente, o que a torna vulnerável a alterações que aí possam ocorrer, por exemplo, devido a restrições na concessão de vistos de viagem ou ao eclodir de crises de saúde, como a do Covid-19; e os seus custos operacionais que são superiores aos das outras companhias aéreas, devido a economias de escala”.
In his opinion, reversing the situation “will not be easy”. However, he mentioned some measures that could help. “The measures to be taken will have to cover several areas, namely, financial restructuring – largely already implemented with the entry of funds by the two main shareholders, now lacking the need to alleviate the financial burdens arising from bank debt; a reduction in costs without loss of operational efficiency; and leveraging the local market by taking advantage of its connection to Air China – a strategic partnership”, he argued.
Félix Pontes highlighted that the Chinese market is quite vast, and Air Macau can reinforce its commitment to optimizing routes, “particularly in connections between Macau and cities on the Mainland, namely in the Greater Bay Area, where competition is not so intense”; attract specific customer segments from certain markets; and, eventually, explore opportunities in cargo transportation.”
 
“Low-cost” companies are one of the “big problems”
With extensive experience in the aviation sector, Commander Vicente Serafim, who joined Air Macau in 1995 and where he remained for 12 years, told the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU that the Macao SAR carrier “has been making a huge loss because it is lowering prices to low-cost prices in order to compete and have passengers”. Furthermore, like Félix Pontes, he also mentioned some factors such as regional competition.
"When Air Macau started, there was no Hong Kong Airport like there is today, there was an airport that was much more limited and with much less offer. Furthermore, we have the Delta Bridge, which for me was the best thing that the Chinese Government could do, and which puts Hong Kong Airport – which has all kinds of offers for the whole world – an hour or less from Macau. It is perfectly within the radius to capture traffic. That is another big problem", he considers.
On the other hand, Vicente Serafim recalls that citizens from Mainland China need visas to travel, pointing out that “this is a major limitation that Air Macau has”, especially because Macau's population is not very high. "Even if there are 700,000 people traveling, how many of those travel on Air Macau? Very few... Air Macau cannot compete with Chinese companies for destinations in China", he argued.
Vicente Serafim considers that “China is fundamental for Macau”: “Let's see if China's social opening continues, because if it continues, people will be freer to travel wherever they want without major obstacles and things will become simpler. And there is always a great desire to get to know Hong Kong and Macau”.
As for international routes, Commander Vicente Serafim noted that Japan has practically no “low-costs” traveling to Macau, nor “full service” companies. “These routes have a positive contribution to Air Macau’s bottom line, because it is more or less alone,” he added. All other routes, such as Bangkok, Seoul, Jeju, Singapore, Kuala Lumpur have “low-cost” companies. “Air Macau is systematically, regionally, fighting the ‘low-cost’, or the ‘low-cost’ are fighting Air Macau”, he noted. “The traffic is not very large and people who go on vacation choose the cheapest fare first, the traffic that remains for Air Macau is very small”, he continued.
The former CEO of the extinct Macau Jet argues that the Macao SAR Government should adopt the same model followed with Singapore Airlines. "It is a State company, but with private management. The Government creates the strategy and they implement it. The Government uses Singapore Airlines to call people to Singapore (…) In my opinion, the Government has to use Air Macau as the Singapore government uses Singapore Airlines", he stated.
On the other hand, he considers that “the expansion of Air Macau is fundamental”, however, he warns that “expansion is a loss”. “In 2024, there was a monumental loss because of this, they opened a series of new routes and the revenue did not compensate for the costs”, he analyzed.
Regarding expansion, “it is essential for Air Macau to go to other richer markets, probably the Middle East”. "For example, go to Dubai. But who's going from Macau to Dubai? There are two people who have to go there to do something, or they're going to visit (...) it's not possible to fill a plane; people who go on business will also be few; who comes here from Dubai? People who want to play? I don't know, it's very difficult", he pointed out.
Regarding the new law that will come into force next year, Vicente Serafim, current CEO of Gratear Bay Aviation Limitada, highlights the fact that it is “very vague”, pointing out that new companies will have to be authorized by the Chief Executive. And it is not yet known how this process will be carried out: "We only know that the Chief has to say yes. And would it be that if, for example, Cathay Pacific appears and says it wants to establish a company in Macau, will the Chief say yes? I have some doubts...".
As for Air Macau, he believes that he will not face any major challenges and that his place will always be guaranteed. “Air Macau has its place, it will continue to develop”, he said, also highlighting the “significant jump” in the Government’s share capital in Air Macau, which is now 24%. "The Government cannot be the legislator, the controller and the investor... If you ask me if I am going to invest in the sector I say no; as long as the Government is in Air Macau I will not invest. This means that there will be primacy, everything that is law will be done to protect Air Macau", he stated.
In his opinion, there will be room for another airline, which will have to be “low-cost”, otherwise “we will have two roosters in the same coop, they will fight against each other and both die, or the weakest link dies, which will not be Air Macau”.
"Air Macau can also become a 'low-cost', but this has financial and personnel costs, because it won't need all those people. Air Macau is capable of having 5,000 employees and in a low-cost this cannot be the case", he observed, arguing, however, that "the ideal is not to reconvert".
In any case, Vicente Serafim believes that until the expansion of the Airport is complete “there will be no big news”. From his perspective, “the important thing is that shareholders create a way of being at Air Macau in which they can manage and control the implementation of strategies”.
 
Uncertainties and new bets
Contrary to Vicente Serafim, deputy Leong Hong Sai predicted that the entry into force of the new law, the consequent “end of the protection of Air Macau's exclusive concession” and the “entry into a phase of total opening” next year “will bring a series of challenges” to the development of the civil aviation sector, including Air Macau.
According to analysis, Air Macau will face the “risk of losing market share”. "According to the Civil Aviation Activity Law, Air Macau will lose its exclusive operating rights, but will operate under a license model. This means that, in the future, more international airlines, such as AirAsia and Cathay Pacific, will enter the Macau market. These carriers will be able to compete for sources of customers through the strategy of low prices or high quality service, which could result in a decrease in Air Macau's market share", he predicted.
Heard by the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, the deputy also pointed to pressure arising from cost control and related to operational efficiency. In this regard, he recalled that Air Macau recorded consecutive losses in recent years, while the average age of the aircraft fleet reached 8.54 years. In his opinion, the Macao SAR flag company will have to bear high maintenance costs. “On the other hand, new competitors may resort to a more flexible cost structure, for example the low-cost airline model, compressing Air Macau’s profit margin”, he warned.
The civil engineer also mentioned the “uncertainty” in the transition phase and adaptation to the new legal regime, since the transitional provisions require Air Macau to submit the license application within 90 days and to prove the capacity for continuous operations. “Although the law allows for a transition period for Air Macau, the anticipated inspection requirements, such as safety criteria and service standards, may increase compliance costs,” said Leong Hong Sai.
The deputy also anticipated an increase in regional competition, understanding that, as the group of airports in the Greater Bay Area has accelerated their integration, the network of air routes and the advantages in terms of capacity at the airports in Hong Kong, Guangzhou and Shenzhen could divert passengers from Macau. “With only around 160 flights per day, Macau Airport will have to compete together with other air hubs in the Greater Bay Area”, he argued.
From his perspective, another challenge will be related to the brand and the reputation of the service: "Air Macau has been the target of criticism for a long time because of the quality of the service, such as the punctuality rate of flights, the customer service response and the long waiting time at the airport. In an open market, the carrier will need to quickly improve the quality of the service in order to maintain competitiveness."
Even so, the deputy believes that the new law will also foster “great opportunities” for the transformation of Macau’s civil aviation sector, including that of Air Macau, the expansion of its business to the Greater Bay Area and the positioning of the Macao SAR as “One Center, One Platform and One Base”. For Leong Hong Sai, the opportunities relate to one of the “four major projects” announced by the Government, the Macau International Air Transport Hub (Port), which “could represent a good opportunity for the transformation and development of Macau’s civil aviation industry”.
Leong Hong Sai believes that Air Macau should take the opportunity to expand its cargo transport capacity and international route network. After the expansion, Macau Airport will gain a new landing platform and new cargo transportation facilities. Therefore, he suggested that Air Macau, taking advantage of the preferential policies of the Deep Cooperation Zone and the intelligent logistics park at Zhuhai Airport with an annual capacity to handle 500,000 tons of goods, develop high-value-added cargo transport, such as the transport of electronic products and cross-border electronic commerce.
“In addition, through the Delta Bridge, combined land and air transport can be implemented that allows a ‘connection to SAR airports within an hour’, in order to reduce logistical costs”, he continued.
Recalling that Macau currently has more than 50 international flight rights, he proposed the expansion of cargo transfer business under the fifth freedom of the air, together with Zhuhai Airport, for example the launch of Macau-Mainland China-Southeast Asia routes, in order to increase the “radiation power” of the Macau International Air Transport Hub.</description><pubDate>2025-10-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Subsidized purchase of equipment for people with disabilities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/subsidiada-compra-de-equipamento-para-pessoas-deficiencia/</link><description>From today onwards, the Government will grant an allowance for the purchase of support equipment for people with disabilities, which can reach 75%. The objective is to support people “with weak economic resources”, so an assessment of the household's economic situation will be made. According to IAS data, by the end of September there were almost 20 thousand people with a valid disability card in Macau
 
Catarina Pereira
 
After a pilot financing plan for the acquisition of auxiliary equipment for people with disabilities, the Government regulated the matter and, from today onwards, will grant a maximum amount of monetary allowance of 75% of the costs incurred when purchasing these devices. According to the regulations published yesterday in the Official Bulletin, the value for each piece of equipment cannot exceed 15,000 patacas.
At stake are almost 80 types of support products and special household equipment, such as wheelchairs, canes, prosthetics and orthoses, therapeutic footwear, instruments for guidance in writing, voice aids, among others, depending on the type of disability the person has. As for domestic equipment, these include electric articulated beds, toilet risers, television hearing aids, anti-slip mats, specially designed kitchen items, emergency alarm systems, fall detectors.
The request for support is made to the Social Action Institute (IAS), and the regulations establish that the total amount of support cannot exceed MOP30,000 per beneficiary over a period of three years, including transport and equipment installation costs.
To be able to benefit from the subsidy, the person must hold a BIR, have resided continuously in the Macao SAR for the last 18 months, hold a valid disability assessment registration card and have passed the assessment of the household's economic situation. This is because the Government's objective is to support people with disabilities “with weak economic resources”.
When assessing the economic situation of the household, the authorities take into account the size and total monthly income, total bank deposits and real estate. For example, the maximum monthly income limit for a family made up of just one person cannot exceed 16,100 patacas, while a family with eight or more members cannot have a monthly income exceeding 75,000 patacas.
As for savings, the maximum limits range from 130,500 patacas (household of one person) to 608,100 patacas (household of eight or more people).
The support applicant will also have to consult the price of three suppliers established in the Macao SAR for each support equipment they intend to purchase; If this is impossible, the regulation defines other rules to be followed.
For payment to be made, the applicant must submit to the IAS a specific completed form and the original invoice for the purchase of support equipment. On this occasion, you must also “display the support equipment purchased for verification purposes”. “However, in the presence of reasonable reasons, the IAS may waive this physical verification”, and instead the presentation of photographs of the equipment or on-site verification by a worker from the organization may be requested.
According to the regulation, of the decisions taken by the president of the IAS, the interested party may, within 15 days from the date of notification, submit a complaint to the leader of the organization or, within 30 days, file a contentious appeal to the Administrative Court.
 
Almost 20 thousand with valid disability card
According to IAS statistical data, by the end of September, there were 19,842 people with a valid disability assessment registration card in the territory, of which 5,456 had hearing impairment (33% of the total) and 6,056 had motor impairment (31%). There were also 3,803 people with mental disabilities, 1,326 with intellectual disabilities, 1,279 with multiple disabilities, 868 with visual disabilities and 52 people with verbal disabilities.
A large proportion of people with disabilities are already 65 years old or over, according to IAS information, a total of 11,890 people. Regarding the degree of disability, there are 9,130 ​​people with mild disabilities, 5,819 with moderate disabilities, 4,253 with severe disabilities and 1,906 with profound disabilities.
It is worth remembering that between 2019 and 2021, the IAS launched a pilot plan to support the purchase of equipment for people with disabilities. Beneficiaries could be subsidized 50% of the cost of each piece of equipment, including transportation expenses. During this period, each applicant could be entitled to three financings, each of which could not exceed MOP10,000.</description><pubDate>2025-10-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Emperor Palace and Waldo close this week</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/emperor-palace-waldo-fecham-esta-semana/</link><description>SJM and Galaxy will close the Emperor Palace and Waldo satellite casinos, respectively, by the end of the 30th and 31st of this month. Both operators stated that they will guarantee the job stability of affected workers and adequate treatment of customers with gaming chips and prizes accumulated in casinos. The Gaming Inspection and Coordination Department will oversee the closure processes, “in order to ensure strict compliance with the commitments assumed” by the two concessionaires
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
The satellite casinos Emperor Palace, from SJM, and Waldo, from Galaxy Entertainment Group (GEG), will cease operations at 11:59 pm on the 30th and 31st of October, respectively, under the coordination of the authorities and “in accordance with legal requirements”. In a statement, the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ) stated that it will designate employees to supervise the closure processes and ensure that the closure procedures proposed to the Government by the concessionaires are complied with.
SJM also guaranteed, in a statement, that all of its workers will remain employed and will be placed in other casinos of the operator, to occupy positions related to gaming, “depending on operational needs”. Local employees who work at Emperor Palace but are not employed by SJM will be invited to apply for positions within the group, with equal priority and the necessary support to facilitate the transition.
Similarly, Waldo employees will be transferred, to other casinos or non-gaming roles under GEG, “based on operational needs” and “with unchanged employment conditions”, read a statement. The group will also provide a series of training to support the “transition to new work environments and ensure continued job stability”.
In relation to the 71 workers at Emperor Palace and the 111 employees at Waldo, the DICJ assured that it “will continue to maintain close communication with the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs, in order to ensure strict compliance with the commitments assumed” by the two operators.
Under the supervision and coordination of the DICJ, the tables and gaming machines from each casino will be relocated to other casinos of the respective concessionaires. The organization will also guarantee “appropriate treatment of cash and gaming chips stored in the treasury, any unused cash coupons, the exchange of gaming chips, the prize pool accumulated in gaming machines, unexchanged gaming machine cash tickets, among others”.
Customers with gaming chips, deposits and discounts accumulated at Emperor Palace will be able to visit other casinos operated by SJM, from October 31st, with the concessionaire's guarantee that “all customer rights are duly honored”. In the same vein, GEG “will guarantee adequate treatment to the interests of customers”, and, from November 1st, holders of Waldo game chips will be able to exchange them at designated counters in the Galaxy Macau and StarWorld casinos.
SJM states that it remains “committed to its corporate responsibilities and to contributing to the stable development of Macau's gaming sector in partnership with the local community”, and that it has consistently supported the Government's measures, according to a company statement.
In turn, GEG remains aligned with the Macao SAR Government in “making significant contributions to Macau’s tourism and leisure industry”. In a statement, the group reiterates that it has actively supported the Executive's policies, in favor of the city's economic diversification and sustainable development. Remember that the three-year “transitional period” granted to “satellite casinos” ends at the end of this year.</description><pubDate>2025-10-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Pereira Coutinho re-elected president of ATFPM</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pereira-coutinho-reeleito-presidente-da-atfpm/</link><description>The elections for the new governing bodies of the Public Service Workers' Association took place this Sunday, with the only candidate list, led by José Pereira Coutinho, being naturally re-elected for another three-year term. The president of the ATFPM promised “loyalty” and “uncompromising defense” of public service rights
 
The members of the Public Service Workers' Association (ATFPM) elected on Sunday the new governing bodies of the associative group, for the period between 2025 and 2028. List A, headed by José Pereira Coutinho and the only candidate, obtained 3,902 votes from the 3,925 members who went to the polls, with 22 blank votes and one null vote being recorded, according to a press release.
Pereira Coutinho, president of the ATFPM board since 2000, thanked the partners for their trust and highlighted “the enormous responsibility that the new management bodies will have to assume”. He also promised that they “will continue to perform their duties with loyalty and fight in the uncompromising defense of the rights of public servants and retirees from public service as well as partners in the private sector”.
According to the ATFPM leader, “guaranteeing the stability of jobs”, both in the public and private sectors, and “being an effective bridge with the Government” are the association's purposes.
José Pereira Coutinho also assured that, together with the deputies of the Legislative Assembly Che Sai Wang and Chan Hao Weng, he will continue to demand the construction of housing and retirement and survival pensions for civil servants, the allocation of seven thousand patacas from the Central Pension Fund for the elderly, more support for the unemployed and small and medium-sized companies and more jobs for young people.
In anticipation of the ATFPM elections, Pereira Coutinho had told TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper that the granting of an electronic consumer card worth 10 thousand patacas and the increase in the economic contribution to 15 thousand patacas would be other of the association's proposals.
Rita Santos, re-elected president of the ATFPM General Assembly Board, said that “the great success is due to the effort and dedication of all the management bodies and the trust that the partners place in us”. He also highlighted the fact that, currently, the association has 19 thousand members.
The President of the Board of the General Assembly guaranteed that “good communication and relations with the Government” will be maintained, as well as support for the Chief Executive in the implementation of the Lines of Government Action. “We will maintain an independent, comprehensive and supportive position in supporting workers, the elderly, the unprotected and families experiencing financial difficulties,” he promised.
“We will continue to organize sporting and cultural activities, as well as holding seminars for members and their families to increase knowledge and reinforce exchanges”, highlighted Rita Santos.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-10-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Projects financed by Macau help develop the Xiushui region</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/projectos-financiados-por-macau-ajudam-desenvolver-regiao-de-xiushui/</link><description>The Macau Government's financial support for several projects carried out in Xiushui, in Jiujiang prefecture, has contributed to the development of sectors such as education and agriculture. The reconstruction of Aoyuan Middle School is one of the main examples. The educational establishment has a partnership with Escola São Paulo and tomorrow will send a delegation of 40 students and some teachers to visit the territory






























VICTOR REBELO In Xiushui
Since 2023, when cooperation agreements were signed in several areas, between the Government of Macau, at the time led by Ho Iat Seng, and officials from Jiangxi Province, the Xiushui region, in Jiujiang prefecture, has made significant investments. The millions of patacas made available by the Macao SAR have helped in the development of rural areas, specifically in sectors such as education and agriculture.
A delegation of representatives from the Portuguese-language media, who are visiting that region for a few days, at the invitation of the Liaison Office of the Central Government in the Macao SAR, had the opportunity to witness the scope of the projects already implemented within the scope of existing cooperation.
One of the examples points to the improvements, as well as the reconstruction of some wings, of the Aoyuan School (Ao is the abbreviation, in Mandarin, of the word Macau), located in Heshi village. Construction began in July 2021 and the school was officially opened on June 25, 2023. The total investment is 69.92 million yuan (of which 30 million was financed by Macau).
The building features white walls and dark tiles, in an elegant and simple style typical of Hakka architecture. The complex consists of a multifunctional block, two teaching blocks, three dormitories, a cafeteria, a sports area for various sports and other auxiliary facilities.
The modern campus can accommodate 31 classes with a capacity of 1,550 students, providing high-quality educational resources for the city's secondary school students.
“We are very grateful to the Government of Macau for supporting the reconstruction of the school and thus providing much better conditions for our students”, said the school director. Yunchun She highlighted the “huge importance” of the Macao SAR’s support, stressing that “it allows us to have good quality education”.
Aoyuan School and São Paulo School of Macau signed an exchange protocol in 2023 and have developed collaborations in areas such as subject teaching seminars and mutual visits between teachers, students and educational administrators. Tomorrow, a delegation of 40 students and some teachers will travel to Macau to continue the established exchange.
Another project with financial contribution from the territorial government is located in the village of Huoshi, municipality of Heshi, aimed at the agricultural sector, with a total investment of 30 million yuan, launched in October 2019 and completed in three phases. It was co-financed by member units of the China Business Association, the Macau Banking Association and the Macau Insurance Association, with a total investment, on the Macao SAR side, of around 12 million yuan.
The base adopts a “leading company + large producers + farmers” model, housing eight operational entities. The utilization rate and productivity of greenhouses exceeds 95%, with an annual output of more than three million kilograms of pollution-free fruits and vegetables, generating an annual output value of 23 million yuan.
The project supplies vegetable markets in the Xiushui region and neighboring areas. It generates employment for more than 280 people and increases per capita income by more than 5,000 yuan, “injecting new vitality into the local economy”, according to those responsible for the agricultural complex told Macau journalists.
 
Nursery and Tea Museum
Macao SAR's support made it possible to realize other dreams of the local community of Xiushui, such as the creation of a daycare center, called Aole, just built inside Nanzhe Hospital. The host of the visit inside the building highlighted that the center “fills a gap in public childcare services in the region”.
With a total area of ​​approximately 14,000 square meters, the center will offer nine classes with a total capacity for 150 children. The total investment is approximately 70 million yuan. After an “on-site” inspection, carried out by Macau figures, in September 2024, it was decided to contribute 8.5 million Hong Kong dollars (approximately 7.65 million yuan) to support the completion of the project.
The center will provide “high quality” childcare services and help alleviate problems faced by young working parents, “increasing social stability”. It will also offer training to social childcare institutions and professionals.
For the same rural area, Macau participated in the Ecological Technological Park, in a project with a total investment of 160 million yuan. Inclui a construção do Museu do Chá Ninghong da China, uma oficina desse património cultural imaterial, centros digital de comércio electrónico da indústria do chá, de testes e serviços científicos e tecnológicos do chá, uma fábrica de demonstração de processamento grosso e fino de folhas de chá e logística de armazenamento, uma rua da cultura do chá, um bar literário urbano temático e uma loja principal do Chá Ninghong.
The part financed by Macau is used for the construction of the tea-themed urban literary bar, which covers an area of ​​600 square meters and a construction area of ​​1,200 square meters. The funding supported the main construction, decoration and purchase of books for the literary bar.
 
Memorial marks collaboration protocol
As a way of thanking Macau for its help in implementing the projects, as well as publicizing this collaboration to the public, the municipal leaders of Xiushui erected a memorial, located in the center of the Ancient City of Ningzhou.
It is a museum that includes an exhibition hall that commemorates the milestone of mutual assistance and cooperation between Macau and the Xiushui region. The total investment is approximately 8.49 million yuan, covering an area of ​​861 square meters.
The memorial project is operated by “Xiushui County Tourism Investment and Development Company”, integrating popular check-in and catering services, and adopting the “sustaining the museum with the museum itself” operation model.
The interior space of the memorial is divided into three areas. The first floor shows the “charm of the Xiushui project supported by Macau”, as described by the guide during the visit to the space, while the second floor offers online and offline experiences of cross-border e-commerce cooperation between Macau and Xiushui, as well as virtual reality video experiences of tourist attractions on both sides.
The atrium area is a place for tourists to take photographs and also serves to promote the cultures of Macau and Xiushui. The rear courtyard is designed as a Portuguese restaurant and tea restaurant, serving mainly Macanese and Chinese snacks, wine tasting and Cantonese tea.
On this visit to Jiangshi Province, the Macau delegation also traveled to the outskirts of the city of Jingdezhen, famous for the production of ceramics and porcelain, climbing Mount Lu, located at an altitude of more than 1,200 meters, with temperatures around 10ºC. This tourist area was very popular with ancient famous figures of Chinese culture, namely philosophers, poets and calligraphers. Mao Zhedong himself resided there for about five months.
The group of journalists also went to the museum that depicts the history of China's war against the Japanese invasion, and it was there, on Mount Lu, that important meetings took place between the leaders of the Chinese Communist Party and the Kuomintang.
 
* JTM journalist traveled to Jiangxi Province at the invitation of the Liaison Office of the Central Government in the Macao SAR.</description><pubDate>2025-10-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>75% of young people support Metro’s “Linha Oeste”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/75-dos-jovens-apoiam-linha-oeste-metro/</link><description>The idea of ​​building the “West Line” of the Light Rail, which could pass through Porto Interior and Fai Chi Kei, has the support of 75% of a total of 647 young people from Macau interviewed by the New Chinese Youth Association. Furthermore, the same survey reveals that, although almost 60% of young people have used the Metro in the last year, they are all low-frequency users
 
A survey promoted by the Macau New Chinese Youth Association on young people's opinions regarding the Light Rail reveals that 75% of a total of 647 local young people aged between 18 and 44 were in favor of the construction of the “West Line”, which is in planning.
It is worth remembering that, in the presentation of the Lines of Government Action for this year, the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, announced two new Metro lines in planning, one of which is the “West Line”. The idea is that this line starts at the Qingmao Border Post, extends to Fai Chi Kei, passing through the Inner Harbor and ending in Barra.
In general, for more than 70% of young people surveyed, the Metro system needs to be further expanded after the construction of the Eastern Line is completed.
On the other hand, although almost 60% of respondents have used the Light Rail over the last year, the majority use this means of transport only once every three months or at an even lower frequency, with all of them being low-frequency users. The study also points out that only 1.5% of young people interviewed use the Metro as their main means of transport. In contrast, local young people tend to travel more by bus, walking or driving, the survey concludes.
On the other hand, in the opinion of 39% of respondents, Light Rail services are generally satisfactory. However, according to the study, there are several factors that affect the willingness to use the Metro, including insufficient network coverage, the long distance between stops and places where people live, the inability to reach destinations directly via the Metro and the current payment methods available in the entry and exit access channels at stations.
Based on the findings of the study, the Chinese New Youth Association suggested the accelerated construction of the Metro network, giving priority to the implementation of the “West Line” planning and expanding the Metro network to the central areas of residents' activities.
Furthermore, he proposed that access channels at Metro stations begin accepting payments using QR codes and credit card readings. Defending, on the other hand, an official mobile application for Metro passengers, the association also called for the rapid implementation of discounts on transfers between buses and the Metro.</description><pubDate>2025-10-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>3×3 basketball livened up Ruins of São Paulo</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/basquetebol-3x3-animou-ruinas-de-sao-paulo/</link><description>Largo das Ruínas de São Paulo was the stage for the finals of the “3×3 Circuit of Grande Baía”. The “Wolf United SGS” team won an “exciting” final in the men’s category, while the women’s competition was won by the “Lang Lang Wan Dui” team.
 
The finals of the “3×3 Circuit of Grande Baía” ended on Sunday, with victories for the men’s team “Wolf United SGS” and the women’s team “Lang Lang Wan Dui”, in Largo das Ruínas de São Paulo. In an “exciting game”, “Wolf United SGS” beat the “Dongguan” team by 21:16, while the “Lang Lang Wan Dui” athletes defeated the “Guangogdong Dong Cha Dao” team by the score of 20:15.
In third place in the men's category was the “Guangdong Dong Cha Dao” team, after defeating “Siu Saam Baa Wolf United” by 21:19. In the female category, “Superbaby” completed the podium, beating “Tian Jian Basquetebol” by 20:19.
The champions of both categories received cash prizes and gifts worth a total of more than MOP700,000, according to the Sports Institute (ID). The awards distribution ceremony was attended by the vice-president of ID, Mok Chi Hang, the executive director of “Starmac”, Lou Kit Long, the president of the Board of Directors of the General Basketball Association of Macau-China, Wu Chong Fai and the financial and administrative director of Wynn Resorts, Craig Fullalove, among others.
The “International Children’s Basketball Tournament 3×3 ‘New Stars’” also took place, in which 35 teams from Guangzhou, Foshan, Hengqin, Macau, Hong Kong and Malaysia participated. According to the ID, young people from different regions showed “the vigor and vitality of 3×3 basketball”. The two teams from “Keang Peng” won the men’s and women’s under-12 categories. In the under-10 category, “Aoguan Whirlwind” became champion, while “Zhongshan Aoguan” won first place in the under-8 category.
Once the competitions were over, the organization launched the “Photography Competition for the ‘3×3 Circuit of Greater Bay Area”, in which interested parties will be able to submit their works, until December 12th.
Multiple cities in Greater Bay Area hosted the various stages of the circuit, which took place between August and October, in an initiative that aimed to “boost sports exchange”, “promote the development of sports tourism” and “actively awaken enthusiasm for the sport”. The ID also hopes that the event has contributed “to publicizing the National Games” and created “an enthusiastic atmosphere for sporting events”.
The circuit was co-organized by ID, the company “Starmac”, Macau-China General Basketball Association, “Chaiioi Sports Company” and “Zhuixing Culture &amp; Media”, with sponsorship from Wynn.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-10-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>GPM will bring “strong” pressure to traffic and changes in careers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/gpm-trara-pressoes-fortes-ao-transito-alteracoes-nas-carreiras/</link><description>The 72nd edition of the Macau Grand Prix (GPM), which will take place from the 13th to the 16th of November, will cause “strong pressure” on traffic on several roads in the north and central zones, said the head of the coordination division of the Traffic Affairs Services Department (DSAT), Mak Hou Kit, at a press conference. These include Avenida Doutor Rodrigo Rodrigues, Avenida do Coronel Mesquita, Avenida do Ouvidor Arriaga, Rua de Francisco Xavier Pereira and Avenida de Sidónio Pais. According to him, ramp B of the viaduct at Rotunda da Amizade will open to traffic in the first half of next month, even before the start of the GPM, through which vehicles will be able to go from Macau Bridge directly to Avenida do Nordeste, “which will ease the flow of vehicles”. Furthermore, he said that the authorities have already coordinated with the Public Works Services to adjust the scope of some works, including the provisional restoration of three lanes on Rua Central da Areia Preta, in order to alleviate traffic pressure. On the other hand, during the GPM, some roads will be temporarily closed, while 52 bus routes will have changed routes, of which two routes will be suspended. In addition, the authorities will once again make two special routes available, namely 12T and 31T, which will run between Praça Ferreira do Amaral and a temporary stop near the Macau Forum. For the official, there will be no “overlapping” impacts on traffic due to the holding, also at this time, of the National Games, as the main competitions will take place on the Islands. According to the GPM Organizing Committee, for this edition they will install 162 mobile gates and have already made some adjustments, including widening the opening of the gates in order to facilitate the movement of citizens. Furthermore, from the afternoon of November 10th, some intersections will be closed.</description><pubDate>2025-10-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Online divorce extended to couples with minor children</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/divorcio-online-alargado-casais-filhos-menores/</link><description>Since yesterday, the Directorate of Justice Affairs Services (DSAJ) has made available, in the Single Account, the online divorce service by mutual consent, applicable to cases in which there are common minor children. The body emphasizes, however, that “the rigor and criteria for assessing the process remain unchanged, with an agreement on the exercise of parental authority over minor children assessed jointly by the Registrar and the Public Prosecutor”. According to the DSAJ, after submitting the request, the spouses will have to go to the Civil Registry Office to attend the divorce conference. Remember that the online divorce service by mutual consent has been available since November last year, but only for couples where the spouses do not have common minor children. In the future, the DSAJ ensures that it will continue to promote the electronic reform of registry and notary services and gradually improve the public services model, “taking into account the maintenance of the rigor of the processes and compliance with legal provisions”. Since January 1st of this year, spouses, regardless of the existence of common minor children, can apply for divorce by mutual consent at the Civil Registry Office.</description><pubDate>2025-10-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Sands Lifestyle” now allows member registration through Alipay</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sands-lifestyle-ja-permite-registo-de-membros-atraves-alipay/</link><description>A new partnership between Sands and “Macau Pass” now allows Alipay users to become members of the “Sands Lifestyle” program, with immediate access to a wide choice of exclusive benefits, including discounts on restaurants, hotels and shopping. “New members can sign up instantly with a single tap during checkout, while existing members are automatically recognized,” with exclusive pricing and a loyalty points program. For merchants, the service integrates payments, member management and other tools into a single digital platform, “designed to elevate the customer experience and improve business efficiency”, says a statement from the gaming concessionaire. “The service not only simplifies payment and sign-up for consumers, but also significantly improves merchant efficiency by integrating what were traditionally three separate functions, checkout, registration and customer engagement,” it reads. By leveraging digital tools, merchants can gain more insight into customer preferences, provide personalized offers and boost sales, according to Sands. “The service gives merchants the possibility of lasting customer loyalty and sustaining business growth.” The announcement was made recently, at a demonstration about innovation that took place at the Londoner. This latest update responds to the “growing demand for digital operations among traders”, argues Sands.</description><pubDate>2025-10-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“King of Snooker” returns to Wynn to face world champion</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/rei-snooker-volta-ao-wynn-para-enfrentar-campeao-mundo/</link><description>Table billiards legend Ronnie O’Sullivan is returning to Macau for a match with world champion Zhao Xintong. At 8pm on Friday, October 31st, the “King of Snooker” will face the 2025 world champion, in a “memorable sporting spectacle for residents and tourists”, according to a press release from Wynn. The “Wynn brand ambassador” and seven-time world champion will face the first Asian player to win the table billiards world championship, in the Wynn Macau Grand Ballroom. Tickets for the meeting are on sale for 580 and 880 patacas, with an exclusive 25% discount for Macau residents and members of the “Wynn Insider” and “Wynn Rewards” programs. They are available on the gaming operator's website, at Wynn Macau, at Wynn Palace and on the “Damai” platform. The event is an initiative aligned with the Government's diversification strategy “1+4”, in order to “boost the intersectoral integration of sports and tourism”, indicates the note. Wynn has actively supported the development of Macau as a “Sports City”, “continuously introducing and launching high-level sporting events” in order to offer residents and tourists “a wider range of quality leisure experiences”. In the future, the operator hopes to continue to “organize world-class sporting events to help improve the development of the sports atmosphere and industry” and to “enrich Macau as a ‘World Center for Tourism and Leisure’”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>BRIEF</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2493/</link><description>Arrested on suspicion of raping and kidnapping countrywoman
A 34-year-old man from Mainland China was arrested in Macau on suspicion of kidnapping and rape in a hotel room. According to the PJ, he attacked the victim in the head with an ashtray, in addition to tying his neck with a charger cord. CPSP agents and firefighters managed to rescue the victim, having detained the suspect in the act. The woman, also middle-aged and from Continente, had known the suspect since last year. In the early hours of Saturday, they met at a restaurant in ZAPE, at which time the suspect threatened the victim that he would reveal to her husband that they had had sexual relations. It was then that he forced the victim to go to a hotel and have sex. Kidnapped for an hour, the woman tried to report the case, but was stopped and attacked. She still managed to contact her older sister, who helped her alert the police. The man refused to cooperate in the investigations, but the evidence collected by the police and the examination report on the victim's injuries indicate that there is strong evidence that the suspect committed the crimes.
 
DSAL offers 111 job openings in three sessions
At the beginning of November, the Labor Affairs Bureau (DSAL) will organize, in collaboration with the Macau Federation of Workers' Associations, three specific job matching sessions, providing 111 jobs. Registration can be made until 12pm on October 31st. Among the vacancies, 19 are at SJM Resorts, S.A., including sales manager, reception supervisor, among others. This session takes place on the 4th. On the 6th, Pak Tat-Gestão de Catering Companhia offers 40 job offers, while on the 7th, Nova Galaxy Entretenimento 2006 Companhia Limitada offers 52 jobs.
 
Public service working hours are maintained
The Public Administration's working hours will remain unchanged, under the new Workers' Statute, which comes into force on November 1st. According to an order published yesterday in the Official Bulletin, the Chief Executive set normal working hours after hearing the 31 members of the sector's associations. Thus, the opening hours continue to be from 9:00 am to 1:00 pm, from Monday to Friday, as well as from 2:30 pm to 5:45 pm, from Monday to Thursday, and from 2:30 pm to 5:30 pm, on Friday.
 
Registration open for ecological activities
Starting today, registration is open for the November activities to be carried out in the Ecological Zones, organized by the Environmental Protection Services. The “Open Day to the Public” takes place on the 8th and 22nd (at 10am and 3pm) and has 120 places. The visit, guided by guides, will last two hours. During the tour, participants will be able to enter Ecological Zone I and Ecological Zone II to enjoy the plants and birds. On the 8th there will also be a workshop on nature, for children and parents, which offers 12 places. Until April next year, the “bird watching in the wetlands” tour will be held monthly. In November, this tour takes place on the 22nd, at 10am and 3pm, with 50 people able to participate.
 
“Radiant Blue” shows 30 works by Hu Jiawen
The Rui Cunha Foundation opens today, at 6:30 pm, Hu Jiawen's solo exhibition, entitled “Azul Radiante”. The artist “invites the viewer to immerse themselves in a world where the traditional and the contemporary coexist, through the dialogue between the calm lines of meticulous brushwork and the intense metallic burns, of blue paint and gold leaf”, indicates the organization. The works will be on display until November 8th, and entry is free.
Entry is free.</description><pubDate>2025-10-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Minimum wage expected to increase to 7,280 patacas per month</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/salario-minimo-devera-aumentar-para-7-280-patacas-por-mes/</link><description>From January 1st next year, the minimum wage is expected to rise from 7,072 patacas per month to 7,280 patacas per month. At least, that is the intention of the Government, which will submit the proposed law to the Legislative Assembly as quickly as possible. Authorities estimate that the measure will benefit around 18,200 people, excluding domestic workers
 
Catarina Pereira*
 
The Government intends to raise the minimum wage to 35 patacas per hour, representing an increase of one pataca per hour, announced the spokesperson of the Executive Council, Wong Sio Chak. Since the idea is for the proposed law to come into force on January 1, 2026, the Secretary for Administration and Justice also indicated that the Government will “immediately submit it” to the Legislative Assembly for consideration.
The diploma proposes that the universal minimum wage be increased from the current 34 patacas per hour to 35 and from 7,072 patacas per month to 7,280 patacas, as well as from 272 to 280 patacas per day and 1,632 to 1,680 patacas per week. The increase is 2.9% in all forms of calculation.
The decision was taken after hearing the opinions of employers and workers within the Permanent Council for Social Coordination (CPCS), “and comprehensively considering the macroeconomy, the labor market, workers' remuneration and the operational situation of employers” during the implementation of the minimum wage between November 1, 2022 and October 31, 2024.
Remember that, before this decision, the expectation was that the minimum wage could increase to between 35 and 37 patacas per hour. The option for the minimum value was justified by the “current economic conditions” in the territory.
When this issue was discussed at the CPCS, employers rejected a possible increase in the minimum wage, arguing that the Executive should launch even more measures to support small and medium-sized companies.
For Vong Kuok Seng, vice-president of the board of the Macau Commercial Association and representative of employers, it would not be favorable to increase the minimum wage, since “the current business environment in Macau is not very optimistic”, he argued at the time. “Companies face many operational difficulties and the desire and form of consumption have also changed”, he explained.
The labor part asked for 37 patacas. Choi Kam Fu, vice-president of the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau and workers' representative, also defending an update of the review mechanism as it is “long overdue”.
According to Wong Sio Chak, the Government estimates that this increase will benefit around 18,200 workers, representing 4.4% of the total, “excluding domestic workers”. The main beneficiary groups will be workers in the building administration and cleaning services sectors.
 
Domestic workers are excluded again
The legal revision once again excludes domestic employees. At the press conference to present the proposal, the director of Labor Affairs Services (DSAL) defended the exclusion of domestic workers. “When the law was established, the main premise was the ‘unique nature’ of domestic work and the need for the worker to ‘integrate’ into the employer’s family life,” said Chan Un Tong.
“However, even if this legislation does not apply to them, this does not mean that their rights are not protected,” he added. For new contracts for domestic workers, signed from July 2024, the minimum remuneration set by DSAL is 3,200 patacas.
Chan Un Tong mentioned, however, that the median salary for these hires is around 3,800 patacas, a value that, in the director's opinion, “demonstrates that, even excluded from the general regime, there are mechanisms that guarantee a reasonable remuneration”.
It is recalled that, in 2022, the UN Human Rights Committee questioned Macau “why non-resident domestic workers are treated differently” and, unlike other workers, are not covered by the minimum wage.
“What measures is DSAL taking to protect the lives of migrant domestic workers, who are particularly vulnerable to illegal and abusive treatment by employers”, asked committee member Shuichi Furuya.
When explaining why domestic workers are not entitled to the minimum wage, DSAL responded to the committee that this group of workers is “a special case” and that “employers are providing employment without a profit motive”.
 
*With Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Loewe has a parade full of colors in its new phase after Anderson</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/loewe-tem-desfile-repleto-de-cores-na-sua-nova-fase-apos-anderson/</link><description>Spanish Loewe bet on intense colors and refined modeling in Paris, at the debut of Jack McCollough and Lazaro Hernandez, the brand's new artistic directors after the departure of Jonathan Anderson.
 



















The Americans took over the position of the now Dior designer, after a decade under the command of Loewe, during which he intensely rejuvenated the brand, transforming it into a sales and notoriety success.
For their debut at the Spanish brand, currently part of the French group LVMH, McCollough and Hernandez opted for an explosion of colors, and some proposals directly recalled the multicolored aesthetic of filmmaker Pedro Almodóvar.
The designers were inspired by the chromatic ideas of the American abstract painter Ellsworth Kelly (1923-2015), and especially by the painting “Yellow Panel with Red Curve”.
“In it resides a vitality and a texture that we consider fundamental to the brand, a chromatic intensity and a sensuality that we consider inherent to its Spanish roots and, ultimately, an optimism and a spirit with which we deeply identify”, they stated in a message on the networks.
The duo, who founded the New York brand Proenza Schouler in 2002, placed a special emphasis on leather, a tradition of Loewe, founded in Madrid in 1846 as a leather goods house.
Short dresses in this material, almost shaped like sculptures, came in vibrant colors or printed versions. Structured and polished jackets gained shades such as radiant blue and coral red.
McCollough and Hernandez, both born in 1978, tend to work a lot with materials and combine different textures.
Jeans-style pants featured soft, plush fabrics, strapless dresses were made from flannel, and tops were made from knits with wavy shapes.
The parade was held in a large white space with glazed ceramic benches, in the south of Paris. Pedro Almodóvar, a supporter of the brand, attended the fashion show with actress Milena Smit, with whom he filmed ‘Mães Paralelas’.
“There is a very bright color palette, I think everything in general is very feminine, very in favor of the female silhouette,” the Spanish director told AFP.
The American duo had a great responsibility in taking over one of the best-positioned brands in the luxury industry, which is facing economic and commercial difficulties.
According to the Lyst index, specialized in fashion, in the second quarter of 2025, Loewe occupied second place among the hottest brands, behind Miu Miu. In the previous period, it led the ranking.
The Loewe show was one of the most anticipated at Paris Women's Fashion Week, and critics considered it a success.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-10-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>