<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Illegal work is more common in wholesale and retail trade</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/trabalho-ilegal-e-mais-frequente-comercio-por-grosso-retalho/</link><description>Chan Chon U, deputy director of Labor Affairs Services, said yesterday that most cases of illegal work occur in the wholesale and retail trade sector. As revealed, in the overall year 2025, 668 people were sanctioned for “illegal work”, an increase of 8.4% in annual terms. The total fines exceeded six million patacas
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
Most illegal labor cases are related to the wholesale and retail trade sector, said Chan Chon U, deputy director of the Labor Affairs Bureau (DSAL), yesterday. During a press conference, the official explained that cases of illegal work often boil down to “a lack of knowledge of the legislation”. Promising more interdepartmental collaboration and law enforcement efforts, Chan also called on citizens to report suspicious cases, assuring that DSAL will take reports “very seriously”.
Regarding complaints from citizens, the deputy director asked them to provide “the place, the time”. “In past cases, we had some difficulty, there was a lack of location data or even photographs”, he explained. "Citizens can provide more information. They can help a lot with this additional information", he asserted.
Yesterday, DSAL carried out an inspection, in which it identified 122 drivers. The authorities found two drivers suspected of carrying out activities other than those authorized, said Chan Chon U, adding that “DSAL will initiate the respective proceedings for illegal work, following current regulations”.
In 2025 overall, DSAL carried out 683 inspections, including 491 independent and 192 in cooperation with other entities. Of this universe, 62 inspections targeted drivers.
Overall, 668 people were sanctioned for “illegal work”, “other than the authorized”, “in a location” or “for an employer other than the authorized” or “self-employed by non-residents”, with a combined amount of fines exceeding six million patacas. Of the drivers inspected, 157 were sanctioned for “illegally exercising driver duties”, with a total fine of 982,500 patacas, according to Chan Chon U.
In 2024, of the 576 inspections carried out by DSAL, 65 involved drivers, with administrative sanctions being applied to 616 people for illegal work, which means that there was an increase of 8.4% in the last year. The total amount of fines was just over six million patacas, in 2024, similar to last year.
On the other hand, there were two fewer drivers sanctioned in 2025, compared to the 159 registered in the previous year. In 2024, the total value of fines imposed on these illegal drivers was more than 1.1 million patacas.
 
More publicity actions
Asked about job advertisements for fraudulent tour guides, Chan replied that DSAL has already “verified these cases on the platforms” and that “some preventive actions have been taken, for example, some legislative clarification sessions”. “We also issue reports and activities with more detailed information that will be continuously disseminated”, he promised.
The deputy director of DSAL urged “all sectors to act in strict accordance with the legislation, refraining from any expectation of impunity”. He also stated that “DSAL will continue to collaborate with the Public Security Police Corps to reinforce law enforcement, monitoring and combating all forms of illegal work”.
“If any illegal act is detected, the foreseen sanctions will be strictly applied, without any tolerance”, warned the person in charge.
Regarding public awareness and publicity activities, Chan Chon U stated that “53 information sessions have already been carried out on the illegal work of non-residents”. “We have been promoting some games with prizes on WeChat”, he said, adding that more activities related to legislation will be developed for the public to know.</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Civics in public spaces shows signs of clear improvement</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/civismo-nos-espacos-publicos-da-sinais-de-franca-melhoria/</link><description>Although there is no clear trend towards a decrease in violations of the General Regulation of Public Spaces in recent years, as the numbers have been fluctuating from year to year, the truth is that in 2025 cases of “lack of civility” registered a minimum since at least 2016, according to data from the Institute for Municipal Affairs analyzed by the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper. The organization recorded 16,102 infractions, which translates into an annual drop of 9.18% and a decrease of 43% compared to around a decade ago. More than half of the fines were given to people who spat or threw rubbish on the ground. Environmentalist Joe Chan argues that fines should be increased to 1,500 patacas, while Nick Lei calls for more awareness among citizens
 
CATARINA PEREIRA
 
Habits that are difficult to break, but are slowly decreasing. The scenario of infractions due to “lack of civility” in the territory is clearly better than it was around 10 years ago. Representative Nick Lei and environmentalist Joe Chan praise the steps taken, but consider that Macau can do more.
Over the past year, 16,102 infractions were recorded within the scope of the General Regulation of Public Spaces, which reflects a decrease of 43% in relation to the 28,362 cases recorded in 2016. In the year 2025, in fact, this type of infractions registered a minimum since at least that year, according to data analyzed by the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper.
In the annual comparison, there was a decrease of 9.18% in relation to the 17,730 infractions recorded by the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) in 2024. In 2023, 17,046 infractions had been recorded in this context.
Environmentalist Joe Chan considers that, “in the last decade, through education and legislation, the Macau Government has managed to increase awareness about public hygiene and cleanliness in the city”. From the outset, he points out that the IAM has “many programs” related to cleaning the city aimed at students and citizens, in addition to that the Environmental Protection Services Directorate “has also launched many new policies that help the public to recycle waste and deal with waste in a much more appropriate way”.
“Therefore, I definitely appreciate all the efforts that the Government has made to make this city a cleaner and healthier place to live,” he said, speaking to this newspaper. Joe Chan, however, argues that common infractions, whose fine varies between 300 and 600 patacas, should be sanctioned with 1,500 patacas, as is the case with the fine for smoking in prohibited places, under the Smoking Prevention and Control Law.
Over the past year, the fines paid due to the application of the General Regulations on Public Spaces yielded 7.1 million patacas to the IAM. Even though 16,102 infractions and fines were recorded in 2025, only 11,586 or 72% of the total were paid, a discrepancy that could be related to cases that had the fine sanction postponed until the following year, because they were under investigation, defense or challenge, as the organization explained to this newspaper in previous years, or even because the IAM may have decided, ultimately, not to apply the sanction after further investigation. in-depth.
Violators can choose to participate in social service programs in lieu of paying fines – but this form of penalty is only applicable to residents. In 2025, a total of 32 offenders participated in the civic service scheme, 16 fewer than the 48 recorded in 2024.
In the same vein, Nick Lei states that “the decreasing trend in the number of infractions shows that awareness has increased among the public and we have also achieved these results thanks to the awareness-raising actions promoted over the years”. The deputy, who was already part of the IAM Advisory Council, therefore praises the organization's work in this area. Furthermore, he believes that the data reflects “an attitude of respect” on the part of the public towards the regulation.
 
54% of fines include throwing rubbish and spitting on the ground
The more than 16,100 fines carried out last year included 8,646 cases of “abandonment of any solid waste”, which registered an annual increase of 5.3%. The reported cases of people throwing rubbish on the ground represented almost 54% of the total. Situations of “spitting or release of nasal mucus” totaled 2,123 (-21.3 in annual terms). These two behaviors alone accounted for 10,769 fines (67% of the total).
“Other” cases followed – which include, for example, “illegal fishing activity, illegal act of harvesting or damaging plants, wiping objects in public space, choosing waste contained in garbage containers” -, with a total of 2,760 fines (-27.2%). Statistical data also points to 2,289 situations of “placement or abandonment of any materials or objects” (-27.2%), 168 of “falling water from an air conditioning unit” (-68.8%) and 116 of “pet waste” (+43.2%).
Nick Lei highlights, however, that “the changes were not significant in relation to the main types of infractions”. On the other hand, it highlights the “evident decrease”, for example, that occurred in some categories, such as “others”. The “fall of water drops from the air conditioning unit” also marked a significant drop in the space of a year. “I believe that this drop contributed to the general trend of decreasing the number of criminal cases”, added the deputy.
It is recalled that, last year, the then Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, argued that the amount of fines provided for in the Regulation is “manifestly incompatible with the current socioeconomic level”, indicating that the regime would be subject to review.
In this regard, Nick Lei says that he receives “a lot of opinions” related to the problem of water dripping from the air conditioning. “In some cases, the problem does not occur on the streets, but in common spaces of residential buildings, which implies difficulties in enforcing the law,” he noted. In this sense, he states that these cases deserve “consideration by the authorities”.
"Will the Government consider defining provisions to regulate this problem in the future revision of the regulation? We need to discuss this issue. We must take as a reference the new tobacco control law, within the scope of which authorities can apply the law in the common spaces of residential buildings", he defended.
 
Increase awareness towards a sustainable city
Nick Lei states, on the other hand, that he hopes that “the authorities reinforce the level of education and awareness regarding the regulation of public spaces among citizens”. Stressing that the regulation has been in force for more than 20 years, the deputy emphasizes that “society has already evolved and the conditions for applying the law have already become very different from the conditions observed more than two decades ago”.
Joe Chan, in turn, says that “in the future, our city must evolve into a more sustainable or ecological city, instead of just a clean city”. “Such as increasing the percentage of recycling, using more renewable energy that makes the air cleaner, or even aiming to build a garden city with more plantations... All of this requires continuous education and legislation, regular and updated reviews on the value of fines and the waste management policy”, concluded the environmentalist.
From another perspective, looking at the IAM data it can be seen that 6,891 offenses were committed by Macau residents, while 9,211 were perpetrated by non-residents.
The data also reveals that people continue to prefer to pay fines in person, as 7,029 were paid over the counter, for a total of 4.4 million patacas. Fines paid via the internet totaled just 4,557, for a total of around 2.7 million patacas.
Last year, January was the month in which the most fines were made, with a total of 2,015, followed by March, with 1,822. October and November recorded the lowest numbers with 1,183 and 1,053 fines, respectively.
The regulation, which has been in force since 2004, and the “Catalog of Infractions” have established the amounts of fines depending on the classification as common infractions (300 or 600 patacas), serious (from 700 to 2,500 patacas or from 700 to 5,000) and very serious (between 2,000 and 5,000 patacas or from 2,000 to 10,000).</description><pubDate>2026-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Nipah leads authorities to reinforce medical assessment at borders</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/nipah-leva-autoridades-reforcar-avaliacao-medica-nas-fronteiras/</link><description>Due to Nipah virus infections detected in India, Macau authorities decided to reinforce medical surveillance at the borders, despite there being no direct flights from the territory to that country. Stressing that they are monitoring the situation, the Health Services indicated that they will intensify assessment and medical examinations at border posts “for those who have a history of travel and present symptoms”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Macao SAR authorities will reinforce border surveillance due to the Nipah virus, following an epidemiological alert launched by Indian health authorities. The virus, which was identified in the state of West Bengal, has already resulted in at least two confirmed cases and led to the quarantine of 190 people. The Health Services (SSM) said yesterday that it was “closely monitoring the situation” caused by the virus infection in eastern India, appealing to residents to “avoid traveling to that region”.
“Individuals who are there must take appropriate preventive measures and, if flu symptoms appear after returning to Macau, they should consult a doctor as soon as possible and inform them of their travel and contact history”, highlighted the organization.
Although there are no direct flights between Macau and India, “as a matter of precaution, assessment and medical examinations will be reinforced at border posts for those who have a history of travel and present symptoms”, indicated the SSM.
The Hong Kong Government also announced a strengthening of health checks for travelers arriving at the airport from India. In a statement, cited by Lusa, the director of the Health Protection Service, Edwin Tsui Lok Kin, confirmed the deployment of teams to the airport.
The objective is to “screen the temperature of travelers at relevant boarding gates, carry out medical assessments on symptomatic travelers and refer suspected cases with a potential impact on public health to hospitals for examination”, explained the director.
Despite the measure, Edwin Tsui highlighted that, to date, no case of Nipah virus infection has been recorded in Hong Kong and that there are no direct flights between the territory and Calcutta, capital of the Indian state of West Bengal.
Here, the SSM state that Nipah is a zoonotic virus that can be fatal. “Frugivorous bats are the natural hosts of the Nipah virus, and it can be transmitted to humans through contaminated food (usually fruit or fruit-derived products) or through contact with infected pigs, or directly between people”, he highlights.
Nipah virus infection causes everything from asymptomatic symptoms to acute respiratory illnesses and fatal encephalitis, with an estimated mortality rate of between 40% and 75%. The first symptoms are similar to those of the flu, and in more serious cases there may be breathing difficulties, dizziness, drowsiness, mental confusion, among others. Generally, the incubation period varies between four and 14 days, with a maximum of 45 days.
Outbreaks of the Nipah virus, for which there is still no approved vaccine or cure, occur almost annually in Bangladesh and the neighboring Indian state of West Bengal, and occasionally in other countries in South and Southeast Asia. India recorded the first human outbreaks in West Bengal in 2001 and 2007, when at least 50 deaths were recorded. The most recent outbreak, in July 2015, resulted in two deaths in the southern state of Kerala.
 
WHO believes India will be able to stop the outbreak
The World Health Organization (WHO) considers the risk of expansion in India of the Nipah virus, a highly lethal pathogen for which there is no vaccine or specific antiviral treatment, to be “low” after the confirmation of two cases in the state of West Bengal and the declaration of an epidemiological alert by Indian authorities. “India has the capacity to contain these outbreaks, as has been proven in past cases,” said a spokesperson for the UN agency in response to EFE, ensuring that the WHO has been in contact with Indian health authorities to carry out a risk assessment and provide technical support.</description><pubDate>2026-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Subsidies benefit almost 6,000 cross-border students</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/subsidios-beneficiam-quase-6-000-alunos-transfronteiricos/</link><description>Around 5,890 non-tertiary education students studying in Guangdong province will benefit from tuition and material subsidies, according to the Education and Youth Development Services Bureau. Iun Pun Iun, deputy director of the organization, stated that, in the current academic year, students at the School for Students of Macao SAR Residents in the Deep Cooperation Zone will not be covered by this support.
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
 
Under the administrative regulation that applies to subsidies for tuition fees and the purchase of school materials for students studying in Guangdong province, in the 2025/2026 school year, around 5,890 students will benefit from support, said Iun Pun Iun, deputy director of the Education and Youth Development Services Bureau (DSEDJ). According to him, the budget is around 33.8 million patacas.
Iun also clarified that students enrolled in the School for Students of Macao SAR Residents in the Deep Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin will not be covered by these subsidies, as they have already started to enjoy the benefits of the Macau education system in the current academic year.
As in the last school year, tuition fees subsidies for pre-school education remain at eight thousand patacas per student, and six thousand patacas for each student in primary, general secondary and complementary secondary education, according to a press release from the Executive Council (EC).
The organization also informed that the amounts for the subsidy for purchasing school materials continue to be 1,150 patacas per pre-school student, 1,450 per primary school student and 1,700 for students in general and complementary secondary education.
Applications must be submitted between April 20th and May 15th of this year, and DSEDJ will only pay the subsidy from October onwards, in a single installment and by bank transfer to the account of a parent, guardian or adult student.
Students in complementary secondary education will also have to attend a course organized by DSEDJ, to reinforce knowledge on the “political, economic and cultural aspects of the Macao SAR and on the “most recent development of the Cooperation Zone”. The training will last a minimum of 12 hours, with a minimum attendance rate of 80% required to be eligible for subsidies.
However, the EC recalled that tuition support cannot be combined with subsidies for free education and recurrent education. Furthermore, the subsidy for the acquisition of school materials provided for in this administrative regulation cannot be combined with the support provided for in the “Subsidy Scheme for Acquisition of School Textbooks”.
Regarding support for higher education, residents enrolled in a course whose duration is not less than two years and which is taught by accredited public or private institutions, will be able to request a subsidy of 3,300 patacas for the purchase of school materials, as in last year. According to Iun Pun Iun, the measure will benefit 26,900 students, costing 89 million patacas to the public coffers.
To this end, candidates must register online between April 1st and May 29th. The information required will be “the name of the course they are attending, the minimum number of years of normal duration of attendance set for the course and the academic year in which they first enroll in the course”.
Beneficiaries of “merit scholarships, scholarships and loan grants granted by public entities in Macau” and “students who, in Macau, attend courses coordinated by local institutions” authorized by the Government are exempt from presenting documents proving their attendance at studies.
The amount relating to this subsidy will be deposited “within 60 days from the last day of the registration period, or within 60 days from the last day of the document submission period”, indicated the EC. Both administrative regulations come into force today.</description><pubDate>2026-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>British PM in China aiming to redefine bilateral relations</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/actual/pm-britanico-na-china-objectivo-de-redefinir-relacoes-bilaterais/</link><description>Keir Starmer traveled to China last night for the first official visit by a British Prime Minister since 2018, in a bid to boost trade relations despite friction. The visit will include a meeting with President Xi Jinping, where some of these concerns – including Beijing's alleged human rights violations, the war in Ukraine and alleged espionage – may be made public. The British leader will then travel to Japan on January 31 for a brief stopover, the Tokyo Ministry of Foreign Affairs confirmed. “You can expect a range of issues to be raised [in China], including but not limited to trade and investment,” said Starmer’s spokesperson. Chinese diplomats stated yesterday that Beijing intends to take advantage of this visit to “improve mutual political trust”, deepen practical cooperation and “open a new chapter” in the “healthy and stable” development of bilateral relations. Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakun stressed that China and the United Kingdom, as permanent members of the UN Security Council, have common interests in maintaining communication and strengthening cooperation in an international scenario marked by instability. The visit highlights Starmer's ambition to reset ties with China at a time when the British economy is struggling and after relations between London and Beijing reached new levels of deterioration under the previous Conservative government. The announcement of the visit comes less than a week after the British government approved controversial plans to build a “mega embassy” in the heart of London. The 20,000m² site is set to become the UK's largest embassy complex in terms of area and one of the largest in the center of a western capital. The construction could still face legal challenges and, last week, angry residents promised to take action. Starmer himself admitted in December that while China offered significant economic opportunities to the UK, it also posed “real threats to national security”. There have also been protests from activists who fear that the extensive area in the former Royal Mint building, next to the Tower of London, could be used to spy on and harass dissidents. The British Government stated that intelligence agencies helped to develop a “series of measures” to manage possible risks, while Beijing agreed to consolidate its seven current facilities in London into one, “bringing clear security advantages”. Bilateral relations plummeted in 2020 after Beijing imposed a sweeping national security law on Hong Kong. Starmer is also expected to mention the case of Hong Kong media mogul Jimmy Lai, 78, who faces years in prison after being found guilty of collusion charges in December. This trip follows Finance Minister Rachel Reeves' visit to Beijing in 2025, as the Labor government seeks to improve trade relations and fulfill its main objective of boosting the UK's economic growth. The approach faced internal resistance, in particular from British parliamentarians who were sanctioned by China for their criticism of Chinese foreign policy. Professor Kerry Brown, director of the Lau China Institute at King’s College London, told AFP that Starmer “could well be getting something in return” for the criticism he has been receiving. “It is time for the British Government to show that the reason for a pragmatic relationship with China is that it actually brings results that create jobs and help with the fundamental priority of improving the British economy,” he said. Brown further noted that this is an “excellent opportunity to try to understand the shape” of a new global geopolitics that is emerging due to the unstable policies and behavior of US President Donald Trump. “Suddenly, we need to rethink the patterns and blocks of traditional alliances,” he noted. "In this context, China may not be an ally, but it is not an enemy either. It is a country that, in some ways, shares the same reason as the United Kingdom and other powers to be so dismayed and horrified by the behavior of the US."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2026-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao SAR bodies say “yes” to the predominance of executive power</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/orgaos-da-raem-dizem-sim-a-predominancia-poder-executivo/</link><description>The legislative and judicial bodies promised to work towards the predominance of executive power in the Macao SAR, following demands from Xia Baolong in Beijing. The five Secretaries, the Commissioners against Corruption and Audit and the director general of Customs also guaranteed to work in this direction
 
After the director of the Hong Kong and Macau Affairs Office at the State Council, Xia Baolong, asked for the joint defense of the predominance of executive power in the SAR, the SAR bodies and the various government officials assured that they will work in this direction.
The Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, assured that he will, together with the Government, “seriously implement the spirit enshrined in the important instructions of President Xi Jinping and the central authorities, further reinforce a ‘master of the house’ consciousness, effectively assume the responsibility of the main leader in the governance of Macau, persist and improve the predominance of executive power”. At the same time, he pointed out that a “coordination mechanism between legislative and judicial bodies” will be “constantly deepened”, as well as combined efforts to encourage all sectors to work “towards a better development of the Macao SAR”.
Song Man Lei, president of the Court of Final Instance (TUI), began by saying that “the predominance of executive power is a system conceived and established by the Constitution and the Basic Law for the Macao SAR, with deep political-legal and real bases, having great significance for safeguarding the constitutional order”. “The judicial bodies, as an important part of this system, must precisely master the constitutional meaning of the predominance of the executive power and, under the assumption of carrying out the trial independently and in accordance with the law, actively collaborate with the Government's governing action, thus providing a solid guarantee of the Rule of Law”, he argued.
Stressing that “the predominance of executive power is a good system proven by practice”, Song Man Lei said that “judicial bodies respect and uphold the predominance of executive power, which is actually respect for the organic combination between the full governance power of the Central Government and the high degree of autonomy of the Macao SAR”. He also considered that “the predominance of executive power constitutes a political system option tailored to the Macao SAR by the Macau Basic Law, being a Macau solution to the great initiative of ‘one country, two systems’”.
Guaranteeing that “the judicial bodies will continue, as always, to exercise independent judicial functions in accordance with the law”, he also stressed that they will promote “the deepening and broadening of cooperation with the executive branch, guiding, guaranteeing and promoting, through high quality justice, the increase in the efficiency of the predominance of the executive branch”.
In turn, prosecutor Tong Hio Fong stated that the MP will “study and assimilate, in a comprehensive and thorough way, the spirit of the speech” and “further deepen the understanding of the advantages of the structure with a predominance of executive power in order to fully understand its relevant meaning in safeguarding the principle of ‘Macau governed by its people’ with a high degree of autonomy”.
Tong Hio Fong assured that the MP “will exercise the supervisory functions that are legally assigned to him, ensuring that administrative bodies act in obedience to the law”, in addition to that, “with a view to the uncompromising defense of justice and impartiality, he will dedicate himself to executing the law and processing processes rigorously, precisely combating crimes that jeopardize national security, harm national interests and harm the stability of the Macao SAR”.
He also promised to “intensify communication with the executive and legislative bodies” and “play its role in achieving the predominance of the executive power, with the aim of making contributions at the judicial level” for the implementation of the “one country, two systems” principle.
The president of the AL stated that Xia's speech “has high relevance and guiding significance”. “All AL deputies will study carefully to understand the spirit of the speech, firmly implement and implement the principle of the predominance of the executive power, act with a sense of responsibility and a practical and efficient stance, and continually consolidate the paradigm of virtuous interaction between the executive and legislative powers”, promised André Cheong.
The former Secretary for Administration and Justice also stated that the AL “will implement the principle of the predominance of executive power with real actions” and reinforce communication and collaboration with the Government, also presenting constructive opinions in the exercise of legislative and supervisory functions.
He also said that the legislative body will “further strengthen its political awareness, firmly defend the sovereignty, security and development interests of the country”, as well as “enter community neighborhoods to advance investigations and studies” and “widely listen to the opinions of the different social sectors”. The priorities, however, will be “legislative and supervisory work related to defending the security of the State, increasing government effectiveness, promoting adequate diversification of the economy and strengthening the articulation of rules between Macau and Hengqin”.
The Commissioner against Corruption, Ao Ieong Seong, and the Commissioner for Audit, Elsie Ao Ieong U, also promised to follow the demands, as did the five Secretaries – Chan Tsz King, Wong Sio Chak, O Lam, Tai Kin Ip and Raymond Tam -, and the director-general of Customs, Adriano Marques Ho.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2026-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hospital das Ilhas will have 200 beds this year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/hospital-das-ilhas-contara-200-camas-este-ano/</link><description>By the third quarter of this year, Hospital das Ilhas will have 200 beds, a quarter of the total expected for the complex to accommodate. Currently, there are 136 hospital beds and 719 workers on duty, of which 488 are healthcare professionals, including 140 doctors
 
The Islands Health Care Complex – Macau Medical Center of the “Peking Union Medical College Hospital” promises to continue to “increase” the “service capacity”, therefore “it will also expand the inpatient wards, with the increase in the number of internal medicine and surgery beds”, indicated the director of Health Services (SSM). According to Alvis Lo, it is estimated that, by the third quarter of 2026, the total number of beds in operation in this medical institution will reach approximately 200.
Designed to accommodate more than 800 beds, Hospital das Ilhas reaches 25% of its planned budget this year. Currently, 136 hospital beds are available, and cooperation with the SSM has already been established to carry out routine surgeries, such as cataracts and prostatectomies, can be read in the response to a question from deputy Nick Lei.
At the same time, Alvis Lo noted that the coverage of imaging exams and therapeutic surgical services, including hemodialysis, radiotherapy, chemotherapy, will continue to be expanded in that hospital complex. “Following the progressive deepening of collaboration between the two parties, the Macau Union Medical Center will contribute to helping to further mitigate the pressure on public healthcare services, with the expectation that it will be able to assume around 25% of the care burden in this regard by the end of 2027”, he reiterated.
According to data cited by the leader of the SSM, since its entry into operation on an experimental basis until the end of 2025, the Macau Union Medical Center carried out, in the context of public medical services, a total of around 34 thousand specialized external consultations and around 24 thousand imaging exams. The hospital “is now in a growth phase, characterized by the continuous expansion of the scope of services and a significant increase in the volume of services”, he stressed.
Other areas in which the hospital intends to collaborate with the SSM include the development of ophthalmology, nephrology, urology, gastroenterology, imaging, oncology, nuclear medicine examinations, assisted procreation, among others. Intensive care services will also be launched, step by step, while maintaining the implementation of integrated external consultation and multidisciplinary diagnosis and treatment service models.
A database of specialists from the “Peking Union Medical College Hospital” has also been created, allowing remote medical consultations to be used “for the treatment of complex diseases and the performance of difficult surgeries”.
Today, remember, the hospital will take over the operation of the Ilhas Emergency Station, providing 24-hour imaging and laboratory analysis services.
Currently, the Macau Union Medical Center has 719 employees on duty, of which 488 (68%) are healthcare professionals, including 140 doctors. Work is also underway to recruit medical personnel.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2026-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Investigative entity suggested to support deputies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sugerida-entidade-de-investigacao-para-dar-apoio-aos-deputados/</link><description>Si Ka Lon presented “four suggestions” to improve the work carried out by the Legislative Assembly. Emphasizing the need to optimize the “professional guarantee system” for deputies, he suggested the creation of a “research institution” to provide in-depth policy analysis reports, support with data and references based on experiences from abroad, in order to reinforce professional support for the AL. Furthermore, he proposed that the Hemicycle and the Government draw up a list of key annual and interim tasks and disseminate it to the public
 
Deputy Si Ka Lon argued that, to promote good governance in the Macao SAR, it is a priority to ensure that legislation is of high quality, with legislative work closely aligned with the real needs of economic and social development, with a prospective, scientific and operational vision. When speaking at a seminar held in Beijing on the theme of “persistence and improvement of the predominance of executive power, and the promotion of good governance in the SARs”, the 1st secretary of the Legislative Assembly (AL) highlighted “four suggestions” for the work of the Hemicycle.
Firstly, Si Ka Lon highlighted the importance of optimizing the “professional guarantee system” for deputies, even suggesting the creation of a “more professionalized and physical research institution”. From his perspective, this entity could provide deputies with in-depth analysis reports on policies, support with data and references based on experiences from abroad, in order to reinforce professional support for the AL.
According to the newspaper “Ou Mun”, in addition, Si Ka Lon hopes that an expert consultation mechanism will be established that operates regularly, providing training in the areas of modern finance and scientific innovation to deputies, with a view to continuously improving the professionalism of legislators.
He also proposed that the AL and the Government negotiate to draw up a “list of key legislative and supervisory issues” that covers essential annual and interim tasks focused, for example, on the development of the “1+4” economic diversification strategy and the construction of Hengqin. At this point, he highlighted that the “list” must be publicized because this could make the work goals of the executive and legislative bodies more explicit, well planned and easier for the public to monitor.
With regard to matters of great relevance, the AL's standing committees can establish a monitoring mechanism with a limited period of time, through which they can periodically evaluate the effectiveness of the improvement measures implemented by the Government, understands Si Ka Lon, who also suggested the introduction of performance evaluation by independent entities regarding public projects of great relevance.
On the other hand, the deputy wants “early intervention” and the communication mechanism of AL committees to be improved, by making current communication practices relating to legislative planning and the drafting of law proposals even more institutionalized and standardized. In this area, he pointed out that standing committees should be encouraged to proactively present professional opinions based on research, in the early stages of legislative preparation, in order to improve the quality of legislation and make the process more fluid.
In general, Si Ka Lon considers that, in order to promote the optimization of the Government's work and increase the effectiveness of governance, the AL's supervision of the Government must be “constructive, professional and results-oriented”. The deputy hopes that the AL will not only be able to discover problems, but also present suggestions for improvement and promote the effective resolution of problems, transforming it into improving the well-being of the population.</description><pubDate>2026-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau will once again organize “China Expo Forum” in 2027</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-voltara-organizar-china-expo-forum-em-2027/</link><description>Two decades later, Macau will once again host the “China Expo Forum For International Cooperation” exhibition next year. This is a professional seminar for conventions and exhibitions at national and international level, as well as one of the most relevant annual events in the sector.
 
Macao SAR was chosen to organize the 2027 edition of the “China Expo Forum For International Cooperation” (CEFCO), a professional convention and exhibition event, considered one of the most relevant and influential annual events in the MICE sector worldwide. The Forum aims to serve as a platform for extensive exchange and cooperation for industry from Mainland China and abroad.
The decision to assign the territory the coordination of the event came during this year's CEFCO, held in Wuhan, where a delegation from the conventions and exhibitions sector of the Trade and Investment Promotion Institute (IPIM) was present, made up of 30 people linked to MICE from Macau and Hengqin.
Furthermore, at the “20th China Convention and Exhibition Industry Transaction Fair”, held last week, Macau won the “Most Influential MICE Destination” award, being honored with this distinction for the first time.
In the exchange activity “Meeting Night in Macau”, the president of IPIM, Che Weng Keong, expressed the expectation that the Macao SAR can contribute to the “process of opening up China to the outside world in the high-quality convention and exhibition sector”, building an “efficient platform for international cooperation in the new circumstances”.
The leader stressed that, “with the experience accumulated over the years of development”, the territory will add differentiated value to CEFCO 2027 in order to provide a differentiated business scenario to promote international MICE cooperation, combining the rich resources of visitor flow with the integrated environment, such as Sino-Western cultural fusion and an open business environment”.
On the other hand, the objective is for Macau to play the role of an “infallible link” between China and Portuguese-speaking countries and take advantage of the Forum's international influence to progressively expand Portuguese-speaking markets, among others.
In the statement, IPIM expresses that it will maintain close contact with the organizing entity of CEFCO and close cooperation with the local MICE sector, adopting the integrated model “exhibitions + prospecting + contact exchanges” to begin the various preparatory work, with a view to creating a “diversified experience” for participants.
The Wuhan forum brought together event organizers, senior company executives, sector elites, experts and academics from more than 20 countries and regions, enabling Macau members to understand the latest trends in sector development, expand their network in the market and explore potential cooperation opportunities.
The event allowed “not only to increase the global capacity and nuclear competitiveness of the sector, but also facilitated the promotion of the advantages of the MICE industry in Macau and Hengqin, attracting more events to the territory”, according to IPIM.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2026-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief hopes that OCS will continue to “support the Government’s work”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-espera-ocs-continuem-apoiar-trabalho-governo/</link><description>Yesterday, the Head of Government welcomed the role of the media, at a lunch with representatives of the Chinese language sector. On the occasion, Sam Hou Fai asked media professionals to support the Government in disseminating promotional information about the Macao SAR and to continue reporting “people's stories” that represent “the unique openness, tolerance and diversity of the Macao SAR”.
 
For Sam Hou Fai, the media must “reflect public opinion in a timely manner”, present “constructive suggestions” and transmit “positive ideas and a ‘good voice’”, in the role of “bridge between society and the Government”, according to the Social Communication Office. Yesterday, during a lunch offered to Chinese-language media outlets, the Chief Executive asked those present to continue “paying attention to and supporting the work of the Macao SAR Government in all areas”.
In this sense, Sam Hou Fai urged the media to continue “to fully take advantage of their professional advantages and their unique role, promoting and adequately guiding all sectors of society to collaborate with the Government”.
The progress of the “vision of ‘Macau based on the Rule of Law’, dynamic, cultural and happy” is due “precisely thanks to the unity and joint efforts of everyone”, acknowledged the Head of Government. “The achievable and noticeable results would not have been possible without the unity, support and collaboration of all Macau residents, nor the active participation and correct dissemination of the media sector”, he argued.
The Chief Executive also said he hopes that “the media will continue to discover and publicize stories of people who, in Mainland China and the Macao SAR, make tireless efforts, build enterprises and achievements and realize their dreams, allowing more readers and spectators, through objective examples, to recognize the peace, justice and kindness of China, and for more domestic and foreign residents and friends to feel the unique openness, tolerance and diversity of the Macao SAR”.
In a contribution “to the construction of a strong country and the rejuvenation of the Chinese nation”, Sam Hou Fai once again asked that the sector continue to report “the history of China and Macau well to the world”.
The highest representative of the Macao SAR promised to “guarantee the rights and interests of the media sector in accordance with the ‘Basic Law’ and the ‘Press Law’” and also assured “support for media professionals in news coverage and reporting”.
Pointing to the future, Sam Hou Fai hopes that the sector “will achieve new and better development”, so that “the Macao SAR's promotional information will be disseminated more widely and reach a wider audience”.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2026-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Rotax Max” brought together 130 pilots in Coloane</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/rotax-max-juntou-130-pilotos-em-coloane/</link><description>Macau received for the first time the Asian trophy in the “Rotax Max Challenge” category, in karting, which brought around 130 drivers from all over the world to the Coloane track. In the main class, Max Senior, the Japanese Lu You-De, who competed with an Italian license, secured the title, ahead of the Thai Toby Gale. The competition will return to Macao SAR in January 2027

VÍTOR REBELO
 
A week of racing hosted the first international karting competition of the year in Macau, with 130 drivers from various countries competing in the various categories of the “Rotax Max Challenge” Asian trophy, which was held in the territory for the first time. There were seven classes that took place at the Coloane circuit, with emphasis on Max Senior, which included riders over 15 years of age, some of whom had already participated in the final round of the IAME Asia-Pacific, held in mid-December last year.
The final day of racing was dedicated to the finals, after the training and qualifying phases, and in the category considered king, Max Senior, the triumph went to the Japanese Lu Tou-De, who raced with an Italian license, from the “Strawberry ROT Motosport” team, ahead of the Thai Toby Gale and the Danish Tobias Normann.
After 20 laps around the circuit, the Japanese driver, who had started from the first position on the grid, alongside his compatriot Sagano Taigen, demonstrated superiority, especially in the final part, when he managed to get away from his rival, crossing the finish line with more than four seconds of difference. The jump to second place was equally interesting, with Gale, who made an excellent recovery, after starting in 12th place, and Normann (seventh at the start of the race), almost always “glued together”. In the end, only 60 hundredths separated the two runners.
In this Max Senior class, 32 pilots lined up at the start, 26 finishing, representing 11 countries or regions, with emphasis on Asia (Taiwan, Hong Kong, China, Philippines, Japan, Thailand and Singapore), but also European pilots (Denmark, Italy and Germany) and Australia filled the grid.
In the remaining categories, Thai Sutumno Peerapongpan, from the “Singha Motosport Team Thailand” team, won in the next lower age group, Junior Max, with riders between 13 and 16 years old. Australian Jay Kostecki was second and Japanese Takeru Shimbashi third, with both competitors being penalized with five seconds by the race stewards.
26 pilots participated, highlighting the Thai (7) and Japanese (4) contingents, in addition to other Asian nations, such as China, Japan, South Korea, Malaysia, Kyrgyzstan and the United Arab Emirates, in what was the race with the most countries or regions on the track (13). Canada, Australia and the USA also had young people competing in this junior class.
Macau also had a driver, Yin Tsui Hau, from the “Solar Racing Team”, who saw the red flag on the fifth of the 16 laps around the circuit and therefore did not qualify.
In the younger classes, Micro Max (from 7 to 10 years old), the fastest on the track was Daniel Yoon, from South Korea, who maintained an exciting “duel” with the second placed, Louis Mikami, from Japan.
The two drivers finished practically evenly matched and only the “photo-finish” determined the winner, as the difference was just 36 thousandths of a second. The third would be Adam Dion Asp, from Denmark.
In Mini Max (from 9 to 12 years old), on a grid with 24 drivers, title went to Mair Alfie, from Great Britain, ahead of Isaac Yoon, from South Korea, and Stubbs Albi-Jay, from the United Arab Emirates. This trio ran a very balanced race and in the end the differences were only 20 and 47 hundredths of a second in relation to the champion. Japan dominated the entry list, with a dozen representatives.
Finally, the oldest riders (over 32 years of age) competed in two “Masters Max” divisions, with victories by Murai Kensuke, from Japan, and Veerus Ragnar, from Estonia. The only Macao SAR driver, Pang Cheong, from the “Solar Racing Team”, did not complete a lap.
This Asian trophy will return to the Coloane kart track in January 2027, as confirmed to the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper by the General Automobile Association of Macau-China.
The “Rotax Max” calendar, endorsed by the International Karting Commission (CIK), also includes “Challenge” trophies in Europe and the USA, in addition to promoting the season-ending “Grand Finals”, this being an invitational competition, with drivers from five continents.
In December 2025, on the Sakhir track, in Bharain, Macauley Bishop, from Great Britain, and Majus Mazinas, from Lithuania, were proclaimed champions in seniors and juniors, respectively. Close to 400 riders participated in all categories.</description><pubDate>2026-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chef Gil Fernandes brings Portuguese flavors to “Guincho a Galera”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chef-gil-fernandes-traz-sabores-lusos-ao-guincho-galera/</link><description>The “Guincho a Galera” restaurant will promote an exclusive dinner with chef Gil Fernandes, considered one of the most promising of the new generation of Portuguese cooks. Promoting Portuguese gastronomy is the objective of the event, whose menu will be designed with selected ingredients that evoke the generosity of the south coast of Portugal.

Gil Fernandes, one of the most promising chefs of the new Portuguese generation, will bring to Macau, specifically to the “Guincho a Galera” restaurant at the Hotel Lisboa, selected ingredients from Portugal to create an exclusive menu to promote Portuguese gastronomy. Dinner will take place on February 7th.
The chef has extensive experience in several of the most prestigious Michelin-starred restaurants in Europe and a distinct gastronomic identity since joining the “Fortaleza do Guincho” restaurant, located within the 17th century fortification of the Sintra-Cascais Natural Park.
“We are going to take Portugal with us to Macau – in our gastronomy, in our culture and in our philosophy”, can be read in a statement by Gil Fernandes, cited in a statement from Hotel Lisboa.
“To convey the rhythm of the Atlantic, the chef's passion, creativity and distinct culinary identity resonate throughout the exclusively designed menu, while selected ingredients from Portugal evoke the generosity of the south coast with authenticity and elegance”, highlights the note.
The dinner will also provide a tasting of the “Guincho a Galera” wine list, recognized by “Wine Spectator”, “World of Fine Wine” and “China’s Wine List of the Year”, which includes more than 17,000 premium labels and a collection of 430,000 bottles from the hotel's cellar. “The personalized wine pairings are designed to harmonize with the exclusive menu, ensuring that guests embark on an unforgettable gastronomic journey”, reinforces the Lisbon hotel.
This “inter-regional culinary journey” within the STDM group will continue from February 11th to 13th at “L’Atelier de Joël Robuchon” in Hong Kong. “By uniting the experience of world-class gastronomy on all continents, this collaboration expands the dialogue of flavors with tradition, creativity and cultural connection”, highlights the note, which praises Gil Fernandes’ talent.
The chef was honored with the prestigious “European Chef of the Year” awards at the “Aurum Awards” in 2021 and “Breakthrough Chef of the Year” at the “Mesa Marcada Awards” in 2023. Appointed chef in 2018, Gil Fernandes led Guincho with a philosophy based on sustainability, respect for ingredients and inspiration from the Atlantic Ocean. The sea, always present in Guincho's landscape and in the chef's own culinary DNA, plays a central role in defining the menu.
The price of dinner is 1,380 patacas per person, with optional wine pairing available for 1,280 patacas.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2026-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Emergency drill at the Heliport had 100 participants</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/simulacro-de-emergencia-heliporto-contou-100-participantes/</link><description>To test the response and collaboration capacity of all entities involved, an emergency exercise was carried out on Monday night at the Heliport of the Outer Port Passenger Maritime Terminal. Starting at 8pm, the exercise lasted around an hour, with the participation of approximately 100 people and seven rescue vehicles and ambulances, revealed the Civil Aviation Authority (AACM), describing that the drill “went smoothly” and “demonstrated the effectiveness of interdepartmental cooperation”. The exercise simulated a failure in the rear wing of a helicopter carrying two crew members and two passengers, which caused the loss of motive power and an emergency landing on the main platform, with some components scattered on the ground. During the exercise, after the “incident” occurred, the Heliport Flight Operations Center immediately activated contingency procedures and all entities involved, as soon as they received notification, went to the location. With the coordination and support of Customs Services, personnel and passengers were evacuated to safety. After receiving the call, the Fire Department also immediately sent personnel to the scene, having also simulated the preliminary treatment procedure and referral of the “injured” to the hospital. East Asia Airlines, as operator of the heliport, coordinated the exercise, which also involved the participation of the Public Security Police Corps, Health Services, Maritime and Water Affairs Bureau and AACM.</description><pubDate>2026-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>In Indonesia, faith and fun create controversy in the Islamic world</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/na-indonesia-fe-diversao-criam-polemica-mundo-islamico/</link><description>One song, one stage and one sensual dress were enough to spark a national debate about the limits between faith and fun.
In Banyuwangi, (East Java), a stage was set up to celebrate Isra’ Mi’raj, one of the holiest nights in Islam, which commemorates the Prophet Muhammad’s journey from Mecca to the Al-Aqsa Mosque in Jerusalem and his ascension to heaven. The place was intended for sermons and prayers.
On January 16, what followed the sermons and prayers was something completely different: a dangdut singer in a tight dress took the stage, her hips swaying to the lively rhythm of modern dance in the Osing dialect, and a man joined in to dance and tip her.
Someone filmed everything. Within hours, the video spread across social media, disturbing many people.
Isra’ Mi’raj is solemn, while dangdut performances thrive on physical proximity and interaction with the audience. For critics, the two worlds collided.
Organizers insisted there was no disrespect. Muhammad Hadiyanto, head of the local committee, said that before the music began, the religious program had ended and the clerics had left. The presentation, according to him, was only intended to entertain the members of the committee during the cleaning.
The apology did little to quell the outrage. Religious leaders considered it a moral failure.
“This incident is deeply regrettable,” said Sunandi Zubaidi, vice president of the Indonesian Ulema Council (MUI) of Banyuwangi. “The nobility of dakwah (Islamic preaching) has been tarnished by actions that do not reflect Islamic values.”
He warned that sacred events should not be mixed with acts that lead to immorality, including the exposure of the aurat (intimate parts of the body according to Islam), erotic dancing and ikhtilat (mixing between men and women). He even warned that such actions could constitute blasphemy.
Parliament echoed the concern. MP Singgih Januratmoko said the issue goes to the heart of how society protects the sanctity of religion. “The allegation that the entertainment took place after the main event does not resolve the issue in itself”, he stressed, arguing that, “from a religious point of view, the setting, symbols and context are inseparable”.
The police said that no crime was committed, but it was confirmed that the show was not included in the event license.
Organizers must understand the nature of an event and ensure presentations are aligned with its concept and audience. For religious occasions, this may mean selecting styles of “religious music,” such as percussion ensembles, modestly dressed singers or religious songs, Said noted.
"When a video goes viral, people only see what happens on stage. They don't see the preparation behind the scenes – the coordination, the briefings, the warnings. Yet the public's reaction is often: 'Why is dangdut like this?'" he added.
Dangdut, one of the most popular musical genres in Indonesia, is built on hypnotic rhythms, similar to tabla, and mixes Indian percussion, Malay melodies and Arabic phrases. It emerged in the 1930s and gained prominence in the 1950s during President Sukarno's anti-Western cultural campaign, which restricted Hollywood films but allowed Hindi cinema. In the 1960s, local singers began to appear, although the genre remained closely linked to villages and lower social classes.
In the 1970s, Indonesian Rhoma Irama, the “King of Dangdut”, electrified dangdut with guitars and rock influences, inspired by bands like Deep Purple, taking the genre beyond rural communities. He renamed his group, Soneta, as “The Voice of the Muslim”, fusing dangdut with Islamic themes, introduced the separation of genres on stage and replaced rock elements with religious-themed performances.
The first concerts were met with hostility, with stones and sandals thrown onto the stage. Initially, MUI (Municipal Indonesia University) declared singing verses from the Quran haram – prohibited by Islamic law – but later endorsed the work of the dangdut legend.
Like other Indonesian musical art forms such as jaipongan and campursari, dangdut has increasingly incorporated sexually suggestive lyrics and sensual dances, movements that test limits in the world's largest Muslim-majority nation.
"This art exists because there is an audience for it. The issue is not the taste, but the location. In a religious event, I would say that this type of performance is highly inappropriate, indecent and inappropriate" concluded ethnomusicologist Endo Suanda.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2026-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>