<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Estrutura dos serviços públicos vai sofrer transformação</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/estrutura-dos-servicos-publicos-vai-sofrer-transformacao/</link><description>The structure of public services will undergo a transformation. From the outset, maximum limits are set for the number of management positions and internal service subunits, taking into account the size of the staff and the functions of the entities. As a general rule, new public services will not be able to be created, unless “a new function arises that is difficult to pursue”. Highlight the changes that will occur at IAM, of which 150 employees will be transferred to public works
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The Public Administration reform saw new progress, with the green light given by the Executive Council (EC) to the draft administrative regulation “General regime for the organization and organic structure of public services and entities”. Considering it necessary to carry out a “global review” of the decree-law that regulates the organic structure of public services and which has been in force for more than 40 years, the Executive prepared the regulation, based on the guidelines and objectives defined by the Public Administration Reform Leadership Group, noted EC spokesperson, André Cheong.
This regulation – which “will serve as a legal basis for mandatory follow-up” – establishes the principles to be observed in future restructuring of public services and entities. Specifically, it defines a series of normative criteria regarding the creation, internal structure and allocation of service personnel, among other aspects.
From the outset, maximum limits are set for the number of management positions and internal subunits of the services, “except in cases where there are special reasons and authorization from the Chief Executive”. The limits take into account the functions of the services and the size of the staff. When the staff size is less than 200 people, there may be two management positions, two department-level subunits, and four division-level subunits.
If the size varies between 200 and 1,000 employees, there may be a maximum of three management positions, six department-level subunits and 12 division-level subunits. In a third scenario, if the staff size exceeds 1,000 people, four management positions, eight department-level subunits and 16 division-level subunits are allowed.
Regarding the internal structure, more specifically the creation of subunits at the department and division level, the regulation stipulates that it is necessary to concentrate functions and work of an identical nature in the same subunit. Department-level subunits are responsible for pursuing the political objectives and core functions of the service, and can only form division-level subunits when necessary.
Furthermore, a new service can only be created when “a new function that is difficult to pursue” arises, even through adjustment of the organic structure of existing services, thus establishing “express restrictions on the creation of new services”.
At the same time, the regulation determines that the Administration and Public Service Services (SAFP) are the coordinating service responsible for monitoring, coordinating and evaluating the work carried out, as well as supervising the implementation of the regulation. In this way, it gives the SAFP the powers to issue an opinion on the project for the creation, restructuring, merger or extinction of public services and entities, as well as visiting the location of the installations. The different services have a duty to collaborate.
According to the EC, the regulation improves the basic regulations for project teams, autonomous funds and consultative bodies, expressly defining that they do not constitute any subunit, nor do they have their own staff.
It also defines that public services and entities must review their organic diplomas in accordance with the work agenda drawn up by the SAFP and present, depending on the situation, any proposed changes. The regulation comes into force on the day following its publication.
 
150 IAM employees go to public works
Regarding restructuring, some changes have already been defined at the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM). The proposed amendment to the law on the creation of the body has yet to be submitted to the Legislative Assembly, however, the idea is that around 150 IAM employees will be transferred to transport and public works services, since their functions “overlap” those of those services.
At stake are employees in the areas of naming public spaces, assigning police numbers, maintenance and repair of roads and drainage networks. With this change, the authorities intend to clarify the division of responsibilities.
The proposed law proposes the revocation of the status of the IAM's own staff and they will be governed by the general civil service regime. With this change, more than a thousand employees will have to sign new contracts.
The EC also concluded the discussion of the administrative regulation on the organization of the Directorate of Justice Affairs Services, with which the Official Press will be merged. Once the organic structure is optimized, the six directors, nine departments and 14 divisions of the current two service directorates will be reduced. The new DSAJ will have a director and two deputy directors, with five departments and four divisions. The diploma comes into force on October 31st.
The draft administrative regulation “Organization and functioning of the Secretariat of the Executive Council” also received the green light from the EC.
 
Reduced to 25 years use of ossuary drawers and ash chambers
The current period of 50 years for the use of ossuary drawers and ash chambers will be increased to 25 years, without changing the rate, under the draft administrative regulation relating to the administration, operation and supervision of cemeteries, the discussion of which was concluded by the Executive Council (EC). On the other hand, the renewal period will be extended from the current five years to 10 years, maintaining the exemption from the renewal fee. According to the EC, the changes only apply to requests submitted after the legal diploma comes into force. Previously approved requests continue to be processed according to the regime previously in force. The regulation, which comes into force on June 1, 2026, also standardizes the deadlines for requesting exhumation and its possible postponement, improves the regime for charging charges associated with the exhumation of mortal remains, and regulates the recording of the names of the deceased, explained EC spokesperson, André Cheong.
 
New rules for selling gold
Segundo a proposta de lei sobre o “Regime de comercialização do ouro e da platina”, que será submetida pelo Conselho Executivo à Assembleia Legislativa, são criadas novas definições de platina, ouro chapeado e artigos revestidos a ouro. Além disso, o padrão do toque de ouro será elevado para não inferior a 999‰, enquanto o padrão de toque para platina será fixado em não inferior a 990‰. A proposta estipula ainda que os artigos de ouro e da platina devem ter aposta uma marca que identifique o toque, e todos os tipos de artigos de ourivesaria devem também ser marcados de acordo com os regulamentos. On the other hand, establishments must post notices about gold or platinum touch standards, issuing invoices or receipts that contain information legally required when selling these items. É também proposto o aumento do valor das multas para infracções administrativas. O Governo considerou necessário alterar a Lei da comercialização do ouro, em vigor há mais de 20 anos, uma vez que “já não consegue satisfazer as expectativas dos consumidores em relação aos tipos e à qualidade dos artigos de ourivesaria”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Venetian Arena filled with NBA return</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/arena-venetian-encheu-regresso-da-nba/</link><description>The Venetian Arena had a full house on Friday for the inaugural game of the “NBA China Games”, contested by the Brooklyn Nets and the Phoenix Suns. The league had not organized games in the country for six years. The program also included several community activities






























PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
This weekend marked the official return of the NBA to China, which had not hosted competition games since 2019. The Venetian Arena was practically sold out, on the opening night of the “NBA China Games”, which pitted the Brooklyn Nets and Phoenix Suns teams against each other, in preparation for the new season. In addition to being treated to additional playing time, the public was able to watch dance shows, a concert and mini-games among other entertainment moments.
Before the start of the match, the arrival of Shaquille O’Neal, former NBA star, was one of the highlights of the night, whose applause was only surpassed by the arrival of Chinese Yao Ming, former Houston Rockets player. Another national figure who received a big ovation was newcomer Zeng Fanbo, from the New York team. However, despite having accumulated 10 minutes of play, the young player was unable to contribute any baskets or assists.
The organization compensated for the relatively low pace of the match, expected in a pre-season game, with gifts and merchandise being distributed from the field and the roof of the venue. The game breaks were also used to pay tribute to the various NBA icons present, such as Dwayne Wade and Vince Carter, among other league legends.
On the “jumbotron”, in addition to the usual interactions with fans, “guests of honor” were also introduced, such as actor Jackie Chan, alongside former footballer David Beckham, and Jeremy Lin, who played in the NBA until 2019. Henry Lau's halftime concert was another highlight of the night.
The Nets remained ahead on the scoreboard for almost the entire game, with the Suns only managing to turn the score around in the last half. The first game ended with a draw at 121 points, in regulation time, to the delight of the spectators, who celebrated Jared Butler's two points that forced the game to take additional time. Friday's match ended with a score of 132-127 in favor of the Arizona team.
 
Basketball as a “community bridge”
Over the course of five days, Sands China and the NBA organized several initiatives that used basketball “as a bridge to extend the ‘NBA Cares’ spirit of compassion and connection with the Macau community.” Yesterday, the last day of “impact week”, Derron Williams, historic NBA figure, and Myisha Hines-Allen, WNBA (USA women's basketball league) player, participated in a five-on-five friendly with local students, as part of the “Her Time to Play” initiative.
On Saturday, NBA legend Shawn Marion also participated in a basketball fair at the Venetian's “Cotai Expo Hall”, with 120 family members from the General Union of Residents' Associations, the General Women's Association and the Macau Federation of Workers' Associations, ambassadors of “Sands Cares” and David Beckham, as Sands' global ambassador. On the same day, fan day was held and an official NBA store was opened in the Londoner.
On Friday, former NBA player Tim Hardaway Sr., Grant Chum, executive director of Sands China, volunteers, teachers from the “Her Time to Play” initiative and ambassadors from “Sands Cares” helped distribute packed lunches at the Pou Lei Center of the Fuhong Association.</description><pubDate>2025-10-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>It will reduce the time it takes to issue restoration licenses</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/diminuira-tempo-de-emissao-de-licencas-de-restauracao/</link><description>A bill will soon be submitted to the Legislative Assembly that aims to reduce the time it takes to issue licenses for restoration, as well as make this entire process more flexible and simple. According to the Executive Council, fines for administrative infractions will increase
 
Making requests, assessment and approval of licenses for food and beverage establishments more flexible, simpler and better are the objectives of the new proposed law, which has already been discussed by the Executive Council, and also aims to reduce the time for this licensing process. As explained by the spokesperson, André Cheong, the idea also involves “reducing operational costs and optimizing the sector's business environment”.
Entitled “law on restaurant and beverage activities and related establishments”, the proposal will, however, be submitted to the Legislative Assembly. According to André Cheong, the diploma was prepared after “collecting the difficulties faced by the restaurant sector in the past and extensive consultation of the optimization opinions presented”, noting that public health and safety will not be neglected.
The proposal calls for the creation of a registration regime for food and beverage establishments. According to the president of the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM), Chao Wai Ieng, it currently takes 40 working days to assess licensing. “In the future, the time could be reduced to 35 working days”, he stressed, when presenting the proposal, at a press conference.
To “optimize” the licensing procedure, it is proposed that the registration regime applies to establishments with a gross area of ​​use not exceeding 120 square meters that involve only simple renovation works with controllable risk, and that they can be opened to the public after the registration certificate is issued. “The authorities will need 10 working days to evaluate documents and the registration certificate can be issued two working days after receiving the complete documents”, clarified Chao Wai Ieng.
On the other hand, the amounts of fines applicable to administrative infractions will be increased, taking into account social developments and economic changes, explained André Cheong. The aim is to reinforce deterrent effects. For example, in the case of restaurant operations without a license, the amount of the fine will be increased from the current range of between 10 thousand and 20 thousand patacas to between 20 thousand and 150 thousand patacas.
After approval of the proposal, the Government will also reformulate the complementary legal diplomas, optimize and improve the administrative licensing procedure, as well as make the technical requirements that establishments are subject to comply with more flexible.
The Executive also intends to “ease the restrictions imposed on works carried out in protection zones and provisional protection zones”. In this sense, the proposed law also introduces changes to the Cultural Heritage Safeguarding Law. Specifically, it is expected that works to modify, conserve and repair the exterior appearance carried out in buildings “outside the published picturesque streets or on lots not immediately adjacent to classified properties or in the process of being classified do not require the prior opinion of the Cultural Institute”. According to the spokesperson for the Executive Council, this way the renovation work on commercial stores will be accelerated.
Under this proposal, “restaurants”, “bars”, “drinking establishments” and “food establishments” are integrated into a single type called “food and beverage establishments”, with IAM responsible for supervision. On the other hand, the “dance rooms” remain an autonomous type, remaining under the supervision of the Directorate of Tourism Services. The transitional provisions provide that, for licensing procedures initiated before the entry into force of the new law, “the previous legislation continues to apply, until the respective license is issued, with supervision being maintained by the originally competent entity”.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2025-10-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New phase of restoration of statues in the Ruins begins</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/arranca-nova-fase-de-restauro-das-estatuas-das-ruinas/</link><description>Between tomorrow and November 30th, the IC will carry out the 2nd phase of work on the bronze statues in the Ruins of S. Paulo, to restore the four statues located on the second level of the monument
 
The second phase of the restoration work on the bronze statues in the Ruins of S. Paulo will be carried out between tomorrow and November 30th, according to the plan published at the beginning of this year. The Cultural Institute (IC) will carry out restoration work on the four bronze statues located on the second level of the Ruins.
During this period, bamboo scaffolding will be installed on the facade of the monument. At the same time, in order to guarantee public safety and enable the execution of the work, the Ruins of Colégio de S. Paulo, including the exhibition “Visiting the Ruins of S. Paulo in Space and Time” and the Museum of Sacred Art and Crypt, will be temporarily closed to the public at a specific time. On the other hand, during the period of the works, fences will be installed in the churchyard and on the staircase in front of the facade of the Ruins to isolate the intervention area.
According to the IC, at the beginning of this year the global restoration of the seven bronze statues of the Ruins of St. Paul began, which is divided into three phases. In June, the restoration and reinforcement of the bronze statue of the Virgin Mary, located on the third level, and the stone base of the statue were completed.
Recalling that the fact that the long period of exposure to sun and rain and natural aging made it necessary to adequately maintain and restore the bronze statues and their stone bases, the IC assured that it will carry out the works in strict accordance with international requirements for the preservation and restoration of cultural heritage and monuments and based on the principles of authenticity, integrity, minimum intervention and reversibility.
In this regard, the organization also highlighted that, to this end, the Center for Preservation and Transmission of Cultural Heritage of the Macau Palace Museum, under the aegis of the IC, has carried out the respective works, with the interdisciplinary support of the Palace Museum and the University of Macau, in terms of engineering, chemistry and metal restoration.
Regarding the provisional measures, the IC announced that scaffolding will be erected and dismantled on site between the 20th and 22nd of October, the 19th and 21st of November and on the 25th of November, when the Ruins, including the area of ​​the Virtual Reality Exhibition in the Ruins, the Museum of Sacred Art and the Crypt, will be temporarily closed to the public.
From the 14th to the 19th of October, from the 23rd of October to the 18th of November, and from the 22nd to the 24th of November, fences will be installed in the churchyard and on the staircase in front of the facade, and the Ruins will be open to the public. In the final phase of the works, the facade of the Ruins will be cleaned between the 26th and 30th of November, with the monument open to the public.</description><pubDate>2025-10-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>André Couto fails again at the Macau Grand Prix</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/andre-couto-volta-falhar-grande-premio-de-macau/</link><description>For the second year in a row, local driver André Couto will not participate in the Macau Grand Prix. The financial issue is one of the obstacles, but also the new tasks of monitoring young talents and his collaboration with Lamborghini prevent him from being present in the Macao SAR race.
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
André Couto will be absent from the Macau Grand Prix (GPM), after also missing the 2024 edition, he confirmed in statements to the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper, shortly before the names of the drivers who will take their place on the grid for this year's program races are officially known. Fans of motor racing who live in the territory will therefore not be able to see André Couto on the asphalt of the Guia Circuit, which is still a major casualty for the event's support races.
Regarding the reasons for his absence, the pilot says he was unable to “take care of things” to make it happen. “Maybe there could have been an opportunity to race for Honda, especially because I did a round with them in the TCR in China, but then I also needed more money and that was complicated, so I decided not to participate again”, he says.
On the other hand, the driver told JTM that he will have to travel to Italy a week before the GPM with Lamborghini for the “World Finals” of the championship organized by the transalpine brand. “In principle, I would race to replace one of the drivers who couldn’t go, but who has now confirmed his presence”, he highlights.
Even so, Lamborghini will take the Macau racer to this competition. “I'm going to drive the car a bit in free practice and also do coaching, be there working with them”, he highlights.
Remember that Couto missed the 2024 GPM precisely because he chose to help the team, which was leading the championship, trying to win the title, at that time in the role of driver, on dates coinciding with the territory's event.
During this year, the driver only completed one of the rounds, with two races on the Zhejiang track, counting for the Chinese Touring Car Championship (CTCC), at the wheel of a Honda, in what was his return to the track, after half a year of absence.
The Portuguese has not competed at this level since November 2023, when he participated in the world finals of the Lamborghini Super Trophy, which took place in Jerez de La Frontera, Spain, after several rounds throughout the year.
Now, in 2025, beyond Zhejiang, he will no longer run again and will no longer make any more trips to the Mainland TCR.
For the current season, Couto hoped to be able to repeat his performance in the Lamborghini championship, in the GT category, but at the start of the season everything changed, as his team canceled their presence and the driver was left without a seat.
Even without serious racing, André Couto, who turns 49 next December, has maintained a strong connection to what made him known and gave him a lot of joy, motorsport.
Despite saying that he is “always available” to do races to which he is invited, he fills his time with other functions, such as “coaching” (pilot training), having the opportunity, through his long experience, to guide young people who want to make it in the sport.
The last time Couto participated in the GPM was in 2023 (after being absent for the previous three years), in the Chinese touring car race, where he finished in seventh place in the first race and retired in the second.</description><pubDate>2025-10-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>André Cheong denies pressure to vote in the legislature</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/andre-cheong-nega-pressoes-para-votar-nas-legislativas/</link><description>In line with the “recommendation” of the electoral commission, the Macao SAR Government only “appealed” to public servants to “go and vote” in the recent legislative elections, stressed the Secretary for Administration and Justice, ruling out interference in this field
 
The Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, denied that the questionnaires given to civil servants about whether they intended to vote affected the September 14 elections for the Legislative Assembly (AL). According to the Lusa agency, less than a week before the vote, public entities and services questioned workers and demanded written justifications from those who admitted that they did not plan to vote for the AL.
At a press conference on Friday, Lusa asked the Secretary for Administration and Justice and the director of Administration and Public Service Affairs, Leong Wen In, who had ordered the interrogations of the officials. André Cheong did not respond directly, but guaranteed that the Macau Government only, “as recommended by the electoral commission, called on [public service] workers to go and vote”.
The Legislative Assembly's Electoral Affairs Commission (CAEAL) “issued a recommendation according to which public servants must actively participate in the election”, said the Secretary.
André Cheong said that, according to the electoral law, voting “constitutes a right and a civic duty”, which also applies to public service workers. “We must enjoy our rights and fulfill our duties”, said the Secretary, who will leave his position on October 16, after being appointed by the leader of Macau, Sam Hou Fai, as one of the 33 AL deputies.
On September 1, Sam Hou Fai had already sent a circular asking all public servants to vote in the elections, to prove their patriotism. In the document, the Government leader recalled that the new civil service statute will require all workers to swear an oath of defense of the Basic Law and loyalty to China.
The revision of the statute, which only comes into force on November 1st, provides that public servants, including those of Portuguese nationality, may be dismissed if they carry out “acts contrary” to their oath.
Sam Hou Fai argued that voting “is, precisely, a relevant demonstration of the defense of the Basic Law and loyalty to the Macao SAR”.
Even so, on September 6, the president of CAEAL, Seng Ioi Man, guaranteed that “the question of disciplinary responsibility” would not arise for public servants who did not vote.
Asked about the interrogation of public officials and whether the circular sent by Sam Hou Fai could be seen as a threat and have had an influence on the outcome of the elections, André Cheong did not respond.
The civil service population – which, according to the latest data available, at the end of 2023, had just under 34,300 workers – will currently represent around 10% of the total voters registered in Macau.
The list with the most votes was the one led by José Pereira Coutinho, who is also the president of the Macau Public Service Workers Association (ATFPM). On the evening of September 14, after the results were announced, Coutinho praised Sam Hou Fai's circular as “an excellent, very positive measure” to “increase the number of voters”.
Almost 53.4% ​​of voters went to vote, 11 percentage points more than in 2021, but below the record of 59.9%, set in 2009, when three pro-democracy lists competed. The number of invalid or blank votes more than doubled, exceeding 13 thousand.
Days later, Coutinho defended, in an interview with Lusa, that the electoral victory of the list supported by ATFPM “has nothing to do with the Chief Executive”.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Secretaries listen to associations to prepare the next LAG</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/secretarios-ouvem-associacoes-para-preparar-proximas-lag/</link><description>Wong Sio Chak, O Lam and André Cheong listened to opinions and received suggestions from sector associations in the areas they oversee, within the scope of the Government Action Lines. Defending national security, encouraging young people and improving the quality of life of residents were some of the topics discussed at the meetings
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The Secretaries for the areas of Security, Social Affairs and Culture and Administration and Justice participated in meetings and lectures with various associations, listening to opinions and receiving suggestions, within the scope of preparing the Lines of Government Action for the next financial year.
Wong Sio Chak, responsible for the Security department, led a group of directors from public services under his supervision, and attended lectures at several local associations, including the Federation of Workers' Associations, the Macau Commercial Association and the General Union of Residents' Associations.
Among the topics discussed were complementary legislation on improving the safeguard of national security, deepening the facilitation of border crossings between Macau and Hengqin, the continuous improvement of Macau's vehicle circulation measures in Guangdong province, the prevention and combat of new types of fraud crimes, traffic management and cybersecurity.
In response, the member of the Government emphasized that “seeking to refer community problems to police work and trying to obtain community support in police work have always been the fundamental concept of government actions in the area of ​​security”.
O Lam, Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, also held meetings with the same purpose, the contents of which included optimizing the planning of the educational system, improving social security measures, the aging of the population, improving family support measures, raising the level of medical services and committing to the protection and revitalization of historical remains.
According to O Lam, his authority “will continue to collect and listen to opinions from sectors through different channels, constantly reviewing and optimizing the work of government action”. At the meeting, among others, the Education Association, the General Women's Association and the Youth Federation were present.
André Cheong, still Secretary for Administration and Justice, who will soon hand over the portfolio to Wong Sio Chak and will assume the role of appointed deputy in the Legislative Assembly, also spoke with association leaders, having highlighted that “the transfer work” to the new holder of guardianship “is progressing satisfactorily”.
In the lectures, the opinions of representatives of the associations focused on increasing recreational and leisure spaces and facilities, intensifying urban afforestation, promoting the development of electronic government, improving different legal regimes and optimizing the careers of public servants, as well as promoting integration between Macau and Hengqin.
André Cheong pointed out that “deepening the reform of public administration and increasing public management capacity and the level of governance are the main guidelines of the current Government”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Companies grow 60% at Sino-Lusophone fair</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/empresas-crescem-60-em-feira-sino-lusofona/</link><description>Reinforced by three new sectors, including agriculture, new energy and the blue economy, the second edition of the C-PLPEX event will bring together more than 480 companies from China and Portuguese-speaking countries in Macau, a number that marks a growth of 60% compared to 2023
The 2nd China-Portuguese-Speaking Countries Economic and Commercial Exhibition (C-PLPEX), which will take place between October 22nd and 25th at the Venetian's Cotai Expo, will bring together more than 480 Chinese and Portuguese-speaking exhibitors, which corresponds to an increase of 60%. The inaugural edition, held in 2023, after six editions of the Exhibition of Products and Services for Portuguese-Speaking Countries, featured 300 companies, of which 260 came from Portuguese-speaking markets.
According to the Institute for Trade and Investment Promotion (IPIM), C-PLPEX's theme this year is “creating new opportunities for cooperation” and will introduce three new sectors, including the agricultural industry chain, new energies and the blue economy. In a statement, the organization highlighted that exhibitors come from sectors such as agriculture, food and beverages, new energies, marine economy, cross-border e-commerce and professional services, with the aim of “promoting multifaceted and cross-sectoral cooperation” between Chinese and Portuguese-speaking companies.
In the case of agriculture, “innovative technologies, such as drones and the use of waste”, will be presented, along with “characteristic agricultural products and derivatives”, including coffee beans and cashews. Companies in the agricultural sector will exhibit “from innovative technologies, such as drones and the use of waste, to characteristic agricultural products and derivatives, such as coffee beans and cashews”, in addition to “other links in the industrial chain, such as storage logistics and sales by agents”.
The new energy sector will prioritize “innovative products and services, including electric motorcycles, new energy space capsules, energy storage and solar energy systems”. In turn, the blue economy area will bring together “reference companies” from China and Portuguese-speaking countries “in the areas of maritime logistics, oceanic renewable energy, marine biotechnology, aquaculture, research and development in blue technologies”.
The C-PLPEX program includes the launch of 13 new projects, the announcement of the winners of awards for wines and spirits and coffee from Portuguese-speaking countries and a networking session between agricultural entrepreneurs.
Recently, IPIM highlighted, among the list of participants in the event, the Port of Sines, Portugal's main cargo port, Prio, the third largest producer of biofuels from waste raw materials at European level, and Amazon, leader in the field of cross-border electronic commerce.
C-PLPEX will take place simultaneously with the 30th Macau International Fair (MIF) and the Macau 2025 Franchise Exhibition. This year, IPIM invited Guangzhou, the capital of Guangdong province, as a MIF partner city and will organize more than 50 economic and commercial promotion sessions, including regional cooperation forums and conferences.
According to the organization, 20 new products and technologies will be launched during MIF, including new themed pavilions dedicated to the robotics industry and one focused on Macau's healthcare brands.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hotel occupancy reached 88% in Golden Week</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ocupacao-hoteleira-atingiu-88-na-semana-dourada/</link><description>The average occupancy rate of hotels in Macau stood at around 88% during Golden Week, a period in which the average price per room fell 7.8% compared to the same period in 2024, announced the Tourism Office

Hotel establishments in Macau registered an average rate of 87.9% during the National Day holidays, that is, between the 1st and 8th of October, reported the Tourism Services Bureau (DST), citing data provided by the sector. The highest rate occurred on October 2nd, at 93.5%.
During “Golden Week”, the average price per room in the sector, including hotels, apartment hotels and low-cost accommodation, decreased by 7.8% to 1,698.8 patacas, compared to the same period last year.
According to preliminary data, Macau received 1.14 million visitors during the National Day and Mooncake Festival holidays, illustrating a daily average of 143 thousand, which represented increases of 1.9% and 2.8% compared to the same periods in 2024 and 2019, respectively. The daily average was the highest for this period since there are records.
During the period under analysis, 943 thousand visitors entered the territory from Mainland China, 128 thousand from Hong Kong, 16 thousand from Taiwan and 57 thousand international visitors. DST highlights the fact that the daily averages of visitors from Mainland China (118 thousand) and international visitors (7,200) have grown by 1.1% and 29.9%, respectively, when compared to the same period in 2024.
The largest flow occurred on October 4th (191 thousand), which became the day with the highest number of visitors since National Day holidays were recorded.
MGTO also reported that the Macau Grand Prix Museum received 8,462 visitors over the eight days of public holidays. On October 1st, the museum had free entry, registering 2,855 visits.
During the “Golden Week” period, DST carried out 165 inspections at border posts, tourist attractions, shopping places and establishments in the hotel industry, in addition to interdepartmental inspection actions with the Economic and Technological Development Services and the Customs Services, and no cases of irregularities were discovered. On the other hand, together with the Public Security Police Corps, it combatted the illegal provision of accommodation, having detected five suspected cases of illegal provision of accommodation in autonomous units.
 
Malaysia and Indonesia “felt” Macau
The Directorate of Tourism Services (DST) held simultaneously in the cities of Putrajaya (Malaysia) and Jakarta (Indonesia) a major tourism sales event “Sense Macau”, for four days, aiming at the “promotional offensive in the international markets of Southeast Asia”. Diverse content, including gastronomic tastings, Portuguese folk dances, magic and lion dancing, as well as travel packages and plane tickets with special offers to attract visitors to Macau, were highlighted in the campaigns that ended yesterday. The activities in Malaysia took place in one of the country's largest shopping centers, mostly frequented by Muslim and Chinese visitors. In Indonesia, tourism products were launched through local travel agencies, offering more options and diversified plans. Macau's six gaming operators and the Hengqin Cooperation Zone Economic Development Services Bureau set up stands during the two campaigns.</description><pubDate>2025-10-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM expands cooperation with Polytechnic of Leiria</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/upm-expande-cooperacao-politecnico-de-leiria/</link><description>The deepening of strategic cooperation in the training of Sino-Lusophone staff is the basis of a new agreement between the Macau Polytechnic University and the Leiria Polytechnic Institute. Artificial intelligence language technology and intercultural research will be strengthened, allowing students learning opportunities abroad
 
The rector of the Macau Polytechnic University (UPM) traveled to Portugal to sign an agreement that reinforces long-standing cooperation with the Polytechnic Institute of Leiria (IPLeiria), allowing for greater expansion in the future in cutting-edge areas, such as language technology with artificial intelligence and intercultural research. The objective of the partnership is, according to Marcus Im, to build a diversified system of training qualified international professionals and provide students with “more learning opportunities abroad”.
Through the first agreement, the two higher education institutions have developed strategic cooperation in the training of Sino-Lusophone talents in the areas of translation, economics and commerce.
With the strengthening of the partnership, the fields of cooperation will further expand, “developing in-depth collaborations in cutting-edge areas”, such as language technology with artificial intelligence and intercultural research, “building a diversified system of training international qualified staff and providing students with more learning opportunities abroad”, said the head of UPM.
In the dialogue with the vice-president of IPLeiria, Graça Poças Santos, an assessment was made of the results obtained so far, considered “achievements” by both sides, in the training of Sino-Lusophone cadres, having also reached “important consensuses”, according to a statement from UPM.
Marcus Im stressed that this “fruitful partnership” contributed to the training of countless qualified bilingual professionals of excellence in Chinese and Portuguese, providing “fundamental support” for the development of Macau’s role as a “Sino-Lusophone Platform”.
Graça Poças Santos highlighted, in turn, that “intercontinental academic cooperation is the fruit of international cooperation between the two institutions, which plays a significant role in deepening cultural exchange between Portugal and China”. He also noted that, through continuous reciprocal visits between teachers and students and collaboration in scientific research, “the two institutions jointly created a model for training qualified international staff with distinct characteristics, which constitutes a good example for cooperation between Portugal and Macau”.
During the visit, the Macau delegation also met with students from UPM, from the Chinese-Portuguese Translation and Interpretation and China-Lusophone Countries Commercial Relations courses, who were participating in exchange and learning programs at IPLeiria.
Looking at the history of cooperation, UPM points out that the two institutions have worked together for almost two decades, since the signing of a cooperation agreement in 2006 and the launch of a student exchange program in 2007.
“Through systematic reciprocal visits between teachers and students, the joint creation of professional courses and academic seminars, the quality of training of qualified staff was raised and innovation and integration of educational concepts were promoted”, highlighted UPM.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-10-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Strengthened partnerships with Australian universities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/reforcadas-parcerias-universidades-australianas/</link><description>The University of Macau sent a delegation, led by vice-rector Rui Martins, to several higher education institutions in Australia to strengthen collaboration in scientific research and the exchange of academic staff
 
Rui Martins, vice-rector of the University of Macau (UM) led a delegation on a visit to several universities in Australia, to discuss potential areas of cooperation, curriculum design, student exchanges and joint research projects and the latest campus developments in Hengqin.
According to UM, the group visited the University of Melbourne and the Royal Melbourne Institute of Technology (RMIT), to meet with Thas Nirmalathas, dean of the Faculty of Engineering and Information Technology at the University of Melbourne and Nick Scarborough, international director of RMIT, among others. Everyone present expressed “strong interest in collaborating with UM in electromechanical engineering and computer engineering programs, with a view to starting academic collaboration”.
The tour also included Monash, Deakin and La Trobe universities. Sunny Yang, vice-president of Monash University, and David Halliwell, deputy vice-chancellor of Deakin University, praised UM “for the latest developments and operating model of its campus in the Hengqin Cooperation Zone”. The possibility of creating platforms for the exchange of students and teachers was also discussed.
With Helen Yang, associate dean of the “Business School” at La Trobe University, Rui Martins analyzed “the partnership between the two universities over three decades”, eventually agreeing to “renew the memorandum of understanding and expand the scale of student exchange”.
Rui Martins also met with Brett Lovegrove, pro-vice-chancellor of the University of Queensland, and Cameron Newton, interim vice-chancellor and vice-president of the Queensland University of Technology, to “explore the possibility of creating joint talent development programs, summer programs and semester-long exchange programs”. UM signed a cooperation agreement with both universities to promote research collaboration and academic exchange.
At Griffith University, the two parties “expressed their commitment to deepening cooperation in cultivating high-quality talent”.
Finally, the Chinese Consulate General in Brisbane received the group led by Rui Martins, with the consul general, Ruan Zongze, promising support to UM “in strengthening its cooperation with universities in Queensland”.
Rui Martins highlighted that UM “will continue to expand its network of global partnerships, improve internationalization and foster more globally competitive talent for Macau and China”.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-10-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Patrick Dumont wants to bring more large-scale sporting events</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/patrick-dumont-quer-trazer-mais-eventos-desportivos-de-grande-escala/</link><description>The Parisian yesterday hosted the colloquium “Pivot Point: How sports ownership is reaching global communities”, in which Patrick Dumont, Joe Tsai and David Beckham participated as owners of sports clubs. The operations director of Las Vegas Sands assured that he intends to bring more events similar to the “NBA China Games” to Macau
 
“The objective is to bring more sports here and highlight [Macau’s] capabilities,” said Patrick Dumont, director of operations at Las Vegas Sands, alluding to the “NBA China Games” that took place in Macao last weekend. The North American executive, who is the son-in-law of Sheldon Adelson, the group's late founder, and is expected to take over leadership of Las Vegas Sands in March 2026, participated yesterday in the lecture “Pivot Point: How sports ownership is reaching global communities”, at the Parisian, together with Joe Tsai, president of the Alibaba group, and David Beckham, former football player. The conversation focused on the evolution of sports broadcasting and the creation of communities, with former NBA player Vince Carter as moderator.
“Macau is truly a city of entertainment and sports, and because of this format, it is easy to hold other sporting events,” noted Dumont, owner of the Dallas Mavericks. According to Joe Tsai and Patrick Dumont, the WNBA (women's professional basketball league in the USA) could be the next major sports franchise to organize an event in Macau.
“The city is immensely proud to demonstrate its capabilities as a tourist destination”, highlighted Dumont. "If you think about Macau in the last 20 years, when our company started here, there wasn't much business tourism. There was a lot of leisure tourism, but it was short. The construction of infrastructure allowed business tourism to happen."
“As someone who feels like Macau, who has been coming here for a long time, with friends and family, it really is an incredible place”, said Patrick Dumont, stressing that “there has been an evolution in the type of tourists who come to Macau”. “With the arrival of investment, better hotel rooms, better restaurants and retail, more people come for longer.”
“Another interesting thing is social media, which has accelerated the way people think about the experiences available in Macau.” "Instead of seeing a magazine or waiting for a television program about travel, it is possible to obtain information directly from people who tell us what we could experience. This is very powerful, because Macau has many good things to offer" highlighted Dumont. "What we have seen is that there are more sophisticated travelers coming to Macau. There are people who [usually] travel to Europe or go skiing to Hokkaido, who are very familiar with other options, but end up choosing Macau."
In turn, Joe Tsai lamented the fact that, “in China, sport is sport and everything else is entertainment”. “[The Chinese] only see sport in the context of competition (…) but it is an integral part of entertainment”, he elaborated. "If you watch an NBA game in the U.S., if you go to a live game or watch it on television, it's an entire entertainment experience. The fan experience is integral to everything."
“Social media is very advanced in China, but the mentality that sport is separate from entertainment needs to change.” “I think these Macau games are a perfect example,” said Tsai, owner of the Brooklyn Nets.
For Tsai, sport is also inseparable from education and he was even one of those responsible for creating the Asian Universities Basketball League, which was inaugurated this summer in Hangzhou. In the same sense, David Beckham, owner of the Inter Miami football team, also argued that investment in young people is essential. “Parents realize that education and sport go hand in hand”, he highlighted.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-10-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau's largest ever delegation received flag for the National Games</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/maior-comitiva-de-sempre-de-macau-recebeu-bandeira-para-os-jogos-nacionais/</link><description>The Macau delegation that will be present at this year's edition of the National Games, made up of almost 600 members, received the Macao SAR flag from the Chief Executive. The ceremony also served as a solemn oath for the 1,500 volunteers. Sam Hou Fai said the competition “provides a platform for the integrated development of the Greater Bay Area”. Therefore, he stressed, “we have to come together, do our best to compete at a high level and organize the competition with the highest quality”
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The Macao SAR flag that will parade at the opening ceremony of the National Games, scheduled for November 9th at the Guangzhou Olympic Stadium, is already in the possession of the three delegations from the territory that will participate in the 15th edition of the National Games, the 12th of the National Games for People with Disabilities and the 9th of the National Special Olympic Games. The session to hand over the banner to the leader of the main delegation, the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, took place at the Mong Há Sports Center and was presided over by the Chief Executive, who in his speech said that the National Games constitute a “great competition” and provide “a platform for the integrated development of the Greater Bay Area”.
After the presentation of the national anthem and the listening to the Games song “Qi Shi Ru Hong” (“Unstoppable combative spirit”), Sam Hou Fai highlighted that this event “expresses the confidence and expectations that the Central Government has for Macau”, adding that “we must come together, do our best to compete at a high level and organize the competition with the highest quality”.
The Macau leader also said he hopes that, “on this stage at the highest national level”, all athletes will take the opportunity to “show their best in full competitive form, be able to surpass themselves, and gain friendships to simultaneously promote the sporting spirit of local athletes: unity, collaboration and persistence, transmitting the unique charm of Macau to friends across the country”.
On the other hand, Sam Hou Fai emphasized that Macau will dedicate its efforts “to achieve a double gain in the performance of competitions and in the demonstration of the civilized spirit that demonstrates to the entire world the determination, integrated capacity and urban charisma of Macau to transform itself into a City of Sports”. Finally, he wished the Macau Sports Delegation “a courageous fight for first place and the glory of the Macao SAR”.
In addition to handing over the flag to the delegation that will be in Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau, the ceremony also served as a solemn oath of the approximately 3,500 volunteers who will accompany the organization from Macau. Addressing them, the Chief Executive expressed “hopes for a fruitful harvest for the service provided, which marks a precious and glorious page in your lives”, highlighting that the “sincere smile” of the volunteers constitutes the “warmest” image of these competitions and they are “the best ambassadors that Macau could hope to have in this event, an essential and indispensable force”.
Macau will send the largest sports delegation ever, with more than 400 members to participate in 23 disciplines of the 15th edition of the National Games, namely, water sports (swimming, artistic swimming, water diving), athletics, badminton, basketball (3X3 and 5X5), boxing, cycling, canoeing (smooth water), fencing, football, golf, handball, judo, shooting, table tennis, taekwondo, tennis, triathlon, volleyball (indoor and beach), Wu Shu, archery, hockey, rowing and sailing.
Likewise, the Macao SAR will also have more than 180 members to participate in seven modalities of the National Games for People with Disabilities, including athletics, badminton, bocce, wheelchair fencing, triathlon, swimming and table tennis, as well as seven other modalities in the National Special Olympic Games: athletics, badminton, basketball, bocce, football, swimming and table tennis.
The National Games will take place between the 9th and 21st of November, while the National Special Olympics Games will take place between the 8th and 15th of December.</description><pubDate>2025-10-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong exhibits 100 never-before-seen aerial photographs from the Second World War</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/hong-kong-expoe-100-fotografias-aereas-ineditas-da-segunda-guerra-mundial/</link><description>One hundred previously unseen aerial photographs of Hong Kong, taken between 1941 and 1945, are being exhibited, for the first time, to document World War II bombings, similar to what led to the recent discovery of a 454-kilogram bomb in Quarry Bay, forcing the evacuation of 6,000 people.

The images, recovered from the US National Archives, are part of an exhibition organized by the Hong Kong Space History Project. Among the photographs, a snapshot of the attack on Whampoa Dock, in Hung Hom, carried out on April 5, 1945, stands out.
Kwong Chi-man, head of the History department at Hong Kong Baptist University, told the newspaper “South China Morning Post” that “an action report clearly shows the bombing and damage from a previous attack”, referring to the largest air raid recorded in the city, on October 16, 1944, which left around 900 dead.
During the Japanese occupation (1941–1945), Hong Kong was a crucial logistical hub for Tokyo, and from 1942 the Allies launched air attacks on naval dockyards to weaken Japanese military capabilities.
“There are probably more unexploded bombs in the waters of Hung Hom, Tai Koo, Admiralty and Wan Chai,” warned Kwong, linking the recent discovery in Pedreira Bay to an American attack on April 2, 1945.
The images, captured by the Allies for pre- and post-attack reconnaissance, show the devastation caused and provide valuable information about urban development and historic buildings of the time.
According to the organizers, the exhibition fills a gap in the historical spatial record, given that the colonial government carried out aerial surveys only in 1924, 1934 and, after the war, in 1945.
Funded with HK$1.9 million through the Built Heritage Conservation Fund, the exhibition includes an interactive map and educational activities to raise awareness among the community.
With free entry, the exhibition will be on display until December 10th in three locations: Jao Tsung-I Academy (Sham Shui Po), CLP Pulse (Kowloon City) and Kwong Wah Hospital (Yau Ma Tei), each displaying images from its district.
Specifically, the discovery of a 1.5 meter long bomb on September 19 at a construction site in Quarry Bay, a busy residential and commercial district in Hong Kong, led to a mass evacuation of the population. The operation included the temporary closure of subway stations and nearby roads due to the risk of instability caused by the explosive, a reminder of the legacy of war that still lingers beneath the urban surface of the city that is now a Special Administrative Region of China.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-10-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>