<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Students will “socialize more” without mobile phones at EPM</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/alunos-vao-socializar-mais-sem-telemoveis-na-epm/</link><description>Students of all levels of the Portuguese School of Macao will, from today, not to be able to use mobile phones inside the facilities. The measure arises following guidelines imposed by education and youth development services. Parents heard by the Jornal Tribuna de Macau are clearly accordingly and believe that there will be more interaction among students. A teacher says it is “a great, well-implemented measure”, because at this moment “children are alone with a mobile phone”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
A partir desta manhã, quando as portas da Escola Portuguesa de Macau (EPM) abrirem para mais um ano lectivo, os alunos serão obrigados a deixar os telemóveis em cacifos instalados à entrada do estabelecimento de ensino. Pais e encarregados de educação tomaram conhecimento das medidas impostas sobre o uso de telemóveis no interior das instalações, que é agora proibido.
Através da sua página oficial na internet, a direcção da escola divulgou um comunicado em que explica as novas regras. Specifically, students will have to turn off their mobile phones and place them in the cliffs that will be on site for this purpose. Os smartphones não poderão ser utilizados nos intervalos e apenas podem ser retirados dos cacifos na pausa do almoço e quando os estudantes regressarem a casa.
However, there will be exceptions. According to the statement, parents and in charge of education should communicate to class directors in writing if students need to use their mobile phones in exceptional situations. In addition, EPM says it will provide a landline at the school entrance with the porter to be used in emergency situations.
However, students will be able to access mobile phones for learning purposes, “but only under the guidance of teachers,” says EPM.
The notice signed by the director, Acácio de Brito, explains that these are guidelines of the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ), which aims to reduce the dependence of these devices by students and follow the world's trend.
For the Parents Association of the Portuguese School of Macao (APEP), this is a “widespread measure of the DSEDJ”. According to the president of APEP, "it will be the DSEDJ that, in principle, will provide the cabinets or the cliffs to put at the entrance of the school to store the mobile phones."
Like the little, primary, they do not have these devices, they should be about 600 mobile phones to control, which, in the opinion of Filipe Figueiredo, "it will be easy to do, because if they do not fulfill they are violating a guidance of the school."
The leader points out that the issue was not placed within classes, but fundamentally at intervals. "Many kids were sitting by phone in hand, with no socialization and interaction," he stresses, adding that "in this first phase there is some change in a habit, which will not be easy, but then the role of continuous assistants will be important to help control and adapt."
The EPM even sent questionnaires to parents about whether or not they agree with the measure and only about 20% whether they opposed the ban. The guardians that JTM has now contacted (who preferred not to disclose their identity) recognize that the measure is "very good", because "that's what is happening in Portugal and around the world."
A father said his daughter "only had a mobile phone around 12 years old," stating that "children use and abuse their mobile phone and that only hurts the brain, they are apathetic." One mother recognizes that she is currently "an exaggeration", having reached a "point without control."
A teacher for several years to teach in the EPM also left his testimony. "I think from now on the relationship between students will be frankly better, they will live more at break time, because we often see five or six kids without a device around a colleague to play on the mobile phone, which is not healthy." “Our children are alone with a mobile phone” and now they have the opportunity to “socialize more,” he said.
The teacher considers that it is "a great, well -implemented measure" to "develop the interpersonal relationship between them more, to talk more, because I believe they will find a way to occupy those 20 minutes." It recognizes, however, that there will be some initial pressure: "Let's go a week, perhaps, when they won't know what to do, they will walk like that, not knowing how to use their hands, but it will be a matter of habit."
Regarding the difficulty of contacting parents, he says that "this is a myth," stressing that "those who have never used mobile phones have always been able to contact their parents through the secretary, or through any school teacher."
The EPM starts today for another school year, on a day that is essentially intended for students reception. Wednesday morning, the school receives the visit of the Prime Minister of Portugal, Luís Montenegro.</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>FINAM receives “Portuguese soul” for the third consecutive year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/fimm-recebe-alma-portuguesa-pelo-terceiro-ano-consecutivo/</link><description>For the third following edition, Fado returns to the Macao International Music Festival, with the voice of Cuca Roseta, who will act with the Chinese orchestra. Between October and November, international renowned musicians and young places will act at the event, which also includes workshops, lectures, behind -the -scenes visits, theater and other initiatives

























Pedro Milheirão
Cuca Roseta will act at the 37th International Music Festival of Macau (FINAM), accompanied by the Chinese Orchestra of Macao, in an interpretation “of the Portuguese Soul” scheduled for October 11 at the Cultural Center, according to the Cultural Institute (IC). It is the third consecutive time that a fadista brings the “sound of Portugal” to the end, after Gisela João and Mariza had acted in 2023 in 2024, respectively. The festival runs from October 3 to November 8 and includes 12 “spectacular” programs and 14 activities. The budget for this edition reaches 25.5 million patacas, about 23% less than last year.
With the theme “Vocal Waves”, the event organized by the IC will bring renowned musicians and rising talents, in a “deep resonance” between the East and the West. The trio consisting of Wu Wei, a famous “Sheng” player, Martin Stegner, a violence of the Berlin and Janne Saksala Philharmonic, willingly, will feature the show “The Sheng in his best”.
In turn, Svetlana Zakharova, an illustrious dancer, and her husband Vadim Repin, violinist, will lead the show “Duets on the fingertips”, with the Macao orchestra and several main dancers from Ballet Bolshoi. Violinist Daniel Hope and the Swiss Gstaad Festival Orchestra will present “The Four Stations” by Antonio Vivaldi and a minimalist reinterpretation of Max Richter's same work.
Baritone Thomas Hampson will interpret “The Magic Horn of the Boy” and “Youth Songs”, in an evocation of Gustav Mahler's “Complex Psychological Landscapes”, demonstrating the composer's “unlimited fascination”. In addition, the “English Concert” and the Sonia Chamber Choir will bring themes by George Frideric Handel, Giovanni Pierluigi of the lecture, Johann Sebastian Bach and Arvo Pärt.
Six young local talents, namely Wang Iat Ham Sabrina, Cheong Tin Ut, Wong Hei U, Lam Cheok Seng, Wu Freya Ka Yu and U Weng Kei, will have the opportunity to act with professional Macao orchestra musicians and Chinese orchestra of Macao.
This year's edition will also have two commemorative concerts, from the 80th anniversary of the victory in the War of Resistance of the Chinese people against the Japanese aggression and the 120th anniversary of the birth of Xian Xinghai, a musician born in Macao. The Chinese orchestra of Macau will present “legacies running in the river”, while the Macao orchestra of Macau and Cheong Hoi Leong, a young pianist from Macao, will present “The Yellow River”.
SJM and FINAM will co-organize the show “Carmen-Opera in four acts of Georges Bizet” to mark the 150th anniversary of the death of the French musician. Maestro Eivind Gullberg Jensen will lead Zurich's opera and the “Opera Comic de Paris”, in collaboration with the Macao Orchestra, the China National Symphony Orchestra Choir and the Macao Youth Choir. This classical opera concert will explore the “timeless theme of humanity through moving and moving songs”.
In another performance, organized by Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, Mikhail Pletnev and the Rachmaninoff International Orchestra will guide the audience on a “exciting and moving trip for Russian music”. The pianist, who "dominates the essence of the Russian school", and the orchestra, known for his "deep" interpretations, will present the four "Rachmaninoff piano concerts".
Within the activities program, interested parties will be able to know the Bizet Genius, in the lecture “Conversation: Unraveling Carmen”, as well as participating in a visit behind the scenes of the respective spectacle. In the improvisation workshop, composer Wu Wei will share a mixture of “traditional instruments and innovative performance techniques”, while the Hong Kong group “Singers Yat Po” will lead the “Workshop to Cappella”.
In addition, the same group will hold two demonstrations of “This Victoria has no secrets - The Theater A Cappella”, in the side space of Jardim da Cidade das Flores and Urban Park of Areia Preta.
Inserted in the program “Music on Screen: Cinemateca Passion”, several film projections will offer the audience “a deeper view and a close meeting with the multiple dimensions of music”.
The “Enjoy Macao” will put the tickets on sale from September 13, with various discounts, and registration for activities will be open from the 12th.</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Montenegro's visit shows appreciation of the Portuguese presence</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/visita-de-montenegro-mostra-valorizacao-da-presenca-lusa/</link><description>EPA12351598 Portuguese Prime Minister Luis Montenegro Talks to the Press to the Council of Minister Meeting Held at the Prime Minister's Official Residence in S. Bento Palace, Lisbon, Portugal, 04 SEPTEMBER 2025. AT LAST 17 PEOPLE DIED IN THE DERAILMENT OF THE GLORIA LIFT ON 03 SEPTEMBER, and 22 Others Were Injured, Emergency Services Reported.  EPA/TIAGO PETINGA



Macau will be a point of passage to the Portuguese Prime Minister, as part of an official visit to China, where he will meet with Chinese President Xi Jipping and his counterpart, Li Qiang. In the territory, Luís Montenegro will, among other points, meet the Chief Executive and visit the Portuguese school, as I had already reported by this newspaper. The visit to the MSAR is a sign given to China that the country continues to value the Portuguese presence in the region, said source of the Portuguese ruler's office
 
The short passage of the Portuguese Prime Minister by Macao is framed as a sign to China that the country continues to value the Portuguese presence in the region, especially in the dimensions of language and culture, and that "are the singularities" of the Misrem that make it "a success case," Luís Montenegro's office from Lusa told Lusa.
The first point on Montenegro's agenda in the territory is a meeting with the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, on Wednesday morning. There is a visit to the Portuguese School of Macao and a reception to the Portuguese community, with a walk through the streets of the region where it will visit the ruins of São Paulo and Senate Largo.
The coming to MSar comes in the context of an official visit to China, as this newspaper had already reported, at the invitation of the Prime Minister of the Council, I read Qiang.
The same source stressed Lusa that the visit to China is part of the “diplomatic tradition” of Portugal, as all heads of state and several prime ministers visited the country.
The delegation, on the government side, is the Minister of State and Foreign Affairs, Paulo Rangel, and the Minister of Economics and Territorial Cohesion, Manuel Castro Almeida, as well as the president of AICEP, Madalena Oliveira e Silva.
According to the provisional program, Luís Montenegro will land in Beijing this afternoon, accompanied by his wife, and will be received with a ceremony that includes a guard of honor. For today, only a walk is expected to be a section of the Great Wall of China.
The official agenda starts tomorrow, with a crown of flower deposition ceremony in the monument to the heroes of the people, in Tiananmen Square, then followed the prime minister to the People's Palace.
In addition to the meeting with the President of the Popular Republic of China, Xi Jinping-the most significant politically because the Chinese head of state receives a few foreign prime ministers-Montenegro will first meet with the president of the China National Assembly, Zhao Leji.
He will then visit the forbidden city, before a working meeting with the Chinese Prime Minister, Li Qiang, where a bilateral legal instrument signing ceremony is planned.
In this part of the visit, we highlight the “at the highest level” meetings with Xi Jinping, with whom it is anticipated that Montenegro addresses “the international context”, and with Li Qiang, in a meeting where the war in Ukraine should be on the table.
In economic terms, the purpose of the visit to China is to improve trade balance between the two countries, "strongly unbalanced" in favor of Beijing, and some memorandum of understanding in the agrifooding area should be signed. Portugal will transmit to China that "believes in a rules -based commercial system," the same source said.
 
More investment in Japan
The five-day trip, until Friday, also includes a passage through Japan. It is there that Montenegro follows after the coming to the mashes. In Tokyo, he will meet with his counterpart, Shigeru Ishiba, with a joint press conference at the end.
Then, the head of the Portuguese government will go to Keidanren (Japanese Business Federation), "where they will have meetings with high representatives of about one dozen Japanese multinational companies."
Montenegro will also visit the place where the Portuguese team for the Athletics World Cup and, in the late afternoon, will chair the signing of a memorandum of understanding between AICEP and its Japanese equivalent, Jetro.
On the last day, he will travel by train to Nagoia, then departed to the last point of the program, the visit to Expo Osaka. Prior to the visit to the Portugal and Japan pavilions, a lunch for all the Portuguese delegation prepared by four hands is planned by the heads of Kitchen Pedro Lemos and Yoshida San.
Expo Osaka ends on October 13 and Portugal is one of 161 countries present. Portuguese participation has as its theme “Ocean: Blue Dialogue”, with the involvement of more than 150 companies, associations, municipalities and national artists.
In Japan, the goal is first to increase the country's investment in Portugal and try to diversify it beyond the auto industry. On the other hand, Portugal wants to “raise the degree of the political and diplomatic relationship with Japan” for a strategy partnership, which will imply more mechanisms for bilateral relations and greater cultural exchange.
In São Bento, it is noteworthy that "there is a great coincidence of the positions of Japan and the European Union in relation to the Ukraine War and the Middle East."
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Public officials without punishment in case of abstention in the elections</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/funcionarios-publicos-sem-punicao-em-caso-de-abstencao-nas-eleicoes/</link><description>People who work in the civil service who cannot vote "will not face any disciplinary measures." The words are from the chairman of the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly, following the sending of the Chief Executive, a letter to civil servants to appeal to the vote
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Public officials, although, by law, the right and duty to vote as voters, “they will not face any disciplinary responsibilities” if they abstain in the elections on the 14th, according to statements by the President of the Legislative Assembly Electoral Affairs Committee (Caeal).
Seng Ioi Man reiterated, however, the appeal to all voters, including civil servants, to exercise their right and civic duty, stating that the government has instructed services to perform the necessary procedures to facilitate the vote of employees working.
The words of Caeal's guardian arose in response to questions about the letter sent by the Chief Executive to civil servants, in which Sam Hou Fai appeals to the vote “actively”, saying that it is a way of demonstrating fidelity to the masters.
According to the latest available data, at the end of 2023, Macau had just under 34,300 civil service workers (38,000 in early 2020), which represents about 10% of the total number of census voters.
"The universe of eligible voters is about 320 thousand, so our recipients are all eligible voters, we have not made a statistics, a certain profession, their rate, etc., but we appeal to all voters to vote on election day," said Seng Ioi Man, quoted by Lusa.
Seng Ioi Man spoke on the sidelines of a survey of the replica of the Voting Assembly in the TAP Seac Multiportive Pavilion on the first day of activity, with a view to verifying the facilities and operation.
As he explained, through the improvement of replicas, the body expects to “increase the attention of all social sectors of Macau to the elections of the Legislative Assembly (AL), to appeal to voters to actively vote and deepen civic education with young people and students”.
The two replicas, elaborated according to the actual assemblies, are in the TAP Seac multipurpose pavilion and the Macao Forum, being open to the public for seven days, including weekends. Seng Ioi Man stressed that the increase in number and opening days aims to attract and facilitate resident visits.
After the CAEAL verification, it was confirmed that the location, the designed guiding routes and other provisions "meet the expected requirements, thus providing better experience for voters to vote, and also accelerate the voting process."
The number one of Caeal also pointed out that the experiences on voting assembly replicas "can help voters master the correct method of marking the voting report and vote effectively on election day." The two simulations will become voting assemblies, with some adjustments in the facilities.
Seng Ioi Man recalled that the election campaign period, which began on August 30, entered its eighth day, and has "elapsed well, in an orderly manner and all lists disclosed their political programs according to the law."
He appealed to candidates to take advantage of time and to inform “efficiently voters” so that they decide their choices “according to their ideas and exercise their voting rights”.
It also took advantage of the occasion to mention that the Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) organized more than 2,600 higher education, secondary and young students to the replicas of the voting Assembly, giving “dynamic civic education classes, to greater awareness of the law, duty and civic responsibility”. At the same time, DSEDJ encouraged qualified teachers and young people to go to the polls.</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Authorities test circulation on the Macau bridge with signal 8</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/autoridades-testam-circulacao-na-ponte-macau-sinal-8/</link><description>The circulation of cars on the Macau Bridge will be tested, with vehicles designated for this purpose, when the next 8 8 sign 8 of Tropical Storm, the authorities announced. Last night, meteorological and geophysical services issued signal 8 due to the passage of the Tapah tropical storm. For today, floods are foreseen in the interior port, from 0.5 meters to 1.0 meters, due to the astronomical tide and the impact of “Storm Surge”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Authorities will take advantage of Tropical Storm signal 8 to start an essay on vehicle circulation on the Macao Bridge, indicated the directions of public works services (DSOP), services to traffic affairs (DSAT) and Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG). Sign 8 was emitted over the past night due to the approximation of the Tapah tropical storm.
"In order to master the concrete situation of circulation on the Macau bridge under adverse weather conditions and further improve the disposition of circulation, it is planned to prepare vehicles designated for the conduct of a circulation test during the period of the next typhoon signal 8," said the three organisms in a statement issued on Saturday. The objective is to “ensure the safety of vehicle driving by citizens under adverse weather conditions”.
However, the analysis of the data on the wind speed collected on the Macao bridge board has already been completed when the “Wipha” typhoon passage. According to the results of the analysis, “the installation and effect of counter-time barriers on the Macau Bridge respond to the conception requirements, and the basic conditions of conditioned circulation under the specific adverse weather conditions”.
According to wind speed monitoring data on the board, "the wind force is in the acceptable area." However, taking into account the principles of prudence and security, “it is still necessary to perform the vehicle circulation test on site, during the passage of signal 8, to master its concrete situation, in order to ensure the safety of vehicle driving by citizens,” the services point out.
In this sense, the authorities state that, when issuing signal 8, the government will prepare vehicles designated for the conduct of the circulation test, hoping that, “through the respective data and the result of the test on site, an evaluation of the various provisions, namely the type of vehicles that may circulate on the Macau Bridge, the circulation rules and the restrictions, during the period of the Typhoon signal 8”.
Prior to the completion of the test and evaluation, the Macao Bridge will continue to maintain the current provisions, ie it will be closed simultaneously with the remaining maritime bridges, when signal 8 or higher. "The Government of Masters appeals to citizens so that during the passage of Typhoon, as far as possible, be in a safe place, reducing the travels and closely following the official information to be disclosed," the organisms asked.
"If the data of this test correspond to safety conditions, the Macau bridge will be opened during the passage of the signal 8," they conclude.
 
“Tapah” can go 150 km from Macau
Yesterday, the SMG predicted that “Tapah”, located in the northern part of the Southern Sea of ​​China, would move from north to northwest, towards the west coast of Guangdong and gradually intensify.
Although the circulation of “Tapah” was relatively small, according to the trajectory expected yesterday, the tropical storm would pass within 150 km southwest of Macau today, early in the day, and the possibility of intensification at the height of its coastal proximity cannot be excluded. Hence the probability of significance of the signal at night was "relatively high".
It was expected that today could occur floods in the inner port, with height between 0.5 and 1.0 meters, due to the astronomical tide in the coming days and the impact of “Storm Surge”.
However, DSOP has attached contingency measures against Typhoon, the Cultural Institute appealed to the head of heritage buildings to take adequate prevention measures and the direction of maritime and water services services appealed to the maritime sector to take precautions against the tropical storm.
Also the Institute of Social Action has asked social equipment and the population to adopt preventive measures against Typhoon and possible floods, while tourism services warned visitors to be aware of the information.
In turn, the Consumer Council (CC) has asked commercial establishments to present the prices of goods and services “clearly and accurately” and not to increase prices under the pretext of the Typhoon's passage. The CC has already ensured that the inspection mechanism has been activated.
Sign 1 of tropical storm was issued at 00h30 on Saturday, and signal 3 was lifted at 08h00 yesterday, and was then replaced by signal 8 to 21h00.</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Solidarity Mand with Tragedy Victims in Lisbon</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-solidaria-vitimas-de-tragedia-em-lisboa/</link><description>Techical Experts Make an Assessment of the Accident of the Gloria Lift in Lisbon, the popular Transportation Used by Tourists, That Derailed Yesterday in Lisbon, Portugal, 4th September 2025. The Accident Caused the Death to 17 People and Also Left 22 People Injred. Tiago Petinga/Lusa



The head of the Executive of the MSAR sent a letter to the President of the Republic, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, to manifest in regret and solidarity with victims of the accident with the elevator of Gloria.
“I want, (..), at this time, address the deepest feelings to the victims and their families and express our solidarity to all those involved in this tragedy” that occurred in Lisbon, wrote Sam Hou Fai, in the missive disclosed by the Communication Office.
Sam Hou Fai also sent the “most felt condolences to Portugal and the city of Lisbon for the tragic accident (…) that caused the irreparable loss of human lives”.
The leader of the MSA spoke of a "moment of pain, dismay and mourning", but has shown confidence in how "the Portuguese people will be able to face this particularly hard moment and overcome this dramatic situation."
Wednesday's accident caused 16 dead and injuries to 22 people, nine of whom are still hospitalized in hospitals in Lisbon, and five are in intensive care and one in the emergency observation service. The Judicial Police (PJ) has announced that the nationalities of the 16 deadly victims are confirmed: five Portuguese, two South Koreans, one Swiss, three British, two Canadians, one Ukrainian, one American and a Frenchman.
On Thursday night, the Macao Tourism Services Directorate (STD) stressed that it did not receive any request for information or assistance related to the accident from residents of the territory. Still, STD has ensured that it will “closely follow the evolution” of the situation and remain “in narrow contact” with Chinese diplomacy and Macao Economic and Commercial Delegation in Lisbon.
 
Santa Casa de Macau expresses “deep regret”
The Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macao also expressed "its deepest regret for the tragic accident in Lisbon." “At this time of mourning and dismaying, we present the most felt condolences to the victims of the victims - among whom there are collaborators of our counterpart to the Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Lisboa - and we formulated rapidly recovery votes to all injured,” says a note from the provider, António José de Freitas, sent to the president of the Portuguese Mercy and the International Confederation of the International Confederation. Mercies.
“As an institution of Portuguese matrix, the Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macau expresses its total solidarity with Portugal and all those involved in this tragedy,” he adds.</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Social Store distributes kittens with support from the Henry Fok Foundation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/loja-social-distribui-cabazes-apoio-da-fundacao-henry-fok/</link><description>The Henry Fok Foundation donated 300,000 Patacas to the Santa Casa da Misericórdia social store to support this month's expenses with the distribution of posters. The check was delivered by the Foundation Director-General, SI Hou, to the provider, António José de Freitas. In total, 372 families who have few resources received the baskets of primary needs, the Santa Casa said.
If so, he stated that “it is an honor” to be able to support the social store again, within its abilities, and showed great identification with the program's philosophy, which regularly distributes the beneficiary families. In concrete, 150 families have been referred by the General Union of Residents Associations (UGAMM) and the Federation of Workers' Associations (Faom), 47 families supported by Santa Casa and 25 families referred by the Association of Family members in charge of the disabled Mental of Macao.
"Since its foundation 23 years ago, the Foundation has been faithful to its initial purpose and will continue to align with the policies of the Government of MSA, promoting the collaborative influence of the cities of the Great Bay area and facilitating a better integration of Macao in national development," Si Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou Hous.
António José de Freitas, in turn, said that the social store has insisted on supporting families of few resources, and expressed gratitude for the “generous sponsorship” of the Henry Fok Foundation. "Over the years, the foundation has grown together with the MSAR, striving tirelessly in promoting the long-term development of the country and Macao, always maintaining the spirit of Mr. Henry Fok of Love to the Fatherland and the homeland, concern for Macao, and retribution to society," he said.
The provider also said the Foundation will continue to support the social store in the future, "so that more families of few resources can benefit and relieve their financial pressures."
At the check ceremony were also the president of the UGAMM Board, Chan Ka Leong, and Faom's vice president and secretary general, Leong Wai Fong. The distribution of the kitchen was made with the support of about 20 students from the Pui Ching Secondary School. The provider thanked Rector's administrative and assistant director Wong Kin for helping to organize students, who received certificates to participate in the initiative.</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Driving force” in the great bay “has been strengthened”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/forca-motriz-na-grande-baia-tem-sido-fortalecida/</link><description>A mashed delegation, led by Sam Hou Fai, was in Beijing, for meetings in the development of Macao. For three days, topics such as the technological industry, Sino-Misophone trade relations, the great bay, Macao's position on the national level and a better interconnection among the different economic sectors were discussed.
 
Sam Hou Fai led a delegation in Beijing in a series of meetings with government officials last week. For three days, the chief executive exchanged opinions on the technological development of MSAR, the role of Macao as a sino-illly platform, the deepened cooperation zone in hengqin, the development of the great bay and economic integration of the sabem with the interior of China, as well as a greater connection between different activity sectors, according to the Social Communication Office.
On Saturday, the MSAR leader visited the Zhongguancun Informatics Industrial Park, with the purpose of “getting to know the development of the new generation computer technology industry”. In the “Salon of Research, Study and Production”, the delegation attended presentations on the history of construction, the advantages and future plans of the park. The group also visited three high -tech companies, focused on computer development, technical services and manufacture of supercomputers and servers.
Sam Hou Fai assured that “Macau is determined to intensify efforts to develop the high -tech industry”, appealing to “greater coordination and preparation” in the area of ​​science and technology, human resources and interconnection between sectors. In this sense, the head of the Government of the MSAR expects that Beijing and Macau can “deepen innovative scientific and technological cooperation” in the “construction of digital cities”.
The day before, the delegation met with Zheng Shanjie, chairman of the National Commission for Development and Reform. The Chief Executive highlighted the fact that it is the fourth anniversary of the publication of the “General Plan for the Construction of the Deepened Cooperation Zone in Guangdong and Macao Hengqin”.
At the time, Sam Hou Fai stated that "the driving force for the development of the Great Bay has been strengthened," hoping that the commission will continue to provide "great support" in the region's rise to "a new stage". In this context, the MSAR is “neatly” advanced by the implementation of four major projects, namely the International Higher Education City in Hengqin, the Macao International Tourist and Cultural Zone, the Areo Complex in the Western Basin of Rio das Pérolas and the Macao Science and Technology Development Park of Research and Development.
On the same day, Sam Hou Fai and Wang Wenta, Minister of Commerce, discussed the “Narrowing Agreement of Economic and Commercial Relations between the interior of China and Macao”, as well as the role of mashes as a sino-illusophone platform. Sam stressed that Macau has expanded trade relations with Portuguese -speaking countries (PLP), in addition to those of Spanish and others in Southeast Asia. In addition, he noted that 'Big Health', traditional Chinese medicine, the sector of conventions and exhibitions, and the sport have achieved "significant effects."
At a meeting with Zhang Yuzhuo, chairman of the State Council's Supervision and Administration Commission, Sam Hou Fai reiterated that Macau can play the role of “accurate interlocutor”, considering “the increase in the weight of state -owned companies and central companies”.
During the morning of Friday, Sam Hou Fai and the Minister of Culture and Tourism, Sun Yeli, exchanged opinions on the “diffusion of the excellence of Chinese culture” and “the development of high quality cultural and tourist industries”. On Thursday, at a meeting with Sun Meijun, Minister of the General Administration of Customs, the Chief Executive, stressed that this is a “crucial year to achieve the second phase” objectives of the in-depth cooperation zone.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Vast space” to cooperate with Hubei</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/vasto-espaco-para-cooperar-hubei/</link><description>It is today the last day of the “Macao Week in Wuhan”, and it is possible to enjoy the Mapping video projections and the light show on the Yangtze River. The director of tourism services, Helena de Senna Fernandes, says that the tourist relations Macau-Hubei “are very narrow”, but there is still a “vast space for cooperation”
 
The “Macao Week in Wuhan-Hubei”, which started on Friday and ends today, took to China “Tourism +” to consolidate the market and look for new sources of visitors, noticed the direction of Tourism Services (STD). Despite this goal, the director of the body and representative of the secretary for the economy and finance, Helena de Senna Fernandes, said during her speech that "tourist relations between Hubei and Macau are very narrow."
Thanks to their “their strategic functions, location and institutional advantages, they provide a wide space for the deepening of cooperation between the two territories,” added Senna Fernandes at the time. In this sense, he said he hoped in the future “Macao and Hubei could explore more areas and deepen cooperation, promote the complementarity of advantages and boost high quality economic development,” as you can read in a statement.
Street promotion has 46 stands in different thematic zones. For five days and to this day, from 16h00 to 23h00, characteristic elements of tourism, commerce, culture, culture and creativity, sport and entertainment will be displayed.
Macao tour operators offer tourist discounts of the total value of more than 26 million Renminbis, including airplane tickets, hotel accommodation, restoration, among others.
Through this exhibition, the Government of MSAR “seeks to attract local residents to visit and consume in Macao, based on the consolidation of the interior market of China, to continue to expand sources of visitors,” says STD.
On the days of the promotion, from 20h00 to 22h30, and today the last one, in total, six three -dimensional sessions of Mapping Video per night, each lasting five minutes. The team presents the projection in the structure of the China Industrial and Commercial Bank building, at “Wuhan Customs House Square”.
Also to this day, between 8 pm and 10 pm, the “Yangtze River Light Show”, Wuhan's most emblematic, will feature the “Macao Week” Thematic Light show on both rivers (Yangtze and Hanjiang).</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hengqin welcomes more than 28,000 mashed residents</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/hengqin-acolhe-mais-de-28-mil-residentes-da-raem/</link><description>More than 28,000 Macau residents lived and worked in Hengqin at the end of the first half of this year, the direction of administrative affairs of the in -depth cooperation zone revealed. In annual terms, hengqin inhabitants and workers in hengqin grew more than 30% and 14%, respectively. On the occasion of the 4th anniversary of the cooperation zone, the Hengqin authorities also indicated that, at the end of July this year, Hengqin had 7,303 Macao capital companies, reflecting a 57.5% increase since the creation of this area. In addition, 306 items have already been defined in terms of the convergence of rules between Hengqin and Macao and reform and innovation. On the other hand, the same organism has already started having started a preliminary study on the new border access plan Hengqin-Macau, and it will be possible to enable Guangdong to Macao's single enrollment vehicles with authorization for circulation in the cooperation zone. In addition, it has ensured that the cooperation zone will launch policies and exclusive measures for the creation of an investment fund dedicated to the development of Sino-Synopane and Sino-Hispane economic and commercial industries, in order to provide “One Stop” services diversified to companies. On the other hand, according to the gongbei customs, in the last four years, the Hengqin post has accounted for more than 69.54 million border passages, which illustrates an average annual increase of 35.9%. Vehicle entries and outputs through this border registered an average annual rise of 30.8%, reaching about 8.11 million. However, today is the fourth anniversary of the entry into operation of the Qingmao Post, which has already accounted for more than 100 million border tickets. Between 2022 and 2024, the volume of inputs and exits by this customs post rose more than 80% per year.</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2468/</link><description>Air Macau reduces maximum weight of basement baggage
From the 17th, Air Macau will adopt several adjustments compared to the maximum weight of the basement baggage. For the economic class, the maximum weight of free dispatched luggage will be reduced from 25 to 23 pounds, and a new restriction will be introduced, according to which each passenger can have only one free basement piece. In the executive class, the maximum weight will download from 40 to 32 pounds, and will be adopted a rule of two pieces of luggage at most. In addition, the sum of the length, width and height of the luggage should not exceed 158 centimeters, including wheels and handles, against the current 203 centimeters.
 
Named three new bosses for game inspection
The Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ) receives three new bosses. According to orders by the Secretary for Economics and Finance, Ieong Hoi Ian, he was appointed head of the DICJ Department of Investigation in Service Commission for one year. Graduated in Business Management, he joined DICJ in 2006, having performed functions such as the Assistant Technical, Higher Technique and Head of the Division. Already Cheang Im Ha was named, for a year period, leadership of the 2nd Division of the DICJ. Graduated in law, she was an employee of services for labor affairs (DSAL) and services for traffic affairs. Choi Kit Wa will lead the DICJ licensing division, also in a service committee, for a period of one year. Graduated in law, she has worked at Dsal and health services.
 
Aggressions between four elderly due to bus seats
The CPSP reported a case of aggression between four local elderly, which will have occurred due to the dispute of priority seats in a public bus. Two were eventually transported to the hospital with slight head injuries. According to CPSP, the case happened on Saturday morning at a bus stop at Zape, where two men and two women, aged 60 to 80, pushed each other. According to some passersby, someone turned to a cane to attack someone else. The case continues to be investigated by the police.
 
Detected two more cases of chikungunya and dengue
Health services recorded the 13th imported case of chikungunya fever in Macau this year. He is a 37-year-old woman, resident on Rua do Commander João Belo. According to the SSM, the patient traveled several times to the interior of China. Presenting a stable clinical state, it is hospitalized. On the other hand, the 14th imported case of dengue fever was registered in a 71-year resident, which lives in Duas Rua dois do Areia Preta. Last month, the elderly woman was in Zhongshan. It is hospitalized with a stable clinical state. The people with which Coabita did not express symptoms.
 
Government attributes additional amount to 2,600 household aggregates
The Institute of Social Action (IAS) began the attribution of an additional amount of subsidy to about 2,600 household aggregates beneficiary of the regular allowance, the total charge of this measure estimated at about 14.6 million patacas. In concrete, the aggregates with an element receive an additional subsidy of 4,350 patacas, while those with two or three elements benefit from 7,990 or 11,020 patacas, respectively. As for families with eight or more people, the value ascends to 20,270 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Complaints in the health sector decreased by 3% in 2024</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/queixas-sector-da-saude-diminuiram-3-em-2024/</link><description>The health services report for 2024 reveals that health complaints decreased by 3.2%, noting the sixth consecutive year of decline. On the other hand, the number of patients treated rose both at the Conde de São Januário hospital center (+5.8%) and in health centers (+4.2%), compared to 2023. In health centers, nutritional counseling found the most notorious increase in the number of users, from 33.3%to 9,712 patients. By the end of 2024, SSM had 4,559 workers, an annual reduction of 82 people
 
Last year, 49 cases were filed in the context of health complaints, which involved 91 alleged offenses, marking an annual break of 3.2%, indicates the Health Services Activities Report (SSM). According to official data consulted by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the complaints fell for the sixth consecutive year.
In 2024, most cases of infringement occurred in polyclinics, mainly implying non -declared medical publicity and medical publicity that did not correspond to the established rules.
In addition, 1,238 inspections were made to private health care establishments and 101 inspections due to the monitoring of complaints.
Regarding health advertising, 433 requests were approved in 2024, which corresponds to an annual decrease of about 42.3%. In total, 426 orders (98.4%) received “green light”. Six joint inspections were also carried out to exhibition activities, and six cases of infringement were detected. After the verbal recommendation to the participating entities, they immediately proceeded to their rectification, the SSM notice.
On the other hand, according to the report, Macao had in 2024 with 675 private health care establishments, which reflects an annual decrease and 2%.
In the public sphere, by the end of last year, the SSM had 4,559 workers, with an annual reduction of 82 people, with health professionals representing about 50% of the total number of staff.
Generally speaking, Macau had 8,264 health professionals from 15 categories and 162 people licensed according to the previous regime, ie a total of 8,426 people. On the other hand, 47 Macao doctors were allowed to practice hengqin, raising the total to 112.
In addition, from 2019 to 2024, 826 candidates became members of the Macao Medical Academy, and certified to 872 academics were assigned.
Between 2004 and 2024, the SSM also supported 1,465 Macao doctors in the registration process for the doctor's qualification exam in the interior of China. Until last year, 427 people have obtained the national qualification to exercise the profession of doctor. In addition, since 2024, the body has helped 109 newly graded in the registration for the nurse qualification exam in the interior of China.
 
Nutrition consultations record greater demand
The report also reveals that the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center (CHCSJ) served 852 thousand people/times, more than 805 thousand accounted for in 2023 (an annual increase of about 5.8%). At the same time, health centers provided external consultations to 896,000 patients/times, meaning an annual increase of 4.2%.
According to the document, more than 524,000 people resorted to external consultations of CHCSJ, an increase of 6.4% before 2023, while the number of urgent consultations rose 4.4% to over 300 thousand. In the hospitalization section, the volume of patients registered an annual rise from 13.3% to 26,899 in 2024, but the average hospitalization time fell 10% to 9.9 days. With regard to CHCSJ beds, the occupancy rate decreased by 1.4 percentage points to 78.5% in 2024. There was also an 8.1% increase in the number of people/times who received complementary diagnostic and therapeutic exams from the public hospital, and over 8.23 ​​million.
Regarding effectiveness, the report states that in 2024, the average waiting time was reduced for the first external consultation at the public hospital, from 3.7 to 3.3 weeks, which translates into a 10%reduction. In the emergency room for adults, the average time of waiting throughout the day remained in about an hour, while the waiting time percentage over two hours went from over 20% to about 10% last year.
On the other hand, until December 2024, more than 780 CHCSJ patients were transferred to the Islands Hospital.
The report also notes that, among the services provided by health centers, it was nutritional counseling that verified a more significant increase of 33.3% in annual terms, involving 9,712 patients in 2024. In addition, the external appointment of tabágic disability is also increasingly sought, having served 1,944 people, an annual increase of 12.6%. On the contrary, child health care served 51,489 people, a break of 6.1%.
In another scope, in 2024, the government granted financial support and acquired about 853,000 medical services to non -profit medical institutions, including external chinese and western medical consultations, emergency services, inpatient, neonatal hearing screening, palliative care, home care, sexually transmitted disease examination, speech therapy, speech therapy examination, speech. For children, among others.
At the same time, the external services of differentiated health care extended to 17 homes of elderly or entities. In this context, 24,321 users were attended. For its part, outdoor distance consultation services began to cover 20 homes, having served 830 people in 2024. As for the dental prosthesis installation program for the elderly, a total of 321 eligible people who gave consent to the installation was registered.
 
Number of new blood donors falls
In the aspect of blood donation, the report indicates that, by the end of 2024, there were 13,740 blood donations in Macao, which guaranteed blood and blood transfusions to 3,626 patients. However, a cumulative total of 1,145 bone marrow or blood stem cells was recorded, five of which were successfully donated bone marrow or blood stem cells to patients in need in the territory.
Em específico, o número de dadores de sangue registados em 2024 foi de 20.587, uma quebra anual de 1,5%, ao passo que 2.899 foram novos dadores, menos 13,6% face a 2023.
However, 21,962 cases of compulsory declaration of transmitted diseases were registered last year, representing an annual breakdown of 28.4%, including influenza, enteroviruses and scarletin diseases. That year, nine local cases and 39 imported cases of dengue fever were registered.
288 cases of tuberculosis were also noted, with the incidence rate of 42 per 100,000 inhabitants. The total number of external consultations at the Tuberculous Prevention and Treatment Center was 12,924, an annual climb of 10.6%.
In addition, last year, 28 cases of HIV infection (10 locations and 18 non -residents) were confirmed. By 2024, 1,200 self-test kits were sold and three confirmed cases of HIV infection were detected.
On the other hand, from November 2016 to December 2024, a total of 27,849 users concluded the consultation and participation in the tracking of colo-rectal cancer, of which 158 were diagnosed. In addition, 1,470 women participated, on their own initiative, in the screening of Cervical Cancer, while the first phase of the Mama Cancer Tracking Program, until the end of 2024, with more than 14,000 participants, of which 21 were diagnosed. At the same time, 63 people were subject to the tracking of pulmonary cancer, of which 18 were accompanied by medical specialties.
Already the 53 posts of self-medication of blood pressure and weight installed in the community neighborhoods served a total of 164 thousand people in 2024.
On the other hand, by the end of the year last year, 230 requests were received for the “reimbursement program in the treatment of medically assisted procreation”.
In addition, since the launch on May 6, 2024 until the end of this year, 288 requests for medical treatment visits in Macau have been approved.
The report also recalls that, in 2024, more than 259,000 inspections were made to establishments in the context of smoking control and alcohol consumption by minors. 3,944 cases of illegal smoke were detected, 156 illegal transportation of electronic cigarettes to the entry of Macau, 71 illegal consumption of electronic cigarettes (+31.5%), three illegal sale of electronic cigarettes, as well as 129 related to other infractions under the law. In total, 851 smokers were authorized.
However, 51 suspected cases of violation of the alcoholic beverages control law were recorded by minors, including 13 of sale or supply of alcoholic beverages to minors. Processes were filed in all cases. At the same time, 4,132 improvement instructions were issued to 3,102 establishments.</description><pubDate>2025-09-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Defended installation of services for dementia prevention</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/defendida-instalacao-de-servicos-para-prevencao-da-demencia/</link><description>Leong Hong Sai argued that dementia must be considered one of the great risks to the health of the elderly of Macao. In this sense, the deputy urged the government to create an exclusive service installation for dementia prevention, taking advantage of the new decenal action plan for support services. The idea is to provide community services for regular hearing tests and the memory capacity of the elderly
 
With the accentuation of population aging in Macao, it is necessary to reinforce the degree of attention and affection for the elderly, Leong Hong stressed, in a written interplies, warning that, in this respect, dementia must be considered one of the great risks that threaten the health of people from the third and middle age.
In order to address the risk of dementia among local elderly, the deputy urged the government to consist to create an exclusive installation of dementia prevention in the elderly, within the new action plan for the development of elderly support services over the next ten years.
Specifically, it proposed that the respective installation widely provides community services for regular testing in relation to the hearing and memory capacity of the elderly. In this aspect, he stressed that, according to the World Health Organization, between four seniors over 60, one person suffers from disabling hearing loss, and hearing loss can raise the risk of dementia, fall and depression.
Leong Hong Sai defended early intervention, that is, the use of hearing aid and performing cochlear implant surgery. For both intervention measures, the deputy suggested financial support granted by the government.
On the other hand, warning that social isolation also constitutes one of the causes of dementia, Leong Hong has exhorted authorities to improve the current home support and visit services to the elderly so that these services are especially contemplated the needs of the elderly living alone and who are "hidden".
In addition, it has suggested measures that may encourage senior residents to participate in community learning activities such as calligraphy, tajiquan and other intellectual training activities to help elderly brain flexibility and interact with people of the same age group, thus reducing the risk of dementia.
For Leong Hong Sai, the government must absorb the country's ideas, technologies and advanced service model in the scope of elderly services, as well as to take as reference the experience of neighboring regions. In addition, it should cooperate with the other cities of the Great Bay in the creation of an “integrated community condominium that encompasses housing, medical services, rehabilitation, culture and entertainment”, for the population of the elderly to live old age in a happily.
The deputy also hopes that the authorities will enjoy the Chinese Traditional Medicine Scientific and Industrial Park for cooperation between Guangdong-Macau in Hengqin, to vigorously develop Chinese Medicine and Health Management services directed to dementia prevention.
 
More courses for seniors
Moreover, also about the population of the elderly, according to a response from the Directorate of Services for Laboral Affairs (DSAL) to a written interpellation of Deputy Zheng Anting, the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) said it will boost higher education institutions and other educational entities to provide more training courses for senior and that they are necessary for the development of society.
Alongside this, he stated that DSEDJ continuously enriches the contents of the certificates and licenses of the continuous development and improvement program to meet the continuous formation of senior training needs.
On the other hand, ensuring the promotion of employability, with a view to creating a friendly social atmosphere of hiring senior residents, DSal has asserted that it will accompany in accordance with its legally attributed competences the complaints in which any candidate understands that he is being discriminated due to his age.
In the same response, DSAL also pointed out that the government has endowed small and medium -sized companies - including those related to industry to seniors - of more capacities and added value, in order to support continuous exploration and stable and healthy development. "The development of related companies can also create more jobs for different age groups," the body added.</description><pubDate>2025-09-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Giorgio Armani was the “king of luxury” to the Italian</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/giorgio-armani-foi-rei-luxo-a-italiana/</link><description>Italian fashion giant deceased at age 91, Giorgio Armani wore the stars and then conquered the world with his empire dedicated to recreating a luxurious lifestyle, from accessories to interior design.
“Discreet elegance and sophisticated luxury” was how his brand on the Time Out Bahrain guide summarized in 2009.
With an intense tan, well -kept white hair and the physicist sculpted by daily training, Armani was famous for his discretion.
Throughout a remarkable career, he maintained his company's full control while moving from fashion to luxury hotels, cosmetics, accessories and interiors. All of this made Armani one of the richest men in the world. In 2017, Forbes magazine estimated its fortune at $ 6.6 billion.
In 1975 he had opened a homonymous house in Milan and raised quickly to the top with "a minimalist collection based on everyday fashion," as Vogue Paris described.
Armani liked to use “clear details and simple fabrics,” he said once. It even developed a new color called “Greige”, a combination of gray and beige.
Attracted by this falsely simple style, the stars began to ask the Italian genius to dress them. Richard Gere in “American Gigolo” (1980) was one of those famous love and style cases between the designer and Hollywood.
The Italian icon was recognized for its fashion contribution made especially to shine in the red carpet. He put on stars like Jodie Foster, Cate Blanchett and Beyoncé for these gala nights. Other stars, including Tom Cruise and Katie Holmes, chose to wear Armani even at the wedding.
He could “make men and women feel confident and comfortable with fluid clothing, which eliminated traditional tailoring restrictions without losing their ability to give sophistication to the client,” said Harper's Bazaar in 2015.
In the 1980s, Armani gained legions of admirers among executives, pioneer in women's fashion -inspired jams with jams that marked a time.
“I want to keep myself constantly updated, but without changing the essential characteristics of my philosophy,” he explained then.
Armani was a frequent attendant of the fashion weeks from Paris to New York, but never felt more at home than in the capital of Italy, Milan.
Traditionally ended the Milan Fashion Week, where it briefly appeared with its characteristic work suit: navy blue sweater and high-tech sports pants.
Over time, he decided to diversify his offer, with the younger and more affordable line Emporio Armani.
In 2010 he opened his first luxury hotel in Dubai, Burj Khalifa, the highest building in the world, where the suites cost several thousand dollars a night.
Armani was born in July 1934 near Milan, in a humble family of Armenian origin. He studied medicine for two years, but changed his way to accept a work as a showcase in the famous Rinascent store of Milan, where he remained until he was 31 years old.
He then graduated as a designer for seven years with Italian fashion designer and producer Nino Cerruti, before opening his own studio with a friend, Sergio Galeotti. Galeotti died 10 years later and Armani became the sole owner, remaining as the main stylist.
Without children, he has no natural heir, although a nephew and two nieces are directly involved in the company.
When asked if he could imagine being replaced as his company's creative force, he joked, "My ego would say, of course, that no one would ever work as Armani." But then admitted: “There are talents out there”…
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>