<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Sam Hou Fai praises “clear laws” and “efficient justice” in Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sam-hou-fai-elogia-leis-claras-justica-eficiente-em-macau/</link><description>At the opening of the XIII Conference of the Forum of Presidents of the Supreme Courts of Justice of Portuguese-Speaking Countries and Territories, Sam Hou Fai highlighted Macau's “clear laws”, as well as “efficient justice”. He also argued that “the Macao SAR went from a new member of the Forum to an active participant and promoter”, which, in his opinion, “demonstrates the firm safeguarding of judicial independence under the principle of ‘one country, two systems’”
 
CATARINA PEREIRA
 
Sam Hou Fai yesterday praised the justice scenario in the territory. Stating that “Macau strives for the defense of ‘one country’ and takes advantage of the advantages of the second system, with its characteristics provided by the fusion of Chinese and Western cultures”, the Chief Executive defended that the territory “is fully capable of delivering quality performance and promoting ‘legal interconnection, mutual trust at the judicial level and mutual benefits for the rule of law’”.
In the speech he gave at the Opening Ceremony of the XIII Conference of the Forum of Presidents of the Supreme Courts of Justice of Portuguese-speaking Countries and Territories, the leader of the Macao SAR and former president of the Court of Final Instance (TUI) spoke, specifically, of “clear laws that increase investor confidence, alternative dispute resolution mechanisms that reduce transaction costs, justice and impartiality that consolidate the connection between our peoples”.
Noting that this edition of the Conference is about “Law and Justice as a factor in bringing people together and their economic and social development”, Sam Hou Fai stressed that “justice is not only a mirror of social development, but also a dynamic force that drives it”. In this sense, and given the changes in the last hundred years, he argued that what the world needs is “dialogue” and not “confrontation”, “cooperation” and not “division”.
"More than at any time in the past, we need to use legal certainty to counter the 'varieties of the world', to use the impartiality of the judicial system to provide guarantees for socioeconomic development, and to use the open nature of the rule of law to bring nations and countries together. Portuguese-speaking countries span Asia, Africa, Europe and Latin America, with a population of almost 300 million people. China is the second largest global economy and the construction of the Greater Bay Area is in full development”, he added.
Sam Hou Fai recalled that, 22 years ago, in October 2003, he presided over the first Conference of Presidents of the Supreme Courts of Justice of Portuguese-speaking Countries and Territories organized by the Macao SAR. He then witnessed the establishment of the “Forum Statute” and witnessed the creation of the permanent secretariat and the regime of periodic meetings. At that time, he said, the “cooperation of the ‘great Portuguese-speaking judicial family’ officially began”.
"After many years, this reunion brings with it the memory of history, and more importantly, it generates hope for the future. Over these 22 years, this intercontinental judicial bridge, the work of the union of our efforts, grew from six seeds and became a giant tree that covers four continents", he continued. For the Chief Executive, the Forum has addressed increasingly in-depth topics, from the “need for judicial reform” to the “administrative and financial autonomy of Court Services as a guarantor of judicial independence”, from the “role of the Judiciary in the face of globalization” to “the judiciary and new technologies”, “demonstrating the constant elevation of our awareness of the value of the Rule of Law”.
It also considers that “the Macao SAR went from a new member of the Forum to an active participant and promoter, which demonstrates the firm safeguarding of judicial independence under the principle of ‘one country, two systems’”. In this context, he also highlighted that “the Macao SAR enjoys, in accordance with the Basic Law, independent judicial power, including that of final judgment, which allows us to consolidate, within the legal framework, the Rule of Law, and, with the unique advantages of Sino-Portuguese bilingualism, to naturally become the bridge between China and the Portuguese-speaking world”.
For Sam Hou Fai, the presence of the presidents of the Supreme Courts of Justice of Portuguese-speaking countries in the territory “represents high recognition of the progress of the Rule of Law in Macau”. More importantly, he said, “it provides us with a strong stimulus to continue writing new chapters of ‘Macau based on the Rule of Law’”.
As he said, the Conference should be used “as a new starting point” to “promote Law as a link for harmony between peoples and an engine for economic development”. Sam Hou Fai also repeated a phrase he said 22 years ago, on the same occasion: “Justice for the people is achieved through their courts”.
 
“We keep alive the heritage and legacy of Portuguese Law”
The president of the Court of Final Instance defended that the Macao SAR judicial system kept “the heritage and legacy of Portuguese Law and the Portuguese Language alive”. In his speech at the Conference of the Forum of Presidents of the Supreme Courts of Justice of Portuguese-Speaking Countries and Territories, and cited by Rádio Macau, Song Man Lei highlighted that “the Macao SAR courts exercise their judicial function independently, being free from any interference and only subject to the law”. Furthermore, he added that the implementation of the Basic Law “guarantees that the legal system” of the MSAR “is compatible” with the “one country, two systems” principle, as well as “ensuring Macau’s high degree of autonomy, with independent courts, predictable laws and efficient handling of cases”. He added that the Macao SAR courts have sought to increase efficiency and argued that judicial failures could undermine trust and worsen social inequalities. In turn, the president of the Supreme Court of Justice of Portugal highlighted the importance of the Supreme Courts as “guardians of democracy” and safe havens for the protection of Fundamental Rights, at a time when authoritarianism and disinformation threaten the Rule of Law in the world. João Cura Mariano also defended the creation of a Lusophone Justice observatory to compare systems and proposed a magistrate exchange program. Furthermore, he pointed to Macau as a secular example of harmony, where continental law coexists with Eastern legal traditions.</description><pubDate>2025-10-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CTM develops AI tool in Portuguese</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ctm-desenvolve-ferramenta-de-ia-em-lingua-portuguesa/</link><description>The Macau Telecommunications Company yesterday presented its “New Vision” for the Macao SAR's technology sector, with emphasis on the development of an artificial intelligence language model in Portuguese. The company also announced a set of discounts for its customers, effective from January 2026
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
Ebel Cham, vice-president of commercial operations at Macau Telecommunications Company (CTM), announced yesterday, at a press conference, plans to develop and implement a Portuguese language model of artificial intelligence (AI) that will support reporting generation, audiovisual translation and consultancy and customer support services in e-commerce. The project, which aims to bring China closer to Portuguese-speaking countries (PLP), is part of CTM's “New Vision” and a comprehensive commitment to the development of the Macao SAR's technology industry.
“The reason we intend to develop the Portuguese language model is because we would like to make it more specific and suitable for the Macau market”, explained Ebel Cham. "We are very confident that we can [implement it] in various industries, such as the retail and tourism sectors. We have many mass events and many PLP visitors. Therefore, we need to improve language proficiencies. In addition to simultaneous translation services, we would also like to have some machines so that tourists and residents can use them conveniently," he said.
Furthermore, the company intends to “leverage the ‘internet of things’, ‘big data’, AI and collaborative road technologies to implement applications such as real-time traffic monitoring and dynamic alert systems”, in order to drive the advancement of the transport system’s intelligent network. In fact, CTM will integrate the “Baidu Maps” service to “improve smart mobility”.
The operator also intends to develop a language model specialized in legal, regulatory and legal contexts, in order to provide more convenient consultancy services to citizens.
To support small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) in expanding their online sales channels, and to accelerate their integration in the Greater Bay Area, CTM plans to launch the “Macau Certified Store” electronic platform, with “effective and reliable direct access” to the cross-border market. The company hopes that by leveraging e-commerce live broadcasts, Macau merchants can connect with consumers in the Greater Bay Area, “thus improving sales and market efficiency”, said Ebel Cham.
With regard to 'big data' services, CTM will improve support for public administration, with real-time anonymous data analysis services, for government and business services. At the same time, the utility plans to “collaborate with partners to create a decentralized data platform that offers compatibility solutions for Greater Bay Area businesses.”
 
One-off discounts for individual customers
All customers of the telecommunications operator who have signed a contract with CTM by September 30, 2025 will benefit from discounts throughout the next year. Price reductions cover individuals, SMEs, large corporations and government departments. In September, the company had announced that it would review the rates for its services.
Eligible individual customers and SMEs will benefit from discounts of 10% and 20%, respectively, in January, April, July and October 2026. Furthermore, from January next year, the price for additional mobile data will fall from 13 to 8 patacas per gigabyte, corresponding to a reduction of 38.5%.
The monthly fixed telephone service plan for companies will be reduced to 140 patacas from next year, and these customers will also benefit from a fee of 112 patacas for broadband services.
Large corporations and Government departments will be able to receive a 20% discount on monthly fees for January and July. Commercial customers who have “Direct Internet Access” services will benefit from a 10% monthly discount in the first month of each semester.
These measures aim to “support the Macao SAR Government in creating a more favorable environment for business, and improving citizen satisfaction”, noted Ebel Cham.</description><pubDate>2025-10-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IAS continues without requests for video surveillance in daycare centers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ias-continua-sem-pedidos-para-videovigilancia-em-creches/</link><description>The president of the IAS revealed that no request has yet been submitted for daycare centers to install video surveillance in bed and activity areas. According to Hon Wai, some guardians are concerned about children's privacy and trust the care provided by daycare staff, which is why they do not agree with the video surveillance measure. In your opinion, it will be difficult to achieve unanimity regarding the program
 
So far, the Institute of Social Action (IAS) has not yet received requests from daycare centers for the video surveillance program aimed at bed and activity areas since registration opened on September 19, said Hon Wai, president of the IAS.
According to Hon Wai, as the scope monitored by video surveillance cameras – the bed and activity areas – involves a relatively large area, some parents are concerned about their children's privacy. Furthermore, as they trust the care provided by daycare staff, they disagreed with video surveillance in these establishments, he continued.
Quoted by the Chinese-language press, the president of the IAS recalled that daycare centers that intend to register for the program will have to obtain the consent of all guardians. Given the situation, Hon Wai highlighted that the IAS respects everyone's decisions, promising that it will continue to carry out training activities and organize information sessions about the program.
Reiterating that the IAS will strictly control the right to store and access videos captured by cameras, Hon Wai stressed that videos can only be viewed in special circumstances or for judicial investigations. Furthermore, he added that the program is very different from video surveillance in public spaces and that parents will not be able to consult the videos at will.
As predicted by the president of the IAS, it will be difficult to obtain unanimous opinions regarding the program. Despite this, Hon Wai assured that, as soon as there are daycare centers able to register, the IAS will provide technical support immediately.
It should be remembered that the program aims to “support daycare centers to reinforce the safety of the children who attend them” and “uncover, whenever necessary, the reality of the event that gave rise to the accident involving children”, according to the IAS.
The idea of ​​installing cameras in daycare centers began to be studied following the death of a four-month-old baby at Creche Fong Chong in Taipa, in October 2023.</description><pubDate>2025-10-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Jorge Rangel and Carlos Cid Álvares will receive the Rocha Vieira Prize</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jorge-rangel-carlos-cid-alvares-vao-receber-premio-rocha-vieira/</link><description>Jorge Rangel and Carlos Cid Álvares are the winners of the first edition of the General Rocha Vieira Prize, established by the Luso-Chinese Chamber of Commerce and Industry, according to Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU. The award ceremony will take place at the Portugal-China Gala, on October 29th. The secretary general of CCILC, Bernardo Mendia, explained that the award “represents not only a tribute to a historical legacy, but also a continuous commitment to building bridges, driving new opportunities between the two countries”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Jorge Rangel, president of the International Institute of Macau, and Carlos Cid Álvares, CEO of Banco Nacional Ultramarino, will receive the General Vasco Rocha Vieira Award, established by the Luso-Chinese Chamber of Commerce and Industry (CCILC), newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU knows. The general secretary of the CCILC, Bernardo Mendia, declined to confirm the names of the winners, only mentioning that the award ceremony will take place on October 29th, during the X Gala Portugal-China, in the Black and Silver Room of Casino Estoril.
Stressing that the award will be awarded this year for the first time – and from now on annually, during the Portugal-China Gala -, Bernardo Mendia also explained to this newspaper that the creation of the award came after consultation with Rocha Vieira's family, symbolizing “a tribute to those who distinguished themselves for their exceptional contribution to strengthening dialogue, cooperation and relations between Portugal and China”.
“General Vasco Rocha Vieira, 138th Governor of Macau and president of the Strategic Council of the CCILC since its creation, played a remarkable and exemplary role throughout his life, standing out for his commitment to service to the Nation, his dedication to relations between Portugal and China, and his historic role in closing the cycle of Portuguese administration in Macau”, said Bernardo Mendia, adding: “In the leadership of the Strategic Council of CCILC, its strategic vision, wisdom and human values have always been a source of inspiration and reference”.
Thus, the award “represents not only a tribute to a historical legacy, but also a continuous commitment to building bridges, promoting new opportunities between the two countries”, highlighted the secretary general of the CCILC.
According to the CCILC online page, this year the event is under the motto “A Decade of Shared Achievements – Technology and Innovation as Drivers for a New Era of Cooperation”. According to the program, Carlos Cid Álvares, one of the winners, and who is also president of the CCILC delegation in Macau, will be in a conversation on stage, invited by António Noronha, president of CCILC.
There will also be space for a speech by the guest of honor, from the Embassy of the People's Republic of China in Portugal, as well as for the awarding of business merit awards, recognizing entities with “relevant contributions to strengthening economic and commercial relations”.
The CCILC Strategic Council is currently chaired by ambassador António Martins da Cruz, with the vice-presidency being in charge of ambassador Pedro Catarino, with the participation of Maria Celeste Hagatong, ambassador José Manuel Duarte de Jesus, General José Garcia Leandro, Maria de Belém Roseira, Hugo Carneiro, among others.</description><pubDate>2025-10-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Two killed in accident at Hong Kong airport</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/dois-mortos-em-acidente-aeroporto-de-hong-kong/</link><description>epa12466424 A Hong Kong police boat sails near a cargo plane that remains on the water after skidding off the runway at Hong Kong International Airport, China, 20 October 2025. A Boeing 747 cargo plane (flight EK9788) skidded off a runway at Hong Kong International Airport and landed in the sea on 20 October. Authorities reported that the four crew members on board were rescued, but two ground staff members were killed in the collision.  EPA/MAY JAMES



Hong Kong authorities are investigating the causes of an accident that occurred yesterday at the international airport, when a Boeing 747 cargo plane from Dubai left the runway and partially fell into the sea, causing two deaths. According to Man Ka-chai, head of investigation at the Air Accidents Investigation Authority (AAIA), the Emirates SkyCargo flight, operated by Turkish Air ACT Cargo, was allowed to land normally and did not emit any emergency signal before losing control and crossing the railing into the sea.
The plane, coming from Al Maktoum airport, touched the northern runway at around 3:50 am, where it collided with a patrol vehicle with two workers, pushing it into the sea, authorities said. The Boeing 747 broke in two and also fell into the water. Firefighters quickly responded to the incident and rescued the four crew members waiting at the door and emerged unharmed.
However, it took divers around 40 minutes to locate the car, which was submerged seven meters deep. A 30-year-old passenger was pronounced dead at the scene, while the 41-year-old driver was removed from the vehicle unconscious and unresponsive and pronounced dead at the hospital.
The Airport Authority's director of operations, Steven Yiu, assured that the vehicle was “in the authorized patrol zone” and that the weather and runway conditions were “optimal”. According to Yiu, the two victims had more than a decade of experience in airport operations.
Data from the “Flightradar24” portal indicates that the plane was traveling at around 167km per hour when it deviated towards the breakwater and at 91km per hour at the time of impact with the sea, which destroyed the front part of the device.
The AAIA opened an investigation to determine whether the accident resulted from technical failure, human error or an unforeseen operational factor. The police did not rule out a possible criminal investigation.
The northbound lane was temporarily closed, with operations concentrated on the central and southbound lanes.
The Department of Civil Aviation and the Secretariat of Transport and Logistics expressed condolences for the death of the workers, stressing that “air safety is a Government priority”.
The incident is similar to the accident of China Airlines flight CA605 in November 1993, when a Boeing 747-400 left the runway at the old Kai Tak airport during a landing in crosswinds and heavy rain, ending with its nose submerged in Vitória Bay, with no casualties.
 
JTM with Lusa and Hong Kong press</description><pubDate>2025-10-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Water tested with advanced technologies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/agua-testada-tecnologias-avancadas/</link><description>Experts from Macau participated in a symposium of the International Water Association on Flavors, Odors and Algal Toxins in Drinking Water Sources and Aquaculture in Shanghai. Kong Yijun and Li Zhixuan, from Macau Water, presented technological solutions for analyzing water quality
 
The Sociedade de Abastecimento de Águas de Macau (SAAM, or Macau Water) has been introducing advanced technologies such as “FlowCAM”, a solution that distinguishes algae in water samples and catalogs them, using artificial intelligence. According to the company, the technology allows the identification and classification of algae species automatically and with a greater degree of precision and effectiveness, offering intelligent support for monitoring water quality.
“FlowCAM” was released by Macau Water in Shanghai, at the “International Water Association Symposium on Flavors, Odors and Algal Toxins in Drinking Water Sources and Aquaculture”, an event in which it participated as an organizing member. In this 12th edition of the event, SAAM took the opportunity to share technologies and study results with counterparts in the water sector.
Kong Yijun and Li Zhixuan, the company's senior director of Microbiology and senior engineer, respectively, gave two lectures. Kong spoke about the “Evaluation of Flow Imaging Microscopy Technology (FlowCAM) in the Quantification of Algae in Freshwater Reservoirs”, while Li discussed the “Spatial and Temporal Distribution of Cyanotoxins in the Aquatic Environment of Macau”, presenting results and practical cases.
In the presence of around 230 academics, engineers, technicians and executives from various countries and regions, the topics covered included “the safeguarding of drinking water sources, sensory evaluation methods, technologies for detecting and identifying flavors and odors, mechanisms for the formation of taste and odor compounds and control strategies”.
As part of knowledge sharing and scientific education, SAAM launched the “Atlas of Common Freshwater Algae in Macau” platform in 2023, the first platform to disseminate information about algae in China's water sector and “a valuable database for studying the impact of algae on raw water quality”. The platform is also publicly accessible, which allows the sharing and application of results among the scientific community.
The Laboratory Research Center, SAAM's integrated research department, ensures that it strictly complies with the Macau Water and Wastewater Drainage Regulations, incorporating standards stipulated by China, the World Health Organization (WHO) and Europe. Accredited since 2000, the Center has continually optimized laboratory management and participated in programs to assess water quality analysis capacity with “exceptional results”.
In the future, the company hopes to continue carrying out studies on quality and promoting the optimization of analysis methods and operational techniques, “with a view to facing potential challenges related to water quality and providing safe, stable and high-quality water supply services in Macau”.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-10-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Investment funds motivate debate at the Rui Cunha Foundation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/fundos-de-investimento-motivam-debate-na-fundacao-rui-cunha/</link><description>The “New Law on Investment Funds in Macau: Perspectives, Opportunities and Challenges”, will give rise to a debate at the Rui Cunha Foundation. The conversation will address, among other topics, the diversification of the economy and the mobilization of underutilized capital funds
 
The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) and MBtv Debates will hold tomorrow, Wednesday, at 6:30 pm, a conference entitled “New Law on Investment Funds in Macau: Perspectives, Opportunities and Challenges”, included in MBtv's “Finance Series” cycle. According to a statement from the organization of the lecture, “the reform aims to improve the city's value proposition, diversify the economy and mobilize underutilized capital funds, through the modernization of the legal framework”.
The debate aims to launch the discussion on reforming legal mechanisms to boost the market and attract capital investment in the territory, as well as finding answers to questions such as: “What will it take to transform the law into a real market boost?”, or “Where are the opportunities in product design, management, distribution and administration of funds?”
A panel of policymakers, sector leaders and legal experts will analyze the prospects, opportunities and future challenges of the Macao SAR's financial situation. Present at the debate will be Amy Ho, senior banking analyst at the Macau Monetary Authority; Bernardo Alves, president and investment director of “A&amp;P Investment Fund”, Calvin Chui, managing partner of Lektou and president of the Board of Directors of the Macau Financial Law Association, Gavin Kwok, director of Prime Brokerage sales of “Maybank Investment Banking Group – Hong Kong”, Rui Proença, partner of MdME and Nuno Sardinha of Mata, senior partner at C&amp;C Advogados.
The session will be moderated by the director of Macau Business and “Macau News Agency”, José Carlos Matias, and will be held in English and broadcast live on the FRC and MBtv Facebook pages. Entry is free.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-10-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Request for a reduction in income in the Residence for the Elderly</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pedida-reducao-da-renda-na-residencia-para-idosos/</link><description>Citing residents who live in the Residence for the Elderly, FAOM suggested that the Government reduce the usage rate of this residential complex. He also called for the creation of exclusive bus routes for the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center and the Kiang Wu Hospital
 
Ella Lei, deputy director of the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau (FAOM), called on the authorities to continuously monitor the opinions of residents at the Residence for the Elderly, in order to optimize the services provided in this Government housing complex, launched a year ago. The challenge arose following a colloquium promoted by FAOM with the aim of collecting opinions from residents at the Residence for the Elderly.
According to FAOM, at the colloquium, many elderly people lamented that, as the real estate market underwent adjustments and the rents of private houses fell, in contrast, the utilization rate of the Residence for the Elderly is no longer low. This is despite the fact that users can benefit from a 20% discount on the usage fee, for a maximum of six years.
Ella Lei highlighted that many residents hope that the Government will consider reducing the rent in that residential complex, in order to help the elderly to alleviate economic pressure.
Furthermore, the deputy also indicated that many users of the Residence want exclusive bus routes, especially with direct connections to the Centro Hospitalar Conde de São Januário and the Kiang Wu Hospital, as well as improvements to existing bus services. After these improvements, they still hope that there will be exclusive buses between the Residence for the Elderly and Hospital das Ilhas.
Some elderly people also asked for the improvement of pedestrian facilities and the optimization of ventilation conditions and water quality in units at the Residence, FAOM pointed out, also suggesting the introduction of domestic cleaning services and equipment repair and maintenance, as well as more medical services.
The Government is implementing in the Residence, on an experimental basis, an application designed to detect the activities of elderly people who live alone, by recording the daily steps of senior citizens. Chan Ka Leong, director of the General Union of Residents' Associations (“Kaifong”), said that expanding the application to elderly people who live alone in other places will be considered, starting next year.
Furthermore, the “Kaifong” intend to open, also in 2026, a center for the elderly in Zone A of Novos Aterros, a project that is in the construction phase, said the same person in charge.
On the other hand, a charity flag sale activity, recently organized by the association, has allowed it to receive, so far, more than 1.5 million patacas in donations. According to Chan Ka Leong, the funds raised are intended to help elderly people who live alone.</description><pubDate>2025-10-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Airport ready to respond to climate challenges</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/aeroporto-pronto-responder-desafios-climaticos/</link><description>Given the increasing intensity and frequency of extreme weather situations, Macau airport will continue to adopt advanced navigation technologies to overcome difficulties in this regard, assured Pun Wa Kin, president of the Civil Aviation Authority (AACM). According to the Chinese language press, Pun Wa Kin highlighted that the Macao SAR uses the “necessary navigation performance operation that requires authorization”, among other measures, in order to reduce problems caused by meteorological factors, such as the plane remaining in the air waiting for authorization and changing route, reducing the impact on passengers and carbon emissions as much as possible.
In this way, the person in charge emphasized, the safety, efficiency and flexibility of the civil aviation sector will be reinforced.
On the other hand, during the 41st Asia-Pacific Regional Conference of the Air Traffic Operators Association, which kicked off yesterday in the territory, the president of the AACM said that the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) and Macau International Airport have been cooperating closely and actively taking various measures, with a view to continuously increasing the accuracy and punctuality of storm warnings. The person in charge mentioned that the SMG holds annual meetings with civil aviation operators in the Macao SAR, promoting direct communication and exchange of information, so that the sector can learn about current and forecast meteorological conditions, especially in situations of tropical storms and “storm surge” that frequently occur during peak tourism seasons.
Pun Wa Kin described the theme of this Air Traffic Operators Association Asia-Pacific Regional Conference – “All Weather Operations at the Airfield” – as “timely” and “crucial to defining strategies that enable safe and efficient operations”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sustainable tourism program awards diploma to 39 graduates</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/programa-em-turismo-sustentavel-confere-diploma-39-formandos/</link><description>Local graduates and those from Portuguese-speaking countries completed a program in sustainable tourism practices. The joint initiative between TODA and the University of São José aimed to provide professionals with the most up-to-date knowledge and tools, “necessary in the evolving global tourism landscape”














The Macau International Tourism Professionals Development Association (TODA) and the University of São José (USJ), through the Faculty of Management and Law, celebrated the completion of the Diploma Program in Sustainable Tourism Practices. The graduation ceremony brought together a total of 39 graduates, including 23 from Macau and 16 from Mozambique, Cape Verde and São Tomé and Príncipe.
The event brought together diplomats, industry leaders and educators, with congratulatory messages being shared from the Eduardo Mondlane University (Mozambique), the Departments of Culture and Tourism of Maputo, Inhambane and Nampula, and the School of Hotel Management and Tourism of Cape Verde.
According to a statement from TODA, the diploma aims to provide professionals with the most up-to-date knowledge and tools, “necessary in the evolving global tourism landscape”. The program was carried out simultaneously in person in Macau and online, from March to June, with participants completing six intensive modules, on topics related to the UN Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs), such as tourism law, marketing strategies, air transport, gastronomic tourism and heritage management.
In the “tribute to the graduates” session, Jenny Phillips, from USJ highlighted “the need to combine academic knowledge with practical training in sustainable tourism”. For his part, José Luís de Sales Marques, chairman of the Board of Directors of TODA Macau, emphasized the transversal impact of the program by allowing the exchange of experiences, namely Macau's “successful achievement in linking sustainable development to tourism development”.
Florence Ian, president of the executive committee, reaffirmed the association's commitment to remaining “dedicated to developing talent in international tourism, promoting the exchange of knowledge and sustainable development between regions”.
Among the main partners and sponsors are the Consulates of Mozambique and Angola in Macau, the Portugal-China Chamber of Commerce and Industry, Gracemind Marketing and Public Relations Limited, as well as Artyzen Grand Lapa Macau.
The TODA note emphasizes that the second edition of the joint diploma will be launched at the beginning of next year. Furthermore, the association is preparing a new short video competition entitled “Exploring Macau’s Sustainable Cultural Tourism – Through the Eyes of University Friends”.
Also present at the ceremony were vice-president of the board Danilo Cândido, as well as directors Mary Mendoza and Pamela Chan.
TODA members say they are committed to fostering the growth of industry talent through a variety of innovative and interactive programs aimed at improving professional skills in tourism and hospitality. “We will continue to recognize the importance of ongoing education and development with more academic programs that empower individuals and contribute to the advancement of sustainable practices in tourism, while fostering a lasting impact on the industry and the communities it serves”, highlights the document.
The association was founded in 2023 and is a non-profit organization dedicated to cultivating a global network of tourism professionals, promoting the exchange of tourism knowledge and inter-regional collaboration through the provision of professional development programs, resources and platforms, with a special focus on strengthening ties between Macau and Portuguese-speaking countries.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-10-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Swiss won 3×3 Basketball Tournament</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/suicos-venceram-torneio-de-basquetebol-3x3/</link><description>International elite teams of three-player basketball participated in the Masters Tournament in Macau. The triumph went to Lugano, from Switzerland, who defeated Miami from the North in the final. The event took place on one of the Wynn Palace lawns














VÍTOR REBELO
 
Macau hosted the final phase of the “FIBA 3×3 Masters Tournament”, where 16 of the best teams in the world in this basketball category were present. All games took place outdoors, at the South Door of the Wynn Palace.
The Swiss from Lugano, who did not lose any game, were the big winners, having beaten the team from Miami (USA) in the title discussion by just one point, 21-20, in a very balanced match that was only decided in the final moments and after a turnaround. The North Americans were winning 20-16, but allowed the Swiss to still have time to achieve victory, mainly thanks to the performance of the best player of the tournament (MVP), Adris León, with eight points obtained.
To guarantee their presence in the final, those two “trios” had to eliminate, in the semi-finals, Ulaanbaatar, from Mongolia, and Ub, from Serbia, respectively, by 21-18 and 22-16.
Meanwhile, in the quarter-finals, after the qualifiers held the previous day, teams from Riffa (Bahrain), Chongming (China), Bordeaux (France) and Kandava Turība (Latvia) also reached the quarter-finals.
The 3×3 Masters Tournament, sponsored by the International Basketball Federation (FIBA), brought together 16 teams and awarded a monetary prize of 185,000 US dollars to the winner, close to 780,000 patacas.
The world circuit of the three-player-per-team variant began in April this year in several cities, reaching Macau to establish the final classification of the season.
During the tests, there were also throwing and slam dunk events, in which the highest scorers were, respectively, the North American Mitch Hahn and the Polish Piotr Grabowski.
Once the final was concluded, the prize distribution ceremony followed, which was attended by, among others, the substitute president of the Sports Institute (ID), Mok Chi Hang, the president of the board of directors of the General Basketball Association of Macau-China, Wu Chong Fai, and the head of the Wynn Macau marketing department, Zoe Zou.
The tournament was co-organized by ID, and StarMac Recreation and Production Company, in collaboration with the General Basketball Association of Macau-China and Chaiioi Sports Company.
Remember that the 3×3 sport will return to the Macao SAR in November, as it is included in the list of sports for the National Games.</description><pubDate>2025-10-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sport motivates double exhibition at City of Dreams</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/desporto-motiva-dupla-exposicao-city-dreams/</link><description>City of Dreams is presenting two exhibitions by artist Laurent Perbos, which explore “the intersection between sport and art”. In “Artletics”, Perbos deconstructs common sporting scenes, while in “Beauty and Gesture”, the Frenchman reinterprets the goddess Venus in the light of the Olympic spirit






























PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment opened the exhibitions “Artletics” and “Beauty and Gesture”, by Laurent Perbos, a French contemporary artist. Present at City of Dreams, both exhibitions “reinterpret the intersection between sport and art” and explore “the relationship between power and beauty”, presenting “an interdisciplinary cultural experience”, indicates a press release.
In line with the inauguration of the 15th National Games, “Artletics” alludes “to the athletic spirit through the language of art”. In this project, the Frenchman sought to deconstruct “familiar sporting scenes to create an artistic space, which is at the same time recognizable and innovative”. Consisting of three central sections, the exhibition invites the public to interact with art, in a “unique immersive experience”.
For “Dream Court”, Perbos created the artistic installation “Aire”, inspired by a tennis court. In this immersive space with lawn and “spatial displacement”, “the audience feels as if they have entered an inverted tennis world”. In “Body Myth”, Perbos applied principles of optical illusion, to “re-imagine Venus dribbling a ball”, deconstructing and reconstituting basketball, “to create sculpted heads of ancient Greek heroes and deities”. Reinterpreted under a contemporary look, these figures “humorously address paradox and irony”. In “Ping-Pong Garden”, Laurent Perbos “breaks existing competitive rules by twisting, folding and stretching tables to create playful and interactive scenes”. The “Puzzle” art installation, in turn, is made up of three tennis tables joined together, intended for a game between seven players.
“Beauty and Gesture”, created for the 2024 Paris Olympic Games, was inspired by the iconic sculpture of Venus de Milo and consists of six colorful representations of the Greek deity, each with instruments that represent different Olympic sports. In this reinterpretation of Venus, Perbos echoes the fundamental values ​​of the Olympic spirit such as freedom, equality and fraternity. This exhibition was on display at the French National Assembly and attracted a lot of attention, according to Melco.
Laurent Perbos is originally from Bordeaux, lives and works between Paris and Marseille. According to the gaming operator, the Frenchman is inspired by “art history and personal experience”, and is also known for having a multidisciplinary approach.
"Art knows no borders. It is a universal language that connects us beyond cultures, distances and languages", observed the artist, during the launch ceremony. “Here, in Macau, I feel deeply honored to witness the encounter between my works and your vision, between French imagination and Chinese reality”.
Lawrence Ho, president of Melco, said that Laurent Perbos' double exhibition “not only redefines the relationship between art and sport, but also deepens Macau's multicultural expression”. “We hope that our audience experiences the humanistic beauty that arises from the fusion between competition and art”, he concluded.
City of Dreams has dedicated itself to bringing world-class exhibitions and multidisciplinary cultural projects to the Macao SAR, highlights Melco. The operator also adds cultural distinction to sporting events organized in Macau, it can be read, “underlining Melco’s commitment to promoting international art exchange and enriching Macau’s cultural tourist landscape”.
The “Beauty and Gesture” exhibition will be on display until November 26th, while the indoor exhibition “Artletics” will be on display until January 4th, 2026.</description><pubDate>2025-10-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Caritas promotes seven excursions for the elderly</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/caritas-promove-sete-excursoes-para-idosos/</link><description>Caritas Macau and its Kin Hang Travel Agency will organize a series of excursions for elderly users of its service centers, with the support of Banco HSBC Macau. The “harvest excursions” program tours will be carried out between this and next month, in a total of seven, one of which has already taken place. According to Caritas, more than 120 people should participate in the initiative. The institution pointed out that this initiative aims to “enrich the social life of elderly people through leisure tourism programs”, in order to improve their physical and mental health. He also revealed that the itinerary of these tours includes “several tourist attractions typical of Macau”, while barrier-free transport services and professional tour guide services will be provided “to ensure that all participants can travel safely”. A social enterprise project launched by Caritas in 2021, Kin Hang Travel Agency aims to provide barrier-free travel services to different groups of people in need with the aim of boosting the development of barrier-free tourism in Macau. The first trip in this series of seven took place on October 17th, taking elderly people, their families and HSBC volunteers to stroll along Hác-Sa Beach, have a meal at Restaurante Praha, at Doca dos Pescadores, and attend an exhibition at the Grand Lisboa Palace Art Gallery. According to the social solidarity institution, the volunteers accompanied the elderly throughout the trip, “demonstrating community solidarity and affection for the elderly population”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>From threatening to “cool!”: How opinions about China changed in Vietnam</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/de-ameacador-fixe-como-opinioes-sobre-china-mudaram-vietname/</link><description>Dozens of young Vietnamese people lined up for hours in September to see “cool” troops march in a huge military parade in Hanoi. But it wasn't their own soldiers they were looking for. It was the Chinese contingent.
The scene reflects a shift in attitude toward China – amid trade tensions with the US – that has allowed Vietnamese leaders to launch sensitive projects such as high-speed rail links and special economic zones near China that could significantly boost bilateral ties.
Just a few years ago, with many Vietnamese wary of a powerful neighbor with which they had fought several wars, these projects were seen as too controversial and caused violent protests. But opinions are softening, as shown by social media posts, online surveys and data on language learning.
Nearly 75% of Vietnamese respondents prefer the US to China as a partner, but the share favoring China is increasing faster than anywhere else in Southeast Asia, bucking the regional trend, according to a survey conducted in early 2025 by the Singapore-based ISEAS – Yusof Ishak Institute.
Social media appears to be playing a crucial role in changing the mood in Vietnam – and in particular, TikTok, which is popular among young people and, in 2024, had 67 million users in Vietnam, the highest number after Facebook, according to the government. When users of the platform owned by Chinese technology giant ByteDance search for the Vietnamese word for China they get extremely positive results, some from 2023.
Among the popular videos suggested by TikTok are clips of Chinese soldiers performing synchronized dances and videos showing Chinese cities, with many viewers expressing admiration for China's rapid development.
TikTok users searching for the Vietnamese name of the South China Sea, a focus of frequent conflict between the two countries, often find clips about tropical storms or tensions between China and the Philippines, which also have claims to parts of the sea, according to tests carried out without user profiles to avoid algorithmic bias.
In September, crowds gathered in Hanoi to celebrate the 80th anniversary of Vietnam's declaration of independence from colonial rule. Tens of thousands crowded the streets, many to watch the Chinese parade. Troops march alongside Vietnamese soldiers - an unprecedented sight in the capital of a country that was last invaded by China in the late 1970s and where major streets are named after anti-Chinese heroes.
"It was worth the wait. Very cool. I admire their discipline," said Le Huyen My, a 22-year-old who traveled from Ho Chi Minh City in the south and camped overnight to secure a spot to watch the Chinese parade.
A video about the parade reached 3.3 million views on TikTok and attracted around 1,400 comments, many praising the “impeccable” march of Chinese soldiers. Similar videos on other platforms also generated positive reactions, although Facebook users were more skeptical about China and the US.
Young Vietnamese online “appear less strident toward China than before, but this is due more to the state's increasingly tighter grip on nationalism than to declining resentment,” said Nguyen Khac Giang of ISEAS.
Online campaigns against China are still rife in Vietnam and often target companies using maps of the South China Sea aligned with Beijing, but they tend to be short-lived.
This marks a change from 2018, when widespread protests against China forced the Vietnamese government to shelve a plan for Special Economic Zones, seen as favorable to Chinese companies. Now, Vietnamese state media frequently report new plans for economic zones on the border with China, without generating protests.
“Economic interests are taking precedence over nationalism,” said Nguyen Hung, an academic at RMIT University in Vietnam, noting that Hanoi has promoted a pragmatic approach towards Beijing, especially as trade tensions with Washington escalate.
Vietnamese data shows that Chinese companies are now among Vietnam's top investors; leaders meet frequently; and interest in Chinese culture is growing. Chinese President Xi Jinping has traveled to Vietnam twice in the past two years, and Vietnamese leader To Lam visited Beijing on his first trip abroad, shortly after being named head of the Communist Party in 2024.
Online searches for China in Vietnam have increased, with a focus on Chinese films and the language, according to Google Trends. In the first quarter of 2025, Vietnam led global registrations for the HSK Chinese Proficiency Test, China's official exam for non-native speakers, according to Chinese state media.
But as China often lives in centuries of ambivalent ties, Vietnamese pride runs deep. “Chinese troops look fascinating, but our soldiers are still the best,” said student Nguyen Hue Van, 21, who attended the parade in Hanoi.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-10-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>