<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Social Security will count domiciles in Hengqin</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/seguranca-social-contabilizara-domicilio-em-hengqin/</link><description>The Executive Council yesterday presented a legislative amendment that aims to include residents who live, study or work in the Deep Cooperation Zone in the counting of days spent in the Macao SAR, within the scope of the Social Security Regime and the non-mandatory central pension regime. Wong Sio Chak also said that the Government intends to extend the sickness benefit scheme to residents living in Hengqin. It is also suggested to “increase, from once to twice a year, the possibility of withdrawing funds from individual accounts of the non-mandatory central pension scheme”
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
The Government intends to extend the Social Security Scheme and the Non-Mandatory Central Pension Scheme to residents who are in the Deep Cooperation Zone living, working or studying, in higher and non-higher education. The idea is to include domicile situations in Hengqin for the purpose of counting the number of days spent in the Macao SAR. The proposed amendment to the law was presented yesterday, at Government Headquarters, by Wong Sio Chak, spokesperson for the Executive Council (EC).
The EC concluded the discussion on this proposed law, which will still be submitted to the Legislative Assembly for consideration and aims to “strengthen the protection of the rights and interests of Macau residents in the Cooperation Zone with regard to the social security regime”, as explained by the Secretary for Administration and Justice. Asked whether this measure would be applied to other cities in the Greater Bay Area, Wong replied that, “for now, the Government is not considering extending this policy to other cities”.
The General Project for the Construction of the In-depth Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin “clearly establishes that the in-depth articulation of the Cooperation Zone with Macau in terms of public services and the social security system will be promoted, with a view to providing Macau residents with more favorable conditions for pursuing studies, employment and entrepreneurship”, said Wong Sio Chak.
According to the chairman of the Social Security Fund (FSS) administration, Chan Pou Wan, “people who do not have 183 days can make a declaration for this”. Chan further explained that the assessment of the counts will be carried out by the Secretary and will then be passed on to the FSS Board of Directors.
Furthermore, expanding “the recognition of medical certificates required for applications for sickness benefits under the social security regime, to cover the Cooperation Zone” is another objective of the Government.
The Executive also intends to “increase, from once to twice a year, the possibility of withdrawing funds from individual accounts of the non-mandatory central pension scheme”, for residents aged at least 65, said Chan Pou Wan.
“Now, with the current law, it is only possible to lift once”, continued the person in charge. "Normally, in the second half of the year, in September, we have money for the social security system. And the resident, after withdrawing the money in the first half, is unable to make the second withdrawal in the second half", he explained.
Asked whether the central welfare regime could become mandatory, as suggested by a recent report from the University of Macau, Chan Pou Wan recalled that the regime “already came into force many years ago”. However, taking into account the post-pandemic economic recovery, “a little time” will be needed to assess the development and recovery of small and medium-sized companies.
“We also have some reference indices to monitor and to see what the level of recovery is, the median salary”, among other parameters, added the person in charge. “These are all elements that we have to consider and we will monitor this situation”, concluded the president of the FSS Board of Directors.
Another legislative change that Wong Sio Chak presented has to do with the elimination of the provisions relating to the mandatory publication, in the Official Bulletin, of “the printed models of the social security regime, and they will now be published on the FSS website”. The intention is “to monitor the development of electronic governance, as well as to add provisions relating to presumptive notification in the social security regime to increase administrative efficiency”, said the EC spokesperson.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ecological Zones continue to attract new species</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/zonas-ecologicas-continuam-atrair-novas-especies/</link><description>Currently, 2,150 species of animals and plants make up the fauna and flora of both COTAI Ecological Zones, 45 more than at the end of 2024, according to data from the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services. New species inhabiting the two areas include new types of insects, fish, amphibians and angiosperms
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
The biodiversity of the COTAI Ecological Zones continues to grow, if we consider that both currently have 2,150 species of animals and plants, 45 more than those recorded at the end of 2024, according to data made available by the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA). These are made up of 785 species of plants and 1,365 of animals.
In terms of flora, 327 species of algae, four of mosses, 22 of ferns, 11 of gymnosperms and 421 of angiosperms are recorded. Compared to those recorded at the end of 2024, eight new species of angiosperms were discovered.
With regard to fauna, the two Ecological Zones together have 143 species of zooplankton, 176 of benthic animals, six of arachnids and 683 of insects. In addition, there are also 119 species of fish, six amphibians, 22 reptiles and 12 mammals. Analyzing the species recorded at the end of 2024, a further 29 types of insects, a new species of fish and another of amphibians were found.
Furthermore, 198 species of birds continue to inhabit the ecological zones as a place to rest or to feed, including the rare bird species black-faced spoonbill, given “the richness of the food resources available there”, can be read on the DSPA website. The black-faced spoonbill is one of the species classified by China as protected.
Completed in 2003, both COTAI Ecological Zones have been managed by a consultancy firm since 2004, which has been collecting data on benthos, plants, birds, water quality and the surrounding environment. The two zones have a combined area of ​​around 55 hectares.
Ecological Zone I is a 15-hectare conditionally open management area located northeast of the Lotus Flower Bridge, with two bird observatories on its southern dike, as well as water shrubs, reed beds and trees, and water channels connected to the Shizimen canal.
Ecological Zone II, an open management area of ​​40 hectares located on the west coast of COTAI and in which mangrove fauna and flora proliferates, has three artificial islands and a walkway for visits. In this area, located north of the Coloane wastewater treatment plant and south of Broadway Macau, DSPA highlights the proliferation of the gray mangrove “Avicennia marina”, “Kandelia obovata” mangrove, “Aegiceras corniculatum”, “Acanthus ilicifolius”, tidal flame and mudskipper.
DSPA states that it has been committed to “optimizing the ecological environment of the Ecological Zones, in order to provide an ideal habitat and food foraging environment for migratory birds that come to spend the winter in Macau”.
Based on the opinions of academics, work has been carried out annually to optimize the banks of Ecological Zone I, outside the bird migration season. These works involve “dredging mud from the channel, removing grass and reeds on the banks of the lake, controlling the growth of reeds and expanding the bank area, as well as improving the environment for shorebirds, benthic animals and fish”.
In recent years, “the number of migratory birds that come to Macau to spend the winter has basically remained at a stable level”, explains DSPA.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Father Áureo Castro remembered in pipe organ concert</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/padre-aureo-castro-lembrado-em-concerto-de-orgao-de-tubos/</link><description>To mark the 33rd anniversary of Father Áureo Castro's death, the Diocese of Macau will hold an inaugural concert with the oldest working pipe organ in Greater China, which was brought to Macau last year. The concert will take place tomorrow at the Church of São Lourenço
 
CATARINA PEREIRA
 
This month marks the 33rd anniversary of the death of Father Áureo Castro and the Diocese of Macau will remember the priest in an inaugural concert on the pipe organ – an instrument that “was originally installed in a chapel of a convent in Cornwall” and which last year was transported to Macau. Built in 1870 by J. W. Walker, it is currently “the oldest working pipe organ in Greater China”.
The concert will take place at the Church of São Lourenço this Wednesday, at 8 pm, with free entry. The program includes choral and organ works by Father Áureo Castro, born in Candelária do Pico (Azores) in January 1917 and who died in 1993 in Macau, where he spent most of his life dedicated to the Church and music.
Taking charge of the concert scheduled for the Church of São Lourenço will be the Perosi Choir, conductor Katrine K. Wong and organist Olga Wong, with accompaniment by Basilla Sam.
Áureo Castro came to Macau at the age of 14 to join the São José Seminary, the year was 1931. At this time, the Seminary recruited students in two parts of Portugal – Freixo de Espada à Cinta and Azores – whose destination would be missionary in China.
In Macau, Father Áureo Castro studied musical theory, solfeggio and harmony with Fathers Wilhelm Schmid and António André Ngan. However, after being ordained a priest in 1943, he ended up serving as a chaplain and vicar at the Cathedral of Macau, as the Chinese communist revolution prevented his move to China.
He was also, later, a parish priest at São Lourenço parish (for which he wrote music for celebrations), and was also a teacher at the Diocesan Seminary (where he taught the subjects of Gregorian Chant, Harmony, Chanting, Polyphonic and Solfeggio), also teaching Choral Singing and Religion and Morals at the Lyceum of Macau and at the Pedro Nolasco Commercial School.
The Academia S. Pio</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Seguro and Ventura guarantee second round and Marques Mendes suffers heavy defeat</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/actual/seguro-ventura-garantem-segunda-volta-marques-mendes-sofre-derrota-pesada/</link><description>epa12659993 Portuguese presidential candidate Antonio Jose Seguro celebrates after advancing to the second round of the presidential elections at his campaign headquarters in Caldas da Rainha, Portugal, 18 January 2026. The runoff is scheduled for 08 February between Seguro and Andre Ventura.  EPA/JOSE COELHO



António José Seguro and André Ventura were the winners of the first round of Sunday's presidential elections, taking part in the dispute on February 8, in an election in which Luís Marques Mendes recorded for the PSD the worst result ever in electoral events.
With 31.1% and around one million 700,000 votes, Seguro will have managed to secure not only the votes of the PS, which he led between 2011 and 2014, but of the overwhelming majority of voters on the left, leaving the candidates supported by Livre, BE and PCP, who in the legislative elections totaled 10%, with a residual vote of around 4%.
The former socialist general secretary was really the big winner of the night, not only because he concentrated the votes of the left, but because he went into the presidential election with adverse polls that almost always placed him behind candidates such as retired admiral Henrique Gouveia e Melo, the first to appear as favorite, or Luís Marques Mendes, who at one point was the best placed in opinion studies.
At the end of the night, Seguro sought to broaden the range of his support for the second round, recovering Mário Soares' maxim and promising that he will be “the President of all Portuguese people” and stating that he received votes “from all political camps”, which “reinforces the independent nature of the candidacy”. “I am free, I live without ties and that is how I will act as President of the Republic”, he emphasized.
"This is the time to defeat fear and raise hope. Our victory on February 8th will be Portugal's victory. The victory of all Portuguese people who love freedom and who love democracy", said Seguro in Caldas da Rainha, where he gave his speech after winning the first round of the elections. "Hope that we will have a better future. Hope in a Portugal that values ​​work and merit, that leaves no one behind, that treats women and men equally, that takes care of our elderly and invests in our young people", he stressed.
André Ventura was the other winner of the election night, despite having missed the objective of victory in the first round reiterated in the electoral campaign. With 23.5% and around one million and 300 thousand votes, Ventura apparently managed to retain Chega's electorate in the last legislative elections (1.43 million votes) and go into the second round to claim the role of leader of the right in Portugal.
“I will join the right from today onwards”, repeated Ventura during election night, taking advantage of the gap opened by the social democratic leader and Prime Minister, Luís Montenegro, who wasted no time in indicating that “the PSD will not issue any voting indication” in the second round of the presidential elections and “will not be involved in the campaign”.
"I wanted to give the country this message: don't be afraid of change. A few months ago, the country suffered a huge political shock, in the legislative elections. We have improved since then, we haven't done everything, but in immigration, taxes, nationality, we have taken steps. What I want to ask you all now is to trust me", appealed Ventura.
In the confrontation scheduled for February 8, António José Seguro will present himself with the support of the PS and the entire left against André Ventura, who despite claiming leadership of the right, will only have the support of Chega. Regardless of the parties, many figures are expected to assume options for the second round, as happened with the former social-democratic minister Miguel Poiares Maduro, on RTP, and José Pacheco Pereira, on TVI, both expressing support for António José Seguro, as well as the president of the Porto City Council, Pedro Duarte, former minister of Parliamentary Affairs in the first government of Luís Montenegro. PAN – People-Animais-Natureza has also decided to support Seguro’s candidacy “at a decisive moment for Portuguese democracy”.
João Cotrim Figueiredo, former leader of the Liberal Initiative, despite having almost tripled his party's result in the last legislative elections, had a bittersweet night, as he failed his main objective of contesting the second round, obtaining 16% of the votes.
After a campaign that was almost always growing, although with two embarrassing moments – when he admitted supporting Ventura in the second round and when he was accused of sexual harassment by a former IL advisor – Cotrim always had hope in the second round, a hypothesis that would come to an end on election night. Despite having admitted to supporting Ventura during the campaign, Cotrim Figueiredo followed Luís Montenegro's lead and announced that he would not endorse the vote for the second round of the presidential elections.
Luís Marques Mendes was the main loser of the night, taking into account that he was the candidate supported by the coalition that supports the Government, PSD and CDS-PP, and came in first place in the polls. But the former Social Democratic minister came in fifth, with 11.3% and just over 630,000 votes, although in the most disputed presidential election ever, with 11 candidates. “The responsibility is mine, all mine and mine alone”, assumed Marques Mendes, who also decided not to support any candidate in the second round.
Henrique Gouveia e Melo, the retired admiral who was seen by commentators as a future President when he appeared prominently in the polls, came in fourth place, with 12.3% and just under 700 thousand votes. Gouveia e Melo admitted that the results fell short of their objectives, but warned that the country will continue to count on their “civic participation”.
The parties to the left of the PS – Livre, PCP and BE – also suffered a heavy defeat, whose candidates Jorge Pinto, António Filipe and Catarina Martins did not exceed a residual vote, which altogether was 4%. Catarina Martins obtained 2%, António Filipe 1.6% and Jorge Pinto 0.6%, the latter with less votes than musician Manuel João Vieira (1.08%).
 
International press highlights socialist and radical right “surprise”
The confrontation in the second round between the socialist surprise, António José Seguro, and a far-right or radical candidate, André Ventura, was highlighted in the international press, which also highlighted the defeat of Luís Marques Mendes.
In an article with the title “The socialist Seguro and the radical Ventura will compete in the second round of the Presidential elections in Portugal”, the Spanish El País highlights how António José Seguro, “retired from politics in the last ten years” and “without much initial support in his own party”, came in first place “against all odds and almost against everyone”, setting up a confrontation in the second round with “the radical right candidate, André Ventura”.
The defeat of Luís Marques Mendes, who came in fifth, is classified by the newspaper as “a major setback” for the candidate supported by the Prime Minister, with the also Spanish La Vanguardia even speaking of a “hard blow” for Luís Montenegro, explainable, among other aspects, by the “candidate’s weakness”, due to “his obscure role as a high-flying lobbyist”.
For the periodical, Seguro is, “unless a catastrophe arises”, “the virtual new president of Portugal”, after “20 years of conservative mandates” and in a country turned “further to the right than ever”.
The Spanish El Mundo also anticipates that the candidate supported by the PS will be the next President of Portugal, by concentrating the vote against the extreme right, without failing to highlight André Ventura's words that “the fight will now be between socialism and non-socialism”.
In France, Le Monde also highlights the confrontation in the second round between the socialist and the far-right candidate, while the Belgian Le Soir points out that the latter was not, after all, “the big winner of election night”.
Politico, dedicated to covering European Union affairs, speaks of a “surprise victory” for the center-left in the first round of the presidential elections, noting that Ventura’s ability “to secure almost a quarter” of the votes is revealing of “how extraordinary” Chega’s growth has been in Portugal.
 
Null votes surpassed white votes and abstention registered a sharp decline
For the first time in presidential elections since the 25th of April, the null vote surpassed the blank vote, in elections in which the ballots had the highest number of candidates ever and three names that were not approved. In the national territory, there were 64,817 invalid votes and 60,899 blank votes, which correspond to increases of 62% and 23%, respectively, in relation to the 2021 elections, the year of Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa's re-election. In the 2021 elections, there were seven candidates (the same ones that appeared on the ballot papers) and, nationwide, invalid votes represented 0.94% (39,854 votes), while white votes were 1.1% (46,862). According to provisional official data, the abstention rate reached 47.7%, 13.1 points less than in 2021.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Marques Mendes won in Macau with 45% of the votes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/marques-mendes-ganhou-em-macau-45-dos-votos/</link><description>The results obtained at the two polling stations in Macau for the Portuguese presidential elections gave victory to Luís Marques Mendes, with 1,073 votes, which means 45.2% of the 2,374 ballots entered at the polls. António José Seguro, the winning candidate in Portugal, was second in the Macao SAR, with 477 votes (20.09%), followed by André Ventura, with 282 (11.9%). For the representative of Insurance in Macau, Jorge Neto Valente, the candidate he supports “does not propose to dismantle the system, nor does he intend to destroy the constitution”. António Bessa Almeida, representative of Marques Mendes, said that the victory in Macau “was easy”, resulting from the “good work done”

VÍTOR REBELO
 
Luís Marques Mendes was the candidate for the Portuguese presidential elections with the most votes in Macau, having totaled 1,073 votes. This number represents 45.2% of the total number of votes (2,374) entered into the ballot boxes at the two tables installed at the Consulate General of Portugal for Macau and Hong Kong.
Marques Mendes, former member of the Government and who received the support of the Social Democratic Party (PSD) – the most representative political force in the Democratic Alliance, which won the elections in Macau for the Portuguese legislature in 2024 – obtained in the territory more than double the votes achieved by the second placed candidate, António José Seguro. The former general secretary of the Socialist Party (PS) received 477 votes (20.09%).
André Ventura, leader of Chega, obtained 282 votes (11.9%), placing him ahead of João Cotrim de Figueiredo (191 votes – 8%), Henrique Gouveia e Melo (133 – 5.6%) and Catarina Martins (128 – 5.4%). Among the remaining five candidates, Manuel Vieira received 39 votes (1.6%), ahead of António Filipe (20 – 0.8%), André Pestana da Silva (14 – 0.6%), Eduardo Costa Pinto (12 – 0.5%) and Humberto Correia (5 – 0.2%).
In Macau, there were still 24 blank votes (1%) and 66 invalid votes (2.8%). Altogether, the percentage of both points to 3.8%.
The elections on Saturday and Sunday in Macau recorded a participation rate of 4.1%, taking into account that 57,748 voters were registered. In 2021, during the pandemic, the rate stood at around 2%.
The notice with the results was only posted in the main atrium of the Consulate yesterday morning, at 9 am, when the facilities opened to the public, unlike what had happened in previous elections, both for the Presidency and for the formation of the Assembly of the Republic, when the outcome was officially known and posted a few hours after the polls closed. Consul Alexandre Leitão told TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper on Sunday night that the decision had to do with the closing of the polls in the Azores, which occurred at around 4 am, Macau time.
Yesterday morning, the diplomat said that the voting process took place “normally, without any incident”. Asked about the reason for the somewhat long waiting time (up to 45 minutes) to vote on the first day, Saturday, he expressed that “this is a consequence of the much higher increase in participation”, which has been rising from election to election, and also a sign of “vitality” in democracy.
Regarding the greater fluidity in the queues on Sunday, Alexandre Leitão explained that there was an “adaptation” of the tables to the flow of voters, that is, whenever a table was overloaded with people, voters moved to the other room.
For the second round, the consul confirmed that there will be two voting days again, on the 7th and 8th of February, at the same times, from 8:00 am to 7:00 pm. Before that, and for three days, there will be early voting for voters who are not registered in Macau and who, for whatever reason, cannot vote in their places of origin. “They do not need to register or register for this purpose”, he informed, adding that “the date for the early election will be announced soon”.
 
Insurance “capable” of uniting the Portuguese
Jorge Neto Valente, representative of António José Seguro's campaign in Macau, began by devaluing the fact that Marques Mendes had obtained the highest number of votes in the territory. “Macau has specificities, leading many people to vote more from a partisan perspective”, he highlighted, stating that the voters who chose António José Seguro “are on the right side of history”.
The lawyer, who had already been the local representative of the campaigns of Mário Soares and Jorge Sampaio, considers that Seguro, “who received votes from several quarters and not just from one party, the PS”, is the only candidate “capable of uniting the Portuguese, because he does not feed extremism, does not feed hatred and is the only one with government experience, although in these elections no party leader is being chosen”.
The important thing, he reinforces, “is that people think carefully about the difference between the two candidates who occupied the first two places in the elections and who, therefore, will discuss the second round”. Insurance “does not propose to dismantle the system, does not intend to destroy the constitution, and can, as he said on election night, take care of what is good and improve what is bad, but he is loyal to the constitution, that is fundamental”, he stressed.
Regarding the voters' stance for the second round, Jorge Neto Valente says that “Ventura has a very high rejection rate”, therefore, he believes that “it will not increase much in relation to this vote”.
Given the difference in votes recorded in the first vote, he believes that this should be enough for Seguro to emerge victorious and be the next President of the Portuguese Republic. “I believe that the voters who voted for the other candidates will use their useful vote and choose António José Seguro, who is a statesman, a free man, capable of representing Portugal with dignity abroad and domestically, and above all on international stages”, he emphasized.
As for André Ventura, he considers that he is “a good party leader for his ideas, he is an individual who mobilizes people to encourage hatred and extremism, which is easier than pushing for moderation”. This candidate, he continues, “has never had government experience, unlike Seguro who has not been in the Government for 10 years and therefore cannot be held responsible for any government action in recent years”.
In turn, António Bessa Almeida, representative of Luís Marques Mendes' campaign, declared that the local victory of the candidate he supported was “awesome” and is the result of “the work carried out in favor of the Macau PSD”. Above all, he emphasizes, it results from “the work of our community, which is done with maximum respect and transparency”.
Regarding electoral participation in the territory, he considers that there was good participation from residents, who “fulfilled their right to vote”.
Analyzing the general outcome of the first round of elections for the Portuguese presidency, Bessa Almeida states that, “if there is a clear winner”, as happened with Seguro, “the elections could and should stop here”. Once “everything is defined”, a new round “will waste time and money”, he reflected.
In assessing the support he provided to Luís Marques Mendes' candidacy, the president said he had “worked hard”. “The fight was worth it and for that I am satisfied”, he confessed.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Executive intends to speed up licenses for small works</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/executivo-pretende-agilizar-licencas-para-pequenas-obras/</link><description>Safety helmet hats, blueprint paper project, measure tape, gloves, and worker dress on concrete floor at modern city with blurred people. Engineer and construction equipment with copy space for text.



The Government intends to facilitate the issuance of licenses for the construction of small-sized non-housing units, as announced yesterday by the Executive Council. Furthermore, the bill presented by Wong Sio Chak also intends to exempt demolitions of illegal works from license requests, as well as work on public transport infrastructure and classified properties.
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
The Executive Council (EC) concluded the discussion on the amendment to the “Legal regime for urban construction” and intends to speed up the granting of licenses for works on autonomous non-housing units, whose gross area of ​​use does not exceed 120 square meters, the organization's spokesperson announced yesterday. Within the scope of the proposed law presented by Wong Sio Chak, if license requests “are submitted electronically, prior communication will be immediately admitted and the preliminary work license will be issued”, also allowing work to begin on the day immediately following issuance.
It is recalled that the Executive carried out work to review the regime, in December, to “improve legislation, simplify essential procedures, in order to increase administrative efficiency, facilitate services provided to sectors and the population, promote the healthy development of the construction sector”.
“As long as the works are not large-scale or not very complex, they do not require prior communication or license,” said Lai Weng Leong, director of Land and Urban Construction Services (DSSCU).
The legal diploma, which will still be evaluated by the Legislative Assembly (AL), also includes sanctioning provisions “in the event of inaccurate or erroneous information being provided”, warned Wong Sio Chak. "Through electronic presentation, in fact, the businessman has the duty to provide true information. Otherwise, he must be subject to the sanction regime", added Lai Weng Leong.
"The electronic platform has some printed models, forms, for suppliers and technicians to fill in. These interested parties have a duty to provide truthful information", reiterated the director of DSSCU. "If there are any errors, your prior notice and license application will also be revoked. Sanctions are applied in accordance with the administrative offense regime," Lai warned.
In addition to adjustments to the sanctioning regime, the legislative proposal also introduces new measures to protect urban legality and forms of notification.
The Government also intends that “illegal works of relatively low risk” can be demolished without licensing or prior communication, in an effort to encourage the demolition of illegal constructions by citizens.
Another of the proposed legal provisions refers to “extending the scope of application of the licensing exemption, covering modification, conservation and repair works to be carried out in airport facilities, public maritime passenger terminals or the light rail system by the entities responsible for their respective operation”, said the EC spokesperson.
At the same time, work carried out by Government bodies on real estate classified, or in the process of being classified, in protection zones, including provisional ones, may also be exempt from licensing, “without prejudice to the continued compliance with the provisions set out” in the “Cultural Heritage Safeguarding Law”.
The allocation of police officers to buildings, the responsibility of the Institute for Municipal Affairs, will now be carried out by DSSCU. Lai Weng Leong predicted that this change will be effective from June 1, adding that this provision still depends on the Law on Restaurant and Beverage Activities and Related Establishments, currently under consideration in the AL.
The last point covered by the EC proposal concerns the issuance of urban conditions covered by the detailed plan. The conditions will now appear in the extract from the detailed plan, instead of the urban conditions plan.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DSAMA granted 863 thousand patacas to the Fishermen's Association</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dsama-concedeu-863-mil-patacas-a-associacao-de-pescadores/</link><description>In 2025, DSAMA granted support to just one association linked to fishing, worth 863 thousand patacas. The money was used, for example, to collect garbage, for tours to promote fishing culture and for the development of the fishing community
 
The Macau Fishermen's Mutual Aid Association was the only one to receive support from the Maritime and Water Affairs Bureau (DSAMA) over the past year. In total, the organization led by Susana Wong granted around 863 thousand patacas to this association in 2025, according to data published on the Platform for public disclosure of financial support information.
It was between October and December that the association received the highest amount, 459,840 patacas, distributed in two tranches, one of 389,840 patacas, intended to support the domestic waste collection plan and surveillance of fishing vessels during the fishing closed period. The second part of the amount (70,000 patacas) was used to support activities related to the promotion of Macau's fishing culture, namely the “Fishing Culture Route” program.
During this period, DSAMA also donated 4,760 patacas to the Ou Mun Newspaper Readers' Charity Fund, for the “Charity March for One Million”.
In the first quarter of last year, the Fishermen's Mutual Aid Association received 129,195 patacas to “reduce pollution on the sea surface in the Inner Port, prevent safety accidents on fishing vessels and provide support for the sustainable development of the fishing community”, under the financial support plan for domestic waste collection and surveillance of fishing vessels.
Between April and June, DSAMA granted the same association 200,000 patacas, and between July and September it was 73,798 patacas. In both cases, the amount was used for the “Sea Tour during the fishing closed period”, included in activities related to the promotion of fishing culture in the territory.
 
Surveillance in the Inner Harbor
Meanwhile, to ensure the maritime safety of the Inner Harbor during the Lunar New Year, DSAMA, and other public services and associations, such as the Fishermen's Mutual Aid Association and the Ocean Fisheries and Boat Owners' Development Association, met to discuss the implementation of a contingency plan.
Given that a greater number of vessels will remain in Macau between the 8th and 22nd of February, DSAMA will mobilize vessels to ensure permanent surveillance, 24 hours a day, in the Inner Harbor, “maintaining maritime order and reinforcing the ability to respond to incidents”.
At the same time, it will increase fishermen's awareness of safety rules at the anchorage, through inspections, visits and communication groups. More vessels and workers will also be deployed to intensify inspections before and after the Lunar New Year to ensure the safety of fishermen.
It should be noted that the provisions on fishing vessels moored in the anchorage and on the jetties of Porto Inner establish limits, for example, on the maximum number of fishing vessels anchored side by side in the same group and on the amount of storage of flammable and explosive products. In addition, fishing vessels must complete an electronic berthing declaration in the Inner Port.
On the other hand, to keep the sea clean, DSAMA will mobilize more workers to remove pollutants and collect debris at sea. Collaboration will also be maintained with the Fishermen's Mutual Aid Association, which ensures the distribution and periodic collection of garbage bags on board vessels, the organization said in a statement.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Updated rules for guides and travel agencies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/actualizadas-regras-para-guias-agencias-de-viagens/</link><description>When the Law on the activity of travel agencies and the profession of tourist guide comes into force, on February 1st, there will also be an administrative regulation, which updates some rules. As for travel agencies, the value of the deposit and insurance coverage will increase. As far as guides are concerned, the changes have to do with training courses
 
The draft administrative regulation of the Law on the activity of travel agencies and the profession of tourist guide has already been discussed by the Executive Council. Since the tourism industry “has undergone major changes” in recent years, and taking into account that the current legal regime came into force more than 20 years ago, a complete review and amendment of the legislation was carried out, which has already resulted in the promulgation of the Law on the activity of travel agencies and the profession of tourist guide, which will come into force on February 1st, the day on which the regulation also begins to be implemented.
Taking into account that the amount of the deposit to be provided by travel agencies and the amount of professional civil liability insurance coverage have not been adjusted since 1998, the administrative regulation now changes these aspects. On the one hand, to “strengthen the protection of insurance beneficiaries” the amount covered was increased from the current 700,000 patacas to a minimum of one million patacas. On the other hand, the value of the deposit increases from 500,000 to 600,000 patacas.
At the conference to present the regulation, the director of Tourism Services, Helena de Senna Fernandes, indicated that, by the end of 2025, there were 197 travel agencies in the territory.
The regulation also updates the provisions relating to academic qualifications or professional training for technical directors. It will be necessary to complete a higher education course in the field of tourism, taught by a higher education institution in the MSAR or by a non-local higher education institution that is recognized by the Macau Tourism University (UTM). As for professional training, it must be in the area of ​​tourism, provided by UTM and lasting no less than 30 hours.
To “guarantee the quality of tourist guides”, the minimum requirement for additional secondary education as academic qualifications is maintained. Regarding professional training, if a tour guide has already completed a higher education course in the area of ​​tourism, in the Macao SAR or abroad, but from an institution recognized by UTM, “they only need to complete a complementary course to exercise the profession of tour guide taught by UTM, lasting no less than 102 hours”.
If you do not have higher education as academic qualifications, you will have to complete the training course for the profession of tourist guide taught by UTM, lasting no less than 150 hours.
The knowledge update course for tourist guides was also “optimized”, and must be taught by UTM and last no less than 3.5 hours.
According to Helena de Senna Fernandes, by the end of last year, there were 1,851 licensed guides in the Macao SAR. “But it’s just a number, what I want to say is that, even if they have a license, they may or may not practice this profession”, he stressed. However, he added, with the entry into force of the new law, all travel agencies will have to make statistical data available to the DST database, so authorities “will be able to master more data about the guides they are working”.
 
Associations stop nominating members of the Sports Council
On the same day, the Executive Council also concluded the discussion on the draft administrative regulation relating to the Organization and functioning of the Judiciary Police and another related to the Sports Council. The latter reduces the total number of Council members from 30 to a maximum of 25, eliminating two vice-presidents of the Sports Institute and increasing the representatives, from one to two, from those involved in Paralympic sport and the Special Olympics.
On the other hand, instead of having as members representatives from the sporting world appointed by associations and the Chief Executive, only the Chief Executive now nominates a maximum of 16 individuals of recognized merit in the sporting world.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Government is defining standards for materials in shipyards</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-esta-definir-normas-para-materiais-nos-estaleiros/</link><description>Various Government bodies are defining “optimized standards and mechanisms” relating to “materials applied in shipyards, inspections and enforcement actions”, indicated the director of DSAL, following the major fire in Hong Kong. Chan Un Tong also ensures that the procedure for monitoring the fire reaction requirements of protective scaffolding nets used on construction sites is rigorous.
 
CATARINA PEREIRA
 
After the huge fire that broke out in Tai Po, Hong Kong, at the end of November, the Macao SAR authorities have been working to reinforce security in this camp. Currently, the Government is proceeding, through interdepartmental meetings, “to define optimized standards and mechanisms relating to materials used in shipyards, inspections and monitoring actions”, said the director of the Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), Chan Un Tong.
Recently, the authorities had also indicated that the Fire Department (CB), in addition to purchasing rescue vehicles, was developing “a specific contingency plan for large fires”.
In response to a question from deputy Kou Ngon Seng, the director of the organization said that, in order to monitor compliance with the fire reaction requirements of scaffolding protective nets used on construction sites, DSAL, with other government bodies, recently carried out joint inspections at all construction sites, having carried out verification of the fire reaction performance of the nets.
During the procedure, the contractors were then asked to present the network quality certificates and carry out in situ flammability tests. Furthermore, “samples were collected for analysis by a third party, to ensure that the fire response performance of the networks met the criteria”, it can be read.
In the context of the special verification of scaffolding protection networks, continuously conducted by DSAL and other services, “whenever there is a lack of presentation by the contractors of quality certificates, the non-compliance with the results of the in situ flammability tests or the non-conformity of the samples sent for analysis and evaluation by a third party, DSAL will require the contractors to immediately dismantle them and acquire others that meet the fire reaction requirements”, guarantees Chan Un Tong.
The new networks, in turn, will be subject to a new collection of samples for analysis and evaluation by a third party, and may only be used after approval.
In the same response, it is said that the CB, in addition to acting at the request of the services or following complaints regarding situations that could put fire safety at risk, the CB also proactively defines inspection plans. Still in the works assessment phase, the Directorate of Land and Urban Construction Services only approves and issues the work license “after confirming that the execution project fully complies with the safety and fire protection requirements”.
In inspection actions, in turn, contractors and management engineers are required to strictly comply with the instructions issued by the competent services, with a view to the effective implementation of fire protection and safety standards when carrying out works.
“If it is found that the existing construction materials at the construction site do not meet the specifications, the Public Works Services Department will require the contractor to immediately dismantle them and remove all non-conforming materials from the construction site, subsequently determining responsibilities and applying the appropriate sanctions, in accordance with current legislation and contractual clauses”, assures Chan Un Tong.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Serious lack” of prison guards worries Chan Hao Weng</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/grave-falta-de-guardas-prisionais-inquieta-chan-hao-weng/</link><description>Deputy Chan Hao Weng warned that, this month and next, “dozens of employees” at the Macau prison will retire, including deputy chiefs and main guards. In these circumstances, he is concerned about the deterioration of the “serious lack of human resources in the prison guards”, also pointing to problems such as the “serious disarticulation between duties and categories” and “excessive work intensity”.
 
The Macau Prison “is facing a crisis linked to the serious lack of human resources in the prison guards, a situation that will deteriorate drastically with the wave of retirements about to begin”, warned Chan Hao Weng.
In a written interpellation, the deputy stated that he knows that, only this month and in February, “dozens of employees” at the prison will retire, including deputy chiefs and main guards.
As he warned, in these circumstances, some basic career police officers “have already been forced to take on higher-level supervisory responsibilities, without having due training and authorization”. Thus, in the context of the “serious disarticulation between duties and categories”, the agents in question have to “face the risk of unreasonable joint liability”.
Furthermore, the deputy pointed the finger at the “excessive intensity of work” among prison guards. Citing “complaints received from frontline staff,” Chan Hao Weng lamented that rotating prison guards have no public holidays or statutory holidays and only enjoy four or five days of compensatory rest a year.
For the deputy, the current three-shift mechanism leads to high turnover among staff, which, in addition to involving security risks, fails to alleviate the shortage of labor.
Chan Hao Weng also stressed that, currently, prison staff cannot choose vacations freely, with there being cases where frontline staff were forced to take vacations at short notice without receiving prior notice. On the other hand, he criticized the 45-minute meal time for prison staff, who consider this duration to be short, especially because it includes travel to and from work and security inspection.
In view of the problems identified, the deputy linked to the Public Service Workers' Association asked the Government whether it already has specific plans to be adopted soon to respond to the crisis. At the same time, it wants the correlations between the career promotion mechanism and the real demand for jobs to be clarified, ensuring that responsibilities, training and categories are compatible.
On the other hand, Chan defended the optimization of shift and rest mechanisms for prison guards, in order to protect the physical and mental health of staff and increase the attractiveness of the profession. Specifically, citing “frontline staff”, he called for the adoption of a shift mechanism under the model of “24 hours of work and 48 hours of rest”, the voluntary selection of holidays and extended meal times.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Caregiver allowance increases this month</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/subsidio-para-cuidadores-sobe-este-mes/</link><description>The Government announced that the allowance for caregivers will increase this month, with the eligibility criteria being expanded. According to the Social Action Institute, the maximum household monthly income limit will also be increased and applications submitted by residents living in Hengqin will be accepted.
 
The increase in the value of the allowance for caregivers, foreseen in the Government Action Lines (LAG) for 2026, will take effect from this month, the Government announced yesterday. According to the Institute of Social Action (IAS), the “maximum limit on the total monthly income of the household” will also be increased and “requests submitted by Macao SAR residents living in the Deep Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin” will be accepted.
Remember that, in the presentation of the LAG for this year, the Executive had announced that support for caregivers would increase from 2,175 to 2,400 patacas, corresponding to an increase of 10.34%. Furthermore, he added that “the eligibility criteria would be expanded”.
The mechanism now covers people with severe or profound intellectual disabilities and people with these disabilities, but without a degree assigned because they are under four years of age, as well as people with severe or profound mental disabilities (limited to autism and primary mental disorder) and with severe or profound motor disabilities, such as bedridden people who are unable to sit and stand up without assistance, due to functional incapacity.
According to an order from the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture published yesterday in the Official Bulletin, and which is in force from today, whenever there is any change in the economic situation or composition of the household, the housing situation, the health of the beneficiary, as well as the loss of capacity or conditions of the caregiver or their replacement, “the beneficiary, the caregiver or another member of the household must communicate this circumstance to the IAS, using a specific form, within 15 days”.
The application forms as well as the respective subsidy award regulations can be downloaded from the IAS website from today. For additional information, interested parties may contact the IAS by telephone or email.
For requests made for people with intellectual, mental or motor disabilities, the IAS Rehabilitation Services Division must be contacted. On the other hand, for requests relating to permanently bedridden people who are unable to sit and stand up without assistance, those responsible should contact the IAS Division of Services for the Elderly.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IIM launches book on drug consumption crime</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/iim-lanca-livro-sobre-crime-de-consumo-de-drogas/</link><description>The book “Crime of Drug Consumption in Macau”, by lawyer David Sá Machado, who has dedicated himself to the study of Law and the legal reality of Macau, will be presented on January 30th, at 6:30 pm, in the auditorium of the International Institute of Macau (IIM). The book is part of the line of research that the author has been developing, seeking to reconcile academic rigor with practical utility for lawyers, magistrates, students and anyone interested in the legal reality of Macau, says the press release. The bilingual work “offers a critical and didactic look at simple and qualified consumer crimes, including considerations about drug trafficking and production, going through a dogmatic, legal and jurisprudential framework of these norms and also an approach at procedural and criminal policy levels”. Furthermore, “a small approach” is made to the reality of consumption in Macau, within and outside the legal context. Drug consumption is a topic that falls within a classic area of ​​Criminal Law, “whose importance and challenges in judicial practice are increasingly greater today”, adds the statement. The session features presentations by the author, Vasco Fong and Helena Ng, collaborators involved in this edition, Augusto Nogueira, president of the Macau Drug Rehabilitation Association (ARTM), and moderated by António Monteiro, general secretary of IIM. The launch has the support of ARTM, and the collaboration “underlines the importance of combining academic research and community intervention, promoting an integrated approach to the phenomenon of drug addiction and its legal and social implications”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Recycled water tariffs defined</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/definidas-tarifas-da-agua-reciclada/</link><description>The “fees and tariffs for the public water supply service” have already been defined, having been published yesterday in the Official Bulletin. As has already been reported, the usage tariff per cubic meter of recycled water is 85% of the drinking water tariff for each type of user. According to the published table, the price is 3.81 patacas per cubic meter of water consumed in residential areas, 5.13 patacas for general non-residential water consumption and 6.59 patacas for special water consumption. The Directorate of Maritime Affairs and Water Services (DSAMA) states that the values ​​were defined in this way “to ensure that precious water resources are not wasted” and taking into account the “whoever uses it pays” principle, meaning that the tariff for using recycled water is calculated based on the tariff for using drinking water established for each type of user. However, in the case of residential water consumption, the recycled water tariff is not calculated by consumption brackets, but only according to the first bracket of the drinking water usage tariff. In a statement, DSAMA also indicates that the Coloane Recycled Water Station will come into operation shortly, after the completion of the work, planning to supply recycled water to the Seac Pai Van public housing and the University of Macau from March 1. On the water invoice issued by the Macau Water Supply Society, the volume and price of drinking water and recycled water will be detailed.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Meteorizations” by Filipa César in Serralves reflects on colonial echoes of Guinea-Bissau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/meteorizacoes-de-filipa-cesar-em-serralves-reflecte-sobre-ecos-coloniais-da-guine-bissau/</link><description>The elements of water, earth, air and fire are the guiding thread of “Meteorizações”, Filipa César's first anthological exhibition opened in Serralves, Porto, summoning Guinea-Bissau's colonial past and echoes in the present.
“We had to find a way to organize all these works and we thought about organizing them through the elements [water, earth, air, fire]”, explained Filipa César, during a visit to the press, about her first major anthological exhibition at the Serralves Museum, in Porto.
In the first room of the exhibition, “Meteorizações” is dedicated to water and the visitor is surrounded by the sounds of running water, which Filipa César explains is the flow of the Trancoso River intertwining with the voices of people from the “mangrove schools”. “Mangrove schools” are spaces that promote environmental education and community development focused on the protection and restoration of mangroves in Guinea-Bissau.
“The water room summons many flows, from passersby across the Trancoso River, like the mangrove schools in Guinea-Bissau, as well as an excerpt from a film with Marinho de Pina [Guinean storyteller], about the conflicts that we [Filipa and Pina] had in the processes of these collaborative works”, describes the artist born in 1975.
The exhibition route takes the visitor to a new room that summons the Earth element. It is in that space that, for example, images of Amílcar Cabral (1924-1973) appear in another film. Amílcar Cabral, politician and agronomist born in Bafatá, Guinea, under Portuguese colonial rule, led the struggle for the liberation and independence of Guinea-Bissau and Cape Verde.
“He was very interested in soil as a historical body”, said the artist about the co-founder of the African Party for the Independence of Guinea and Cape Verde.
The title of the exhibition – “Meteorizations” – refers to a notion originating from geology, reinterpreted by Amílcar Cabral, who understands the earth “as a product of natural forces and historical and political dynamics in permanent mutation”, reads the press dossier.
“It was from there that I developed many research texts, films that start from this common principle of a soil as an inscribed body and what I called agropoetics, which is this research relationship, but the soil as a starting point to think about the possibilities and conditions of the earth in relation to the humanity that inhabits it”, adds Filipa César.
Filipa César has been investigating the practice of militant cinema and the agropoetics of the African liberation movement in Guinea-Bissau - that is, in the context of the political and social movements that fought for the decolonization of Africa -, through the production of workshops, texts, films, performances, publications and community meetings.
The exhibition route has two other rooms. In the one dedicated to the air, “to thoughts and ideas”, there is a weaving collection and several questions about ‘panu di pinti’, a traditional handmade fabric from Guinea-Bissau.
The ‘panu di pinti’ “inscribes many questions that connect us and that bring up the issue of Creole as a place of meeting, union and transformation and not a space of separation”, highlights Filipa César.
There is also a room dedicated to the element of fire, where you can see a film and installation that explore how optical technologies of military and colonial design – from Fresnel lenses in lighthouses to global satellite navigation systems – inform and are informed by Western models of knowledge, adopting a critical approach to the ideologies behind the development of these guidance and surveillance instruments.
The entire exhibition route has films, several books (some were banned in Portugal during Salazar's dictatorship), documents and unpublished materials, from initial works such as “The Embassy” (2011), to more recent productions by the artist.
The anthological exhibition reveals a continuous process of research over the last 15 years, said Filipa César, highlighting that it is not only made by herself, but in collaboration with researchers, filmmakers and local communities, including a close collaboration with the Guinean director Sana na N´Hada, who filmed the guerrilla and was responsible for the National Institute of Cinema and Audiovisual of Guinea-Bissau.
It is an exhibition that “builds transversal relationships between different times, supports and contexts”, inviting “the public to think critically about the colonial past and its effects on the present”.
The presentation text highlights “films, objects and documents that evoke historical events such as Portuguese anti-fascist disobedience and Guinean anti-colonial resistance”, in a journey that crosses “audiovisual archives from the period of liberation struggles, reflections on mangroves, optics and weaving policies, and the agropoetic thought of Amílcar Cabral”.
The exhibition, produced by the Serralves Foundation, is curated by Inês Grosso, chief curator of the Museum, and Paula Nascimento. The exhibition also includes a new publication, designed by Bárbara Says and coordinated by Amarante Abramovici, bringing together an archive of essays, conversations and correspondence that accompanied the research process over the last 15 years.
Filipa César is a filmmaker, educator and community organizer and, since 2011, has been collectively investigating the practice of militant cinema.
The “Meteorização” exhibition will be on display in Serralves until May 31st.
 
JTM/Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>