<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Rocha Vieira, the last Governor, who had “Macau in his heart” has died</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/morreu-rocha-vieira-ultimo-governador-tinha-macau-coracao/</link><description>








Vasco Rocha Vieira morreu aos 85 anos, em Portugal. O último Governador de Macau há-de ficar para sempre na memória de muitos, com a bandeira portuguesa ao peito, a poucas horas da transferência de soberania, em 1999. Na última visita ao território, o General dizia ter “Macau no coração” e mostrava-se “optimista” quanto ao futuro do território. Ao Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU, várias personalidades enalteceram o seu papel no processo de transição e recordaram-no como um homem que “dedicou muito da sua vida a Macau”. Disseram ainda ter perdido “um grande amigo”



















CATARINA PEREIRA E VÍTOR REBELO
 
A imagem do General Vasco Rocha Vieira com a bandeira de Portugal junto ao coração, em 19 de Dezembro de 1999, a poucas horas da transferência de Macau para a República Popular da China, há-de ficar para sempre na memória de muitos. “Senti que não era eu que estava ali. Eram muitas gerações. Senti que era um momento que representava séculos de história. Que representava o esforço e a vida de gerações e gerações de portugueses”, descreveu, no livro “Todos os Portos a que Cheguei”. Na memória, ficam também os nove anos que Rocha Vieira esteve à frente do Palácio da Praia Grande, num período decisivo para o território. O último Governador de Macau morreu ontem em Portugal, aos 85 anos. Deixa a esposa, Leonor Rocha Vieira, com quem casou em Lisboa em 1976, e três filhos.
Nascido em Lagoa, Portugal, a 16 de Agosto de 1939, Vasco Joaquim Rocha Vieira era filho de João da Silva Vieira e de Maria Vieira Rocha. Passou a maior parte da infância além-fronteiras: com um ano, foi para Moçambique, onde permaneceu até aos 10. Seguiu depois para Portugal, tendo sido aluno do Colégio Militar, em Lisboa.
Ocupou muitos cargos ao longo da carreira, até que, em 1991 foi nomeado Governador de Macau pelo Presidente Mário Soares, tendo sido confirmado no cargo em 1996, após a eleição do novo Presidente, Jorge Sampaio. Rocha Vieira tomou posse como Governador a 23 de Abril de 1991. Macau, lugar a Oriente onde já tinha estado em comissão serviço nos anos 1970, passou a ser casa.
Como Governador, foi responsável por um vasto programa que teve como intuito o reforço da identidade própria de Macau, a consolidação da sua autonomia e a promoção do território como plataforma regional, com um papel específico, naquela altura e para o futuro, nas relações da China com o exterior. Sob a sua administração, Macau assistiu, nos últimos anos, ao reforço do sistema político local e do Estado de Direito, nomeadamente através da consolidação do sistema judicial, à reforma do sistema de educação, à formação de quadros, à modernização e extensão dos sistemas de saúde e assistência.
A três dias da transferência de Macau, numa entrevista à RTP, quando questionado sobre como era ser o último Governador, Rocha Vieira dizia ter a sensação de que desempenhou o papel “num momento histórico”, mas descreveu-se apenas como sendo “o intérprete dos órgãos de soberania aqui do território” e o “intérprete do cumprimento das obrigações que Portugal assumiu na Declaração Conjunta”. “Encaro isso de forma natural”, afirmou, então.
Dizia ter a convicção de que Portugal administrou o território “de uma maneira única”. E isso, vincava, via-se na forma como os chineses se despediam dos portugueses: “Vêm junto de nós, abraçam-nos, querem tirar fotografias, dizem que vão ter saudades nossas”. “Acho que Portugal cumpriu ao longo dos séculos (…) Acho que deixamos aqui uma obra boa, de que nos podemos orgulhar”, defendia.
“Não há futuro se não houver história, se não houver uma memória. E essa história está fundamentalmente ligada à presença de Portugal e dos portugueses aqui em Macau”, prosseguia, acrescentando que no território ficavam “muitíssimas coisas” de Portugal. Desde logo, um sistema político baseado na separação de poderes, as leis, as instruções judiciais, uma cultura administrativa, enumerava.
Questionado sobre se a fórmula de Deng Xiaoping “um país, dois sistemas” dava alguma segurança ao nível dos direitos, liberdades e garantias no futuro de Macau sob a soberania da República Popular da China, Rocha Vieira afirmou: “Acho que quando assinou e escreveu o que escreveu, e quando escreveu na Lei Básica o capítulo dos direitos fundamentais, o fez de uma forma sincera e responsável. Depois acho que as futuras autoridades da RAEM partilham dos mesmos valores, dos mesmos princípios que nós partilhamos, a Administração Portuguesa”.
Quanto ao relacionamento com a China enquanto desempenhou o cargo de Governador, disse que foi “sempre bom”. “Eu consegui ter uma relação muito franca, de boa cooperação, muito aberta, com os chineses. Naturalmente, tivemos muitas divergências (…) Mas esse entendimento, num quadro aliás que tem sido sempre favorável, de amizade, que é tradicional e histórica dos portugueses e dos chineses, ajudou muito. E acho que as divergências nunca levaram a situações de ruptura”.
Do lado de Portugal, o relacionamento também foi “sempre bom”, segundo disse na altura, mas sublinhava: “Naturalmente que Macau e Portugal estão separados fisicamente, mas estiveram sempre juntos pelo afecto, pela solidariedade e pelo sentido de responsabilidade que os órgãos de soberania sempre tiveram perante Macau”.
Para o futuro, o último Governador pedia atenção ao território. “Portugal deve continuar a estar atento a Macau e acho que a comunidade internacional deve estar atenta a Macau, naturalmente sem interferir na soberania chinesa, que a deve exercer. Mas deve acompanhar esse processo, porque a Declaração Conjunta é um tratado internacional, assinada por dois países”.
Sobre as críticas de que Portugal pudesse ter sido “submisso” em relação à República Popular da China, Rocha Vieira dizia, a dias da transferência, que já não ouvia esse tipo de acusações. “Hoje as pessoas perceberam que nós aproveitámos bem – no bom sentido do termo ‘aproveitar’ – as boas relações com a China para defender do melhor modo os nossos interesses. Porque o ter boas relações, o falar franco, o ser amigo, o ter sentido de futuro, o ser sério nos propósitos não é incompatível com o ser firme, determinado. Pelo contrário. Nós aproveitámos esse clima para podermos ser muito determinados e muito firmes, dizermos o que pensávamos e batermo-nos pelos interesses que julgamos ser os interesses de Macau”, rematava, na mesma entrevista.
Na noite da transferência, após a cerimónia oficial, os presidentes de cada país, Jorge Sampaio e Jiang Zemin, trocaram cumprimentos formais, mas não foram os únicos. Entre as várias saudações, especial destaque para a de Vasco Rocha Vieira, que findava o seu cargo, e Edmund Ho, o seu sucessor e primeiro Chefe do Executivo da RAEM.
Se é certo que o último Governador foi acarinhado por muitos, e o seu papel nas negociações da transferência foi reconhecido “no país e no seio da comunidade internacional”, certo é também que Rocha Vieira foi alvo de muitas críticas. Principalmente no âmbito do caso Fundação Jorge Álvares, que causou polémica, quer logo no primeiro mês da administração chinesa no território, quer em Portugal.
Formalizada em 18 de Dezembro de 1999, véspera da despedida da administração portuguesa de Macau, a Fundação contou com uma dotação inicial de 100 milhões de patacas oriundos, em partes iguais, da Sociedade de Turismo e Diversões de Macau e da Fundação para a Cooperação e Desenvolvimento, com sede no território e alimentada por fundos públicos locais. O presidente do Conselho de Curadores desta última fundação era o próprio Rocha Vieira à data em que ficou decidida a transferência de 50 milhões de patacas para a recém-constituída Fundação Jorge Álvares.
Ao longo dos anos após a transferência, o General foi voltando esporadicamente a Macau. A última vez que esteve no território, pelo menos que se saiba publicamente, foi em Março de 2023. Veio receber um doutoramento honoris causa em Ciências Sociais, atribuído pela Universidade de Ciência e Tecnologia de Macau. “Voltar a Macau é sempre muito agradável. Todas as pessoas que aqui estiveram, viveram e trabalharam têm Macau no coração, como eu tenho, portanto, voltar aqui nestas circunstâncias é muito agradável”, disse então aos jornalistas, afirmando ainda estar optimista quanto ao futuro do território.
Rocha Vieira foi Chefe do Estado-Maior do Exército e, por inerência, membro do Conselho da Revolução entre 1976 e 1978. Em 2015, foi agraciado com a Grã-Cruz da Ordem Militar da Torre e Espada pelo ex-Presidente Cavaco Silva. Anteriormente, fora condecorado com a Grã-Cruz da Ordem do Infante D. Henrique (1986), atribuída pelo general Ramalho Eanes, com a Grã-Cruz da Ordem de Cristo (1996), conferida por Mário Soares, e com o Grande Colar da Ordem do Infante D. Henrique (2001), atribuída por Jorge Sampaio, uma condecoração atribuída excepcionalmente, já que é normalmente destinada a chefes de Estado.
 
“Uma perda enorme”
“Desolada”, assim reagiu Anabela Ritchie à morte do último Governador. “Fiquei muito consternada. Eu sabia-o gravemente doente, mas nunca estamos preparados. Eu não estou”, afirmou, em declarações ao Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU. Privou de perto com Rocha Vieira, enquanto presidente da Assembleia Legislativa, e garante que, além da relação de trabalho, acabaram por criar uma amizade.
“Tive com o Governador uma relação de trabalho excelente. Uma relação de grande solidariedade, também muito determinada pelo facto de termos consciência de que estávamos no período de transição. E tínhamos muito trabalho à nossa frente”, lembrou. “Foi possível tornarmo-nos amigos”, acrescentou.
Anabela Ritchie aponta que sempre sentiu que “podia falar à vontade” com Rocha Vieira. “Posso dizer que tinha uma relação muito boa. Umas vezes concordávamos, outras vezes discordávamos. Mas havia espaço para explicarmos a nossa maneira de pensar, o sentido como estávamos a ver as coisas”. O objectivo era sempre “encontrar soluções”.
Sublinhando que gostou de trabalhar o Governador, Anabela Ritchie enalteceu também a “figura importante” que foi para a transição: “Admirei muito a determinação com que ele fazia as coisas, a competência e a dedicação”.
Recordou ainda que Rocha Vieira “escutava os outros e permitia que eles falassem”, ouvia opiniões diferentes, das mais variadas pessoas. “Era uma faceta que eu admirava bastante”, observou, dizendo também que era um homem “calmo, sereno”.
Por sua vez, Jorge Rangel afirmou ter sido “uma enorme honra” servir Portugal ao lado de Rocha Vieira, “no Governo de Macau, integrando a sua equipa governativa, e em instituições da sociedade civil, como a Sociedade Histórica da Independência de Portugal, associações militares, fundações ligadas a Macau e o Centro Científico e Cultural de Macau, em Lisboa, de que ele foi o fundador”.
“Realço o seu sentido de Estado, o apego ao cumprimento da missão, a inteligência, a capacidade de liderança e de realização, a dignidade, a responsabilidade, a dedicação à família e a causas e o amor a Portugal”, disse o antigo Secretário para a Administração, Educação e Juventude do Governo de Macau, acrescentando que o recordará sempre “com respeito e admiração pelo exemplo de vida que foi para quantos com ele trabalharam e de algum modo colaboraram”.
“Foi um privilégio conhecê-lo de perto, acompanhá-lo em múltiplas e diversificadas jornadas ao serviço de Portugal e de Macau, com ele conviver no seio de instituições da sociedade civil e merecer a sua confiança e amizade”, finalizou.
José Luís de Sales Marques trabalhou directamente com Rocha Vieira durante cerca de oito anos e meio no período da transição, como presidente do Leal Senado e também como membro do Conselho Consultivo Governador. Posteriormente, o economista continuou a trabalhar com o General no âmbito da Escola Portuguesa.
“É uma perda enorme, em termos de importância da figura que foi o General Rocha Vieira, a sua importância na história de Macau como último Governador, mas não só por isso, porque efectivamente ele trabalhou a transição de Macau”, afirmou.
“Ao mesmo tempo que se construíam as infra-estruturas e se preparavam as condições materiais para a transferência de administração para a China, também se fazia isso através da sua sabedoria, da sua diplomacia e da visão que ele tinha das coisas”, prosseguiu.
Para Sales Marques, o antigo Governador teve sempre o cuidado de manter a estabilidade e a prosperidade de Macau. “É conhecido o seu papel no processo de transição e o seu papel até de moderador em certas circunstâncias daquilo que se passou, e por isso é uma figura incontornável”, disse ainda a este jornal.
 
“Dedicou muito a Macau”
Enquanto isso, Jorge Neto Valente vincou que perdeu um amigo e recorda o último Governador de Macau como um “homem que fica na história, não no rodapé, no centro da história”. O advogado considera que “Macau ficou a dever-lhe muito”. Para Neto Valente, Rocha Vieira foi muito importante no período de transição, “que ele acompanhou até ao fim, como se sabe, e deixou Macau com toda a dignidade”.
Após regressar a Portugal, relembra o causídico, “o General continuou a interessar-se pelas coisas de Macau e a contribuir para o bem de Macau”. Rocha Vieira voltou ao território algumas vezes e numa das últimas visitas recebeu da Universidade de Macau o grau de doutoramento Honoris Causa.
O advogado reforça que o ex-Governador “fez o que tinha de fazer e foi uma pessoa que dedicou muito da sua vida a Macau”, tendo estado muito antes disso no território, nos anos 1970, como engenheiro da tropa.
“Eu conheci-o nessa altura”, assinala Jorge Neto Valente, para acrescentar que Rocha Vieira regressou para ser Governador “pela mão de Mário Soares, depois de não ter corrido bem a experiência dos governadores civis do ponto de vista de Portugal, do ponto de vista político, e Mário Soares foi buscá-lo aos Açores”.
Depois de lembrar que Rocha Vieira era membro do Conselho de Curadores da Fundação Escola Portuguesa de Macau, estabelecimento de ensino fundado no seu mandato, em 1998, acordado no Gabinete de Ligação, Neto Valente assinala que o antigo representante máximo de Portugal em Macau deixou muitas coisas que ainda hoje são válidas.
“Ele e as pessoas que escolheu para o acompanharem na governação nos últimos anos enfrentaram um período muito difícil, de muito trabalho e só realmente pessoas com muita vontade e amor a Macau e a Portugal é que conseguiam fazer o que ele fez”, considerou. Depois de sair de Macau, finaliza o seu depoimento, “o General continuou sempre ligado ao território”.
Também José Rocha Diniz, co-fundador do JTM, lamentou a morte de Rocha Vieira. “Lamento muito, mas foi algo que não me surpreendeu, porque acompanhei os últimos meses, em que ele esteve hospitalizado, com gravidade”, disse, acrescentando: “Estive com ele num jantar após a homenagem ao Dr. António Aresta no Centro Cultural e Científico de Macau, em Lisboa”.
Recordando que o último governador “conseguiu mobilizar a maioria da população de Macau durante os últimos anos da transição”, Rocha Diniz apontou que tinha uma “grande vantagem”. “Conhecia muito bem o Território, porque já tinha sido secretário-adjunto, conhecia as duas diversificadas comunidades e também o modo como os chineses entendem o poder, pelo que tinha uma grande vantagem em relação aos governadores anteriores”, disse.
“Homem do 25 de Abril e do 25 de Novembro,” prossegue Rocha Diniz, “hoje em dia, quando se fala do General Rocha Vieira Portugal quase toda a gente salienta o modo como ele colocou a bandeira portuguesa ao peito” na altura da transferência. “Em Portugal desconhece-se toda a complexidade do processo de transição, em que Macau não foi chamado às negociações, que eram entre Portugal e a China, mas Macau tinha, contudo, inúmeras questões fundamentais a resolver, ‘in loco’”.
“Rocha Vieira foi muito criativo e firme na forma como sempre manteve as posições de Macau, algumas vezes mesmo contra as instituições portuguesas”, recordou, adiantando que “ao contrário do que algumas pessoas possam pensar, era um homem dialogante, com um profundo espírito de missão dos interesses de Portugal e dos portugueses que residiam em Macau, mas sempre reconhecendo que se encontrava num momento decisivo para a solução de um ‘problema herdado da história’, em que Portugal tinha que sair bem”.
“A administração portuguesa saiu de Macau, mas os portugueses aqui permanecem, continuando a contribuir para o seu progresso e desenvolvimento”. Rocha Diniz concluiu com uma palavra de profundos pêsames, nesta hora de dor, “à Dra. Leonor Rocha Vieira e aos filhos”.
Por sua vez, António José de Freitas começou por afirmar: “Mais do que o último Governador de Macau, perdi um grande amigo”. Depois, recordou que ainda há três meses tinha falado com Rocha Vieira ao telefone.
O Provedor lembrou também que Rocha Vieira vinha a Macau anualmente, por fazer parte do Conselho de Curadores da Fundação Escola Portuguesa, e em 2019 veio a convite da Santa Casa, por ocasião do 450º aniversário da instituição. “Na altura, foi proclamado benemérito da Santa Casa”, apontou, reiterando que perdeu “um grande amigo”.
“Para mim, foi o melhor Governador de Macau”, prosseguiu António José de Freitas, acrescentando que sempre tiveram muito contacto.
Já António Félix Pontes, economista e antigo administrador da Autoridade Monetária, afirmou que Rocha Vieira “foi um bom governador, amado e respeitado por toda a população de Macau, e que honrou Portugal numa fase histórica deste Território”.
“Devo-lhe a nomeação para deputado à Assembleia Legislativa de Macau, de 1991 a 1999, nunca tendo interferido na minha acção política nessa função”, recordou ainda, lamentando ter perdido “um grande amigo”.
 
“Cumpriu”, mas não foi do “agrado de todos”
Jorge Fão disse também ter ficado triste com a notícia, que lhe foi dada através do JTM. Sobre o mandato do antigo Governador, o presidente da assembleia-geral da Associação dos Aposentados, Reformados e Pensionistas de Macau salienta que “cumpriu com o que tinha que cumprir, mas não foi totalmente do agrado dos trabalhadores da administração pública”.
No entanto, Jorge Fão diz que o general Rocha Vieira agradou à população em geral e também aos empresários. “Penso que aí esteve bem”.
Em relação aos trabalhadores da função pública, “ele não se preocupou assim tanto, mas no final tivemos um desfecho alegre, digamos, uma vez que toda a administração pública conseguiu o que pretendia, ou seja, aquilo por que estava a lutar: por uma pensão, por uma transferência das suas funções para Portugal”.
Fão diz não ter pessoalmente razões de queixa. “Tive muitos contactos com ele devido à função que exercia fora da função pública, mas eu estava afecto à Associação dos Trabalhadores da Função Pública, tendo dialogado muito com ele, embora esses diálogos não tenham sido muito satisfatórios”, reconhece.
Apesar de tudo, ressalva, a associação “conseguiu felizmente alcançar os resultados pretendidos, também porque nos deslocámos a Portugal e tivemos vários encontros com Mário Soares e Cavaco Silva e estivemos em Pequim para falar dos nossos anseios, das nossas preocupações”.
Jorge Fão conclui salientando que o antigo Governador de Macau, como o mais alto representante de Portugal no território, “cumpriu a missão que lhe foi entregue, ainda que, repito, não tenha sido do agrado de todos”.
A Associação dos Trabalhadores da Função Pública, dirigida por José Pereira Coutinho, lamentou igualmente a perda de Rocha Vieira e deixou-lhe um agradecimento “por ter resolvido, durante a fase de transição, muitas questões dos trabalhadores da função pública, dos macaenses e dos portugueses que optaram por continuar a prestar serviços na RAEM”. Numa mensagem, Coutinho recorda ainda que a utilização da actual sede da associação foi autorizada por Rocha Vieira.
 
PR e PM recordam “sentido de Estado”
O Presidente da República manifestou “profundo pesar” pela morte de Vasco Rocha Vieira, enaltecendo o seu “marcado patriotismo” e recordando-o como “um dos mais ilustres oficiais do Exército Português na transição para a Democracia e nas primeiras décadas da sua afirmação”. “Desde sempre muito ligado aos Comandos, exerceu ainda funções políticas como as de Ministro da República para a Região Autónoma dos Açores”, refere a nota publicada no sítio oficial da Presidência da República. Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa destaca ainda que Rocha Vieira foi “muito próximo do Presidente António Ramalho Eanes”, tendo sido por ele “designado Chanceler das Antigas Ordens Militares”. “O simbolismo do momento da transferência da administração portuguesa para a chinesa permanecerá na memória de muitos portugueses como um exemplo de sentido de Estado, sentido de serviço da causa pública e de marcado patriotismo”, pode ler-se. O Presidente da República, que afirma ter acompanhado “de perto os últimos meses” da vida de Rocha Vieira, “apresenta à sua família, e, muito em especial, à sua viúva e filhos, o testemunho de gratidão de Portugal, com muito saudosa amizade”. Também o primeiro-ministro recordou Rocha Vieira como “um dos mais brilhantes militares a dar corpo ao sentido patriótico de ser português”, destacando a sua ligação “histórica e marcante e Macau”. “O general Vasco Rocha Vieira foi um dos mais brilhantes militares a dar corpo ao sentido patriótico de ser português, com especiais serviços na consolidação da nossa democracia e na ligação histórica e marcante a Macau, onde foi o último governador”, escreveu Luís Montenegro, numa publicação na rede social X. Apresentou ainda condolências à família e amigos e disse guardar de Rocha Vieira “gestos de amabilidade e palavras de responsabilidade cívica e política”.
 
Eanes lembra “homem extraordinário”
“O general Rocha Vieira era um homem de excepção pela sua acção de excelência e pela sua responsabilidade social assumida, merecendo ser, justamente, considerado ‘um dos melhores dos nossos maiores’”, escreveu o antigo Presidente da República Ramalho Eanes numa nota enviada à Lusa. Lembra-o como “um homem extraordinário”, sobretudo “a três níveis: pela sua personalidade distintiva, pelo seu desempenho militar relevante e pelos serviços prestados ao País a nível político”. A nível pessoal, “possuía qualidades de espírito superiores”, tinha “uma inteligência excepcional”, “um bom temperamento” e “dispunha de uma personalidade forte”. Ao nível militar, “foi um dos mais distintos da sua geração, prestando, ao Exército, serviços relevantes, em tempos difíceis, nomeadamente, no estertor do regime político anterior ao 25 de Abril, no decurso do 25 de Abril e, mesmo, no 25 de Novembro, tendo, ainda, desempenhado um importante papel enquanto representante das Forças Armadas portuguesas junto da NATO”. Quanto ao nível político, teve uma actividade de “grande qualidade e grande importância para o país, quer como ministro da República para os Açores, quer ainda, como governador de Macau, colocando todo o seu empenho no desenho e execução, com sucesso, de uma política de transformação bem-sucedida de Macau, participando, igualmente, com o sucesso que é conhecido, na transferência da administração do território de Macau para a República Popular da China”.
 
Exército enaltece “patriotismo” e “legado de serviço”
O Exército manifestou pesar pela morte do tenente-general Vasco Rocha Vieira e enalteceu o seu “legado de serviço e patriotismo”, desejando que “continue a inspirar gerações futuras”. Numa nota, o Exército afirma que “está de luto, por ter deixado de contar com um dos seus mais notáveis soldados”. “A sua vida e o seu legado justificam um profundo reconhecimento e perene respeito pela sua memória, e constituem factor de motivação e orgulho para todos os que servem nesta secular instituição. Que o seu legado de serviço e patriotismo continue a inspirar gerações futuras”, realça. De acordo com nota, o velório vai ocorrer hoje, entre as 17:00 e as 22:00 (hora de Lisboa), na Capela da Academia Militar, em Lisboa. Amanhã, o velório será retomado às 10:00, seguido de uma missa antes de almoço. Após as cerimónias em Lisboa, o cortejo seguirá para o Algarve, onde irá decorrer o funeral, no Cemitério Municipal de Lagoa.
 
“Dignificou” presença portuguesa no Oriente
O ex-Presidente da República Aníbal Cavaco Silva lamentou a morte de Rocha Vieira, “figura marcante” cujo legado dignifica os últimos anos da presença portuguesa no Oriente. “Guardamos do general Rocha Vieira a imagem solene e digna do arriar da Bandeira Nacional em Macau, fez agora 25 anos. Mais importante do que essa imagem, é o trabalho de Rocha Vieira como último Governador de Macau, dignificando os últimos anos da nossa presença no Oriente, permitindo-nos deixar o território reconciliados com a nossa História e orgulhosos da obra que deixámos”, afirmou, numa nota de condolências enviada à Lusa. Cavaco Silva manifestou “profunda tristeza” pela morte de Rocha Vieira, “figura marcante” da história recente, com quem mantinha “estreitos laços de amizade”. Sublinhou ainda a “importância das altas funções militares que desempenhou, como chefe do Estado-Maior do Exército, num período crítico de consolidação” da democracia portuguesa, entre 1976 e 1978. “As suas excepcionais qualidades de comando, a sua firmeza, integridade de carácter, e a sua formação ética e militar ajudaram a repor a autoridade hierárquica e a disciplina nas Forças Armadas num período conturbado da vida do país”, sustentou.
 
“Um dos melhores intérpretes da importância” de Macau
O PS manifestou pesar pela morte de Rocha Vieira, enaltecendo uma vida “inteiramente dedicada ao serviço de Portugal”. Referindo que “a sua vida ficou para sempre ligada a Macau”, para o PS este “foi um dos melhores intérpretes da importância” daquele território “para a relação entre Portugal e a República Popular da China”, bem como da singularidade da RAE. “Os últimos anos da administração portuguesa do Território de Macau, sob a liderança do general Rocha Vieira, são marcados pela concretização de várias obras públicas infra-estruturais importantes de suporte ao desenvolvimento subsequente de Macau, bem como de reformas na administração para a sua preparação para o período subsequente”, enaltece. Os socialistas referem ainda a cerimónia de transferência, na qual foi inegável a forma como Rocha Vieira “personificou e simbolizou a dignidade e o tributo à presença portuguesa ao longo de séculos em Macau”. “E marcou a amizade e o respeito que os portugueses mantêm com Macau e com a República Popular da China, e que permite, ao fim de 25 anos de transição, preservar a singularidade de Macau que continua a ser ponto de encontro entre culturas”, acrescentou. O PS dá assim “nota pública do seu profundo respeito pelos serviços ao país” e “endereça à sua família e aos seus amigos as suas mais sentidas condolências”.
 
Desempenhou funções públicas “sempre com dignidade”
O presidente do Governo dos Açores, José Manuel Bolieiro, lamentou a morte de Vasco Rocha Vieira, recordando que o tenente-general “desempenhou sempre as suas funções públicas com dignidade”. “Presto homenagem a um homem que, ao longo da sua carreira, desempenhou sempre as suas funções públicas com dignidade, sentido de dever e profundo compromisso com o interesse público”, afirmou, citado numa nota de imprensa. Acrescenta ainda que “deixa um legado de serviço ao país, que será lembrado com respeito e gratidão”, manifestando “profundo pesar pelo falecimento do tenente-general”, que “desempenhou relevantes funções ao serviço de Portugal”. Rocha Vieira, que foi ministro da República para os Açores entre 1986 e 1991, “destacou-se pela forma íntegra e responsável com que exerceu o cargo, contribuindo para o fortalecimento das relações entre a Região Autónoma dos Açores e o Estado, sempre com respeito pela autonomia regional e pelas especificidades dos Açores”. O executivo açoriano refere também o desempenho no cargo de Governador de Macau.

</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“We have to enrich” functions of the Sino-Lusophone platform</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/temos-de-enriquecer-funcoes-da-plataforma-sino-lusofona/</link><description>The Macao SAR must “further enrich and expand the role and functions of the Sino-Lusophone platform”, which has a “relevant significance” in the process of opening up to the outside world, highlighted the Chief Executive before the consuls general in the territory and delegates of Portuguese-speaking countries in the Macau Forum. Sam Hou Fai also defended the strengthening of cooperation with Southeast Asia and praised the contributions of the Filipino community to the development of Macau
 
Macau will remain committed to boosting cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, as well as between the territory and Southeast Asia, assured the Chief Executive, at a dinner offered to the consuls-general in the Macao SAR and delegates from Portuguese-speaking countries at the Secretariat Permanent of the Macau Forum. “Macau has deep and friendly historical links with Portuguese-speaking countries and Southeast Asia”, highlighted Sam Hou Fai, considering that the results achieved in the areas of exchange and cooperation are “inseparable from the extraordinary work and diligent dedication” of the consuls. general and delegates of the Forum.
“In the new phase, guided by President Xi's important speeches, the Macao SAR will continue to comprehensively, precisely and unswervingly implement the 'one country, two systems' principle and boost development in all aspects, and will certainly provide new opportunities and platforms for strengthening cooperative relations” between China and Macau with Portuguese-speaking countries and Southeast Asia, he highlighted when speaking at the dinner, which was also attended by the commissioner of the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Liu Xianfa.
Taking into account the Macao SAR's opening and exchange process with the outside world, and in line with the guidelines recently transmitted by President Xi Jinping, Sam Hou Fai began by highlighting that cooperation with Portuguese-speaking countries is “very important and has a relevant meaning ”. “(…) We must further enrich and expand the role and functions of the Sino-Lusophone platform, actively implement the various agreements and instruments established within the scope of the 6th Ministerial Conference of Forum Macau, especially the Action Plan for Economic Cooperation and Commercial (2024-2027) and we must continue to promote joint development characterized by equality, cooperation and mutual benefits, comprehensively raising the level of Sino-Lusophone cooperation” in several areas, he stressed, calling for the intensification of exchanges, both at official level and in the private sphere.
“Delegations arriving from your countries to visit Macau, and also to see the Guangdong-Macao Deep Cooperation Zone in Hengqin, the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area and the other provinces and cities of the Mainland China,” he said, addressing the diplomats and delegates present at the reception. He further argued that Macao SAR “has become one of the favorite destinations for international investments, which provides advantageous conditions to become a place for the concentration of high-quality international qualified staff”.
At the same time, the Chief Executive expressed the desire to “constantly deepen cooperation between the Macao SAR and Southeast Asian countries”. “The MSAR and the countries of Southeast Asia, including the Philippines, which are geographically close, have close economic and commercial cooperation, with intense exchange of people and in the cultural area, being traditionally good neighbors and good partners. For example, according to data from the 2021 Census, the Filipino population accounts for around 5% of the total population of Macau, being the second largest community in the Region after the Chinese community, and makes valuable contributions to development socio-economic situation of Macau”, he acknowledged.
From his perspective, it is important to “take advantage of this good basis of traditional cooperation” to “seize new opportunities, explore more potential for cooperation in all aspects and encourage greater progress” in exchanges between Macau and Southeast Asian countries.
It is recalled that, during the celebrations of the 25th anniversary of the Macao SAR, Xi Jinping stressed that the territory must adopt “a more open and inclusive stance to intensify international ties and increase global projection and attractiveness”. In particular, according to the Chinese leader, “Macau must concentrate efforts on building a platform for opening up to the outside world at a higher level, to reinforce bilateral openness with Portuguese-speaking Countries, promoting comprehensive cooperation of mutual benefits”.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Up to 670,000 border crossings expected on Chinese New Year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/esperadas-ate-670-mil-passagens-nas-fronteiras-ano-novo-chines/</link><description>Between January 28th and February 4th, during the Lunar New Year holidays, Macau could see 630,000 to 670,000 border crossings per day, the CPSP predicts, anticipating that the peak of entries and exits will occur on the 1st and 2nd of February. On the other hand, according to DST, as of last Thursday, 80% of hotel rooms had already been booked for this festive season, with the average price of rooms varying between 1,000 and 2,000 patacas.
 
The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) predicts that, during the Lunar New Year holidays, between January 28th and February 4th, Macau's borders will be able to record 630,000 to 670,000 entries and exits per day, which which means a total volume that varies between 5.04 million and 5.36 million. The estimates were presented yesterday, at a press conference where representatives from various public services presented the preparatory work to respond to the increase in tourists during this festive period.
Compared to Chinese New Year 2024, there could be an increase of at least 3%, the CPSP predicted, pointing out the peak period for border crossings to be the 1st and 2nd of February (4th and 5th day of the lunar calendar).
Furthermore, the corporation revealed that, between the 1st and 21st of this month, the “one entry per week” visa policy, aimed at residents of Zhuhai, attracted 73 thousand visitors, which translates into a daily average of 3,500 people, while the “one visa, multiple entries” measure, applicable to Hengqin residence card holders, brought 18 thousand visitors to the Macao SAR, a daily average of 900 people.
Regarding Chinese New Year, the CPSP assured that it had prepared a series of action plans, in order to ensure the fluidity and order of the flow of people in the city, road safety and smooth border crossings.
According to what he presented, in places of festive activities and popular tourist attractions, the CPSP will reinforce patrol agents and activate measures to control the flow of people when necessary, in order to maintain a good travel environment. In addition to planning to deploy more agents at the borders and open more customs inspection counters, the corporation assured that it will be committed to strengthening the fight against taxi violations and illegal driving behavior. At the same time, more agents will be mobilized to combat illegal pedestrian crossings.
In turn, the Directorate of Tourism Services (DST) pointed out that there will be an increase in both the number of visitors and the hotel occupancy rate during the Lunar New Year. As noted, by the 16th of this month, the hotel sector already had an occupancy rate of almost 80%, and this rate could record constant increases as the holidays approach. According to the organization, during this festive season, the average price of hotel rooms varies between 1,000 and 2,000 patacas.
DST highlighted that, on the one hand, it has made many preparations to serve tourists well and guarantee the quality of the tourist service, and, on the other, it will maintain regular inspections at border posts, tourist attractions and shopping places, to combat illegal guides and illicit accommodation.
The Customs Services (SA) anticipated the peak of car exits through the Macau Post on the Delta Bridge on the 28th of January (the eve of the Lunar New Year) and the peak period of vehicle entry through the same border on the 31st. (3rd day of the lunar calendar), with around 500 passes per hour.
In view of the increase in car movements on the Delta Bridge, the SA is prepared to put more crossing routes into operation during peak flows, as well as deploying more customs agents and technical personnel, in order to increase the efficiency of car passage at the customs post.
At the same time, the SA will intensify inspections at borders, in the city and at sea, with a view to maintaining the stability of Macau's public security environment during the Spring Festival. Customs will also continue to monitor the trend of “fake tourists” activities and will reinforce inspections to prevent holidays from being taken advantage of by illegals for smuggling.
On the other hand, due to the Lunar New Year, a time when decorative plants from Mainland China, such as orchids, are frequently transported, the Institute for Municipal Affairs will set up a temporary checkpoint for plant inspection on arrivals at the Chinese border. Portas do Cerco, which will run between the 26th and 28th of January, from 9:00 am to 11:00 pm. Inspection fees will be waived.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Fines for illegal works totaled 1.5 million</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/multas-por-obras-ilegais-totalizaram-15-milhoes/</link><description>Last year, fines totaling around 1.5 million patacas were issued due to the execution of illegal works in the territory, and the Public Works Services Department warned that the fines relating to eight cases had not yet been paid, so that there will be coercive collection. There were 838 cases opened in 2024, an annual drop of 25%, with demolitions rising 85% to 238
 
Last year, authorities issued fines totaling around 1.5 million patacas due to illegal works, said the Land and Urban Construction Services Directorate (DSSCU), which initiated 838 cases in this area. According to the data available, there was a drop of around 25% in relation to processes opened in 2023, which totaled 1,114.
Of the total number of cases, 238 concerned voluntary demolitions – an increase of 85% compared to the previous year, and 39 concerned the imposition of fines for carrying out illegal works. The body responsible for Public Works states in a statement that “the fines relating to eight cases were not paid within the set deadline, so the Administration will proceed with the respective coercive collection”.
“Compared to the past, the new legislation increased the fines imposed on offenders who carry out illegal works and added new fines for offenders who do not comply with demolition orders. In addition, other sanctioning measures were also created, including the crime of disobedience, the interruption of water and energy supply”, states the DSSCU, justifying the increase in voluntary demolitions.
Since the entry into force of the legal regime for urban construction, the Macao SAR Government has reinforced the fight against illegal works, with the DSSCU giving priority to cases of new illegal works, renovation of illegal works, buildings in a state of disrepair and to cases of illegal works located in buildings whose use license was issued after the new law came into force.
The data available on the DSSCU website shows that, in 2024, there were 48 processes with notification of the final decision. In this regard, the organization explains that it acts in accordance with the law and that offenders must demolish illegal works and restore the site “as soon as possible”. However, in case of non-compliance, DSSCU will continue the administrative procedures until the final decision is made in the case. “Once notification of the final decision is received, the offenders must proceed with the demolition of illegal works and the replacement of the site within the stipulated period, otherwise, DSSCU will carry out the appropriate demolition actions, the expenses of which will be borne by the offenders”, he adds.
If after the hearing regarding the illegal work and after the DSSCU makes a final decision and issues the demolition order, the offender requests voluntary demolition within the set deadline, the fine is reduced by half. However, the law determines that this reduction and exemption benefit can only be applied once. The DSSCU also states that if the offender violates the law again within the next five years, it is considered a repeat offense, meaning the fine is increased by a quarter.
The organization reiterated, in a statement, that it will continue the fight against illegal works to safeguard the safety of buildings and the housing environment in the territory.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>World leaders congratulated Trump but according to their interests</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/actual/lideres-mundiais-felicitaram-trump-mas-de-acordo-os-seus-interesses/</link><description>Leaders from around the world congratulated Donald Trump, but in different ways, as you can see. This was the most unique political return in recent US history, that of a former president who did not recognize his defeat in 2020, who promises to “take revenge” on his opponents and who was criminally convicted, in addition to being the target of two assassination attempts.
China stated that it is “willing to work” with the new US administration to “strengthen dialogue and cooperation” and highlighted by Foreign Ministry spokesman Mao Ning that “the history of the development of relations between the China and the US tells us that if the two countries work together, both parties will benefit, but if they fight each other, both will be harmed.”
Also before the inauguration, Russian leader Vladimir Putin said he is “open to dialogue” on Ukraine to achieve “lasting peace”. “As for resolving the situation, I would like to emphasize that its objective should not be a brief truce, but a lasting peace, based on respect for the legitimate interests of all people,” he added. For his part, India's PM, Narendra Modi, congratulated “dear friend” Donald Trump, and said he hopes the two countries will work together again. “I look forward to working closely together again, to benefit both our countries and to shape a better future for the world”, he posted on the social network X. Also, Japanese PM, Shigeru Ishiba, “expressed his desire to work in close collaboration” with Trump “to have a free and open Asia-Pacific region”, according to a government statement.
In another quarter, Israel's PM, Benjamin Netanyahu, stated in a video message that “the most beautiful days” of their alliance are yet to come. “I believe we will work together to take the U.S.-Israel alliance to even greater heights.” For his part, the Palestinian PR, Mahmoud Abbas, expressed his willingness to cooperate with him in the search for a “two-state solution”. “We are ready to work with you to achieve peace during your term, with an internationally recognized two-state solution (…) living side by side in security and peace,” declared Abbas, according to information released by the official Palestinian news agency, Wafa.
PR Lula da Silva expressed the desire for the USA to continue to be “a historic partner” of Brazil during Donald Trump's government. “We don’t want conflict. Not with Venezuela, not with the Americans, not with China, not with India and not with Russia”, emphasized Lula.
Ukrainian leader Volodymyr Zelensky said his return to the White House represents an “opportunity” to achieve a “just peace” in Ukraine. “Today is a day of change, and also a day of hope for the resolution of many problems, including global challenges,” Zelensky said on social media. “President Trump is always decisive, and the peace through strength policy he announced provides an opportunity to strengthen American leadership and achieve a just, long-term peace, which is a top priority,” he added.
The European Union (EU) also hopes to work with Trump to face “global challenges”, said the president of the European Commission), Ursula Von der Leyen. “Together, our societies can achieve greater prosperity and strengthen their common security. This is the lasting strength of the transatlantic association”, Ursula published on the X social network.
Mexican PR, Claudia Sheinbaum, defended a relationship based on “dialogue” and “respect” and the Canadian Prime Minister. “We are stronger when we act together”, said Prime Minister Justin Trudeau, stressing that “Canada and the USA maintain the most fruitful economic partnership in the world, and are each other’s largest trading partner”, foreseeing the threat of imposing 25% tariffs.
The head of the German government, Olaf Scholz, wished for the continuation of what he called “good transatlantic relations” with the USA, Germany's “closest ally” and reinforced that “the aim of our policy continues to be to maintain good transatlantic relations. The EU, which has 27 members and more than 400 million people, is a strong union”, highlighted Scholz. Still in Europe, Italy's PM, Giorgia Meloni, expressed her “best wishes” to US President Donald Trump. “I am sure that the friendship between our nations and the values ​​that unite us will continue to reinforce the partnership between Italy and the United States, facing global challenges together and building a future of prosperity and security for our people”, published the extreme leader right on social media, the only European leader to go to Washington. For his part, King Charles III sent a personal message of congratulations to Donald Trump, in which he cited what he called the “special and lasting relationship between the United Kingdom and the USA”, while the PM, Viktor Orban, one of the few European leaders close to of Trump, anticipated that it is “our turn to occupy Brussels”, the headquarters of the EU.
In Portugal, PR Marcelo defined Trump as a President “for whom the Pacific is very important, for whom relations with China are very important, for whom relations with Russia are the same as they were in his first term, in which Russia, therefore, is not a problem for his vision of the USA”, and that he does not give importance to Europe, which, “on its own has to make a living”.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Suggested improvement in the training of patriotic cadres</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sugerida-melhoria-da-formacao-de-quadros-patrioticos/</link><description>The General Association of Overseas Chinese proposed improving the system for training qualified patriotic political cadres. The suggestion was made in the meeting with the Secretary for Administration and Justice, within the scope of the Lines of Government Action
 
The area of ​​administration and justice motivated suggestions from the General Association of Overseas Chinese of Macau, involving the improvement of the system for training qualified patriotic political personnel in Macau. During the meeting with Secretary André Cheong, within the scope of the Governing Action Lines, the association also proposed that good work be done in publicizing the law on minority languages.
Among several issues addressed, the Government member spoke of the Deep Cooperation Zone, “where Macau has some deficiencies, such as the shortage of qualified staff”, stating that, in the future, it will reinforce the Macao SAR's participation and increase the number of public servants, ensuring that the team under his supervision will continue “to study and increase the efficiency of public administration”.
André Cheong also attended a meeting with the General Union of Residents' Associations of Macau (“Kaifong”), where he heard suggestions from its leaders. Saying she was attentive to a series of large-scale works carried out by the Government, the president of the “Kaifong”, Ng Siu Lai, said she hoped that these works, related to the lives of the population, “can be continuously optimized to meet the needs of the society and guarantee the improvement of people’s quality of life”.
He added that, in the future, “the progress of legislative production and review must be accelerated, to allow Macau's legal regime to keep up with the times”.
In other meetings held by the Secretaries, the person responsible for Security, Wong Sio Chak, was at the Macau General Women's Association. In the lecture, the president of the board said she hopes that the authority will implement the goal of “actively preventing the various risks to national security and consolidating the security and stability of society”. This can only be achieved, in Un Sio Leng's view, through the constant improvement of the national security legal system, the creation of a mechanism for monitoring possible risks and the reinforcement of education on the subject.
Wong Sio Chak revealed that, in response to urban development, the security department will begin, this year, the sixth phase of the “Eyes in the Sky” system, further enhancing crime prevention and combat capabilities with scientific and technological resources.
Meanwhile, visiting the Macau Youth Federation was the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, who made some suggestions. Highlight is the proposal to continue expanding industry-university-research coverage, “to encourage young people to maintain a dynamic of innovation”, as well as maintaining support for the development of small and medium-sized companies and improving the Development Plan. Support for Young Entrepreneurs.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DSAT will study suggestions from schools to improve road safety</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dsat-estudara-sugestoes-de-escolas-para-melhorar-seguranca-rodoviaria/</link><description>After a student was run over by a public bus in the North Zone, representatives from several schools in the area were invited to an urgent meeting on road safety, organized by DSAT, CPSP and DSEDJ. At the meeting, they suggested, for example, adjusting the location of some crossings and extending the crossing time for pedestrians at some traffic lights. DSAT promised that it will analyze the feasibility of the proposals discussed as quickly as possible
 
Following an accident that occurred three days ago on Rua da Tribuna, in which a secondary school student was run over by a public bus on a pedestrian crossing, the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT), the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) and the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) organized an urgent meeting on road safety the day before yesterday, together with representatives from several schools located in the North Zone. The meeting aimed to encourage interested parties to jointly assess the current traffic situation around schools and discuss improvement proposals.
According to a statement issued by the three organizations, school representatives made several suggestions, including adjusting the location of some crossings, making the crossings at some intersections controlled by traffic lights, extending the crossing time for pedestrians at some traffic lights and expanding the scope of some pedestrian islands.
In reaction, DSAT promised that it will study the feasibility of the respective proposals as quickly as possible and organize interdepartmental “on-site” inspections together with schools in a timely manner, in order to continuously improve the road environment.
At the same time, the organization revealed that it will collect suggestions from all educational establishments in Macau regarding improving road safety around schools. To this end, DSAT, CPSP and DSEDJ will create a specific channel to collect opinions on the matter, in order to make student travel safer.
DSEDJ called on schools to continue to reinforce road safety education among teachers and students. For its part, the CPSP recalled having promoted 124 lectures on road safety last year, with 11,000 participants.
DSAT noted that, since 2019, it has prepared more than 300 proposals for optimizing pedestrian crossings, of which 286 have been implemented, including 60 carried out last year. As for the remaining proposals, the organization indicated that they are being developed in an orderly manner.
At the same time, since the end of 2021, DSAT began installing diagonal crossings in suitable locations, creating omnidirectional pedestrian crossing facilities. Currently, eight intersections with traffic lights in Macau are equipped with similar facilities for pedestrians. This year, four more locations in the North Zone will also host this type of installation, indicated DSAT.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Guaranteed stable food supply</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/garantido-fornecimento-estavel-de-alimentos/</link><description>The Chinese Ministry of Commerce guarantees the arrival of safe food products for consumption by the population of Macau. A Chinese delegation met with officials from the Institute for Municipal Affairs and went to two markets in the territory
 
A delegation from the Chinese Ministry of Commerce traveled to the territory to learn about the situation regarding the supply of agricultural products and derivatives from the Mainland to Macau. During the visit, the delegation visited the New Macau Supply Market and the Patane Market.
With the Spring Festival just around the corner, several measures have been taken to ensure the stable supply and quality security of agricultural products and derivatives to Macau. In this sense, supply sources were organized, emergency plans were activated, cooperation between departments was reinforced and a safe line of defense was established.
The deputy director of the Ministry of Commerce said that the Central Government has attached great importance to the supply of agricultural products and derivatives to Macau over the years. Li Na highlighted, in the meeting he held with officials from the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM), that there has been close cooperation between the Central Government's plan, the respective Services, provinces and cities in Mainland China.
Local governments and various Central Government services have directed the establishment of a series of high-standard production and processing bases, with the aim of ensuring that the Macao SAR population can consume safe food products.
In a note about the Ministry's visit, the IAM highlights that, since 2024, companies that supply agricultural products and derivatives to Macau have overcome adverse factors, such as the increase in breeding costs and the African swine fever epidemic, and have better guaranteed supply of agricultural products and derivatives.
Between January and November last year, Mainland China supplied Macau with 400 thousand tons of agricultural products and derivatives, a year-on-year increase of 9.4%. Products include live pigs and cattle, chilled and frozen chickens, cereals, vegetables, fruits, aquatic products, drinking water, among others.
During the visit to the territory, the Ministry's delegation also held exchanges and discussions with the chairman of the Board of Directors for Municipal Affairs, Chao Wai Ieng, and Administrator Ung Sau Hong, in which they learned about the demand and left the guarantee supply of fresh and live food to the Macau market, defining several measures to further ensure a stable supply of food products.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Art with 3,000 years of history showcases pieces from Hebei and Guizhou</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/arte-3-000-anos-de-historia-divulga-pecas-de-hebei-guizhou/</link><description>Making gold and silver crafts from Hebei and Guizhou known is the aim of some workshops that will be promoted by the Cultural Institute, as part of an exhibition of crafts from those Chinese provinces. The pieces of filigree inlaid art and Chinese cloisonné art are characterized by a high degree of technical refinement and their dazzling ornamentation, of great artistic value.
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
“Glow of Art – Exhibition of Gold and Silver Crafts from Hebei and Guizhou Provinces” opens to the public tomorrow at the Tap Seac Gallery, at 6:30 pm. To publicize the artistic value of the pieces, the Cultural Institute (IC) promotes the holding of four workshops, on the 8th and 9th of February, open to the public and with free participation, upon registration.
The art of creating gold and silver pieces is a type of traditional Chinese craftsmanship with more than 3,000 years of history. In this context, the filigree inlaid art and Chinese cloisonné art from Hebei Province and the goldsmithing of the Miao ethnic group from Guizhou Province, which appear on the National List of Items Representative of the Intangible Cultural Heritage of China, stand out “as particularly brilliant examples”, according to a note released by the IC.
The pieces from Hebei are characterized by a high degree of technical refinement, the diversity of their motifs and their dazzling ornamentation, possessing great artistic value. In turn, Guizhou goldsmithing denotes a multiplicity of cultural connotations, giving rise to works with a markedly ethnic style, with excellent artistic taste.
The exhibition presents more than 160 sets of jewelry and exquisite gold and silver items. These works, created by heirs of intangible cultural heritage and master craftsmen, feature sophisticated formats, a very high degree of technical refinement and a variety of styles. “Inheriting long-standing traditional techniques and incorporating a modern aesthetic, this traditional art radiates a contemporary aura”, highlights the IC.
The exhibition has guided tours on Saturdays, Sundays and holidays, with sessions in Cantonese at 3pm and in Mandarin at 4:15pm.
The workshops will take place in the Activities Room of the Xian Xinghai Memorial Museum, located on Rua Francisco Xavier Pereira, in Macau. On February 8, from 10:00 to 12:00 and from 15:00 to 17:00, an instructor, a representative heir at the provincial level of Hebei Province, will introduce the techniques of filigree inlaid art. The following day, at the same times, a monitor will present Miao silver carving techniques from Guizhou.
Each of the four workshops, aimed at people over 16 years of age, will be conducted in Mandarin, with 16 places available. Registration can be made from 10 am on Saturday, January 25th.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Market with live music brings together bands and SMEs in Barra</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mercado-musica-ao-vivo-junta-bandas-pme-na-barra/</link><description>More than three dozen small and medium-sized companies and popular music bands from Macau, Hong Kong and Taiwan will create a festive atmosphere in Barra. The “Music Festival” will be held on two Saturdays, January 25th and February 1st, and joins the “Bênção da Sorte and Weekend Markets”, in addition to other activities, including an exhibition of paintings by Japanese Shinri Murakami
 
The Barra area will have special entertainment starting tomorrow, with the opening of the “Mercado da Bênção da Sorte”, including the “Weekend Market” which will welcome more than 35 small and medium-sized companies (SMEs) . There you will find, through various activities, cultural heritage with a contemporary style.
MGM's initiative, “Lucky Blessing Bar”, will take place between the 24th and 26th and from January 31st to February 2nd, offering a diverse range of products covering cultural creations, technological innovations, crafts and pet products .
In addition, visitors have another attraction: the “Music Festival”, scheduled for two Saturdays (25 January and 1 February), bringing together well-known bands and musicians from Macau, Hong Kong and Taiwan, such as Wendy Wander, SCAMPER and Otome Syndream, among others.
The “pet-friendly” spirit of the event will translate into the opening of all areas of Barra to pets.
Tomorrow there will also be an exhibition of 22 works of painting in the former Slaughterhouse, by Japanese illustrator Shinri Murakami, which can be enjoyed by the public until the 25th of February. This is a partnership between MGM and Prince Kung's Palace Museum, with the aim of promoting and combining Chinese intangible cultural heritage with a modern touch.
The Japanese artist presents his fashion illustrations in a creative intersection between art and retail.
The exhibition is complemented by a “Pop-up Café”, which offers themed gastronomic experiences and exclusive products. Before the Spring Festival, Shinri will also join local students to create a mural in Bairro da Barra, further enhancing its artistic appeal.
The “New Year Creative Painting Workshop” will also be organized, which will allow you to participate in the ancient art of friction printing, a craft recognized as Chinese intangible heritage. Participants will have the opportunity to enjoy modern reinterpretations of the museum's artwork to create their own impressions of Chinese New Year. To enhance the experience, MGM has transformed the friction modules into exclusive sets of printing materials, available as exclusive holiday souvenirs.
In the presentation, Shinri Murakami stated that he was honored to be able to show his artistic works “in such a historically rich space, adding that “the fusion of heritage and modernity in this neighborhood is truly inspiring”. The artist highlighted that “together, we created an innovative shared space where my art goes beyond traditional exhibitions, connecting with various activities and integrating into the daily life of Macau”.
The Barra events mark the beginning of the Year of the Snake in that area of ​​the city, around elements of trends, arts, culture and retail.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Almost 180 thousand people vaccinated against the flu</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/quase-180-mil-pessoas-vacinadas-contra-gripe/</link><description>Close up of unrecognizable doctor vaccinating child in medical clinic, copy space										



Until the 19th of this month, anti-flu vaccines had been administered to 179 thousand people in Macau, the situation being “satisfactory”, observed yesterday Leong Iek Hou, director of the Center for Disease Prevention and Control of the Health Services. Even so, in a “Ou Mun Tin Toi” program, the doctor advised people who have already been infected to receive vaccines against this disease, in order to prevent infection with different types of viruses. According to Education Services, almost 80% of non-tertiary education students have already had flu vaccines. In turn, the Social Action Institute noted that the inoculation rate in homes exceeded 90%, while more than 60% of children enrolled in daycare centers have already taken the same preventive measure. On the program, Leong Iek Hou once again warned that, in the territory, the peak period of the flu virus will last until February. According to findings, currently the two main hospitals in Macau have received a stable number of flu patients while the number of acute flu cases tends to decrease compared to the same period last year. Specifically, patients with fever caused by the flu currently represent 16.2% of the total. On the other hand, with the Lunar New Year holidays approaching, the authorities have been carrying out preventive work relating to the flu in the last week, having contacted around 15 thousand people.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2331/</link><description>Consumers received electronic benefits of 227 million
Organized by the Government and Commercial Association (ACM) over 13 weeks last year, the “Grand prize for consumption in Macau” had around 22 thousand participating stores and led to the use of electronic benefits worth around 227 million of patacas and a total consumption of more than 1.1 billion, informed the Directorate of Economic and Technological Development Services (DSEDT). The commercial establishments benefiting belong to different sectors, with emphasis on retail trade (around 60% of the total), restaurants (31%) and services and other branches (9%). During this activity, 559 establishments simultaneously offered additional offers to boost consumption in community neighborhoods, highlighted the DSEDT. According to the results of the questionnaires promoted by the organization, around 70% of the establishments and more than 65% of the residents surveyed pointed to increases in the frequency and amount of average weekly consumption in Macau, compared to the period prior to this program, and “showed satisfied with the general situation of this activity”. Around 5.9 million transactions were eligible for the grand final draw, held on Tuesday. The total value of the prizes awarded exceeded 1.68 million patacas, including 300 thousand patacas from ACM sponsorship and electronic coupons for restaurants and hotels, offered by other organizations. The list of 499 winners will be published online today (http://www.macaospendingrewards.com/).</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Loss of 68 million in fraud committed on students</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/prejuizo-de-68-milhoes-nas-burlas-cometidas-sobre-estudantes/</link><description>Telephone fraud crimes perpetrated on students in 2024 totaled 109 cases, out of a total of 354, and caused losses of around 68 million patacas. The Judiciary Police has been fighting hard in this matter, having managed to reduce the number of cases. Cases of internet fraud increased by 4% year-on-year to 906, with phishing being the crime that saw the biggest increase
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
In a city where violent crimes have decreased year after year, with only one case of homicide having been recorded in 2024, authorities are currently focusing a large part of their investigations on the increasing number of frauds. The director of the Judiciary Police (PJ) is peremptory in stating that “criminals no longer steal; defraud using increasingly advanced technological means”.
And among those targeted there are many students. Of the 354 cases of telephone fraud, 109 concerned young students (around 30%), which caused losses of around 68 million patacas, and in total losses of around 154 million were recorded. “It’s a very high value,” said Sit Chong Meng. Despite the large losses, misleading situations via telephone still reduced by 13% annually.
This reality received special attention yesterday at the PJ's annual meeting with the media, where the head of the corporation took stock of last year's activity, releasing statistical data and comparing them with 2023 and 2019.
“We have carried out many awareness campaigns at schools, also to alert parents, so that great care must be taken when students intend to go and study abroad”, said the director of the PJ, adding that “criminals use technologies increasingly advanced, very concealed, hence the great difficulty for the police in discovering them”.
Referring specifically to students, the director of PJ highlighted the actions that have been carried out in schools, and also to alert parents, “so that great care can be taken when students intend to study abroad”.
On the other hand, and taking into account the issue of security in educational establishments in the territory, the PJ seeks to “create a safe environment for young people to grow and guide them towards development and success”. The Minors Monitoring Center continues to play “the role of a communication bridge”. Last year, 152 cases were monitored at the request of schools, 27 of which resulted in the initiation of monitoring processes.
 
Scams via the internet registered an increase
On the other hand, in cases of fraud via the internet, there was an increase of 4% to 906 cases. “We have carried out many awareness campaigns so that cases of fraud can be reduced”, assured Sit Chong Meng.
According to the PJ, fraudsters have abusively used phishing messages and websites to steal credit card data, attracting the public through news, “which has made prevention difficult”. In 2024, there were 689 cases related to this type of crime, an increase of 1.1 times, and which caused losses of more than 14 million patacas to companies and the population.
“This is the type of crime that registered the biggest increase last year”, maintains the PJ, which states that throughout 2024, 697 sessions were held to disseminate information about fraud, which had 120,000 participants and 1,600 posts were published online. Among the actions, the PJ launched, in cooperation with the Education Services, the “Anti-fraud vaccine program on campus”, to consolidate awareness among students.
In the fight against money exchange scammers, “new achievements were achieved”, says the PJ. With the coordination of the Ministry of Public Security and in collaboration with the public security authorities of Mainland China, “the PJ carried out a strong repression, which fought crime at its origin and dismantled its entire chain up to the black and gray industry that is behind”, stated the director of the corporation.
Furthermore, “it was possible to produce a deterrent effect on these illicit activities through several phases of the ant removal operation”. According to the data released, until last December, the police resolved 84 cases of illegal exchange of money for gambling, which resulted in the arrest of 120 fraudsters and the seizure of money and chips, with a total value exceeding 11 million Hong Kong dollars .
Following communication with the banks, the PJ revealed that 680 accounts suspected of being used by fraudsters were reported, with 991 websites being blocked that were used by fraudsters to try to achieve their intentions.
In 689 cases of various types of bank fraud, victims revealed their credit card details when trying to buy goods or services online, more than double the number recorded in 2023, causing losses of 14 million patacas.
The PJ noted at the conference that, thanks to an alert mechanism to suspend suspicious transactions and stop payments, it managed to recover almost 110 million patacas in 597 fraud attempts.
In the context of cross-border crime, the authorities arrested 236 members of groups, an annual increase of approximately 50%, having managed to dismantle “guess who am I” and false soothsayer networks, preventing the spread of crime, in collaboration with the Chinese police , Hong Kong and internationally.
 
Almost 1,500 investigations into gambling crimes
In other aspects, there was an increase in crimes of robbery, theft or crimes related to gambling, however, this number is still lower than in 2019. In cases linked to the gambling industry, 1,423 investigations and complaints were opened, amounting to an increase of 28.6% compared to 2023 and a reduction of 34% compared to 2019.
There were 252 cases of loan sharking and 47 cases of kidnapping. Despite being higher figures than in 2023, it is still significantly lower than what occurred in 2019. The proportion of violent and serious crimes related to gambling continued to decrease. “This is the very positive result of prevention and combat”, highlights the PJ.
Another issue addressed was the information given by the PJ about human trafficking, specifically that it had managed to prevent a resident from being a victim of human trafficking to a center, in Southeast Asia, dedicated to fraud and extortion using telecommunications and the Internet. Two weeks earlier, the PJ said that five residents had been victims of the same crime, in Taiwan and Cambodia, deceived with false promises of high remuneration for supposed jobs.
Finally, the statistics relating to serious and violent crimes. The director of the PJ considers that the situation has remained at a “very low” level. There was one case of homicide, three of serious bodily harm, none of kidnapping, one of secret association, 25 of criminal association, 12 of domestic violence, 43 of arson and 169 of extortion. All represent a reduction compared to 2023.
It should be noted that, during the last year, 14,049 criminal cases were initiated, registering an increase of 13.4%. Of this number, 7,762 are inquiries and complaints, which represents an increase of 14.1%. In 2024, the total number of completed processes was 12,856, which translates into an increase of 22.7%. Additionally, 3,323 individuals were referred to judicial bodies.
On the other hand, the PJ prosecuted 49 cases of trafficking and 15 cases of drug consumption, which represents a reduction of one case and an increase of six, respectively. In general, drug-related crimes remained a “limited occurrence”.</description><pubDate>2025-01-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>AI pets “comfort” young Chinese people</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/animais-de-estimacao-ia-consolam-jovens-chineses/</link><description>In a Beijing shopping mall, Zhang Yachun chats calmly with her best confidant: a stuffed robot with artificial intelligence whose captivating sounds make her feel like she doesn't feel alone.
The 19-year-old had long-standing anxiety problems at school and found it difficult to make new friends. However, he eventually found solace in “BooBoo,” a pet-like robot that uses artificial intelligence (AI) to interact with humans.
“I feel like I have someone to share happy moments with,” he confessed to AFP in his apartment, where he lives with his parents and a pet duck.
AI-powered devices are increasingly being used in China to combat social isolation.
“BooBoo”, a furry robot that looks like a guinea pig created by “Hangzhou Genmoor Technology”, costs 1,400 yuan. Since May last year, around a thousand copies of the rugby ball-sized robot, designed to meet the social needs of young people, have been sold, according to Adam Duan, from the company that developed it.
Zhang Yachun named his “Aluo” and carries it in a shoulder bag. Your furry companion has the same role as a human friend, she says, ensuring that “he makes us feel like someone is needed.”
The market for “social robots”, such as “BooBoo”, could grow seven times by 2033, reaching 42.5 billion US dollars, according to consultancy IMARC Group. Asia already dominates this market.
Guo Zichen, 33, believes that a pet robot makes up for the time he doesn't spend with his children. “People are spending less time with their children now”, observes this man, as he looks at a robot dog in a “Weilan” company store in Nanjing, in the east of the country. A robot can help “check or carry out other activities”, he highlights.
“Baby Alpha”, the robot dog from the company “Weilan”, is sold for 26,000 yuan. About 70% of buyers are families with young children, according to the company.
However, Guo Zichen is skeptical about the ability of these robots to provide the same joy as a flesh-and-blood dog. “The main difference is that real dogs have souls”, he highlights.
In China, there are a growing number of AI products that aim to respond to consumers' emotional needs, such as conversational agents or virtual avatars of deceased people.
According to several experts, the effects of the long-lasting one-child policy are boosting this market. People born at the beginning of this policy, in the 1980s, are now in their forties and often do not have time to dedicate themselves to their family, because competition for jobs is fierce.
This leaves “little space for personal interactions, which leads people to look for alternatives to meet their emotional needs”, considers Wu Haiyan, a professor specializing in AI and psychology at the University of Macau. This monitoring, even if it is virtual, “improves the well-being of individuals who would otherwise feel isolated”, says the researcher.
Zhang Peng, Zhang Yachun's father, understands his daughter's attachment to the robot “Aluo”. “When we were young, there was no shortage of friends. We had a lot of them as soon as we walked out the door,” explains the 51-year-old. But, “currently, young urban people seem to be under a lot of pressure and, as a result, may not have friends”, he adds.
Zhang Yachun, an only child, highlights that purchasing “Aluo” helped her discuss her concerns with her parents. “People of my generation generally have difficulty communicating in person, but what they feel inside hasn’t changed,” he says, stroking the mascot.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>