<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>More than half of public housing in zone A is ready by 2026</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-de-metade-da-habitacao-publica-na-zona-fica-pronta-ate-2026/</link><description>Next to eight thousand public housing fractions in the area A will be ready until next year, according to data from the Directorate of Public Works. In concrete, in 2026 there will be 2,352 social houses and 4,500 economic apartments, show information from the Housing Institute. Later this year and in the same area of ​​the city, 754 social housing houses are also expected to be completed. The data analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao point out that, until next year, more than half of public housing in zone A will be completed
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Next year, the design and construction of seven public housing buildings in zone A of the new landfills will be completed, according to the information provided by the Directorate of Public Works (DSOP) services. In addition, this year, in November, another public housing will be completed. It means that by 2026, they will be made available close to eight thousand public fractions in that new area of ​​the city, show the data from DSOP and the Housing Institute (IH) consulted by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao.
In concrete, and regarding next year, we talk about three social housing buildings and four economic housing. In lots A6, A10 and A11 will be available 2,352 social houses, namely 1,064 in the first, 728 in the second and 560 in the third. Regarding economic housing, lots A1, A2, A4 and A12 will offer, respectively, 880, 1,100, 1,566 and 954 fractions, totaling 4,500 apartments.
According to DSOP data, in February, public housing should be ready in lots A2 and A12, followed by buildings in lots A10 and A11 in July. Already in August, will be completed the houses in lot A1 and A4, and in September in lot A6. According to IH, the execution of the works of the structures is completed in all lots, and the interior remodeling is underway, except in the A6, where the construction of the buildings of the buildings is underway.
As for the public housing whose termination of the conception and construction work is scheduled for November, in Lot A3, will offer 754 houses. According to IH, “the execution of the structure of the structure is completed”, being underway the remodeling of interiors.
In total, 14 public dwellings are listed on the DSOP website of the new landfills, which will make 14,754 fractions available, some are still on planning, others should be ready in 2027 and 2028. Made the accounts, means that in the next year, more than 52%) will be completed if the deadlines are actually fulfilled. In total, there will be 7,606 houses.
It is recalled that, by the end of 2023, the then Chief Executive, Ho Iat Seng, confirmed that the construction plan of 28,000 public housing fractions and four thousand private buildings in zone A would be maintained. However, in March last year, the then Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raimundo do Rosário, revealed that the executive was going to suspend the building of economic houses for the A.
"Given the real demand of the population, the government will suspend the construction of five economic housing projects in zone A, originally scheduled for this year," the ruler said in the Legislative Assembly. The projects concerned involve a total of 5,700 fractions, which were planned for lots A13, B14, B15, B16 and B17.
 
Other projects
On the other hand, at the end of next year, in December, it is the time to end the building building of the collective use building in Lot A8 of Zone A. Regarding the educational building, in lot B1, foundations and cellars will be completed in September 2026.
Also in this area, it will be ready, early on the year, the work of conception and construction of the technical gallery and streets, specifically in the South Zone.
Regarding public housing, there is also highlighting the conclusion of the works of foundations and cellars of the building on Eight Street of the Iao Hon neighborhood, and the conception and construction contract is missing. In this case, 250 fractions will be available.
From other works that are under consideration, also the construction of the building of the last court, on Avenida da Praia Grande, whose work of superstructure will be ready in January; As well as the building of the building of the Second Instance Court, in lots C12 and C14 of Lake Nam Van, in this case will be completed in December.
In March 2026 it is also expected to end the construction contract for the foundations and cellars of the office building for the administration in the Zape area.
As for this year, it is expected that in December the work of demolition and foundations and cellars of the Central Library, where it was the former Hotel Estoril, as well as the foundations and cellars of the Support Building to the Athletes Training and Internship Center, on Tennis Street and Rua da Skating, next to the Training Center and athletes.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Music, Dance, Craft and Gastronomy at Sino-Lusophone Cultural Week</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/musica-danca-artesanato-gastronomia-na-semana-cultural-sino-lusofona/</link><description>This year's edition of China Cultural Week and Portuguese -speaking countries will take, for the first time, music and dance to the cities of Zhongshan and Beijing. The event starts 26 of this month and extends the program until November 18, with diverse activities, including a Craft Fair, Lusophone Gastronomy Workshops, exhibition of audiovisual works and musical shows. From Portugal will come the band “Karetus” and Brazil a samba school. One of the guest artisans is the Portuguese Arlindo Moura, who will present works in Filigrana



















Victor Rebelo
 
This broader year, with the extension of the program to two cities in the interior, Zhongshan and Beijing, where will take place exhibitions of music and dance, the 17th Cultural Week of China and Portuguese -speaking countries (PLP) on September 26 at the fishermen's dock, extending activities until November 18.
The event, whose motto is “playing the role of Macau as a platform, telling the Chinese stories well and articulating the capital of Beijing with the Great Bay”, will bring together artistic groups from China (Province of Qinghai) and nine PLP countries, namely Angola, Brazil, Cape Verde, Guinea-Bissau, Equatorial Guinea, Mozambique, Portugal, São Tome and Prince and Prince Timor-Leste.
The first seven days will feature daily sessions covering various topics, including dance and music, handicraft fair, gastronomic demonstrations and exhibition stalls and sale of products characteristic of PLP and Macao.
At the same time, cooking heads will collaborate with local restoration establishments in the fishermen's dock “to create unique menus that fuse authentic Lusophone flavors, offering an unforgettable dining experience,” according to a press conference, the organization of the forum forum for economic and commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries (Macau) Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment, Directorate of Tourism Services and Institute for Municipal Affairs.
With regard to music and dance shows, which constitute highlights of the program and are always attractive to the public, highlighting the trip of the Portuguese band “Karetus”, formed in 2010 by two old DJs and producers, Carlos Silva and André Reis, who have joined Paulo Silva and an MC.
In the known information about the band, it is a group passionate about innovative electronic music, starring energetic concerts on mixing styles and rhythms, which they call “Full Flavour”, whose main objective is to try to make and play good music.
The name of the band is inspired by the faces, traditional figures of Portugal, typical of carnival and Christmas, which convey joy and tradition.
In addition to the performance of the Luso ensemble, the cultural week will be filled with actions of the traditional Balet Tweza Ngola (Angola), Recreational Grêmio Nine Dragões School (Brazil), MC Speel (Cape Verde), united by a cause (Guinea-Bissau), Double M (Equatorial Guinea), Valdemiro José and Banda (Mozambique) (Sao Tome and Principe) and Salurik Banda (Timor-Leste).
In gastronomy activities, September 24 marks the beginning of culinary outreach events, with a lunch of Lusophone flavors, at Vic's restaurant, in the fishermen's dock.
“The goal is to enjoy unique gastronomies and wines from PLP,” said Danilo Henriques, Deputy Secretary-General of the Forum Secretariat, adding that the five bosses of Brazil, Cape Verde, Guinea-Bissau, Equatorial Guinea and Mozambique, together with Macao heads, “will create different menus in the space of the Doca Doca space. Fishermen, with dishes based on the cooking of their countries, where the public can taste these flavors. ” It will be between September 26 and October 2.
As for the Craft Fair, in the Legend Boulevard, which takes place during the same period, products made of refined handcrafted techniques will be displayed, including metal, silver, stone, wood and other material sculptures.
In the field of jewelery, Portugal will be represented by Arlindo Moura, considered one of the greatest experts in the production of pieces in Filigrana. The artisan, born in Gondomar, repeats his trip to the territory, since already in 2018 showed his works in this art of jewelery. One of his most emblematic works was a replica of the Gondomar City Council.
Its products, thus those of the other artisans, including a timor-Leste artist, equally of jewelery, can be acquired by visitors.
In evidence will also be, for the second year in a row, an initiative of the audiovisual and cultural exchange sector “Collective Audiovisual Works Exhibition of China and PLP”, which will take place on September 26, at the Movie Hall of the University of Science and Technology of Macao.
Will be presented, offline, three documentaries, one of which, “inspiration · Great Bay - an investigation from southern China by a French synologist”, unveils the secrets of the development of the region. The other films are “Marine Life”, which promotes diversity and harmonious coexistence between man and nature, and “ice kingdom”, which completely records the process of building the “snow and ice world in the city of Harbin”, highlighting the collaboration of farmers in extreme cold conditions.
The display of the documentaries will be followed by exchange sessions between production teams and directors. The films will be translated into Portuguese, being later offered for transmission at PLP stations.
The projection will be developed in conjunction with the “Exhibition of Plastic Arts of Portuguese -Speaking Countries”, which will be evident until November 18, and the “launch of the new PLP literary works book” to be held on October 24 at the Institute's Gallery for Municipal Affairs. This publication, entitled “Is this book a novel?”, It is by Angolan João Melo.
The cultural week will present, on the other hand, several tents for games and other fun, as well as to promote creative products of representatives of China and PLP.
 
Zhongshan and Beijing are associated with the event
For the first time, the event will transcend the borders of Macao, adopting a format of two main stages, Macau and Beijing, with an extension to the city of Zhongshan. Here, the main activities will take place from September 29 to October 12, with an opening ceremony, dance and music performances at Xingzhong Square, and the PLP countries' fine arts exhibition, which will take place at the Xiangshan Museum of Commercial Culture in the same period.
In Beijing, Big Shopping Park Square will host, on October 3rd and 4th, the opening ceremony and dance and music performances, in addition to promotional events with artistic groups in other points of interest to the Chinese capital.
"This expansion to Beijing and Zhongshan reflects the singular role of Macau as a sino-illusopone platform, turning the cultural week a window to demonstrate the successful practice of the" a country, two systems "principle, promotes multifaceted exchanges between China and PLP, spreads Chinese culture and fosters mutual learning between civilizations," says the permanent secretariat of the forum.
The participation of those two cities in the interior of China in this year's Cultural Week program increases the overall budget to a total of 19.4 million patacas, and the Macao part equals 2024 (13 million).
Yesterday, at the program's press conference, the permanent secretary's secretary general said that Cultural Week is a “very important tool to strengthen the humanistic exchange between China and PLP and also has a lot to do with Macao's goal to build a center”.
Xie Ying also pointed out that “our name has to do with economic and commercial cooperation, but in fact cooperation areas involve many aspects”, such as education, human resources, cultural exchange, technology, among others, “cultural exchange is a very important part” in cooperation between China and PLP. "Although countries are widely spread over a long distance, the secretariat and the government have offered a meeting platform for artists from different countries, which also allows the public to know their diverse cultures, and this reinforces the understanding between people," he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Will increase support to disabled and elderly in the purchase of equipment</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/vai-aumentar-apoio-deficientes-idosos-na-compra-de-equipamentos/</link><description>Later this year, financial support should be increased by elderly and people with disabilities to buy auxiliary equipment and home equipment, said the president of the Institute of Social Action. At this time, a pilot plans are being balanced, as well as a study for their optimization. The idea is that they become permanent plans, and it is expected to alleviate the application requirements
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The president of the Institute of Social Action (IAS) revealed that there will be an increase in financial support to the elderly and people with disabilities to buy auxiliary equipment, and the application requirements will be mitigated. Measures that Hon Wai expects them to be ready later this year.
It is recalled that “Financial Support Pilot Plan in the acquisition of auxiliary equipment for the disabled” and the “Financial Support Pilot Plan for the acquisition of auxiliary equipment and special household equipment” were launched in 2019 and 2021, respectively.
"Given the continuous increase in the demand for auxiliary equipment and special domestic equipment on the part [of people with] disabilities and the elderly, IAS is taking stock of the experience gained with the implementation of these pilot plans, so that they have permanent character," Hon Wai said in response to an interpellation of Deputy Nick Lei.
At the same time, a study of the optimization of these plans will be conducted, continued Hon Wai, ", in the sense that, namely, properly aligning the application requirements, as well as increasing the amount of financial support." "Efforts will be made to complete their work later this year," added the president of the body.
Alongside this, and after the opinion of Youth Education and Development Services, IAS recalled that the Educational Fund (FE) provides the “Financing Plan for the Acquisition of Auxiliary Equipment for Special Education students”, to support special education students who attend regular education and who have economic difficulties. Under the plan, these students can acquire support materials necessary for learning, "in order to ensure integration into school life."
According to the answer, this plan for special education students was optimized for this school year 2025/2026, “increasing the types of subsidized auxiliary equipment”. "In the future, FE will continue to review and optimize the content of the respective financing plans," he said.
On the other hand, the president of IAS also says that, in relation to the use of affected pools for people with disabilities, the Sport Institute “will perform the respective rates”, and the review is currently underway. The aim is that the new rates will be implemented later this year, "in order to encourage people with disabilities to participate in sports."</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DSPA Study Electric Vehicle Batteries</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/baterias-de-veiculos-electricos-alvo-de-estudo-da-dspa/</link><description>A study related to solid waste management, which includes measures for recycling electric vehicles, is being developed by environmental protection services. Meanwhile, a joint inspection mechanism was created to make periodic actions to the repair establishments of motor vehicles, aiming to warn of the duty to comply with the respective provisions
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) is developing a study related to solid waste management, including recycling and deactivated battery management measures. Currently, lithium batteries can be recycled through the electronic and electric equipment recycling program.
DSPA, which participates, at the request of the competent services, in the inspections to establishments and issues technical opinions within the scope of environmental protection, states that the company hired within that specialized personal provision to pretreat the batteries, namely dismantling, discharging electrical and sealing in order to ensure safety.
If an eligible institution accumulates 50 kg or more of batteries, the contracted company can offer a free collection service on site.
This information is contained in DSPA's response to a written interpellation of Deputy Ma Io Fong, in which the body points out the objective of “helping the sector in improving repair techniques and professional knowledge about electric vehicle safety”.
It also points out that, in articulation with the policy of promoting electric vehicles, in collaboration with competent services and associations, has already organized various training actions on repair and safety of that type of vehicles powered by electricity.
In the future, it reinforces the DSPA response signed by its director, IP Kuong Lam, this "will continue to maintain communication with the sector", as well as "will consider new training actions according to the actual situation." It also adds that the management of services for traffic issues organized, in 2024, two training actions on technologies and inspection of this type of vehicles with the participation of more than 100 graduates, following the continuous increase in the number of vehicles powered by new energies in Macao.
The courses have mainly focused on the structure and safety of vehicles powered by new energies, as well as in the requirements of the “National Standard for Vehicle Safety Performance Procedure powered to new energies”, recently implemented by the state. The purpose of these actions consisted of preparing human resources and technical capabilities, in view of the future definition of specifications and inspection requirements applicable to electric vehicles.
Meanwhile, the response to the interpellation of the Hemiciclo member also points out that DSPA, the Institute for Municipal Affairs and the Fire Department created a joint inspection mechanism. The same intends to perform periodic inspections to vehicle repair establishments and deliver the “guidelines for the control of pollution in motor vehicle repair workshops” and the “catalog of the general regulation of public spaces”, warning those responsible for the establishments for the duty to comply with the respective provisions.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong leader emphasizes stability and national identity</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/lider-de-hong-kong-enfatiza-estabilidade-identidade-nacional/</link><description>EPA12383930 Hong Kong Chief Executive John Lee Ka-Chiu Deliverse His 2025 Policy Address at The Legislative Counciling in Hong Kong, China, 17 Septamber 2025. Lee Histor Histo Polycy Address of Hist Five-Youar Term, Outlinging Measures to Boost The Economy, Improve Liveliods, and Strengthen the City's Integration with National Development Plans for the Special Administrative Region.  Epa/Leung Mah Hei



In the presentation of his Wednesdays of Government Action, Hong Kong's Chief Executive Highlighting yesterday the intention to promote patriotic education and reinforce the National Security Act, in an effort to consolidate stability and national identity. John Lee stressed the importance of deepening reforms, fostering economic growth and improving living conditions, capitalizing on Raehk's strengths.
Reflecting on the five years since the implementation of the National Security Law, Lee reiterated that Hong Kong has exceeded a period of "chaos and disorder" to head to prosperity. Still, it has promised to continue to improve the law and its execution mechanisms to punish any act that threatens national security.
According to the ruler, an exhibition on national security has attracted more than one million visitors since its inauguration in 2024, and more than 3,300 instructors were formed to promote awareness of the theme.
Lee also reaffirmed his commitment to the 'a country, two systems' principle - which he described as the best option to ensure long -term Hong Kong's prosperity and stability - and with the maintenance of the order stipulated in the Constitution and Basic Law.
The chief executive promised to promote facilities in mainland China as “bases for patriotic education” for students and young people. The Department of Education will integrate this subject in daily learning, as part of the efforts to strengthen national identity, he stressed.
 
Bet on yuan, AI and global connectivity
On the other hand, it outlined a plan to strengthen industry, economy and quality of life by leveraging Hong Kong's position as a global financial center, highlighting measures to consolidate Yuan, boost artificial intelligence (AI) and expand international connectivity. For the first time, he proposed the use of Chinese currency for government expenses, seeking to consolidate Hong Kong as the world's leading Yuan Settlement Center.
Hong Kong (HKMA) monetary authority will facilitate quotations and transactions in regional currencies, issue more titles called Yuan and encourage business emissions. In addition, connections with markets such as Switzerland and the United Arab Emirates will be opened, and the use of Chinese titles as a guarantee is allowed.
Among other measures, Lee also announced the creation of the “Task Force Goglobal”, which will support continental companies in their expansion to Southeast Asia and Middle East. HKMA will encourage Chinese banks to open regional headquarters and organize missions with banking association in markets such as Vietnam.
In innovation, AI will be a central area: an I&amp;D institute will be established by 2026 with a billion of Hong Kong's dollars, while a three billion program will attract international investigators. AI will be applied to government systems, hospitals and customer service, including chatbots and caregiver support robots.
In the sea sector, which represents 10% of the global fleet, the ships will be digitized and the launch of a community port system in 2026. There will be tax exemptions and a risk capital fund to reinforce subscription.
Similarly, the attraction of international auctioneers and galleries to consolidate Hong Kong as an artistic center will be encouraged. Finally, Lee will promote gold trade with "tokenized" products, a centralized compensation system and mutual access to the Shangoi Golden Bag.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Studio City opens “IRAD” medical center in October</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/studio-city-abre-centro-medico-irad-em-outubro/</link><description>Melco will inaugurate a clinic operated by the “IRAD” group in October, in a contract that extends until November 2034. Studio City's new medical center will offer a variety of medical image and diagnostic services services
 
Pedro Milheirão
Hong Kong's “IRAD” group will open a clinic at Studio City in October, with an area of ​​1,172 square meters and equipment from Raehk, according to an announcement by Melco quoted by the “Gggrasia” portal. The partnership will imply monthly payments from Melco to the “IRAD” of 2.08 million patacas per month, during the first three months, and 1.25 million, from 4th to 34th month of activity. The contract will be valid until November 2034, with the option of being renewed "for two more periods of five years each".
The proposal was defined by Melco as part of an operator's investment commitment, under his new 10 -year concession terms, which began on January 1, 2023. In the past, the concessionaire had already mentioned a plan to launch an “IRAD” medical center in its integrated resort, with “medical diagnostic services, including magnetic resonance imaging, computed tomography and 2D mammography, as well as services, as well as services ultrasound and x-rays ”.
In the document quoted by “Gggrasia”, Melco states that the subsidiary “Studio City Retail Services” had signed an agreement with the Hong Kong medical group, in force since the beginning of this year, which gives Raehk company the “right to operate a private hospital focused on medical image and diagnostic services at the Studio City integrated resort”.
Melco explained that the initial investment will help “IRAD” “cover capital expenses such as pre-opening costs and computer and office technology equipment, as well as essential day-to-day operating expenses, including the recruitment and employment of qualified health professionals”.
In July, the Hong Kong company began recruiting medical staff for the private clinic to be inaugurated at the Melco resort, in the areas of aesthetic medicine, general medicine and radiography services, among other posts.
"Industry support is expected to be allocated by approximately 8% for capital expenses and 92% for operating expenses, especially labor costs to hire experienced radiologists and medical personnel, reflecting the need to bring experienced medical professionals to the relatively new health care market," said the operator.
For its part, the medical group will have to pay an income at a base rate of 694,981 patacas per month, or a rate of 1.5% of monthly turnover, if higher than the base rate. "IRAD will only be required to pay the highest base rate or the turnover fee, but not both," says the Melco document. From the fourth year, the Hong Kong company will have to pay a management fee of 61,450 monthly patacas.
Other game operators have also been intended to open medical spaces to help Macau diversify their economy and develop medical tourism in the region.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New houses for sale in the new neighborhood</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/novas-casas-a-venda-novo-bairro/</link><description>Sales of Torre 11 apartments of the “New neighborhood of Macau” start tomorrow, with several promotions for new buyers, according to Macau Renewal Urbana
 
Towering the “New neighborhood of Macau” tower tomorrow starts tomorrow in Hengqin, according to Macau Urban Renewal. To mark the occasion, the “New Macao neighborhood” will launch the “Massive Triple Treat” initiative for new buyers, with discounts on parking spaces, renewals and electrodomestic equipment.
The two -bedroom apartments have an area of ​​about 88 square meters. The three bedroom units are approximately 188 square meters. In addition to having seven apartments per floor and the all glazed elevator lobby, the large corridors, with “open view”, create a “light and airy” environment.
All units are fully equipped, with heating, air conditioning, smart gas water heaters and have balconies in the kitchen and living room. The kitchens are equipped with brand disinfection cabinets, gas stoves and exhausts.
To ensure “a rich and varied leisure lifestyle”, the “New Macao neighborhood” also offers a “Shuttle Bus” service and the possibility of enjoying the new tower 4 Clubhouse facilities. These include a pilates studio, a gym room, a kid and a billiard room, in addition to the existing table, yoga and ion rooms rooms. Gymnasium. In addition, the neighborhood also welcomes “large -scale festive events”.
The venture is located between the Xiao Hengqin mountain, to the north, and the Tianmu River, to the south, in a “harmonious” scenario, with “splendid mountains, crystal clear waters and a serene environment”, with a green area above 35%, the statement says.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MSAR WALL Wood forum for the 3rd year in a row</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-acolhe-forum-de-madeira-pelo-3o-ano-seguido/</link><description>For the third consecutive year, Macau will again receive the Global Legal and Sustainable Wood Forum, with dozens of activities under the theme “From Forest to Home”. Conferences and exhibition will be focused on the supply chains and the sustainability of the industry
 
Pedro Milheirão
On September 23 and 24, representatives of the forest, wood and furniture industries, from 40 countries, will meet at MGM Cotai, for the Global Forum of Legal and Sustainable Madeira. During the event, about 20 activities will be held, such as “Conferences, Rounds, Exhibitions, B2B Business Meetings and Launch Sessions”, according to the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM). “From Forest to Home - International Dialogue on Consumer and Innovation Trends in the Supply Chain” will be the theme of this year's edition.
The prominent conferences will focus on “consumer trends in the global industry of Madeira and Innovation in the Supply Chain”, the “new trends of consumption of wood products and the furniture and decoration industry” and the “legality and sustainability of wood”. In focus will also be the “sustainable resources of wood, markets and commerce”, “market trends and development of the furniture and personalized decoration industry for home” and the “sustainable development of global forests and supply chain financing”.
At the same time, the “Sustainable Wood Exhibition” will provide approximately 30 stands for international companies, associations and organizations. Participating entities will come from countries and regions such as the interior of China, Macau, Brazil, Japan, Germany, Indonesia, Malaysia, Thailand, Switzerland and Italy. On display, there will be a variety of forest and wood products, such as blasts, sawders, furniture, floors, panels, wooden doors and handcrafted pieces.
With the show, IPIM expects to be provided “pairing opportunities in various scenarios between suppliers and buyers”, encouraging “sector product and technologies cooperation”.
In addition, several representatives of different sectors of Macau activity will discuss “the perspectives of masters in the areas of green and low carbon initiatives, green finances, forest investment, interior design and furniture, sustainable wooden development and business culture of the large bay,” IPIM said. The purpose of the initiative will be to “encourage innovation and modernization throughout the forest and wooden industry chain at global level”, can read.
The Forum has been held annually at MSAR, since 2023, taking advantage of the Macao Convention and Exhibition Platform and based on various transnational action plans, such as the action of promoting legal and sustainable wood supply chains or the global index platform of Madeira, among others.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Rolls” to players reached 26 billion</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/borlas-aos-jogadores-atingiram-26-mil-milhoes/</link><description>The global expenses of the game sector rose 18% last year. It should be noted that companies continued to spend a high amount on free goods and services for customers, in a amount of almost 26 billion, representing an annual rise of 31%
 
Exploration expenses in the 2024 game sector show that spending on goods and services provided free to customers - such as hotel and restoration rooms - rose 31% in annual terms to 25.58 billion Patacas reveal data from the Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). The amount represents 63% of the total exploration expenses, which reached 40.58 billion patacas, an increase of 28% compared to 2023.
Also in this chapter there are also spending on management services and services hired to third parties, which rose to 6.99 billion patacas (+29.4%), and market prospecting, advertising and marketing, where 2.67 billion (+28.0%) were spent.
According to the DSEC, the global expenses of the sector, excluding taxes, set at 94.37 billion patacas, an increase of 18% in annual terms. Expenses for purchases of goods, commissions and customer offerings (23.20 billion) also increased 28%, while staff expenses (21.48 billion) grew by 7%.
In turn, non -operational expenses (which include interest and depreciation) dropped 9.6%to 9.10 billion.
According to DSEC, in 2024, the game sector "registered a gradual recovery as tourist activities returned to normality in a stable manner, with the sector's revenues and expenses to grow." Namely, global revenues (including those of the game and others) rose 23.1%, ciphering at 231.45 billion.
Note that the inquiry into the game sector mainly collects statistical data related to game activities, with the companies.
In 2024 there were nine companies that explored game activities, one of which - the Jockey Club - ceased activities. At the end of last year, there were six fortune or bad lucky games and two who explored lottery activities. From this inquiry the data on hotels, retail trade, among others, exploited in companies are excluded.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Fewer fossil fuels and more electric motors</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/menos-combustiveis-fosseis-mais-motores-electricos/</link><description>Consumption and imports of fuel for vehicles decreased in the first half of the year compared to the same period of 2024. The phenomenon is partly due to the increase in the number of electric vehicles. According to official data, families and commercial and industrial sectors consumed less electricity, in annual terms, while the consumption of public institutions grew
 
Pedro Milheirão
Vehicle gasoline consumption decreased about 10%in the first half of the year to a total of 38.6 million liters, compared to the same period of 2024. Similarly, the use of diesel also dropped 9.6%to a total of 44.1 million liters, according to the direction of statistics and censuses (DSEC) services (DSEC).
The break in consumption was also accompanied by a descent in average fuel prices. In the first half of this year, vehicle diesel cost, on average, 15.88 patacas per liter, less 3.3% than at the same interval of 2024. The average price of gasoline without lead was 14.41 patacas, corresponding to an annual decrease of 2.57%.
In general, fuel imports have all decreased, like consumer trends. The MSAR bought less diesel from mainland China and Singapore, whose imports registered breaks of 14.89% and 18.1%, respectively, to 54.3 million and 7.3 million liters.
Vehicle gasoline imports also fell. Between January and June, the MSAR imported 39 million liters from the interior of China, compared to the 40 million liters recorded in the first half of 2024, corresponding to a decrease of 3%. The purchase of gasoline from Saudi Arabia also decreased about 9.4%to 889 thousand liters.
Among other factors, the generalized descent in imports and fuel consumption may be explained by increasing electric vehicles in the territory. Light electric cars grew 47.5%to a total of 7,591, while light cyclomotors increased 78.75%to 1,943. Electric heavy motorcycles went from 2,582 to 3,593 and the electrical heavy cars from 1,132 to 1,259.
At the end of June, 6.3% of the 113,500 light cars enrolled in the MSAR were electrical, plus 1.9 percentage points in homologous terms. Regarding heavy cars, 18.8% of the 5.4 thousand vehicles were electric, corresponding to an annual increase of 2.1 percentage points. In the category of light mopeds, the electric models began to represent almost 11% of the vehicles of this typology enrolled in Macau, almost double the quota they represented in the same month of 2024 (5.9%).
Although another 1,510 light cars with combustion engines were registered, there was a decrease in heavy cars (-209) and light mopeds (-1,484) with traditional engines, according to DSEC data.
Another aspect to highlight is the evolution of the different forms of electricity production, which indicate that Macau has also been moving to cleaner energy sources. In the second quarter of 2025, electricity from natural gas rose 9%, in homologous terms, to 269 million kWh, although the total gas consumption of the MSAR has fallen 5.6%to 80.2 million cubic meters. For its turn, production originated from fuels fell a third to 10 million kWh. In addition, the electricity produced through the incineration of garbage also descended to 53 million kWh (-8.6%).
In the general calculation, families consumed 2.65%of electricity less, in annual terms, while consumption by the industrial sector and trade registered descents of 3.9%, 0.9%, respectively. On the other hand, government institutions, which include public administrative services, urban public lighting and health and teaching care institutions, consumed 1.8% more electricity.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>100 vacancies for new SME support program</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/100-vagas-para-novo-programa-de-apoio-pme/</link><description>Between October and December, local companies will be able to compete for the classification program “Stores with specialized and delicate characteristics” of the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services. Limited to 100 vacancies, the plan aims to provide financing and counseling to the selected companies
 
The Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) will open 100 vacancies for the “Financial Support Plan for Stores with specialized and delicate characteristics”. The first round of applications for the new classification will take place between October 21 and December 2. The classification “Stores with specialized and delicate characteristics” will allow small and medium -sized companies (SMEs) to receive financial support and professional counseling, DSEDT announced.
Selected companies will be able to receive 60% financing of the value of designated rates related “with the implementation of online marketing, creating distinct monsters and launching collaboration products with intellectual property”, a maximum of 150,000 patacas, the statement says.
To apply, candidates must already hold the “Certified Store” qualification. In addition, they will have to present a business plan and exploration project that can be evaluated and improved with the help of Macao's productivity and technology transfer center if companies are selected.
This year, the classification program also introduced the distinction “Centenary brand”, based on the “typical brand of Macau”, in the sense of “further improving the classification criteria, emphasizing both historical continuity and brand value”. Registration for both categories opened this week and extend until November 30th.
In the presentation of the programs, the president of Macau Chain Stores and Franchise Association, Wong Ian Man, said they are being carried out “the preparatory work of the 'Centenary brand' and the new edition of Macau's 'typical brand'”. These include “the creation of the classification committee, negotiation on the classification criteria, compilation and updating of the companies' database and conducting specific visits to community neighborhood stores,” Wong said.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Reinforcement Reinforcement of Young Employment Support</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pedido-reforco-apoio-ao-emprego-jovem/</link><description>In the context of the elaboration of the lines of government action, the Secretary for the Economy and Finance met with various associations. Among the topics discussed include requests for reinforcing youth employment support and continuing measures to help small and medium enterprises
 
The Secretary for Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP, has met with “Think Tank” associations to hear opinions in the context of the elaboration of the government lines. Some of the themes in focus were young employment and support for small and medium -sized companies (SMEs).
Firstly, the executive vice president of the Grand Thought Think Tank, Yin Yifen, "recommended reinforcement of youth job support." The president of the Board, Law Ngan Leng, suggested reinforcing global planning and coordination of the development of the proper diversification of the economy, “promoting the cultural industry and the economy of low altitude” and “deepening the integrated construction of Macao and Hengqin”.
The Association also presented proposals related to the creation of a good business environment, attraction of visitors to the community neighborhoods, promoting the construction of the “city of gastronomy” and impulse to the creation of the investment fund.
On the other hand, and according to a statement from the secretary's office, the president of the Union of scholars, IP Kuai Peng, presented suggestions for the “optimization of the IP economy and the support for the employment of young people”. What suggestions were these, the statement does not refer. Vice President Chan Peng Peng suggested that the attractiveness of the six major historical areas increased further.
The Union of Macao scholars also presented suggestions on the capture of international tourists, the revitalization of the old neighborhoods and the simplification of the commercial registration regime.
The vice president of the Board of the Macao Economic Association, Lei Chun Kuok, predicted that Macau's economy could register a growth between 3% and 5% this year, suggesting that the development of SMEs is continued, promoting the actual IP economy, implementing the government fund for industries and the guidance for the transformation of scientific and technological results. At the same time, he asked for efforts to attract investments. In turn, Deputy Secretary-General Wong Un Fai, presented suggestions to develop the night economy, the obligation market and expand the scenarios of PATACA application.
Regarding the IP economy, the secretary general of the Strategic Research Center for the development of Macao, Chan Chi Fong, "recognized its effectiveness," read the press, having suggested "suggested the introduction of various types of IP combined with the unique characteristics of Macao."
The Department of Study of Economic Policies of Doctoral Think Tank, by the words of its coordinator Chan Kam Kun, "recognized the effectiveness of the revitalization of Zape and has made recommendations to reinforce cooperation and promoting the combat of capital bleaching, as well as to improve the ease of visa abroad."
Finally, the president of the Directorate of the Political Economy Study Association, Tong Kai Chung, pointed out that "currently there are still uncertainties in the global economy." In this sense, and taking into account the economic recovery of the interior of China and “the energetic efforts of the Government of MSAR” to promote the diverse development “1 + 4”, argued that “SMEs must take the initiative to adjust business strategies and accelerate transformation and modernization”. At the same time, it recommended that the government continue to support the SMEs.
The vice president, Liu Yide, made suggestions on creating a specific fund to support technological innovation companies, accelerate the implementation of the investment fund law and cultivate diverse talents.
In the replica, Tai Kin IP stressed that his team "will continue to improve SME support measures, streamline the community economy, optimize employment support services, [as well as] reinforcing preparatory work for the revitalization of historical zones." He assured that all efforts will be made to “formulate policies in the area of ​​economics and finances that correspond to real needs”.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sands and Associations held responsible game fair for families</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sands-associacoes-realizaram-feira-de-jogo-responsavel-para-familias/</link><description>The third game fair responsible for families of Sands China brought to Londoner close to 160 company workers and members of local organizations, accompanied by their families, for a series of financial management activities
 
Sands China organized the third edition of its family -responsible game fair, which took place at Londoner, in collaboration with five Macao associations. About 160 game operator workers and members of the associations participated, in the company of their families, in the 12 activities designed to cultivate “good financial habits”, under the theme “seek help to win the future” of the government.
Wilfred Wong, Sands China's executive vice president, stressed that since 2023, the initiative "has educated children in a fun way to help them understand the importance of learning to spend, save and make rational decisions" in building "a prosperous future through financial education between parents and children." "We firmly believe that the only way to instill the concept of the game responsible in every corner of the community is to continually put efforts on promoting education and prevention," Wong said, quoted in a Sands note.
The fair was co-organized by the Coordinating Office of Sheng Kung Hui Macao Social Services, Macao Youth Christian Association, the Macao Game Industry House, the Macao Voluntary Youth Association and the Bosco Juvenile Services Network. The event was supported by the Institute of Social Action, the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services, the University of Macao and the Macao Polytechnic University.
Sands China was one of the first operators to include formations about the game responsible in its employee orientation program. The responsible game program, established in 2007, defined the objective of "contributing to the continuous development of the community of Macao, assuming corporate responsibility in addressing social issues."</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Jennifer Lawrence, Binoche and Farrell, Stars of the San Sebastián Festival</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/jennifer-lawrence-binoche-farrell-estrelas-festival-de-san-sebastian/</link><description>The San Sebastián Film Festival, which begins on Friday, will honor American actress Jennifer Lawrence and will feature other stars such as Colin Farrell and Juliette Binoche, in an official section with a strong presence of Argentine and Spanish films.
The French actress winner of the Oscar (“The English Patient”) will present in the official section, but out of competition, her debut as a director, “In-i In Motion”, a documentary about a theatrical tour held in 2007. Paul Dano, Matt Dillon, Ron Pearl, Harris Dickinson and Stellan Skarsgard are other recognizable faces that will parade for parade Red carpet of the festival, which takes place in northern Spain, from September 19th to 27th.
The 73rd edition of this festival, the smallest of major film meetings in Europe after Cannes and Venice, will be inaugurated with the exhibition of “27 Noches”, Argentine production directed by Uruguayan Daniel Hendler. Two other Argentine feature films will compete for the best film award: “Las Corrientes” by Milagros Mumenthaler and “Belén” by Dolores Fonzi, in a official section that also features French Claire Denis (“The Fence”), German Edward Berger (“Ballad of a Player”) and Belgian Joachim Lafosse (“Six Jours CE Printemps-Là ”).
The host country participates in the official section with four competition productions, including Alberto Rodríguez's “Los Tigers”, the director of “Old Sins, Long Shadows” who returns with a story starring Antonio de la Torre and Bárbara Lennie, and “Maspalomas”, Basque filmmakers Jose Mari Goenaga and Aitor Arregi.
In total, 17 films rival the official section, whose jury, chaired by Spanish director J.A. Bayona, will decide the main awards to be delivered to the closing ceremony on the 27th.
 
“Destroy Gaza”
As with Cannes and Venice, the participating personalities are expected to comment on the situation in the Gaza Strip and the Israeli offensive, although this time the festival itself has already shown its repudiation to the “unimaginable massacres” that would occur there.
"They kill Palestinian civilians. They kill girls and boys. They kill journalists and humanitarian workers. They use hunger as a weapon (…) destroy Gaza," said the festival's management committee in a statement published in recent days. "It is necessary, therefore, to condemn today ... The genocide that is being perpetrated by the government" of Benjamin Netanyahu, added the text, demanding "an immediate ceasefire and the liberation of all hostages kidnapped by Hamas."
The festival's belligerent stance takes place in a country whose leftist government has become one of the most critical European voices for Netanyahu and where pro-Palestinian protests are frequent, including those who led to the cancellation of the last stage of Spain last Sunday in Madrid.
One of the San Sebastián Festival Honorary Honorary Awards will be handed over to American actress Jennifer Lawrence, Oscar's winner for her role in “Silver Linings Playbook” and is expected in Basque city on September 26. The other Donostia award of this edition will be awarded to Spanish Esther García, who since 1986 has been a producer of Pedro Almodóvar's films and has accumulated six Goya awards during his career.
At the festival, considered as a bridge to Europe of Latin American cinema, 12 films from Argentina, Brazil, Chile, Colombia, Ecuador, Mexico and Uruguay will compete for the Latin Horizon Award.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>