<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>“Adopter a grandfather” program fights loneliness among the elderly</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/programa-adopte-um-avo-combate-solidao-entre-idosos/</link><description>Solitude is a reality among the elderly who are admitted to the homes - to combat this feeling, the Santa Casa created the project “adopt a grandfather”, which has been fruit and, if all goes as planned, will grow in May to reach the bedridden elderly. Chao Sai Cham, 94, always expects SJM volunteers "come back again", while Kuok Tang Fong, 78, says they are "more intimate" than the family itself



















































Catarina Pereira
 
Chao leaves call a small photo album, points to the smiling faces and speaks of those different, happier days. Sitting in the living room of the Our Lady of Mercy Home -the skin of the face very smooth to hide the 94 years -says she arrived at the institution almost two years ago. Since then, and despite being quite active and being surrounded by many people, it makes sense what loneliness is. “My children are abroad, I'm here alone. I feel very alone, ”he says to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao.
The elderly woman spoke after another session of the program "Adopts a grandfather", launched last year by Santa Casa da Misericórdia, in collaboration with SJM Resorts volunteers, and which intends to help combat loneliness among the elderly of home. Chao Sai Cham says they all seem "a big family."
Born in Hong Kong, she moved with her husband to Macau after marrying. “My husband passed away and I was alone,” he says, and then add: “One day in Tai Chi class, he told a friend that he lived alone. She told me it was very dangerous, if no one would fall to know… He told me it was better to go to a home. ” And so it was.
It is "autonomous", as she herself says. The day begins with breakfast, then goes to the porch. “I do gymnastics and Tai Chi,” says Chao Sai Cam, always smiling. He likes to read newspapers and search for health and nutrition mobile phone information. “And at night, I have traditional Chinese medical classes. I see on YouTube, ”he says. "I take notes and everything." There are also days when it suits lunch with friends and Tai Chi master, but most of the time spend it at home.
The volunteers of the project "adopt a grandfather" came to bring some animation to the days. Chao Sai Cham says that those volunteers are "very friendly". “They bring a lot of games and talk,” he says, saying that in festive times they carry activities alluding to celebrations, such as Christmas, Easter, the Chinese New Year. This was the case, on the day the JTM visited the home of Our Lady of Mercies - the elderly, or rather the elderly, because they were only women, were committed, together with the volunteers, to set up flashlights at the festival of the lanterns.
For Chao comes out the activity "was a challenge." “My eyes are no longer that well. And today it was a very thorough activity, ”he explained, saying, yet it was“ fun ”. Everything they produce during these sessions, the 94 -year -old lady keeps in the room. “It's all there, so when I look at things I remember these moments,” he says.
“They are very good people, I hope whenever they come back again. And they are very sincere, I trust them and I can talk about everything, ”says Chao Sai Cham. The home and SJM initiative happens twice a month, and there are two fixed groups of elderly who are visited, one of each of these times, also always by the same volunteers.
Gisela Nunes, driving and coordinator of the initiative, explained that “the elderly sometimes feel some loneliness,” a problem that worsened during the three years of pandemic. “Being alone and feeling only two different things…” he continued, pointing out that Santa Casa invited the SJM volunteer team to launch the program in January last year.
The program aims to customize the friendship needs of each user with regular visits from their “godparents”, explains Gisela Nunes. “Throughout the year, beautiful friendships were established. The balance is very positive, especially with regard to the affection and positive energy that the volunteers led to the hearts of home users, ”he noted. The initial phase integrates 20 elderly without mobility problem and more than 40 game operator volunteers.
For the future, the idea is to bring this joy to the elderly, this time, those who have no mobility. The new phase of the initiative is pointed out for May. The home of Our Lady of Mercy has 129 beds, with about 95 elderly. About 98% of the elderly who are admitted are bedridden and dependent.
“Frequent activities not only enrich the spiritual life of the elderly, but it also allows them to remember the atmosphere between friends and family,” Gisela Nunes continued. "What is even more touching is that the team of volunteers always carefully plan the content of the various activities according to the physical fitness and the conditions of the 'godchildren', so that they are not just 'spectators' in activities, but those who participate physically and intellectually," he said.
Also the Santa Casa Secretary-General noted that the elderly who make up this project “beyond ancient memories, now also have recent memories” of contact with other people other than home employees or, in some cases, family members and friends who visit them.
The institution was inspired by a project that was born in Spain-"adopts a abuelo." It was in 2013 that Spanish Alberto Cabanes decided to create the project after a personal experience in a senior home. Alberto Cabanes, visiting his grandfather, noticed that most of the occupants of the home did not receive visits from family or friends. Even one of the users he met at home, Bernardo, without children, told him that the biggest dream was to have grandchildren to visit him for Christmas. Alberto Cabanes realized his desire and decided to adopt Bernardo.
 
“They are more intimate than my family”
The regent of the Home of Our Lady of Mercy, Paulo Cartaxo, noted that "loneliness is a fact" among the elderly - "and is one of the worst things that can happen to people in a home, because they have no family or friends, or because their lives do not allow visits so often." Paulo Cartaxo says that the initiative “adopts a grandfather” “is not a replacement for a visit by a family member or a friend, but a way of showing appreciation, speaking, listening”.
And one can see that the elderly react well: "They look at this as a very positive thing." Paulo Cartaxo indicated that, at home, there are "a lot of elderly people" who do not receive visits regularly, "some because of their age and because family members are in other countries, others because family members work in Hong Kong or are not always here, or in China." "We try to give priority to these people to have a little of contact and comfort," he added.
At the age of 78, Kuok Tang Fong also says he is “very active” - he usually leaves home and going to the day centers. “I will talk to the other old men, as a volunteer,” says JTM. Her husband died very early and Kuok Tang Fong got used to living alone-almost 40 years ago.
He learned to get ways to spend time, but admits that he likes it very much of the volunteer company. “When they come, it's always different. They bring games, talk a lot, ask questions and I answer. They want to know what I have been doing… ”, says the elderly woman, who for almost six years has entered the home of Our Lady of Mercy. Recalling the meetings sessions with the volunteers, he says that he has learned a lot: "They are taught to do manual work, that's good."
As for the family, Kuok Tang Fong notes that "the first generation has been all away." The daughter, in turn, who lives in Zhongshan, “comes home one, two or three times a year,” he notes. When we ask you if volunteers are like family, the elderly woman is peremptory: "Volunteers don't look like my family - they are even more intimate than my own family."
They came to change the way he lives in the home. “The home itself is very good, but with the visits I am even more happy,” he continues. The elderly woman says that social equipment staff are "very attentive," but "they have their work." “They can't always be taking care of us, so it's great to have these 'godparents',” he says.
 
“We want to widen the affection, the friendship”
José Luís Achiam, coordinator of the SJM volunteer team, also outlined a very positive balance. “I believe the project is walking very well. This is the first time SJM has been such a program, in these molds, with the home, and I think it will be the first of the genre in Macau, where the same volunteers always visit the same seniors, ”he said.
Volunteers were “finger chosen” as the responsibility is great: to be available to visit the elderly every month. "This is very important, because otherwise the elderly are waiting for the volunteer and it does not appear, which will generate a lot of sadness," José Luís Achiam. The meetings between volunteers and the elderly last for about two hours.
“For SJM it is also essential to participate in this genre of initiatives, since it has this culture of social responsibility,” noted the coordinator.
As for the volunteers, they participated in seminars organized by Santa Casa, through the home, on interaction skills with the elderly, the difference between independent and bedridden elderly, as well as on loneliness and the various degrees of dementia.
Before each visit, and according to Gisela Nunes, the "godparents" prepare topics of conversation, games and interactive sessions that focus on the cognitive skills of an elderly - focus, creativity, memory and understanding. "Unfortunately there is no cure for dementia, but maintaining quality of life and promoting well-being, such as the practice of physical activity and participation in activities and social interactions, help to stimulate the brain," he noted.
José Luís Achiam noted that “volunteers are enjoying the project a lot”. As for the new phase of the initiative, the idea is that the focus is focused on the bedridden elderly. “In the next phase, the activities they will bring will be different. And they will have with them to the room… it will be more visual things and conversations, there will be no games, for example. But it's a company. ”
In the next phase the number of volunteers is expected to grow to 50, at least that's the objective, “so that they can simultaneously take over these elderly and the bedridden,” explained Gisela Nunes, and then add: “We don't want to enter the second phase and then reduce the activities of these independent seniors. What we want is to widen the affection, friendship, to others. ”</description><pubDate>2025-03-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Caeal recognizes “gray zones” in the interpretation of the electoral law</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/caeal-reconhece-zonas-cinzentas-na-interpretacao-da-lei-eleitoral/</link><description>The role to play by the media in the dissemination of news about the next September elections is considered, by the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly, "fundamental to creating an environment of impartiality." CAEAL recognizes, however, that there are “gray zones” in the interpretation of the law
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) promoted a lecture directed to the Communication Bodies (OCS), in order to disclose the main recommendations for the coverage of the next September electoral act, as well as to receive suggestions.
In the opening speech of the session, the president of Caeal stated that journalists "play a role of bridge and platform that connects all sectors of society" and, therefore, "are an indispensable element in the elections." Considering that the OCS also constitute “an essential means of inspection for elections to take place according to the law,” Seng Ioi Man recalls that the entire population, “without exception”, will have to comply with what is determined.
That is, the official recalled that any electoral propaganda is prohibited, “that can be understood as an early campaign”, between June 27 and August 29, and that the campaign will take place between August 30 and September 12. The 13th will be of reflection and 14 will take place the suffrage.
OCS's main issues focused precisely on the prohibition period, raising doubts about what may or may not be reported. Seng Ioi Man said that the press, written or spoken, "knows very well what should or should not do" and that Caeal has not promoted the lecture to "teach the OCS to do its work, which has always been done with great professionalism, but, together, we can create an impartial environment."
The committee chairman admitted that there are "gray zones" in the interpretation of the law and clarified that, for example, news about campaign actions carried out by the groups of candidates or associations created for the purpose of election on the last day of the campaign, on September 12, can be released the next day (already in full ban…) and their online contents do not need to be removed.
The reasonableness of some situations has been guided in the answers given to OCS by Seng Ioi Man, as can happen with broadcasting on radio or television. "What we want is that they have the same goal as we, who is to comply with the law, to ensure impartiality in the elections and to deal with equality all definitely admitted application lists," he said.
Admitting that the internet and social networks came to “change society”, Seng Ioi Man asked for a greater containment and attention to what should or should not be permitted by law in the news coverage of the elections.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese vice-PM says Mand's economy is in a "key phase"</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/vice-pm-chines-diz-economia-da-raem-esta-numa-fase-chave/</link><description>Deputy Prime Minister Ding Xuexiang has accentuated yesterday that Macau is in a "important phase" in terms of economic development. In this sense, he urged the Macao vowels at CCPPC to fully support the Government of Masters to “have a good opening”
 
The vowels of Hong Kong and Macao at the 14th Chinese Povo Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC) participated yesterday in Beijing, in a joint meeting that aimed to discuss the central government's work report and was attended by Chinese vice-prime minister.
Ho Ion Sang, a member of the CCPPC Permanent Committee, has revealed that the vice-PM expects Macau vowels to fully support the mashed government to “have a good opening” as Macau is in a “important and key phase” of “fighting for the economy and seeking development”.
According to Ho Ion Sang, Ding Xuexiang also expects vowels to move more to community neighborhoods to perceive the public situation and reinforce the exchange of international cooperation, playing well the role of “super contact person”. In addition, they were urged to understand, learn and reinforce the spirit of the spirit of the “two sessions”, so that the Macau audience knows national political guidelines and development opportunities, thus gaining more confidence.
Vowel Frederico MA indicated that the vice-PM said he hoped the competent departments to consider some suggestions for MSAR vowels, including greater integration with Hengqin in the domains of human resources, finance and logistics.
According to vowel Chen Jimin, the vice-PM "encouraged" vowels to play the positive double role in the domains of science and technology, industrial innovation and education, proactively articulating with the country's strategies.
A meeting was held among MSAR vowels at CCPPC, with Edmund Ho, Vice President of CCPPC, to exhort representatives of the territory to “persist in four aspects”. In concrete, he expects them to persevere in learning and innovation to constantly raise their political abilities, increase the quality of the suggestions presented, active and face -to -face participation in “interconnection with the interior of China and connection abroad”, as well as in fulfilling the functions to better promote inclusion and harmony.
 
Suggested Syno-Delusópone Logistics in Hengqin
Moreover, in the “two sessions”, Ho Ka Lon, a CCPPC vowel, proposed the creation of a “Syno-Lusophone Commodity Trade Center”, including an “international logistics base” in the deepened cooperation zone, which serves to provide an import base and a surveillance space for commodities, electronic components, aircraft, cars and top consumer goods Gama. The objective is to boost the high quality development of manufacture, processing and trade in these industries, he explained.
On the other hand, Chen Jimin and Leonel Alves submitted a proposal aimed at building a “modernized university park” in Hengqin, where all Macau higher education institutions can teach courses independently, share pedagogical resources, improve the distribution of courses, and allow mutual recognition of credits.
Lam Lon Wai, on the other hand, defended an “international academic community” in Hengqin, where the study environment is similar to that of Macao. In addition, he suggested exclusive border passage with simple procedures for the staff of Higher Education Institutions.
On the other hand, Chui Sai Cheong appealed to a review of MSAR legal regimes “in timely time”, according to the real needs of the Great Bay, to accelerate hengqin integration into the ball of legal services.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau confirmed host of the 2026 AULP meeting</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-confirmado-anfitriao-encontro-da-aulp-de-2026/</link><description>The Association of Portuguese Language Universities will hold in Macau, in 2026, its annual meeting. At the meeting of AULP's Board of Directors, the University of Macau reiterated the availability to organize the event
 
The University of Macao (one) had already proposed, in February 2024, that the annual meeting of the Association of Portuguese Language Universities (AULP) of 2026 was held in the territory. A year later, at a meeting of the Association's Board of Directors, it was confirmed the coming of the Four of Higher Education Institutions of Portuguese -Speaking Countries (PLP) in June, as part of the celebration of birthdays of the 40th anniversary of AULP and 45 of UM.
The availability of the MSAR was reiterated by UM Vice Rector, Rui Martins, during the 2025 Conference, held in Lisbon, chaired by José Arlindo Barreto, leader of AULP and Rector of the University of Cape Verde. The Council unanimously approved the decision to bring to the territory the annual meeting.
The meeting, which attracted representatives of 13 higher education institutions of the PLP, approved the 2024 Activities and Accounts Report, as well as the ongoing year budget. The work schedule also highlighted the published editions of AULP and the statistical data of mobility programs, including the AULP Mobility Program and Erasmus+programs.
In his intervention, Rui Martins praised AULP programs and proposed that the 2026 International Language Magazine was published in Portuguese and English so that SCOPUS, a database of summaries and scientific citations in the future.
In addition, Bettencourt Capece, dean of Zambeze University (Mozambique), reported the preparations for the 34th AULP Meeting that will take place from 16 to 18 June this year in the Mozambican City of Beira, under the welcome of Zambeze University and in conjunction with the universities of Licungo, Catholic, open and Alberto Chipande.
AULP brings together more than 200 Lusophone Higher Education Institutions and has the mission of promoting communication between its members, as well as the development of the teaching of the language of Camões. The one is currently serving as vice president of AULP for the 2024-2027 term.
It is recalled that at the 2024 session, in which one launched the proposal for the organization of the 2026 meeting, João Nuno Calvão da Silva, at the time president of AULP and vice-rector of the University of Coimbra, conferred the diploma of an honorary member of AULP to Rui Martins, in recognition of its “significant contributions” for the association over the years. This honor, granted to only five people in the world, had been attributed to Rui Martins in 2021, having been formally delivered during this meeting.
 
V.r</description><pubDate>2025-03-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Early election scenario gains strength in Portugal</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/cenario-de-eleicoes-antecipadas-ganha-forca-em-portugal/</link><description>Prime Minister Luís Montenegro (C), flanked by the Minister of the Presidency, António Leitão Amaro (D), and the Minister of Parliamentary Affairs, Pedro Duarte (E), during the discussion of the Motion of Censorship of the PCP to the XXIV Constitutional Government, in the Assembly of the Republic, Lisbon, March 5, 2025. Manuel de Almeida/Lusa



Portugal was closer to conducting early legislative elections, after the prime minister announced that he will advance with the proposal of a motion of trust to the Executive by Parliament, not knowing if there are conditions on the part of the parties for the continuity of the government.
The President of the Republic has promised to act “as soon as possible” if the motion of trust is rejected. "If rejected, I will immediately summon the parties, if possible for the next day, and the State Council for two days later," said Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, in Viseu, promising "an intervention calendar as soon as possible", letting it understand as a hypothesis of early legislature in May.
Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa said, however, to want to hear the parties first, namely those who support the government (PSD and CDS-PP), to confirm that they intend to present themselves to elections, if summoned, with the same leaders.
Despite the international crisis that the world is facing, especially after the new US administration, the head of state recalled that the state budget is approved and that the calendar does not collide with the calendar of the preparation of accounts to 2026. "The first possible date is somewhere between 11 and 18 May," he said, in the event of legislative elections.
The prime minister yesterday alluded to his continuity ahead of the PSD and the government if there are early elections, noting that the situation "will not change." At the entrance to an extraordinary meeting of the European Council in Brussels, Montenegro argued that "it was desirable" that there was no "political disturbance" in the country, but insisted that Parliament has to clarify if it has doubts about the legitimacy of the government.
On Wednesday, Parliament rejected a motion of censorship to the government, presented by the PCP, with the votes against the PSD, CDS-PP and IL and the abstention of the PS and the arrival. At the opening of this debate, Montenegro announced that the government will advance with a motion of trust, whose text has already been approved yesterday by the Council of Ministers. Socialist leader Pedro Nuno Santos confirmed that the PS will vote against, which will lead to the fall of the government, and accused Montenegro of prefering elections to face an inquiry committee.
Already the president of the arrival, André Ventura, accused the prime minister of having announced a motion of trust to the government for "fear of scrutiny" and said that the party will never "give him any vote of confidence."
At the end of the debate, the Foreign Minister challenged the PS to abstain in the motion of trust, "if he wants" a parliamentary committee on the situation of Montenegro regarding the company Spinumviva. On the way out of the plenary, Pedro Nuno Santos was asked about this challenge and said only that it was now the time to hear the President of the Republic and that the PS had already said what it was going to do.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-03-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>300,000 residents registered for the use of iris on the border</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/300-mil-residentes-registados-para-uso-da-iris-na-fronteira/</link><description>According to CPSP, 300,000 residents are already registered to use iris recognition in the border passage, and last year 7.84 million passages were accounted for through this method. There are 81 copies currently that allow the use of this technology
 
There are already 300,000 residents of Macao who were registered to use the recognition of iris in the border passage, revealed the Public Security Police (CPSP), indicating that, last year, 7.84 million tickets were verified through this method. It is recalled that this technology was used in the territory in June 2023.
The corporation also added that, currently, in the border stations there are 81 ways that allow the passage with the recognition of the iris. Remembering that the first border to resort to this passage technology was the doors of the siege, the authorities indicated that this post registered a ticket rate through the iris of over 40% of total tickets through automatic roads.
CPSP also indicated that in the border posts of the doors of the siege, Qingmao and Hengqin, the exclusive pathways for students are used by 3,500 students daily.
In relation to the QR code among the RAE, which went into operation in mid -July last year, it has had more than 210,000 uses for Hong Kong entries and exits, which translate into a daily average of 1,200 tickets. On the other hand, 403,000 Hong Kong residents have already used this code to enter and leave the MSAR, the equivalent of a daily average of more than 2,400 passages.
CPSP also revealed that last year the Hengqin Border Post accounted for almost 1.97 million vehicle tickets, representing an annual increase of 29.5%.
On the other hand, the police mentioned, in a statement, that it has been fighting the crimes committed in the context of migration. Last year, CPSP punished 14,554 people involved in over -permanence, which means an annual decrease of 1.5%. In addition, it repatriated 249 illegal emigrants, an annual decrease of 31%.
The corporation also reported 36 cases of fake marriage, which involved 78 people, and also discovered 51 cases of false hiring, in which 156 people were involved.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Coutinho wants less tnr</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/coutinho-quer-menos-tnr/</link><description>Concerned about the future of casinos-satellite workers, José Pereira Coutinho questioned the government on what measures there is to respond to this situation. The deputy also defended a cut in the number of TNR
 
Catarina Pereira
 
José Pereira Coutinho asked the government to brake the increase in the number of non-resident workers (TNR), still concerned about the economic, social and labor impact derived from the eventual closure of the satellite casinos. The deputy also requested a shift and night work allowance, as well as an enlargement of the period of unemployment allowance.
The last review of the game of the game set a period of three years to finish the satellite casinos model. The transition period ends later this year, and the chief executive has said that it is up to the operators to have solutions for workers, which will be about 12,000.
“In the event of the satellite casinos (…), what concrete and effective measures will be adopted by the Macau government to prevent workers who have employment contracts with the concessionaires (…) are required to resign their positions due to their physical condition and difficulties in adapting to new functions?” He asked. In the same vein, he asked that solutions there are for these workers to "immediately have new jobs and do not stay in unemployment for many years."
In this context, the deputy argued that the government must review the legislation “extending the current maximum period from 90 days to 360 days to be able to enjoy unemployment allowance”.
On the other hand, Coutinho asked the government if he will ask the gamekeepers that the special reform anticipation program - to be in place of companies - be extended to casino workers and “all others who are under the same conditions, but who work in different departments and services”. He also questioned whether the government will “promote the change in the current labor legislation allowing casino workers to earn shift and night subsidies like all others who receive in other economic activities”.
Finally, he says there has been a "brutal increase" of the number of TNR in the last 16 years. According to data data for labor affairs, in late January, Macau had 181,843 TNR. Coutinho intends to know the reasons for increasing abroad labor "and that reflections have led to the reduction of local workers posts."
In this sense, it asks "what concrete measures will be implemented to reduce this high number of TNR as well as improve the supervision of TNR that perform different functions for which they were authorized to work." It also argues that the amounts of the fines should be raised for these cases.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Book “Beyond Look” summarizes Frank Law's view</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/livro-para-alem-olhar-resume-visao-de-frank-lei/</link><description>A posthumous work by photographer Frank Lei sums up in a book The Author's Vision about Macau. The publication, seen as a reference in the practice and teaching of photography, will be presented today at the Rui Cunha Foundation
 
The book “Beyond the Look” is a work by the late photographer Frank Law, that the Rui Cunha Foundation and the Macau Photographic Club announce today, in a ceremony scheduled for 18:30.
The publication summarizes Frank Law's view of Macau, a city that estimated so much. “Frank Law lived at a time of major social, economic and urban changes in Macao, performed not only through an expansion process -extensive landfills -but also through the demolition of existing informal urban settlements, or old buildings, which shaped the traditional city and its way of life,” according to the architect and also photographer Francisco Ricarte, which will conduct the presentation of the book.
The posthumous work was a reference in the practice and teaching of photography in the territory, in the late twentieth century and early twentieth century. Frank Law was able to portray these transformations "with a deep sense of belonging, of humanity, but also of loss."
In the text of publicity it is also said that Frank Law's photography went far beyond a documentary record of the physical changes of a place. "Frank Law's visual sensitivity for the composition, scale and balance of light and shadow (sometimes transmitting deep and dramatic shadows), to portray Macau as a land of perpetual change (…), allows us to better understand this city and its human identity."
In Frank Law's photography, “space is always transmitted by a human scale, which emphasizes its meaning and role,” adds Francisco Ricarte, one of the founders of the Halftone Association and driving the photographic book club.
The conversation “among friends intends to remember the work of the author and highlight the visual sensitivity of this for the photographic composition, walking through the images that marked his time and witnessed this place,” he says.
The author of this posthumous work was born in Beijing in 1962, but came to live to Macau when very young. After completing his academic studies in Cinema and Video at the University of Paris III, and in photography at the French capital's content, he returned to Macao where he settled.
His professional activity went through the Macau Daily News, was curator of the hostel and later curator of the Boi Warehouse, published several photography books, held individual exhibitions in Macao and France, and won important photographic awards. Frank Law died in 2022 after a long period of illness.
The session will be attended by Jane Lei, sister of the honoree, and Alan Ieong, editor of the work. The session will be held in English and the book will be available for sale during the event.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Youth Orchestra acts at the Military Club</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/orquestra-juvenil-actua-clube-militar/</link><description>The Military Club's “Musical Days” returns on Sunday, March 9, at 5:00 pm, with the Macao Youth String Orchestra to present the “The Sound of Spring” concert. The group of young musicians will divide the program with various interpretations, from tango, waltz, serenades and popular Chinese songs. The concert will open with “String Quartel: Una Cabeza” (“From Scent of a Woman)” by singer Carlos Gardel, composed of an iconic tango that captures the essence of Argentina passion, in which the arrangement of the string quartet wears violin lines with the rhythm of the tango. As part of the Macao Youth Musicians Association, the Youth String Orchestra develops its hearing and execution skills with a diverse repertoire. Members learn musical theory, whole techniques and team work, fostering creativity and musical passion. Since its founding in 2023, the orchestra has been actuated in major events and has launched its first MV string quartet, “Una Cabeza”, receiving criticism compliments. It also collaborates with international and local musicians, with some of its members won awards in competitions such as the “Singapore International Solo &amp; Ensemble”. Those interested in watching Sunday concert at the Military Club will have to pay 120 Patacas, with cocktail, while the ticket to those who want to add dinner at the club's restaurant costs 330 Patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2354/</link><description>Detained for sexual harassment to a woman
A 60 -year -old resident was arrested following a 20 -year -old resident, three times. According to the Public Security Police Corps, the victim made the complaint on the 4th, and the preliminary investigation reveals that the suspect will have filed the young woman on the rest of the rest, something she had also done in the same place and with the same victim in December and January. The detainee has already been sent to the prosecutor.
 
SSM do pilot inquiries on “Health of Macau 2026”
Health Services (SSM) are preparing the “Macao 2026 health inquiry” in order to help residents know the basic health situation and increase the proactive health management capacity. The SSM plan to perform four pilot inquiries in the second half of this month. The recipients will be 200 upper permanent residents of randomly selected who will be subject to the analysis of blood and urine samples, body mediation, health questionnaire interview, as well as two new mediation items: hearing (part of the recipients) and the grip force.
 
Suggested deposit for filming
Wong Chi Choi, a member of the Central Community Affairs Advisory Board, suggested the creation of a security mechanism, as the teams intended to film in Macau have to pay an amount, "in accordance with the nature of the activity, the size and duration of the shoot." According to the Chinese language press, the vowel recalled the recently occurred accident during a tread on the territory and injured 12 people, including four children. In addition, he called on the authorities to reinforce inspection actions, "in order to ensure that filming teams always respect legal provisions."
 
Registration starts for session on elections for al
Enrollment for the clarification session on procedures for the elections of the Legislative Assembly will begin today, which will be held on September 14. The clarification session, directed to those interested in applying and to the public, will take place on the 26th, from 18:30 to 20:00, at the Science Center. Registration can be made through the account only or in person, in the Public Administration building, until March 21.
 
SPU opened 100 vacancies for civil protection volunteers
Unit Police Services (SPU) began recruitment of civil protection volunteers to 2025. Vacancies, in a total of 100, are intended for residents aged 18 to 55, interested in participating in awareness, civic education, and post-integral assistance. Registration takes place until March 29, in the Department of Resource Management of SPU, online or through the mobile application “Civil Protection Volunteers”. If the registrations exceed the number of vacancies, the selection will be made by lot. Admitted applicants will be subject to basic education and evaluation tests.
 
Almost completed 3rd phase of the
Elevatory Station Work
About 91% of the work of the third phase of the construction of the rainwater and drainage in southern port is completed. The Directorate of Public Works (DSOP) services informs that the lane along with the Pontes 7 and 7a, on Dr. Lourenço Pereira Marques Street, will be reopened to traffic from the 15th of this month. DSOP also provides that, with the conclusion of more phases of the work, the pressure on traffic will be relieved and the impact on commercial establishments will be relieved. The endeavor is expected to be finalized in June this year.
 
Hospital suspended use of antiviral medicine
As a preventive measure, the manufacturer of the antiviral drug “Zovirax IV Infusion Inj 250mg” collected a lot that was imported by Macau after glass -shaped particles were detected in a vial, the Institute for Supervision and Pharmaceutical Administration (ISAF) reported. Italy's “Glaxosmithkline” has ensured that there is no evidence that other products of the same lot have been affected. According to Isaf, in Macao, the lot was only supplied to the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, which failed to use it "immediately." The hospital did not register any indisposition case after the consumption of this medicine, which is intended only for hospitalized patients.
 
Wynn integrates LinkedIn network project
Wynn was invited by Linjedin to participate in the “Future Ready Program” project, launched in Hong Kong by the global social platform. Through this collaboration, Wynn “expects to understand the latest learning trends in the job market, innovative concepts and technology to empower its workers and promote innovation and sustainable development of talents in Macao”. The company also explained that it will be supported by LinkedIn in the formulation of plans on the retention of long -term frames and holding exclusive events and quarterly round tables with executives.
 
Philatelic catalog brings together two years of emissions
The “Macau XII Philatelic Catalog” is already on sale at the central station's filately store, the Communications Museum and at Rua do Campo station, for the price of 100 Patacas. Respecting the model of previous editions, the new catalog compiles information on the philatelic emissions of the last two years, ie data, texts and images related to launches made in 2023 and 2024, indicated the Post and Telecommunications services.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Birth has reached minimal since 1985</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/natalidade-atingiu-minimo-desde-1985/</link><description>They continue to increase imbalances in Macau's population structure. The population aging rate rose to 116.6%, marking the 28th consecutive year. The elderly population, that is, 65 or older, represented 14.6% of the total. On the other hand, the birth rate suffered again, having been the lowest since 1985, according to the data analyzed by this newspaper. Last year, only 3,607 babies were born in the territory
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The scenario of population aging continues to accentuate, while less and less babies are born in the territory. The number of undead totaled 3,607 last year, 105 in annual terms-the birth rate was 5.3 °, the lowest since 1985, according to the data analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macau. Not even the rise recorded in the last quarter, another 77 babies for a total of 987, it has reached the trend.
In Macao, and contrary to what happened in China, not even the fact that it was the year of the dragon, considered “favorable to procreation” by the characteristics of that sign of the Chinese zodiac, contributed to an increase in the number of births. The Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) observed before the birth rate signs of "continuing to go down."
Official data report that there were 114.7 male underecting for 100 female women, 58% of which were firstborn, 33.7% were second children and 8.2% were third and following children and following. Already the median of the age of women at the birth of the first child was 31.3 years (+0.3 years). Parents of the undead who were residents of Macau represented 84.4% of the total and mothers 78%, of which 41 fathers and 15 mothers had Portuguese nationality.
At the end of last year, Macao's total population consisted of 688,300 people, plus 4,600, "mainly due to the increase in the number of non -resident workers (TNR) domiciled in Macao." The number of TNR grew 5.7% to 91,400, which in absolute terms equals another 4,900 people. Also the number of students abroad living in the MSAR increased by 8.5% to 28,200. The female population represented 53.7% of the total universe.
The local population (which excludes TNR and students from abroad, both domiciled in Macao) reached 568,700 people, slightly down 0.4%in annual terms. Note that the elderly and adults performed 17.2% and 67.4% of the local population, respectively.
The “continuous decrease in the number of births” also influences the young population, which tends to decrease. In concrete, this group included 85,900 people, equivalent to 12.5% ​​of the total population. The proportion of young people from 0 to 14 years old descended 0.7 percentage points.
In the opposite direction, the elderly population (65 years or older) stood at 100,200, corresponding to 14.6% of the total population. The proportion of elderly grew 0.6 percentage points in annual terms.
The trend of population aging remained, observes the DSEC, and the official data even reveals that the aging rate reached 116.6%, plus 10.5 percentage points in annual terms, and the highest since 1990 and marking the 28th consecutive year of growth. Also the dependence rate of the elderly grew 0.8 percentage points to 20%, also marking the highest since 34 years ago.
Deaths registered 2,477 over the past year, less 504 compared to the previous year, of which 57.7% were male. The mortality rate dropped 0.8 permit points to 3.6 ° (3.6 per thousand). Analyzing by age group, 1,885 deaths occurred at ages equal to or over or more than 65 (-477, compared to 2023) and 15 at less than 15 years (-7).
The “malignant tumors” caused 937 deaths, corresponding to 37.8% of the total; It followed “other causes” with 24.1%. In turn, the “heart disease” accounted for 362 deaths, making up 14.6% of the total, while “pneumonia” caused 268 deaths (10.8%). Cerebrovascular diseases, self -project (suicide) and diabetes lesions also contributed, representing 5.8%, 3.5% and 3.4% of total deaths last year.
 
Almost 23,000 residents domiciled in Zhuhai
Migratory data, in turn, show that in November 2024 they were domiciled in Zhuhai and around 22,800 residents of Macao, who had activities in the territory (+14%, in annual terms). As for age distribution, 55.7% were aged between 25 and 54 years. In addition, 53.1% were men.
On the other hand, last year, a new residence permit was granted in Macao to 1,074 individuals (196), with successive increases since 2022. The sins also had 3,677 individuals from the interior of newly arrived “Save-Conduct” (another 260), of which 34.9% were between 30 and 39 years old, followed by the age group above 60 years, 13.4%.
As regards imported labor, an increase was observed. The MSAR ended 2024 with 182,542 TNR (5,881 more than in 2023). The TNR from the interior of China, the Philippines and Vietnam represented 66.4%, 16.9% and 4.5% of the total, respectively.
 
MEDIAN AGE INCREASES TO FIRST MARRIAGE
Last year, 3,187 marriages were recorded, 19 more than in 2023, and the nuptial rate was 4.6 ° (less 0.1 permitting points). According to statistics and census services, “the median of age at the first marriage for both sexes continued to rise”, noting that men and women were 31.4 and 29.7 years, respectively, another 0.2 years in annual terms. On the other hand, 1,361 divorces were accounted for, another 62, and the divorce rate reached 2.0 ° (plus 0.1 permitting points). The number of household aggregates in Macau totaled 205,000, another 600 in annual terms.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese PM reaffirms support for the economy and social welfare of RAE</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pm-chines-reafirma-apoio-a-economia-bem-estar-social-das-rae/</link><description>EPA11941112 Chinese Premier Li Qiang is seen on screen as he delivers His speech during the opening ceremony of the third session of the 14th National People's Congress of China at the Great Hall of the People in Beijing, China, 05 March 2025. China Holds Two Major Annual Political Meetings, The National People's Congress (NPC) and the Chinese People's Political Consultive Conference (CPPCC), Which Run Concurently and Are Known As The 'Lianghi' or 'Two Sessions.'  EPA/WU HAO



At the opening of the ANP, Chinese prime minister reiterated the guarantee that the central government will support Hong Kong and Macau in economic development and improve the welfare of its populations. The leader of the mandate promised to transform the spirit of the "two sessions" into "concrete actions"

The 3rd session of the 14th National Popular Assembly (ANP) began yesterday, with Chinese Prime Minister (PM), Li Qiang, presenting the central government's work report. The document highlights the duty of full, accurate and unshakable pursuit of the guidelines “a country, two systems” and Hong Kong and Macau governed by their people, with a high degree of autonomy.
Another underlined duty is based on the defense of the constitutional order of the RAE defined in the Constitution and in basic laws, as well as in the implementation of the principles of Hong Kong and Macao to be governed by "patriots".
In addition, the PM has asserted that it will support the RAE to develop the economy, improve the well-being of the population, integrate better into the conjuncture of national development, and maintain long-term prosperity and stability.
The head of the Executive of the MSAR, who was present at the opening of ANP, in Beijing, returned to thank the attention and support of the central government in relation to Macao. Sam Hou Fai stressed that the Government of MSar will continue to implement the “a country, two systems” principle in an “unshakable, full and accurate way”, and “consolidate and develop the successes” obtained in the practice of this political formula with Macao characteristics. At the same time, according to an official note, he stressed that “Mand has to continue to safeguard sovereignty, security and state development interests”, as “national security is the fundamental principle” of “one country, two systems”.
Sam Hou Fai has promised that the government “will learn seriously and implement the spirit of the 'two sessions',” as well as “grasping the opportunities” derived from modernization with Chinese characteristics, following the spirit consecrated in President Xi Jinping's speeches during his visit to Macau at the end of last year to write “a new chapter in brilliant development” of the territory.
He stressed, the Executive of the MSAR will, according to Beijing's plan to fully deepen the reform, transform the spirit of the "two sessions" into "concrete actions". This implies “reinforcement of interdepartal collaboration and policy synergy, increasing the effectiveness and level of governance”, boosting the development of the proper diversification of the economy, “building a higher -level opening platform” and “effectively enhancing Macau as an interlocutor between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, contributing to the country's high quality development”.
Sam Hou Fai expects Macao vowels to continue to scrupulously fulfill their duties, play the double role, as well as actively participate and discuss political affairs, with the purpose of contributing further to the development of the country and Macau, and to the stable and lasting implementation of “one country, two systems”.
Already Chui Sai Peng, Member of Mand at ANP, praised the report of Li Qiang for its "high quality", "highlight in science and technology" and "very clear focus on the economy". From its perspective, the document will make the population “gain even more confidence”. Another vowel, Chan Hong, described the report as "pragmatic" since "contemplates economic development and mentions education at the same time."
In the same vein, Kevin Ho considered that the document is "pragmatic" and also "progressive", especially because the central government plans for this year in the aspect of the revitalization of the economy "occupy a considerable weight" in the content of the report.
Prior to the opening of the ANP, the director of the Hong Kong and Macao affairs office with the Council of State, Xia Baolong, met in Beijing with Raehk and Master deputies at ANP. At the meeting, Xia Baolong linked their expectations so that the vowels, with a high sense of responsibility and mission, properly fulfill their functions, actively transmit public opinion and present suggestions.
 
From the “background” to the “talent sharing”
On the other hand, several MSAR vowels at the Chinese people's Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC) presented proposals in Beijing. Choy Meng has suggested the creation, by the governments of Guangdong and MSar, of an “investment fund” of Hengqin dedicated to the development of Artificial Intelligence (AI), low altitude economy and green energies.
Un Kin Kuan hopes that small and medium -sized companies in Macao with potential, in the areas of souvenir sales or linked to cultural and creative industries, are supported to transfer production to hengqin and expand business to the interior of China and Lusophone countries.
On the other hand, Chui Sai Cheong, a member of the CCPPC Permanent Committee, defended the “talent sharing” in the Great Bay, proposing to the governments of the three regions that study and jointly define measures of simplification of talent flow.
 
Rae astronauts praised
Os dois astronautas de Hong Kong e Macau encontram-se em “muito bom estado” e têm obtido “bons resultados” nos treinos, adiantou Yang Liwei, vogal da Conferência Consultiva Política do Povo Chinês e também o primeiro astronauta da China no espaço. À margem das “Duas Sessões”, Yang considerou que os dois astronautas, especialistas em carga útil, têm uma “boa base” e “não deverá demorar muito tempo para eles navegarem” no espaço. However, it pointed out that this will “depend on the organization of the whole mission”. The two experts were selected for China's fourth group of astronauts along with eight space pilots.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Caritas Clinic will grow and hire three doctors</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/clinica-da-caritas-vai-crescer-contratar-tres-medicos/</link><description>The Secretary General of Caritas said that the institution's clinic, with the “mission” of helping low health care people, will reopen later this year, in the black sand, with three consultation rooms and three western medicine doctors, possibly including a dentist. Regarding the consultation fee, Paul Pun indicated that the "goal" is to charge between 100 and 200 patacas. On the other hand, it pointed to the entry into operation of the Caritas Bakery for April this year
 
At the last charity dinner, Caritas received donations in a value of 300,000 Patacas, Paul Pun, secretary general of the institution, told the Tribuba de Macao newspaper, noting that these funds will be used to support some projects not subsidized by the government, for example the future clinical.
Located in Sand Black, Caritas Clinic will have three offices and three Western Medicine doctors, enabling the care of several patients at the same time, Paul Pun said, stressing that the institution expects one of the doctors to be a dentist to provide services such as tooth cleaning. This is because, he explained, dentistry services are “very important” for some elderly people who live in that zone, especially for periodontal disease.
Paul Pun pointed, however, that Caritas does not intend to make pediatric dental services available, since "the government already exempts fees of this type of consultations to children."
In addition, the clinic, whose “mission” is to benefit low income, including non -resident workers (TNR), the needy and elderly population, “should also be able to provide vaccination services,” added Paul Pun.
It is recalled that, before the closure in March 2021, due to the lack of doctors, among other operational difficulties, the Caritas Clinic, located at Rua da Caldeira, worked with two consultation rooms and two doctors. For the new phase of the clinic, and in relation to doctors, Paul Pun pointed out that "it would be great to know how to speak English and Mandarin."
After the request for the opening of the clinic has recently been approved by the Fire Department, the institution will again submit the documents to the Directorate of Soil Services and Urban Construction (DSSCU) for appreciation. After receiving “green light” from DSSCU, Caritas will ask for endorsement with health services, and simultaneously, will start hiring doctors.
Under these circumstances, there is not yet a concrete calendar for the entry into operation of this medical institution of philanthropic matrix. Still, the secretary general of Caritas believes he could start working later this year.
Regarding the consultation fee, Paul Pun said that, as it is a Caritas entity, the clinic “cannot charge 300 or 500 patacas” and should not allow the use of health valleys. “Services will require a certain cost, but will not aim to profit. In this sense, [a consultation fee] slightly more than 100 patacas will be our goal. We hope you will not reach 200 patacas, ”he said.
In this respect, Paul Pun also revealed that the institution will consider granting “coupons” to low income patients to cover part of the paid rates.
On the other hand, the clinic may also promote health education. “For example, doctors will be able to move to schools or provide TNR blood pressure and blood glucose services. The cost should not be very high, but you will need to request an authorization one to two months in advance. In one day, it is possible to perform blood glucose measurement to 100 to 200 people, ”he added.
Regarding the other Caritas project, the bakery, located in the São Lázaro neighborhood, Paul Pun clarified that the institution is dealing with commercial registration and requesting the license. The bakery, where people with disabilities will work, will be able to operate in April this year, awaits the institution.
On the current financial situation of Caritas, the same responsible said that “it is not facing many difficulties” with regard to the services funded by the government, however, he confessed that there are obstacles regarding unsubsidized services. For this reason, the institution “will have to find solutions”, including arrange donations and spaces that allow exemption or reduction of incomes. “The repair of facilities is also a little costly. For example, in our rehabilitation center for people with mental illness, located in Colaane, the kitchen repair will cost a lot of money, ”he said.
 
Aposes for more affection to the international community
On the other hand, the United States Agency for International Development (USAID) has decided to suspend its humanitarian aid and development programs worldwide, which led Caritas Internacional to “censor strongly” this decision, warning that “dramatically affects Caritas in Latin America and the Caribbean and threatens millions of people around the world”.
On this issue, Paul Pun explained that Caritas de Macao does not receive donations from USAID, so it will not be affected. However, he recalled that currently residents of Macao “do not usually donate much” to the international community, and Caritas de Macao manages to raise a maximum of hundreds of thousands of levels per year.
“I hope that, taking advantage of this opportunity, residents think more about international aid. USAID will cut substantially or completely suspend [help programs]. But worldwide crises, disasters and medical seizures can also affect us, especially medical seizures… If we can give some more affection, and if Caritas de Macao receives more donations from residents designed to demonstrate international charity, we can reinforce the degree of our support to the international community, ”he said, pointing out that another way of demonstrating support for organizing young people or architects to help victims to rebuild their homes.
According to Paul Pun, in addition to the annual initiative of raising donations for international aid, Caritas promotes charity sales to the same end. At Fai Chi Kei, a sales station of this nature is open whose raised funds are intended to help countries and regions in need due to disasters or other difficulties, including some Portuguese-speaking countries such as Timor-Leste, Sao Tome and Angola, shot the Secretary General of Caritas.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese Liu Jiakun wins Pritzker Prize</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/chines-liu-jiakun-vence-premio-pritzker/</link><description>Chinese architect Liu Jiakun, whose “path to architecture was neither linear nor expected”, is the winner of this year's Pritzker Architecture Prize, considered the most important in this area worldwide.
Born in 1956 in Chengdu, the son of a doctor, in a family linked to the practice of medicine, over four decades, Liu, along with his team, have designed more than 30 projects, from academic and cultural institutions to civic spaces, commercial buildings and urban planning throughout China, and was selected to project Serpentine Pavilion of Beijing (2018). Award organization.
“Writing novels and practicing architecture are distinct forms of art, and I have not deliberately seeking both. However, perhaps due to my double formation, there is an inherent connection between them in my work - such as narrative quality and pocket search for my 'designs', ”said Chinese architect quoted by the Pritzker Award website.
Jiakun, at age 17 he was part of the “Zhiqing da China”, a state program of “youth education”, having been designated for agriculture, but chose to study engineering with an emphasis on architecture in 1982, and was among the first generation of former students in charge of rebuilding China during a period of transformation to the country.
Working for the state's Chengdu Research and Architectural Design Institute at the beginning of his career, he offered temporarily to Nagqu, Tibeta (1984–1986), the tallest region on Earth. “My greatest strength at the time seemed to be my fear of nothing and, besides, my capabilities of painting and writing,” he said.
During these years he was architect during the day, but author at night, deeply involved in literary creation.
Liu Jiakun participated in international exhibitions inside and outside China. She is currently a guest professor at the School of Architecture of the Central Academy of Fine Arts in Beijing, having already taught at Cité de L'Architecture et du Patrimoine, Paris, at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, USA, at the Royal Academy of Arts in London, among other institutions in China.
Its Palmarés includes Far Eastern Architectural Design, Outstanding Award (2007 and 2017), ASC Grand Architectural Creation (2009), Architectural Record China Award (2010), WA Prize for Chinese Architecture (2016), Building with Nature, Architecture Prize China (2020), Sanalian Prize, Lifeweek City for Humanity of Public Contribution (2020) and UNESCO ASIA-Pacific Award for the Conservation of Cultural Heritage, New Design in Heritage Contexts (2021).
Liu Jiakun was almost abandoning architecture until an individual exhibition of architecture of Tang Hua, a former university colleague, in 1993, at the Shanghai Art Museum, "rekindling his passion for the profession and feeding a new mindset that he could also deviate from prescribed social aesthetics." The reward considers "this transformative perception - that the built environment can serve as a means of personal expression - such as the moment when its architectural career has really begun."
The list of reward includes the Portuguese Álvaro Siza Vieira (1992) and Eduardo de Souto Moura (2011).
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>