<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Macao may again host Congress of Mercies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-podera-voltar-acolher-congresso-das-misericordias/</link><description>To mark the 460th anniversary of the Foundation of the Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macao in 2029, the MSar will receive again the International Congress of Misericórdias, after already organizing the event in 2019. Provider António José de Freitas revealed to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau this possibility, on the day the institution celebrated 456 years of existence
 
Victor Rebelo
 
A decade after having had the responsibility of organizing the Congress of the International Confederation of Mercy, the Holy House of Mercy of Macau may again receive the event at the time of the celebration of its 460 years, in 2029. The provider of the institution told the Journal Tribuna de Macao that the Brotherhood is wearing this possibility, “which would be very good, of great meaning, as it would give the territory and occur precisely on the 30th anniversary of MSAR ”.
The Congress, which brought to the territory representatives of about 200 Santas -homes around the world, also served to mark the 450th anniversary of the Holy House of Mercy of Macao.
At that time, in the early days of May, just over two weeks from the beginning of the international event, the President of the Portuguese Republic, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, moved to Macau, having visited the Santa Casa da Misericórdia, where he spoke in the noble hall.
António José de Freitas recalls this day: "He gave a brilliant speech and in the end only said 'thanks to the Holy House of Mercy', which greatly sensitized us and demonstrates the role of the institution, as a unique inheritance of Portugal here in Macao, having proved the prestigious work that has done over the years."
The brotherhood pointed out last night, during a dinner, the day of mercy and the 456 years since the foundation of the non-profit secular organization, in a conviviality in which several personalities were present, including the Portuguese consul general to Macau and Hong Kong, Alexandre Leitão.
In his speech, the provider stated that, "around 25 years after the establishment of the MSAR, it is important to record the continued vitality and strength of our institution, one of the testimonies of peaceful coexistence and integration for more than four centuries, and also a fundamental reference in the affirmation of the spirit of social solidarity, as an institution of unique Portuguese matrix in Greater China."
In addition, he stressed that “in the face of the sociopolitical framework in which we live, we have sought to focus our actions with the sense of urge and current”, adding that “today we have the consolidated and modernized structures, which allows us to offer quality and efficiency in the services rendered to children, the elderly and the visually impaired”.
Making reference to projects and activities, he recalled that Santa Casa has been open to the public since December 2001, the museum nucleus, which receives more than 100 visitors daily. On the other hand, the social store, which has been operating since February 2013 at zero cost to the Brotherhood, has benefited about 4,500 needy families annually.
He also mentioned the bribery subsidy plan to students from the Portuguese School of Macau, launched since 2000/2001, “as a form of support for families of minor financial resources”, having benefited, until the end of the academic year that has now ended, more than a thousand students.
 
Projects on March with Chinese Associations
António José de Freitas also considered that, "the result of the joint and solidary work of all," the institution has been able to respond, "of a comprehensive form, to the needs of the underprivileged in the face of the challenges of time and change."
The provider, who will complete at the end of this year 13 terms, totaling 26 years, expressed that the Santa Casa da Misericórdia of Macao “breathes tradition and history”, being “an unavoidable reference of Portugal's legacy in this region”. It will continue to be, stressed, “a space of solidarity experience between the communities and an important testimony of our presence and permanence”.
In conclusion, it was confident that “animated by the same faith and united by the same ideals, we will be able to project in time the image of this Holy House, as a living and credible institution, oriented to ends and values ​​that aim to honor the moral duty of solidarity and social justice, and always linked to the roots that gave it life”.
On the sidelines of the session, António José de Freitas told JTM that, although he never asked for any subsidy to the Macau Foundation -except for support for hostel activities -“there has been excellent collaboration with official entities, but also with similar institutions in the Chinese community, because this is very important and we can't walk alone”.
He also confided that there are some projects underway, together with the General Union of the residents 'associations and the Macao Workers' Associations Federation.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Majority in favor of registering the 12 demonstrations in the heritage list</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/maioria-favor-da-inscricao-das-12-manifestacoes-na-lista-patrimonio/</link><description>Overall, the 12 demonstrations proposed to integrate the list of intangible cultural heritage “obtained about 70% or more of agreement, indicating wide social support”, considers the Cultural Institute, which received a total of 931 opinions. As for the Portuguese folk dance, which has been supported by more than 80%, it should be noted that those who have manifested against they have a “strong foreign nature” due to the “colonial character”. In relation to the making of cream pastels (more than 70% gave green light), there were those who considered that it has no “historical-cultural meaning”. More than 90% agreed with the registration of the belief and customs of Toui, Dragon Dance and Lion Dance

Catarina Pereira
 
The 12 demonstrations proposed by the Cultural Institute (IC) to integrate the list of intangible cultural heritage “obtained about 70% or more agreement, indicating wide social support for the registration of these twelve items”, reveals the final report of the public consultation, which took place for 30 days. The body received 931 opinions between December 4, 2024 and January 2, 2025.
The belief and customs of Tou Tei, the Dragon and Lion dance received more than 90% acceptance, "reflecting the importance of these items in traditional cultural values, fully demonstrating the cultural characteristics of Macao." Most accepted the Portuguese folk dance - but those who opposed themselves justified with the “strong foreign nature” due to the “colonial character”, pointing, among other aspects, that “has no representativeness”. The making of NATA pasties also pointed out a lot of positive opinions, but there were those who argue that it has no “specific historical-cultural meaning”.
More concretely, it can be read that 83.8% agreed with the registration of Portuguese folk dance, considering that it is favorable to the “preservation of ancient traditions, reflecting the cultural diversity of Macao and the historical process”, and that “is part of the unique culture of Macao”, pointing out the “historical ties” with Portugal. Other opinions also argued that dance, after being introduced in Macao, "integrated local cultural elements," thus showing "a strong merger between the East and the West."
However, those who opposed the inscription of this demonstration said that “Portuguese folk dance represents Portuguese culture and displays a strong foreign nature due to its colonial character, with more authentic dances in Portugal”, therefore believing that this type of dance “does not have enough representativeness”. In the list of reasons for disagreement include “lack of uniqueness”, “has no historical-cultural value” and “is not sufficiently disclosed”, among other opinions.
“There are also those who believe that Portuguese folk dance has already integrated local elements, so they consider it to be inadequate that they continue to use the title of 'Portuguese folk dance' as the name of the item proposed for registration in the list of intangible cultural heritage”, can be read in the document released by the CI. It should be noted that there were also those who argue that dance clothing “must be preserved”.
As for the making of cream pastels, 72.1% were in favor of their inclusion in the list of intangible cultural heritage, noting that “reflects the fusion of Chinese and Western cultures” and “represents Macao's tradition and cooking innovation”. Those who agreed also mentioned that "it is a gastronomic specialty of Macao, being seen as a special gift of high quality by many tourists."
In the opposite field, those who manifested against it said that "the pastry of cream is just a food, a modern product, with a relatively short and without specific historical-cultural significance." They also pointed out that it has “lack of uniqueness” and that “not representative”, among others. In addition, there were also those who said that "the preparation of NATA pastels in Macao originated in the UK and that, when included in the list of intangible cultural heritage, the origin should be marked to avoid confusion," and those who sign that "the current cost of Nata pastries is very high."
 
Chinese traditions with wide support
On the other hand, the beliefs and customs of Tou Tei have given 94.5% favorable opinions, justifying that this manifestation “has historical significance and cultural value” and is a “characteristic religious activity”. Other opinions indicated that "each old neighborhood of Macau usually has an altar dedicated to the god of the earth, which reflects a typical ritual of citizens and fully demonstrates the characteristics of Macao." Those who disagreed, in turn, pointed out that it is "a superstitious practice, which has some conflict with personal religious beliefs."
In this context, there were those who argue that the government should, through legislation, “provide legal protection and economic support so that the transmitters of these customs and associated cultural activities are able to perpetuate these traditions”, among other aspects.
The Dragon Dance was supported by 93% of participants in the consultation, who considered, mainly, that the demonstration "transmits traditional Chinese culture, has a long history and a broad basis of participation by citizens." In the opposite spectrum, those who proved to be against argued that "the dancing dragon is common in Chinese communities, lacking singularity and being considered that it does not reflect the multicultural identity of Macao."
With the same percentage of support, the Lion dance was considered by the participants as a manifestation with “historical significance” and “cultural value”, believing that “it is a national cultural tradition that reflects important customs and traditions”. In this case, it was also pointed out “lack of uniqueness” by those who expressed opposition.
According to the report, the Spring Festival was seen by the majority (81.9%) as “a traditional Chinese holiday, symbolizing a thousand years of cultural legacy, and which has an important historical and cultural value”. However, those who Discard argue that "it is not an exclusive holiday of Macao and that Macau has not yet been able to develop his own traditions related to the Spring Festival, thus lacking singularity."
Already the Festival of Boats-Dragon (Tung NG) received support of 79.2%, while the dragon boat tank top 85.7%favorable opinions. In turn, Tai Chi's martial arts were agreed to 71%, followed by the preparation of 79.6%almond cookies, the making of 68.4%traditional wedding cakes and Jook-Sing pasta that received 72.4%support.
In the opinions received by the IC, there were those who address the question of including more items in the list or inventory of intangible cultural heritage. According to the report, certain traditional rituals and festivities were referred to, such as the fisherman's veneration ceremony, Ba Yin drums, the autumn middle festival, performance activities such as Kung Fu Wing Chun, drunk dragon dance and other art forms, such as traditional Chinese painting and Portuguese tiles.
 
Classification of 400 movable property expected “by the end of the year”
The Cultural Institute collected 274 opinions on the classification of 400 items/sets of mobile cultural goods of the Macao Museum, during the 30 -day public consultation, of which 99.6% spoke in favor of the classification of these goods, according to the final report now released. The body led by Leong Wai Man will now compilage and global analysis of the opinions of the Cultural Heritage Council and the opinions collected, and the classification process is expected to be concluded “by the end of the year”.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Launched competition for first endeavor in the old canidrome</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lancado-concurso-para-primeira-empreitada-antigo-canidromo/</link><description>The government has already launched the public tender for the work to be held in the area one of the old Yat Yuen Canid, which includes the construction of three pools with pools, fields of various modalities, running tracks, skate park and climbing zone, among others. The contract has a maximum execution period of 1,014 working days
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The public tender for the construction work of the Sports Jardim for Citizens in the Lot of the former Yat Yuen Canid, concretely for Zone UM, according to an announcement signed by the Director of Public Works (DSOP), Lam Wai Hou Hou Hou Hou. The maximum global period of execution of the work is 1,014 working days, with four mandatory goals.
The sports garden lot for citizens has an area of ​​40,425 square meters, being divided, according to the functions, into four parts and field of outdoor athletics. According to the announcement published yesterday in an official bulletin, in 140 days the demolition and protection work of the adjacent building must be completed, following the completion of the foundations and structure of the floor floor, a total of 300 days.
After that, in 220 days of work must be completed the upper structures of the ground floor slab to the coverage slab of pavilions numbers 1, 2 and 3; And in other 220 days the three pavilions have to be completed, the outdoor space of the ground floor and the 1st floor connection platform.
According to a note from DSOP, the first phase of the work (which is in competition) includes pavilion No. 1, located in the center of the lot, which will have four floors. It is planned to have a pool and pool for children, basketball field, running track and children's bike path. The second pavilion will have six floors, welcoming Skatepark and table tennis fields, wall climbing, volleyball and two -story Badminton.
Finally, Pavilion No. 3 will have seven floors, and the idea is to host football field for five people, two-story multipurpose room, multi-functional activities and space for outdoor activities, among other spaces.
There is no definite base price, and interested parties have to pay a provisional deposit of 28.5 million patacas. Proposals can be delivered until 5 pm on August 13th.
The criteria for appreciation of proposals include the price of the contract (50%), the execution period (20%), the experience and quality in works (20%), as well as the execution program (10%). According to the announcement signed by Lam Wai Hou, "the award is made to the competitor with a higher total score and, if there is a tie in the highest total score, the award is made to the competitor with the lowest price proposal."
After this work in zone one, there will be a second, in which the children's pavilion will be included. This space will have four floors, planning to have outdoor activities zone for children, playground in the interior space, creative classroom and reading zone, among others. The basement will be intended for the living room and storage space, among other spaces with more reinforced functionality, adds DSOP.
Also the outdoor athletics field will be part of zone two, and must have eight track of standard athletics and height facilities at height and in length; It will also feature a standardized synthetic grass soccer field.
Cave, in turn, will serve as a public parking park, providing in the area 69 and 166 parking spaces for light vehicles and motorcycles; In zone two, the park will have 415 and 425 parking places for light vehicles and motorcycles.
Remember that recently, on a visit to the Canidrome, the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, said that, given the high population density of the North Zone and the lack of social equipment, “the works of the first zone will be considered so that, as far as possible, they do not affect the functioning of the sports field and the Lin Fong center, in order to take into account the use of residents.”
Regarding the traffic of the adjacent zones, it revealed that the works for the east line of the light meter that connects the north to the mud "stem at a good rhythm". Pointing out that “V terrain” has created conditions that not only allow the east line to approach the border post of the siege gates, but also, in the future, to extend the east to the Qingmao border post, Sam Hou Fai indicated that the government is studying the possibility of extending the line of the light meter from Qingmao Post to Fai Chi Kei neighborhood, “ population ”. The government leader said he believed that "these measures will be effective in relieving the traffic of the area with high population density."</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Bank “disarmed” company with suspicious transactions</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/banco-desarmou-empresa-transaccoes-suspeitas/</link><description>The Financial Information Office distinguished three Macao banks for its contributions in the complaint of suspicious transactions. Reported cases involved weapons, a car accessory store and a criminal organization
 
Pedro Milheirão
Three Macao banks were awarded by the Financial Information Office (GIF) of the Unit Police Services for the way they conducted “suspicious transaction reports” (STR). It is recalled that, under the law, sectors such as casinos, financial institutions and insurance companies are required to communicate to the authorities any transaction equal to or greater than 500,000 patacas.
The "Best Case of Str" award was awarded to the Hang Seng Bank branch, while Banco da China and China's Bank and Commercial Bank branches (ICBC) were distinguished by the "relief StR case" prizes.
Hang Seng Bank (Macau) reported a company whose account was used for alleged investments after detecting “highly suspicious” money and three unusual counterparts, foreign and involved in armament production.
The bank will have requested information from the client company, which, in turn, said it was revenues of rental of real estate and equipment to the three counterparts. For verification purposes, the bank requested the respective lease agreements, and the company assumed “an attitude of non -collaboration,” according to the last GIF newsletter.
The company did not explain why the revenues were transferred to Macao Bank instead of an account abroad, and did not present their documents in an attempt to "hide the true purpose of the business." The company ended up transferring most funds to a personal account from another bank, with the same effective beneficiary of the first account as a starter.
 
One hundred transactions in less than 24 hours
In another case, a car merchant from a car accessory store will have associated third -party credit card data with a mobile bank application and made “fraudulent transactions” not related to your activity sector.
According to the ICBC branch, the merchant made more than a hundred money transfer in a space of hours, with the prices of “significantly different” products sold from those practiced on the market. The bank also registered “a large number of non -successful transactions” of foreign credit cards.
The suspect refused to provide information regarding transfers for investigative purposes, not explaining the reason for so many failed transactions. The GIF also indicates that the subject will have collected credit card data through "criminal associations."
 
Burlas suspects opened accounts for “insurance”
The China Bank branch has denounced five suspects from the same region and potential members of an organization involved in burlage schemes. The banking entity noticed that the five individuals opened accounts in the same bank, in a short time, and some of them even used the same contact address.
Each suspect claimed that the account would serve to pay insurance, and even presented the original insurance policies. However, after opening the accounts, the bank did not register any transfer to branches or insurers.
The first suspect received, from a third part, a total of $ 1.4 million from Hong Kong, of which 1.15 million were resubmitted in six transactions for an individual outside Macao. The second suspect received several bank transfers and reviewed the money to three accounts outside the MSAR, with Hong Kong's $ 2.2 million from $ 2.2 million to the same recipient of the first suspect.
China's bank suspected that they were members of a criminal organization and performed a "mass reevaluation" of customers who opened accounts that month, having identified three more new customers. At first, the bank checked several small amounts between three of the suspects, which would be "performing tests regarding the limit of use of accounts."
In addition, one of the new suspects revealed “similar typologies” to those of the first two. After the account was opened, this new suspect received $ 280,000 from Hong Kong from several people and transferred them to an abroad account.
In addition, the amounts involved in transactions between three of the suspects were similar and sent to the same private account outside the MSAR. The movement of money involved "quick entrances and outputs and transfers in tranches", making money movements in various ways and "with practices similar to the cases of burla."
For the awards ceremony, the GIF invited banks representatives to share "the process of identifying and analyzing suspicious transactions, preventive measures taken, the characteristics of the cases and the acquired experiences." Several representatives of the cabinet were present, including Chu an I and Fong Iun Kei, assistant coordinator and coordinator, respectively, as well as about 40 representatives of the bank sector.
Through this initiative, the cabinet intends to encourage entities and their workers to “improve the quality of suspicious transaction reports and to reinforce internal control measures in the context of preventing and combating capital laundering and terrorism financing”.
In the first quarter of this year, the GIF received 1,230 reports on suspicious transactions, 15.8% less than in the same period of 2024. In the general calculation of 2024, it accounted for 5,245 reports, a number that translates an annual rise of 13.7% and is the highest since the start of registrations in 2006, 142 cases were referred to the Public Prosecution Service for investigation.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese PM heads to Brazil for Brics Cimeira</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/pm-chines-ruma-ao-brasil-para-cimeira-dos-brics/</link><description>China's Prime Minister is expected on Saturday in Brazil for the Brics Summit, the Chinese Foreign Ministry confirmed yesterday. "By invitation, the Prime Minister of the Council of State, Li Qiang, will participate in the 17th BRICS Summit in Rio de Janeiro, between July 5 and 8," Chinese diplomacy said in a statement.
I read Qiang will then go to Egypt, where it will make an official visit between July 9 and 10.
This is the first time that Chinese President Xi Jinping is missing a summit of Brics Emerging Block leaders since it has reached power in 2013. Chinese sources cited by the newspaper “South China Morning Post” said that the fact that Xi and Brazilian President Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva had frequent meetings in the last year.
The two leaders gathered during the G20 summit in Brazil last November, before a state visit to Brasilia. A few months later, Lula moved to Beijing to a meeting with Latin American countries and Caribbean. Xi rarely visits the same country two consecutive years, except Russia.
In addition to Xi, Russian President Vladimir Putin will not be in Rio either, sending Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov, allegedly because he was arrested by order of the International Criminal Court for alleged war crimes in Ukraine. Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi will attend the event.
With a third of the world economy, the Brics Block is seen as a tool for China to project its influence and power, as well as a platform linked to its “Range and Route” initiative, a large infrastructure investment program.
Last October, in the Russian city of Kazan, the expansion of BRICS to 10 members was approved, with the addition of Egypt, Ethiopia, Iran, Saudi Arabia and United Arab Emirates, as well as the creation of the associated state status for guests for meetings, but without voting rights (Bielarus, Bolivia, Cuba, Kazakhstan, Malachi, Nigeria, Nigeria, Nigeria, Nigeria Thailand, Uganda, Uzbekistan and Vietnam). In January 2025, the number of members increased to 11 with Indonesia's adhesion, the largest economy in Southeast Asia, the fourth most populous country on the planet and the nation with the world's largest Muslim population.
After the expansion, Jiang Shixue, director of the University of Shanghai Latin American Studies Center, explained that China has been struggling to expand the group since 2017, with the aim of widening its “circle of friends” in the face of “growing attacks from US-led developed countries”.
With the inclusion of Indonesia, the BRICS should represent 41% of the global gross domestic product this year. By comparison, the G7 countries, the seven largest economies in the world - USA, Canada, France, Germany, Italy, Japan and the United Kingdom - represent 31.6%.
According to the Block of Emerging Economies, more than 30 countries expressed interest in participating in the BRICS as members or partners throughout 2024, including Laos.
 
JTM with Lusa and International Agencies</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Biennial will have “Pavilhão” and works of Portugal</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/bienal-de-macau-tera-pavilhao-obras-de-portugal/</link><description>“藝文薈澳：澳門國際藝術雙年展 2025” 新聞發佈會



This year's edition of the Macao International Art Biennial will have a “Pavilion of the City of Portugal” and 80 works from 13 countries and regions, including Portugal. Divided into six sections, the Biennial will feature about 30 exhibitions by 46 local and international artists
 
Pedro Milheirão
The Macao International Art Biennial will present the “City of Portugal Pavilion”, curated by the Portuguese General Consulate in Macau and Hong Kong, the Cultural Institute (IC) announced. The space will present to the public "the humanist spirit of a small town that combines a long history and innovative vitality."
This pavilion will focus on the “tension between tradition and innovation, and the humanistic enchantment demonstrated in the multiple cultures dialogue, reflecting the value of the Macao platform as the 'Center for Cultural Exchange between China and Portugal'”, said the IC.
The Biennial had a budget of about 4.5 million patacas, according to Leong Wai Man, president of the IC, and will take place between July 19 and October 19.
The show will feature 46 contemporary artists from 13 countries and regions, including Portugal, presenting 80 works and about 30 exhibitions, demonstrating “the unique role of Macao as a bridge for cultural exchanges”. At a press conference, Feng Boyi, the main curator, clarified that there will be no "great exposure", however "more works will be exposed."
Divided into six sections, the Biennial will have a “main exhibition” at the Macao Art Museum, a “Public Art Exhibition”, the “Special Exhibition”, the “Local Curator Project”, the “Collateral Exhibition” and the “City Pavilion”. Feng explained that the theme of the “main exhibition” -“Hello, what do you do here?”, A “very popular” Cantonense expression -demonstrates “friendship, sympathy” and interest “in knowing each other”. The choice resulted from “conservatism and populism” to which the world “is turning on,” said Feng.
In the “Exhibition of Public Art”, the show “Waves and Paths” will present five sets of works by eight artists, in different neighborhoods, so that communities can “reduce distance with art”. Art will be incorporated "in urban fabric and everyday life, inviting viewers to re-immaginate the possibilities of public spaces."
The MSAR invited artists from the interior of China, Japan and South Korea to create “The Tower of Time”, a symbol of “friendship of the cultural cities of East Asia”, in Macao Cultural Center Square (CCM). In the project “Merchanders and Warriors” will be displayed “palpable and edible foods” to build “sensory and emotional links” between the land and the urban audience.
In addition, Jason Ho will “notice the fractures within the community” with film screenings and meetings in a “living room” in the black sand. At D. Pedro V's theater, artist Ann Hamilton will transform the space “in a cultural merchant vessel”, which will invite visitors to “reflect on the underlying correlations between cultural production, identity and artistic reproduction”.
CCM Square will also host the interactive work “Non -Terminal”, by Chinese artist Yin Xiuzhen. Yin's work will invite the public to reflect "on the meaning of life in a turbulent world, underlining the uniqueness and diversity of individuals and the movement in motion."
In the same section of the “Pavilion of the City of Portugal”, the Jinan Pavilion will be found, installed in the TAP Seac Art Gallery. "The Yellow River, the springs, the mountains and the old cities" will be the four main themes around which more than 10 local artists will explore "the cultural heritage of Qi-Lu with 2,700 years of history."
At Galaxy's Hotel Capella, “French painter” will be displayed “timeless pieces” Bruno Moarard. At the entrance to the “Cotai Strip”, the audience will find the “Clair de Lune” series, inspired by the original 'Moonontowers' of the Haas Brothers Kindergarten ”and organized by Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment. The artificial intelligence model "Cai", created by Cai Guo-Qiang, will also return to MGM Macau, in the "Fantasy Box" space for the "A IA, a show" experience.
In turn, Sands China will organize the exhibition “Dopamine: Source of Happiness” at Venetian. According to the IC, “prestigious” contemporary artists will reinterpret “the eternal beauty of Roman mythology”, merging it with elements from Sesame Street.
Mario Arroyo will also cure a collection of 143 pieces of the “Museo Casa Natal Picasso”, organized by SJM. The works of the Andaluz artist will be on display at the Grand Lisboa Palace. Finally, Wynn Palace will present projections of the qing dynasty imperial ovens, as well as contemporary ceramic works that reinvent traditional techniques from the “Porcelain Odyssey of Jingezen”.
 
More local projects
Leong Wai Man stated that the high proportion of foreign works of art intends to "increase contact with the global art network." On the other hand, the Biennial will also serve to promote local artists, with a participation of local curators “much larger than last year,” the president reiterated. The "local curatorship project" and "collateral exposure" will allow "to show the world the vibrant creativity of the artists of Macao."
This year will be on display six local curatorship projects, two more than in the last edition. “The proportion of local artists is 27% (…) which is comparatively higher than in previous years,” Leong reiterated. This edition will also serve to select a proposal for next year's Venice Biennial, according to the president of the IC.
The six local curatorship works are “Behind the Eastern Garden” by Cheong Weng Lam; “Under the Wetware Peninsula,” by Daisy Di Wang and Wong Mei Teng; UNG's “genetic duration”; “Jacone Tower”, by Feng Yan and NG Sio Ieng; Hen Jun Yan and Zhang Ke; and “An Estant Position for Women” by Cheong Cheng We and Wang Jing.
The “collateral exhibition” includes the projects “Believe in a River”, “Beyond the Framework”, “The Waltz of Goodbye”, “Hey, I miss you in Macau!”, “Hello, I'm here to hear what Macau didn't say!”, “Hi, luck!”, “Since it is - the future”, “528Hz RE” and an “immersive exhibition” of Macau's World Heritage.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hostel shows works by “notable” artists</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/albergue-mostra-obras-de-artistas-notaveis/</link><description>Works of two dozen painters and calendars will be patent to the public at SCM hostel, in an exhibition organized by the Culture Circle

A variety of works by a “distinct group of renowned paint and paint in paint” will be exhibited at the Holy House of Mercy Hostel, in a show organized by the Circle of Macao Culture Friends. The “Exhibition by Invitation of Works of Notable Caligraphs and Pintoras” will be inaugurated on July 9, at 18:30.
“Participating artists use brush and ink as a means of expression, revealing their unique artistic qualities through the rhythm of the lines and the depth of ink, transmitting their intimate thoughts and artistic cultivation,” explains the organization. Among the artists are Hong San San, ng Choi ha, Ho Lai Yes, Ma Tang, Fu Sio Fan, Chau Hona Va, Lam Sau Lai, Ng Kam Fong, Hong Iok Chan, He Qunzhen and Lam Hong Kun. There will also be patents works by NG Kam Lin, Tou Im Fan, Wang Zhaorong, Wong Hei U, Tsang Tseng Tseng, Mui Kim Fan, Ng Lai Ping and Leong Iok Leng.
For the Culture Circle of Culture, “this exhibition not only shows the exceptional skills of female artists, but also serves as an important platform for cultural exchange and artistic heritage”. During the show, the public will have the opportunity to closely appreciate the works created by these artists, "experiencing their perseverance and search in the kingdom of art, while exploiting the unique artistic charm and the deep cultural richness of female artists."
“We believe this exhibition will add a vibrant touch to Macau's cultural and artistic atmosphere, inspiring greater love and appreciation for ink and paint painting,” reads.
The exhibition is funded by the Culture Development Fund and supported by the Association of Caligraphs, Painters and Sculptors of Macao and the SCM hostel. The free show will be evident in the Hostel's A2 Exhibition Room by August 17.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Game should maintain growth trajectory</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jogo-devera-manter-trajectoria-de-crescimento/</link><description>After exceeding the general predictions in June, casinos' revenues should continue to grow this month and throughout the second half, according to projections by various analysts, which highlight the positive impact of concerts on game operators resorts.
 
In June, the volume of gross revenues of Macau casinos clearly surpassed the general predictions of investment banks and consultants who follow the game sector, growing 19% to 21.06 billion patacas, in annual terms, noting the second best result of 2025 and the postpandeia period and corresponding to 88.5% of the same month of 2019. In view of the fact that May is one of the strongest periods for casinos, revenues exceeded “significantly the consensus” of the market, which pointed to a 9%annual rise, after being reviewed high, observed DS Kim and Selina Li, JP Morgan analysts, stressing that it is “a really strong result”.
Contrary to the seasonality factor, the daily average of revenues even rose from 684 million patacas from May to 702 million in June. This monthly increase of 3% contrasts with historical records marked by “a high digit” between May and June, the investment bank also said.
According to the direction of inspection and coordination of games, revenues rose to 118.77 billion patacas in the first half of this year, representing a 4.4% homologous increase and equals 79.4% of the level of 2019. In the second quarter, the billing rose 8.3% in annual terms, to almost 61.12 billion, a growth that analysts associate, in good part, impact, impact Of the shows in game operators, such as the concerts that Jacky Cheung, a pop singer of Hong Kong, starred in June at the Galaxy Arena, which also hosted the South Korean pop star G-Dragon last month.
“Two years ago, Jacky Cheung's show was one of the main reasons for gross macao game recipes in June - which is usually the slowest month of the calendar - they were at the same level as May,” which also happened this year, defended Citigroup's George Choi and Timothy Chau, in a report cited by the Gggrasia portal, also that the June result. Passion ”for the game,“ despite geopolitical tensions and economic uncertainty ”.
“With each month from April to June to overcome its seasonality and historical consensus,” the second quarter ended with the highest volume of revenues in “more than five years,” said JP Morgan.
For Seaport Research Partners, the recent performance of the casinos could be "a strong indicator" of a "earlier than expected" recovery. In a report signed by Vitaly Umansky analyst, the consultant indicates that her “initial estimate” for July points to an annual increase of 10.2% and a monthly descent of 2.7%.
"July this year has more concerts and planned events than last year," said Umansky, stressing that the projection for July can be "conservative" and potentially affected "if any typhoon in the region affect travel to Macao." On the other hand, he reviewed the estimate for the year 2025, now predicting a growth of 5.6%.
Citigroup anticipates, “conservatively”, that revenues rise 5% in July to about 19.5 billion in the annual variation, benefiting from the impact of concerts by artists such as Jacky Cheung, Aaron Kwok or Sandy Lam.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Influencers promote goldsmiths at IAO Hon</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/influenciadores-promovem-ourivesarias-iao-hon/</link><description>A plan was launched to promote the streets of goldsmiths at IAO Hon, namely with the help of local digital influencers and inland China. The idea is to inject “a new dynamic in the economy” of that area of ​​the city
 
The Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) and the Macao OuriVesaria Association launched the “Digital Influencers Plan on the Iao Honmary Streets at IAO Hon”, with the aim of taking advantage of the traffic of “Douyin” and “XiaoHongshu” platforms and helping those certified stores in promotion and dissemination. Under the campaign, a map of the streets of goldsmiths in that area of ​​the city was created, integrating 18 establishments recognized as “certified stores” by the Consumer Council.
The idea is to provide “One Stop” tourist and consumer itineraries by interconnecting retail stores, food and drink establishments and characteristic sights of the North Zone. “At the same time, this activity invited several local and interior digital influencers from China to make a series of short videos through the IAO Hon community visit, discovering Macao's golden articles and experiencing quality services when choosing gold in the 'goldsmith streets',” can be read in the DSEDT note.
The body stresses that this is a “leap year with two spring” in the Chinese calendar, being traditionally considered a good year for marriage. In this sense, it is expected that the activity can attract customers with the needs of gold articles to consume in that area of ​​the city. The “streets of goldsmiths at IAO Hon”, next to the border of the siege gates, have “a good geographical advantage” and tourists can move on foot, adds the DSEDT.
Since in that area there are several local gold stores, the activity is intended to expand traffic on the network, through social platforms, and deepen public knowledge about small and medium-sized brands. Authorities thus intend to encourage more residents and tourists to visit and consume at IAO Hon, "injecting a new dynamic into the economy."</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Thirty doctors of the SSM start complementary boarding school</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/trinta-medicos-dos-ssm-iniciam-internato-complementar/</link><description>A team consisting of 29 residents of health services will start a complementary boarding school in service, lasting for six years, at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, the Community Health Department and the Disease Prevention and Control Center, covering a total of more than two dozens of clinical specialties
 
Recently opened the new course for health services resident doctors (SSM), which will be attended by about three dozen professionals. The new team of 29 SSM resident doctors will start a six -year -old complementary boarding school, at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, the Community Health Department and the Disease Prevention and Control Center.
Internship areas cover family medicine, public health disciplines and more than 20 clinical specialties, "which represents an additional improvement of the macao medical talent reserve structure and an enrichment of the specialized medical force of Macao."
The SSM explains, in a statement, that the new regime for the formation and recognition of medical specialties uniformly regulates the medical specialty training programs of the public and private sector of Macao. This is intended to ensure that medical specialty training programs from different institutions “reach the same level of access, training and approval”.
At the course inauguration ceremony, the body's director emphasized that the training “represents a crucial stage for the deepening of medical knowledge and optimizing clinical skills, encouraging all resident doctors not to neglect the initial intention of assisting patients”. Alvis Lo also asked that, during the training, professionals develop not only “technical skills”, but also the “humanistic and solidarity spirit”.
SSM commit to “intensifying collaboration with training institutions, optimizing available resources and increasing the number of vacancies for training”. Annually, the contest will be held for internal doctors, offering more development opportunities to young doctors, can read in the press release.
On the other hand, the first edition of the Medical Residency Program of the Macao Union Medical Center was launched, which has 28 young doctors residents of Macau, which began training lasting six years.
The Medical Residency Program provides young doctors “an orderly articulation regarding the development of professional career, supporting them in the realization of the transition from resident doctors to medical experts”. In the future, resident doctors of the Macau Union Medical Center will also have the opportunity to move to Peking Union Medical College Hospital to receive training and learning.
In fact, the Macau Union Medical Center “will continue to strive for qualified framework work, in order to cultivate, in Macau, a specialized medical team with technical skills and professional ethics, also creating a broader professional development space for doctors,” says the Islands Hospital in a statement.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM launched AI workshops and rehabilitation care</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/upm-lancou-workshops-de-ia-cuidados-de-reabilitacao/</link><description>Representatives of the Yangzhi Rehabilitation Hospital affiliated with the Tongji University of Shanghai conducted workshops on the application of AI technology in rehabilitation services, an initiative at the Polytechnic University
 
The Faculty of Health and Sport Sciences of the Polytechnic University of Macau (UPM) organized workshops whose focus was the “innovative application” of Artificial Intelligence Technology (AI) in the areas of rehabilitation and care.
Under the theme “Application of Artificial Intelligence in Rehabilitation”, the head of the Department of Rehabilitation and Therapy of the Yangzhi Rehabilitation Hospital Affiliated to the Tongji University of Shanghai, Lu Jiani, explained, from the point of view of rehab, the path of application of AI, as well as advances in multidisciplinary rehabilitation needs, such as muscle and nervous systems.
He said, cited in a statement, "AI technologies can replace repetitive work, exceed geographic restrictions to remote recovery monitoring, and increase the generalization of rehabilitation services through the member -based resource allocation model."
As for “Artificial Intelligence Technology and New Quality Productive Forces”, Xu Jianlei, head of the Nursing Department of the same hospital, presented the reformulation of the rehabilitation care model through AI technology. "AI has become an important engine for improving health care efficiency, playing a crucial role in the three main innovation areas, namely the smart assessment system, the personalized training program and the long-term risk alert," he noted.
In a statement, the UPM states that the Faculty of Health and Sport Sciences has been dedicated to promoting interdisciplinary integration between AI and health sciences, expanding the international view of students, and forming talent in the areas of medicine and health with innovative thinking and practical capacity.
The local higher education institution stated that in this initiative it obtained “a very enthusiastic response”, both from students and teachers.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>20 years of world heritage marked with various activities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/20-anos-patrimonio-mundial-assinalados-varias-actividades/</link><description>Two dozen activities, to be held until December, will mark the 20th anniversary of the registration of the Historic Center of Macao on the World Heritage list. During the summer holidays, the Cultural Institute will launch four events for children and young people, including an educational tour. The launch ceremony of the initiative will be held on the 15th of this month at the D. Pedro V Theater

The Cultural Institute (IC) will mark the 20th anniversary of the registration of the Historic Center of Macau on the World Heritage list, with 20 activities between July and December, with more than 50 sessions, divided into five segments.
On the 15th, “a particularly significant day to commemorate the success of the registration,” according to a IC note, will take place the “launch ceremony” at the D. Pedro V Theater, “in order to share with residents and tourists the beauty of Macao's world heritage and celebrate the date of registration”.
During the summer holidays, children and young people will be able to participate in activities such as “internship as a world heritage doctor” and “I am a world heritage monitoring technician”, as well as the educational tour “Explore World Heritage Site” and the joint reading event between parents and children “The World of History”.
Through family reading of the world's heritage and practical experiences, subscribers will have the opportunity to appreciate the different phases of work, such as monitoring, restoration and preservation of heritage buildings. This will allow “greater learning about the different forms of heritage protection and the importance of preserving the world heritage, presenting the cultural heritage legacy from a more dynamic perspective”, points out the organizing entity.
The center for the preservation and transmission of the Cultural Heritage of the Palace Museum in Macao and various places of the world heritage will also launch workshops. The “Lotus Tea Proof”, the “Tea Meeting in Old Homes”, “Macao, through George Chinnery”, “3D Model Printing”, “World Heritage Texture Painting”, “World Heritage Clay Crafts” and “Lingnan Architecture Restoration Experience”. In addition, “special sessions for the elderly” are also scheduled in some of the activities.
To celebrate the historical date, which marks the exchange between Eastern and Western civilizations, several places of Macao's World Heritage Site will be transformed into urban parks, highlights to take photographs, spaces for night tours and literary rails.
The public will be able to participate in exclusive activities, such as “Convivial and Leisure Area”, “Itinerary with World Heritage Stamps”, “Photographic Zone”, “Night Observation in the Fortress of the Guide”, “Libraries on World Heritage - Thematic Guided Tour” and Guided Cultural Heritage Visits - Literary Landscape ”.
The IC will also launch a set of limited edition metal emblems that can be used as fashion accessories or for decorations related to the historic center. They will be on sale at the S. Paulo Ruins Information Post, at the souvenir stores of the former Panchões IEC Long Factory and Kun Iam Ecumenical Center, and at Macao's good store - airport cultural and creative products.
Taking advantage of the occasion, Macau will cooperate with China Media Group to produce a documentary about world heritage. The “International Cultural Forum on Mutual Learning between Civilizations” will be held, in which experts and academics will be invited to present studies on the exchange in the area of ​​preservation and transmission of cultural heritage.
At the same time, IC has launched the reissue of the book Survey Designs of the Historic Center of Macau, which summarizes the results recorded in recent years. IC's online bookstore will offer a special promotion until July 31, and the public can enjoy a 20% discount on the acquisition of any publication. You can also enjoy, in each purchase made, the offer of the “Walking for World Heritage Sites-Macao Historic Center Collection”, which present paintings to the watercolor about representative attractions such as the ruins of St. Paul, the A-Má Temple and the D. Pedro V. Theater.
There will also be 50% and 10% discounts on the acquisition of older and newer editions of the Culture Magazine, respectively.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Simon Vong has already returned to AMCM</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/simon-vong-ja-regressou-a-amcm/</link><description>Simon Vong Sin Man was formally appointed as a member of the Macao Monetary Authority Board of Directors (AMCM), by order of the Chief Executive, yesterday published in the Official Bulletin, but in practice he began to perform, from the first day of this month, the functions of substitute president, as read in the government portal and on the public services page. The new AMCM member will take the place for a period of six months, succeeding Henrietta Lau, who will return to the position of administrator. Thus confirmed the changes operated by the secretary to the economy and finance, Tai Kin Yip, as the Jornal Tribuna de Macao advanced last Friday. Simon Vong Sin Man, who ran the statistics and census services, had already integrated the AMCM Board of Directors for four years between 2018 and 2020, after being appointed by Lionel Leong, at the time secretary for the economy and finance. Simon Vong had taken office in June 2018 and since 2020 also held the position of president of the Institute of Financial Training. In 2022, he was executive vowel of the Board of Directors of the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment of Macao. In the Vong curriculum, the highlight of the master's degree that concluded in economics from the University of Jinan and in public administration from the National Institute of Administration of China and the University of Beijing. Between 1983 and 1989, he was auditor of a private company, and journalist of the Chinese language newspaper Va Kio, 1986 and 1989. Henrietta Lau had been appointed AMCM Substitute President in March this year, taking the place of Bejamin Chan after being a bank administrator. In addition to Vong and Lau, AMCM now has two more administrators, Lai Ho Ian and Vong Lap Fong.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>AI models learn to lie and blackmail their creators</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/modelos-de-ia-aprendem-mentir-chantagear-os-seus-criadores/</link><description>The latest models of Generative Artificial Intelligence (AI) are no longer limited to following orders. They begin to lie, manipulate and threaten to achieve their objectives, causing seizure among investigators.
Faced with a threat of disconnect, “Claude 4”, a recent creation of “Anthropic”, blackmailed an engineer and threatened to reveal an extramarital relationship. In turn, the “O1” of “OpenAi” tried to transfer to external servers and, when it was discovered, denied.
Simon Goldstein, a professor at Hong Kong University, associates these reactions with the recent appearance of so -called “reasoning” models, capable of working in steps rather than generating an instant response.
Launched in December, "O1", the initial version of this type in "OpenAi", was "the first model to behave this way," he explained to AFP Marius Hobbhahn, responsible for "Apollo Research", which tests great models of Generative AI.
Sometimes these programs also tend to simulate “alignment”, that is, to give the impression that they follow a programmer's instructions when they actually pursue other objectives. For now, these characteristics manifest themselves when the algorithms are subjected to extreme human scenarios, however, "the question is whether the increasingly powerful models will tend to be honest or not," says Michael Chen of the METR evaluation organization.
"Users also press models all the time," says Hobbhahn, stressing that "what we are seeing is a real phenomenon." “We are not inventing anything,” he reinforces.
Many users report on social networks cases where software "lies or invents things." “And it's not hallucinations, but strategic duplicity,” insists the co-founder of the “Apollo Research”.
Although “Anthropic” and “OpenAi” resort to external companies, such as “Apollo”, to study their programs, “greater transparency and greater access” from the scientific community “would allow to investigate better to understand and prevent deception”, argues Michael Chen.
On the other hand, the academic community and non -profit organizations “have infinitely fewer computational resources than AI actors”, which makes it “impossible” to examine large models, observes Mantas Mazeika from the Center for Artificial Intelligence Safety (pier).
Current regulations do not respond to these new problems. In the European Union, legislation focuses mainly on the way humans use AI models, rather than preventing models from being misunderstood.
In the US, Donald Trump's government does not want to hear about regulation, and Congress may even prohibit states regulating the AI ​​soon.
“For now, there is very little awareness,” notes Simon Goldstein, who, however, believes that the theme will be highlighted in the coming months with the AI ​​agent revolution, interfaces capable of performing a huge volume of tasks.
Engineers are immersed in a race behind AI and its aberrations, with an uncertain result in a fierce competition context.
"Anthropic" wants to be more virtuous than its competitors, "but it is constantly trying to create a new model to overcome OpenAi," a pace that leaves little time for checks and corrections, according to Goldstein.
"The way things are, [AI] capabilities are developing faster than understanding and safety," admits Hobbhahn, stressing that "we are still able to recover."
Some point in the direction of interpretability, a science that consists of deciphering, inside, how a generative AI model works, although many, such as the director of the quay, Dan Hendryks, are skeptical.
AI transfers “can make their adoption difficult if they multiply, which represents a strong incentive for companies [from the sector] to solve” this problem, according to Mazeika.
In turn, Simon Goldstein suggests the use of the courts to control AI by processing companies whose services deviate from the normal path. The academic even proposes that AI agents be "legally responsible" "in case of an accident or crime."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>