<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Al “has achieved fruit results” in the last four years</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/al-alcancou-resultados-frutiferos-nos-ultimos-quatro-anos/</link><description>There were several compliments that the Chief Executive made the deputies and the work they have done during the last four years. At a dinner that marked the end of the legislative session, Sam Hou Fai said they were achieved "important successes," which "marked a new level and a new phase of the work" of Hemiciclo. He also stated that the deputies presented constructive suggestions, “promoting increasingly reinforced representativeness and professionalism”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, praised the "important successes" of the seventh legislature of the Legislative Assembly (AL) and spoke in a "new phase" of the work of Hemiciclo. All of this at a dinner he offered to all deputies - unlike previous years, the MSAR leader did not answer the questions of deputies in the context of government action and matters linked to the life of the population, something that usually happened before the end of the legislative session.
"The seventh legislature of Almaguard effectively the constitutional order of the Misremiors established by the Constitution and the Basic Law, ensured the effective and smooth functioning of the structure with the predominance of the Executive Power established by the Basic Law, always supported and overseeed the government in governance, effectively exercised the powers and functions attributed by the basic law, reached extraordinary results and difficulties," He considered the boss in his speech.
For Sam Hou Fai, "the important successes" achieved "mark a new level and a new phase of work" of the legislative body, "thus providing solid foundations for the new legislature." According to the past four years, the hemiciclo "has constantly boosted the modernization of the legal system of masters and has achieved fruitful results."
In particular, he spoke in the approval of 86 laws related to the improvement of the state security defense of the State Security, the elevation of the governing capacity of the MSAR, the development of the proper diversification of the economy, the areas related to the well-being of the population, and the functioning of the AL, as well as the rights and duties of deputies.
"At the same time, (…) actively performed the attributions of supervision conferred by the law, effectively fulfilling their inspection functions, as well as maintained close connection with all social sectors and residents in general, had actively opinions and constructive suggestions, promoting an increasingly reinforced representativeness and professionalism in the Legislative Assembly," Sam Hou Fai continued.
The boss also reiterated that the principle “Macao macao ruled by patriots” should be reiterated, "ensuring a correct direction" for the work of al. In addition, he continued, "the legislative body and the executive body must fulfill their own functions and responsibilities well to ensure the smooth functioning of the structure with the predominance of the executive branch." On the other hand, it argued that it is necessary to “continue to improve legislative efficiency and quality to ensure legal compliance with Macau's environment and prestige based on the rule of law”, as you can read in a statement issued by the media.
On the other hand, he indicated that the Government of MSAR “will reinforce close collaboration with the legislative and judiciary”, as well as “unite and lead all social sectors”. It will also “correctly identify, manage properly and actively seek changes” and “take full party from the institutional advantages of the 'one country, two systems' principle”. At the same time, having the country as a back, it will "implement the various governing plans, and respond to the uncertainties of the external conjuncture with the certainty of development itself."
Sam Hou Fai thanked the president of AL, Kou Hoi In, Vice President Chui Sai Cheong, and all deputies, "for the exceptional contribution to MSAR and the support provided to the new Government of MSAR." He also said he hopes that Kou Hoi In, Chui Sai Cheong and the deputies who will soon leave the position "continue to support the government."
At dinner was also present Ron Lam, who leaves the position of deputy, after being disqualified from the race to the elections for, according to the State Security Defense Commission, "not to defend the basic law or not to be faithful to mashes." Another 11 candidates were also disqualified for the same reason.
As for the elections scheduled for September 14, the chief executive stressed that "it is an important moment of political life in the Masheries," pointing out that the government "will organize them in a committed manner, ensuring a fair, impartial and whole environment."
 
Nine deputies reiterated requests in the balance sheet
Deputies Ella Law, Leong Sun IOK, Lam Lon Wai and Lei Chan U concluded that, at the 4th Legislative Session of the 7th Legislative Assembly, they received 6,000 requests for help, involving labor rights, employment and irregularities in hiring. Ella Lei appealed to the government to further reduce the quotas of non -resident workers of large companies, game operators and the bank sector. Law Chan U suggested increased maternity leave to 90 days, promoting the mandatory central pension regime and transformation of the dragon boat festival on a mandatory holiday. In turn, Zheng Anting and Lo Choi in received 2,343 requests for help, of which 2,179 were accompanied. Zheng Anting stressed that some elderly people complained about the long waiting time for homes and the “expensive income” of the residence for the elderly, so suggested the adjustment of income and speed in the construction of homes. Lo Choi in Waiting to build a residence for the elderly, of relatively low income, intended for the “intermediate class”. Si Ka Lon, Song Pek Kei and Nick Law followed 3,838 out of a total of 5,774 requests for help. Si Ka Lon urged to improve the execution mechanism of liability of senior leaders, while Song Pek Kei requested measures to improve the business environment and attract investment.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Approved two teachers requested by the Portuguese school</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/aprovados-dois-docentes-solicitados-pela-escola-portuguesa/</link><description>The new academic year at the Portuguese School of Macao will start with all classes and subjects to have teachers, assured the president of the EPM Foundation. Jorge Neto Valente told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that they were recently authorized by the Ministry of Education of Portugal the 36 teachers with special license - of which only two are new, having been selected in the last contest held. As for the number of students, according to the registrations confirmed so far, there are 809, against 780 in the school year 2024/2025. Works inside the building, which will be completed at the end of this month, enable this slight increase
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Within three weeks, it starts another academic year at the Portuguese School of Macau (EPM) and this time there should be no lack of teachers. Everything points out, therefore, so that it is a startless starter. "Everything is guaranteed for the new school year, with regard to teachers who will teach at school," the EPM Foundation (FEPM) president told the Tribuna de Macao newspaper.
Jorge Neto Valente revealed that “the special licenses of the 36 teachers were recently authorized to the Ministry of Education of Portugal, which means that the difficulties arising in the previous two years should not be repeated. "All the teachers that the school has requested have already been approved, and there is no problem in this regard," he said, adding that, of these special leave, "only two are new, having been selected in the contest we held."
These teachers, recruited for the subjects of Mathematics and Geography, will cover those who left. “Two teachers came out of their own will that we considered they missed, so we replaced them, because we don't have it at school,” he assumes.
Moreover, "others left, but they are not missing, so there is no reason for replacement, among which some who had been dismissed last year and that the minister decided to stay." For Neto Valente "now it is proved that the times are made and they are not missing." Remember that a few months ago she knew about the departure of six teachers and two EPM psychologists. The educational institution will have a total of 80 teachers in the next school year.
Regarding the number of students actually enrolled for the school year that begins on September 9 -one day after the students' reception -it is at this time 809, slightly more than the 780s who attended the school during the school year 2024/2025.
This small increase is possible because the improvement works inside the building, which are about to be completed, will allow you to gain some more spaces. “Everything that was scheduled is doing and the work can even end before the scheduled date, which is August 31,” says Neto Valente.
With regard to the widening of some classrooms, the school officials had already recognized them were very small, since they were divided in the middle, stating that there was mismanagement of space. On the other hand, after the completion of the works, considered urgent, the showers are practically twice as long as they were nine, which will allow more students to bathe faster after sports activities in the gym or the game room.
 
Cost of works is supported by DSEDJ
The budget of the works is just over seven million patacas. The money will be paid first for the school and then reimbursed by the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ). “This is how we now work, we advance and later DSEDJ gives us the money,” explains FEPM number one.
The subsidy assignment procedures will also be applied to the works scheduled for next year. At that time about 10 million patacas will be spent, although the work to be done do not have the same dimension as those who are now being completed.
“Next year, this budget will not only be for works themselves, it will also be applied to the acquisition of computer equipment, for example, as it is necessary to replace computers, but also furniture, ie things we need for school,” he says, adding that this budget is pre-approved. "If the school has this money available, it is good for the purchase of the equipment and then it will be reimbursed," he explains.
The EPM, with regard to finances, will live a little more loosely, due to the amount that the Government of Portugal, through the Ministry of Education, will make available, with a percentage higher than what happened for several years.
The announcement of the replacement of the amount, made when traveling to the territory of the Portuguese Minister of Foreign Affairs, Paulo Rangel, has had practical effects. The money entered the coffers of the Foundation significantly in mid -July. Under Lisbon's decision, EPM is now supported by more than one million euros for school expenses, against the 776,000 it has received in recent years.
Holding 51% of the EPM Foundation capital, the successive governments of Portugal reduced to 10% the contribution to the expenses of the school, from the time of the Troika, in 2014, a situation that caused some dissatisfaction in the leaders of the school.
It is recalled that, in statements to journalists, during a reception to the Portuguese community, in his visit to late March, the Minister of Foreign Affairs stated that the financing was again “at legal levels”, considering that there was no reason to have the cut.
Questioned whether the addition of funds will greatly relieve EPM expenses, Jorge Neto Valente considers that this will allow to “cover expenses without searching the capital of the Foundation, which was what happened until I entered, in 2023/2024”. In previous years, he says, "it always hurt and therefore it was necessary to go to the foundation's background." “Throughout that way, the money would disappear, it was a matter of time,” he comments.
The proposed budget for EPM this year is 80 million patacas, slightly higher than the previous one. "It is not yet approved, but it is expected to stay for this money," he said, realizing that "in the budget there is no deficit or surplus, expenses match revenues," he says, adding that "there has been a reduction in expenses, which allows spending money on things that are missing for school."
With regard to relations with the Ministry of Education of Portugal, it states that “they are perfectly normal” and recalls that the EPM does not always have to be talking to Lisbon, because the school “has autonomy”. “We just need the money and that they give us licenses, that's what we need,” he concludes.
 
Santa Casa supports 62 students in the payment of bribes
Santa Casa da Misericórdia will support more than 60 families in the payment of the bribes of the Portuguese school, next school year, said Radio Macau. The provider of the institution, António José de Freitas, indicated to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that, in total, 62 requests for support were received, and 66 registration bulletins had been raised. According to it, Santa Casa will channel, in total, more than half a million patacas in support of these students, a value “slightly higher” than last year. More than a thousand students have already benefited from this Santa Casa bribes allowance, a support program that already has over 25 years of existence.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Iam is already accepting requests for a license from Esplanada</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/iam-ja-esta-aceitar-pedidos-de-licenca-de-esplanada/</link><description>AMI began to accept, by way, requests for a license of Esplanade presented by food and drink, restaurants and bars establishments. For this, it redefined requirements for licensing terraces and operating rules
 
After a 16 -year -old hiatus, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) is experimentally accepting termination requests from Esplanade license from food and beverage, restaurants and bars that meet the requirements, and new criteria have been defined for this request as well as new provisions.
According to AMI, the decision was made in order to optimize the business environment of Macao's small and medium -sized companies, given that the restoration sector has been presenting requirements on the installation of terraces.
The body revealed that it had colloquia with the Advisory Board for Municipal Affairs, the Advisory Board of Community Services of the Three Zones and with the industrial, commercial and restoration associations, with the purpose of arguing opinions to determine the new request requirements and operating rules. According to he said, in this regard, he took into account several factors, such as the balance between the community environment and the life of the population.
In addition, it was reviewed and adjusting the order conditions and the operation of terraces defined in the past and analyzed the operational situation of the terraces in the “Anim'Arte Nam Van” and the courtyard of Commander Mata e Oliveira.
New demands include fire prevention, environmental protection and health, noise control and space for pedestrian circulation. The requests will be considered and approved in conjunction with the competent surveillance services, noted the AMI.
By stressing that the Esplanade is a characteristic model of restoration and leisure, the AMI explains that the instructions on the “Esplanade Licensing Requirements” and the “Esplanade Exploration Rules”, including the prohibition of the functioning of the following day and the non -placement of similar equipment, as well as compliance with the provisions of the “Prevention and Control of environmental noise ”.
In addition, merchants who placed the order should maintain cleaning and hygiene of the terrace and surrounding space, periodically cleaning the area during the opening period and immediately arranging the site after daily use, namely the cleaning of stains on the floor, the immediate removal of all objects in the place after daily closing and the elaboration of exploration safety instruction in bad weather, such as tropical storms or storm It arises, taking into account public safety and hygiene.
AMI also assured that, after the authorized establishments, will highlight more personnel for inspection, exhorting traders to meet the exploration requirements. In general, he said he will constantly monitor the effectiveness of this measure, creating favorable conditions to revitalize the community economy.
A few days ago, the president of the Union of the Associations of Restoration and Beverages Owners, Chan Chak Mo, had said that the government had expressed the intention of moving forward with the resumption of Esplanade licenses. The association also said he hoped that the appreciation and approval of orders would be accelerated after the retake.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Podul” originated the longest sign of intense rain</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/podul-originou-mais-longo-sinal-de-chuva-intensa/</link><description>The heavy rainfall that was emitted due to the passage of the “Podul” tropical cyclone was the longest emitted in Macao since implementation in 2020 of the intense rainfall system of three levels, revealed the meteorological and geophysical services
 
During the passage of the “Podul” tropical cyclone, Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) emitted the black signal of heavy rain for three hours and 48 minutes, marking this longer signal the longest since the implementation of the three -level heavy rain system in Macao in September 2020.
At the same time, the heavy rain concentrated in the Cotai area, recalled the SMG, noting that the area with the highest precipitation was larger and five times more intense than the area that occupied the Macao peninsula.
At 5 pm on Thursday, the maximum total rainfall recorded in several zones was 269 millimeters in Coloane, 253.8 mm in the mud and 135.8 mm in the peninsula. During the term of the black signal of heavy rainfall, the highest water level was 0.92 meters at the Path of the Vegetable Station.
Regarding the factors that gave rise to the “heavy and prolonged rains”, the SMG analyzed that it was precisely due to the convergence of the peripheral circulation of “podul” and a southwest air flow combined with the terrain and other factors that the rain area remained stagnant over a long time.
“In the context of global warming, extreme weather phenomena have often occurred,” SMG noted, providing for a vast low pressure area to approach the southern coast of China between yesterday and tomorrow. Time in the territory will become unstable with heavy and thunder rain.
However, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) has discovered landslides in 22 places, having already completed the cleaning work. In addition, the body followed the situation of the sewage channel network in serious flooding zones. According to the AMI, the inspections have revealed that, in addition to the sudden flood factor caused by heavy and prolonged rains, some areas affected involve uncovered land and workforcers that, due to the lack of drainage facilities, will have faced overload, which has led a large volume of rainwater to overcome shipyards and flood the roads. The AMI ensured that it has coordinated emergency measures.
On the other hand, after inspecting the public parking parks, the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) stated that everyone managed to function as normally. However, the self-siles of the Taipa Central Park, Ferreira do Amaral Square and the Koi NGA building recorded light advances of rainwater, and the managing companies intensified the treatment of stagnant water.
 
Yesterday Sign 3 of Tropical Storm
Due to the influence of low pressure area, it was emitted yesterday, since noon, signal 3 of tropical storm in Macao. As a result, the classes of children's, primary and special teachings were suspended in the afternoon. Also due to the weather conditions, the event “Zape with Flavors” was closed. However, several cultural and sports activities were also canceled originally planned to take place yesterday. Some public services have appealed to the public to prepare, in advance, the necessary measures to face the typhoon and flooding.
 
Demored building in the Patio do Espinho
A degraded building, located in the Pátio do Espinho, was demolished because it has collapse of its coverage, slab and part of the outer wall, which was a high imminent danger of ruin. According to the Directorate of Soil Services and Urban Construction (DSSCU), the situation was a serious threat to public safety. After a follow-up process was established and after a survey by DSSCU and the Cultural Institute, the demolition was proceeded. DSSCU calls for citizens to redouble attention to the state of conservation of buildings, especially at this time of rainfall and typhoons, noting that the lack of maintenance that causes loss of human lives or equity damage to third parties implies the responsibility of the owners.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky goes to Washington with European leaders</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/zelensky-vai-washington-lideres-europeus/</link><description>Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky will meet today with his US homologist Donald Trump. But it doesn't go alone. Yesterday, Ursula Von Der Leyen, Friedrich Merz, Emmanuel Macron, Giorgia Meloni and Keir Stmerer announced that they will travel to Washington to, along with Zelensky, to discuss the future of the conflict after the summit between Trump and Putin in Alaska on Friday, ending without agreement for a ceasefire, which was the leader's goal American.
According to several sources cited by Reuters and “The Guardian”, the president of Russia will have proposed to assign small installments of territory busy in exchange for extensive areas at other points, namely the regions of Donetsk and Lugansk.
Yesterday, at a joint press conference in Brussels, Zelensky and the president of the European Commission, Ursula von der Leyen, stressed the impossibility of Kiev voluntarily yielding territories to Russia as part of a possible peace agreement. Regarding the territorial issues of Ukraine, the position of the European Union and Kiev is "clear," said von der Leyen: "international borders cannot be changed through the use of strength."
Von der Leyen also stared that the term “ceasefire” was less important than the need to stop the deaths. "What matters is the effect. And the effect should be to stop the deaths," he said.
On the other hand, Ursula Von der Leyen praised Donald Trump's proposal to offer Ukraine safety guarantees, inspired by the NATO and said he expects a tripartite summit "as quickly as possible."
"We greeted President Trump's desire to provide security guarantees to Ukraine, similar to Article 5," he said.
Earlier, in a statement published on social network X, Zelensky said Moscow was "hindering" efforts to end the conflict. "We see that Russia rejects the numerous appeals to a ceasefire and has not yet determined when it will end the deaths. This complicates the situation," he said.
"We are preparing for Monday's meeting with President Trump, and I am grateful for the invitation. It is important that everyone agrees that there is a conversation at the leader level to clarify all the details and determine which measures are needed and effective," he added.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Expenses from residents abroad in the face of expenses on the Mand</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sobem-gastos-de-residentes-exterior-face-as-despesas-na-raem/</link><description>In the second quarter of the year, MSAR residents spent less money on the territory and registered higher expenses abroad, compared to the same period of 2024. In the first six months of 2024, the RAME GDP exceeded 200 billion, according to official data
 
Pedro Milheirão
 
The population of Macao spent more money abroad and less in the local market, in the second quarter of this year, in relation to the same period of 2024. According to the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), private consumer expense rose 0.3%, driven by the growth of abroad resident spending (5.4%). However, the final consumer expense of families in the local market contracted 0.2%.
Between April and June, the value of GDP was reviewed to 100.39 billion patacas, representing 88.8% of the amount recorded in the same period of 2019 and an annual growth of 5.1%. In the first half of the year, the actual GDP growth was 1.8% compared to the first six months of 2024, having set at 200.15 billion of patacas, representing 87% of the economic volume of the same period of 2019.
In annual terms, game service exports grew 5.7%, while exports of other tourist services fell 3.9%in the first half of 2025. However, the latter grew 5.9%in the second quarter of the year, in homologous terms. Globally, service exports rose 1% and goods fell 7.9%. In turn, service imports rose 1.4% and goods registered a 4.6% break. The growth of services, particularly in the second quarter (+6%), was due to the growth of 20% of the number of visitors, according to DSEC.
From April to June, investments in construction and equipment by the public sector increased 19.9% and 83%, respectively, when compared to the same period of 2024. In contrast, private investment in the construction sector fell 28.4% while private equipment spending increased 11.7%. In homologous terms, gross fixed capital formation decreased 3.7%, and in the first two quarters, increased by 1.8%in annual terms.
The government has also seen its expenses increase 1%between April and June, for the same months last year. Civil service remuneration also rose 1%, while net purchases of goods and services grew 1.1%. In the previous three months, employees' salaries had grown 2.7% and net purchases of goods and services had fallen 1.5% in annual terms.
In May, DSEC stressed that "since the beginning of this year, the international conjuncture marks some volatility and challenges, the driving force of the growth of the global economy is not sufficient, and uncertainties in Sino-American relations have grown." It also mentioned that the “rapid changes” on visitors' consumption habits had “a certain impact on the development of the Macao tourism sector” and resulted in “fluctuations in the process of recovery of the local economy” in the first three months.
However, at the time, DSEC also stated that "Macao economy maintains the pace of recovery in global terms, public finances remain stable and local development is planned." "In general, Macao's economy will not mark a cyclic recession if there are no major changes in the internal and external context, a continuous tendency of recovery, the body reiterated.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Malpated credit ascends to 78.4 million</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/credito-malparado-ascende-784-milhoes/</link><description>There were 78.4 million patacas in “Malporated Credit” at MSAR at the end of the first half. The total amount of mobile payments exceeded eight billion patacas, between April and June
 
At the end of June, the total debt to pay for more than three months, in cards issued by the Banks of the MSAR, was 78.4 million patacas. This was the equivalent of 2.8% of the total debt balance, 2.8 billion patacas, 0.1 point percentage less than in the previous quarter. Of the total balance in debt, 741.7 million (26.9%) corresponded to the 'rollover' balance. In addition, the credit limit related to cards issued by the MSAR banks ascended to 50.3 billion patacas, an increase of 0.5%, compared to the previous quarter.
From April to June, the credit used reached 5.87 billion patacas, less 0.1% compared to the first three months of the year. According to the data, 143 million (2.4%) corresponded to advances of cash, a drop of 0.2 percentage points. There were also 12.5 million transactions, an increase of 6.3% over the previous quarter. The amount of the refund, including interest and expenses, was 5.7 billion, 6.3% less than in the first three months of the year.
98 million local mobile payments were also made in the second quarter of the year, representing an 8.4% increase over the previous three months, according to the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM). The total value of these transactions has risen to 8.1 billion patacas, translating a quarterly increase of 2.3%, with an average value per transaction of 82.8 patacas. Until the end of the first half, there were 111,452 devices that accepted mobile payments and supported “QR code”, more 2,703 (+2.4%) than at the end of the first quarter (108,749).
In the second quarter, 1.8 million transactions that resorted to debit cards were also accounted for, excluding surveys, totaling 434 million patacas, a break of 6.7% over the end of March (464.9 million). At the end of June, there were 2,577,765 debit card accounts, more 50,266 (+2%) than at the end of the first quarter (2,527,499). The number of credit cards went from 1,751,792 to 1,758,386 (+0.4%).
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Boss wants “joint projects” in investigation with Hangzhou</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-quer-projectos-conjuntos-em-investigacao-hangzhou/</link><description>From an official visit to Hangzhou, the Chief Executive said the Macao Higher Education Institutions will carry out joint scientific research projects. Sam Hou Fai started in that Chinese city a five -day journey through the continent
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Leading a MSAR delegation, the Chief Executive was in Hangzhou, in what was the first stop of a five -day journey on the continent, which also includes the city of Shanghai and the Zhejiang province.
Sam Hou Fai began the program with a trip to the Global Center for Scientific and Technological Innovation of the University of Zhejiang, having heard the presentation on its construction and operation, the mechanisms and systems of the transformation of scientific research results and the formation and aggregation situation of qualified staff in the area of scientific and technological innovation.
In the end, he said he hoped Macau's center and higher education institutions reinforce exchange and cooperation, and carry out joint scientific research projects.
Then he met with several representatives of scientific and technological companies in Hangzhou. During the meeting, he said that “over several years, Hangzhou has actively promoted the development of scientific and technological innovation, and through the capture and formation of qualified pictures, promotes new dynamics and creates advantages for industry”.
In the Balance Sheet text, widespread by the Social Communication Office, Sam Hou Fai considered it to be "good cooperation between Macau and Hangzhou, hoping that more scientific and technological companies will expand their business in Macao and develop with Raem companies."
Missing that the Macao government is building four relevant works and projects, including an industrial park for research and development of science and technologies and the Macao and Hengqin University City of Education, the government's official said that Hangzhou scientific and technological companies are “welcome to take advantage of these opportunities and develop in Macao”.
Yesterday afternoon, Sam Hou Fai moved to the city of Shanghai.
 
Sam Hou Fai received Minister of Education
Sam Hou Fai met at the Government headquarters with the Minister of Education, Huai Jinpeng, in which they addressed the possibility of greater impetus in the development of education matters and the phased creation of the University City of International Education of Macao and Hengqin. The Chief Executive said the Ministry of Education could continue to support the long -term development of MSAR Educational Affairs, "uninterruptedly deepening exchange and cooperation." Huai Jinpeng, accompanied by the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM, visited the Hengqin cooperation zone to find out, among other subjects, from the planning of the university city, the use of the land for educational purposes, as well as the conception of the construction of the sub -center of the traditional Chinese medical area.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Exhibition and Symposium mark China's victory over Japan</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/exposicao-simposio-assinalam-vitoria-da-china-sobre-japao/</link><description>Honor “The Martyrs” and extol “the noble patriotic spirits” guide the exhibition that marks the 80th anniversary of the “victory in the War of Resistance of the Chinese people against Japanese aggression and anti -fascist World War”. The show will be inaugurated on August 25 at the Complex of the Commercial Cooperation Platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries
 
With the purpose of “recalling the historical achievement, honoring the martyrs and extolling the noble patriotic spirits”, the show “For National Liberation and World Peace - Exhibition of the 80th Anniversary of the Chinese People's War War against Japanese aggression and anti -fascist World War” opens on August 25 and will be evident to the public until September 24 in the Commercial Cooperation Platform between China and Language Platform Portuguese.
The exhibition consists of six sections, namely: “the outbreak of war-rising through national salvation”, “resistance from the whole nation-fighting together against Japanese aggression”, “united as one-a common resolution against invaders”, “growing enthusiasm-the macao resistance”, “fighting together against fascism-the main eastern battlefield” and “the great victory-a turning point for rejuvenation-a turning point for rejuvenation National ”.
According to a note from the Social Communication Office, the event conveys the central concept “recalling history, paying tribute to martyrs, valuing peace and creating a great future”. Through a large amount of historical images and videos, the exhibition presents “systematically the arduous 14th anniversary of the Chinese people's resistance war” elapsed between 1931 and 1945, showing “the epic chapter of the bloody resistance of the Chinese people and the value of victory in the resistance war”.
It is also shown “the support provided by the sectors of the Macao society in the Fatherland struggle against Japanese aggression through funds raising, disclosure of information on national salvation, aid refugees, and participation in the front line, highlighting the solidarity bond between the macao compatriots and the country's people, united by blood ties and a common destination”.
The inauguration ceremony is scheduled for the morning of 25 August and the show will be available for visits from 15h00 of the same day. The time is from Monday to Sunday, from 10h00 to 20h00. Groups of 20 or more people can register online and mark the guided tour service from 10 am today, through the “Group Registration” thematic page. The maximum limit per session is 50 people.
In addition, the Cultural Institute and the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services will organize a thematic symposium on September 20, at the small auditorium of the Cultural Center, where experts and academics will be invited from the interior of China and Macao to address the historical significance of victory in the resistance war. Registration is now open.
The thematic session will be attended by the Shaanxi Provincial Committee of the Wang Xiaoli PCC Provincial Committee and the Directors of the Faculty of Humanities and Social Sciences of the Macao Polytechnic University, Lam Fat IAM, and the Institute of Social and Cultural Research at Macao University of Science and Technology, Lin Guangzhi.
The invited speakers will share studies on the involvement of young patriots in the revolution and their convictions during the War of Resistance, as well as the achievements and contributions of all sectors of Macao society during the war.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Provisional parking in Coloane begins to be built in September</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/estacionamento-provisorio-em-coloane-comeca-ser-construido-em-setembro/</link><description>The beginning of the works for the construction of a Provisional Parking Park in Coloane, next to the Cheoc Van Road and Rua da Cordoaria on an unoccupied land, is scheduled for September, indicated the Directorate of Public Works (DSOP) services. The body predicts that no less than 70 places for light cars and motorcycles can be provided, "thus contributing to relieving the insufficiency of parking places near the village of Coloane." In the short term, weed removal work, objects and elimination of stagnant water on the floor will begin, among others, in order to maintain the hygiene of the site and prevent the proliferation of mosquitoes and larvae, can be read in the statement. The land has an area of about 5,300 square meters, of which the space for vehicle parking will be located, mainly, in the open places of the south and north, with the total area of about 3,000 square meters. According to DSOP, the work consists of the earthmoving of the southern and north ends for vehicle parking; The walls will be reformulated by the Cordoaria Street and built access to the vehicles; The bay of accusage for public transport will be built on the Cheoc Van Road, next to the Provisional Park; and lighting and telecommunications facilities will be placed, among others, as well as the water and drainage supply systems.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Proposal of the “road traffic law” without conditions for voting</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/proposta-da-lei-transito-rodoviario-sem-condicoes-para-votacao/</link><description>After the approval by the Legislative Assembly (AL), generally, on 11 April 2024, the proposal of the “Road Traffic Law”, which was analyzed by the 1st Permanent Commission of AL, had the initial appreciation period until August 7. However, after overall weighting of various situations, the Ali table has decided that the proposal does not gather the requirements for voting by the plenary. “After the end of this legislature, the government can renew the initiative when it understands timely”, can be read in the document. In the deliberation, the table recalls that on May 13 was presented the work text, which, despite implying “significant changes and improvements”, “also presented problems of principle and articulation with other laws by solving”. At this point, a report of the 1st Permanent Commission on the subject exemplifies that the “Point Registration System” may after all lead to the cancellation of the driving license, so “it is debatable if this new regime is compatible with the current regime”. In addition, on various issues raised by the Commission during the meetings, including the feasibility of certain norms and the interpretation of others, government representatives said they needed more time to analyze and study, and to hear more opinions. Moreover, through the media, the Commission learned that "some issues originated controversy," understanding that the matter "requires prudence, because any adjustment of the law implies relevant impact on society." After being informed to “the immaturity of the work text and the initial version of the law proposal”, the president of AL has realized from the government that, given the complexity of follow -up and studies on the diploma, “it is difficult to conclude and present, soon, the formal and conclusive alternative version”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2456/</link><description>Seventh imported case of chikungunya fever
Macau registered the seventh imported case of chikungunya fever. According to health services, this is a 19-year-old, resident in the Kin Wa building, on Novo Canal Street, which participated in a training camp in Baiyun district in Cantão. After returning to Macao, he presented fever, rash on his face and right forearm as well as joint pain. The tests performed by the Public Health Laboratory confirmed that the patient gave positive to the Chikungunya virus. Its health is stable and is admitted to the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center to receive treatment.
 
Detained after Burla investigation to two elderly
The Judicial Police (PJ) received complaints from two elderly people from Macao, who claimed to have suffered losses of more than 8.42 million patacas, following burlas after investment in cryptocurrencies. In the investigation, PJ detained a 40 -year -old Hong Kong man who will have helped a criminal network whiten capitals, worth $ 60 million since May last year. Authorities are investigating other suspects, who are on the run.
 
“Zape with flavors” should receive 4,000 a day
It started on Friday, extending until the 24th, “Zape with Flavors”, Gastronomy Fair. On the sidelines of the opening ceremony, the director of tourism services predicted that the event will host 4,000 daily visitors. Helena de Senna Fernandes said the fair could return in the future, "if the results are satisfactory." It also revealed that the government will consider the extension for the Zape of the International Festival of Cities of Gastronomy, previously carried out at the fishermen's dock.
 
Ron Lam stop writing in the newspaper Son Pou
Former Deputy Ron Lam stopped writing articles in the Son Pou newspaper, the same publication where the former Member of Hemiciclo Au Kam San even had a column of Opinão for several years. Ron Lam said that, as he needs to "change his way," the time has come to stop writing, apologizing to readers. It also claims not to regret having “fought with love for the city”, witnessing its growth, which included four years as a deputy and 17 as a worker of social services. In the last article, he returned to the reduction of TNR.
 
"Shuttle Buses" collision caused 30 injuries
Two shuttles belonging to game operators crashed into the Friendship Bridge on Saturday night. From the accident resulted in 30 injuries, aged between 23 and 63 years. According to the investigation of the Public Security Police Corps, one of the buses circulated from macao to Macao, having changed range to avoid a damaged vehicle, which has caused the collision. The drivers of the two shuttles passed the alcohol test. The injured were transported to the hospital.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Nine days of play in Macau exceed a month in Las Vegas</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/nove-dias-de-jogo-em-macau-superam-um-mes-em-las-vegas/</link><description>Macao reinforced the status of the world's largest market in the first half of this year, registering 84 billion more patacas in gross revenues than the Las Vegas strip casinos, which is more than triple. Between January and June, the invoicing in Macao reached almost double the amount accounted for throughout the state of Nevada. In average terms, according to official data analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, nine days in the 30 local casinos yielded more than a month in the 60s game spaces in the celebrated Las Vegas area
 
Sérgio Terra
 
In the first six months of this year, the Macao game market consolidated the world leadership, a statute it first won in 2006 and only gave in 2022 to Las Vegas 'strip' due to the strong impact of the Covid-19 pandemic. Between January and June 2025, the two jurisdictions had different annual variations, with a 4.4% growth in the contrast with a 0.7% break in Las Vegas, according to statistics from the Macao Games and the Nevada State Game Control Committee.
According to the official data analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the gross revenues of the 30 casinos in the territory rose to 118.77 billion patacas, which represents $ 3.34 billion ($ 35.07 billion to the current exchange rates) for about 60 Las Vegas Strip Spaces. It should be noted that the number of casinos considered by the regulatory entity of Nevada suffers monthly fluctuations, and in June it was fixed in 57.
Despite increasing 62.2% compared to 2019, the pre-pound year, the billing in Las Vegas in the first half of this year only reached 29.5% of the amount recorded in Macao, reflecting a difference of about 84 billion between the two largest markets in the world. On the other hand, in the MSAR, revenues are still short of the pre-pound level, corresponding to 79.4% of the first six months of 2019.
Between January and June, the daily averages of revenues ciphed at 656.20 million patacas in Macao and 193.77 million in Las Vegas. Thus, nine days in local casinos yielded more than an entire month in the old "Mecca do Game."
In the period under analysis, Macau also exceeded the total raised by the nearly 440 casinos in the state of Nevada, which closed the semester with gross revenues of $ 7.79 billion (62.99 billion patacas), at a daily average of approximately 348 million patacas. This value reflects a 0.4% homologous rise and equals 53% of Macao level.
Using the daily averages again, it appears that 16 days in Macau were enough to match a month of revenues in Nevada.
In the general calculation of last year, the revenues of Las Vegas 'strip' (about 71.25 billion patacas) and the state of Nevada (126.18 billion patacas) dropped 1% and 0.5% compared to 2023, respectively, and accounted for 31.4% and 55.6% of the Macao market, which grew 23.9% to 226.78 billion.
Already in 2023, although they established a new annual record, the revenues in the iconic Las Vegas zone also did not reach half the value generated by the Casinos of the MSAR, which were still in the early phase of the Postcovid resum. Official statistics show that by 2023, Las Vegas and the state of Nevada registered revenues of 71.97 billion and 125.50 billion patacas, ie 39.3% and 68.6% of 183.06 billion in Macao.
In 2022, the situation was quite distinct, with strong travel restrictions motivating an annual break from 51.4% to 42.20 billion patacas in Macao, a value far below Nevada results (119.67 billion patacas) and Las Vegas 'strip' (66.82 billion). In turn, the 2021 accounts illustrated a difference of 30.1 billion patacas, with Las Vegas casinos reaching 65.3% of the level of the MSAR. In 2020 and 2019, Macao had generated twice and more from the member of the revenues, respectively.
 
Las Vegas faces tourism decline
In response to the latest indicators, both in tourism and in the game, Macau casinos should continue to expand the advantage over Las Vegas during the second half of this year. After July have marked a postpande record in the game, several analysts were already rising the projections to 2025, animated by the growing flow of visitors, which rose 14.9% to 19.22 million between January and June, in annual terms.
In Las Vegas, the perspectives are much less laughing, and do not show signs of improvement during summer. According to data from the convention and visitors authority (LVCVA), the number of tourists fell 11.3% to 3.09 million in June and 7.3% to 19.5 million in the first half. With the city losing 1.5 million visitors since the beginning of 2025, the hotel occupancy rate retreated 6.5 points to 78.7% in June and 2.1 points to 82% in the set of six months.
In the analysis of June data, LVCVA maintained that the decline in tourism reflects “the broader scenario of persistent economic uncertainty” and the weakening of consumer confidence, in a “slower” month in the convention sector, where the participating public dropped 10.7% to 375,000 people. At Harry Reid International Airport, passengers dropped 6.3% in June to 4.7 million and 4.1% to 27.6 million in the first half.
Still, by presenting the financial results of the second quarter, executives of MGM Resorts International and Caesars Entertainment anticipated that Las Vegas will recover in the coming months, with an intense calendar of events, namely conventions, at the end of this fall and in 2026. "I want to take advantage of this opportunity to emphasize that Las Vegas continues to be fundamentally solid," said CEO of MGM, Bill, Bill, Bill, Bill Hornbuckle, highlighting the strong business volumes in the group's ventures.
However, new national immigration and visas policies are also affecting Las Vegas's tourist perspectives. The announced imposition of a $ 250 visa fee on all non -immigrant foreign visitors may discourage international tourism, while reinforcing immigration inspection and doubts around workers protection originate operational challenges and foster work instability in the local hotel sector.
These concerns are not unfair, given the strong weight of tourism in the Las Vegas economy, where travel -related branches of activity ensure more than one fifth of jobs and hotels and casinos absorb more than 13% of work force. Restaurants, transportation services, space spaces and stretch trade establishments now face times of uncertainty, which in some strands have a national dimension.
A report from the World Travel and Tourism Council estimated that the US will be able to lose $ 12.5 billion in spending on international visitors throughout this year. "While other nations extend the welcome rug, the US government puts the 'closed' sign," said Julia Simpson, chairman of the board, in a statement.
The report cited March air reserve data, which signaled breaks between 15% and 20% on expected trips from large tourist markets, including the United Kingdom, Germany and Canada.
Visitors from Canada and Mexico represented more than half of international tourists in Las Vegas in 2024, according to LVCVA. However, the ambition of US President Donald Trump of making Canada in the 51st US state and its decision to impose tariffs on Canada will have removed many travelers from the neighboring country. In addition, the media have reported several cases of refusal and bizarre arrests at US border stations.</description><pubDate>2025-08-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Online rooster struggles thrive in the Philippines, despite the ban and death</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/lutas-de-galos-online-prosperam-nas-filipinas-apesar-da-proibicao-mortes/</link><description>The divers spent more than a month to scour a lake south of Manila in search of the bodies of men linked to the bloody national obsession of the Philippines: the fighting fights. They were murdered by corrupt police, according to a government witness, allegedly for defrauding games at the height of the fever of betting on the struggle of broadcasting in direct, or "e-sabong" during the pandemic.
The disappearances led then-President Rodrigo Duterte to announce the total ban, but three years later, the e-Sabong industry continues to prosper. On a recent Saturday, in Bulacan's suburb, in Manila, the rooster fighters, or "sabunges", made evil jokes about the missing compatriots.
Inside the “Tarian”, a full room where blades are stuck in each bird's leg, Sabunger Marcelo Parang insisted that the murders had nothing to do with the cool world of rooster fights.
"We don't know if (dead men) did something wrong," said the 60 -year -old man. "We are not afraid ... Here, we are peaceful. Here, the struggles are performed fairly," he said about the deadly disputes.
Outside, the multitude in the 800 -seat arena vibrated when another fight ended with the losing rooster thrown without ceremonies for an empty paint bucket.
Rooster boards like Bulacan's were once a second home to Mr. Ray Gibraltar, who grew up in a family of rooster fighting enthusiasts. An uncle was a creator.
When the fighting began to be online during the Covid-19 pandemic, the former director who became a painter began to bet on them as well.
But the easy access, the anonymity of the online world and the large volume of betting sites led to e-sabong addiction, and one year, Mr. Gibraltar won and lost more than 15,000 USD a day.
"I wasn't eating. I just drank coffee and smoked ... I didn't sleep," he said about a three -day session. "In terms of money I lost in e-sabong ... I could have bought a house and a car," he said, adding that "he borrowed money from everyone."
Before joining a rehab clinic, he bet on the last 300 pesos in his electronic wallet.
The story is familiar to Reagan Prafe, founder of the recovering Gamblers of the Philippines, which says few customers appear before they reach the bottom of the well.
"They don't care if they still have money," he said. The first e-sabong addicts began to arrive in 2020. Since then, about 30% of cases have revolved around the struggles transmitted live.
"(In the arenas) It was necessary to go somewhere to raise money. Now ... is connected to an electronic wallet," he explained, adding that other forms of play are being inspired by e-Sabong. "Most sites have reproduced their platforms."
 
Deputy followed fights on voting day
Jay, a graphic artist, still accesses an illegal site each time he receives the salary. The 24 -year -old, who asked to use a pseudonym for fearing the family judgment, showed how to make only 10 pesos in two rainfalls shown on his mobile phone.
Authorities estimate that gamblers like Jay are feeding an industry that generates millions of dollars in revenues weekly. "It's not the money I'm looking for, it's emotion," he explained about an addiction that he says he is trying to control. "It's easier to pursue this (in e-sabong) because it's available on my mobile phone."
While making relatively low bets, Jay was forced to make excuses after losing the money for her younger brother's school supplies.
Since the E-Sabong ban was started, the country's telecommunications committee blocked more than 6,800 e-sabong sites, police brigadeiro-general Bernard Yang told AFP. But the use of VPN makes it almost impossible to identify the true origins of streamings.
When asked about examples of IP devices that led to Rusas, he cited a successful operation in Cebu province in the center of the Philippines-although it had occurred years earlier.
Although he admits that current penalties - with fines up to 1,000 pesos - are poorly determined, Yang insisted that the problem simply "is no longer so serious."
Senator Erwin Tulfo told Congress that E-Sabong remains a threat, pressuring the country's Central Bank to take action against a series of online game sites. Hours later, the monetary authority issued a directive for electronic portfolio companies to remove links to illegal websites within 48 hours.
Deputy Rolando Valeriano, who told AFP that the situation remains “very alarming”, is the author of a bill against rooster struggles and online game that would drastically increase fines and prison penalties. "In all communities, you can see children who know (bet on) e-sabong. That's what worries me," he said.
"This may be a lonely battle, but we will continue to fight." The fight can be really lonely. One day after the new Congress session began, a photograph, verified by AFP, began to circulate in local media. The image was a deputy looking at the smartphone during the vote to the House. I was watching a rooster fight ...</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>