<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>“Life Hope Line” registered a 50% increase in support requests</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/linha-esperanca-de-vida-registou-subida-de-50-nos-pedidos-de-apoio/</link><description>Caritas's “Life Hope line” received more than 15,000 requests for help over 2024, which translates into a 50% increase over the previous year, the institution's secretary general told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau. The number of suicide -related support requests has registered an annual rise from 30% to 178. Paul Pun said that Caritas intends to optimize this year the online counseling segment of the line, so that this service is more professional

Last year, the “Life Hope line” of Caritas de Macao, which is intended to support people with emotional or psychological problems or even vulnerable to suicide, has registered more than 15,000 requests for help. This number reflects a significant increase of 50% compared to 2023, the year the line received "a little over 10,000" calls to request support, said the secretary general of Caritas.
Speaking to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, Paul Pun also said that in 2024 there was an annual increase of almost 30% in the number of requests to help the “Life Hope line” related to suicide, which totaled 178. According to the person responsible for Institution, among these cases, those involving young people or adolescents recorded a higher increase percentage than other age groups, exceeding 30%.
According to Paul Pun, both in 2023 and last year, the users of the line sought maintenance mainly due to psychological, emotional or study problems.
For the secretary general of Caritas, the significant climb of requests for help will also be associated with the reinforcement of the line of the line and the institution itself. In this aspect, he mentioned that Caritas has been able to make free dissemination actions on this emotional support channel at an establishment in the McDonald's chain in the tape.
“It is not known if it was the pandemic that led more people in Macao to ask for help in terms of mental health. But in fact, we started to see relatively many situations with young people or adolescents wanting to end life. All parties need to attribute attention and importance to this issue, ”said Paul Pun.
On the other hand, it revealed that last year, Caritas received “very few” requests for help in the line segment in foreign language (English). “They (citizens of foreign nationality) rarely called us. Usually, they prefer to move to our social equipment, the Welanser Center, to receive support, ”he said.
Although the “Life Hope Line” has suffered a notorious addition of calls, the secretary general of Caritas understands that the number of users in the last year was not high for a service that, on the other hand, continues to have a number Reduced from personnel. Still, Paul Pun stressed that this year the line will remain open for 24 hours, and that to answer the calls, "there must be, at least one worker who knows how to speak English every day." In fact, he said, the service has already had foreign nationality volunteers.
Paul Pun expressed the desire to widen the service, namely in terms of foreign languages, but admitted that it would be necessary to gather many resources. "In the long run, to expand the coverage of the service, it would make sense that the line would also provide services in the languages ​​Nepalesa, Filipina and Indonesia," he said.
However, there are still no conditions for Caritas to expand this segment of the line, as the institution has to channel resources to other services. In this sense, this year, the institution intends, above all, to maintain the current conditions of the “Life Hope line” and optimize the online counseling segment, to raise the professionalism of this service.
“On the computer, staff cannot immediately analyze whether help applicants are in crisis. For example, if you come to say on social networks that you want to die, the team cannot send personal soon to intervene. We need to observe and analyze, so we will reinforce the training, ”said Paul Pun.
Regarding mental health, the secretary general of Caritas believes that “there is room” for the local population, especially young people and adolescents, to improve the ability to support stress. “All residents should give greater importance to mental health, rest, sleep and do more exercise. It cannot be considered that this is only a responsibility of government or society, as the population itself must do something. In turn, it is obvious that if the government increases the piped resources for mental health, it will also be beneficial to people's general health, ”said Paul Pun.
Authorities have been appealing to citizens so that, in case of need, they call the “Life Hope of Caritas” line (2852 5222), which also has a foreign language segment (2852 5777).</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Secretary promises to respond to "three great" concerns</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/secretaria-promete-responder-tres-grandes-preocupacoes/</link><description>Low birth rate, population aging and mental and physical health were the three major areas in which associations focused during meetings with the secretary for social affairs and culture. LAM promises that in the elaboration of the lag will take into account the opinions presented and ensures that “integrated and coordination measures will be implemented to resolve the most pressing issues”
 
After meeting with some associations, as part of the elaboration of the Government Action Lines (LAG), the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture identified “three major questions” that are concerning society in general: the low birth rate , population aging and physical and mental health. Lam promises answers to try to solve these problems.
In particular, the secretary stated, according to an official statement, that “integrated and coordination measures of various entities will be implemented to resolve the most pressing issues that concern the community, such as low birth rates, aging and physical health and mental". The ruler also stressed that the executive attributes “great importance” to the well-being of the population, namely regarding the work of caring for the elderly and children, as well as regarding the development of young people.
"The government and the community will work together to form a synergy, and the Social Security Fund and the Institute of Social Action will study relevant policies to ensure the safeguarding of the population's well-being," Lam said.
To respond to the impact of the low birth rate, the associations suggested reinforcing education on the concepts of fertility and families ideal to have children, as well as the increase in subsidies for delivery and related services. In the context of aging, they proposed to increase the pension for the elderly and disability, the availability of more facilities and services for the elderly and the improvement of the environment without barriers.
On the other hand, when it comes to physical and mental health, associative leaders said they expect to promote “more comprehensive attention to the mental health of various groups”, which improves the coverage and accessibility of measures and services, and Which reinforces the formation of psychiatry and psychological counseling personnel, can be read in the press release.
The associations listened also expressed attention to the development of the medical system, Big Health, cultural and sports industries, as well as investment in educational resources, studies and use of young people, the transfer of the results of scientific research from higher education and the introduction of qualified frames. The construction of “a base”, the preservation of cultural heritage and the development of the six historical zones were also addressed, along with zone A planning, national games and the preparation of the athlete team.
The LAM pointed out that in the pharmaceutical and health domain, “the government will implement the XI Jinping Directive”, ensuring that health services cover residents of all levels and promoting the development of the Big Health industry.
And with the aim of creating “a place of aggregation of international qualified frames,” he said that the government will coordinate and promote “the integrated development of education, science and technology and qualified staff”, promising that it will “cultivate and attract vigorously ”the necessary talents in various domains. In the cultural field, “we will continue to do a good job in implementing 'a base', reinforcing the promotion of the 'Business Card' of 'East Asia Cultural City' and making Macau an important door for exchange and mutual understanding between the Sino-West Civilizations. ”
According to the secretary, the team of her guardianship "is currently conducting balance and serious studies to plan this year's LAG, and will continue to collect and hear opinions from various sectors." During the sessions already held, representatives of various associations “demonstrated a genuine interest in sharing their opinions and suggestions,” noted the LAM, indicating that more than 250 opinions were collected. Expressing “gratitude” to the community for “continuous concern and support”, reaffirmed the commitment to carefully consider the opinions presented in the elaboration of lag.
 
LAM ensures Xia Baolong study and implementation of the XI speech
The Director of the Hong Kong and Macao Cabinet of the Council of State, Xia Baolong, received in Beijing the secretary for social affairs and culture. LAM guaranteed Xia Baolong, also director of the Hong Kong and Macau Work Office of the CCP Central Committee, which the area of ​​social affairs and culture “has studied and implemented the spirit of Xi Jinping's important discourse, focusing on Near the mission entrusted to Macau by the president, ”also defending the executive's chief executive's philosophy of governance. In addition, he stressed that his guardianship has insisted on “maintaining the population as a main focus on the preparation of the government lines and the main tasks of the next phase”. In Beijing, the secretary and his delegation also visited the Pekin Union Medical College Hospital, the National Health Commission, the National Cultural Heritage Administration, among other places.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Retail, Hospitality and Game boiled jobs</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/retalho-hotelaria-jogo-impulsionaram-emprego/</link><description>Macao ended 2024 with an unemployment rate of 1.8%, a percentage that represents an annual decrease of 0.9 points and almost equals the level of 2019. Employment improvements were driven by retail, hotel and playing trade sectors sectors sectors sectors sectors
 
Sérgio Terra
 
The global unemployment rate at MSAR set up at 1.8% in 2024, reflecting an annual decrease of 0.9 points and the lower percentage after 1.7% recorded in 2019, the pre-pound year, according to data published by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). The unemployment rate of the residents retreated a percentage point to 2.4%, compared to 2023.
The first data related to the general calculation of 2024 also indicate that the medians of the monthly income of the employed population were 18,000 and 20,500 patacas, in general terms and among the residents, respectively. In both cases, they illustrate an annual increase of 500 patacas.
According to DSEC, the global unemployment rate (1.7%) and the resident's unemployment rate (2.3%) did not change in the fourth quarter of 2024 compared to the previous three months. On the other hand, the global sub -unemployment rate rose 0.4 points to 1.5%.
Between October and December, the total number of employees (378,300) and that of residents employed (286,000) descended 1,000 and 1,700 people, respectively, in quarterly terms. However, the employed population grew 1.9% (plus 7,200 people) compared to the last quarter of 2023.
Comparative analysis with the fourth quarter of 2023 shows that employment growth was essentially promoted by retail, hotel and game sectors, which together added 13,600 jobs. Within one year, employee workers and other betting games (about 71,600), thick and retail trade (41,200) and hotels and similar (30,400) increased 6.2%, 17.4% and 13.2%, respectively, compensating for 10% breaks in the construction business (25,100 employees) and 1.4% in similar restaurants and establishments (21,600).
In the fourth quarter of last year, cultural and recreational activities, lottery and other services encompassed 22.1% of the population employed, followed by hotels, restaurants and similar establishments (13.7%), thick trade and retail ( 10.9%), real estate activities and services provided to companies (8.9%), Public Administration and Social Security (8.4%), domestic work (7.3%), construction (6.6%) and education (6.1%).
On the other hand, the number of unemployed (6,700) descended 22.1% or 1,900 people, compared to the last three months of 2023. Among the unemployed people looking for a new job, most previously worked in the sectors of the game and commerce flap. Already the individuals looking for the first job corresponded to 13.9% of the unemployed population, less 0.7 points than in the preceding period (September to November 2024).
In the quarter under analysis, the underemployed population was part of 5,700 people, 2.2% less than in the previous period and 9.6% more in annual terms.
Employment inquiry excluded residents and non -residents who work on the MSAR but live abroad, whose average number was estimated at about 104,700 in the period under analysis. Including this group, the total labor gathered 489,600 people.
 
Dsal supported 14,700 on access to employment
In turn, the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) stressed that it helped hiring 14,699 people in 2024, including 648 in the construction sector. The total number of people who got employment through DSAL increased by 6.2% (plus 864 individuals) compared to 2023.
Over the past year, Dsal has organized 135 pairing sessions for specific sectors, 42 for leisure companies and three large wingspan fairs. Until mid -December, 2,291 people got a job through the pairing system, the body indicated, stressing that there are currently more than 6,000 work vacancies, covering more than 140 professions.
At the same time, in 2024, DSAL launched 27 “specific employment + training plans” taught in the “first hiring and then training” modality in order to help residents integrate into tourism and leisure sectors. In addition, he organized more than 530 vocational training courses with the participation of more than 10,700 graduates, of which more than 3,200 received certificates of professional techniques recognized in Macao, in the interior of China and at international level.</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Advance commercial licensing review work</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/avancam-trabalhos-de-revisao-de-licenciamento-comercial/</link><description>To build “an efficient and convenient business environment” in the territory, an interdepartal group was created that will review the various types of licensing regimes related to commercial exploitation. Associations have already begun to be heard and, according to DSAJ, the priority will be for the regimes of economic activities “of the highest and strong and strong social requirement”
 
The working group for the revision of legal diplomas related to commercial exploitation, created by the government to “increasingly optimize the business environment”, will review the various types of licensing regimes related to commercial exploitation, as well as discuss improvement measures to level of legal diplomas and administrative procedures. According to the Directorate of Justice Affairs Services (DSAJ), two colloquies have already been performed, with a view to obtaining opinions and suggestions from the sector.
The proposals presented by the participants have, among others, on the simplification of licensing conditions and the procedures for appreciation and approval, the stimulation and support for the flexibility and innovation of the exploration models, and the proper relief of the requirements related to the facilities and equipment of Establishments depending on the different architectural environments, says a statement from DSAJ.
Other issues that were on the table included promoting the renewal of facilities and equipment in older establishments, the improvement of public space occupation rules, the reinforcement of food security control, the simplification of procedures and requirements for entry. and output of goods in Macao, and the improvement of the public hiring regime.
According to the press release, the interdepartal group indicated that the opinions “will be studied and analyzed hard, to serve as a reference in a future optimization of the procedures for appreciation and administrative approval and launch of improvement measures”. According to it was said, “priority will be given to the monitoring of the work intended to improve the licensing regimes of economic activities of greater coverage and strong social requirement, as well as legal diplomas or procedures relating to the simplification of the process of appreciation and approval and the widening of scope of the 'One-Stop' services.
The objective is to “create favorable conditions for the construction of an efficient and convenient business environment” in the territory.</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>2025 According to “Feng Shui”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/2025-segundo-feng-shui-mickey-hung/</link><description>Mickey Hung*

鼠 - Mouse
Two good stars radiate brilliantly, illuminating one with a mesmerizing attractiveness. Thus, wealth and luck naturally follow in abundance. Perseverance is essential at this time, as challenges may arise unexpectedly. Remain strong and the desires of your heart will be fulfilled. Careers will flourish and the flow of wealth will be continuous, providing wide growth opportunities. Although some bad stars may be present, the energy of a luck star can effectively contradict these negative effects. Be prepared for minor loss of wealth; This is part of the trip. Choose your friends carefully and avoid the role of guarantor to protect your finances. This will naturally help prevent unforeseen problems, unexpected losses and unnecessary legal proceedings.
 
牛 - Buffalo
The combination of stars has an unsatisfactory result, throwing a shadow over the year that begins. Beware of the effects of the star of the five ghosts, which can cause confusion and misfortune. Be careful with non -reliable people who may be engendering evil plans that may cause significant financial losses. Your health may also be vulnerable this year, becoming crucial to focus more on self-care and well-being. Practice good actions to foster hope and positivity around you. It is advisable to participate in ceremonies designed to ask for luck, which can help open doors to fortune. Always remember that the more you will, the more you will receive in return. Stay away from loving triangles and never expose or reveal your attributes to protect your interests. This year has a period of uncertainty, and it is important to recognize that satisfaction can sometimes lead to disappointment. Follow your firm beliefs and principles to cultivate a sense of peace of mind in the midst of chaos.
 
虎 - Tiger
The great Yin stars assume power, establishing a dynamic change in energy. Yin energy is strong, while Yang energy seems weak, leading to different fortunes to men and women. Women will reap more benefits this year, while men will be able to be so lucky. A good star aligns with his way, illuminating opportunities and leading him to happiness. An atmosphere of joy prevails, and beauty and wealth come together harmoniously. Vibrant energy enters your home, promoting a welcoming environment. However, men should remain vigilant about possible women's betrayals, as loving cases and temptations can become sources of headaches. Be careful with friends you keep and avoid intruding on others' affairs to maintain your peace of mind.
 
兔 - Rabbit
Bad and notorious stars abound this year, which is not a good sign. When we do not see immediate concerns, it is essential to seek hidden problems that may be lurking under the surface. A good travel star illuminates your way, indicating that beneficial effects can be found far. Therefore, it aims at opportunities far from wealth generation as they can generate positive results. Wealth may be spread far away, so literally, so keep open to new possibilities. Remember not to attend funerals and avoid watching funeral processions to protect your energy. Keep distance from sick people to maintain your health. It is best to perform ceremonies at the beginning of the year that transform the negative effects of bad stars into luck and fortune. Make more good actions to reverse bad energies in good energies, creating a more harmonious environment for you.
 
龍 - Dragon
The great star Yang shines intensely, announcing a promising future. Men are very lucky this year, while women enjoy a moderate fortune. Several signs point to celebrations, and one of them has a beauty glow that attracts positive energy. Wealth and happiness will warm their home, creating a welcoming space for the loved ones. Hundreds of lucky events are likely to happen in your home, as unlimited blessings surround it. Be aware that a bad star lurks nearby, indicating the risk of losses along with the gains obtained. Be cautious about legal proceedings related to personal issues and try to avoid discussions between partners. Give priority to increased security to protect yourself against theft and ensure a quiet life environment.
 
蛇 - Serpent
There is an overwhelming presence of uncontrolled energy this year. Happiness seems illusory, replaced by concerns and concerns. Loss of wealth, serious diseases and even bloodshed can cause problems at this time. Therefore, get involved in more good works this year; This proactive approach will help eliminate potential disasters. Strive for being more understanding when dealing with people and situations, as empathy can make all the difference. Be patient and bring up the practicality that exists in itself, as these qualities will make all problems seem controllable. When happy occasions arise in the family, such as weddings, inaugurations of houses, pregnancies or births, problems dissipate themselves. As the old saying goes, a celebration will teach three disasters in life. Set up an altar for the great star before January 15 to meditate on peace and security. A harmful star may appear, indicating conflicts or unexpected problems that may arise. Also, another bad star shines, bringing concerns about disease. Be very careful and, in the end, everything will be fine and at peace. As a consolation, a good star offers shelter and protection, allowing him to venture safely.
 
馬 - Horse
A good star shines intensely, suggesting that hundreds of good things will start at home. Around your home there are blessings waiting to be performed. Wealth and happiness will come home, making this a year to celebrate. However, a bad star plays his shadow, potentially affecting his health negatively. Be careful, as illicit loving cases can disturb the harmony of your home environment. Be careful with theft and dangers that can lead to bloodshed. While keeping careful and vigilant, peace and stability can be maintained. This year is not suitable for visiting sick people. Avoid participating in everything related to funeral or funerals and does not intrude on the subjects of others. Exercise defensive strategies in all aspects of life; Being aggressive can easily lead to unwanted problems.
 
羊 - Goat
The malevolent stars abound this year, signaling caution. Beware of the betrayal and the crimes of the traitors. Thefts and lawsuits are very likely problems to occur, so be alert. Be careful with the potential loss of wealth and the risk of physical damage. Get ready for the sadness that can come from the death of a loved one. Approach prayers and requests with careful consideration and sincerity. Stay vigilant against threats such as abduction or blackmail and avoid being involved in hazardous tasks that may cause accidents. Although it is possible to get riches from afar, they will not come easily. Avoid night activities that can expose it to risks. Seek spiritual guidance at the beginning of the year to counteract bad elements and increase good luck.
 
猴 - Monkey
Good honorable stars abound this year, presenting a positive omen for the coming months. Everything will progress gently, and wealth and luck will be at your door, ready to hug. Fame and fortune are within their reach. However, the only concern lies in the presence of a distorted negative star, indicating that traitors may be at the close near, wanting to approach themselves. To maintain your good luck, avoid all discussions and Quezilias. By doing so, good luck will fill your home. All blessings will be fully performed, leading to a prosperous environment. It is better to make offerings and prayers every day 1 and 15 of each month, expressing gratitude for all the blessings received. This continuous recognition will guarantee a constant flow of good luck. As long as you keep your feet on the ground and don't let others deceive you, you can avoid unnecessary worries and confusion.
 
雞 - Rooster
A white tiger star dominates the year, creating a mixture of good and bad luck. Even though everything seems calm and peaceful, be aware of unsuccessful problems or betrayals from those who can lead to loss of wealth. Be aware of theft and bloodshed as they may pose serious risks. It is likely to undergo some small surgery this year, so be careful to avoid physical injuries. Be careful not to accumulate wealth without investing in your health; Balance is essential. Avoid being a guarantor, as it can originate complications. Be cautious when you travel, especially when you make new friends. It is important to be generous, but not at the expense of your own well-being. Participating in happy celebrations and occasions can help break the unhappy chain of events.
 
狗 - Dog
Lucky stars abound and everything becomes possible. Projects will flow smoothly and wealth will flow as if the universe is aligning itself to its advantage. A dragon star shines intensely, turning all bad things into good. Even with the presence of bad stars affecting the fortune of the family, the power of the good stars tends to dominate. If anyone can do good actions sincerely, they can benefit from the end of misfortunes and the arrival of good fortunes. Expect to be attractive in every respect, for wealth and luck will naturally follow.
 
豬 - Pig
Although good exists, bad things also stalle, creating a challenging atmosphere. A negative energy permeates the year, making each task look like a challenge. Study and carefully examine each task before proceeding to avoid traps. There is a higher risk of bankruptcy and loss of wealth, so remain vigilant. Be careful not to fall into traps prepared by unscrupulous people who can explore your trust. Lawsuits, bankruptcy and rumors will probably raise numerous concerns. A negative star can cause significant financial losses, potentially leading to poverty or total failure. Practice good actions at the beginning of the year.
 
*Famous Master Master of Macau</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Inflation retreated to 0.74% in 2024</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/inflacao-recuou-para-074-em-2024/</link><description>Between 2023 and 2024, the inflation rate descended 0.2 points, remaining below 1%. The main price rates, involving housing and fuels and food products and non -alcoholic beverages, registered increases of 0.45% and 1.10%, respectively
 
The inflation rate in Macao reached 0.74% in 2024, reflecting a downward of 0.2 percentage points compared to 0.94% estimated to 2023, the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) announced. In annual terms, the overall consumer pricing rate (IPC) rose 0.7% in category A, which includes about 50% of family aggregates with monthly average expenses between 11 thousand and 35,999 patacas, and increased 0.79% In echelon B, which covers 30% of families with average spending between 36 thousand and 71,999 patacas.
The General IPC covers all household aggregates, and expenses with higher weights in the calculation of inflation are housing and fuels sections, food products and non -alcoholic beverages and transportation, with weights of 34.47, 29.47 and 8.33, respectively. According to DSEC, the Housing and Fuel Price Index increased by 0.45%, in annual terms, driven by the rise of 6.49% in liquefied oil gas, whose weighting is 0.72.
In turn, the index of food products and non-alcoholic beverages grew 1.1%, highlighting the climbs on non-alcoholic beverages (+2.67%), meals purchased away from home and “Take-Away” (+ 2.31%), bread and cookies (+1.64%), pastries and cakes (+1.4%), fruit (+1.33%) and vegetables (+0.86%) increased. In this section, the highest weighting is that of meals acquired away from home and “Take-Away” (18,21). In contrast to the overall growth in this category, descents were recorded in the rates of fresh/refrigerated/frozen pork (-13.54%) and oils and fat (-3.45%).
The Transport Section Index, on the other hand, descended 3.26% between 2023 and 2024, mainly due to a break of 23.55% in the prices of passenger air transport services, whose consideration is 0.56. The price index of domestic equipment and services (with a weight of 3.43) also lowered 0.29%.
In the remaining sections of goods and services, there were increases in the education indices (+3.53%), various products and services (+2.57%), health (2.35%), leisure, recreation, sports and Culture (+2.15%), clothing and footwear (+1.7%) and alcoholic beverages and tobacco (+0.4%). In contrast, the price and communication section price index fell 0.21% compared to 2023.
Considering only December, the General IPC grew 0.23% compared to the same period of 2023 and 0.2% compared to November 2024. In the fourth quarter of 2024 the average General IPC increased 0.28%, compared to homologous period of the previous year.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Residence evaluation for the elderly relaunched in mid -February</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/avaliacao-da-residencia-para-idosos-relancada-em-meados-de-fevereiro/</link><description>The Institute of Social Action (IAS) will proceed, in the middle of next month, to the evaluation work of the next round of the government's residence for the elderly.
In order to allow more eligible elderly people to move to housing as soon as possible, IAS will perform the requirements evaluation phase, punctuation and ordering of candidates and verification of self-care capacity to live at home, for applications presented until February 14 this year. Upon completion of the work, the selected elderly will be distributed in groups and will choose the preferred residential apartment, the conclusion of the Use Agreement and the entry into the dwellings.
The elderly wishing to change may be presented by February 14 this year (the presentation in person must be held within the hours of office hours and the online presentation will be until 23:59 of that date).
The residence has a total of 1,815 apartments, and the number of individuals who chose the fractions during the first phase of application (between November 6 and December 31, 2023) was about 900. 400 applications presented between January 1, 2024 and January 23, 2025.
Holders of the Macao Single Account may present the candidacy through access to the “Electronic Candidacy System to the Government's Residence for the Elderly” to make the online registration. In addition, they also have the possibility of moving to 15 certain locations, including IAS headquarters, social action centers, the government's residence exposure zone for the elderly, or at 62 social equipment to obtain assistance in the presentation of an online application. . The application submitted after February 14 will be evaluated in the next candidacy round.
IAS remembered the eligible candidates who presented the candidacy between November 6 and December 31, 2023 and who chose to stay on the waiting list, as well as those who presented it until or after 1 January 2024, which, in the event of There are situations of data change, such as the situation of the usual residence, current cohabitation, period of years of acquisition of the status of resident of MSAR, duration of the residence in MSAR, among others, can update the data, online or in person, until February 14.</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Secretary wants to facilitate passage to hengqin</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/secretario-quer-facilitar-passagem-para-hengqin/</link><description>Wong Sio Chak stated, in a meeting with the Overseas Chinese Association, that one of the priorities for this year is to facilitate the border passage at the post of Hengqin
 
One of the priorities of the security guardian action for this year “is further promoting the facilities of passage at Hengqin's border post,” said Secretary Wong Sio Chak, quoted in a statement. The ruler was met with the General Association of the Overseas Chinese of Macao, in the context of the preparation of the government lines.
Continue to negotiate with the services of the interior of China, “taking advantage of all means to optimize the border passage experience of residents of Macao and tourists,” is one of the gog's goals of Wong Sio Chak, who also said he intends to commit to committing Improve the efficiency and abilities of border posts, including studying the opening of more automatic passages using the use of iris.
At the meeting, the president of the Association's General Assembly, Lao NGA Wong, said the ultra-ultra-alive Chinese community “feels profoundly that any social agitation can severely affect the development of the economy, so to safeguard the social stability of Macao plays a role. crucial in promoting the development of the appropriate diversification of Macau's economy. ”
According to a statement, the representatives who participated in the meeting presented opinions on the defense of state security, education on national security, the work of transionous rescue between Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau, the contingency plans under the protection Civil, the facilities of border passage, prevention and anti-bubble, tourism security, cooperation between the police and the population, among other topics. What suggestions presented in concrete is not said in the press release.
 
Inspected security work
On the other hand, and within the Chinese New Year, the protection of safety, along with organisms from other areas, surveys safety work to implement at events during the Spring Party. The idea is to “ensure public order of the region” during the festive period and “protect the safety of life and goods from residents and tourists”.
This is because, in this period of celebration, “Macao will be the scene of a series of festive activities, providing for a great affluence of public and at the same time the existence of potential safety risks”, explained the Unit Police Services (SPU).
The leaders and bosses traveled the Zones of the A-Má Temple, the route of the float parade and the Lunar New Year Fair of Tap Seac Square, in order to find out the situation on the ground, the multitude control plan , the measures of management of road traffic, the mobilization of the police device, the emergency evacuation plan, among other works.
“It is intended through these surveys to instruct the services and competent entities to be prepared and define well the plans and strategies in order to raise the ability to respond to emergencies in the face of possible sudden incidents, ensuring the realization of commemorative and securely commemorative activities. ”The SPU stress.
The inspection work, besides having counted on the participation of managers and heads of the security area, also included the participation of the Directorate of Tourism Services, the Cultural Institute, the Institute for Municipal Affairs and the Directorate of Services for the Affairs of traffic.
In a statement, the SPU states that during this festive week, “security forces and services will remain firm at their posts, in comply adjusting police strategies and specific combat operations in accordance with the local security situation, to safeguard the social order and the safety of the population. ”</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>STD reinforced promotion in Madrid</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dst-reforcou-promocao-em-madrid/</link><description>With eyes on European markets, Macao tourism services have expanded their presence at Fitur, an important tourism event that has taken place in recent days in Madrid
 
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) reinforced this year the actions of promotion of Macau at Fitur, one of the largest international tourism fairs, which took place from January 22 to 26 in Madrid. During the event, he held several initiatives directed to European operators and consumers, in the context of efforts to attract international visitors to the MSAR.
After returning to Fitur last year with a promotion event organized in partnership with the Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies (APAVT), STD cooperated again with APAVT, this time expanding the presence with a stand under the theme “ Feeling Macao ”. Throughout the five days of the fair, the stand presented the offers of Macao “Tourism +”, including a tour through virtual reality around the city, and served as a platform for contacts with tour operators.
The stand also welcomed “Macao's tourist product to 50 travel agents, which is part of the activities of a joint marketing campaign with HBX Group directed to tour operators from various European countries. In the Spanish capital, STD also supported a "afterparty" organized by the HBX Group for its strategic partners, which gathered 850 guests. According to the body, the joint campaign for Europe in 2025 will spread Macao promotion content in six countries (Portugal, Spain, France, Italy, Germany and the United Kingdom) through "Hotelbeds" and "Bedsonline", reserve online platforms of services and products for tourist operators of HBX Group.
The start of promotional activities at Fitur included a “Macao Tourism Exchange” at the STD stand, with the presence of Tourism of Portugal, APAVT, European Confederation of Travel Agency Associations and Tour Operators (ECTAA), Spanish Confederation Travel agencies and travel agencies, among others, in a total of more than 40 participants. In speaking at the event, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, director of STD, stressed the relevance of joining efforts with key partners such as APAVT and its ectaa similar, as well as major online tourism platforms, to “show the new Macao Development Dynamics as the World Center for Tourism and Leisure ”and increase the tourist flows of Europe.
On the same occasion, Lídia Monteiro, a member of the Portuguese Tourism Board of Directors, thanked Apavt for helping to “approach Macao”, and confirmed her intention to organize a “roadshow” that will end at the APAVT Congress in Macau. In turn, APAVT President Pedro Costa Ferreira and Ectaa Secretary-General Eric Drésin argued that initiatives to be in partnership with STD in 2025, such as the APAVT Congress and the Ectaa Summit on the MG. , they will contribute to "attracting much attention to the destination among their member travel agents."
This year, online marketing initiatives and special hotel offers will also be developed through the Travelport reserve platform and online travel agency “Edreams Odigeo”, among other channels, to increase travel sales and encourage more stays. Longs in Macao.
After Fitur, STD will return in March, for the first time since the pandemic, to ITB Berlin, the largest tourism fair in the world. In April, he hopes to receive a delegation of tourist operators and European press to participate in the 13th International Tourism Expo (Industry) of Macao, among other activities to continue to explore the European market.</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Game lacks more confidence from Chinese consumers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jogo-carece-de-mais-confianca-dos-consumidores-chineses/</link><description>Macao casinos' revenues can grow up to 7% in the lunar year of the serpent, depending on the recovery of the Chinese real estate and trust, but they will be away from the pre-pound peak, analysts told Lusa.
"The biggest positive factor for Macao would be if the Chinese economy grew and consumer confidence levels improve," said Vitaly Umnsky, analyst at the Seaport Research Partners consultancy company.
More than 70% of people who visited the MSAR in 2024 came from mainland China, whose economic growth reached the 5% target by Beijing. But Nicholas Chen, Creditsights analyst, said the company of the Financial Notation Agency group Fitch expects a slowdown to 4.7% this year, in part due to poor private consumption.
The consumer confidence index in China fell in September to the lowest level of the last 34 years, stressed Jeffrey Kiang, analyst at Consultant CLSA.
That is, "if the prospects for Chinese consumers are not good, they will be able to tighten their belt, reduce travel and consumption," including Macao, Nicholas Chen explained.
Beijing has launched a series of stimulus measures, including the reduction of interest rates and the mandatory reserves of banks and the anticipation of thousands of millions of their budget in 2025 to finance construction projects. He also widened a consumer goods exchange system and increased the salaries of millions of civil servants to revive internal demand.
"The [Chinese] government has said it will launch more measures to stimulate the economy," said Vitaly Umansky, who expects mainly a recovery of the middle class confidence: "I think it will happen, it's just a matter of time."
Creditsights expects Chinese consumer confidence to rise in the second half of 2025, along with real estate price stabilization, which have been falling for 19 consecutive months. The issue concerns a lot of Beijing, due to the implications for social stability, since housing is one of the main investment vehicles of families and the real estate sector - adding indirect factors - represents about 30% of the Chinese economy.
"There will certainly be some side effect, because part of the measures that are adopted to boost domestic consumption may flow to the Macao game sector," said Nicholas Chen.
The analyst believes that China will still widen the list of cities whose residents can ask for 'individual visas' to visit Hong Kong and Macau, a method used by 35.2% of tourists who passed by Macao in 2024.
Vitaly Umansky has no opinion and recalls that since January 1, Zhuhai residents can visit Macau once a week and stay up to seven days.
On the other hand, analysts agree that casino revenues will be next year away from the maximum historical 303 billion patacas recorded in 2018.
"One thing is clear: the government aims to moderately growth in revenue in the future," said Jeffrey Kiang, recalling authorities predict gaming revenues of 240 billion patacas in 2025, which would be a 5.8%increase.
“When the Macao government publishes a forecast, it is usually very conservative and is based on a prior discussion with the central government's connecting cabinet in the city, said Unsky.
The analyst does not believe that Beijing has some measure to control the resuming of casinos, similar to the campaign that began with the detention of the leader of the largest company raising VIP in the world, in November 2021. “Much of the reprehensible behavior in Macau disappeared with the 'junkets'. As long as things like that do not happen again, I don't expect any short -term campaign, ”he said.
 
Casinos revenues can rise 8% in 2025
The game's revenues could rise 8% to 245 billion patacas by 2025, in annual terms, reaching about 84% of the level recorded in 2019, predicted Creditsights, Fitch's agency investigation unit. "This projection presupposes that visitors in 2025 will improve to about 94% of 2019 levels, and ragous game revenues by visitor will record a modest increase of 2% in homologous terms to 6,606 patacas," says the analysts report Nicholas Chen, David Bussey and Zerlina Zeng. Creditsights also believes that hotel occupation will also grow "with the completion of the renewals of casinos and bedroom conversions." However, it points out that the game faces “potential challenges”, especially due to the “slowing down the growth” of the Chinese economy and the “slow internal consumption”.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Video game about Chinese tradition inspires symphony at the MGM Theater</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/videojogo-sobre-tradicao-chinesa-inspira-sinfonia-teatro-mgm/</link><description>In Lunar New Year celebration, MGM will present the concert “Black Myth: Wukong”, a bold cross between music and video games that combines symphonic and traditional Chinese passages. In addition, game short films will be reproduced during the show to allow the audience to penetrate the majestic and fantastic world of the oriental mythology of “Journey to the West”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
A concert of symphonic music will take place in the first two days of February at the MGM Theater, presenting a new art form to promote traditional Chinese culture. “Black Myth: Wukong” is a Chinese video game that incorporates a deep traditional cultural heritage and shows the richness of the Chinese tradition.
The concert will provide the opportunity to know the prosperous video game industry of China and the depth of its culture, “starting a new chapter of cultural exchange and heritage,” says a note from MGM.
Integrated in Chinese New Year celebrations, the “Show” will consist of a video game music selection, resulting in the bold cross between music and game that combines symphonic music and traditional Chinese music “to create an unprecedented epic adventure”. In addition, the game's animated short films will be reproduced during the show to allow the audience to "dive into the majestic and fantastic world of the eastern mythology of" Journey to the West. "
After performances in various cities in the interior of China, including Taiyuan, Nanquim, Harbin and Wuhan, the choice of the MGM theater for this show is closely linked to the unique strengths of this place, “which offers the public a new visualization experience”,, It stresses the organization of the concert.
The MGM Theater, in Cotai, “The First Dynamic Cinema of Asia”, is equipped with a 4K 900 -square -meter 4K LED screen - the size of three tennis fields - and is a pioneer in offering 28 million pixels visualization pleasure . AAA Game Scenes will be shown to the giant screen.
Cinema is using L-SISA, an engaging sound technology that goes beyond the difficulties of traditional amplification methods to create a multidimensional hearing experience. This cutting -edge technology accurately reproduces all the sound details of the game, “allowing viewers to hear from the wind while Wukong rides in the clouds and the intense shock of weapons in battle with unique clarity,” says MGM.
Last December, when the Macau 2049 residence show, directed by Zhang Yimou, premiered at the MGM Theater, the production presented in an innovative way eight forms of intangible cultural heritage. Sun Wukong's timeless history is presented vividly through the art of telling Shanbei stories.
“Try the moments of breathing the breath when music meets the game, the east with the West and the tradition with modernity,” says MGM. Three new songs will be debuted in this show and each member of the audience will receive a set of exquisite thematic articles, including a T-shirt, a new year canvas bag and desticics.
The show will take place on February 1st and 2nd, with two daily sessions, at 15:00 and 19:30. Ticket prices range from 180 to 880 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cycling Tour celebrates the year of the serpent</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/passeio-de-cicloturismo-celebra-ano-da-serpente/</link><description>A series of sports and recreational activities will take place in the early days of the Lunar New Year. Highlight for a cycling tour of 20 km to 300 people. The celebrations will also feature a motorcycle and cars parade
 
The Institute of Sport (ID) will carry out some recreational and sports activities integrated in the Festivities of the Lunar New Year, including a cycling tour, which will take place on January 31, Friday.
300 registrations are accepted, and the vacancies are filled in order of arrival. On the day of activity, participants must focus at 08:30, in the open space near the Três Basketball field of the Olympic Sports Center. The match is scheduled for 09:00, being a route of approximately 20 km, through different zones of mud and coloane.
Participants must use their own bicycles, and the use of helmet is mandatory. Entries, intended for children under 70 years of age, with those born from 2013 to need follow -up by an adult, are open to this day.
Other events will be integrated into the “recreational and sports activities of the 2025 Lunar New Year”. The Sports Festival is scheduled for January 31, from 14:00 to 17:00, at IAO Hon Market Square. There will be Dragon and Lion Dance presentation, several exhibitions of people with disabilities, besides beyond Game tents are available.
The “Lunar New Year's“ Classic Cars Parade ”will take place on February 9, at 14:00, departing from the Grand Prix building. Harley Davidson brand motorcycles and classic cars will go through Macao and Cotai zones, lasting two hours of course. The parade will end at the Largo of the Science Center, where the public will be able to enjoy motorcycles and cars exposed at the site after the parade.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Far from Casinos, looking for prosperity in the Lunar New Year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/longe-dos-casinos-a-procura-da-prosperidade-ano-novo-lunar-catarina-domingues-jing-wu-vitor-quinta/</link><description>Lunar New Year celebrations in Macao, January 23, 2025. It is the main party of Chinese families, equivalent to Christmas in Western countries, and for many workers the breaks and holidays granted on this court constitute the only vacation of the year. (Accompanies text on January 26, 2025). Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro/Lusa



Catarina Domingues, Jing Wu and Vitor Quintã*
Away from the brilliance of the Macao Casinos, the manager of a Cantonense seafood, a 'Feng Shui' master and a young couple question the economic moment for the new year of the serpent.
At the entrance of Tong Vu, large lobsters drag themselves inside aquariums. This year are being sold to the purchase price, because the times so require it.
Tong Keng Seoi, the manager, has the Australian lobster at 498 Patacas, instead of the usual 900. Option that brings more business volume to the old Macao seafood during Lunar New Year, with full house and “a 30% increase orders compared to the previous year ”.
By this time, a banquet for 12 people, with lobster, ears and sea cucumbers, shark fin soup, piglet and roasted chicken, can cost between four thousand and 12 thousand patacas.
“Consumption is, this year, much lower than previous years, but we are very busy and the main reason is because we offer the lowest possible price,” says Tong, who laments the fall in local purchasing power.
At the Campo do Dragão restaurant, 200 meters there, the numbers also suggest retraction. Lin Zhiyuan, space manager, speaks of “600 to 800 tables” reserved throughout the month - “less 20% to 30%” than in 2024.
The difficulties are recognized in other spaces of the city. On a walk through Macao Baixa, small street food businesses gain in this fight to traditional restaurants and tabscas.
Chan Chak Mo, deputy and president of the Union of Associations of Restoration and Beverage Owners, confirms the caution environment in spending: “General consumption is low, street food costs around 60-70 patacas,” he says .
After three years of pandemic and rigorous politics 'zero covid', the game's engine, the engine of the local economy, are already approaching the values ​​of 2019. However, despite the regeneration of the sector, in small and medium enterprises, the wound maintains open.
In the case of restoration, in November, according to the latest official statistics, the volume of “Chinese restaurants and the food and soup stores and soup stores dropped 4.3% and 3.7%, respectively” .
And then there is the other side of the border. Quality products and services, lower prices and the possibility of, since 2023, a daily circulate of two thousand vehicles with Macao enrollment in the interior of China, make neighboring Zhuhai a fierce competitor of the small local commerce.
“It is estimated that about 50 million US dollars who were once spent on Macau and Hong Kong per month and are now spent on Shenzhen and Zhuhai. And obviously this has a huge reflection on the welfare of small businesses, ”says the Mayor of Commerce and Luso-Chinese industry.
Carlos Cid Álvares, also executive director of the Macao National Bank Overseas Bank, suggests adaptations: “Small businesses have done business equally for 20 years or 30 years and have to adapt to a new reality that is that of a younger population, with other needs ”.
Another sequelae of the economic moment: in 2023, 3,712 birth births were 43.5% than 10 years (6,571).
For Tao Xuemei and Wong Chio Fan, a young couple, the personal and Chinese coffers do not allow us to step: “We worry to have children because of national debt due to economic recession. The option for motherhood really depends on the country's economic capacity and the debt payment capacity, ”says Tao, 28, to work as a school advisor.
“We don't want to have children just to pass them [our] debts,” adds Wong, a 35 -year -old contractor.
Finances are the theme that about 20% of people lead to consultations with Mickey Hung Sen Chun, Master of Feng Shui, a Chinese millennial practice that studies the influence of space on people's welfare.
This Lunar New Year, which starts on Wednesday, the casinos will continue to prosper, says the master. "Because the serpent symbolism is associated with wisdom and mystical luck, many visitors may be more inclined to play, Hung also predicts.
In the negative level, the year of the serpent “is often accompanied by indifference and hatred”, and the fact that “there were many important historical events” in this sign of the lunar calendar may be a source of apprehension, warns the master, who points to the risk of future “similar occurrences”.
The Japanese attacked Pearl Harbor in 1941; Tiananmen's massacre in Beijing took place in 1989 and the September 11 terrorist attacks in 2001. Every year of the serpent.
In the national level, Hung estimates, "With the gradual recovery of the world economy, China exports may be positively affected, which will help you achieve the purpose of fixed growth."
China, shaken by a profound real estate crisis, the main investment vehicle of Chinese families, launched several economic stimulus measures in the last quarter of last year, including the reduction of mandatory bank reserves ratios and interest rates. Beijing also promised to pursue “more proactive” budgetary policies and “moderate flexibility” of monetary policy to boost domestic consumption.
"The point is to know if what they are doing right now, with all these macroeconomic support policies, is sufficient to stimulate domestic consumption," says Nicholas Chen, analyst at consultant Fitch Solutions, underlining the weight of the real estate crisis "no feeling of the consumer ”.
Chen notes that, although China's gross domestic product reached Beijing's goal and grew 5% by 2024, Fitch Solutions foresees a slight slowdown by 2025 “to about 4.7% due to macroeconomic contrary winds, as well as slow domestic consumption, ”he adds.
Legend has it that 'Nian' ('Year' in Mandarin), a mythical beast, goes out on the street and hunting animals and people to devour and cultivation fields to ruin. As it is intolerant of noise and red color, people began to decorate the houses in red and throw firefighting and panchões to chase the monster.
Macao does not challenge the conviction. The city prepares the crossing for the new year. The streets dress as tradition dictates. Tong Vu, waiting for the serpent, hung red lanterns, to see also if for the year the lobsters sell better.
 
*From the Lusa Agency</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>‘I'm still here’ competes for three Oscars; Fernanda Torres disputes the best actress</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/ainda-estou-aqui-concorre-tres-oscares-fernanda-torres-disputa-de-melhor-actriz/</link><description>“I'm still here”, a movie starring Fernanda Torres and made by Walter Salles, was nominated for the Oscar for best film and best international film, the Hollywood Academy of Film and Film Sciences reported. Fernanda Torres was also named for the best actress statuette for the role of Eunice Paiva, widow of Deputy Rubens Paiva, killed during the military dictatorship.
In an unprecedented dispute, “I'm still here” competes for the best film with “Anora”, “The Brutalist”, “A Complete Unknown”, “Conclave”, “Dune: Part Two”, “Emilia Pérez”, “Nickel Boys ”,“ The Substance ”and“ Wicked ”.
Already in the category of best international film, Salles's feature film will compete in the statuette with “Emilia Pérez”, “The Girl With The Needle” (Denmark), “The Seed of the Sacred Fig” and “Germany) and“ Flow ”(Latvia).
Fernanda Torres will compete for the Oscar for best actress with Demi Moore (“The Substance”), Cynthia Erivo (“Wicked”), Karla Sofa Gasco (“Emilia Pérez”) and Mikey Madison (“Anora”).
“Emilia Perez”, an audacious musical performed by Frenchman Jacques Audiard about a violent Mexican drug baron that undergoes a gender change to live as a woman, leads the dispute, with 13 nominations.
The film, a Netflix production, destroyed “The Tiger and the Dragon” and “Roma” (each with ten nominations) as the most appointed in non-English language-the feature film was filmed almost totally totally Spanish.
Crowning its beautiful trajectory this season of awards that will end with Oscar's delivery, production was nominated for very crowded categories, as a better achievement for Audiard, best actress for Spanish Karla Sofa Gasco-who made history when becoming in the first trans women to obtain this recognition -best secondary actress, best international film and best song, among others.
The epic Sagra migratory "The Brutalist" and the adaptation of the Broadway musical "Wicked", with 10 nominations each follows.
“A Complete Unknown,” Bob Dylan's biographical film, and “Conclave”, the saga on the inner fights in the Vatican, had eight nominations each.
This year, the announcement of the nominees to the academy awards had to be postponed due to the forest fires that devastated Los Angeles. The deadline to vote was extended this month, due to the fires that plagued the entertainment capital and left at least 28 dead and tens of thousands of evacuates.
Experts such as Pete Hammond, from the “Deadline” publication, predicted a greater influence from the gym's international voters, as many local members still suffer the consequences of the flames.
Nevertheless, the 97th Oscar Delivery Ceremony was kept on March 2 in Los Angeles, California.
In the category of best male interpretation are in the dispute Adrien Brody (“The Brutalist”), Timothee Chalamet (“A Complete Unknown”) and Ralph Fiennes (“Conclave”).
Like Colman Domingo (“Sing Sing”) and Sebastian Stan, in the role of a young Donald Trump in the biographical film “The Apprentice,” which, according to experts, could be seen as a political manifesto at a time when the 78 -year -old Republican Back to the White House. The film suffered Trump's lawyer process threats, particularly for a scene where the newly deposed president appears to rape his wife.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>