<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Fall to nine candidacies for direct suffrage in AL</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/caem-para-nove-candidaturas-para-sufragio-directo-na-al/</link><description>The number of lists candidates for direct suffrage for the Legislative Assembly not only fell from 2021, the year five lists were disqualified, but the lowest ever since the creation of the MSAR. According to the Electoral Affairs Committee, nine requests were received for the constitution of a direct election committee - seven of which currently have representation in the Hemiciclo - and six for indirect suffrage. The State Security Defense Commission will now determine if the candidates “defend the basic law and are faithful to the MSAR”, and the decision is disclosed to the late 15 July. On September 14, 333,391 people may exercise the right to vote. Academics told this newspaper that the scenario could result from the “background censorship” verified in the last electoral act, as well as the “feeling of impotence of citizens”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Applications for elections for the Legislative Assembly (AL), scheduled for September 14, fell to less than half compared to those submitted in 2021. On Friday, the time he ended the deadline for the request for recognition of the Candidacy Committee, the Al (Caeal) Commission of Electoral Affairs (Caeal) revealed that he received a total of 15 orders-nine for direct suffrage and six for the suffrage.
Four years ago, the body had received 19 application for direct suffrage; These requests that were then reduced to 14, with the disqualification of five lists and 21 candidates (15 of which pro-democracy), by, according to the authorities, “not defending the basic law” and “not being faithful to the masters”.
This number of candidacies for direct suffrage not only decreased by 2021, but also the lowest since it is registered. According to CAEAL data consulted by the Jornal Tribuna de Macau, between 2001 and 2021, the candidate lists have always been close to two dozen or above that. For example, in 2017 there was the largest number of applications to AL, totaling 25, while in 2001 there were 15-this counting only the lists for direct suffrage.
Speaking to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, academic Leon Ieong recalled that Caeal's decision "implied background censorship in 2021", so "all candidates must take this factor in account before they decide to run for elections."
Asked if he anticipates that in the future there may be even fewer candidacies, the professor at the University of Macao Faculty of Social Sciences said that "it is likely," adding: "This would not change the standard of distribution of places, would only make public opinion less diverse."
Leon Ieong argued that "it can currently be considered that the Legislative Assembly is closer to the National Popular Assembly in Continental China."
Also in statements to this newspaper, an academic, who asked not to be identified, considered that "reducing the number of candidates groups reflects that the public is very aware that organizations that do not have visibility and resources are simply unable to compete with traditional, pro-government organizations." “This may also be the feeling of impotence of the citizens of Macao. Knowing that these organizations will be elected, what is the meaning of participating in the elections?” He asked.
The same academic said it also believed that this year the voting rate "could reach a new minimum." "Young people, in particular, have no motivation to participate," he said. In 2021, the influx rate to the direct suffrage, reached 42.38%, representing the lower percentage since the establishment of the MSAR. That year, 137,279 people voted in a universe of 323,907.
As this newspaper reported in January, at the end of 2024 9,759 new singular voters, well below the 2016 (-61%) and 2020 (-39%) records, which preceded equally years of legislatures were counted. For former deputy Agnes Lam, the decrease may be associated with demographic factors, but also with the disqualification of deputies in 2021.
"The phenomenon of the disqualification of political candidates in Macao probably played a role in reducing the vigor of electoral competition. When potential voters realize that the range of candidates does not fully represent their political opinions, particularly those of opposition, this can lead to shutdown," he said. In general, Macau has 333,391 people qualified to vote.
Caeal explained that the “verification process to follow the eligibility of the candidates now begins, and if the information presented is according to the regulations”. It is incumbent upon the MSar State Security Defense Commission to determine whether the candidates "defend the basic law and are faithful to MSAR", in which they are the first elections under the new electoral law, "which aims at a greater implementation of the" Macao Macau ruled by patriots "principle.
The commission will give Caeal an opinion, and from the decision that a candidate “does not have the ability to be a candidate (…) there is no complaint or litigation”. The decision will be announced, until late, until July 15.
 
Seven lists remain in the hemiciclo race
Of the nine candidates for direct suffrage, seven are linked to deputies with a seat in Hemiciclo. From the outset, the list “Macao Citizens Association” linked to the Fujian community, which in the last elections won three seats (Si Ka Lon, Song Pek Kei and Nick Law); as well as the “Union for Development”, of the Federation of Workers' Associations (Ella Law and Leong Sun Iok).
Also the “New Hope”, linked to the Association of Public Function Workers and which currently has deputies José Pereira Coutinho and Che Sai Wang, continues in the race. In the presentation of the application for candidacy, Coutinho said he is confident that he will not be disqualified: "The fact that being critical does not mean that I am not a patriot, I am also a patriot." Despite not having revealed the composition of the list, he guaranteed the presence of Rita Santos, who requested in October the suspension of the mandate of advisor to the Portuguese communities.
The “Macau-Guangdong Union”, linked to the province of Jiangmen (Zheng Anting and Lo Choi In), has also reappointed, like the “Promoting Union for Progress” list, which elected Leong Hong Sai and Ngan Iek Hang in 2021, which is linked to the general union of residents' associations.
The “Good Home Alliance”, linked to the Women's Association, which has reached two places for four years (Wong Kit Cheng and Ma Io Fong), advances again for direct suffrage. And the same is true of the “Synergy Power” list of the Synergy Association, whose only elected deputy was Ron Lam.
However, it is not yet known if the current deputies will remain in the race, or what are the priorities of each of the lists. Both the composition of the lists and the political program must be presented until the 26th of this month.
There are also two new lists: “Mutual Help Grassroots”, which should have as a head-cloak Wong Wai Man, who is running for the second time; And the list linked to the Citizens and Economy Life Promotion Association, which competes for the first time, and has as number one Tim Wong, linked to the Myanmar community.
A total of 33 deputies are part of AL, 14 of which are elected by direct suffrage, 12 by indirect suffrage, through associations, and seven appointed later by the Chief Executive.
In the case of indirect suffrage, Caeal received six application, more than in 2021, for the five sectors: industrial, commercial and financial; workers; Liberal professionals; social and educational services; and cultural and sports.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Formulas 4 and Regional are part of the Grand Prix Program</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/formulas-4-regional-integram-programa-grande-premio/</link><description>Less than six months from another edition of the Macao Grand Prix, the organization has confirmed seven races on the program. The main novelty is Formula 4, which will thus join the other monoloar test, the regional formula. FIA President Mohammed Ben Suulayem was yesterday in the territory to inaugurate the exhibition of another car at the Grand Prix Museum, the winner of the last year's regional formula, the American Ugo Ugochwu

Victor Rebelo
 
The Macao Great Prize (GPM) 2025 program is defined, consisting of seven races, the same number as the previous edition. However, there is a change in relation to the categories that will evolve in the guide circuit, returning to Formula 4 (F4), now with the name Cup of the International Automobile Federation (FIA), to the detriment of one of the support races, Roadsport - Establishment Cup of MSAR.
The presence of young F4 riders thus raises to two monoloar competitions, always pleasing the spectators, joining the Regional Formula (FR) test, also supervised by the FIA.
The F4 World Cup returns to the guide asphalt, certainly bringing the best pilots from various continents, as well as you can open some vacancies to representatives of the territory. It is recalled that in 2023 Macao took Charles Leong to second place, behind British Arvid Lindald, in a year when another house pilot, Tiago Rodrigues, ended in sixth.
At this time there are 13 national F4 championships, where all competitors will have to use Mygale M21-F4 singlesuar, recently renamed Ligier JS F422. This will be the fourth time the category will run in the MSAR, after 2020 to 2023.
Already the FR comes to the territory for the second consecutive year. The triumph in 2024 was reached by Ugo Ugochukwu, from the United States, ahead of the German damage Oliver Goethe and the Mexican Noel Léon. The driver of Macau Tiago Rodrigues was 33rd in the qualification race and did not qualify in the main race.
In short, this year's program will have four FIA World Cups, as in addition to the monologes, the GT and TCR World Tour (Guide Race) Cup are included.
Moreover, the GPM, which will take place from 13 to 16 November, will feature, in terms of car racing, with the usual fight between Macao and Hong Kong riders in Roadsport Challenge. The Big Motorcycle Award also integrates the program of the 72nd edition of the event.
The news was announced yesterday afternoon, at a press conference held at the Grand Prix Museum, by the President of the Institute of Sport (ID), which is also the coordinator of the organizing committee.
By his side the president of the FIA, Mohammed Ben Suulaym, Luís Gomes said that the event “has been taking place with innovations and incorporating new elements in the events, being confident that this year the races“ can attract the attention of fans from around the world ”, adding that“ the success of the GPM depends a lot on the confidence and long time support for the sectors and support for the sectors of the sectors and support. society".
The ID official also said that "in this edition we continue to cooperate with the FIA ​​in the organization of world class events, in order to continue to show on the international sports stage the high position of the event."
Luís Gomes stressed that the GPM annually attracts “huge visitors from the abroad of Macao and the interior of China, taking advantage of the promotion of economics and tourism and stimulating the development of markets such as hotels, transport, restoration and retail”. Therefore, it reinforced the event "not only contributes to itself, but also benefits society and the economy."
Thus, the government will “oppose” the organization of the event continuously, by increasing the quality of the evidence, the reinforcement of the promotions carried out in the neighboring regions and the organization of various related activities, “in order to increase the effect of the brightness of the great award”.
Meanwhile, the FIA ​​president defended the coming to Macau of the FR World Cup and praised the history of the competition.
Mohammed Ben Suulayem then watched the inauguration of a new car that will be evident to the public at the Grand Prix Museum. This is the monoligue of the 2024 FR winner, the American Ugo Ugochukwu.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Guinea-Bissau wants to attract Macau's investment</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/guine-bissau-quer-atrair-investimento-de-macau/</link><description>The president of Guinea-Bissau moved to Macao on an official visit and met with the chief executive. During the meeting, Sam Hou Fai and Umro Sissoco Embaló exchanged impressions on how to make the most of the role of Macao as a sino-illusopone platform, and boost bilateral economic and commercial cooperation. Attracting investment to the African country was another goal assumed by Embaló
 
Victor Rebelo
 
In a meeting of about an hour, the head of the Executive of the MSAR and the president of Guinea-Bissau gathered at the Government headquarters, in the one that was the first point of the agenda of Umaro Sissoco Embaló in the short visit to the territory. Among other topics, dialogue focused on bilateral economic and commercial cooperation and the better use of the role of Macao as a sino-illusophone platform.
Sam Hou Fai stressed that China and Guinea-Bissau maintain a good relationship and highlighted the establishment of the strategic partnership last year, noting that the Macao Forum Ministerial Conference, held in 2024, contributed to a broader and higher and high level cooperation perspective between China and all Portuguese-speaking countries (PLP).
According to an official statement, the chief executive assured that the MSar will continue to “perform its advantages” of “a center, a platform and a base”, providing help to Guinea-Bissau “in full use” of the commercial cooperation platform between China and PLP, promoting and supporting companies on both sides to reinforce mutual investment and cooperation. This in the sense of "helping Guinea-Bissau transforms its potential to the level of resources into a development engine."
In addition, he argued that Macau and Guinea-Bissau can deepen exchange and cooperation in the domains of health, education and youth.
Later, Umro Embaló held a meeting with guardians from the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment, Associations and Entrepreneurs, during which he said that Guinea-Bissau offers many advantages. "Our currency is open and we have parity with the euro, which is very important and facilitates commercial transactions," said the Chief of Staff of the African country, in statements that were reproduced by Radio Macau.
Umro Embaló, who was accompanied by the other members of the entourage, including the Minister of Economy, Plan and Regional Integration, Soares Sambú, and the Secretary of State for International Cooperation, Fatumata Jau, appealed to entrepreneurs to bet on Guinea-Bissau. "We will create conditions to facilitate your business," he said, adding that his country "may be the gateway to Macao investors on the African continent, particularly in the economic community of West African states that have over 300 million inhabitants."
In this meeting were also present, among others, the commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Popular Republic of China at MSAR, Liu Xianfa, and the secretary for Macao Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP.
On Friday night, Umro Embaló received about three dozen elements of the Guinesse community, mostly students. In his speech, the head of state encouraged students in Macao to dedicate themselves solely to studies, leaving aside politics.
On the other hand, it emphasized that Guinea-Bissau will bet on scholarships in areas where the country needs the most, such as agronomy and some technologies.
According to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the president of the Association of Naturals and Friends of Guinea-Bissau, Graziela Lopes, the students reported some problems they face in the MSAR, such as integration issues and the value of the scholarship, while other elements of the community spoke of the difficulty in bringing Macao artisans and cooks.
The president of Guinea-Bissau ended a visit to the territory at noon on Friday, having proceeded to Hong Kong, where he was a few hours before traveling to Washington. Today, Umaro Sissoco Umaló should be received by US President Donald Trump.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Malparado in the board registers second consecutive descent</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/malparado-na-banca-regista-segunda-descida-consecutiva/</link><description>Contrary to a long trend in the rise, Macao's badly raised credit came down in April for the second consecutive month, although it remains at a high level, above 55 billion patacas. The expired credit ratio retreated to 5.4%
 
At the end of April, loans with more than 90 days late in Macao banks totaled about 55.78 billion Patacas, which represents a drop of 0.6% or 314.6 million compared to the previous month, according to data published by the Monetary Authority (AMCM). After reaching 57.62 billion in February -the highest value since AMCM began compiling this data in 1990 -the “non -productive” or overdue credit (NPL, in the English acronym) thus recorded the second consecutive decrease as it had already dropped 2.7% in March.
On the other hand, the badly raised credit increased by 21.2% or 9.77 billion compared to the end of April 2024. Since the end of 2019, when it has been encrypted by 2.77 billion, the NPL has grown 20 times.
In April this year, the expired credit accounted for 5.4% of local banks loans, less percentage points than in the previous month, and 1.1 points more than in the same period of 2024. The global delayed amount includes 33.93 billion not resident clients (60.8% of the total) and 21.85 billion residents, translating into racings of 6.3% and 4.3%, respectively.
Official data also show that internal loans to the private sector reached 505.3 billion patacas in April, noting decreases of 1.2% and 5.1% in monthly and annual terms, respectively. Foreign credit (535.80 billion) grew 4.5% in a month, but decreased by 2.5% compared to April 2024.
In general, the credit granted to the private sector increased by 1.7% to 1,041.1 billion patacas between March and April. Hong Kong dollar loans maintained a dominant weight (42.2%), followed by pataca (21.4%), US dollar (21.2%) and Renminbi (12.1%).
Already the deposits of the public sector in local banks totaled 209.59 billion, illustrating a monthly descent of 0.8% and an annual increase of 4.3%. Resident deposits (784.12 billion) decreased 0.6% in a month, but advanced 8.1% in the annual range, while non-residents (349.66 billion) dropped 2.9% and rose 6.8% on the same comparative bases.
As a result, bank activity deposits fell 1.2%to 1,343.3 billion compared to March this year.
 
Bank sector profit rose 44% until April
Macao banks exploration results increased 44.2% to 3.71 billion levels at the end of April, compared to the 2024 homologous period, according to data from the monetary authority, which point to a 25.3% increase in bank service and operations (3.37 billion) and an increase of 329.8% in the income of financial investments (558.3 ​​million). On the other hand, banks suffered a 1.7% break in interest margin (4.97 billion). It is recalled that banks closed 2024 with operational profits of 4.01 billion, which reflected an annual decrease of 21.3% and was the lowest since 2010. The 2024 profits marked the fourth consecutive descent after 12 years, including 10 successive records, starting in 2011.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Seminar left clues about mental health of young people</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/seminario-deixou-pistas-sobre-saude-mental-dos-jovens/</link><description>The challenges and strategies to face the mental health of young people in the context of the internet were approached in a seminar on the mental and psychological health of children and adolescents. In its intervention, the Deputy Director of Health Services said it is “essential to reinforce communication”
 
Experts and academics, in a total of 180, participated in a seminar on mental and psychological health of children and adolescents, which took place at the Center of Health of the Areia Preta. Through dialogues and interdisciplinary sharing, the debates provided multidimensional ideas and strategies of response to the protection of the mental and psychological health of children and adolescents in the age of the internet.
In the opening speech, Kuok Cheong U, Deputy Director of Health Services (SSM), said that the government attributes great importance to the problems and challenges that children and young people face in the scope of mental and psychological health. "Given the rapid change in the social environment, it is understood that, in addition to being concerned with the physical health of children and adolescents, it is essential to reinforce communication, to follow more children and young people, guiding them to create good emotional management since childhood," he said, according to a note from SSM.
The lectures promoted by the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center (CHCSJ), with the collaboration of Macao Pediatric Society, included several thematic sessions, covering areas such as Clinical Medicine, Psychological Intervention and Social Phenomena, analyzed from different perspectives.
The head of the ChCSJ Pediatric Service mentioned that current adolescents - the first generation of digital natives - "have behaviors and difficulties whose analysis through traditional development theories prove insufficient, creating challenges in the elaboration of adequate intervention strategies." Exemplifying, Wong Fong stressed that "when doctors, in external consultations, stress that children have to do 60 minutes of physical exercise a day, many of them are immersed on electronic devices, such as short or mobile videos, clinging to the screens until high hours, although they are advised to guarantee nine hours of sleep per night."
The same responsible said that, in the internet age, "the pressure of peers goes from the physical field to social networking groups," cyberbullying "gets worse with the anonymization mechanism, even emotional expression becomes a competition for" likes "." These phenomena, they emphasize, reflect "the characteristics of the mental and psychological changes of young people today, as well as the unique challenges of the time they are in."
Cheang Sut Ieng, Wong Wai Kei and Pang Weng SI, SSM psychotherapists, discussed topics such as “Children's Psychological Health series: Alert Signal Identification-Causes Analysis-Intervention Techniques” and combined clinical cases of Macau with Statistical Data on Emotional Welfare of Hong Kong and Macau students, to detail the early signs of problems. psychological in children.
The experts and academics of the two RAE also discussed “healthy lifestyle”, “family influence”, “role of school and community”, “labeling effect”, among others, considering that the growth of children and young people is a “highly complex development process that involves various physical, psychological and social factors”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SJM intends to “rescue” two satellite casinos</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sjm-tenciona-resgatar-dois-casinos-satelite/</link><description>Prior to the end of the year, the 11 satellite casinos under SJM, Melco and Galaxy will close doors-however, SJM intends to “rescue” two of these spaces through the acquisition of the properties of hotels where Ponte 16 and Le Royal Arc casinos are located. The negotiations, however, have not yet begun and the concessionaire is necessary to request the direct operation of these casinos. The decision of the game companies involves almost 6,000 jobs, which will be secured by the operators, the authorities guaranteed. With the closure of these spaces, also hundreds of SMEs in the immediate vicinity will suffer and consequently their employees. In this context, the Executive intends to help “reconvert” stores, with the secretary for the economy and finance to say that they glimpse “a challenge and an opportunity”. Melco, in turn, intends to keep three of the current six mocha rooms
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The 11 existing satellite casinos in the territory will close doors before the end of the year, when the “transition deadline” provided for by the game law, a “commercial decision” taken by the three game operators involved, SJM Resorts, Melco Resorts and Galaxy Casino, said the secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong. However, two satellite casinos can be “absorbed”-at least, this is the intention of SJM, which intends to acquire the ownership of the hotels where Casino Ponte 16 and Casino Le Royal Arc are located. Melco intends to keep three of the six existing “mocha clubs”. As for employees, the government "demanded" to the gamekeepers to ensure jobs.
The spaces that will end before the end of the year - no concrete date has not been advanced - include the GrandView, Legend Palace, Fortune, Landmark, Ponte 16, Le Royal Arc, Emperor Palace, Kam Pek Paradise and Casa Real (SJM), Grand Dragon (Melco) and Waldo (Galaxy). According to the director of the inspection and coordination of games, there are 480 game tables and 270 slot machines.
Regarding Ponte 16 and L'ARC, after the negotiation procedure, SJM will have to apply to the government "the exploration of games to adopt the form of" directly operated casinos "after the closure of the" satellite casinos ", he said the same ruler at a press conference.
Following a “profound analysis and evaluation”, and taking into account SJM's “long-term alignment”, as well as “the global group's competitiveness and the strategic location of the satellite casinos”, the company's board has decided to advance for the acquisition of those properties. But in a note sent to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange, SJM states that "negotiations related to potential acquisitions have not yet begun, and no binding agreements have been celebrated."
"Regardless of the result of the negotiations related to potential acquisitions, all game tables and slot machines of affected satellite casinos will be reaffeved to SJM Resorts' own casinos," he added. The board of directors has not yet stressed that restructuring “has any significant adverse effect on the group's operations, liquidity or profitability”.
Regarding the six places of exploration of game machines operated on non -own properties, Melco will ask the government to explore, by hiring a management society, three “Mocha Clubs”: Golden Dragon, Porto and Sintra. However, the company decided to end Grand Dragon, Royal and Kuong Fat, "after considering the global development strategy." The gaming tables and the electronic game machines operating in these three spaces "will be redistributed", continuing to operate in other casinos or play areas, explained Melco.
 
Almost 6,000 workers involved
The issue of workers affected by the end of satellite casinos has raised concerns, but the government has ensured that the employability of these employees is a priority. According to the Secretary for Economics and Finance, the decision of the operators affects 5,600 local workers employed in the satellite casinos of which 4,800 are directly hired by the game concessionaires and 800 by the satellite casinos themselves. There are also 400 non-resident workers (TNR) in these spaces. In the “Mocha Clubs”, in turn, 300 local workers and 50 TNR are employed, Tai Kin IP said.
As for the workers hired by the concessionaires, the companies committed to ensuring their jobs. Ensuring that it is “committed to safeguarding local employment”, SJM has stated that “all residents who work currently in the satellite casinos whose closure is expected, regardless of whether they are directly employed by SJM Resorts or their third parties, will have job opportunities” on operator properties.
"Those who are already employees of SJM Resorts will maintain their use and will be transferred to similar functions related to the game in other casinos, based on operational needs. Staff not to SJM Resorts who are local resident will also be invited to apply for appropriate positions in the group," he said.
Melco, in turn, indicated that employees of the “Mocha Clubs” that will close doors “will be highlighted to work on other properties of the company in Macao, which will ensure the continuation of the use of these workers within their current functions”.
Galaxy Entertainment stressed, in a note sent to Gggrasia, that employees who work in the Waldo Casino-Satellite “will be reappeted to their other properties and casinos”. He added: "The competent departments will discuss the best options with team members and will provide them with a number of vocational training programs to help them adapt to their new work environment."
As for the 800 hired by the satellite casinos, Secretary André Cheong said the gamekeepers have “already guaranteed the government” that they will help them if they have employment problems. "They said they will absorb these workers and provide appropriate posts," he said.
Tai Kin IP stressed that the government, in particular the direction of services to labor affairs, will proceed to “rigorous supervision to local workers' transition processes”, as well as providing job conjugation and professional formations.
 
Hundreds of “directly affected” stores
In addition to casinos-satellite and mocha room employees, the existing stores in the vicinity of these spaces will also suffer from the impact of their closure and, consequently, there will also be affected workers. Tai Kin IP explained yesterday that there are 320 stores operating in the vicinity of the satellite casinos: “We ranked the nature of these stores and SMEs, namely, the relationship with casinos customers. Half of these stores will be affected directly by closing, namely homes of pledge, cigarettes, alcoholic beverages, phone stores, typical restaurants”, typical restaurants, ” He enumerated.
According to the secretary, 400 workers will be directly affected by a total of 800 who are employed in those stores. Tai Kin IP described as "a challenge and an opportunity" what he called the "reconversion process" to which these stores have to submit. "We are trying to optimize the business environment. Traditional stores that have an intimate relationship with casinos customers need a conversion. We will help those who are interested (…) competent services are already working and forming interdepartal groups to promote this project. We are prepared to attract new stores or existing stores and make a conversion," he said.
 
Case of satellite casinos without “effective impact” on game recipes
The Government of MSAR said yesterday that the closure of the 11 satellite casinos “will not have an effective impact” on the game's recipes. "We believe that the decision to explore the game and its development will not have an effective impact on the game's revenues, but it will have a positive impact on the exploration of the game activity," said the secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong. Asked about the weight of satellite casinos revenues last year, the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP, said only that they “occupy a very low proportion, a percentage of only one digit” in gross game recipes.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>June 10 in Macau maintains “deep meaning”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/10-de-junho-em-macau-mantem-significado-profundo/</link><description>Macao is one of many places in the world where Portuguese live that today celebrate June 10, “Portugal, Camões and Portuguese Communities”. The Içar da Bandeira in the Garden of the Consulate will be the first act, followed by the usual rown to the Camões Cave and, in the late afternoon, the traditional reception to the community in the consular residence, moments that involve great symbolism and are expected with expectation expectations
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The raising of the flag will start, this morning, at 9:30 am, to the celebrations of the “Portugal, Camões and Portuguese Communities” in Macao, with the ceremony to take place as usually in the Chancellery of the General Consulate of Portugal at MSAR. As is the tradition, the act of lifting the flag of the corps of the Public Security Police body and the group of lusophone scouts (Gelmac).
There will be the romage to the cave of Camões, in Jardim Homony, where students of the Portuguese School (EPM) and Luiz Gonzaga Gomes School, will have the opportunity to declare poems of “Os Lusíadas” by Luís Vaz de Camões.
Regarding the participation of EPM students, just over 40 will recite the sonnet “Betish Love New Arts, New Engenho”. It is a “very beautiful sonnet, that the 10th grade students, including non-maternal language, will declare,” said Alexandra Domingues, a Portuguese teacher teacher.
Students will each bring a flower to the cave that honors one that is considered one of the greatest figures of Lusophone literature and one of the great poets of Western tradition.
The celebrations will continue in the late afternoon, with the traditional reception to the community, scheduled to start at 6:30 pm, which will return to the official residence of the consul General of Portugal.
At the presentation of the “June, Portugal Month” program, the consul explained that the conviviality will be open to the bearers of the citizen card or national citizen identity ticket of the Portuguese Republic. However, Alexandre Leitão warned of the need to make a pre-registration to better control the influx of people to the site.
At the reception is expected a representative of the Government of MSAR, usually the chief executive himself. To confirm the presence of Sam Hou Fai, this will be his first participation as a government official in the official celebrations of June 10.
"The speech of the Chief Executive is always awaited with expectation and is very important, since it usually refer directly to the Portuguese community, or Macaense, in a conviviality that is always very comforting," he told the Journal Tribuna de Macau Anabela Ritchie, for whom the flag is equally a beautiful moment. "There I will be to sing the hymn, tuned or challenged, because I like to be present, listen to the police band and see the scouts to rise the flag," he says.
The former president of the Legislative Assembly does not lose the way to the cave of Camões, since it reminds him of his childhood. “I revive a lot of moments from when I was a child and young man and when I went with school, remembering that after the ceremonies we were very happy to give us a box that contained a refreshment and a cake, so it is very special for me to relive these moments,” he recalls.
Macaense regrets, on the other hand, that no one from Portugal will be represented this year, recognizing that changes in government in Lisbon "made it all more complicated."
For its part, Jorge Neto Valente states that June 10th is a “naturally limited convention to the Portuguese community, but has a lot of value because it is a day that is respected by all Portuguese around the world wherever they are and not just in Portugal”.
The lawyer considers that "there has been a tradition of many years when the Portuguese community celebrates June 10 and all the steps of this tradition have a deep meaning." What is important is that “this tradition is a moment of union of the Portuguese”, he stresses, adding that “the Portuguese in Macau are a different community, with traditions that others all, regardless of the number of those who are here, do not have”.
Nelson António, chief of Gelmac, says young scouts like to participate in these ceremonies. “For them it is a satisfaction and a pride can contribute to a more official and more formal act,” he says, noting that Gelmac has been uninterrupted from the first hour in these celebrations.
"It is important for all of us, to feel closer to our country, since people have some nostalgia because they are far away and so it makes perfect sense to mark this day," he said.
The group of lusophone scouts, “which will be in tune with the CPSP band”, will be represented this year by about 40 elements, which will also be present in the romach to the Cave of Camões.
 
Events present exhibition and concert
Today's ceremonies are included in the “June, Portugal month” program, which will last by the end of the month. Tomorrow, Wednesday, the Rui Cunha Foundation features “Metamorphoses”, an individual exhibition of art, by artist and curator Lúcia Lemos, with scheduled inauguration for 18h00.
The synopsis speaks of an exhibition that emerges from lived transformations and personal visual observations of the physical space - Macau - "where it has allowed itself to contaminate, never failing to practice portugality, as a sense of belonging from where it departed four decades ago."
The show also means the “symbiosis of construction and maturation of your identity”, modeled by changes in adaptation and adoption to the metamorphosis of the new place. “Art and the artistic process are looking for forms of integration and connection of the human being into nature and the world around him,” mentions the introduction of the exhibition, which brings together 44 pieces that link diverse artistic expressions and aesthetics, such as engraving, photography, installation, painting and ceramic.
Also tomorrow, at 19h00, it will be the turn of the Portuguese bookstore to receive a seminar and the book launch, in an event that serves to mark the 40th anniversary of the bookstore.
On Thursday, from 6.30 pm, there is the “Portuguese Gristronomic Festival”, promoted by Sofitel, BNU and Luso-Chinese Chamber of Commerce and Industry, in Sofitel Macau's Baccara Room-Bridge 16. An exclusive selection of the best Portuguese delicacies will be offered, including a variety of cheese, homemade handmade breads, cod and traditional swim balls from butter. All accompanied by 30 wines from nine different regions.
For June 13, Friday, at 6.30 pm, the Event Program reserves a collective exhibition, organized by Casa de Portugal at Casa de Glass, entitled “Santos Popular”. At night, at 8:30 pm it is the turn of a live music concert at Red House Macau, the initiative of “None of Your Business”, played by guitarist Bruno Pernadas.
The musician was the first Portuguese to produce a album from a Japanese band, “Massada Temples”, by Kikagaku Moyo, and composed several Sono bands for cinema, theater, dance and television.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Parks with weaker performance in cultural and educational functions</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/parques-desempenho-mais-fraco-nas-funcoes-culturais-educativas/</link><description>The urban parks of the Macao Peninsula have a worse perception by users in relation to their cultural and educational functions and public facilities, completed a study conducted by professors from the University of Macao and the University of Agriculture and Fojiculture of Fujian. Researchers argue that the implementation of visits, interactive display and digital cultural experiences, as well as multitudes control measures, could improve the cultural expression of parks and the participation of users
 
Pedro Milheirão
A study, published in the expert magazine “Applied Sciences”, concluded that the urban parks of the Macau Peninsula have a relatively weak performance in terms of the functions of science education and cultural heritage. The users of the parks also revealed concerns about the insufficient maintenance of the facilities and the overcrowding of the parks, concluded researchers Liu Kehui, professor at the Department of Literature and Art at Fujian College of Agriculture and Silviculture College, Wang Poshun and Liu Jing, teachers at the University of Macau Innovation and Design, through the analysis of contents generated by users, generated by users, Between 2020 and 2024, from the platforms “Google Maps” and “TripAdvisor”.
Data include text, geographical labels and comments from users, relating to 12 Macau Peninsula Parks: Jardim Vasco da Gama, Dr. Carlos D'Asumpção Park, Russian Mountain Garden, Lou Lim IOC Garden, Chunambeiro Municipal Kindergarten, São Francisco Garden, Monte do Forte Park, Louis de Camões Jardim, Hac Municipal Park and Dr. Sun Yat Sen.
To expand the educational functions of the parks, “ecological exposure, interactive educational activities and digital scientific content could be added to increase public awareness to cultural heritage and ecological conservation”, can read in the study. The authors suggest "the use of multimedia interaction techniques such as virtual visits, interactive educational exhibitions and digital cultural experiences."
According to academics, the application of technologies such as virtual reality and augmented reality on digital guided tours could enrich cultural services presentations, reinforcing interactivity and attractiveness of parks, as well as improving users' perceptions and emotional connections with the cultural value of spaces.
The investigation also indicates that dynamic multitudes control dynamic measures should be implemented to maintain high quality standards and the efficiency of services, even with a considerable number of visitors.
The authors believe that "these measures may improve cultural expression and educational functions, diversify parks services and improve users' participation in the future" and argue that "Macao's historical and cultural resources must be fully explored." “Cultural landscape projects, historical narrative exhibitions and local cultural symbols could be integrated into the park's planning,” they add.
Macao's urban parks show “considerable potential as patients with cultural heritage”, as they integrate natural landscapes with Chinese and Western cultural elements, recognize researchers. However, “facilities and activities related to local culture, such as historical exhibitions and ecological education programs, were considered relatively scarce in the Macao parks”.
On the other hand, and in general terms, the 12 parks that were the subject of study obtained a positive assessment in terms of aesthetic appreciation and landscape experience. The data collected reveal that parks such as Dr. Carlos D'Assumpção Park, Colina da Guia Park and Jardim Lou Lim Ieoc effectively integrate natural landscapes with the elements of cultural heritage.
Still, Fortaleza do Monte Park and Jardim Vasco da Gama received neutral scores for landscape experience, indicating that their potential in terms of cultural heritage has not yet been fully explored. The study points to an “insufficient interactive design” and the lack of cultural interpretation methods as the main reasons for these lower scores.
 
Gaps in peripheral parks
“Parks located in central urban areas benefit from high visit rates and various demands for activities, improving visitors' perception of cultural services. On the other hand, peripheral parks, characterized by lower visit rates, tend to have their under -slanted cultural service functions,” the study indicates.
“Limited investment in management resources in peripheral parks restricts its capacity for cultural diffusion,” as is the case of Hac Sá Park, with a weaker performance in cultural and educational functions, according to the authors. This is partly due to the fact that it is located in a more peripheral area of ​​Macao.
In turn, Dr. Carlos D'Asumpção Park has adequate facilities and sufficient management resources, because it is located in a central urban area. Overall, Macao parks also achieved good evaluations in the other evaluated categories, recreation and tourism and social interaction.
The research group states that the climate of Macao “provides an ecological environment suitable for green spaces” and that “urban parks play especially important roles in aesthetic, recreational and educational aspects”, highlighting the high urbanization and the remarkable cultural diversity of the territory.
“In highly urbanized environments, urban parks serve as essential green spaces. They provide various ecological services and also reflect urban historical heritage, spatial memory and social interaction functions,” according to the authors.
Macao is one of the most densely populated regions in the world, with limited resources of green spaces. "Urban parks, however, emerge as open spaces that significantly improve the ecological quality and well-being of residents," they underline.
The parks of the MSAR are part of Chinese and Western cultural elements with natural landscapes, such as Jardim Lou Lim Ieoc and Monte do Forte Park, and have “a significant cultural heritage value” that attracts a diverse group of users, from local residents to international tourists.
The authors of the study expect that, in the future, “spatial heterogeneity and diversity in the expression of cultural services can be improved by optimizing resource affectation, improving facilities and conception of cultural functions”. They also add that "the homogeneity of services not only limits the potential of urban parks to satisfy various cultural demands, but also weakens Macau's ability to express cultural diversity as a city recognized for its heritage."
The integration of multimedia and interactive technologies in the context of Macao's cultural heritage “would allow each park to develop a more distinct cultural service theme”, concludes the study.
Researchers also observe that optimization measures are not only applicable to improve MSAR urban parks, as well as practical references for the management of green spaces and conservation of cultural heritage in other highly urbanized regions of the world.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Infrastructure Forum will bring together about 70 ministers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/forum-das-infra-estruturas-vai-reunir-cerca-de-70-ministros/</link><description>Between today and Thursday, the 16th International Forum and Infrastructure Investment and Construction Exhibition will bring together about 70 ministers to promote cooperation in the interconnection of infrastructure. “30 pioneer technological results” will also be revealed
 
The 16th International Forum and Infrastructure Investment and Construction Exhibition (IIICF) will be attended by about 70 ministers, a record number, and the first realization of the “premiere@macau-ceremony of launching the innovative achievements in international infrastructure”, where “30 pioneer technological results” will be revealed with eight world premieres.
The event, which starts today and extends until Thursday at Cotai Expo do Venetian, also features another 3,500 elite figures from 70 countries and regions and includes the holding of over 250 thematic forums, among other complementary events, under the theme “Improved connectivity for mutually beneficial cooperation”, said the Institute for Commerce and Investment Promotion (IPIM). There will also be more than 200 exchange activities, including a guided tour of the exhibition, corporate roadshows, project promotions and contact scholarships. Admission is free access over the three days.
The forum aims to promote “pragmatically” forming cooperation in the field of infrastructure interconnection and widening the “circle of international friends”, according to IPIM. In parallel, the event program also seeks to reinforce “distinctive elements” of MSAR and “enhance the effectiveness of the participation of companies in Macau and Hengqin”.
This year, there was a 16% growth in the participation of countries of the Association of Southeast Asia (Asean), in view of 2024, and the current edition has the unprecedented presence of representatives of Indonesia, Laos, Thailand, Singapore and Vietnam.
During the IICF press conference, the president of the China International Civil Builders Association (Chinca), Fang Qiuchen, assured that the event highlights four main functions, which are exchanges and mutual learning, exhibitions, official releases and business promotion.
In addition, Fang highlighted the “220 international elite figures from the government, industrial, academic and investigative spheres, in the field of infrastructure”, which were invited “to discuss issues of the great current and avant-garde topics”. For the president of Chinca, the event “further enhances the characteristics of the combination of conferences and exhibitions” and “presents prominently a set of new technologies, products, results and solutions”. Fang reiterated that "the combination of conferences and exhibitions shows the great power of the country."
Regarding the “debut@macau”, he also said that the “launch of innovative achievements is centered on scientific and technological innovation”. During the event, the latest rates and reports on the development of infrastructures will be released within the “Range and Route” initiative and Portuguese-speaking countries, according to Fang.
On the same occasion, it linked the main highlights of this edition through “three synergies and a driving force”. The IPIM president explained that the first synergy consists of the "synergy of business opportunities for the debut economy with the infrastructure sector." The second refers to the “integration between conference and exposure”, while the third is the “connection between the international community and Macau”.
The driving force, in turn, refers to “the driving role of Macao's economy that the IIICF assumes as an international convention and international exhibition event”, continued Vincent U. The IPIM leader said that in 2024 the per capita expense of participating traders was 4,099 patacas and the average consumption of participants reached 23,000 patacas. "It is estimated that the 16th IIICF will generate revenues of 20 million patacas for the assembly sector in exhibition conventions," read in the statement.
Until Thursday, senior executives of more than 20 international financial institutions, representatives of more than 10 international organizations, presidents of more than 20 international trade associations and higher than 800 international engineering companies will meet to promote “global cooperation in infrastructure construction”.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Entrepreneurship Contest focused on the Great Bay</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/concurso-de-empreendedorismo-focado-na-grande-baia/</link><description>The 1st “Great Bay Entrepreneurship Contest” has already open registrations, being directed to the young layer. Projects to be presented can be in five domains, including artificial intelligence and robotics and medicine and health and biofabrication. Winners will have help in financial and resources
 
They have already started the registration for the 1st “Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau Bay Entrepreneurship Contest”, extending until July 31. The initiative, subordinate to the theme “Great Bay creates the future, Guangdong brings together talents”, aims to “stimulate the vitality of innovation and entrepreneurship in different regions, accelerating the articulation of resources, in order to support the integration of young people from Hong Kong and Macau at the conjuncture of national development”.
The contest is divided into five domains: artificial and robotic intelligence; Integrated circuits and low altitude economy; Medicine and Health and Biofabrication; Modern Food and Food and Agriculture Science and Technology; And modern services and culture and creativity, explains the direction of economy and technological development services (DSEDT). The areas “are precisely aligned with the needs of major national strategies and the industrial advantages of the great bay,” says the body.
Each domain is supported by sector and resource leaders' jury teams, and teams can apply for one of the domains according to the situation of their project, adds the DSEDT. Registrations can be made through the online page (http://dwqds.newjobs.com.cn/).
Winning projects will be provided financial support, as well as complementary diversified services, including brand training, talent services and political support, resource articulation, in order to create a complete entrepreneurship ecosystem. The goal is to help projects associate with capital and the market.
Participants are not limited to the home and geographical location, and those who have already started their activity in the great bay may be applied or that they want to start it. Projects must belong to operating entities already made up of or after January 1, 2020. In addition, participants must have been 16 years old and the number of team members cannot exceed five.
Hong Kong and Macao candidate projects must belong to RAE societies or whose members are resident of Chinese regions and nationality, or students or graduates from Hong Kong and Macau Higher Education Institutions, says DSEDT.
The initiative is organized by the State Ministry of Human Resources and Social Security, the Hong Kong and Macao CCP Committee, Hong Kong and Macao Central Committee to the Guangdong Province and Popular Government, and DSEDT is one of the collaborating entities.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Three plans of scholarships</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/relancados-tres-planos-de-bolsas-de-estudo/</link><description>Applications to scholarship plans for higher education for the Educational Fund will start on the 23rd. The support program for next school year is intended for students with economic difficulties or “excellent academic results”, and includes the continuation of studies in Portugal
 
Applications to the three plans of scholarships for Higher Education of the Educational Fund (FE), referring to the next school year, start on June 23. The deadline for the “Higher Education Scholarship Financing Plan” and the “Merit Scholarship Plan for the attendance of the best higher education institutions in the world ranking” runs until July 11. Candidates for the “interest payment plan for credit for studies” may apply until December 30.
The scholarship plan covers higher education courses, from pre-university to PhD, indicates the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ). This promotion scholarship is intended for students with economic difficulties, whose applications will be assessed and approved based on the total monthly income of the Family Anger of the Financial Year of 2024.
The foreground scholarship aims to finance students who have obtained “excellent academic results” in the last school year. The study scholarship in Portugal aims to “support Macao students who continue their studies in that country”, whose assignment will be made “based on document analysis and a selection test,” said the DSEDJ.
The scholarship for the indicated specialization area is intended for students who study in courses articulated with the development of the Government of the Government of the Government. Specialization areas include Big Health, modern finances, cutting -edge technology, culture, tourism, conventions and exhibitions, among others.
The “Merit Scholarship Plan for the frequency of the best higher education institutions in the world ranking” is intended for students who study in an institution classified in the first 50 positions of the “World Higher Education” world universities classification, or among the 10 best universities in other world rankings “of recognized merit”.
Finally, the purpose of the interest payment plan is to grant a monthly support to the interest payment, “during the frequency period of the course that the beneficiary frequents”. The maximum number of support installments is equivalent to “12 times the number of remaining years of the minimum course frequency duration”, says the statement. The concession ends with the completion of the installments or the course, explains the DSEDJ.
FE will publish information about the selection and results of the application on the Higher Education Scholarship Program page, instituting the candidates to “take the initiative to consult them”. The FE proceeds to send mobile and electronic mail messages, so candidates can provide contacts for this purpose.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Arts Festival for Children with Program Full of Activities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/festival-de-artes-para-criancas-programa-cheio-de-actividades/</link><description>The second edition of the International Children's Arts Festival will take place between July and August with a program full of activities for all ages, such as shows, workshops, an artistic camp and a film festival

























The 2nd International Arts Festival for Children of Macau will take place between July and August, with a set of activities for all ages, such as shows, workshops, an artistic camp and a film festival. Registration for workshops are already open, and tickets for the shows and artistic camp will be on sale from 10 am tomorrow, at the ticket of “Enjoy Macao”. At the same time, will also be available at Cinematheque Paixão, tickets for the International Film Festival for Macao Children.
This year's shows include Ballet Cinderella, presented by the BRNO Czech National Theater Ballet, with choreography of Markéta Habalová and a SERGEI Prokofiev score, recreating “The Dream Travel” by Disney Princess. According to the Cultural Institute (IC), Slava Polunin's acclaimed “Snow Show”, founder of the Clown Theater Academy will return to Macao, offering a combination of classical music, exquisite art and “moving elements”, which will show “an infinite creativity”, with props such as colorful balloons and a giant white network and snowflakes.
The Full Moon Theater of Portugal will present the interactive play for Bebeethoven Babies, in which babies will be "taken into the fantasy world of notes and light and shadow", accompanied by "Sonata to the moonlight of Bebeethoven".
The event promises special programs, under the theme “East-Kidade Meeting, Asia in Harmony” of the “East Asia City of Culture” program. The South Korea Push Theater will present the multimedia play “Poli Pop”, in which a child's room is transformed into a playground. The play a day of astronaut will bring a “space station” to the stage and “an immersive and interactive orbital adventure with cosmic environments” so that viewers “feel in the vastness of the universe” can be read in the statement.
Other selected projects will also be presented at the festival, as part of the “Commissioning of Performative Arts Productions 2024-2026”. "The Hamsters of Chong Chong" is a play produced by the puppet theater "Rolling Puppet", co-created by Nick Yu, Chinese playwright, and his son, Godot Yu. The play combines puppets, immersive sound effects, video and music in a “vibrant stage experience”. According to the IC, this show "transforms life lessons into a soft artistic language" and shows "how life is fantastic, in a wreck of emotions."
The Chinese orchestra of Macao, in turn, will return to “unite forces” with the vocal group Cappella “Water Singers” in the play “Varinha Magic Music IV - the percussive struggle against King Taurus”. The work conjugates Chinese music, sing Cappella and animated and entertaining theater and leads the audience “to feel the charm of Chinese music”, with iconic scenes from the “West Travel - The Battle against King Taurus”. Already the musical play “whispering the zodiac: the choir concert of the Chinese zodiac” will be presented by the three schools of the Macao do IC Conservatory and will share the stories of the 12 “small animals”.
In addition to the shows, the organization will launch sessions of the “creative camp for children” and “family artistic camp”. Participants will be able to camp at the Cultural Center, participate in art workshops and make a night visit to the Art Museum, "to enjoy the pleasure of art from a new perspective."
At the Macao International Festival for Children of Macau will be presented outdoor projections and “excellent works”, such as “Snow White and Seven Dwarfs” and “Where the Monsters live”, based on the illustrated book that sold over 19 million copies around the world. The festival will be divided into five sections, including “Outdoor Projections”, “From Book to the Movie, Abracadabra”, “Classics for All Children”, “Annual Children's Movie Selection” and “Community Projects”.
According to the IC statement, the Film Festival will spread for the first time "its festive atmosphere for the community." Projections in libraries and museums, among other places, as well as other activities will allow “adults and children to explore the fun of the film world”.
The more than 35 workshops presented by the festival cover music, theater, painting and dance “for all ages”. To children's workshops, “Fun Chinese Opera”, “Creation of Adventure Drama” and “Body is Fun”, will follow sharing sessions so that participants can show the results of learning. In the “Casa Magic das Star” workshop, designed for children with special educational needs, instructors will inspire the younger ones to “develop their imagination and move the body”.
The music workshop for families "colorful fun for babes" will give parents "trying out small games with their babies to stimulate their curiosity." In the workshop “Beginners in Music”, in turn, young people will be able to know the classics and practice basic singing, dance and action, in order to better understand musical theater.
Finally, in the “Golden Voices for Senior Voices” and “Happy Rhythm of the Seniors” workshops, the elderly will be able to demonstrate their musical and dance talents “in a relaxed and interactive way,” says the IC.
Vacancies are limited and some activities require payment of a fee.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cheong and Sala debut new works at CCCM</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cheong-sala-estreiam-novas-obras-cccm/</link><description>The Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) in Lisbon inaugurated on Thursday “The Slazes and Curious Travel”, a new show of contemporary art and visual anthropology of Cheong Kin Man and Marta Stanisława Room in collaboration with German filmmaker Deborah Uhde.
In speaking at the ceremony, Carmen Mendes, president of CCCM, classified the initiative of “exceptional”. "They are artists who work on cultural links through art, travel to parallel worlds, personal archive, as well as linguistic experiments such as the musicality of Cantonense poetry, invented languages, ideograms that exist only in fiction," he said.
Several works by Cheong and Room debuted at the show, namely the installation in textile and bamboo “The Utopia compass”, with 13 fabrics representing the universe, in a construction that alludes to the scaffolding in bamboo. Part of the work was supported by the East Foundation and Municipalities of Krakow and Nuremberg.
"Another work worthy of mention," according to the leader of the research center, is "Entrevista, Między-Widzenie, Roz-Mowa, Loccation," a "experimental and experimental project that is based on a series of interviews on the Macanese diaspora."
Also in debut comes a set of nine palimpses in chemical paper with phrases in Cantonese and Polish letters. Called “Flora Macanensis”, the work results from the duo's show, with the same title and on the clandestine arrival of Cheong's mother to Macao in the 1980s. This exhibition took place in the Polish city of Katowice between January and February this year.
The anthropologist in turn exposes an individual work "the process of thought." It is a 30 -meter roller with acrylic ink in which abstract symbols are used to evoke writing function as a visual system.
Carlos Enrique Valencia Muñoz, plenipotentiary minister of the Colombia Embassy in Lisbon, Katarzyna O'Neill, representative of the Poland ambassador, as well as Jana Binder, director of Goethe-Institut Portugal and Rui Dantas, director of the CCCM Macao Museum, attended the inauguration.
The exhibition “The Slazes and Curious Travel” is curated by researcher Lorena Tabares Salamanca and the high sponsorship of the embassies of Poland and Colombia. It has the support of the Ministry of Culture and National Heritage and the Adam Mickiewicz Institute of Poland, as well as the partnership of the municipality of Krakow, Goethe-Institut Portugal and Boym Institute of Poland.</description><pubDate>2025-06-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ana de Armas is better to kill than to dance in “Ballerina”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/ana-de-armas-e-melhor-matar-dancar-em-bailarina/</link><description>JOCELYN NOVECK*
You begin to think that everyone is a killer. The type of newspaper bank, the street musician, the passenger of the metro, that friendly neighbor in the elevator - relentless salary killers, all.
So, maybe it's not that surprising that in “from John Wick's world: dancer,” the latest movie in the Wickian universe, come to the logical end: a city where each inhabitant is a killer. Yes, it is a snowy and picturesque winter landscape in Austria, where everyone wears wool caps and very beautiful nightgowns. But they also wield a relentless launcher, and school-age children have a mandatory shooting training.
The initial scenes in this crazy place on top of the mountains are the best part of “The Ballerina” - they really contain ingenious surprises and even a touch of humor, which we would hardly expect from a John Wick movie. (Have you ever seen the type smile?) Seeing our energy star Ana de Armas, participating in a competition to leave dishes with a sweet table maid that has become a cruel murderer reminds us that the action can be intelligent, even though most scenes in this series become inevitably numbing as bodies count stretch.
Before we go on, some clarifications about where this movie fits the timeline. Let's forget (for now) that there was a John Wick 4, because the events of "The Ballerina" happen during the third movie. Thus, erase from your mind any striking and transformative event that may or may not have happened in the last movie. Right?
For Ana de Arma, Keanu Reeves colleague for 10 years and once again, “The Ballerina” is a pirouette.
Eagle -eyed spectators may recall a brief scene in the third movie in which a dancer tries to make a series of Fouettés, those one -legged whip curves that are a big attraction in “The Swan Lake”. The same scene returns to "The Ballerina", with the character of Armai, Eve, trying to stubbornly master them in training. Why does it continue to fall - every time, after years and years of classes - it's a mystery.
We do not seek total realism in action movies, guys, but we can suggest that falling to the floor with the tips sneakers each time a curve looks like a much harder stunt than anything else in “The Ballerina” - including annihilating a horde of inhabitants of the city. This also demonstrates a worrying lack of coordination, a definitive problem for a killer.
Anyway! In fact, we first met Eve as a child, living alone with his dear father in a wind residence swept by the wind. Suddenly a team of black killers arrived by the sea, aiming at the father. It can protect Eve, but dies as a result of the injuries.
Soon, Eve, now orphan, is approached by Winston (Ian McShane, return), owner of the continental hotel. Winston says he can take her to his father's family. He takes her to the director (the arrogant Anjelica Huston), who welcomes the aspiring dancer in what appears to be an elite ballet gym, but is also the Ruska Roma training field, the criminal organization where Wick himself learned his craft.
The years pass. Eve is now a young woman determined to walk her own way, although she still has difficulty completing a Fouetté's return. Fortunately, she shows more aptitude with firearms. And this is important because its main objective is to avenge the death of the father. So when Wick himself (Keanu Reeves, of course, appearing in some important scenes) makes a crucial stop at the gym, Eve looks at him and asks, "How do I leave here?"
“The front door is unlocked,” says Wick - a speech that deserved applause in the exhibition I was in, but also just about everything Wick said or did. "No, how do I start doing what you do?" Asks Eve. Wick says she can still leave - has the option of rejecting a killer's life. The sad subtext: he is not.
But while Wick wants to leave - always - Eve wants to come in. Otherwise, we would not have a movie. And so, her search for revenge takes her, the dangerous track (and against the strict orders of the director), to Hallstatt's snow village. Then the fearsome chancellor (Gabriel Byrne, properly cold) leads a bunch of killers - all who want to kill her. Oh, and more: the chancellor killed his father.
And then Eve has to fight, using all the training and mill that has accumulated. A lesson she must learn from a trust teacher: "Fight like a girl."
In this case, as you might imagine, this is not a derogatory phrase. What it means is to use your strengths-you will not overcome a man by brute force, the teacher told him, but with intelligence and inventiveness.
This means using increasingly interesting weapons to kill an infinite supply of people (it must be said, the applause of viewers are, as always, disconcerting). And in the end, you can be quite comfortable with a flames.
 
*Journalist of the Associated Press specializing in culture and gender, as well as film critic.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>