<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Ella Lei calls for salary increases in public service and large companies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ella-lei-pede-aumentos-salariais-na-funcao-publica-grandes-empresas/</link><description>Increasing salaries in the public sector and in large companies was one of the requests made by deputy Ella Lei, who pointed out that residents continue to feel economic “pressure”. In this sense, he suggested even more incentives for consumption, remembering that those currently in force end at the end of the month. Song Pek Kei, in turn, defended the creation of “a fair remuneration and allowance regime” in the public service
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Ella Lei yesterday urged the Government to study “increasing the salaries of public servants, encouraging gaming concessionaires or public utility companies, among other large companies or those with the conditions to do so, to increase salaries”. The deputy also asked the Executive to launch “more specific” consumption incentives to “increase domestic demand, boost consumption and alleviate pressure on residents”.
In the period before the agenda, in the Legislative Assembly, the deputy linked to the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau cited recent surveys that have demonstrated “the lack of consumer confidence, who are entering a phase of prudence”, in addition to pointing out that “measures to stimulate short-term consumption can produce positive effects, reinforcing consumer confidence”.
“Families are faced with great economic pressures, so it’s not even worth talking about confidence in consumption,” he said, adding: “Even the salaries of public servants, which are capable of being adjusted, have only been increased once in recent years.”
In this sense, Ella Lei said she hopes that the Government “carries out studies on the timely updating of public servants’ salaries to boost their morale”. “It can also appeal to and encourage large companies with conditions, for example, gaming concessionaires or public utility entities, to rationally increase the salaries of their workers, with a view to stimulating domestic demand and increasing confidence in consumption”, he suggested.
Recalling that the authorities recently renewed the “Great prize for consumption in community areas”, the deputy also recalled that it ends at the end of this month. In this sense, he stated that “residents hope that the authorities, in addition to continuously monitoring the variation in product prices, will consider including more incentives or support for consumption in the Lines of Government Action for next year, which will not only boost the economy, but also, and more importantly, grant, in a simple way, a subsidy for daily expenses to residents, to alleviate their pressure, in conjunction with the various measures for the well-being of the population”.
In turn, Congresswoman Song Pek Kei argued that, in the new context of Administration reform, the Government must “improve the performance evaluation mechanism and create a fair remuneration and allowance regime”.
Pointing out that public servants have “worked hard”, Song Pek Kei stressed that, over the years, their requests “have not been properly met”. “For example, civil servants in the lowest categories who live with difficulties are not supported, and those who joined the social security scheme, after retiring, are not entitled to the residence allowance and are not treated fairly”, he considered.</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Minimum wage increase approved after little discussion in AL</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/aprovado-aumento-salario-minimo-apos-pouca-discussao-na-al/</link><description>The Legislative Assembly yesterday discussed the proposed law that provides for an increase in the universal minimum wage to 35 patacas per hour, with only one deputy asking questions about the matter. The diploma ended up being approved, in general, but with abstentions from three deputies
 
The proposal to revise the universal minimum wage law in the Macao SAR, which provides for increases from the current 34 patacas per hour to 35 and from 7,072 patacas per month to 7,280, was approved yesterday, in general, by the Legislative Assembly (AL). Even so, the three deputies linked to the Public Service Workers Association – Pereira Coutinho, Chan Hao Weng and Che Sai Wang – abstained.
In introducing the diploma, the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, highlighted that this increase will benefit around 18,200 workers, representing 4.4% of the total, excluding domestic workers. The main beneficiary groups will be workers in the building administration and cleaning services sectors.
On the matter, only one deputy asked questions. “Until now, there are still no clear concepts or quantitative measurement criteria in Macau, nor have explicit foundations been disclosed” for adjusting the minimum wage, lamented Che Sai Wang, urging the Government to “try to quantify, as much as possible, the reference bases”.
The deputy praised the HKSAR authorities' approach of annually reviewing the minimum wage and publishing annual reports online with the rationale for adjustments. Furthermore, he highlighted that the minimum wage has been adjusted annually in Taiwan in the last decade, praising the participation of experts in studies on the subject.
In response, the Secretary for Economy and Finance stated that this review took into account Macau's economic situation between 2020 and 2024, including the support capacity of companies and residents during that period. Regarding the models of neighboring regions mentioned by Che Sai Wang, Tai Kin Ip highlighted that the MSAR is a micro-economy, susceptible to external fluctuations, and therefore has distinct characteristics.
“When guaranteeing the rights and interests of workers, it is necessary to comprehensively consider residents, employers and small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs), especially the support capacity of residents in the face of the percentage increase [of the minimum wage]”, highlighted the Secretary, reiterating the importance of having a “general consideration”.
Guaranteeing that the increase was proposed after hearing the opinions of labor and employer parties and the Permanent Council for Social Coordination, Tai Kin Ip emphasized that the adjustment to the minimum wage, in addition to being flexible, corresponds to the current situation and the Macao SAR's own conditions and “involved the evaluation of many factors”.
Na declaração de voto, Lam Lon Wai, Ella Lei, Leong Sun Iok e Leong Pou U apontaram para situações de “atraso” na execução do actual mecanismo de revisão ao salário mínimo, pedindo ao Governo que melhore o mecanismo, através da combinação de “fórmulas e indicadores mais científicos”, de modo a que as actualizações “se adaptem à situação de desenvolvimento económico e representem uma devida garantia para os trabalhadores”. Além disso, apelaram ao Governo para lançar “mais medidas pragmáticas” em prol da população de baixo rendimento e dos trabalhadores carenciados.
Chui Sai Peng, Ip Sio Kai, Si Ka Lon and Kevin Ho warned, in their voting declaration, of “a series of chain reactions” following the implementation of the new minimum wage, especially in the building administration sector. Thus, they defended reinforced support for SMEs in difficulties, such as the interest-free loan measure and the subsidy of water and electricity tariffs.
Também Chan Lai Kei, Song Pek Kei e Nick Lei mostraram preocupação com o impacto da revisão do salário mínimo e do “consequente aumento da taxa de gestão predial” nas famílias de baixo rendimento, instando o Executivo e prestar apoio às famílias vulneráveis. Por seu turno, Loi I Weng e Wong Kit Cheng sugeriram um plano de apoio à remuneração para subsidiar os empregadores que adoptem medidas “amigas da família”.
 
Marketing of gold and platinum will follow new rules
The Legislative Assembly generally approved the proposal for the “Gold and platinum marketing regime”, which advocates higher standards for platinum, gold-plated and gold-coated articles. Several deputies expressed attention to gold inspections and testing. According to the Secretary for Economy and Finance, preliminary surveys indicate that, in general, gold items sold in the territory meet the new standards. Furthermore, a small number of stores that do not comply with the new standards will have sufficient time for the transition, as the diploma provides for a transitional period of 90 days. Explaining that the increase in standards is based on practice in neighboring regions, Tai Kin Ip clarified that traders can adopt even higher criteria. Furthermore, he assured that the Government will continue to exchange views with the sector, to analyze the feasibility of creating a local gold testing entity. According to Choi Sao Leng, head of the Department of Licensing and Inspection of Economic and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), between 2020 and October this year, authorities carried out 1,383 inspections of gold retailers, having opened 180 cases. In the last five years, the DSEDT has received only two complaints, one of which was related to the failure to post a gold notice and the other involved a suspected case of fake gold. For the same person in charge, the self-discipline of local gold retailers “gives people confidence”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Expanded digital services for citizens and businesses</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/expandidos-servicos-digitais-para-cidadaos-empresas/</link><description>The Administration and Public Service Services announced yesterday a series of new features for the Single Account and the Platform for Companies and Associations. Among others, we highlight car insurance and license renewal services for companies and professionals and real estate registrations. Furthermore, in this new phase of expansion of e-governance, new smart lockers and remote service counters were installed in Macau and Hengqin
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
The Government continues to consolidate the digitalization of public services, with more and more government departments and types of services available on the Single Account and the Platform for Companies and Associations, as announced yesterday by Chan Chi Kin. In a press conference, the deputy director of Administration and Public Service Services (SAFP), informed that users of both applications can now take advantage of new administrative services and digital functionalities from various public entities.
Residents who own vehicles can now use the Single Account to renew their car insurance, one month before it expires. In addition to consulting information about drivers and vehicles, the new features include a reminder service for insurance renewal, as well as an option to pay for it. Chan said that, in the first phase, the solution will apply exclusively to customers of the China Tai Ping Insurance Company, adding that the Government will invite “more insurance companies to join this service”.
Regarding the Platform for Companies and Associations, entities can link their registered vehicles to check and pay fines and annual road tax.
As part of the renewal of licenses, the Government also added the services of five more public entities and 23 types of licensing to the Platform for Companies and Associations. In total, the application now has 55 types of license renewal services available that concern seven government entities. The platform allows you to consult information regarding licenses and receive a renewal notice, in a process that Chan Chi Kin argued is simpler and more effective. Furthermore, the “Certified Store” Program is also now available on the same platform.
Soon, students will be able to apply for a scholarship for higher education, through the Single Account, which will also include a refund functionality. This month, the same application will have an “Exclusive Zone for Parents”, with different types of services, related to school admission, daycare, declarations and request for subsidies, in coordination with the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services, the Institute of Social Action and Health Services. On the Companies and Associations Platform, a request can be made for a license to operate tutoring rooms.
From December onwards, the Single Account will also allow users to register the acquisition of a property or mortgage as well as issue certificates.
In total, the Single Account already includes 480 types of services, available to 670 thousand users. In turn, the Platform for Companies and Associations provides 180 services for 20 thousand users. Regarding the electronic notification system, which aims to replace legal written communication, 220 thousand people are registered.
 
More smart lockers and self-service counters
The Macao SAR's “Easy Collection” system now covers eight more public service entities and 51 types of services, as of yesterday, said Chan Chi Kin. Currently, 11 entities already provide 126 types of services to the population, through smart lockers, allowing citizens to automatically collect documents issued by the Government, such as certificates and licenses, within a 24-hour period.
In December this year, the Government will also install a smart locker at the Public Service Provision Center of the Deep Cooperation Zone in Hengqin, in order to “make [life] even easier for Macau residents” and “prevent them from crossing the border to collect documents”. According to Chan Chi Kin, since the Macao SAR implemented the system in June last year, it has already exceeded 25 thousand users, with “satisfactory reactions”.
“Easy Collection” has already been installed in eight 24-hour Self-Service Centers in the Macao SAR and in the “New Neighborhood of Macau” in Hengqin. The Government expects that, next year, more public services will be integrated, in a phased manner, into the program.
For “direct handling of cross-border formalities”, two new remote service counters were also installed in the “New Neighborhood of Macau”, providing a total of 175 types of services.
At the Service Center on Avenida Venceslau de Morais, three remote service counters are now available, in order to serve citizens in Macau, in the treatment of 120 types of services provided by six public entities in Hengqin. These services refer to the consultation of relevant information on commercial, tax, real estate and notary matters.</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Portugal and Macau deepen protocol in the pharmaceutical area</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/portugal-macau-aprofundam-protocolo-na-area-farmaceutica/</link><description>Topics related to pharmaceutical supervision were discussed in Lisbon between the Institute for Pharmaceutical Supervision and Administration of Macau and INFARMED. Focusing on strengthening exchanges and cooperation in the areas of medicines, medical devices and pharmaceutical services, as well as the promotion and development of traditional Chinese medicine products
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
A delegation from the Institute for Pharmaceutical Supervision and Administration (ISAF) traveled to Lisbon to deepen exchanges and cooperation between Macau and Portugal in areas related to industry, specifically medicines, medical devices and pharmaceutical services, as well as promoting the development of traditional Chinese medicine products abroad.
ISAF visited the National Authority for Medicines and Health Products, I. P. (INFARMED), with both parties exchanging opinions on pharmaceutical supervision and discussing aspects of updating the content of the cooperation protocol signed in 1999. The objective was to “further promote the common development of the two parties in the areas of technical exchange, collaboration in supervision and administration, as well as market expansion”, according to a statement from ISAF.
Considering the “significant changes” in the scope of supervision, administration and legislation of medicines and medical devices in Portugal and the European Union in recent years, the president of INFARMED, Rui Santos Ivo, expressed his desire to “further deepen bilateral cooperation in the area of ​​pharmaceutical supervision” through the renewal of the cooperation protocol with the Macao SAR.
Meanwhile, the president of ISAF, Choi Peng Cheong, said he hopes that, through deepening cooperation, it will be possible to promote “the entry of quality traditional Chinese medicine products from Macau into the markets of Portugal and the European Union”. In this sense, he believes that Macau “plays the role of a bridge for exchange between Chinese and Western cultures”.
Both sides exchanged views on expanding the scope of cooperation from medicines to medical devices and strengthening technical exchange on Good Manufacturing Practices and Good Clinical Practices for medicines and medical devices and communication on information related to quality testing and safety, modern management and training.
The Macao SAR delegation paid a visit to the Faculty of Pharmacy of the University of Lisbon to learn about the situation of Portugal's development in the areas of pharmacy education, community pharmacy, pharmaceutical care for the elderly and the transformation of scientific research results.
The delegation also visited Hovione, which established a pharmaceutical factory in Macau in 1986, and which has extensive experience in the research, development and production of medicines. Another stop was a community pharmacy, “to learn about how community pharmacies use smart technologies to optimize the management and dispensing process of medicines, as well as consultation services and individual health management for patients”, highlights the ISAF note.</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Academics advocate strengthening the focus on electric vehicles</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/academicos-defendem-reforco-da-aposta-nos-veiculos-electricos/</link><description>The Macao SAR needs to develop its infrastructure to support electric vehicles and the public transport system, argues a recent study. The authors state that the suggested measures could mitigate Macau's air pollution, as well as guarantee the region's energy security.
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
The authors of the study “How does the transport sector affect energy consumption in Macau?” state that the promotion of electric vehicles (EV) and vehicles powered by alternative fuels “is crucial”, arguing that “these measures should focus on expanding charging infrastructure, granting tax incentives and supporting research and development of battery technologies”. This research analyzed the relationship between the transport sector and energy consumption in Macau, with the authors listing some recommendations for policy measures to help Macau “become a sustainable energy-saving city”.
Bingjie Xu, from the City University of Macau, and Arshian Sharif, from Korea University, also argue that the Government should prioritize investment in the development of efficient public transport systems, cycle paths and pedestrian infrastructure, in addition to continuing to encourage the population to use public transport services and subsidize them, in order to reduce the use of private cars. Furthermore, “it is essential to launch awareness campaigns and involve the public in understanding the positive impacts of sustainable transport on energy conservation”. These campaigns should target individuals, communities and organizations “to encourage the adoption of greener travel habits and promote a culture of sustainable transport”.
“Macau, as a consuming city highly dependent on imported energy, needs to recognize the importance of energy security and sustainability and take proactive measures”, warn Bingjie Xu and Arshian Sharif. “By diversifying energy supplies, improving energy efficiency, promoting the development of clean energy and promoting innovative technologies, Macau can achieve sustainable energy use, reduce emissions and create a sustainable transport system for a green future”, assert the authors.
“The increase in the number of motor vehicles has caused a series of problems and has become a significant challenge in Macau”, it reads. Due to its geographic limitations and lack of resources, Macau relies heavily on importing energy for consumption. The Macao SAR imports energy resources such as gasoline, diesel, kerosene, jet fuel, fuel oil, liquefied petroleum gas, natural gas and electricity from several countries. In 2023, gasoline and “light diesel” represented, respectively, 46.95% and 45.65% of energy sources in the transport sector.
The growth in the number of vehicles in circulation, researchers warn, generates problems of air pollution and traffic congestion, which, in turn, also worsens the deterioration of air quality. Excessive emissions of pollutants such as carbon monoxide, nitrogen oxides and other particulates have a negative impact on public health, increasing the risk of respiratory illnesses and other health problems for residents. “The problems of traffic congestion and energy consumption are particularly prominent in Macau because it is a busy international tourist city,” they emphasize.
In fact, data from the Statistics and Census Services Directorate indicates that the number of registered vehicles has risen consistently since 2023. The need for EV support infrastructure is even more urgent, considering that the number of this category of vehicles almost doubled from the end of 2023 to the month of August this year. In December 2023, there were 8,131 EVs registered in the Macao SAR, while in August 2025 there were already 15,088 (+85.56%). However, in the first eight months of this year, of the 7,708 vehicles with new registrations, 2,918 were electric, representing 37.9% of the total, which indicates that there is still a preference for cars with combustion engines.
Researchers Bingjie Xu and Arshian Sharif consider that vehicle emissions represent around 70% of total urban air pollution and that “the transport industry is responsible for a large proportion of global warming”. "The transport sector is responsible for more than half of the world's oil demand and contributes almost a quarter of carbon dioxide emissions. In particular, cars and engines that use diesel cause serious air pollution, resulting in millions of premature deaths every year."
In addition to contributing to the emission of greenhouse gases, and being one of the main sectors responsible for increasing energy consumption, transport also influences energy prices, researchers argue.</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Jurisprudence on breach of security deposit established</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/fixada-jurisprudencia-sobre-quebra-da-caucao/</link><description>O TUI fixou jurisprudência sobre a quebra da caução, considerando que “é possível responsabilizar o arguido pelo seu incumprimento anterior das obrigações decorrentes da caução após a prolação da sentença absolutória”
 
The Public Prosecutor's Office (MP) filed an extraordinary appeal with the Court of Final Instance (TUI) to establish jurisprudence in relation to two agreements issued by the Court of Second Instance (TSI), since, in its opinion, they are “in opposition, in the field of the same legislation and on the same question of law”. One was delivered in 2022 and the other in 2024.
According to the statement from the Office of the President of the TUI, the MP understands that the two agreements “adopted opposing solutions regarding the question of whether, during the process, if the defendant has violated the obligations arising from the bond coercion measure, the court can, after issuing an acquittal ruling, declare the reversion of the bond amount to the Macao SAR”.
When considering the appeal, the TUI Panel stated that article 192 of the Code of Criminal Procedure “expressly” provided that the legislator immediately considers the bail to be broken when there is an unjustified absence by the defendant of the procedural act to which he must attend or failure to comply with obligations that have been imposed on him, and the respective amount must immediately revert to the Macao SAR. Thus, by the expressions “the deposit is considered broken” and “its value reverts to the Macao SAR”, the legislator reveals that the legal effects of the breach of the security occur in accordance with the law, from the moment of its breach, regardless of a judicial declaration of reversion to the Macao SAR, he considered.
Furthermore, although it is expected that the coercive measures will be extinguished immediately with the acquittal sentence, “this extinction is limited only to the fact that the defendant is no longer subject to coercive measures after the acquittal sentence is handed down, without prejudice to the responsibilities and legal consequences arising from the previous breach of obligations”.
In the opinion of the TUI, the rules established in that article “aim to guarantee compliance with the obligations imposed on him and his attendance at the procedural act”. “If with the delivery of the acquittal sentence it became impossible to hold the agent responsible for his previous failure to comply with the inherent obligations, the function of the deposit as a coercive measure would be weakened”, emphasizes the TUI Collective.
Basically, he understands that “it is possible to hold the defendant responsible for his previous failure to comply with the obligations arising from the bail after the acquittal sentence has been handed down”.
Therefore, the appeal was upheld, establishing the mandatory jurisprudence for the Macao SAR Courts: “If the breach of the security deposit occurred before the delivery of the acquittal sentence has been verified, the judicial confirmation of the assumptions of the breach of the security deposit after the acquittal sentence does not prevent the application of the provisions of article 192 of the Code of Criminal Procedure”. The establishment of jurisprudence was published yesterday in the Official Bulletin.
 
Electronic platform completed for the Courts and DSI
The creation of the electronic services platform has already been completed by the Courts and the Directorate of Identification Services (DSI) so that the Courts can submit the application for the Criminal Record Certificate and consult the information electronically, they indicated in a statement. At the same time, DSI issues electronic certificates to the Courts, thus replacing the traditional model of paper correspondence, increasing the efficiency of work through technology, reinforcing the interconnection and interconnection of data between the two parties, “expanding the scope of activities of both parties without the use of paper”.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Next academic year “takes” UM to the Cooperation Zone</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/proximo-ano-lectivo-leva-um-para-zona-de-cooperacao/</link><description>The Deep Cooperation Zone in Hengqin will “open doors” to some courses at the University of Macau in the next academic year 2026/2027. In the transition phase, courses will be taught in two Transitional Research and Education Centers. Artificial Intelligence, robotics and finance are some of the areas to be taught on the other side of the border
 
Starting from the next academic year, 2026/2027, the University of Macau (UM) will teach some of its courses at the new campus in the Deep Cooperation Zone, in Hengqin, the institution announced. UM, remember, will be the first local higher education institution to “cross over” to the other side of the border and serving as an example for the rest.
By creating a campus in the Cooperation Zone, UM intends to train more talents to respond to the industrial development needs of both the Macao SAR and the Cooperation Zone. Therefore, during the transition period, some of UM's postgraduate programs are offered in the Cooperation Zone, according to a statement.
During the transition period, the teaching and research activities of the new faculties that will be established on the UM campus in the Cooperation Zone – including the Faculty of Medicine, the Faculty of Science and Information Technology, the Faculty of Engineering and the Faculty of Design – are carried out in two Transitional Research and Education Centers in the Cooperation Zone.
With a main focus on postgraduate education, in 2026/2027, these Centers will offer postgraduate programs and research activities focused on artificial intelligence, Internet of Things, robotics and autonomous systems, microelectronics, smart electrical grids, public health, visual communication design, finance, business analysis, computer science, electrical and computer engineering, electromechanical engineering, construction project management and data science.
“In addition, UM is committed to training high-level and well-educated talents for society and offers a variety of scholarships and financial aid to postgraduate students,” says the institution, which include the UM Doctoral Scholarship, the UM Doctoral Research and Teaching Assistantship Scholarship and the University of Macau Scholarship for Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM) Programs.
UM is accepting applications until March 13th for the doctoral, master's and postgraduate certificate programs for the academic year 2026/2027.</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Financial investments generated revenue of 16.8 billion in 2024</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/investimentos-financeiros-geraram-receitas-de-168-mil-milhoes-em-2024/</link><description>The report on the execution of the 2024 budget was presented to AL. According to the document, net revenues from financial investments reached 16.81 billion patacas, 1.63 billion less than in 2023
 
The Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, presented the report on the execution of the 2024 budget to the Legislative Assembly (AL) yesterday. The document indicates that net revenues from financial investments amounted to 16.81 billion patacas, representing a reduction of 1.63 billion compared to 2023.
This downward variation was fundamentally due to the fact that the global financial market suffered more fluctuations last year, which also led to an increase in financial expenses in relation to 2023.
Furthermore, last year, the authorized budget for ordinary revenue was 107.1 billion, with an effective revenue of 116 billion, representing an annual increase of 15.5%. Specifically, “current revenues” registered an increase of 25.68 billion patacas, while “capital revenues” registered a decrease of 10.06 billion patacas.
No ano em análise, o orçamento autorizado da despesa ordinária integrada atingiu 105,9 mil milhões, com a despesa efectiva a situar-se em 97,95 mil milhões, traduzindo-se numa subida de 8,1% face a 2023.
As “despesas correntes” ascenderam a um total de 78,16 mil milhões de patacas, com um aumento de 8,5 mil milhões em relação a 2023, enquanto as “despesas de capital” no Plano de Investimentos e Despesas de Desenvolvimento de Administração (PIDDA) registaram 19,78 mil milhões, representando uma descida anual de 1,19 mil milhões.
Within the scope of “Capital expenditure”, the initial PIDDA budget for 2024 was 17.41 billion and the authorized amount was 19.09 billion, with the actual expenditure (17.68 billion) corresponding to an execution rate of 92.6%. Compared to 2023, PIDDA's actual expenditure decreased by 10.1%.
On the other hand, until September of this year, the Macao SAR Financial Reserve totaled 657.9 billion. The basic reserve stood at 167.2 billion and the extraordinary reserve at 490.6 billion.
Also in AL, the Commissioner of Audit, Elsie Ao Ieong U, presented the Audit Report of the 2024 General Account. In addition to the revenues and expenses amounting to around 116.1 billion and 97.9 billion patacas, respectively, the Commissioner completed the audit of the total assets of the Macao SAR's integrated ordinary account worth 83.3 billion patacas. According to the audit, the final balance of the Financial Reserve was around 616.2 billion patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Double aging” requires more measures for families</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/duplo-envelhecimento-requer-mais-medidas-para-familias/</link><description>Representative Chan Lai Kei defended the extension of the caregiver allowance for elderly people from families with “double aging” and an incentive program for elderly volunteers. Loi I Weng wants the link between the elderly allowance and pension and the consumer price index
 
Expanding the scope of the allowance for caregivers, to alleviate the difficulties and concerns of “double aging families”, was one of the proposals made by deputy Chan Lai Kei, in the period before the agenda, in the Legislative Assembly. “In an aging society, the pressure from ‘double-aged families’ is even greater, as ‘the elderly are the ones who take care of the elderly’”, he lamented.
Therefore, he argued that they need support in terms of health care and also economic support from society. "I propose that the Government study expanding the scope of application of the current subsidy for caregivers of healthy elderly people from 'double aging families', especially with healthy elderly people of very advanced age. This is a more humane act that recognizes the contribution of elderly people from this type of families, which shares economic pressure, supports the idea of ​​'keeping elderly people at home' and achieves the objective of social inclusion", he stated.
Chan Lai Kei also suggested that technological equipment be introduced for the elderly to operate on an experimental basis in the Residence for the Elderly, “offering financial support to those who are advanced in age or have chronic illnesses, who live in old buildings without elevators or who have already requested the allocation of social housing”.
On the other hand, he defended the creation of a “Volunteer Elderly Incentive Program” to reward those who have provided certain hours of service, “in favor of promoting the future development of the value of social inclusion for the elderly”.
In the same context, deputy Loi I Weng pointed to the challenges of low birth rates and high aging, considering that it is necessary for the Government to adopt a “more systematic and prospective” political vision, intervening from the definition of policies and planning, in a scientific way, the coordination of policies, resources and services, in order to create a support network for families that covers the entire family life cycle”.
Specifically, he defended the link between the pension and allowance for the elderly and the consumer price index, “to guarantee the quality of life of the elderly, reduce the pressure on care and achieve the objective of family development”.
He also highlighted the need to reduce waiting times for healthcare for adults and homes, as well as promoting the development of artificial intelligence and smart community care services, both for children and the elderly.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Gross retail surplus fell by 45% in 2024</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/excedente-bruto-retalho-baixou-45-em-2024/</link><description>The gross surplus of retail trade decreased by almost 45% to around 6.9 billion patacas in 2024, reflecting the impact of the 17.5% drop in revenue, according to official data
 
In the general calculation of 2024, revenues from the wholesale and retail sector in Macau reached 126.18 billion patacas, illustrating an annual drop of 8.4%, while expenses fell 6.7% to 115.39 billion, reveal data released by the Statistics and Census Service (DSEC). Thus, the sector's gross surplus fell 29.6% to 11.61 billion patacas in annual terms.
The decline in gross surplus was more pronounced in the retail sector, translating into an annual decline of 44.8% to 6.87 billion patacas between 2023 and 2024.
Retail revenues amounted to 72.43 billion patacas (down 17.5%), with DSEC highlighting the declines in warehouses and trinkets (down 26.5%, watches and jewelery items (down 23.3%) and leather goods (down 22.2%). On the other hand, expenses (65.81 billion) grew 14.8% in the space of one year.
In turn, the volume of revenue from the vehicle and fuel trade sector rose 2.4% to 5.79 billion patacas and expenses increased by 6.8% to 5.46 billion, leading to a gross surplus of 445 million (25.1% less).
Official statistics also show that income from tenants in municipal markets and street vendors with a fixed place (837 million) and expenses (731 million) increased by 1.2% and 4.0%, respectively, compared to 2023. In this sector, the gross surplus was 105 million (14.5% less).
In 2024, wholesale trade recorded revenues of 47.13 billion patacas (up 8.4%), expenses of 43.40 billion (up 6.8%) and a gross surplus of 4.19 billion (up 8.4%).
In 2024, 6,972 wholesale trade establishments were active in the territory (two fewer than in the previous year), 7,666 retail trade establishments (171 more), 1,125 vehicles and fuels trade (18 less) and 1,160 tenants in municipal markets and street vendors with a fixed place (14 more).</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hostel hosts festival that promotes patriotism</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/albergue-acolhe-festival-promove-patriotismo/</link><description>The thematic exhibition “Ecos Eternos” is taking place at the Albergue and presents a diverse program, with film screenings, debates with filmmakers and workshops. Promoted by the Círculo dos Amigos da Cultura, the event marks the anniversary of the end of the Second World War

VÍTOR REBELO
 
The Film Festival and Exhibition “Echoes Eternos: Remembering War and Peace” takes place at Gallery D1 of Albergue da Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macau until the 15th of November. The initiative, carried out by CAC – Círculo dos Amigos da Cultura, uses the power of cinematographic art through film screenings, exhibitions and creative workshops “to preserve the memory of the war, promote patriotism and inspire the public, especially young people, to get involved with history and cultural heritage”, says the organization.
The exhibition will feature seven films, presenting behind-the-scenes materials and exploring their historical context, along with artefacts and content from six other featured films.
“Visitors will experience a rich mix of film scenes, historical comparisons, archival materials and dialogue, offering a comprehensive exploration of the history of war and the values ​​of peace and justice,” highlights the CAC. The exhibition is free, encouraging public involvement “with this important cultural and historical discourse”.
The film festival itself features 14 screenings at the Bona International Cineplex, showing a selection of films that “balance historical significance and artistic merit”. Highlights include the 2025 premieres of “731” and “Dongji Rescue,” along with acclaimed classics like “Railway Heroes,” “The Message,” “The Eight Hundred” and “Bloody Battle of Taierzhuang.”
The 4K restored version of the timeless masterpiece “The Spring River Flows East” (1947, Parts I and II) will also be shown. These films offer a multidimensional perspective, linking China's victory in the War of Resistance to the global narrative of the Anti-Fascist War.
The highlight of the festival is the launch and screening ceremony of “731” next Saturday. The event will be attended by director Zhao Linshan and actor Li Shanyu, who will share behind-the-scenes insights and creative inspirations. This discussion offers “a rare opportunity” to explore the film’s historical and artistic context. “By revisiting the history of the war and celebrating the resilience of the Chinese people, the event inspires a deeper understanding of patriotism and cultural identity, particularly among younger generations,” highlights the CAC.
The program also includes a creative workshop, inviting participants of all ages to design and create ecological bags, using screen printing techniques. Registration is now open and details are available in the event's promotional materials.</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Madeiran guitarists play at Casa Garden</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/guitarristas-madeirenses-tocam-na-casa-garden/</link><description>The brothers André Santos and Bruno Santos, guitarists from Funchal, will perform at Casa Garden next Saturday. “Trilogy of Shadows” is the name of the show organized by Somos – Portuguese Language Communication Association
 
The show “Trilogia das Sombras” will promote the latest album by Mano a Mano, the duo of Madeiran brothers and guitarists André and Bruno Santos, which includes music, poetry, performance and visual arts, inspired by the work and life of the renowned artist Lourdes Castro. The event, which will take place on Saturday, November 8th, at 8pm, at Casa Garden, will also feature a performance by Tiago Martins and a setting by Ponto Atelier.
According to a note from “Somos! – Associação de Comunicação em Língua Portuguesa”, which organizes the concert, this fifth Mano a Mano album has the format of a book-disc, designed by Carla Cabral with inspiration from publications by Lourdes Castro, and using sewing, painting, drawing and transfer on fabric and paper. A text by José Tolentino Mendonça and the recitation of Lourdes Castro's poem, Rua da Olaria, are also added, in one of the ten themes.
“In addition to the brothers' usual paraphernalia of guitars and chordophones, the show features a performance by Tiago Martins who, behind a screen and inspired by Lourdes Castro's Shadow Theater, interacts with the music”, says the Somos statement.
Citing Tolentino Mendonça, the Association emphasizes that “the incredible visual work that the artist Lourdes Castro left is too intense and polyhedral to be limited to a single field”, adding that “its reach is greater” and “Lourdes Castro's work helps us to be, gives us music”.
Given the “pertinence of the fusion of cultures and identities”, there will be a special guest at this concert, instrumentalist Fang Teng, concertmaster of the Macau Chinese Orchestra, who will perform on stage emblematic works of Portuguese musical culture, “in this way strengthening ties that have united our peoples for centuries and creating a moment of perfect musical and cultural bond”. Fang will punctuate the notes of Portuguese music with the dramatic and melancholic capacity of the erhu, a traditional Chinese instrument with two strings and played with a bow.
The “Trilogia das Sombras” concert has the support (sponsorship) of the Cultural Development Fund, as well as the Fundação Oriente and the Instituto Português do Oriente (IPOR).
In the biographical notes of the musicians born in Funchal, it is highlighted, in the case of André Santos, the fact that he took his first steps in music by imitating his brother. “Precious tips from the older brother encouraged self-education and searching for and listening to records, ranging from Rage Against the Machine, João Gilberto or Thelonious Monk”, highlights Somos.
This broad taste and curiosity shaped André Santos' musical personality, making him a versatile guitarist, who ranges between Jazz and Rock, traditional Madeiran music and MPB, playing various guitars and chordophones. Known for his timbre and exploration of different sound textures, the musician participated in several projects, concerts and recordings with musicians such as Teresa Salgueiro, Salvador Sobral, António Zambujo, Júlio Resende, Carminho or Ana Moura.
As for Bruno Santos, he began his musical journey at the age of 15, self-taught. Together with two childhood friends, he founded the rock band Quarto Quadrante.
In 2014 he was awarded the title of “specialist” in the field of jazz, by ESML. He released four albums under his own name, another three as composer and arranger for 7to at Hot Clube de Portugal and four in partnership with his brother in the duo Mano a Mano. He has also performed as a duo with singer and songwriter Rita Redshoes and has participated in dozens of albums as a “sideman”.
Tiago Martins “immersed himself” in studies of visual arts, theater and dance. He graduated in Painting and developed a career as an interpreter, dancer and performer in a new circus all over the world “where he lives and sculpts his creativity and practice”.
Fang Teng was an erhu teacher at the School of Continuing Education at the Central Conservatory of Music, a guest musician with the Macau Chinese Orchestra and participated in several national and international concerts, including Portugal, Bahrain and other cities in China.
Currently, Fang is dedicated to promoting traditional Chinese music education in Macau and has taught erhu to thousands of students at Hou Kong Secondary School.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Docomomo promotes lectures with architect Johannes Widodo</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/docomomo-promove-palestras-arquitecto-johannes-widodo/</link><description>Two lectures led by Indonesian architect Johannes Widodo will address public housing in Singapore and the concept of modernism through an Asian lens. Both are organized by Docomomo and will take place on different days, first at Casa Garden and then at Fundação Rui Cunha
 
Architect Joahnnes Widodo will trace the evolution of housing schemes from the colonial era in Singapore to the transformative policies of the “Housing Development Board” (HDB), in a lecture to be held tomorrow, 6 November, at 6:45 pm, at Casa Garden, Fundação Oriente, organized by Docomomo Macau.
The following day, at the same time, but with the Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) as the stage, the Indonesian-born and Singapore-based researcher will be at the Rui Cunha Foundation to talk about the concept of modernism through an Asian lens, challenging dominant Eurocentric narratives and proposing a reformulation rooted in local cultural and environmental contexts.
In the first event, Joahnnes Widodo will present “From SIT to HDB: Morphology and Politics of Public Housing in Singapore in the 20th Century”, addressing the redefinition of housing not as a social benefit, but as a pillar of national development. As Docomomos highlights, Singapore's journey into collective housing began with the “Singapore Improvement Trust” (SIT) in the 1920s, laying the foundations for what would become one of the “most comprehensive” public housing programs in the world.
In the introduction to the talk, it is highlighted that the central point of this transformation was the integration of housing into the “Central Provident Fund” (CPF), allowing citizens to acquire homes through a mandatory savings scheme. This innovative financial model “promoted a sense of ownership and social stability, distinguishing Singapore public housing from Western social housing paradigms”.
Through spatial and political analysis, the conference highlights how public housing in Singapore has become a tool for social engineering, identity formation and sustainable urban development. It also looks at future challenges, including redeveloping aging neighborhoods, increasing inclusion and adapting to climate imperatives.
In the second talk, titled “Reframing Modernism: Grounded Modernities in Mediterranean Asia”, Johannes Widodo revisits the concept of modernism through an Asian lens, challenging dominant Eurocentric narratives and proposing a reformulation rooted in local cultural and environmental contexts.
Focusing on Southeast Asia and the region around the “Mediterranean Sea of ​​Asia”, where Macau is located, the professor's dissertation will highlight architectural expressions that incorporate local responses to global influences. “These grounded modernities are not mere adaptations, but creative syntheses that reflect indigenous values, climatic conditions and sociopolitical histories”, adds the event's introductory note.
Through selected case studies, the talk illustrates how modern architecture in Asia is a testament to “the ingenuity of past generations and a foundation for future cultural resilience”.
By revisiting the principles set out in the mAAN Declaration, the conference advocates a “renewed commitment to documentation, conservation and critical engagement with Asia’s modern architectural heritage”, calling for a pluralistic understanding of modernism, that is, “inclusive, context-sensitive and reflective of Asia’s rich and complex trajectories towards modernity”.
This initiative is part of a curated series developed by Docomomo Macau, with the support of the Rui Cunha Foundation, aimed at architects, academics, students and the general public. The series promotes critical dialogue about the legacy and future of collective housing and urban design in the Portuguese-speaking world and beyond.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Death becomes a booming business in an aging country</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/morte-torna-se-um-negocio-em-expansao-num-pais-envelhecido/</link><description>In a photo taken on September 24, 2025, an instructor shows a funeral altar set up in a classroom during a funeral administration class at the Busan Institute of Science and Technology in Busan. Growing numbers are finding work in the business of death in the face of massive demographic change in South Korea, where birth rates are among the lowest on earth and almost half the population is aged 50 or older. (Photo by Jung Yeon-je / AFP) / To go with 'SKOREA-DEATH-DEMOGRAPHICS-FUNERALS,FOCUS' by Claire LEE



Rows of coffins line a university classroom in the South Korean port city of Busan, ready to be used to train future funeral directors in a rapidly aging country. A growing number of people are finding work in the funeral business as South Korea undergoes a huge demographic transformation, with birth rates among the lowest in the world and almost half the population over 50.
 

Students from the Busan Institute of Science and Technology carefully covered a mannequin with traditional Korean burial cloth, smoothing the fabric as if it were real skin, before gently lowering it into a coffin.
“As our society ages, I imagined that the demand for this type of work would only increase,” said Jang Jin-yeong, 27, a funeral management student.
Another student, 23-year-old Im Sae-jin, decided to enter the zone after his grandmother's death. "At her funeral, I saw how beautifully the directors prepared her for her final farewell. I felt deep gratitude", he confessed.
More and more South Koreans live – and die – alone. Single-person homes now account for about 42% of all housing in Asia's fourth-largest economy.
A new profession emerged reflecting this statistic: that of cleaners, professionals hired to clean houses after the death of their occupants, most of whom lived alone.
Former classical musician Cho Eun-seok cleaned many houses where dead people were found, sometimes months after their deaths. Their homes are “like their portraits”, Cho, 47, told AFP.
He described heartbreaking remains: hundreds of carefully sealed bottles of soju and dusty gift boxes that had never been opened.
South Korea has the highest suicide rate among developed countries, and these “lonely deaths” include those who die alone, taking their own lives.
Cho recently began receiving calls from used car leasing companies to clean up vehicles that were later found to be locations where customers had taken their own lives.
He is also developing a device to detect signs of unattended deaths, which he says can harm the environment, causing pest infestations and requiring the disposal of entire families' belongings. In summer, the smell spreads quickly, he said, “and nothing can be saved.”
The home of a recently deceased woman in her late 90s was still filled with traces of her life when AFP visited – an old air conditioner, cosmetic bottles and a portable toilet, while several walking sticks stood near the door.
The work sometimes requires more than just cleaning. Mr. Kim Seok-jung once emptied the house of a deceased lyricist and found a set of songs that she had not shared with her family. He turned them into a song for the bereaved family.
And Mr Cho remembers a high school student who lived alone in a gosiwon – a cramped room, usually less than five square meters – after escaping domestic violence.
I visited her once a month to clean. The teenager, who suffered from depression, was unable to clean her room alone. Piles of belongings and rotting food covered the bed, and the air was infested with flies. But she took great care of a small box, insisting that Cho never throw it away.
A year later, she took her own life in that small room.
When Cho went back to clean, he discovered that a hamster had been living in the box the entire time. Next to him was her guitar – she dreamed of being a composer.
“The moment I saw the hamster, all I could think was that I had to save it and keep it alive,” Cho said.
Back in the classroom in Busan, Mr. Im admitted some apprehension about his chosen career path. “I’m scared,” he said. “No matter how much you prepare, facing a deceased person is scary.”
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>