<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>"Without a great quality of life, there is no great economy"</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sem-uma-grande-qualidade-de-vida-nao-ha-uma-grande-economia/</link><description>Environmental policies are again at the center of attention of another edition of the Forum and International Exhibition of Environmental Cooperation, which yesterday started in Venetian. Several companies take advantage of the event to publicize their ideas and principles, as well as know new concepts. For the president of Cesl Asia, a company based in the territory for 37 years, the issue of environmental sustainability continues to be considered of high importance these days, with Macao having to “operate changes” in the sense of “ending the problems that are known and have been degraded in the last 20 years”. To the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, António Trindade says he expects the new governing team to “promote policies and execute programs”, considering that “without a great quality of life, there is no great economy”. The company presents in this event a “new corporate identity”, which aims to follow the very evolution of
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The holding in Macao of another Forum and International Exhibition of Environmental Cooperation (MIECF) returns to gather experts linked to environmental protection and ecological transformation. Contact bags, exchanges, debates, presentation of ideas, mark the event, in which companies also take the opportunity to publicize their concepts and know new policies.
Cesl Asia is one of those companies that, assiduously, since the creation of the event in 2008, and especially from its professional certification, three years later, has been present to show the innovations introduced in the scenario of environmental protection.
Regarding the policies that have been followed by the governments of Macao in this matter and in the way of suggestion for the lines of government action (LAG), the president and CEO of the Portuguese matrix company, who operates in the area of ​​consultancy and in the sectors of energy and environment, told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that “the most important policy is to adapt Macau to what is today, and what will have to be in the future” "Need changes".
António Trindade hopes that the current secretary for transport and public works, Raymond Tam, who has the protection of environmental protection services, "have this vision and make the changes that have to be made." Mostly, it reinforces, "that promotes policies and execute programs so that Macau can achieve not only the objectives of double carbon stabilization, which are national policies, but also increase people's quality of life."
The civil engineer advocates “a cleaner city for residents and tourists”, and it is necessary for Macau to “improve the environment of the waters around him”. It states that "situations have been getting worse" and that, therefore, "it would be good to take advantage of this government's term" to "end the problems that are known and have been degraded in the last 20 years."
"These things cannot be done overnight," but "in four or five years I hope significant changes in the environment," said António Trindade, stressing that "when there is leadership and will, in a very short time is 80% of what is needed to perform, performing the rest gradually."
The entrepreneur says he has no knowledge of the ideas of the new secretary, but, "for what the chief executive says, it is believed that there is at least harmony for greater attention to the environment, because without quality of life of people, there is no other way to look at the subject." “Without a great quality of life there is no great economy,” he emphasizes.
 
Environmental protection “has been neglected”
Making a retrospective of recent years regarding environmental protection policies in Macao, the president of Cesl Asia observes the existence of "constant degradation for 20 years, so there is no way to look at this otherwise, as I have said publicly." Trinity warns that "this is a question that has been neglected in Macao," but expects "to change to the right way, which corresponds to national politics."
It is not possible to recognize, according to the words of the Luso businessman, "that the government speaks, in its speeches, of improvements and in adhering to national objectives, but also what are the expectations of people, who smell the stench, who can not walk by the sea because it smells bad and this is also a public health problem, with the endemic gastroenteritis that exist in Macao."
Name other problems: "the floods, wastewater, sea waters, where one cannot bathe, the contamination that exists, the emissions of polluting gases and the billion that has been spent."
For Cesl Asia's official, "Macao has announced several times that he was going to do" Wolders "and solid waste treatment stations of the best in the world, and for that, many millions have been spent, but everything is still getting worse." Antonio Trindade considers that there is no reason for this to happen. "We have to change these circumstances and ensure that new partners are."
It also notes that the coming of your company to Macau "had as mission to help and contribute to the improvement of environmental quality and, suddenly, we were replaced and nothing has improved."
This year, Cesl Asia will make known in MIECF the “change of corporate identity” that has been verified along the company's operations course. The company's president said the event serves, beyond the benefits as a whole, to present the changes that have been implemented. "We are changing some things, such as logo, management itself, which is, by the way, something we have been doing over 37 years."
The CEO considers that this change and evolution aims to “accompany the evolution of Macau”, a territory that, a few years ago, “basically the cycle of construction of the mega resorts and casinos ended, and therefore there is a new way to economic development”.
In the engineer's opinion, “the company's perspective or philosophy, its principles and values ​​remain, but there has been a better adaptation with the development of partnerships with companies in the continent, with global technological companies, in order to add new technologies to our services”.
António Trindade points out that the firm he leads has been changing and monitoring the development of Macao "with the new growth cycles in the economy itself, not growth based on construction and increasing tourists, for example, but the economic value of what is done in the territory, through new infrastructures."</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao without plans to restrict bamboo scaffolding</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-sem-planos-para-restringir-andaimes-de-bambu/</link><description>The Government of the MSAR claims to have an “open attitude” in the face of using metal scaffolding instead of bamboo scaffolding - but for now, and unlike Hong Kong, it does not seem to have measures to end the traditional wooden scaffolding. The Association of Barqueiros explained to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that the genesis of the safety problems observed in the neighboring region is lacking technique, something that does not happen in Macau. In a sector where workers' aging is one of the difficulties, the association's director, Chi Tak Siu, guarantees that he will continue to work to form younger generations in this one that is also an art
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Bamboo scaffolding is part of the Macau landscape and, unlike Hong Kong -where bamboo tubes will begin to disappear from the facades of the buildings after the government's announcement to replace them with metal scaffolding -it seems to be visible throughout the city. Despite the difficulties, and the government says that it has “an open attitude towards the use of metal scaffolding”, the sector intends to continue to resist and is sure that iron scaffolding is no longer used.
The neighboring region recently announced plans to replace the old practice of using bamboo scaffolding with metal scaffolding, citing safety worries - since 2018, 23 people have died in bamboo scaffolding accidents, according to official data. It was then decided that at least half of the new public buildings will use metal scaffolding. The private sector was also urged to follow the example of the government.
When asked by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao about whether to follow the same steps as Hong Kong, the MSar government said it was "attentive" to the development of the sector and having an "open attitude." "If society and the sector have consensus on the regulation of scaffolding materials, an analysis and study will be made," said the Directorate of Public Works (DSOP) services, also taking into account the opinion of the Directorate of Soil Services and Urban Construction.
"At this time, in the process of competition of public works, the requirements related to the characteristic of scaffolding materials are not stipulated," the body added in the response to this newspaper. As for private works, DSOP indicated that, taking into account the Free Market Principle, “provided that legal diplomas are fulfilled, at present, the government does not require the use of certain instruments or the regulation of technique for the execution of the work in the construction sector”.
Since scaffolding is one of the instruments used in the execution of the work, but not the subject of appreciation and approval under the project, the authorities remind you that "they must comply with the security provisions in the shipyards." As for this issue, the director of the Macao Barqueiros Association, Chiu Tak Siu, ensures that in the territory the sector works “in a safe environment”.
Heard by the Jornal Tribuna de Macau, Chi Tak Siu explained that the association he directs was several times to Hong Kong to realize the sector's situation. "We have noticed that there are many gray areas for accidents and it is difficult to find the person responsible for the problem. Our association has often warned the Hong Kong sector for the importance of ascertaining responsibilities in the event of incidents involving bamboo scaffolding. You should not ignore the issue by attributing responsibility only to the material," he defended.
In the case of Macau, he points out that “incidents rarely occur” involving bamboo scaffolding. For Chiu Tak Siu, the genesis of the problems lies in ignorance of the techniques of assembling and disassembling the bamboo scaffolding. The associative leader also warns that "using metal scaffolding is much more dangerous."
This newspaper questioned the direction of services for labor affairs on how many accidents have been registered since 2018 related to bamboo scaffolding and how many resulted in deaths, but until the closing of this edition did not receive any response.
With the rapid economic development of China and special administrative regions, the construction flourished and scaffolding became part of the city landscapes. But bamboo scaffolding, whose origin dates back to the period prior to China's first dynasty -the XXI (21st century BC BC) dynasty -have been replaced by steel tubes on the continent, something that will now extend to Hong Kong. In Macao, the old technique still “Reina”, and is also included in the inventory of intangible cultural heritage, recognized as “the art of bamboo scaffolding”.
According to Chiu Tak Siu, who entered this area when he was just a 12 -year -old, "in Macao there was no tendency to increase metal scaffolding." Of the more than two dozen existing scaffolding stores, only two have iron scaffolding - "and these do not work in very high buildings," he noted.
 
Youth formation is “long -term objective”
Although the association wants to continue work in this area, the truth is that it is faced with a series of difficulties. Currently, there are hundreds workers who work in the sector, most of which non -resident workers (TNR), who are an average of 50 years of age. "As for local workers, they are an average of 70 years and about 20 residents who work in the assembly and disassembly of bamboo scaffolding," he said.
Chiu Tak Siu noted that in recent years, very few people have entered the sector. “We tried to train young people, but after the formation most ended up giving up because they are afraid,” he told this newspaper. The associative leader lamented that the government "does not support" the sector, specifically in the context of training. "The association has to take from its own pocket to pay the courses. We have already promoted three to four courses to teach scaffolding techniques, but without government support it will be difficult to continue," he continued.
"Even with so many difficulties, we will try to form more young residents for the sector. It is our long -term goal," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Medical Academy will increase vacancies to train specialists</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/academia-medica-aumentara-vagas-para-formar-especialistas/</link><description>Law Chin Ion, president of the Macao Medical Academy Specialties Council, revealed plans to increase specialist medical training vacancies and annually implement recruitment and admission examination annually.
 
The Macao Medical Academy (AM) intends to increase specialist doctors training vacancies and perform the recruitment and admission exam annually, said Lei Chin Ion, president of the AM Specialties Council, recently appointed to the secretary for social matters and culture.
Specifically, it indicated that the number of specialties and recruitment vacancies will be adjusted according to the actual situation. As exemplified, taking into account population aging, more vacancies of training of doctors for geriatrics may be opened, while decreasing the birth rate may lead to the reduction of formation vacancies for pediatric, obstetrics and gynecology.
According to the newspaper “or Mun”, Law Chin Ion also revealed that, within the 1st edition of the Specialist Doctors Training Plan, 64 vacancies were available for medical residency for six years. Spread over 28 specialties, the 64 doctors are about to enter the hospital training phase, Lei Chin Ion said, stating that the Academy has also begun preparations for a new admission examination to the medical residency, with increased vacancies.
Since its founding in 2018, AM has issued 879 academic qualifications and defined medical residency training plans directed to 39 specialties. In the last six years, 51 doctors have been approved on the exam and have obtained expert titles in Macao.
According to Chin Ion Law, Macao's public and private hospitals have a considerable number of abroad doctors, which mirrors that the number of local specialists remains insufficient. By the end of last year, Macau registered 751 doctors specializing in office.
Given that the Macao medical service market is relatively reduced, authorities will control the number of training vacancies, he stressed, suggesting, at the same time, local specialists who also seek employment opportunities in the Great Bay or in the in -depth cooperation zone.
On the other hand, law Chin Ion said that another priority work is based on the revision of the regulation of the medical training procedure and in specialized nursing, in order to streamline admission tests. In addition, the Academy intends to establish a mechanism to study and more systematically investigate the types of specialties and the number of vacancies needed for training in medical residency. The official also said that AM will actively promote the recognition of the professional qualifications of Macao specialist doctors by Hong Kong or Singapore.
 
Obesity
However, health services (SSM) warned of the tendency to worsen the problem of overweight and obesity, due to the evolution of the city, lifestyle changes, increased sedentary behaviors between residents and popularization of food delivery culture.
At a press conference, the SSM said they intend to wrap the obesity rate by 2030. The body suggests to adults to practice weight measurement and calculation of body mass at least once a year, and establish achievable objectives, for example, losing 0.5 to a kilo of weight per week, but avoiding extreme methods.
According to the “Macao Health Inquiry”, in 2016, about 21.3% of adult residents were overweight and 30.6% were classified as obese. As for young people and adolescents, in the school 2022/2023, the excess weight and obesity rate was 21.7%, a slight rise of 0.5% in five years.
 
High risk of dengue fever transmission
This year, there will be a high risk of dengue fever transmission in Macao, due to the frequency of the flow of people and the continuous climb of the risk of transfrontic transmission, predicted the Dengue Fever Prevention Working Group. According to last year, Macau registered nine local cases and 39 imported from dengue fever, which shows that "the risk of propagation through important cases is quite high."
 
Symposium Approaches Medical Tourism
A medical tourism symposium will take place today, between 9:00 am and 12:30 pm, in the Londoner Greenwich room. The seminar aims to explore innovative strategies to connect Macau's medical and tourist sectors, and through the integration of traditional Chinese medicine, to build “a distinct and attractive medical tourism destination”. The first session, on the theme “Perspectives of Medical Tourism Development and the likely profile of the medical tourist”, will feature interventions by Glenn McCartney, Nial Murray, Xin Chen, Devonne IAO and Carolina Ung. The second panel, with the theme “The Integration of Traditional Chinese Medicine in the Development of Medical Tourism of Macao”, will start at 10:45 am, with the speakers Gabriel Lee, Vincent Wong, Lao Tai Hang, Zhou Hwa and Lin Penghui, these last two from Hengqin.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Artists expose it on equal screens in the three years of the amagao</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/artistas-expoem-em-telas-iguais-nos-tres-anos-da-amagao/</link><description>An exhibition of painting works, photography, mixed technique and digital art of 29 artists is inaugurated today at Gallery Amagao. The show marks the third anniversary of that exhibition room for private parts of art. Two dozen works are the responsibility of Macao authors and the rest of Portugal, China and Indonesia, all on the same size screens. Lina Ramadas and Victor Marreiros, who generate the gallery, consider that the path of love results in a “very positive balance” and that “despite not making a profit, it is worth by passion”






























Victor Rebelo
 
Paintings, photographs, mixed technique and digital art make up the works that will be exhibited from the Amagao Gallery, located at the Artyzen Grand Lapa Hotel. The show celebrates the 3rd anniversary of the commercial gallery, hence the name of the exhibition: “Year 3”.
The works are 29 artists, twenty of which from Macao, seven from Portugal, one from China and one from Indonesia. The exhibition, which inaugurates at 6.30 pm, presents the originality of integrating works with screens of the same size, 30 × 30 centimeters.
"This idea of ​​equal screens results in a very balanced, very beautiful exhibition, which has to do with the conception of the exhibition itself," Lina Ramadas told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. Victor Hugo Marreiros, equally managers of the gallery, states that "this is the first time that artists have exposed in canvases of the same dimension, in a concept of format, so that the paintings are all homogeneous."
Victor Marreiros, who is also one of the artists integrated in the exhibition that will be evident until May 25, points out that the concern has been to get new blood for the exhibitions of the amagao. “We do it again, without forgetting the traditional, the classics, in an attempt to diversify more and more,” he explains.
Recognizing that this is the following line for the softener, the space official suggested to artists not to perform their own style, but gave a different nature to the paintings. “We want to do a new test,” he says.
Among the authors of the works are Abílio Febra, Alexandre Marreiros, Ana Vale, André Pedro, Au Chon Hin, Ben Ieong Man Fai, Catarina Cottineli, Clara Leitão, Cristina Leiria, Cristina Vinhas, Denis Murrell, Eric Fok, Francisco Ricarte, Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro, Ieong Nga Kei Alice and João Palla. Works will also be present by Lúcia Lemos, Maria Odeta Sequeira, Miguel Quental, Natalie Lao, Nono Leong Chi Hang, Nuno Calçada Bastos, Nyoman Suornata, Raquel Gralheiro Susu, Suzy Bila, Thomas Potter, Vicente and Victor Marreiros.
On the three -year course of this art object exhibition room, Victor Hugo Marreiros and Lina Ramadas confess that “it has been very positive and has been worth it”, although it is a commercial place, ie private, without institutional subsidies.
“Those who work for taste doesn't get tired and give more enjoyment than profit, presenting exhibitions in a very beautiful space,” says one. “We do it for passion, for enjoying what we do,” says the other.
The amagao already has in mind three other exhibitions in 2025. One will integrate the celebrations of June 10, Portugal, Camões and Portuguese communities, with Portuguese artists, another will celebrate Spain Day, with posters from Miró and Picasso in October. For the end of the year, the gallery officials plan a different experience. “The idea is that two artists paint the same picture, which will be an innovation,” said Victor Hugo Marreiros.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing exhorts Asia to combat protectionism</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/pequim-exorta-asia-combater-proteccionismo/</link><description>Chinese vice-master-master, Ding Xuexiang, yesterday asked “resolute opposition to protectionism,” at the Boao Forum to Asia in Haião. "Asia has become the world's most dynamic region in terms of development and growth potential," said Ding, a member of the Chinese Communist Party Permanent Committee, a power summit in China, in his intervention at the event, which was attended by Portuguese Foreign Minister Paulo Rangel.
"Asia has actively opened its doors and took the initiative to integrate into the world," recalled the vice-minister, in a period of growing commercial frictions the US and the rest of the world.
Ding Xuexiang stated that the region should “work together to protect free trade, adhere to open regionalism and resolutely oppose commercial and investment protectionism”. He appealed to the “resolution of differences and differences through dialogue and consultation” and defended “opening, cooperation and economic globalization” as “inevitable choices” for the region.
According to the deputy minister, China's economic performance “remains stable” and “industry growth rates, consumption, investment and other indicators in the first two months of this year were higher than those last year”.
Ding said authorities “will implement more pro-active macroeconomic policies” and “expand internal demand on all fronts” at a time when weak domestic consumption raises deflationary pressures in the second largest economy in the world. It reiterated that the Chinese government will "promote the healthy development of real estate and scholarship more vigorously."
The forum, which continues today under the theme “Asia in a change world: towards a shared future”, stressed the resilience of the region in a global environment marked by geopolitical tensions, moderate inflation and unequal recovery, with a report on Tuesday to predict real 4.5%GDP growth in 2025, compared to 4.4%in 2024.
Known as “Asian Davos”, the Boao for Asia Forum, created in 2000 by agreement from 29 countries in the region, was first held in February 2001, in order to promote Asian economic integration, which later widened a global scale. Trump's return to the White House and the imposed or announced customs rates that particularly affected the largest US business partners, such as China, Canada, Mexico and the European Union, were the focus of this edition.
 
MGI wishes to expand cooperation with Haião
The Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, met in Haião with the Secretary of the Provincial Committee of the CCP, Feng FEI, with whom he exchanged impressions on the widening and deepening of cooperation between the two regions in various areas. Yesterday the leader of the MSA participated in the opening ceremony of the Boao Forum for Asia 2025 and maintained meetings with the vice president of the State Council's Supervisory and Administration Commission, Gou Ping, and the vice president of the Boao forum for Asia and former governor of the Popular Bank of China, Zhou Xiaochuan.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Support for SME digitization offers 1,500 vacancies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/apoio-a-digitalizacao-das-pme-oferece-1-500-vagas/</link><description>The “SME Scan Support Services” plan has 1,500 vacancies and aims to assist the digital transformation of local companies, a maximum of 18 thousand Patacas
 
In order to support Small and Medium Enterprises (SME) in digital transformation, the “SME Scanning Support Services” plan was launched. According to the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) and the Macao Technology Productivity and Transfer Center (CPTTM), the idea is to offer training in business scanning and free solutions to help SMEs use digital tools.
The number of vacancies increased from 900 last year to 1,500. This is because the number of applications for support services in the last two editions demonstrates “a great demand from the SMEs in digital transformation,” according to DSEDT.
The plan is intended for companies of activities such as retail trade, restoration or subsistence services, among others. There will be two phases of applications, one in June and one in November, and the candidate companies must have purchased or apply for the quality of a “certified store”, with the Consumer Council. Companies will be selected and sorted by lot.
The plan is divided into two parts and covers courses, solution evaluation and systems construction. The first part consists of a training course on the knowledge of digital operation, a diagnosis of the operation model and the evaluation of the renovation program.
The second will provide companies with systems, and construction costs are paid by CPTTM to suppliers. Candidate companies will be able to choose from the solutions provided by the recognized suppliers, and the supply with qualified solutions companies will have a maximum value of 18,000 patacas.
Chan Chou Weng, a subdirector of DSEDT, stressed that the government "has been paying attention to SME development and supporting them in digital transformation." In turn, CPTTM's chairman Victoria Kuan said the center successively performed several phases of SME digitization services, benefiting “over a thousand companies”.
According to the statement, CPTTM “will continue to review and optimize supplier recruitment procedures”, striving to assist SMEs, in the scope of digital transformation. In the same vein, DSEDT will reinforce cooperation with other public services and institutions, in order to create “a better environment and conditions favorable to the development of local SMEs”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China guarantees that it has stopped building coal centers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/china-garante-parou-de-construir-centrais-carvao/</link><description>The Deputy Minister of Chinese Ecology and Environment, Sun Jinlong, announced yesterday that China stopped building new coal centers, unlike in an academic report released in February. “We completely interrupt the construction of new coal centers,” said Sun, during the opening ceremony of the Macao's International Environmental Cooperation (MIECF) forum.
The event, which started yesterday at Cotai Expo do Venetian and will take place until Saturday, has 26 companies from Portugal, Brazil and Timor-Leste, according to the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM).
Sun Jinlong said in a speech that Macau, such as "the only region in the world that has Chinese and Portuguese as official languages," can play "a unique role in promoting financial cooperation and investment with Portuguese -speaking countries."
The vice -minister also pointed out that China has signed agreements with more than 40 countries to meet the impact of climate change. Sun argued that “the results of Chinese policies are notorious to improve the environment, highlighting forest cover, which“ exceeded 25%”of the country's total area.
China has “the world's largest green electricity system” and leads globally in the production of hydroelectric, wind and solar energy, the leader added.
Sun's guarantee comes about a month after a report warned that China began, in 2024, the construction of the largest coal centers in the last ten years, raising doubts about the country's environmental goals. Beijing began the construction of units with a joint capacity of 94.5 gigawatts (GW), ie 93% of the world total, according to a document published by the Center for Research on Energy and Clean Air and the “Global Energy Monitor”, based in Finland and the United States, respectively.
China is the largest emitter in the world of greenhouse gases, but is also at the forefront of renewable energy. In 2024, it will have 356 GW of new wind and solar capacity, 4.5 times more than the European Union, according to official data.
Although coal has served as an essential source of energy in China for decades, the explosive growth of wind and solar capacity in recent years has raised the hope that the country will be able to move away from this highly polluting fossil fuel. China has announced that it intends to reach carbonic neutrality by 2060.
"The rapid expansion of renewable energy in China has the potential to reshape its electrical system, but this opportunity is impaired by the simultaneous expansion on a large scale of coal energy," said Qi Qin, the main author of the report.
This increase occurs despite the commitment made by Chinese President Xi Jinping in 2021 to “strictly control” coal -central projects and increased consumption of that fossil fuel before “gradually reduced” between 2026 and 2030.
Coal production in China has increased constantly in recent years, from 3.9 billion tons in 2020 to 4.8 billion tons in 2024. “In the absence of urgent political changes, China risks reinforcing an additional energy model, rather than transition, thus limiting the full potential of its clean energy boom,” said the report.
This year's edition of MIECF has exhibitors from 40 countries or regions, bringing together renowned experts and academics from the interior of China, Southeast Asia, Europe, Hong Kong and Macau, who intend to jointly explore new opportunities for environmental exchange and cooperation at the international level.
According to estimates by the organization, the number of international professional participants in the fair may record an annual increase of 23%. The number of international participants overall should grow about 17% compared to the 2024 event.
This year's edition focuses on the “debut economy”. In the exclusive exhibition zone for this theme, more than 20 new products or projects will be first launched, for example, a mechanical dog, automatic electric motorcycle parking technology and a new biodegradable material, among others.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Interregional legal aid requires “more in-depth studies”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/assistencia-judiciaria-inter-regional-exige-estudos-mais-aprofundados/</link><description>As the authorities have been reaching, “it is necessary to reinforce the interregional legal aid in criminal matters” between the sons, the interior of China and Hong Kong. However, the Director of Justice Affairs Services, Leong Weng In argues that “the Government of MSar needs to perform further studies” as it is necessary to consider, for example, issues such as the guarantee of the fundamental rights of suspects of crimes
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The executive considers, as he has been relying over the years, that “it is necessary to reinforce interregional legal aid in criminal matters” between the masters, the interior of China and Hong Kong, however, more studies are needed to move forward with its development. Authorities also ensure that the three regions will continue to reinforce police cooperation.
Since legal assistance in criminal matters covers, for example, “the transfer of convicted persons, the assistance in the investigation and the obtaining evidence, the delivery of escape infrastructors”, the direction of Justice Services (DSAJ) indicates that the government “will, according to the principle of progression of greater ease for greater complexity, actively study and gradually develop interregional legal assistance in criminal matters”.
In response to an interpellation of Deputy Song Pek Kei, DSAJ Director Leong Weng In, it also states that, in relation to the formulation of a law in this context, “it is necessary to consider, comprehensively, the characteristics of interregional legal aid, namely those related to the exercise of judicial jurisdiction, the guarantee of the fundamental rights of the suspects of crimes, among others, as well as the concrete situation negotiations of agreements on legal assistance in criminal matters ”. In this sense, "the Government of MSAR also needs to conduct further studies."
Song Pek Kei had pointed out that legislative work on the interregional legal aid law drags on "for about 10 years", and there is a new situation of social development. Thus, the deputy argued that the government should advance with the restart of these legislative works, even to “better promote the integration of Macau in national development”.
In the replica, Leong Weng in underlines that the MSar “has maintained extremely close contacts” with the interior of China and Raehk, at the economic and personnel level, so “to combat transfrontic crime together, it is necessary to reinforce interregional legal aid between the three parts”. Regarding practical work, “Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macao will continue to reinforce police cooperation, jointly fighting transfrontic and organized crime through police cooperation mechanisms, joint police operations, among other means,” he added.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Zhongshan, Zhuhai and Macao “Unem” tourist itineraries</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/zhongshan-zhuhai-macau-unem-itinerarios-turisticos/</link><description>Tourism Alliance Zhongshan, Zhuhai and Macau aims to promote the development of multidestic itineraries to attract more visitors
 
Zhongshan, Zhuhai and Macao tourism authorities met to take stock of work in 2024 and discuss the priority work for this year. The Directorate of Macao Tourism Services (STD), which assumed the rotating presidency of this tourism alliance for this year, succeeding the services of culture, radio, television and tourism in the municipality of Zhongshan, presented the work plan for 2025, which will continue to unite the resources of Zhongshan, Zhuhai and Macao, and to deepen multiustinian tourism.
According to STD, during the meeting, held in Zhongshan, the tourism authorities of the three cities discussed and defined street promotions in the cities of the Great Bay, together with online travel agencies in the interior of China, the updating of the “Zhongshan, Zhuhai and Macau Gastronomy Guide”, the tourist promotion of the three regions of Southeast Asia and the tourist brand image. From Zhongshan, Zhuhai and Macau, in order to attract visitors from the country and abroad.
In the last year, STD actively promoted joint tourist tours of the Great Bay, in cooperation with online travel agencies in the interior of China, “boosting tourism from the great bay”, and promoting the development of multi -communicial itineraries.
In 2006, the three cities created the alliance, under the image of “Xiangshan in the past, Zhongshan, Zhuhai and Macau today”, in order to create a regional tourist brand of the River Delta Delta.
In addition to the director of tourism services, Huang Jianmin, director of culture, radio, television and tourism services in the municipality of Zhongshan, and Zhong Guohuai, member of the Party Committee of the Department of Culture, Radio, Television, Tourism and Sports of the Zhuhai Tourism Development Center, were present.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Extended awards to foster quality of services</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/alargados-premios-para-fomentar-qualidade-de-servicos/</link><description>The Directorate of Tourism Services announced new awards under the 2025 Quality Tourist Services Evaluation Program. In addition to maintaining existing prizes, four to the restoration sector and three for travel agencies were added to the awards sector sector.
 
Like the previous editions, the Quality Tourism Evaluation Program (QTASS), launched by the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), will assign to the restoration sectors and travel agencies the Quality Tourist Services and Gold Quality Services Awards, each worth 10,000 patacas. The excellent prize in quality tourist services, 20,000 patacas, is intended for companies that have won the gold prize for three consecutive years.
This year, more special theme prizes were created, with a pecuniary value of 5,000 patacas. In the restoration sector, in addition to the existing sustainable eating prize, establishments can receive the community care award, the local characteristic award, the operational innovation award and the good practices in integrity.
Travel agencies, in turn, will be able to receive the courtesy company award, the team of team training quality and, such as restoration, the good practices in integrity. The program aims to reward the good performance of the establishments that operate “with integrity” and that “provide quality services and experiences”, stressed the STD.
In addition to monetary awards, winning establishments will have priority in the recommendation to participate in promotions, activities and training courses organized by STD.
Since 2014, QTASSA has served to “support the increase in the quality of tourist services, to show the unique attraction and the spirit of Macao”. According to STD Substitute Director Cheng Wai Tong, "the quality of tourist services is fundamental for the sustainable development of the Macao industry."
STD simplified the QTSSA evaluation system and canceled the limit of the number of registration. For selected companies, STD plans to organize clarification sessions about evaluation criteria. Companies interested in participating in the program should visit the STD Electronic page (www.dst.gov.mo), provide the requested information and deliver the candidacy newsletter by March 31.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Up to two million for the repair of real estate of cultural interest</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ate-dois-milhoes-para-reparacao-de-imoveis-de-interesse-cultural/</link><description>There will be two rounds of applications for the “Financial Support Plan for the Benefit of Historical Buildings,” said the Culture Development Fund (FDC). The first from March 31 to May 30 and the second between September 15 and November 14. The plan is intended for owners of real estate of cultural interest, classified or on classification, and whose reparation works have not yet been started until the application period. The initiative aims to support the owners to perform regular structural inspections and tests, external repairs and the necessary restoration according to the test results. Financial support will be a value between 50% and 80% of the expected expenses, up to two million patacas, over a maximum period of 12 months. The FDC will verify the documentation and qualifications of the candidate projects, which will also be analyzed by the Cultural Institute. The Cultural Heritage Council will issue an opinion, taking into account the need and urgency of repairs, the cultural interest of the property, as well as the impact on “on the awareness and safeguarding of cultural heritage”. If the application is approved, the FDC will ask the candidate a repair plan, prepared by consulting services, and will be evaluated by the Activities and Project Evaluation Committee. The evaluation will be made according to the “need for the repair work, result of the expected improvement of the state of the building and reasonableness of the budget”. A clarification session is scheduled for April 8, at 3 pm, in the auditorium of the Cheng Feng shopping center, at Alameda Dr. Carlos D'Assumpção.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cold weather and rain are back on the weekend</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/tempo-frio-chuva-estao-de-regresso-fim-de-semana/</link><description>Meteorological and geophysical services (SMG) warned of the temperature descent already on the weekend and the return of rain. Although in recent days the sky has been not cloudy and with weak wind, "time in the region is expected to undergo a significant change next week." According to the body's predictions, today the weather will still be hot, with a higher percentage of relative moisture and fog. However, with the arrival of a cold front to the southern Chinese coast "there is an increase in cloudiness and water, not excluding the possibility that thunderstorms approach Macau after affecting the interior of China." Under the influence of a Northeast Monsoon, SMG predicts that the temperature of the Chinese southern region “descends sharply” tomorrow, and the cooling may be approximately 10ºC within 24 hours. Already between the weekend and the beginning of next week, the body estimates that the minimum temperature goes down at approximately 15ºC. "However, due to the existence of divergences in the prediction of cold air mass intensity in the different modes of forecasting and the continuous influence of rainy and cloudy time, the minimum temperature may be slightly lower than the current prediction," he says. In recent weeks, it has been found in Macao an alternation between cold and hot weather.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Basic Law registers “Extraordinary Trail”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lei-basica-regista-percurso-extraordinario/</link><description>The Secretary for Administration and Justice defended yesterday that the implementation of basic law "has had an extraordinary course for 25 years" and that the practice of the principle "one country, two systems" is "in an important historical phase, in which the future is embraced by continuing the past." The ruler spoke in the scope of a seminar organized by the Basic Law Disclosure Association, entitled “New Journey of the Implementation of the Principle‘ One Country, Two Systems ’in Macao”, which had experts to discuss various issues. André Cheong said the government will "continue to improve the legal regime and the mechanisms of execution of state security defense, in order to create a national security defense barrier", as well as "build a government oriented to serve with high efficiency and dedication." Regarding the diversification of the economy, it has stated that the positioning of MSA as “a center, a platform, a base” is “very clear”, so it is necessary to “maintain the stability of policies” in the territory. To realize the diversification of the economy, defended André Cheong, "the construction and development of hengqin are crucial." "The development of Hengqin aims to serve Macau and the successful progress of Hengqin will surely bring benefits to Macao," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Finland follows in the lead of the ranking of the happiest countries in the world</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/finlandia-segue-na-lideranca-ranking-dos-paises-mais-felizes-mundo/</link><description>Finland is the happiest country in the world for the eighth consecutive year, according to the annual report on the happiness elaborated with the support of the UN. All Nordic countries remain among the 10 happiest, with Denmark, Iceland and Sweden behind Finland, which slightly expanded its distance to the runner -up.
In turn, the US fell to 24th place, the worst result of the country since the publication of the first edition of the report in 2012, when they ranked 11th, its best classification.
Sharing meals “is strongly linked to well-being,” write the authors of the study. The "number of people who have dinner alone in the US has increased 53% in the last two decades."
By 2023, almost 25% of Americans stated that they had a meal alone the day before, according to the report. "The growing number of people who make meals alone is one of the reasons for the fall of welfare in the US," the study says.
The US is also one of the few countries that record an increase in “deaths from despair” (suicide or as a consequence of excessive alcohol consumption, drugs, etc.), at a time when this type of death is falling in most countries.
The report analyzes the behavior of populations around the world in 2022-2024, which means it is not linked to the changes triggered by Donald Trump's return to the White House.
Latin American countries with the best positions were Costa Rica and Mexico, in sixth and tenth, respectively.
Afghanistan, the scenario of a humanitarian catastrophe since the Talibans resumed power in 2020, will appear again as the most unhappy country in the world.
The classification of happiness is based on an average of three years of personal assessment of life satisfaction, as well as GDP per capita, social support, life expectancy with good health, freedom, generosity and corruption rates.
"It seems that Finns are relatively pleased with their lives," said AFP Frank Martela, a deputy professor specializing in well-being research and happiness at the Helsinki university of Esporte.
The result can be largely explained by the fact that Finns live in a “society that works quite well,” he added. "Democracy works well, we have free elections, freedom of expression, low levels of corruption, and all this demonstrates that it is possible to predict higher levels of national well-being," he added.
All Nordic countries have relatively strong social protection systems, with maternity and paternity licenses, majority universal unemployment and health care subsidies, which also contribute to higher average welfare levels.
Eveliina Ylitolonen, a 23 -year -old student in Helsinquia, believes that the Finnish appreciation for the beauty of nature explains the country's level of happiness, known for their deep forests and more than 160,000 lakes. "Nature is an important element of happiness," he said.
In this year's report, the authors claim to have new evidence that acts of generosity and belief in the goodness of others are "significant predators of happiness, even more than receiving a higher salary." "People are very pessimistic about the kindness of their community; the rate of return of lost wallets is much higher than people expect," they add.
The Nordic countries are also “among the best places in terms of expected and real rates of return of lost wallets,” says the report.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>