<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Approved 81% of TNR in a year with fewer requests</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/aprovados-81-dos-tnr-num-ano-menos-pedidos/</link><description>After registered a strong increase in 2023, requests related to the hiring of non-resident workers decreased almost 13% in 2024, in annual terms, according to services for work issues on the completed processes. The number of authorized individuals also fell 9.3%, but the approval rate rose to 81.4% generally and 95.6% for specialized workers
 
Sérgio Terra
 
The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) concluded the assessment of 29,219 Requests related to the hiring of non-resident workers (TNR) in 2024, a number that illustrates an annual descent of 4,249 or 12.7% and contrasts with the increase of 32.3% between 2022 and 2023, then driven by the postcovid period. Among cases of importation, renewal and transfer, the processes completed last year included 18,877 requests related to non -specialized workers, 2,808 for specialized and 7,534 in the context of home work.
In general, requests involved 194,588 TNR, less 29,987 or 13.3% than the previous year, after 22.3% to 224,575 in 2023. 16,188, led to an increase of 3.7 percentage points to 81.4% at the general approval rate.
Including TNR who were already employed, Macau ended 2024 with 182,542 individuals in the imported labor universe, ie 5,881 or 3.3% in the annual comparison. However, this segment of work force continues below 196,538 non-resident workers accounted for in late 2019, the pre-pound year.
According to the official data analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, DSSA approved 146,089 of 181,990 non -specialized workers included in the applications, which corresponds to a 9% decline and an approval rate of 80.3% (+3.9 percentage points). In concrete, the importation of 29,228 non-specialized workers (-20.7%) and the renewal of 116,861 (-5.5%) was authorized.
On the other hand, the percentage of specialized workers approved advanced 1.9 points to 95.6%, with the body authorizing 4,841 (-3.1%) of the 5,064 requested. In this domain, DSSA has endorsed the importation of 1,948 specialized TNR (+0.7%), renewal of 2,875 (-5.1%) and transfer of 18 (-43.7%).
The approval rate was even higher in domestic work, when it is 98%, maintaining the level of the previous year. In assessment of requests that covered 7,534 domestic workers, DSSA authorized 7,386 (-17.8%), including imports of 6,415 (-21.1%) and renewal of 971 (+13.8%).
Last year, the construction sector led the list of TNR authorized in the three strands (specialized, non -specialized and housework), with a total of 44,636, equivalent to an approval rate of 83.5%, followed by hotels, restaurants and similar establishments, with 41,336 workers, or 84.4% of the requested. Among the main branches of economic activity are also highlighted real estate and services (24,907 authorized) and the thick and retail trade (15,747), with approval percentages of 71.8% and 77.6%, respectively.
The only area where TNR's approval reached 100% was once again the public administration and social security, involving 195 workers.
At the end of 2024, the interior of China continued to be, by large margin, the main labor import market with 121,161 TNR (66.4% of the total), although it only grew 0.1% in a year. In the “top 5” there were also 30,912 workers from the Philippines (+7.3%), 8,261 from Vietname (+6%), Indonesia (+21.1%) and 4,314 Myanmar (+25.4%).
Hotels and Restoration (53,948), domestic work (27,435), construction (25,641), real estate activities (23,647) and the thick and retail trade (21,279) were the most TNR sectors at the end of December.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Celebrated more than 50 agreements on environmental projects</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/celebrados-mais-de-50-acordos-sobre-projectos-ambientais/</link><description>The Macao's International Environmental Cooperation Forum and Exhibition provided the signing of more than 50 cooperation projects and the holding of 450 contact scholarship sessions, boosting green business opportunities. In the balance of the event, the organization says that some companies expressed their intention to settle in the territory
 
Victor Rebelo
 
About four hundreds of national and international companies participated this year at the Macao International Environmental Cooperation (MIECF) Forum and Exhibition, and 450 contact scholarship sessions were held and more than 50 projects signed. In addition, eight companies formalized their establishment in the territory.
The MIECF has organized three Green Forum theme sessions, bringing together more than 30 national and foreign experts and academics, who debated the sustainable transition, technological innovation and cooperation in the environmental protection of Rio das Pearl Pan-Delta.
In the organization done by the organization, it is said that some Hong Kong scientific and technological companies, which participated in the fair for the first time, were successful in negotiations with local, national and foreign professional organizations, and recognized the functions of Miecf and the Macao business platform. One of these examples came from Spain, with a supplier of biological agricultural products to seal agreements on the intention to cooperate with large gross and hotels, planning to establish a company in Macao to expand activity.
An exhibitor of a Lusophone country stressed that the exhibition provided opportunities to identify potential business partners and allowed the expansion of its market horizons. Another participant, from Malaysia, highlighted the role of Miecf in facilitating international commercial contacts. Also some companies from the interior of China have signed business agreements.
Meanwhile, one of Macao's car exhibitors, who presented new models of passenger and goods electric vehicles, stressed that, in the first participation in the event, in 2024, managed to establish contacts with public services, which translated into orders for environmentally friendly vehicles. This year, the company was once again present at the exhibition, with the aim of getting contacts with institutions and companies interested in the acquisition of environmental vehicles, thus exploiting even more business opportunities.
MIECF considers that, in general, representatives of the companies expressed satisfaction with the general provisions of the event, recognizing their organization and effectiveness.
 
Fair promoted state -of -the -art technologies
Under the event, promotions and demonstrations of nine relevance debut projects were held, demonstrating cutting -edge technologies, including new biodegradable material, liquid -cooled super charging technology, autonomous electric yachts and smart energy management systems.
“Companies have benefited from project promotions and demonstrations and contact scholarship sessions, which provided them with an active promotion and interconnection platform for green innovation projects, thus expanding the impact of the exhibition,” read the MIECF 2025 balance sheet.
More than three dozen experts and academics from various countries or regions have been gathered at the Green Forum to discuss the future of sustainable development, including Ilei Secretary-General-Local Sustainability Governments, Gino Van Begin, who was the main speaker on the theme “Green Innovation and Development for the construction of a beautiful city”.
The three thematic sessions discussed ecological transition, technological innovation and cooperation in environmental protection in the Pan-Delta region of Rio das Pérolas.
To extend the effectiveness of the event, guided tours of the city's neighborhoods, organized during the MIECF, attracted 77 participants.
The last day of the fair was dedicated to the “Green Public Day”, and attracted numerous residents for fun and educational environmental activities. Additionally, technical visits were organized to the recycling facilities of electronic and electric equipment and the ecological zones of Cotai, promoting the exchange of environmental protection technology.
"These initiatives have allowed direct contact with the updated environmental protection information and technologies, raising ecological awareness and encouraging the adoption of a sustainable lifestyle, as well as progressing in the low carbon goal," says the MIECF.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Tói Sán and Green Island Target of Reordering</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/toi-san-ilha-verde-alvo-de-reordenamento/</link><description>There are eight leisure zones of Tói San and Ilha Verde that will be reordered, to give greater comfort and diversity of facilities to the population of that area of ​​the territory. According to the Institute for Municipal Affairs, the works will start in the 2nd semester of the year, in a phased way, and the first target will be the leisure zone of Central de Tói Sán Street. The entire general project, which encompasses several streets, will be completed in the first half of 2027

Catarina Pereira
 
The leisure zones of Tói Sán and Ilha Verde "have been operating for many years" and the facilities have "degradation and monotony". For this reason -and because in these areas of the city there is “high population density”, with more children and the elderly -the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) will give you a new life. In concrete, it will reorder eight leisure zones, “based on the principle of optimization and integration”.
The start of reordering work is scheduled for the 2nd semester of this year, and the first task is to deal with the leisure zone of Central Rua De Tói Sán. The AMI plans that the works will end later this year, and the remaining zones “started in an orderly and separate way”. "It is expected that all will be completed and entering the first half of 2027," said the body.
Regarding Central Rua de Tói Sán, which occupies 870 square meters, the objective is to create “an urban oasis”, as it is located near several schools and has a “high” use rate by parents and children. In this sense, AMI intends a design that integrates natural elements, preserving the existing trees.
"Under the surroundings of trees, personalized equipment will be added to children in tree -shaped children, installed adventure air rails, with a view to fully taking advantage of the limited space to provide young people and children to play and explore nature," explains the body. At the same time, a new planning of the arrangement will be carried out, creating sports and recreational zones, and optimizing the pedestrian circulation line.
Among the eight remodeling leisure zones include, in addition to Central Street of Tói Sán, the leisure zones of the Fatima Mission Street, Tamagnini Barbosa Social neighborhood, Pou Ch'oni Rua, Rua da Canal das Hortas (next to Caritas), Factory Street, Lotus Flower Square and the Marginal Road of Ilha Verde.
The general idea is to give new planning, rationally distribute functional areas, as well as diversify fun and physical maintenance equipment, explained AMI adding that it intends to “create leisure zones with new themes and their own characteristics, in order to contribute to meet the needs of residents of different age groups”. In addition, it will also introduce facilities without architectural barriers that give shadow, as well as reinforce “safety and comfort, raising the quality of green zones”.
 
From the leisure corner to chess and sport
As for the street of the Fatima Mission, AMI intends to create a leisure corner, in about 225 square meters. What is intended for this area is to raise accessibility and improve the pedestrian environment, with the improvement of the lighting atmosphere at night, “for the construction of a safe and open corner space”. In concrete, and in articulation with the functions of child fun existing after the reordering of the central street of Tói Sán, this zone will be added to new physical maintenance facilities, also preserving the existing trees and adding shelters, and the low walls and sealing nets are removed.
With about 1,680 square meters, the leisure zone of the social neighborhood of Tamagnini Barbosa is surrounded by various social and educational entities, as well as elderly homes. In this sense, AMI intends to plan the space to create a zone with “unique characteristics”. In concrete, air facilities and entertainment sets in the form of flower beds will be introduced, creating “a quality space for families”.
At the same time, and taking into account the needs of the elderly and disabled, physical maintenance facilities will be added in quantity and typology that contributes to enriching inclusive experience. Moreover, this resting area will also have facilities that allow you to protect from sun and rain to “raise comfort” citizens.
The AMI will also reorder the leisure zones of the marginal street of the Hortas Canal and the factory street, with 495 and 540 square meters, respectively. Being “smaller” than all others, AMI observes that “are ideal for performing static leisure activities”. Thus, the spaces will be reorganized and chess tables and leisure facilities will be added so that residents and the elderly can sit and play chess. The area will also receive fitness equipment suitable for the elderly, while the wooded landscape will be “enriched” to “increase environmental comfort and meet the different needs of older people”.
 
Statue remains at Flor de Lotus Square
In relation to the leisure zone of Flor de Lotus Square, located in the public housing sets of the Ilha Verde neighborhood, AMI ensures that it will keep the statue of the god of the Earth in the original place, separated with trees. In addition, it intends to respond to a problem: the “lack of leisure and physical maintenance facilities”.
However, and despite the large dimension of space, it is necessary to reserve zones for access to fire prevention, explains the body. Therefore, “conception will make the most of the exterior space of access to fire prevention to place fun facilities, physical maintenance, square and rest areas, among others”.
According to AMI, the introduction of personalized fun and physical maintenance facilities serves to “enrich” the wooded landscape of the community neighborhood. In addition, the square and roads, in addition to access to fire prevention, will be widened, adding benches and shelters of the sun, in order to raise the comfort of those who spend time there.
Lastly, in the leisure zone of the marginal road of Ilha Verde, with 7,245 square meters, a leisure and sports corridor will be created. “Given the sports elements and the characteristics of the narrow and long space of the various sports fields in this leisure zone, the reordering plan will interconnect the various functional zones with leisure tours and existing trees on the streets,” explains AI. The coating of sports fields will also be optimized and enriched the visual face of the place.
Explaining that the installation of chairs and partial shading will provide a better experience to the users of the countryside, the body indicates that there will be several sets of climbing equipment in the children's recreational zone, "so that children can exercise their physical fitness while having fun." In the physical maintenance zone, various types of recreational and sports equipment will be installed, and also added washbasins, drinking fountains, public toilets and other complementary facilities, besides being optimized the Canino Park.
 
Authorities promote cleaning campaign
A working group composed of various public services will develop this month and in May a “city cleaning campaign” to improve the environmental hygiene of community neighborhoods, the Institute announced for municipal affairs (AMI). With launch scheduled for April 5, the campaign involves various associations and includes rodent prevention and mosquito extermination measures, the reinforcement of inspections in the workshops, restoration establishments and transformation of food products and awareness in “three zero buildings” (buildings without a meeting of owners, organization of residents or business company), explained the body. During the period of this initiative, it will also be installed information posts and itinerant exhibitions to promote environmental hygienic education.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New routes on the airport radar</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/novas-rotas-radar-aeroporto/</link><description>Macao International Airport accounted for 1.85 million passengers in the first quarter of this year, which translates into an annual increase of 3%, said the director of Cam's marketing department. For this year, the opening of several routes is planned
 
Macau International Airport registered 1.85 million passengers in the first quarter of this year, representing an annual increase of 3%, a “satisfactory” result for the Macao International Airport Society (CAM), Eric Fong, director of CAM's marketing department. In addition, it revealed that, in the same temporal interval, the number of dropouts and landings of airport at the local airport rose 1.5% to 14 thousand.
According to the Chinese language press, Eric Fong also indicated that in January this year, travelers in the interior of China occupied 46% of the total passengers at the airport, followed by those of Southeast Asia and Northeast Asia, which represented 37% of the total. At the same time, 100,000 international passengers were registered, translating an annual increase of 8%.
Also according to the same responsible, will be launched in May this year the air route between Macau and Jeju. In addition, the Macau-Cheongju route, also from South Korea, can be inaugurated after Easter or before the summer holidays. Another news is that the launch of flights between Macao and Phu Quoc is the island in Vietnam is scheduled for this year.
On the other hand, CAM plans to open service centers from Macau Airport in Shekou, Shenzhen; Port of Zhongshan; and Zhuhai, in the second half of this year.
According to Eric Fong, Macau airport currently welcomes 43 airlines and more than 1,200 round trip flights per week, including six to eight between Macau and Thailand a day. Regarding the earthquake in Thailand, the official of Cam noted that air transport between mashes and that country have been poorly affected, ensuring that Cam will closely follow the situation.
In addition, regarding the sharing of codes between Eva Air and Air Macau, in force since March 30, the director of the Cama Marketing Department considered that this measure will facilitate the trips of passengers who go to Europe or the US, scale in Taiwan.
 
Air Macau squeezes rules on “power banks”
In turn, Air Macau warned that, starting April 8, passengers will no longer be able to use power banks during flights, nor place them on the dispatched travel bags. According to the carrier, passengers will be prohibited from carrying onboard porters whose power exceeds 160Wh (Watts-Hora) or who have no explicit energy parameters.
Each passenger will be limited to a maximum of two power banks whose power varies between 100Wh and 160Wh, and this should be approved previously by the check-in counter people. Those with power of less than 100Wh do not need declaration and may be taken on board, but the number will be limited to personal use.
According to Eric Fong, the airport has already received notifications from six or seven airlines on the adjustment of rules in this context.
 
Cam will increase capital in response to the expansion of the airport
The Campo General Assembly approved yesterday the capital increase in the needs of the Macao Airport expansion project. A deliberation was also approved about the “project for rehabilitation and improvement of the track”, and the company coordinated to carry out the work of consolidation and coating of the track while the expansion work at night will be performed. To meet the expansion project financing needs, it was decided to issue new ordinary actions this year to increase the company's capital by 500 million Patacas, thus launching a “solid base” for the development of the long -term airport, said CAM. By 2024, Camp revenues ascended to 1.478 billion patacas, plus 24% in terms annually, with profits before taxes reached 383 million, the highest value after the pandemic. In addition, CAM revealed that the public tender for the league terminal project is completed by hengqin, and the expected construction is the second quarter of this year.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Balance of earthquake in Myanmar already surpasses two thousand dead</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/balanco-de-sismo-em-myanmar-ja-supera-dois-mil-mortos/</link><description>The provisional balance of earthquake victims in Myanmar increased to 2,056 dead and more than 3,900 injured, the Military Junta who rules the country announced yesterday. A military spokesman in power said 270 people were still missing, three days after the 7.7 magnitude earthquake that also hit Thailand.
The board decreed seven days of national mourning, until April 6, as a “recognition for the loss of life and the damage caused” by the earthquake, which destroyed thousands of buildings, roads and bridges.
Meanwhile, rescuers are still looking for missing in the rubble. Teams from rescuer sent by China have rescued three people in recent hours, including a 29-year-old pregnant woman and a five-year-old child in the city of Mandalay (downtown Myanmar), just 20 kilometers from Friday's earthquake epicenter. "All were sent to the hospital for treatment," said the China embassy.
The United Nations (UN) stated that the “magnitude of the disaster” provoked by the “remains uncertain” earthquake. In a statement, the multilateral organization team in Myanmar reported a “widespread destruction” and whole communities devastated by the earthquake.
"Hospitals in the affected regions are overloaded and communication and transportation routes have been severely interrupted. Thousands of people are sleeping in the open, fearing secondary tremors and unable to return to their damaged homes," he said.
Non-governmental organizations and sources on site confirm that destruction in the cities of Mandalay-the second largest in the country-and Sagaing, those closest to the epicenter, is extensive.
The UN demanded “unrestricted access” to send humanitarian personnel to the country, which has been living an armed conflict that has worsened since the military coup in 2021. The military is also denying the entry of the foreign press to cover the earthquake, which justify with difficulties in finding housing and cuts of energy and water.
UN Humanitarian Coordinator in Southeast Asian country, Marcoluigi Corsi, said the agency is mobilizing emergency medical teams, shelter materials, food, water, sanitation and hygiene aid, "despite the serious logistical challenges." China, which promised to provide 100 million yuans in “Emergency Humanitarian Aid,” sent the first lot of assistance material yesterday, consisting of first aid tents, blankets and equipment.
The earthquake also caused the death of 19 people in the Thai capital, Bangcoque, after the collapse of a building under construction. Rescuers continued to look for about 80 people as missing yesterday, according to the Thai newspaper The Nation.
 
JTM with Lusa and International Agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Awarded 16 “healthy companies”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/premiadas-16-empresas-saudaveis/</link><description>The “Healthy Company” program awarded 16 companies from various sectors for implementing health promotion measures over 2024, covering about 100,000 workers
 
MGM, China Industrial and Commercial Bank, Macao China Bank, Four Star Company, Sands China, Nam Kwong - Commercial and Industrial Union, Macau Science Center, Macao Telecommunications Company, Macao Electricity Company, National Overseas Bank, Galaxy Entertainment, Macau Water Supply Society, Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, Wynnn Resorts, TDM - Macao teledifusion and SJM Resorts received the “healthy company” distinction because they achieved remarkable results in “creating a healthy culture at the workplace” over the past year.
The “Healthy Company” program, launched at the end of 2023, by the Healthy City Commission and Health Services (SSM) aims to integrate health promotion measures in the workplace and create a healthy work environment under Macao Feliz.
The SSM director highlighted the implementation of participating companies of policies and measures that include the supply of healthy eating, sports and psychological health support, health monitoring equipment, information dissemination and the promotion of health activities. Alvis Lo Iek Long said that the measures “fully raised the quality of workers' health” and achieved “a win-win situation” for both companies and workers.
According to the SSM, the program benefited about 100,000 workers from the 16 companies, demonstrating “a broad influence of the program with the various sectors of society”.
Together, companies organized a total of 202 sessions for workers, which included workshops, experience courses, challenges, lectures, among others, to reinforce employee involvement and interactivity, raise consciousness and health knowledge level and promote healthy lifestyles.
According to a note from the SSM, all companies that participated in the program promoted sports through regular reminders and staff education. Workers were encouraged to do simple stretching exercises and develop regular exercise habits.
In 98 workplaces of 15 of the participating companies, health self-assessment stations were installed, with blood voltage meters and scales, among other devices, which were used by about 51,000 workers.
The 10 companies with restaurants for workers have established 22 “healthy eating” restaurants, offering a variety of healthy dishes and benefiting 85,000 people a day. In the same sense, given guidelines for the practice of healthy and balanced eating.
The SSM also released, periodically, information about health activities and programs, to help companies integrate the latest health information in internal dissemination, sensitizing workers. The program has a mechanism that evaluates various parameters from the implementation of policies and measures to the degree of workers' satisfaction.
This year, the number of participating companies increased to 26, which, according to the SSM, "reflects a wide recognition and support of all sectors of society" in the construction of a "happy macao".</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Maritime energy transition target of study at the MSAR</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/transicao-energetica-maritima-alvo-de-estudo-na-raem/</link><description>Macau was one of the places selected by the University of Portsmouth, the United Kingdom, to study the inheritance of the energy transition in the coastal communities of the global southern coastal and how they cross the era of decarbonization, the person responsible for the project told Lusa. Relief commercial warehouse has a “very rich history” linked to the sea, a factor that weighed on the center's decision to port cities and maritime cultures.
"It is probably one of the first European enclaves in East Asia and has a long history of international travel by sea from 1500," researcher Melanie Bassett said. The creation of a doctoral research scholarship will bring to MSAR an academic, which is still the mission to understand how these communities can adapt to a sustainable future.
The project “From Spa to Steam, from Carbon to Green: Training Port Communities in the Global South”, which extends for six and a half years, started in February, with the investigation to focus on the Peruvian Port of Callao, but should later expand two other regions “somewhere in the Indian subcontinent and western Africa”.
Only the investigation will bring tangible results, but Bassett points out that, with the primacy of the steam vessel, the travel of communities and industries were generally away from the sea waterfront. Changes have also occurred in several businesses linked to the sector, from the fishing industry to naval construction.
“We anticipate seeing this kind of changes, but also with the advent of European colonization, we see changes in cultures and architecture and how it affects the population, and then how, over time, these cultures merge and hybridize to create new cultures and new understandings of the world,” he said.
Lloyds Register Foundation finances the project, which, in the case of Macau, will be collaborated by the University of Macao and the Maritime Museum. It is also expected to have the communities active. Therefore, the recruitment of the academic that will lead the investigation requires language skills to ensure communication with the population.
Recruitment for this research that is divided between Portsmouth and Macau is expected to be completed in April, and the project starts in October.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>USJ and University of Minho united by cooperation agreement</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/usj-universidade-minho-unidas-por-acordo-de-cooperacao/</link><description>The University of São José sent a delegation to Portugal to sign a cooperation protocol with the University of Minho and participate in the Porto Education Fair. The Purple aimed to promote academic exchange between the two places and promote Macau as a destination for foreign students
 
In order to expand existing collaboration and reinforce the cooperation network, the University of São José (USJ) sent a delegation to the University of Minho (Uminho) to sign a protocol between the two institutions.
According to a USJ note, the agreement aims to develop, over five years, “partnerships in teaching, research, technological innovation and entrepreneurship”, joint conferences and “student mobility programs, academic and technical personnel”.
For USJ, UMinho is currently recognized for the “competence and quality of its faculty”, the excellence of scientific research, the high level of interaction with other institutions and the “vast offer of courses”. It also plays a central role in the region, being an important reference and “a recognized partner in the European and world landscape,” says the statement.
The USJ delegation joined the Vice Rector for internationalization and academic affairs, Álvaro Barbosa, the vice-rector for academic investigation and innovation, Alexandre Lobo, and the head of the USJ delegation in Portugal, Francisco Peixoto.
USJ was also present at the “Qualifica” Education Fair, in Porto, for the second consecutive year, having been the only higher education institution in Asia to be present at the event. “Qualifica” is an annual fair that acts as a vital platform for universities to bind to potential students and executives in Porto.
According to USJ, it had more than 42,000 visitors, who included high school and postgraduate students, advisors and teachers from the city of Porto, interested in pursuing studies in Asia.
Throughout the event, visitors of the USJ Pavilion have shown “especially interested in knowing the Macao Higher Education System”, as well as the opportunities for scholarships available to students from Portuguese-speaking countries and the university's admission process. USJ promoted “The Distinct Cultural Profile of Macao” as a “exceptional destination” for foreign students.
This year's edition also inaugurated a postgraduate and executive pavilion, dedicated to masters, doctors and executive training programs, in which USJ was present. In addition to Francisco Peixoto, the delegation included the head of the International Affairs Office, Ana Paula Mota.
In the same statement, the university thanked the support of the Directorate of Education and Development Services of Youth and the Fund of Education of Mashes “to make possible participation in the Education Fair”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>One will open a master's degree on education in Ia</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/um-vai-abrir-mestrado-sobre-educacao-em-ia/</link><description>In the school year 2026/2027, the University of Macao (one) will begin teaching a Master in Artificial Intelligence Education (IA) lasting two years, yesterday revealed Yonghua Song, Rector of UM. He explained, the institution is proceeding to the curriculum preparation and hiring of teachers, in the hope that the new course contributes to forming, more systematically and comprehensively, teachers who teach IA content in primary and secondary education. In addition, quoted by the “or Mun Tin Toi”, Yonghua Song pointed to the employment problems resulting from AI development, stressing that university education needs to be adjusted so that students of different courses can also master the knowledge about AI, thus strengthening competitiveness in the labor market. In this aspect, the Rector of UM stressed that the institution encourages students to use AI tools, as well as promoting general knowledge of AI in different areas. The rector of UM spoke on the sidelines of a forum on the interdisciplinary promotion of sustainable development, organized by one together with the University of Cambridge, with the participation of more than 20 academics. In his intervention, Yonghua Song said that urban diversified economic development brings challenges and problems in sustainable development, climate change, energy supply and low carbon economy. UM Rector argued that these problems should be discussed at the political, regulatory and technical level through the social and human sciences.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief presents lag on April 14</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-apresenta-lag-dia-14-de-abril/</link><description>Session of presentation and clarification on the political program of the candidate for the position of Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, in the building of Forum Macau, in Macau, China, September 28, 2024. Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro/Lusa



The Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, goes to the Legislative Assembly (AL) on April 14 to submit the Governing Action Lines Report (LAG) for the Financial Year of 2025. The session is scheduled for 15h00. That same day, there will be a press conference at 5:30 pm at the government headquarters, in which it will respond to the media. The next day, at 15h00, the leader of the MSAR will again be in Hemiciclo to answer the deputies' questions about the lag. The sectoral debates are then followed, starting with the administration and justice portfolio, with André Cheong moving to AL on April 17. Already Tai Kin IP presents the lag for the economy and finance area on the 23rd and Wong Sio Chak will do so on April 25. The debates of the folders of Social and Culture and Transport and Public Works are then left, with Lam and Raymond Tam to travel to AL on April 28 and 30, respectively. This year, and contrary to what has happened in recent years, the debate of different folders will take place in the morning and afternoon (from 09h30 to 13h00 and from 15h00 to 20h00). The presentation of the report, the press conference and the deputies' questions session to the Chief Executive may be accompanied live on TDM. Debates can also be followed on various internet channels, including on the Government of the Government portal, and on the chief executive's office pages, the Al and the Social Communication Office (GCS), as well as the mobile and facebook and Facebook channel applications. In addition, GCS's Facebook and English pages, recently created, will also disclose information about LAG.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2371/</link><description>UCM academic will perform
Investigations at the Palace Museum
Zhao Qiang, from the City of Macau University (UCM), became the first academic of the Rae selected for the “Scholarship Program for Academics Visitors of the Taihe Palace Museum”. Under the program, academics were invited and funded of excellence of museums and higher education institutions in the world, to conduct investigations at the Palace Museum, with a view to promoting interpretations of Chinese civilization from new perspectives. To the Chinese language press, Zhao Qiang has revealed that he will move to the Department of Protection of Cultural Relics and Science and Technology of the Palace Museum between June and December, to conduct academic exchanges and investigations. Zhao specializes in old handwriting and painting and identification of Buddhist cultural relics.
 
Road Works Platform
available for private
Private entities now have access to some features of the “uniform platform for road works management”, experimental. The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) and the Institute for Municipal Affairs reported that users of the “Platform for Business and Associations” may already require, at the same time, the license to open ditches on public roads and the warning of provisional traffic measures. DSAT will follow the results of this pilot phase to evaluate the progressive expansion of the features.
 
Completed 1st phase of works
on Avenida Marginal do Patane
The first phase of the work of lifting and assembling the steel structure of the upper pass for pedestrians on the Marginal Avenue of Patane was completed in advance. Provisional traffic measures have already been raised, but vehicle circulation will remain conditioned in a part of the section until mid -April, according to public works services. It is expected that the construction of the superior passage to pedestrians will be completed in September.
 
Public Notices of the Courts
Pass the electronics
The edicts published by the courts of the three instances of the MSAR have passed, since yesterday to be disclosed through electronic, at the site of courts. The objective, according to the office of the president of the last court, is to replace the form of posting in the courts and the headquarters of the Institute for municipal affairs, as well as to promote the development of digitization. In the future, the courts will promote, in an orderly manner, the digitization of matters of justice, in order to provide more convenient electronic services to the population.
 
Parking at Mong Son
with collection for half an hour
The public parking park of the Mong Son Building, located on Avenida de Venceslau de Morais, starts in operation today. The space, consisting of three cellars, offers 530 places for light cars and 338 for motorcycles and mopeds. The park does not provide a monthly pass, all vehicles being charged for half an hour of permanence, with three -patacas tariffs for cars during the day and 1.5 patacas at night. The motorcycles will pay one and 0.5 patacas, respectively. The information contains an order of the Chief Executive.
 
DSAT launches inquiry
on buses
Throughout April, the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) will carry out the quarterly assessment survey of the public bus service of the first quarter of this year. DSAT calls for passenger participation through the mobile applications “Bus Location” and “Macao Smart Go”, as well as the DSAT Electronic page. The evaluation score is based on three indicators: “Service and Management”, “Transport and Safety and Safety Equipment” and “Degree of Passenger Satisfaction”.
 
Subsidy request for
Disabled begins today
Starting today and by the end of the month, the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) accepts requests for the “Plan of the Supplementary Subsidy to Labor Income for workers with disabilities” from the first quarter of 2025. The printed, to be filled by local workers who meet the requirements, can be raised at the premises of DSAL and the social security institute, or unloaded on the theme page Dsal on the plane.
 
More than 530 students
explore nautical culture
In the last quarter, more than 530 students from nine secondary schools participated in the activities of the “Program for the Dissemination of Maritime Knowledge in Schools - let's get to know the sea security”. The Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs Services (DSAMA) has organized four activities, such as lectures on sea knowledge, maritime experience and guided tours of the Maritime Museum and the guide headlight. According to Dsama, since 2022 the program has involved more than 7,300 participants in the 109 sessions designed to stimulate students' interest in nautical culture.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Air Macau net loss rose 240% to 656 million</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/prejuizo-liquido-da-air-macau-subiu-240-para-656-milhoes/</link><description>Air Macau's financial situation was aggravated by 2024, with the company to suffer net loss more than 650 million patacas, more than three times the previous year, although operating revenues have grown about 16%. Since 2020, the carrier has accumulated nearly four billion patacas in losses
 
Sérgio Terra
 
Air Macau's 2024 financial year ended with net losses of 595 million Renminbis (about 656.6 million patacas to the current exchange rate), according to data registered in the annual report of Air China, a majority shareholder of the MSAR carrier. In the fifth consecutive year with negative results, the value of losses increased by 240%, ie 3.4 times, compared to 175 million Renminbis (193.1 million) reported a year earlier, according to Air China information, although Air Macao has eventually declared losses of 236 million patacas in 2023, a discrepancy that arrests with accounting and currency factors.
According to the annual reports analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, Air Macau accumulated more than 3.7 billion in net losses between 2020 and 2024, more than double the profits generated in the previous 10 years (about 1.7 billion). The year 2020 was the most negative, with the losses to reach approximately 1.04 billion.
In the first half of last year, the airline had already registered a negative balance of 378 million Renminbis (about 417.1 million patacas), 118.5% more than between January and June 2023, due to the aggravation of operating costs.
The Air China report reveals, on the other hand, that the MSAR Flag Company's operating revenues increased by 15.85% to 3.11 billion Renminbis (3.43 billion of patacas) in the 2024 general calculation compared to the previous annual year. In the first half, revenues had advanced 20.6% to 1.47 billion Renminbis (1.62 billion patacas) in annual terms.
Over the past year, Air Macau transported 3.21 million passengers, a number that represents an annual increase of 56.41% and corresponds to 87.7% of the 3.66 million record reached in 2019. Flight occupation rate reached 74.59%, plus 2.93 percentage points than 2023.
In the air transport chapter, the recovery has been higher on the demand side than the offer. RPK (average passenger/kilometer revenue), an indicator that reflects the real demand for transport, rose 59.5% between 2023 and 2024, while ASK (places available per kilometer) grew 53.23%.
At the end of 2024, the Air Macau fleet consisted of 23 aircraft (plus three), all manufactured by Airbus, with an average age of 8.54 years.
According to Air China, Macao's total assets were valued at almost 5.56 billion Renminbis (6.13 billion patacas) in late 2024.
In December, the Government of MSAR indicated that it will inject 344 million more at Air Macau in 2025, as the company "has faced a difficult exploration situation that led to relevant losses" resulting from "the suffering of accumulation of various unfavorable factors." According to an opinion from the 2nd Permanent Committee of the Legislative Assembly on the Budget Proposal for 2025, which cites a representative of the Executive, Air Macau is “in a situation of capital mobility” and to feel “the pressure of the reimbursement of the loan and payment of their interest”, so that the mainstream partner proposed that the rame will provide financial support through a capital increase.
This is the fourth time Air Macau has been in accordance with the main shareholders since 2009. The “China National Aviation Corporation” - integrated into Air China's “Holding” - is the largest shareholder of Air Macau, with 66.9%of the capital, followed by 21.5%, and the Macao Tourism and Diverse Society (STDM), with 11.57%. The shareholder group also includes “Evergreen Airways Service”, IPE (Macau) - investments and business participation, the Macao World Trade Center and the Macao Insurance Company, with residual appearances.
 
Largest Chinese carriers remain in the “red”
In 2024, China's three main state airlines completed five successive years in the “red”, although they were able to reduce joint losses by 53.4% ​​to about 6.2 billion Renminbis compared to 2023. Competition in the domestic market, the weak search for international and business travel, supply chain problems, and the devaluation of currency appear as the main challenges pointed out by Air China, China Eastern Airlines and China Southern Airlines. Air China has announced a net loss of 230 million Renminbis (-99%in annual terms), China Eastern lost 4.2 billion (-48.6%) and China Southern suffered losses of 1.8 billion (-57.2%).</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lisbon replenishes EPM financing after 11 years of cuts</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lisboa-repoe-financiamento-da-epm-apos-11-anos-de-cortes/</link><description>Fulfilling the usual rulers of the Portuguese Republic when moving to Macau, the Minister of State and Foreign Affairs of Portugal, Paulo Rangel, was at the Portuguese school. He visited the facilities, was received with flowers and was sensitized to hear “The Portuguese” sung by the students of the educational establishment. In the end, he announced that the Portuguese government replaced financial support to the school, whose “role” made a point of stressing

Victor Rebelo
 
The visit to the territory was short, but, as usual, the Portuguese School of Macau (EPM) was a mandatory point of passage to the Minister of State and Foreign Affairs of Portugal. Paulo Rangel was received with flowers, heard “The Portuguese” -and was sensitized -visited the facilities and met with the leaders of the educational establishment. In the end, it was known that the Portuguese government replaced financial support to the EPM.
The cut in the support of the government of Portugal to the EPM had been set up, with the contribution of only 10% in the expenses of the school. Holding 51% of the EPM Foundation's capital since the Troika time in 2014 that successive governments have reduced the amount, a situation that has caused some dissatisfaction in school leaders over these long years.
Speaking to journalists already during the reception to the Portuguese community, the Portuguese Minister of Foreign Affairs said the financing is again “at legal levels”, which is the first time “after 11 years”.
Paulo Rangel considered that there was no longer "reason" to have this cut, so the government of Luís Montenegro, currently in management, increased the value assigned. Jorge Neto Valente, president of the EPM Foundation, told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that the amount granted became 1.2 million euros, an increase of just over 40% compared to what was being paid in recent years, 776 thousand euros.
"The increase is something that is highly significant of the commitment we have," said Paulo Rangel, adding that "there are governments that really give importance to Macau and China and there are others that do not," in a clear accusation to the government of the socialist party that has been in power in the last eight years. The help that will now be granted by Lisbon to EPM is “important” in a school that “has a role to play in Macao,” said the head of Portuguese diplomacy.
Rangel also recorded “pleasing” that “there have never been so many Portuguese students - and now I speak of students from the Chinese community - as there are today in multiple schools”. "It means that masters have also encouraged Portuguese teaching and knowledge of Portuguese, and this is something that can only bring good relationships between both sides," he said.
After visiting the school, the president of the EPM Foundation was pleased with the meeting. "We talked at the meeting that this year, exceptionally, there was a greater commitment to the Portuguese state by increasing the subsidy for the school as established, which had not been happening for many years," said Neto Valente.
“It is always positive to exchange from a living of a living of the perception of reality and the visit of the minister allowed us to show unanimity of points of view regarding the operation of the school and the needs we have,” said the manager. The EPM Foundation number one revealed that the minister was "sensitized to the situation of the school, which is the only Portuguese school in China, which has its characteristics and its own needs."
Neto Valente considers that the meeting was positive: "He was also pleased, because, as well as knowledge, you never know everything." "It was an opportunity for those here to express what they think and the concerns they have, and his, as minister, to ask questions to be aware of the situation," he added.
On the issue of teachers, so spoken in the first months of the academic year, Paulo Rangel learned of the difficulties felt by the EPM. “These are the only difficulties regarding Portugal,” which is the coming of teachers to Macau, “for whom we need a license from the Ministry of Education, so we have sensitized the Minister of Foreign Affairs and asked him to intercede in this regard,” said Jorge Neto Valente.
 
Minister sensitized when hearing the anthem
Fulfilling the usual rulers of the Portuguese Republic when they move to Macau, Paulo Rangel was at EPM on Friday morning, in the one that was the first visit point in the territory. It was just at 10:15 am when the Minister of State and Foreign Affairs of Portugal entered the facilities of the educational establishment, accompanied by the consul General of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong, Alexandre Leitão, after being received abroad by the director of EPM, Acácio de Brito, by the president and vice president of the EPM Foundation, Jorge Neto Valente and Miguel de Senna Fernandes.
In compliance with the chief of Portuguese diplomacy, Edite Silva, president of the EPM curators, Filipe Figueiredo, president of the EPM Parents and Parents Association, Diana Antunes, president of the EPM Student Association, and Patrícia Ribeiro, director of the Portuguese Institute of Oriente (IPOR) were also.
Inside the school, Paulo Rangel received a branch of flowers and headed to the outdoor space, where the outdoor recreation operates. The minister was waiting for a few dozen students from the first and second cycles, all with yellow and blue uniforms, and the EPM choir, wearing in shades of blue, which played the Portugal anthem.
Paulo Rangel and all his companions, including elements of his office, listened closely to the stanzas of the anthem, from “heroes of the sea ..” to “against marching, marching cannons”, applauding the performance of young students. "I liked it a lot, it was impeccable, you were very well," said the minister.
"One of the great rewards of being in foreign affairs is to reach the four corners of the world and to see, on the one hand, the knowledge of Portugal, which is sometimes deeper than in Europe, and then we have the Portuguese anthem sung by children, students, clearly from the Portuguese community, but also other Chinese. It is evident that it cuts the heart of anyone and we feel completely at home."
After listening to “The Portuguese”, the ruler toured the first floor of the building, attentive to Acácio de Brito's explanations, passing in the corridor through several classrooms, until entering the meeting site in a space adjacent to the school's director, for a conversation with representatives of the EPM.
After the meeting, Paulo Rangel moved to the headquarters of the government to meet the chief executive, during which the relations between Portugal and China, with Macao as a platform, were addressed.
In the afternoon, he was at the Portuguese Consulate General in Macau and Hong Kong, including IPOR and AICEP, and had a meeting with the three counselors of the Portuguese communities elected by the Circle of China. He then headed in the middle of the afternoon to Hong Kong, where he visited the exhibition “Lush Stories” at the Raehk History Museum, and the Lusitano club. That same night, he returned to Lisbon.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Tapau’ and several Asian expressions added to the Oxford dictionary</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/tapau-varias-expressoes-asiaticas-adicionadas-ao-dicionario-de-oxford/</link><description>"Alamak" and "Nasi Lemak" were added to the Oxford English Dictionary (Oed) for the first time. According to the dictionary, they are among a series of “intradisible words” of Malaysia, Singapore or Hong Kong who arrived at the last update in March.
Borrowed from the Malaysian language, the colloquial exclamation “Alamak”, since its first appearance recorded in 1952, is used to convey surprise, shock, dismay or indignation.
The original names of various eating items were also added to the dictionary, reflecting the influence of Malaysian cuisine in both countries. These include ketupat (a small rice cake cooked in an entrenched palm leaf bag) and otak-key (ground fish or other shellfish mixed with spices and coconut milk, wrapped in banana or palm-cooked or grilled coal-cooked sheets).
Singapore's "Kaya Toast" and "Kaya Toast" and "Half-Boiled Egg" were also included in the last update, along with the ever-green "Nasi Lemak" and two plates with angliced ​​names-"Fish Head Carry" and "Steam Boat".
Another popular colloquial word that came to the dictionary is “Tapau”, which means packing food to take and is used daily in Hong Kong, Macau or Canton.
Another definition of the word "terror" - which can mean terrible or horrible, but can also be a general approval term that means admirable or excellent - was equally integrated into the dictionary. According to the OED, terror is often preceded by "Wah" and followed by "aiaaah" or "wah! Soterrorlah."
Other words from all over the world who arrived at the OED updated edition include “Yoh!” from South Africa. (A cry or exclamation that is used to express various emotions or reactions, such as surprise, admiration, shock or anguish) and “gigil” of the Philippines. "Giligil" refers to the feeling that people have when they see someone or something cute, such an intense feeling that creates an irresistible will to tighten their hands hard, grind their teeth and pinch or tighten the person or thing they find so adorable.
This is not the first time Asian words have appeared in the OED.
In 2016, he added 19 new items from “Singapore English” to his lexicon, including the words “Blur”, “Ang Moh” and “Shiok”.
For the year there will be a new update at Oxford English Dictionary!
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>