<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Au Kam San accused of violating State Security Law</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/au-kam-san-acusado-de-violar-lei-de-seguranca-estado/</link><description>Former Deputy Au Kam San was arrested, under the scope of the first case of suspicions of violation of the law on the defense of state security. The Judicial Police said yesterday in a statement that he had "strong evidence" that the individual he stopped was in collusion with a "anti-china organization", having provided "a large amount of false provocative information, for public display abroad and online." In addition, he will "disturb" the election to the 2024 Chief Executive, as well as "to which foreign countries take measures against Macao." Au was yesterday present to the prosecutor, a day after being taken from his home. The crime that you are accused can be punished with prison sentence of three to 10 years
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Au Kam San was arrested on suspicion of violating the law on the defense of state security-this is thus the first case in Macao prosecutors under the law since 2009, but was revised in 2023. Although the Judicial Police (PJ) mention the defendant only by the AU nickname, the former deputy was confirmed yesterday. On Wednesday afternoon, Au Kam San was intercepted at his residence in the Central Zone and taken to the PJ facilities for investigation. Yesterday, it was present to the Public Prosecution Service (MP) for the crime of “establishment of connections with organizations, associations or individuals from outside the MSAR for the practice of state security”.
The Jornal Tribuna de Macao contacted PJ yesterday morning to know more details about the detention, but did not receive any response until the closing of this edition. At a press conference that took place yesterday afternoon, the PJ said it had no more information to give. In the same line, the MP told this newspaper no information to provide.
According to a PJ statement, the authorities have found that Au “has acted since 2022 with an anti-china organization that is outside the sinhers and has provided a large amount of false provocative information for public display abroad and online on social networks”. However, even after the entry into force of the Revised Law, "this organization continued to use the information in its activities with the same effect."
That "false information" is these or what concern, the authorities do not explain; Nor do they name that organization is at stake.
In addition, the PJ suspected that Au Kam San -who was a deputy for 20 years, between 2001 and 2021 -"has kept contacts for a long time, with several anti -china entities that are outside the masters." It will also have provided "repeatedly false information about Macau to these entities or the media operated by these entities, for the purpose of advertising and dissemination."
The PJ says that these actions have aroused "hatred" among residents of Macao "and even among people from various countries who are unaware of the truth about the Central RPC government and the Government of MSAR, disturbing the election to the 2024 executive head in Macao and leading to foreign countries to take action against Macau."
"After a long period of investigation and proof accumulation, the subunit dedicated to the defense of PJ State Security was able to identify a 68-year-old Macao resident of Au, adopted actions yesterday afternoon [Wednesday] and intercepted the individual in his residence in the central zone, which was taken to the PJ facilities for investigation."
According to what was determined in the investigation, the PJ considers that “there are strong evidence that the individual, in a nickname, in collusion for a long time with external forces, collaborated in the collection or public dissemination of false or grossly deformed news, acting isolated or jointly to incite the hatred against the Central Popular Government, to provoke anti-china forces to take hostile actions against the People's Republic of China and the fields, and disturb the elections in the masters, seriously endangered the security of the state. ”
According to the law in force, the establishment of links with organizations, associations or individuals from outside the MSAR for acts against state security can be punished with prison sentence of three to ten years. Acts include “unlawfully disturbing the organs of the central political power of the state in the definition and execution of laws and policies”, “manipulating or harming the elections of masters”, “imposing sanctions or blockages, or involving other hostile actions against the State or against the MSAR” or “incites, using any illicit means, mashely residents against the Central Popular Government consequences ”.
A holder of Portuguese nationality, Au Kam San worked as a teacher and founded the Novo Macau Association - which advocated the introduction of universal suffrage in the election to the Legislative Assembly, as well as in the election of the chief executive. It was also one of the main organizers of the June 4 vigils over more than three decades.
The Jornal Tribuna de Macao sent an email to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Portugal, in order to obtain a comment from the minister, Paulo Rangel, about this case, however, until the closing of this edition did not receive any response.
In addition to Au Kam San was present yesterday to the MP, also his wife, Virginia Cheang Mio San, will have gone to testify. According to the online newspaper “All About Macau”, Au Kam San's family was unaware of his situation from the moment of detention at 4 pm on Wednesday, and until at least 3 pm yesterday. At the time of the closing of this edition, there was no information on what the next measures the authorities would take.</description><pubDate>2025-08-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mand GDP with modest growth</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pib-da-raem-crescimento-modesto/</link><description>In the first six months of the year, the MSAR GDP was in 200.1 billion patacas, rising only 1.8% in annual terms, contrasting with the annual increase of 15.7% registered in the first six months of 2024. In the second quarter, the territory economy grew 5.1% in annual terms and 0.6% compared to the previous period, from January to March, from March to March
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Gross Domestic Product (GDP) only increased by 1.8% in the first six months of this year, in real and annual terms, with preliminary data released by statistics and censuses (DSEC) to point to 200.14 billion patacas, representing 87% of the economic volume of the same period of 2019. GDP was led by 204.3 billion, increasing annually 15.7%.
In the second quarter, the economy was encrypted at 100.38 billion patacas, plus 5.1% in real terms, compared to the same year's same year quarter. In this case, GDP equivalent to 88.8% of the economic volume recorded in the second quarter of 2019. After six consecutive quarters of slowdown between April and June, GDP rose 0.62% compared to the previous period (January to March), considering the still preliminary data and taking into account the first quarter -reviewed numbers.
DSEC points out that "Macao's economy has grown again due to significant recovery of service exports, driven by the remarkable increase in the number of visitors that benefited from a number of measures (…), and the maintenance of private consumer expense in the local market to have stabilized."
Analyzing the main components of GDP, global exports of service increased 5.8% in homologous terms, as the number of visitors in Macao rose about 20% in the second quarter of this year. Regarding internal demand, the government's final consumer consumption and private consumer expense also increased by 1.1% and 0.3%, respectively, in annual terms. In turn, gross fixed capital formation decreased by 3.6%due to the decrease in the number of private construction works.
Between January and March, it is recalled, the GDP of the MSA retreated annually for the first time since the end of 2022, suffering a break of 1.3%. The GDP was then headquartered at 99.76 billion. At the time, one of the justifications for the scenario was the “change in the consumption pattern of visitors”. DSEC said, nevertheless, that the local economy would not mark a cyclic recession, "if there are no major changes in the internal and external context."
In April, the International Monetary Fund again reduced projections on the economy of Macao, pointing to a 3.6% growth in 2025, half of the estimated announced in October, and a 3.5% rise in 2026. Expectations regarding the world economy also suffered a cut to 2.8% this year, with the IMF warning that the “rapid climbing of commercial tensions” and the high “political uncertainty” should have to have "A significant impact on global economic activity."
In the general calculation of 2024, the territory GDP increased by 8.8%, in annual and real terms, reaching 84.6%of the volume of 2019, however, it fell short of government projections, which had pointed to 10.3%.
The data now released by DSEC are only preliminary, and the detailed and reviewed results for the second quarter will be known on August 15.</description><pubDate>2025-08-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Continent students attracted by the Portuguese summer course of a</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/alunos-continente-atraidos-pelo-curso-de-verao-de-portugues-da-um/</link><description>The University of Macao finished another edition of the Portuguese Summer Course. This time, there was an increase in the number of students compared to last year, 406, equivalent to an 18%increase. According to Vítor Silva, one of the course coordinators, most students came from the interior of China, making 81% of the total. In addition, 61% of students attended the beginner level of the course. To the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the teacher has set a positive balance of this year's edition, arguing that the initiative is able to “entice” more and more people

Catarina Pereira
 
Another edition of the summer course promoted by the Portuguese Department of Macao (one) ended. Over the course of several weeks, students from around the world have been in the territory to learn more about the language of Camões. One of the initiative's coordinators, Vítor Silva, told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that "it was a very well achieved goal by the one and that it was noted even by the increase in the number of students." This year there were 406, against 343 in 2024, an 18%rise.
Most students are from mainland China, a total of 331, equivalent to 81.5% of the total. There were also 67 from Macau, three from Timor-Leste, one from Taiwan and one from Australia. "In general, the 18 classes had all between 20 and 23 students, and 10 classes were from the basic level, four of the elementary, three of the intermediate and one of advanced," explained Vitor Silva, stiving that much are of initiation.
In concrete, the teacher indicated that 248 students attended the level of initiation, representing 61% of the total, while 96 were at the elementary level, 48 in the intermediate and 14 at the advanced level. "Many students were, for example, the elementary level coming from China, many of them from places like Sichuan, Beijing ... But many students come from other degrees or who come from other tongues, but not exactly Portuguese. Hence there is this exponential number of basic level classes," said Vítor Silva.
The teacher at UM indicated that most of the students are from the first years of undergraduate, with the exception of 24 who are sent by the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services, which are a little younger, as they attend secondary schools. "Of course there is one or another more specific case. I am remembering a student who came from Xinjiang, a degree in Economics, who is studying Portuguese because he was working in Angola," he said.
The intermediate and advanced levels had 45 hours of language -oriented disciplines and three 15 -hour modules, facing other related aspects: literature, translation and interpretation and even research.
According to Vítor Silva, the course worked more or less in the same way as the last two editions, in addition to the classes themselves, there were activities for students to also bind to culture. "In the afternoon they had folk dances and capoeira. They also had two other topics, which was introduction to Portuguese -speaking countries and another entitled Contemporary Portugal," he said.
In addition, "the teachers were all motivated to take their students, to take each class, for example, to walk around the city, there were some who went to visit exhibitions." "I, for example, took two classes to the rija trunk," he added, explaining that they could get to know a little about Portuguese cuisine. "The students also took advantage of for a walk in Coloane and mud, and it is certainly a context that do not have in the places where they live," he said.
As for the number of teachers, in this 39th edition 20 language teachers or specific areas were involved. "There were some classes that had a first part with one teacher and another with another teacher, given the difficulty of finding teachers at this time," explained Vitor Silva. In addition, there were other trainers for extracurricular activities.
Vítor Silva considers that the Portuguese summer course “has all the conditions to continue to be increasingly enticing and motivate more people”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Diocese of Macau opens process for Beatification of Father Nicosía</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/diocese-de-macau-abre-processo-para-beatificacao-padre-nicosia/</link><description>The Diocese of Macao opened a process for the beatification and canonization of Father Gaetano Nicosía, who died in 2017 in Hong Kong. Since, according to canonical provisions, it is necessary to gather all the writings attributed to him, such as diaries, letters or others, the diocese asks those who return them to the Diocesan Court of Macao, if they have not yet been delivered to Salesian postulation, can be read in an edict signed by the Bishop of Macau, D. Stephen Lee, and Reverend Cyril Jerome Law, Jr. “Those who wish to conserve the originals may present a copy, which will be properly authenticated,” adds the diocese.
Moreover, the diocese asks all the faithful to communicate "all the information that can somehow be deduced elements in favor or against the reputation of holiness of said servant of God Father Gaetano Nicosía."
Born in Italy in 1915, Father Gaetano Nicosía arrived in China in 1935 as a missionary. He became Salesian of Don Bosco in 1937, continued his Salesian and Priestly Formation in Hong Kong and Macau, where he was ordered a priest at the São José Seminary Church in 1946.
“After 17 years of work in Salesian houses at the service of young people and faithful from Macao, Hong Kong and Continental China, in 1963 was sent to take care of leprosy patients [lepers] near Ká-Hó, Coloane, Macao. It served them and other Hansen patients for 47 years, while also serving poor and abandoned children,” recalls the diocese.
Severely injured in 2010, he was hospitalized in Hong Kong, having been assisted by the small sisters of the poor, in whose home of the elderly Santa Maria died on November 6, 2017, already 102 years old.
As “his reputation for holiness and signs has been growing over the years,” the general postulant of the Salesians of Don Bosco, Father Pierluigi Cameroni, asked in January last year to begin the cause of beatification and canonization. In May this year was obtained the “Nihil Odstat”, that is, a statement that there is nothing contrary to the opening of this process.
 
Catarina Pereira</description><pubDate>2025-08-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MGM won five billion in six months</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mgm-ganhou-cinco-mil-milhoes-em-seis-meses/</link><description>MGM China's operational gains totaled nearly $ 5 billion from Hong Kong in the first six months of this year, after the company registered a new quarterly record in this chapter between April and June. The results were driven by the growth of the quota in the game market, to 16.6%
 
Sérgio Terra
 
MGM China ended the financial year of the second quarter of 2025 with the best result of its history in terms of operational gains. Between April and June, profits before interest, taxes, amortization and depreciation (EBITDA) ascended to $ 2.51 billion from Hong Kong, reflecting increases of 2.8% and 6.1% over the same period of 2024 and the previous three months, respectively, and corresponding to 172% of the pre-pound level, according to the game operator and its main shareholder, MGM Resorts International.
According to a statement from MGM, the EBITDA margin-a profitability indicator that illustrates the relationship between net revenues and operational gains-was 29% in the quarter under analysis.
In the first half of the first half, MGM China wrote down operational gains of Hong Kong's $ 4.88 billion, 1.4% less than in the first half of 2024. Net revenues advanced 2.7% to almost 16.66 billion in one year, including 8.67 billion in the second quarter (8.9% in homologous variation and 8.4% in three months).
MGM China “shone in the second quarter, with a recorded EBITDA and a market share of 16.6%, representing the largest sequential gain among all concessionaires” in the territory, said Bill Hornbuckle, president and CEO of the group, in the usual teleconference with analysts.
The market share in the game rose 0.6 points in terms annually, with Casino MGM Cotai to stop a percentage close to 10.5%, surpassing the 6.2% of MGM Macao. In a period when visits to the company's ventures equivalent to 175% of the pre-pound movement, the daily gross revenues of the two MGM casinos settled in 111.2 million patacas, plus 12% in annual terms and plus 10.8% on a quarterly base.
MGM Cotai was once again the operator's main business source in the second quarter, with revenues of $ 5.28 billion from Hong Kong (plus 12% in a year) and Ebitda earnings of 1.46 billion (plus 5%). On the peninsula, MGM Macau scored revenues of about 3.38 billion (plus 4%) and operational profits of 975.7 million (less 1%). The average occupancy rate of the two hotels was 94.5%.
The game operator also stressed that her financial situation remains “healthy”. On June 30, the total liquidity rose to about $ 22.5 billion from Hong Kong, including cash, cash equivalents and available credit lines, reflecting an increase of 4.7 billion within three months.
 
28 “Villas” and Game Club
"We are very pleased to see another quarter of growth driven by our deep knowledge of customers and the ability to update our products and offers to meet customer preferences," said Kenneth Feng, MGM China's executive director, quoted in the statement.
In this context, the company completed the construction of “Alpha Villas” on MGM Macau, a set of 28 accommodation already fully available. "The villas have been well received by customers, as we adapt to their latest tastes and trends," he said, revealing that MGM Cotai also began to convert rooms to about 60 new suites, and the works should extend to the first quarter of 2026.
In another operational front, the “Alpha Club” was inaugurated on MGM Macau, an exclusive space that provides 20 game tables, in a “very high standard offer”.
"Our performance is quite robust. We are observing robust volumes in almost every business segments, as well as market share and solid margins. We expect a promising summer," Feng said in the teleconference.</description><pubDate>2025-08-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Unemployment set at 1.9% in the second quarter</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/desemprego-fixou-se-em-19-segundo-trimestre/</link><description>Unemployment rates in Macao did not change in the second quarter, remaining 1.9% in general and 2.5% for residents. The sub -unemployment recorded a small climb, according to official data
 
In the second quarter of this year, the level of unemployment in the MSAR registered changes in relation to the previous three months, reported the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), whose data point to an overall rate of 1.9% and a percentage of 2.5% considering only residents. On the other hand, the global sub -unemployment rate (1.6%) and residents' subfather rate (2.0%), which includes unpaid licenses, increased both 0.4 percentage points in quarterly terms.
Between April and June, the total number of employees (372,700) grew by about 900 compared to the first quarter of the year, including 281,600 residents (plus 1,400). DSEC highlights the fact of the numbers of residents employed in the transport and storage branches (17,300) and the construction (15,500) to increase 1,600 and 1,500, respectively, compensating for a decrease of 1,000 in hotels, restaurants and the like (for about 27,200).
In the quarter -on -analysis quarter, the average monthly income of the general employed population (17,800 patacas) and the residents employed (20,000 patacas) retreated 1,000 and 1,500 patacas, respectively, compared to the first three months of 2025. According to DSEC, this decline derived mainly from the fact that some branches of economic activity have attributed the 13th month of salary and profit sharing in the first. quarter of 2025, which generated a higher comparison base.
Excluding the 13th month of salary and profit sharing, the average monthly income of full-time workers' employment (who worked 35 or more hours a week) was in 21,000 patacas, equivalent to the first quarter of this year.
According to the same data, global unemployment, resident unemployment, and global underemployment rates were also identical to those of the previous serial period (March to May 2025), which happened for the fourth consecutive period, however, the residents' disqualification (2.0%) lowered 0.1 percentage points. In the same comparative basis, the total number of employees and that of residents with work reflect decreases of 300 and 600 people.
Unemployed residents (7,300) rose 2.0% (100 more people) compared to the previous period. Among the unemployed looking for a new job, most previously worked in retail, construction and game sectors. Individuals looking for the first job equivalent to 11.0% of unemployed residents, more than 2.6 points than in the period between March and May.
A nível geral, comparativamente ao período anterior, os trabalhadores dos sectores das lotarias e outros jogos de aposta (cerca de 70.200) e da construção (23.000) cresceram 1,3% e 2,7%, respectivamente. Em sentido inverso, a mão-de-obra no comércio por grosso e a retalho (45.200), hotelaria (29.100 empregados) e restauração (20.500) caiu 0,4%, 2,9% e 1,7%, respectivamente, no mesmo espaço de tempo.
Os dados oficiais mostram que, entre Abril e Junho, as actividades culturais e recreativas, lotarias e outros serviços absorviam 26,9% da população empregada, superando o comércio por grosso e a retalho (13,8%), a administração pública e segurança social (10,9%) e os hotéis, restaurantes e estabelecimentos similares (9,7%). Seguem-se as actividades imobiliárias e serviços prestados às empresas (7,4%), educação (7,0%), transportes, armazenagem e comunicações (6,8%), construção (5,5%), saúde e acção social (5,1%) e actividades financeiras (4,2%).
Employment survey excluded residents and non -residents who, despite working in Macao, live abroad, whose average number was calculated at about 106,700 in the period under analysis. Including this group, the total labor encompassed 486,700 people.</description><pubDate>2025-08-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Approved data guide data</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/aprovado-guia-de-anonimizacao-de-dados/</link><description>The Directorate of Personal Data Protection Services (DSPDP), the Commissioner for Hong Kong Personal Data Protection (PCPD, English) and Australia data protection authorities, Canada, Japan, South Korea, New Zealand and Singapore approved a “guide to start with anonymization”, at the 63rd Forum of Authorities Privacy of Pacific Asia. The guide presents basic concepts and describes the recommended steps for the processing of data anonymization by the entities, according to DSPDP.
In the first step, it suggests that “entities should identify data categories before treatment”, discerning “direct identifiers” such as the name or number of the identity ticket, “indirect identifiers”, such as the date of birth or the genre of the individual. Secondly, “direct identifiers” must be removed.
The third step stipulates that the “anonymization technique to treat 'indirect identifiers' should be used in order to prevent others from identifying the person through the combination of identifiers”. The fourth step provides for an assessment of the risk of personal identification through anonymous data, determining whether anonymization is sufficient or not. Finally, in a fifth phase, "measures should be taken to mitigate risks," such as "limiting data use and restricting access to authorized personnel only."
Yang Chongwei, director of DSPDP, said that "personal data anonymization measures reduce to some extent the risk of personal data escape, being an active measure to solve protection of personal data security in the application of new technology."
In turn, Ada Chung Lai-Ling, a commissioner for the privacy of the PCPD, explained that “as more and more Hong Kong and Macau entities use Artificial Intelligence (AI) in their daily operations, the anonymization of personal data in the use and sharing of data not only increases AI security and data security, but also preserves data use.”
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-08-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Border transport only accelerate on land</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/transportes-fronteiricos-so-aceleram-em-terra/</link><description>Automobile tickets at border stations increased by almost a quarter in the first six months of this year, when vehicles with new enrollment also grew 21%, according to official data. On the other hand, air and sea transportation closed the semester in break
 
Automobile movements at Macau border stations rose 23.2% to 5,302,937 in the first half of 2025, in annual terms, and in the case of passenger lights grew 25% to 5,027,358, reported the management of statistics and census services (DSEC).
Between January and June, 1,036 thousands of starters and exits involved automobiles with a single registration of the sinters that circulated between Macau and Hengqin, which illustrates a 45.8%homologous increase. Already the entrances and exits of cars under the measure of “circulation of vehicles of Macao in Guangdong province” rose 14.7% to 813 thousands.
On the other hand, the gross weight of the contained load entry and exit of macau by land (32,134 tons) descended 7.2%in the annual variation.
According to DSEC, at the end of June, Macao had 253,089 vehicles enrolled, 1% more than one year earlier, including 14,386 electric, which corresponds to 5.7% of the total and marks an annual rise of 44.6%. In the same period of 2024, electric vehicles (VE) were about 4% of the total.
The VE list includes 7,591 light cars (+47.4%), 3,593 motorcycles (+39.1%), 1,943 mopeds (+78.7%) and 1,259 heavy cars (+11.2%).
In the first six months of this year, the number of vehicles with new enrollment retreated 0.7% to 5,901 in general, compared to the same period of 2024, with the VE (2,218) to represent 37.6% of the total (+7.1 percentage points). However, in June, new enrollment advanced 21.1% to 1,046, including 477 VE (45.6% of the total).
Despite the increase in vehicles in circulation, the number of road accidents dropped 4.4% to 7,331 in the first half of the year. According to the public security police, the accidents did not cause deaths, but left 2,620 injured (-3.7%).
 
Commercial flights dropped 3%
In contrast to the situation of land transport, passenger vessel movements (39,408) and the number of commercial flights at Macau International Airport (2684) fell 1.4% and 3.2% in the first semester, respectively, when compared to the same period of 2024. Flights at the airport reached 75.4% of the level reached in the first half of 2019, the year the year Prepandy.
Official statistics indicate that flights from the interior of China (5,962) represented 44.3% of the 13,443 that landed in the territory between January and June. In all six months, the airport also received 2,247 flights from Taiwan, 1,165 from Vietname, 1,041 from Thailand, 812 from South Korea, 623 Malaysia, 398 of the Philippines, 346 from Japan, 278 from Singapore and 571 from other countries or not specified regions.
On the contrary, 13,441 flights took off from Macau to various destinations, including 5,963 (44.4% of the total) to mainland cities.
It is recalled that, as reported by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao based on statistics from the company of Macau Airport (CAM), the infrastructure received 3.6 million passengers in the first half, less 3% than in the same period last year. The passenger volume is equivalent to 76.5% of the registered between January and June 2019.
In line with the decline on flights, gross air load weight also decreased 4.5% to 46,813 tons, despite increasing 154.8% compared to the first semester of 2019. The gross weight of the exported load (41,910 tons) descended 6.3%, however, the imported load (2,477 tons) and the load on traffic regime (2.426 tons) climbed) 5.0% and 25.9%, respectively.
In maritime ports, gross weight of contained load input and output decreased 7% to 89,499 tons.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-08-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lusophone and China entrepreneurs were in Guinea-Equatorial</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/empresarios-lusofonos-da-china-encontraram-se-na-guine-equatorial/</link><description>More than 500 government representatives and entrepreneurs from Continental China, Macao and Lusophone countries were in Equatorial Guinea, as part of the industrialization of the agricultural sector
 
Equatorial Guinea welcomed, this week, the 16th “Meeting of Entrepreneurs for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese -Speaking Countries - Malabo”, under the theme “Industrialization drives agricultural development”. The event took place in the city of Malabo and was attended by more than 500 representatives of governments and the business sector of the interior of China, Portuguese-speaking countries (PLP) and Macau-Hengqin, according to a statement.
During the meeting, about 40 entrepreneurs and interior representatives of China, including Hengqin, and Macao were present, from areas such as “Commodity Trade, Finance, Transphronic Electronic Trade, Agriculture, Big Health, Medical Technology, Professional Services and Tourism”. Over the three days, more than 120 contact scholarship sessions have been organized and six cooperation protocols signed.
The session “Bilateral Economic and Commercial Relations between China and Guinea Equatorial”, a product exhibition of 30 companies from Equatorial Guinea and Visits to farms and cultural and tourist projects, among other activities, according to the Institute for Commerce and Investment Promotion (IPIM), were also held.
Equatorial Guinea representatives said the meeting allowed them to “realize the numerous opportunities brought by the development of integration between Macao and Hengqin for international investors”, read in the statement. Entrepreneurs even expressed “interest in visiting Macau and Hengqin” “to explore the vast Chinese market through the advantages of the Macao platform”.
Luiz Jacinto, a vowel of the IPIM Administrative Council, said the body will “continue to organize and participate in economic and commercial activities, such as the 2nd China-Paraís-Parais Economic and Commercial Exhibition”, to be held in October, at the MSc. The exhibition will "enhance the role of Macao as" Sino-Lusophone Platform "and" Infallible Connection link ", and further deepen economic and commercial cooperation between China and PLP."
For Jacinto, the meeting offered "support in promoting projects, helping companies to expand to abroad and promoting industrial cooperation." It also highlighted the fact that it was the first time that Equatorial Guinea has received the event since joining the Macao Forum.
The “Meeting of Entrepreneurs for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-Speaking Countries” is an “important mechanism for Syno-Lusophone Economic and Commercial Cooperation”. The cooperation project was established in 2003, during the 1st Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, the statement says.
Since 2005, the event has been held on a rotary regime in the PLP, having accounted for more than 6,800 participants, about 3,900 contact scholarship sessions and the signature of more than 120 projects over the years.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-08-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Autumn Hall returns to Casa Garden</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/salao-de-outono-regressa-a-casa-garden/</link><description>The work can already be submitted to the next edition of the fall hall, which this year returns to the renewed Casa Garden. For the first time, there will be collaboration with a goldsmith. On the other hand, this year there will be no monetary prize awarded by the Oriente Foundation, which is now granted every two years
 
The fall hall is back at Casa Garden of the East Foundation, "a place -laden place, originally built in 1770 and recently renewed." “Here, contemporary art and cultural heritage will converge, creating a unique glow,” says Art for All (AFA) in a statement. The poster of this 16th edition was really inspired by the “EMBLETATIC ARCHITECTURAL LANGUAGE OF CASA GARDEN” as a tribute.
This year, the autumn hall will present an “unprecedented” collaboration. “For the first time, we joined forces with O'Che 1867, a renowned brand of goldsmiths with over 150 years of glorious history in Macao, to explore new possibilities in art,” says the organization. Thus, artists will have the opportunity to collaborate with top artisans, combining a contemporary artistic view with traditional handicrafts, “to co-create unique and tradable works of art”. “This is not only a creative challenge, but also a valuable opportunity to merge artistic concepts with eternal materials, creating masterpieces that will last,” says AFA.
On the other hand, the art prize usually attributed by the East Foundation has been delivered every two years, so it will not be granted this year, returning in 2026. In this sense, AFA encourages artists to concentrate energy in creating the project with the goldsmith brand.
AFA warns that all residents of Macao, students or professionals working at MSAR can submit works, and “all art forms are welcome”, including painting, photography, sculpture, engraving, video and installation. The works must have been created in 2023 or after this year. In addition, each artist can submit to three works/series for evaluation. The work can be delivered until August 31st.
As for the jury, it will be composed of representatives of the East Foundation and AFA, based on criteria such as innovation, technique, artistic merit, thematic depth, expository quality, commercial value.
As for the project with the goldsmith, those interested in participating should submit drafts or models of the proposed work, incorporating elements in gold, as well as an artistic statement about the works, curriculum and personal portfolio of the artist. In this case, the submissions can be made until August 15, being the number of proposals unlimited.</description><pubDate>2025-08-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mandar guarantees podium in the hockey Asian</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-garante-podio-asiatico-de-hoquei/</link><description>The triumph over Japan, on the penultimate journey, gave third place to the senior men's selection of macao skate hockey at the Asia-Oceania championship. Taiwan revalidated the title. In the category of juniors, the mandate let the bronze medal out of just one goal of difference. In the female sector it was fifth classified

Victor Rebelo
 
Macao's third place in the Asia-Cenania Roller Hockey Championship Men's race, which ended in the South Korean city of Jecheon, was in the forecasts and, therefore, the provision of the team oriented by Nuno Antunes may consider himself positive.
However, in order for the formation of the MSAR to ensure this objective, it was necessary to beat Japan, in the penultimate journey, in one of the most balanced challenges of the competition. The "five" of the territory was losing 4-2 at the entrance to the final five minutes, but it was still in time to turn the result, winning 5-4, with goals from Helder Ricardo (2), Augusto Ramos (2) and Miguel Resende.
Already in the last meeting of the Asian, Macau was defeated by the champion of the tournament, Taiwan, 11-4. The Taiwanese formation thus revalidated the title, which had reached two years ago in Beidaihe, China, having not lost any challenge.
In the balance of the competition, in six games held, the territory team endorsed four wins and two losses. He obtained triumphs against Hong Kong (71-0), New Zealand (7-4), the People's Republic of China (34-2) and Japan, and suffered desaires against India (11-2) and Taiwan.
Taiwan, who introduced a team with very fast, although median players in technical terms, was holes above the opponents, closing the championship ahead of India, who won 7-4.
In the list of the best markers, which was not disclosed due to the participation of two very weak teams, such as Hong Kong and China, Hélder Ricardo ended with 60 goals, 31 of which obtained in the game with Raehk and 20 in the match with the Chinese.
With the goals pointed out, the Portuguese Hokist, who acts in the veteran championships in Portugal and was invited by the Macau Skating Association (APM) to return to the territory, occupies the second position among the largest scale goals in all time, worldwide, behind the former Macao player, Alberto Lisbon, who also participates in some veteran tournaments in Portugal.
To the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, Helder Ricardo said the championship was "no doubt the most challenging," said Macau joined "athletes with experience, but also less experienced kids who helped the team a lot."
The player stressed that the selection "wanted more, but it was possible, given the adversities that came to happen after game." Even so, he says, "it's a positive balance of a team that never gives up." “Everyone can be proud of the performance throughout the championship,” he says.
 
Juniors evolve towards the future
Macau's entourage participated in two more categories of Jecheon Asian, having achieved two wins and a draw in the junior echelon (U-19) and two triumphs in the female seniors.
In the younger ones, the team also oriented by Nuno Antunes, entered the race to draw (5-5) against New Zealand. Soon after, he was defeated by India (12-2) and Taiwan (10-0). In the last two challenges, the U19 won to China (23-2) and Australia (6-0).
In the last meeting, the Junior Set was looking for a victory for seven goals difference, which would happen third place in the classification, ahead of New Zealand. The six goals did not arrive, despite the domain throughout the match, which caused a great disappointment in the team. India beat Taiwan 3-1 and was crowned champion.
With regard to the female team, guided by José Sousa, the task is anticipated complicated, in the face of the surplus value of most selections. Even so, Macao gave New Zealand a good replica, with whom he lost the minimum margin, 4-3, endorsing three more Desires: Japan (7-0), Australia (10-0) and India (21-1). The two wins took place against Hong Kong (13-1) and China (6-1).
The female level was won by India, followed by Japan and Australia.
The president of APM stressed to JTM that, at the general calculation, the delegation of Macao "fulfilled all objectives and made globally a very good championship." According to António Aguiar, who is also a leader of the “World Skate”, the territory “has been very well represented, once again, and he has to note that we remain an Asian power hockey power”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Local athletes eliminated at the Badminton Open</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/atletas-locais-eliminados-open-de-badminton/</link><description>All local players registered to participate in the Badminton de Macau Open are already out of race.
Pang Fong Pui, one of the guests for Open's main board, almost caused a sensation in the first round of male singles. It was up to him to face his first Head Head, Lee Cheuk Yin, from Hong Kong, and gave an excellent replica.
Pang, 25, who occupies the 124th place on the international list, only drummed in the final part, eventually losing for three points in the first clash (21-18) and two in the second (21-19), forcing the 15th ranking opponent, “pulling gallons” so as not to be surprised. The home player, strongly supported by the public, thus gave good nominations to the National Games of the Popular Republic of China (RPC).
The competition has started on Tuesday and will last until Sunday at the East Asia Games Sports ship, encompassing five categories: male and female singles, male and women pairs, and mixed teams.
In female singles, also in the inaugural elimination of the main picture, Hao Wai Chan, only 16, was defeated by Wen Chi Hsu of Taiwan, by 21-13 and 21-16. Chan is one of the great promises of Badminton de Macao and should also participate in the national games.
Besides, Macau had teams of peers and mixed. In men, Leong Iok Chong and Vong Kok Weng were defeated by Hung Kui Chun/Lui Chun Wai, from Hong Kong, 21-8 and 21-9.
In the female sector, still in the qualification phase, Ng Wen Chi/Pui Chi Wa Baquear before Lui Lok Lok/Tsang Hiu Yan, also from Raehk, 21-10 and 21-10. In the mixed pairs, Leong Iok Chong and NG Weng Chi entered the main board, but lost the two sets (21-11 and 21-11) with the Malays Chen Tang Jie and Toh Ee Wei.
Organized by Sands China and the Badminton Association, with the support of the Sports Institute, Open did not count this year with any Chinese player in the main board of male singles. However, the RPC presented two young people in the qualification phase, Hu Zhe An (19) and Zhu Xuan Chen (21), who have already secured the determination for the round of 16.
In this category, Lee Cheuk Yiu, considered the main favorite, since he performed with “head-heads” status, ahead of Indian Lakshya Sen, 17th in the world ranking, was eliminated yesterday. The Raehk representative lost with Tharn Mannepalli from India from 19-21, 21-14 and 22-20, which thus qualified for the fourth rooms.
In female singles, the RPC brought the 27 -year -old accredited Chen Yufei, fifth positioned on the Badminton International Federation. The Golden Medal at the Tokyo Olympic Games in 2020 has as the next opponent Malay Goh Jin Wei and in case of Vitória will be present in the last eight of this Macao Open.
The international federation level 300 tournament this year made a “upgrade” of the General Monetary Award, now with US $ 370,000, nearly three million Patacas, against $ 200,000 in 2024. The first classifieds, male and female, will receive a check of just over 200,000 patacas.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-08-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Benfica wins Macau Cup</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/benfica-vence-taca-de-macau/</link><description>Benfica's team won the Macao Cup in soccer, intended for elite league clubs. In the final, held at the Canid Trade field, the “Incarnate” formation defeated Ching Fung 6-2. At the break, the "eagles" already won 1-0, with a goal of the game man, the Portuguese striker Niki Torrão, 24 minutes. In the second half, Benfica, oriented by Luís Moura, was even more dominant, with Niki scoring for another three times (53, 74 and 77 minutes), which joined the goals of Joaquim Figueira (79) and David Kadial (87). By the Ching Fung, by coach João Rosa, highlight for João Machado and Danilo Lins, authors of the goals, respectively at 52 and 83 minutes. To determine the third classified of the cup, Shao Jiang surpassed the University of Macao (one) by 1-0, goal of Daniel Ortiz. In the semi-finals, both Benfica and Cwung had guaranteed qualification through the penalty of the penalty brand, after 2-2 in regular time, in front of one and Shao Jiang, respectively. Tomorrow can be known the champion of the Elite League. In case of victory or draw, in the “duel” with the second classified Shao Jiang, leader Must IPO will ensure the title, as it has four points of advantage when only two hours left for the end of the championship. The game is scheduled for 9 pm at the Taipa stadium.</description><pubDate>2025-08-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Singapore Medical Trainee in Melbourne detained for filming colleagues in bathrooms</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/medico-de-singapura-estagiario-em-melbourne-detido-por-filmar-colegas-em-casas-de-banho/</link><description>A Singapore trainee in Melbourne was allegedly arrested filming co-workers in hospitals since 2021, and more than 10,000 photos and videos were found on devices seized by police.
The 27 -year -old was identified as Ryan Cho, who worked at Austin Hospital at the time, ABC News said. Other reports indicate their age in 28 years. His medical record was suspended by the Australian authorities.
Quoting judicial documents, Jornal de Melbourne The Age reported that, on June 25, a hospital employee raised concerns about a man who was looking for the emergency employees of the emergency staff.
At the time, there were already investigations in the hospital related to blockages and damage to the houses. Police now claim that this is done to force potential victims to enter cubicles equipped with recording devices, the Age reported.
ABC News reported that, on several occasions, Cho was seen by hospital staff at the emergency room outside their working hours.
On July 3, a nurse found a purse with a mobile phone shooting in a bathroom and reported what happened to the hospital management. The same suitcase was found several days later for the safety of the hospital, which led to the police call.
Cho was arrested, and police seized two mobile phones, a laptop and a hard disk. Several white mesh bags and removable hooks were seized, allegedly similar to that previously found by the police.
A search at the hospital led to the discovery of similar hooks on other floors, including in the sick bathrooms, which were not installed by the administration.
According to the New Zealand newspaper 1News, Cho was first arrested on July 10, initially accused of crimes such as persecution and released under bail. Police analyzed the devices-whose Cho passage words will have refused to provide-and will have found more than 10,000 videos and images.
The images showed the genital regions of the victims to use showers or houses and were recorded between 2021 and 2025. Many of them were allegedly doctors, nurses, paramedics and other hospital staff.
They will have been categorized in different folders, with references to Austin Hospital, Peter Maccallum Cancer Center and Royal Melbourne Hospital, ordered according to the names of the alleged victims. Judicial documents report that the images were separated by "classification", with some in "level 1" and others in "level 2".
Other allegedly raised files were found outside health environments, including homes.
Cho was again arrested on July 25. His bail request was denied and will be in custody until the next hearing on August 29.
Austin Health's executive director Jodie Geissler said: "This has been an extremely distressing situation for our team, and its safety and well-being are our absolute priority."
"Right now, our focus is on taking care of our team. We have comprehensive support services in force and we are doing everything we can to help them at this challenging moment."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-08-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>