<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Casa Revitalized Garden receives events from “June, Portugal month”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/casa-garden-revitalizada-recebe-eventos-junho-mes-de-portugal/</link><description>The reopening of Casa Garden, after five months of works of consolidation and repair from abroad, begins a new cycle for the iconic building of the responsibility of the Oriente Foundation. The protagonism of the European Mansion in a historic area of ​​the city “has to be more developed,” Catarina Cottinelli told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. The foundation prepares the reprint of a book, a monograph, telling the story of Casa Garden, which should be released next year, along with a small exhibition. “Lavada Cara”, the space will officially open at a ceremony to be held on June 17, but will receive special cultural activities, inserted in the program of “June, month of Portugal”

Victor Rebelo
 
After five months of external consolidation and repair work, the iconic Casa Garden, with more than two centuries of history, will open the doors to the public with some events early next month. A ceremony to be held at 18h00 on June 17 will officially mark the reopening of the space.
Coinciding with the 20th anniversary of the Historic Center of Macao, the building, built in 1770 and classified as a World Heritage Site by UNESCO in 2005, is ready to continue the activities it develops at the cultural level.
The works only moved on the façade, ie, in the outer look, including the waterproofing of the coverage, having not performed “any intervention in the interior”, according to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau the delegate of the Oriente Foundation (FO), who feels “very happy and surprised, by the final result of the works” performed by a company hired by the Cultural Institute (IC), “with extensive experience in urban revitalization and the historical buildings of the historical buildings of the historical and the historical buildings of the historical and the historical buildings of the historical and the historical buildings of the urban and the historical buildings of city".
With the topic of reopening as a backdrop, Catarina Cottinelli stressed the protagonism that the European traits mansion has in that area of ​​the city, with three elements, the garden of Camões, the house, which was all the property, and the Protestant cemetery.
For this very reason, and attending her assets classification, the guardian emphasizes that the house, “in terms of architecture, has to be more developed”, with projects on the table. “Let's see if we got it out next year the reissue of a book, which has existed, but there is no longer, made by Beltrão Coelho, who told the story of those who passed here, who had inhabited the house, among other very interesting aspects,” he said, conveying the idea that the launch of this publication is accompanied by a small exhibition.
Being also architect of profession, the delegate of FO “would like to have more description from the point of view of architecture and more investigation, so that we could see a little bit that made this house look this aspect”.
It also says that Casa Garden, through time, “has undergone some changes, for a variety of reasons, so there are a number of things that in the future I would like to have in this book, that is, a denser story about the building's architecture”, acknowledging that IC has also done some research, and there is a publication in Chinese. In the background, he says, "is to gather all this information and make a book, a monograph, about Casa Garden, but from the point of view of its architecture, its importance in this site of the historic center of Macao."
"We are in this packaging of a new cycle, so to speak, because we will open after five months," he says.
 
Some events are part of “June, Portugal month”
Casa Garden is likely to be able to receive activities again, some of which are inserted at the celebrations of June 10, Portugal, Camões and Portuguese communities. “These events not only reinforce the Sino-Melusópone cultural exchange, but also enrich the cultural panorama of Macau, promoting a space for dialogue and interaction between cultures,” says a statement from FO.
The reopening follows “extensive reforms” that restored Casa Garden, with the support of IC, ensuring “preserving its architectural and cultural importance for future generations”, reinforces the note. In space will take place diversified events, including workshops, lectures and interactive initiatives that "will encourage cultural exchange between Macao and the world."
In addition, the press release adds, its revitalization reflects “a commitment to maintaining the rich history of Macao”, while “promoting cultural exchange and community involvement”.
The first events of FO's revitalized “headquarters” will be two major exhibitions in its main and temporary galleries, as well as a Portuguese film show, which will be shown in its auditorium. From June 3 to 29, Casa Garden will be the scene of the exhibitions “When the Island projects its shadows” and “Soul Objects”.
The first, which is not part of the activities included in the program of “June, Portugal's month”, is “a retrospective of Frank Law”, which honors the legacy of this contemporary photographer, presenting more than 60 works, black and white, as well as a book and personal objects, which include his career from the 1990s to the latest projects.
"He is a local artist, who has a vision of the spaces, the experience of Macau, where people are in the background the focus of their photographs, taken in places that are no longer recognizable, because they were altered, certainly for the better," argues Catarina Cottinelli, for whom the exhibition "is a perspective and a look of what happened socially here in Macau".
The second exhibition, already integrated in the “Month of Portugal”, highlights the rich tradition of the Portuguese puppet. With a collection of more than 1,000 puppets of various eras and styles, from the private collection of Elisa Vilaça, curator of the event, visitors will have the opportunity to explore the construction and manipulation techniques that make this art form unique. “The exhibition not only celebrates the History of the puppet, but also emphasizes its educational and cultural role,” says Fo.
As for the cinematic variant, organized in collaboration with Portugal Film and the Cinem, Cinemateca Passion Association, will present a selection of films in Portuguese, started with the screening of “Greice”, by Leonardo Mouramateus, acclaimed at film festivals around the world. The show will also publicize a series of innovative short films, highlighting the panorama of contemporary Portuguese cinema.
It should be noted that these initiatives integrated into the program of “June, Portugal Month” are already starting tomorrow, Thursday, with the inauguration of the exhibition “Dialogues of Creativity”, with 50 works by 24 contemporary Portuguese artists, promoted by the love of the Artyzen Grand Lapa Hotel.
There are two more events this May. On Friday, Somos-Portuguese Language Communication Association organizes the photography exhibition “The Man and the Divine” in Parisian. On Saturday, another photographic show is inaugurated, called “Macau Cultural Heritage”, accompanied by the view of the documentary “Heritople”, which will take place at the Portuguese General, with organization of the International Institute of Macao.
All remaining activities will take place during June.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>"Cuza is Rene?" Take the stage with satire focused on education</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cuza-ta-rena-sobe-ao-palco-satira-focada-na-educacao/</link><description>The presence on stage of six young people will be one of the main focuses of the Dóci Papiaçá Di Macau show, titled “Cuza Tá Renenia?”, Which will be on Friday and Saturday at the Cultural Center, with a cast of 18 actors. The theater in Patuá presents this year a story that comes down to a “center of explanation”, so “the younger elements play an important role in the plot,” according to the Journal of Macao producer Miguel de Senna Fernandes. The argument has as its central figure the arrival, coming from the great bay, a new director of the center, the "Dr. Semedo", played by João Picanço, who intends to make a deep restructuring. The piece will have some technical experiences, such as the use of LED in the scenarios












































Electronic Waste and Garbage for Recycling




Victor Rebelo
 
For the 31st time will climb the cloth for two more nights of laughter and curse that characterize the show in Patuá of the theater group Dóci Papiaçá di Macau. “Cuza is Rene?”, In a fool of dialect (“What's going on?” In the Portuguese translation), it is the title of this year's play.
The theme turns around education, specifically a “center of explanations”, which receives a new director. It is from there that everything unfolds, in a story that, as always, has hilarious scenes, but also of scathing humor, in the way of “Portuguese magazine”, in this case spoken in Creole.
One of the few characters who will not use Patuá in the interpretation is “Dr. Semedo”, who will express himself in Portuguese. João Picanço is the new “Manager” of the “Center for Explanations” and, around it, will unfold most of the plot of the show, which will take place in the large auditorium of the Cultural Center, inserted in the Macao Arts Festival program.
According to the script, produced by the theater mentor, Miguel de Senna Fernandes, the new boss of the center was hired in the great bay to make a deep restructuring. "The adventures happen from my arrival in Macao and the center of explanations," he told the Journal Tribuna de Macau João Picanço. The journalist by profession already has some experience in these wanderings, but this time will have a more prominent role, more time on stage, that is, will be one of the key characters of the story.
"I do not say that I am the main character, this is always very debatable, because there are several people who play an important role, have another kind of weight, although they do not appear so many times," says João Picanço, for those who are more time on stage is not something that considers "necessarily as a lead role, in a cast that is extensive and in which one works in team."
About what to expect from this year's show, available on two consecutive days, on Friday at 20h00 and Saturday at 15h00, the actor says that, "despite being a new piece, with different approaches, sometimes more or less musical, sometimes playing or not in more delicate matters, the shows are always made with the same purpose, which is to entertain people and that it is another beautiful chapter in the history of the Papiaçá."
The member of an 18 -person cast (about 30 will be in the backstage) wants “people to have fun, to be two hours well spent in good mood and fair play, because every year there is criticism, not specific people, but to an event or an institution”. Therefore, he considers that "we should start by knowing ourselves, which is a great quality, that not everyone has, and we should take more affordable."
About being used to talking to the microphone on Macau radio, "this can help" in the theater, he says, but recognizes not to like to be the center of attention. "Although it is apparently a more outgoing person, this is more related to my shyness and is a defense mechanism," he says, confessing that being on stage sometimes intimidates him "a little bit."
Despite the shyness, it states that "it is not a very big effort," which is due to how it was first received, "affable, with great sympathy, always with open doors, making me feel integrated."
Above all, it says, it is "gratifying to be part of this one that we can call it community, which wants to protect Patuá." Although not talking about the Creole language, the journalist expresses that being present there "also gives this strength, the notion of responsibility of this Patuá protection, and this turns out to be what gratifies me most," he says.
Meanwhile, Joana Freitas, also a journalist, on the stage for the sixth time. “I had seen them for several years, until in 2019 I entered the first piece and spoke in Portuguese,” he says. From there, he began to play roles in which he spoke Patuá. “As is the case with this, where I am Selma,” he says.
TDM's Macao news newscour host recognizes she is enjoying "even much to be part of the Docy," stressing that "although it may seem like a cliché, they are actually a family."
Going to the stage and doing it with this theater group, "it has other levels of pleasure, for everything I encompass and we are talking about people I admire, comedy, social criticism and a language that has to be protected not to disappear." For this edition, he observes, "we will have a show focused on a center of explanations that wants to be the best, but that is seen in the midst of many slogans, politiques, things we often say, only happen here."
Selma is a tutor who is looking for work, has training, but ends up doing anything but what he studied. “Let's see how to get bored,” he concludes.
 
Macao in the context of the great bay
Since 1993, with a few, few, interruptions, the Dóci Papiaçá di Macau have this theater in Patuá, founded by Miguel de Senna Fernandes. The show producer revealed to JTM that this year "the children's component will play an important role." There are five girls and a boy, and the youngest is 10 years old and they are all actors, "actively participate, they have dialogue, they are not like that of extras just to fill the stage and so I am already very happy with them."
Some of the young people came from last year. "This age group is very interesting, because the boys grow, some are ashamed and come to this age are no longer ashamed, it is funny, so we have to enjoy this age," he emphasizes.
The producer of the theater states that "obviously this is not a recovery for children, but to be present, since we will talk about a center of explanations," he clarifies, adding that the "center seems to be a practically essential level in Macao and when we talk about education even more is justified."
Regarding the topics that will be addressed throughout the play, the official always has the concern of presenting matters of the current. He says "deep down is talking about things and drawing attention to certain aspects in a humorous way." It admits that this causes several reactions: "Sometimes people do not like, but those who are in the best assistance will judge."
Miguel de Senna Fernandes considers that "Macau is in this context, in the middle of the great bay, but we still do not know what is done in the great bay." In the background, “it is to play a lot around this, because it is important to situate ourselves where we find ourselves, what is the current context,” adding “there is always hope, and this hope is in children, in education, because we all want the success of the great bay, but we have to sit our feet on earth too,” he says. “I believe people will understand where I want to go,” he notes.
Summing up the story of “ass is renons?”, The producer concludes that “people, when they think of the big bay, begin to dream of great projects, but it is all a center of explanation”.
In the texts of cursing interpreted by the elements of the group, there will be no shortage of references to the teaching of the Portuguese language, the use of English, some schools “integrated in the context of diversification”.
In the technical aspect, the show will continue to have videos, produced by Sérgio Perez, as well as new experiences on stage. "Let's try the use of the LED and see, deep down, what is the versatility of this for the scenarios, because I have seen LED shows and I was amazed, so I hope it works with us," he concludes.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Electronic garbage “yielded” 16 million to mashes in five years</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lixo-electronico-rendeu-16-milhoes-a-raem-em-cinco-anos/</link><description>Electronic Waste and Garbage for Recycling



Between 2020 and 2024, customs intercepted more than 4,100 cases of illegal electronic waste transport, with 94% of the total to be detected to exit the territory and aiming at the interior of China. The fines applied yielded an amount of more than 16 million patacas to the MSAR, the body told this newspaper
 
Catarina Pereira
 
More than 970,700 pieces of electronic waste - such as mobile phones, computers, headphones, tablets, cameras, smart watches, chips, among others - were intercepted at the entrance and exit of the MSAR, between 2020 and 2024. There were more than 4,100 the cases that the authorities detected and that "surrendered" more than 16 million patacas in fines, according to the data provided by services of services Customs (SA) to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao.
A small part of the more than four thousand cases was discovered at the entrance of the MSAR and came from nearby regions such as the Chinese continent or Hong Kong, but also from more distant countries such as Canada, Italy and India. Most were detected on the way out of the territory, all of which were destined for the interior of China.
Previously, the SAs had already explained to this newspaper that there is a waste recycling industry in the interior of China, so “criminals illegally transport this type of toxic and harmful solid waste into China to dismantle, processing and reuse to make a frequent activities of parallel trading practitioners who carry used electronic waste”.
In the last year, 1,128 situations of the genre were discovered, of which 1,026 were destined for the Chinese continent and 93 came from the interior of China, Raehk and India. In concrete, more than 151,774 pieces were detected, including mobile phones and computers and their components, tablets, cameras and objectives, smart watches, batteries and chips. All material already used.
Ensuring that it has supervised foreign trade activities, the body indicates that, in the case of these illicit activities, it proceeds, in accordance with the Foreign Trade Law, and if there is condemnation, to a punishment, which can go to 50 thousand patacas, "being the goods seized declared lost in favor of masters".
Now, according to the data provided by Customs, in 2024, the fines paid in this context totaled 360,000 Patacas, moreover, the lowest amount of recent years. In 2021 and 2022, for example, the amounts paid in fines were far higher: 7,811,000 and 6,767,000 patacas, respectively.
Asked if there are companies behind these cases, the SA said that between 2020 and 2024, they intercepted "11 cases involving companies that carried waste illegally to the interior of China," companies that "conducted business in Macao." More details were not, however, provided, with the body stressing that "involve the privacy of companies and the people involved."
About this phenomenon, the body also states that in recent years it has implemented police concepts of “using technology to improve police work”, introducing “advanced customs surveillance equipment”, as well as sharing information at the transfronical level, “in the sense of suppressing and combating illegal trafficking activities”.
"In the context of elimination at source, the SAs intensify, successively, through the risk management system and new surveillance equipment, inspections and controls in relation to imported and exported goods," he may be read. Regarding combat in the city, the authorities carry actions in "points of supply and distribution to parallel trade practitioners, in order to repress the activity of parallel waste of waste, in the form of ant stratagem to the interior of China."</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Government heard social support associations</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-ouviu-associacoes-sobre-apoios-sociais/</link><description>Social support measures continue to be discussed, with the secretary Lam to meet with associations to hear opinions about aging and birth
 
The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM, continues to hear Social Work Associations in the context of the well-being of the population, having met with about 30 representatives. Given the accelerated evolution of demographic aging and low birth rate, many addressed the work of “support for the elderly and children”.
According to a statement from the Secretary's Office, they made suggestions “in order to disclose as soon as possible the details about the childhood assistance allowance, namely the application requirements and the calendar of the assignment”. They also want to reinforce the identification of vulnerable people inserted in the community and that they need support, as well as increasing the bet on resources for caregivers. The application of technology to enable the care services for the elderly and rehabilitation was another of the topics covered.
The LAM stressed that being the government “highly attentive to the challenges brought by demographic aging and the low birth rate, it will further reinforce intersectoral cooperation, to adopt comprehensive measures to encourage birth, as well as promote the availability of directed social benefits, more accurately, to low income social groups, in vulnerable and precarious situations”.
He also said that, within the portfolio he directs, he will continue to hear the opinions of the various quadrants of society, "in the sense of gathering consensus and promoting the continuous optimization of various policies related to the life of the population."
Also present at the meeting were the head of the Secretary's Office for Social Affairs and Culture, Lin Yuan, and the president of the Institute of Social Action, Hon Wai.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>ASEAN WANTS EXPANSION OF THE FOUND FREE IN MYANMAR</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/asean-quer-expansao-cessar-fogo-em-myanmar/</link><description>EPA12138427 (L-R) Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC) Secretary-General Jasem Mohamed al-Budaiwi, Myanmar's Permanent Secretary of the Ministry of Foreign Aung Kyaw Moe, Qatar's Minister of Commerce and Industry Faisal Bin Thani Faisal Al Thani, Singapore's Prime Minister Lawrence Wong, Ooman's Deputy Prime Minister for Relations and International Affairs Sayyid ASA'ad bin tariq al Said, Thailand's Prime Minister Paetongtarn Shinawatra, Saudi Arabia's Minister Prince Faisal Farhan al Saud, Philippines' President Ferdinand 'Bongbong' Marcos Jr, Kuwait's Crown Prince Sheikh Sabah al-Khaled al-Hamad al-Sabah, Malaysia's Prime Minister anWar Ibrahim, China's Premier Li Qiang, Brunei's Second Foreign Minister Erywan Yusof, Ruler of the Uae's Emirate of Ras al Khaiimah Sheikh Saud Bin Saqr Al Qasimi, Cambodia's Prime Minister Hun Manet, Indonesia's Foreign Minister Sugeno, Laos' Prime Minister Sonexay Siphandone, East Timor's Prime Minister Xanana Gusmao, and Asean Secretary-General Kao Kim Hourn Pose for a Family Photo Before The Asean-Guild Cooperation Council (GCC) -China Summit Following The 46th Asean Summit in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, 27 May 2025. The inaugural Trilateral Summit Place in Kuala Lumpur Within the 46th Association of Southeast Asian Nations (Asean) Summit.  EPA/Fazry Ismail



The Association of Southeast Asian Nations (Asean) yesterday requested a widening of the ceasefire in Myanmar to ensure humanitarian aid to the country's central areas, devastated by the March 28 earthquake, which made almost 3,800 dead. “We appeal to the sustained extension and national expansion of ceasefire as a first step to end violence, with a view to creating a safe and protected environment, conducive to ensuring the delivery of help and humanitarian assistance,” reads a statement of the bloc, signed by Asean leaders in Malaysia.
Indonesian leaders, Singapore, Malaysia, Thailand, Philippines, Vietnam, Laos, Cambodia and Brunei reiterated their concern “with the climb of conflict and the deterioration of the humanitarian situation” in the country, ruled by a military government since February 2021, when Asean excluded them from their high level meetings. “We have made all parties immediately cease acts of violence against civilians and public facilities. We have all taken to take concrete measures to immediately lock the indiscriminate violence, denounce any climbing, exercise the maximum containment and ensure the protection and safety of all civilians,” the statement emphasizes.
These requests appear four days before the end of the ceasefire declared by the military junta in power, although the truce was violated dozens of times, according to complaints from the opposition and the UN.
At Kuala Lumpur summit, Asean stressed the importance of “ensuring safe, effective, effective and transparent delivery of humanitarian assistance without discrimination,” as ethnic guerrillas and pro-democracy groups accuse the military to use these donations as a means of control in conflict zones.
He also encouraged the parties to “build confidence to convene an inclusive national dialogue to achieve a peaceful and lasting solution to the crisis”, which has worsened since the coup and maintains the isolated military junta of much of the international community, which does not recognize its legitimacy.
 
Reinforcement of ties with China and Gulf countries
Asean leaders yesterday made an unprecedented summit with Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang and representatives of the Gulf Cooperation Council (CCG), seeking to reinforce economic ties in the middle of a trade war. "For the first time, ASEAN, CCG and China are uniting ... to open a new chapter of dialogue and cooperation," Malay Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim said at the opening of the forum.
The Prime Minister of China, Asean's largest commercial partner, classified the opportunity as “historical” and asked for greater opening for the three markets and regions to share a space where “resources, technology and talent flow more efficiently, as well as trade and investment”.
Li Qiang's presence reinforces China's recent measures in the region after President Xi Jinping's trip during the height of the US tariff attack during which he promoted Beijing as a leading partner and signed hundreds of agreements.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing and Macau reinforce synergies in digital commerce</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pequim-macau-reforcam-sinergias-comercio-digital/</link><description>Macau and Beijing signed a memo of cooperation that aims to “realize the sharing of resources”, promote “digital training” and inject “a new dynamic in the digital economy”
 
The participation of a delegation of the Macao Electronic Commerce Sector of the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) at the “Beijing Live Transmission Electronic Trade Festival” resulted in the signing of a memo of cooperation between the sectoral associations of both locations.
According to a DSEDT statement, the two parts established “a close cooperation mechanism to realize the sharing of resources and the complementarity of advantages”, promoted “digital training” and injected “a new dynamic in the digital economy of both territories”.
For the mashed organism, cooperation "reflects the deepening of exchanges and economic and commercial cooperation between Beijing and Macau," says bilateral synergy and creates a platform for companies to "expand their markets."
In the same statement, DSEDT states that the Government of MSar will continue to deepen cooperation with Beijing, promoting mutual benefits and positive results for industries for both sides and aiming to jointly boost “high quality economic and commercial development”.
O festival de Pequim atraiu a participação de várias empresas da RAEM, onde foram apresentados e promovidos 60 produtos com “características próprias de Macau”, na “Zona de Exposição dos Produtos de Qualidade de Macau”, criada nos dois primeiros dias do evento.
The event included an inauguration ceremony, as well as the holding of nine main activities and other initiatives to promote a “consumption with special characteristics”, according to the DSEDT statement.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Feeling Macao” returns to Korea</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sentir-macau-regressa-a-coreia/</link><description>Tourism services will organize a set of activities through the streets of Seoul, with a view to attracting Korea visitors during the summer holidays and the second half of the year
 
From May 30 to June 2, the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) will, like last year, promote the campaign “Feel Macau”, on the streets of Seoul. The idea is to encourage visitors to South Korea, particularly the generations of millennium and Z, to meet Macau during the summer holidays and the second half of the year, in order to consolidate the “current largest market of international visitors in Macao”.
STD is preparing a set of immersive interactive experiences and promotions, online and in -person, to show “in all aspects the diversified charm” of the territory. On the opening day of the promotion, the organization will assign a “special award”, drawn on site.
The winners will have the opportunity to enjoy a trip to Macao on the day, and a stay of three days and two nights. The “lucky visitors” will be able to experience “the romantic beauty of the city” and the “wonderful‘ Tourism +’”, according to a statement.
Over the course of four days, the “Secret Doors of Macao” dissemination action will also be presented, under last year's promotional theme “My Favorite Macao”, in the “Epic Seoul” exhibition room of Seoul's largest shopping center, “The Hyundai Seoul”.
The site has been a background of known South Korean series and a space for media exposure for famous singers, becoming a “very popular place between the generation of millennium and generation Z”, says the statement.
The shows, interactive games, and photographs were designed under the “romance” theme to allow South Korean residents and visitors to experience five romantic trips by Macao.
STD cooperated with “Kakaopay”, a means of payment “widely used by South Korea residents”, and “Good Choice”, the largest South Korean application of tourism and online leisure. From May 30 to June 30, the “Good Choice” platform will establish “an online channel to offer discounts” to “try to attract visitors”.
The body also created the “Macao Week” thematic page and released discounts on the prices of Macao flights and housing. In the same vein, airlines such as Cathay Pacific, Korea Airlines, Jeju Air and Air Busan launched “attractive tourist products and exclusive offers” for South Korea tourists.
“South Korea occupies the first place in the international visitors of Macao,” can be read in the statement, being “an important market of visitors” for the MSAR. Provisional data show that until May 16 this year, close to 235,000 Korea visitors came to Macau, an increase of 26%, compared to the same period of 2024, and 65% of 2019 values.
With about 35 flights per week, the air transport capacity between Macao and South Korea is stable, says STD.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New partnership reinforces lusophone arbitration</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/nova-parceria-reforca-arbitragem-lusofona/</link><description>The Lusophone Association of Arbitration and Mediation, created in Macao in 2019, and the Center for Arbitration, Conciliation and Mediation of Mozambique seized a partnership to promote arbitration in Portuguese -speaking countries, namely through academic initiatives and the promotion of knowledge exchange
 
The Lusophone Association of Arbitration and Mediation (Alam), established in Macao, and the Center for Arbitration, Conciliation and Mediation (CACM) of Mozambique signed a cooperation protocol, in that which is described as a “historical step” to promote arbitration in Portuguese -speaking countries. Collaboration aims to enable both associations “to jointly develop scientific activities in the context of arbitration law and alternative dispute resolution means, including the exchange of legal documentation, publications and jurisprudence summaries”, according to Alam.
The idea is to advance with initiatives such as training programs, international conferences and research projects, through which "both parties seek to improve professional expertise in arbitration and mediation, promoting legal harmonization in Lusophone jurisdictions."
In the context of joint academic initiatives, the joint hold of training, conferences, meetings, discussion and normative studies or texts on arbitration and other extrajudicial means of dispute resolution. In the field of promotion of knowledge exchange the intention is to exchange documentation, publications and summaries of jurisprudence of the respective countries about arbitration and other means of extrajudicial resolution of disputes.
Alam aims to promote, in Portuguese -speaking countries, the resolution, through mediation or arbitration, of transionic disputes that arise between parts belonging to any of the jurisdictions of Portuguese language; and parts belonging and parts not belonging to any of the Lusophone jurisdictions.
The Lusophone space, refers to the association, encompasses all the jurisdictions that have the Portuguese language as their own or as one of their official languages. Alam currently has 203 members of 21 jurisdictions.
Alam, founded in 2019, has cooperation protocols established with the Portuguese Arbitration Association, the Brazilian Arbitration Committee, the Brazilian Center for Mediation and Arbitration and the Chamber of Commerce, Industry, Agriculture and Services Arbitration Center, as well as with the Chamber of Mediation and Business Arbitration - Brazil, University of São José and Canal Arbitration. There are also other agreements in the negotiation phase.
In turn, CACM offers alternative and appropriate mechanisms for preventing and resolving commercial disputes and encourages their use in other areas of activity.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Forty works present “beauty and wisdom” of the elderly</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/quarenta-obras-apresentam-beleza-sabedoria-de-idosos/</link><description>The artm will hold two initiatives next month, linked to the elderly and the children. During the month of June there will be 40 works created by users of the association that represent the unique stories of their authors. On June 1st, in celebration of World Children's Day, “healthy” activities will be held for children
 
During the month of June, the Macao Toxicode Rehabilitation Association (ArtM) will exhibit 40 works created by the elderly in a celebration of “beauty and wisdom that come with age”. According to the association, each piece reflects the “unique perspectives” “experiences, stories and perspectives” and enhance the “vibrant spirit of the community”.
The exhibition that will be patent between June 1 and 29 will present handicrafts, made with wood and plastics recovered and under the guidance of the artm psychologist, by people with cognitive problems associated with drug and alcohol use, according to Augusto Nogueira.
The President of the ArtM highlighted the importance of these initiatives. The association has opted for this type of activities to help your users as “they have difficulty tracking recovery processes and normal therapies”. These projects allow them to “exercise their mental ability, their creativity and exercise,” he explained.
Since it was founded in 1993, ArtM has provided detoxification and rehabilitation services for dependents, using a model of “therapeutic community”. "The goal is to deepen individuals' understanding of their dependence and personal issues, promote personal growth, rebuild family relationships and assist them in reintegration in society with a new healthy lifestyle," the association explains.
In recent years, works of art and handicrafts have become “vital elements” of daily life in the therapeutic community of ArtM, with participants exploring “their perceptions about the world around them”. “These activities have shown to improve physical functioning and produce very positive results,” can be read in the statement.
On the other hand, to mark World Children's Day, ArtM will also organize an event for children in the village of Nossa Senhora de Ká-Hó, in collaboration with “Hold on To Hope Project”. Participation is free and does not require registration.
Between 15h00 and 17h00 on June 1, and under the theme “I Can Cook My Healthy Meals”, participants will have the opportunity to participate in a kitchen workshop with Joanna. There will also be a fitness activity with Veronica and the “Healthy Lifestyle” question and answers session.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ipor creates cultural “bridges” with Matosinhos Design School</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ipor-cria-pontes-culturais-escola-de-design-de-matosinhos/</link><description>IPOR signed an agreement of collaboration with the School of Arts and Design, in Matosinhos, which aims to “foster exchange in the arts area between Portugal and the masters”. The first project to be carried out in the context of this memorandum will be under the celebrations of the V Centenary of Luís de Camões
 
Training, research and cultural exchange: These are the foundations of a new agreement, signed between the Portuguese Institute of the East (IPOR) and the School of Arts and Design (ESAD), in Matosinhos. "The established partnership will be operationalized through the promotion of joint initiatives and knowledge sharing in the areas of arts, design and culture," said IPOR. The agreement now known was signed in mid -May, in Portugal.
With a faculty with various connections to Macau, the first initiative framed in the established agreement will involve teachers and students of the School of Arts and Design, who will participate in a project under the celebrations of the V Centenary of Luís de Camões. In it will also be involved artists from Macao and students from the Faculty of Arts and Design of the Macao Polytechnic University. For now, IPOR told this newspaper not being able to advance with more information about the project in question.
Specializing in the areas of design and digital arts, ESAD “stands out for the prestige of its faculty, the quality of its facilities and the successful professionals it has formed,” says the IPOR statement. "Throughout its history, the quality of teaching and intense cultural activity have consolidated ESAD as a school, positioning it at the center of design culture."
“If there is an inseparable relationship between language and culture it is up to the subject, in the context of the attributions entered in its mission, to articulate these two dimensions of its intervention,” can be read. Thus, the production, dissemination and display of content that translate creative relationships between language and culture, “preferably with the involvement of the extended community of language practice that IPOR configures, is now reinforced by the celebration of this protocol that aims to foster exchange in the arts area between Portugal and the masters”.
For IPOR, it is certain that the agreement will establish “bridges” that will allow the promotion and initiatives “as a way to increasingly inscribe the Portuguese language and the expressions of their cultures in dialogues with other languages ​​and other cultures”.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Barcelos Rooster “Unite” to Colbert's lobster</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/galo-de-barcelos-une-se-a-lagosta-de-colbert/</link><description>Sands China and artist Philip Colbert again collaborated to launch a new iconic lobster statuette, 38 centimeters high and inspired by the traditional Portuguese rooster. The 100 limited edition figures are for sale at Venetian, in a “rare opportunity” for collectors, says the game operator

The artist “Pop Art” Philip Colbert, in collaboration with Sands China, launched a limited edition of the lobster, 38 centimeters high, inspired by the iconic Portuguese rooster, the Barcelos Rooster. The 100 pieces are exclusively for sale in four points in Venetian, in this one that is, according to the operator, "a rare opportunity" for art enthusiasts.
The new figure is a smaller version of Colbert's original urban sculpture, which reflects the “thematic essence of mud houses”, one of the most significant scenic places of MSAR. Each copy of the collectible figure costs 4,770 patacas and comes with a single serial number, valuing it with collectors.
The red lobster embodies local characteristics and wears traditional rock robes of the Barcelos Rooster, turning it into a "cultural ambassador that celebrates the unique inheritance of Macao, where the East and West meet."
Colbert captivated global audiences with his iconic character by mixing "Surrealism Avant-Grade with contemporary appeal." According to Sands, the lobsters constitute a symbol of "auspice, longevity and eternal love", considering that "they carry blessings." For the operator, it is a “distinct urban and cultural icon” that represents the identity of the city.
According to the company's statement, Sands and Philip Colbert left an “indelible artistic legacy in Macao”, creating numerous unique sculptures that remain exposed by the city, “loved by residents and tourists”. The operator hopes that the collaboration behind this new collectible starts to begin a "resurgence of enthusiasm for pop art."</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 200 million patacas used for consumption benefits</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/utilizados-mais-de-200-milhoes-de-patacas-em-beneficios-de-consumo/</link><description>Since the “Grand Prix for Consumption in Community Zones 2025” was launched on 24 March, and until May 18, “electronic benefits have been used in the amount of 200 million patacas,” said the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), noting that the activity is now entering its last week. In total, there will be 10 weeks aimed at “boosting the consumer cycle in community neighborhoods and promoting trust in the consumer market”, in a joint DSEDT initiative, monetary authority and commercial association. "Organizing entities expect that, through the joint efforts of all parties, residents will be continually encouraged to consume in community neighborhoods during the weekends, thus promoting the community consumption cycle and reinforcing the confidence of small and medium enterprises in exploring their business," reads a press release. This activity also provides the elderly 65 years old or another benefit of 300 Patacas, through the new version of the “Macau Pass” elderly card. Until 1 June, the elderly who have not yet raised the benefit can, with the new version of Macau Pass, lift it into more than 100 service stations. After the first day of next month, "the unused immediate discount benefits will be automatically reduced to zero, and the part of the capital self -injection will not be affected."</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Government reviews Public Procurement Criteria</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-reve-criterios-de-concursos-publicos/</link><description>Public works services are reviewing the public works contest regime, and the secretary of the tutelage, Raymond Tam, indicated that "the system will be optimized in order to foster healthy competition and sustainable development of industry." According to a note issued after a meeting with the development group of the development of the construction sector, consisting of six associations, the ruler said that, in the past, “some public enterprises were affected by an abnormally low award price, compromising the quality and progress of works”. In this sense, within the contest of consultation, “the adoption of a 'most reasonable price adjudication' mechanism will be studied, replacing the traditional 'lower price' criterion, ensuring the fluid execution of public works and compliance with the required standards”. On the other hand, and with the objective of “expanding employment opportunities for resident workers and promoting the formation and development of qualified staff”, procedures related to the contract of works and the acquisition of services launched by the services of the protection of transport and public works should stipulate “the requirement of priority hiring of resident workers and the setting of a minimum proportion of them, whenever conditions allow it”. Awards will also be encouraged to gradually increase the percentage of residents in technical, management and specialized positions, “providing, especially young places, opportunities for entry, training and career progression”. The associations expressed “full support” to the proposed measures, considering “timely” the optimization of the contest regime.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Centenary show brings together the last geisha in Tokyo</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/espectaculo-centenario-reune-ultimas-gueixas-em-toquio/</link><description>On the gloss parquet floor of a room of a discreet Tokyo building, the latest geishas of the Japanese capital slide with millimeter steps to the rhythm of music and perpetuate an ancestral art in decline.



















Under the attentive look of his teachers, the geishas of the Shinbashi neighborhood, near the Imperial Palace, repeat these choreography daily to Azuma Odori, a dance show born a century ago.
Because of this centenary, between May 21 and 27, geishas from 19 regions of Japan shared the stage for the first time with their Shinbashi mates, now reduced to about forty women. These women are the latest guardians of an in danger art, heirs to an millennial tradition that Japan sometimes observes how something from the past, explains Hisafumi Iwashita, writer and expert of this theme.
“The Japanese themselves have difficulty understanding or not knowing the true reality of geishas,” he says to AFP.
The stereotypes are diverse. In the collective imagination they often consider them prostitutes. But in Japanese, the word "geisha" means "person of art," a man or woman graduated in the traditional Japanese arts.
The role of geishas goes beyond “simply dancing and singing,” insists Iwashita.
“We are there first to welcome and entertain customers in traditional restaurants called Ryotei,” confirms Koiku, a shinbashi geisha.
 
Postwar Renaissance
Dressed in a dark kimono highlighted by an obi (belt) with spring prints, Koiku decided to become a geisha to live on his passion for dance and music.
"In general, it takes 10 years to be considered competent," says this veteran that he has been participating in Azuma Odori for over three decades.
In this closed world, the show offers the general public a rare opportunity to appreciate this traditional art on the stage of “Shinbashi Enbujo”, a theater built with this goal in 1925.
In this centenary, the arrival of geisha across the country allows you to discover the typical styles and traditions of each region in two daily representations of more than one and a half.
In Kyoto, “dance is considered the main art, while in Tokyo, geishas differ by the skill with Shamisen [a Japanese string instrument] and the corners,” explains Hisafumi Iwashita.
At the beginning of the shows, Shinbashi's geishas entertained in official banquets the new leaders arrived in Tokyo, which became the capital of Japan over the century in place of Kyoto. These women played an “essential role” in the definition of modern Japanese culture, says the expert.
The Shinbashi Enbujo Theater, inaugurated in the first edition of Azuma Odori a hundred years ago, was destroyed during World War II and rebuilt in 1948. After the conflict, the show was reborn and its scenography influenced the traditional Kabuki Theater. But, “she started losing popularity in the 1950s-1960s, because the public preferred simpler shows,” explains Iwashita.
Now, in the Rising Sun Archipelago, the art of geisha is threatened to disappear.
"A while ago, we were still 100, then 60 ... and the number continues to decrease," Koiku worries, for those who are "essential to find solutions" before "it's too late."
For Iwashita, the decline of geisha in the capital responds mainly to the disappearance of the wealthy clientele that supported the business earlier.
One inflection point was in 1993, when Prime Minister Morihiro Hosokaw asked to end official dinners Ryote in a context of serious economic crisis. “A hard blow to the industry,” says Iwashita.
“The world has changed and, with it, how to receive customers,” laments Koiku. “Now, companies organize their receptions in their places or other places,” he continues.
The future of the profession is uncertain, warns Iwashita. "The fact that such a theater still exists and receives the centenary edition of Azuma Odori is a miracle."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>