<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Rocha Vieira, the last Governor, who had “Macau in his heart” has died</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/morreu-rocha-vieira-ultimo-governador-tinha-macau-coracao/</link><description>Vasco Rocha Vieira died at the age of 85 in Portugal. The last governor of Macao will be forever in the memory of many, with the Portuguese flag on his chest, within hours of sovereignty transfer in 1999. In the last visit to the territory, the general said he had “Macao in the heart” and It was “optimistic” as to the future of the territory. To the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, several personalities praised their role in the transition process and remembered him as a man who "dedicated a lot from his life to Macao." They said they had lost “a great friend”



















Catarina Pereira and Vítor Rebelo
 
The image of General Vasco Rocha Vieira with the Portuguese flag next to his heart on December 19, 1999, a few hours from the transfer of Macau to the Popular Republic of China, will be forever in the memory of many. “I felt it wasn't me who was there. There were many generations. I felt that it was a moment that represented centuries of history. Which represented the effort and life of generations and generations of Portuguese, ”he described in the book“ All the ports I arrived ”. In memory, there are also the nine years that Rocha Vieira was at the head of the Praia Grande Palace, in a decisive period for the territory. Macau's last governor died yesterday in Portugal at the age of 85. He leaves his wife, Leonor Rocha Vieira, with whom he married in Lisbon in 1976, and three children.
Born in Lagoa, Portugal, on August 16, 1939, Vasco Joaquim Rocha Vieira was the son of João da Silva Vieira and Maria Vieira Rocha. He spent most of his childhood beyond borders: With a year, he went to Mozambique, where he remained until 10. He then went to Portugal, having been a student at the Military College in Lisbon.
He held many positions throughout his career, until in 1991 he was appointed governor of Macau by President Mário Soares, having been confirmed in office in 1996, after the election of the new president, Jorge Sampaio. Rocha Vieira took office as governor on April 23, 1991. Macau, a place to the East where he had already been in committee service in the 1970s, became home.
As governor, he was responsible for a vast program that was intended to reinforce Macau's own identity, the consolidation of its autonomy and the promotion of territory as a regional platform, with a specific role, at that time and for the future, in the relations of the China with the outside. Under his administration, Macao has seen, in recent years, to reinforce the local political system and the rule of law, namely through the consolidation of the judicial system, the reform of the education system, the formation of staff, the modernization and extension of the systems of health and assistance.
Three days before the transfer of Macau, in an interview with RTP, when asked about what it was like to be the last Governor, Rocha Vieira said he had the feeling that he played the role “at a historic moment”, but he described himself simply as being “the interpreter of the sovereign bodies here in the territory” and the “interpreter of the fulfillment of the obligations that Portugal assumed in the Joint Declaration”. “I take it naturally”, he stated then.
He said he was convinced that Portugal administered the territory “in a unique way”. And this, he stressed, was seen in the way the Chinese said goodbye to the Portuguese: “They come to us, they hug us, they want to take photographs, they say they will miss us”. “I think Portugal has fulfilled it over the centuries (…) I think we left behind a good work, of which we can be proud”, he argued.
“There is no future if there is no history, if there is no memory. And this history is fundamentally linked to the presence of Portugal and the Portuguese here in Macau”, he continued, adding that there were “very many things” from Portugal in the territory. From the outset, a political system based on the separation of powers, laws, judicial instructions, and an administrative culture were enumerated.
Asked if the Deng Xiaoping formula “A Country, Two Systems” gave some security in the rights, freedoms and guarantees in the future of Macau under the sovereignty of the Popular Republic of China, Rocha Vieira said: “I think when he signed and wrote What he wrote, and when he wrote in Basic Law the chapter of fundamental rights, did so in a sincere and responsible way. Then I think the future authorities of MSA share the same values, the same principles as we share, the Portuguese Administration. ”
As for the relationship with China while performing the position of governor, he said it was "always good." “I managed to have a very frank, very open, very open relationship with the Chinese. Of course, we had many disagreements (…) but this understanding, in a picture, which has always been favorable, of friendship, which is traditional and historical of the Portuguese and the Chinese, helped a lot. And I think the divergences never led to breakdown situations. ”
On Portugal's side, the relationship was also “always good”, as he said at the time, but he stressed: “Of course, Macau and Portugal are physically separated, but they were always together through affection, solidarity and the sense of responsibility that the governing bodies sovereignty they always had before Macau”.
For the future, the last governor asked for attention to the territory. “Portugal should continue to be aware of Macao and I think the international community must be aware of Macau, naturally without interfering with Chinese sovereignty, which must exercise it. But it should follow this process, because the joint statement is an international treaty, signed by two countries. ”
Regarding the criticism that Portugal could have been “submissive” in relation to the People's Republic of China, Rocha Vieira said, days before the transfer, that he no longer heard these types of accusations. “Today people realized that we took good advantage – in the good sense of the term ‘taking advantage’ – of good relations with China to defend our interests in the best way possible. Because having good relationships, speaking frankly, being friends, having a sense of the future, being serious in your goals is not incompatible with being firm, determined. On the contrary. We took advantage of this climate to be able to be very determined and very firm, say what we thought and fight for the interests that we believe to be the interests of Macau”, he concluded, in the same interview.
On the night of the transfer, after the official ceremony, the presidents of each country, Jorge Sampaio and Jiang Zemin, exchanged formal compliments, but were not the only ones. Among the various greetings, a special highlight to Vasco Rocha Vieira, who was after his position, and Edmund Ho, his successor and first head of the Executive of the MSAR.
If it is true that the last Governor was loved by many, and his role in the transfer negotiations was recognized “in the country and within the international community”, it is also true that Rocha Vieira was the target of much criticism. Mainly in the context of the Jorge Álvares Foundation case, which caused controversy, both in the first month of Chinese administration in the territory, and in Portugal.
Formalized on December 18, 1999, the eve of the farewell of the Portuguese Administration of Macao, the Foundation had an initial allocation of 100 million patacas from the equal parts of the Macao Tourism Society and the Foundation for Cooperation and Foundation and Development, based on the territory and fueled by local public funds. The chairman of the curators of this last foundation was Rocha Vieira himself at the date on which the transfer of 50 million Patacas was decided to the newly created Jorge Álvares Foundation.
Over the years after the transfer, the general was sporadically returning to Macau. The last time he was in the territory, at least that it goes publicly, was in March 2023. He came to receive a Honoris Doctorate in Social Sciences, attributed by the University of Science and Technology of Macao. “Back to Macau is always very pleasant. All the people who were here, lived and worked have Macau in my heart, as I have, therefore, coming back here in these circumstances is very pleasant, ”he said to journalists, stating that he was optimistic about the future of the territory.
Rocha Vieira was Chief of Staff of the Army and, inherently, member of the Council of the Revolution between 1976 and 1978. In 2015, he was awarded the Grand Cross of the Military Order of the Tower and Sword by former President Cavaco Silva. Previously, he was decorated with the Grand Cross of the Order of Infante D. Henrique (1986), awarded by General Ramalho Eanes, with the Grand Cross of the Order of Christ (1996), awarded by Mário Soares, and with the Grand Collar of Order of Infante D. Henrique (2001), awarded by Jorge Sampaio, a decoration awarded exceptionally, as it is normally intended for heads of State.
 
“A huge loss”
"Deholate", thus reacted Anabela Ritchie to the death of the last governor. “I was very dismayed. I knew him seriously sick, but we are never prepared. I am not, ”he said in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. He deprived closely with Rocha Vieira, as president of the Legislative Assembly, and ensures that, besides the work relationship, they eventually created a friendship.
“I had an excellent working relationship with the Governor. A relationship of great solidarity, also very determined by the fact that we were aware that we were in the transition period. And we had a lot of work ahead of us”, he recalled. “It was possible for us to become friends”, he added.
Anabela Ritchie points out that she always felt that she “could speak at ease” with Rocha Vieira. “I can say I had a very good relationship. Sometimes we agreed, sometimes we disagreed. But there was room to explain our way of thinking, the meaning as we were seeing things. ” The goal was always to "find solutions."
Stressing that she enjoyed working with the Governor, Anabela Ritchie also praised the “important figure” he was for the transition: “I really admired the determination with which he did things, his competence and dedication”.
He also recalled that Rocha Vieira “listened to others and allowed them to speak,” heard different opinions from the most varied people. "It was a facet that I admired a lot," he noted, also saying that he was a "calm, serene" man.
In turn, Jorge Rangel said it was “a huge honor” to serve Portugal alongside Rocha Vieira, “in the government of Macao, integrating his governance team, and in civil society institutions, such as the Historical Society of Independence of Portugal, Military Associations, Foundations linked to Macau and the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center in Lisbon that he was the founder. ”
"I highlight its sense of state, attachment to fulfill the mission, intelligence, leadership and accomplishment, dignity, responsibility, dedication to the family and causes and love to Portugal," said the former secretary For the administration, education and youth of the Government of Macao, adding that it will always remember "with respect and admiration for the example of life that went to how many worked with it and somehow collaborated."
"It was a privilege to get to know him closely, to accompany him in multiple and diverse journeys at the service of Portugal and Macau, with him to live in the civil society institutions and deserve his confidence and friendship," he said.
José Luís de Sales Marques worked directly with Rocha Vieira for around eight and a half years during the transition period, as president of the Leal Senado and also as a member of the Governor's Advisory Council. Subsequently, the economist continued to work with the General within the scope of the Portuguese School.
"It is a huge loss, in terms of the importance of the figure that was General Rocha Vieira, its importance in the history of Macau as the last governor, but not only for this, because it actually worked the transition from Macao," he said.
"At the same time as infrastructures were built and material conditions for the transfer of administration to China were prepared, this was also done through his wisdom, his diplomacy and his vision of things," he continued.
For Sales Marques, the former Governor was always careful to maintain the stability and prosperity of Macau. “His role in the transition process and his role as a moderator in certain circumstances of what happened is known, and that is why he is an unavoidable figure”, he also told this newspaper.
 
“It dedicated Macau a lot”
Meanwhile, Jorge Neto Valente stressed that he lost a friend and remembers the last Governor of Macau as a “man who remains in history, not in the footnotes, at the center of history”. The lawyer considers that “Macau owed him a lot”. For Neto Valente, Rocha Vieira was very important in the transition period, “which he followed until the end, as we know, and left Macau with all dignity”.
After returning to Portugal, recalls the lawyer, “the General continued to be interested in things in Macau and contributing to the good of Macau”. Rocha Vieira returned to the territory a few times and on one of his last visits he received an Honoris Causa doctorate from the University of Macau.
The lawyer reinforces that the former Governor “did what he had to do and was a person who dedicated a lot of his life to Macau”, having been in the territory long before that, in the 1970s, as a troop engineer.
“I met him at that time”, points out Jorge Neto Valente, adding that Rocha Vieira returned to be Governor “at the hands of Mário Soares, after the experience of civil governors had not gone well from the point of view of Portugal, from the point of view of from a political point of view, and Mário Soares went to get him from the Azores”.
After remembering that Rocha Vieira was a member of the Board of Trustees of the Fundação Escola Portuguesa de Macau, an educational establishment founded during his mandate in 1998, agreed in the Liaison Office, Neto Valente points out that the former highest representative of Portugal in Macau left many things that are still valid today.
"He and the people who chose to accompany him in governance in recent years have faced a very difficult time, hard work and only really people with a lot of desire and love Macau and Portugal could do what he did," he said. After leaving Macao, he finishes his statement, "the general has always remained linked to the territory."
José Rocha Diniz, co-founder of JTM, also mourned the death of Rocha Vieira. “I'm very sorry, but it was something that didn't surprise me, because I followed the last few months, in which he was hospitalized, seriously”, he said, adding: “I was with him at a dinner after the tribute to Dr. António Aresta at the Cultural and Scientific from Macau, in Lisbon”.
Recalling that the last governor “managed to mobilize the majority of Macau's population during the last years of the transition”, Rocha Diniz pointed out that he had a “great advantage”. “I knew the Territory very well, because I had already been deputy secretary, I knew the two diverse communities and also the way the Chinese understand power, so I had a great advantage over previous governors,” he said.
“April 25 and November 25,” Purchase Rocha Diniz, “Nowadays, when it comes to General Rocha Vieira Portugal almost everyone stresses the way he put the Portuguese flag to his chest” at the time of transfer . "In Portugal, all the complexity of the transition process is unknown, in which Macao was not called to negotiations, which were between Portugal and China, but Macau had, however, numerous fundamental questions to resolve," on loco "."
“Rocha Vieira was very creative and firm in the way he always kept Macau's positions, sometimes even against Portuguese institutions,” he recalled, adding that “contrary to what some people may think, he was a dialogue man with a deep spirit Mission of the interests of Portugal and the Portuguese who lived in Macau, but always recognizing that it was in a decisive moment to solve a 'problem inherited from history', where Portugal had to go well ”.
“The Portuguese administration left Macau, but the Portuguese remain here, continuing to contribute to its progress and development”. Rocha Diniz concluded with a word of deep condolences, in this hour of pain, “to Dr. Leonor Rocha Vieira and her children”.
In turn, António José de Freitas began by stating: “More than the last Governor of Macau, I lost a great friend”. Then, he remembered that three months ago he had spoken to Rocha Vieira on the phone.
The provider also recalled that Rocha Vieira came to Macau annually, being part of the curators of the Portuguese School Foundation, and in 2019 came at the invitation of Santa Casa, on the 450th anniversary of the institution. "At the time, he was proclaimed meritorious from Santa Casa," he said, reiterating that he lost "a great friend."
“For me, he was the best Governor of Macau”, continued António José de Freitas, adding that they always had a lot of contact.
António Félix Pontes, economist and former administrator of the Monetary Authority, stated that Rocha Vieira “was a good governor, loved and respected by the entire population of Macau, and who honored Portugal in a historic phase of this Territory”.
"I owe you the appointment for deputy to the Legislative Assembly of Macao, from 1991 to 1999, never having interfered with my political action in this function," he said, regretting that he lost "a great friend."
 
“It fulfilled”, but it was not to “everyone’s liking”
Jorge Fão also said he was saddened by the news, which was given to him through JTM. Regarding the mandate of the former Governor, the president of the general assembly of the Association of Retirees, Retirees and Pensioners of Macau highlights that “he did what he had to do, but it was not completely to the satisfaction of public administration workers”.
However, Jorge Fão says that General Rocha Vieira pleased the general population and also businesspeople. “I think he did well there.”
Regarding public service workers, “he wasn't that worried, but in the end we had a happy outcome, let's say, since the entire public administration achieved what it wanted, that is, what it was fighting for: for a pension, for a transfer of his functions to Portugal”.
Fão says he has no person in person. "I had a lot of contacts with him due to his function outside the civil service, but I was affectionate to the Association of Public Service, having dialogued a lot with him, although these dialogues were not very satisfactory," he acknowledges.
Despite everything, he points out, the association “happily managed to achieve the desired results, also because we traveled to Portugal and had several meetings with Mário Soares and Cavaco Silva and were in Beijing to talk about our desires and concerns”.
Jorge Fão concludes by stressing that the former governor of Macao, as the highest representative of Portugal in the territory, "fulfilled the mission that was given to him, even if, I repeat, it was not the liking of all."
The Association of Public Function Workers, directed by José Pereira Coutinho, also regretted the loss of Rocha Vieira and left him a thank you “for resolving, during the transition phase, many issues of the civil service workers, the Macaenses and those Portuguese who chose to continue to provide services in the MSAR ”. In a message, Coutinho also recalls that the use of the current headquarters of the association was authorized by Rocha Vieira.
 
PR and PM recall “sense of state”
The President of the Republic expressed “deep grief” for the death of Vasco Rocha Vieira, praising his “marked patriotism” and recalling him as “one of the most illustrious officers of the Portuguese army in the transition to democracy and the first decades of his statement” . “Always closely linked to commands, it has also performed political functions such as those of Minister of the Republic for the Autonomous Region of the Azores,” says the note published in the official site of the Presidency of the Republic. Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa also points out that Rocha Vieira was “very close to President António Ramalho Eanes”, having been “designated chancellor of the old military orders”. "The symbolism of the moment of transferring the Portuguese administration to the Chinese will remain in the memory of many Portuguese as an example of meaning, meaning of the public cause and marked patriotism," can be read. The President of the Republic, who claims to have followed “closely the last months” of Rocha Vieira's life, “presents to his family, and, much in particular, to his widow and children, the testimony of gratitude of Portugal, with very longing friendship". Also the Prime Minister recalled Rocha Vieira as "one of the most brilliant military personnel to give body to the patriotic meaning of being Portuguese", highlighting his "historical and striking and macau" connection. “General Vasco Rocha Vieira was one of the brightest military personnel to give body to the patriotic sense of being Portuguese, with special services in the consolidation of our democracy and in the historical and striking connection to Macao, where he was the last governor,” wrote Luís Montenegro, In a publication on the social network X. He also presented condolences to family and friends and said to keep from Rocha Vieira “gestures of kindness and words of civic and political responsibility”.
 
Eanes remembers “Extraordinary Man”
“General Rocha Vieira was an exceptional man for his excellent actions and his assumed social responsibility, deserving to be, rightly, considered 'one of the best of our greatest'”, wrote former President of the Republic Ramalho Eanes in a note sent to Lusa. He remembers him as “an extraordinary man”, especially “on three levels: for his distinctive personality, for his relevant military performance and for the services he provided to the country at a political level”. On a personal level, he “possessed superior qualities of spirit”, had “exceptional intelligence”, “a good temperament” and “had a strong personality”. At the military level, “he was one of the most distinguished of his generation, providing relevant services to the Army, in difficult times, namely, in the throes of the political regime prior to the 25th of April, during the 25th of April and, even, in the 25th of November, having also played an important role as a representative of the Portuguese Armed Forces within NATO”. Regarding the political level, he had an activity of “great quality and great importance for the country, both as minister of the Republic for the Azores, and also as governor of Macau, putting all his commitment into the design and successful execution of a policy of successful transformation of Macau, also participating, with the success that is known, in the transfer of the administration of the territory of Macau to the People's Republic of China”.
 
Army praises “patriotism” and “Legacy of Service”
The Army expressed its regret over the death of Lieutenant General Vasco Rocha Vieira and praised his “legacy of service and patriotism”, hoping that he “continues to inspire future generations”. In a note, the Army states that “it is in mourning, having lost one of its most notable soldiers”. “His life and legacy justify deep recognition and enduring respect for his memory, and constitute a factor of motivation and pride for all who serve in this centuries-old institution. May his legacy of service and patriotism continue to inspire future generations”, he highlights. According to a note, the wake will take place today, between 5:00 pm and 10:00 pm (Lisbon time), at the Military Academy Chapel, in Lisbon. Tomorrow, the wake will resume at 10:00, followed by a mass before lunch. After the ceremonies in Lisbon, the procession will head to the Algarve, where the funeral will take place at the Lagoa Municipal Cemetery.
 
“Dignified” Portuguese presence in the East
Former President of the Republic Aníbal Cavaco Silva lamented the death of Rocha Vieira, a “remarkable figure” whose legacy dignifies the last years of the Portuguese presence in the East. “We keep from General Rocha Vieira the solemn and dignified image of lowering the National Flag in Macau, now 25 years old. More important than this image, is the work of Rocha Vieira as the last Governor of Macau, dignifying the last years of our presence in the East, allowing us to leave the territory reconciled with our History and proud of the work we left behind”, he stated, in a condolence note sent to Lusa. Cavaco Silva expressed “deep sadness” over the death of Rocha Vieira, a “remarkable figure” in recent history, with whom he maintained “close bonds of friendship”. He also highlighted the “importance of the high military functions he performed, as Chief of the Army General Staff, in a critical period of consolidation” of Portuguese democracy, between 1976 and 1978. “His exceptional qualities of command, his firmness, integrity of character, and his ethical and military training helped to restore hierarchical authority and discipline in the Armed Forces in a troubled period in the country's life”, he maintained.
 
“One of the best interpreters of the importance” of Macau
The PS expressed regret for the death of Rocha Vieira, praising a life “entirely dedicated to the service of Portugal”. Noting that “his life was forever linked to Macau”, for the PS this “was one of the best interpreters of the importance” of that territory “for the relationship between Portugal and the Popular Republic of China”, as well as the uniqueness of RAE. “The last years of the Portuguese administration of the territory of Macao, under the leadership of General Rocha Vieira, are marked by the realization of several important infrastructural public works to support the subsequent development of Macao, as well as management reforms for its preparation For the subsequent period, ”he praises. The socialists also refer to the transfer ceremony, in which it was undeniable the way Rocha Vieira "embodied and symbolized dignity and tribute to the Portuguese presence over the centuries in Macao." "And marked the friendship and respect that the Portuguese maintain with Macao and the Popular Republic of China, and which allows, after 25 years of transition, to preserve the uniqueness of Macao that remains a meeting point between cultures," He added. The PS thus gives "public note of its deep respect for services to the country" and "addresses to your family and your friends your most felt condolences."
 
He performed public functions “always with dignity”
The president of the Government of the Azores, José Manuel Bolieiro, lamented the death of Vasco Rocha Vieira, recalling that the lieutenant general "always performed his public functions with dignity." "Pay tribute to a man who, throughout his career, has always performed his public functions with dignity, sense of duty and profound commitment to the public interest," he said, quoted in a press release. He adds that "leaves a legacy of service to the country, which will be remembered with respect and gratitude", manifesting "deep regret for the death of the lieutenant general", which "performed relevant functions to the service of Portugal." Rocha Vieira, who was Minister of the Republic for the Azores between 1986 and 1991, “stood out for the full and responsible way with which he held the position, contributing to the strengthening of relations between the Autonomous Region of the Azores and the State, always with respect for the regional autonomy and the specificities of the Azores ”. The Azorean executive also refers to the performance as governor of Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“We have to enrich” functions of the Sino-Lirofona platform</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/temos-de-enriquecer-funcoes-da-plataforma-sino-lusofona/</link><description>The MSAR has to “further enrich and widen the role and functions of the Sino-Lusophone platform”, which has a “relevant meaning” in the process of opening abroad, stressed the chief executive before the general consuls in the territory and delegates of Portuguese -speaking countries at the Macao Forum. Sam Hou Fai also defended the reinforcement of cooperation with Southeast Asia and praised the contributions of the Philippine community to the development of Macau
 
Macau will remain committed to boosting cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, as well as between the territory and Southeast Asia, assured the Chief Executive, at a dinner offered to the consuls-general in the Macao SAR and delegates from Portuguese-speaking countries at the Secretariat Permanent of the Macau Forum. “Macau has deep and friendly historical links with Portuguese-speaking countries and Southeast Asia”, highlighted Sam Hou Fai, considering that the results achieved in the areas of exchange and cooperation are “inseparable from the extraordinary work and diligent dedication” of the consuls. general and delegates of the Forum.
“In the new phase, guided by President XI's important speeches, the MSar will continue to implement the comprehensive, precise and unshakable manner 'a country, two systems' and boost development in all aspects, and will certainly provide new opportunities and platforms for the narrowing of cooperation relations ”from China and Macao with Lusophone and Southeast Asia countries, he stressed at dinner, which was also attended by the Commissioner of China's Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Liu Xianfa.
Given the process of opening and exchange of MSAR with the abroad, and in line with the guidelines recently transmitted by President XI Jinping, Sam Hou Fai began to highlight that cooperation with Lusophone countries is “very important and has a relevant meaning ”. “(…) We have to further enrich and widen the role and functions of the Sino-Lusophone platform, actively implement the various agreements and instruments established within the 6th Macao Forum Ministerial Conference, especially the action plan for economic cooperation and commercial (2024-2027) and we have to continue to boost a joint development characterized by equality, cooperation and mutual benefits, comprehensively raising the level of sino-illusophone cooperation ”in various areas, he accentuated, appealing to the intensification of exchanges, both, both officially as in the private sphere.
“The delegations that come from your countries to visit Macau will always be warm, and also to see the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin, the large Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau Bay and the other provinces and cities of Inland China, ”he said, addressing diplomats and delegates present at the reception. He also argued that the Misrem "has become one of the favorite destinations for international investments, which provides advantageous conditions to become a place of concentration of high quality international qualified frames."
At the same time, the Chief Executive expressed the desire to "constantly deepen cooperation between Sabem and Southeast Asia countries." “Southeast Asian countries and countries, including the geographically close Philippines, have a narrow economic and commercial cooperation, with intense exchange of people and in the cultural area, being traditionally good neighbors and good partners. By way of example, according to the 2021 census data, the Philippine population corresponds to about 5% of Macau's total population, being the second largest community in the region following the Chinese community, and makes valuable contributions to development Socioeconomic of Macao, ”he acknowledged.
From his perspective, it is important to “take advantage of this good basis of traditional cooperation” to “seize new opportunities, explore more potential for cooperation in all aspects and encourage greater progress” in exchanges between Macau and Southeast Asian countries.
It is recalled that, during the celebrations of the 25th anniversary of the Macao SAR, Xi Jinping stressed that the territory must adopt “a more open and inclusive stance to intensify international ties and increase global projection and attractiveness”. In particular, according to the Chinese leader, “Macau must concentrate efforts on building a platform for opening up to the outside world at a higher level, to reinforce bilateral openness with Portuguese-speaking Countries, promoting comprehensive cooperation of mutual benefits”.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Expected up to 670,000 border tickets in the Chinese New Year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/esperadas-ate-670-mil-passagens-nas-fronteiras-ano-novo-chines/</link><description>Between January 28 and February 4, New Year's holidays period, Macau could register 630,000 to 670,000 border tickets per day, anticipates the CPSP, anticipating that the peak entrances and exits will occur on days 1 and 2 February. On the other hand, according to STD, until last Thursday, 80% of hotel rooms had already been reserved for this festive season, with the average price of the rooms ranging from 1,000 to 2,000 patacas
 
The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) provides that, during the Lunar New Year's holidays, between January 28 and February 4, Macau borders may register, 630,000 to 670,000 tickets and exits, the day which means a total volume ranging from 5.04 million to 5.36 million. The estimates were presented yesterday, at a press conference where representatives of various public services presented the preparatory work to respond to the increase of tourists during this festive period.
Compared to Chinese New Year 2024, there could be an increase of at least 3%, the CPSP predicted, pointing out the peak period for border crossings to be the 1st and 2nd of February (4th and 5th day of the lunar calendar).
In addition, the corporation revealed that, between 1 and 21 this month, the “one entrance per week” visa policy, intended for Zhuhai residents, attracted 73,000 visitors, which translates into a daily average of 3,500 people, While the measure “a visa, multiple entries”, applicable to hengqin residence card holders, brought 18,000 visitors to the MSAR, a daily average of 900 people.
Regarding Chinese New Year, the CPSP assured that it had prepared a series of action plans, in order to ensure the fluidity and order of the flow of people in the city, road safety and smooth border crossings.
According to the places of festive activities and popular sights, CPSP will reinforce patrol agents and activate people flow control measures when necessary to maintain a good travel environment. In addition to planning to highlight more border agents and open more customs inspection counters, the corporation has ensured that it will be committed to strengthening the fight against taxi offenses and illegal driving behaviors. At the same time, more agents will be mobilized to combat the illegal pedestrian crossing.
In turn, the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) pointed out that there will be an increase in both the number of visitors and the hotel occupancy rate during the Lunar New Year. According to it, by the 16th of this month, the hotel sector already verified an occupancy rate of almost 80%, and this rate may record constant climbs with the approach of the holidays. According to the body, at this festive season, the average price of hotel rooms ranges from 1,000 to 2,000 patacas.
DST highlighted that, on the one hand, it has made many preparations to serve tourists well and guarantee the quality of the tourist service, and, on the other, it will maintain regular inspections at border posts, tourist attractions and shopping places, to combat illegal guides and illicit accommodation.
The Customs Services (SA) anticipated the peak of car exits through the Macau Post on the Delta Bridge on the 28th of January (the eve of the Lunar New Year) and the peak period of vehicle entry through the same border on the 31st. (3rd day of the lunar calendar), with around 500 passes per hour.
In view of the increase in car movements on the Delta Bridge, the SA is prepared to put more crossing routes into operation during peak flows, as well as deploying more customs agents and technical personnel, in order to increase the efficiency of car passage at the customs post.
At the same time, the SA will intensify inspections at borders, in the city and in the sea, with a view to maintaining the stability of Macau's public safety environment during the Spring Party. Customs will also continue to monitor the trend of “false tourists” activities and reinforce the inspections to prevent holidays from being used by illegal to smuggling.
On the other hand, due to the occasion of the Lunar New Year, when it is frequent to transport decorative plants from mainland China, such as orchids, the institute for municipal issues will install a provisional post for plant inspection in the arrivals of the border of the SERCO DOORS, which will operate from January 26 to 28, from 9h00 to 23h00. Inspection rates will be exempt.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Fines for illegal works totaled 1.5 million</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/multas-por-obras-ilegais-totalizaram-15-milhoes/</link><description>Last year, fines totaling around 1.5 million patacas were issued due to the execution of illegal works in the territory, and the Public Works Services Department warned that the fines relating to eight cases had not yet been paid, so that there will be coercive collection. There were 838 cases opened in 2024, an annual drop of 25%, with demolitions rising 85% to 238
 
Last year, authorities issued fines totaling around 1.5 million patacas due to illegal works, according to the Land and Urban Construction Services Directorate (DSSCU), which initiated 838 cases in this area. According to the data available, there was a drop of around 25% in relation to processes opened in 2023, which totaled 1,114.
Of the total number of cases, 238 concerned voluntary demolitions – an increase of 85% compared to the previous year, and 39 concerned the imposition of fines for carrying out illegal works. The body responsible for Public Works states in a statement that “the fines relating to eight cases were not paid within the set deadline, so the Administration will proceed with the respective coercive collection”.
“Compared to the past, the new legislation increased fines to apply to infrastructors that perform illegal works and added new fines to infrastructors that do not comply with the demolition orders. In addition, other sanctioning measures were also created, including the crime of disobedience, the interruption of water and energy supply, ”says DSSCU, justifying the increase of voluntary demolitions.
Since the entry into force of the legal regime for urban construction, the Macao SAR Government has reinforced the fight against illegal works, with the DSSCU giving priority to cases of new illegal works, renovation of illegal works, buildings in a state of disrepair and to cases of illegal works located in buildings whose use license was issued after the new law came into force.
The data available on the DSSCU website show that in 2024 there were 48 processes with notification of the final decision. In this regard, the body explains that it acts in accordance with the law and that infrastructors should demolish illegal works and replace the place “as soon as possible”. However, in case of non -compliance, DSSCU will follow up on administrative procedures until the final decision of the case is made. "Received the notification of the final decision, the infrastructors must demolish illegal works and replace the place within the stipulated period, otherwise DSSCU will make the proper demolitional actions, whose expenses are borne by the offenders," he adds.
If after the hearing for the illegal work and after the DSSCu makes a final decision and issue the demolition order, the offender requires voluntary demolition within the deadline, the fine is halved. However, the law states that this benefit of reduction and exemption can only be applied once. DSSCU also states that if the offender again violates the law in the next five years, he is considered recurrence, so the fine is high in a quarter.
The body reiterated, in a statement, that it will continue to combat illegal works to safeguard the safety of buildings and the housing environment in the territory.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>World leaders congratulated Trump but according to their interests</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/actual/lideres-mundiais-felicitaram-trump-mas-de-acordo-os-seus-interesses/</link><description>Leaders from around the world have congratulated Donald Trump, but differently, as you can see. This was the most unique political return in recent US history, that of a former president who did not recognize his defeat in 2020, who promises to "avenge" from his opponents and who was criminally convicted, and was the target of two Murder attempts.
China stated that it is “willing to work” with the new US administration to “strengthen dialogue and cooperation” and highlighted by Foreign Ministry spokesman Mao Ning that “the history of the development of relations between the China and the US tells us that if the two countries work together, both parties will benefit, but if they fight each other, both will be harmed.”
Also before the inauguration, Russian leader Vladimir Putin said he is “open to dialogue” on Ukraine to achieve “lasting peace”. “As for resolving the situation, I would like to emphasize that its objective should not be a brief truce, but a lasting peace, based on respect for the legitimate interests of all people,” he added. For his part, India's PM, Narendra Modi, congratulated “dear friend” Donald Trump, and said he hopes the two countries will work together again. “I look forward to working closely together again, to benefit both our countries and to shape a better future for the world”, he posted on the social network X. Also, Japanese PM, Shigeru Ishiba, “expressed his desire to work in close collaboration” with Trump “to have a free and open Asia-Pacific region”, according to a government statement.
In another quadrant, Israel's PM, Benjamin Netanyahu, said in a video message that “the most beautiful days” of his alliance are to come. "I believe we will work together to bring the US-Israel alliance to even higher levels." For his part, the Palestinian PR, Mahmoud Abbas, expressed the willingness to cooperate with him in search of a “two -state solution”. “We are ready to work with you to achieve peace during your term, with a solution of two internationally recognized states (…) living side by side in security and peace,” said Abbas, according to information released by the official Palestinian news agency, WAFA.
PR Lula da Silva expressed the desire for the USA to continue to be “a historic partner” of Brazil during Donald Trump's government. “We don’t want conflict. Not with Venezuela, not with the Americans, not with China, not with India and not with Russia”, emphasized Lula.
Ukrainian leader Volodymyr Zelensky said his return to the White House represents a "opportunity" to reach "fair peace" in Ukraine. "Today is a day of change, and also a day of hope to solve many problems, including global challenges," Zelensky said on social networks. "President Trump is always decisive, and the peace policy through the strength he has announced offers an opportunity to strengthen American leadership and achieve just and long -term peace, which is the main priority," he added.
The European Union (EU) also hopes to work with Trump to face “global challenges”, said the president of the European Commission), Ursula Von der Leyen. “Together, our societies can achieve greater prosperity and strengthen their common security. This is the lasting strength of the transatlantic association”, Ursula published on the X social network.
Mexican PR, Claudia Sheinbaum, defended a relationship based on “dialogue” and “respect” and the Canadian Prime Minister. “We are stronger when we act together”, said Prime Minister Justin Trudeau, stressing that “Canada and the USA maintain the most fruitful economic partnership in the world, and are each other’s largest trading partner”, foreseeing the threat of imposing 25% tariffs.
German head of government, Olaf Scholz, wished the continuation of what he called “good transatlantic relations” with the US, Germany's “closest ally” and stressed that “the purpose of our policy continues to maintain good transatlantic relations. The EU, which has 27 members and over 400 million people, is a strong union, ”said Scholz. Still in Europe, Italy's PM, Giorgia Meloni, expressed its “best votes” to US President Donald Trump. “I am sure that the friendship between our nations and the values ​​that unite us will continue to reinforce the partnership between Italy and the United States, facing the global challenges together and building a future of prosperity and security for our peoples,” the Extreme Leader said Right on social networks, the only European leader to travel to Washington. For his part, King Carlos III sent a personal message of congratulating Donald Trump, in which he cited what he called the “special and lasting relationship between the United Kingdom and the US”, while the PM, Viktor Orban, one of the few next European leaders From Trump, he anticipated that it is “our turn to occupy Brussels,” the EU headquarters.
In Portugal, PR Marcelo defined Trump as a president “for whom the Pacific is very important, for whom relations with China are very important, for whom relations with Russia are equal to what were already in the first term, in which Russia, therefore, is not a problem for its US vision, ”which gives no importance to Europe, which," has to do it for life. "
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Suggested improvement in the formation of patriotic staff</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sugerida-melhoria-da-formacao-de-quadros-patrioticos/</link><description>The General Association of Overseas Chinese proposed an improvement in the formation of qualified patriotic political frames. The suggestion was made at the meeting with the Secretary for Administration and Justice, in the context of the government lines
 
The area of ​​administration and justice motivated suggestions from the General Association of Overseas Chinese of Macau, involving the improvement of the system for training qualified patriotic political personnel in Macau. During the meeting with Secretary André Cheong, within the scope of the Lines of Government Action, the association also proposed that good work be done in publicizing the law on minority languages.
Among several issues addressed, the Government member spoke of the Deep Cooperation Zone, “where Macau has some deficiencies, such as the shortage of qualified staff”, stating that, in the future, it will reinforce the Macao SAR's participation and increase the number of public servants, ensuring that the team under his supervision will continue “to study and increase the efficiency of public administration”.
André Cheong also attended a meeting with the General Union of the Macao residents' associations (“Kaifong”), where he heard suggestions from his leaders. Saying a look at a series of large works carried out by the government, the president of “kaifong”, ng siu lai, said they hoped these works, related to the life of the population, “can be continuously optimized to meet the needs of society and ensure the improvement of people's quality of life ”.
He added that in the future, "the progress of production and legislative review must be accelerated, to allow the legal regime of Macao to follow the evolution of the times."
In other meetings maintained by the secretaries, the security guard, Wong Sio Chak, was at the Macao General Association of Women. In the lecture, the chairman of the board said he hoped the guardianship implements the goal of "actively preventing the various risks to national security and consolidating the security and stability of society." This can only be achieved, from the perspective of Un Sio Leng, through the constant improvement of the legal system of national security, the creation of a mechanism for monitoring any risks and the reinforcement of education on the subject.
Wong Sio Chak revealed that, in response to urban development, the security department will begin, this year, the sixth phase of the “Eyes in the Sky” system, further enhancing crime prevention and combat capabilities with scientific and technological resources.
Visiting the Macau Youth Federation, however, was the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP, who recorded some suggestions. Highlight for the proposal to continue the expansion of industry-university-investment coverage, “to encourage the young layer to maintain an innovation dynamic”, as well as maintaining the support for the development of small and medium enterprises and the improvement of the plan Support for young entrepreneurs.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DSAT will study suggestions from schools to improve road safety</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dsat-estudara-sugestoes-de-escolas-para-melhorar-seguranca-rodoviaria/</link><description>After a student was run over by a public bus in the North Zone, representatives from several schools in the area were invited to an urgent meeting on road safety, organized by DSAT, CPSP and DSEDJ. At the meeting, they suggested, for example, adjusting the location of some crossings and extending the crossing time for pedestrians at some traffic lights. DSAT promised that it will analyze the feasibility of the proposals discussed as quickly as possible
 
Following an accident that occurred three days ago on Rua da Tribuna, in which a secondary school student was run over by a public bus on a pedestrian crossing, the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT), the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) and the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) organized an urgent meeting on road safety the day before yesterday, together with representatives from several schools located in the North Zone. The meeting aimed to encourage interested parties to jointly assess the current traffic situation around schools and discuss improvement proposals.
According to a statement issued by the three organizations, school representatives made several suggestions, including adjusting the location of some crossings, making the crossings at some intersections controlled by traffic lights, extending the crossing time for pedestrians at some traffic lights and expanding the scope of some pedestrian islands.
In a reaction, DSAT has promised that it will study the viability of their proposals as soon as possible and organize interdepartal inspections “on -site” together with schools, in order to continually improve the road environment.
At the same time, the body revealed that it will collect suggestions, with all Macao educational establishments, regarding the improvement of road safety on the outskirts of schools. For this, DSAT, CPSP and DSEDJ will create a specific channel for collecting opinions on the subject, so that it makes students' displacement safer.
DSEDJ has called for schools to continue to reinforce road safety education with teachers and students. For its part, CPSP recalled that it promoted 124 lectures on road safety last year, with 11,000 participants.
Already DSAT noted that, since 2019, has prepared more than 300 proposals for optimization of crossings, of which 286 were executed, including 60 performed last year. As for the other proposals, the body indicated that they are being developed in an orderly manner.
At the same time, since the end of 2021, DSAT has begun to install diagonal treadmills in places with conditions, constituting omnidirectional pedestrian crossing installations. Currently, eight crosses with traffic lights in Macao are equipped with pedestrian gender facilities. In this year, four other places in the North Zone will also welcome this type of facilities, DSAT said.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Guaranteed stable food supply</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/garantido-fornecimento-estavel-de-alimentos/</link><description>The Chinese Ministry of Commerce guarantees the arrival of safe food products for consumption by the population of Macau. A Chinese delegation met with officials from the Institute for Municipal Affairs and went to two markets in the territory
 
A delegation from the China Ministry of Commerce went to the territory to learn about the situation related to the supply of agricultural products and derivatives from the continent to Macau. During the visit, the entourage visited the new Macao supply market and the Patane market.
With the Spring Festival just around the corner, several measures have been taken to ensure the stable supply and quality security of agricultural products and derivatives to Macau. In this sense, supply sources were organized, emergency plans were activated, cooperation between departments was reinforced and a safe line of defense was established.
The deputy director of the Ministry of Commerce said that the Central Government has attached great importance to the supply of agricultural products and derivatives to Macau over the years. Li Na highlighted, in the meeting he held with officials from the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM), that there has been close cooperation between the Central Government's plan, the respective Services, provinces and cities in Mainland China.
Local governments and various central government services have guided the establishment of a series of high standard production and processing bases, with the purpose of ensuring that the Population of the MSAR can consume safe food products.
In a note about the Ministry's visit, the IAM highlights that, since 2024, companies that supply agricultural products and derivatives to Macau have overcome adverse factors, such as the increase in breeding costs and the African swine fever epidemic, and have better guaranteed supply of agricultural products and derivatives.
Between January and November last year, Mainland China supplied Macau with 400 thousand tons of agricultural products and derivatives, a year-on-year increase of 9.4%. Products include live pigs and cattle, chilled and frozen chickens, cereals, vegetables, fruits, aquatic products, drinking water, among others.
During the visit to the territory, the Ministry's delegation also held exchanges and discussions with the chairman of the Board of Directors for Municipal Affairs, Chao Wai Ieng, and Administrator Ung Sau Hong, in which they learned about the demand and left the guarantee supply of fresh and live food to the Macau market, defining several measures to further ensure a stable supply of food products.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Art with 3,000 years of history showcases pieces from Hebei and Guizhou</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/arte-3-000-anos-de-historia-divulga-pecas-de-hebei-guizhou/</link><description>Making known to the Gold and Silver Crafts of Hebei and Guizhou is the objective of some workshops that will be promoted by the Cultural Institute, in the context of a craft exhibition of those Chinese provinces. The pieces of art-embedded art and Chinese art in Cloisonné are characterized by a high degree of technical refinement and their stunning ornamentation, of great artistic value
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
“Brightness of Art - Gold and Silver Craft Exhibition of the Provinces of Hebei and Guizhou” opens the public tomorrow at the TAP Seac Gallery, at 18:30. To make known the artistic value of the pieces, the Cultural Institute (IC) promotes four workshops on February 8 and 9, open to the public and with free participation, upon registration.
The art of creating gold and silver pieces is a type of traditional Chinese craftsmanship with more than 3,000 years of history. In this context, the filigree inlaid art and Chinese cloisonné art from Hebei Province and the goldsmithing of the Miao ethnic group from Guizhou Province, which appear on the National List of Items Representative of the Intangible Cultural Heritage of China, stand out “as particularly brilliant examples”, according to a note released by the IC.
The pieces from Hebei are characterized by a high degree of technical refinement, the diversity of their motifs and their dazzling ornamentation, possessing great artistic value. In turn, Guizhou goldsmithing denotes a multiplicity of cultural connotations, giving rise to works with a markedly ethnic style, with excellent artistic taste.
The exhibition features more than 160 sets of jewelery and exquisite gold and silver articles. These works, created by heirs of intangible cultural heritage and masters artisans, have sophisticated formats, a very high degree of technical refinement and a variety of styles. “Inheriting longtime traditional techniques and incorporating a modern aesthetic, this traditional art radiates a contemporary aura,” says the IC.
The exhibition has guided tours on Saturdays, Sundays and holidays, with sessions in Cantonese at 3pm and in Mandarin at 4:15pm.
The workshops will take place in the Activities Room of the Xian Xinghai Memorial Museum, located on Rua Francisco Xavier Pereira, in Macau. On February 8, from 10:00 to 12:00 and from 15:00 to 17:00, an instructor, a representative heir at the provincial level of Hebei Province, will introduce the techniques of filigree inlaid art. The following day, at the same times, a monitor will present Miao silver carving techniques from Guizhou.
Each of the four workshops, aimed at people over 16 years of age, will be conducted in Mandarin, with 16 places available. Registration can be made from 10 am on Saturday, January 25th.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Market with live music brings together bands and SMEs in Barra</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mercado-musica-ao-vivo-junta-bandas-pme-na-barra/</link><description>More than three dozen small and medium-sized companies and popular music bands from Macau, Hong Kong and Taiwan will create a festive atmosphere in Barra. The “Music Festival” will be held on two Saturdays, January 25th and February 1st, and joins the “Bênção da Sorte and Weekend Markets”, in addition to other activities, including an exhibition of paintings by Japanese Shinri Murakami
 
The Barra zone will have a special animation as of tomorrow, with the opening of the “lucky blessing market”, including the “weekend market” that will host more than 35 small and medium-sized businesses (SME) . There will be found, through various activities, the cultural heritage with the contemporary style.
MGM's initiative, “Barra Lucky Blessing”, will take place between 24 and 26 and from January 31 to February 2, offering a diverse range of products that cover cultural creations, technological innovations, handicrafts and pet products .
In addition, visitors have another attraction: the “Music Festival”, scheduled for two Saturdays (January 25 and February 1), bringing together well -known bands and musicians from Macau, Hong Kong and Taiwan, such as Wendy Wander, Scamper and Otome Syndream, among others.
The spirit of “pet-friendly” of the event will translate into the opening of all areas of the bar to pets.
Tomorrow also starts an exhibition from 22 painting works in the old slaughterhouse, by the Japanese illustrator Shinri Murakami, who can be appreciated by the public until February 25. It is a partnership between MGM and the Prince Kung Palace Museum, with the aim of publicizing and combining the Chinese intangible cultural heritage with a modern touch.
The Japanese artist presents his fashion illustrations in a creative cross between art and retail.
The exhibition is complemented by a “pop-up coffee”, which offers thematic gastronomic experiences and exclusive products. Before the Spring Festival, Shinri will also join local students to create a mural in the Barra neighborhood, further reinforcing its artistic attraction.
The “New Year Creative Painting Workshop” will also be organized, which will allow you to participate in the ancient art of friction printing, a craft recognized as Chinese intangible heritage. Participants will have the opportunity to enjoy modern reinterpretations of the museum's artwork to create their own impressions of Chinese New Year. To enhance the experience, MGM has transformed the friction modules into exclusive sets of printing materials, available as exclusive holiday souvenirs.
In the presentation, Shinri Murakami stated that he was honored to be able to show his artistic works “in such a historically rich space, adding that “the fusion of heritage and modernity in this neighborhood is truly inspiring”. The artist highlighted that “together, we created an innovative shared space where my art goes beyond traditional exhibitions, connecting with various activities and integrating into the daily life of Macau”.
Barra events mark the beginning of the year of the serpent in that area of ​​the city, around elements of trends, arts, culture and flap.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Almost 180 thousand people vaccinated against the flu</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/quase-180-mil-pessoas-vacinadas-contra-gripe/</link><description>Close up of unrecognizable Doctor Vaccinating Child in Medical Clinic, Copy Space



Until the 19th of this month, anti-flu vaccines had been administered to 179 thousand people in Macau, the situation being “satisfactory”, observed yesterday Leong Iek Hou, director of the Center for Disease Prevention and Control of the Health Services. Even so, in a “Ou Mun Tin Toi” program, the doctor advised people who have already been infected to receive vaccines against this disease, in order to prevent infection with different types of viruses. According to Education Services, almost 80% of non-tertiary education students have already had flu vaccines. In turn, the Social Action Institute noted that the inoculation rate in homes exceeded 90%, while more than 60% of children enrolled in daycare centers have already taken the same preventive measure. On the program, Leong Iek Hou once again warned that, in the territory, the peak period of the flu virus will last until February. According to findings, currently the two main hospitals in Macau have received a stable number of flu patients while the number of acute flu cases tends to decrease compared to the same period last year. Specifically, patients with fever caused by the flu currently represent 16.2% of the total. On the other hand, with the Lunar New Year holidays approaching, the authorities have been carrying out preventive work relating to the flu in the last week, having contacted around 15 thousand people.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2331/</link><description>Consumers received electronic benefits of 227 million
Organized by the Government and Commercial Association (ACM) over 13 weeks last year, the “Great Award for Consumption in Macao” featured about 22,000 adherent stores and led to the use of electronic benefits of about 227 million Of Patacas and a total consumption of more than 1.1 billion, the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) said. Benefited commercial establishments belong to various sectors, especially retail trade (about 60%of the total), restoration (31%) and services and other branches (9%). During this activity, 559 establishments simultaneously offered additional offers to boost consumption in community neighborhoods, said DSEDT. According to the results of the questionnaires promoted by the organization, about 70% of the establishments and more than 65% of the residents responded to increases in the frequency and the amount of average weekly consumption in Macao, compared to the period prior to the realization of this program, and “showed -If satisfied with the general situation of this activity ”. About 5.9 million transactions were enabled to the big final draw on Tuesday. The total amount of the awarded prizes exceeded 1.68 million patacas, including 300,000 PATACA PATACES from ACM and electronic coupons from restaurants and hotels, offered by other organisms. The 499 award -winning list will be released online today (http://www.macaospendingarwards.com/).</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Loss of 68 million in the students committed on students</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/prejuizo-de-68-milhoes-nas-burlas-cometidas-sobre-estudantes/</link><description>The crimes of telephone burla perpetrated on students in 2024 totaled 109 cases from a total of 354, and caused a loss of about 68 million patacas. The Judicial Police have been in a strong combat in this matter, having been able to decrease. Cases of burla through the internet increased 4% in annual terms to 906, and phishing was the crime that recorded the largest increase
 
Victor Rebelo
 
In a city where violent crimes have decreased year after year, with only one case of homicide having been recorded in 2024, authorities are currently focusing a large part of their investigations on the increasing number of frauds. The director of the Judiciary Police (PJ) is peremptory in stating that “criminals no longer steal; defraud using increasingly advanced technological means”.
And among those targeted there are many students. Of the 354 cases of telephone fraud, 109 concerned young students (around 30%), which caused losses of around 68 million patacas, and in total losses of around 154 million were recorded. “It’s a very high value,” said Sit Chong Meng. Despite the large losses, misleading situations via telephone still reduced by 13% annually.
This reality received special attention yesterday at the PJ's annual meeting with the media, where the head of the corporation took stock of last year's activity, releasing statistical data and comparing them with 2023 and 2019.
“We have carried out many awareness campaigns at schools, also to alert parents, so that great care must be taken when students intend to go and study abroad”, said the director of the PJ, adding that “criminals use technologies increasingly advanced, very concealed, hence the great difficulty for the police in discovering them”.
Referring specifically to students, the PJ director highlighted the actions that have been carried out in schools, and also to alert parents, “so that great care can be taken when students intend to go and study abroad”.
On the other hand, and taking into account the issue of security in educational establishments in the territory, the PJ seeks to “create a safe environment for young people to grow and guide them towards development and success”. The Minors Monitoring Center continues to play “the role of a communication bridge”. Last year, 152 cases were monitored at the request of schools, 27 of which resulted in the initiation of monitoring processes.
 
Burlas through NET registered increase
On the other hand, in cases of fraud via the internet, there was an increase of 4% to 906 cases. “We have carried out many awareness campaigns so that cases of fraud can be reduced”, assured Sit Chong Meng.
According to the PJ, fraudsters have abusively used phishing messages and websites to steal credit card data, attracting the public through news, “which has made prevention difficult”. In 2024, there were 689 cases related to this type of crime, an increase of 1.1 times, and which caused losses of more than 14 million patacas to companies and the population.
“This is the type of crime that registered the biggest increase last year”, maintains the PJ, which states that throughout 2024, 697 sessions were held to disseminate information about fraud, which had 120,000 participants and 1,600 posts were published online. Among the actions, the PJ launched, in cooperation with the Education Services, the “Anti-fraud vaccine program on campus”, to consolidate awareness among students.
In the fight against money exchange scammers, “new achievements were achieved”, says the PJ. With the coordination of the Ministry of Public Security and in collaboration with the public security authorities of Mainland China, “the PJ carried out a strong repression, which fought crime at its origin and dismantled its entire chain up to the black and gray industry that is behind”, stated the director of the corporation.
Furthermore, “it was possible to produce a deterrent effect on these illicit activities through several phases of the ant removal operation”. According to the data released, until last December, the police resolved 84 cases of illegal exchange of money for gambling, which resulted in the arrest of 120 fraudsters and the seizure of money and chips, with a total value exceeding 11 million Hong Kong dollars .
Following communication with the banks, the PJ revealed that 680 accounts suspected of being used by fraudsters were reported, with 991 websites being blocked that were used by fraudsters to try to achieve their intentions.
In the 689 cases of various types of banking, the victims revealed their credit card data when they tried to buy goods or services online, more than double the record in 2023, causing losses of 14 million patacas.
The PJ noted at the conference that, thanks to an alert mechanism to suspend suspicious transactions and stop payments, it managed to recover almost 110 million patacas in 597 fraud attempts.
In the context of cross-border crime, the authorities arrested 236 members of groups, an annual increase of approximately 50%, having managed to dismantle “guess who am I” and false soothsayer networks, preventing the spread of crime, in collaboration with the Chinese police , Hong Kong and internationally.
 
Almost 1,500 inquiries on game crimes
In other aspects, there was an increase in crimes of robbery, theft or crimes related to gambling, however, this number is still lower than in 2019. In cases linked to the gambling industry, 1,423 investigations and complaints were opened, amounting to an increase of 28.6% compared to 2023 and a reduction of 34% compared to 2019.
There were 252 cases of loan sharking and 47 cases of kidnapping. Despite being higher figures than in 2023, it is still significantly lower than what occurred in 2019. The proportion of violent and serious crimes related to gambling continued to decrease. “This is the very positive result of prevention and combat”, highlights the PJ.
Another issue addressed was the information given by the PJ about human trafficking, specifically that it had managed to prevent a resident from being a victim of human trafficking to a center, in Southeast Asia, dedicated to fraud and extortion using telecommunications and the Internet. Two weeks earlier, the PJ said that five residents had been victims of the same crime, in Taiwan and Cambodia, deceived with false promises of high remuneration for supposed jobs.
Finally, the statistics relating to serious and violent crimes. The director of the PJ considers that the situation has remained at a “very low” level. There was one case of homicide, three of serious bodily harm, none of kidnapping, one of secret association, 25 of criminal association, 12 of domestic violence, 43 of arson and 169 of extortion. All represent a reduction compared to 2023.
It should be noted that, during the last year, 14,049 criminal cases were initiated, registering an increase of 13.4%. Of this number, 7,762 are inquiries and complaints, which represents an increase of 14.1%. In 2024, the total number of completed processes was 12,856, which translates into an increase of 22.7%. Additionally, 3,323 individuals were referred to judicial bodies.
On the other hand, the PJ set up 49 trafficking and 15 drug use, which represents a case reduction and an increase of six, respectively. In general, drug -related crimes maintained a “limited occurrence”.</description><pubDate>2025-01-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>AI pets “comfort” young Chinese people</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/animais-de-estimacao-ia-consolam-jovens-chineses/</link><description>In a Beijing shopping center, Zhang Yachun talks quietly with his best confidant: an artificial intelligence stabber robot whose captivating sounds make her not feel alone.
The 19-year-old had long-standing anxiety problems at school and found it difficult to make new friends. However, he eventually found solace in “BooBoo,” a pet-like robot that uses artificial intelligence (AI) to interact with humans.
“I feel that I have someone to share happy moments with,” he confessed to AFP agency in his apartment, where he lives with his parents and a pet duck.
AI-powered devices are increasingly being used in China to combat social isolation.
“BooBoo”, a furry robot that looks like a guinea pig created by “Hangzhou Genmoor Technology”, costs 1,400 yuan. Since May last year, around a thousand copies of the rugby ball-sized robot, designed to meet the social needs of young people, have been sold, according to Adam Duan, from the company that developed it.
Zhang Yachun named his “Aluo” and carries it in a shoulder bag. Your furry companion has the same role as a human friend, she says, ensuring that “he makes us feel like someone is needed.”
The “social robot” market, such as “BOOBOO”, can grow seven times by 2033, reaching US $ 42.5 billion, according to consultant Imc Group. Asia already dominates this market.
Guo Zichen, 33, believes that a pet robot compensates for the time that does not spend with his children. “People are spending less time with their children now,” watch this man while looking at a robot dog at a Weilan store in Nanjing in the east of the country. A robot can help “check or do other activities,” he says.
"Baby Alpha", the robot dog of the company "Weilan", is sold by 26,000 yuans. About 70% of buyers are families with young children, according to the company.
However, Guo Zichen is skeptical about the ability of these robots of providing the same joy as a dog of flesh and bone. “The main difference is that real dogs have soul,” he says.
In China, there are a growing number of AI products that aim to respond to consumers' emotional needs, such as conversational agents or virtual avatars of deceased people.
According to several experts, the effects of the policy of the only time, which has long been long, are boosting this market. People born at the beginning of this policy in the 1980s are now quadractors and often do not have time to dedicate themselves to the family, because competition in employment is fierce.
This leaves “little room for personal interactions, leading people to look for alternatives to meet their emotional needs,” says Wu Haiyan, a specialist AI and Psychology professor at the University of Macao. This follow-up, even if it is virtual, “improves the well-being of individuals who would otherwise feel isolated,” says the researcher.
Zhang Peng, father of Zhang Yachun, comprises his daughter's attachment to the "student" robot. “When we were young, there was no shortage of friends. We had many as soon as we left the door, ”explains the 51 -year -old man. But "currently, urban young people seem to be under great pressure, so they may not have friends," he adds.
Zhang Yachun, the only daughter, emphasizes that the acquisition of "students" helped her discuss her concerns with her parents. "The people of my generation often have difficulty communicating personally, but what they feel in their heart has not changed," he says, caressing the mascot.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>