<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Value and form of attribution of the still uncertain checks</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/valor-forma-de-atribuicao-dos-cheques-ainda-incertos/</link><description>The Chief Executive admits that there may be changes in the value and the distribution of pecuniary checks, a matter that is not yet closed. The budget for this year's pecuniary reimbursement plan is 7.48 billion of patacas. Sam Hou Fai also reiterated the attention that the government gives problems such as the aging of the population and the low birth rate. As for the viaduct between zones A and B, it assumed the intention to “improve” the proposal
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Admittedly, pecuniary checks will be distributed this year, but the government has not yet decided whether there will be changes in both the value and the form of attribution. “The budget for this year is 7.48 billion Patacas and, when they asked for my opinion at the time, I agreed to issue the checks. Currently, the global inflation rate is still low, so the measures for this year have to be implemented, ”began by telling Sam Hou Fai to journalists.
“If there is room for improvement, how much and how to distribute, the public must give opinions, to demonstrate more justice, accuracy and the connection to the MSAR. And in these ways we should ponder more, ”added the chief executive, on the sidelines of the Spring Dinner offered by the Macao Chinese Companies Association.
As I said, it is necessary to take into account "the global economic environment." “If they do not forget that monthly revenues of the game worth 20 billion patacas were used as a base, there is a small surplus. But see the month of December: there was only about 18 billion. The government will consider this question as a whole and will announce it to the public when a decision is made, ”he continued.
Admitting that the pecuniary reimbursement plan benefits residents and creates expectations in society, Sam Hou Fai recalled that it was implemented in 2008, as a temporary measure, and whose objective was to share with the population the result of economic development, if there were conditions in the public coffers. The leader of the MSAR also recalled that, so far, have been awarded 90 billion patacas in this context.
"The Government of MSar will continue to hear the opinions of the various sectors of society, hoping to improve and improve this measure," he said. Remember that in recent times there have been the voices to consider that the form of attribution of the checks must be changed, arguing, for example, that residents living abroad will no longer receive this benefit.
At the same time, Sam Hou Fai guaranteed, according to a statement from the Social Communication Office, that "the improvement of the welfare of the population and the support for vulnerable groups are the focus of governance actions." Regarding the rigid public expenses of the welfare of the population and that occupy the highest proportion of overview, ensured that the government "will continue to maintain close communication with the sectors of society, alarming more opinions and suggestions."
In this field, he said he hopes-under the assumption of safeguarding the basic needs of the welfare of the population and if the financial situation allows-"to fully consider the various factors and study the policy of adjusting various benefits."
It also underlined the “high attention that gives matters related to the elderly and children”, especially at a time when Macao is facing a double challenge: the aging of the population and the low rate of birth. The government “will, through a series of policies and services, provide support and affection to needy families, as well as encourage young families to have children,” he said.
 
Operators “have responsibility” in the case of satellite casinos
The three-year period of transition from the satellite casinos ends in late 2025 and, asked about the future of workers in those spaces, the chief executive recalled that "they are recruited by the operators, so they have the responsibility of taking appropriate action."
Sam Hou Fai added that the government is available to help if necessary. He also said he believed that game operators and satellite casinos managers will coordinate according to the contract entered into and proceed well to transition work. ”
There are 11 satellite casinos that can close, implying about 12,000 workers.
On the other hand, asked about the viaduct proposal between zones A and B, he pointed out that the government “has the need to proceed well to planning and complementary road facilities, linking it to several adjacent zones”, as zone A will become an important area of ​​education and housing ”.
Urbanists and deputies have warned that the viaduct can have impacts on world heritage. Recognizing that there are different opinions, Sam Hou Fai stated that the services will continue to collect opinions, "which will be studied and analyzed, to improve the respective proposal."
In relation to the flood protection work in Coloane -which environmentalists, urban planners and deputies also question, due to any impacts on the environment and protected animals -the chief executive stressed the “importance of the work to prevent flooding”. He stated that the work aims to favor “safeguarding the life of the population” and the “security of their goods”. In this sense, it ensured that the services “will plan the work well”.
Sam Hou Fai reiterates bet on science and technology
In a meeting with the Undersecretary-General of the United Nations, Tshilidzi Marwala, the Chief Executive stained that the government “gives high importance to the application of innovative science and technology in various areas” and has fostered growth of this type of industries. Sam Hou Fai also stressed that "there is a determination to boost the industrialization of innovative science and technology, which can also introduce new dynamics in local economic development." More specifically, he highlighted the incentive to “foreign universities and companies” to enjoy Macao and the deepened cooperation zone. Tshilidzi Marwala, who is also a rector of the United Nations University, was visiting Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>GDP grew 8.8% in 2024 after fifth quarterly deceleration</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pib-cresceu-88-em-2024-apos-quinta-desaceleracao-trimestral/</link><description>MSAR Gross Domestic Product increased by 8.8% in 2024, in annual and real terms, falling short of government projections and the international monetary fund. In the last three months of last year, homologous growth has reached only 3.4%, reflecting the fifth consecutive quarterly slowdown
 
Sérgio Terra
 
Calculated at current prices, the value of Macau's Gross Domestic Product (GDP) was 403.3 billion patacas by 2024, translating an annual growth of 8.8% in real terms and corresponding to 86.4% of the volume of 2019, before the pandemic, announced the direction of statistics and censuses (DSEC) services (DSEC). The performance of the local economy was thus short of the forecast made about a year ago by the then Secretary for Economics and Finance, Law Wai Nong, who pointed to a 10.3%growth, as well as the Projections of the International Monetary Fund (IMF), which started at 13.9%and were low magazines to 10.6%.
The per capita GDP, which reflects the average value of goods and services produced per person, grew 7.6% to 587,922 patacas compared to 2023, in a year when the implicit deflator of GDP, which measures global price variation, increased by 0.4%.
After increasing 75.1% in 2023 -considering the data reviewed by DSEC -GDP has followed a deceleration trajectory, in a context influenced by a relatively high comparative base and the slowdown or stabilization of the game's revenues. In the last three months of 2024, Macau's economy registered the fifth consecutive quarter of slowdown, growing only 3.4% in real terms, compared to 3.8% in the previous three months, 7.1% between April and June, 23.0% between January and March and 79.7% in the fourth quarter of 2023.
Between October and December, the GDP value equivalent to 88%of the economic volume of the same period of 2019. In the fourth quarter analysis, DSEC highlights homologous additions in internal demand (plus 2.8%) and service exports (plus 2.1%).
In the general calculation of last year, the economy was again driven by service exports, which grew by 9.2% compared to 2023, benefiting from the 23.8% increase in the number of visitors. In turn, the internal demand, which encompasses private consumer expense, the government's final consumer consumer expense and investment, advanced 2.3%.
According to official statistics, game service exports increased by 21.8%, contrary to the decline of 6.1%in exports of other tourist services, although they exceeded the 2019 level by 13%. In the field of foreign trade in goods, exports and imports of goods retreated 14.5% and 7.6%, in homologous terms, respectively.
 
Private compensates for breaking in public investment
Gross fixed capital formation grew 4.6% between 2023 and 2024, thanks to the reinforcement of 12.6% in the investment in the private sector, which pays a decrease of 8.4% in the public sphere. The investment in construction rose 5.1% in the private, however, it lowered 10% in the public sector, due to the completion of several works of large scope.
In turn, the values ​​of equipment investment illustrate annual increase of 31.1% and 1.2% in the private and public sectors, respectively.
The contribution of investment to general economic growth in 2024 was estimated at 0.7 percentage points. In this chapter, the largest weight was again detained by exports of services (7.3 points), followed by imports of goods (2,9) and private consumer expense (1.5).
At the level of internal demand, there is a 4.9% increase in private consumer expense, which DSEC attributes “continuous recovery of economic activities” and “uninterrupted labor market stability”. Still, the final consumption expenses of families had different evolutions, with the rise to be more modest in the local market (more 3.8%) than abroad (11.1%more).
Among the main components of GDP expense, the government's final consumer consumer expense fell 5.1% last year, following the end of the measures adopted under the “Living Subsidy Plan”, the body says, noting that net purchases of goods and services lowered 11.2% and employees remuneration rose 0.2%.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Unemployment reached a minimum historical</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/desemprego-atingiu-minimo-historico/</link><description>Between November and January, the unemployment rate in Macao retreated to 1.6%, the lower percentage since the beginning of these statistical records in 1992. Subtregae fell to 1.3%, and also becoming the historical minimum
 
The global unemployment rate in the MSAR was estimated at 1.6% between November 2024 and January this year, thus reaching the lowest level since the start of this type of statistical records, in 1992. According to data from the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC), the general rate decreased 0.1 points compared to the previous period (October to December) and 0.6 points in homologists, while Residents' unemployment fell 0.2 and 0.7 points on the same comparative bases by settling at 2.1%.
According to DSEC, the breaks registered between November and January are mainly due to the fact that the Chinese New Year has “giving rise to a reduction in the number of individuals looking for employment”, which led to a decrease in the number of unemployed people.
The Global Sub -Camping rate (1.3%), which encompasses cases of unpaid licenses, also decreased 0.2 percentage points, both in relation to the proper period and in the annual variation. In the sub-unemployment chapter, the lowest rate since there are records remains at 1.1%and was obtained between July and September last year.
Despite unemployment and underemployment descents, the population employed (376,300 individuals) decreased 0.5% (2,000 people) compared to the immediately preceding period. Employee residents (285,000) was the “loss” of about 1,000 people (less 0.3%).
Compared to the previous period, employee workers and other betting games (about 72,500) and thick and retail trade (41,400) increased 1.3% and 0.4%, respectively. On the other hand, the workforce in the hotel (29,300 employees), construction (24,000) and restoration (21,000) was decline of 3.6%, 4.3%and 2.5%, respectively.
In turn, the unemployed population (6,200) descended 6.5% (less 500 people), compared to the previous period. Among the unemployed looking for a new job, most previously worked in retail and game trade sectors.
According to DSEC, individuals looking for the first job equivalent to 10.8% of the unemployed population, less 3.1 points than in the period between October and December 2024.
Official data also show that, between November and January, cultural and recreational activities, stationery and other services absorbed 22.4%of the population employed, surpassing hotels, restaurants and similar establishments (13.4%) and thick and retail trade (11.0%). In a second line, real estate and services provided to companies are maintained (8.9%), Public Administration and Social Security (8.6%), domestic work (7.4%), construction (6.4%), education (6.2%), transportation, storage and communications (5.4%), financial activities (4.0%) and health and social action (3.9%).
The number of undereased decreased 11.9% (700 people) to about 5,000 in sequential terms, including 4,900 residents. Most of the sub -employer belonged to the business of real estate and services provided to companies.
On the other hand, the active population living in the MSAR (382,500) registered a decrease of 0.6% (less 2,500) compared to the preceding period. Employment survey excluded residents and non -residents who, despite working in Macao, live abroad, whose average number was calculated at about 104,900 in the period under analysis. Including this group, the total labor encompassed 487,500 people.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>"House of Dancing Water" returns to "City of Dreams" in May</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/house-dancing-water-regressa-ao-city-dreams-em-maio/</link><description>Megaproduction “House of Dancing Water” is back on “City of Dreams”, with the first sessions of the new version scheduled for May. The show, marked by innovative visual effects, will feature a new cast, a renewed plot and cutting -edge technologies. Ticket sales start on March 10

Victor Rebelo
 
Almost five years after being suspended, due to the pandemic, the show "House of Dancing Water" is back in Macao and "City of Dreams". The “Entertainment Show” will have the first sessions of the new version in May and tickets will be on sale from March 10th.
The “rebirth” of “water -based extravagance”, as Melco Resorts refers, comes with a new look, combining water, aerial stunts and other performances.
With rich scene content and avant -garde stage effects, megaproduction will have greater visual and immersive impact, the company guarantees. To expose history beyond the traditional relations between public and interpreter, the cast will interact with viewers from the seat area before the beginning of the show, “creating a personalized and seductive experience,” according to Melco.
The exhibition will show a mixture of dynamic dance choreography and daring aquatic acrobatics from a team of almost 300 cast elements from over 30 countries.
"House of Dancing Water" will maintain the essence of the past, when he exhibited in Macao for 10 years, until June 2020, although he is reimagined with a narrative form that aligns with contemporary artistic contexts.
The show will take place in a 270 -degree amphitheater, with a capacity of 2,000 seats and a pool of 19 million liters that cost about $ 250 million (about two billion patacas). The theater has cutting -edge stage technology, advanced water systems, hydraulic elevators, precision lighting and lasers, along with sophisticated projection technology to ensure unparalleled visual experience.
In “City of Dreams”, the audience will have the opportunity to watch “a pioneering theatrical innovation that provides stunning visual effects, with the epic recount to revolve around a romantic plot, contributing to a breathing aquatic show”, emphasizes Melco.
The new version of the "House of Dancing Water" is directed by Giuliano Peparini, artistic director of "Peparini Studios", and produced by "Our Legacy Creatations".
At the release ceremony of the new phase of the show, the guests were able to watch a similar show that will be presented from May at City of Dreams.
Lawrence Ho, president and CEO of Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, said the company again publicizing to the public “without parallel cultural and tourist experiences” and “this dedication gains life through reference entertainment projects that contribute to the development of new and high quality tourism in Macao”. He also stressed that this “world class production further reinforces the City of Dreams portfolio and establishes a new standard of excellence and innovation in terms of leisure and entertainment”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Green Week includes guided ecological visits</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/semana-verde-inclui-visitas-ecologicas-guiadas/</link><description>This year's Green Week again wants to bring the public closer to nature, providing a series of activities, such as maintenance of tree seedlings planted in previous editions, guided ecological visits and plant distribution
 
Scheduled for the period from March 15 to 23, the Green Week aims to convey the “love” by the afforestation and the “construction of a beautiful city” - for this, several activities are planned in various areas of the territory. According to the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI), several guided ecological visits and experience activities intended for the public will be made, “making known the green buildings, ecological resources and the current situation of Macao's conservation”.
In concrete, it is said that, together with citizens, it will be maintained the seedlings of tree planted in the past editions of the Green Week, allowing the public to witness the growth of seedlings and protect natural ecological resources. In addition, AMI will organize an ecological visit to Hengqin, with a view to providing more opportunities to approach the public to nature.
In this 44th edition of the Green Week, there will be a fair on Avenida da Praia, Taipa, on the 15th and 16th, from 14h00 to 18h00, and on the first day will be present some invited to the opening ceremony of the initiative. On site, the public will find thematic tents with information about tree species for forest recovery, protection and conservation of old trees and recognized value, and briefly present ornamental plants in parks and gardens, embalmed animals, insect hotel, among others.
There will be no shortage of game tents, craft workshops and guided ecological visits, with a view to providing information about afforestation and conservation.
During this week, more than 40 approach activities will be held to nature, intended for schools, associations and residents. The highlighted activity, the “march of the 44th edition of the Green Week of Macao and maintenance of the trees planted”, will be held on March 23, at Seac Pai Van Park. During this initiative, associations and citizens will deal with tree seedlings planted in previous editions of Green Week.
AMI will also organize six plant distribution sessions in various areas of Macao, under the theme “Green City”, and citizens may bring plants home. At the same time, the rates of the guide cable car and the children's quadricycles of the Hac Sá-terrain vehicle circuit will be exempt.
 
Iam will “clean” vines to protect hill from the guide
The forest area of ​​Colina da Guia Municipal Park has a very green surface, “but in fact it is covered by a large length of invasive vines,” says the institute for municipal affairs (AMI), announcing that he will start climbing cleaning work on March 18. Explaining that vines prevent trees from obtaining sufficient sunlight to perform the photosynthesis, and that they do not grow. Normally, “which eventually prevents the natural renewal of forest zones”, the body states that the cleaning action aims to “maintain forest health and enrich biodiversity”. The first phase consists of removing vines, withered branches and defective growth trees that can cause danger, "reducing the eventuality of trees -falling accidents, increasing trees growth space and improving their health." These actions will be carried out next to the 33 curve rail and the hill maintenance circuit of the guide, an area of ​​about 50 meters. Protection work, carried out in various phases, should be completed in mid-July. In this context, AMI has installed in February a scientific education zone to inform citizens about the protection of forest zones, “displaying some branches of vine” and presenting images, descriptions and objects about cleaning work and potential dangers to the ecological environment caused by the growth of this type of plants.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau promoted in the Middle East</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-promovido-medio-oriente/</link><description>More than two hundred representatives of the MSAR tourist industry moved to Riade and Dubai to participate in territory promotion actions, having discussed opportunities for cooperation in areas such as tourist products, marketing, conventions and exhibitions and business environment. STD also launched a tour guide for Muslims
 
For two days, the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), accompanied by representatives of the sector, moved to Riade, in Saudi Arabia, and Dubai, in the United Arab Emirates, to hold promotion seminars on the latest “Tourism + Conventions and Exhibitions of Macao and Contact Bags. The events served to promote Macao as an international tourist destination, to call more visitors from the Middle East to the city to experience the varied range of “Tourism +” offers, exploring the markets of international visitors.
In May, STD will also participate in the largest tourism fair in the Middle East, the “Arabian Travel Market” (ATM), with the aim of attracting high level and business tourists.
STD subdirector Cheng Wai Tong, in conjunction with representatives of the Institute for Commerce and Investment Promotion (IPIM), integrated tourism and leisure companies and the tourist industry participated in the promotion, intended to strengthen contacts with Middle East operators and promote bilateral cooperation.
During the disclosure actions, more than 200 representatives of the Macao tourist industry and the two locations participated in contact scholarships, which provided the discussion of opportunities for cooperation in the areas of tourism, marketing, conventions and businesses and business environment, among others, “establishing a solid base for Macau exploring visitors from Middle East”, could read in a DSAT statement.
In cooperation with a Singapore Halal Professional Tourism Consulting company, STD also programmed, during the campaign, the launch of a Muslim tour guide and the distribution to local operators of the English and Arabic version. The guide presents the aspects to take into account during the stay in Macau, gastronomic culture, itinerary recommendations, among other useful information for Muslim visitors.
STD states that it will soon translate the guide to Chinese, Malay and Indonesian, for distribution in other promotional activities to be done abroad in order to show that Macau continues to improve the Halal Offer facilities.
Following the promotion work launched in 2024, this visit to Riade and Dubai constituted, STD says, “an important measure to reinforce Macau's promotion in the Middle East”, allowing more tourist operators and visitors to “know the unique charm of Macao, promoting the diversified development of visitors' markets”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Suggested monthly “tax” of 13 thousand patacas for each TNR</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sugerido-imposto-mensal-de-13-mil-patacas-por-cada-tnr/</link><description>The “Macao People Power” association submitted a letter to the Chief Executive, in which he argues that the unemployment of residents and the problem of “freezing the wages of the local population” must be resolved by collecting a “non -resident worker tax (TNR)”. The idea is to “substantially increase the cost for companies to use TNR”.
Macao People Power, whose president is Lam Weng Ioi, points out that the value of this “tax” must be equivalent to the amount of difference between the median of the monthly income of residents and the universal minimum wage. This would mean a monthly tax of 13,428 Patacas charged to the company for each TNR hired, if calculated on the basis of the monthly minimum wage of 7,072 patacas and the median of 20,500 patacas, registered in the 4th quarter of 2024.
Thus, even if a TNR receives only the “minimum wage”, the total cost for the company would be higher than the average monthly remuneration of residents. This would “lead companies to pay off hiring residents,” the association holds, convinced that, in this way, “more than 10,000 jobs for residents” and the salaries of local workers could be “substantially high”.
In addition, it asserts that the increase in TNR hiring “could be mostly transferred to consumers,” adding that in Hong Kong and Nordic countries, “companies can still survive very well even under a high salaries” and “this does not affect the desire of tourists to travel to these places”.
Predicting a “short -term price climb” after the implementation of the “TNR tax”, the subscribers of the letter also propose an “vacant real estate”, so that it, together with the “TNR tax”, “brings tens of millions of millions of patacas to government coffers”. This amount, they argue, "should be used, in its entirety, in the benefits to the population," as a "pecuniary check of tens of thousands of patacas for each resident per year" and "increase in the pension for the elderly."
On the other hand, the letter includes a request for authorities to reinforce the fight against illegal workers.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Airport squeezes the siege of birds</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/aeroporto-aperta-cerco-as-aves/</link><description>Authorities have been reviewing the prevention and treatment plans of poultry -related cases in the area of ​​Macao Airport. Measures are also planned to expand the infrastructure
 
Macao government and airport held a Wildlife Management Council meeting to review the impact of wildlife on the airport area, and to evaluate the effectiveness of the execution of prevention and treatment measures. The board focuses on “management strategies in order to reduce the risks that wild animals pose to aircraft”.
“Since birds are more frequent wild species at airports, the committee's control and monitoring programs are mostly birds,” says a note from the Civil Aviation Authority (AACM), which participates in this board led by the Macao Airport Society (CAM), which also has specialists in preventatives caused by birds, and institute representatives for municipal affairs for municipal affairs. (AMI), Environmental Protection Services, Fire Department and Airlines.
During the meeting, CAM made a situation of bird attacks in 2024 and the implementation of prevention and control measures. In the statement, numbers are not made available, so this newspaper contacted CAM and AACM to realize how many cases occurred over the past year.
In addition, bird damage prevention experts shared the evaluation report for 2024, "elaborated after the identification of bird remains and the visit to the site, according to the bird attack report." The report includes bird attack prevention and control measures to ensure safety during the airport expansion period.
Over the years, AACM has exhorted Cam to apply the “Airport Wildlife Management Plan” to bird prevention and treatment work, “in order to achieve the double objective of protecting bird ecology and flying safety in a natural and human way”.
Regarding environmental planning, CAM and AMI periodically perform joint inspections to know the evolution of wild birds at the airport. CAM also periodically proceeds to the pruning of the pitch adjacent to the track, as well as disinfestation, eliminating the sources of the bird food chain. In this context, a seal on the edge of the artificial island of the track was built to prevent the invasion of wild animals.
In everyday operations, Cam highlights a specialized group to perform several patrols on the artificial island of the track, "increasing the frequency of inspections according to the starting time and grounding of flights." "The specialized team uses a remote sound device installed on the piloting vehicle and a pistol to ward off birds through shots, flashes and smoke, and record the types and amount of birds for analysis," says AACM.
It is recalled that the issue of birds was revived after an accident in late December, when the crash of a Jeju Air plane landing in Muan, South Korea, apparently caused by a bird attack, left 179 dead. With only two survivors of the 181 people on board, it was the deadliest air crash in South Korea history.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Requested new suicide prevention measures</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pedidas-novas-medidas-de-prevencao-suicidio/</link><description>Deputy Ho Ion Sang considers that the government should launch new suicide prevention measures and defends regular surveys to the population on mental health
 
For Ho Ion Sang, the fact that Macao has registered 90 suicide cases in 2024, the largest number in the last decade, reflects that “society has faced, after the end of the pandemic, challenges in the level of mental health, especially in the accumulation of problems such as slow economic recovery and the emotional and financial pressure of residents”.
In a written interpellation, the deputy stressed that, "in the face of the increase in the number of people who have committed suicide, Macau still needs to strengthen the social support network." In concrete, by increasing the channeling of resources, the reinforcement of awareness for mental health and the support of professional services, as well as the promotion of an inclusive social environment.
Specifically, Ho Ion Sang urged the government to analyze the causes, professions and age groups of the people who committed suicide, to define new prevention measures, according to the goals set in the “Healthy Macao Action Plan”. For the deputy, the “new measures” should include early identification and intervention in relation to people of high risk, support to family members of the victims, as well as the introduction of indicators to reduce the suicide rate.
At the same time, Ho Ion Sang expects authorities to regularly perform inquiries of mental health assessment to the entire local population, especially monitoring the mental health of the elderly, young people, among other groups of the population, in order to respond more effectively to challenges in public health and to arouse the attention of more people with the matter.
On the other hand, in the context of increasingly pronounced aging in the territory, “loneliness, depressive emotions, among other psychological problems, have become important factors that affect the quality of life of the elderly,” he warned, appealing to the government to reinforce depression between the elderly, the sensitization of mental health and the application of technological means in the mental health of the elderly so that it population group is more supported at the psychological level.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Uma Visit to Ireland opens perspectives of cooperation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/visita-da-um-a-irlanda-abre-perspectivas-de-cooperacao/</link><description>In order to expand the international cooperation network and reinforce academic partnerships with the universities of English -speaking countries, a delegation from the University of Macao (one) visited several higher education institutions in the Republic of Ireland.
At Trinity College Dublin, the entourage met with representatives of the School of Engineering, and both parties discussed students and teachers' exchange programs, double diploma and joint research projects. In the end, they came to a consensus to reinforce cooperation in areas such as energy engineering and the Internet of things to smart cities.
Visits also included Griffith College, where points of view on the reinforcement of collaboration in teaching and investigation were exchanged.
Both institutions have expressed interest in exploring cooperation in undergraduate programs in areas such as international and electronic relations, as well as promoting cooperation in material science, microelectronics and electrical engineering to develop innovative and competitive talents worldwide.
At the University College Dublin, collaboration between the two universities was addressed through the exchanges of students and teachers, as well as discussion projects of joint research and academic seminars. One took the opportunity to present the results of the investigation into the collaboration industry-academy in microelectronics in recent years.
Finally, on travel to Dublin City University, the conversation focused on cooperation in engineering, microelectronics, computer sciences and smart cities, establishing a consensus on the creation of double title programs.
In the balance of the trip, the vice-rector of UM, who led the group, considered that the visits strengthened the relationship with the Irish counterparts. On the other hand, he stressed, open “broad perspectives for future cooperation in teaching, investigation and talent cultivation”.
Rui Martins stressed that partnerships with top universities in Ireland “will further reinforce ties with institutions in the Anglophone world and will give a new momentum to the internationalization efforts of UM”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Game recipes rose again in February</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/receitas-jogo-voltaram-subir-em-fevereiro/</link><description>After downloading in homologous terms in January, the gross revenues of the game in Macao increased again in February, reaching the highest value after 20.79 billion of the Patacas noted in October last year. In February, the casinos earned 19.74 billion patacas, which represents a 6.8% increase compared to 18.49 billion accounted for in the same month of 2024 and corresponds to 77.8% of the level of the same period of 2019 (25.37 billion), according to data published on the electronic page of the inspection direction and coordination of games. In addition, the February result, which encompassed the last four days of Chinese New Year's holidays, reflects a monthly growth of 8.2%. In January, casinos had raised 18.25 billion patacas, thus registering an annual break of 5.6% and a monthly rise of 0.3%. In the first two months of this year, casinos revenues totaled approximately 38 billion patacas, reflecting a 0.5% residual increase compared to the same period of 2024. The amount calculated by the end of February represents a recovery of 75.5% compared to 50.31 billion in the first two months of 2019. It is recalled that in the budget for 2025, the government estimated that revenues could ascend to 240. billion throughout this year. In 2024, they reached almost 226.8 billion patacas, more 23.9% than in 2023 and 77.5% of 2019 level.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MNE Portuguese visits Macau and China later this month</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mne-portugues-visita-macau-china-final-deste-mes/</link><description>The Portuguese Minister of State and Foreign Affairs will visit Macau later this month, reported the TDM, citing a source from Paulo Rangel's office. The one who will be the highest representative of the Portuguese State to visit the territory since the pandemic should have a meeting with the head of the Executive of the MSAR, marking the first contact of a Portuguese minister with Sam Hou Fai. Rangel should also meet with the consul general, Alexandre Leitão, and members of the Portuguese community. The head of Portuguese diplomacy will also go to China, and should meet in Beijing with Chinese counterpart, Wang Yi, and participate in the Boao Forum in Haião. Later this year, the Portuguese MNE should return to Macau again, following the trip that Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa will make to mark June 10.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2351/</link><description>300 taxis licenses expire in June
About three hundred taxis (200 black vehicles and 100 radio taxis) will see the circulation license expired in June. Knowing that the government is studying a new competition for the assignment of new licenses, the director of the Taxi Driver Mutual Assistance Association suggested the holding of clarification sessions. Speaking to “or Mun Tin Toi”, Tony Kuok also said that the association is trying to solve some technical problems to improve a mobile taxi application, hoping that the system will be activated again in the first half of this year. Meanwhile, Ku Heng Cheong, a vowel of the Traffic Advisory Board, said the government expected the government to organize public consultations on private taxi service, a “global trend” if you want to study the subject.
 
Elderly found dead in the black sand
An elderly resident was found lifeless by the stairs of a building located in the black sand. The case happened on Saturday afternoon and, according to the Judiciary Police, the individual will have hanged himself. No suspicious injuries were found or indicate criminal act. Authorities have been appealing to citizens so that, in case of need, they call the “Life Hope of Caritas” line (2852 5222).
 
Hospitalized after being run over by bus
A 28 -year -old girl, a US passport holder, has been hit by a public bus. Was transported to the hospital in conscious state. The accident was registered near Macau airport. On the other hand, police found a drunk and injured man on Tribuna Street. According to the authorities, at the time of detection of the individual a public bus passed by the scene, however, it is not confirmed whether the injuries will have been caused by the collision of the vehicle. The Public Security Police body indicated that the individual did not use the treadmill to cross the road. The man was taken to the hospital in a stable state.
 
Center completed or filed 53 cases on infiltration
From September 1, 2023 to December 31, 2024, the Macao World Trade Center Arbitration Center received 87 arbitration requirements for infiltration in buildings, and 53 cases were completed or filed, of which the transaction between the parties that ended the arbitration process (HI) revealed or filed. In response to an interpellation of Ella Law, IH also noted that, among these cases, more than half took less than four months between the establishment and term, while the rest were generally completed within five to six months. The cases that requested more time were mainly due to the most complex situations that occurred in the citation and proof phases.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mystery surrounds the deaths of Gene Hackman and his wife</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/misterio-rodeia-mortes-de-gene-hackman-da-esposa/</link><description>Preliminary autopsy results did not determine the way Gene Hackman and his wife died at their home, but excluded the hypothesis of died from carbon monoxide poisoning. The state of the bodies found last Wednesday next to the corpse of one of the couple's dogs indicated that the deaths occurred at least several days earlier and there was no evidence of crime, but police described the circumstances of the case as "suspicions."
At a press conference on Friday, Santa Fe County Sheriff, Adan Mendoza, said the initial examination performed by the coroner did not reveal any sign of carbon monoxide, colorless and odorless gas produced by cooking appliances and other fuel-burning articles, which may be fatal when accumulated in poorly ventilated houses. Nor were gas leakage inside or around the house.
Mendoza also said that a 95 -year -old Hackman Pacemaker test revealed that he stopped operating on February 17, which means it could have died nine days earlier.
Hackman's body was found at an entrance, while his wife, Betsy Arakawa, 65, was in a bathroom, with a heater was near his head. The investigators said the heater was probably pulled down when it fell. There was also an open bottle of medicines and tablets scattered on a bench.
According to a document quoted by TMZ, the pianist was apparently dead "for some time" and the body is already decomposing, while Hackman was found completely dressed and with sunglasses near him. Two dogs were found alive and in good condition.
You will only know if tablets or other drugs were a determining factor when toxicological tests are completed in the coming weeks.
Philip Keen, a retired doctor at Maricopa County in Arizona, said it would be unlikely that a person who initially tested negative to carbon monoxide was later poisoned by him.
The investigators planned to comb the couple's phones and monthly schedules and contact family members, neighbors and closed condominium workers to discover the last time someone saw or spoke to Hackman or Arakawa. It was a “very reserved family,” said Mendoza, which makes it difficult to reconstruct a chronology.
The authorities who later searched the house recovered medicines that treat high blood pressure and chest pain, thyroid, tylenol medications and medical diagnostic test records, according to court records presented on Friday.
Detectives wrote in a search warrant statement that investigators thought that deaths were "sufficiently suspicious by nature to demand a detailed search and investigation."
An employee of the maintenance that appeared to do a routine work in the house could not enter and called a security official who saw two people on the floor, added the sheriff. The worker called 112 and told an operator that he didn't know if people were breathing.
Later, he and another worker told authorities that they rarely saw the homeowners and that the last contact with them had been about two weeks ago.
Hackman, 95, was named five times for the Oscars, has starred in dozens of films and is one of the most respected and honored artists in the industry. The actor won an Oscar for best actor with the movie "The French Connection" in 1972 and another as the best secondary actor in "Unforgiven" in 1993.
He also entered films such as “Bonnie and Clyde” and “Superman: The Movie” in the late 1970s and 1980s, where he became known for his interpretation as Lex Luthor. Hackman has played a variety of roles, appearing in action movies, thrillers and even a comic book in "Young Frankenstein."
Apart from the appearances in awards ceremonies, it was rarely seen at the Hollywood social circuit.
Francis Ford Coppola, who directed him in the movie "The Conversation" (1974, winner of the Golden Palm in Cannes) reacted to the news of death and called Hackman "a great artist, inspiring and magnificent in his work and complexity."
 
JTM with Lusa and International Agencies</description><pubDate>2025-03-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>