<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Therapies for children with six -week waiting time</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/terapias-para-criancas-tempo-de-espera-de-seis-semanas/</link><description>Although the pediatric joint evaluation center has a waiting time of about three weeks, it is in the application of therapies - speech and occupational - that this time increases. According to the director of health services, you may need to wait up to six weeks for intervention in these areas. Alvis Lo also revealed that artificial intelligence in speech therapy has helped almost 1,900 children
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The waiting time at the Pediatric Joint Evaluation Center is about three weeks, said the Director of Health Services (SSM), taking into account data until the end of the last year. According to Alvis Lo, after evaluation, a waiting mechanism for classification is adopted to carry out occupational therapy and speech therapy for children with needs. "Very urgent cases do not need to wait," he said, in response to Chest Sai Wang written interpellation.
However, in the second phase, that is, of the application of therapies, the time that children have to wait increases. In both urgent and common cases, “waiting time for occupational therapy is 3 to 6 weeks”, while “for speech therapy is 5 to 6 weeks, which is significantly shorter than waiting time between 12 and 18 months before the center's creation,” said Alvis Lo.
"The SSM have been striving to further reduce the waiting time for medical treatment, through the extension of opening hours, and the acquisition of early intervention services to non-profit institutions," he said. Also to help, the cloud platform was introduced for the training of Cognitive Rehabilitation of Artificial Intelligence Language (AI) as “effective complement” of speech therapy services. The idea is that children can receive home training, in the company of their parents, in order to increase their linguistic abilities.
The system is already being used in various early intervention institutions for children of SSM, the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) and the Institute of Social Action (IAS), and can offer 200 vacancies to professionals and 3,000 for child rehabilitation treatment. "Until December 2024, there was a number of 1,878 children, and the system was used by more than 44,000 users," he said.
According to the SSM director, the system currently has "enough vacancies" to provide services to children. Alvis Lo also noted that the government has also cooperated with early treatment institutions in the organization of training courses for parents and the development of indirect therapy, and therapists are responsible for training parents to perform the rehabilitation training of children at home, "further increasing the effectiveness of early treatment."
According to the data, between July 2019 and December 2024, 926 lectures and workshops were organized, with 9,099 in charge of education received training in indirect therapy.
 
Support for children under the age of three will have 500 vacancies
Understanding that early childhood intervention “is a prolonged and continuous process of rehabilitation”, Alvis Lo explained that the SSM provide evaluation and diagnosis, and then develop a medical treatment program of eight sessions. Upon completion, for children with later treatment needs, treatment and rehabilitation training will be organized by the DSEDJ or IAS in subsidized early intervention institutions, until their improvements are notorious.
Between 2021 and 2024, IAS promoted the development of services for children with developmental disorders under the age of three, helping to create or change equipment providing early intervention services. During this period, he added more than 200 service vacancies. "In 2025, another equipment of this kind will be created with 44 service vacancies, which should increase the total number of service vacancies to about 500," said Alvis Lo.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mass of tribute to Francis took hundreds of faithful to the Cathedral</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/missa-de-homenagem-francisco-levou-centenas-de-fieis-a-se-catedral/</link><description>Several hundreds of the faithful participated yesterday at the Mass celebrated by the soul of Pope Francis, in the See. The bishop of Macau, D. Stephen Lee, presided over the act and, in his homily, historized the pontificate of the Holy Father, highlighting his simplicity

























Victor Rebelo
 
The Cathedral of Macao registered one of the biggest floods by receiving several hundred faithful who participated, at the beginning of last night, at the Mass of Requiem for the death of Pope Francis. There were many who responded to the appeal of the Diocese of Macao so that the Catholics honor the Supreme Pontiff, died on April 21, at the age of 88, but not all fit inside the church.
The religious act, interspersed with Portuguese and Chinese languages, was chaired by Bishop D. Stephen Lee, on an altar with about five dozen priests and acolytes.
Among the faithful, in a majority of Chinese ethnicity, that about half an hour from the beginning of the Mass was completely filled the church, highlighting the conservatives Alexandre Leitão (Portugal) and Eduardo Galiano (Angola) and some directors of services of the RaEM, as well as many sisters of the congregations represented in Macao.
In his homily, D. Stephen Lee recalled the Pope's story and reinforced the acceptance that the Supreme Pontiff has always awakened with the Christian community, noting that his followers were more than 10 million.
During yesterday, between 9 am and 6 pm, many dozen faithful entered the church to devote a few minutes of prayer by Pope Francis and sign a book of presence inside the See, along with a branch of flowers and the Holy Father's photography.
Then he said his prayer, Paula Carion told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that Francis was the third Pope in her life and the one who led her to be closer to the church. "In the first 30 years of my life, I did not dedicate myself much to religion and church, but for certain reasons it was in his pontificate that I returned to Mass again and I take my son to church," he said.
Macaense stressed that Francis was "a very kind person, with their feet on the ground, was concerned with the poor and the most needy," adding that "this is the message that Catholics should follow."
As for the next Pope, he stressed that "everything is delivered into God's hands and the decision of the cardinals that will be in the conclave to vote."
 
In a world of hatred value to hope
In turn, Carmen Sousa considered that "Pope Francis' pontificate was marked by several inspiring words and gestures," highlighting the theme of the Jubilee of 2025 called by him, "which is hope, a value, and virtue so necessary in a world often marked by indifference, distrust, hatred and discouragement." A hope, he reinforces, "founded on the certainty of God's mercy that he never tires of forgiving who sincerely calls for divine forgiveness, which is another teaching quite repeated by the magisterium of Pope Francis."
In reference to courage always given, especially to young people, “to live faith with joy and spread it”, Carmen Sousa points, as relevant aspects, the care that the Pope had for the environment, “our Common House”.
Francisco was also concerned with “social justice and the defense of the dignity of the human person, especially those found in situations of greater vulnerability, such as those still in the womb, the elderly, the poor, the refugees, the migrants and those who suffer from war,” he emphasizes.
In search of peace, "he endeavored a lot in the interreligious dialogue and the fraternity among all," reinforces the catechist, also highlighting "his efforts to reform the church, so that it can be more missionary, simpler and closer to the people, listening and walking together with all towards God."
For Carmen Sousa, these were remarkable points, some of them covered in last Sunday's catechesis.
"With faith and gratitude, I thank God for the positive contributions of this pontificate and pray for the eternal rest of Pope Francis, hoping that each of us can be a reflection of God's mercy in our communities," he concluded.
 
Francisco's concern with poor and disadvantaged
Oscar Norway, for his side, says Francis was a Pope of all. "Affectionate, charismatic, understandable, with great concern for the poor, the disadvantaged, the marginalized and those who suffer from war, mistreatment and all that was inhuman," he says.
For the Catholic, the High Pontiff, "unlike others, has chosen a life of simplicity rather than the greatness, and undoubtedly left an indelible mark in the church and the world, which will hardly be forgotten."
Oscar Norway said he was "always more linked to this Pope than his predecessors," so "the news of his death filled my heart and the world of great sadness." "We will miss you."
Remat by stating that he never had the opportunity to see the Holy Father live, despite visiting the Vatican. "At that time the Pope unfortunately did not appear in St. Peter's Square due to health problems."
José Basto da Silva also gave his testimony, noting that "at a time when many feel crushed and discouraged by violence and uncertainty in this world, Pope Francis' message - of hope, mercy, and compassion - was a true balm to the soul." Macaense points out that the high pontiff "encouraged us to look beyond the surface divisions between good and evil, to recognize our shared humanity and to work together for a fairer and more inclusive world."
Feeling someone who seeks to live faith in an authentic way, the believer is "deeply" grateful for the example of service to the Pope's neighbor, who argues that he was "humble and without prejudice, who recalls us that faith is not just about words and intentions, but to live the gospel through action, charity and forgiveness."</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Service for the elderly alone should advance in the 3rd quarter</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/servico-para-idosos-sozinhos-deve-avancar-3o-trimestre/</link><description>The start of the proximity service project for the elderly for the elderly is being pointed to the 3rd quarter of this year. The Institute of Social Action says it is working intensively on the project
 
The Institute of Social Action (IAS) is developing, “intensively”, the pilot project of proximity services intended for the elderly living alone, assured the president of the body, Hon Wai. As indicated, the implementation is scheduled for the 3rd quarter of this year.
In response to an interpellation of Deputy Zheng Anting, it is said that the government “gives attention to the needs of the elderly”, paying, through interdepportional cooperation, “adequate services” and helping to create a community support network. With this pilot project, IAS wants to “reinforce attention” to the “hidden elderly”.
With the creation of a proximity team in Macao and another on the islands, Hon Wai expects to identify, “through direct contacts, hidden and high-risk elderly in the community, assess their living conditions, help them create a support network and provide them with service supports and referrals as needed”.
In response to the deputy, and as regards the medical services intended for the elderly, the president of IAS states that health services “have continued the principle of effective treatment in which prevention is privileged, providing them with comprehensive and perfected medical services, starting with the chain of prevention, treatment and rehabilitation services”.
"In recent years, SSM have continuously expanded medical support in the elderly homes, providing medical services for the proximity of specialty or general medicine to the elderly with reduced mobility," he adds. This team consists of health professionals from various areas, including doctors, nurses and pharmacists.
According to Hon Wai, currently, proximity medical services include all government -subsidized homes and two rehabilitation centers, as well as residence for the elderly. In the future, through the “medical cooperation model” model, the services will be extended to other homes of non-subsidized elderly, he said.
In addition, SSM, in collaboration with non -profit medical institutions, provide home care to patients with reduced mobility.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hotel sector foresees 70% occupation in the golden week</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sector-hoteleiro-preve-ocupacao-de-70-na-semana-dourada/</link><description>Between May 1st and 5th, local hotel establishments will be able to see 70% of the busy rooms, estimated the president of the Macao Hotel Association, further anticipating that room prices will fall about 20% compared to those checked in last year's golden week
 
Macao hotels will be able to record an occupancy rate of 70% in the two -day golden week, which will start tomorrow, predicted Wong Suk Yan, president of the Macao Hotel Association. As pointed out, the peak of occupation in local hotel establishments should be on May 2 and 3.
Regarding prices, the associative leader noted that, after the Chinese New Year, they have fallen, so he believes that, compared to last year's same year, there will be a break of about 20%.
Generally speaking, according to the Chinese language press, the official described that, looking at “the tourist market to constantly improve,” the Macao Hospitality sector is “very confident” in the future.
It also found that, currently, tourists remain, on average, about 1.3 days in the territory, while having diminished tourists who stay overnight in Macao. In this sense, the president of the Hotel Association argued that the development of the night economy and the promotion of community tours should constitute important guidelines for the development of the tourist sector.
However, Wong Suk Yan lamented that concerts and sports events “cannot sufficiently stimulate the community economy,” as they usually take place in game operators establishments. By way of example, the official called for more events and festivities in the North and Central Zone, as these parts of the city welcome many sights classified as a world heritage. In addition, it expects the national games, which will be held in Macao in November, will be used for the extension of sports activities for the community neighborhoods.
On the other hand, the associative leader stressed that Macao tourist operators and hotels have been releasing more promotional activities such as coupons and discount packages. In addition, they recently began cooperating with airlines to give discounts on passport holders who are in hotels located in community neighborhoods.
Wong Suk Yan also indicated that the sector intends to launch more services and products for tourists, while reinforcing the campaign with international markets, especially South Korea and Southeast Asia countries, such as Malaysia, Singapore and Thailand.
 
Circulation on the free delta bridge on holidays
The authorities responsible for the operations of the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge announced that they will exempt the circulation rate during the five days of holidays with up to seven places, being implemented from 0h00 from 1 May to midnight on the 5th. Anticipating a significant increase in the transionic movement between Hong Kong, Macau and Zhuhai, the bridge authorities appealed to travel in different periods. Specifically, they predicted the peak of the flow of vehicles from Hong Kong to Zhuhai and Macau on May 1 and 3 from 9h00 to 16h00. As for the cars that will circulate from Zhuhai to Hong Kong, they believe the flow will be higher on 4 and 5 from 15h00 to midnight.
 
RECOMMENDED FOUR HENGQIN-MACAU TURNS
The Directorate of Administrative Affairs Services in the Deepened Cooperation Zone has launched “Four Recommended Tour Itineraries” for the Golden Week of May. According to the body, an itinerary is intended for family trips, integrating various points of interest, such as the Chimelong theme park, the Giant Panda Pavilion in Seac Pai Van and the Lai Chi Vun Naval Shipyards. Another, with emphasis on gastronomy, involves activities in a commercial area of ​​Hengqin, San Ma Lo and Rua do Cunha. In addition, a “cultural and artistic” script was also recommended with visits to the TianmuQintai cultural complex in Hengqin and the digital art exhibition of the ancient Shu civilization, patent on MGM Macau, as well as a script for “exploring the outdoor nature”, which allows you to visit “Sumlodol Camping Town”, the Hengqin flower corridor, among other points.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Spain and Portugal recover after a long "blackout"</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/espanha-portugal-recuperam-apos-longo-apagao/</link><description>A group of people awaits the restoration of light in the Liberdade neighborhood, due to the blackout that affects Portugal from North to South and other European countries in Lisbon, April 28, 2025. The government has created a working group to accompany the blackout that affects Portugal from North to South and other European countries and points out that the problem “originated” outside Portugal. António Pedro Santos/Lusa



The supply of electricity was restored yesterday almost completely in Spain and Portugal, allowing a progressive return to normal, after a total "blackout" that began at 11:30 on Monday (Portuguese time) and lasted between 10 and 20 hours. Closed airports, congestion in transport and traffic in large cities, lack of fuels, disconnecting mobile communications and disturbances in commerce and industry were some of the consequences of the "blackout", which the authorities described as "absolutely exceptional".
“After an intense night, it was possible to restore 99.95% of energy demand,” wrote in the morning on the social network X the Spanish Prime Minister, Pedro Sánchez, thanking the “responsibility and civilian” of the population during the unprecedented power cut. In Portugal, REN - National Energy Nets also ensured that the electricity grid was “perfectly stabilized” and that its 6.4 million customers had service.
In Spain, the return of electricity allowed the resumption of rail traffic on several important paths, including Madrid-Barcelona and Madrid-Seville, according to National Renfe Company. However, circulation remained suspended in other important lines, as the authorities prioritized the restart of travel in the suburban axes.
In Portugal, the airport operation was normally taking place at the time of the closing of this edition, although some impacts related to the canceled or delayed flights on Monday, due to blackout, and high influx for luggage delivery, Ana said. The normal activity of health facilities was also resumed and non-urgent situations that had to be postponed on Monday are being rescheduled for the coming days, the National Health Service (NHS) executive direction has been resumed.
The Portuguese government will create an independent technical committee and request a European audit to evaluate the electric systems of countries affected by the "blackout," the prime minister said. "We will not save efforts on the clarifications in the face of a serious problem that had no origin in Portugal," said Luís Montenegro.
The Spanish Prime Minister said there is still no explanation for the blackout in the Iberian Peninsula and no hypothesis is discarded, after the company that manages the country's electricity grid rejecting the possibility of cyberatoque. "The Government of Spain will reach the back of this matter" and, in the face of conclusions, will make renovations and adopt the necessary measures "so that it does not happen again," as well as "demanding all the responsibilities pertinent to private operators," Pedro Sánchez said at a press conference in Madrid.
Sánchez alerted again to the misinformation that is circulating in relation to the "blackout" and warned of the "huge complexity of the electric system", requiring time to make a "light and accurate diagnosis and diagnosis".
The Portuguese carrier denied having issued a shared statement with the assigned networks that posted a “rare atmospheric phenomenon” as the cause of the interruption. On Monday, “no unusual meteorological or atmospheric phenomenon was detected in Spain,” said the Spanish weather agency.
 
JTM with Lusa and International Agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Standards for day hospitals require “flexibility”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/normas-para-hospitais-de-dia-requerem-flexibilidade/</link><description>Health services held sessions on the “legal regime for the exercise of activity of private institutions providing health care”, having heard opinions of about 80 representatives of various sectors. Several participants advocated “flexibility” in the elaboration of norms and a “rigorous” supervision of day hospitals
 
Health Services (SSM) have already held sessions to collect opinions regarding the “legal regime for the exercise of activity of private health care institutions”, whose public consultation takes place until May 16th. The sessions had about 80 representatives of residents and health, industry, commerce and tourism sectors.
According to the body, several participants have considered that the Government of MSAR can support the health sector to develop more diverse medical services. However, they underlined, "must have some flexibility in the elaboration of the rules."
Some participants even agreed with the “proper widening of medical advertising content” and the space for dissemination of the sector, so that “users receive correct medical information”.
According to the same note, there were also participants who considered that the operation of day hospitals should be “strictly supervised” in order to protect health and public safety.
Health services representatives have responded that the government will consider the suggestions of the various sectors and "balance the needs of all stakeholders." Generally speaking, participants in the consultation sessions agreed that the review of the law “contributes to the development of the sector and guarantees the health of residents”, can be read in the statement.
SSM subdirector and substitute subdirect, Cheang Seng and Loi I Leng, respectively, pointed out that the government intends to create “a new type of license from the hospital between the hospital and the clinic”, further widening the development space of the Macao medical market. At the same time, Macao authorities intend to "provide residents and tourists with diverse options, with high quality of medical services."</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DSAL INTENDES NEW ELECTRONIC TRADE COURSES</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dsal-introduz-novos-cursos-de-comercio-electronico/</link><description>_Cuva



Services for labor affairs will launch 800 participation vacancies in the “Plan to increase digital skills and certification”. In addition, new training courses and certification exams on the application of artificial intelligence will be introduced
 
Given the active enrollment in the electronic trade courses and the tendency to develop artificial intelligence IA), the direction of services for labor affairs (DSAL) will launch about 800 vacancies in the “plan for increasing digital skills and certification”.
With the change of the consumer model, it is developing more and more online. Electronic trade has thus become “an important business growth point for small and medium enterprises,” according to DSal.
The body promoted several practical electronic trade courses, which encompasses the creation and management of online store operations, online marketing (video production, sales transmission), data analysis, and other complete training chains on techniques in this area.
The launch of courses will continue this year and Dsal will broadcast live in electronic trade and production of short videos in product marketing, research and study of the tourist market and analysis techniques.
In addition to image design courses, short video production at Douyin and text writing at XiaoHongShu, as well as Certifications for Instructor and Alibaba Cloud-ACA and Huawei (HCIA-AI) engineers, DSSA will promote other electrical trade operation actions, including the application of commercial data (member analysis) and certification for electrical trade (level specialists (level analysis) intermediate).
At the same time, the body says, several new courses will be made available, including certification for seller on the internet, video and marketing producer and practical training on filming and promotional video assembly of companies, being especially suitable for retail sales and marketing operators for appreciation for their appreciation.
Since the launch of the “Plan to increase digital skills and certification” in the year 2024, more than 40 courses have been held, bringing together more than 820 graduates, of which more 230 have obtained professional certification.
Interested parties can get more information about the plan, accessing the thematic page or calling the DSSA Vocational Training Center.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>International guests rose 8% by March</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/hospedes-internacionais-subiram-8-ate-marco/</link><description>Although the total number of guests went down 5.4%, MSAR hotel units recorded an 8.1% increase in international customers during the first quarter of this year, official statistics indicate official statistics
 
Between January and March, MSAR hotel establishments hosted 3.57 million individuals, representing an annual decline of 5.4%, reveals data from the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). In the case of guests from the interior of China (2.72 million), the break reached 3.4%.
In contrast, the number of international guests (292,000) grew 8.1%, in annual terms, with DSEC highlighting South Korea (92 thousand), Japan (26 thousand), Malaysia (22 thousand) and Indonesia (17,000) markets, which increased 16.1%, 9.8%, 14.7%and 31.2%, respectively. On the other hand, guests from Thailand (17 thousand), India (13 thousand) and the US (13,000) fell 9.2%, 5%and 0.9%, respectively.
At the end of the first quarter of this year, the 147 hotel establishments providing public accommodation services (six more than in the same period of 2024), available a total of about 44,000 rooms of guests (-5.8%). According to official data, the average occupancy rate of guest rooms rose 5.2 points to 90.1%between January and March, in annual terms, having been higher in five -star units (93.2%), than in four -star developments (84.5%) and three stars (86.6%).
The average period of permanence of guests remained in 1.7 nights during the quarter under analysis.
In March, the average occupancy rate was below the quarter average, settling at 88.8%, plus 5.1 percentage points. Last month, hotel establishments hosted 1,203,000 individuals, 2.7% less than March 2024.
On the other hand, in the first three months of 2025, the number of entries from visitors who arrived at excursions to Macau grew 9.1% to about 550,000. Visitors in excursions from the interior of China (477 thousand) and international markets (60,000) increased 6.3% and 19.8%, respectively. South Korea's tour rose 43.5% to 33,000.
Macao residents who purchased travel agencies for travel abroad rose 8.7% to 124,000 in the first quarter.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Boss wants Macau and Zhongshan working as “hands”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-quer-macau-zhongshan-trabalhar-de-maos-dadas/</link><description>The chief executive said in Zhongshan that he wants Macau and that city to work with "hands" to promote bilateral cooperation with "more fruitful" results
 
A delegation from Macao, led by Sam Hou Fai, kept meetings with leaders of cities in the Great Bay. In Zhongshan, the chief executive said he hoped that, based on the good cooperation, the two regions "continue to work hand in hand" in order to promote bilateral cooperation with "even more fruitful" results.
At the meeting with the Zhongshan Municipal Committee Secretary of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP), Guo Wenhai, Sam Hou Fai said that Macau and Zhongshan have a "deep" connection in historical terms, with frequent contact exchanges. On the other hand, he stressed that the two cities have been rapidly developed, presenting “good trends of progress”, both social and economic, “with potential cooperation in various areas”.
In an official note, the boss assured that, in the future, the Government of MSar will advance “stable” with bilateral cooperation projects and will support Macao companies so that they can explore business opportunities in the interior of China, in various domains, such as economy and commerce, biomedicine, cultural tourism, cutting -edge technology and higher education.
During the visits made, the Macao entourage, which also joined, among others, the secretary for transport and public works, Raymond Tam, met the biomedical industry in Zhongshan, where he suggested that the two cities study the possibility of creating a cooperation base, "that will be demonstrated for the production of drugs from Macau in Guangdong."
Sam Hou Fai then went to Jiangmen, where he met with the secretary of the Municipal Committee of the CCP, Chen Anming, and the municipal leader, Wu Xiaohui.
Noting that this city of the continent is well known for human resources and the historical cultural wealth of Chinese overseas, it has expressed that both parties can create high quality tourist products in the area of ​​world cultural heritage characterized by “various sights on a trip”, promoting a common advance of the sector of both cities.
Aludling, on the other hand, that Jiangmen has rich land resources and a good transport network that connects abroad in the Great Bay area, the maximum ruler of the MSAR intends to “grasp the opportunities generated by the development of the great bay”, and create “a new chapter of highly qualified development for both cities”.
The Chief Executive also recalled that the Daguang Bay Economic Zone, which is located in the southern Jiangmen city, is a point of connection between Hong Kong, Zhuhai and Macau, and represents a great perspective for the future “in a reinforcement of sectoral coordination to install an important cooperative platform for the great bay”. The delegation also visited a food company in Jiangmen with Macao investment.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Discussed tax area in the context of “a track, a route”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/discutida-area-fiscal-ambito-de-uma-faixa-uma-rota/</link><description>Several experts and senior tax officials met in Beijing to discuss the future work of the cooperation mechanism on tax administration of the initiative “a track, a route”
 
At the Fiscal Academy, the meetings of the Council of Cooperation Mechanism on Tax Administration, under the initiative “a track, a route” were held at the Fiscal Academy. The meetings were attended by specialists from international organizations and high tax officials from more than 20 countries and regions.
According to a statement from the Directorate of Finance Services, discussions focused on topics such as the practice of multilateralism, the deepening of international tax cooperation, the improvement of the service of global economic governance and the promotion of economic globalization.
During the two days, participants exchanged ideas about innovative work to be performed over the next five years, regarding the cooperation mechanism on tax administration. According to a statement, high employees from China, Tajiquistan, Indonesia, Cameroon and the United Arab Emirates shared work experiences on the reinforcement of tax administration and optimizing tax services.
China's Tax Administration Commissioner has submitted three proposals to "better promote the creation of the cooperation mechanism on Tax Administration" and "deepen, multilateralism and boost economic globalization."
Hu Jinglin defended the development of “higher quality reciprocal benefits and gains”, the promotion of “constructions with a higher capacity level” and a “intellectual modal center” for the fiscal administration -promoting alliance, as well as the exploitation of “higher level innovative practices”.
In the context of digital transformation, for the Commissioner, it is necessary to develop “a tax administration system and chain exploration tax services and products”, so as to “enrich multilateral cooperation” in international tax matters and boost “more intense” economic globalization.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Art Museum displays “charm” of Shiwan ceramics</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/museu-de-arte-exibe-encanto-da-ceramica-de-shiwan/</link><description>The Macau Museum of Art hosts until October the exhibition “Preciosities of Ovens: Shiwan Ceramic Collection”, which promotes Lingnan's local culture



















The exhibition “Preciosities of Ovens” presents at the Macao Art Museum (MAM) 123 pieces and sets of the Shiwan ceramic collection. The four themes, “Shiwan's ceramic ridges”, “Shiwan Ceramics”, “Images of Flora and Fauna” and “Shiwan stickers”, map the “Ceramic of Shiwan ceramics from a regional art to an art in international dialogue,” said the Cultural Institute (IC).
Shiwan's ridge is an architectural decoration with local characteristics in the Lingnan region, very present in Macao temples, such as the Kun Iam Tong Temple or the Bazaar Temple. Since its in the middle of the Ming Dynasty, this type of ceramics have combined practices of the central plains with Lingnan's local culture, becoming known for the "richness and chromatic variety of their glazes and unique techniques."
The play “ridge” demonstrates “the hope of the people of Lingnan in a better life” and marks the first year of the reign of Guangxu in 1875, and the identification of the commercial establishment of flower vessels “made in the Wu Qiyu workshop”. The large -scale ceramic figures, such as “Hua Tuo” and “Lu Yu”, witness the “deep dialogue between Chinese and Western aesthetics, demonstrating“ the unique charm of popular handicrafts, ”says the IC statement.
In articulation with the promotion of the exhibition, a multimedia device will be installed in the museum, to provide by phase the images of Shiwan ridge in the Temple of Bazaar and show the details of the collection, with an area of ​​interaction between parents and children and the distribution of limited edition postcards.
The former collection of pieces by the Portuguese synologist Manuel da Silva Mendes, antiquities of Ming and Qing Dynasties, as well as Qing dynasty with floral motives, fruits, poultry and symbolic animals and the innovative works of Pan Yushu and Chen Weiyan are others of the highlights of the exhibition.
From May, MAM will offer guided tours in Cantonense during Saturdays, Sundays and public holidays. Ceramic workshops, concerts, thematic lectures and artistic visits to parents and children will also be held, among other activities.
The exhibition will be patent on the fourth floor of MAM until October 7th. MAM is open between Tuesday and Sunday, including holidays, between 10:00 and 19:00 and with free admission.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Treasure Box” awakens “genes of civilization”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/treasure-box-desperta-genes-da-civilizacao/</link><description>The exhibition “Brilliant Stars: Immersive Digital Art Exhibition of the Ancient Shu Civilization” will be evident in MGM Macau's “Treasure Box” until June. Through digital art and interactive technology, the new MGM space has cultural relics of a civilization with thousands of years
 
The exhibition “Brilliant Stars: Immersive Digital Art Exhibition of the Ancient Shu Civilization” is evident in the new MGM Macau multifunctional space, “Treasure Box”, until June 24, with free admission. Co-organized by the Macau Foundation (FM), Executive Committee of the Deepened Cooperation Zone and China Poly Group, the project received the support of several cultural and museum institutions, such as the Cultural Institute, the Jinsha Site Museum and the Sanxingdi Museum.
The initiative integrates digital art, interactive technology and archaeological narrative. The physical exhibition arrived in Macau after being shown in Hengqin, attracting more than 300 thousand visitors.
Exposure uses the use of advanced technology such as ultra-high images definition, immersive interaction, and digital decoding macro “to arouse dormant civilizations and reconnect fragmented patterns”. According to FM, it is not just a display, but "a contemporary awakening for the genes of civilization."
The show focuses on the Sanxingdui and Jinsha culture and begins in the “galaxy tunnel”, with a demonstration of the old shu astrological patterns. The first unit, “Sparkling Stars: 12K Digital Art Movie”, uses “pure visual art” to show the ecology, natural scenes of life and the Sanxingdui and Jinsha belief system.
In the unit “Awakening National Treasures”, visitors can find “sleeping” cultural relics and “feel the shock of the reappearance of civilization” through interactive technology.
The unit “Macro 12K Vision of National Treasures” presents the “detailed beauty” of cultural relics, such as bronze masks and gold masks, using ultra-high definition images. Finally, in the “Cultural and Creative Space, Gallery of Patterns”, visitors will be able to buy cultural and creative products and immersive memories.
At the inauguration ceremony, Wu Zhiliang, president of the FM Board of Directors, said that the ancient Shu civilization has a story of thousands of years, which makes it an indispensable and magnificent chapter in the diverse and unified structure of Chinese civilization. ” The exhibition is a tribute to Shu's ancestors and a contemporary response to the question why China? ”, The statement says.
The deputy director of the Executive Committee of the Deepened Cooperation Zone, Su Kun, said Hengqin and Macao have “innovative” the “two -place exhibition” model “an exposure”, to make “Macau + Hengqin” in a “new model of practical enrichment” of the “a country, two systems”, marking a new level in promoting and building the great bay.
In turn, Liu Juncai, China Poly Group's deputy director, highlighted the fact that Macau is "a historic and cultural city where Chinese and Western cultures meet." From its perspective, the exhibition is another attempt by the group to “develop an innovative culture based on the innovative genes of China's excellent traditional culture”.
The same statement states that Poly Group will be more proactive in promoting the Integration of the Great Bay through joint efforts and the presentation of cultural events, so that “various coexist cultures and thrive”. The group will also reinforce the exploitation in the development of industries, infrastructure and civil services in Hengqin and Macao, introducing a new momentum in promoting the diversification of the MSAR economy.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong visitors with free trips to the</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/visitantes-em-hong-kong-viagens-gratis-para-raem/</link><description>International visitors traveling to Hong Kong will again have free bus and boat tickets to visit Macau. The promotion, which will be launched tomorrow, extends until the last day of this year, with tourism services intending to attract more foreign visitors to the territory. Ticket reservation can be made in advance on the operators' websites. Last year, the promotion boosted the coming of 310,000 international visitors to
 
From tomorrow, international Hong Kong visitors have free trips to come to Macau, specifically on bus and boat, announced yesterday the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), which returns to cooperate with transport operators. The promotion “Free Direct and Boat Bus Tickets”, intended for visitors from outside the Greater China, aims to “widen the number of international visitors who extend the trip to Macao”.
Specifically, the promotion is in force between May 1st and December 31 this year. STD is collaborating with passenger transport services at Hong Kong International Airport (Macau), Turbojet and Cotai Water Jet, providing free tickets. Elegable visitors immediately receive the bus or boat tickets to travel from Hong Kong to Macau after filling in the specified formalities.
According to STD, the ticket reserve can be made in advance on the official page of transport services operators. As for the boats, the reserve can be made showing the valid foreign travel document and the boarding card, the electronic ticket or the transport receipt, proof of arrival at Hong Kong seven days prior to Macao.
During the promotion period, visitors will be entitled, unlimited, to the benefit of “free and free bus tickets”, but these discounts are subject to the terms and rules of service exploiting entities and the availability of places. “Due to the limit in the number of offers, tickets are processed in order of arrival,” aims at the body led by Helena de Senna Fernandes.
It is also said that, after arriving at Hong Kong International Airport, just show the valid travel document from abroad and the boarding card, within the restricted zone, to get the free ticket and take the direct bus to Macao, via Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge, at the Skypier Transfers Terminal from the neighboring region.
The promotion, already released earlier, boosted last year the coming of 310,000 international visitors to the territory, the STD said in a statement. Recalling that in 2023 he launched special offers of bus and boat tickets and that between February and December last year, launched for the first time the promotion of free direct and boat ticket tickets for international visitors who arrive in Hong Kong, the body was pleased with the impact brought.
"The results were satisfactory, with more than 310,000 visitors visiting Macau and consuming through the promotional project in 2024 lasting 11 months," read the press release. The Government of MSAR, it is recalled, has been struggling to attract foreign visitors, since the interior market of China is the one that has the highest weight. The idea is to diversify the sources of tourists.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Africans dream of a continent Pope</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/africanos-sonham-um-papa-continente/</link><description>Congolese Cardinal Fridolin Ambongo Besungu Speaks During A Mass in Commemoration of the Late Pope Francis at the Notre Dame Du Congo Cathedral in Kinshasa on April 21, 2025. Pope Francis, An Energetic Reformer Who Inspired Widespread Devotion from Catholics But Riled TRADITIONALISTS, DIED ON APRIL 21, 2025 AGED 88 (Photo by Hardy Bope / AFP) (Photo by Hardy Bope / AFP via Getty Images)



Ghanaian cardinal Peter Turkson said in 2010 that he was not prepared to become Pope and that perhaps the Catholic Church was not ready either. However, more than 15 years later, this influential African religious appears as one of the favorites of the next conclave.
"I wouldn't like to be the first black pope. I think it would be difficult," he said at the time, but after Francisco's death, the name of this African cardinal is quoted by many analysts.
Turkson is not the only possible African candidate at the conclave for the election of Francisco's successor, nor would it be the first pontiff of this continent. Pope Vítor, who led the church between 189 and 199 AD, was from North Africa.
But as the percentage of African faithful increases compared to an increasingly secular Europe, the debate is taken up on whether the church is prepared for a first black porridge.
"It is increasing the feeling that if the Pope must be an international authority, and so he has to proceed from the global church," says Miles Pattenden, historian of Catholicism.
Turkson was born in a humble family of 10 children and was Ghana's first cleric to become Cardinal in 2003.
In 2008, he played as a mediator on a peacekeeper after disputed elections that threatened to trigger a scenario of violence. He also performed high -ranking duties in the Vatican bureaucracy and recently showed a more moderate tone on the LGBTQia+rights, criticizing Ghanaian politicians who stated that same -sex relations were not native to Africa.
In 2023, the British BBC network argued that "LGBTQia+ people should not be criminalized because they have not committed any crime."
This may be more acceptable to moderate sectors than the guinean rhetoric Robert Sarah, a traditionalist cardinal praised by conservatives and who compared abortion, “Islamic fanaticism” and homosexuality with Nazi ideology.
Another cardinal on the list, Fridolin Ambongo, from the Democratic Republic of Congo, led the campaign against the blessing to same -sex couples in Africa after Francis has exhorted the church to advance on the subject.
Despite its most moderate rhetoric, the Argentine pontiff maintained many conservative dogmas, also against egalitarian marriage and abortion.
The balance between its rhetoric and real reforms paves the way for African candidates who, for some critics, are very conservative, says Cristina Traina, professor of religious studies at New York Fordham University.
Pattenden also points out that there is no reason to think that the next Pope necessarily follows Francisco's most liberal stance.
The first Latin American Pope marked a great break in a European-dominated church. His effort for the Vatican hierarchy to reflect the reality of the faithful led to a scenario in which 12% of Cardinals with the right to vote in the conclave are Africans, against 8% in the previous.
Despite the changes, the continent remains underrected in the conclave, as 20% of the 1.400 billion of Catholics in the world live in Africa.
"It would be almost impossible to imagine a world that accepts an African Pope without the transition of Pope Francis being Argentine," says Traina.
A Congolese priest who asked not to have his name revealed considers that there is a reason why there was no African Pope in 1,500 years. "Discrimination, although not obvious among our European brothers, is still a reality that we do not speak often," he said.
An African Pope would represent a new perspective for some of the current problems of the Church.
Faced with the lack of seminarians, some members of the clergy in Africa claim the revision of the veto to the married priests, says Traina.
“It has always been on our lips, as we would like to have an African pope,” says Father Paul Maji, a priest in the Nigerian capital, Abuja. But he is not especially “sentimental” as to the origin of the next Pope, he says.
The opinion is shared by the Dean of the Faculty of Theology of the Catholic University of Congo, Sylvain Badibanga. "We shouldn't think it's our turn," he said. "It's God's turn."
The Turkson Ghanabug also came to a similar conclusion. When his name circulated in 2013 as a possible pontiff, he finally accepted the idea of ​​becoming the first black pope "if this is the will of the Lord."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>