<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>390 thousand patacas in four years for victims of domestic violence</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/390-mil-patacas-em-quatro-anos-para-vitimas-de-violencia-domestica/</link><description>Over the past year, 13 people have been supported by a total amount of 115,770 patacas, as part of the protection measure that enables the assignment of financial support for an urgent character to victims of domestic violence and household members, which has been in force since 2016. In the last four years, the Institute of Social Action has channeled more than 391 thousand Patacas, helping 51 people, most women
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Over the course of four years, between 2021 and 2024, the Institute of Social Action (IAS) has granted more than 391,000 Patacas to victims of domestic violence, which, under the Law on Prevention and Combating Domestic Violence - in force since October 2016 - may request urgent economic support. The information was revealed to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao by the body led by Hon Wai.
According to the IAS, there were 20 requests for urgent economic support, "which were all approved", benefiting a total of 51 people, 38 of whom were female. "Given the sudden economic problems of families, this institute, according to the law, provides emergency assistance, whose value is calculated according to the social risk value and the number of members of household aggregates in each case," explained the body.
According to data provided, throughout the year, 115,770 patacas were assigned to a total of 13 people (five cases). It should be noted that this measure, like all the others covered in the article in question, can be extended to members of the household that cohabit with the victim or with the person at risk.
The increase was light in 2023, when 12 victims of domestic violence (five cases) were supported by 101,820 patacas. Already in 2022, the channeled amount for these cases was the lowest of recent years: six people were helped, involved in two cases of domestic violence, totaling 42,760 patacas. On the contrary, 2021 was the year when the financial support granted was the highest - 130,960 patacas. This year, 20 people were benefited, respecting eight processes of domestic violence.
According to the annual report of the Judicial Police, the number of cases sent to the Public Prosecution Service for the crime of domestic violence, after investigation, decreased between 2023 and 2024, from 15 to 12. The number is also below cases referred in 2019, which totaled 17.
According to data regarding the first half of last year of the Central Case of Domestic Violence System, 864 communications were received on suspicion of risk related to this crime. However, after evaluation 29 suspicious cases were cleared.
The Law on Prevention and Combating Domestic Violence also gives victims the right to temporary reception in social services facilities. In this sense, IAS provides assistance to reception homes through technical support and the assignment of financial support. This newspaper has questioned IAS about the financial support granted over the last few years.
The body began by saying that it provides regular subsidy to the two reception centers to women, "so the concrete amount of subsidy depends on the number of workers, operating situation and the service plans of the year in question." From year to year, there was no “evident change,” said IAS, adding that, between 2021 and 2025, the amount of subsidy attributed to homes that provide assistance to victims of domestic violence was about 10 million Patacas annually.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Epic confrontation of love and adventure” in “House of Dancing Water”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/confronto-epico-de-amor-aventura-em-house-dancing-water/</link><description>Today a new era from the resident show “House of Dancing Water” at the City of Dreams Theater. This is an updated version of the show presented from 2010 to 2020, created by Franco Dragone. The reimaginated megaproduction, which is based on water, presents, in its plot, a novel that transcends time and space, played by over 80 gymnasts, dancers, divers, circus artists and motorcyclists, totaling about three hundred elements of the production team. A house full of guests witnessed the prior of the show, which is the first of the genre in Asia



































Victor Rebelo
 
The show “House of Dancing Water” is, from today, open to the public, returning to the City of Dreams Theater, five years after being interrupted, due to the pandemic. The “Show” created by Franco Dragone, who was 10 consecutive years on display in that space of Cotai Strip, between 2010 and 2020, comes with a new image, although the base of the performances continues to be focused on the pool with a capacity of 17 million liters of water, the equivalent of more than five Olympic pools.
Megaproduction, to which the Jornal Tribuna de Macao watched, cost about $ 250 million and took five years to be staged. It was presented on Thursday night in prior to about 2,000 guests, including the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin Yip, and the former chief executive, Edmund Ho.
The show of about an hour and 45 minutes seduced assistance for its quality, both at the level of actors, male and female, of high professionalism, as well as the technical means used. The exhibition has about 80 acrobats, with gymnastics and dance formation, circus artists, dancers, divers, motorcyclists and a contortionist, who evolve throughout a story that turns around an “epic confrontation of love and adventure, light and darkness”.
The plot presents a brave unknown who enters a mysterious kingdom to rescue Princess Aani, a prisoner of the Dark Queen. Water becomes the connecting link in this passionate tale of romance and courage, where there is no shortage of humor and fun, starring the Sailor, whose history acts as a complement to the existing heroic journey.
The reimaginated version, directed by choreographer Giuliano Peparini, artistic director of Peparini Studios, and produced by Our Legacy Creatations, takes place in a 270 degree room, equipped with cutting -edge technology in terms of stage, advanced water systems, hydraulic lifts, precision lighting and lasers, and projection for unusual visual experience.
The stage, placed in the center of the auditorium, has an elevation system involving 32 hydraulic cylinders and supports eight main elevators, capable of raising a total of 208 tons. The center of the enclosure is consonant to the scenes of the exhibition, which may be an ocean, a jungle, a fairy tale and a six motorcycle jump track.
More than 239 water jets are integrated on the stage, creating dynamic source effects that reach 25 meter heights, working in conjunction with 540 smart lights to provide visual effects.
 
Members of 30 countries participate in the show
With a team of about 300 members of the cast, crew and behind -the -scenes personnel from over 30 countries, the resident “show” mixes dynamic dance choreography and bold water acrobatics.
Prior to the start of the action, members of the cast interact with the public from the seat area, which immediately aroused great curiosity to what would happen when the lights went out, because first -row viewers are distributed covers and towels to protect from a "small wet."
As its name implies, the water component is practically at all times in the show, especially when acrobats dive from platforms, which emerge from the inside of the pool, about 18 meters high.
In the prior, and in one of those moments of “breathing”, the spotlight took the public eyes to the theater ceiling, from which one of the acrobats challenged the distance to the pool, which has a depth of 9.4 meters, jumping over 30 meters high.
Since it was inaugurated, “House of Dancing Water” has had nearly 4,000 sessions, witnessed by six million viewers. Franco Dragone's show has the collaboration of Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment in the organization and is appropriate for all ages.
The price of ticket tickets ranges from 698 to 1,598 patacas. For this month of May, more than half days are already sold out.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy results exceeded forecasts in the first quarter</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/resultados-da-galaxy-excederam-previsoes-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>Galaxy Entertainment ended the first quarter exercise with Hong Kong's $ 3.3 billion operating gains, an annual 16% rise that exceeded analysts' expectations. Financial liquidity also increased again
 
Sérgio Terra
 
The Galaxy Entertainment Group registered EBITDA gains (results before interest, taxes, amortization and depreciation) of nearly 3.3 billion Hong Kong (HKD) in the first quarter of this year, which represents an increase of 16.3% over the same period of 2024. In addition, contrary to the slowdown faced by other playing operators, profits Operational grew 1.8% compared to the fourth quarter of last year.
In the general 2024 calculation, the Galaxy had already accounted for a positive EBITDA of 12.19 billion HKD, 22.4% of the 9.96 billion noted in 2023, the year that marked the return to positive ground, after the 553 million losses suffered in 2022.
In a statement sent yesterday to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange, the company also indicates that net revenues reached 11.2 billion HKD between January and March, noting an annual increase of 6.2% and a quarterly decrease of 1%. Game operations contributed 8.92 billion, corresponding to 79.6% of total net revenues.
Gross terms, Galaxy casinos revenues ciphed at 10.94 billion, reflecting an annual improvement of 14% and a quarterly break of 1%, including 8.23 ​​billion of mass market tables, an increase of 6% and a 5% decrease in the same comparative intervals. The group also fitted 1.98 billion in the VIP segment (52% and 29% in annual and quarterly terms) and 729 million in electronic games (22% more in a year and 7% less in three months).
Between January and March, only the Mega Resort Galaxy Macau registered operational gains of 3.02 billion HKD, 15% and 6% than in the same period of 2024 and the quarter ended in December, respectively. Net revenues from the venture rose 10% to 9.15 billion within one year.
In an analysis of the financial year, JP Morgan analysts stressed that the results of Galaxy Entertainment "were widely consistent in all aspects, including the market quota of the game's gross recipes, EBITDA and margins." "Galaxy's EBITDA grew 2% over the previous quarter, surpassing JP Morgan's consensus and estimates," the investment bank acknowledged, noting that operating profit exceeded the overall performance of the game sector, which recorded a 1% break in this strand compared to the previous quarter.
According to Galaxy, the fortunate factor in game operations had a positive reflection of approximately 330 million in the final result of Ebitda.
The group led by Francis Lui maintains a “healthy” financial situation with wide liquidity. At the end of March this year, the value in cash and net investments of the Galaxy totaled 33 billion HKD, plus 1.7 billion in three months, while the debt dropped from 4.2 billion to 4.0 billion.
"This financial solidity allows us to finance our development plan, explore opportunities abroad and return capital to shareholders through dividends," said the president of Galaxy, again admitting the group's interest in the Thailand market, which should advance to legalize the game in casino.
In general, Francis Lui was “satisfied” with the performance of casinos during and after the Chinese New Year. “Despite geopolitical turbulence and continuous economic slowdown,” the game market in Macau remained “resilient” in the first quarter, he accentuated.
"Recently, the chief executive of Macao indicated that, with the slowdown of the global economy and the potential impact of recently announced [commercial] tariffs, it may be difficult to achieve the global goal of gross game revenues to 2025. We recognize that there are short -term challenges, but we are still confident of long -term prospects for Macao," Francis Lui said, further ensuring phase 4 of the phase 4 Galaxy Macau is "well referred".
Expected to be completed in 2027, this expansion phase will include new luxury hotel brands, a 5,000 -seat amphitheater, restaurants, shops, game -related spaces, a water entertainment zone and a casino.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Space near Bridge 16 can be reserved for the West Line</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/espaco-junto-a-ponte-16-podera-ser-reservado-para-linha-oeste/</link><description>To collaborate with the construction of the western line of the Light Metro, a space can be reserved in a lot next to Bridge 16, DSSCU said at a CPU meeting
 
The Urban Planning Council (CPU) discussed on Wednesday an Urban Conditions Plant (PCU) for two lots, one next to Rua das Lorchas and the other near Visconde Paço de Arcos Street, which welcome the Sofitel Hotel. The space between the two lots, which belongs to the government, can be reserved in the future for the construction of the western line of Metro Ligeiro, said Leong Io Hong, head of the Urban Planning Department of Soil and Urban Construction Services (DSSCU).
As stated, the viability of the west of the metro will be studied with regard to its route, location and stations, so that in that land has already been reserved a "margin" in the original base, so that the future line of the metro can pass by. Recently, the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, explained, in the presentation of the government lines of his tutelage, that the idea is that the Western line starts at the Qingmao post, extending to Fai Chi Kei, passing through the inner port and ending in Barra.
According to the Chinese language press, Leong Io Hong has now assured that the construction of the West line will not cause new obstacles in the maritime area used by existing buildings. In addition, he said that the tread and pedestrians were adjusted and optimized on Rua das Lorchas, for example, the tours were straightened.
In addition to the west line, Raymond Tam revealed that the government plans another line of metro on the peninsula, which is in ring format. Starting at the border post of the artificial island of the Delta Bridge, the idea is to pass through Zone A, the outdoor port, the lakes Nam Van and leaves van and ending in Barra.
Already in the other 11 plants discussed by the CPU, one implies a lot on the marginal road of Ilha Verde, which, according to the urban planning plan of Ilha Verde, can welcome buildings of housing use. A CPU vowel asked why the use of the land was limited to the housing and how the factories will be treated.
In response, Leong Io Hong said that housing use was defined and considered as a priority according to the directing plane, adding that future buildings will be integrated into the community neighborhood. In addition, the official noted that, according to the directing plan, factories can only be established in industrial areas, so the surrounding industrial buildings will not be destined for industrial use in their reconstruction.
On the other hand, in relation to a PCU involving an urban renewal project in the Nam Wai Kwok building, on Artur Tamagnini Barbosa Avenue, several vowels suggested that the number of fractions be kept in the reconstruction of the building and that there is no limit to the gross use area (abu) of fraction, in order to respond to the expectations of original residents to improve the housing environment and to foster a motivation that boosts other urban renewal projects in the same zone.
Saying that he agrees with these suggestions, Lai Weng Leong, director of DSSCU, said the authorities will collect vowel opinions to study the plant again, including the hypothesis of widening the abu permitted to the fractions of this building.
According to the PCU, with a land area of ​​1,032 square meters, this location cannot welcome buildings more than 90 meters, while the maximum allowed land use index is 10 times, of which the maximum abu allowed for housing is 4,900 square meters and the maximum authorized number of housing fractions is 104.
Leong Io Hong explained that the lot is located in an area of ​​high population density, with 180,000 inhabitants per square kilometer, in this sense, the most effective method of population control is to limit the construction area and the number of fractions.
In this respect, he added that the government slightly increased the area of ​​housing fractions by 5% after taking as reference the base of the original area. According to it, the plant foresees a total surface area of ​​15,000 square meters, of which the total abu of fractions occupies about 70%, and the remaining areas may serve as commercial spaces or for parking.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Anxiety and nerves “on the skin” before the Benfica-Sporting derby</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/desporto/ansiedade-nervos-a-flor-da-pele-antes-derbi-benfica-sporting/</link><description>The Estádio da Luz will be the stage of an almost decisive game tomorrow in the issue of the title in the Portuguese Football League, among the top two classifieds, Benfica and Sporting, equals at points on a journey of the end. The expectation is high and the Jornal Tribuna de Macau has recorded opinions of local fans of both clubs. Everyone expects it to be, above all, “a great spectacle”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
There may be “white smoke” already tomorrow at Estádio da Luz in the issue of the title of the main Portuguese football league. The accounts are easy to do. If Benfica wins by two goals of difference becomes champion. If Sporting wins by any margin ensures the Ceptro for the second year in a row.
If there is a draw, everything will be decided on the last journey, with the "lions" receiving in Alvalade Vitória de Guimarães and Benfica to move to Sporting de Braga's ground.
Despite playing out of his environment, Rui Borges's training has been presented with some advantage. First because he defeated his rival on the first lap (1-0) and then for the current best difference of scored and conceded goals, a factor who will decide the champion if the “incarnated” will win tomorrow's meeting by a goal.
Emotions are therefore to the red and probably many fans rooted in Macau who will not want to lose the challenge live on televisions, or hear the report through the radio. The game starts at 18h00, Portugal time, 01h00 in the morning in the territory.
The Jornal Tribuna de Macao recorded the opinion of supporters of both emblems, naturally with antagonistic expectations.
Tiago Assumpção, a sportinguista adept, hopes “an electrifying clash”, in which it is the first time the two candidates, departing on punctual equality, can crown champions in the same game.
On the one hand, Sporting, "which has the super advanced Swedish Gyokeres scoring goals in Catadupa," is looking for a two -time championship that has not happened for over 70 years and, "perhaps, the icing on the cake that would be to have the party in the field of the biggest rival."
On the other hand, Benfica, with a well -crafted team that made a second half of the “phenomenal” season, managing to nullify the six points of disadvantage at the end of the first lap, “and that will do everything to solve the dispute to his side, with his partners and fans,” he says.
Tiago Assumpção considers that “this unpublished scenario adds several extra layers of tension” and believes that Sporting will “go out”, since “Benfica's advantage for playing at home is attenuated by the need to win if he wants to be champion or at least depending on himself”.
Sporting knows that “the non -obligation to win” allows a “more mapling approach”, waiting for Benfica, “in the eagerness to launch themselves for the attack, unprotects the defensive and open spaces for the Gyokeres riders and the flashes of Trincão, Pot and Geny Catamo”.
Tiago Assumpção notes that "the atmosphere is heavy" and concludes his analysis hoping that "his" coach is not "too cautious" and that it is a great clash and that in the end "win Sporting".
 
Teams in a good time in a
On the other side of the “barricade” is Vítor Almeida, who is of the opinion that the two teams are in a “great moment”. Sporting has not lost 15 games and Benfica for 10 games. "Just out there we can see how much balanced will be tomorrow's game," he says, stating that it will be a game of "a lot of caution for both coaches." However, he believes Benfica, for playing at home and having to win, "will take more responsibility for the game."
José Carapinha is also a sympathizer of the “Eagles” club. In his anticipation, he uses the expression “together we turn off the light”, alluding to the stripe of Sporting at the end of the meeting against Gil Vicente. "They say, as if it were possible to extinguish the volcano waiting for them, escape the passion of 62,000 benfiquists who, in unison, will lead the real eagles to, once again, misery among those across the second circular," he says.
The "incarnate" fan stresses that Sporting is a "one man" team, referring to the influence of Gyokeres. Less playing, he asks "a great show, without strange interference, and that wins the best, Benfica." Ends with "we met in the Marquis."
The "white green" João Telo Mexia recognizes that "nervousness and excitement take part of the spirit and conversations of many fervent fans of Portuguese football." As a sportinguista, he points out that "this team is ready to make history: winning the two -time championship."
Speaking of coach Rui Borges, he expresses that "he has proved that he knows how to suffer and how to win at crucial times." The forecast is that "it will not be easy." Although Benfica play at home, "we know that our players will not be intimidated and will be prepared to surprise - the lion grows when the light is stronger."
The Leonino sympathizer believes that "with" Jerricans "of Sportinguista Faith, with the expectation of a good tactical organization, the determination of the squad and that touch of magic from Viktor Gyokeres, there may be a decisive moment, perhaps in the final minutes of the game, and the star will shine again for Sporting."
Outlining tactics, he understands that the counterattack will be decisive, thanks to the "speed" of Gyokeres, the "creativity" of Trincão and the "claw" of Pedro Gonçalves. Therefore, "Sporting has perfect weapons to explore the back of the benfiquist defense." In addition, he wants "a war midfield" and a goalkeeper, Rui Silva, "essential" to keep calm in the decisive moments and guide the centrals.
Telo Mexia ends by manifesting sportsmanship. "The furor for the club does not erase respect for the opponent", and stresses that "we are stronger - where one goes, all go."
 
Special attention to the advanced Gyokeres
Ana Pinto, Benfiquista, left her preview for tomorrow's challenge late in the afternoon in Lisbon. "Despite so many doubtful arbitrations, with controversial bids that hurt them Benfica, the team managed to stay in the fight until this penultimate journey."
The adept believes that, “with the value of its players and with a stadium to cram from fervent fans,” Benfica “will reach the long -awaited and deserved 39th championship”. To this end, he adds, Bruno Lage's set "will have to be in particular attention at the Gyokeres scorer and Captain Hjulmand, who maneuver the entire Sporting team from midfield."
Nevertheless, Ana Pinto guarantees that Benfica has "good elements to be able to manage those opponents." The focus will be important and "essentially they do not make mistakes." About arbitration, "let it be exempt and do not harm or benefit any of the teams."
Returning to Sporting's supporters, Paulo Conde says the hypotheses are “50/50”, pointing out that Benfica plays more “in positional attack”, with different dynamics to Sporting “that acts with a three -central system”.
He adds that the "lions" game is based on direct football and with quick transitions through the corridors, as it has very fast players in these positions. "
Already Niki Torrão Vaticin even the victory of Sporting 2-1, "with Gyokeres scoring both goals." It states that “the stage is set up for a soccer show at the highest level, hoping that his club will solve the championship“ at home of the biggest rival ”.
It considers Sporting to “advantage” because the minimum margin victory guarantees the title. "I think the set of Rui Borges will enter the game with caution, but with the focus of winning."
After a time of “entrances and exits of coaches, it is with great joy to see Sporting reach this phase of the championship with the possibility of being two -time champion,” he says.
 
João Pinheiro whistles Light Game
The referee who will have the responsibility to direct tomorrow's derby is chosen. This is João Pinheiro, Judge of the Braga Association, 37, international since 2016. It will be for the 18th time in a classic, having been the referee of the League Cup final, in which Benfica led the best about Sporting in Penaltis. Just 48 hours before the Light Game, João Pinheiro will direct the challenge of the League Settlements between Chelsea and Djurgarden.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DICJ wants to “raise” “smart” management of the game</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dicj-quer-elevar-gestao-inteligente-jogo/</link><description>The DICJ intends to raise the “intelligent” management of the game sector, through the introduction of computer technology, indicated the new manager of the body, NG Wai Han
 
The new director of Game Inspection and Coordination (DICJ), Ng Wai Han, is betting on "raising the intelligent management level of the sector, so that it develops healthily." For this, “computer technologies” will be introduced ”in the game area, indicated, at the inauguration ceremony.
With a vast experience in the area of ​​Public Administration, namely in the development of electronic governance and the optimization of administrative procedures, Ng Wai Han previously directed the administration and public function services (SAFP). In the possession, he also promised that he will strive “in the coordination and supervision of the effective implementation of the non-playing elements, in order to contribute to the proper diversification of the economy of Macao and to the articulated development of different industries”.
The secretary for the economy and finance, in turn, said he believed that Ng Wai Han will lead the DICJ team "to persist in the spirit of reform and innovation, to be guided by pragmatism and the sense of responsibility", as well as "to advance resolvedly, in order to promote the healthy and ordered functioning of the sector."
Tai Kin IP also pointed out some important works to take into account, such as combating illicit game, supervising concessionaire investment in non -game elements, compliance with social responsibilities by concessionaires and optimizing the management of the game sector.
According to a DICJ press release, in his speech, NG Wai Han thanked the Government of MSA, the Chief Executive and the Secretary for Confidence, stating that he will be mission to "promote the healthy and ordained development of the game sector in accordance with the law." He also guaranteed that he will lead the team to perform supervision work, with a spirit of “justice and impartiality, integrity, modesty, defense of fundamental principles and opening new paths, notion of responsibility”.
Ng Wai Han has a degree in Law and Master in Criminal Law from the University of Zhongshan. In 1999, he entered the civil service as a higher technician in the direction of services for labor affairs, where he remained until 2019, having assumed, since mid -2017, the position of subdirector of the body. It was in 2020 that it moved to the SAFP, first as a subdirector and later as leader of the body.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Discussed future of young health professionals</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/discutido-futuro-dos-jovens-profissionais-de-saude/</link><description>The future of young health professionals was focused on the last plenary meeting of the Council for Medical Affairs. The meeting, which addressed the support for the development of the career of young health professionals, was attended by about 30 young people from young people from medical associations in the territory. The director of health services recalled that the government will support these young people to travel to the interior of China, in order to integrate into national development.
"The Great Bay and the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin are the easiest starting points," said Alvis Lo, quoted in a statement. At the meeting, the director of subsistence affairs services, Fong Fong Tan, stressed that, "although the area of ​​the in -depth cooperation zone is small, the development dynamic is quite large."
Fong Fong Tan talked about opportunities for young health professionals in Macau, including employment policies, as well as the situation on the medical training basis between Hengqin and Macau. "All health professionals in Macau are welcome to work and develop in the deepened cooperation zone," he said.
Already Leong Iek Ham presented the “Professional Training Program for Young Macao Doctors in the Great Bay”, which aims to “raise the technical and professional capacity and professional competitiveness of young doctors from Macao”, encouraging them to work and develop in the Great Bay.
According to a statement from SSM, participants "recommended planning of more systematic short, medium and long term systematic formations, so that young health professionals can apply acquired knowledge." Regarding those who go to the large bay and in -depth cooperation zone, they suggested the launch of accommodation policies, such as the construction of homes for qualified paintings, and even more training courses on clinical practice between Hengqin and Macau can be organized.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Polyphony” by Gu Yue transcends tradition and contemporaneity</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/polifonia-de-gu-yue-transcende-tradicao-contemporaneidade/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation and the Faculty of Humanities and Arts of UCTM co-organized a collective exhibition by artist Gu Yue and six doctoral students. The show, which “transcends tradition and contemporaneity” to create “cognitive disorientation”, will be evident until the 17th









































The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) inaugurated yesterday the exhibition of collective art “Polyphony” by artist Gu Yue and six doctoral students at the Faculty of Humanities and Arts of the University of Science and Technology of Macao (UCTM), and will be patent until May 17, with free admission.
According to a Foundation's press release, the project features 20 works representing “the forms and styles” of Gu and his disciples Luo Su, Zhu Zhaohui, Wang Kongbin, Ding Song, Guo Weiwei and Wei Dongsheng.
According to the FRC, the exhibition is a “visual banquet that transcends tradition and contemporaneity, material and digital, place and global, through the collision of various media and the resonance of ideas”.
The works include various art forms, such as facilities, sand paintings, oil, and lacquer, and works brush of detail, in a display of Macao's “Unique Artistic Ecosystem as a cultural convergence point”.
"The mission of art is to create cognitive disorientation" is the preface to the exposure and the term "polyphony", from music, refers to the "opposition and symbiosis of multiple voices", a concept whose curator introduced into visual art to explore "the reconfiguration of meaning under the fragmentation of the means," explains the FrC.
The audience is invited to calibrate their cognition in the "gap between brightness and residual shadow", in a "broken" linear narrative, through the confrontation between traditional crafts and the new media and the "rapport of local cultural genes and global issues". The FRC clarifies that, in addition to an exhibition of academic achievements, the project is also a “speculative experience on the essence of art”.
The works of the six doctoral students of UCTM come from "individual experiences" and respond to propositions such as "identity, time and memory in the age of digital capital." The team states that "polyphony" aims to use art as "a prism to reflect the symbiotic possibilities of multiple realities."</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Percussion concert takes duet to the Military Club</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/concerto-de-percussao-leva-dueto-ao-clube-militar/</link><description>Two percussionists will act this Sunday at the Military Club, in another concert integrated in the “Musical Days”. Uly Chan and Yukie Lai participate in the concert entitled “Redefining Groove”, scheduled for 5 pm at Stanley Ho Salon. The duo will play excerpts from composers such as Emil Kuyumcuyan, Kato Daiki, Brian Blume and Nicholas MartynCoiw. Uly Chan, 26, born in Macao, besides percussionist is an educator, theater artist and composer, and is attending the master's degree at the Conservatory of Music of Geneva, Switzerland. It has collaborated with contemporary composers, interested in experimenting and developing the diversity of percussion music. Your last composition is a solo piece for a candy, electronic music and video. He also collaborated with visual artist Behzard Dehno in the installation of the street "The Speech", exhibited in the city center of Rome. Yukie Lai is a founding member and artistic director of the Macau Percussion Association. He often participates in international art festivals and has acted in countries and regions such as Estonia, Mexico, Canada, Japan, Singapore, Thailand, South Korea, China and Taiwan. Active interpreter and tutor, Yukie regularly performs percussion concerts, symphony and chamber music and is a collaborator of several genres for theater groups at MSAR. He obtained several awards in different contests, namely “young musicians from Macau” and “Asian percussion festival” in Japan and “exceptional performance” in the Marimba and Taro group.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2393/</link><description>Reinforced hengqin border capacity
The Heignqin Border Post will reserve an area for new passage roads, including 46 automatic and six manuals, which can raise the 65%inspection capacity, the Public Security Police (CPSP) said. In addition, 64 automatic roads will be transformed to allow passage by facial recognition. On the other hand, the extension of the target audience of automatic passage channels will be studied. According to CPSP, since the beginning of the year and until 14h00 on Wednesday, the number of tickets in the Hengqin post exceeded 10 million, which translates a daily average of 79 thousand (+32% annually). Visitors accounted for 37.8% of the total.
 
MGA recovered ground next to Sidónio Pais
The Government of MSAR has carried out another interdepartmental action of eviction to recover a land of the illegally occupied state, with about 121 square meters, located on the slope next to Avenida de Sidónio Pais. According to the direction of soil services and urban construction (DSSCU), the land was paved and on site were noticeable unauthorized works. DSSCU ordered the lot to be vacated and reversed to the government, but, as it was not fully vacated or returned, the body has recovered.
 
SSM warns of rising varicella cases
Health services (SSM) warned of “a trend of increasing the number of varicella cases”. This year, until May 6, 195 cases were recorded in Macao, 90 more than in the same period of 2024. The body indicates, however, that there were no "severe or deadly cases." SSM say that, preventively, infected students and teachers "should be temporarily removed from school attendance and other activities developed in educational institutions." In case of collective infection, schools should inform the disease prevention and control center. SSM recall that children can be vaccinated.
 
Simulacro tested airport emergency plan
Macao airport performed an exercise at its fuel deposit, which simulated a fire on the premises and the execution of relief and emergency work. According to the civil aviation authority, the simulacrum tested the emergency and evacuation plans of the various departments, and also reinforced the cooperation between them.
 
More than 3,500 annual cases of accidental fall
According to data from the injury monitoring system, more than 3,500 accidental drop in Macao register annually, health services (SSM) have been reported. In a statement, the body adds that "homes and streets are the places with the highest incidence of injuries" and that the elderly are a "high risk" group. SSM have been making awareness activities within the “Preventing Injuries, Begin” and the “Healthy Community Program” series. In this sense, they recommend some preventive measures, including maintaining sufficient lighting at home, equilibrium exercises or choice of appropriate clothing and shoes.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau lawyers want to bet on Hengqin and Big Bay</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/advogados-de-macau-querem-apostar-em-hengqin-grande-baia/</link><description>The economic conjuncture of the territory has an impact on the activity of lawyers, acknowledged the Macao Lawyers Association, which considers crucial "to take advantage of opportunities" in Hengqin and the Great Bay, where, said Oriana Pun, the association's secretary general, the causes of the territory "can play a very important role." In the presentation of the activities of the lawyer day, there was still no progress in the protocol with the Portuguese Bar Association, noting that, for this “there has to be a mutual will”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Macao Lawyers Association (AAM) admits that the sector is impacting the new economic environment, but is willing to work to take advantage of the opportunities arising from the development of Hengqin. At a press conference held yesterday to present the activities of the lawyer's day, the association's secretary general, Oriana Pun, spoke specifically in the fall of the purchase and sale of houses in the MSAR. "There is some impact, but as there is in other sectors," he noted.
"In fact, lawyers who are more linked to private notaries, who make purchasing deeds and real estate sales ... Just see the number of deeds or purchases and sales to know that, for sure, has an impact," said the lawyer.
Therefore, he said, "we have to take advantage of the opportunities, following the measures announced in the government lines of action, be aware, follow economic development and seek these opportunities."
In this respect, he focused on the case of Hengqin. "We have lawyers in the great bay that can play a very important role in this development and can help foreign investors bet inside China and vice versa, as well as bring the continent's entrepreneurs to Portuguese-speaking countries," he said.
Oriana Pun said that "this is where we are trying to develop our work, looking for opportunities to provide these services." In the Great Bay there are about 90 lawyers to perform functions. At this time, Macau has 457 registered lawyers.
Regarding the spectrum of interns lawyers, Oriana Pun indicated that they are currently close to 180. "The number has been stable in recent years," he said. He said, annually there are about a hundred students who are completing the law degree and who take admission examination, of which 20 to 30 pass the assessment and are recognized as interns.
As for the possibility of being restarted the protocol with the Portuguese Bar Association, Oriana Pun was peremptory in stating that "there has to be mutual will and not only on our part."
The lawyer indicated that on the visit of an AAM entourage to Portugal in 2024, this issue was not spoken at the meeting maintained with the Portuguese order. "They don't seem so willing to talk about it," he said.
It is recalled that the protocol between AAM and the Bar Association existed for a while, having as its main purpose the mutual recognition of the qualifications of lawyers from both parties. The deal was suspended about 10 years ago and has never been reactivated.
 
Legal Consultations and Forum on Professor's Day
Regarding the activities planned for lawyer day, free legal consultations are once again one of the strengths of the program, which starts this Saturday with sports events in the University of Science and Technology Stadium fields (UCTM). In the competitions will participate, in addition to lawyers, interns, and workers of the Directorate of Justice Services, also students from the universities of Macau, Macao, UCTM and São José.
In the event list, highlight the possibility that the general public has once again to receive legal consultations for free, an initiative that AMM has been making over the years.
Fulfilling what had been announced in 2024, consultations will have a wider scope this year. "This initiative will have a special focus, as we will be able to count on the presence of representatives of Hong Kong and the interior of China," said Vong Hin Fai. May 17 and 18 will take place between 10h00 and 20h00, at the Tourist Information Center of the Tourism Services Directorate.
Another highlight is the holding of a conference entitled “Integrating the interior and abroad - Forum on the Development of High Quality Legal Services in the context of the“ One Rota ”initiative”, on May 16, between 14:30 and 17:30, at the Celebrity Tower Ballroom of the Studio City Hotel.
In the Forum, they will intervene, in addition to Macao lawyers, professionals from the continent, Hong Kong and Southeast Asia. In the same place, at 6.30 pm, the opening ceremony of the lawyer day will follow. "In this official opening we will have representatives of the government and the Greater Bay region, as well as those who participate in the forum," said the president of AMM. The traditional cocktail and commemorative dinner will take place about 7 pm.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>233 can vote for the consulate for Portuguese legislatures</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/233-podem-votar-consulado-para-legislativas-portuguesas/</link><description>From a universe of 55,789 voters registered in the territory, only 233 people are registered to vote in person, on May 17 and 18, for the legislative elections of Portugal, the Consul General told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. As for correspondence vote, Alexandre Leitão called for the bulletins to be sent as soon as possible. However, today the anticipated vote ends
 
Catarina Pereira*
 
There are only 233 people who will be able to vote in person in Macao for the legislative elections of Portugal, in a universe of 55,789 voters registered in the territory, the consul General of Portugal revealed in Macao and Hong Kong, in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. Alexandre Leitão also appealed to the vote and asked that, in the case of correspondence vote, the bulletins be sent as quickly as possible.
In the territory, citizens can exercise the right to vote in person at the consulate's facilities, on May 17 and 18, Saturday and Sunday, throughout the day, between 08h00 and 19h00. There will be only one vote table.
As for the voting reports, the Portuguese ambassador said he was informed by the Macao Post Office Director that voters are already receiving the electoral correspondence.
"People, as soon as they receive [the voting report], and I think many have already received, vote and go to the Post Office, because, of course, the sooner the vote will leave, the more guarantees it is to arrive at Portugal. On the side of Macao Post Office there is a commitment to give an immediate referral," said Alexandre Leitão, to make the CTT always have an opening stance in this scope.
However, census citizens in Portugal and who are abroad on May 18 can vote to this day at the consulate in Macao. Voters who are displaced in public or private functions can do so, representing national selections, as well as students, researchers, teachers and research pockets, as well as patients undergoing treatment. According to the consul, in this modality "there are not many people to vote".
Alexandre Leitão noted that "abstention is usually high", but not so much in the face -to -face [votes], "noting that by 2024 it was 33%." In voting bulletins could frankly decrease, "he said.
In this sense, he recalled that the vote is a right and a duty. "In Portugal it is not an obligation in the legal sense, we have to respect the individual freedom of each one. However, our political system is based on the choice of citizens from whom they governs them and, therefore, it is natural and understandable that I appeal to that everyone uses this faculty that the law can choose who will be deputies to the Assembly of the Republic in this case and, therefore, indirectly, who will govern Portugal."
 
*With Vítor Rebelo</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Al condemns “acts” of journalists from “All About Macau”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/al-condena-actos-de-jornalistas-all-macau/</link><description>The "acts" of two journalists from "All About Macau" were convicted by the Legislative Assembly, which says "much of the legitimate right of the media and journalists to do interviews and reports", but that this right "must be exercised within the limits established by law"
 
The Legislative Assembly (AL) condemned the "acts" of the journalists of the All About Macau, which, according to the police, will have committed the crime of disturbance of functioning of MSAR organs, specifically the legislative body. The case, which took place on April 17, was sent to the prosecutor. “The handle and condemns the acts (…) of journalists,” can be read in a statement.
It is recalled that, according to the online newspaper, two journalists of the publication were taken by police while trying to enter the AL hall to attend the presentation of the 2025 Governing Action (LAG) lines for the Secretary's Guardianship for Administration and Justice, André Cheong. In a video published by the newspaper on social networks, it is possible to observe employees of the public security police body trying to remove one of the journalists from the entrance of AL.
On social networks, the newspaper, which has a monthly edition on paper, wrote that the journalists' request to enter the plenary session was refused, and the police were called to remove the two professionals, "claiming they were suspected of" disturbing the operation of the authorities "from Macao and" illegal video recording ".
Still inside Al, the newspaper indicated, the journalists received a 'blue card', which forces to watch the session in another room, through television broadcast - something they refused. "Apparently there were still vacant places" for the media in the main hall, according to the "All About Macau".
The legislative body, in turn, has another perspective. First of all, it argues that “reasonable measures have been adopted regarding assistance to meetings by journalists from the media and public bodies”. Then he says that "as there was a great influx of journalists" during the LAG, and "since the space for interviews, as well as the places available in the plenary room is limited," Al "allowed journalists who had not been able to access the plenary room after the necessary filming, could watch the broadcast."
"Regrettably, journalists of a particular publication did not comply with these reasonable measures during the three days of the meetings held on April 14, 15 and 17, shouting and pushing the security lines, which severely disturbed the order of the functioning of plenary meetings," reads. In this sense, "to cease the situation and to avoid its aggravation, the staff of the support services to the ALCATED the police to assist, on April 17, with the same removed the journalists from the AL, in order to ensure the effective continuation of the plenary." That day, the journalists remained in police custody until 21:00, still according to the "All About Macau" on social networks.
In the same note, AL ensures that “it has given great importance to the public information of the public about the work done” and that “it respects the legitimate right of the media and journalists to do interviews and reports”. However, he underlines, "this right must be exercised within the limits established by law." "As for acts that severely disturb the normal functioning of AL, it adopts, under the law, the appropriate measures to suppress them," he adds.
The Macao Journalists Association (AJM) said to “deeply” lament the detention of reporters, including Association President Ian Sio Tou. The AJM had expressed, days before, concern about the increase of official events without coverage of the media and “discriminatory practices” with the sector.
Already the president of the Portuguese and English Press Association of Macau reacted to Lusa, saying that "the unprecedented situation is sad and worries us, because we consider that it opens a precedent-at least-embarrassing." José Miguel Incarnation asked the MP “that there is a consideration in the evaluation of the facts, so that there is no greater consequences”.
 
Newspaper refuses “biased accusations”
All About Macao newspaper said it "deeply regrets the statements and biased accusations" of the Legislative Assembly (AL) against the two journalists expelled from Parliament, also criticizing the fact that the legislature has issued "an response to the incident" only "after more than a month of silence." In a statement released on social networks, he said that the AL prevented "repeatedly All About Macau journalists from doing their normal reporting work under false pretexts." He also accused the "ignoring the provisions of the Press Law and Article 94 of his regiment." The article states that "they are reserved to representatives of the media, duly accredited, own places in the meeting room." The newspaper also regretted the one that was "the first incident in Macao's history in which journalists who covered the ALS were taken by police for investigation - and even face criminal proceedings."
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Increases chickens in the US because of increasing egg price</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/aumenta-aluguer-de-galinhas-nos-eua-por-causa-aumento-preco-dos-ovos/</link><description>Frustrated by increasing egg price and rationing in supermarkets, Yong-Mi Kim decided it was time to rent chickens.
A US Aviary Influenza crisis has cost eggs in recent months. While many chose to raise their own animals, this university professor who lives in the La Crescenta, California community preferred to rent them.
“I want to try this and see if I like it or not,” he comments. "I know people who have chickens at home, but they do a lot of work. They had to adapt the garden." "I think renting a chicken is a good start."
Chicken rental began to gain strength in the US over a decade ago, when Jenn and Phil Tompkins created the “Rent a Chicken” project in Pennsylvania. The service has expanded to about 40 cities by farmers and has gained even more popularity in recent months.
“From the pandemic we have seen more interest than usual, but it was especially greater this year. I would say that three to four times more than we saw at the same time last year,” Victoria Lee, who serves the Los Angeles region on her farm in the Agua Dolce community, told AFP.
At the peak of the crisis, the Americans even paid more than $ 10 for a dozen eggs, which, depending on the city, used to cost between three to five dollars.
The supermarkets began to ration the carton packaging, and the issue infiltrated the 2024 presidential campaign, when Donald Trump promised to reduce the cost of food, including eggs as soon as he took office.
But the Republican politician is the current president and the product is up to the rise. In March last year, egg prices rose 1.2% compared to the previous month and were 60.4% more expensive, according to the US Department of Agriculture.
Although raising chickens at home is no cheaper than buying eggs on the market, Lee explains that this improves quality.
"When they arrive at the store, eggs have, on average, 48 to 60 days. Over time, egg protein begins to decompose," he says.
On the other hand, the garden eggs last the time their owners take to collect them.
“Rent the chicken” offers different packages that, depending on the location and number of chickens, range from about $ 500 to $ 1,000 for six months. The rental includes the bird, food, drinking fountains and feeders, a guide on how to take care of chickens and the key element of the proposal: the mobile chicken coop.
It is a kind of mini pit, individual for each chicken, fully closed by grids and transportable, with wheels at the bottom. This protects animals from predator and, being portable, ensures that birds live in a natural environment without much space.
“Every day, customers raise the chicken coop and move it to another location, so that chickens have access to fresh herb daily in a seven-day cycle,” explains Lee.
"So chickens have the experience of being in an open area, with new stimuli, new insects to look, new grass to dig, but in a safe environment."
The practicality of the chicken coop is what makes your rental to people like Kim attractive. The 52 -year -old teacher received the chickens at home with great enthusiasm.
“Free eggs!” He exclaimed when Lee came to his home to deliver the kit, which included a dozen fresh eggs put by animals last week.
A client with two chickens can wait up to 14 eggs a week, explains Lee.
Kim, whose son is athlete and consumes eggs often, says that although the supply crisis has led her to rent the chickens, "it's something deeper than that." "I wanted to learn (that) as a way of life and also compare the taste of eggs."
Proof that the US continues to be the land “of opportunities”…
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>