<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>“Let the city grow to a million people”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/deixem-crescer-cidade-para-um-milhao-de-pessoas/</link><description>For the economy to grow, “Macau should increase its population to one million people, which would be good for housing, the real estate sector, small and medium-sized companies, and all commerce”, argues local businessman Filipe Cunha Santos. In an interview with the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, the general director of “Global Remit” and also a member of the Luso-Chinese Chamber of Commerce warns that the policy of reducing non-resident workers “severely restricts the attraction of staff and talents”. Only with the free attraction of new staff can “the diversification policy can advance”, he emphasizes














VÍTOR REBELO
 
The policy of restricting labor imports in Macau is, for local businessman Filipe Cunha Santos, detrimental to economic growth. Analyzing the current situation of Macau's economy, the Portuguese, who has lived in the territory for over 30 years, regrets that many small and medium-sized companies (SMEs) are closing, “because the city really doesn't grow, there is no development”.
Recognizing that this is a topic that is “not easy to debate”, the general director of the “Global Remittances Company” (“Global Remit”), a money remittance company, points out some possible solutions, one of which is “letting the city grow to one million people”. The suggestion is based on what he considers to be a “wrong” policy – ​​restricting the attribution of “blue cards” to those who wish to come to work in Macau, as it “immensely limits the attraction of talent and the establishment of new companies that create new jobs”.
In an interview with the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, the also member of the Luso-Chinese Chamber of Commerce states that, in this capacity, he recently participated in a meeting with directors of the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM), where the economic situation was addressed, specifically the difficulties that many local companies face and the obstacles they face when they want to establish themselves in Macau.
"Basically, it's a bit of a chicken and egg story, companies don't come here because, when they set up here, despite actually having a very low tax base, they are unable to hire staff, neither for marketing, nor for finance, nor for the IT [information technology] of the companies. Therefore, few settle, and even senior management themselves, sometimes, are unable to establish themselves, as they are not given 'blue cards'", highlights Filipe Cunha Santos, regretting that the situation is different in neighboring HKSAR. “We know that Hong Kong, last year, even received the award for being the fourth best city in terms of attracting talent”, he says.
Referring to the specific situation in Macau, he also notes that, after the Covid-19 pandemic, the Government developed a policy to attract talent, which did not result in concrete terms. “We continue to have 670,000 inhabitants, as ‘blue cards’ are extremely difficult to obtain and the Labor Affairs Bureau itself cancels ‘blue cards’, claiming that certain professions, such as cooks, accountants, salespeople, etc., exist among Macau residents”, he laments.
Faced with these difficulties, “companies give up”. Regarding the closure of stores, he explains that small and family businesses cannot find resident staff willing to receive less than 15,000 or 20,000 patacas. In this context, argues the businessman, “it would be a profitable alternative to be able to import cheaper labor, both from China, Hong Kong or Asia, to pay a salary, economically viable for companies, to each employee”.
With the obstacles placed on hiring non-resident workers (TNR), “companies cannot survive”. “And we are also talking about engineering, hotel, financial or other sector companies, which to hire 10 staff, need 70 locations, which is, for me, a completely unsustainable policy”, he emphasizes.
Furthermore, he continues, the term of “blue cards” should be, for example, four years and workers can be transferred to other functions without the need to return to their countries of origin.
To support his ideas and suggestions, the 69-year-old businessman gives another example. “Students who come from China, who are excellent, are studying here for four years, unable to work during the course, unlike the locals, and as soon as they finish they have to return to China, they cannot be recruited here”, he criticizes, warning that this is a “harmful measure, since these are talents in which Macau has invested, they have become accustomed to the culture and the city and are ready to support small businesses and economic diversification”.
 
Benefits for SMEs and all commerce
Reinforcing the idea that the Government should let the population grow so that the city can reach up to one million people, Filipe Cunha Santos considers that “we have structures to add more people and that would be good for housing, real estate, SMEs, all commerce”. "You don't need to be great Nobel prize-winning talents to work here. The important thing is to let local, regional and foreign companies establish themselves in Macau, as 'holdings' or financial centers, taking advantage of the low taxation", he argues.
Recalling that Macau residents now go a lot to the Chinese mainland to shop, because prices are cheaper, the person responsible for “Global Remit” recalls policies implemented in Hengqin. “The Government subsidizes rents for two years, in a first store, salaries are 5,000 to 7,000 renminbi per month, and in this way locals are attracted to consume there, because the prices are cheap”. On the other hand, in Macau, “if they don't allow cheap labor to enter, we are not giving SMEs the chance to survive or be competitive, even if rents were not so subsidized”, he declares.
Regarding casinos, “the difficulties are less than for SMEs”, he observes, highlighting that gaming operators “are managing to hire more people, because they have more money”. For example, with regard to recent local graduates, around 600, “the Government asked the casinos to integrate them”, he notes.
Regarding the permanence of TNR in Macau, he condemns the fact that there are “local ‘lobbies’ that complain and say that they are not necessary”. These statements “are demagogic, as they know that locals do not intend to go to work for low-quality jobs, and that the unemployment rate in Macau is one of the lowest in the world”, he emphasizes.
In short, Filipe Cunha Santos recommends an alternative dynamic in economic policy. “For the economy to grow, for economic diversification, to stop the reduction of small and medium-sized companies, for there to be an increase in employment, it was necessary for the city to increase to numbers close to one million”.
This “was good, first of all due to the consumption that was being done”, pointing to the “aggravated” problems that exist in real estate and in SMEs, “which cannot survive with salaries similar to those of casinos and high rents, which therefore have to close, as can be seen by the many unoccupied stores for rent in the city center”.
 
“Global Remit” partners and offers fast services
Filipe Cunha Santos came to Macau in 1982, to work at CTM, after which he was in London, at “Cable and Wireless”. He was then invited to Marconi, in Macau, holding the position of head of Portugal Telecom (PT) for Asia Pacific.
With the sale of everything that PT had in the territory, in 2008, Filipe Cunha Santos acquired, with his compatriot Óscar Marques, Páginas Amarelas, which was one of PT's businesses in Macau.
In 2017, together with two partners, one linked to Indonesia and the other to the Philippines, he founded “Global Remit”, a money remittance company licensed by the Macau Monetary Authority (AMCM). “Not to be confused with ‘exchange house’”, as he made a point of remembering in the interview he gave to this newspaper.
Recently, “MoneyGram”, a leading global payments network for consumers, businesses and communities, announced a partnership with “Global Remit”, offering fast, secure and globally reliable cross-border payments services through the “MoneyGram” network, which covers almost 500,000 points of sale and five billion digital terminals in more than 200 countries and territories.
Coincident with this partnership, AMCM approved this month the cooperation of “Global Remit” with “Mpay” from “Macau Pass”, for the creation of an application that anyone can download, called “Global Remit Macau”, and which has daily exchange rates. “Those interested can register all the data, the beneficiary, the bank, etc., having the option of choosing payment through the bank's Easy Transfer, or through Mpay”, explains Filipe Cunha Santos.
“The advantage is that people do not have to come to the store with cash, which is often inconvenient, and can make the transfer from home, as happens all over the world”, says the general director of the company “which is the first in Macau to do this”.
At the moment, there are only four licensed money remittance companies in Macau, while there are multiple in Hong Kong. “We are the third, which has been operating since June 2020”, working mostly with Filipinos, but also sending many transfers to Indonesia, Thailand, India, Bangladesh, Nepal, that is, “all Asian countries that have this type of TNR here”.
“Global Remit” has direct relationships with banks in the Philippines and Indonesia. “The shipments are there in 10 minutes,” he says. “For other countries in the world we do it through Moneygram and we are the only one that does it globally”, he indicates, ensuring that the company he runs has exchange rates, in relation to pataca, “quite competitive compared to banks”.
 
Foreign exchange business gives profit margin
The businessman emphasizes that every day the company negotiates with Philippine banks what the Hong Kong exchange rate is for the peso. “We do the exchange business, we buy Hong Kong dollars, and we add a small margin on top, this margin being the company's profit, because the price we charge per transaction is very cheap, not exceeding 25 patacas”, he highlights.
Often, “maybe not for bigger countries, like China, but, for example, for all Portuguese-speaking countries and Europe, Global Remit is very cheap in terms of exchange rates and remittance fees”, he says, confirming that “through our correspondent banks, like Moneygram, the money goes to the beneficiary's account abroad in less than half an hour”.
The “only disadvantage”, he admits, “is that we have a limit of 20,000 patacas per person per day”. This is a law that dates back to the Portuguese administration. “We have been asking AMCM to increase this amount, but this change could take a long time to be approved in the Legislative Assembly, making it difficult to change the law at this time”.
According to the person responsible, after two years of requests and explanations to AMCM, cooperation with “MPay” from “Macau Pass” was recently authorized. “Now we have the possibility of trying to reach another market, in addition to ‘bluecards’, and we are going to launch a campaign, to inform the local community, expatriates, and the Portuguese community, how to use their cell phone for a simple and safe remittance of money abroad with payment through MPay”.
Asked whether the four remittance licenses that currently exist in the Macao SAR are sufficient, Filipe Cunha Santos responds in the affirmative. “We would like it to be like this, because in Hong Kong they are now restricting licenses, because of ‘anti-money laundering’ (AML) and international legislation, but there was a time when they had around a thousand companies operating, because licensing in Hong Kong was much easier than in Macau”, he notes.
In the Macao SAR, “it is necessary to have close collaboration with the AMCM, which requires very restrictive regulations, and there is a database that the organization sends us, which is the United Nations database on terrorist operations, and which requires that all remittances, both from the sender and the beneficiary, must be verified, by computer, in relation to identification and country of destination”, he explains.
“Global Remit” has 11 employees, most of whom are Filipinos and Indonesians. The Philippines constitutes the largest market, followed by Indonesia.
Filipe Cunha Santos also discussed one of his “hobbies”, wine. The president of the Confraria dos Oenophiles of Macau, an institution that is celebrating 30 years since its founding, says that “in the global Chinese market, not to mention Hong Kong, the tendency is for young people to no longer drink so much wine, which has somewhat lost the symbol of ‘status’ that it acquired in the past”. Therefore, he concludes that the wine business and consumption in China have remained stable, “without much growth”.
In relation to Portuguese wines, there has been a notable increase in quality, which is reflected in the growth of exports. “And the variety of indigenous grape varieties we have bodes well for our penetration into new markets.”</description><pubDate>2025-11-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Science Park will be a “bridge” between young people and technology companies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/parque-de-ciencias-sera-ponte-entre-jovens-empresas-tecnologicas/</link><description>The Government is collecting opinions on the Macau Science and Technology Research and Development Industrial Park (PIIDCT). According to the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, there will be six sessions until December 26, having instructed the Beijing Institute of Industrial Design and Research to carry out “an in-depth analysis” on global planning, industrial direction, operational model and political support.














Specifically, the operation of the PIIDCT will focus on four areas. Within the scope of “biomedicine”, it will promote the development of gene therapy, new generation of vaccines, innovative traditional Chinese medicine medicines, artificial intelligence (AI) medical devices, aesthetic medicine and oncology treatment. It will also have the mission of expanding integrated services of “pharmaceutical industry + health and well-being tourism”.
In the sphere of “digital technologies”, large-scale models will be developed for specific sectors, digital entertainment, immersive VR/AR/MR solutions and industrial applications of AI technologies, forming a distinctive model of “AI + IP” dynamization.
As for “integrated circuits”, the focus will be on the development of computing and support chips, industrial and for the Internet of Things. In the area of ​​“aerospace technologies”, satellite payloads and structural components of spacecraft will be developed.
The document recommends that the Government be responsible for the general positioning of the Park: introduction of projects of great importance, development suggestions and support for specific policies. The creation of a public capital company for the PIIDCT, responsible for managing the facilities, operations and attracting investments, will be studied.
In addition, the Park will provide one-stop services for property management, business registration, business financing, brand promotion, patent matters, among others. It will also provide various support to companies in the initial, growth and maturity stages. Specialized laboratories, office areas for R&amp;D, convention and exhibition rooms will also be created.
On the other hand, venture capital, co-investment and industrial-oriented funds will be made available, combining them with social capital. The Park will also promote cooperation between local and international companies, offering opportunities for international financing and business contacts.
For the authorities, the Macao SAR has the advantages of international, institutional connections and a scientific research base. In particular, it points to “close ties” with Portuguese-speaking countries (PLP), which will facilitate the establishment of a platform for agglomeration of qualified staff, technologies, capital and projects.
Regarding construction objectives, the Government hopes that the Park will contribute to leveraging the “great resources” of the Greater Bay Area, breaking the “physical restrictions” of the soil and implementing the “R&amp;D in Macau + transformation in Hengqin” and “Portuguese-speaking market + Chinese technology” models. Taking as a basis the market of Portuguese-speaking countries, through the Park, Macau “will seek to value local advantages in scientific research and the advantages of connection to PLP markets”.
In his speech, the Secretary highlighted that the construction of the PIIDCT aims to create an attractive environment for cutting-edge innovation resources at an international level, attracting recognized science and technology companies, both domestic and foreign, to establish themselves in the territory. The official believes that the project “will not only open up broad perspectives for Macau's technological innovation industry, but will also bring new opportunities for the development of local young people”. As predicted, it will serve as a bridge between young people and technological innovation companies.
 
Open location
Remember that there are two possible locations: Wai Long Avenue and Zone E1 of the New Landfills. As for the first, the lot occupies a strategic position of industry-university-research, with favorable accessibility and transport conditions. In this case, the Park has 83 thousand square meters, including the slopes and the Taipa Grande Hill Tunnel. A maximum height of 70 meters is proposed.
The planning structure takes as its main axis the development chain of the industrial ecosystem, integrating the functions of research and development (R&amp;D), office and industrial production, and articulating exhibition spaces, landscape and productive services. In this way, the Park is organized by functional zones to support R&amp;D, production and manufacturing, covering a high-level innovation platform and applicational R&amp;D platform, customized factories and facilities to support industrial services.
The second location is the western portion of Zone E1, with the text praising the “privileged geographical conditions”. The idea is that the project adopts the concept of an ecological and low-carbon coastal park.
Here, the Park will have 177 thousand square meters. The maximum height will be 53 meters, with the project covering six plots of land. According to this hypothesis, the PIIDCT will include areas for digital technologies, integrated circuits, aerospace technologies, a data and computing center, an urban reception room, a public services pavilion, a riverside area, a landscape area and green spaces.</description><pubDate>2025-11-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Amendment to the Penal Code requires “careful analysis”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/alteracao-codigo-penal-exige-analise-cuidadosa/</link><description>Urged to review the Penal Code to toughen penalties for crimes of sexual abuse of minors, the Secretary for Security argued that more severe penalties may not necessarily be “the most effective solution” to the problem
 
The Secretary for Security, Chan Tsz King, considers that increasing penalties for child sexual abuse crimes may not be the “most effective” solution to deter criminals. The position was demonstrated during the discussion of the Lines of Government Action under his supervision, within the scope of some issues raised by deputy Loi I Weng.
Linked to the General Association of Women of Macau, the new deputy cited official data, recalling that in the first half of this year there were 19 crimes of sexual abuse of minors, including cases involving the sharing of pornographic images and situations in which elderly men abused girls in their own homes. In this regard, Loi I Weng called for amendments to the Penal Code to increase deterrence.
In the reply, Chan Tsz King argued that changing the Penal Code requires “careful analysis”. From his perspective, amendments to the Penal Code must be approached with “caution and seriousness”.
"Changes should not be made only in response to isolated and short-term cases, it is necessary to observe whether there is social consensus. The chapter on sexual crimes of the Penal Code was changed several years ago, with an increase in penalties", he stated. In this sense, he reiterated that it is necessary to carefully consider whether “increasing penalties is the most effective solution to the problem”.
Loi I Weng, in turn, stressed that there is room for improvement in terms of strengthening the protection of minors, particularly against sexual abuse. As he recalled, the 19 cases registered between January and June represented an increase of 46% compared to the same period last year.
As he noted, adolescents, and especially children, face a “high risk” of sexual abuse. Although she recognized that the 22 cases of child sexual abuse registered over the past year represented a decrease compared to 2023, the deputy considers that the number remains high compared to 2021 or 2019.
Furthermore, Loi I Weng also expressed concern about prostitution, stressing that cases can “influence the values ​​of young people”. Also in this case, the deputy considers that the measures applied by the authorities are not sufficient.
 
11 residents lured into scams abroad
The director of the Judiciary Police revealed that, since the second half of 2024, 11 residents, mostly young people, have been enticed to work in centers that engage in fraud activities abroad or have received fraud funds. Sit Chong Meng indicated that two of these people were safely repatriated from Cambodia and the remaining nine were detained in Taiwan for receiving fraudulent funds. Five are currently serving sentences, while four have already served their sentences and returned to Macau.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2025-11-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Suspicions of corruption add to the dimension of the tragedy in Hong Kong</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/actual/suspeitas-de-corrupcao-adensam-dimensao-da-tragedia-em-hong-kong/</link><description>In a climate of constant anguish, families and residents of the “Wang Fuk Court” housing complex in Hong Kong were still waiting yesterday for news about neighbors and loved ones trapped in the buildings hit by the huge fire that left at least 75 dead and more than 200 missing. Police detained three executives and consultants from the company responsible for the building renovations, while the Independent Commission Against Corruption promised a full investigation into possible corruption.

























The fire that consumed seven buildings in a residential complex in Hong Kong caused at least 75 deaths, including a firefighter, according to the latest data released by emergency services at the close of this edition, at a time when more than 200 people were still missing. The official report also included 76 injured people, 70 of whom were hospitalized.
At least 62 residents remained trapped in the rubble. Firefighters also confirmed the rescue of another survivor, a man found on the 16th floor staircase of one of the affected buildings.
The fire, which broke out on Wednesday afternoon, devastated seven of the eight 31-storey buildings that make up the “Wang Fuk Court” complex in the Tai Po district of the New Territories, becoming Hong Kong's worst urban fire in three decades. The fire started in a building and spread extremely quickly, fueled by bamboo scaffolding covered with safety nets, waterproof tarpaulins and expanded polystyrene sheets used in exterior renovation work that began in July 2024.
By early morning, the fires in the seven buildings were under control, with some flames remaining in only three of them, after almost 10 hours of continuous operations.
The Fire Department mobilized 1,250 people, 304 emergency vehicles, 26 specialized teams and four drones for aerial surveillance and continued to advance step by step in rescue and cooling operations. Authorities warned of the risk of partial collapse of the scaffolding, forcing teams to exercise extreme caution.
 
Possible corruption investigated
The Hong Kong Independent Anti-Corruption Commission (ICAC) announced the creation of a special team to investigate possible irregularities or corrupt practices in the renovation works of “Wang Fuk Court”, valued at HKD 330 million, in response to the “significant public interest” generated by the fire. The ICAC promised to “thoroughly” examine whether maintenance work may have involved “corrupt” practices or decisions that contributed to the rapid spread of the flames.
The police have already detained two directors and a consultant from the company “Prestige Construction &amp; Engineering”, on suspicion of negligent homicide. Additionally, agents carried out searches at the offices of the company that manages the complex and at the home of one of the suspects.
Describing the fire as a “major catastrophe”, the Chief Executive of Hong Kong assured that authorities will review whether ongoing projects comply with fire safety standards. “The Government has ordered all building complexes in the city that are undergoing major renovations to be inspected to check the safety of scaffolding and construction materials,” said John Lee.
Several residents of “Wang Fuk Court” told AFP that they did not hear any fire alarms and went door to door to alert neighbors.
Derek Armstrong Chan, deputy director of fire operations, said the temperature at the scene was “very high”. “On some floors, we couldn’t reach people asking for help, but we kept trying,” Chan said.
A Red Cross spokesperson explained to the EFE agency that eight shelters were set up, each receiving around 200 people, although many are constantly moving between hospitals, police stations and the fire perimeter in search of information about family and friends.
 
Wave of solidarity
The EFE agency also highlighted the monumental demonstration of solidarity: large companies donated shipments of water, portable batteries, thermal blankets, face masks and ready-to-eat meals. Several transportation companies offered vehicles and personnel to move supplies, while healthcare companies donated emergency equipment, portable fans, and psychological support equipment.
Shopping centers and hotels opened rest areas for rescuers and their families, and thousands of citizens went to hospitals to donate blood, to the point that the Blood Bank requested staggered visits due to overcrowding.
The wave of support intensified with announcements of help from the private sector. The Jack Ma Foundation, Alibaba and Ant Group have pledged 60 million HDD to support affected families and rescue services. Additionally, companies such as BYD, NetEase, Trip.com, ByteDance and Didi each donated 10 million to relief efforts.
This disaster far exceeds the death toll from the fire at the Garley Building in Kowloon in 1996, which left 41 dead and was, until then, the worst fire of its kind in Hong Kong in peacetime.
 
Xi calls for full commitment to rescue efforts
The Chinese President expressed condolences to the families of the victims and people affected by the fire in Hong Kong. Xi Jinping “attached great importance to the accident and immediately requested updates on rescue efforts and victims,” Xinhua reported. The President requested the Hong Kong and Macao Labor Department of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China and the Central Government Liaison Office in the HKSAR to support the local government in “all efforts to extinguish the fire, do everything possible in search and rescue, treat the injured and comfort the families of the victims”.
 
Fund of 300 million HKD created to help victims
The Hong Kong Government yesterday created a fund with 300 million local dollars for the victims of the fire in Tai Po. The Chief Executive said that the fund, created at the Bank of China, would start accepting donations from 7pm, and that the Government will distribute 10 thousand HKD dollars to each affected family. According to John Lee, the Department of Home Affairs and Youth has reserved 1,000 apartments in youth hostels and hotels for affected residents to stay for a maximum period of two weeks. They will then be transferred to 1,800 subsidized apartments reserved for them to settle in temporarily. Authorities will also make special arrangements for families in need of burial or cremation services. Civil servants will be mobilized to help with any follow-up and assistance work, Lee assured, adding that government-led commemorative events will be canceled for some time.
 
Legislative elections may be postponed
The leader of Hong Kong admitted yesterday that elections for the local parliament, scheduled for December 7, could be postponed following the fire. “We will carry out a thorough analysis and make a decision within a few days based on the overall interests of Hong Kong,” said John Lee, after an emergency meeting with government officials. The debates between candidates for the Legislative Council that were scheduled for yesterday and today were postponed, with no new date set. The remaining electoral campaign activities were also suspended, he told journalists. “The Government is committed to dealing with this major disaster”, he highlighted.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-11-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Military took power but there are different versions</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/actual/militares-tomaram-poder-mas-ha-diferentes-versoes/</link><description>The military took power in Guinea-Bissau, after a shootout that lasted around half an hour, according to a statement from the Guinean Armed Forces. The statement was read on state television TGB by the spokesman for the Military High Command, Dinis N'Tchama, who reports that the military has assumed leadership of the country.














There are, however, more complicated versions (read the piece with statements by activist Armando Lona) that say it was “a false coup d'état” to prevent the opposition's victory in Sunday's presidential elections.
The military's communication states that it was “established by the senior military leaders of the different branches of the Armed Forces, the Military High Command for the restoration of national security and public order”, which “has just assumed full State powers” ​​in Guinea-Bissau.
The Military High Command informs that it has deposed the President of the Republic, Umaro Sissoco Embaló, and that it has closed, “until further orders, all institutions of the Republic of Guinea-Bissau”. It also informs that “the activities of all media outlets” are suspended, as well as deciding to “immediately suspend the ongoing electoral process”.
The military also closed all borders, land, sea and national airspace, and established “mandatory curfew from 7:00 pm until 6:00 am, until the necessary conditions are restored to restore the constitutional normality of the Guinean State”.
In the statement, he explains that this is a reaction “to the discovery of an ongoing plan to destabilize the country”, attributed to “some national politicians with the participation of well-known national and foreign drug barons”. According to the military, the plan would consist of an “attempt to manipulate the results” of Sunday’s general elections, the release of which was scheduled for yesterday, with “a cache of war weapons” having been “discovered by the State Information Service” intended for “the implementation of this plan”.
The Military High Command will exercise State power “until the entire situation is adequately clarified and the conditions for a full return to constitutional normality are met”, he adds, appealing “for calm, for the collaboration of Guineans and for everyone’s understanding in the face of” the “serious situation imposed by a national emergency”.
Sources from the telecommunications sector told the local newspaper “O Democrat” yesterday that the military restricted access to social media platforms such as Facebook, TikTok and YouTube, to minimize the risk of disseminating content that could incite violence or misinformation.
The electoral observation missions of the African Union and the Community of Portuguese Speaking Countries had stated that the electoral process had taken place in an “orderly and organized” manner, calling for respect for the will of voters and democratic principles, in a preliminary assessment of the elections in Guinea-Bissau made at the beginning of the week.
On Tuesday, and after the candidate Fernando Dias da Costa had declared himself the winner of the elections without the need for a second round, Sissoco Embaló's spokesperson also said that “everything indicates that there will be no second round”, but did not discuss the results achieved by the then President of the Republic. At the time, Óscar Barbosa urged Guineans “to remain calm and wait for the election results to be released by the National Elections Commission, to be made on Thursday”.
The Portuguese Ministry of Foreign Affairs stated that constitutional normality had been interrupted and appealed for tranquility. It also calls for “the regular functioning of the institutions to be restored, so that the process of counting and announcing the electoral results can be completed”.
 
General Horta Inta-A sworn in as transitional president
General Horta Inta-A was yesterday sworn in as transitional President of Guinea-Bissau, in a ceremony that took place at the General Staff of the Guinean Armed Forces, one day after the military took power. The information was disseminated on the social networks of Guinean media outlets, namely Television of Guinea-Bissau (TGB). General Horta Inta-A, who will assume the position for one year, was appointed chief of the Private General Staff of President Umaro Sissoco Embaló, in 2023, but, days later, he was dismissed and appointed chief of the army General Staff.
 
Guterres expresses “deep concern”
The UN Secretary-General, António Guterres, is following the situation in Guinea-Bissau with “deep concern”, according to a statement released yesterday by his spokesman, Stéphane Dujarric. Guterres urged those involved in the current crisis to “exercise moderation” and “respect the rule of law”, adding that the UN “will continue to closely monitor developments in the country”. The UN chief's call for calm, according to the statement, is based on the fear of “a new institutional collapse, as the results of the presidential and legislative elections were awaited” in Guinea-Bissau. The elections were marked by “tensions, restrictions imposed on the opposition and accusations of manipulation”, according to the United Nations.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-11-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Demand for labor increased in banks</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/procura-de-mao-de-obra-aumentou-nos-bancos/</link><description>Vacancy and recruitment rates grew in the financial sector during the third quarter. At the end of September, banks alone had 256 jobs to be filled, according to official data
 
In the third quarter of this year, financial activities recorded 315 job vacancies, 107 more than in the same period of 2024, including 256 in banks (104 more) and 39 in insurance companies (one more). The total number of jobs to be filled also included 15 vacancies in the area of ​​financial intermediation (plus five) and five in auxiliary intermediation activities, a segment that covers exchange offices and rapid cash delivery companies, among other entities (minus three).
According to data released by the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC), the vacancy rate in banks rose 1.3 percentage points to 3.4% in the space of one year. On the other hand, this financial branch hired 329 workers in the third quarter (25 more in annual terms), reflecting a recruitment rate of 4.6% (0.4 percentage points more), DSEC indicated, underlining that “these indicators reflect an increase in demand for labor in banks”.
Higher education was required in 99.4% of vacancies in the financial activities sector, where the “majority” of jobs offered also required proficiency in Mandarin and English. In banks, Mandarin and English were included in the requirements of 97.7% and 93.4% of vacancies, percentages that also reached 92.3% and 100% in insurance. Furthermore, professional certification was required in 30.5% of vacancies in banks and 51.3% in insurance.
Official data also indicate that the financial activities sector employed a total of 8,546 full-time workers at the end of September, a similar number to that recorded a year earlier, with the majority being female (4,995). Banks alone had 7,225 full-time people and insurance had 840.
The average remuneration (excluding irregular remuneration) of full-time workers in financial activities was 32,460 patacas, representing an annual growth of 2%. Average salaries in banks (32,680 patacas), insurance companies (34,810), financial intermediation (30,720) and auxiliary activities in this area (18,630) rose by 1.8%, 2.9%, 3.9% and 3.8%, respectively, compared to the third quarter of 2024.
The statistics cover financial institutions subject to the supervision of the Macau Monetary Authority and exclude intermediaries and agents not directly linked to insurance companies.</description><pubDate>2025-11-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>ARTM charity project brought together 25 local chefs</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/projecto-de-caridade-da-artm-reuniu-25-chefs-locais/</link><description>“Recipes with a Hope”, a charity project carried out over two years by the Macau Drug Addict Rehabilitation Association, brought together 25 local chefs in the kitchen of “Old On To Hope”, in Coloane. During the sessions, a variety of dishes were prepared and illustrated in a book, scheduled for release tomorrow.
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
For two years, starting in 2023, the Macau Drug Addict Rehabilitation Association (ARTM) promoted a project involving local cooks interacting with residents of the “Old On to Hope” Center in Ká-Hó. The initiative resulted in the publication of a recipe book, which will be launched this Saturday, at 4pm, at the premises of the International Institute of Macau.
Augusto Nogueira, president of ARTM, told TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper that “the idea was to bring together the chefs to provide training to our residents of the center and publish a recipe book”. There were 25 local cooks from private restaurants or those belonging to gaming operators who participated in the sessions, “having created their own dishes and also prepared them for everyone present”.
The main objective of the event was “to provide an interesting experience for our residents, helping them to feel cared for by society”, says the director.
Many of the photographs captured during the activities, over 25 sessions, one for each chef, can be seen in the publication entitled “Recipes with a Hope”.
“The book will contain photographs of the dishes and recipes in English and Chinese, and will also have a few pages with photos of the exchange between the chefs and the residents, that is, of the interaction that, in essence, was the most important thing”, highlights the ARTM leader, adding that the work includes two or three recipes from the center's own chef and some residents.
As for the type of food, “we wanted this project to represent the most dominant gourmet in Macau, with the flavors that distinguish the territory's gastronomy, including, in a fusion of foods, Macanese, Portuguese, Chinese and an Indian dish”. The book shows recipes such as feijoada, cod, octopus, cataplana, seafood, rancho gordo, minchi, but also Chinese dishes and one Indian. Most of the recipes are original.
The association leader emphasizes that ARTM dedicated special attention to the project. “The interaction between everyone, through gastronomy, was something that worked in terms of charity and conviviality, constituting a very interesting initiative”.
Among the chefs who participated in the initiative, highlights include Martinho Moniz, Pedro Almeida, Hernandez, Justin, Desmond, Florita Alves, Antonieta Manhão (Neta) and cooks from the Galaxy, Wynn and Venetian restaurants.
At the launch ceremony, Augusto Nogueira will introduce the publication and some of the chefs will also speak and autograph the book, which will be available to anyone who wants to buy it.</description><pubDate>2025-11-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sands takes “best” from UTM to “École Ducasse”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sands-leva-melhores-da-utm-a-ecole-ducasse/</link><description>The new Sands China program will finance the training of the “best graduates” of UTM Culinary Arts Management at the “École Ducasse”, in France. Lasting two years, the training includes eight weeks at the prestigious French school
 
Sands China and the University of Tourism of Macau (UTM) will take the best graduates of the educational institution's Culinary Arts Management course to “École Ducasse”, in France, under the new Sands China Western Culinary Elite Program, after having signed a memorandum of understanding. The initiative, which includes an eight-week training course at the renowned French school, “aims to cultivate Western culinary talent and further strengthen collaboration between industry, academia and research”, says the gaming operator.
Using the “hiring and training” model, the new program is aimed at the best students on that UTM course. The idea is for participants to acquire knowledge about international culinary culture and professional standards. The training, which lasts two years, covers academic theory, professional certification and practical training in integrated resorts. Upon completion, they will be offered Cook I positions at Sands China.
“Talent development is not only key to a company's sustainable development, but also an essential part of Sands China's corporate social responsibility,” said Grant Chum, CEO of Sands China. "Therefore, we have consistently launched several talent development programs with various institutions. UTM is our long-time partner and we are delighted to sign a memorandum of understanding," he added, as quoted in a statement.
Chum went on to say that by supporting young local culinary talents to study at “École Ducasse”, he hopes that they can “enhance their skills and broaden their international perspectives”, thus enriching Macau’s talents.
Fanny Vong, dean of UTM, in turn, argued that “university education must go hand in hand with the needs of industry”. “Through this new partnership, our graduates will acquire practical training in integrated resorts, while studying abroad will broaden their intercultural horizons, further supporting the long-term growth of Macau’s tourism sector”, he anticipated.
Following the signing of the memorandum of understanding, Sands China and UTM held a symposium on Innovative Hotel Management, which explored the application and prospects of technologies such as artificial intelligence in the hotel industry. University experts and academics, Sands China management and industry representatives were invited to share ideas to inject new momentum into the sustainable development of the sector.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2025-11-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MSAR supportive and willing to help</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-solidaria-disposta-ajudar/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai expressed “heartfelt solidarity” with the victims and families of the fire in the Tai Po district, in Hong Kong, and was available for “any necessary assistance”. Following the tragedy, the Macao SAR Government called for “increased awareness” about the risks of fire and “strengthening preventive measures”
 
The Chief Executive of the Macao SAR offered “his most sincere condolences” for the fatalities of the fire that devastated several residential buildings in the Tai Po district, in Hong Kong, and conveyed “his heartfelt solidarity” to the families and those injured.
According to a statement, in contact with his HKSAR counterpart, John Lee, Sam Hou Fai stressed that “the close relations between Macau and Hong Kong are like those of brothers who feel the same sadness and share the same grief”. The Macao SAR Government was also available to “provide any necessary assistance”.
The Macao SAR Executive called, however, for “increased awareness against fires and the reinforcement of preventive measures” for all sectors of society. “Autumn and winter are considered a period of high incidence of fires, and the competent services, as always, adequately carried out the necessary work arrangements”, says a statement from the Social Communication Office.
Different Government departments carried out inspections at multiple construction sites, “to understand the various work processes”, verify fire resistance certificates and test results for scaffolding and safety nets”, as well as other “relevant preventive measures”.
During inspections, contractors indicated that “manufacturers provide fire resistance documentation for materials”, and that tests are carried out “on each batch of materials received, including combustion tests, to evaluate fire resistance”.
The Fire Department, the Directorate of Land and Urban Construction Services, the Directorate of Labor Affairs Services and the Institute for Municipal Affairs will also inspect constructions on Rua de São Paulo, Rua do Almirante Costa Cabral and in the north zone and examine the closed areas, in addition to consulting the respective contractors, in order to “promote awareness of fire safety”.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-11-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Almost 1,000 TNR sent for repatriation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/quase-1-000-tnr-encaminhados-para-repatriamento/</link><description>During the first two phases of the joint operation “Trovoada 2025” carried out by the police authorities of Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau, in the territory, the Unitary Police Services (SPU) of Macau reinforced inspection and identification actions in the Macao SAR, having carried out 906 inspections in 2,210 locations. As part of the operations carried out, 991 non-resident individuals were intercepted, and they were sent to the repatriation process for committing crimes, illegal immigration, overstaying, illicit exchange practices, prostitution, among others. Following the interventions, 163 individuals were arrested for theft, as well as 140 in cases of exploiting illicit exchange for gambling. There were also 14 situations of illicit exploitation of online games of chance or online mutual betting, resulting in the arrest of 21 individuals. Regarding drug cases, it is worth noting the detection of 20 people involved, including 11 related to drug trafficking. Authorities seized 3,098.76 grams of cocaine and 271.64 grams of cigarette oil containing “synthetic cannabinoids.” In addition, the police detained 40 individuals for criminal association and 17 for exploiting prostitution. As part of this operation, 586 people were referred to the judiciary for prosecution on suspicion of committing a crime, 20 of whom were subject to preventive detention, one was sentenced to prison and two were detained at the Juvenile Institute.</description><pubDate>2025-11-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Grand consumer prize has already generated benefits of 328 million</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/grande-premio-de-consumo-ja-gerou-beneficios-de-328-milhoes/</link><description>As of November 16, the accumulated value of electronic benefits used in the Grand Prix for Consumption in community areas exceeded 328 million patacas. The 13-week program, which began on September 1st, will end this Sunday. The organization of the plan, under the responsibility of the Directorate of Economic and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), aims, “through the joint effort of all parties”, to encourage residents to consume in community neighborhoods on weekends, thus promoting “the local consumption cycle” and reinforcing the “confidence of small and medium-sized companies in their operation”. The promotional activity allows for immediate discount benefits with a Macau Pass card. DSEDT reminds that elderly people who have not yet used the benefits can go to more than 100 designated service stations until the end of the month, in order to obtain an immediate discount of 500 patacas, by topping up the Macau Pass Card for Seniors. Until today, holders of the Disability Assessment Registration Card can present the card at institutions and centers coordinated by the Institute of Social Action to collect the Social Care Card with 500 patacas in immediate discount benefits. After the end of the plan, the unused amount will automatically be reset to zero, but the amount loaded with your own money will not be affected and can be used normally.</description><pubDate>2025-11-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CEM joins six operators to promote green energy</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cem-une-se-as-seis-operadoras-para-promover-energia-verde/</link><description>The Macau Electricity Company (CEM) has established a memorandum of understanding on cooperation for sustainable development with the six gaming operators. The partnership aims to promote the application and popularization of green energy. “As an important component of Macau’s electricity consumption, the participation of integrated resort and leisure companies is of great importance in driving green transformation,” CEM said in a statement. The company states that, in 2023, “the Studio City photovoltaic power generation project was successfully connected to the electricity grid, becoming Macau's first megawatt-scale photovoltaic solar power generation project”. The agreement came on the occasion of the “Round Table on the Cross-Border Development of Guangdong-Macau Green Electricity Certificates (GEC), organized by CEM and China Southern Power Grid International (GSGI), which covered topics such as “green energy”, “Guangdong-Macao cooperation” and “GEC and green electricity”. During the seminar, another agreement was sealed between CEM and GSGI, marking a new stage in green energy cooperation. Following the memorandum, both parties will adopt, “in an innovative way”, a “dual agency” model, a mechanism that will create an “efficient and convenient” GEC “cross-border marketing platform”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IAM transfers monkeys from Flora to Seac Pai Van</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/iam-transfere-macacos-da-flora-para-seac-pai-van/</link><description>At the beginning of December, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) will transfer the 11 monkeys from Jardim da Flora to Seac Pai Van Park, to “provide them with a more comfortable habitat”. The IAM guarantees that the decision took into account “the safety and health of the animals”, and was taken after consulting the opinions of animal husbandry experts from Mainland China. According to the organization, the monkey area in Jardim da Flora has been used for many years and the cages have suffered various damages, from the detachment of concrete to the exposure of steel reinforcement. Furthermore, some visitors feed the monkeys, which poses a risk to the animals' health and can lead to the transmission of diseases. On the other hand, the Monkey Pavilion in Seac Pai Van Park offers “a nature-like layout” and its activity space includes a wide variety of plants and perches for the animals to practice climbing. Each activity location is connected to the animal house, inside which a temperature adjustment system is installed, to guarantee a comfortable living and resting space, according to different climates.</description><pubDate>2025-11-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mother of North Korean abduction victim regrets passing 48 years without reunion</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/mae-de-vitima-de-rapto-pela-coreia-norte-lamenta-passagem-de-48-anos-sem-reencontro/</link><description>On November 15th, it was 48 years since the disappearance of Megumi Yokota, symbolic victim of the abduction of Japanese citizens by North Korea decades ago, and her mother. Sakie continues to regret the long period without progress in the case.
Mrs Yokota, 89, told journalists ahead of the anniversary that the prolonged separation leaves her “in shock” but still clings to the hope of a reunion, after she and other family members of those abducted appealed to Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi and US President Donald Trump to bring their loved ones back.
Megumi disappeared at the age of 13, while returning home from badminton training at her high school in Niigata, on the coast of the Sea of ​​Japan, on November 15, 1977.
“It was as if I had been thrown into total darkness,” said mother Yokota, recalling her desperate search for her daughter. “I cried and screamed every day.”
Twenty years later, in 1997, Japanese police stated that Megumi had been kidnapped by North Korea and, in the same year, Yokota and her husband, Shigeru, founded the kidnapped families group. Since then, the couple have led the campaign to bring the victims back. But her husband passed away in 2020.
Over the years, Yokota has repeatedly expressed outrage at the lack of progress regarding the abductions, describing them as “a terrible thing.”
Mrs. Yokota, who turns 90 in February, admits that she feels exhausted: "I have exhausted my energy and willpower. Sometimes I think I may never see her again."
However, he said he has “high expectations” that Prime Minister Takaichi can move things forward. Takaichi met with the families of kidnapping victims just two days after taking office, and also stated that he had proposed a summit meeting with North Korean leader Kim Jong-un.
"There is no time to waste when it comes to solving this problem. I would like to obtain a concrete result" through a meeting with Kim, Takaichi told reporters on November 14.
Donald Trump, during his visit to Japan for talks with Takaichi, also met with the families, including Yokota, and reiterated his commitment to the issue, saying: “We always have this in mind”.
Ms Yokota said at a recent meeting with her supporters: "I have had a truly sad feeling for many, many years. I know she is there (in North Korea), but I can't see her or hear her voice. But, I believe she is fine."
Megumi is among 17 Japanese citizens that the Japanese government officially lists as having been abducted by North Korea throughout the 1970s and 1980s. The government also alleges Pyongyang's involvement in many other disappearances.
The Kyodo agency recalls that in 2002, five kidnapped people were returned, after the then Japanese Prime Minister, Junichiro Koizumi, met with Kim Jong Il, in Pyongyang, on September 17 of that year, the first summit between the two countries that do not maintain diplomatic relations.
 
JTM with international news agencies</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>