<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>37% of cases instituted by DSAT are based on complaints against buses</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/37-dos-casos-instaurados-pela-dsat-tem-por-base-queixas-contra-autocarros/</link><description>The complaints that arrived at DSAT in the first half of this year aimed at large parts the buses - there were 1,002, making 37% of the total complaints (2,710). Data on information requests and complaints also show that second and third places emerge trafficking facilities and taxi services
 
Catarina Pereira
 
In the first half of this year, the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) received a total of 2,710 complaints from the population - in the first quarter were 1,340, a number that rose slightly to 1,370 in the second quarter. Buses, traffic premises and taxis occupy the first three places under the processes based on citizens' complaints, reveal data from the organism analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao.
The buses motivated the opening of 1,002 cases (522 in the first quarter and 480 in the second quarter) between January and June this year, representing 37% of the total complaints. However, in concrete, DSAT does not indicate what type of complaints were made. It should be noted that, in the same period, the number of passengers in TCM and Transmac transport services grew by 2.25%, in annual terms, to 113 million passengers.
There are then cases related to planning and traffic equipment facilities originated 516 processes (264 in the first quarter against 252 in the second), while related to taxis originated 309 cases (152 against 157).
The other DSAT data relating to taxis point out that in the first semester, 580 complaints were made by the drivers' attitude in the service (443), taxi equipment (12) and “other” not specified (58). They also state that 67 suggestions were made in this context.
Returning to the main types of cases instituted by DSAT based on the complaints, there are also the auto-siles, totaling 211, and vehicle-related issues, which totaled 151 over the first half.
Regarding the total complaints answered (2,710), 1,408 arrived at the body through electronic mail, followed by the open line (679), “others”-which includes cases presented by correspondence and transfer by other government departments-(578), and public service (45).
According to the statistical data available, in the first six months of 2025, the public addressed the body a total of 30,820 requests of information. Questions related to the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge lead information requests made through telephone call, making 3,698, while vehicle inspection is the second topic that raises the most issues by the population (2,726 requests).
Third and fourth places are requests for information related to the driving license (2,176) and the circulation of Macao vehicles in Guangdong Province (2,093). Finally, there are also many issues involving vehicle affairs, not specified by DSAT, specifically 1,757 cases.</description><pubDate>2025-09-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Tapah passage forced 18 hours of signal 8</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/passagem-tapah-obrigou-18-horas-de-sinal-8/</link><description>The passage of the Tapah tropical cyclone just 110 kilometers from Macao forced the meteorological authorities to make the tropical storm signal 8, which in force for 18 hours. This was the ninth tropical storm affecting Macau this year, something that has not happened since 1993, according to weather and geophysical services. Civil protection recorded dozens of incidents and four injured, and there are “light floods” in the mud and in the interior port area. Classes were suspended and public services were closed



















Pedro Milheirão
Sign 8 of Tropical Storm was in force for 18 hours due to the Tapah tropical cyclone, which rode to 110 kilometers away from Macau. Sign 8 was lifted at 9 pm on Sunday, when the Chief Executive declared the immediate prevention state by order, having been maintained until 15h00 yesterday. According to Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG), Tapah was the ninth tropical cyclone to affect the territory this year - since 1993 there was no such high number in one year.
In a balance of the authorities' response work, Secretary for Security, Wong Sio Chak, advanced yesterday that until late afternoon, four injuries had been recorded, including three with light injuries and a person who needed to be hospitalized.
Until early afternoon, the Civil Protection Operations Center (COPC) had recorded 25 occurrences on the peninsula and one on the islands. In addition, 13 users were received by the emergency reception centers of the Social Action Institute. The COPC assistance line, in turn, received 23 requests for information related to the storm.
In the mud and in the interior port area were “light floods”, and in Coloane there was an increase in water level along the coast. Still, some commercial establishments remained in operation.
According to the SMG, the forecast of the cyclone was a "huge challenge." During the period when the eight sign was in force, "the sustained maximum winds of 10 minutes recorded in the four macao bridges were of levels 8 and 9 with gusts of 10," the body explained. He also added that the astronomical tide in conjunction with the “Storm Surge” raised the water level by about one meter, while the maximum height of the registered tide was 3.7 meters.
Because of the storm, the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services suspended classes at all levels of non-superior education. Scheduled for yesterday, the reception to the students of the Portuguese School of Macau was eventually postponed to today.
Public services were also closed throughout the day and the same happened with the Consulate General of Portugal. The banks did not open either, according to a statement from the Banks Association.
According to the civil aviation authority, until 14h00, more than a hundred flights scheduled at Macau airport were affected by Tapah. In concrete, 81 were canceled, 29 were delays and nine underwent schedules. In addition, about 100 flights from Hong Kong airport were also canceled, according to the neighboring region's press.
Traffic on Ponte Flor de Lotus was suspended, such as the generality of public transport services, which made about 100 residents and visitors retained at the Hengqin border post, waiting for taxi services. Police officers were highlighted to the site "to maintain order," the Chinese press said.
In “close connection with game concessionaires”, the inspection and coordination of games coordinated the preparation work of rest areas for workers and customers in the operators' enclosures to avoid traveling.
Sign 8 was replaced by 3 at 15h00 yesterday, with the different public transportation services reaped in operation. The circulation of buses between the Macao border post and Hong Kong airport was also gradually resumed. The Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs Services and Maritime Link Operators coordinated, in turn, the resuming of trips from the outdoor port and the mud to Hong Kong.
Wong Sio Chak considered that "all members of the civil protection structure have demonstrated full communication and narrow coordination." For Wong, the alerts issued, mobilizations and preventive measures reflected "the strong awareness of the crisis of the members of the structure."
 
Sam Hou Fai praised “high level of alert”
Shortly before signal 8 and decree the immediate prevention state, Sam Hou Fai presided over a working meeting in the COPC to a hellish preparations for the Tapah Typhoon passage, according to a statement from the media. The head of the government stated that "due to the successive passage of tropical cyclones through Macao, in recent months, the structure of civil protection has continued its alert and has done numerous preparative work of immediate reaction." "With the continuous improvement of the civil protection mechanism and the facilities against wind and flooding, the accumulation of experience of services and institutions," allowed to "maintain a high level of alert," he said.
At the time, it also required the “planning of restoration work of the normality of the post-tuff city”, in order to mitigate the impact on traveling residents of different services and schools. In addition, he asked the different departments to prepare plans well “from the removal of obstacles on public roads and the elimination of potential dangers”.
The leader of the MSAR has requested even more coordination and communication between the different departments of the government, installing them to “closely monitor the low zones, ensure the normal functioning of drainage systems, prepare evacuation plans (…) to minimize risks to the population”.
For Sam Hou Fai, "the works of civil protection must be implemented based on coordination between the government and the participation of civil society, the associations, and through the conjugated force between the authorities, residents and associations, allowing to increase the effectiveness and capacity of full prevention and reaction against natural disasters."
In turn, Wong Sio Chak stated that the COPC "implemented all countertop prevention and flooding measures." The secretary also added that all members of civil protection were "on a state of warning and immediate reaction," ready to "act urgently and protect with the life and goods of residents with all the efforts."
 
Authorities completed tests on the Macau Bridge
The vehicle circulation test on the Macau Bridge with Sign 8 was completed, for which public works services, services for traffic issues and meteorological and geophysicists highlighted multiple vehicles and analysis technicians. The various departments are now integrating the data and will “analyze and evaluate the specific details of the implementation of vehicle circulation plans on the Macau Bridge,” the organisms indicated. Prioritizing public safety, the authorities will define and disseminate the provisions related to the types of vehicles authorized to circulate on the bridge during signal 8, as well as circulation rules and restrictions.</description><pubDate>2025-09-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>"We are determined to give citizens more voice"</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/estamos-determinados-dar-mais-voz-aos-cidadaos/</link><description>Candidate number 5 list for direct suffrage, the union for development, says he wants to “give more voice to citizens” and ensures that their candidates “can take the well-being pulse of the population more accurately and provide more practical and viable solutions”. In an interview with the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the team points to the goal of winning three seats in Hemiciclo, promising that it will ensure that legal provisions "correspond to the actual development of Macao and that they can make themselves the rights and interests of workers." On the other hand, it emphasizes that it advocates strong support for small and medium enterprises and will seek the elevation of basic labor criteria
 
What led to the Union list for development to apply for the Legislative Assembly?
-In 1992, even before Macao's return to the country, the Union for Development (Upod) began to apply for elections for the Legislative Assembly (AL). Since then, in over 30 years, he has never failed to apply for legislative elections, having remained at his post. This time, our team left again and we are determined to give citizens more voice and play a more active supervisory role in AL.
 
What way is this candidacy different from the rest?
-A AL is not only a legislative body, but also an important platform that transmits public opinion and oversees the governmental actions. Many of the UPod candidates come from workers' and professional sector associations. Upod deeply knows the real life difficulties of basic -level citizens and, at the same time, also realizes the fundamental role that professionals play in social development. Therefore, our candidates can take the well-being pulse of the population more accurately and provide more practical and viable solutions to citizens.
 
What are the priority problems and what solutions propose to solve them?
-In the transformation of the economy of Macao and the modification of social structure, Upod considers employment, social benefits and the development of young people as the essential and priority issues of their political program. Regarding the employment issue, Upod advocates several measures taken simultaneously. In the short term, UPOD suggests the implementation of a “non -resident workers' departure mechanism”, the revision of the TNR hiring dimension in companies and application of multidimensional indicators in the evaluation of human resources demand to reserve more employment opportunities for residents. In addition, we will look for the optimization of labor rights and interests, including raising the various basic labor criteria. In the long run, UPod supports the “1+4” diversified development strategy advocated by the government. At the same time, it advocates reinforcing support for game -related sectors, in order to create more high quality and high -tech jobs, widening young people's access to professional rise.
In terms of social benefits, UPod's political program reflects the idea of ​​“being oriented to people”. Upod will support the government to further establish the welfare protection system of the population that encompasses "the entire life cycle and all areas of life." The concrete measures we advocate include the improvement of the pension adjustment mechanism for the elderly, widening the coverage of subsidies, promoting family -friendly measures, as well as the optimization of caregiver support resources. Upod emphasizes the aim of allowing all residents - especially the elderly, women and needy groups - effectively benefit from the fruits of social development, ensuring the quality and dignity of life of residents.
Regarding the development of young people, UPod also defends the priority execution of the principle of prioritizing the hiring of residents, rigorous implementation of the law that “defines the basis of employment policy and labor rights” and the law of hiring non -resident workers, as well as the cautious assessment of the dimension and number of young college students and local graduates, especially in the importation of advanced level professionals, who belong to category 3 From the qualified framework of capturing, to ensure that their imports of tables do not affect the employment opportunities of local graduates.
Simultaneously, UPod advocates strongly support Small and Medium Enterprises (SMEs), develop new Macau Quality Productive Forces according to local conditions, boost the growth of companies with “specialized, refined, distinct and innovative” development characteristics, to guide companies to reduce policies operating costs and establish an inclusive economic system to stimulate SME dynamics. In addition, the government must provide more financial incentives and tax benefits for companies, as well as technical advice and management services, to raise operational efficiency and business competitiveness. On the other hand, we will drive the government to help create a SME financing guarantee mechanism, in order to relieve companies' financing difficulties, thus giving impetus to the sustainable and healthy development of companies.
 
What are the expectations in terms of elections? How many seats do you expect to win at the Legislative Assembly?
-In these elections, Upod will try to win three seats, hoping to further reinforce, in AL, the degree of supervision of government actions. Upod considers that AL deputies should play a positive role inside and outside the hemiciclo. In AL, UPod will, through interpeação and interventions, constantly oversee the governance of the Executive in accordance with the law. At the level of legislative work, UPod promises - through consulting workers and citizens of various sectors and industries widely - ensuring that legal provisions correspond to the actual development of Macao and that they can protect workers' rights and interests at most, seeking greater consensus for the whole of society.
 
JTM and Electoral Act
In accordance with the electoral law, the Jornal Tribuna de Macao continues to cover the campaign for legislative elections on September 14. Like previous years, we will adopt a model that aims to inform our readers about the ideas defended by the various candidacies, under the premise of granting the same journalistic treatment to all competing lists in direct suffrage. Without prejudice to any general reports on the elections, never focused on specific lists, we will present interviews with the different candidacy teams, which will be entitled to a page until the campaign is closed, naturally without any charges for the lists, as a way to provide a public interest service to readers.
In this sense, we sent a fixed set of questions to all applications, whose answers will be published over the next few days, in increasing order of the number of the lists in the voting newsletters, among those we have received until the day of production of the edition.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-09-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>University students can be cultural ambassadors</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/universitarios-podem-ser-embaixadores-culturais/</link><description>The Cultural Institute is looking for young college students to play the role of cultural ambassadors within the East Asia City. The program unfolds in three phases, and in the last young people will make study visits to South Korea and Japan
 
To promote the fundamental values ​​of “coexistence, innovation and harmony” of the city of Culture of East Asia and “deepen the understanding and knowledge of Macao young people about the cultures of the East Asia region”, as well as foster cooperation and exchange exchange, the Cultural Institute (IC) is recruiting college students to play the role of cultural ambassadors. In this sense, the body invites all young people from Macao, between 18 and 25, who are attending higher education institutions to participate in this exchange visiting program.
Divided into three phases, the program runs between October and November. In the first phase, participants will attend, in Macao, general knowledge courses on culture. “The goal is to deepen the knowledge in Macao's history and culture, so topics such as social customs, artistic characteristics and multiculturalism in the region will be addressed,” explains the body led by Leong Wai Man.
In a second phase, young people will be involved in cultural exchange activities with young people from the cities designated Cultural Cities of East Asia 2025, namely Anseong (South Korea) and Kamakura (Japan) ”. The idea is that young people, as cultural ambassadors, “guide their Japanese and South Korean counterparts on a visit to Macau, promoting the role of the city as a 'exchange and cooperation platform, centered on Chinese culture and characterized by multicultural coexistence',” reads the press note.
In the last phase of the program, young people will travel to the cities of Anseong and Kamakura, where they will conduct study visits and cultural exchange activities. Macao young people should spread the characteristics of Chinese culture, "sharing China's stories in these places."
A participação tem um custo de 3.000 patacas por pessoa, sendo que estão isentos de pagamento os participantes que, no acto de apresentação da candidatura, se encontrem em situação de carência económica devidamente comprovada pelo Instituto de Acção Social.
Interested students may submit the registration form duly completed, along with the necessary documents, until September 12, in the Cultural Institute building, or email to [Email Protected].
The CI will proceed with the selection and will choose between 25 and 30 participants. Regulation and details about the registration process are available on the IC website.
Through this program, the body expects to “promote the development of young talents, to contain an international cultural exchange platform, to expand the international view and cultural literacy of young people, in order to contribute to the preservation and innovation of Macao's cultural heritage”.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-09-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Relationship between Portugal and China is “quite defurched”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/relacionamento-entre-portugal-china-esta-bastante-desanuviado/</link><description>Minister of State and Foreign Affairs, Paulo Rangel, (3-E) during the meeting with his Chinese counterpart Wang Wang Wang (2-D), which took place at the Great People's Palace in Beijing, China, September 8, 2025. António Cotrim/Lusa



The Portuguese Minister of Foreign Affairs highlighted yesterday “The Single Role” that China may have with Russia from persuasion to a negotiating commitment to Ukraine, and classified the relationship between Portugal and China as “quite decanced”. Paulo Rangel spoke to the Portuguese Social Communication in Beijing, after a meeting with his Chinese counterpart, Wang Yi, in the Great Palace of the People, and which served as a preparation for the official visit that Prime Minister Luís Montenegro, holds this country from today.
"It was a meeting that went very well, in which there was a great convergence of points of view regarding the issues we have to take to the international agenda and where there is a good relationship, a very unanoured relationship between Portugal and the Popular Republic of China," he said.
In the short initial intervention at the meeting at the Great Palace of the People, the Minister of Foreign Affairs of China defended the importance of the “multilateral system, centered on the United Nations and International Law”. According to the simultaneous translation of his intervention, Wang Yi argued that the current international situation "makes dialogue and cooperation more urgent" and stressed the initiative of President XI Jinping Global Governance, "joint work for human progress." "I hope and I believe that the prime minister's visit will promote advances in bilateral relations and face challenges," he said.
Asked how the defense of multilateralism advocated by both ministers with the meeting in Beijing of Chinese leaders, Xi Jinping, Russian, Vladimir Putin, and North Korean, Kim Jong-un, in a military arrest that marked the 80th anniversary of the end of World War II, Rangel made a point of “separating” both plans. "China has always defended, at the level of principles, multilateralism and the United Nations Charter and the position of international institutions and even their reform," he said.
The government number two said, by the way, that Portugal “counts a lot with China to play a major influence to bring the Russian federation to accept a ceasefire and a business-either business process” in Ukraine, stressing that it is “a single role that few world powers will have”.
On the other hand, he separated the timing of the first-minister's visit, already scheduled for this meeting in Beijing, which deserved strong criticism from the European Union. "A trip to Japan was scheduled in the first half and one to China in the second half. Because of the [early legislature] elections, we had to compress things, we have local elections, we have presidential elections," he said.
Asked if there was any sensitivity in the authorities of both countries by visits glued to China and Japan -precisely when China celebrates 80 years of victory over the Japanese in World War II -the minister responded negatively. "These are two countries that we have known 500 years ago and have had relations with us for 500 years, of course they understand," he said.
Rangel admitted that the initial idea "was to make two even longer trips to each of them," but this was not possible due to the political crisis. "Which, by the way, now happened in Japan, we do not know if this will still have any impact on this visit, it is likely to have," he said, referring to the dismissal announced on Saturday by Japanese Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba.
The Portuguese Prime Minister today begins an official visit to China for two days, during which he will have a meeting with President Xi Jinping and will pass Macao, then heading to Japan, where he will be until Friday, with tickets for Tokyo and Osaka.
 
Sara Madeira, sent from Lusa agency. Edited text</description><pubDate>2025-09-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New connection to Hengqin may be maritime or terrestrial</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/nova-ligacao-hengqin-podera-ser-maritima-ou-terrestre/</link><description>The government is studying the need and feasibility of planning, in an appropriate place, a new land or maritime access with direct connection with Hengqin. On the other hand, the cooperation zone is conducting preliminary studies on the stroke, the form of construction and the size of the project. The objective is to learn about the transport needs between Hengqin and Macau
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Given the creation of the Shizimen Regional Modal Center for Regional Cooperation, provided for in the Director Plan, the Government is studying the need and feasibility of planning, in an appropriate place, a new terrestrial or maritime access with direct connection with Hengqin, “actively developing corresponding work”.
In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Nick Law, the Directorate of Public Works (DSOP) services recalls that the Secretary's Office for Administration and Justice stressed that, in January this year, the “General Planning of the Territorial Space of the Deepened Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin (2021-2035)”, which clearly defines the planning of the meter network is clearly defined. Light Hengqin-Macau.
On the other hand, the same plan foresees the reservation of space for the new border access between the cooperation zone and Macao, in order to precipate important conditions for the subsequent development of the integration of transport systems between the two regions.
Thus, says the text signed by the director of DSOP, Lam Wai Hou Hou Hou Hou Hou the cooperation zone is conducting preliminary studies on the layout, form of construction and dimension of the new border access, “with a view to integrating the transmitting transmitting needs Hengqin-Macau”, as well as proceeding to “comparative analysis of connection projects and their viability”.
The respective projects include highways, bridges, tunnels, rail systems, among other modes of travel.
In the answer, it is stated that the management of services to traffic issues stressed that it will continue to collaborate with the planning services, issuing opinions on the Road Connection project of the Shizimen Regional Modal Cooperation Center, with the aim of “ensuring that the new access not only responds to the growing searches of traffic on both sides, but also ensures lasting support for coordinated regional development”.
It should be noted that more than 28,000 residents of Macau lived and worked in Hengqin at the end of the first half of this year, according to the direction of administrative affairs services in the deepened cooperation zone. In annual terms, hengqin inhabitants and workers in hengqin grew more than 30% and 14%, respectively. On the occasion of the 4th anniversary of the cooperation zone, the Hengqin authorities also indicated that, at the end of July this year, Hengqin had 7,303 Macao capital companies, reflecting a 57.5% rise since this zone was created.</description><pubDate>2025-09-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MPOP Style Brand Electoral Campaign</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/estilo-mpop-marca-campanha-eleitoral/</link><description>Crowded audience, all dressed in the list gowns; Chinese drums next to the stage and above candidates and supporters, various microphones, music and choreographies, is the campaign for Macao legislatures, “MPOP” style.
The microphones change hands, reproducing the same slogans with different voices, in short and acute scales, which end almost all in a party instruction. At this point, the drums are listened to loudly and the audience reproduces the last note heard, while shaking the political 'merchandising' that is handed over to the start of the rally: plastic hands to clap, numbers on the list with led lights, malleable straws, fans, all with the same color. In the end, some of these props will be collected.
Campaign actions in Macao, restricted to the last two weeks before legislative elections scheduled for the 14th, do not assume the purpose of informing. There are no speeches at the events of the six lists that will elect 14 of the 33 deputies to the Legislative Assembly. Another 12 are chosen by indirect suffrage through associations, and seven will be appointed by the executive leader, Sam Hou Fai.
The events resemble pop concerts, gender "kpop", among the lists led by younger candidates, or genus "Pop Old-Style", with Elvis and Olivia Newton John Risen, and even Chinese, between lists led by candidates with another court.
These MPOP -style rallies are practically ignored by the population - and when not ignored, some result in complaints to the Electoral Affairs Commission, which has admitted them, but stressed, by the voice of its president, Seng Ioi Man, which, "during the election campaign period, propaganda is a necessity."
The concentrations are made up of the members of the lists and the people mobilized by them, some and the other dresses with the same uniforms. But there are no politicians on stage and spectators listening to them. In these events, politicians assume themselves as artists. On the other hand, there are no audiences either, because these are part of the choreography, play a role. Finally, there are very few people besides and each other, that is, people watching who are not directly linked to the lists.
Abstention is the great ghost that hangs over the whole process, which takes place for the first time under the framing of the new Electoral Law of April 2024, designed to "reinforce the implementation of the" Macao Macao governed by Patriotas "principle.
Ilia Chou, 40, an employee of the financial sector, was with a child and a friend watching one of these rallies and seemed to be one of those few people present not involved in the campaign list. He agreed to talk to Lusa after he had spoken to another microphone.
Ilia was attracted to the list that was there because those people have a "young and community aspect" and are concerned with "offering prospects for progress" to young people.
"Given the current challenging economic climate, we face a critical question: our young people now have fewer options than before. This specific aspect is what attracts me most in this initiative," he said.
But “other groups also talk about youth and employment, what are the differences? Why do you like this particular group?” We asked. "I don't know them [the other groups]. Well, I was attracted to the charming characters of this list," he replied.
"I think these four characters quite charming," Ilia added, they talk about "love, the title is very charming, and the color is pink, it looks very welcoming."
It's not just the campaign that is childish and infantilizer. The political programs themselves are, without exception, lists of requests to an “provider father”, incarnated by the executive, who has the responsibility of managing a comfortable and growing financial reserve, fueled by the six game dealers in Macao.
Lists want to be applied to things like the creation of a development fund and the reversal of 10% of profits for distribution by all citizens, want to increase pensions or more money in consumer coupons, subsidies and maternity licenses, want more social housing, want free health and higher education, or simply require greater annual money distribution.
There are also more sophisticated demands, such as promoting the diversification of the economy, measures to support the transformation and modernization of small and medium enterprises or development of the intelligent city, but the most significant part of the six lists programs points directly to the distribution of money by the provider father, in the most varied forms. The other recipients of the requests are the game dealers, to which the candidates go with warnings that they are determined to defend the priority of residents in access to the best paid jobs.
Macao's unemployment rate is at 2% and permanent residents at 2.6%. That is, technically, Macau has full employment. However, as Lusa told a candidate, the employment issue has nothing to do with statistics, it just holds on with "perception." Like almost everything in this campaign.
 
Agostinho Leite and Jing Wu, from Lusa. Edited text</description><pubDate>2025-09-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Fringe already animates the neighborhoods of the city</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/fringe-ja-anima-os-bairros-da-cidade/</link><description>There are several shows that the public can watch over the coming weeks, between immersive and interactive theaters, concerts and workshops. The Fringe Festival runs until the end of the month and “several artistic surprises” already “emerge in the neighborhoods”
 
The 23rd Fringe Festival, which runs until September 28, is already cheering up the city and will bring a series of shows and activities to the communities, within the Extra Festival. “Throughout various paths of the city of Macau several artistic surprises emerge in the neighborhoods,” describes the Cultural Institute (IC), adding that tickets are still available for some of the shows.
We highlight some of the shows that will take place over the coming weeks. First of all, "thanks for being here" is an immersive theatrical experience that promises to take viewers for three timelines: the past's past "self" to dance freely in nightclubs, his "self" present "drowned in the choro of the baby" and his future "self" to get lost. "
A production from Suzuki Cheng, with interpretation of his own and from Moon to Ieong, the theater lasts about an hour and a half, being the cost of the 120 -pass ticket. The play, which will take place at Bookand on 16, 17 and 19 at 8:30 pm, is played in Cantonense and addresses “The Battlefield of Parentality, where husbands are powerless, the silent judgment of society over the 'perfect mother' and the blurred contours of their own face in the mirror”. The public will be invited to move during the show, so the use of comfortable clothing is advised.
In the context of the Association's show for the development of herbal tea culture, the new generation herbalist master presents an unprecedented infusion - the “multifunctional herbal tea”, designed as a ritualized response to the “seven sins”, which condition contemporary urban life.
The conception is by Jason Fong, while production was up to Ieong Pui San and the interpretation of Jason Fong and AK. The show will take place on the 19th and 20th, at 6:30 pm, 19h45 and 21h00, with a cost of 80 PATACA. Interpreted in Cantonense, the piece has a duration of about 45 minutes.
As for free admission productions, Fringe offers a series of them. For example, “The Monster”, to happen on the 12th and 21st, from 10h00 to 21h00, in the parish of São Lázaro. This is “an immersive and personal adventure theater”, argued by Nero Lio, production of Erik Kuong and Barrie Law's dramaturgy.
“This innovative digital interactive theater experience redefines the limits of traditional representation. Through an application, participants become the protagonists-journalists in charge of unraveling the truth behind a mysterious creature,” reads the description of the Fringe page.
Registration has to be made until September 20, through the single account, and to participate, a mobile device compatible with iOS 15.0 (or higher) or Android 9.0 (or higher) is required. The application offers interfaces in Chinese and English. The program does not have a fixed start or end time, and participants can start when they want. The aim is to follow the tracks, explore the corners of the city and navigate urban landscapes and the virtual world.
On the other hand, Jazzés &amp; The Blackbird is "where jazz wins wings." Celebrating the 70th anniversary of Charlie Parker's death, Casa de Portugal presents a jazz concert in honor of the legendary saxophonist. The concert will be held on the porch of the headquarters of Casa de Portugal, with an artistic installation of giant birds by Elisa Vilaça.
Three musicians - Tomás Ramos de Deus, Miguel Andrade and Paulo Pereira - will interpret themes such as “Bye Bye Blackbird”, “Moon River” and “Ipanema Girl”, some of which with original band arrangements. The concert will last about half an hour on 22 and 23, at 1:30 pm and 3:30 pm.
The complete Fringe program can be consulted online. Several workshops and sessions are scheduled such as "Can the immersive acts fail?" and “Interactive Medicinal Tea Workshop”. In “Exchange Fringe: Contact with other festivals” are invited representatives of international festivals to share experiences and promote joint reflection sessions.
Due to the passage of Taphon “Tapah”, some activities were postponed and others canceled. The Cultural Institute has said it will reimburse the value of tickets.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-09-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Students will “socialize more” without mobile phones at EPM</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/alunos-vao-socializar-mais-sem-telemoveis-na-epm/</link><description>Students of all levels of the Portuguese School of Macao will, from today, not to be able to use mobile phones inside the facilities. The measure arises following guidelines imposed by education and youth development services. Parents heard by the Jornal Tribuna de Macau are clearly accordingly and believe that there will be more interaction among students. A teacher says it is “a great, well-implemented measure”, because at this moment “children are alone with a mobile phone”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Starting this morning, when the doors of the Portuguese School of Macao (EPM) open for another school year, students will be required to leave their mobile phones in the entrance of the educational establishment. Parents and guardians have learned of the measures imposed on the use of mobile phones within the facilities, which is now prohibited.
Through its official website, the school board issued a statement explaining the new rules. Specifically, students will have to turn off their mobile phones and place them in the cliffs that will be on site for this purpose. Smartphones cannot be used at intervals and can only be removed from cacifos at lunch break and when students return home.
However, there will be exceptions. According to the statement, parents and in charge of education should communicate to class directors in writing if students need to use their mobile phones in exceptional situations. In addition, EPM says it will provide a landline at the school entrance with the porter to be used in emergency situations.
However, students will be able to access mobile phones for learning purposes, “but only under the guidance of teachers,” says EPM.
The notice signed by the director, Acácio de Brito, explains that these are guidelines of the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ), which aims to reduce the dependence of these devices by students and follow the world's trend.
For the Parents Association of the Portuguese School of Macao (APEP), this is a “widespread measure of the DSEDJ”. According to the president of APEP, "it will be the DSEDJ that, in principle, will provide the cabinets or the cliffs to put at the entrance of the school to store the mobile phones."
Since the little ones, in primary, do not have these devices, should be about 600 mobile phones to control, which, in the opinion of Filipe Figueiredo, "it will be easy to do, because if they do not fulfill they are violating a guidance of the school."
The leader points out that the issue was not placed within classes, but fundamentally at intervals. "Many kids were sitting by phone in hand, with no socialization and interaction," he stresses, adding that "in this first phase there is some change in a habit, which will not be easy, but then the role of continuous assistants will be important to help control and adapt."
The EPM even sent questionnaires to parents about whether or not they agree with the measure and only about 20% whether they opposed the ban. The guardians that JTM has now contacted (who preferred not to disclose their identity) recognize that the measure is "very good", because "that's what is happening in Portugal and around the world."
A father said his daughter "only had a mobile phone around 12 years old," stating that "children use and abuse their mobile phone and that only hurts the brain, they are apathetic." One mother recognizes that she is currently "an exaggeration", having reached a "point without control."
A teacher for several years to teach in the EPM also left his testimony. "I think from now on the relationship between students will be frankly better, they will live more at break time, because we often see five or six kids without a device around a colleague to play on the mobile phone, which is not healthy." “Our children are alone with a mobile phone” and now they have the opportunity to “socialize more,” he said.
The teacher considers that it is "a great, well -implemented measure" to "develop the interpersonal relationship between them more, to talk more, because I believe they will find a way to occupy those 20 minutes." It recognizes, however, that there will be some initial pressure: "Let's go a week, perhaps, when they won't know what to do, they will walk like that, not knowing how to use their hands, but it will be a matter of habit."
Regarding the difficulty of contacting parents, he says that "this is a myth," stressing that "those who have never used mobile phones have always been able to contact their parents through the secretary, or through any school teacher."
The EPM starts today for another school year, on a day that is essentially intended for students reception. Wednesday morning, the school receives the visit of the Prime Minister of Portugal, Luís Montenegro.</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>FINAM receives “Portuguese soul” for the third consecutive year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/fimm-recebe-alma-portuguesa-pelo-terceiro-ano-consecutivo/</link><description>For the third following edition, Fado returns to the Macao International Music Festival, with the voice of Cuca Roseta, who will act with the Chinese orchestra. Between October and November, international renowned musicians and young places will act at the event, which also includes workshops, lectures, behind -the -scenes visits, theater and other initiatives

























Pedro Milheirão
Cuca Roseta will act at the 37th International Music Festival of Macau (FINAM), accompanied by the Chinese Orchestra of Macao, in an interpretation “of the Portuguese Soul” scheduled for October 11 at the Cultural Center, according to the Cultural Institute (IC). It is the third consecutive time that a fadista brings the “sound of Portugal” to the end, after Gisela João and Mariza had acted in 2023 in 2024, respectively. The festival runs from October 3 to November 8 and includes 12 “spectacular” programs and 14 activities. The budget for this edition reaches 25.5 million patacas, about 23% less than last year.
With the theme “Vocal Waves”, the event organized by the IC will bring renowned musicians and rising talents, in a “deep resonance” between the East and the West. The trio consisting of Wu Wei, a famous “Sheng” player, Martin Stegner, a violence of the Berlin and Janne Saksala Philharmonic, willingly, will feature the show “The Sheng in his best”.
In turn, Svetlana Zakharova, an illustrious dancer, and her husband Vadim Repin, violinist, will lead the show “Duets on the fingertips”, with the Macao orchestra and several main dancers from Ballet Bolshoi. Violinist Daniel Hope and the Swiss Gstaad Festival Orchestra will present “The Four Stations” by Antonio Vivaldi and a minimalist reinterpretation of Max Richter's same work.
Baritone Thomas Hampson will interpret “The Magic Horn of the Boy” and “Youth Songs”, in an evocation of Gustav Mahler's “Complex Psychological Landscapes”, demonstrating the composer's “unlimited fascination”. In addition, the “English Concert” and the Sonia Chamber Choir will bring themes by George Frideric Handel, Giovanni Pierluigi of the lecture, Johann Sebastian Bach and Arvo Pärt.
Six young local talents, namely Wang Iat Ham Sabrina, Cheong Tin Ut, Wong Hei U, Lam Cheok Seng, Wu Freya Ka Yu and U Weng Kei, will have the opportunity to act with professional Macao orchestra musicians and Chinese orchestra of Macao.
This year's edition will also have two commemorative concerts, from the 80th anniversary of the victory in the War of Resistance of the Chinese people against the Japanese aggression and the 120th anniversary of the birth of Xian Xinghai, a musician born in Macao. The Chinese orchestra of Macau will present “legacies running in the river”, while the Macao orchestra of Macau and Cheong Hoi Leong, a young pianist from Macao, will present “The Yellow River”.
SJM and FINAM will co-organize the show “Carmen-Opera in four acts of Georges Bizet” to mark the 150th anniversary of the death of the French musician. Maestro Eivind Gullberg Jensen will lead Zurich's opera and the “Opera Comic de Paris”, in collaboration with the Macao Orchestra, the China National Symphony Orchestra Choir and the Macao Youth Choir. This classical opera concert will explore the “timeless theme of humanity through moving and moving songs”.
In another performance, organized by Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, Mikhail Pletnev and the Rachmaninoff International Orchestra will guide the audience on a “exciting and moving trip for Russian music”. The pianist, who "dominates the essence of the Russian school", and the orchestra, known for his "deep" interpretations, will present the four "Rachmaninoff piano concerts".
Within the activities program, interested parties will be able to know the Bizet Genius, in the lecture “Conversation: Unraveling Carmen”, as well as participating in a visit behind the scenes of the respective spectacle. In the improvisation workshop, composer Wu Wei will share a mixture of “traditional instruments and innovative performance techniques”, while the Hong Kong group “Singers Yat Po” will lead the “Workshop to Cappella”.
In addition, the same group will hold two demonstrations of “This Victoria has no secrets - The Theater A Cappella”, in the side space of Jardim da Cidade das Flores and Urban Park of Areia Preta.
Inserted in the program “Music on Screen: Cinemateca Passion”, several film projections will offer the audience “a deeper view and a close meeting with the multiple dimensions of music”.
The “Enjoy Macao” will put the tickets on sale from September 13, with various discounts, and registration for activities will be open from the 12th.</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Montenegro's visit shows appreciation of the Portuguese presence</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/visita-de-montenegro-mostra-valorizacao-da-presenca-lusa/</link><description>EPA12351598 Portuguese Prime Minister Luis Montenegro Talks to the Press to the Council of Minister Meeting Held at the Prime Minister's Official Residence in S. Bento Palace, Lisbon, Portugal, 04 SEPTEMBER 2025. AT LAST 17 PEOPLE DIED IN THE DERAILMENT OF THE GLORIA LIFT ON 03 SEPTEMBER, and 22 Others Were Injured, Emergency Services Reported.  EPA/TIAGO PETINGA



Macau will be a point of passage to the Portuguese Prime Minister, as part of an official visit to China, where he will meet with Chinese President Xi Jipping and his counterpart, Li Qiang. In the territory, Luís Montenegro will, among other points, meet the Chief Executive and visit the Portuguese school, as I had already reported by this newspaper. The visit to the MSAR is a sign given to China that the country continues to value the Portuguese presence in the region, said source of the Portuguese ruler's office
 
The short passage of the Portuguese Prime Minister by Macao is framed as a sign to China that the country continues to value the Portuguese presence in the region, especially in the dimensions of language and culture, and that "are the singularities" of the Misrem that make it "a success case," Luís Montenegro's office from Lusa told Lusa.
The first point on Montenegro's agenda in the territory is a meeting with the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, on Wednesday morning. There is a visit to the Portuguese School of Macao and a reception to the Portuguese community, with a walk through the streets of the region where it will visit the ruins of São Paulo and Senate Largo.
The coming to MSar comes in the context of an official visit to China, as this newspaper had already reported, at the invitation of the Prime Minister of the Council, I read Qiang.
The same source stressed Lusa that the visit to China is part of the “diplomatic tradition” of Portugal, as all heads of state and several prime ministers visited the country.
The delegation, on the government side, is the Minister of State and Foreign Affairs, Paulo Rangel, and the Minister of Economics and Territorial Cohesion, Manuel Castro Almeida, as well as the president of AICEP, Madalena Oliveira e Silva.
According to the provisional program, Luís Montenegro will land in Beijing this afternoon, accompanied by his wife, and will be received with a ceremony that includes a guard of honor. For today, only a walk is expected to be a section of the Great Wall of China.
The official agenda starts tomorrow, with a crown of flower deposition ceremony in the monument to the heroes of the people, in Tiananmen Square, then followed the prime minister to the People's Palace.
In addition to the meeting with the President of the Popular Republic of China, Xi Jinping-the most significant politically because the Chinese head of state receives a few foreign prime ministers-Montenegro will first meet with the president of the China National Assembly, Zhao Leji.
He will then visit the forbidden city, before a working meeting with the Chinese Prime Minister, Li Qiang, where a bilateral legal instrument signing ceremony is planned.
In this part of the visit, we highlight the “at the highest level” meetings with Xi Jinping, with whom it is anticipated that Montenegro addresses “the international context”, and with Li Qiang, in a meeting where the war in Ukraine should be on the table.
In economic terms, the purpose of the visit to China is to improve trade balance between the two countries, "strongly unbalanced" in favor of Beijing, and some memorandum of understanding in the agrifooding area should be signed. Portugal will transmit to China that "believes in a rules -based commercial system," the same source said.
 
More investment in Japan
The five-day trip, until Friday, also includes a passage through Japan. It is there that Montenegro follows after the coming to the mashes. In Tokyo, he will meet with his counterpart, Shigeru Ishiba, with a joint press conference at the end.
Then, the head of the Portuguese government will go to Keidanren (Japanese Business Federation), "where they will have meetings with high representatives of about one dozen Japanese multinational companies."
Montenegro will also visit the place where the Portuguese team for the Athletics World Cup and, in the late afternoon, will chair the signing of a memorandum of understanding between AICEP and its Japanese equivalent, Jetro.
On the last day, he will travel by train to Nagoia, then departed to the last point of the program, the visit to Expo Osaka. Prior to the visit to the Portugal and Japan pavilions, a lunch for all the Portuguese delegation prepared by four hands is planned by the heads of Kitchen Pedro Lemos and Yoshida San.
Expo Osaka ends on October 13 and Portugal is one of 161 countries present. Portuguese participation has as its theme “Ocean: Blue Dialogue”, with the involvement of more than 150 companies, associations, municipalities and national artists.
In Japan, the goal is first to increase the country's investment in Portugal and try to diversify it beyond the auto industry. On the other hand, Portugal wants to “raise the degree of the political and diplomatic relationship with Japan” for a strategy partnership, which will imply more mechanisms for bilateral relations and greater cultural exchange.
In São Bento, it is noteworthy that "there is a great coincidence of the positions of Japan and the European Union in relation to the Ukraine War and the Middle East."
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Public officials without punishment in case of abstention in the elections</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/funcionarios-publicos-sem-punicao-em-caso-de-abstencao-nas-eleicoes/</link><description>People who work in the civil service who cannot vote "will not face any disciplinary measures." The words are from the chairman of the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly, following the sending of the Chief Executive, a letter to civil servants to appeal to the vote
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Public officials, although, by law, the right and duty to vote as voters, “they will not face any disciplinary responsibilities” if they abstain in the elections on the 14th, according to statements by the President of the Legislative Assembly Electoral Affairs Committee (Caeal).
Seng Ioi Man reiterated, however, the appeal to all voters, including civil servants, to exercise their right and civic duty, stating that the government has instructed services to perform the necessary procedures to facilitate the vote of employees working.
The words of Caeal's guardian arose in response to questions about the letter sent by the Chief Executive to civil servants, in which Sam Hou Fai appeals to the vote “actively”, saying that it is a way of demonstrating fidelity to the masters.
According to the latest available data, at the end of 2023, Macau had just under 34,300 civil service workers (38,000 in early 2020), which represents about 10% of the total number of census voters.
"The universe of eligible voters is about 320 thousand, so our recipients are all eligible voters, we have not made a statistics, a certain profession, their rate, etc., but we appeal to all voters to vote on election day," said Seng Ioi Man, quoted by Lusa.
Seng Ioi Man spoke on the sidelines of a survey of the replica of the Voting Assembly in the TAP Seac Multiportive Pavilion on the first day of activity, with a view to verifying the facilities and operation.
As he explained, through the improvement of replicas, the body expects to “increase the attention of all social sectors of Macau to the elections of the Legislative Assembly (AL), to appeal to voters to actively vote and deepen civic education with young people and students”.
The two replicas, elaborated according to the actual assemblies, are in the TAP Seac multipurpose pavilion and the Macao Forum, being open to the public for seven days, including weekends. Seng Ioi Man stressed that the increase in number and opening days aims to attract and facilitate resident visits.
After the CAEAL verification, it was confirmed that the location, the designed guiding routes and other provisions "meet the expected requirements, thus providing better experience for voters to vote, and also accelerate the voting process."
The number one of Caeal also pointed out that the experiences on voting assembly replicas "can help voters master the correct method of marking the voting report and vote effectively on election day." The two simulations will become voting assemblies, with some adjustments in the facilities.
Seng Ioi Man recalled that the election campaign period, which began on August 30, entered its eighth day, and has "elapsed well, in an orderly manner and all lists disclosed their political programs according to the law."
He appealed to candidates to take advantage of time and to inform “efficiently voters” so that they decide their choices “according to their ideas and exercise their voting rights”.
It also took advantage of the occasion to mention that the Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) organized more than 2,600 higher education, secondary and young students to the replicas of the voting Assembly, giving “dynamic civic education classes, to greater awareness of the law, duty and civic responsibility”. At the same time, DSEDJ encouraged qualified teachers and young people to go to the polls.</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Authorities test circulation on the Macau bridge with signal 8</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/autoridades-testam-circulacao-na-ponte-macau-sinal-8/</link><description>The circulation of cars on the Macau Bridge will be tested, with vehicles designated for this purpose, when the next 8 8 sign 8 of Tropical Storm, the authorities announced. Last night, meteorological and geophysical services issued signal 8 due to the passage of the Tapah tropical storm. For today, floods are foreseen in the interior port, from 0.5 meters to 1.0 meters, due to the astronomical tide and the impact of “Storm Surge”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Authorities will take advantage of Tropical Storm signal 8 to start an essay on vehicle circulation on the Macao Bridge, indicated the directions of public works services (DSOP), services to traffic affairs (DSAT) and Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG). Sign 8 was emitted over the past night due to the approximation of the Tapah tropical storm.
"In order to master the concrete situation of circulation on the Macau bridge under adverse weather conditions and further improve the disposition of circulation, it is planned to prepare vehicles designated for the conduct of a circulation test during the period of the next typhoon signal 8," said the three organisms in a statement issued on Saturday. The objective is to “ensure the safety of vehicle driving by citizens under adverse weather conditions”.
However, the analysis of the data on the wind speed collected on the Macao bridge board has already been completed when the “Wipha” typhoon passage. According to the results of the analysis, “the installation and effect of counter-time barriers on the Macau Bridge respond to the conception requirements, and the basic conditions of conditioned circulation under the specific adverse weather conditions”.
According to wind speed monitoring data on the board, "the wind force is in the acceptable area." However, taking into account the principles of prudence and security, “it is still necessary to perform the vehicle circulation test on site, during the passage of signal 8, to master its concrete situation, in order to ensure the safety of vehicle driving by citizens,” the services point out.
In this sense, the authorities state that, when issuing signal 8, the government will prepare vehicles designated for the conduct of the circulation test, hoping that, “through the respective data and the result of the test on site, an evaluation of the various provisions, namely the type of vehicles that may circulate on the Macau Bridge, the circulation rules and the restrictions, during the period of the Typhoon signal 8”.
Prior to the completion of the test and evaluation, the Macao Bridge will continue to maintain the current provisions, ie it will be closed simultaneously with the remaining maritime bridges, when signal 8 or higher. "The Government of Masters appeals to citizens so that during the passage of Typhoon, as far as possible, be in a safe place, reducing the travels and closely following the official information to be disclosed," the organisms asked.
"If the data of this test correspond to safety conditions, the Macau bridge will be opened during the passage of the signal 8," they conclude.
 
“Tapah” can go 150 km from Macau
Yesterday, the SMG predicted that “Tapah”, located in the northern part of the Southern Sea of ​​China, would move from north to northwest, towards the west coast of Guangdong and gradually intensify.
Although the circulation of “Tapah” was relatively small, according to the trajectory expected yesterday, the tropical storm would pass within 150 km southwest of Macau today, early in the day, and the possibility of intensification at the height of its coastal proximity cannot be excluded. Hence the probability of significance of the signal at night was "relatively high".
It was expected that today could occur floods in the inner port, with height between 0.5 and 1.0 meters, due to the astronomical tide in the coming days and the impact of “Storm Surge”.
However, DSOP has attached contingency measures against Typhoon, the Cultural Institute appealed to the head of heritage buildings to take adequate prevention measures and the direction of maritime and water services services appealed to the maritime sector to take precautions against the tropical storm.
Also the Institute of Social Action has asked social equipment and the population to adopt preventive measures against Typhoon and possible floods, while tourism services warned visitors to be aware of the information.
In turn, the Consumer Council (CC) has asked commercial establishments to present the prices of goods and services “clearly and accurately” and not to increase prices under the pretext of the Typhoon's passage. The CC has already ensured that the inspection mechanism has been activated.
Sign 1 of tropical storm was issued at 00h30 on Saturday, and signal 3 was lifted at 08h00 yesterday, and was then replaced by signal 8 to 21h00.</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Jim Jarmusch wins a golden lion with 'Father Mother Sister Brother'</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/jim-jarmusch-ganha-leao-de-ouro-father-mother-sister-brother/</link><description>EPASELECT EPA12358370 US Director Jim Jarmusch Poses with His Golden Lion for Beast Film Award for 'Father Sister Brother' During the Closing and Awards Ceremony of the 82nd Annual Venice International Film Festival, In Venice, Italy, 06 SEPETEMBER 2025. EPA/ETTORE FERRARI



“Father Mother Sister Sister Brother” by American director Jim Jarmusch, took the Golden Lion of the 82nd edition of the Venice Festival over the weekend, which awarded the second award of the show “The Voice of Hind Rajab”, a film on the war in Gaza from Franco-Tunisian Kaouther Ben Hania.
Twenty -one films played the coveted prize, granted by a jury chaired by American filmmaker Alexander Payne.
In his new production, Jarmusch explores family relationships through three distinct stories, set in New York, Dublin and Paris, starring Cate Blanchett, Adam Driver and Tom Waits.
The director himself called his work "anti-action movie" and, upon receiving the award, thanked "for enjoying our quiet movie."
In the second position, with the silver lion, was the impactful “The Voice of Hind Rajab”, a feature film by Franco-Tunisian Ben Hania, who, after being received with a 23-minute ovation during the official screening, was pointed as a favorite for the maximum award.
The plot is based on the real story of a Palestinian girl, Hind Rajab, murdered by Israelites forces while trying to escape the city of Gaza in January 2024. In the film were used the real recordings of calls with Hind Rajab relief requests to a center of the Ramallah Ramal Crescent Organization in Ramallah, West Bank.
"Cinema cannot return it or erase the atrocity committed against it, nothing can restore what was raised from it, but cinema can preserve its voice and make it resonate through borders," the director said when he received the prize alluding to Rajab. "I hope this movie will help end the war," he added.
Great productions, such as Netflix's “Frankenstein”, directed by Guillermo Del Toro and produced by the streaming service; Noah Baumbach's “Jay Kelly” and Yorgos Lanthimos's latest movie “Bugonia”, starring Emma Stone, came out empty -handed.
This 82nd edition was full of stars, with a red rug for which they paraded - on a few days under rain - George Clooney, Julia Roberts and Jacob Elderi, who plays a captivating Frankenstein monster.
Among all the actors and actresses of the official show films, the jury awarded the work of Toni Servillo and Chinese Xin Zhilei, awarded the Volpi Cup.
Serilllo won the best actor award for his role in Paolo Sorrentino's “La Grazia”, in which he plays an Italian president who reaches the end of his term with the dilemma of approving or not a law of euthanasia and two indulgers.
Chinese Xin Zhilei got the best actress Volpi Cup for her work on Cai Shangjun's “The Sun Rises on Us”, in which she plays a woman consumed by remorse, which is surprised by the return of an old lover with whom she shares a dark past.
At the Horizontes Show, dedicated to new trends, Mexican director David Pablos got the best film award for “En El Camino”, a love story marked by the violence that plagues northern Mexico between a young man who flees from the past and a truck driver who helps him.
“This movie comes from a very personal place […] and it's beautiful to see that you turn on with so many people,” said the filmmaker upon receiving the prize.
The jury of the Horizontes Show also recognized Ecuadorian Ana Cristina Barragán, screenwriter and director of the movie “Hiedra”, winner of the best script award. The film tells the story of the meeting between Azucena and Julio, two young people who carry childhood wounds. She had to leave her son who had a girl, and he, who grew up in a home, for never meeting his parents.
Since the show began on August 27, the glamor of the festival has been overshadowed at various times by the devastating situation in the Gaza Strip, the scene of a war triggered by the attack of the Palestinian Islamist movement Hamas on October 7, 2023 in Israel.
A collective founded by 10 Italian filmmakers, Venice4Palestine, published an open letter condemning the war and several personalities were pronounced against the Israeli offensive.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-09-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>