<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Government prepares introduction of four more substances in the control list</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-prepara-introducao-de-mais-quatro-substancias-na-lista-de-controlo/</link><description>The government wants to conclude this year the legislative process to add four more substances, including “ethomidate” in the control list. This "new drug" has already been regulated inside China in Hong Kong and Taiwan. Augusto Nogueira, president of the Macao Toxicode Rehabilitation Association, considers that, in this way, “authorities can combat illegal trafficking” of “ethomidate”

Catarina Pereira
 
The “ethomidate” - intravenous hypnotic of short action, indicated for the induction of general anesthesia - has been used by young people for consumption through electronic cigarettes. In Hong Kong, authorities suspect that at least three deaths are related to this substance, also known as “space oil”. Here, authorities have discovered, since 2023, at least four cases linked to the use of this "new drug". In this sense, and after the Judicial Police proposed the regulation, the government aims to include the “ethomidate”, and three other substances, in the list of control during this year.
In the context of drug-associated crime and to “be able to avoid a possible Low-Land Effect in Macao, the drug fighting commission, after performing an exhaustive review, suggested to the government of Ethomyidate inclusion, and three similar substances (metomyidat, prophaxate and isopropoxate), adding them to the law.” The revelation was made by the Secretary's Chief of Staff for Security, Chang Cheong, in response to an interpellation of Deputy Ella Law.
According to Chang Cheong, security authorities have already completed the work of improving the text of the bill of the law proposal and "will present it timely to the Executive Board for consideration." The idea, he added, is “to complete the legislative process in this year”. The "ethomidate" is not yet subject to the international convention, but in recent years, the interior of China, Hong Kong and Taiwan have regulated this substance.
Augusto Nogueira, president of the Macao toxicodependent Rehabilitation Association, told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that the “ethomyidate” has been used in the composition of the known “Space Oil” drug ”by its Zombie Drug effects, quite harmful to mental health, causing addition”. Although it has medical value, Augusto Nogueira considers that, being placed on the control list, "authorities may combat illegal trafficking."
Since it came into force in 2009, the Drug Fighting Law has been reviewed and annually new types of drugs are controlled in accordance with the decisions of the United Nations Commission for Drags. So far, seven changes have been made and more than 70 types of substances and pre-care has been added to the list of substances subject to control, “in order to ensure that substances controlled in Macao coincide with those included in the International Control list and are tendinally similar to those who are controlled in neighboring jurisdictions, to prevent new types of drugs” in the territory.
In addition to regulating this substance, Ella Lei argued that Macau should reinforce prevention and that authorities should take as reference the introduction of kits - already used in Hong Kong by the authorities - to accelerate the detection of suspicious cases. I also wanted to know the balance of the pilot project released last year about the fight against drugs and which results were obtained.
Wong Sio Chak's chief of staff stressed that security authorities "have paid more attention to drug -related issues, increasing prevention and combat, with a view to resolutely intercepting the drug entry into Macao from the source." Pointing out that customs services and police have been maintained “in close connection with the similar entities of neighboring regions and have increased the exchange of information,” Chang Cheong adds that to prevent residents from bringing articles that contain “ethomyidate” technology is used to “improve police work”.
It also states that it is continued to “optimize” police organization, including the introduction of technological equipment, such as portable devices for drug detection, postal order inspection systems, goods and vehicle inspection systems, as well as security control systems for visitors and luggage and travel articles. "These drug detection devices have the function of quickly and accurately detecting 'ethomidate' and similar psychoactive substances," he said.
In addition, he recalled that in February and March, PJ sent staff to Hong Kong to exchange police experiences in this area, and also continues to “optimize” detection technology to increase the effectiveness of work in this context.
 
“Ethomidate” represented 3.4% of the tests in 2024
As for the “Pilot Program on New Drug Test”, promoted by the Institute of Social Action (IAS) to “evaluate the risks linked to abusive use in Macao, of some substances that are not yet internationally controlled”, it is said that the test data of 2024 showed that “ethomidate” represents 3.4% of total positive urine tests. It is not said, however, how many tests were performed and which group of people was tested.
"IAS closely followed the respective cases, providing individualized counseling plans and, at the same time, based on these data, integrated the substances with greater risk of abuse in the regular urine testing program for toxicode dependents in treatment."</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Science Center registered a 16% increase in operational losses</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/centro-de-ciencia-registou-subida-de-16-nos-prejuizos-operacionais/</link><description>Last year, the Society of the Science Center registered operating revenues of 16.14 million patacas, an annual break of 20%. In addition, operational losses before government subsidies rose 16% to 141 million
 
Prior to the executive's subsidies, the Macao Center of Sciences, S.A. suffered operational losses of 141 million patacas in 2024, which translates into a 15.8% increase in the 121.7 million losses in 2023, the audited financial statements of this public capital company reveal.
In total, the Science Center received subsidies of over 140.9 million by 2024, an annual increase of 15.8%.
Regarding operating revenues, the center registered an annual break from 20% to 16.14 million, resulting in a decrease of about 13.4% to 20.8 million in the company's total revenues.
The Chapter of Expenses points to a rise from almost 11%to 161.8 million compared to 2023. The company spent almost 9.17 million patacas in the field of education, dissemination and campaign (+11.8%), 6.93 million in short-term exposure activities (-33.8%), 6.96 million in safety services (+20.6%) and 4.82 million in repair work (-21.6%).
In addition, the Science Center raised 3.34 million patacas last year with rent, which means an annual climb of 25.5%. On the other hand, tickets generated revenues of 10.72 million, more 9.3% than a year earlier.
Regarding activities, the report shows that the Science Center received more than 715,000 visits, an annual increase of 8%. Among local visitors, there was an increase of 4.3% to more than 287 thousand, while in the non-places there was an increase of 8.1% to over 337 thousand. In another segment, the center served more than 67,800 visitors, a growth of 9.8%.
As for the distribution of visitors, the exhibition center attracted 73.8%, while 13.4% visited the planetarium and 12.7% were at the Convention Center.
In addition, in 2024, thanks to the festive activities promoted in the heart -shaped tree square, the flow of participants in convention and exhibition activities has reached the highest level since the inauguration of the Science Center. In total, 217 convention and exhibition activities were promoted, while the center's spaces were leased 808 times for activities of this nature. In total, they captivated about 91,300 participants, plus 22%.
According to the report, the spaces intended for conventions and exhibitions registered, in general, a "satisfactory" lease. For example, the heart -shaped tree square has been leased 116 times, a 22%rise.
In addition, the Center inquired users of 135 convention and exhibition activities, which awarded 4.96 points, from zero to five, to describe the degree of satisfaction with spaces, environment, equipment and services.
Regarding 217 activities, those in the category “Education and Training” had the highest percentage (41% of the total), although 17.4% compared to 2023. Several activities were also organized in the areas of “information and other technologies” (27% of the total), “Culture and Arts” (14%) and “Medicine and Health” (6%), which grew by 74%, 94% and 71%, 94%, 94%, 94% and 71%, 94% and 71%, 94% and 71% respectively.
Already in the sphere of science education, the Science Center cooperated with 117 school units, an increase of 10.4%. The number of activities organized together grew 2.4% to 1,729, but there was a decrease of 8.9% to more than 62,000 participating students. In addition, the Center participated in the formation of 2,478 teachers, a decrease of 16%. At the same time, the number of participants in science education activities rose 2.4% to over 145 thousand (3,891 activities, +12.9%).
The report explains that to “increase the quality and depth of activities”, the center has reduced large surface activities, but increased more interactive deep cooperation programs. The company believes that although the number of participants in some programs, the effectiveness of learning and the level of satisfaction increased among students, which “corresponds to the strategic goals of the long term science center”.
 
“Aumentar a reputação internacional”
Generally speaking, society points out that, "in terms of the operational model, the Science Center has actively widened sources of revenue and sought to raise operational efficiency through the reform of the internal system, which has allowed significant advances in the aspects of scientific education, teacher education and science and innovation frames."
Regarding this year, Sio Hon Pan, director of the space, stressed that the center will reinforce cooperation with government, science and technology companies and educational institutions to promote the multilevel formation of science and technology talents. At the same time, it will strengthen international exchange and cooperation, that is “importing and exporting more concepts of science education and high advanced technologies, playing the role of bridge between Macao and Lusophone countries in exchanges in science education and science and technology, as well as increasing the international reputation of the Center for Science”.
In addition, it mentioned the task of reinforcing the constitution of the team of science education staff, professional quality and the pedagogical capacity of science and technology teachers.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>2019 candidates want lower prices from economic houses</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/candidatos-de-2019-querem-precos-mais-baixos-das-casas-economicas/</link><description>He was handed over to the executive chief, by candidates of the 2019 contest, a petition on the prices of economic houses. Require prices to be adjusted in the fractions of the three lots of zone A
 
A 2019 Economic Housing Price Follow -up Group delivered a petition to the Chief Executive on Sunday, complaining against “too high and unreasonable” prices of such houses in zone A of new landfills. Candidates even said prices "are higher than those adopted in the past" and warned that, consequently, "some households can give up buying houses." In this sense, they expect the government to review the values.
These candidates for the 2019 contest can purchase houses in lots B4, B9 and B10 in zone A, totaling 3,017 fractions. Currently, the phase of choosing apartments takes place.
According to the group representative, Man Chao, quoted by the Chinese language press, the price in these three lots is defined according to the former Economic Housing Law, that is, about 35,600 patacas per square meter, equivalent to 3,300 patacas per square foot, while the bonus ratio is 64.4% to 64.5%. However, it states that this price is much higher than that applied to the fractions whose selected households have already moved before 2019, which is about 1,900 patacas per square foot, with a subsidiary range ranging from 50% to 60%.
Noting that the government has been emphasizing that prices are linked to the market situation, Man Chao points out that prices have increased more than 70%. For the group, "this approach is not preceded or based on reasonable foundations," leading to "disappointment" among some candidates and making them feel "in a dilemma".
The group's representative stressed that, according to the former Housing and Connemic Housing Law, the prices of these homes have to contemplate the purchasing power of the beneficiaries, but following the same legal regime the government eventually sets non -acceptable prices for candidates. "This will lead to some household aggregates to give up this choice because it will challenge the financial capacity of many people, especially family aggregates who have become T1 fractions," he warned.
In this sense, the group urged the government to review and adjust the prices of economic houses in the three lots in Zone A. Thus, the prices and the bonus ratio applied to this group of economic houses will be adjusted to return to the previous level.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Almeida Ribeiro may have higher seals on the tours</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/almeida-ribeiro-podera-vir-ter-vedacoes-mais-altas-nos-passeios/</link><description>Cases of illegal crossing on the roads of Macau may lead the executive to take action on Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro. The subject was addressed between representatives of various government bodies and the general union of residents' associations. One of the solutions will be to raise the existing seals along the tours in high traffic zones
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The crossing of the macao roads by pedestrians without the use of the treadmills or security sites may cause the implementation of more effective measures to avoid illegal acts and possible accidents specifically on Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro (San MA Lou). One of the solutions, in addition to the fines imposed by the transit agents of the Public Security Police Corps, may be the rise of seals on pedestrian walks.
At a meeting with leaders of the South Zone Residents' General Union (“Kaifong”), representatives of various government organizations stated that the executive intends to rise the seals at the critical points of Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro. This central artery of the city is one of the most popular points among tourists, also having a huge extension.
Choi Hou in, president of the Mutual Assistance Association of residents of that avenue, says agree with this measure and suggests, in the short term, the use of iron material to connect the seals that are on the tours, thus preventing illegal crossing cases.
In addition to increasing height and extent of the scope of the sealing, the associative leader is of the opinion that reflective signs and warnings are introduced into multiple languages ​​to guide the pedestrians to cross the road under safety conditions.
Choi has also appeals to the government to continue to adjust the facilities and “strive to sensitize to create a more orderly travel environment,” he says.
On Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro there are arcade -shaped buildings, will the highest seals affect the overall landscape of the zone? Regarding this plan, the Cultural Institute said only that "when there is a concrete proposal will actively issue opinions," in a response sent to the newspaper or Mun.
Already André Lui, architect and scholar of cultural heritage, said he was aware of the government plan, considering that it is viable. "However, so far it is not yet known the concrete height that will be raised for the seals," he said, adding "to be better to wait for the proposal to study whether or not the measure will constitute disharmony with the area's visual corridor and the bundle -structured buildings."
The equity expert noted, however, that although some road accidents that involved illegal crossing on Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro occurred, "not all cases had to do with the existence or not of appropriate seals, since throughout the avenue there are several places without that type of protection structure."
Hence André Lui awaits “several public services to review together, in many ways, the situation of illegal crossing”, hoping that “optimize their facilities and reinforce the guidelines, in order to lead tourists to use the crosswalks safely”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong led collapse from Asian bags</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/hong-kong-liderou-derrocada-das-bolsas-asiaticas/</link><description>EPA12015567 Screens Displaying The Hang Seng Index at Exchange Square In Hong Kong, China, 07 April 2025. The Hang Seng Index Closed at 19828.30, Down 13 Percent, in Response to recent US Tariffs.  EPA/BERTHA WANG



Asia and Europe scholarships ran yesterday among fears that a trade war provides a large -scale recession, triggered by the US tariffs on their business partners. The day was particularly negative in Hong Kong, where the Hang Seng Index retreated 13.2% in its worst session since October 1997, during the Asian financial crisis.
The Shanghai and Shenzhen scholarships fell 7.34% and 9.66%, respectively, on a day marked by the market reaction to the Chinese contracted announced on Friday at Washington imposed rates on Asia products. The two indices thus have been evaporate the accumulated gains since September, when the economic stimulus ads of the Chinese authorities have led the index to maximums not seen since 2023.
The Taipe Exchange Reference Index, Taiex, sank 9.7%, the largest daily drop in its history. Technological companies were the ones that lost the most, with TSMC, Hon Hai (Foxconn) and MediaTek fall below the 10% daily limit as soon as the session began. Quoted by the local press, the president of the Taiwan Stock Exchange, Sherman Lin, said the stock market remains in "maximum alert" and will implement "adequate measures to stabilize the market if necessary."
In Tokyo, the main index, Nikkei, fell 7.83%, while the Seoul Kospi index dropped 5.57%and Sydney registered a 4.2%decrease. The descending curve extended to the financial squares of Southeast Asia, including Singapore (-7.46%), Kuala Lumpur (-4.01%) and Manila (-4.3%). Jakarta, Bangkok and Ho Chi Minh's bags were closed due to holidays in their respective countries.
In Europe, the main rates also opened in free fall, following the Asian trend. Frankfurt gave 7.86% after registering losses of more than 10% for a few minutes. Paris opened with a descent of 6.19%, London retreated 5.83%, Madrid 3.6%and Milan 2.32%.
In Asian markets, all actions have been affected, from technology companies to cars, through banks, casinos or power companies. The main losers include major Chinese technology companies such as Alibaba, which lost more than 17%, and their rival JD.com (-14%).
"We can see a US recession very quickly, which could last approximately a year, quite prolonged," said Steve Cochrane, chief economist for Asia and Pacific "Moody's Analytics," cited by AFP.
"So far, Trump's team is not backing down ... Of course Washington is using market difficulties as a lever to negotiate, not as a sign that encourages them to change course," Stephen Innes, "SPI Asset Management", said.
The Chinese Communist Party's official newspaper admitted yesterday that the rates imposed by Washington will impact the Chinese economy, but pointed out that the leadership in Beijing was already preparing for this moment. "Although international markets generally consider that US tariff abuses exceeded expectations, the party's central committee had already foreseen this new round of economic and commercial restraint and repression against China, fully estimated its potential impact and prepared response plans with sufficient time and reservations," said the People's Gazette.
 
Devaluation reached 14% among game operators
Macao playing operators did not escape “Black Monday” in capital markets, with six companies listed in Hong Kong to have an average devaluation of 14.3%. SJM Holdings and Melco International Development, a mother company of Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, were the most penalized, with 18% and 16.1%, respectively. Two digits also marked the descent of Sands China (-14.3%), Wynn Macau (-13%), Galaxy Entertainment (-12.4%) and MGM China (-11.9%).
 
JTM with Lusa and International Agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Associations promote “charm” of coastal tourism</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/associacoes-promovem-encanto-turismo-costeiro/</link><description>Several local associations have organized activities with the support of tourism services and running between April and May, so that residents and tourists can know the “Knitting of Costeiro de Macau” tourism "
 
Some local associations have organized various tourist activities for April and May, with the support of the Tourism Services Directorate (STD), in order to promote the flow of visitors and consumption in community neighborhoods and boost the local economy. Participants will have the opportunity to experience the “Charm of Macao Costeiro Tourism”, according to the STD statement.
One of the initiatives is the “Mak's Great Adventure in Macao-Love on a Boat Tour”, which began this weekend and will be repeated on April 12 and 13. The “Mak Mak” mascot will guide the participants on the coastal route between Barra da Barra Bridge and Coloane's Cali Bridge, to know the history of Macao and visit the Sam Seng Temple, where the Coloane Central and the Largo of President António Ramalho Eanes are located.
The activity also includes interactive games and thematic manual work, in order to “enrich the tourist experience of participants”. This initiative has the collaboration of 30 community stores, such as beverage stores, souvenir shops, pastries, restaurants, beauty stores, shoats and pharmacies.
On April 18, 19, 20 and 26, the participants of the “Maritime Voyage-Immersive Hi-Tea: The Art of Tea Journey” will be able to experience the tea art, with an instructor, in the panoramic boats departing from Barra da Barra and reach the Coloane-CAIS bridge. Storytellers will lead participants to visit historic places, such as the São Francisco Xavier Church, and will be able to receive a discount coupon for stores in the village of Coloane.
On April 27 and May 11, 18 and 25, the “Hanfu Island Tour-Coastal Journey Through Ancient Charm” is held. After boarding the Barra Cais, participants will wear traditional Chinese costumes, experience interactive games and enjoy desserts. The guide will present the history and culture of Macao and the “the charm of the fusion between Chinese and Portuguese cultures”, says STD.
Through the “Macao Navigation Tourism Manual”, distributed during the activity, participants will “feel the sights along the route” and get special offers and discounts promoted by stores.
These initiatives are part of the 2025 Financial Support Program for Community Tourism “Traveling by Macao”, Gastronomic Promotion “Macao Flavors” and Maritime Tourism “Fun on the Coastal Cord”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Diplomas that regulate associations will be reviewed</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/diplomas-regulam-associacoes-serao-revistos/</link><description>Diplomas that regulate the associations will be reviewed, taking into account the requirements in terms of national security and the social development of the territory
 
The Director of Administration and Public Function Services (SAFP), NG Wai Han, has revealed that, “depending on the requirements inherent to the General Perspective of National Security and the real needs for the social development of Macao”, the government will “review and optimize, in timely, the legal diplomas that regulate associations”. The objective is to improve management, as well as regular and guide its construction.
The information arises in response to an interpellation of Deputy Lei Chan U, who asked how the authorities will regulate the construction of associations, at a time when there are more than 12,000 in the territory.
“Macao associations have a long history of development and have played, over time, an important role of participants in community governance and the provision of public services,” says NG Wai Han. Then, he adds: "The present mandate of the government will expedite the important leading spirit of President XI Jinping, attributing special importance to communication and cooperation with associations that love the country and Macao, establishing the permanent mechanism of communication and exchange."
The SAFP director also emphasizes that the government will improve the mechanism of expression of opinions of associations, "in the sense of reinforcing the cohesion of common aspirations of the population, the collection of opinions and the union of the wisdom of the population."
It also ensures that it will support "the growing development of associations that love the homeland and Macao in grassroots governance, improve the network of community work, consolidate and expand the adhesion of residents." The work to be developed include the study and elaboration of social service plans, discussion about the establishment of the criteria for the quality of social services and the creation of an examination and evaluation system, as well as the promotion of intelligent and professional development of social services provided by associations.
NG Wai Han also states that public services provided by the Government of the Raem to the Base Social Layer will be expanded, as well as the participation of associations that love the homeland and Macau in community construction, providing them to enhance contributions in the in-depth cooperation zone.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Urban Pratice” wins a prize in London contest</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/urban-pratice-ganha-premio-em-concurso-de-londres/</link><description>The “Urban Practice” (UP), which brings together architects and designers from Macao, was distinguished with the silver award in the landscape conception category in the “London Design Awards 2024”. The project presented by the team led by architect Nuno Soares, entitled “Park of Tides” (“Parque das Marés”) was inserted in a public tender by invitation from the Institute for Municipal Affairs at the beginning of last year, aiming to create an affordable pedestrian path that would connect the two ends of Hac Sá beach.
UP's work simultaneously incorporates leisure facilities and was inspired by the natural rhythm of the tides. The project has an area of ​​12,000 m² and reinterprets the route with a wave-shaped expansion, advocating a modern, green and accessible space by the sea, to highlight the natural and recreational beauty of Hac Sá Beach.
The project is divided into three zones, each improving the coastal experience in different ways: zone A focuses on leisure, with interactive spaces, B encourages exploration through natural materials and outdoor activities and C enhances the landscape with design and contemporary installations.
Together, says the UP, the areas "reimagine the riverside area as a multifunctional and inclusive destination for visitors to engage, explore and relax".
Nuno Soares says that “this project adopts a minimal impact approach, where permeable structures and natural materials are involved with the terrain, representing our commitment to sustainable and inclusive architectural practices”, by ensuring ecological preservation and increasing community welfare. For the architect, "if priority is given to environmental responsibility," spaces can be created that "not only protect nature, but also contribute to a more resilient local economy and a healthier and more vibrant public sphere."
The “London Design Awards”, together with the International Awards Associate, recognize projects considered exceptional and creative influence proposing to promote designers' work involved in various fields and bringing recognition to those who overcome the industry.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Gymnastics Club Conquest Medals in Hong Kong</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/clube-de-ginastica-conquista-medalhas-em-hong-kong/</link><description>In what was its first internationalization, the Gymnastics Club of Macao gave views of a tournament in Hong Kong, where he won several medals. The race also featured representatives of Raehk, Taiwan and the continent. The historic presence of the mashed team, which performed with 28 athletes in various echelons, male and female, "is the reflection of our dedication to gymnastics," the Journal Tribuna de Macau told coach Ana Conde told the newspaper Ana Conde

























Victor Rebelo
 
For the first time in the history of the “Gymnastics Club of Macau”, founded in 2013, their athletes were able to participate in an international competition. The Hong Kong tournament took place last weekend, with the RAM team to sight, when they got several trips to the podium, including three first places.
The club led to the neighboring territory 28 gymnasts, all residents of Macao, from various age, male and female echelons, highlighted Fabio Kapuscinski, who reached a victory in ground exercises and a second place in the jumps (boys between six and eight years). Mia Tuay (girls between nine and 12 years old) also raised two medals, thanks to a second position in the jumps and a third post of the soil exercises.
Moreover, in focus were also Charlotte Law, first classified in the soil, and Iris Lu, with triumph in the jumps, both in the level between 9 and 12 years, as well as Casslyn Lau, second in the soil, and Aykie Chan, third in the jumps (both in the class of girls over 13).
Almost 200 gymnasts from Hong Kong, Taiwan and the Popular Republic of China participated in the tournament.
Ana Conde, coach, referred to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that "these results reflect the dedication and evolution of young people of the Gymnastics Club, in the confrontation with athletes of good level of the other formations that were present."
The former international gymnast for Portugal states that there has been increasing adherence of young people in the sport, leading to the club, with about 300 gymnasts, can not receive anymore at this time. "There are many interested in waiting list, because our gym is not very large and we want to give quality to our classes, with one monitor for every eight young people," he said.
The “Gymnastics Club of Macau” also has coaches Nuno Fernandes, founder of the club and equally renowned athlete in Portugal, having left in 2008 the “Cirque du Soleil”, a show of City of Dreams, and Polaco Tomek Kapuscinski, another international gymnast for his country, playing champion, recruited in 2011 for “The House Of The House of of Dancing Water. ”
Since 2019, the Trampoline Gymnastics has had several competitions, organized by the Association of Trampolins and Acrobatic Sports, of which the Gymnastics Club is part. However, those responsible for the association are still waiting for recognition by the Sports Institute (ID).
"It has been a fight of several years, with ID A not accepting our registration, considering that there is already in Macao a general association of gymnastics," said the coach.
For this year, the “Gymnastics Club” has scheduled the organization of a tournament at the international school on 17 and 18 May, followed by the annual soiree.
In a statement issued shortly after participating in the Hong Kong race, the “Gymnastics Club” points out that “this success launches the foundations for future international adventures, and the club is enthusiastic to continue to reach new levels”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“The Spirit of China” in photographs</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/o-espirito-da-china-em-fotografias/</link><description>SICHUAN 2019



The exhibition “The Spirit of China”, organized by Halftone - Macau Photographic Association, will be inaugurated on April 11, at 6.30 pm, in Parisian, being evident to the public until May 11. The collective exhibition brings together the works of 17 photographers based in Macao, "which explore, through strong visual narratives, the evolution of Chinese identity and its contemporary meaning."












SICHUAN 2019















According to the association, the show "proposes a reflection on how fast urbanization and the emergence of megacities coexist with historical neighborhoods, such as religious rituals and old festivities dialogue with digital culture, and how new generations are redefining what it means to be Chinese in the 21st century."
“With the use of documentary, contemporary and conceptual photography, the works go through time and space-past, present and future imagined-offering deep visions about heritage, urban landmarks and new forms of visual expression,” can be read in the press release.
The works of António Mil-Homens, Carmen Serejo, Cássia Schutt, Elói Scarva, Flávio Andrade and Francisco Ricarte will be exhibited. They will also be part of the photographs show captured by João M. Rato, João Palla Martins, Jorge Veiga Alves, José das Neves, José Sales Marques, Marta Pereira, Nelson Silva, Sara Augusto, Sara Marçal, Sofia Mota and Stefan Nunes.
More than a representation of Chinese legacy, "The Spirit of China" reveals identity as "a living force - constantly shaped by social, dynamic diaspora and digital interconnectivity." The public is thus invited to reflect on the coexistence between the old and the new, and to get involved with the spirit of a nation in transformation.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Lotus Art Space” welcomes Macau curators in Venice</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lotus-art-space-acolhe-curadoras-de-macau-em-veneza/</link><description>“Lotus Art Space” is the name of a new gallery, which opened doors at the Legend Palace Hotel, on the fishermen's dock on March 26, with the debut exhibition of local artists Wong Weng Cheong and Rusty Fox.
Titled “Whispers of the Unseen”, the show presents to the public, by the end of this month, the artistic works of various representatives of the MSAR at the Venice Biennial. Wong Weng Cheong was the highlighted artist at the Macao Pavilion at last year's Italian event.
The curators of the event at Las, Chang and Sio Man Lam, signed the curators of Macao exhibitions at the 2023 and 2019 Venice Biennial, respectively.
With 20 exposed photographs, Rusty Fox “captures, through photography, the neglected absurdities of urban life, creating a unique visual poetics,” describes a statement from the organizer. In turn, Wong Weng Cheong “employs” in the 14 funds, “exquisite engraving techniques to represent hyper-realistic scenes and, at the same time, surreal, revealing subconscious desires and interior conflicts,” according to Las.
“Whispers of the Unseen” is also the first exhibition of the “International Promotion of Macao Artists Promotion abroad”, an initiative of the International Lotus Arts Exchange Association, with the support of the Culture Development Fund.
Speaking to journalists, Sio Man Lam stated that “the objective of artistic space is to stimulate creativity and imagination through a diversified program of exhibitions and events, linking the local audience, the great bay and the international artistic scene”. LAS “will continue to collaborate with various entities and personalities to promote the development of creative industry and cultural tourism,” added the founding director of artistic space.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sands donates one million for the game responsible</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sands-doa-um-milhao-em-prol-jogo-responsavel/</link><description>Sands China has donated a total of one million patacas to five non -governmental local organizations to support responsible game promotion initiatives. The gambling operator continued an annual practice that has involved more than 8.9 million patacas in donations since 2006. “Sands China has always been committed to corporate social responsibility. The company has supported the promotions of the several local social NGOs with 20 consecutive years. Last year alone, the company organized more than 150 events, continuing to improve workers and the public game,” he highlighted. Andy Kobel, the company's casino senior vice president, at the donation's delivery ceremony to the Macao Youth Volunteer Association, Coordinating Coordinator of Social Services Sheng Kung Hui, Youth Christian Association, Game Industry Workers House and Juveni Bosco Services Network. Supported initiatives include responsible playing and financial management activities between parents and children, 'roadshows', 'workshops', training actions, sharing sessions, promotional videos and questions and answers games, among others. In 2004, Sands became the first resort operator integrated to launch a casinos self-cycle system and three years later created a responsible game program. In addition, the training of responsible game has been part of the company's workers' guidance program since its launch.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Modernization of the awarded Coloane WWTP for billion</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/modernizacao-da-etar-de-coloane-adjudicada-por-mil-milhoes/</link><description>The project of modernization, operation and maintenance of Coloane's wastewater treatment plant (ETAR) was awarded for a value of more than 1.07 billion. With a period of eight years and scheduled completion in February 2032, the works involve two phases: the modernization and remodeling of the WWTP, and the passage of wastewater deeply treated to adjacent recycled water treatment facilities, to serve as raw water for recycled water production purposes. According to the direction of environmental protection services, only the modernization of the WWTP will cost about 605 million patacas. Upon completion of the works, Coloane's WWTP may treat about 65,000 cubic meters of wastewater respecting the highest level I-A level of national standards on the emission of pollutants by the WWTP in rustic and urban areas. According to environmental protection services, “ETAR odor treatment system will also be optimized during modernization works, to minimize environmental impacts on air quality nearby”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Nintendo Announces Switch Console 2 as available from June 5</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/nintendo-anuncia-consola-switch-2-como-disponivel-partir-5-de-junho/</link><description>The Japanese giant of Nintendo video games has announced that the new version of your Switch console will be available on June 5th.
The Kyoto -based company has also revealed new Switch 2 features -an updated version of the original 2017 model -as a chat button that will allow players to talk to each other while playing.
This new device, which succeeds the first switch, launched in 2017, with over 150 million units sold worldwide, preserves the concept of hybrid console, usable in both travel and connected to a TV set.
In particular, Switch 2 will feature a larger screen, detachable and magnetic commands that can be used as a “rat” and a function called “Game Chat”, which will allow you to talk to other live players. The device will also have a more powerful internal memory and integrated fan, detailed Nintendo during a video watched by nearly four million people.
Among the games available at its release will be "Mario Kart World", developed exclusively for Switch 2, but also titles such as "Split Fiction", "Elden Ring" and "Hogwarts Legacy".
With over 75 million copies sold from Wii U and Switch, “Mario Kart 8” is, in fact, the second best-selling game in the company's history, approaching the record set by “Wii Sports” (82 million).
However, this new console does not represent a revolution for Nintendo, as was the case, in 2006, with the detection of movements introduced by the Wii, or to a lesser extent with Gamepad, Wii U Tablet Command in 2012.
“I believe what (players) want most is simply a better performance,” said Hideki Yasuda, an analyst at Japanese company Toyo Securities. The expert estimates that six million new consoles will be available immediately.
In the long run, Nintendo could sell 19 million units during the fiscal year of 2025 and 21 million next year, calculates Toyo Securities.
Refilling this release is “fundamental” to the manufacturer's survival, recalled Piers Harding-Rolls, a specialist of the British market analysis company Amprere Analysis, because despite a diversification strategy in recent years in cinema and themed parks, Nintendo's activity has been based mainly on video games.
Admittedly, the video game industry is going through a growth crisis around the world, marked by waves of layoffs, and the arrival of Switch 2 should revitalize sales of falling consoles. In the US, they decreased by 35% in 2024, according to data provided by the Leisure Software Editors Union (SELL) and the American Circa Specialized Company.
The brand's recent announcement about lending digital Switch titles to friends through “virtual game cards” could also be a way to encourage consumers to invest in a second console, facilitating exchanges.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>