<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>André Cheong's appointment to Al Visa “Greater Positive Interaction” with Government</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/nomeacao-de-andre-cheong-para-al-visa-maior-interaccao-positiva-governo/</link><description>The chief executive justified his decision to appoint André Cheong to deputy with the desire to bring the government and the Legislative Assembly closer and “promote better interaction” between the two bodies. Sam Hou Fai also believes that the seven appointed deputies give “a greater representativeness” of the various sectors of society. In turn, the Secretary for Administration and Justice thanked the boss for the Hemiciclo, promising to dedicate "all his efforts to work." Identic promise was also left by his successor, Wong Sio Chak, and the remaining holders of high positions involved in the changes, Chan Tsz King and Tong Hio Fong
 
Pedro Milheirão
Sam Hou Fai stated that he hopes to “continually reinforce executive-legislative cooperation and promote better interaction” between the two parties, referring to André Cheong's appointment to deputy. On the sidelines of the official commemorative reception of the 76th anniversary of the implementation of the Popular Republic of China, the head of the government also stated that the seven appointed deputies were chosen for “greater representativeness”, according to a press office press release.
In addition, for the leader of the MSAR, the decision to appoint deputies from different activity sectors will also allow to “better promote the diversified and adequate growth of the local economy, strengthen the management of civil service, strengthen the creation of the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin and promote the macao science and technology industry”.
It is recalled that André Cheong, current secretary for administration and justice, was one of the seven deputies appointed by Sam Hou Fai, which will force a remodeling in the government. From October 16, the current Secretary for Security, Wong Sio Chak, will be with the administration and justice folder, while the prosecutor (MP), Chan Tsz King, will assume safety protection. In turn, the President of the Court of Second Instance, Tong Hio Fong, will hold the position of Prosecutor.
The chief executive justified the invitation to André Cheong to the role of deputy for his “vast experience” and to ensure, “during the process of policy preparation and even debates in the Legislative Assembly, greater positive interaction and close communication between the executive and legislative powers, in order to better coordinate the legislative work and respond to the expectations of the various sectors of society”. "The government and the Legislative Assembly, as they perform their functions in accordance with their legal responsibilities, will continue to reinforce communication, coordination and positive interaction with each other, which will certainly contribute to better development of the economy and society of Macao," he reiterated.
For Sam Hou Fai, “these new adjustments represent changes in time and guided by the general tendency and pragmatic responses to real circumstances, aiming to take advantage of innovative thinking and determination to promote reforms to make even better use of the executive power's predominance system under the framing 'one country, two systems'”. The government leader has promised "an environment more favorable to the next phase of Macao's renovation and development" and that responds "to the appeals for the long time of the different sectors of society."
 
Enjoy “experience” in administration and justice
André Cheong, in turn, thanked the confidence of the central government and chief executive by appointing him as a deputy for the new legislature. Looking at future functions, promised to “make the most of” his “experience” in public administration and justice to
promote a more positive interaction ”between the executive and legislative powers and to engage in the best way in the works of al.
Asked about the possibility of assuming the position of President of the Legislative Assembly, André Cheong recalled that, according to the R regiment, the Legislative Leader must be elected by all deputies. He stressed, regardless of the position he assumes in the hemiciclo, he will do his best, and although the executive and legislature agencies have their own competences and responsibilities, this does not mean that each one does their own things, and there must be positive communication and interaction under the principle of predominance of the executive branch.
In addition, he emphasized his determination to proceed well to the transfer of work with the secretary to the administration and justice, Wong Sio Chak, in order to ensure a “quiet transition” in this tutelage.
On the other hand, André Cheong said that with the move to the AL, he will also leave the roles of director of the executive committee of the in -depth cooperation zone.
In turn, Wong Sio Chak has asserted that, in the next four years, he will perform solidly the work of his new guardianship, highlighting “the reform of the Public Administration, a macao based on the rule of law, the improvement of the management of municipal affairs, the great integration of Guangdong-Hacau Bay and the integrated development between Macau and Hengqin”.
Specifically, he said he will strive to create an efficient, committed and service-oriented government, dedicate himself to creating a legal system with Macao characteristics and corresponding to the development needs of “one country, two systems” as well as reorganizing the institute for municipal matters.
In turn, the secretary for nominated security, Chan Tsz King, said he was convinced that, under the leadership of the new prosecutor Tong Hio Fong, the prosecutor (MP) will certainly continue to progress.
Chan Tsz King has also manifested himself that he could quickly adapt to his new position, stressing that he will follow the nuclear spirit of "one country" that is the presupposition for "two systems", placing above all the defense of sovereignty, security and the interests of national development. He stressed, the safety of the MSAR is inseparable from state security, so it is important to understand accurately the relevant issues in this domain and accelerate the promotion of system modernization and the capacity of national security.
From your perspective, it is necessary to contribute to a new development conjuncture through the new safety panorama.
Generally speaking, he assured that he will lead the safety relief team, continuing to make efforts to maintain public order, stability and social harmony in Macao.
Already Tong Hio Fong emphasized “a greater requirement to the team of magistrates of the MP, regarding compliance with the law, respect for disciplinary rules and integrity”, warning that, if any irregularity is detected, “will be treated with seriousness”. The judge reported that more than 20 bailiffs will complete the training course in September next year, noting to believe that their entrance may relieve the overload of current workers, as well as increase judicial effectiveness. He said, after taking office, he will study in detail and implement measures with a view to raising judicial effectiveness.
In addition, Tong Hio Fong said that if any conduct is detected that impair national security, the MP will “undoubtedly” proper follow -up and treatment in close compliance with the state security defense law.
 
Boss can visit Portugal in the first half of 2026
The chief executive said he was confident that his visit to Portugal will happen "in the first half of next year." Sam Hou Fai also said that Portugal "was always the first destination that pondered to visit abroad", adding that "contacts and programming were always maintained." The official assured that he continues to prepare and coordinate the visit “actively”, which has not yet been materialized due to the “urgent issues of the government” of MSAR. Sam Hou Fai's move to Portugal, as well as Spain, was scheduled in the first half of the year, and was postponed due to the change of government in Portugal and the presentation of the government lines in April. Reacted to mid -September, the trip would eventually be canceled again.</description><pubDate>2025-10-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Visitors may increase a third at the end of the decade</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/visitantes-poderao-aumentar-um-terco-final-da-decada/</link><description>By 2030, the MSAR could exceed 46 million visitors and reach 111 billion patacas in revenues not related to the game, according to the new review of the “General Plan for the Macao Tourism Industry Development” of the Tourism Services Directorate. In addition to designing widespread growth of the sector, Deloitte, author of the review, also prepared a set of suggestions that aim to optimize the execution of scheduled initiatives
 
Pedro Milheirão
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) released the conclusions of the second phase of the review of the “General Plan for the Development of the Macao Tourism Industry”, conducted by “Deloitte”. The report indicates that in 2030 Macau could receive between 39.47 million and 46.43 million visitors, which would correspond to increases of 13%to 33%, respectively, compared to the 35 million recorded in 2024. Already the expenses not reached 111 billion patacas, a growth of 29.9%, compared to the 85.47 billion expected to the general of it year.
The consultant also expects visitors who to overcome in the territory to grow to numbers between 18.22 million and 21.85 million, by 2030. These values ​​would mean a rise between 11.2% and 33.3%, if we consider the 16.39 million that the government provides for the MSar to reach this year. The authors also anticipate that the number of rooms in the hotel sector will reach 52,849 units, with an occupancy rate of 91.4%at the end of the decade. In addition, the "Deloitte" projects that the average spending by visitor increases 2,157 patacas in 2024 for values ​​between 2,252 and 3,229, while the average duration of each stay will be 2.5 days, compared to current 2.3.
The review also added 20 new plans of action to the general plan, excluding 14 and integrated 23 of them to other plans, resulting in a new total of 74 initiatives, to be carried out by the end of 2030. Programmed initiatives containing six areas, namely “Tourist Products and Experiences”, “Tourism and Quality Cooperation”, “Exploitation of Customer Sources”, “Urban Construction”, “Intelligent Technology”, “Cooperation” regional and international tourist ”.
As one of the six key issues, the study segments five distinct markets for the Macao tourist industry, which include “family” groups, elderly, “elite business travelers”, “personality pioneers” and “backpackers”.
According to the authors, “elite business travelers” are individuals who prefer a “high quality experience” that combines business and leisure. “Pioneers of Personality” are looking for “unique sights” and “personalized consumer choices”, while “backpackers” are intended to find promoted attractions on social networks, suitable for more limited calendars and budgets. Families are looking for playful and educational trips, focusing on the younger ones, while “old age” prefers local cultural experiences.
The study also notes that the MSAR needs "further complementary tourist products that are characteristic, differentiated and directed." It should also be prioritized “the focus on gastronomy, health, events and education, focusing on the development of sports fields and conventions, maintaining continuous attention in the fields of technology, creative culture and electronic trade”, can read.
 
Tourism faces “limitations”
On the other hand, the report indicates that “Macao faces limitations in the construction of a 'world center of tourism and leisure', with a structure of poorly diverse tourists with low internationalization”, and in 2024 more than 93% of visitors came from the interior of China, Hong Kong or Taiwan.
In order to mitigate this phenomenon, the authors suggest that "accurate marketing" strategies are used to attract international tourists, as well as "increase" online and offline "promotions and exhibitions and identify groups that stay longer and spend more money during their stay.
Another key theme is related to regional tourism, which needs a reinforcement in the “promotion, joint organization of events, characteristic products and strengthening of transport connections”, in order to “explore and release the huge potential for tourism development of the great bay”. The authors consider that, currently, the tourist brand of the great bay "is not clear enough" and that the "railway between Macao and other cities needs to be improved." Inquired for this study, mainly highlighted the needs of improving transport infrastructure, whose “congestion problem” needs to be managed.
Finally, the authors propose to educational institutions to include artificial intelligence (AI) content in their curricula, so that “local qualified frames” are formed, and small and medium -sized companies to use “intelligent data analysis and marketing”, using AI tools. Improving reserve services or interactive audiovisual experiences are other of the proposals.</description><pubDate>2025-10-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Human trafficking motivates new “collision” with USA</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/trafico-humano-motiva-nova-colisao-eua/</link><description>Washington kept Macao on the list of countries and territories that do not fully fulfill the minimum standards in the fight against human trafficking, an assessment that was strongly contested by the Government of MSAR. For the Macao executive, the US report is “full of political prejudices” and “ignores objective facts”, so “it has no credibility”
 
Sérgio Terra
 
The US State Department has decided to keep Macau at level 3 of human trafficking, as it understands that the government "does not fully fulfill the minimum rules for eliminating trafficking and is not working on significant efforts to do so." This assessment also covers countries and regions such as Afghanistan, Belarus, Cambodia, Chad, China, North Korea, Cuba, Eritrea, Iran, Laos, Myanmar, Nicaragua, Papua New Guinea, Russia, Saint Martin, Syria, South Sudan and Venezuela, and could lead the US President to impose “certain restrictions on non-humanitarian external assistance and not related to trade ”.
"Despite the lack of significant efforts, the government has taken some measures to combat trafficking, including the investigation of a possible case of trafficking, the formation of some employees and the organization of sensitization seminars in schools. However, the general efforts to apply anti-process law and the protection of the victims continued to be inadequate," the state department in the 2025 report, adding that local authorities did not report to reports. Proactive screening of vulnerable populations, such as individuals who have commercial sex, for trafficking indicators ”, nor have it indicated to have identified or provided support services to any victims since 2022.
"The government has not sued a trafficking case, has not condemned a trafficker since 2021 and never identified a victim of forced labor exploited in Macao," the document reiterates, which once again led the mashely authorities to express "firm opposition" and "dissatisfaction."
"The alleged 'report' of the US State Department is full of political prejudices and subjective judgments, as well as ignoring the objective facts," a government statement stresses, giving as an example the fact that the document states that Southeast Asian macao to practice circumventions with telecommunications and cybernetic can be accused after returning to the territory. "In fact, these victims were arrested by local police because they violated local law, and were not accused by the Macao authorities," the note stresses that the "greater efforts" to ensure their return on security, as well as reinforce awareness and investigation, to suppress the occurrence of burlas.
Considering that "this" report "has denigrated the sons and contains defamatory and arbitrary statements related to the remarkable fruits obtained" in the fight against human trafficking, the government emphasizes that the document "has no credibility." "The US has prepared, year after year, reports with false information regarding issues of persons, in an attempt to launch confusion in international society, constituting serious and expressed interference in the internal affairs of the MSAR," the security authorities lament, which, therefore, "vehemently repudiate" the comments of American diplomacy.
Human trafficking “is a worldwide public danger”, emphasizes the government, ensuring that it maintains “deepened cooperation with society sectors” and, “in tune with judicial bodies, develops the law of law enforcement and participates in international and interregional exchanges”. Thus, it intends to "constantly optimize work strategies and eliminate with all commitment to trafficking in people and all forms of exploitation."
In this sense, it asserts that it “strictly” applies the law on the fight against human trafficking and “fully” implements the international conventions that apply to the MSAR, without forgetting the role of the commission of tracking measures to determine trafficking in persons, which has coordinated cooperation between public services and non -governmental organizations. Thanks to these efforts, "crimes related to trafficking in people have always recorded a low percentage or almost null percentage, which shows that Macau is one of the safest cities in the world," the statement states.
 
Ancient criticism
In the 2025 report, the US repeat criticism in previous years, as well as “priority recommendations”, namely “significantly increasing the proactive identification of victims” and “efforts to investigate, process and condemn people's traffickers for sexual and working purposes, including those who potentially operate in casinos and other entertainment facilities”, and the application of heavy penalties to penalties to penalties condemned traffickers.
The reinforcement of victim support channels, the formation of government officials on the law - so that “the victim's initial consent is not seen as proof that trafficking did not occur” - and the updating of the action plan against this scourge are other appeals renewed by Washington. Among other measures, it also insists that foreign domestic workers must benefit from proper work protection and the general minimum wage, and be exempt from recruitment rates by employment agencies in Macao and their home countries.
Citing data from the follow -up committee, the report indicates that in 2024 more than 40 training actions were carried out, especially for police officers.
On the other hand, it continues to echo a "news" of 2019, according to which "traffickers recruit victims, mainly from mainland China, Russia and Southeast Asia, using fake advertisements for jobs such as singers and models or casinos in Macao."</description><pubDate>2025-10-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Metro “crosses” with anti-chewing plane in the interior port</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/metro-cruza-se-plano-anti-cheias-porto-interior/</link><description>The Light Metro Line Extension Plan will take into account an integral study on the inner port planning, including flood prevention infrastructures, Secretary Raymond Tam said
 
Under the Light Metro Extension Planning, the Government will perform a “global approach” on the inner Port area, the secretary said for transport and public works. Speaking to journalists after the reception of National Day, Raymond Tam said that, considering that the Western Metro line involves the inner port, it will be necessary to plan and study a series of factors that make up “flood prevention infrastructures, peripheral streets, planning and landscaping” of this city zone.
In addition, it will be evaluated, “by comparison”, the installation of protection complibrates and flood prevention dams, stressed the secretary, ensuring that the results of this study will be released in “timely time”.
Regarding urban renewal and temporary housing, Raymond Tam stressed that the “directing plan” prioritizes the reordering of zones where there are older buildings and “overcrowding” housing. Urban renewal work not only encompasses demolition and reconstruction, he noted, by promising a “multifaceted approach”, including “the increase in infrastructure, improving landscape conditions and the implementation of building maintenance projects”.
In this context, the work team selects “the appropriate neighborhoods for beautification” and reviews the financing regime for the maintenance of buildings, he added.
According to Raymond Tam, in addition to the renewal of the “seven blocks of Iao Hon”, the “Most Mature” plan is the revitalization of the former residence for CTT workers with the Red Market, whose project of the urban conditions plan was recently approved by the urban planning council. This revitalization process includes the creation of an air corridor for the former CTT residence building.
As for the temporary housing project, the procedures for the survey of completed works have already completed, and “measures will be taken for residents who need based on the actual circumstances,” he said, without any details.
In another area of ​​his tutelage, Raymond Tam stressed that, after completion of the third phase of the expansion, the solid waste incineration center can now process three thousand tons of household waste per day, enough volume to meet the needs in the next 30 years. Regarding construction waste, he said that in the future the slag of the incineration center may be recycled in resources for the manufacture of bricks in gross.</description><pubDate>2025-10-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Calema and Marisa Liz sing at the Lusofonia Festival</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/calema-marisa-liz-cantam-festival-da-lusofonia/</link><description>The duo of São-Tome singers Calema is the main head of this year's edition of the Lusophony Festival. Also highlighted will be Portuguese Marisa Liz. The two-time weekend event, late October and Principle of November, will take place at the same time with the meeting in Macao-Festival of Arts and Culture between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, which will present more than 80 activities

Victor Rebelo
 
The program of the Lusophony Festival is already known, which, for the second consecutive time, takes place on two weekends. In the first, between October 24 and 26, Calema, duo of singers from Sao Tome and Principe, is the great attraction of the party. The concert is scheduled for October 25 at 9:30 pm.
The brothers Fradique and António Mendes Ferreira had already been probed by the organization in previous years, having now responded to the invitation to participate in the festival.
According to musical criticism, the Calema, based on Portugal, conquered what no artist in the Lusophone world had been achieved so far: filling the Stadium of Luz, where about 50,000 people witnessed the show last June. The duo plays songs of Afro Pop, Kizomba, R&amp;B and Pop.
In 2017, in Portugal, they released the album “Our Top”, or simply “ANV”, and two years later they were announced as composers and performers of the song “A Two”, with which they participated in the Song Festival. Last year, they digested to celebrate their 15 years of career, with two concerts sold out at MEO Arena.
In this first trip to Macao and Asia, Calema should interpret the topics that most notable them, as well as recent excerpts, which have greatly popular with fans in Portugal and the African continent.
In the second weekend of the Lusophony Festival, on November 1, at 9:30 pm, the stage of the homes of the Taipa will receive another featured figure in the musical program, the Portuguese Marisa Liz. The singer and songwriter is known mainly for being vocalist of the band Amor Electro, with which she released successful albums and won awards. In 2022, he began a solo career with the album “Sunflowers and Storms”, and also stood out as a mentor in several editions of the television program “The Voice Portugal”.
At the 28th Lusophony Festival other musical artists will act over the six days of the event, namely Rui Orlando (Angola), Stamp Paidégua (Brazil), Memu Sunhu (Guinea-Bissau), Josslyn (Cape Verde), Tafika (Mozambique), Galaxy (East Timor), Sanskruti Sangam (Goa) and Diu) Black United (Equatorial Guinea).
At this year's popular party, it will be highlighted the promotion of Angolan culture, with the presentation of typical gastronomy, where a boss should be present expressly from Angola, and artistic works of this Lusophone country, all pointing out so that an artisan can show his art over the six days with the Angolan tent.
In addition, there will also be performances interpreted by artistic groups from 10 countries and regions of Portuguese, as well as more than 40 local Lusophone artists. To musical shows will join, as usual, traditional games and gastronomic tasting.
 
Meeting of Arts and Culture brings artists to the community
The Lusophony Festival will be held simultaneously with the 7th Meeting in Macao-Festival of Arts and Culture between China and the Portuguese-speaking countries (PLP), although it is extended until December, with more than 80 activity sessions, in the context of six main events, namely: The Spiritual Narrative-2025 Annual Exhibition of Arts between China and PLP, Exhibition of Illustrated Books in Chinese and PLPs and Portuguese, music shows and traditional dance in the community, film festival, Sino-Lirophone concert and tasting workshop. According to the organization, more than 780 national and foreign performers and interpreters will offer the public “a multicultural party, in historical spaces for world heritage, community neighborhoods and modern theaters”.
The integrated performances in the music and dance shows at various parts of the community and the Galaxy Macau will take place between October 23rd and November 2, with the aim of “highlighting the fascination and diversity of the performance arts of China and PLP,” says a note from the Cultural Institute (IC), the body responsible for several supports, the main one of which Galaxy Entertainment.
As an East Asia Culture City 2025, Macao also hosts the 7th Film Festival, under the theme “Transcending Borders”. The event will present a special selection of works from China, PLP and East Asia.
The exhibition of Illustrated Books, under the theme “World of Fairy Tales”, will be held between October 24 and November 2, at the Carmo Auditorium. For 10 consecutive days, more than 800 children's books will be available, mostly in Chinese and Portuguese, with free admission.
In focus will also be the tasting workshop, which will include three hand -prepared coffee sessions, allowing participants to taste the typical PLP and interior coffees of China.
At the presentation of the Lusofonia Meeting and Festival, which took place at the Cultural Center, IC President Leong Wai Man, said he believed that “the importance of arts and culture lies not only in the exhibition and appreciation, but also in promoting communication between people and the dialogue between peoples”, highlighting “interest in sharing deep essence and innovative vitality of Chinephon and Lusophone cultures and experience Macao charm as a multicultural city ”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>National power “increasingly strong” offers laughing perspectives to Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/poder-nacional-cada-vez-mais-forte-oferece-perspectivas-risonhas-macau/</link><description>The MSA will take advantage of the opportunities generated by national prosperity to “open new high quality development conjunctures” of the cause “a country, two systems,” said Sam Hou Fai, on the occasion of the 76th anniversary of the Popular Republic of China. The chief executive's optimism is based on the conviction that “national power is increasingly strong”







































慶祝中華人民共和國成立七十六周年及濠江月明夜文藝晚會 - 新創雜技劇《天鵝》總綵排




Over the past 76 years, the China Communist Party “united and led all ethnic groups in the country” to generate “two miracles” - “rapid economic development” and “permanent social stability”, thus highlighting the “prosperity of a large flowering and notable worldwide country”, said the head of the Executive of the Raem, at the commemorative reception of the 76th anniversary of the Popular Republic of China (RPC). Defending that "national power is increasingly strong," Sam Hou Fai stressed that "we are, thus, closer, more confident and more able to realize the goal of the grand revitalization of the Chinese nation than in any other moment in history."
“The prosperity of the homeland gives us a strong support for the development of Macao. We will take advantage of the opportunities provided by national development to continue to open new high quality development conjunctures of the cause 'a country, two systems',” he reiterated, when he talked about about 1,300 guests gathered at the Commercial Cooperation Complex between China and Portuguese-speaking countries.
According to the leader of MSAR, in general, the socioeconomic development of the territory records “a stable and positive evolution, and moves to a new phase: from recovery to high quality development”.
 
“New concepts” of governance
Remembering that this is the first year of action of the sixth government of MSAR, Sam Hou Fai stressed to be committed to implementing "new concepts" and "new mechanisms of governance." By way of example, he pointed to the creation of the leadership mechanism and coordination of the Public Administration reform, as well as the reinforcement of the link between the government and the “patriotic” associations.
From his perspective, the work of response to the “Ragasa” super tuffer prove that “since we persist in new concepts and new mechanisms of unity and struggle, we will certainly be able to overcome difficulties and challenges and open a laughing future for development”.
The Chief Executive mentioned some of the main guidelines entered in the government lines, namely about economic diversification, “integrated” development with hengqin and the supervision of the game, to ensure a “healthy” evolution of the sector, as the issue of “satellite casinos” was “properly treated”. "We endeavored to stabilize the economy and to ensure employment, we have made all attempts to vitalize the community economy and reinforced support for small and medium enterprises," he emphasized, also arguing that the four "key health" of traditional Chinese medicine, modern finances, cutting-edge technology and the branches of conventions and exhibitions) are advancing with "quality".
In the field of social welfare and urban development, the executive has also been betting on “new approaches and new measures”, he said, in arguing that the creation of the “Working Group for the Coordination of Employment Promotion” contributed to safeguard the priority of residents in access to the labor market, and the support provided in “more than 5,000 hires, cumulatively, in the first semester”. In the same sphere, he also highlighted the increase in the value of pensions for the elderly and disability and the subsidy for the elderly, among other measures.
On the other hand, by justifying the recent changes in the government, he said that the adjustments "constitute pragmatic responses found due to time and needs." “The objective is, with an innovative approach and the reformist determination, to take advantage of the political regime with a predominance of the executive branch, which is framed by the principle of a country, two systems', to reinforce the exercise, according to the law, the functions of the administrative, legislative and judicial bodies, as well as to deepen its constructive interaction, for the creation of a more favorable environment for the renovations and development of macao in the next phase and the next phase and the development of macao in the next phase and the next phase and the next phase and the next phase and the next phase and the next phase and the next phase and the next From the opening of a new conjuncture in these times of transformation, ”he argued.
Looking to the future, he assured that "we will boost the development of Macao with high quality in all domains, to realize with all the commitment the desired perspective of a macao based on the rule of law, dynamic, cultural and happy." Thus, he added, "we will contribute even more to the strengthening of the country and the great cause of national rejuvenation."
Prior to the reception, the chief executive and about 660 guests were present at the traditional ceremony of the flags Içar, which preceded the race “running in celebration of National Day and World March”, organized by the Institute of Sport. The event program also included other activities, such as fireworks.
 
Xi underlines “unshakable” politics of “a country, two systems”
The Chinese president stressed the “need to implement unobaribly” the politics “a country, two systems” and support Hong Kong and Macau “to better integrate into the country's overall development, as well as to develop their economies and improve people's welfare”. When speaking at a reception held on Tuesday, at the Great Palace of the People in Beijing, to celebrate the 76th anniversary of the Foundation of the Popular Republic of China, Xi Jinping also reiterated that efforts should be made to deepen the exchanges and cooperation through the Taiwan Strait, to “resolve” the separatist activities of Taiwan and the external interference and firmly safeguarded interference. national and territorial integrity. According to the Xinhua agency, the Chinese leader also urged the nation to advance with “determination” in the promotion of “Chinese modernization”. "Achieving the great revitalization of the Chinese nation is an unprecedented cause," he said, adding that "both aspirations and challenges inspire us to enjoy every moment and to persevere with unshakable vigor." In addition, in the face of rapid global changes, “we must practice true multilateralism, promote the implementation of the global development initiative, global security initiative, global civilization initiative and global governance initiative, and work with other countries to build a community shared for humanity,” he said.</description><pubDate>2025-10-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Secretary highlights retailers after Typhoon</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/secretario-destaca-recuperacao-dos-lojistas-apos-tufao/</link><description>Popular clean up after the passage of Superrthoph Ragasa in Macao, China, September 24, 2025. Superirty Ragasa, the most powerful storm registered on the planet in 2025, is passing off the Chinese regions of Macau and Hong Kong, after causing at least 14 dead in Taiwan and three in the Philippines. Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro/Lusa



At least about 700 commercial establishments were damaged due to the “Ragasa” super tuffon, but the sector recovered “relatively rapidly”, in part due to “good preparation” for the storm, considered the secretary for the economy and finance
 
After the “Ragasa” super tuft passed last week, the authorities inspected about 1,400 commercial establishments, having found that “50% suffered certain losses,” the secretary said to the economy and finance. However, according to an official note, Tai Kin IP assured that "even if the floods were inevitable, due to adequate preparatory work before the Typhoon's passage, commercial establishments recovered relatively fast."
Tai Kin IP also reiterated that the government has mechanisms to help small and medium -sized companies (SMEs), including providing interest -free loans to help facing “force majeure situations,” such as typicals. However, "so far, the authorities have not received requests for granting interest without interest by traders because of the" Ragasa "typhoon," he said.
The secretary took advantage of the occasion to emphasize that the government prepared “much in advance” for the passage of “Ragasa” and had the collaboration of the traders in the prevention work. After the typhoon, according to the same responsible, the competent services highlighted personal “immediately” to different neighborhoods to determine whether the SMEs needed support, having verified that those who acquired insurance of assets against large disasters had “immediate follow -up” and “received proper compensation with brevity”.
In another scope, Tai Kin IP has ensured that the government is “to promote active and pragmatically” the works related to the planning and construction of the Industrial Park for Research and Development of Sciences and Technologies. He explained, the functional plans, industrial development and the park's support facilities are being studied. The government will reference the “successful experience” of advanced parks from the interior of China and abroad and will consult the parties involved about the location and the projects in question.
Regarding the “great consumption award in community zones”, he insisted that this program supports the development of SMEs and contributes to raising the consumer power of residents. In the first three weeks of the campaign, electronic benefits were discounted in the total amount of 110 million patacas, generating an impulse rate of up to four times, said, maintaining that these data prove that the program "effectively stimulates and substantially streamlines consumption and the local economy."
In any case, it has ensured that the government will continue to evaluate the effects of these measures on commercial establishments and with residents to "proceed with necessary reviews and improvements."</description><pubDate>2025-10-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>100 “blue taxis” have ceased to operate</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/100-taxis-azuis-ja-deixaram-de-operar/</link><description>Os 100 “táxis azuis” da Companhia de Rádio Táxi deixaram de prestar serviço em Macau desde quarta-feira, devido ao término do seu contrato. Desse modo, o número total de táxis no território baixou para mais de 1.400, sendo que este cenário vai continuar até ao segundo trimestre do próximo ano, altura em que deverão começar a operar 100 novos táxis regulares
 
On September 30, he expired the contract term of the 100 “blue taxis” of the Radio Taxi. This means that since 0h00 on October 1, Macau has ceased to have a hundred blue taxis, the direction of services for traffic issues (DSAT), noting, on the other hand, that the 200 red taxis ”of the same company will continue to operate normally.
According to DSAT, after the termination of the “blue taxis” contract, the total number of taxis in Macau is greater than 1,400 vehicles. On the other hand, the government recently attributed two general licenses involving a total of 100 regular taxis through a public tender process. According to DSAT, these vehicles are expected to start operating at the latest in the second quarter of next year, and the authorities justified the decision to authorize new "black taxis" for the "public interest" and the "response to pressing public demand for taxi services."
At the same time, preparations are underway for a new public tender round for taxi licenses, with the aim of “rapidly increasing the number of taxis available and reinforcing affordable taxis requirements”.
Regarding passengers, DSAT stressed that anyone who needs taxi services by call can continue to use existing means, such as telephone or mobile application, to access the special taxis service provided by the “red taxis”, or opt for regular taxis services provided by other companies.
On the other hand, DSAT has ensured that it has maintained a close communication with the Radio Taxi company, to closely monitor the work related to the termination of the contract and continuously monitor the provision of services during the term of the contract. In addition, he stressed that he has given special attention to the professional situation of the 200 drivers of the “blue taxis”, installing the company to do a good job in the relocation or compensation of drivers.
According to "information" cited by DSAL, about 70% of drivers were reused by the company to conduct the "red taxis". The other taxi drivers expressed the intention of continuing in the sector, moving to other areas of the transportation business, or proceeding to professional conversion.
In this regard, DSAT has assured it to have coordinated with regular taxi companies in order to provide information on vacancies to drivers who wish to remain in the sector, facilitating their active job demand. At the same time, in collaboration with the management of services for labor affairs, DSAT recently organized an employment information session for drivers of “blue taxis” about to leave employment, providing clarifications on employment services and, according to professional drivers' intentions, providing recruitment information in different sectors and organized employment opportunities.</description><pubDate>2025-10-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Executive insists on reinforcing cybersecurity</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/executivo-insiste-reforco-da-ciberseguranca/</link><description>All public services should “actively” drive the infrastructures of cybersecurity, stressed the chief executive, asking for special attention to national games
 
The defense of cybersecurity is “fundamental” to “safeguard the national security, the harmony and stability of society and the well-being of the general public”, said Sam Hou Fai, charging a plenary meeting of the Commission for Cybersecurity (CPC).
Considering that “cyber and technological wars continue to evolve” and the new types of cyber crimes reveal a “diverse modus operandi”, the chief executive and president of the CPC warned “the uncertainties and instabilities of network security”. In this context, “all public services must work in collaboration and perform their own functions, actively boost the infrastructures of cybersecurity”, do “good protection work” in this context with “responsible attitude” and “effectively reinforce the resilience of cybersecurity” in local society, ”said the leader of MSAR, according to an official note.
Sam Hou Fai reiterated that the government attributes great importance to the preparation work of the 15th edition of the National Games and Special Olympic Games for the disabled, so he instructed the services responsible to “firmly” to “firmly” cybersecurity measures, to “ensure safe and stable functioning of the systems of different competitions and critical services to the population”. In addition, it has required all services to persist in “thinking based on more unfavorable situations,” taking concrete measures, preventing and proactively resolving various risks of cybersecurity.
During the meeting, CPC Vice President, Secretary for Security Wong Sio Chak, took stock of the government's work in 2024 in this area, while a representative of the Cyberrsecurity Alert and Incident Response presented the main content of the “General Cybersecurity Report of the Year 2024” and suggestions for improvements in public services and in general. CPC members discussed various topics about cybersecurity and defined objectives and concrete plans of the following tasks, the statement indicates without presenting details.
Also present at the meeting were Secretaries for Administration and Justice (André Cheong), Economics and Finance (Tai Kin IP), Social Affairs and Culture (LAM) and Transport and Public Works (TAM Vai Man), among others.</description><pubDate>2025-10-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ipor donates exposure on poetry to UCM</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ipor-doa-exposicao-sobre-poesia-a-ucm/</link><description>The exhibition “Poetry in the Garden” will remain at the City of Macau University (UCM), after being donated to the Higher Education Institution by the Portuguese Institute of the East (IPOR). Inaugurated in May of this in the Seac Pai Van Garden, to mark World Portuguese Day, this exhibition organized by IPOR, in collaboration with Casa de Portugal in Macao and the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, was also patent in the Garden Garden of the East Foundation.
The exhibition, which was also supported by the Macau Foundation and the International Institute of Portuguese Language, “represents a creative project in the area of ​​literature that calls for the celebration of the Portuguese language and the cultures that express themselves”, underlines a statement from IPOR.
“By bringing poetry to the community, the exhibition intended to be a vehicle for the dissemination of contemporary writers of Portuguese -speaking countries, while creatively sought to streamline the public spaces of Macao, appealing to the interest of reading, the book and the Portuguese language,” says the same note, emphasizing that this project, “which evidences the multicentary of its Portuguese language and its Variants also provided due recognition to the translators of the Chinese and Portuguese language ”.
Composed of 11 panels, the show presents 10 poems, a small biography and the photographs of the respective authors, thus being represented the nine Portuguese -speaking countries and the masters. Enrolled in Portuguese and translated into Chinese language, texts can also be heard in both languages ​​by reading a QR code, some of which, declared in the original language by the author himself.
“Fixing the final address of the exhibition in one of Macau's most prestigious higher education institutions is also a way of promoting and disseminating the Portuguese language and the cultures that are expressed in it and the multiculturality that is living in this special administrative region”, also maintains IPOR.</description><pubDate>2025-10-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China highlights Macao at the Osaka World Expo</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/china-destaca-macau-na-expo-mundial-de-osaka/</link><description>Fifteen years later, Macau "returned" to the stage of a world expo, with the China pavilion in Osaka to highlight the multiculturality of the territory, from heritage to the main festivities
 
Since yesterday and until tomorrow, the China Pavilion at Expo 2025 in Osaka, Japan, presents the “Macao Week” event, organized by the Government of Masters, through the Cultural Institute (IC) and tourism services, together with the China Cultural Chamber and Tourist Industry Committee. Executed by MGM China, supported by the Poly Culture Group, this initiative “promotes the World Heritage of Macao, the immaterial cultural heritage and the main festivities of the city”, showing international visitors “The Unique Urban Charm where the East finds the West and the past harmonizes with the present”, according to a note from the IC.
Recalling that 2025 marks the 20th anniversary of the registration of the Macao Historic Center in the UNESCO World Heritage list, as well as the attribution of the title of “East Asia Cultural City”, the exhibition features emblematic buildings, such as the ruins of São Paulo and the A-Má temple, among others, in different sections of the China Pavilion, creating a simulation of a walk on foot. The program also includes several artistic and cultural performances -including Portuguese folk dance and lion dance -workshops on intangible cultural heritage and interactive experiences.
In the square in front of the China Pavilion, Mak Mak, the Macau Tourism Mascot, will welcome visitors in front of a large photographic wall. The “Impressions of Macau” zone releases several sites of world heritage, festivities and cultural tourism projects, using digital images, while the “East-Kidade” zone exhibits in video annual events such as the International Firefighting Contest and the International Festival of Macao Gastronomy Cities.
In the “Exploring World Heritage” area, the public can embark on a “time and space trip” through virtual visits to the Historic Center of Macau. For this purpose, interactive tactile screen were installed that allow us to explore about 20 heritage sites and cultural facilities, namely the Dom Pedro V Theater and the Fortress of Monte, revealing traces of the architecture and urban landscape of Macao World Heritage to visitors, who will also have the opportunity to receive symbolic memories.
The IC also points out that this event in Osaka marks the return of Macao on the stage of a world expo, 15 years after its presence at Expo 2010 in Shanghai. In addition, it also points out MSAR's first participation in a worldwide foreign soil exhibition after its establishment, which, for the body, "constitutes a significant milestone in the valorization of cultural diversity and projection of the remarkable development of the region."
"This presence reflects the success of the principle" a country, two systems ", deepens the role of Macau as the world center of Tourism and Leisure, and the 'service platform for commercial cooperation between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries', in a 'base of exchange and cooperation for the promotion of multicultural coexistence, predominantly from Chinese culture', the IC concludes that the show is a" platform figure. " To narrate the historical paths of China and Masters, reinforcing the role of the city as a crucial bridge for the high -level opening of China to the outside world and in the dialogue between civilizations. ”
 
Expo closes ticket sales two weeks before the closure
Ticket sales for Osaka Expo ended on Tuesday, although there are still two weeks to close, due to the large number of people who have tickets, but did not reserve schedules for visits. "All time reserves will be granted to those who have already bought tickets, but have not yet made the reservation," said Jun Takashina, Deputy Secretary General of the Expo organization. More than 25 million people have visited Osaka Expo, including more than three million press accreditation and other professionals. As the Expo approaches the end, more and more people crowd for the event, with queues up to two hours to enter, Takashina explained. Inaugurated on April 13, the Osaka Expo extends until October 13. The organizers expected to attract about 28 million visitors during the six months of the event.</description><pubDate>2025-10-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Marathon increases vacancies for the main race</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/maratona-aumenta-vagas-para-corrida-principal/</link><description>Two more hundreds of vacancies were added to the Queen of the Macao International Marathon, which will go to the road on the first Sunday of December. The available places go from 1,600 to 1,800. In total, 12,000 athletes will fill the three competitions, marathon, half and mini. Registrations start on 11 this month
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Sports Institute (ID), the Galaxy Entertainment and the Athletics Association prepare another edition of the Macao International Marathon, which will take place on December 7, with departure and arrival at the Taipa Stadium.
As the main news for this year, in terms of number of participants, it is the increase of vacancies for the main race of the program, the marathon. The 42,195 kilometers race will have a maximum of 1,800 athletes, unlike 2024 in which 1,600 registration was allowed.
However, so that the total corridors in the three distances do not exceed 12,000, as it has happened several years ago, the organization reduced registrations in the mini race (about 4.5 km) to 5,400, when last year were 5,600. As for the half marathon (21,0975 km), the limit number of participants remains at 4,800.
The athletes will depart from the Olympic Sports Center Stadium (Taipa), at 6:00 am in the marathon and half marathon categories, and at 6:15 am to the mini-marathon, and the first two will pass through the Noble Governor Bridge, A-Má Temple, classified as World Heritage, and Sai Van Bridge.
The competition, which has no list of confirmed founders, will open registration on two dates. For the marathon and half marathon, it will be at 9 am on October 11 (Saturday), while for the mini marathon will take place at 9:00 am the next day. Interested parties may register through the official page of the event, or the application of “Macao International Marathon” mobile phone. Registrations will be closed after all vacancies are filled.
All individuals who want to align at the outset for edition 44 of the “Macao International Marathon” should have an online personal account. After creating an account, participants will be able to start session in the system and register online during the registration period. Participants with an existing account must have their personal data for the purpose of registration, including an electronic copy of the respective identification document and the respective member card of the General Athletics Association of the current year (if applicable).
Those who are already registered online, but have forgotten their username and their password, may request a new word 'pass'.
Participants will be able to raise the respective dorsal and the timing chip on the Broadway Macau M -floor, between December 3 and 6, upon presentation of the proof of registration and identification document.
A series of parallel activities will take place this year again, including the “Galaxy Entertainment Festival Macao International Marathon”, as the popular “most creative clothing award”. He invites the athletes to take a photograph with their clothing during the race, carrying it in the “Macao International Marathon” application and filling the necessary data.
This information was released at a press conference, during which ID's substitute president, law SI Leng, said that the continuation of the Macao International Marathon “will contribute to further consolidating the status of sports event, whose objective, he stressed,“ is to promote the proper diversification of the sports sector and the economy of Macau, thus enhancing, continuously, the social benefits of this sports event large dimension ”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Free anti-gripe vaccine for risk groups</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/vacina-anti-gripe-gratuita-para-grupos-de-risco/</link><description>Close up of unrecognizable Doctor Vaccinating Child in Medical Clinic, Copy Space



“High-risk” individuals can already receive, free of charge, the anti-the-flu vaccine for 2025-2026, reported health services (SSM), reiterating that vaccination is the most effective measure for flu prevention. SSM has acquired inactive vaccines produced by Sanofi and Abbott companies and will buy more than other brands that correspond to World Health Organization rules. According to the body, free vaccination will be given priority to residents of Macau aged six months and under 18 years, individuals aged 50 or older, pregnant and women to breastfeed, chronic patients, casin workers, casin workers, casinos workers, casinos workers, casinos workers, casinos workers, casinos workers, casinos workers, casinos workers and people with urgent need to move abroad. The priority group also includes students, teaching and non-teaching staff who performs duties in day care centers, kindergartens, primary and secondary schools and higher education institutions, users and homes, all health personnel, and individuals that SSM consider necessary to submit to vaccination, such as workers who perform functions in public services, among others. The recipients with priority to vaccination can move to health centers or health post, without the need for prior marking. By December, SSM will also highlight staff to perform collective vaccination actions in day care centers, kindergartens, primary and secondary schools, elderly and rehabilitation homes, public services or other institutions with large number of workers.</description><pubDate>2025-10-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Museum of UNESCO stolen cultural goods opened in Barcelona with six objects from Portugal</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/museu-de-bens-culturais-roubados-da-unesco-abriu-em-barcelona-seis-objectos-de-portugal/</link><description>UNESCO has launched the virtual museum of stolen cultural objects, which includes six pieces reported as missing by Portugal.
The UNESCO Virtual Museum, announced in 2022, results from a collaboration with Interpol and start, for now, with 250 initial objects from 56 countries. In the Portugal Gallery, there are six stolen objects, including jewelry of the Royal Treasury and the painting “Bust of Roman Woman”, 1882, by Henrique Pousão.
Among the Portuguese jewelry is a diamond necklace of 1834 commissioned by D. Maria II (1819-1853) and a cable cable of D. José I (1750-1777), made of gold and embedded with 387 diamonds of various sizes.
The UNESCO Virtual Museum of Cultural Objects (https://museum.unesco.org/), designed by architect Francis Kéré, born in Burkina Faso and Pritzker award in 2022, is “a unique museum in the world”, “no walls, but not memory,” said UNESCO Culture Director Ernestone Ottone, in the presentation of the project.
Ernesto Ottone stressed that stolen cultural goods “hurt the collective memory”, break chains of cultural transmission between generations and “prevent science from evolving” by hiding knowledge.
This type of theft is from the “most profitable” black markets, results from organized crime, finances terrorism and prospered especially in war zones, said UNESCO's deputy general director, who stressed that the purpose of the virtual museum is to recover and restore stole objects, but also to sensitize on this type of crime and the impact on various levels, as well as appealing a “more paper more paper active in this struggle ”by all, especially the younger ones.
The Virtual Museum also wants to help in promoting education on cultural goods and “facilitates inter-generational transmission” of knowledge, he added. “Learning about these missing objects is the first step towards your recovery” and “when a cultural object is stolen we lose part of our identity” are precisely the first two phrases that reads the UNESCO Virtual Museum platform.
Ernesto Ottone appealed to the 60 UNESCO Member States that they did not officially record cultural objects stolen to do so, as they only enter this virtual museum pieces that are already in the interpol database.
The ambition of UNESCO is that the number of objects exposed to increase immediately, but the hope is that the galleries will be emptied as they are found and restored to countries and owners of origin.
According to Interpol, the 250 objects integrated in the inaugural galleries of this museum are only a small sample of an illicit trafficking involving at least 57,000 goods. This trafficking results from theft and counterfeit of works of art, but also piles in clandestine archaeological zones or excavations, Interpol tells.
UNESCO's Virtual Museum of Cultural Objects was presented on the first day of the Moniacult 2025 conference in Barcelona, ​​Spain. The Moniacult 2025 is the UNESCO World Conference on Cultural Policies and Sustainable Development and is held this year for the third time, after editions in Mexico in 1982 and 2022, under the motto "Free the power of culture to achieve sustainable development."
120 ministers around the world are gathered in Barcelona.
 
JTM/LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-10-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>