<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Lusophone associations lament little information about the cultural week</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/associacoes-lusofonas-lamentam-pouca-informacao-sobre-semana-cultural/</link><description>This year's edition of China Cultural Week and Portuguese-speaking countries, organized by the Forum, will be held from September 26 to October 2, with the main events scheduled for the same place of 2024, the fisherman's dock. The associations are already preparing their participation, although they do not yet have much information about the event, told the Jornal of Macau Amelia António, president of the House of Portugal, which hopes to bring to the territory Arlindo Moura, specialist in Filigran works. Carla Fellini, from Casa do Brasil, says she is waiting for confirmation to bring “an artisan and a cooking”. Mozambique will also bring a representative of the country's handicrafts and a cook. In addition to Macao, Cultural Week will also take place in Zhongshan and Beijing
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The 17th Cultural Week of China and Portuguese -speaking countries, promoted by the Permanent Secretariat of the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese -Speaking Countries (Macau), will take place in the fishermen's dock, learned the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. Exchange activities will take place between September 26 and October 2.
About three weeks from the beginning of the event, which in addition to Macau will cover the cities of Zhongshan and Beijing, local associations told JTM that they are still unaware of the program, awaiting official information to give “green light” around the artists who will represent each country.
The president of Casa de Portugal questions the repercussion that such an event will have when the disclosure is made very close to the start of the activities. “It is a pity that at this time, a short time ago, there is practically not disclosure,” he criticizes. Amelia António points out that, beyond the dates, he knows little about the program.
The same is true of Carla Fellini, president of Casa do Brasil. “We are waiting for confirmation to bring an artisan and a cooking,” says no allowance for travel. “The Independence Festival of Brazil, which will take place at the Tromba Rija restaurant, next Sunday, in a celebration of the 200 years, will also serve to know details about the cultural week. We have invited all presidents of Lusophone associations to participate in dinner and then we will try to know more about this year's Cultural Week,” he says.
Ângelo Rafael, responsible for the association of friends of Mozambique, also contacted by our newspaper, expects confirmation of the coming of an artisan and a cooking. "At this point we have no official knowledge about the place and the Cultural Week program," he said.
Even not even knowing what this year's event will be, Ângelo Rafael guarantees the coming of an artisan's macao, to be present at the Craft Fair, and a cooking head.
Regarding gastronomy, Mozambicans resident in the MSA will be able to count on the presence of chief Joaquina Marlene Domingos Diogo. "It will come to publicize typical dishes of our country," says the leader, for whom the presence of the cook "will allow us to interact and share the menu before the Macao Cultural Week, in 2023, by another representative of gastronomy."
The African country will also have in the territory musical artists, in band or solo, "but this is already the responsibility of our delegate in the forum," says the associative president.
Regarding Casa de Portugal, he intends to bring an artisan from northern Portugal, Arlindo Moura, born in Gondomar, considered one of the greatest experts in the production of jewelery pieces in Philigher. "He is very reputable and his works are in the shrink, so we understand that he was an artist who was worth bringing to Macao," said Amelia António.
Arlindo Moura, who was in the territory, in 2018, for the Lusofonia Festival, has been the author of important and awarded works, as is the example of a replica of the Gondomar City Council.
Directly from Brazil will come two female elements, an artisan and a cooking, still without green light to travel to Macao. So “they are a little desperate, especially the cook, since it does not know how much food will have to transport to Macau,” he says.
The boss is from Minas Gerais, but lives currently in Rio de Janeiro. "The recipes that will present in Macau are mainly minerals, where there is very good food, such as the cow drove," he reveals. This dish is basically made with beef ribs and cassava, but made to eliminate most of the fat of the meat itself.
The element that will represent the country of samba in craft events comes from São Luís do Maranhão. “She will show how diverse objects are made with the straw of a tree that only exists in that Brazilian region,” says Carla Fellini.</description><pubDate>2025-09-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“We will do as much as possible to defend the rights and interests of residents”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/faremos-mais-possivel-para-defender-os-direitos-interesses-dos-residentes/</link><description>Composed mainly by “community workers and professionals with extensive experience”, the candidate number 3, the promoting union for progress, highlights the “candidacy goals”, which consists of “improving the well-being of the population, boosting the development of all sectors, promoting good governance, widening the platform and creating a new conjuncture”. In response to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the list also promises to boost the government to accelerate support for emerging industries, stabilize small and medium enterprises, build an inclusive society, create new job openings and define scientific and long -term planning on the development of qualified frames
 
-What reasons have led the Promoting Union list for progress to apply for the Legislative Assembly?
- How is this candidacy from the rest?
- What are the priority problems and what solutions do they propose to solve them?
- What are the expectations in terms of elections? How many seats do you expect to win at the Legislative Assembly?
“Uniting and moving on” is our idea of ​​candidacy. “Improving the well-being of the population, boosting the development of all sectors, promoting good governance, widening the platform and creating a new conjuncture” are our application goals. Focusing on the well-being of the population and the economy, we will propel, with all commitment, the government to effectively solve difficult problems linked to the well-being of the population, such as those related to employment, housing, transport, medical services, education, urban renewal and flooding. In addition, we will install the government to accelerate support for emerging industries, stabilize Small and Medium Enterprises (SMEs), to realize the four projects [announced in the 2025 government lines], to quickly grab the opportunities of the great bay and to build an inclusive society, giving macao in the process of writing a new chapter for the practice of “one country, two systems”.
The Promoting Union for Progress began to run for elections for the Legislative Assembly in 1991 and never stopped. In this edition of the elections, we advanced to another candidacy, persisting in our initial intention to “work effectively for the population”. This time, our team of candidates is made up of 10 people, who are Leong Hong Sai, Ngan Iek Hang, Lam Ka Chun, Leong Chon Kit, Cheong Sok Leng, Li Yongjian, Hong Wai Tong, Chan Meng Kei, Choi Hang Kit and Cheang Man Hou.
Our team has absorbed, on its own initiative, young candidates, which injects a new dynamic throughout the team. On the other hand, candidates are mainly community and professional workers with extensive experience. We actively increased the percentage of experienced economy professionals, in order to respond to increasingly growing economic and employment challenges and to pronounce the welfare of residents, thus boosting Macau's development to reach a new level.
Our team will continually boost the government to “raise the quality of social services, improve the use of residents, support emerging industries, stabilize SMEs, respond to housing demand, further facilitate travel, accelerate remodeling of old neighborhoods, reinforce legislative coordination, jointly build a full environment, to safeguard a beautiful environment, to make the four projects together, to make the four projects. foster an inclusive society, and negotiate and build together hengqin ”.
In addition, we will do as much as possible to defend the reasonable rights and interests of residents, transmit the real demands of the local population, to oversee governance, according to the law, of the executive, to promote the improvement of the population's well-being, to boost social progress and to realize the beautiful desire of residents of living and working in peace and satisfactorily. In the areas to which residents pay more attention, the economy and use, currently, the industrial structure of Macau is evolving from focus on a single sector to a diversified structure. However, the development of emerging industries requires some time, SME operations are facing many difficulties, residents face the problem of structural unemployment and low performance groups live difficult.
In the future, we will try, with all the commitment, the continuation and adjustment of employment support measures, and to boost the government to coordinate game operators to continuously increase the investment in the game -related elements, establish effectiveness assessment indicators and do well the revitalization work of the six historical zones. In addition, we will promote the implementation of “three levels” support plans for SMEs. At the same time, we intend to boost the government, taking advantage of Macau, make good use of the city's various business cards, related to cuisine and world heritage, as well as, through the opportunities of the “East Asia Culture City” and national games, develop abundant community tourist activities.
In the long run, we will urge the government to detail medium and long -term planning related to the development of emerging industries and to create more favorable conditions, to inject dynamics into the lasting and healthy development of the economy and create new job openings, so that we write a new chapter for the development of Macao.
In addition, we will propel the government to continuously improve social policies and linked to the well-being of the population, and to optimize the benefit regime and the general support system. In addition, we will work so that the government defines measures to support employment directed to different groups of the population and establish the integrated vocational training platform. On the other hand, we will work to reinforce road transport infrastructures and optimize public transportation services. We will also promote the work of elaboration of detail plans for different zones of the city, systematic planning and the reasonable use of resources consisting of the unoccupied land.
Another task of our team is to try to realize the connection mechanism between public housing from different scales, the reconstruction of the seven housing blocks in the Iao Hon neighborhood and the change of permanent deposit location to dangerous substances. As for education, we will work to increase the quality of education and the acceleration of the construction of the set of schools in zone A of new landfills. We also intend to boost the government to define a long -term scientific planning on the development of qualified staff and, on the other hand, to improve, in a timely manner, the departure mechanism of non -resident workers. In addition, we will promote the development of modern finances and the effective supervision of financial risks by the government.
 
*Note: List 3 chose to send full text, not specifically answering the questions.
 
JTM and Electoral Act
In accordance with the electoral law, the Jornal Tribuna de Macao continues to cover the campaign for legislative elections on September 14. Like previous years, we will adopt a model that aims to inform our readers about the ideas defended by the various candidacies, under the premise of granting the same journalistic treatment to all competing lists in direct suffrage. Without prejudice to any general reports on the elections, never focused on specific lists, we will present interviews with the different candidacy teams, which will be entitled to a page until the campaign is closed, naturally without any charges for the lists, as a way to provide a public interest service to readers.
In this sense, we sent a fixed set of questions to all applications, whose answers will be published over the next few days, in increasing order of the number of the lists in the voting newsletters, among those we have received until the day of production of the edition.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-09-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Boss appeals to the vote in letters sent to civil servants</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-apela-ao-voto-em-cartas-enviadas-aos-funcionarios-publicos/</link><description>Civil servants are receiving a letter from the Chief Executive to appeal to the vote for the Legislative Assembly elections, on September 14, reported the Macao of TDM. Sam Hou Fai says the vote is a way for civil servants to demonstrate that they are faithful to MSAR and also asks workers to encourage others to go to the polls. This year, it should be noted, two lists were disqualified, with only six competitors to direct suffrage. In 2021, when there were disqualifications for the first time, Macau then recorded the highest abstention rate of 57.6%
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The chief executive sent letters to civil servants to appeal to the vote in the legislative elections, scheduled for September 14, advanced the Macau of TDM channel, saying that the letters are being delivered in hand to the workers and that they have to sign a document that proves that they have learned of the content. In the missive signed by Sam Hou Fai, the government leader says that the vote is a way for civil servants to demonstrate that they are faithful to masters.
According to the channel Macao, in the letter, Sam Hou Fai begins by saying that the elections for the Legislative Assembly are the first that happen after the revision of the electoral law, noting that the amendments aim to reinforce the implementation of the “Macao governed by Patriotas” principle. He then states that the New Public Service Statute (ETAPM) - which will only come into force in November - provides for employees to defend the basic law and be faithful to MSAR. Going to vote is, for the chief executive, the way workers show that they meet the new rule.
“According to the recently revised ETAPM, workers of public services and public entities should defend the basic law and be faithful to the Masters of the Popular Republic of China,” says Sam Hou Fai in the Massive, according to the public television station.
Then he adds that the Legislative Assembly (AL) "is the Legislative body of the MSAR provided for in the Basic Law, and the fact that the workers of public services and entities elect representatives in the legislative body through their vote is precisely a relevant demonstration of the defense of basic law and the fidelity to masters."
Entitled “Letter to all workers of the public services and entities”, the mass, which arrives from the chief executive's office also points out that the vote is a right, but also a duty. In this sense, the population should participate “actively” in the elections, especially civil servants.
The letter says that, "being part of the Governing Team of the MSAR, workers of services and public entities must actively respond to the appeal of the ALC Electoral Affairs, diligently fulfill their duty to vote and encourage family and friends to vote."
The leader of the MSAR also asks public services that they are flexible so that workers who are in service can vote. As for employees who are not at work on this day, Sam Hou Fai leaves a message: “The remaining workers of services and public entities must act in advance and actively participate in the election day, moving to the voting assembly to vote to elect representatives in the Legislative Body of the Masters and offer their contribution to stable and lasting implementation of the principle, two systems.
In the race to the AL there are six candidate lists for direct suffrage, the lowest number of ever. It is recalled that two lists, including one led by the current deputy Ron Lam, were disqualified by the State Security Defense Commission to consider candidates "not defending the basic law or are not faithful to masters." Judge Seng Ioi Man, president of Caeal, refused to explain the concrete reasons for disqualification, arguing that he could "represent certain risks to national security."
In 2021, it is recalled, Caeal disqualified, for the first time, candidates for legislative elections-five lists and 21 candidates, 15 of which pro-democracy. This year, Macau then registered the highest abstention rate of 57.6%.</description><pubDate>2025-09-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DSAT studies regulation to order online taxis</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dsat-estuda-regulamentacao-para-pedir-taxis-online/</link><description>DSAT had said that in a timely manner it would study taxis marking through online platforms-now the body is doing it “actively” as well as analyzing how this activity can be regulated in the territory. Until the end of June, Macau had 1,583 taxis, of which only three hundred were radiotaxis
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The government “is actively promoting the study related to the introduction of taxi calls by online platforms, as well as the regulation of the respective activity”. Earlier this year, the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) had indicated that this issue would be the subject of timely analysis.
Now, in response to an interpellation of Deputy Ron Lam, the government organism points out that the idea is “the introduction of a normalized management model that allows effectively to safeguard the rights and interests of both passengers and drivers, while responding to social development and market needs”. Other details on the subject are sent later.
DSAT recalls that last year studies were commissioned from academic institutions on the number of taxis required and the appropriate service level for Macao, and a new study is underway in this context. This new study “includes research and evaluation of data on the development of the future fleet dimension, as well as the analysis of the impacts and benefits of the development of radiotaxis service on the functioning of urban traffic and the quality of services provided”.
In the background, the investigation intends to “contribute to the improvement of call and marking services”. In this sense, DSAT says it expects that “strict scientific data and in -depth analysis” by experts and academics can provide “solid references and foundations for policy formulation and sector supervision, ensuring order in the exploitation of taxis and the defense of the legitimate rights and interests of all parties involved”.
By the end of June, Macau had a total of 1,583 taxis, of which 1,283 were the normal "black" taxis. As for special or radiotaxis, DSAT statistics were counted, a total of 300, of which most were normal (258), with large vehicles (20), affordable taxis (12) and lift seat taxis (10). Only three hundred taxis are licensed for online services.
It is recalled that, according to Dsat data, in the first nine months of the year, about 30.39 million calls of special taxis were recorded, with “a response rate not exceeding 50%”.
Taxi picking up the city is not an easy task, with many voices asking for online marking and many others to talk about introducing a service similar to Uber.
On the other hand, in the same response to Ron Lam, DSAT says it attributes “great importance” to the opinions of the Audit Commissioner regarding the provision of services by the special taxis. In this sense, it states that it required the company that “it takes the vehicle detachment at a 30 minutes in advance, as stipulated in the contract”.
In addition, “to encourage a quick response from special taxis to passenger calls, particularly in old areas, hospitals, public housing and other areas of population interest”, DSAT has created in various places specific to special taxis, allowing special taxis to wait for passengers' calls, “thus increasing the success rate in service”.
"To safeguard the public interest and respond to the population's demand for taxi services, DSAT has been committed to maintaining the stability of the number of taxis in circulation," says the body.</description><pubDate>2025-09-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Xi says that China's rejuvenation is “unstoppable”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/xi-diz-rejuvenescimento-da-china-e-imparavel/</link><description>EPA12347639 Chinese President XI JINPING (C) Attends The Military Parade Marking The 80th Anniversary of the End of the Sino-Japanese War in Beijing, China, 03 SEPTEMBER 2025. CHINA HOLDS ON 03 SEPTEMBER CELEBRATIONS TO MARK THE ENDIVERSARY OF THE SECHD SINE-JAPANESE WAR, KNOWN IN CHINA AS THE WAR OF RESISTANCE AGAINST THE JAPANESE AGGRESSION, AND THE END OF WORLD WAR II.  EPA/WU HAO



China yesterday paralyzed its capital to display military power in a parade in which President XI Jinping, flanked by his Russian and North Korean counterparts Vladimir Putin and Kim Jong-un, said that "the great rejuvenation of the Chinese nation is unstoppable." The arrival of the three leaders to Tiananmen Square gave way to a 80th artillery shot that symbolized the anniversary of the end of World War II, before the flag of the Popular Republic of China and the solemn execution of the National Anthem, the “Volunteer March”, composed in 1935 during the resistance to the Japanese invasion.
"The Chinese people made a great contribution to save human civilization and defend world peace. Today, humanity once again faces choices: peace or war, dialogue or confrontation, mutually beneficial cooperation or zero -sum games," proclaimed the Chinese leader. With Putin sitting on his right and Kim on the left, Xi warned that "only when countries treat themselves as equal and live in harmony, common security can be safeguarded, the causes of the eliminated war, and the tragedies of history prevented from repeating themselves."
"The great rejuvenation of the Chinese nation is unstoppable, and the noble cause of peace and development for humanity will undoubtedly triumph," he said, from a car with panoramic ceiling, passing 45 columns of the Popular Liberation Army (ELP), which leads as president of his central commission.
In a brief speech, Xi recalled the victims of World War II (1939-1945) and called on the eradication of the causes of war to prevent the repetition of history. The main message, however, was the affirmation of China's role in the world: "The Chinese people are a people who do not fear violence, they are self-sufficient and strong," he said.
"We will follow the path of peaceful development and work hand in hand with the peoples of all countries to build a community of future shared for humanity," he said.
In a choreographed event to the tiny detail, the parade went on a troop exhibition, heavy weaponry and a flywth of aircraft, with the participation of war veterans against Japan and modern units. Among them, drugs equipped with artificial intelligence, state-of-the-art early warning aircraft and new anti-navy hypersonic missiles, such as YJ-20 and YJ-21, as well as DF-61, considered the most advanced intercontinental missile after the DF-41, which received applause from thousands of people who attended the event.
Anti-Missile defense systems were also presented, such as HQ-29 and HQ-20, in addition to the KJ-600, China's first early warning aircraft to operate from aircraft carrier. Also noteworthy is the Type 99B tank, with active drone protection, and the PHL-16 launcher, known as “Chinese Himars” for its role in potential war scenarios in Taiwan Strait. And before the launch of colorful balloons and doves of peace, the main event: the “global” nuclear missile Dongfeng-5C.
The parade pointed out the formal surrender of Japan in 1945 and emphasized Beijing's role in the fight against fascism in the Asian operations Theater, which, according to the official press, was “selectively ignored and underestimated” in the West.
Chinese historians argue that World War II actually began in 1931 with the Japanese invasion of China (1931-1945), which caused more than 35 million casualties among troops and civilians until 1945, according to data from Beijing. Beijing emphasizes their role in the exhaustion of Japanese military resources during the war, contributing to the defeat of the axis powers.
The parade also took place in a context of tensions with the US and at a time when China seeks to present itself as a trusting partner as an alternative to the West, especially in the global south, and to defend multipolarity against Western hegemony. Beijing has sought to take advantage of the uncertainties caused by the return of Donald Trump to the US presidency, while continuing to take steps towards the purpose of consolidating his position as the main global superpower of the 21st century, which also requires the use of a modern army that projects power.
 
JTM with Lusa and International Agencies</description><pubDate>2025-09-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CSR renews contract for another 10 years</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/csr-renova-contrato-por-mais-10-anos/</link><description>The company that currently proceeds to the city's urban cleaning services will renew the concession contract for another 10 years. CSR won the public tender launched last November by the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services. The company is expected to receive more than three million patacas over the next decade
The Limited Waste Systems Company (CSR) will continue to provide urban cleaning services for another 10 years after winning the public tender launched by the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) in November last year, Macau News Agency ”.
Eight companies participated in the contest, having one of them later disqualified. In February, DSPA revealed the identity of the seven admitted competitors. CSR's proposal was in the middle range, with three competitors to have higher and three lower proposals.
According to Macau News Agency, pursuant to the new contract, CSR is expected to receive approximately 3.3 billion patacas over the next decade. The previous concession, also awarded for 10 years of duration (between 2014 and 2024), was evaluated by 2.07 billion patacas, but was increased in 2015 by about 66 million to reflect the increase in costs in Macao.
With the beginning of this new contract, in 2014, the government assured that it would introduce a service evaluation system, in addition to existing inspection, in order to reinforce supervision and control and raise the quality of services provided.
Control was made through various urban cleaning, maintenance and management and public relations classification indicators, covering periodic evaluation items, namely the levels of cleaning of neighborhoods, containers and cargo vehicles and discharge of solid waste, adaptation to new government policies, rapidly issuing answers to cases of complaints, monitoring of cases, among others.
In this contract that now expired, the environment was introduced for the first time, requiring the operating company to have necessarily opted for products with environmental efficiency, such as adequate vehicles, facilities, equipment, materials and consumer products with environmental preservation effects.
In May 2013, the company won the public tender, a result that was contested in court by Urbaser S.A. The court ruled in favor of this company, and CSR remained in the market, where it has been for over 10 years. At the time, CSR presented the lowest price for the service and received the highest score.
The urban solid waste collection company and the city's cleaning under contract with the government, employs more than 670 employees and operates more than 200 vehicles and equipment, being controlled by Veoli Environment, a French multinational founded in 1853, whose activities mainly include four areas: water supply and management, waste management, energy and transport. Veolo employs about 300,000 people and is quoted at Euronext Paris and the New York Stock Exchange.
At Raehk, Veolo leads several projects, including the T-Park installation, which treats sewage slams using a self-sufficient energy and water system. The muds are incinerated, with the heat generated to be used to produce electricity to feed the installation itself, while surplus energy is fed to the public network. The complex also houses a seawater desalination unit and an environmental education center.
According to the official bulletin, CSR Macau has gained concession contracts since 1999. The company's former directors were considered guilty and convicted in a case of corruption related to former Secretary of Transport and Public Works, to Man Long, relating to contracts between 2002 and 2006.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-09-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>STD brings Portuguese gastronomy and culture to Wuhan</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dst-leva-gastronomia-cultura-portuguesas-wuhan/</link><description>Folklore dance and Portuguese gastronomy will be part of a Macao tourist promotion action in downtown China, from 5 to 8 September, the authorities announced. The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) said Macao Week in Wuhan, the capital of Hubei province, will bring spectacles to a popular public square in the historic area of ​​Hankou, one of China's first places open to trade with abroad in 1861.
Among the shows will be the Portuguese Folk Dance Group Association of Portuguese Dances and Singing 'Macau in the Heart', "to allow more people in Wuhan to feel the culture and hospitality of Macao," added STD in a statement.
In the historic area of ​​Hankou will also be installed several thematic zones, one of which will present products from Portuguese -speaking countries.
Macao Week in Wuhan will also start a gastronomic festival, which will take place between September 5 and October 8, in a Chinese city hotel, STD added in the same note.
Two Portuguese chiefs based in Macau, Herlander Fernandes and Pedro Santos do Carmo will prepare a 'buffet' with Portuguese and macanese dishes, STD said.
Even before Macao's Week in Wuhan, STD, the Macao Trade and Investment Promotion Institute (IPIM), and the authorities of the Hengqin Special Economic Zone will also seek to promote cooperation with Hubei Province.
The three entities will organize a business exchange session and event promotion conference to encourage entrepreneurs from both cities to “deepen the pragmatic exchange” in areas such as tourism, conventions and exhibitions, economics and commerce, STD said. According to Ipim yesterday in a statement, in the delegation there will be 40 entrepreneurs to make these contacts.
It is also said that game operators will present their services and products, and several online travel agencies and China's interior airlines will also sell tourist products. Tour operators will present tourist promotions in the total amount of more than 26 million Renminbis, including plane tickets, hotel accommodation, restoration, among others.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-09-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Local Curator Project Revive “Jacone”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/projecto-de-curadoria-local-reaviva-jacone/</link><description>The “Jacone Tower”, one of the six local curator projects of the Macao International Biennial, will be inaugurated on the 19th of this month. The exhibition has the participation of several artists, local and interior of China, in honor of Wu Li, who resided in Macao and was one of the six masters of the beginning of the Qing Dynasty

























Pedro Milheirão
Inserted in the Macao International Art Biennial Program, the show “The Jacone Tower” will be inaugurated on September 19, curated by Cindy Ng Sio Ieng and Fen Yan. The exhibition is one of the six local curatorship projects and will be evident until November 16, in a restored building of Rua dos Curtores, in No. 3 of Travessa dos Poços, according to a statement from the Artistic Association of the New Macao means. With the authorship of multiple creators, videos, multimedia pieces, music, performance and “fascinating” installations that “channel the spirit of the artist Wu Li” will be presented.
Beijing's artist Jiang Jun will present the “data sonnets”, using Wu Li's poetry “as the basis for generating new visual texts through algorithms to give body to contemporary historical genes and contexts,” says the statement. Liu Xiangbo, from Shanghai, will reshape Wu Li's sacred song, "Tianae Zhengyin PU", with paper bricks, and create "concrete symbols of faith" alongside recycled materials. In “100 × 100 container”, Liu will collect information from the former Wu Li cemetery in Shanghai, with a view to “solidify historical traces in portable and reconfigurable micro-units”, which will be taken to the exhibition.
Macaense Veronica Lei Fong Ieng will build a “spiritual dialogue with Wu Li through time and space”, using wax, wood and aluminum foil, in “Veneration of the Rose”. Chi Wai, also Macao's artist, will resort to distorted images generated “through dynamic errors in 3D digital scanning” to represent 12 states of human existence in “Divine spread: between data and meat”. In the play “Prayers for Writing”, Chi Wai will deconstruct symbols of faith and 3D images of sacred spaces, reorganizing and presenting them to “echo the contemporary resonance of Macao's multiculturalism and historical memory”.
Loi Nok Man will use your voice to trigger “dynamic visuals in real time through a microphone, with intangible sound waves generating fluid visual projections”. In turn, also Curator Cindy NG Sio Ieng will present three works. In "fluid polyphony," the "divine genes of church stained glass" and "oriental abstractions" will become visual emotions of space. In "Void Sub-Nom, he will create" a space for spiritual healing. " The ink, the light and the “luminous quantity pupil” space.
Rua dos Tankers was once known as the village of Liang Shui Jing, a community where the poet, painter and caleigion Wu Li lived, who resided three years in Macao. In addition to being one of the six masters of the beginning of the Qing period, Wu was also a devout Catholic and Jiangsu's Jesuit missionary, referring to himself as "Jacone", having studied Latin and theology at the São Paulo College.
On the afternoon of September 18, there will also be an inaugural reception, a musical show by Loi Nok Man, a meeting with the artists and a guided tour with the curators. From 4 pm on the 20th, there will be a second guided tour with the curators, another action by Loi Nok Man and a meeting with the authors of the exhibition. Interested parties will be able to visit the exhibition from Tuesday to Sunday, between noon and 19h00. In addition, guided tours will be organized in Mandarin every Sunday.</description><pubDate>2025-09-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Canton Theater celebrates China's birthday with “Swan”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/teatro-de-cantao-comemora-aniversario-da-china-cisne/</link><description>On September 30th and October 1st, the Venetian Theater will mark the 76th anniversary of the Popular Republic of China with two sessions of the Canton Acrobatic Art Theater “Cisne”, in an account of the acrobat formative journey Yu Meng
 
The Venetian Theater will host the “76th Anniversary Show show of the Implementation of the Popular Republic of China and Haojiang's Luar Night - New Acrobatic Sign Scyel”, at 8 pm on September 30 and October 1, the Cultural Institute (IC) announced. “Swan” is a production of the award -winning Canton Acrobatic Art Theater, which reports the “exciting course of growth and formation of acrobatic artist Yu Meng”.
Yu's journey begins in "Sweating Training Fields" and unfolds to its climb to a "stunning stage," the press release says. In a course between the "dream" and the "real", the spectators will experience a "impressive fusion between national artistic excellence and a fantastic visual show."
Under the direction of Zhao Ming, a renowned choreographer, the production involves “prestigious artists”, as well as “timeless melodies” of the classic western work “The Lake of Swan”, integrating a series of “great and unpublished” Chinese acrobatics, in a mix of oriental and western art. In addition, the actress and founder of the “Shoulder Ballet”, Wu Zhengdan will be in charge of the Artistic Directorate.
“Cisne” was selected for the Financial Support Program by the National Arts Fund, and even won a prize of excellence. Tickets for the show are available today, at the ticket of “Enjoy Macao”, with prices of 200, 300 and 400 patacas. Cotai ticket will also make tickets available on a date to be announced later, says the IC.
BIR MACAU holders, full -time student card, Macao teacher card, elderly card or disability assessment card will benefit a 50%discount. Tickets can also be reserved by telephone line through “Enjoy Macao” or “Cotai Ticketing”.
The show is organized by the Ministry of Culture and Tourism, the Secretariat for Social Affairs and Culture, the Department of Advertising and Culture of the Central Government connection in the MSAR, coordinated by the IC and the “China Performing Arts Agency Productions”, and has the support of Sands China.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-09-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Boss expects “Espírito da Resistance” East “Macao Compatriots”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-espera-espirito-da-resistencia-oriente-compatriotas-de-macau/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai moved to Beijing, in the context of the celebration of the 80th anniversary of the victory of the War of Resistance of the Chinese people against Japanese aggression. The Chief Executive said that the people of the Mand must be guided by the "spirit of resistance" in strengthening "love of the country and Macao". The five secretaries and various public services praised the celebration of the ephemeris, and about 60,000 people attended the celebrations in the territory

The chief executive was yesterday at the celebrations of the 80th anniversary of the victory of the War of Resistance of the Chinese people against Japanese aggression and the anti -fascist World War, which took place at Tiananmen Square in Beijing. In a statement issued after the celebration of the ephemeris, Sam Hou Fai stated that “the entire population of Macau should be oriented by the spirit of resistance against Japanese aggression, strengthen the conviction in the love of the homeland and Macau and strive tirelessly to move on on the new journey”, according to the Cabinet of Social Communication (GCS).
For the leader of MSAR, "All Macao compatriots" must "remember the story, pay tribute to the martyrs and value the stability that was not easy to achieve." He also asserted that "all residents of Macao should contribute determination to national development, mutual learning between civilizations and world peace, making greater contributions to writing new chapters of the principle of" one country, two systems "."
Sam Hou Fai recalled that, "During the 14 years of resistance against Japanese aggression, the Communist Party of China defended and always persisted in a united national front against Japanese aggression, playing a fundamental role." After being "wrapped in gunpowder," the People's Republic of China has established its position as a great world power. " He also expressed pride in the form "how the country raised, enriched and strengthened, starting a historical journey, reborn from the ashes and gaining splendid success."
For the leader of the MSAR, the ceremony was an incentive "to overcome all difficulties and obstacles." "The dedication and sacrifice of the ancestors" established "the conscience of a community with a shared future for humanity," believing that it must "firmly follow the path of peaceful development" and safeguard stability "with commitment". Sovereignty, security and interests of state development must be defended, "in order to inject a strong intellectual dynamics for the realization of the great revitalization of the Chinese nation."
 
André Cheong praised Macau's role in the war
In turn, André Cheong, as the interim executive chief, stressed that "Macau has never been lacking in the participation and support of the homeland in the resistance war, always being with his homeland in all good and bad moments and the Macao compatriots have always expressed a great spirit of patriotism in their actions."
In a speech given at the Macao Polytechnic University (UPM) multipurpose pavilion, to an audience of young students and government representatives who attended a broadcast of celebrations, the Secretary for Administration and Justice recalled the participation of Macao Associations, who organized activities and raised funds, committed to supporting and assisting the front line.
"The Macao compatriots justified the great patriotic spirit with their actions," said André Cheong, reminding young people who "surpassed difficulties bravely and marched to the battlefields." He also added that "the grand development of the homeland, the stability and prosperity of the sinters are fruits achieved by blood and sacrifice of the martyrs."
"We must remember the history of the War of Resistance, so that the Spirit of Love for the Fatherland and Macao can succeed itself from generation to generation, boosting Macao to develop and prosper together with the homeland," said the secretary in a statement. To the same time, history should "encourage young people to study with determination and commitment, broaden their vision and reinforce their abilities, bind their personal growth with national progress, with a view to contributing more to the construction of the country and Macao."
Manifesting a "deep sadness for the compatriots who tragically lost their lives during the war," Cheong pointed out that the "significant victories" of the Chinese people, "after the persistence and resilience of 14 years of bloody struggles," were "a historical turning point, where the Chinese nation went from humiliation to rebirth." The Chinese people demonstrated an "extraordinary courage," "also consolidating the foundations for China to restore their position as great world power."
André Cheong also stated that "the military parade was an important element," demonstrating "China's commitment to defense the fruits of victory in World War II, and promoting a community with a shared future for humanity."
In addition, he encouraged the Chinese people to “fight united in favor of the construction of a strong country and the revitalization of the Chinese nation”. "Commemorative activities are to celebrate victories, and also as a message so that the pain of war will never forget, and value and safeguard peace and tranquility," he said.
Kou Hoi In, President of the Legislative Assembly, believes that the parade has transmitted a "firm confidence." "The eyes of the military were full of faithfulness to the country, telling us that we should not forget the story, but we must value peace and fight constantly." He also asked the residents of Macao, and in particular to young people, to "be aware of where today's happiness comes from."
“We are capable and determined in safeguarding sovereignty, security and state development interests and we do not allow the tragic repetition of history. We realized that victory was not easily achieved,” Kou reiterated. "The military parade is a demonstration of the nation's cohesion and the affection for the homeland. It allows us to evaluate the present, display national power and firmly safeguard peace," he said.
Educational institutions and various departments of the Government of MSA have organized sessions for students and civil servants to be able to attend the broadcast of the celebrations. According to GCS, about 60,000 people watched the celebrations. The five secretaries of the Government of MSAR, various government services and the Public Prosecution Service praised the festivities.
The event that took place at UPM was attended by the secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM, Secretary for Security, Wong Sio Chak, Commander-General of Unit Police Services, Leong Man Cheong, subdirector of the Central Government Cabinet, Zhang Yingjie, and the RPC Ministry of Foreign Ministry, Liu Xianfa, between Other government officials, individualities of different sectors and students' representatives.</description><pubDate>2025-09-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Luís Montenegro will come to Macau on September 10</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/luis-montenegro-vira-macau-10-de-setembro/</link><description>EPA12158372 Portuguese Prime Minister Luis Montenegro Speaks During Swearing in Ceremony of the XXV Constitutional Government Held at Help Palace, in Lisbon, Portugal, 05 June 2025. The ad coalition (PSD/CDS-PP), LED by Luis Montenegro, won the legislative elections with absolute an absolute an absolute Majority, Electing 91 Deputies Out Of 230, Of Which 89 Are from the PSD and Two from the CDS-PP. ARRIVES BECAME THE SECOND LARGEST PARULIARY FORCE WITH 60 MPS, FOLLOWED BY PS WITH 58, IL WITH NINE, FREE WITH SIX, PCP WITH THREE AND BE, PAN AND JPP WITH ONE EACH.  EPA/JOSE SENA GOULAO



Portuguese Prime Minister Luís Montenegro will be in Macao on September 10, confirmed his office to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. The visit to the MSAR takes place as part of a trip to China. In the territory, Montenegro has foreseen a meeting with the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, and will visit the Portuguese school, a usual point of passage of the Portuguese rulers. From the agenda of the Portuguese Government head will still be a reception to the community. It is recalled that it was in June that the President of the Republic, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, announced that Luís Montenegro should pass through Macau during a visit to the Popular Republic of China. At the time, Marcelo was expected to come to the territory at the time of the June 10th celebrations. Asked if he would still come to Macau in his second and last presidential term, which will end on March 9 next year, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa replied: "No. Go Prime Minister, if you can, but further forward in September." "While I go to the United Nations, he goes to Macao, China. Because he has a visit to China that also was around Macao," he added. However, Sam Hou Fai's official visit to Portugal and Spain, which was scheduled for the period from September 16 to 20, was postponed, without a new date for its realization. The visit to Portugal would be the first trip to foreigners since Sam Hou Fai took office as head of the Executive of MSA in December last year.</description><pubDate>2025-09-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Government grants 230 million for childhood support</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-concede-230-milhoes-para-apoio-na-infancia/</link><description>The government will attribute, tomorrow, the childhood assistance allowance for this year, in a single installment, to the qualified persons of the first round, in the amount of 18,000 patacas. According to IAS, until July 31, 13,000 cases were presented and approved, and the total amount of assignment of the respective subsidy will be more than 230 million Patacas
 
Tomorrow, September 4, the Government will assign the childhood assistance for this year, of single performance to the qualified persons of the first round, in the amount of 18,000 patacas, the Institute of Social Action (IAS) announced yesterday.
According to the body, until July 31 this year, about 13,000 lawsuits were presented and approved. The father, mother or tutor of babies or children who have been born from 2022 to 2025 and who hold the permanent resident identity ticket of the MSAR, may submit the request of the childhood assistance allowance for the year 2025 since July 16 this year and until June 30, 2026.
IAS has revealed that it will assign the subsidy for this year to qualified persons, tomorrow, through bank transfer, being the total amount of attribution of more than 230 million patacas.
On the other hand, in relation to the requests submitted between August 1 this year and June 30 of next year, the allowance will be awarded within 60 days from the day after the date on which the request has been approved, IAS added, recalling that the creation of this support aims to “encourage the birth and to realize financial support measures for families with babies or children”.
It is recalled that, according to the stipulations defined by the authorities, the support, paid in a single installment, provisional in nature and intended for families with babies or permanent resident children with under three years, has a value of 18,000 patacas, which means that, in the three years, the beneficiary family will receive a total of 54,000 patacas.
Regarding the possibility of the measure continuity after 2027, IAS President Hon Wai said in June this year that, being a new plan, it is necessary to “collect more data” and make an analysis and then make a decision. Already the spokesman for the Executive Board and Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, added that intention is not to “cut” the measure after three years, reiterating that it is necessary to do an analysis and understand if the plan must be optimized or, for example, create a different measure.
Birth in the territory has continued to give signs of decrease, having registered, in the second quarter of this year, the lowest number of births since at least 1998, according to data from statistics and census services. Between April and June, 671 babies were counted, 79 less than the 750 registered in the first three months of the year.
Looking at the semester, 1,421 babies were born in Macao, 17% less compared to last year's same-year period, when 1,710 was registered.
It is recalled that, at the beginning of the year, the Deputy Director of Health Services predicted that there should be less than 3,500 births in the territory this year, which, to happen, will be the lowest since 2004.
In the general calculation of last year, the number of undead totaled 3,607, 105 less in terms, with the birth rate to be 5.3 °, the lowest since 1985. Macau registered only 0.58 births per woman, the lowest fertility rate ever in the world and the lowest in the world.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Gilberto Camacho appointed Costa Nunes Subdirector</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/gilberto-camacho-nomeado-subdirector-costa-nunes/</link><description>D. José da Costa Nunes Kindergarten this year has a subdirector. This is Gilberto Camacho, who took office on the first day of September. For Miguel de Senna Fernandes, president of the Macanese Instruction Promoter Association, the day care manager, the appointment arrested with the school's work needs and because “now conditions are increasingly complex and the requirements of education services are more strict”. The nursery starts today for another school year and has a new reduction of children. There will be 191, less 33 than in 2024/2025. The director, Felizbina Carmelita Gomes, notes that there is a decrease in the number of children for three consecutive years

Victor Rebelo
 
There is a new position in the organic structure of the kindergarten D. José da Costa Nunes, with the entry of a subdirector, a position that has not existed in the institution for about 10 years. This is Gilberto Camacho, who hitherto performed duties in the computer sector of the same child school, and that from the first day of September began to assist the director, Felizbina Carmelita Gomes.
For the president of the Macanese Instruction Association (Apim), who manages the day care center, the appointment was a decision “for the kind of kindergarten”, because “now conditions are increasingly complex and the requirements of education services (DSEDJ) are more rigorous, so that, in order to charge all this, it is necessary, beyond the competence of the director, that there is someone who can coad.”
Miguel de Senna Fernandes told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that "during this time, the computer man eventually met all the intricacies of the house, and is therefore the person who could best hold his hand to the director, with all due respect for all employees who work on Costa Nunes."
The leader adds that Apim also wants, "with this opportunity, to make known that he is aware of the situation and working conditions of all staff." Therefore, he stresses, "we want to reinforce Apim's own administrative body, and, as we have this close relationship with the kindergarten, we naturally intend the best for school, that is, to endow it with another very important person, at least to give it the status he had long been having in practice, which was the subdirector."
The number one of the Apim points out that this is a “very good bet”, hoping that the element recently promoted to a management position “can charge all the situations that are placed”.
It concludes, admitting that the association itself will strive to reinforce the administrative body, "since there must be a new vision on how to act."
Since Macaense took the lead of Apim in 2016, "there has never been a subdirector," he said. “I remember that the school was subdirector Pedro Ascension, who would later assume the roles of director after the departure of Lola Couto do Rosário,” said Senna Fernandes.
Regarding the appointment of Gilberto Camacho, the director of the infantary, Felizbina Carmelita Gomes, confirmed to JTM that the entry of a subdirector, proposed by Apim, “actually comes to help with the work we have and the connection with DSEDJ, since it takes more personal to work in the part of the school itself, to provide better services to the community”.
The nursery starts today another academic year, after yesterday a meeting with parents and guardians of children of children.
Regarding the number of students enrolled for 2025/2026, it is totaling 191, less 33 than last year, when the school was 224, divided by three levels, from three to five years of age. Children will be distributed by 11 classes, less than in the previous school year, and 10 of the rooms are intended for regular education and one to special education.
It is recalled that in 2023/2024 there were Nunes 13 classes (12+1) on the Costa Nunes and a total of 250 students. There has been, therefore, the reduction of a class in each of the last three years.
The low birth rate remains the main reason for decreasing students. "This is the reality, that is, reduction of students directly caused by the weak birth in Macao, a situation that has been reflected at the beginning of each academic year for three consecutive years," noted the director of the nursery.
Despite the reduction of children, the school did not reduce the number of educators, who are currently 24, including the director, who join nine teaching agents and 12 assistants, as well as a dozen employees who perform diverse functions in the school. "It is our policy not to say goodbye to anyone, notwithstanding this decrease of children, therefore, there is no exits or entries," the guardian reinforces.
In the previous school year, Costa Nunes had a lack of speech therapists, but the situation is already resolved. "We are not lacking these experts for this year," he said in statements to this newspaper.
 
English language development
Another important part of teaching is the learning and development of the English language. In this field, the nursery has an educator expressly for this purpose, teaching all classes once a week. “Through the DSEDJ subsidy, we had a contract to provide this type of work and service that we have been doing for two years, encompassing children from the three levels of the school,” he says.
Regarding extracurricular activities, which will take place throughout the year, “after classes, because sometimes parents have this need to leave children”, the childhood garden will keep entertainment dedicated to sport, specifically soccer, and also painting, cooking, Chinese martial arts, yoga, among others.
Felizbina Carmelita Gomes, director of Costa Nunes since 2022, says that these activities are performed by semesters. "After registration in the first, parents decide if the child wants to develop another type of activities in the second half, this is how we work," he says, adding that "the school is always open to the suggestions of parents and guardians."
Already in the musical component, "this aspect is mandatory in our curriculum," he says, specifying that "for the students of K3 (five years) the music is properly incorporated into their classes, while children from K1 and K2 (three and four years) have a discipline once a week."</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Vietnam celebrates independence from French dominance, but not in gastronomy</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/vietname-celebra-independencia-dominio-frances-mas-nao-na-gastronomia/</link><description>Red Croissants Decorate with Yellow Stars are displayed at the Bakery Shop in Hanoi, Vietnam, August 31, 2025. Reuters/Francesco Guarascio



While Vietnam celebrates the 80th anniversary of its declaration of independence from colonial rule, French cultural influence remains omnipresent, but few people in the country of Southeast Asia are aware of their prevalence.
A great military parade on Tuesday announced independence proclaimed by the revolutionary leader Ho Chi Minh on September 2, 1945, who was supposed to end nearly a century of French dominance, but instead began a war from a decade until the defeated French finally departed in 1954.
Ba Dinh Square, in the center of Hanoi, where the legendary leader, affectionately known in Vietname as Uncle Ho, made his historical statement, is flanked by two of the capital's best preserved French colonial buildings - now the presidential palace and the Ministry of Foreign Affairs.
But none of the six born in Hanoi with less than 30 years interviewed by Reuters in front of the headquarters of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs painted yellow, a masterpiece of the French Indochina-style style, was aware of its architectural origin.
"I came here because it has a unique architecture and is a popular place promoted by celebrities," said Nguyen Thi Trang, 30, who showed surprise when he was informed about the French origin of the building.
Vietname's relationships with France went from colonials to pleasant. When French President Emmanuel Macron visited Hanoi in May, the two countries signed agreements worth $ 10 billion, including purchase of aircraft and satellites.
Macron was delighted when the students of a university event went to him in a perfect French. However, this French fluency - once the language of the elites in Vietname - is increasingly rare, reflecting the global decline of Molière's language.
In 2025, only 400 Vietnamese high school students chose Frenchman as one of the subjects for their undergraduate exams, according to the Ministry of Education, while more than 358,000 chose English and about 4,400 opted for the Chinese.
"If I had to choose, I preferred the Chinese to French as a second foreign language to study because it seems more familiar to me. And China is our neighbor," said 25 -year -old Hoang Thu Ha content creator.
The French Embassy in Hanoi reported that in 2025, 63,000 people were enrolled in French classes, with approximately 400 teachers in Vietnam.
The Frenchman “maintains a certain prestige” in Vietnam, while other languages ​​are rapidly gaining ground in the country of 100 million, including Japanese and Korean, he said.
 
Croissants and pate
Nowhere is the French legacy more visible than in Vietnamese cuisine. Cafes spread throughout the country's streets, croissants are displayed in numerous pastries and the pate is regularly added to local dishes.
Bread -shaped bread is used in the most common local fast food option, known as bath Mi, a salty sandwich with unlimited fillings to please all palates, including vegetarians.
But among the young people of Hanoi interviewed, none recognized the French Banh Mi roots.
Mr. Nguyen Van Hoan, a 60 -year -old entrepreneur, owner of a famous bakery in the center of Hanoi, recognized the French heritage in the love of the Vietnamese for bread.
He explained, however, that, to survive, "French cuisine had to adapt to Vietnamese tastes."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-09-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>