<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Kou Hoi In and Chui Saa Cheong does not compete for al</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/kou-hoi-chui-sai-cheong-nao-concorrem-as-eleicoes-da-al/</link><description>In the field of indirect suffrage, Chui Sai Peng, IP Sio Kai, Si Ka Lon and Kevin Ho constitute the only list of candidates from the industrial, commercial and financial sectors. This time, the current president of AL, Kou Hoi In, does not advance with a reciplination. Also Chui Sai Cheong, the current vice president of AL, is not on the list of professional sector candidates, which consists of Iau Teng Pio, Vong Hou Piu and Jerry Wong Chon Kit. In direct suffrage, Song Pek Kei, Nick Law, Ella Law and Leong Sun Iok apply to apply.
 
The current President of the Legislative Assembly (AL), Kou Hoi In, is not on the list of candidates from the industrial, commercial and financial sectors, for the indirect suffrage of the elections for al. Also Chui Sai Cheong, the current vice president of AL, does not advance with a re-candidacy to the elections, not including his name from the list of candidates from the professional sector.
According to the Chinese language press, the union of Macau business interests submitted, on Friday, to the Commission of Electoral Affairs (Caeal) the political program and a list of four candidates, the only of industrial, commercial and financial sectors. The list consists of the current deputies Chui Sai Peng and IP Sio Kai, elected from these sectors for indirect suffrage, current deputy Si Ka Lon, elected by direct suffrage, as well as the new candidate Kevin Ho.
Of the 108 legal persons of these sectors, the appointment committee to unite business interests is composed of 103 legal persons.
Chui Sai Peng stressed that the team's political program aims to serve the industrial, commercial and financial sectors well, and to defend the reasonable and legitimate rights and interests through scrupulous auscultation, effective analysis and timely transmission. Specifically, it will seek the elaboration and update of legal regimes in favor of the healthy development of traditional companies, growth of emerging companies and establishment of future companies in the territory, also aiming to make Macau's business environment more attractive.
Kevin Ho promised to hear the sectors' requests about promoting the most harmonious and balanced relationship between the labor and employer parts and the creation of more incentives to attract investment from abroad.
On the same day, Lau Veng Seng, the mandate of the interests of Macao professionals, delivered a list of three candidates, the only professional sector, and the team's political program, which obtained 50 support signatures out of a total of 63 voter legal persons.
In the list, in addition to the current deputy named Iau Teng Pio, there are the qualified accountant Vong Hou Piu and doctor Jerry Wong Chon Kit.
Iau Teng Pio stressed that in the future, the team will continue to make suggestions for the development of Macao and contribute to improving social and welfare issues.
Vong Hou Piu said he hopes to present suggestions to oversee the government and do the legislative work well. Jerry Wong said he will pay attention to how the government should make good use of public and private resources in the provision of medical services, as well as the optimization of training and benefits and guarantees for medical staff.
 
Song Pek Kei, Nick Law, Ella Law and Leong Sun IOK recondite
On the other hand, the agent of the Macao United Citizens Association, Chan Meng Kam, submitted to Caeal a list of 10 candidates, who has the current deputy Song Pek Kei as a head-head. Following are the current deputy Nick Kei and Chan Lai Kei.
As revealed, candidates on this list have an average age of 33 years. This time, if Ka Lon, head-heads in 2021, will apply for indirect suffrage.
Song Pek Kei considered that this year's elections will be the most competitive ever, because there are another 10,000 voters. As indicated, the team aims to secure two seats in the hemiciclo.
The political program of the team has several focuses, including the resuming of the investment development fund and the attribution of 1% of fund revenues to boner all residents; A requirement that 85% of gaming companies will be resident and the launch of a 5,000 patacas employment allowance.
There are also the objectives of continuation of the consumer subsidy plan; Creation of general health insurance for the entire population and shortening of waiting time in hospitals; Adjustment of the mechanism for raising the amount of the pension to the elderly and attempts to allow the subsidy for the elderly to be increased to 15 thousand patacas; as well as the extension of childhood assistance allowance up to six years and a progressive increase in the amount of this subsidy.
In turn, the Union for Development has delivered a list of 12 candidates, again led by the current deputies Ella Lei and Leong Sun Iok. In addition, lawyer Cheng Ka Man is the number three on the list. According to candidates, the team is mainly composed of young people.
Ella Law has revealed that the team's political program is the improvement of Macau's business environment, effective promotion of resident use and the creation of better conditions for the well-being of the population. In addition, the candidate assured that the team will reinforce attention and support for the elderly, children, vulnerable groups and women.
In turn, Leong Sun Iok emphasized the team's commitment to promote “good resident jobs” and foster a new cooperation and mutual benefit ecology between the labor and employer parts.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Promised more support to the community economy</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/prometido-mais-apoio-a-economia-comunitaria/</link><description>On a visit to various areas of the city, Sam Hou Fai promised more support for the community economy, in order to “reinforce vitality, attractiveness and competitiveness”. On the other hand, about the canhy, indicated that the contest for the first of two sports zones will soon be launched soon

Catarina Pereira
 
Several neighborhoods of the city received a visit from the Chief Executive, during Saturday - the objective, stressed Sam Hou Fai, was to “pay special attention to the current situation of the community economy”, as well as “listening to more opinions from trade establishments”. In the end, he left some promises, namely to continue supporting these zones of the territory.
"The government will continue to take action, in various dimensions, to improve the business exploration environment in social neighborhoods, reinforce vitality, attractiveness and competitiveness of the community economy, as well as improve social infrastructure and equipment," said Sam Hou Fai, quoted in a note from the Social Communication Office. He also said that he could "feel" the "success" of stores with their own characteristics "to attract residents and tourists."
In the morning, Sam Hou Fai began to visit the Patane Mercado Municipal Complex, accompanied by the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong. There, “dialogue with several sails” to realize the sales situation, exploration and operation of the newsstands. He was also at the Patane Food Center, having talked to residents and tourists. On site, he encouraged food operators "to constantly implement news, so as to explore characteristics that attract more visitors."
Sam Hou Fai vincou que o centro de comidas do Patane “é um exemplo muito bom de transformação característica do mercado”, afirmando que o Executivo e os diferentes sectores da sociedade “devem reflectir e ponderar consoante a situação dos bairros sociais, para que, em conjunto (…) possam aperfeiçoar o ambiente de exploração de negócios e elevar a atractividade aos consumidores”.
Ilha Verde and Fai Chi Kei were the following places, this time accompanied by the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP. The leader of the MSAR visited several trade establishments -to find out about the development of the community economy and to alert opinions about the current business exploitation environment -and also took the opportunity to visit the great social activity to boost the development of the community economy -the “Sanrio Character Dream Garden” and the Feliz of Love Pavilion. According to the press release, the boss "interacted with the students who enjoyed the services" on site.
According to Tai Kin IP, the project of the “Sanrio Character Dream Garden” was launched about 80 days ago, having so far achieved more than 240,000 visitors to the social neighborhood, which reflects the effectiveness of the measure ”. He also explained that the various guardianship services he directs are preparing more projects to “direct visitors to social neighborhoods to activate the community economy”, giving more support to small and medium -sized companies in the North Zone.
 
Contest for works in the canidrome soon
Finally, Sam Hou Fai visited the land of the former Yat Yuen Canid, where it is planned to build a sports park for the population. On the spot, he heard the secretary's presentation for transport and public works, Raymond Tam, about the reordering plan and the situation of the work.
In this context, the leader of the MSAR stated that the government "has started the plan that will turn this space into a sports park for the population, consisting of two zones, and the public contest of the works for the first zone is planned soon." Given the high population density of the North Zone and the lack of social equipment, he explained that “the works of the first zone will be considered so that, as far as possible, they do not affect the functioning of the sports field and the Lin Fong Sports Center, in order to take into account the needs of use of residents”.
Regarding the traffic of the adjacent zones, Sam Hou Fai revealed that the works for the eastern line of the light meter that connects the north to the mud "result in good rhythm". Pointing out that “V terrain” has created conditions that not only allow the east line to approach the border post of the siege gates, but also, in the future, to extend the east to the Qingmao border post, Sam Hou Fai indicated that the government is studying the possibility of extending the line of the light meter from Qingmao Post to Fai Chi Kei neighborhood, “ population ”. The government leader said he believed that "these measures will be effective in relieving the traffic of the area with high population density."
Raymond Tam added that in the underground part of the Sports Park a parking lot will be built with more than 400 places for motor vehicles, and the adjacent road network will be adjusted according to the park's accesses. The secretary also explained that the works of the first and second zone will cover the construction of higher passages for existing pawns, while the facilities without barriers will be perfected.
As for the lots of Jockey Club and Oceanis Park, Sam Hou Fai said only that, for now, they are spare land.
 
Visit to Portugal postponed to the fall
The chief executive revealed that the visit to Portugal, which was designed for July, will be postponed. Sam Hou Fai said that "originally, he had plans to visit Portugal during the summer holidays, however, due to the transition needs of the new government of Portugal and also because there are several important matters in Macao, the official visit abroad is planned to be postponed to the fall." At the time, Sam Hou Fai said, it will also be thoughtful to include Spain and Brussels in the program, "what is currently being approached and coordinated."
 
Rode for six cities in the great bay
Sam Hou Fai will be, until tomorrow, leading a mashed delegation on a visit to six cities in the interior of China that are part of the Great Bay: Shenzhen, Huizhou, Dongguan, Canton, Zhaoqing and Foshan. During his stay, Sam Hou Fai will keep meetings with the leaders of the six cities, to exchange ideas about the continuous boost development, the reinforcement of cooperation with mutual benefits, among other topics, says a note from the Communication Office. The program also includes visits to developments under development and companies in the areas of technological innovation, energy resources, among others, "in order to know the development situation of the important industries of those cities." The delegation, among others, the Secretary for Economics and Finance, the Chief Executive's Chief of Staff and the Director of Policy Study and Regional Development Services.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Arraial had less influx in the tower but “the most important thing is to keep the party”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/arraial-teve-menos-afluencia-na-torre-mas-o-mais-importante-e-manter-festa/</link><description>On the weekend, the São João village was held, which took place in the macao tower enclosure for the second year in a row. Organizers and exhibitors lamented the least influx to the event, even despite the favorable weather conditions



































Pedro Milheirão
The Arraial de São João again held this year at the Torre de Macao venue. The threats of rain for the weekend did not dissuade the public who participated in the festivities who, according to Miguel de Senna Fernandes, pointed out “a historic date of Macao”. To the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the president of the Macanese Association said this was a date that goes beyond the celebration of a popular saint and a day "celebrated by all the macanese communities."
Miguel de Senna Fernandes regretted the fact that there is no “that volume of people as we would like”, due to the “which is not so large” dissemination and the space of Arraial is more tiny. “As much as we want to be outdoors, it is always the space of someone,” adding that the organization has only “thanking the logistical support of the tower”, however, that it would take place in a neighborhood space or street.
"For 11 years, we celebrated in the neighborhood of São Lázaro, with very hot, but it was a very typical thing, attracted the tourists and was very crowded," explaining that "the most important thing is to keep the party." He also addressed the budget issue, short of what is desirable for "a party of burglary."
For António Monteiro, president of the Association of Young Macanese (AJM), “if it wasn't for June 24 (…) Macao would not be the same, since the heritage, the Portuguese language and presence”. Monteiro asserted that “this village is younger” and recalled when the festivities were held in Coloane, at Hac-Sá beach, where “there were bonfires, such hammer, even in the style of Porto”.
Speaking to this newspaper, the AJM leader said that the organization's challenge is currently greater, "because we want [the Arraial] to be classified as Macao's intangible heritage." In this sense, he collaborated with the Association of Macao Heritage Ambassadors, an association formed by young Chinese, with which he tells “to open a window into the Chinese community”, in order to integrate it, “because after all is a Macao party”.
Finally, he highlighted the “small entertainment of the Portuguese part”, such as pimba, brand and folk dance, stressing that it is not a “typical village of Lisbon or Porto, is a Macao Arraial”.
Manuela Guerreiro, the exhibitor at the event, also highlighted the “Portuguese” of the party, where she finds known faces that sometimes “we don't see for almost a year” and where she releases Portuguese condom products. "I've participated since it started in São Lazarus," he said, remembering the neighborhood he considered to be "the ideal site to make St. John." "The community was all over there, even if it rained, which usually happened every year. But it was very cute because people gathered there, no one failed," he said, mourning the fact that there was less influx this year.
Sérgio, son of Manuela Guerreiro, said it was a good opportunity to join the Portuguese community and expose the Portuguese products. The owner of the “Lotus Cocktail” in Taipa says there has been an effort [by the organization] to have “more offer and more tents”, which “unfortunately did not translate into a larger number of visitors,” he lamented.
Marília Coutinho, the exhibitor, also stated that in last year's edition “there was more adhesion”. It justified with the lack of dissemination of the event, asking for more support from the media, and admitting to prefer when the camp was held in the neighborhood of São Lázaro.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Review of the Tabogic Control Law should start soon</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/revisao-a-lei-controlo-tabagico-deve-arrancar-em-breve/</link><description>KITCHING SMOKING CONCEPT. Hand is Refusing Cigarette Offer.



Authorities expect to begin the revision of the smoking control law, and are studying the prohibition of smoking in access to schools and day care centers, "with a view to reducing the impact of tobacco on children and young people." Nevertheless, the government does not intend to implement the “generation without tobacco” policy, according to which the acquisition of tobacco products for individuals who were born from a certain year is prohibited.
 
Os Serviços de Saúde (SSM) vão estudar a criação de mais “locais onde é proibido fumar” nos acessos de entrada e saída das escolas e creches, “com vista a reduzir o impacto do tabaco nas crianças e jovens”, indicou o director substituto do organismo, Cheang Seng Ip, em resposta a uma interpelação de Ron Lam. O organismo afasta também, pelo menos para já, a introdução da política “geração sem tabaco”.
In response to the deputy, it is said that, in view of society's demands on the reinforcement of the control of “smoking” problems, it was explored the creation of a new model of “areas where smoking” is prohibited in larger public spaces. It is thus "allowed to smoke only in certain places."
Ron Lam also questioned the policy “generation without tobacco” - that is, the ban on the acquisition of tobacco products by individuals born after a given year - which the SSM have removed, for now. “According to the information available, New Zealand had organized the launch of this policy, but it was not officially implemented for several reasons.
The body underlines, however, that it has been “observing and investigating” the situation of implementation of smoking control policy in various countries of the world, so that it can “be able to“ prudent assessment ”.
Regarding “the ban on new types of tobacco, non -tobacco products and fashionable tobacco, as well as simple packaging for tobacco products, and timely regulation on prohibition of electronic cigarettes”, SSM say they are investigating, “dynamically, with competent authorities, based on the preliminary phase”. It is also said that efforts are being made so that "the review of the law can be started as soon as possible."
It is recalled that the body proposed, in the report on monitoring and evaluation of the prevention and control regime of smoking between 2021 and 2023, a heavier hand over alternative products to traditional cigarettes.
In concrete, the government argued that it is necessary to study the change in the law to prohibit these new products from tobacco or other non -tabogic but considered equally harmful to health. As for electronic cigarettes, regulation will also be reinforced, including the prohibition of possession of these products.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump threatens to launch new attacks against Iran</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/trump-ameaca-lancar-novos-ataques-contra-irao/</link><description>EPA12190424 A NEWS REPORT ON US STRIKES AGAINST IRAN'S NUCLEAR FACILITIES IS Broadcasted on Television Screen at The Installing International Airport In Inceon, South Korea, 22 June 2025. EPA/Yonhap South Krea Out



The air attacks made yesterday by the US "completely and completely destroyed" the main nuclear enrichment facilities of Iran, said the US President, threatening to order new military operations if Teer will not look for peace. In a speech to the nation, from the White House, after the US joined the Israelon Air Campaign against Tehran, Donald Trump classified American attacks as a "spectacular military success."
"Iran, the Middle East tyrant, should seek peace now. If not, the future attacks will be much larger and much easier," added Trump, who was accompanied by Vice President J.D. Vance, Secretary of Defense, Pete Hegseth, and Secretary of State Marco Rubio.
"There will be peace or a tragedy for Iran much larger than we have witnessed in the last eight days," the president accentuated, after being surprised by the world by announcing on social networks that US aircraft had hit the Nuclear Enrichment Center, as well as the Natanz and Isfahan facilities.
According to Iranian news agency Irna, the Islamic Republic authorities have ensured that the population is not in danger after US attacks. The International Atomic Energy Agency said it has not yet been recorded "any increase in radiation levels outside the three attacked nuclear facilities."
This US military involvement occurs despite Trump's promises to avoid another “eternal war” in the Middle East, and will have threatened to retaliate against US forces in the region if Washington was involved in the conflict. After the nation's speech, Trump insisted on his "social truth" network that "any Iran retaliation against the US will be received with a much larger force than that was witnessed tonight."
The US use seven B-2 stealing bombers in the attacks on nuclear facilities in Iran, explained hours later the head of joint state-state, Dan Caine. The main attack group "consisting of seven B-2 Spirit bombers flew 18 hours from US continental territory to Iran, with multiple flight refueling systems," he added.
"Iranian fighters did not flew, and apparently the Iranian earth missile systems did not detect us during the mission," the general said at a press conference.
In turn, Pentagon Chief Pete Hegseth stated that the attacks "devastated" the nuclear program of Iran and also urged Tehran leaders to follow the path of peace to avoid further bombing.
The Israeli Prime Minister thanked the US President for the “bold” attack on Iranian nuclear facilities. During this operation, "the US has been truly incomparable," said Benjamin Netanyahu, supporting what action marks "a historical turning point that can help lead the Middle East and beyond towards a future of prosperity and peace."
After American attacks on Iran, Israel closed its airspace, but asserted that "the terrestrial crossings [with Egypt] and Jordan are operating normally." Three areas of Israel, including Telavive, were hit yesterday morning by Iranian missiles, resulting in at least 23 injured, officials.
Iranian President Masoud Pezeshkian had warned the day before a "devastating" retaliation if Israel proceeded with the bombing, ensuring that Tehran would not interrupt his nuclear program "under any circumstances." Yesterday, Pezeshkian said that "this aggression proved that the US is the main factor behind the hostile actions of the Zionist regime."
 
“Explode diplomacy”
The Iranian Minister of Foreign Affairs reacted to the European Union (EU) and London appeals to return to the dialogue by stating that the US and Israel "decided to explode" diplomacy by bombing Iran. Platform X and then in statements in Istanbul. In addition, referring to negotiations in Geneva, "the US has decided, in turn, to reverse this diplomacy."
Several Arab countries condemned the US attack on Iran, which they considered a "serious threat" to the security of the Middle East, and defended the urgency of containing the situation through the diplomatic way. UN Secretary-General Antonio Guterres manifested "severely alarmed by the use of US force against Iran", and warned that "there is no military solution" to replace diplomacy.
 
Russia and China condemn US Bombardes
Russia and China, through their Foreign Ministries (MNE), condemned US bombing against nuclear facilities in Iran, whose chief of diplomacy, ABBAS ARAGHCHI, is expected to meet today with Vladimir Putin in Moscow. Dmitry Medvedev, vice president of the Russian Security Council, led by Vladimir Putin, said several countries are prepared to provide nuclear weapons to Tehran. The former Russian president did not specify what these countries are, but said that the US onslaught has caused minimal damage and will not prevent nuclear weapons. The MNE of Russia considered that the attacks represent "a serious violation of international law, the United Nations Charter and the UN Security Council resolutions." China has joined the many countries and world organizations to "firmly" to "firmly" US attacks, warning that "they have led to a climb of tensions in the Middle East." "China appeals to all parties involved in the conflict, and particularly Israel, to reach a ceasefire as soon as possible," reads a statement from Chinese MNE.
 
JTM with Lusa and International Agencies</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Inaugurated Family Medicine Training Base</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/inaugurada-base-de-formacao-em-medicina-familiar/</link><description>Family medicine, as a core of primary health care, now has a training basis. At the launch ceremony, the secretary LAM said that this measure will contribute to implement the global planning on the formation of medical staff and promoting regional cooperation
 
Health services (SSM) organized a medical forum and at the same time inaugurated the formation base in family medicine. According to the SSM, the event emerged following the indicators defined in the “Healthy Macao Action Plan”, which has been “decentralizing resources in community neighborhoods, raising professional quality and clinical health professionals and boosting the progress of Macao medical techniques”.
At the inauguration ceremony of the training base, the secretary for social affairs and culture said that family medicine is the core of primary health care and is directly related to the realization of the universal health objective.
"The creation and beginning of the Family Medicine Training Base symbolize the entry into a new phase of development of the MSAR Health Sector," said Lam, for whom the measure will "realize the government's global planning in the formation of medical talents, the construction of healthy macao and the promotion of regional cooperation."
In addition, it stressed that this project will strengthen the primary health care network focused on community neighborhoods, promote the change of paradigms in disease prevention, as well as taking advantage of the “a country, two systems” principle, with integration of large bay resources and the impulse of “complementarity of regional medical resources and innovative cooperation”.
Also present at the inauguration of the training base, the director of the Western Pacific Region of the World Health Organization (WHO) stressed that family medicine, as an important part of primary health care, can train health professionals who “respond effectively to the needs and emergencies of the population, constituting a key strategy for the realization of universal health coverage”. Ma'u Piukala skirt has ensured that WHO will continue to cooperate with Macau to strengthen the health system to achieve universal health coverage.
In turn, the department of the Department of Primary Health Care of the National Health Commission, Huang Law, said that the cooperation base between China and health in health is "deep" and obtained "fruit" results. According to recalled, in 2016 was renewed the memo of cooperation on study visits and training of community health services personnel, continuing to develop collaboration in the field of the training of general clinic and nurses, and more than 100 managers and health professionals have been selected in Macao, something that will continue in the second half of this year.
“The inauguration of the Family Medicine Training Base has provided a new support for the exchange between the two parts,” the SSM manifests, adding that the National Health Commission will promote the close connection between China's academic organizations, such as the Chinese Association of Medicine Professionals, and Macao Medical Associations.
During the Forum, the 18 experts, integrated from the Family Medicine Training Base Group received the appointment certificates, delivered by the secretary.
Currently, 90,000 patients with hypertension and 40,000 with diabetes are recorded in the SSM, of which about 90% are accompanied at health centers. With regard to diabetes, the global blood glucose compliance rate, blood pressure and blood lipids increased from 20 to 29%, while the blood pressure control rate went from 49 to 63%. Meanwhile, the number of health self-management posts increased from 53 to 145.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>TSI denies guest resource accused of sexual harassment</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/tsi-nega-recurso-de-hospede-acusado-de-assedio-sexual/</link><description>The Court of Second Instance denied the appeal of a guest accused of harassing a maid of a hotel in the mud. Thus upheld the decision of the basic court, which sentenced the individual to five months in prison with suspended sentence
 
The Collective Court of the Court of Second Instance (TSI) denied the appeal filed by a guest of a Taipa hotel, sentenced to five months in prison by the Base Judicial Court (TJB) for harassing a room service employee. For the collective court, the TJB indicated, "clear, objective and firmly the applicant's fault and responsibility for his crime committed." The TJB sentence remained, being five months in prison, suspended in execution for a period of two years.
In July 2023, the guest will have called the hotel meal delivery service where he was housed. The individual let the maid enter the room and tried to caress his arm, which in turn tried to dodge. According to the statement of the office of the president of the last court (Tui), the guest "persisted in his acts", touching over his clothes on his back and trying to detach the victim's bra. It will also have hinted that the maid wanted to have sex, having refused.
Later, a victim's colleague helped her and eventually notified the hotel manager, who called the police. The Public Prosecution Service deduced an accusation against the guest, which would eventually be convicted by the TJB "for the practice, in material authorship, in willful form, of a crime of sexual harassment." Disagreeing, the accused appealed to the TSI, claiming that the court "incurred a notorious error in the assessment of the evidence" and that the sentence "violated the principle" in dubio pro reo ".
Since the case occurred in a hotel room “without the presence of third parties or surveillance videos”, the evidence depended “on the allegations of both parties and other indirect evidence,” the collective court explained. The applicant argued that he played "accidentally in the hand of the offended", while the victim claimed that he was sexually harassed "several times."
Following an analysis of the testimonials of the other witnesses and documentary evidence, and the fact that the two individuals did not know each other and because there were no evidence that the offended had reasons to slander the applicant, the collective court understood that there was no notorious error of the TJB.
The collective court added that the "" principle in dubio pro reo "only applies when there are insatiable, reasonable and substantiated doubts" and that the applicant had no right to refute the TJB's decision "based on his personal point of view."
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Inflation keeps curve downward</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/inflacao-mantem-curva-descendente/</link><description>The annual inflation rate was estimated at 0.38% in May, confirming the slowdown trend in August 2024, according to official data
 
The overall consumer pricing (IPC) general index in Macau rose 0.38% in the annual cycle ended in May compared to the immediately preceding 12 months, said the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). Considering this comparative basis, the most used by economists to calculate the annual inflation rate, the CPI has been successively retreating since August 2024.
In the same temporal interval, the IPC grew 0.35% in level A, which involves about 50% of monthly medium aggregates between 11,000 and 35,999 patacas, and 0.39% in category B, which encompasses 30% of families with average spending between 36,000 and 71,999 patacas. In the period under analysis, in general, the additions of the indices of jewelery, goldsmiths and watches (+2.41%), education (+1.9%) and health (+1.44%) and descents in transport sections (-2.87%) and information and communication (-1.34%).
DSEC data also show that the General IPC advanced 0.19% compared to May 2024, with the highest growth involving the section of leisure, recreation, sport and culture (+4.14%). Price rates of food products and non-alcoholic beverages and housing and fuels increased by 0.21%, mainly due to the increase of meals acquired away from home and “take-soway” and home lace. In the opposite direction, the rates of information and communication and the clothing and footwear registered descents of 3.09% and 2.47%, respectively.
On the other hand, the IPC descended 0.05%in the monthly variation, with DSEC highlighting the cases of food products and non-alcoholic beverages (-0.03%), transportation (-0.56%) and leisure, recreation, sport and culture (-0.42%), due to falls in airplane tickets, hotel rooms and outflows after the holidays of the holidays. Easter. On the other hand, clothing and shoe rates (+0.71%) and domestic equipment and services (+0.28%) rose in monthly terms.
In the first five months of this year, the average General IPC grew 0.17%, compared to the same period of 2024.
The General IPC covers all household aggregates, and expenses with higher weights in the calculation of inflation are housing and fuels, food products and non -alcoholic beverages and transportation, with weights of 34.47, 29.47 and 8.33, respectively.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao focused on the rankings of Muslim tourism</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-em-foco-nos-rankings-turismo-muculmano/</link><description>Good results in the global Muslim travel index reinforce Macau's attraction to Islamic travelers. This segment of tourism has been developed in recent years, creating a favorable Halal reception environment in the territory
 
Macao was first included this year in the Global Muslim Travel Index 2025 (GMTI) published by Crescentrate and Mastercard, with the efforts of destination to welcome this recognized travelers segment.
GMTI has placed their masters fifth at fifth place in the category of friendly fate for Muslim women, 16th in the overall ranking of friendly destinations for Islamic tourism, and at the top of the friendly friendly destination list for Muslims, all classifications between non-member organization for Islamic cooperation (OIC, in the English acronym).
The good results achieved reinforce Macau's attraction to Islamic travelers, “an important tourism segment to which the direction of tourism services (STD) has been directing attention in recent years through various preparations for the creation of a favorable halal welcoming environment in the city, as part of the efforts to diversify visitors,” says the body.
The index is performed a comprehensive analysis of 153 destinations, including inside and outside the OIC. This year in its 10th edition, GMTI intends to serve as a guide for Muslim travelers as well as to foster a favorable environment for Halal tourism.
With Macao known for his long history of “Multicultural Harmony between the East and the West, world-level tourism infrastructures and safe environment,” STD stresses that it has been taking advantage of the city's offerings and fostering initiatives to make fate more attractive to Islamic travelers. “The inclusion of destination in GMTI as a new entrance this year reinforces the promotional exhibition,” says the note.
Regarding the classification between friendly destinations for women, the evaluation takes into account the “general security environment to ensure peace of mind, without restrictions on beliefs for Muslim women who travel alone or in groups”.
On the other hand, in the category of accessible destination friendly for Muslims, the “travel environment to meet visitors with special needs” is evaluated, including people with physical disabilities, multigenerational family groups, among others, taking into account the accessibility environment, transport infrastructure, safety and receptivity of fates to Muslims.
Among the Halal Tourism Promotional Campaigns, highlighting the publication at the beginning of the “Macao for Muslim Travelers - Travel Guide Halal”, which followed the installation of a pavilion with certified product display at the International Tourism Expo in April, where the “Seminar on the Friendly Muslim Hotel Classification” was also held to help in the preparation of the various tourist industry sectors. Territory.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Scarcity of resources still restricts the Mozambican presence in the</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/escassez-de-recursos-ainda-restringe-presenca-mocambicana-na-raem/</link><description>Experts consider that Mozambican bet on Macau is kept conditioned by the lack of industry and financial resources, and that new partnerships, including the scope of the large bay, can project Mozambique in the territory.
By visiting the Macao Forum Product Exhibition Center last year, Academic Fatima Papolo, which studies Sino-Mozambican relations, realized the existence of few Mozambique products on site, where articles from various Lusophone countries are exposed. "There are many more Brazilian products, but it is, to some extent, a reflection of the Mozambican economic structure. I believe that, through the Macao Forum, we can also think about how to transform this economic structure positively and that will result in the existence of more Mozambican products to be sold in Macao," she has now told Lusa.
Official data from the Government of Macau support the perception of the Academic of Joaquim Chissano University in Maputo: the territory imported from Mozambique in 2024, goods worth about 12 million patacas. In the case of Brazil, the value exceeded a billion million patacas.
In this sense, paper refers to the need to create “more events” that put agents of the Macao and Mozambique trade “to discuss and explore possibilities for deepening these relationships”.
"It is also necessary to put other individuals linked to industry, because only a developed industry can check out products that will be changed. Mozambique still needs to work hard on this development of the industry and this is how it will turn their products into manufactured, put them in the Macao market and, perhaps, from all over China," he says.
Created in 2003, the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese -Speaking Countries is “a differential” in the relationship between Mozambique and China, it says, but “there is a long time that“ there is not yet not done ”. "It is important to look like a space of exchanges. In this case, investments should come to Mozambique, but Mozambican investments should also go to Macau. This second sense needs to be worked," he says.
Although China was one of the first countries to recognize Mozambique as a sovereign state, on the day it declared independence on June 25, 1975, the “fortification of ties” with Macau, then under Portuguese administration, will only take place after 1999. Much more alive, much more present, ”he says.
Historian Wu Zhiliang considers the creation of the Macao Forum “a recognition” of the role of the territory as a bridge between China and Lusophone partners. Assuming that the region “has a lot to do to fulfill this mission well”, also president of the Macau Foundation refers to Lusa that the Forum should “expand its action, as well as the promotion of economic and commercial exchange, to the areas of teaching, culture and scientific research”.
Higher education, for example, was one of the areas of cooperation that gained encouragement in the post-transition. Of the 60 Mozambicans residing in Macao, more than half are students, estimates the president of the Friends of Mozambique Association. Ângelo Patrício Rafael, also a professor at the University of São José, arrived in the territory in 2012 for a master's degree in international trade law, the result of a protocol between Eduardo Mondlane University and the University of Macao.
But here, there is difficulties. "Universities, especially private, do not have financial capacity, for example, to assign complete scholarships to international students coming from Portuguese -speaking countries. On the other hand, it can be very expensive for these students to leave these countries," he says.
Rafael believes that "the challenge often goes through the right partners who believe in this role of Macao, who are willing to finance or somehow help in this process."
Regarding the reinforcement of sino-mozambican ties, “the hardest part”, reflects the person responsible, is probably “the narrowing of these relationships beyond the institutional level”: “There is also a lot of cultural level, but I think [it is necessary] to enhance this interaction among peoples”.
An opportunity for Mozambique constitutes, according to Fatima Papalo, the Great Bay, which Maputo must “enjoy and explore”. “I see a space in which Mozambique can promote their potential, can also seek services that will allow their economic development in various areas, from energy, industry, transportation, communication, because there is a lot of technological development in the area of ​​transport, to public policy formulation,” he proposes.
And the Portuguese language, he says, will be “always advantage”: “It is necessary that Mozambique realizes this special place that has and makes good use of it, in the positive sense”.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Isabel Rio Novo presents biography of Camões</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/isabel-rio-novo-apresenta-biografia-de-camoes/</link><description>A biography of Luís Vaz de Camões will be presented in Macau on the 28th, with the presence of the author of the work, Isabel Rio Novo. The publication revisits the sources already established by the academic tradition, but also brings to light a series of unpublished data, hitherto unknown or neglected
 
“Fortuna, Case, Time and Luck” is the title of a biography of Luís Vaz de Camões that the Portuguese Institute of the East (IPOR) will present next Saturday, June 28, at 17h00, at the Dr. Stanley Ho auditorium of the Portuguese Consulate General in Macau and Hong Kong. The session, integrated in the activities of “June, Portugal Month”, will be attended by the book's author, Isabel Rio Novo.
As if you can read in the synopsis of the event, the fifth centenary about the birth of Camões could not go unnoticed to Portugal and the Portuguese around the world. The East and considering that the poet had in life a presence in this part of the world, Ipor proposes to celebrate the life of Camões.
The work, the result of a meticulous and exhaustive study, not only revisits the sources already consecrated by the academic tradition, but also brings to light a series of unpublished data, hitherto unknown or neglected.
"By gathering, analyzing and interconnecting hundreds of dispersed contributions, the book is not limited to compiling information, but reconstructs with a thorough wealth the historical, social and cultural context of the time in question," underline the IPOR and the organizing committee of "June, Portugal's month".
For this reason, they add, "this book does not only recover the trajectory of an extraordinary personality, but it also illuminates aspects that have long obscured by time, revealing nuances that have remained hidden over centuries."
More than a simple biography, the work, which will also be presented in Canton and Beijing, seeks to reevaluate and reaffirm “the legacy of both man and poet” in order to restore to history the “complexity and brightness of a singular figure”, whose influence and relevance transcend the barriers of time.
Written in an accessible language “without sacrificing academic rigor”, “Fortuna, Case, Time and Luck - Luís Vaz de Camões Biography” is also a “16th century privileged access door, showing how Camões became an eternal symbol of a nation,” says the presentation note.
A native of Porto, Isabel Rio Novo Doctorate in comparative literature at the Faculty of Letters of the University of that city, is a professor of creative writing and disciplines in the literary scope, but also teaches about cinema and other art forms, having written academically, and not only, about all these areas.
Outside the academy, she is the author of several poems, short stories and novels, including “Rio do Forget”, Leya Prize finalist and semifinalist of the Oceans award, both in 2016. Regarding the writing of biographies, she published in 2019 “The Well and the Road”, a biography of Agustina Bessa-Luís, and in 2024, the book that will now be presented in Macao: "Fortuna, case, time and luck - Biography of Luís Vaz de Camões."
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Open candidates for short films festival</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/abertas-candidaturas-para-festival-de-curtas-metragens/</link><description>Until July 21, candidacies are open for the Short Film Festival, organized by the Cultural Institute and the Galaxy Entertainment. The prize for the winners can reach 45 thousand patacas
 
Registration for the “2nd GEG International Film Festival” is open until July 21. According to the Cultural Institute (IC), the contest is intended for all residents and the winners are qualified to receive a trophy and a monetary prize up to 45,000 patacas. The festival's advisory committee will select the finalist films of the “Shorts de Macao” section, says the statement, and the chosen proposals will be aired at the event and will apply to the “Macao Award” and the “Special Jury Mention Prize”.
The “Broad Event Program” will include an inaugural ceremony, projections, the “featured director” section, specialist lectures, movie themed workshops, a forum, a closing ceremony, the awards and a red treadmill. According to the IC, “Experienced Filmmakers” will be part of the jury, will give workshops and present the forum.
The cinema sessions will be divided into five sections, namely “Shorts of Macao”, “New Voices of the Horizon”, “Highlight Director”, “East Asia Vision” and “Special Sessions”. The festival will take place in September, in the Galaxy theaters, the Galaxy auditorium of the International Convention Center and the Andaz Hotel, as well as at Cinemateca Paixão.
Regulation and registration forms are available on IC sites and Macao's cultural and creative industries. Candidates can deliver the form to the IC building in Tap Siac Square, until 5:45 pm on July 21, or by electronic mail until the end of the same day.
The event, co-organized by the IC and the Galaxy Entertainment Group, aims to “establish an international platform for the exchange and display of short films” as well as promote “local film and television productions with global audience”.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IAM removed vines on the hill of the guide</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/iam-removeu-trepadeiras-na-colina-da-guia/</link><description>The Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) concluded in late May the work of cleaning vines to protect the forest zone of the Colina da Guia Municipal Park. In addition to removing the vines, it was treatment of poor growth and household waste, it can be read in a note. The work has been started by phases in March. AMI ensures that "it will continue its forest protection work, in order to face the growth of vines and maintain the health of the forests of the hill of the guide." It also recalls that Macau entered the time of typhoons and rain, and that trees are at risk of falling due to the influence of rain and wind, "so citizens should avoid entering and staying in forest zones during a storm or in the following days." AMI also asks citizens who preserve the natural environment and do not lay trash “indiscriminately in the middle of the forest, so as not to cause damage to the environment and public health”. To report anomalies in the trees the population may contact the citizen line (28337676) or present opinions in the application “in contact”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New York parade resorts to collective funds after withdrawal from companies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/desfile-de-nova-iorque-recorre-fundos-colectivos-apos-desistencia-de-empresas/</link><description>The drop in business donations after Donald Trump's policies against diversity and inclusion led the New York pride parade, the largest annual LGBTQ+ meeting in the US, seeking funds among community members.
According to NYC Pride spokesman Kevin Kilbride, this year was reached “only about 80% of the background goal” for the city's big pride party, which will be held on June 29 and expects to gather about two million people.
“We are trying to fill this gap with a participatory fundraising campaign,” says Kilbride.
In mid-May, the organization launched a campaign “between equals so that people can start their own background collections on the internet, share them with friends and allow people to donate,” he says.
The group “wants to lean a little more for individual donations and participatory support,” he says.
The organization responsible for the annual parade and other community projects said it has raised “almost 25,000 dollars of almost 200 donors” in a matter of days.
In previous years, extravagant floats sponsored by large companies paraded along the fifth Avenida de Manhattan along with others organized by community groups. And while many companies continue to contribute, some have discreetly reduced their commitments.
Muneer Panjwani, who leads the Engage for Good, said that "there was a massive withdrawal last year, specifically from companies that supported pride events for a long time and decided not to support anyone."
Panjwani Organization connects companies to non -profit organizations and reports on consumer contributions when they have the option of making a donation by paying a purchase in a store. “While companies remove their philanthropic money, consumers say: 'This theme is still important to us,'” he says.
One of the most prominent brands that decided to limit his participation in pride was Target, a popular chain of stores. Last week, he reported to AFP that he will not participate in the parade.
The network has been criticized and saw the price of its stocks on the stock market to fall as a result of a boycott on the Internet in response to its suppression of diversity programs, which justified by the "evolution of the external scenario."
At Brooklyn's annual pride parade, Progressive Democratic Councilman Chi Osse told AFP that "pride began on the basis through the community, and corporations that bend before a president who thinks a king only show us who they really are to us."
Brooklyn's pride manifestation is less scale and has long been considered more radical than Manhattan's, although it has a small number of participating companies.
Anya Glow-Kollisch, one of the leaders of the Sirens Women’s Motorcycle Club group of the parade, says that "it is great that companies are willing to say that they support equal rights." "But I think that, in the end, it is a movement driven by people who demand their rights, and many companies simply do it because they think they should do so," he says.
"Therefore, it is very valuable that people in the community manifest themselves and show that this is what we are."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>