<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Per capita expenditure of visitors fell by more than 7% to 2,000 patacas</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/despesa-per-capita-dos-visitantes-caiu-mais-de-7-para-2-000-patacas/</link><description>Per capita spending by visitors to Macau fell by more than 7% between 2024 and 2025, suffering the third consecutive annual drop. Official data nevertheless reveals increases in some market segments. For example, visitors from Zhejiang spent the most. Outside of Greater China, Singapore remains in the spotlight. In absolute terms, excluding gambling, total expenditure exceeded 80 billion patacas, an increase of around 6% resulting from the increase in the number of visitors
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Even though total spending, excluding gambling, grew last year in absolute terms, this does not mean that visitors are spending more in the territory. On the contrary, official data show that per capita spending continues to show a downward trend.
In the general calculation of last year, the 'per capita' expenditure of visitors was estimated at 2,000 patacas, 7.3% less than in 2024, reported the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC). Although it remained above the 2019 level (1,626 patacas), the value represents the third consecutive annual drop, after falling 20.8% to 2,525 patacas between 2022 and 2023 and 14.6% to 2,157 patacas between 2023 and 2024.
Savings were notable among tourists, with per capita expenditure dropping 1.5% to 3,827 patacas. In the case of day trippers, there was an increase of 3.5% to 715 patacas.
Regarding the per capita expenditure of visitors by main origins, that of Mainland China was the one with the biggest drop in annual terms, from 10.3% to 2,245 patacas. It should be noted that visitors from Zhejiang province were the biggest spenders, with an average of 5,235 patacas (up 17.3%), followed by those from Shanghai, with 5,093 patacas (down 8.6%).
In the segment of international visitors, per capita spending decreased by 3.5% to 2,046 patacas, while that of visitors from Hong Kong decreased by 2.1% to 988 patacas. Conversely, the per capita expenditure of visitors to Taiwan grew by 6.7% to 2,083 patacas.
In Northeast Asia, the highlights were drops of 11.6% for South Koreans (2,127 patacas) and 9.4% for Japanese (1,897). In Southeast Asia, there were increases of 7.5% and 3.8% in the markets of Singapore (3,047 patacas) and Malaysia (2,067 patacas). Thailand, in turn, recorded a drop of 9.4% to 2,353 patacas.
According to official statistics, which exclude gaming expenses, “shopping” absorbed 43.8% of visitors’ per capita spending over the past year, followed by “accommodation” (25.1%) and “food” (21.8%).
It should be noted that the ‘per capita’ expenses of those who came to watch shows or competitions decreased by 28% in the space of a year to 3,632 patacas. The number of those who came to participate in conventions/exhibitions, highlights DSEC, “continued to be higher”, at an average of 4,572 patacas (5.8% more).
In absolute terms, after rising 5.8% in 2024, total visitor expenditure amounted to 80.12 billion patacas in 2025, an annual growth of 6.3% driven by the 14.7% increase in the number of entries into the Macao SAR (40.07 million) and which once again exceeded the value of 2019 (64.1 billion patacas). Day trippers spent 16,814 patacas (28.9% more), while tourists spent 63,308 patacas (1.6% more).
Looking only at the last quarter of last year, the data shows that total non-gaming related visitor spending stood at MOP21.87 billion, up 14.2% year-on-year. DSEC indicates that it was mainly thanks to “the total expenditure of excursionists (5.34 billion) having increased by 85.9%”. Total tourist spending (16.54 billion) also increased by 1.6%. However, per capita expenditure decreased by 1.0% to 2,104 patacas, but increased by 7.9% compared to the previous quarter.</description><pubDate>2026-02-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Seguro won in Macao with 66.6% of the votes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/seguro-venceu-na-raem-666-dos-votos/</link><description>Of the more than 57 thousand voters registered in the Macao SAR, 934 voted for António José Seguro, against the 429 votes obtained by André Ventura. Regarding the first round of the election of the President of the Portuguese Republic, the participation rate fell from 4.1% to 2.4%. In general, voters surveyed by this newspaper yesterday anticipated a victory for the former leader of the Socialist Party

PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
António José Seguro was the most voted in the Macao SAR, with 934 votes (66.6%), against the 429 voters (30.6%) in the territory who chose André Ventura, at the two polling stations at the Consulate General of Portugal for Macau and Hong Kong. In Macau, there were still 32 blank votes (2.3%) and eight invalid votes (0.6%).
Overall, the second round of the presidential elections in Macau had a participation rate of 2.4%, considering that 57,748 voters were registered in the territory. In the first round, the rate reached 4.1%.
Yesterday, on the second day of the elections, the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper spoke to some of the few voters who went to the polling stations, and who took advantage of the almost non-existent movement at the Consulate General.
For Fernando, the voting process went as expected, explaining that “the second round is not as complicated as the first”. The 73-year-old resident also said he expected more people to show up during the afternoon. “Now with the weather so cold, and today is Sunday, maybe they will come after noon or 1 pm,” he said.
In anticipation of the electoral outcome, Fernando, who “as a matter of principle” votes in all elections, said he believes that the weather in Portugal and the state of some locations could influence the results of the presidential elections. "With these situations, things are complicated. Without water, without electricity, it is very complicated", he lamented.
In turn, Carlos, a native of Macau, was not concerned about the impact of the storms on electoral participation. “I don’t think there will be any major changes, because the polls give Seguro a very ‘safe’ victory”, he projected. Unlike Fernando, the 61-year-old resident confessed to not having the habit of voting, despite having decided to do so in these elections. “I voted this year because I want a change”, he argued, adding that the voting process “went well, it was quick”.
Fátima Galvão, in turn, lamented the lack of “charisma” of the two candidates, stating that “seeing the candidates nowadays is sad”. “Although I didn’t vote for anyone, I absolutely believe that there is a candidate who will win and that things in Portugal will remain as the majority of the Portuguese people want them to remain”, said the also president of MASDAW.
"It is very easy to identify who votes for whom. And from the moment that one of the candidates is mostly supported by men and seeing the comments from these men on social media, I am very happy to, in advance, be sure that this candidate will not win", he concluded.
Between the 27th, 28th and 29th of January, people registered in Portugal who were in the Macao SAR also had the opportunity to vote. According to information released by the Consulate General of Portugal, 78 voters voted early in this second round, more than triple the 25 who voted early in the first round, in January.
It should be remembered that neither of the two candidates vying for the position of Head of State had won in Macau in the first round. Luís Marques Mendes had received 1,073 votes, corresponding to 45.2% of the 2,374 ballots submitted, while Seguro had collected 477 votes (20.09%) and Ventura 282 (11.9%). In the first electoral round, there were still 24 blank votes (1%) and 66 invalid votes (2.8%) in Macau.</description><pubDate>2026-02-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MGM no longer faces “down seasons”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mgm-ja-nao-enfrenta-epocas-baixas/</link><description>After registering record growth in several operational segments in 2025, MGM China continues to face the future in Macau with clear “optimism”, assured its CEO. Kenneth Feng's confidence is reinforced by a “new phenomenon”, marked by the absence of “low seasons” even before holiday periods, such as Chinese New Year
 
SERGIO TERRA
 
Those responsible for MGM China are “very optimistic” about business prospects during the Chinese New Year period, taking into account, first of all, “very encouraging booking trends”. “We even have a long waiting list for our top-tier hotel products, highlighted Kenneth Feng, CEO of the gaming operator, in a conference call with analysts to discuss the financial results achieved by the parent company, MGM Resorts International, during the fourth quarter of 2025.
Assuring that MGM has invested a lot in the ‘premium’ pasta segment and is focused on “quality over quantity”, Kenneth Feng highlighted the high level of demand in Macau. "Currently, even before the holidays, there are no off-season periods. We are satisfied with that in general," he said.
Last year, the company opened 28 “Alpha Villas” and the “Alpha Club” – for wealthy players – at MGM Macau, and launched the project to convert MGM Cotai rooms into 60 new suites, to offer “a differentiated experience” to premium customers. “If we look at our reinvestment rate in relation to the trend of gross gaming revenues, there may be a little volatility due to the composition of the business, however, in general, it is very stable”, highlighted Feng, also considering that competition in the market has been “very rational” in recent quarters.
MGM China recorded record growth in several business segments in 2025, a year in which visits to its properties increased by 14% and the average daily casino turnover rose by 11%. The company absorbed 16.1% of total gross gaming revenue in Macau, reaching a new historic high, after having achieved shares of 15.8% in 2024 and 15.2% in 2023. In individual terms, MGM Cotai's casino share (10.1%) once again surpassed that of MGM Macau (6.0%).
According to data confirmed on Friday, hours after they were partially “inadvertently” released by MGM Resorts, MGM China's 2025 financial year was also marked by a record in adjusted EBITDA (earnings before interest, taxes, amortization and depreciation), which grew by around 10% to approximately 10 billion Hong Kong dollars (HKD), while net revenues increased by 11% to 34.8 billion.
The EBITDA margin, an indicator widely used by analysts and investors to evaluate the percentage of a company's operating profit in relation to its total revenue, reached 28.8% in 2025, almost the same percentage as the previous year (28.9%). This performance, according to MGM China, derives from its focus on the mass market and “operational efficiency”.
In a context of continuous growth, the financial situation once again showed increasing solidity. As of December 31, 2025, MGM China's total liquidity amounted to approximately 24 billion HKD dollars, 6.8 billion more than a year earlier, including cash on hand, cash equivalents and available credit lines.
MGM Resorts management also praised the company's performance in Macau. “A relentlessly competitive environment is the norm there [in Macau], but our team has consistently maintained margins between 25% and 30%, focusing on maintaining high levels of service while at the same time anticipating changing customer tastes and preferences,” noted Jonathan Halkyard, chief financial officer of the North American group.</description><pubDate>2026-02-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Firefighters reinforce training against fires in tall buildings</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/bombeiros-reforcam-formacao-contra-incendios-em-edificios-altos/</link><description>The Fire Commander, Wong Kin, revealed that the corporation will reinforce its focus on training against fires in tall buildings. Specifically, it plans to send personnel to Mainland China and Hong Kong to learn strategies for responding to this type of fire. In a report on 2025, it was said that 850 fires had been recorded in the territory, a drop of 3.4%, in the majority of which it was not necessary to use a hose. On the other hand, ambulance departures increased
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The Fire Department (CB) will “reinforce personnel training”, said the commander, Wong Kin, revealing that he plans to send personnel, in the second half of this year, to “exchange in Mainland China and Hong Kong, to learn strategies for responding to fires in high-rise buildings”. He also guaranteed that the corporation is “constantly monitoring the development of rescue technologies at national and international level, matching the reality of the territory”.
Wong Kin stressed that the CB has been acquiring new equipment and vehicles to face the “challenges” of firefighting brought about “by rapid urban development”. Specifically, he recalled that ladders with an 18 and 20 meter water pump have already been introduced, an important piece of equipment taking into account the narrow streets. Since the big fire in Tai Po, Hong Kong, the Macao SAR authorities have been reinforcing safety procedures in this area.
He also recalled that authorities carry out inspection work in community neighborhoods, notifying the police if there is illegal parking that impedes evacuation channels. At the spring lunch offered by CB to the media, Wong Kin also assured that the corporation will continue to carry out fire prevention drills with public services and other institutions, “in order to reestablish the safety of fire prevention”.
In the balance for 2025, the commander reported that 850 cases of fire were recorded, a drop of 3.36% or 32 fewer fires compared to the previous year. The main causes of fire, according to statistics, were forgetting to turn off the stoves (159 cases), not completely extinguishing the flames (115), burning incense and candles/votive papers (96), mechanical/equipment failures (95) and electrical short circuits (69), totaling 534 cases, a value that corresponds to 62.82% of the total fires reported last year.
Only 145 fires required the use of hoses, a drop of 18.54% or 33 situations, he added. Wong Kin noted that “cases requiring the use of hoses are often related to residents' day-to-day negligence or lack of awareness about safety prevention, all of which are preventable.”
With regard to fire safety inspection and monitoring actions in buildings, the commander revealed that, last year, 11,760 actions were carried out and administrative sanctioning procedures were completed in relation to 126 cases, “including, above all, situations of placing objects and parking motorcycles on evacuation paths, among others”. In addition, another 10 cases are also being subject to administrative sanctioning procedures.
 
Ambulance departures increased
On the other hand, and according to statistical data, ambulance departures increased by 0.3% to 45,370 cases (134 more in annual terms). The main causes of the calls were related to “dizziness, abdominal pain, fever and bruises”.
Wong Kin stressed that, “given the limited nature of ambulance service resources, the CB will continue its awareness campaigns against inappropriate use of services”. In this context, it revealed that 1,218 abusive calls were recorded.
Over the past year, Firefighters carried out 1,700 rescue operations, 92 fewer or a reduction of 5.13% year-on-year. These jobs mainly involved assistance in opening doors and providing medical assistance to injured people.
The total number of departures for special services, in turn, was 5,270, “mainly involving the response to incidents such as the removal of objects and washing/cleaning the floor/removing oil stains”. In this case, there were 953 fewer departures, a drop of 15.31%.
The volume of incidents reported by the CB in 2025 decreased by 1.74% to 53,190 cases, that is, there were 943 fewer situations compared to 2024.</description><pubDate>2026-02-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM and University of Coimbra cooperate in digital research</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/upm-universidade-de-coimbra-cooperam-em-investigacao-digital/</link><description>The promotion of Sino-Portuguese studies is the basis of a research program in Digital Humanities launched jointly by the Macau Polytechnic University and the University of Coimbra. The new agreement aims to further develop Macau's role as a bridge for academic exchange between China and Portuguese-speaking countries
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The Macau Polytechnic University (UPM) and the University of Coimbra (UC) jointly launched a research program in Digital Humanities, focused on language and text technologies and digital applications. The new exchange agreement between the two higher education institutions aims to further develop Macau's role as a bridge for academic exchange between China and Portuguese Speaking Countries (PLP) and deepen international cooperation in interdisciplinary scientific research.
“Based on the solid strategic partnership, the two universities further expand new areas of collaboration in higher education and build a multilingual digital humanities ecosystem”, according to a statement from UPM.
The Joint Digital Humanities Research Program will bring together the “advantages of the two universities” to develop multidimensional research innovations, focusing on promoting Sino-Portuguese humanities studies.
The initiative includes the digitization of historical archives, research and development into large-scale Portuguese language models and artificial intelligence, the digital revitalization of cultural heritage, as well as contemporary digital communication.
The same note states that the program has Macau as its main link, “transcending geographical restrictions and characterized by openness, sharing and sustainable development, in order to inject an innovative impetus into academic and cultural exchanges between China and the PLP”.
The recently launched program assumes “a significant mission”, said the rector of UPM at the launch ceremony. Marcus Im highlighted that the agreement “promotes data innovation in the humanities and social sciences, through the construction of a database of interlingual texts”. Furthermore, through digital exhibitions and interactive experiences, “it encourages the dissemination and sharing of multicultural resources”, he highlighted.
The rector of UPM also highlighted in his speech that the two universities have been cooperating for more than 30 years and that the level of collaboration has deepened, from the exchange of qualified staff to the construction of joint laboratories in the areas of the smart city and 'big health'. Looking to the future, he added that the two parties have already signed the agreement to establish a base of cooperation in the field of higher education in the “Macao and Hengqin International Education (University) City”, “in order to build an international campus oriented towards the world community”.
In turn, Nuno Mendonça, vice-rector of UPM, highlighted that the humanities are “a central area of ​​critical thinking and the creation of meaning” and, with artificial intelligence “profoundly changing the mode of research and teaching”, the rise of digital humanities “is not only a technical challenge, but also a profound dialogue involving ethics and culture”.
The UPM statement emphasizes that “with centuries of experience in studying Chinese culture, the UC serves as an academic bridge between East and West, with the aim of integrating linguistic technologies, creative industries and research into cultural heritage through this Program”. In the future, he continues, “the two universities will cooperate to create academic laboratories that will pioneer technological innovation on the Campus in Hengqin, a space that symbolizes the fusion between tradition and innovation”.
The UC delegation included the directors of the General Library and the Department of Computer Engineering, respectively António Mendes and Manuel Portela; professor Hugo Oliveira; the coordinator of the PhD Course in Anthropology and Professor of the Department of Life Sciences, Gonçalo Santos; and the coordinator of Global Projects, Ricardo Dias.</description><pubDate>2026-02-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korean band took the stage without a Japanese singer</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/banda-sul-coreana-subiu-ao-palco-sem-cantor-japones/</link><description>The organization of two Riize concerts in Macau, which took place over the weekend, announced that the South Korean male group decided to perform without Japanese singer Shotaro, at a time of tensions between Beijing and Tokyo. Riize, who currently have six members, took to the stage at the Galaxy Arena with just five artists, said the company IME Macau, in a statement published on social media.
“Although all parties have prepared in good time for all members to participate, unfortunately, due to unforeseeable circumstances, member Shotaro will not be able to participate” in the concerts in the Macao SAR, the statement said. The company asked for the “understanding of fans who have waited and supported Riize for a long time”, without adding details.
Asked on Tuesday about the cancellation of shows with Japanese artists, the director of the Tourism Services said she had “no concrete information about the situation”. Helena de Senna Fernandes was speaking on the sidelines of the Lunar New Year parade, which celebrates the Year of the Horse. Unlike previous years, there will be no groups from Japan.
On January 28, South Korean broadcaster MBC, which was organizing the ‘Show! Music Core in Macau’, a music festival in South Korea, which included bands featuring Japanese artists, canceled the event. The festival was scheduled for the weekend, at the outdoor performance venue.
MBC did not provide any explanation for the decision, saying only that it was taken “after a thorough analysis of local circumstances and general logistical conditions”. Even before the official announcement, the South Korean press had already discussed the possible cancellation due to the alleged difficulty of Japanese artists in obtaining visas to perform in Macau.
Lusa tried to confirm this information with the Immigration Services of the Public Security Police Corps, the Cultural Institute (IC) and the Directorate of Labor Affairs Services, but did not receive any response.
On December 12, the president of the IC denied any interference in the cancellation of concerts with Japanese artists scheduled for the region and assured that these were solely commercial decisions by the organizers. "I think different parties have their own weighting factors," said Leong Wai Man. "It's normal to have adjustments about concerts or different events. Situations of cancellation due to force majeure are common," he added.
Asked by Lusa whether there were indications from the Government not to hold cultural events with artists from Japan, Leong Wai Man assured that “this is a matter for the commercial sector, it is the organizer's decision”. “I have nothing more to add”, stressed the leader.
In December, shows with Japanese artists in at least three different hotel-casinos had been canceled.
In November, the Prime Minister of Japan spoke about a possible Japanese military intervention in a conflict between mainland China and Taiwan. Sanae Takaichi stated that if an emergency situation in Taiwan involved “the deployment of warships and the use of force, this could constitute a threat to Japan’s survival.” Days later, Beijing advised against traveling to Japan, an example later followed by Macau and Hong Kong.
Contrary to usual, the Hong Kong Government did not send any representatives to an event organized by the Japanese consulate on Thursday, to mark the birthday of Japanese Emperor Naruhito, according to the Hong Kong Free Press news portal.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Company terminations decreased by 14%</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/extincoes-de-sociedades-diminuiram-14/</link><description>Business team briefing the idea concept before the next meeting in modern office with laptop computer



Macau “gained” 3,732 companies in 2025, due to a 14% drop in dissolutions and a 2.7% increase in company creation
 
Over the past year, 4,678 new companies were created in the Macao SAR, a number that represents an increase of 2.7% compared to the 4,555 created in 2024, while cases of dissolution fell by 13.8%, from 1,098 to 946 in the same time period, according to data released by the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC). Macau thus ended the year with a net growth of 3,732 companies, 8% more than the 3,457 recorded in 2024.
Among the extinct companies, those that operated in the wholesale and retail trade (323) and services provided to companies (264) stood out, corresponding to 34.1% and 27.9% of the total, respectively. According to DSEC, the share capital of the dissolved companies totaled 547.8 million patacas.
On the other hand, the majority of companies incorporated in 2025 operate in wholesale and retail trade (1,640) and services provided to companies (1,352), equivalent to 35.1% and 28.9% of the total, respectively. Altogether, the share capital of the new companies amounted to 544.7 million patacas.
Official data indicate that 3,430 incorporated companies (73.3% of the total) are in the category of share capital below 50 thousand patacas, involving 88 million patacas (16.2% of the total). 52 companies were also created with share capital equal to or greater than one million patacas, with a global value of 287 million (52.7% of the total).
In the last quarter of 2025 alone, 1,401 companies were formed and 233 were dissolved. Thus, there was a net growth of 1,168 companies between October and December.
In the fourth quarter of 2025, the share capital from the Macao SAR stood at 76 million patacas and that from Mainland China at 32 million, equivalent to 61.2% and 26% of the total, respectively. The share capital from Mainland cities located in the Greater Bay Area totaled MOP10 million, of which 45.7% came from Zhuhai. The share capital originating from Hong Kong amounted to nine million patacas.</description><pubDate>2026-02-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sands completes 14 years of supporting Loja Social</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sands-completa-14-anos-de-apoio-a-loja-social/</link><description>Sands China donated 300 thousand patacas to the Santa Casa da Misericórdia Social Store, in support provided by the gaming operator for 14 consecutive years. The food baskets distributed contain essential items. To celebrate Chinese New Year, the company also offered families festive gift packages

The Santa Casa da Misericórdia of Macau held another basket donation on Saturday, this time with the sponsorship of Sands China, which is happening for the 14th consecutive time. The gaming operator's subsidy amounts to MOP300,000.
The goods were delivered to Loja Social by volunteers from the “Sands Cares Ambassadors” program, and were subsequently sent to 370 local families experiencing difficulties. The pataca baskets contain basic necessities, such as rice, pasta, biscuits, canned food, cooking oil, toothpaste and shower gel, “in the hope of reducing the beneficiaries' living expenses”, according to Sands China.
To celebrate Chinese New Year, the company also provided each family with festive gift packages purchased from the Tung Sin Tong Charitable Association. A “God of Fortune” was also present to bless the participants and give the event a festive spirit.
On the occasion, the executive vice-president of Sands China, Wilfred Wong, stated that, “as the oldest charitable organization in Macau, Santa Casa has remained steadfast in its mission to support local disadvantaged groups and promote the well-being of the community”, adding that the company has supported this community work over the years.
Looking to the future, he promised that Sands will continue “to work with local associations to build a warmer and more harmonious community in Macau”.
After receiving the donation check, and in the presence of several guests, the Irmandade Ombudsman, António José de Freitas, expressed “sincere gratitude” for Sands' support to Loja Social over the last 14 years. “Through this initiative, Sands demonstrated its dedication to the community, providing continuous assistance to disadvantaged local families and providing care to those who need it most”, highlighted the head of Santa Casa, expressing the desire to deepen collaboration to “generate a more positive impact on the community”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2026-02-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Taipa Line “dresses up” for the New Year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/linha-da-taipa-veste-se-rigor-para-ano-novo/</link><description>The Metro Society (MLM) will launch a series of activities to celebrate Chinese New Year with residents and tourists, “including the unprecedented launch of trains decorated in the festive colors and a public event at Barra Station”. From February 14th, the Taipa Line will introduce a New Year-themed light rail, specially decorated inside and out to create a festive atmosphere for passengers. According to the company, there will also be a subway decorated with “a surprise theme that will be unveiled during Chinese New Year”. Metro's mascot, “Heng Chai”, will also be present at stations to wish for a good Chinese New Year, interact with passengers and distribute small gifts. Still on the 14th, between 2:00 pm and 5:00 pm, at Barra Station there will be free distribution of Chinese New Year stickers and “lai si” envelopes to decorate with festive stamps. MLM will invite calligraphy enthusiasts to write auspicious messages on Chinese New Year couplets, which will be offered to the public, and participants will also be able to write good luck messages. A painting and drawing experience is also planned, as well as a selection of festive stamps. On the same day, two guided tours of Barra Station will also be organized.</description><pubDate>2026-02-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New BNU notes highlight the history and evolution of Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/novas-notas-bnu-destacam-historia-evolucao-de-macau/</link><description>New notes with a higher monetary value, 1,000 and 500 patacas, issued by Banco Nacional Ultramarino (BNU), are now in circulation. According to the banking institution, the launch completes the cycle of the entire new series of BNU banknotes, “a significant milestone in the modernization of Macau's monetary system”, and the design of the banknotes “continues to be inspired by the rich history and evolution” of the territory, presenting the map of the region in different eras and generations. Each note tells a story related to the transformation of the city, “reflecting the unique cultural heritage and historical importance that Macau represents” and constituting more than a means of transaction. “It is a reflection of Macau’s identity as a multicultural and prosperous community”, highlights the text. With the introduction of 1,000 and 500 patacas banknotes, BNU “once again reinforces its commitment to providing citizens with modern and aesthetically interesting banknotes, also incorporating updated security elements”. This issue of banknotes with a higher nominal value continues the launch of 10, 20, 50 and 100 patacas notes. BNU was the first bank issuing paper money in Macau, having been entrusted with this mission in 1905.</description><pubDate>2026-02-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>YOUNG BLOOD DONORS ARE DECLINING IN THE Macao SAR</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jovens-doadores-de-sangue-estao-em-declinio-na-raem/</link><description>The number of young blood donors has been steadily decreasing, indicated the Health Services Blood Transfusion Center. Last year, donors under 30 years of age represented 19% of the total. In contrast, donors from this age group accounted for 53% of the total in 2016. Cited by “Ou Mun Tin Toi”, the Center also revealed that, in 2025, almost 14 thousand citizens registered as blood donors, which means an annual increase of 1.5%. In total, around 19 thousand units of blood were donated, an increase of 6.86% compared to 2024. At the same time, local hospitals registered, in total, 3,669 patients who received blood transfusions. According to Hui Ping, director of the Blood Transfusion Center, the total amount of blood collected exceeded hospital demand last year, and in general, reserves in Macau are sufficient. Currently, 80 people are needed per day to donate blood. However, the same official warned that the blood stock is likely to register significant fluctuations, taking into account that storage has an expiration date and that, facing extreme heat or cold, or before and after long holidays, citizens tend to be less active in donating. Given the current situation, the Center's director stressed the desire for the public to be more aware of the importance of donating blood, in order to encourage donors to do so regularly and in the long term, thus ensuring a stable supply to hospitals. Hui Ping spoke on the sidelines of the prize giving ceremony for the blood donation poster design competition, which took place on Saturday.</description><pubDate>2026-02-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>BRIEF</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2545/</link><description>Pharmacy will have helped to launder 4.9 million
The manager of a pharmacy in the Central Zone was arrested by the PJ, on suspicion of helping a fraud network to launder 4.9 million patacas. The case also involves at least three individuals on the run. According to the PJ, between March and May 2025, the fugitives used 34 bank cards from Mainland China to make false purchases at the pharmacy (the “purchased” medicines were not taken), in a total of 60 transactions valued at 4.9 million. Police believe that 1.39 million involved 10 cases of telephone fraud on the Mainland, in which victims lost 2.67 million renminbi.
 
Illegal boarding house accommodated four overstays
The CPSP discovered an illegal boarding house in a building on Rua de Évora, in Taipa, where they detained four men from Mainland China for overstaying. Two detainees had other people's identity cards and another had a falsified residence authorization form, having admitted to having bought the document from an unknown person for 300 renminbis. The three were sent to the Public Ministry. The illegal boarding house was sealed by the Tourism Office. Police found eight Mainland individuals in the house, most of whom claimed to have paid HK$150 per day.
 
Shelter Center opens doors due to the cold
Taking into account the issuing of the yellow alert due to the cold by the Meteorological and Geophysical Services, the Winter Shelter Center, on Rua Leste da Ilha Verde, has been open to the public since Saturday. According to the Institute of Social Action, while the Macao SAR is on yellow alert, daily reception hours remain between 6pm and 8am the following day, with the shelter providing comforters, food and drinks to users.
 
Authorities on the lookout for powdered milk collected in the HKSAR
A batch of powdered milk product for infants, recalled by Hong Kong authorities, was not imported into Macau due to possible contamination with the Bacillus cereus microorganism. Designated as “Aptamil Profutura DUO Advance 1 800g”, the batch in question is valid until April 21, 2027. The Institute for Pharmaceutical Supervision and Administration and the Institute for Municipal Affairs continue to monitor the situation and appeal to residents, regardless of whether the product was purchased online, from intermediaries or other means, to stop consuming it.
 
Daily record for border crossings broken
Macau registered a new daily record for border crossings on Saturday, with 867 thousand entries and exits. According to the CPSP, residents represented 36.7% of tickets, visitors 39.1% and TNR 21.6%. On that day, the Macao SAR welcomed 174 thousand visitors. With 463 thousand entries and exits, the Portas do Cerco border also broke the daily record for border crossings over the last five years.
 
House price index decreased by 9.4% in 2025
In 2025, the global average housing price index stood at 195.5, 9.4% less than in 2024, revealed the Statistics and Census Services. On the other hand, between October and December 2025, the global housing price index grew 0.1% compared to the previous period (September to November). Specifically, the index in Taipa and Coloane (200.1) rose 1.0% and that of the Peninsula (189.7) fell 0.3%. In the same time period, the price index for constructed housing (204.6) rose 0.2%, while that for housing under construction (238.8) grew 0.7%, compared to the previous period.</description><pubDate>2026-02-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>PJ warns of three types of scams that remain “at a high level”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pj-alerta-para-tres-tipos-de-burlas-permanecem-num-nivel-elevado/</link><description>Telephone and cyber fraud fell by 22% and 41% year-on-year, but the losses caused by these crimes amounted to 300 million patacas last year. Despite the drop in the number of crimes, the director of the Judiciary Police warned that investment scams, false customer support and online purchases have remained at a “high level”. On the other hand, the number of cyber attacks in the Macao SAR stood at a daily average of 5,700, 10% below the figure in 2024. Inquiry cases related to gambling rose 63%, for a total of 2,314, which Sit Chong Meng attributed to the “addition of the crime of ‘exploitation of illicit exchange’” to the gambling law
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
Last year, the losses caused by fraud using telecommunications amounted to 300 million patacas, close to the value recorded in 2023, said Sit Chong Meng, director of the Judiciary Police (PJ) yesterday. As revealed, there were 277 cases of telephone fraud and 533 of cyber fraud, corresponding to 21.8% and 41.2% fewer incidents in 2024, respectively.
Sit Chong Meng, who was speaking at the Lunar New Year meeting between the PJ and the media, explained that, despite the general drop in fraud cases, investment fraud, false customer support fraud and online shopping fraud have remained at a “high level”. As part of the fight against fraud, the PJ arrested a total of 178 members of criminal networks involved in fraud schemes last year. With the help of the telecommunications sector, 545 phishing sites were also blocked.
In fact, in 2025, "there were three cases linked to 'deepfakes' with artificial intelligence (AI) related to fake investments. Some criminals pretended to be influencers to convince people to invest in fake projects." Others presented themselves as “investment platform assistants and enticed people to write down their personal details and bank account number”, reported Sit.
The director of the PJ said that the organization is studying “deepfakes” and AI technologies that could help authorities intercept false messages. "We want to see if there are measures to prevent these scams", he said, noting that "for now there is no technology to intercept these messages. This has to do with our right to privacy", he clarified.
Sit Chong Meng said the police have been cooperating with telecommunications operators “to find out whether it is possible to intercept these fraudulent messages before people receive them”.
Throughout the year, banks assisted the police by stopping payments in 683 cases, totaling more than 84 million patacas. In turn, the PJ reported 551 suspicious accounts to the banks.
The PJ continues to focus on the integrated strategy “Prevention”, “Recovery” and “Combat”, guaranteed the organization's number one, noting that “the anti-fraud program has demonstrated remarkable effectiveness”, with more than 50 thousand visits throughout the year and the issuance of around 5,100 high-risk alerts.
With regard to cybersecurity defense, the Cybersecurity Incident Alert and Response Center (CARIC) detected an average of 5,700 attacks per day, which represents an annual decrease of 9.5%. Still, the PJ considers it to be “a high number”, which keeps the Macao SAR’s cybersecurity in a “quite serious” situation, warned Sit.
In this context, 295 alert communications were issued, the highest number in recent years. For Sit Chong Meng, the PJ has done “a very good job in prevention”. “We issue a lot of alerts, but the number of cases is few.” In 2025, CARIC received only 23 incident reports, of which four were cyber attacks, the lowest figure in recent years.
 
Legislative review increased crimes in the game
Contrary to scams and cyber attacks, the PJ opened 2,314 investigations and complaints related to gambling, an increase of 62.6% in annual terms. The organization justified this increase with the “addition of the crime of ‘exploitation of illicit exchange for gambling’ and the improvement of the statistical method in this context”.
Furthermore, “due to the increase in the number of tourists and gambling activities in the mass area (…) it is easy for there to be collisions between people, thus creating opportunities for thieves, which has led to an increase in cases of harm to physical integrity, theft and illegitimate appropriation”. In response, Sit Chong Meng stated that “communication with gaming companies has been improved to reinforce security personnel in hotels”.
Until the end of December, the police resolved 567 cases of “exploitation of illicit exchange for gambling”, including 492 cases of illegal money exchange and another 75 related to offenses of this nature. These cases resulted in the arrest of 867 people and the seizure of 94 million Hong Kong dollars in cash and tokens.
"We are currently facing a big challenge because these money exchange groups do not do this in public spaces. Our colleagues are also reinforcing work in casinos. These crimes are generating more problems because lately there have also been more cases of robbery", acknowledged Sit.
"Victims are usually also members of these illegal exchange groups. They exchange in hotel rooms because it is more difficult to be detected. And criminals often take advantage of these opportunities to steal from these rooms," he explained.
The 192 cases of illicit gambling loans and the 28 cases of kidnapping registered last year correspond to annual declines of 23.8% and 40.4%, respectively.
 
Three homicides due to “emotional problems”
Similarly, serious and organized crimes related to gambling continue to maintain “a downward trend and low rate of occurrence”, highlighted the director.
On the other hand, last year, three cases of homicide were recorded, whereas in 2024 there had been none. The director of the PJ, however, clarified that these cases were not related to gambling and that “they only had to do with emotional problems or labor conflicts”.
In relation to drug crimes, authorities registered 61 cases of trafficking and 29 of consumption, representing respective increases of 24.5% and 93.3%. Sit Chong Meng believes that this increase is due to “the deepening of the concept of ‘information-driven criminal investigation’”, better cooperation with neighboring regions and the resolution of several cases.
Over the past year, Macao SAR and Zhuhai police investigated 29 cases of cross-border drug trafficking, with Macau authorities arresting 31 individuals. With regard to drug addicts, of the 146 people registered, 75 were foreigners and 51 residents. “The number of foreigners who use and traffic drugs is growing, [among] those who work in Macau and seek comfort through drugs.”
In another context, arson incidents fell by 34.9%, to 28, in the same time period.
In the overall year 2025, the PJ initiated 14,308 criminal cases, including 6,916 investigations and complaints, 5,502 summary investigations and 1,890 requested due diligence. The total number of cases opened increased by 1.84%, compared to 2024, and 15.48% compared to 2023.
 
They committed sexual crimes against minors
In general, almost all crimes of a sexual nature increased between 2024 and 2025, except for rapes, which fell from 48 to 32 and cases of sexual harassment, which rose from 31 to 28, according to statistical data released by the Judiciary Police. Sexual abuse of children soared by 73%, to a total of 26 cases last year, while there were four cases of recourse to prostitution of minors, three more than a year before. Crimes of pornography against minors more than doubled, from 14 to 28. Episodes of sexual coercion increased from eight to 13 and situations of exploitation of prostitution rose from seven to 12, statistics reveal. The 12 “other crimes against sexual self-determination” represent almost double the previous year (7), while seven “other crimes against sexual freedom” were recorded, repeating the figure from 2024.</description><pubDate>2026-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Aonishiki, the Ukrainian Sumo wrestler in Japan who fled the Russian invasion</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/aonishiki-ucraniano-lutador-de-sumo-japao-fugiu-da-invasao-russa/</link><description>Danylo Yavhusishyn, known as Aonishiki in the world of Sumo, fled the war in Ukraine and is about to reach the highest position in the great traditional Japanese sport in record time. But he remains with his feet on the ground and makes his objective clear after the arduous training: “To get stronger”.
At just 21 years old, Yavhusishyn achieved in just over two years what most fighters can only dream of during their entire career. After a meteoric rise, he won the last two bimonthly tournaments, which determine the general ranking – similar to tennis – and was proclaimed ozeki, the second highest position in Sumo.
If he wins the next tournament in March, his promotion to yokozuna, the highest rank in the discipline, never before achieved by a European, will be practically guaranteed.
But Yavhusishyn avoids succumbing to pressure: “If I think about it too much, I risk becoming tense.” “So far, I’ve managed to do what I usually do, so I just need to keep it up,” he adds.
The young rikishi (wrestler) has been practicing Sumo since he was seven years old and has always dreamed of trying his luck in Japan, in the professional world.
His plans were precipitated by the Russian invasion of his country in February 2022. He left Ukraine a few weeks before turning 18, narrowly escaping military service, and landed in Japan, where he was welcomed by an acquaintance before entering the world of Sumo with the desire to “get stronger”. “To this day, I wake up every day with this desire,” emphasizes Yavhusishyn.
After clarifying to interviewers, including AFP, that he only wanted to talk about Sumo, he confessed that his parents, who live in Germany, visited him last year. "I would like to invite them in June to celebrate my promotion to the rank of ozeki. They are very happy for me and we talk almost every day," he says.
“My friends and former teachers in Ukraine follow Sumo much more than I imagined, and that motivates me even more to dedicate myself”, he continues.
Yavhusishyn explains that he spends his free time sleeping, going to restaurants – “as a fighter, I need to eat a lot” – or bathing in hot springs with his teammates to “disconnect a little from Sumo”.
Sumo is experiencing a resurgence in popularity in Japan, where tournaments sell out and attract large numbers of foreign tourists.
Aonishiki já se tornou um embaixador do desporto nacional japonês, que recentemente retomou as digressões internacionais, com um torneio agendado para Paris em Junho após um evento em Londres no ano passado. O ucraniano espera que espectadores de todo o mundo possam descobrir o Sumo e entender o seu fascínio vendo-o “com seus próprios olhos, em vez de apenas explicá-lo em palavras”.
The truth is that many of Japan's most popular rikishi have not been Japanese nationals for a long time. Over the last few years, several champions of the sport are from Mongolia, taken to Japan from a young age to become fighters and learn the specific culture of the Japanese and this sport.
With similar facies, they gain Japanese names and go unnoticed among the thousands of sumo practitioners, occupying prominent places in a sport that treats champions as “Hollywood stars”.
European, however, Ukrainian Danylo Yavhusishyn is the first to be able to become a yokozuna. If you succeed, you will become a pioneer.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2026-02-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>