<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Caritas Clinic expected to open before Lunar New Year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/clinica-da-caritas-devera-abrir-antes-ano-novo-lunar/</link><description>Doctor with stethoscope in a hospital. High resolution. 3D render



The Health Services recently issued a license for the Caritas clinic, located in Areia Preta, and this medical space could begin providing services before the Lunar New Year, the institution's secretary general revealed to the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper. Furthermore, Paul Pun said that the consultation fee for Western medicine services will be 150 patacas, with a subsidy equivalent to one third of the fee being granted to people with low incomes.

In recent days, Caritas de Macau received the license issued by the Health Services (SSM) for the operation of the clinic, located in Areia Preta, said the institution's general secretary, Paul Pun. As predicted, the space should start operating before Chinese New Year, which this year begins on February 17th, with two types of services, namely physiotherapy and western medicine.
Speaking to the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, Paul Pun stated that, currently, Caritas is purchasing insurance for the two health professionals hired (a Western medicine doctor and a physiotherapist) and purchasing medicines from pharmacies.
"As the clinic is a social services institution, the charge for both physiotherapy and Western medicine services will be relatively affordable for the public. Previously, when the Caritas clinic operated near San Ma Lo [on Rua da Caldeira], it adopted a consultation fee of 120 patacas. It has been several years. Furthermore, you cannot save on the doctors' salaries. Therefore, we preliminarily defined a consultation fee of 150 patacas", said Paul Pun.
At this point, he also revealed that the institution will continue to look for benefactors in society to subsidize part of the consultation fee for local citizens and non-resident workers (TNR) with low incomes, among other people with difficulties. As he recalled, this model had already been adopted in the previous clinic.
"So far, we have found a benefactor, but of course he will not be able to subsidize many people, so we need to continue looking for more benefactors. In relation to the physiotherapy service, the subsidy amount could be 100 patacas, while the subsidy for the Western medicine consultation fee could be 50 patacas", he indicated.
For Paul Pun, after deducting the subsidized amount, a final fee of 100 patacas should be “acceptable” for people in need. "If we count on the support of more benefactors, for example, who are available to subsidize up to 100 patacas, it would also be good for the person assisted to only need to pay a consultation fee of 50 patacas. The benefactors with whom we are now in contact prefer to grant subsidies, rather than bearing all the consultation fees. It is appropriate that the people assisted also assume some responsibilities", he stressed.
 
Six days a week until 10pm
Regarding the clinic's opening hours, Paul Pun predicted that it would be difficult to remain open every day, but pointed to a more viable model of closing at 10 pm daily and resting one day a week. In the long term, the general secretary of Caritas would like the clinic to be open every day and close “a little later” every day, which, however, would be difficult to achieve, he lamented.
On the other hand, the clinic also has a consultation room that will be used for dental services. As revealed, these services are in preparation, with some dental equipment having already been transferred to the clinic. After this stage, the institution will begin to recruit a dentist, which, for Paul Pun, “should not involve many difficulties”.
In general, the person in charge noted that, last year, Caritas received a small number of requests for help in the context of medical services, made mainly by TNR of foreign nationality. This is because the residents who asked for support were mostly trying to solve problems with paying their house rent, while TNRs from Mainland China tend to deal with health problems in hospitals in Zhuhai.
As specified, the foreign TNR mentioned above were facing difficulties because they suddenly fell ill or, after undergoing surgery at the public hospital, were unable to return medical expenses to the hospital.
"This did not happen because they wanted to owe money to the hospital, but because they were experiencing financial difficulties. For example, a person had to return 1,000 patacas every month to Centro Hospitalar Conde de São Januário, but was only able to pay 600 patacas. In this way, Caritas granted some subsidies. In 2025, the number of requests for help of this kind decreased significantly compared to previous years, since many cases received in those years were related with the pandemic”, noted Paul Pun.
According to his observation, despite there being a low number of requests for support in the context of medical services, in reality, “there are many foreign TNRs with these needs”. “Above all [they need] physiotherapy.
"With the provision of [medical] services aimed at people with low incomes, the desire to go to the doctor can be slightly increased. At the same time, it can contribute to reducing situations in which diseases progress to a critical phase, allowing them to look for solutions in advance", concluded the general secretary of Caritas.</description><pubDate>2026-01-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusion of access to casinos motivated an additional 68% of requests</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/exclusao-de-acesso-casinos-motivou-mais-68-de-pedidos/</link><description>In 2025, the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate registered a total of 952 requests for exclusion from access to casinos, a number that represents a new annual record and an increase of 68% year-on-year. Around 87% of requests were submitted by bettors themselves, the latest official data shows
 
During the past year, the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ) received 952 requests for exclusion from access to casinos, a number that exceeds by 67.90% the requests recorded in the general calculation for 2024. As this newspaper had already anticipated, requests for exclusion thus reached a new absolute record since the implementation, on November 1, 2012, of the law that conditions entry, work and gambling in gaming spaces. game.
According to data published on the DICJ website, the number of requests processed between January and December includes 828 requests for self-exclusion (86.97% of the total) and 124 submitted by third parties. In these two aspects, which grew 74.31% and 34.78% in relation to the total for 2024, new annual records were also established.
According to statistical data, the regulatory entity received 214 requests between January and March last year, 221 in the second quarter and 281 in the following three months, including 181, 195 and 242 for self-exclusion, respectively. In the fourth quarter, a total of 236 requests reached the DICJ, of which 210 were for self-exclusion.
In 2024, the DICJ had already registered a record number of requests for exclusion from entry into casinos, with the total growing 14.8% to 567 compared to 2023. Specifically, requests for self-exclusion (475, or 83.8% of the total) and third parties (92) increased by 13.6% and 21%, respectively, in annual terms.
Between November 1, 2012 and the end of last year, the DICJ received 5,789 requests, with those for self-exclusion (5,041) representing 87% of the total. In the same period, 748 requests were submitted by third parties, official information indicates.
Under the aforementioned law, the director of the DICJ may prohibit entry into all casinos, or just some, for a maximum period of two years, to people who request it or who confirm a request presented for this purpose by a spouse, ascendant, descendant or second-degree relative.
In addition to these cases, entry to casinos is prohibited, among other situations, for anyone under 21 years of age; people disqualified by final court decision; who suffer from a notorious psychic anomaly; who are drunk or under the influence of drugs; public servants, except when performing their duties or when authorized by the Chief Executive; and casino workers off duty, except for the first three days of the Lunar New Year.
 
VIP gaming growth expected to slow in 2026
Broker Jefferies Hong Kong expects annual growth in gross revenue from the gaming mass market in Macau to accelerate to 6.6% in 2026, after rising 4.3% in 2025, according to estimates cited by the GGRAsia portal. Conversely, the institution predicts that growth in VIP gaming revenue will slow from 24.1% in 2025 to 2.0% this year. It means that revenue from the mass market could reach just over 191.26 billion patacas, compared to 69.34 billion from the VIP game. Official data shows that VIP baccarat gross revenues rose about 20% sequentially in the fourth quarter and increased 3.7 points in terms of market share to 30.7%. In turn, Citigroup recorded an annual increase of 72.3% in the observed volume of bets made by “whales” (high value players) in local casinos in January. JP Morgan recently reduced its forecast for earnings before interest, taxes, amortization and depreciation in 2026, citing an adverse mix of games – including “super-premium and premium games” with lower margins – and operating costs.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2026-01-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Completed in April 2029 1st part of Jardim do Canídromo</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/concluida-em-abril-de-2029-1a-parte-jardim-canidromo/</link><description>Information from DSOP indicates that zone 1 of the Citizens' Sports Garden, in the former Canídromo, will be completed in April 2029. This area has three pavilions, which could begin to be used by the public before the construction of zone 2 begins.
 
CATARINA PEREIRA
 
The construction contract for zone 1 of the Citizens' Sports Garden on the plot of the former Yat Yuen Canidrome is expected to be completed in April 2029, according to information from the Public Works Services Department (DSOP). The work – awarded for 1.34 billion patacas to the Consortium of Grupo Construção Omas Limitada, Companhia de Engenharia de Tuneis Shanghai S.A., Branch in Macau and China Zhong Ji Indústria e Instabilidade (Macau) Lda – began this month.
According to the information provided, the sports garden plot has an area of ​​40,425 square meters, divided, depending on the functions, into four parts and an outdoor athletics field. More specifically, pavilion 1, in the center of the lot and with four floors, should have a swimming pool and children's pool, basketball court, running track and cycle path for children, among others.
The plan also includes a 'skatepark' and two-story table tennis, wall climbing, volleyball and badminton courts, among others, in pavilion 2, which has six floors. On the other hand, pavilion 3 includes a football field for five people, a two-story multipurpose room, a multifunctional activities room and space for outdoor activities, among others, on a total of seven floors.
In zone 2 there will be a pavilion for children, which will have four floors. The idea is to build an outdoor activity area for children, an indoor playground, a creative classroom and a reading area, among others. The basement will be used as an activity room and storage space, “among other spaces with more enhanced functionality”, it can be read.
The outdoor athletics field (also a zone 2 project) will have eight standardized athletics tracks and high and long jump facilities, among others, and will also feature a standardized synthetic grass football field in the center of the athletics field.
After the construction of the first zone is completed and the spaces come into operation, the authorities will then move on to the construction of zone 2. During the execution of the work, and in collaboration with the competent services, the operation of the adjacent sports field and the Lin Fong Sports Center will remain “normal”.
 
Super charging station at COTAI ready in June
The design and construction of a super charging station for light and heavy vehicles on Rua da Patinagem, in COTAI, has already begun and will be completed next June, according to the Public Works Services Department. It should be noted that this is a pilot project that aims to further boost the use of electric vehicles. On the other hand, the contract to expand the Reservoir in Seac Pai Van is scheduled for February 2028, according to information from the same organization.</description><pubDate>2026-01-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>International parade scheduled for March 29th</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/desfile-internacional-agendado-para-29-de-marco/</link><description>The “Macau International Parade 2026” will take place on March 29th, announced the Cultural Institute, which is looking for local proposals. Ideas can be submitted until the 25th. This year, in addition to the extension activities, the IC plans to organize the “VIVA Carnival” at Anim’Arte NAM VAN on the eve and day of the event, to “increase the participation of local SMEs in major events and expand the reach of the Parade”

The “2026 Macau International Parade” is scheduled for March 29th, announced the Cultural Institute (IC), inviting registered local artistic and cultural associations, schools and small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) interested in participating in the event to submit proposals by 5:30 pm on January 25th.
To demonstrate Macau's important role during the Age of Discoveries, this year's Parade encourages participating groups to showcase the essence of Macau as the “City of Sailors”, expressing their creativity and showing the charm of Macau's cultural integration and innovation, explains the organization led by Leong Wai Man.
This year, the route will start at the Ruins of St. Paul and end at Praça do Lago Sai Van. Groups can participate in the Parade in four ways, including “Parade Theme”, “Artistic Group Parade”, “Large-Scale Artistic Installation Parade” and “Special Planning Parade”. “In order to increase the participation of groups, various prizes will continue to be awarded”, adds the statement.
Furthermore, in order to incorporate the atmosphere of the event into the community, several outreach activities will be carried out before the Parade. Groups can choose to sign up for the “Community Performance and Street Art Groups” modality, bringing different forms of culture and art to local communities, or sign up for the opening and/or closing shows.
On the other hand, to increase the participation of local SMEs in major events and expand the reach of the Parade, the IC plans to hold “Carnival VIVA” at Anim’Arte NAM VAN on the eve and day of the Parade. “Local SMEs are invited to offer gastronomic specialties and various creative interactive experiences, transforming the area into a prominent location alongside the Parade’s main activities”, explains the press release.
Since the first edition, in 2011, the Parade has invited performing arts groups from all over the world to team up with local artists “so that, with their distinctive costumes and styles, they can provide Macau residents and tourists with a cultural and joyful environment, highlighting the unique landscape of the Historic Center of Macau, spreading the concept of ‘Love, Peace and Cultural Integration’ and promoting interaction and exchange of arts and culture”, says the IC.
Interested local artistic groups and SMEs can send proposals and information to the IC Recreational Activities Division, indicating on the envelope: “2026 Macau International Parade – Call for Proposals from Local Artistic Groups” or “2026 Macau International Parade – Call for Proposals from Local Small and Medium Enterprises for VIVA Carnival”. More information about registration can be consulted and downloaded on the IC website.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2026-01-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China denounces return to the “law of the jungle” in Davos</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/china-denuncia-em-davos-regresso-a-lei-da-selva/</link><description>epa12663743 He Lifeng, Vice-Premier of the People’s Republic of China, speaks during a session in the Congress Hall at the 56th annual meeting of the World Economic Forum (WEF) in Davos, Switzerland, 20 January 2026. The meeting, held under the theme 'A Spirit of Dialogue,' brings together, scientists, and corporate and political leaders and runs from 19 to 23 January.  EPA/GIAN EHRENZELLER



China protested yesterday, at the Davos Forum, in Switzerland, against what it classified as the return to the “law of the jungle” in international relations, “where the strong attack the weak”, criticizing tariffs and trade wars, for their “severe impacts” on the global economy.
Speaking at a forum that this year takes place in a context of heightened geopolitical and commercial tensions, Chinese Vice Prime Minister He Lifeng, without ever expressly referring to the USA, argued that “a small number of privileged countries should not benefit from advantages based solely on their interests, and the world cannot return to the law of the jungle, where the strong attack the weak”.
In his speech, the Beijing official also implicitly criticized North American trade policy, stating that “tariffs and trade wars have no winners”, advocating the benefits of “free trade and economic globalization”.
Considering that the global trading system is currently facing its biggest challenge in many years, He Lifeng “the unilateral acts and trade agreements of certain countries clearly violate the fundamental principles and rules of the World Trade Organization”.
Regarding the criticism that China's trade surplus with the rest of the world is unbalanced, the Chinese vice-premier, highlighting his country's ambition if, in addition to wanting to be “the world's factory”, it is also “the world's market”, commented that, “when China wants to buy, other countries don't want to sell”, in a new allusion to the policy of the North American administration led by Donald Trump, which imposed restrictions on the sale of the best microchips used in Artificial Intelligence to China.
The Davos Forum, which annually brings together the world's economic and political elites, takes place throughout this week in that alpine resort in Switzerland, in a context of great global instability, with all attention focused on the participation of the North American President, Donald Trump, who will speak this Wednesday. Under the theme of this 56th edition “A Spirit of Dialogue”, the event, which runs until Friday, could hardly take place in an environment of greater tension and risks on a global scale, and will feature one of the main protagonists of this tense environment, Donald Trump, who returns in person to Davos six years later, after having been present in 2020, during his first term in the White House (2017-2021).
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Beauty of Macau “discovered” more than 70 million times</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/beleza-de-macau-descoberta-mais-de-70-milhoes-de-vezes/</link><description>The Tourism Services Department ensured that the contents relating to the series of activities “Discover the beauty of Macau” were viewed more than 70 million times. For dissemination, DST had the support of media outlets in Mainland China, digital influencers and groups on social media
 
The Tourist Office's (DST) series of activities “Discover the beauty of Macau” reached 70.25 million views, according to a press release. A hundred media outlets from Mainland China, 100 groups on social media and 97 digital influencers “promoted consumption in restaurants and entertainment in community neighborhoods in Macau”, said the MGTO.
Within the scope of the same initiative, 17 routes were explored in community areas. These included themed filming, gastronomic photography and culture-related itineraries, with the purpose of “promoting Macau’s tourist and cultural resources, the tourist elements of community neighborhoods, typical gastronomy, among others”.
DST stated that the itineraries were combined with offers of accommodation in the Macao SAR, restaurants in community areas and other entertainment, to “attract visitors to visit and consume”, for the benefit of “surrounding small and medium-sized businesses, boosting the flow of people in community neighborhoods and boosting their economy”. The initiative also promoted several events in Macau, with the aim of attracting more tourists to the territory.
Repeating the collaboration of 2024, when DST and “Meituan” launched the “Encontro Alegre” project, both returned to cooperate in promoting the tourist characteristics of “Macao Culture” last year. In addition to the “Discover the Beauty of Macau” initiative, the joint efforts of the MSAR tourism authorities and the Chinese company resulted in the activities “Macau in the Heart”, “Finding Macau Street Foodies” and “Era Brilhante de Macau”.
Macau promotional pages were also created in the mobile applications of “Meituan” and “Dianping”, with tourist itineraries in community neighborhoods and promotions in surrounding stores, “to enrich the tourist experience of visitors and thus contribute to the development of tourism and the economy”, can be read in the note.
Taking advantage of Macau's previous status as the “City of Culture of East Asia”, MGTO organized promotional events and publicity activities in the central commercial circles of the cities of Qingdao, Changsha, Xi'an, Yangzhou and Chengdu, as well as in 50 stores.
The “Xiaohongshu” and “Dianping” platforms also launched the “Macau no Coração” interactive photography contest. MGTO also invited restaurant managers in community areas, heirs of traditional cuisine and gastronomy experts to record promotional videos about Macau's gastronomy.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2026-01-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Authorities call for measures against “sharp” drop in temperature</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/autoridades-apelam-medidas-contra-descida-acentuada-da-temperatura/</link><description>With the forecast of a “sharp” drop in temperature for today and tomorrow, the Meteorological and Geophysical Services and the Health Services appeal to the population, especially the elderly and people with illnesses, to take precautionary measures to prevent hypothermia
 
The Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) predict, for today and tomorrow, a “sharp drop” in temperature in the territory, recommending the population to “pay attention to sharp changes in temperatures and protect themselves against the cold”.
The forecast for today pointed to temperatures between 11 °C and 16 °C, that is, cold and dry weather, as well as “very cloudy skies with intervals of clear skies”. For tomorrow, the SMG expect temperatures to drop to 10º C, rising to a maximum of 15º C.
Yesterday, the maximum temperature was 19º C, and at night, the minimum temperature dropped to around 15º C, according to information from SMG.
The Winter Shelter Center opened its doors at 6pm yesterday, and while the Macao SAR is on yellow alert, daily reception hours remain from 6pm to 8am the following day. The shelter facilities provide comforters, food and drinks to users, recalled the Social Action Institute.
Taking into account the forecasts of falling temperatures, the SMG recommended that the population prepare additional clothing and drink more water. Furthermore, people with weaker constitutions should protect themselves from the cold when going out.
Warning that the drop in temperature is often accompanied by strong winds, they ask that people with respiratory illnesses or those who are more fragile be careful with dust raised by the wind, as well as observe changes in air quality levels and adjust travel plans.
"The drop in temperature is often accompanied by rain. When strong winds combine with weather conditions such as cloudy skies and precipitation, the thermal sensation may be lower than the actual temperature", he adds.
As the SMG predicted a sharp drop in temperatures over the next 48 hours, the Health Services appealed to the population to prevent hypothermia and take care to maintain body temperature. He warned, in particular, that the elderly, people with chronic illnesses and their caregivers, as well as institutions that provide services to these groups, must take appropriate preventive and care measures to guarantee their health.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2026-01-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Support from the Reparation Fund can be requested online</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/apoio-fundo-de-reparacao-pode-ser-pedido-online/</link><description>Requests for support for repairs to class P and M buildings to the Building Repair Fund can now be made online, through the Single Account or the Platform for Companies and Associations. The Housing Institute then intends to gradually expand the types of services provided online
 
The Housing Institute (IH) launched online submission services for applications to the Financial Support Plan for Repair of Common Parts of Class P and M Buildings (Low Buildings), in conjunction with the development of electronic governance. In this first phase, applications can only be made for this Building Repair Fund plan, and the objective is to then “gradually” expand the scope of services provided online.
Applications can be submitted by owners, administrations and commercial condominium management companies through the Platform for Companies and Associations or the Single Account. The progress of the processes can also be consulted online.
According to IH, as of January 9, 4,341 cases of the Financial Support Plan for Repair of Common Parts of Class P and M Buildings had been approved, involving 3,354 buildings, with an approved value of more than 510 million patacas. “It is the financial support plan approved with the largest number of cases and awarded the highest value by the Building Repair Fund”, he points out.
Owners and administrations that access the Single Account, as well as commercial condominium management companies that access the Platform for Companies and Associations, can process seven types of services online, such as new application, consultation of application records, amendment of application information, delivery of missing documents, delivery of hearing documents, delivery of documents relating to the completion of works and cancellation of the application.
At the time of submitting an application, says IH, applicants can also authorize contractors to use the Platform for Companies and Associations to handle subsequent procedures, such as uploading application documents, missing documents and documents relating to the completion of works. For the organization, this makes it easier to present applications.
It is worth remembering that support granted by the Building Repair Fund to help owners repair their properties increased by almost 19% in 2025, in annual terms, as reported by this newspaper. Last year alone, 66.05 million patacas were allocated to around 500 buildings. Since it was created in 2007, the Fund has channeled more than 714.3 million patacas towards various types of works.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2026-01-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Conversations and workshops complement Chinese Culture Shows</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/conversas-workshops-complementam-espectaculos-de-cultura-chinesa/</link><description>The theater play “Goodbye, My Concubine”, one of the highlights of the first “Chinese Culture Show Season”, will feature a series of complementary activities. The Cultural Institute organized a series of conversations and workshops for young and old viewers

PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
The Cultural Institute (IC) prepared a series of workshops and complementary activities to the show “Goodbye, My Concubine”, by the Beijing People's Theatre, as part of the inaugural edition of the “Chinese Culture Show Season”. The multiple initiatives will allow interested parties to “experience the beauty of traditional Chinese culture from multiple perspectives”, says a press release.
On January 27th, between 8:00 pm and 9:30 pm, the Auditorium of the Macau Art Museum will host the “Inter-regional Dialogue and Young Actors”. The main creators of the production and young actors from local and Mainland China will have an “in-depth discussion about character construction and performing arts, deconstructing the creative process, perceptions and techniques for representing dramatic characters from multiple dimensions, such as action, personality and image”.
On January 31st, from 4:30 pm to 5:30 pm, the Enamel Jewelery Workshop will also be held in the Conference Room of the Macau Cultural Center (CCM), which will allow participants, at least six years old, to “experience, under professional guidance, traditional crafts and the aesthetics of scenography”.
The same space will host the Calligraphy Workshop for the Elderly, on February 1st, aimed at residents over 55 years of age. On February 1st, the same space will host a Post-Show Conversation, between 4:30 pm and 5:30 pm, for residents of the same age. On the 30th and 31st of January, from 10pm to 10:30pm, Studio II of the Cultural Center will have a Post-Show Conversation for spectators.
Registration for the different activities is limited and can be done through the Single Account. Admission to the “Dialogue between Young Artists” will be on a first-come, first-serve basis, while those selected for the workshops will be drawn if the number of registrations exceeds the number of places available.
Between January 29th and February 1st, the Beijing People's Theater will present, at CCM Studio II, the immersive play “Goodbye, My Concubine”, one of the highlights of the season. The work, written by Nobel Prize winner for Literature Mo Yan, “breaks with the traditional narrative structure of historical drama”, by exploring “timeless themes such as power, survival and responsibility through multiple encounters and a structure of temporally intertwined dialogues”.
Through an immersive scenic design, a Chu Army camp surrounding the audience will allow viewers to witness “up close and personal the intense love and hate plots between the characters.”
The Beijing People's Theater is a professional group founded in 1952, initially directed by Cao Yu, a renowned playwright. Over seven decades, the group has trained countless artists and staged more than 300 productions of various genres in China and abroad.
Tickets for all shows of the season are available at “Enjoy Macao”. Residents, students, teachers, the elderly and the disabled will be able to benefit from discounts, with only one discounted ticket allowed to each eligible cardholder.</description><pubDate>2026-01-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MAM hosts colloquium on heritage preservation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mam-recebe-coloquio-sobre-preservacao-patrimonio/</link><description>At 2:30 pm on January 25th, the Macau Museum of Art will host the Seminar on Preservation and Restoration of Cultural Heritage, to which local experts from Australia and Greece will be invited. Registration for the event, organized by the Cultural Heritage Preservation and Transmission Center of the Palace Museum in Macau, is open until tomorrow
 
The Center for Preservation and Transmission of Cultural Heritage of the Palace Museum in Macau will organize the Seminar on Preservation and Restoration of Cultural Heritage, between 2:30 pm and 5:30 pm on January 25th, at the Macau Museum of Art. According to the Cultural Institute (IC), experts in heritage restoration from Australia and Greece will participate, as well as local academics.
Guest speakers include Qu Liang, director of the Conservation Standards Department of the Palace Museum, Ian Miles, a renowned metal conservation expert from Australia, Amalia Siatou, a heritage conservation expert from Greece, and Kin Hong Ip, research assistant professor at the University of Macau.
Participants will present various topics, namely “the state of safeguarding cultural heritage in Mainland China, techniques for safeguarding metals and bronze, the practice of restoring and maintaining bronze statues in the Ruins of Saint Paul and the experiences of restoring cultural heritage in Greece”.
The IC will also accept the participation of academics and professionals from the heritage and architecture sectors, as well as the general public, for an exchange session. The initiative aims to “strengthen international exchange on heritage preservation and restoration techniques, increase public understanding of heritage restoration and promote education and joint safeguarding of cultural heritage”.
The seminar will be held in Mandarin and English, with simultaneous translation into both languages. Registration for the event, with free entry, can be made through the Single Account, until tomorrow. Spaces are limited and will be allocated in order of registration, warns the IC.
As the first cultural space co-created between the Macao SAR Government and the Palace Museum, the Center has been carrying out, since 2025, restoration and conservation work on the bronze statues in the Ruins of São Paulo, which are in the second phase.
For the IC, the Center serves as a platform “for the exchange of restoration techniques for eastern and western architectural heritage”, dedicated to “promoting international collaboration and exchange in the restoration of architectural heritage, fostering local talent in restoration and promoting education and dissemination”.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2026-01-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Pretrial detention for HKSAR woman for cannabis trafficking</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/prisao-preventiva-para-mulher-da-raehk-por-trafico-de-canabis/</link><description>A Hong Kong resident, who was intercepted a few days ago at Macau Airport, for transporting 30 packages of cannabis, weighing a total of 17 kilos according to information from the authorities, is in preventive detention awaiting trial. The Criminal Investigation Court, under the direction of the MP, applied the coercive measure of preventive detention to him, a measure that was due to “the existence of strong evidence of the commission of the crime of illicit trafficking in narcotics and psychotropic substances (…), taking into account the factors, namely, the seriousness of the crime, the criminal framework and the avoidance of escape from Macau, as well as the possibility of some suspects being on the run”, says a statement from the MP and the Prosecutor's Office. According to the preliminary investigation, it appears that the defendant was hired by a transnational drug trafficking group in order to transport drugs as directed on a flight that departed Southeast Asia for the Macao SAR. The MP states in a statement that “it will rigorously combat crimes associated with drugs”, also calling on citizens to report “any news of drug crimes to the entities responsible for enforcing the law or to the MP, in order to jointly build a healthy and drug-free social environment”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Businesspeople went to learn about the reality of Portuguese industries</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/empresarios-foram-conhecer-realidade-das-industrias-portuguesas/</link><description>A delegation of businesspeople from Macau and Mainland China is in Lisbon until the 23rd of January to establish contacts and explore opportunities for commercial cooperation. The delegation, promoted by the Guangdong and Macau Federation of Industry and Commerce and led by the president of the association, Si Ka Lon, visited some scientific parks and learned about “start-up” projects in environmental protection and the pharmaceutical industry. He also visited the Macau Economic and Commercial Delegation in the Portuguese capital, the Chinese embassy in Portugal and the Assembly of the Republic, in addition to Macau companies and institutions established there. According to the association, the group of businesspeople intends to learn “in depth the policies and legal regimes of Portugal”, hoping that the visit “will help to establish a bridge for Macau companies to explore the market in Portuguese-speaking countries”. The delegation hopes that results will be achieved in three areas: promoting effective cooperation projects between Macau companies and the industrial and commercial sector in Portugal; establish a stronger economic and commercial contact network, through institutions and commercial associations that operate in Portugal; and explore more opportunities to go abroad. The trip was also used to strengthen connections with students and other young people from Macau who study and work in Portugal, “so that they can make their contributions to the implementation of Macau's staffing policies”, emphasizes the association.</description><pubDate>2026-01-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese skateboarding champion comes to Macau for “Battle of Champions”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/campea-chinesa-de-skate-vem-macau-para-batalha-dos-campeoes/</link><description>Chenxi Cui, winner of the last season's skateboarding championship in China, will be present at the second edition of the “Battle of Champions”, between March 13th and 15th, which will take place on a track to be installed by Melco at the Studio City Event Center. Alongside Chenxi, there will be “skaters” who are equally renowned internationally, such as compatriots Jiajie PAN and Hong Yun, Filipina Margielyn Didal and South Korean Juni Kang. The competition is part of the International Skateboarding Festival Extreme Sports (FISE), being organized by the International Federation of the sport, with the collaboration of Melco Resorts, Rakuten Sports and the Hurricane Group. Athletes will compete in the Pro, men's and women's, amateur and junior divisions in a system of individual matches. 7:30 pm (women). The park where the event will take place will adopt a new creative direction inspired by the cinematic theme of the integrated resort. The organization announced that tickets to watch the “Battle of Champions” have now gone on sale,” says a statement from Melco.</description><pubDate>2026-01-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Meteorizations” by Filipa César in Serralves reflects on colonial echoes of Guinea-Bissau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/meteorizacoes-de-filipa-cesar-em-serralves-reflecte-sobre-ecos-coloniais-da-guine-bissau/</link><description>The elements of water, earth, air and fire are the guiding thread of “Meteorizações”, Filipa César's first anthological exhibition opened in Serralves, Porto, summoning Guinea-Bissau's colonial past and echoes in the present.
“We had to find a way to organize all these works and we thought about organizing them through the elements [water, earth, air, fire]”, explained Filipa César, during a visit to the press, about her first major anthological exhibition at the Serralves Museum, in Porto.
In the first room of the exhibition, “Meteorizações” is dedicated to water and the visitor is surrounded by the sounds of running water, which Filipa César explains is the flow of the Trancoso River intertwining with the voices of people from the “mangrove schools”. “Mangrove schools” are spaces that promote environmental education and community development focused on the protection and restoration of mangroves in Guinea-Bissau.
“The water room summons many flows, from passersby across the Trancoso River, like the mangrove schools in Guinea-Bissau, as well as an excerpt from a film with Marinho de Pina [Guinean storyteller], about the conflicts that we [Filipa and Pina] had in the processes of these collaborative works”, describes the artist born in 1975.
The exhibition route takes the visitor to a new room that summons the Earth element. It is in that space that, for example, images of Amílcar Cabral (1924-1973) appear in another film. Amílcar Cabral, politician and agronomist born in Bafatá, Guinea, under Portuguese colonial rule, led the struggle for the liberation and independence of Guinea-Bissau and Cape Verde.
“He was very interested in soil as a historical body”, said the artist about the co-founder of the African Party for the Independence of Guinea and Cape Verde.
The title of the exhibition – “Meteorizations” – refers to a notion originating from geology, reinterpreted by Amílcar Cabral, who understands the earth “as a product of natural forces and historical and political dynamics in permanent mutation”, reads the press dossier.
“It was from there that I developed many research texts, films that start from this common principle of a soil as an inscribed body and what I called agropoetics, which is this research relationship, but the soil as a starting point to think about the possibilities and conditions of the earth in relation to the humanity that inhabits it”, adds Filipa César.
Filipa César has been investigating the practice of militant cinema and the agropoetics of the African liberation movement in Guinea-Bissau - that is, in the context of the political and social movements that fought for the decolonization of Africa -, through the production of workshops, texts, films, performances, publications and community meetings.
The exhibition route has two other rooms. In the one dedicated to the air, “to thoughts and ideas”, there is a weaving collection and several questions about ‘panu di pinti’, a traditional handmade fabric from Guinea-Bissau.
The ‘panu di pinti’ “inscribes many questions that connect us and that bring up the issue of Creole as a place of meeting, union and transformation and not a space of separation”, highlights Filipa César.
There is also a room dedicated to the element of fire, where you can see a film and installation that explore how optical technologies of military and colonial design – from Fresnel lenses in lighthouses to global satellite navigation systems – inform and are informed by Western models of knowledge, adopting a critical approach to the ideologies behind the development of these guidance and surveillance instruments.
The entire exhibition route has films, several books (some were banned in Portugal during Salazar's dictatorship), documents and unpublished materials, from initial works such as “The Embassy” (2011), to more recent productions by the artist.
The anthological exhibition reveals a continuous process of research over the last 15 years, said Filipa César, highlighting that it is not only made by herself, but in collaboration with researchers, filmmakers and local communities, including a close collaboration with the Guinean director Sana na N´Hada, who filmed the guerrilla and was responsible for the National Institute of Cinema and Audiovisual of Guinea-Bissau.
It is an exhibition that “builds transversal relationships between different times, supports and contexts”, inviting “the public to think critically about the colonial past and its effects on the present”.
The presentation text highlights “films, objects and documents that evoke historical events such as Portuguese anti-fascist disobedience and Guinean anti-colonial resistance”, in a journey that crosses “audiovisual archives from the period of liberation struggles, reflections on mangroves, optics and weaving policies, and the agropoetic thought of Amílcar Cabral”.
The exhibition, produced by the Serralves Foundation, is curated by Inês Grosso, chief curator of the Museum, and Paula Nascimento. The exhibition also includes a new publication, designed by Bárbara Says and coordinated by Amarante Abramovici, bringing together an archive of essays, conversations and correspondence that accompanied the research process over the last 15 years.
Filipa César is a filmmaker, educator and community organizer and, since 2011, has been collectively investigating the practice of militant cinema.
The “Meteorização” exhibition will be on display in Serralves until May 31st.
 
JTM/Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>