<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Police authorities will invest more in technology</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/autoridades-policiais-vao-investir-mais-na-tecnologia/</link><description>The bet on technology in the service of security will be reinforced, won Wong Sio Chak in the presentation of the government lines. By way of example, he said that “more advanced equipment” will be purchased to respond to the evolution of burla crimes and small automatic drone airports. The secretary admitted that there is more “pressure” and fewer employees, so these equipment will help increase the “effectiveness” of work
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Wong Sio Chak's tutelage will bet more on technology to safeguard safety in the territory, thus increasing the “effectiveness” of work at various levels, the secretary said in the presentation of the government lines for 2025 in the Legislative Assembly. The ruler also admitted that there is more work at borders and fewer employees, a problem that also extends to Coloane's prison establishment.
According to it, the Judiciary Police (PJ) will expand the structure of the Coordination Center to Combat Bonds and “will acquire more advanced equipment, with a view to monitoring and analyzing more efficiently the evolution of burla crimes and the consequent adoption of better prevention and combating these crimes”. In recent years, the crime of burla has been growing, affecting several layers of the population, from young people to the elderly.
Thus, the authorities also ensure that they will continue to "intensify cooperation with neighboring regions and improve communication and alertness in relation to new moderandi." At the same time, it will continue to cooperate with the bank sector and the police of neighboring regions, further improving the immediate termination mechanism of payment and alertness. In addition, Wong Sio Chak has indicated that PJ "will continue to promote and improve the Wechat Anti-Burning mini-programming, as well as organize awareness activities, with a view to improving the awareness of the community in relation to burla crimes."
In turn, later this year, customs services will create smaller automatic drone airports and introduce robots to inspect the lower part of vehicles, "to increase the effectiveness of work in border posts and the application of maritime law." The Public Security Police Corps will increase self-service collection equipment for the “biometric characteristics system of tourists visiting Macao”, “all foreign tourists will be subject to this collection”.
As for borders, Wong Sio Chak admitted that work is now more, but there are fewer workers. "There is great pressure on the passage of vehicles on the border. If there are conditions we want to improve the situation."
He also said that in October the border passage without document will enter into the post of Hengqin, through facial recognition. In addition, it ruled out the hypothesis of widening the vehicle circulation measure in Guangdong to the Hengqin border.
In the hemiciclo, he also stated that the PJ will continue to study and update criminal investigation techniques, will introduce “more advanced” devices for drug detection and activate the advanced police training system. Corporate services, in turn, will introduce a new medical system in prison zones, "which enables health professionals to quick access to medical records and allows the issuance of prescriptions to ensure the health of prisoners and, simultaneously, save police resources allocated to the submission of prisoners to the hospital for medical treatment." Also with regard to prison, Wong Sio Chak noted that it is becoming increasingly difficult to hire staff. At the session, he also assured that the authorities will continue to reinforce the fight against the illegal exchange of money.
In addition, the secretary indicated that the bill to integrate the “ethomidate” into the substance control list has already been delivered to the Executive Board. As reported by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao earlier this month, the government intends to complete the legislative process this year. The proposal will be discussed on May 2.
 
Detected first case of burla using artificial intelligence
The first case of Burla is detected in Macao using Artificial Intelligence (IA), the secretary revealed for security. At a press conference, police explained that the case was denounced by an elderly man, who claimed that his face was used in a fake video. In the video, the man offers a foolproof investment opportunity to attract people to click. An initial investigation revealed that when people clicked, they were taken to a fake website that was going through a local media. On this site, there was a video made using Deepfake AI techniques, in which the elderly faded an investment scheme, leading others to false investment platforms to commit fraud. Police said there was no record of victims.
 
National Security Commission will be the target of restructuring
Wong Sio Chak said in Hemiciclo that the MSAR State Security Defense Commission is mainly composed of the Administration and Justice and Security Guardianships, so the government will study restructuring "to widen functions to all tutelage." Pointing out that the commission operates part-time, it also indicated that in the future it will become in a physical entity. According to the authorities, the authorities are also creating a risk alert system for national security.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Crystal Fish” mobilized 385 citizens</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/peixe-de-cristal-mobilizou-385-cidadaos/</link><description>The exercise “Crystal Fish” was attended by 385 citizens. For 4 hours and 15 minutes, 40 possible accidents were simulated that may occur during the passage of a typhoon



















During the “Crystal Fish 2025” civil protection exercise, which lasted about 4 hours and 15 minutes, 40 possible accidents that could occur during a typhoon was simulated. The simulacrum was chaired by the Secretary for Security and Joint Action Commander, Wong Sio Chak, accompanied by the Commander General of Unit Police Services (SPU) and supporting joint action commander, Leong Man Cheong.
Wong Sio Chak considered that the exercise took place “no problems in general”, having thanked the “active participation” of the civil protection structure. He also stressed that, in view of the possible extreme weather conditions it is necessary to consider “more complex scenarios” to protect the lives of citizens.
"Members of the civil protection structure should continue to work hard to review the deficiencies in the exercises as soon as possible, provide opinions for the review of special response plans and minimize the impact and losses caused by natural disasters," said the secretary, quoted in a statement.
The exercise simulated the passage of Super Typhoon, accompanied by the phenomenon “Storm Surge”, causing serious flooding in the low and various incidents. The civil protection structure has tested several emergency and rescue response operations.
According to the press release, accidents that were tested included failures in the transmission system in the Civil Protection Operations Center system, prisoners who needed to be removed, energy cuts due to accidents in high voltage substations, fires, works overthrown by strong winds and who blocked the streets, among others.
The objective was "to examine the emergency plans of various departments, the effectiveness of implementing information transmission and linking mechanisms and strengthening coordinated macao emergency response capabilities."
The simulacrum included 2,486 participants (31 civil protection volunteers and 385 citizens), involving a total of 4,588 families to be removed.
To “continually raise the ability to predict, alert and response” to adverse and extreme weather situations, weather and geophysical services have also performed a simulacrum. The idea was to review and optimize working procedures, the operation of the systems and the collaboration capacity and response of the various jobs.
However, with the approach of Typhoon's time, the Institute for Municipal Affairs made, in the first quarter, 480 Actions of Surveillance to the Fat Retractors I deduct 20 News of News against Food and Drink Establishments and 10 against shipyards.
The body also inspected and cleaning the low zones. Between January and March, it completed the cleaning of more than 55,000 meters of sewage and more than 2,500 sinks, as well as the registration and analysis of CCTV images of about nine thousand meters of sewers.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourist neighborhood could cost 12 billion patacas</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/bairro-turistico-podera-custar-12-mil-milhoes-de-patacas/</link><description>The chief executive revealed yesterday that the project of Macau's “tourist neighborhood” could cost 12 billion patacas, predicting, on the other hand, that a budget of 20 billion is required to build the “University City”
 
The “International Integrated Tour and Cultural neighborhood of Macao”, one of the four “relevant projects” announced in the government lines, may require a budget of the order of 12 billion Patacas, anticipated yesterday the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai. He said, from the second half of this year and with a time horizon of two or three years, the government will advance with the public tender related to this project, for which it is necessary to make “full and good use” of the area between the peninsula and the mud.
According to “or Mun Tin Toi”, also in a series of interviews under the theme of “Opportunities in Macao”, Sam Hou Fai indicated that, for this project, a National Museum, an International Center for Culture and Arts and an International Exhibition Center, and a symbolic base for the Asia Pacific and even the world ”will be built. The chief executive expects the construction of the National Museum to start as soon as possible.
Generally speaking, Sam Hou Fai has foresaw that the goals for the four projects will be achieved in eight to 10 years. Among these projects, there is also the phased construction of the “University City”, for which the government will be able to invest about 20 billion patacas. According to emphasized, one of the project's objectives is to cultivate for the country and for the high -level talents of the tourism and leisure area.
Regarding the “Industrial Park of Research and Development of Macao Sciences and Technologies”, Sam Hou Fai said the next step will be to consider the development model. The objective is, under the leadership of the government, to build the park, taking advantage of the location and unique advantages of masters, he stressed, to bind the desire that headquarters and research bases of large national and foreign companies can be established in the territory.
As for the expansion of the airport, it provided for an investment of six billion patacas. The endeavor is part of the “relevant project” to build an “macao international air transport hub on the west bank of Rio das Pearls”. For this, equipment will be built, such as the parking platform, and the utmost party of the advantages of the in -depth cooperation zone, the International Air Traffic Rights and the Macao Free Trade Zone, stressed.
On the other hand, the chief executive noted that many companies in Macau are not in royal operation in Hengqin, so it considers that it should be strongly driven. In general, the government should guide and encourage local society to develop in that area, it defended.
In addition, about the trade war, Sam Hou Fai stated that the indirect impact on the MSAR will be large, including the consumption of tourists. Still, it minimized the impact of the scenario on government reserve investments.
In turn, the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, stressed that MSar and Hengqin have to overcome the cooperation model that works among the cities of the great bay, being more bold and innovative in the convergence of rules and mechanisms.
The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM, noted that currently the rate of continuation of studies for higher education is 97.3%, which reflects preliminary results of the formation of local higher education staff. Looking to the future, the secretary said that the government will try to support the country to establish a “Regional Center for Transfer and Technological Transformation of National Universities”. In addition, he stressed that he expects to create more joint research institutes and research platforms in the deepened cooperation zone.
 
Boss visits Zhuhai, Zhongshan and Jiangmen
Since yesterday afternoon, the chief executive leads a delegation of the Government of MSAR to visit Zhuhai, Zhongshan and Jiangmen. During the trip, which ends today, Sam Hou Fai will have meetings with the leaders of the three cities, to exchange impressions on how to deepen bilateral cooperation and propel together the construction of the Great Bay. The program also includes visits to find out the development of these cities and cultural tourism projects. The delegation is part of the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, and the Commander General of Unit Police Services, Leong Man Cheong, among other personalities.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Iam will notice source, mural and flower beds with the See</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/iam-vai-reparar-fonte-mural-canteiros-junto-a-se/</link><description>The Institute for Municipal Affairs will start in May repair work on the facilities in Largo da Sé and around Travessa do Meio. The works should be completed in October

From May 7, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) will remodel the Source Source and surrounding facilities to solve the “aging and deterioration problem”, and the works should be completed at the beginning of the fourth quarter of this year. In a statement, AMI stresses that the goal is to provide a “beautiful and clean” leisure space to residents and visitors.
The works will be divided into three phases, and by areas, and include the reconstruction of the waterproof waterproofs, repairing the cracks at the central source and the source wall around Travessa do Meio, replacement of pumps, water pipes and deteriorated tiles and murals, as well as the coating of flower beds and stone benches.
The vintage stone source with European elements, the flower flowers with Portuguese -style tiles and the mural make the Largo da Sé and Travessa do Meio in a “popular place” for residents and tourists, according to AMI. Having been built in 2004, and although they were subjected to various interventions, the facilities are “aged and damaged”.
Part of source supply pipes are obstructed due to rust, which prevents water sprinkling, and the source wall itself shows leaks to varying degrees, which makes it difficult to partial repair. According to the body, the “ineffective waterproofing” of the lining of the beds and stone benches at the wide of the See is due to the aging of them, which originates dirt, visible spots on the walls of the wall, discoloration and detachment of wall painting, among other problems.
Given that the site of the work belongs to the World Heritage Protection Zone and is an area with a large flow of people, adjacent to schools and the Cathedral, the AMI consulted soil services and urban construction, the Cultural Institute, the Diocese of Macao and community neighborhood associations to present repair work and arrange opinions.
The Institute guarantees that during the period of work, "the contractor will be strictly supervised" with regard to sealing and cleaning measures, in order to "minimize the impact caused to residents and users."</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>56 agreements at the Tourism Expo</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/assinados-56-acordos-na-expo-de-turismo/</link><description>The 13th International Tourism Expo, where 56 cooperation agreements were signed. Helena de Senna Fernandes was pleased with the role of the initiative and stressed that this year the number of international stands “increased significantly 50%” compared to last year

The 13th International Tourism Expo (Industry) of Macau (Mite), which took place for three days, ended with the signature of 56 agreements of various projects, indicated the Tourism Services (STD). Under the slogan “Explore Mite, try the world” and six highlights, the event attracted the participation of 755 tourism -related companies and official entities from 70 countries and regions.
Organized by STD, Mite has recorded a new record of both the number of participating countries and regions, as well as exhibitors and stands, among which the international stands stand out. For the organism this is a sign that the initiative plays “effectively the role of international platform”: favors the exploitation of business opportunities, promotes the exchange and regional and international tourist cooperation, and contributes to the construction of Macao as a “high -level opening platform abroad”.
STD director Helena de Senna Fernandes said, in her speech she gave, that as an international professional tourism fair, “Tourism Expo has been reinforcing her role as a bridge of connection between Macao tour operators from the interior of China and international, becoming increasingly grand”. In this edition, the number of international stands increased significantly 50% compared to last year, it continued, "highlighting the unique advantages of Macao and its international connection role."
Noting that the Expo is already in the 13th edition, Senna Fernandes said it has accumulated “solid experience, based on which continues to promote qualitative innovation, to deepen the intersectory integration of 'Tourism +', and to increase the effectiveness of the exhibition to correspond to the high support and recognition of national and foreign participants”. "It is expected that tour operators from around the world will continue to participate in the event, expanding the 'circle of friends' international and working together to promote the development of world tourism with benefits and mutual gains," he added.
Already the Deputy Director of the Exchange and International Cooperation of the Ministry of Culture and Tourism (Office for Hong Kong, Macao and Taiwan), Kong Lun, said that this year the Departments of Culture and Tourism, Tourism Companies and Museum Entities of 20 Provinces in the interior of China gathered in an exhibition zone, showing the cultural and tourist resources of the tourism. Continent.
 
Five continents represented and more products “one track, a route”
Expo has also attracted travel agencies, organizations and companies related to the tourist industry and more than 20 official tourism entities from 70 countries and regions of Asia, Europe, America, Africa and Oceania. The official tourism entities included the Asia Tourism Exchange Center, the first time of South Korea, Qatar, Abu Dhabi, Hamburg, Sweden, Burundi, Kenya, Tajikistan, Turkey and Kazakhstan.
There were also tourism agencies, such as those from Japan, Thailand, Malaysia, Philippines, Indonesia, Laos, Portugal, Spain, Poland, Jordan, Tunisia and Norway. Among these, 51 are tourism entities from countries or regions throughout the “one track, one route” initiative and nine are from Lusophone countries. According to STD, there were also 98 exhibitors from eight cities in the Great Bay (excluding Hong Kong, Macao and Hengqin).
The “one track, a route” product pavilion expanded to an area by close to 700 square meters and approximately 80% were new exhibitors who first participated, “with a variety of 37% higher than last year” products. In addition, also for the first time, the initiative “a track, a route” was included in the broadcast broadcasts to promote products, “and influencers with millions of fans from countries along the track and the route transmitted, in conjunction with presenters from Macao, Bilingual Advertising and Selling of Goods”.
Also noteworthy is the “Coffee Station”, where the idea was to sell coffee beans from Portuguese -speaking countries and typical brands; In addition, roasting and coffee preparation workshops were performed, among others. Already the "gourmet market" focused on "stores with its own characteristics", certified by economics and technological development services, bringing together 26 local restoration companies. Finally, “A cellar” offered “fun moments” under the theme “Culture of East Asia Culture” brought by the three countries (China, Japan and Korea).
 
Mand can receive 700,000 visitors in the golden week
The director of tourism services predicted at least 4.1% on the number of visitors during the holidays of Labor Day. Helena de Senna Fernandes said she expects a daily average of between 127,000 and 140,000 tourists during the golden week, between May 1 and 5. To Portuguese -speaking journalists, the leader added that Macau could receive between 630,000 and 700,000 visitors during these five days, one of the high seasons for tourism in the territory. The most conservative forecast would mean an increase of 4.1% compared to the same golden week of 2024, while the most optimistic forecast would be a 15.7% increase.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Submitted medical team to help Myanmar</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/enviada-equipa-medica-para-ajudar-myanmar/</link><description>Macau sent a medical team on Thursday to help Myanmar, namely in preventing contagious disease outbreaks after the March 28 earthquake, which caused thousands of dead.
 
In a statement, Macao health services (SSM) said that this international emergency medical team, made up of five elements, should work in Myanmar for at least 14 days in some of the areas most affected by the earthquake. "During this period, a narrow work mechanism will be established with Myanmar health authorities, providing support in the analysis of the medical needs of affected areas and providing technical suggestions on the treatment of trauma and the prevention and control of communicable diseases," SSM said.
The body believes that the team will “fully take advantage of its professional advantages to demonstrate Macau's professional capacity in emergency medical work”, gaining “more international experience” at the same time.
Formed at the request of the World Health Organization (WHO), and with the agreement of the Office for Hong Kong and Macau Affairs of the State Council and the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of China, under the guidance of the National Health Commission, the team includes the head of the SSM International Cooperation Affairs, the Leong, who performs the functions of coordinator of the medical team; Mio Chi Fong, assistant doctor of the Emergency Center of the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, as head of the medical team; Ieong PUI I, assistant doctor of the same emergency service, as head of the clinical group; Chan Soi Fan, the main technique of the main advisor to the Division of Prevention and Control of Communicable Diseases of the SSM Disease Prevention and Control Center, responsible for the prevention and control of transmitted diseases; and the deputy chief of the Special Rescue Team of the Fire Department, Lam Wai Lap, responsible for the work of guaranteeing logistics materials.
The SSM recalled that the first time Macau sent a team abroad was in May 2020, when five local doctors were supporting Algeria and Sudan in combating Covid-19 pandemic.
The earthquake of magnitude 7.7 on the Richter scale that hit Myanmar on March 28 caused more than 3,700 dead in the country, as well as 22 in neighboring Thailand, leading the military junta in power to declare a temporary ceasefire. Although both pro-democracy opposition and ethnic guerrillas adhered to the truce, to facilitate the arrival of humanitarian aid, the United Nations accounted for more than 120 attacks perpetrated by the Army after the earthquake.
Since the 2021 military coup, Myanmar has been immersed in a deep political and humanitarian crisis, with an armed conflict that has moved more than 2.6 million people, according to the UN.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Audit Commissioner presents work plan in Beijing</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/comissaria-da-auditoria-apresenta-plano-de-trabalhos-em-pequim/</link><description>The Audit Commissioner (CA) sent a delegation to Beijing to present the audit work to be implemented, argued opinions and perform technical exchanges. The group led by Elsie to Ieong U, a commissioner of the audit, visited the Hong Kong and Macao work office of the China Communist Party Central Committee, the Hong Kong and Macao affairs cabinet with the State Council and the National Audit Office (Gan).
During the meeting with Xia Baolong, director of the Office for Hong Kong and Macau affairs, Elsie to Ieong U spoke about the issuance of “observation reports” to public services, the implementation of the “permanent monitoring and correction mechanism” and a series of initiatives to reinforce the role of government accounts “according to the general guidance of the executive's head of the chief executive”.
According to CA, at the same meeting, the commissioner highlighted the intention of “promoting governance from origin” and “helping public entities identify potential risks”, installing them to take preventive measures to promote “good governance”. Elsie to Ieong U also expressed the intention to lead CA to “assume a proactive and responsible attitude” and to take “seriously the work of reforms and innovations”.
The next day, the CA delegation met with Hou Kai, Gan's general auditor, to exchange impressions on the promotion of internal audit, the application of 'big data' and cooperation with the interior of China and the international community.
According to the CA statement, the Commissioner thanked Hou "for its long -term guidance for the Audit work of MSAR" and for the "continuous support" in the formation of auditors.
Gan's deputy auditor Wang Benqiang, as well as the chief of staff for Hong Kong, Macau and Taiwan of Gan, Jiang Haiying, and Yin Qiang, head of division, were also at the meeting.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections for direct suffrage will have 38 voting assemblies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/eleicoes-pelo-sufragio-directo-terao-38-assembleias-de-voto/</link><description>The elections for the Legislative Assembly, scheduled for September 14, will have 38 voting assemblies for direct suffrage and five for the indirect
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) has revealed the existence of 38 voting assemblies for direct suffrage and five for the indirect suffrage for the elections of 14 September. According to the president of Caeal, the indirect suffrage will be performed for the first time in two different places, with the aim of diverting the flow of voters and reducing the waiting time.
Seng Ioi Man indicated that last month, Caeal inspected the planned voting places and, after a “comprehensive evaluation of various factors”, namely voters distribution, the convenience of locations, the space environment and accessibility facilities, selected 37 voting places for this year's electoral act.
He also said that, after analyzing the waiting situation of voters at the voting places for the indirect suffrage in the last electoral act, Caeal decided to distribute the five voting assemblies in two locations. Three will be installed, as earlier, in the Multipurpose University Polydestive Pavilion of Macao, and the other two at Kao IP high school in Nape, which is the news for this year.
Quoted by the Social Communication Office, Seng Ioi Man pointed out that the two places will also provide voting assemblies for direct suffrage, “in order to facilitate voters, with quality of legal person, to exercise their right to vote for direct and indirect suffrages in the same space”.
The Caeal official mentioned, on the other hand, that there will also be a slight change in the voting places for direct suffrage. "Some of the places used in the previous elections will be replaced by more appropriate ones in the same area and more easily for voters," he said, revealing that the commission expected to announce all voting places in detail in the early July, through a notice.
Regarding the constitution of the application committee, Seng Ioi Man stressed that, for now, he has not received any request for recognition, warning the interested parties who must submit to Caeal the bulletin duly completed, until June 6, for recognition of legal existence.
In addition, Caeal appeals to voters who have changed residence, but have not yet changed the electoral census to perform the update by May 31, so that Caeal can assign them the closest voting assembly.
At the end of the meeting, Seng Ioi Man also said that the Public Prosecution Service received a complaint filed by officials from various local associations with the Judicial Police, claiming that an individual had published on social networks content that impaired the honor of the associations. On this, he added that, according to the information, the defendant is suspected of the crime of advertising and slander provided for in the Penal Code, “which is why he has been applied to his coercion”, indicating that the conduct “may also constitute the crime of coercion and fraudulent devices on the application committee provided for in the AL”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Inflation continues to slow down</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/inflacao-continua-abrandar/</link><description>The inflation rate in the MSAR was estimated at 0.48% in March, which represents a new slowdown, according to official data
 
Considering the average consumer price rate variation (IPC) in the annual cycle ended in the reference month, compared to the immediately preceding 12 months, the rate of inflation in MSAR set up at 0.48%in March, marking new deceleration compared to February (0.57%) and January (0.7%), as well as the general calculation of 2024 (0.74%). According to the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), the March IPC rose 0.46% in category A, which encompasses about 50% of family aggregates with average monthly expenses between 11 thousand and 35,999 Patacas, and 0.49% in level B, which includes 30% of families with average spending between 36 thousand and 71,999 Patacas.
In the same comparative interval, the increases in the indexes of “education” (+2.52%), “various products and services” (+2.52%) and “health” (+1.98%), and the decrease in “transport” (-3.15%).
Regarding March 2024, the General IPC advanced only 0.04%, driven by the 1.99% rise in the “Miscellaneous Products and Services” section, which encompasses personal care, insurance, jewelery, goldsmiths and watches. Less expressive were the annual increases in “food products and non -alcoholic beverages” (+0.48%) and “housing and fuels” (+0.32%). The prices of “Information and Communication”, “Transport” and “Clothing and Footwear” suffered homologous breaks of 2.92%, 2.77%and 2.62%, respectively.
The GENERAL IPC of March also lowered 0.08%compared to February, including breaks in the sections of “clothing and footwear” (-1.4%), “transport” (-0.46%), “food products and non-alcoholic beverages” (-0.08%). In the opposite direction, monthly additions were recorded in the categories of “alcoholic and tobacco beverages” (+0.46%), “health” (+0.07%) and “housing and fuels” (+0.05%).
In the first quarter of 2025, the average General IPC grew 0.15%, in annual terms, with the DSEC stressing that the price index of “food products and non -alcoholic beverages” increased by 0.68%.
The General IPC covers all household aggregates, and expenses with higher weights in the calculation of inflation are those of housing and fuels, food products and non -alcoholic beverages and transportation, with considerations of 34.47, 29.47 and 8.33, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>FAM opened with “PI life”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/fam-abriu-a-vida-de-pi/</link><description>The 35th Macao Arts Festival (FAM), this year under the theme “Growth”, started on Friday and features a varied program until May 31, including major international productions, exhibitions and workshops. The opening of the 2025 edition took place at the Cultural Center (CCM), with the great theatrical production “The Life of PI”, a piece adapted from the book by Yann Martel, and passed to the cinema by the famous Chinese director Ang Lee, who snatched Oscar for best director.
Among the main events that follow, the FAM features between May 8 and 11, the play “Food”, a show conceived and interpreted with soil by Geoff Sobelle. “Invited to an intimate dinner, the audience sits on a giant table while you are asked to foster a meditation on our diet,” says the introduction of the event, which will take place in CCM studio II. The table ticket costs 400 Patacas and the entry to the 300 Patacas audience.
The Cantonense Opera Concert “Discorting Harmonious Voices”, presented by the Macao Chinese Orchestra and the Guangdong Cantonense Opera Institute, is scheduled for May 9 at Broadway Macau. The show proposes a program of excerpts from operatic classics such as “sweet girl” and “The Legend of White Snake”, played by Zeng Xiaomin and Wen Ruqing.
The next day, the Cantonense Opera Troupe of Foshan, with “The Felic Felic”, will be in the Great Auditorium of CCM. It is an adaptation of a classic play, centered on the life of the talented playwright Kong Yu-Kau.
On May 17, FAM features “Bate Fado” at the small CCM auditorium, choreographic staging of the responsibility of Jonas &amp; Lander and composed of four dancers, a singer and four musicians. The "Show" of "Fado Beat" is a danced and forgotten version of a musical genre traditionally associated with the environment of Tabernas and Bairro cafes. The cast, which includes the creators themselves, interprets a mix of guitar, voice and fado singer with "showy and sensual tapped measures." Tickets cost 200 and 300 patacas.
Later, on May 24, there is the “shaman beat”, also in the small auditorium, consisting of South Korea's old rituals with a contemporary touch.
The FAM also has events with local artists, highlighting “Nungém Sleep”, on May 9th and 10th, “in Party-Vibration Z”, 23 and 24, and the theater in Patuá, “Cuza is Renenial? Ticket prices for the Dóci Papiaçá play di Macau range from 120 to 300 patacas.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Geopolitical Situation” threatens Airport Goals to 2025</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/situacao-geopolitica-ameaca-metas-aeroporto-para-2025/</link><description>The Macao International Airport Society (CAM) has admitted that it could fail the passenger and load goals set to 2025, due to the “geopolitical situation and world economic instability”.
The airport management company revealed that about 1.83 million passengers went through the infrastructure in the first three months of the year, more than in the same period of 2024. In a statement, stressed that the airport sued about 14,000 flights of passengers, more 1.6% than between January and March last year, however, the volume of load that underwent 9.5% fell annual.
CAM admitted that the airport had "not as good as expected," at a time when "the geopolitical situation and world economic instability have imposed challenges to the development of routes."
"Increased operating costs for airlines has further restricted its capacity, leading to noticeable changes in market structure and having a significant impact on passenger and load operations. It is expected that passenger and load volume in 2025 is not aligned with the goal of the year," said the company.
In February, CAM executive committee chairman Simon Chan predicted to 2025 a movement over eight million passengers -which would be an 8% increase -65,000 flight movements and a load volume of 113,000 tons. On April 3, Ethiopian Airlines launched the first long -haul load route from Macao, bound for the Spanish capital, Madrid, with two round trip a week.
According to the CAM statement, the low -cost company Airasia will start 'charter' flights to Tawau, Malaysia, early May. In the same month, Macau is expected to have a new route to Jeju, in southern South Korea, operated by Jeju Air, Low Cost that also plans to start flying from Cheongju in the center of the country. In addition, in July, flights between Macau and Taiyuan, in mainland China, can be resumed.
Macao airport currently has regular passenger flights operated by 27 companies for 41 destinations in mainland China, Taiwan, Southeast Asia, Japan and South Korea, according to the Cam portal. In January, the company promised, together with the government, “explore more international markets with foreign and local airlines” to promote the development of routes in 2025.
In the first quarter, passengers in the mainstantial China accounted for 46% of the total, while the Routes with Taiwan equivalent to 18%. Already the passengers of the airlines of Southeast Asia and Northeast Asian corresponded to 36% of the total.
According to CAM, in the first two months, the volume of international passengers grew 13% to about 200 thousand, in annual terms.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Portuguese agencies expect more flights with China</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/agencias-portuguesas-esperam-haja-mais-voos-china/</link><description>The president of the Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies (APAVT) told Lusa to expect the new government to promote more direct flights with China. "We will see if, when we recover political stability in Portugal, there will be space and time to begin to develop more aerial connections [with China]," said Pedro Costa Ferreira.
Portugal goes to early legislative elections on May 18, following the political crisis that led to the resignation of the PSD/CDS-PP government, led by Prime Minister Luís Montenegro.
Pedro Costa Ferreira said he had no doubt that direct flights between Portugal and China "will always be a success" and that the current problem "will never be economic." "It is the question of finding a space at the airport and the [operators] interested in flying. (…) It will eventually be [a problem] logistics and we hope it can be solved," he added.
There is currently only one direct connection between China and Portugal, with a frequency of four flights per week from Lisbon, bound for Hangzhou, the capital of Zhejiang Province, one of the most prosperous in China. "We are very far from what we want and far from what are, of course, the ambitions on both sides," said the president of APAVT.
Also the leader of the European Block of Tour and Tour Operators, Eric Drésin, told Lusa that the lack of flights to China is the main challenge to attract more visitors in Europe. “The main problem (…) is connectivity. Flying is expensive,” lamented the secretary general of the European Confederation of travel agency associations and tour operators (ECTAA).
"European airlines cannot reach China flying over Russia because of the war in Ukraine, so they reduced the number of flights to mainland China," Drissin recalled.
The European Union closed airspace to Russian aircraft after the invasion of Ukraine, and Moscow retaliated with similar prohibitions, making the links between Asia and Europe more expensive.
“Thus, we depend a lot on non -European airlines to bring travelers” to the Asian continent, Drésin explained, including companies from Singapore, Japan and South Korea.
In the case of China, "it is not very common for European travelers to travel with Chinese airlines. They need to better establish their mark in Europe," said the Frenchman. Chinese airlines are still resuming the routes that connected China to the rest of the world before the Covid-19 pandemic after the Asian country limited international air traffic to less than 2% in 2019.
Drésin, who was speaking during the first day of the 13th International Tourism Expo (Industry) of Macao, also said that the number of Europeans to visit the US should continue to fall, especially due to Donald Trump.
 
Consul de Portugal criticizes the lack of direct routes with Portugal
The Portuguese Consul General in Macao lamented that the only direct airline connection between Macao and Europe is not to Lisbon or Porto, but to Madrid. “Days I wrote for days [a letter] to Lisbon, very angry, when Ethiopia Airlines inaugurated its triangular load flight Adis Ababa-Madrid-Macau and with that created the first direct connection of Macao to Europe,” Alexandre Leitão said at the International Tourism Expo, cited by the News Daily. According to said, it has been insisting with the Portuguese authorities that this connection could be made by a Portuguese company, with a national airport as a European platform. "I have been insisting on this two years ago, so they do not convince me that it is not viable," he said, noting that in Macau they live 153 thousand Portuguese, inserted in a region that within 200 kilometers has two urban poles such as Shenzen and Canton, and Hong Kong. The flights of Ethiopia Airlines, he explained, will bring 20,000 tons per year of load "through a purely commercial flight." “Explain me there why Lisbon is not an Atlantic and also European plate, besides being Lusophone for markets like Brazil, which are served like no other? Or why African, Lusophone capitals, are not also instruments, platforms for distributing goods and services to other countries in Africa who want to come here?” He criticized.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Success of “one country, two systems” highlighted at a UNESCAP meeting</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sucesso-de-um-pais-dois-sistemas-realcado-em-reuniao-da-unescap/</link><description>The Director of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), Yau Yun Wah, represented Macao at the 81st Meeting of the United Nations Economic and Social Commission for Asia and the Pacific (UNESCAP), which ended Friday in Bangkok. Participants entered discussions under the theme “Regional Cooperation to boost the sustainable development of resilient cities in Asia and Pacific”. According to DSEDT, Yau Yun Wah gave a presentation on the successful implementation of the “one country, two systems” principle in the MSAR. According to the statement, the director of DSEDT also spoke about the opportunities brought by the agreement to narrow economic and commercial relations between the interior of China and Macau (strain), highlighting the participation of the masters “in the construction of the large bay and the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin” and the role of platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries. On the other hand, he stressed the government's support of the digital transformation and the technological innovation of small and medium enterprises. During the UNESCAP meeting, the situation of execution of the “2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development” for the Asia Pacific region and “progress in the implementation of relevant subjects from subordinate institutions” to the Commission, according to DSEDT, was appreciated. Over the years, Macau has participated in the annual meetings of UNESCAP and proactively supported the committee's work.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Shenzhou-20 Mission has already started experiences at the space station</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/missao-shenzhou-20-ja-iniciou-experiencias-na-estacao-espacial/</link><description>Samples of biological experiences and life sciences transported by the Shenzhou-20 ship were successfully transferred to China's space station, the Xinhua agency reported, citing the Center for Technology and Engineering for Space Use (CSU) of the Chinese Academy of Sciences.
Astronauts completed the orbit installation of samples and started scientific experiments, having already obtained experimental data along with image and video records. All samples, including planaries, unlucky fish and streptomycetes, are in good condition, the CSU said.
The study of the effects of microgravity and spatial radiation on the regeneration of planaries continued as planned, with the specimens observed in a “relaxed state”.
Radent fish and keratophyllum (an aquatic plant) housed in an aquarium to study the regulatory mechanisms of protein homeostasis in bone loss induced by weight lack and myocardial remodeling are in good condition. According to the CSU, aquarium lighting tests were performed and the images and videos of the experience were transmitted back to Earth. The main parameters, including dissolved oxygen levels, water temperature and the internal pressure of the module, remain within the normal ranges, according to the center.
Research that explores the mechanism of effect of microgravity on microorganisms has completed the calibration of microscopic focus and generating images of samples of streptomycetes, which are also in good condition.
Leading the latest crew is the 46-year-old former veteran space driver Chen Dong who in 2022 became the first Chinese astronaut to record more than 200 cumulative days in orbit. The other two crew members-former 40-year-old Chen Zhongrui Air Force pilot and former 35-year-old space-technology-mannery-perform their first space flight.
During its permanence in orbit, the shenzhou-20 crew will also conduct research in various disciplines, including space sciences in space, physics of microgravity and new space technologies. Planned experiments include the cultivation of vascularized cerebral organoid chips, studies on the dynamics of non -balance of soft matter, and research on high temperature superconductors.
China successfully launched the Shenzhou-20 manned ship on Thursday, sending three astronauts to its orbit space station to a six-month mission. Shenzhou-20 successfully attracted the combination of the space station on Thursday night, according to China's manned space agency (CMSA). The whole process took about six and a half hours.
The three astronauts of the new Chinese mission entered the Tiangong space station and met with the other trio of astronauts at dawn on Friday, starting a new round of the crew transfer in orbit. The six astronauts will work together for about five days to complete the planned tasks and delivery work, said CMSA.
The Shenzhou-19 crew is expected to return to the grounding site in Dongfeng, in the autonomous region of Mongolia Interior, northern China.
 
Jtm with xinhua</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>