<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>TNR hiring with a rise in requests and approval rates</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/contratacao-de-tnr-em-alta-nos-pedidos-na-taxa-de-aprovacao/</link><description>Tired young woman standing at living room with cleaning products and equipment, Housework concept



Requests for hiring non-resident workers (TNR) increased by 8.3% in the first 10 months of this year, after having decreased by almost 13% in annual terms in 2024, according to data from the Labor Affairs Services on completed processes. The number of authorized individuals rose by 7.5%, with the approval rate also increasing to 84.3% overall. As for non-specialized TNR, the authorization rate was 43%, compared to 50% in the same period last year. Andy Wu, director of the General Federal Commercial Association of Small and Medium-sized Enterprises, highlighted that “SMEs depend heavily on TNR in terms of human resources”. Therefore, he urges the Government to carry out “separate assessments” regarding SMEs and large companies, “and should lean a little more towards SMEs because their competitiveness is already relatively weak”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Over the first 10 months of this year, the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) concluded the assessment of 24,508 requests related to the hiring of non-resident workers (TNR), reflecting an increase of 1,880 or 8.3% compared to the same period last year. Although data for the last two months of the year are not yet available, the number contrasts with the 12.7% decrease seen between 2023 and 2024.
Including cases of import, renewal and transfer, the processes completed between January and October included 15,661 requests relating to unskilled workers, 2,794 for specialized workers and 6,053 in the context of domestic work.
The requests involved 153,868 TNR, 7,507 or 5.1% more than in the same period last year, after having registered a drop of 13.4% to 194,588 in 2024. According to data consulted by the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper, DSAL ended up “failing” 24,159 workers (-5.8%) and giving the “green light” to 129,709, a number that translated into a year-on-year increase of 7.5% or 9,018 and led to an increase of 1.8 percentage points to 84.3% in the general approval rate.
At the end of October, and including the TNR who were already employed, Macau had 184,307 people in the imported workforce, a number that is the highest since June 2020, but illustrates an increase of just 1% or 1,765 compared to the 182,542 counted at the end of 2024. However, this segment of the labor force remains below the 196,538 counted at the end of 2024. 2019, the pre-pandemic year.
Looking at the different categories, the data shows that DSAL approved 119,120 of the 142,861 unskilled workers included in the completed applications, which corresponds to an increase of 7% and an approval rate of 83.4% (+2 points). More specifically, the import of 15,092 unskilled workers (-33%) was authorized, that is, only 42.6% of the total TNR requested (35,448). Between January and October last year, the approval rate in the field of imports had been around 50%. As for renewals, this year 107,413 individuals were requested, of which 104,028 were authorized (+17%).
Andy Wu, director of the General Federal Commercial Association of Small and Medium Enterprises of Macau, told this newspaper that SME workers are mainly from the catering and retail sectors “performing professions that few residents want to undertake”, stressing that these companies “rely heavily on TNR to add manpower”.
Noting that the TNR import approval rate was “relatively low”, Wu stressed that “this constitutes a difficulty for SMEs”. “I believe that the TNR policy is intended to address the lack of local human resources, but I think that the Government should carry out separate assessments regarding large companies and SMEs, and should lean a little more towards SMEs because their competitiveness is already relatively weak”, he added.
"For example, in the profession of waiter, if a resident wants to do this job, he will choose to work for a gaming operator instead of working for a small or medium-sized company. Therefore, in these circumstances, SMEs depend heavily on TNR in terms of human resources. In this regard, the Government should launch some policies favorable to SMEs, that is, relax the requirements in the consideration and approval of applications for hiring", argued Andy Wu.
Although he emphasizes that “this phenomenon has not yet caused a threat to the survival of small and medium-sized companies”, the association leader warns that “as SMEs face a lack of human resources, they may not have room for development”. "Furthermore, because of the human resources problem, the quality of services provided by SMEs may not be very good. In the long run, this could have a negative impact on their development," he noted.
 
Hotels, restaurants and similar top the list of authorizations
On the other hand, and according to official data, the approval percentage of specialized workers dropped 1.1 points to 94.2%, with the organization authorizing 4,592 (+25%) of the 4,874 requested. In this field, DSAL approved the import of 1,598 specialized TNR (+8.7%), the renewal of 2,966 (+36%) and the transfer of 28 (+133%).
In the context of domestic work, and as has been usual, the approval rate was even higher, at 97.8%, although it fell 0.2 points compared to the same period in 2024. In evaluating the requests covering 6,133 domestic workers, DSAL authorized 5,997 (+3.5%), including the import of 5,079 (+1.03%) and the renewal of 918 (+19.5%).
Until October, the list of TNR authorized in the three areas (specialized, non-specialized and domestic work) was led by the hotel, restaurant and similar sector, with 39,603, corresponding to an approval rate of 85.4%, followed by construction, a sector where 29,136 workers were approved (82% of those requested). Among the main economic sectors, real estate activities and services provided to companies (19,388 authorized) and wholesale and retail trade (13,493) stand out, with approval percentages of 81.7% and 76.9%, respectively.
The area of ​​public administration and social security was again the only one where TNR approval reached 100%, involving 83 workers.
In October, imported labor grew by 0.5% and 0.7% in monthly and annual terms, respectively, maintaining a decelerating trend. According to the data, TNRs from Mainland China (121,091) remained the main non-resident labor force, followed by those from the Philippines (31,917), Indonesia (8,184), Vietnam (7,918), Myanmar (4,785), Nepal (3,896), Hong Kong (2,113) and Thailand (890).
The hotel, restaurant and similar sector dominated the labor import panorama, with 54,272 non-resident workers, or 29.4% of the total.</description><pubDate>2025-12-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Christmas brought more than a million visitors</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/natal-trouxe-mais-de-um-milhao-de-visitantes/</link><description>During the Christmas period, Macau welcomed more than 1.1 million visitors. On the other hand, according to the CPSP, as of 11:00 am on December 27th, the annual number of visitors to the Macao SAR reached 39.411 million, already surpassing the record set in 2019
 
Between December 20th and 27th, Macau received more than one million visitors, according to data from the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP). On the other hand, until 5pm yesterday, 113,451 visitors were recorded.
Specifically, on Christmas Day and the day before, 129,974 and 115,194 visitors entered the territory, respectively. Furthermore, on Macao SAR Day, December 20th, the city welcomed 149,484 visitors. Later, on the day of the Winter Solstice, December 22, the number of visitors reached 110,181. On the 21st, 23rd and 27th, Macau registered 109,878, 110,089 and 156,918 visitors, respectively.
According to official data, considering the period between December 20th and 26th, the daily average of visitors rose 16.7% to 850,003 in annual terms.
Jennifer Si Tou, deputy director of Tourism Services, said that, according to information from the sector, the average occupancy rate of hotel establishments exceeded 90% this festive season.
On the other hand, on December 24th, the highest temperature recorded in Macau reached 25.8°C, marking the second hottest Christmas Eve since records were recorded in 1952, revealed the Meteorological and Geophysical Services.
During the Christmas period, the six revitalized historic areas hosted various activities, including Christmas decorations on Rua da Felicidade. According to the Chinese-language press, managers of some souvenir shops on that street pointed to a 20% increase in turnover, compared to the same time last year.
At the same time, many restaurants in the city launched special Christmas menus and dishes. Some catering establishments in Taipa had 90% of tables booked on Christmas Eve and all occupied on the 25th. On the other hand, some restaurants in the North Zone recorded a year-on-year drop of more than 10% in the rate of booked tables, which was between 70% and 80% this Christmas.
On the other hand, Christmas “significantly” boosted the business of several stores that sell luxury items, workers at these establishments assured. According to estimates, sales rose between 20% and 30% compared to November.
Conversely, some goldsmiths predicted a 10% to 20% year-on-year drop in turnover during the Christmas period, associating the phenomenon with the rise in the price of gold and an “unsatisfactory” market environment.
 
Annual number of visitors has already surpassed the 2019 record
Furthermore, the CPSP announced that, as of 11:00 a.m. on December 27, the cumulative number of visitors to the Macao SAR in 2025 reached 39.411 million, surpassing the record of 39.406 million recorded in the entire year 2019. As of that date, 72.4% of visitors came from Mainland China, while 18.3%, 2.5% and 6.8% arrived from Hong Kong, Taiwan and other origins respectively.
Anticipating the arrival of “many visitors” to the Macao SAR on New Year's Eve, the CPSP assured that it had prepared several plans to ensure security and good order at border crossings and countdown activities.
Furthermore, the corporation announced that, as of 1pm yesterday, the annual volume of crossings through the Hengqin Border Post exceeded, for the first time, 30 million (average daily number of 83 thousand), reflecting an annual increase of 32.6%. Macau residents accounted for 26.9% of entries and exits across this border, while 38.9%, 17.9% and 15.7% involved visitors, non-local university students and non-resident workers, respectively.
 
DST wants to open office in Kuala Lumpur in the first half of 2026
The Directorate of Tourism Services (DST) plans to open economic and commercial offices in Southeast Asia and Northeast Asia. According to Jennifer Si Tou, deputy director of DST, the office in Southeast Asia will be located in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, and could begin operating in the first half of 2026. As for Northeast Asia, she said that the location must take into account the main sources of tourists, the situation in that region and the global situation. Under these circumstances, DST will first complete preparations for the Southeast Asia office.</description><pubDate>2025-12-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Bishop remembers “hurt world” and places confidence in young people</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/bispo-lembra-mundo-ferido-deposita-confianca-nos-jovens/</link><description>In his usual message on the occasion of the Christmas celebration, the Bishop of Macau lamented the wars and natural disasters that have “deeply” hurt the world. On the other hand, D. Stephen Lee said he believes that young people will play an important role in realizing a better future and highlighted the important role played by the Diocese of Macau
VÍTOR REBELO

On Christmas Day, the Bishop of Macau released his usual Christmas message, focusing his speech on the current situation in the world, where wars and natural disasters prevail over peace and social stability.
“We are aware that our world remains deeply wounded”, said D. Stephen Lee, recalling that, “in recent years, armed conflicts in the Middle East and the prolonged war between Russia and Ukraine have continued unabated”.
Furthermore, he referred to natural disasters and “tragic incidents that have hit many regions”, giving the example of the heavy flooding in the Beijing-Tianjin-Hebei area, the devastating fire in Hong Kong and the recent shooting on Bondi beach in Sydney.
For the Macao SAR Bishop, “such events have brought loss and uncertainty to countless families”, adding that “at times like these, people understandably feel tired, vulnerable and even discouraged”. It is in this reality that Christmas “reveals its deepest meaning”, he said.
In the communication to local Catholics, published on the Diocese's website, the priest mentioned the Pope's General Audience, held recently, to recall the words of Leo Instead, recalling the words of the Supreme Pontiff, “He walks with us – along a road that is often difficult, painful and mysterious”.
The work carried out by the Diocese of Macau, which will celebrate its 450th anniversary in January, was also mentioned in D. Stephen Lee's message. “As we look back at the Jubilee Year that is now approaching its end, our Diocese continued to follow its established pastoral direction, striving at all levels to live this hope”, he highlighted, considering that “hope cannot remain a slogan; it must be practiced with patience and fidelity in daily life”.
For this reason, he noted, “we continue our efforts in the four main areas of pastoral focus: education, social services, family and youth, seeking to respond to the needs of our time and allow the light of the Gospel to illuminate concrete people and situations.”
In the areas of education and social services, the Diocese remained “committed” to defending the value of life and “the dignity of each person”. By promoting a values-based education, “rooted in Christ,” who is ‘the Way, the Truth and the Life,’ we hope to help young people find direction amid the confusion of conflicting values.”
At the same time, he highlighted in his Christmas speech, “we place particular emphasis on caring for the elderly and those who are poor, sick or vulnerable, striving, through monitoring and concrete support, to ensure that they feel respected, valued and never forgotten”.
The family was another theme of the Bishop of Macau's speech, which he joined the ecclesial communities and the youth ministry. “We continue to support families in their growth in faith and love and accompany young people as they discern their path and build hope in an uncertain time”, he said, stressing that the family “is the first school of faith”, while young people “carry the promise of the future”.
Furthermore, he expressed that, as the 450th anniversary of the Diocese approaches, “this moment is not just a look at history, but a joyful and grateful testimony that attests to God's perennial care and guidance” throughout the generations.
“Heirs of this grace, we are called to transmit faith, hope and charity from one generation to the next, so that the joy of the Gospel can continue to travel from Macau to the world”, he declared, emphasizing the importance of approaching the nativity scenes and contemplating “the Savior who became flesh for our sake”.
At the conclusion of his message to the Catholic community in the territory, D. Stephen Lee also said he had faith that “the peace of Christ rests upon those who suffer and strengthens tired hearts”.
 
Nativity scene competition mobilized 15 schools
Fifteen schools participated in the “Admirabile Signum Macau Interschool Nativity Scene Competition”, organized by the Macau Catholic Cultural Association (ACCM), with the sponsorship of the Cultural Development Fund, to promote the Christmas tradition. The “Jury Prize” was awarded to Escola de Santa Madalena, while Colégio Canossiano do Sagrado Coração and Escola da Sagrada Família occupied second and third positions. The Concordia School for Special Education and the Colégio Diocesano de São José 5 and the Colégio Diocesano de São José received honorable mentions. The jury also awarded the prizes for “Creative Theme” (Escola Dom Luís Versiglia), “Best Environmental Project” (Instituto Salesiano), “Best Group Collaboration” (Escola de Santa Teresa do Menino Jesus) and “Popularity on the Internet” (Colégio de Santa Rosa de Lima – Chinese Section). According to ACCM, at the awards ceremony, the Bishop of Macau, Stephen Lee, highlighted that Christmas should not only focus on external decorations, but rather on inviting the faithful to reflect on the true meaning of the birth of Jesus Christ. In this sense, he expressed the hope that the activity of “Admirable Signum” will continue to spread the Good News, just as the missionaries brought the Gospel to Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-12-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Schools will have more psychological counseling agents</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/escolas-vao-ter-mais-agentes-de-aconselhamento-psicologico/</link><description>In response to an inquiry from Loi I Weng, DSEDJ revealed that it will increase the number of psychological counseling agents for students to more than 410. The organization also intends to implement in Macau an instrument for assessing the mental health of primary and secondary school students
 
The Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) assured that it has been optimizing psychological counseling services for students. According to him, in the current academic year 2025/2026, the number of agents on the student counseling teams will increase to more than 410, with a special reinforcement of the counseling agents for extensive services external to students, to provide them with “more comprehensive counseling”.
In response to a written question from Congresswoman Loi I Weng, DSEDJ also pointed out that, this academic year, the “Open Student Counseling Line and Online Consultation Platform” will be launched, available 24 hours a day, to offer students “immediate online counseling and emotional support”, also proceeding with “proactive online identification of cases that require intervention and positive guidance”. “DSEDJ will reinforce the coordination between these online and in-person counseling services, in order to jointly provide care to students, through a collaborative division of labor”, highlighted the organization led by Kong Chi Meng.
In the interpellation, Loi I Weng pointed out that, among the approximately 400 existing counseling agents, only 330 provide psychological counseling to the remaining 85,000 non-higher education students, except for the 2,900 integrated students who require at least 70 agents for monitoring. In this context, the deputy warned that “the pressure from frontline staff cannot be neglected”.
In the response, the DSEDJ also revealed negotiations with student counseling institutions on work related to the implementation in Macau of an instrument for assessing the mental health of primary and secondary school students, as well as the launch of thematic training activities aimed at teachers and student counseling agents, with the aim of “strengthening the capacity for early identification and intervention”.
On the other hand, in the sphere of community support, in addition to pointing out that Health Services (SSM) cooperate with non-profit institutions to increase the number of subsidized mental health counseling consultations, DSEDJ reported that, since June this year, around 6,600 people have used the self-assessment tool called “Emotional Self-Verification”, on the “Conta Única” platform.
“Whenever high-risk cases are identified, the SSM will carry out immediate telephone follow-ups, providing appropriate support and referral in a timely manner, according to the clinical needs of each case”, he added.</description><pubDate>2025-12-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Casino L’Arc transitions tomorrow to the direct management of SJM</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/casino-larc-transita-amanha-para-gestao-directa-da-sjm/</link><description>SJM Resorts concluded the deal to purchase the company that owns the L’Arc hotel, whose casino it will operate directly from tomorrow
 
The Macao SAR Government authorized SJM Resorts to operate the L’Arc Macau casino under the form of direct management and exploitation, starting at 02:00 tomorrow, December 30th. The decision, communicated by the gaming operator and the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ), was taken following the completion of the acquisition of the L’Arc hotel by SJM and taking into account that the three-year transitional period granted to satellite casinos expires at the end of this year.
Through two subsidiaries, SJM Holdings acquired Companhia de Desenvolvimento Arco do Triunfo, owner of the hotel, in exchange for 1.75 billion Hong Kong dollars, in order to maintain the only one of the 11 satellite casinos that will continue to operate in 2026. With the approval of the Macao SAR Government and the group's shareholders, SJM-Investment and SJM Resorts purchased 100% of the share capital of the target company to Goldarch Holdings and Solar King Investments.
"With the transaction now complete, SJM Resorts has taken over the integrated operations of the L'Arc hotel. This addition to the group's portfolio reinforces its position in a high-density catchment area, enhancing synergies between its Lisbon brand properties and allowing SJM Resorts to maintain geographically loyal customers, improve customer circulation and expand its market reach", highlighted the gaming operator in a statement.
SJM Resorts also reaffirmed its “commitment to contributing to the long-term development of Macau, strengthening the urban fabric of the Macau Peninsula, improving the quality and diversity of tourist offerings” and supporting the city to enrich its role as a “World Center for Tourism and Leisure”.
At the end of November, investment bank JP Morgan predicted that the purchase of L’Arc should have a positive impact on SJM’s operating results. “L’Arc offers 283 rooms – in addition to small shops, parking, etc. – so the price of 1.75 billion HKD is equivalent to 6.2 million HKD or 0.8 million dollars per room – an attractive valuation, especially considering its privileged location on the peninsula”, argued analysts DS Kim, Selina Li and Lindsey Qian, from JP Morgan, highlighting that it is a “good deal”.
Furthermore, they indicated that the hotel will not require major renovations because “the quality of the rooms and offerings are comparable to SJM's existing properties on the peninsula.”
According to JP Morgan, the 45 tables at L'Arc casino generated gross revenue of around HKD 1.4 billion in 2024 and HKD 1.3 billion in the first 10 months of 2025. With the purchase of the hotel, SJM's earnings before interest, taxes, amortization and depreciation (EBITDA) could rise by 8% or 9% between 2025 and 2026, forecasters predict. analysts.
The DICJ stated that it will “strictly inspect and assign employees to inspect on site” the operation of the L’Arc casino. The regulatory entity requires “compliance with procedures in accordance with the operating plan presented by SJM, with a view to ensuring the normal functioning of the venue”.
The organization also reiterates that “it will continue to strictly inspect and supervise concessionaires operating games of chance in accordance with the law and in accordance with its powers, in order to promote the healthy and orderly development of the gaming sector in Macau”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Experts foresee challenges for the local economy</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/especialistas-anteveem-desafios-para-economia-local/</link><description>Experts contacted by the Lusa agency foresee challenges in the growth of Macau's economy for 2026, with the recovery of the gaming sector contrasting with weak domestic consumption and pressure for diversification.
Economist Henry Chun Kwok Lei, professor of Business Economics at the University of Macau and vice-president of the Macau Economic Association, maintains a “cautiously optimistic” outlook for 2026, predicting Gross Domestic Product (GDP) growth of around 2.5% during the next financial year.
“The high base of gross gaming revenue this year, projected between 246 and 248 billion patacas, will constrain the growth potential in 2026. Even if casino revenue increases by around 4%, to more than 250 billion patacas, its contribution to global economic growth will decrease”, stated Henry Lei.
Ben Lee, a consultant for gaming activity in Southeast Asia, has a more positive outlook. “Gross gaming revenue has already reached 226.5 billion patacas by November this year, so it is more than likely that we will exceed the projection of 228 billion,” he said.
The estimate for game revenue in 2026, the analyst added, is “a little conservative”. “Unless we go back next year, based on the current situation, gross revenues could reach a value between 260 and 270 billion patacas by the end of 2026”, he estimated.
The forecast included in the Budget for 2025 pointed to total revenues in the order of 240 billion patacas, but the weak start of the year, especially after the tariff war triggered by the USA, raised alarms among the economic team of Sam Hou Fai's Executive, which approved in June an Amending Budget in which it cut 4.56 billion in the revenue forecast, highly dependent on the gaming sector (around 83% of the country's GDP). Macau).
The Macau Economic Association predicts that annual GDP growth in 2025 will be around 5.4%, an estimate based on the “stable and positive trend of the main indicators of economic development, the globally stable functioning of the budgetary and financial systems and the maintenance of low unemployment rates”.
As for next year, adds the association, “the Macau economy is expected to maintain a stable and positive trajectory”, although the global panorama “continues to be characterized by interconnected turbulence and complexity”.
The Macao SAR Budget for 2026 points to a 3.5% increase in casino revenues, reaching 236 billion patacas.
Other critical challenges that Macau faces in 2026 are stimulating local consumption and supporting small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs). Speaking to Lusa, Lei Choek Kuan, president of the Federation of Industry and Commerce of Macau, pointed to the “irreversible” change in consumption patterns underway and highlighted the importance of government support for companies to maintain confidence.
Henry Lei advocates a deeper structural transformation that goes beyond subsidies and suggested that local SMEs should look for differentiation and premium services – such as “improving after-sales service, developing creative cultural products and creating high-end culinary experiences” – to serve a niche demographic with high purchasing power, rather than competing on price with Mainland China.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Unemployment rate remains at 1.7%</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/taxa-de-desemprego-mantem-se-em-17-2/</link><description>Between September and November, the overall unemployment rate in the Macao SAR reached 1.7%, maintaining the level of the previous period (August to October) and the same period of 2024, informed the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). The unemployment rate for residents also did not change in both comparative bases, remaining at 2.3%.
In turn, the rates of global underemployment (1.5%) and resident underemployment (2.0%), which encompass unpaid leave situations, rose by 0.1 and 0.2 percentage points, respectively, when compared to the previous period. Within a year, there were no changes in both cases.
In the three-month period to November, the active population living in Macau grew by 0.6% to 385,600, in sequential terms. The employed population (378,900 individuals) increased by 0.6% (2,100 more people), including 287,800 residents (0.5% more).
Compared to the period between August and October, workers in the gaming (around 69,100), wholesale and retail trade (43,600) and catering (19,700) sectors decreased by 0.2%, 1.0% and 0.4%, respectively. On the other hand, the workforce rose 0.3% in hotels (to 29,700) and 0.3% in construction (24,900).
DSEC data also shows that unemployed residents fell by 0.4% to 6,700 in the same period of time. Among the unemployed people looking for a new job, the majority previously worked in the retail and gaming sectors. Individuals looking for their first job corresponded to 14.4% of unemployed residents, 0.5 points more than in the period between August and October.
The number of underemployed residents (5,900) increased by 11.5% (600 more people), with the majority belonging to the sectors of real estate activities and services provided to companies, transport and storage and retail trade.
The employment survey excluded residents and non-residents who, despite working in Macau, live abroad, whose average number was calculated at around 109,300 in the period under analysis. Including this group, the total workforce comprised 494,900 people.</description><pubDate>2025-12-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Social institutions encouraged to hire senior trainers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/instituicoes-da-area-social-incentivadas-contratar-formadores-seniores/</link><description>The Institute of Social Action (IAS) and the Senior Citizen Academy of the Macau Polytechnic University (UPM) completed the “Advanced Training Course for Senior Trainers”, which took place between October and December. All participants have completed the course and will be included in the “Senior Trainers Database”.
In this way, the IAS encourages social service institutions to consider hiring these senior trainers, providing them with “a broader teaching stage”.
Speaking at the closing ceremony, the president of the IAS, Hon Wai, assured that the “promotion of social participation and active aging” of the elderly is an important principle of government policy for the elderly. Hon Wai expressed admiration for the trainees' enthusiasm and their willingness to continue learning, hoping that they can apply the knowledge and techniques acquired to continually improve the quality of teaching and actively participate in society.
The course focused, in fact, on improving the practical teaching skills of senior trainees through pedagogical practice.
In turn, the deputy dean of UPM, Vivian Lei, expressed the expectation that participants in the course can serve as trainers for various interest groups in support service centers for the elderly in the community, continuing to promote “the spirit of solidarity and mutual progress”.
This course aimed to continue previous training actions, to further improve the teaching skills of trainees and the quality of the program through reinforced practical application and professional guidance. Participants completed a total of 17 hours of face-to-face training, teaching practice and exchange and summary sessions.</description><pubDate>2025-12-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Water storage is above previous years</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/armazenamento-de-agua-esta-acima-de-anos-anteriores/</link><description>The water reservoirs in Zhuhai, which supply Macau, are operating at high levels, and maintenance on the facilities was completed before the dry period, in order to guarantee supply security. Current storage capacity reaches 90%, a value above previous years, according to DSAMA
 
According to forecasts from water authorities in Mainland China, the natural inflow into the Xi River basin will present drier conditions than usual this winter and next spring. The Directorate of Maritime Affairs and Water Services (DSAMA) said that the inflow should be between 10% and 30% below the average between December and February.
To combat the intrusion of salt water during the dry period, the main reservoirs began storing water in advance, whose effective capacity reached 90%, exceeding the levels observed in the same period of previous years.
The data was released during a meeting between DSAMA, the Zhuhai Water Affairs Department and the “Zhuhai Water Environment Holdings” group, which discussed water conditions and coordinated salinity control measures during the dry period.
Furthermore, all reservoirs in Zhuhai are operating at high water levels, and maintenance of the facilities was completed before the dry period to ensure the security of water supply from Zhuhai to Macau.
According to the director of DSAMA, the relationship between Macau and Zhuhai in terms of water supply is “close and interdependent”. Wong Soi Man added that, “over the years, the Zhuhai Water Affairs Bureau has continuously strengthened the ability to guarantee raw water supply to Macau, effectively enhancing the joint capacity of both regions to resist saltwater intrusion and respond to contamination.”
Regarding the emergency supply capacity in Macau, the same official highlighted that the project to expand the Seac Pai Van Reservoir is ongoing and that after its completion, scheduled for 2028, Macau's water consumption autonomy will increase to 12 days.
During the meeting, opinions were exchanged on various topics, including water supply projects in Macau, quality of water supplied and incident response procedures.
A statement from DSAMA states that the Guangdong-Macao Water Supply Agreement provides for a three-yearly adjustment of the price of raw water supplied by Zhuhai to Macau, which will take place in 2026, so “the parties also held preliminary discussions on the price of raw water for the period from 2026 to 2028”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-12-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Tennis tournament offered competition and interaction with the public</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/torneio-de-tenis-ofereceu-competicao-interaccao-publico/</link><description>Spaniard Davidovich Fokina, 14th in the world rankings, was the main figure at the Tennis Masters that took place at the Forum Pavilion over the weekend. Also top of the bill, but in the women's sector, Russian Mirra Andreeva, ninth on the international list, only performed on the second day. The tournament, promoted by MGM, also included some parallel activities, with the public interacting with the players

























VÍTOR REBELO
 
For the third consecutive year, MGM brought to the territory some leading figures in international tennis, men's and women's, who performed in an exhibition tournament held over the weekend at the Forum Pavilion.
The most highly rated players were Spaniard Davidovich Fokina, who occupies 14th place in the ranking, and Russian Mirra Andreeva, ninth. However, the public who went to the venue were only able to see Andreeva on the second day, as the 20-year-old was ill on the first day.
Furthermore, the Frenchman Ugo Humbert, the Filipina Alex Eala and the Chinese Jerry Shang and Yibing Wu participated, forming part of three-man teams captained by the legends of the sport, Li Na (China) and Conchita Martinez (Spain).
The competition had a different format than usual, with the aim of being more dynamic and exciting, both for athletes and spectators. The “duels” began with the “Captains' Challenge”, with players rotating after losing a move, needing three consecutive victories to win a point.
Two quick three-minute rounds were played. In the end, the Li Na team (which included Humbert, Shang and Eala) won 2-1. In the following clashes, in men's singles, Davidovich overcame Shang by 7-6 and 7-5. In doubles, the Spaniard teamed up with Wu (in light of Andreeva's absence) and the pair beat Shang and Eala 7-5, 7-6.
At the end of the matches, Davidovich Fokina said that he traveled to Macau after finishing the pre-season. “Timing and jet lag were things I had to deal with, but coming here, having fun with the best players and getting to know the city is a different experience for me,” said the Spaniard, adding that he had never started the season in a tournament with this team format.
In the last singles of the day, Chinese Yibing Wu defeated Humbert 6-4, 3-6 and 10-6, completing the Conchita Martinez team's victory. “I had never played mixed doubles in my life, but I really enjoyed it”, mentioned the winner, adding that the recent triumph in the National Games was a very good result. “I gained a lot of confidence and my objective now is to start the 2026 season well”, he revealed.
Yesterday, in the second round, the debut of Mirra Andreeva stood out, as she recovered and was able to face Alexandra Eala. The star from Russia won both sets, 6-4 and 6-2, showing that she is on track to move up a few more places in the rankings next year, getting closer to players like the Italian Jasmine Paolini (eighth) and the North American Madison Keys (seventh).
 
Intergenerational dialogue
In addition to the games themselves, the tournament co-organized by MGM and the events company MARI Group, with the support of the Sports Institute, the Tourism Services Bureau and the Macau Tennis Association, included some activities, one of which was a sharing session, called “Four Voices, One Court”, held on Saturday morning at The Fantasy Box, at MGM Macau. The event brought together Grand Slam champions and members of the International Tennis Hall of Fame Li Na and Conchita Martínez, together with Filipina Alexandra Eala, “for an unprecedented intergenerational dialogue”, according to a statement from MGM.
Moderated by former Hong Kong Olympian Robyn Lamsam, the conversation covered topics “from tennis to life philosophies, adding a deeper and more inspiring dimension to the tournament”. During the session, the players reflected on their initial motivations for choosing tennis and the challenges in their professional careers.
Li Na shared that after achieving her dreams, the biggest lesson was to “perform like a champion, not only on the court, but also off it”, encouraging the younger generation to “be courageous and give themselves the opportunity to try to achieve their goals”.
For her part, Conchita Martínez recalled how she first connected with tennis, using her own experiences to encourage young players to enjoy the process “with a smile and passion, maintaining a positive mindset”. Alexandra Eala also stated that family support shaped her path and encouraged young people to follow their dreams.
Open to the public, the session attracted more than 300 participants, including university teachers and students, representatives from sports and youth associations, corporate partners and athletes.
In other parallel actions, on Friday, the invited players held a tennis clinic for local juniors, monitored by Mirra Andreeva and Yibing Wu, and promoted by the Macau Tennis Association.
The players also participated in a gastronomic and cultural experience specially organized at Rua da Praia do Manduco and Barra Kitchen, in the Barra area, where they tasted authentic local flavors and gained a “first-hand view of Macau’s unique mix of heritage, tradition and cuisine”, in line with the theme of the event: “Play. Celebrate. Repeat”, highlights the MGM text.</description><pubDate>2025-12-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>YouTube star helps attract “Generation Z”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/estrela-youtube-ajuda-atrair-geracao-z/</link><description>The Directorate of Tourism Services (DST) collaborated with Alan Chikin Chow, considered the “most viewed content creator on YouTube worldwide”, to produce a creative short piece with the aim of expanding the market of young international visitors. Taking advantage of the creator's international reach, the initiative aims to promote “the urban landscape and cultural charm of Macau through a humorous and relaxed narrative aimed at Generation Z”, explained DST, highlighting that this is Alan Chikin Chow's first creative project outside the USA.

The short film is part of the popular universe of American high school series, combining iconic Macau settings with a fast pace and comedy. With the city as the central stage, it connects emblematic places such as Travessa da Paixão, Praia de Hac Sá, Casa de Chá Long Wa and the Cotai Strip, “creating an intercultural youth story”. In the first two weeks, the short attracted more than 6.9 million views, “expanding visibility and debate about Macau”, believes DST.
Alan Chikin Chow, actor and producer, ranks 35th on the 2025 Forbes list of creators. His main channel “Alan’s Universe” has more than 98 million subscribers, exerting great influence among young audiences in English-speaking countries and regions.
For this project, Chinese creator Steven He, who has more than 17 million followers on social media, was also invited to enhance interaction around the work.
Alan Chikin Chow participated in “CreatorWeek Macao 2025”, held in October, where he shared his creative experience. On the occasion, he highlighted the unique architecture of Travessa da Paixão and the photographic potential of the Cotai Strip for Generation Z.
After the success of 22 episodes in Indonesian and Thai on its TikTok account, with more than 180 million views, DST continues to collaborate with prominent global creators to explore the potential of “short play + tourism experience” marketing. “This strategy allows for a greater approach to young audiences, highlighting Macau’s diverse offer as a world center for tourism and leisure”, argues the organization, promising to continue to deepen the intersectoral integration of “tourism +” to match online advertising trends.</description><pubDate>2025-12-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SJM sponsors TVB series that highlights the “charm” of Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sjm-patrocina-serie-da-tvb-realca-charme-de-macau/</link><description>TVB will air the series “This City Never Sleeps” in 2026, a production sponsored by SJM that pays special attention to Macau’s “multifaceted identity”.
 
The “This City Never Sleeps” series will allow the territory’s “captivating urban landscapes” to be promoted by “Television Broadcasts” (TVB) to a global audience, including Malaysia, Singapore, USA, Canada, Australia, United Kingdom, Europe, New Zealand, Vietnam, Taiwan and Thailand, to “further increase the fascination of Macau as a top tourist destination for Chinese communities abroad”, highlighted SJM Resorts, main sponsor of this project produced by the Hong Kong channel.
Starring Julian Cheung, Ron Ng, Samantha Ko, Kelly Cheung, Elena Kong and David Chiang, the series will be shown on TVB channels and streaming platforms in 2026. “The story revolves around power struggles, betrayal and brotherhood, weaving an engaging narrative in a context of ambition and emotional complexity”, says the statement, further emphasizing that this production “aims to show the multifaceted identity and unique charm of Macau through the lens of the cameras”.
“By attracting visitors to different neighborhoods and points of interest, the project is expected to increase the flow of people, stimulate local businesses and support tourism and commercial activity throughout the city, contributing to Macau’s ‘Tourism+’ integration strategy”, highlights SJM.
At the “blessing” ceremony of “This City Never Sleeps”, held at Kam Pek Market, the managing director of SJM argued that “cinema and television are not only a form of entertainment, but also a powerful medium for promoting the city's brand and tourism”. "Through this collaboration with TVB, we are inviting audiences to roam the streets and alleys of Macau – to experience the city's warmth, stories and cultural richness. We hope the series brings Macau closer to audiences across Asia, while generating tangible economic benefits for our local districts and community," said Daisy Ho.
The series will feature several “iconic locations” linked to SJM, such as the Grand Lisboa Palace, the Grand Lisboa, the Macau Tower, the “Macau Palace” floating casino and the Kam Pek Market. It will also highlight “culturally rich neighborhoods”, such as Rua de Cinco de Outubro, San Ma Lo and other areas.
The production “will capture the fusion of East and West and the constantly evolving dialogue between old and new that defines Macau’s urban identity, triggering a wave of community tourism in filming locations”, says SJM, highlighting the “reappearance of Macau Palace”.
"This iconic floating structure, once a popular tourist attraction in the 1980s and 1990s, stood as a symbol of the city's timeless allure. Now revitalized after years of closure, it will return through the TV series, evoking cherished collective memories of this 'Palace on the Sea'", the statement read.
 
S.T.</description><pubDate>2025-12-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CPSP agent prosecuted for driving drunk while off duty</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/agente-cpsp-alvo-de-processo-por-conduzir-embriagado-na-folga/</link><description>The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) initiated disciplinary proceedings against one of its officers, aged 31, on suspicion of committing the crime of driving while drunk. According to a note published on the website of the Office of the Secretary for Security, Chan Tsz King, the officer, who was off duty, had a traffic accident at the intersection between Rua da Barca and Rua de João de Araújo in the early hours of December 24th. The light vehicle he was driving ended up colliding with a flowerbed on the side of the street. The result of the alcohol test exceeded the values ​​permitted by law, meaning the case was referred to the Public Prosecutor's Office for investigation purposes. “The CPSP deeply regrets the case of drunk driving by a police officer, reiterating that it has always given great importance to the disciplinary behavior of its personnel”, states the same note, with the corporation guaranteeing that the acts of its agents that violate the law and discipline “are treated severely” and in accordance with the current legal framework. According to the office of the security portfolio holder, “all departments received immediate instructions to continuously reinforce the awareness and education of their subordinate officers”, reminding them that “their personal conduct is linked to the positive image of the police force”. “Even when off duty, officers must maintain the highest standards of self-discipline and comply with laws and regulations,” the statement emphasizes.</description><pubDate>2025-12-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cinemateca exceeded the objective of digitizing a thousand Portuguese films</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/cinemateca-ultrapassou-objectivo-de-digitalizacao-de-mil-filmes-portugueses/</link><description>The Cinemateca Portuguesa has already surpassed the objective of digitizing a thousand Portuguese cinema films, within the scope of the Recovery and Resilience Plan (PRR), and should reach 1,300 in the next quarter, the director, Rui Machado, told Lusa.
The Cinemateca Portuguesa, in Lisbon, symbolically marked the achievement of the goal defined in the PRR, with the screening of an excerpt from the thousandth digitized film, “Três Dias sem Deus” (1946), by Bárbara Virgínia, and with the announcement of an online page where data from all digitized films will be available. "We wanted to show that we fulfilled the measure within the established deadline, but this does not mean that the project is over, because we will have the possibility of digitizing more films by at least March. (…) We can easily reach 1,200, 1,300 digitized films", explained Rui Machado.
According to the Cinemateca, between 2022 and 2025, 333 feature films and 697 short films were digitized, and in some cases digitally restored, 333 feature films and 697 short films, in a total of 1,030 films, that is, 43,645 digitized minutes, by more than 283 authors.
The PRR measure had an allocation of 10.8 million euros, with a final execution deadline of December 31, 2025 – according to information on the Transparency Portal – and involved the participation of 30 to 40 external professionals.
According to Rui Machado, this PRR measure “was essential” to safeguard the heritage of Portuguese cinema, “despite not structurally solving the problem of the Cinemateca laboratory”, namely the lack of human resources and bureaucratic management constraints. The director of the Cinemateca stressed that "without digitization, most films would quickly stop being seen. Apart from the Cinemateca and very few cinemas, no cinema can project a 35mm copy".
The PRR measure covers more than a century of cinematographic works and, consequently, the History of Portuguese cinema, from silent cinema to the present, from different genres and eras.
Information about digitized films is available on the page https://digital.cinemateca.pt/, serving as a “consultation tool” for anyone who wants to program them, such as “festivals, film clubs, distributors, museums, universities or other entities, both national and international”.
Rui Machado recalls that, from now on, there will be a catalog of Portuguese films with the possibility of reaching more audiences both in cinemas, television channels and streaming. The Cinemateca grants the use of the new digital film supports through a contract with the holders of the rights to the cinematographic works, which includes the payment of a sum, depending on the duration of the films.
“We have more than 200 films with signed contracts and we no longer have them because, for this type of work, we did not have support from PRR, we have a person to deal with this”, said Rui Machado, clarifying that there are still cases in which cinematographic works are under the supervision of the State or in the public domain.
The director admitted that some producers disagree with the clauses of the agreement and that, in most cases, the disagreement relates to the values ​​requested for the transfer. According to the draft agreements, the rights holder of a digitized film undertakes to pay Cinemateca between 200 euros (for a work lasting less than 10 minutes) and a thousand euros (for a film lasting more than an hour) “for the definitive transfer of the digital copy”.
"This is an economic good. We are asking for a single amount forever and ever. The matrix [digital of each film] will be responsible for exploring the film in theaters, on television, on platforms for all the years that it is possible to explore. (…) There are detailed things that we can negotiate in the clauses, but others cannot", he highlighted.
For Rui Machado, this PRR measure to digitize Portuguese cinema will facilitate its circulation, “but it is not enough to have a room with a digital projector”. “We have always believed that digitalization could help fill out the schedules of cinemas in Portugal a little, not to mention the rest of the world, but it all depends on who is on the other side”, he said.
The presentation session of the thousandth film was attended by the Minister of Culture, Youth and Sports, Margarida Balseiro Lopes, for whom the digitalization of Portuguese cinema “is a first big step”, but it is necessary to “consolidate public access to this collective heritage, guarantee its sustained circulation”.
 
JTM/Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>