<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Urban cleaning contest values ​​environmental vehicles of the environment</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/concurso-para-limpeza-urbana-valoriza-veiculos-amigos-ambiente/</link><description>In some areas of the mud, the garbage collection will be done in the night, experimental. In addition, the new contract for urban cleaning services, collection and transportation of waste stipulates that the award will have to priority to environmental and low noise vehicles, as well as install equipment to reduce smells and noise
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The new contract for urban cleaning services, waste collection and transportation will include environmental requirements, as well as providing for garbage nocturnal collection, in experimental, in some areas of the mud, the new director of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) revealed. , IP Kuong Lam. Complaints about the daytime collection in mud and coloane and on the noise of vehicles arrived at the office of Deputy Ron Lam, who addressed a series of issues to the government.
By stressing that the public tender has already begun, the DSPA Director justified the consecutive celebration of new contracts, by direct and waiver of consultation, with the current company, “CSR Macau - Limited Waste Systems Company”, by to “ensure that the operation of services (including the maintenance of facilities and equipment, the salary adjustment of the staff, etc.) is not affected”. The contract between MSAR and CSR was signed in 2013 for a period of 10 years and renewed in March last year and then in October.
Ron Lam had criticized government performance in recent years. The deputy pointed out that the executive has "resorted to different reasons to renew, continuously and with dismissal of public tender, the short -term contracts." In his opinion, the action "not only does not favor the attraction of new operators to the market, but it is also very unfavorable to the long -term investments of the concessionaires, as well as for the reasonable adjustment of their workers' perks."
Residents of Taipa and Coloane complained to Ron Lam, due to garbage collection during the day. Given the development of the islands, “which are already important tourist zones of Macau, the smell and noise produced by the vehicles of collecting A during the day severely affect passersby and shopkeepers,” said the deputy, suggesting that the vehicles pass In the night to take the trash. In this regard, IP Kuong Lam indicated that “the new contract will adjust the waste collection periods according to the actual situation, and in some areas of the mud, will be performed, by experimental, the collection of waste in the night period ”.
The noise of garbage trucks has also affected some residents of the old Peninsula neighborhoods, where the streets are narrow and low buildings. In addition, he said Ron Lam, also complains because "garbage deposits are crowded every day before noon, which affects the hygiene of the neighborhoods."
Pointing out that some of the waste collection vehicles have already been replaced by new hybrid models with low noise technology, “with the aim of reducing, as far as possible, the noise generated”, the DSPA leader stressed that “the new contract stipulates Although the operator, in the acquisition of new vehicles, should consider primarily friendly vehicles of the environment and low noise, as well as install equipment to reduce smells and noise. ”
 
Garbage collection thought of detail plans
On the other hand, IP Kuong Lam indicated that public dwellings in zone A of new landfills will have as its main model for the collection of household waste compression containers installed in closed spaces, “to effectively reduce the impact the impact for the surrounding environment ”. Quoting the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI), it states that the number of garbage compactive containers in the territory increased to 132, while the number of large containers on the roads was “substantially” from about 1,600 to 92. This, note, "only effectively improves environmental hygiene, as well as significantly relieves traffic problems in traffic and the sound uncomfortable caused by garbage collection."
Ron Lam also argued that the authorities should include “expressly”, the facilities of garbage compression container and the reserve of spaces for their installation, in detail plans, “with a view to minimizing the impact of garbage collection from of planning ”. Regarding the future planning, more specifically in relation to public housing projects to be built, "AMI has already presented the suggestions on the use of garbage compactrs in the treatment of household waste with competent public services."
In this field, the Directorate of Soil Services and Urban Construction (DSSCU) clarified that, during the elaboration of detail plans, the government “will, taking into account the current situation and the development needs of each zone, to improve the general disposition of space and build public infrastructures to meet the integrated development needs of the entire community ”.
By way of example, it points out that in the detail plan of zone A, the planning of the works related to waste treatment based on the principle of rational soil use and the scientific and rational planning of the waste collection system was proposed. Thus, it was established that the entry and exit of garbage deposits, located in the lot where there are garbage compactors, is facing the lane.
“Regarding concrete provisions, batch buildings will be installed electric waste compactrs for the collection and treatment of waste or other solid waste resulting from everyday life, and in green areas located at the end north to the A4 and the east of the lot lot. C27, underground space will be reserved to store equipment intended for cleaning public roads ”, can be read.
On the other hand, the deputy questioned the government about why the “Study on the Quality of Urban Cleaning Services, Collection and Transport of Macau Waste (2019-2024)” is still underway, “because it is still on the list of the Scientific Research Projects ”of the Macao Institute of Systems Engineering, on the Electronic page of the University of Science and Technology of Macao. To this question, the director of DSPA did not answer directly.
IP Kuong Lam said only that the Executive of the MSAR “proceeds, in each year of the activity, to the standardized evaluation of urban cleaning services, collection and transportation of waste, through a third independent academic institution, constituting quantitative data and Suggestions resulting from the evaluation fundamentals for the internal reference of the government ”. In addition, opinions and suggestions are collected through various means, such as the “environmental line” of DSPA and the online opinion collection platform, “in the sense of supervising in various aspects and continually improving urban cleaning services, collection and transportation of waste ”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>International visitors grew 10.2% in the golden week</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/visitantes-internacionais-cresceram-102-na-semana-dourada/</link><description>During the Golden Week of the Chinese New Year, Macau received 58,000 international visitors, an increase of 10.2%, according to STD. A number that is well regarded by the sector. However, there was an annual break in the total of visitors, which may be related to economic factors and more travel options to China, in the case of Hong Kong visitors. There are also those who believe that there was a difference in the accounting of the days, by STD
 
Catarina Pereira
 
International visitors reached 58,000 during the eight days of the Chinese New Year's Golden Week holidays, the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) revealed, which equivalent to about 7,300 per day. The increase was 10.2% over the same period last year. The body led by Helena de Senna Fernandes was no use details about the countries of origin of these visitors.
“The industry is extremely happy to see more international visitors. It is very good. I think the increase was driven by visitors from South Korea, Japan and other Southeast Asia countries, ”Rutger Verschuren, vice president of the Hotel Association in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau. It is the reflection of the “efforts” of STD and integrated resorts, he added.
Verschuren considers that "it is very healthy for Macau to have a larger international market." Pointing out that mainland China and Hong Kong have been doing a lot to attract international visitors, which is good, ”the associative leader also states that it turns out to be“ competitive ”to Macau. "It may be a threat, but it may also be an opportunity," he warned. The opportunity will be if Macao can be the starting or final point of those who come to explore the interior of China or Hong Kong.
He also recalled that last year was talked about direct flights from Macau to Dubai, for example. “This would be sensational because it would mean a more direct contact with Europe, the Middle East and North Africa countries. They could come to Macao and then explore mainland China and Hong Kong, ”he noted, stressing that the territory would be less dependent on Hong Kong airport and others in the interior of China.
Also Penny Wan, a professor at the University of Tourism of Macau (UTM), said that "this is undoubtedly excellent news, a big breakthrough for Macau." "International visitors tend to spend more and will also benefit the neighboring cities of the Great Bay, as many will not only come to Macau," he said to this newspaper.
“I believe Macau is benefiting from recent political and social disorders in some destinations. Macau is considered a safe place to visit and interesting to learn about the rich cultural heritage (…) Macao's uniqueness as a tourist and leisure destination is currently in good shape, ”said Penny Wan, although there was generally a Break in the number of visitors at this point. Thus, he argued that "more efforts should be made and developed services and more innovative products to attract international visitors."
STD, in turn, has ensured that “this year will continue to consolidate the markets of Greater China and Southeast Asia, as well as to expand the northeast Asia, to relaunch the markets of Europe, America and India, as well as the Explore the Middle East ”.
In the general calculation, the tourist flow at MSAR during this festive period suffered a 3.5% break in annual terms, to almost 1.31 million visitors, according to preliminary data. The daily average was close to 164 thousand - below 185 thousand expected by Helena de Senna Fernandes - and which for the body represents "a slight descent". STD also stressed that the daily average approaches the level recorded in the Golden Week of the 2019 Chinese New Year, when almost 172,000 were accounted for.
For Verschuren, contributing to the annual breakage may be the fact that this year the Chinese New Year has ended on a weekday. He also believes that there was a difference, compared to last year, in the accounting of the days, by STD.
Visitors from the interior of China exceeded one million, with 125,000 per day, with a decrease of 3.2% in annual terms, since in 2023 there were 129,000 daily. Already the arrivals of neighboring Hong Kong totaled 230 thousand, almost 29 thousand a day, says the STD, a break of almost 9%, according to the data provided on the body's electronic page. From Taiwan came 20 thousand visitors or a daily average of 2,500.
In the first three days of the Lunar New Year (January 29-11), the number of visitors has increased consecutively, and on the third day (January 31) reached the peak with 219,000 visitors, a 9.1% increase in relation to On the fourth day of the Golden Week of 2024, “which was also the highest second daily value of which there is record,” says STD in a statement. The Grand Prix Museum received 7,590 visitors, an increase of 2%, which was the highest number of holidays.
 
Reasons for the breakage
Penny Wan believes there are "four main reasons" for the fall of visitors on the continent and Hong Kong. Firstly, he pointed out that “Macau hotels are very expensive during the Chinese New Year, so some inhabitants of the continent can postpone their visit to the low time”, especially those living in the great bay and who have been in the territory several times. "This delay in visiting Macau is also due to global economic bad conditions, as people are generally becoming wiser in using their money," he noted.
Given the data provided to STD by the hotel sector operators, during the golden week, the average hotel occupancy rate was 95%, “remaining virtually unchanged compared to the 2024 Chinese New Year”. The highest amount of the occupancy rate was reached on the fourth day of the Lunar New Year (February 1) with 97.8%. As for the average price per room, hotels, apartments and low cost accommodation, it was about 1,839.5 patacas, a 2.4% decrease compared to the same festive period as last year.
Rutger Verschuren told this newspaper that, in terms of room revenues, "they were generally a little lower than in previous years, including last year and 2019." In addition, "Purchasing Power in terms of spas restoration and use, etc., was also slightly inferior than last year." "We can see that people are very cautious in spending," he noted.
On the other hand, Penny Wan pointed out that Hong Kong residents have been shopping and being attracted to cities in the Great Bay, where they “spend less money than in Macao, but can enjoy the same quality of services and products and get new experiences". Thus, in your opinion, STD should bet on “creation of more packages, discounts, new attractions and activities to attract this segment”. Due to these changes, "the profile, preferences, expense patterns and consumer behaviors of this segment may be required to re -expense to attract it to visit Macao."
Trips to foreigners by Hong Kong's inhabitants are another of the factors pointed out, as this year they could enjoy nine days of holidays, needing to use two days of annual holidays. In addition, it is possible that the recent pandemic crisis and economic recession contributed to the Chinese to give “more value” to this time of family union in China. "People are increasingly realizing that having an opportunity to meet annually is very precious," he noted.
 
24 Complaints and Information Requests
The open line for tourism, which worked for 24 hours between January 28 and February 4, received 24 complaints and requests for information from visitors, “mainly involving hotel reservations, service attitude, transport and purchases”. The cases were accompanied by the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) or sent to the competent services. In the same period, STD made 114 inspections at border stations, sights, purchasing places and hotel establishments, "having not detected any offenses."</description><pubDate>2025-02-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Companies provide more than 700 job openings</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/empresas-disponibilizam-mais-de-700-vagas-de-emprego/</link><description>Hundreds of vacancies will be made available in employment conjugation actions to be performed during this month by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs. The pairing sessions are intended for sectors such as hospitality, restoration, information technologies, retail selling pharmaceuticals, among others
 
February brings more opportunities for those interested in entering the job market in Macao, as the management of work for work, in conjunction with the Macao Workers' Associations Federation, will promote several pairing sessions , with a view to filling a total of 740 job vacancies.
On the 13th, in the morning, there will be a special conjugation action of CDFG Macau, a limited unipessoal company, for the retail sales sector of pharmaceutical products, with the offer of 15 vacancies for the position of seller. In the afternoon, there will be a session for the information technology sector, with the participation of the “Kingdee Software Company (Macau), limited” and the company “Boardware Limited Information System” and 13 vacancies are provided for positions as assistant of Project, business analyst, system analyst, on -site installer, software delivery assistant and seller.
The next day, February 14, both in the morning and in the afternoon, will take place sessions of the responsibility of SJM Resorts, directed to the hospitality. 20 jobs will be offered to, among others, positions as head of VIP Care Service, room reserve service agent, telephone marketing, concierge and receptionist.
Registration will be open from today and until noon of February 12.
Later, DSAL, in order to mitigate the pressure on the demand for human resources by companies, as well as providing jobs to residents, will take six more interview periods to interested parties.
The actions are organized in partnership with the six integrated resort and leisure companies, offering a total of 691 vacancies available by various front line departments and backstage of hotel and restoration establishments belonging to the portfolio of those operators. The vacancies are mainly part of the groups of “Restoration”, “Rooms and Cleaning” and “Front Line Operations”, which account for more than 70% of the total vacancies.
The places offered also include some management positions and specialized technical posts, such as strategic analysis manager, Game Audit Manager, Customer Administration and Raising Manager, Senior Room Meter, Systems Engineer for Shows and Heads of Different Kitchen .
Initial pairing sessions for companies will take place on February 18 (Melco and MGM), 25 (SJM Resorts), 26 (Galaxy Entertainment Group) and 27 (Sands China and Wynn). In addition to these, companies will be able to mark other meetings depending on the number of participants. The exact place, date and time of interviews will be communicated by companies by phone or SMS message.
Between February 7th and 24th, stakeholders from Macao residents can make the appointment and application to vacancies by accessing the “Local Employment Offers” Portal of the Sitio da Dsal.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao “slides” at the Winter Asian Games</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-desliza-nos-jogos-asiaticos-de-inverno/</link><description>The male selection of ice hockey of the mashes has already made two challenges in the winter Asian games, having lost both by dilated margin, against Hong Kong and Turquemenistan. The territory is represented only in this modality. The event takes place in the Chinese city of Harbin and officially starts today with the opening ceremony, in which the head of the Executive of the MSA will be present. Games have a record of athletes and countries or regions
 
Victor Rebelo
 
A Macao delegation made up of 21 ice hockey athletes in the men's sector is among the 34 participating in another edition of the Winter Asian Games, which today are officially opened in the Chinese city of Harbin.
The MSar team has already started their participation, integrated in Group C of the first phase of the tournament, having endorsed two heavy losses. The first face to Hong Kong, 26-1, with the goal of Macao being pointed by Argus Hong Lai-li, and the second against Turquemenistan by 26-0.
The next challenge will be on Sunday, early afternoon at the Harbin Arena against India, a team they lost with Hong Kong 30-0, which could mean the possibility of Macao discussing at least the result in his last meeting of the series .
Today, at the opening ceremony, Macao will parade, among the delegations present at the event, with some ice hockey athletes, one of which will be the standard carrier, carrying the flag of the MSAR. The Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, will be watching the opening show of the games on the bench intended for official representatives of the participating nations or regions.
Macau participates for the third time at the Winter Asian Games, always in the ice hockey mode, after 2007 and 2017. The competition, which integrates 11 modalities and a total of 64 disciplines, will unfold until February 14 and register Two records: Delegations (34, against the 32 of the 2017 Games in Sapporo and Obihiro, Japan) and athletes (1,275, against 1,145 of the previous edition).
The host entourage, the Popular Republic of China, has 170 athletes, five of which have won gold medals in the last 2022 Winter Olympic games in Beijing. Chinese representatives will discuss first place in the total picture of the podium with the rivals of South Korea and Japan.
This is the second time that the test has taken place in Harbin, known as “Ice City” (the minimum expected temperature for today is 20 degrees Celsius, better than yesterday when the thermometers recorded 32 below zero).
This year's edition has the premieres of Butão, Cambodia and Saudi Arabia, and this last country will organize the next competition in 2029, the first in the Middle East. It will be in Trojena, the only outdoor ski tourist resort of the Persian Gulf, located in the futuristic city of Neom, on the banks of the Red Sea.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China and Thailand united against burla nets</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/china-tailandia-unidas-contra-redes-de-burlas/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping and Thai Prime Minister Paetongtarn Shinawatra yesterday promised to combat Southeast Asia, during a meeting in Beijing.
Myanmar, Cambodia and Laos, which are south of China and share borders with Thailand, have become the main centers of online fraud operations, where people attracted to false advertisements for well-paid jobs are kept in secret complexes and forced to Work for criminal groups that generate mockery -driven molds around the world. The situation has affected Thailand's reputation, as several cases of Chinese attracted to work in Bangcoque arose and then trafficked to some complexes in Myanmar, being actor Wang Xing the latest victim.
Thailand and China have taken steps to solve the problem of the mockery, including a visit by Liu Zhongyi, Chinese deputy minister of public security, to the border region.
“China appreciates the strong measures adopted by Thailand to combat online fraud. Both parties should continue to reinforce law enforcement, security and judicial cooperation, ”said Xi, quoted by state television CCTV.
"Thailand is willing to reinforce the cooperation of law enforcement with China and other neighboring countries and to adopt resolute and effective measures to combat transionic crimes such as game and fraud," said Paetongtarn.
This week, Thailand has cut electricity to some areas of Myanmar by its border to try to disturb the operations of fraudulent groups. The effect of this measure is not clear, since complexes often have their own generators.
The visit to China is the first of Paetongtarn as Prime Minister and occurs at a time when the two countries celebrate 50 years of diplomatic ties.
On the other hand, Xi said China is ready to work on a new rail project between the two countries. On Tuesday, Thailand approved a $ 10 billion railway call that will connect Bangkok to the Laos-China High Speed ​​Line. According to Xi, the two countries also expect to deepen cooperation in the domain of electric vehicles, as Thailand is an emerging market for Chinese manufacturers.
China was once a significant part of the Thailand tourist segment, but by 2024, the number of visitors dropped to 6.7 million, well below 11 million in 2019, when the Chinese represented almost a third of all arrivals. Paetongtarn stressed that Thailand is willing to accommodate Chinese interests on fundamental issues.
It also stared that Thailand “firmly” respects the principle of 'one China', Beijing's position that Taiwan is part of China.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-02-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Urban Practice” wins award for heritage pavilion</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/urban-practice-conquista-premio-para-pavilhao-patrimonio/</link><description>The proposal of the team of architects, urban planners, engineers and designers of the Urban Practice for the Macao World Heritage Pavilion won a French design award. The public contest was launched by the Cultural Institute and the work of the group led by Nuno Soares presents the concept of interaction between Chinese and Western cultures

Victor Rebelo
 
Revealing, displaying and promoting heritage were at the base of the presentation of a proposal from “The Urban Practice” (UP) to the Macao World Heritage Pavilion, following a public tender launched by the Cultural Institute (IC) in 2022, having has been distinguished in the French design prizes. The work of the team of architects, urban planners, engineers and designers won the silver prize of “French Design Awards 2024”, in the “Interior Design/Exhibits, Pavilions &amp; Exhibitions” category.
The concept focuses on showing what makes Macau a unique city as a UNESCO World Heritage Site: interaction between Chinese and Western cultures. The location of the project, on D. Belchior Carneiro Street, is linked to historical monuments such as the ruins of St. Paulo and Fortaleza do Monte.
According to a note issued by the UP, the pavilion presents "a dynamic façade that allows a permeability between interior and exterior for flexible inner lighting and for visitors to explore Macao's heritage from various perspectives."
The structure was conceived with state -of -the -art technology and interactive characteristics to increase visitors involvement, while the input atrium was created to offer views of St. Paul's ruins and, through augmented reality technology, restore their original disposition.
To harmoniously integrate the pavilion into the outer surroundings, the UP proposal organized the spaces according to the height of the terrain, preserving old trees and vegetation, and implemented drawing principles without barriers for accessibility.
Nuno Soares, the main architect of the UP, points out that this approach was primarily aimed at preserving and enhancing Macao's world heritage to a wider audience. “The selection of materials and technologies for this project was based on principles and best preservation practices,” says Nuno Soares, for whom, “with the ambition to celebrate the history of Macau”, one of the main features is the vertical patio with A wall, from the top to the top, made with a beaten dirt, a material once used in the old wall of the city that crossed the place.
French Design Awards is a professional contest recognized internationally under the “International Awards Associate” (IAA), which aims to recognize creatives in the domains of architecture, interiors and design.
By facing complex challenges “from idea to execution”, UP is said to be committed to each specialization area “to design excellence and technical domain in architectural design, interior design, construction engineering, urban planning, sustainable solutions and project management ”.
With its work, UP intends to “explore the potential of the place”, promoting “human interaction and creating a positive impact”, being the creation of significant innovations its main commitment.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Commercial registration service “crosses” borders</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/servico-de-registo-comercial-cruza-fronteiras/</link><description>Several companies in Macao were supported by the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and investing in processing of about 90 commercial registration requests, through the transionic service in the in -depth cooperation zone. Macao and Hengqin authorities together launched the technical meetings mechanism to respond online to business establishment consultations online
 
With a view to helping Macao companies to take advantage of business opportunities generated by the development of the in -depth cooperation zone, the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment (IPIM) has made a series of facilitation services in processing commercial registration services available. Through the “Transfronho Commercial Registration Service in the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin”, IPIM allows companies to deal with procedures in Macao and obtain business licenses without the need to leave the territory.
The service reduces the time and economic costs of investors who are interested in investing and developing activities in the deepened cooperation zone. Since the launch, more than 100 requests have already been fulfilled, supporting MSAR companies in processing almost 90 commercial registration requests, of which more than 40% are involved in the integrated tourism and leisure industries, 'Big Health', Modern finances, state -of -the -art technologies, conventions and exhibitions, trade, culture and sport.
According to IPIM, companies with foreign capital from Portugal, Germany, Czech Republic and Australia, who have used this service to address the commercial registration procedures of the deepened cooperation zone, “are optimistic about the unique advantages of masks as a link of Internal and external connection and will take advantage of Macau-Hengqin's joint development model to expand the interior market of China. ”
To allow investors to efficiently understand administrative formalities and procedures on the establishment of business, IPIM and several competent authorities in the deepened cooperation zone, have together promoted the “technical meetings mechanism before the investment process ”In order to help potential investors in the coordination of online consulting sessions.
Through the service, underlines the IPIM note, investors can clarify beforehand the doubts related to the business establishment process and the license application, “accelerating the process of implementing investment projects in the in -depth cooperation zone”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Intellectual property motivates lecture at the Art Museum</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/propriedade-intelectual-motiva-palestra-museu-de-arte/</link><description>Presentation of Protection of Intellectual Property



Two experts in the area of ​​Intellectual Property (IP) will give a lecture in the auditorium of the Macao Art Museum. The session “Unraveling the PI industry: How to master its operations and legislation, promoted by the Cultural Institute (IC) will take place on March 1, Saturday, at 15:00. Rosia, founder of a well -known PI authorization agency in the interior of China, and Rebecca Lo, a lawyer who works in the PI authorization area, were invited to share their experiences in operations, marketing and authorization strategies, as well as Commerce, describing some relevant legal cases. According to the IC, Rosia has over 10 years of business experience in management and creativity industry, being a specialist in the field of PI creation, operations management, marketing and promotion, developing cultural and creative products, brands development, Cooperation in authorization for commercial purposes and event management, having collaborated with more than 30 PI owners and known artists in the interior of China. Rebecca Lo is experienced in intellectual property legislation and management, including in the application, registration and pledge of registered/design/patent, PI guarantee financing and treatment of objection/revocation/invalidation, among others. The lecture will be held in Cantonense and Mandarin. Interested parties can apply through the “Activities Registration” section of the “Macao Unique Account” mobile application, or online by computer until February 20th.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2338/</link><description>Air Macau wants to reinforce flights to Taichung
Air Macau plans to increase the frequency of the route between MSAR and Taichung, Taiwan's second largest city, from March 1 to 29. The local carrier is expected to make six flights available a week instead of the four current. The Taiwanese company Starlux Airlines also operates the same route.
 
Michelin Guide Ceremony at Grand Lisbon Palace
The 17th edition of the Michelin Hong Kong &amp; Macau Guide Selection of Restaurants, scheduled for March 13, will take place at Grand Lisboa Palace, the organization said. Prior to that, on March 6, the “Bib Gourmand” team will be launched, which lists the restaurants that offer “good quality kitchen and good quality/price”. All establishments are selected according to the same five criteria: quality of the ingredients; mastery of the kitchen and culinary techniques; harmony of flavors; Expression of the boss's personality in the kitchen; and consistency, both over time and throughout the menu.
 
Open registrations for international parade
The Macao International Parade will take place on March 23, indicated the Cultural Institute (IC), inviting artistic and cultural associations, schools and institutions to present proposals until February 15. The themes include “East Asian City of Culture” and “East-King Meeting, Asia in Harmony”. Groups can participate in four modalities: “Parade theme”, “Artistic Group Parade”, “Large Artistic Facilities Parade” and “Special Planning Parade”. There will also be several extension activities. The IC also informs that interested parties can register in the “street art groups” modality, bringing different forms of culture and art to communities. The event will end with international groups.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sustained economic growth “dependent on increased productivity”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/crescimento-economico-sustentado-dependente-aumento-da-produtividade/</link><description>Structural policies and reforms that support the growth of long -term productivity - this is Isabel W.T. Choy of the monetary authority's investigation and statistics department to respond to population aging in the territory, which, warns, is a challenge and could limit the economic growth of masters. With the prospects for decreasing the active population in the coming years, the labor market will be affected by decreasing productivity. Sustained economic development will be “dependent on increased productivity”, points out
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Population aging could be an obstacle to the economic growth of Macao, as it will impact the productivity of the labor market, warns Isabel W.T. Choy of the Macao Monetary Authority Research and Statistics Department (AMCM). “A fundamental challenge for Macao medium -term growth prospects is the aging of the population, due to the low birth rate and increased life expectancy. This demographic trend is likely to slow down the active population growth rate, ”says the economist in a study entitled“ Estimation of Potential Output and Output Gap of Macao ”.
According to the projections of the population of Macau 2022-2041, which is based on the results of the latest censuses, carried out in 2021, the rate of labor participation should have a decreasing trend, decreasing 2.0 and 5, 7 percentage points (men and women, respectively) in 2041 compared to 2021. “Active population growth should slow down,” says Isabel W.T. Choy, pointing out that a slowdown was already registered after 2010.
"Even from the principle that the growth in labor productivity will remain stable, the prospects for growth in the medium term of Macao in the next decade will be inevitably limited by the tendency to decrease the active population's growth rate," He argues, adding: "The weak growth of labor will affect the growth of per capita GDP in the future."
In Isabel W.T. Choy, for a “sustained growth” in the territory, is necessary to explore “increasingly productive” ways to use “production factors”. According to it, "the main source of medium -term sustained economic growth will necessarily provide for increased productivity."
“Although it is not as important as the growth of labor productivity, employment increases that it has contributed remarkably to the development of Macao over the last three decades. In prospective terms, the aging of the population will slow down the growth of labor, thus limiting the potential for economic growth from employment, ”he notes.
According to the projections of the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services, for the next twenty years, it is expected that the proportion of elderly (65 years or older) over the total population continues to rise, from 12.2% in 2021 to 20.9% in 2041. The numbers point to the oldest layer of the population to increase from 83,200 people to 164,400 in 2041, at an average annual growth rate of 3.5% - “considerably higher” than the population Total (0.7%).
The proportion of the adult population in relation to the total will decrease. The number of adults (15-64 years) will increase, but the growth of the adult population (+7.7%) will be “much lower” to that of the elderly population (+97.6%), as “it is dragged by the fall Continuous of the young population (under 14 years or equal to or equal), which in the future will expand the adult population. ” The proportion of the adult population will continually decrease, and it is expected to go down from 73.3% (500,600) by 2021 to 68.6% (539,000) by 2041. In this sense, the total dependence index will be increased, so “ sustaining seniors will become a greater weight. ”
To counteract the challenges imposed by demographic changes, Isabel W.T. Choy considers that "medium -term growth strategies should be oriented to stimulate greater productivity growth." In this sense, political priority should be given to “reaching resources for more productive uses, including relocation within each sector and between sectors”.
“In addition, the current tendency of digitization in Macao would facilitate these relocations. These structural reforms would be well aligned with the strategic objective of diversification of Macao's economy in order to release new sources of productivity growth and support Macau's growth in the medium and long term, ”he may read.
Stressing that the analysis he has revealed revealed “a more pronounced volatility of production in the last decade, even excluding the pandemic period”, the author adds that Macau, being an open economy, “is highly susceptible to external shocks, which emphasizes the importance of the budget reserve to safeguard macroeconomic stability ”. "Budgetary reserves allow you to resist the amplification of shocks and facilitate quick disbursement for emergency and recovery efforts in the sequence of serious shocks," he says.
“The challenges placed by population aging require structural reforms to support long -term productivity growth. In particular, reform priorities should be aligned with Macao's strategic objectives established in the proper diversification plan of the Mashed economy (2024-2028). In the future, progressive political measures are needed to trigger a new growth in productivity and to achieve a more balanced and high quality growth trajectory, ”he argues. In short, "sustained economic growth will depend on increased productivity."
 
“Capacity” to recover from negative deviations
In his analysis, the economist states that Macao "recorded five episodes of negative production deviations in the last three decades, the most serious of which it occurred during the Covid-19 pandemic." The longest, which lasted six years, began in the late 1990s, during the Asian financial crisis. However, "in terms of magnitude, the economy recorded its lowest point during the Covid-19 pandemic between 2020 and 2022, representing the worst negative deviation during the sample period."
Three other episodes of negative production deviations were also recorded, but which were “eliminated” within two years, as the economy recovered and effective production levels returned to its potential.
On the other hand, the economy recorded the largest positive deviations between 2013 and 2014, followed by 2017-2019. “The economy dived abruptly in the negative zone with the start of the pandemic in 2020. In terms of duration, the longest positive hiatus lasted four years in 2010-2014,” he says.
With regard to economic recovery after pandemic, the results suggest that “the economy has been robustly recovering from the great negative deviations during the crisis, and it is estimated that production in 2023 returned to its pre-standard tendency, effectively closing the tendency. production gap ”.
Given the observed results, Isabel W.T. Choy points out that "in terms of duration, most negative deviations were eliminated within two to three years in Macao, which partly reflects the capacity of the economy to gradually return to its potential level."</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Animal species and plants proliferate in ecological zones</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/especies-de-animais-plantas-proliferam-nas-zonas-ecologicas/</link><description>Animal species and plants in the ecological zones of Cotai continue to grow. Last year, 2,105 types were counted, including algae, mosses, fetuses, zooplankton, insects, fish, mammals, among others. DSPA stresses that the “richness of food resources” in that area of ​​the territory has brought to the place 198 species of birds to feed or rest there
 
Cotai ecological areas have attracted new visitors, judging by increasing the number of animals and plants. Currently, ecological zones I and II, whose total area extends by about 55 hectares, already gather more than two thousand species. The data released by the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) reveal that by the end of 2024 the ecological zones already gathered 2,105 types of animals and plants.
In concrete and regarding plants, by the end of last year, ecological areas had a total of 773 types, including 327 algae species, four moss, 22 fetuses, 11 gymnosperms and 413 angiosperms. Looking at the statistics of the previous year, we can see that new species of algae and angiosperms were found, since in 2023 had been accounted for 319 and 406, respectively.
As regards animals, 1,328 species were recorded, including 143 of zooplankton, 176 of benthic animals and 654 of insects. There are also 118 fish species, five amphibians, 22 reptiles and 12 mammals. In this case, new types of insects and fish were found, compared to the previous year, when 652 and 116 species were known, respectively.
"The richness of the food resources available there has led 198 bird species to choose the ecological zones as a place of rest or to feed, among which the black harvester (Platalea Minor), one, is included," one Rare bird integrated into the International Union Red List for Nature Conservation and Natural Resources (IUCN), DSPA stresses on its electronic page.
Ecological Zones I and II COTAI were completed in late 2003. In the middle of the following year, the Macao authorities hired a consulting company to ensure the management and maintenance of these environmental spaces, and systematically collecting it, data on data The bents, plants, birds, water quality and the surrounding environment.
DSPA asserts that "it has been striving to optimize the ecological environment of ecological zones, in order to provide a habitat and an environment of ideal food for migratory birds that come to winter in Macao." In this sense, and taking into account opinions collected from academic institutions, annual works have been developed on the banks of the ecological zone I outside the time of migration of birds.
These works involve, for example, “the dredging of channel's slams, the removal of herbs and reeds on the lake banks, the control of reed growth and the widening of the margin area, as well as the improvement of the environment of boundary birds, Bentonic animals and fish ”, underline environmental protection services, adding that, in recent years, the number of migratory birds that have been winter in the territory has kept a“ stable level ”.
Located Northeast of the Lotus Flor Bridge, the Ecological Zone I, which occupies 15 hectares, is an area of ​​conditionally open management. Two bird observatories were installed in the south dike of this zone, where aquatic shrubs, sugarcane fields and trees can be found, as well as water channels that connect the Shizimen channel.
The open management zone II is located on the west coast of Cotai, with the south of Coloane's WWTP and bordering the north with the Broadway Macau complex. It covers an area of ​​about 40 hectares, where three artificial islands and a slope for visits were built in the mudflasses, being rich in fauna and flora of the mangal, namely gray mangrove, mangrove “kandalia obovata”, “aegiceras corniculatum”, “acanthus ilicifolius ”, called-Maré and lodaded jumping.
 
Vao Hoi Ieong is again subdirector of DSPA
The Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, appointed, in Service Commission, Vai Hoi Ieong for the position of Deputy Director of the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA). The information, which was published yesterday in an Official Report, indicates that the appointment has effects from February 17 and for a period of one year. Vai Hoi Ieong had already held the same position, between June 2009 and June 2015, and was even director of the same organism (June 2015 to March 2016), and also went through the weather and geophysical services, so far as date . Degree in Chemical Engineering (University of Calgary, Canada), and Master in Environmental Engineering (Hong Kong Polytechnic University), Vai Hoi Ieong, who began his career in the civil service in 1999, also has a master's degree in Public Administration (National Institute China's administration).
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau won 5,881 tnr in a year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-ganhou-5-881-tnr-num-ano/</link><description>Within a year, the number of TNR in Macao grew 5,881 to a total of 182,542. If we look at the end of 2019, when the TNR peak was reached, with 196,538, the numbers represent about 93% of the labor then accounted for
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Macao had, at the end of last year, with 182,542 non -resident workers (TNR), an increase of 5,881 compared to the end of 2023, when 176,661 were counted, equivalent to an annual rise of 3.32%, show the data from the Public Security Police Corps, released by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL). If we look at the end of 2019, when the TNR peak was reached, a total of 196,538, the numbers are still below, but already represent about 93% of the labor then accounted for.
Compared to January 2023, when authorities ended the covid zero policy, there was an increase of 30,664 workers. This month, the labor coming from abroad, including from mainland China, had fallen to less than 151,878 TNR, the lowest number since April 2014.
Returning last year, statistics point out that a large slice of TNR (66%) originates from the interior of China, totaling 121.161, followed by the Philippines (30,912 or about 17% of the total), Vietnam (8,261 TNR ), Indonesia (7,418), Myanmar (4,314), Nepal (3,776) and Hong Kong (2,228).
The sector of hotels, restaurants and the like accounted for 53,948 TNR at the end of last year, representing 29.55% of the total imported labor. Used, the number did not reach the volume of 2019, when there were 54,749 TNR in this sector. In the end of 2023, hotels, restaurants and the like hired another 4,561 TNR. This had been the area most affected by loss of labor in the Covid-19 years, during which more than 17,600 TNR have been dismissed since the end of the pre-pound year.
The second sector that hired the most was that of families with maids, which won 1,678 TNR, rising to a total of 27,435 (15% of imported labor). For the area of ​​cultural and recreational activities, another 1,418 workers were imported, with the sector to finish the year with 11,372 TNR. This area includes casinos, and in this case there was an increase of 913 workers to 4,446.
 
Construction lost more than 4,500 tnr
On the other hand, the construction sector lost, within a year, more than four thousand TNR. At the end of 2024, Macao had 25,641 workers from abroad in the construction area, less 4,568 than a year earlier. Still, the sector is third in terms of the “weight” of imported labor, representing 14% of the total.
In fourth place is the area of ​​real estate activities and services provided to companies, representing 13% of total TNR, with 23,647 workers. Also in this case, there were 1,023 at the end of 2023. In the opposite direction, the thick and retail trade-which equals 12% of the universe of labor from abroad-raised 725, with counting on counting on 21,279.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Bank exploration results decreased by 21% last year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/resultados-de-exploracao-dos-bancos-diminuiram-21-ano-passado/</link><description>Macao banks operational profits fell more than one fifth by 2024 to four billion patacas, marking the fourth consecutive homologous descent and the lowest since 2010. The breakdown essentially derived from the 18.3% reduction on margin of fees
 
The Macao bank sector ended the 2024 accounts with total operational profits of 4.01 billion patacas, which has been the lowest since 2010 and represents a decrease of 21.3% compared to the 5.09 billion accounted for in 2023. According to the statistical data released by the Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM), the results of bank exploration thus suffered the fourth consecutive annual break, contrary to 12 years of growth, including 10 successive records from 2011.
The decrease in profits by 2024 was essentially due to a drop of 18.3%to 16.1 billion patacas on the interest margin, the difference between loan revenues and deposit expenses. This after the AMCM approved three descents of the main reference interest rate in the last three months of 2024, the last of which a 0.25 percentage points, introduced on December 19, following the US Federal Reserve.
On the other hand, after several months up, the bank sector operating costs eventually dropped 6.8% in the general calculation of 2024 to 21.41 billion patacas. Provisions for bank credit impairment, which represented 45.6% of operating costs, decreased 16.3% to 9.76 billion.
The loans, the main source of revenue of the worldwide banking, decreased 7.2% compared to the end of December 2023, setting at 1.01 billion of patacas. On the contrary, deposits with Macau banks increased 4%to 1.27 billion of patacas in late 2024.
As reported yesterday the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the “non-productive” credit (NPL, in the English acronym) in local banking institutions was 56.07 billion patacas at the end of last year, illustrating an annual increase of 30, 3% or 13.04 billion and reaching a new record in the territory, according to AMCM data. The NPL, which includes loans with delays of over 90 days, grew more than 20 times or 53.30 billion compared to the end of 2019, the pre-pound year, and recorded increases in 21 of the last 22 months.
Overdue loans accounted for 5.5% of Macao banks loans at the end of 2024, plus 1.6 percentage points within one year, and the percentage rises to 6.9% if we consider credit to institutions or individuals only to consider credit to credit or individuals non-residents. The European Banking Authority, the EU regulatory agency, for example, considers that banks with at least 5% of bad loans have “high exposure” at risk and should establish a strategy to solve the problem.
Still, the NPL ratio in Macao is far from the 25.3% record reached in mid -2001, in the world's economic crisis caused by the outbreak of the speculative bubble of companies linked to the internet.
In the first “Monetary and Financial Stability Review” report of 2025, AMCM's Department of Studies and Statistics stressed that “Macau's financial system has shown continuous resilience, supported by solid capital and liquidity positions”. "Capitalization and the liquidity position of the bank sector remains solid, providing robust support to financial stability and sufficient resources to respond to future demand for credit," he says, recognizing, on the other hand, that "uncertainties about rhythm FROM FOMC FUCKING CUTS FOMC [US Federal Reserve Federal Market Committee] require vigilant credit risk management by Macao banks and an agile response to changes in macrofinance conditions. ”
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Most tattoos in South Korea are clandestine and can lead to prison</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/maioria-das-tatuagens-na-coreia-sul-sao-clandestinas-podem-levar-prisao/</link><description>Narr worked as a tattoo artist in South Korea two years ago when he had a frightening experience. “When the tattoo session was about to finish, I asked the customer to check the mirror tattoo,” she says. "Instead, he started to open the pants zipper, revealing that he didn't wear underwear."
Narr politely told him to climb the zipper and left the room, but when he came back, he was still showing off and said anything like: “Do you want to make a movie with me? We have a bed and there's no one here. ”
“I was really scared, and told him to stop the game. I answered casually because I was afraid that it was anger or fear could make things worse. And if that happened, I would not have been able to report to the police. ”
Narr did not feel able to go to the police because, since a 1992 Supreme Court ruling, the tattoo has been classified as a medical procedure in South Korea. In practice, this means that you have to have a medical license to get a tattoo.
Anyone who gets a tattoo without medical credentials faces severe penalties, including up to five years in prison or a fine of up to 50 million Korean wons (about 275,000 patacas).
There are no official statistics on how many tattoo artists have been processed, but the South Korea Tattoo Union says it annually gives legal support to at least 50 and believes there are many more cases - possibly hundreds - that tend to end in fines.
Despite the rules, mostly, tattoo artists in South Korea, as Narr, are not licensed doctors.
According to an approximate estimate of the Ministry of Health and Welfare, in 2021, there were about 350,000 tattoo artists in the country, with the majority specialized in semi-permanent makeup for areas such as eyebrows, lips and hair line. Excluding these semi -permanent tattoo artists, the number drops to something between 20,000 and 30,000, according to the Tattoo Union.
In recent years, the South Korean courts have acquitted several non-medical professionals for tattooing, signaling a change in attitudes and now there are increasing requests for change in legislation.
Last year, both the Popular Power Party (PPP) and the main opposition party, the Democratic Korea Party (DPK), presented projects on tattoo artists, which aim to make legal to doctors to get tattoos.
"I often think that Congress is the last place that properly reflects public opinion," says DPK representative Kang Sun-Woo, who presented a similar bill in January. The deputy adds that only 1.4% of people in South Korea with tattoos did them with a medical professional, highlighting the need for legal reform.
However, the Korean Medical Association (KMA) recently issued a statement expressing strong opposition and serious concern for the proposals.
The association said that “tattooing not only damages the skin, but can also pose other health risks, including interference in the diagnosis of cancer”, adding that “tattooing is fundamentally a medical procedure, and its growing popularity does not reduce risks associated ”.
If the legislation is approved, it should be accompanied by clear rules on licensing and “rigid regulations to ensure that the tattoo is done hygienically and safe” to protect customers, says Lee Kwang-Jun, dermatologist and KMA member.
Including semi -permanent treatments, a quarter of people in the country tattooed, according to a June 2021 survey conducted by Gallup Korea. When these treatments are excluded, the number drops to 5%.
In addition to protecting customers, new laws would also protect tattoo artists like narr. She finally managed to persuade the client who exposed herself, to leave, but the trial played a role in her decision to close her studio a few months later. Now he works in a shared studio with several other tattoo artists.
“I feel much more comfortable there,” he concludes.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-02-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>