<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Economy must remain “stable” but there are “potential risks”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/economia-deve-manter-se-estavel-mas-ha-potenciais-riscos/</link><description>The MSAR economy should remain “stable” in the coming months, but there are several indicators that “reflect potential risks”, warns the Economic Association. These include, for example, the “price of game companies' actions”, the “Chinese consumer confidence rate” and the “resident loan and deposit ratio in local banks”. The association also warned of the “pressure” that the closing of the 11 satellite casinos could cause in the surrounding areas
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The Macao Economic Association foresees that, between June and August, the territory economy should remain “at a stable level”, given that the economic perspective index could remain at about 5.9 points. However, in the latest study it has elaborated, it warns that "several indicators reflect potential risks that should not be ignored."
Indicators with pessimistic predictions include “actions of the six integrated tourism and leisure companies”, the “Chinese consumer confidence index”, the “resident loan and deposits ratio in local banks” and the “housing property price index”. The association considers, according to the various data analyzed, that these indicators may be “at a low level”.
Among the indicators with optimistic predictions is the “unemployment rate”. In this context, the association points out that, in the period under analysis, the active population should remain between 470 thousand and 480 thousand people, "which means a low level of unemployment rate."
In this sense and taking into account the recent unemployment rate, he warns: "It is noted that employment pressure has recorded a slight increase, and the Macao labor market may record some subtle changes."
The Economic Association also refers to the closure of the 11 satellite casinos. "With the end of the operations of various satellite casinos, this situation may result in great pressure on the commercial vitality of some community neighborhoods," read the report.
Before the end of the year, all satellite casinos, under SJM, Melco and Galaxy, will close doors-however, SJM intends to “rescue” two of these spaces through the acquisition of the properties of hotels where Ponte 16 and Le Royal Arc casinos are located.
The decision of the game companies involves almost 6,000 jobs, which will be secured by the operators, the authorities guaranteed. With the closure of these spaces, also hundreds of small and medium -sized companies will suffer and consequently their employees. About 400 workers will be directly affected by a total of 800 who are employed in those stores.
Moreover, he recalled that, in general, the Malparado credit ratio recorded a break in three consecutive months, which means that, preliminarily, it has entered a good trend, "however, the Macao residents of residents of Macao and the ratio in a high level."
In addition, the housing property price rate has decreased to 203.6 points in April, the lowest level in the last three years, "which reflects that the local real estate market continues to live a poor conjuncture, where trust in investment is not enough."
On the other hand, the range of loans and deposits of residents at local banks continued to decrease, to 50.9%, which has established the lowest registration in the last 10 years, showing the lack of consumption among residents. In addition, the level of deposits is “evidently higher” than demand for loans. "In this context, it is difficult for the capital to be effectively transformed into a driving force of physical economy," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Infrastructure Forum registers $ 10 million agreements</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/forum-de-infra-estruturas-regista-acordos-de-10-milhoes-de-dolares/</link><description>Cooperation protocols worth more than US $ 10 billion were signed during the infrastructure Forum that took place for three days. Some projects involve companies from Portuguese -speaking and Macao countries in areas such as transportation, construction and electricity. More than two hundred contact scholarship sessions were also organized, covering local and hengqin companies, meaning an increase of more than 30% compared to the previous year
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The 16th edition of the Forum and International Exhibition on Investment Investment and Construction (IIICF) provided the signature of 31 cooperation protocols, worth about $ 10.1 billion. The agreements provide for cooperation in domains such as transport, construction, electricity, water resources and renewable energy in 22 countries and regions.
About one third of the projects involve companies from Portuguese -speaking (PLP) and Macau countries. "Over the three days of the event, more than 200 contact scholarship sessions were organized, more than 70 of which were attended by companies from Macau and Hengqin, representing an increase of more than 30% compared to the 52 sessions last year," said a statement released by the Institute for Commerce and Investment Promotion (IPIM).
These results “further highlight the role of Macao as a sino-sirophone platform, as well as the efforts of this region in the proactive joint with national development strategies, especially the construction of the large bay,” adds IPIM.
At the closing press conference, IPIM President Vincent U said the record number of ministerial level leaders "demonstrates the growing internationalization and the continuous increase in the event level." From its perspective, the Forum not only “boosted international cooperation in infrastructure”, but also “generated estimated revenues of about 20 million patacas for the convention and exhibition assembly sector and contributed to the Macao High Gama Business Tourism market”.
The event was attended by more than 3,500 professionals from the World Infrastructure Sector, from over 70 countries and regions around the world, as well as a new record in terms of the presence of high-level guests, specifically with almost 70 ministerial leaders. More than 250 thematic and complementary activities were scheduled.
Meanwhile, the “premiere@macau-launch ceremony of the innovative achievements in international infrastructure” received the support of 11 companies listed at Fortune Global 500, among the 250 largest international contractors, considered leaders of the industrial or renowned brand chain. These companies provided the debut of 30 products and infrastructure technologies.
According to IPIM, PLP representatives recognized the effective role of Macao as a platform to create contacts between companies and institutions in China and Lusophone countries, having revealed that they have achieved cooperation agreements with companies in the interior of China in the areas of Information Technology and Electric Engineering.
 
China will increase support to Mozambique
The Minister of Foreign Affairs and Cooperation of Mozambique said that China will increase support to her country, especially in projects in health and infrastructure. Maria Lucas, who spoke in Macau on the sidelines of a meeting with China's Foreign Minister, Wen He, said the meeting exceeded her expectations, especially with the announcement of a reinforcement of Chinese support to Mozambique in several key areas. According to Lusa, the minister indicated that Wen said that support for Mozambique serves, above all, to galvanize the implementation of the project on the construction of the Surgical Center of Maputo Central Hospital and a Health Training Center in Sofala. Maria Lucas assured that Mozambique is prepared to receive Chinese investments and bring trade between the two countries to higher levels.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Elderly killed his wife for not liking dinner</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/idoso-matou-esposa-por-nao-gostar-jantar/</link><description>Being dissatisfied with a dinner prepared by his wife, with whom he married 50 years ago, a 74 -year resident will have deadly 71 -year -old wife. The case happened on Friday afternoon in a fraction in Praia Grande. According to PJ, the suspect was mentally stable when he was arrested
 
A retired 74 -year -old resident was arrested by police on suspicion of qualified homicide, after allegedly stabbed his 71 -year -old wife using a knife to cut bones. According to information released by the Judicial Police (PJ), the case occurred last Friday afternoon, and the suspect will have committed the crime because he was dissatisfied with the dinner prepared by his wife.
The couple initially had verbal and physical conflicts in the kitchen of the fraction that lived in Praia Grande, and the victim suffered serious injuries and eventually died, although he was still assisted at the hospital. In the victim's body, at least 16 injuries were found caused by stabbing, especially in the head and neck, PJ said.
The man was sent to the prosecutor on suspicion of qualified homicide. When he was arrested, the suspect was mentally stable, presenting various lacerations on the skin of the head that did not need points. According to PJ, the individual collaborated with the police investigation.
For almost 50 years of marriage, the couple often had verbal conflicts due to everyday issues. However, according to the authorities, the two had never made any complaints to the police due to family conflicts.
This time, it was the daughter of the couple who warned the police after seeing their parents lying in the kitchen. In the kitchen washbasin, the agents found, besides the knife, a sharp scissors, also with bloodstains. The preliminary investigation indicates that the victim was stabbed several times by the suspect with the knife until the woman fell to the kitchen floor.
 
Fake wedding with promise to fulfill
In another case, police detained two suspects of fake marriage, specifically a 50 -year -old resident and a man from the interior of China after his wife reported the police because he did not receive a reward of 100,000 Renminbis promised by the fake husband.
According to the Public Security Police Corps, the resident married this man in 2015, helping him become a permanent resident of Macao. However, the promise of 100,000 Renminbis was not fulfilled, and lost contact with the "husband."
On the 10th of this month, the man was intercepted at Qingmao's border post while trying to enter Macao. To the authorities, the detainee admitted the false marriage.
 
More than 100 burlads for false customer support services
Between early April and mid -May, more than 100 people were deceived through fraudulent telephone calls, made by individuals who presented themselves as representatives of client support services on online payment platforms, reveals the secretary's new monthly article for security. Appealing to the public to stay aware of the constant changes in the fraudulent schemes, Wong Sio Chak admitted that, due to the sophistication of the modus operandi of criminal groups, the work to combat the crosswords still face long -term challenges. However, the Judicial Police (PJ) warned that some citizens recently received false emails, pretending to be from the government of the Masters and mentioning the pecuniary reimbursement plan. In addition, the PJ has recorded, in recent days, several complaints against fraudulent telephone calls, in which the burns have passed representatives of customer support services of "Alipay".</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysis of check requirements starts on the 18th</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/analise-de-requerimentos-de-cheques-arranca-dia-18/</link><description>Next Wednesday, the Social Security Fund will begin the analysis of requests submitted by residents who have not preliminarily fulfilled the requirements of attribution of the checking checks
 
From 18 June, residents, “who do not preliminarily fulfill the assignment requirements” of pecuniary reimbursement checks, will be able to submit the request for attribution, through the “Cash Plan for Economic Development” page of the Single Account. Requests may be made until December 31, 2028, according to the Social Communication Office.
The request can also be sent to the Aparta Box No. 3094 or delivered, personally or by third party, at the special counters of the Institute's Service Center for Municipal Affairs, Rua Nova da Areia Preta, and the Mashare das Islas, at Rua de Coimbra, as well as the service centers to the Central Zone or the islands, at the Pai Van Seac Van station.
The Social Security Fund (FSS) will begin to analyze the requirements and their documents from this Wednesday, within 10 business days. The FSS will notify the applicants about the result and send to the direction of finance services the list of residents who meet the requirements for the assignment, contacting residents in case "additional information" is required.
"If the applicant has requested, for the same reason, the attribution of the amounts of the plan, it is dismissed to proceed, again, to the formalities related to the attribution of funds as an extraordinary office of budgetary balances of the non-mandatory central social security regime," read the statement.
Residents must receive the amount, by check or by bank transfer, about a month after being notified. The amounts of the monetary reimbursement will be assigned "when the 183 -day requirement in Macau is fulfilled after verification and calculation."
According to the Administrative Regulation, those who are absent from Macao are considered to have been in Macau for attending a “recognized on -site” higher education course, for living in the interior in China, having completed 65 years or for health reasons, for providing work outside Macao to an EMS employer or being responsible for the subsistence of their household, or resident, resident, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing, residing Study in the in -depth cooperation zone or by working in the cities of mainland China integrated in the Great Bay.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>What was the impact of Israelite attacks on Iran's nuclear program?</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/actual/qual-tera-sido-impacto-dos-ataques-israelitas-programa-nuclear-irao/</link><description>EPA12173611 HOUTHHI SUPPORTERS HOLD A BANNER Showing Iranian Officials (R-L) Major General Gholam Ali Rashid, Hossein Salami, Commander-in-Chief of Iran's Elite Revolutionary Guards Corps, and Major General Mohammad Bagheri, Who Were Killed in Israel's Recent AIRSTRIKES, During an Anti-Us and Anti-Israel Protest in Sana'a, Yemen, 13 June 2025. Thousands of Houthi Supporters Demonstrated Against US Support for Israel's Military Operation in the Gaza Strip and Iran. HOUTHHI LEADER ABDUL-MALIK AL-HOUTHHI STATED IN A TEELVISED SPEECH THAT HIS GROUP HAD FIED 11 BALLISTIC AND HYPERSONIC MISSILES AND DRONES AT ISRAELI TARGETS IN THE PAST WEEK, IN THE NEW SCALATION IN THE GROUP'S CONTINUED SUPPORT FOR THE PALETINIAN PEOPLE IN GAZA.  EPA/YAHYA ARHAB



The unprecedented attack launched by Israel against Iran on Friday hit the Islamic Nuclear Program, but experts interviewed by AFP say the impact so far has been limited. The operation will last "how many days are necessary," warned the Israelite PM, Benjamin Netanyahu, who justified the attack claiming to have information that Iran approached a "point without return" in obtaining a nuclear weapon. "Israel may harm Iran's nuclear program, but it is unlikely to be able to destroy it," said Vaez, a researcher at the International Crisis Group, an American "Think Tank". The reason, he explains, is that Israel does not have the powerful bombs necessary “to destroy the fortified facilities of Natanz and Ford”, buried underground. For this, it would need “US military assistance,” confirms Kelsey Davenport of the Arms Control Association. The knowledge acquired by Tehran cannot be destroyed, although nine scientists died in the attacks, he adds. The International Atomic Energy Agency (AIEA), citing information from Iranian authorities, said the attack "destroyed" the part on the surface of the Natanz uranium enrichment installation in the center of the country. This destruction, confirmed by satellite images, is “significant,” according to the Institute of International Science and Security (ISIS), an American organization specializing in nuclear proliferation. Electric power attacks "can cause serious damage" to thousands of centrifuges used to enrich uranium, "if reserve batteries are sold out." Isis believes Natanz "will be unable to operate for a while." The other uranium enrichment center, Ford, south of Tehran, was also attacked, but, according to the Iranian authorities, suffered less serious damage. The Isfahan Conversion Center in the center of the country has also been the target of Israeli attacks. This complex allegedly housed large highly enriched uranium reserves. What happened to these reserves? For now, it is impossible to know. “If I will be able to transfer some to secret facilities, Israel will have lost the game,” emphasizes Vaez. The UN nuclear agency did not report an increase in radiation levels around the various areas. "There is very little risk that attacks on uranium enrichment facilities cause liberation of hazardous radioactive particles," said Davenport. But an attack on the Bushehr Nuclear Center in the south of the country could have “serious consequences for health and the environment,” he added. Nuclear facilities “should never be attacked, regardless of the context or circumstances, as this can damage the population and the environment,” insisted the General Director of AIEA, Rafael Grossi. The question is still: Iran was really close to getting an atomic bomb? It is true that after unilateral US withdrawal from the International Nuclear Agreement in 2018, Iran gradually detached itself from certain obligations and accelerated uranium enrichment well above the 3.67%limit. In mid -May, it was 408.6 kg of 60% enriched uranium, close to the 90% needed to project an atomic bomb. Iran is the only state without nuclear weapons that produces this type of material, AIEA said, which mourned Tehran's lack of cooperation. However, “the agency has no reliable indications of a structured nuclear program” focused on the acquisition of nuclear weapons, as may have occurred in the past. Tehran denies having such ambitions. "So far, the costs associated with militarization have surpassed the benefits. But this calculation may change in the coming weeks," warns Davenport. "The Israelite attacks pushed Iran back technically, but politically approached it to nuclear weapons," he added. Mainly because now there is a “real risk of diversion of enriched uranium”, an operation that “can go unnoticed for weeks,” as current attacks prevent AEEA inspectors from accepting locations.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Storm signs lifted for five days</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sinais-de-tempestade-icados-durante-cinco-dias/</link><description>After the first sign of tropical storm was lifted on Wednesday, all yesterday were canceled all signs. Over the course of several days, signs 1 and 3 have been interspersed, but the territory was not much affected, except for the classes of some levels of education, which were suspended
 
All signs of tropical storm were canceled at 3:30 pm yesterday, indicated the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG), due to the passage of “Wutip”. Although the storm has extended over several days, the truth is that Macau was not very affected, except for the classes of children's, primary and special teachings that were suspended.
It was on Wednesday that the authorities lifted signal 1, which was in force for 24 hours. The next day, also at six in the morning, the SMG went up to number 3, which went back to 6 pm on the same day, again to sign 1. On Friday, the same signal remained and only at 08:00 am on Saturday morning did SMG again.
Swords and strong winds were felt in the territory. Yesterday, the SMG predicted that today and tomorrow "remain frequent and thunderstorm, sometimes strong due to the influence of high altitude disturbance." However, it is expected that time in the region “gradually improves”.
The "Wutip", the first typhoon of the season, passed Haião, and then reached Guangdong, according to Xinhua. The Wutip arrived in Haião around 8 pm on Friday, and weakened to a severe tropical storm, with winds of about 100 kilometers per hour.
After passing near the city of Dongfang around 11 pm, Wutip went to the Northeast, returning to Tonkin's Gulf and recovering the Typhoon Statute, according to the Zoom.Earth Meteorological Platform. The "Wutip" played back on land that day in Guangdong province.
Typhoon brought heavy rainfall, strong winds and interrupted various transportation services to the coastal provinces of southern China, where more than 12,000 people were taken from their homes.
The “Wutip” is the first typhoon of the time in China, but its formation was over two months late in the usual beginning of the season, which usually occurs at the end of March. Experts attribute the delay in a system of unusual subtropical pressure and the late arrival of the summer monsoon to the southern sea of ​​China, factors that inhibited the necessary tropical convection for the development of cyclones.
 
Deputy suggests use of AI to prevent flooding
Ngan Iek Hang suggested the introduction of artificial intelligence in monitoring water levels in order to reinforce flood prevention measures. In a written interpellation, and with the entry at the time of typhoons, the deputy was concerned about the masters' ability to deal with floods and the consequences of tropical storms. In addition to questioning the government that measures are being prepared to optimize flood prevention, Ngan Iek Hang warned of the risk of landslide caused by heavy rainfall. In this sense, he asked the authorities to accelerate the stabilization of slopes in the territory and reinforce inspections to degraded buildings.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>TSI relieves penalties for defendants accused of falsifying documents</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/tsi-alivia-penas-para-arguidos-acusados-de-falsificar-documentos/</link><description>Law, Judge and Closeup of Lawyer with Gavel for Justice, Court Hearing and Legal Trial for Magistrate. Government, Attorney Career and Zoom of Desk for Investigation, Criminal Case and Verdict Order



The Court of Second Instance partially accepted the appeal filed by four defendants, convicted by the Judicial Court to falsify documents. The penalties of the four recurrents were relieved, with suspended execution for three years. Crimes refer to a case dating back to 2006, in which five people falsified documents to obtain permanent resident status
 
The Collective Court of the Court of Second Instance (TSI) has granted a partial granting to the appeal filed by four individuals, accused by the Public Prosecution Service and convicted by the Base Judicial Court for the commission of a document forgery. The collective court understood that the penalty of three years and three months in effect, determined by the TJB, was “slightly excessive” and should be changed and suspended in its execution, considering “the fact that they were primary delinquents and has passed some time since the commitment of the crime”, according to a note from the office of the last court.
The counterfeit crimes refer to a case dating back to July 2006, in which the four recurrents will have helped a fifth element to falsify public buying and selling real estate deeds in the Macao Permanent Resident Identity (BIR) identity. Three of the defendants who turned to TSI claimed that “they only participated in the act of the 'public deed celebration'” and not in the process of obtaining the BIR, adding that their crimes had already prescribed.
For TSI, the BIR "was sought by all defendants," so they "should be punished as co-authors." The collective court indicated that “reimbursement did not require the mandatory participation of each of the defendants in all acts of the criminal plan” and that the existence of the joint crime practice “was already sufficient for the defendant to be fully responsible for all criminal action”.
The five defendants committed the criminal acts imputed to them “with common determination and in conjugation of efforts and distribution of tasks,” the collective court said. In addition, the crime of falsification of a joint document ended only on June 20, 2014, when the statute of permanent resident was requested, "having not expired the period of prescription of 10 years of the crime." One of the applicants now faces a sentence of two years and nine months in prison, while the other three were sentenced to two years and six months, all suspended in their execution for three years.
In 2006, a couple from the interior of China agreed to require a residence permit for the man, with the competent authority of the MSAR and through real estate investments. The objective would later ask BIR for the couple's wife and three children, with the foundation of “being members of the household”. Having no resources to acquire a property, the couple decided to ask for help from three people with properties in the MSAR.
In July of the same year, the man bought a property for $ 510,000 from Hong Kong to two people, and these, following the signature of the public deed of purchase and sale, returned the money through family and friends. In the same month, the man bought another property, worth 530,000 dollars from Hong Kong, to a fifth person, who would also return the amount to him.
In September of this year, the main defendant opened an account on a bank and deposited Hong Kong's dollars half a million dollars, to request the residence permit for the “immigration for real estate investments” regime, as well as their extension to members of their household.
In 2007, the non -permanent resident identity tickets of the MSAR were awarded and, seven years later, the man presented the request to acquire the status of permanent resident for himself and his family, having raised suspicions of the commissioner against corruption regarding the process of acquisition of real estate.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>NAM VAN AND TAPA MARKET RECEIVE OPTIMIZATION WORKS</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/nam-van-mercado-da-taipa-recebem-obras-de-optimizacao/</link><description>Today begins the works of optimization of the tours of Panoramic Avenue of Lake Nam Van and peripheral areas. On Wednesday it is the turn of the beginning of the beautification of the foreign market and the creation of space for meals
 
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) will start this week Improvement works on the Tours of Panoramic Avenue of Lake Nam Van and peripheral areas, and abroad of the Taipa Market.
Today it starts the work of the Nam Van Lake Zone, where AMI will replace the tours, raising the non -slip safety level, increasing afforestation and leisure facilities, and transforming the existing bus stop into a bay stop.
The works must be completed at the end of this year, and during the execution period, the work area of ​​the work, which is located between Jorge Álvares Square stop and the Lake View Mansion building, with an area of ​​about 3,300 square meters. Improvements consist of replacing coating with more non-slip coating with a view to increasing safety and improving night lighting.
In addition, the location of the streets crossing by pedestrians will be adjusted, as well as extended the waiting space of the plates and the dynamic line of passers -by in the streets crossing, in order to prevent them from passing through ventilation exits. The AMI will also optimize existing afforestation by the entrance to the parking lot.
In addition, at the request of the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT), the existing bus stop will be transformed into a bay stop, “minimizing the eventual impact on road flow and passenger passenger flows,” says a note of the two organisms.
Among the main changes, Jorge Álvares Square Business Stop will be temporarily deactivated, being replaced by a provisional (about 40 meters from the original, towards the Macao Tower), to the service of careers 6B, 9, 18, 18b, 23, 28b, 32 and n2. Between October and November a new phase of traffic conditioning will be implemented.
Meanwhile, AMI will, from Wednesday, be able to beautify the exterior of the mud market and creation of area for meals. However, the works will not affect the normal functioning of the market.
The goal is to beautify the architectural façade of the market and create meals and cafeteria zones. Large outdoor LED screen will be installed, “so as to provide traders and consumers a more comfortable shopping environment, giving gastronomy and new consumer experiences with macao cultural and creative characteristics,” said AMI.
During this period, market entrances and exits and elevators will be phased. The work should be completed before the fourth quarter of this year.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao on the marches of Lisbon to expand European market</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-nas-marchas-de-lisboa-para-expandir-mercado-europeu/</link><description>The presence of Macau in the popular marches of Lisbon served to expand markets from visitors from Europe and deepen the cultural and tourist exchange between the two sides. This year, the sgas was represented in the parade by the group "Street Dance", which presented the dance of the Dourado Peixe Lantern. The Rua Performative Artists of the Master opened the parade on Avenida da Liberdade, presenting performances that mixed costumes of Chinese culture with modern hip hop style



















Victor Rebelo*
 
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) went back to Portugal to participate in the Lisbon parties, leading a street dance group of Macau to participate in the popular marches that took place at Avenida da Liberdade, integrated into the festivities program to celebrate Santo António.
The Association of Macau Street Dance opened the parade and showed the characteristics of Macao's multicultural coexistence, “deepening the cultural and tourist exchange between the two sides, which contributes to the continuous expansion of visitors from Portugal and Europe”, according to a STD statement.
After STD organized a Dragon Dance team in 2024, this year the performance groups presented actions that mixed outfits of Chinese culture with modern hip hop dance style, interacting with residents and visitors of the Portuguese capital.
The parade served to show Macau's “singular charm” as “Tourism + Culture” and its image as an international tourist city of cultural exchange between the East and the West.
This typically Portuguese festivity takes place for more than a month, one of the most important tourist events and popular celebrations in the city, attracting thousands of residents and visitors every year, including popular marches, with over 90 years of history. Annually, on the night of June 12, the Santo António is celebrated, with television broadcast to the Portuguese Language Cultural World.
The Lisbon parties are organized by the Lisbon City Council's Cultural Equipment and Animation Management Company, and in 2012, STD and the company started an exchange program, having promoted the mutual participation of the artistic groups on both sides at the Lisbon Festival parade and the Chinese New Year's Parade in Macau, “in order to promote cooperation in the areas of culture and tourism, as well as mutual visits,” adds the STD.
 
“Street Dance” opened the parade
The Lusa agency states that the “Association of Macau Street Dance” opened the parade, followed by the children's march of the schools of Lisbon and the three non-controlling marches: “The voice of the worker”, markets and Santa Casa. The Alma de Lisboa was the central theme of this year's edition of the Great March of Lisbon, with lyrics and music by Gimba, played by all participating groups (besides the own songs). The event gathered more than 1,800 participants.
Alcântara and Bairro Alto won the Popular Marches Contest with the Bica March, which won in the 2023 edition, to be classified in third position. 17 other groups were exhibited, such as Alfama (4th place), Madragoa (5th) and Marvila (6th). In 2024, Alcântara had been the winner.
São Vicente and Alcântara gained in the categories of best choreography and best scenography, respectively. The best costume was also attributed to both gears.
The distinction of the best lyrics was to Alcântara, a group that shared the award for best musicality with Bairro Alto, Bica and Marvila.
In the category of best original composition, Bica occupied the first opposition, with “half door, door and a half”, while the best parade on the avenue went to the marches of Bairro Alto, Bica and Madragoa.
 
*With Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Graduates 1,500 UPM students</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/graduados-1-500-estudantes-da-upm/</link><description>More than 1,500 students from the Polytechnic University of Macao (UPM) were graduated, including the first graduates of the University of Beijing and UPM University Nursing Academy of the Center for Health Sciences Center and UPM
 
More than 1,500 doctoral students, masters and degree graduated from the Macao Polytechnic University (UPM) at the end of the last school year. The newly graduates, from more than 30 courses, include the first graduates from the Academy of Nursing at the University of Beijing and UPM Health Sciences Center. The undergraduate ceremony took place at the UPM multi-sport pavilion and was chaired by the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM, which recognized the contribution of the institution “to the construction and expansion of the“ ‘Sino-Madophone platform” ”, says the statement.
The secretary recognized “the results obtained by the UPM in promoting educational cooperation between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries and the formation of qualified bilingual frames in Chinese and Portuguese”. The LAM also mentioned that the Government of MSAR has been “constantly optimizing the distribution of resources, raising the level of scientific education and research”, and reinforced cooperation between sectors, increasing investment and support for higher education.
LAM also said that “the university will continue to develop its pedagogical and research advantages in the areas of artificial intelligence, 'Big Health', languages ​​and translation and sports sciences,” according to the UPM statement.
In turn, Marcus Im, rector of UPM, asserted that the university has based on its pedagogical activities in the principle “Love for the Fatherland and Macao”. He stressed the fact that the institution achieved “a comprehensive leap in diverse education” and “profound results in the integral development of students”.
Marcus IM also stressed that “characteristics of interdisciplinary and interregional scientific innovation centered on artificial intelligence” were formed. Finally, the rector encouraged the graduates to be "guardians of the" love for the homeland and Macau "principle, practitioners of 'diversity and inclusion' and realization and innovation.
The representative of the graduates, Benedict Valentine Sheryl Law, thanked the government for the “significant investment and long -term support in higher education”, for the “interdisciplinary formation of qualified frames”, for “dedication and confidence of teachers”, and families “for care and incentive”. In a Portuguese message encouraged the newly graduates to “overcome difficulties and achieve success”, ending with the Portuguese proverb “Calm Mar Never Made Good Marinheiro”.
Among the four thousand present at the ceremony were also the head of the Department of Education and Youth Affairs of the Central Government Cabinet in the Central Government, Li Xuefei, and Guo Xiaofeng, director of the Department of General Affairs of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Popular Republic of China, among others.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Book and photographs mark five centuries of Camões</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/livro-fotografias-assinalam-cinco-seculos-de-camoes/</link><description>The Portuguese Institute of the East will present the work “The Vast Empire of the Heart”, at the Consulate General of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong, on Wednesday. The presentation of Sara Augusto's book will be accompanied by a photographic exhibition, in the Chancellery
 
Sara Augusto's book “The Vast Empire of Heart” will be presented at the Dr. Stanley Ho auditorium of the Portuguese Consulate-General in Macao and Hong Kong, at 6:30 pm next Wednesday, June 18. At the same time, a photographic exhibition will be inaugurated, in the consulate's Chancellery, to accompany and amplify the publication.
The anthological work, which resulted from a study of the author, deals with “the visitation of Camões in the literature of Macao in Portuguese”, according to a statement from the Portuguese Institute of the East (IPOR). For the book, Sara Augusto brought together "records of literary texts, prose and poetry, from Portuguese writers who passed through Macau, others who lived or live in the territory" and reveal "the ties that unite these voices around the figure of Camões."
In parallel, the exhibition invites a "poetic look" over the garden and the cave of Camões, "emblematic place where a small bust of the poet has become a point of literary pilgrimage" and a "mythical and deeply human" space. The show “of shadows, daily gestures, dances, games, laughs and silences” can be visited between June 19 and 30, from 9:30 am to 6 pm.
Organized by IPOR, with the support of the consulate and the mission structure of the celebrations of the vy centenary of the birth of Luís de Camões, the initiative "celebrates not only the power of the word, but also that of imagination and time." For the Institute, "the exhibition and the anthology highlight how Camões continues to inspire generations, transcending borders and ages."
The event serves to mark the poet's fifth centenary, “the largest exponent of Portuguese literature and symbol of the universalist vocation of Portuguese language and culture”, can be read in the statement.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>11 proposals for exploration of six self-siles</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/admitidas-11-propostas-para-exploracao-de-seis-auto-silos/</link><description>The public tender for the granting of the exploitation of the public parking service of six authorses received 12 candidacy proposals, indicated the management of services for traffic issues (DSAT), which received a letter of withdrawal from the contest. "Following the assessment of the opening committee of the proposals, 11 competing companies were admitted, which presented proposals for quarterly basis between 1.068 million patacas and 3.5 million patacas," the body explained. According to DSAT, a company was excluded due to “voluntary withdrawal”. At stake are the self-siles of Jardim Comendador Ho Yin, Rua de Malaca, Mong Sin Building, Mong In Building, Tranquility and Rua do Almirante Sérgio. The deadline for granting the exploitation of the public parking service of the six auto-silos is six years, covering 1,119 seats for light cars and 1,772 for motorcycles and mopeds. The concessionaire will be responsible not only for the management and daily exploitation of the auto-subsi, but also for the optimization of the electronic and without contact system, the reinforcement of safety surveillance systems, the implementation of ecological and energetically efficient equipment, and the improvement of existing facilities. According to DSAT, the award criteria “not only take into account the base retribution proposed by societies”, but also the plans.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Enchanting Macao” promotes city of digital celebrities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/enchanting-macao-promove-cidade-de-celebridades-digitais/</link><description>Two hundred influencers from the interior of China participated in the launch of “Enchanting Macao”, a large -scale promotional action that aims to develop the image of Macau as a city of digital celebrities. The event has gathered several popular figures from the interior of China in Douyin and Macao's artistic and commercial groups to perform stage, fair and parades. According to the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), the initiative now launched from “Tourism +” from MSAR and influencers with millions of fans, serves to “increase enthusiasm for Macao in the mainland market” and stimulate “the desire to visit the territory, boosting the tourism economy in community zones”. This was the first time STD cooperated with a social networking platform to carry out a large campaign with digital influencers. "This activity is expected to contribute to the germination of Macau as a city of digital influencers, allowing more friends from the interior of China to explore new tourist elements of MSAR," DST director Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes said at the opening ceremony. 19 stands were installed at the “Star Fair”, with typical gastronomy and local cultural and creative products, including three tents occupied by digital influencers, including gastronomy, idols and elements of intangible cultural heritage.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Pro-Governo newspaper in Japan surprises with “radical” support to an imperator</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/jornal-pro-governo-japao-surpreende-apoio-radical-uma-imperadora/</link><description>The two main conservative communication agencies of Japan are waging a battle for public opinion, after the Yomiuri newspaper has approached an idea for a long time considered taboo and that breaks with the right values.
"We should not rule out the possibility of an imperator, or an emperor by female lineage," said Yomiuri on his first page on May 15, revealing policies proposals on the issue of imperial succession. "If we continue to insist on male descendants in the male lineage, the survival of the symbolic emperor system will be at risk," he added.
It is not surprising that the influential Yomiuri Shimbun - Japan's largest newspaper, with a daily circulation of 6.2 million copies - was giving political recommendations. Since 1994, it has leveraged its position as the country's most read newspaper to boost the political agenda through its proposals.
However, what has had repercussions on Japanese political corridors is the way Yomiuri, often considered pro-government for its alignment with the conservative Liberal Democratic Party (PLD), adopted a more aligned stance with the political left.
The Blicoso Cariz Sankei newspaper, with a circulation of less than one million copies, launched an offensive, recruiting commentators who accused Yomiuri of "deceiving the public" with "sloppy contents." His editorial boss, Satoshi Sakakibara, said the Yomiuri brushed the blasphemous and would lead "Japan to stop being Japanese."
A Sankei editorial noted that traditional newspapers should not adhere to the popular wave and engage in "impulsive policies, drawing hasty conclusions based on superficial information, without considering the weight of history or responsibility for the future."
Cultural war emerges at a time when the future of the Japanese monarchy - the oldest hereditary royal lineage in the world, dates from 660 BC - appears as a controversial issue in Parliament, due to the decrease in the number of political heirs.
Public opinion, however, firmly supports a monarch or an emperor of matrilinear descent. This is shocked by LDP hardline conservatives, who want to preserve the chrysanthemum throne exclusively for male men's descendants.
This has nothing to do with a gender division: among the most arrest of hardline policy is former Minister of Economic Security, Sanae Takaichi, a first-minister candidate who recently intensified her criticism of the current leader, Shigeru Ishiba.
Kiyotaka Akasaka, president of Nippon Communications Foundation, a non -profit organization, told The Straits Times that Yomiuri proposals are "radical", given the newspaper's usual position, and represent a "bomb to the political right."
Political ideas could not have been possible if the veteran journalist Tsunea Watanabe, who was the 1985 Yomiuri editor-in-chief until his death at the age of 98 in 2024, was still alive, Akasaka said.
The conflict of opinions, he pointed out, stems from the unshakable commitment of hardline members to traditional values, regardless of circumstances and despite the alarming decline of members of the imperial family.
However, he noted: "It is very difficult to predict the impact that these proposals will have on current political considerations, but have encouraged political opposition."
Emperor Naruhito, 65, is the 126th reigning monarch, after his father, Akihito, 91, has broken with tradition and abdicated in 2019, becoming Emperor Emeritus.
There are only three heirs to the Throne of Chrysanthemum: the 59 -year -old heir prince Akishino, the emperor's younger brother; Prince Hisahito, 18, son of the heir prince; And finally, the 89 -year -old Prince Hitachi, uncle of the brothers. This is the harsh reality: if Prince Hisahito decides not to marry or has no son, there will be no one to succeed the throne.
There is already resistance.
Unlike his grandfather, the late Emperor Hirohito, who was venerated as a deity until Japan loses war, the heir to Kishino heir said at a 2024 press conference that politicians should not lose sight of as royal members affected by public policies are "real human beings."
There are now five single women in the 16 -member imperial house, including 23 -year -old Princess Aiko, the only daughter of Emperor Naruhito and Empress Masako.
While common women marry members of the Imperial Family, such as Empress Masako, princesses born in the family lose their royal identity and become commonplace when marrying commoner.
The most recent to leave the family was the daughter of the 33-year-old heir Prince Akishino, who married his college boyfriend in 2021. The couple immediately moved to the US and has not returned to Japan ever since. On May 30, the Imperial House agency reported that the couple had given birth to their first child without revealing sex.
As a solution to the fall of the numbers, Yomiuri Shimbun suggests that princesses maintain royal status after marriage, with their husbands and children joining the imperial house.
Traditionalists agree that princesses should remain royalty members and continue their official duties after marriage. But they set a limit to the admission of their spouses and children in the family, arguing that this could lead to a matrilinear emperor and stain the real lineage.
Note that although eight imperators existed, all were single and patrilineal heirs. There has never been a matrilinear emperor.
Yomiuri, however, believes that the idea of ​​“one family, two statutes” is unrealistic. As commonplace, spouses and children would be free to express their opinions that could contest the “neutrality and political dignity” of the imperial family. It also points out how the uninterrupted lineage along millennia has been sustained by concubines, with 55 illegitimate children to become emperors.
However, traditionalists also advocate the return of members of 11 former branches of the Imperial Family who were dissolved after World War II through "adoption." There are at least 10 single male descendants, 20 years or less, among these branches.
But the idea has little acceptance with the public. Eighty years have spent years since the war, and the members of these branched families will have been used to life as commoners, far from the public eyes and the rigid rules of the Imperial House.
Kanda University Professor Jeffrey Hall warns that this plan "would raise questions about the human rights of the individuals involved," saying that Yomiuri sees this as "a less reliable and unpredictable solution that could dilute public support to the monarchy."
Jeffrey Hall stresses that the monarchy is not an important issue for moderate or center-right voters, although there is a "very expressive minority" of extremists who prefer Sankei to Yomiuri for "taking their party more consistently on cultural war issues."
Although they do not represent most PLD voters, the party would have difficulty winning elections without their support, he said.
"For many Japanese, the insistence on exclusively male succession seems to collide with the concepts of gender equality and women's rights," said Hall. "But convinced conservatives will do almost everything to protect the one who consider it to be one of the most sacred traditions of their nation."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>