<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Planned inclusive model for all day care centers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/planeado-modelo-inclusivo-para-todas-creches/</link><description>The Institute of Social Action plans to create a “operational model” of support and monitoring of children with special needs, so that it will be implemented in all day care centers in the territory, gradually. There are currently three kindergartens with inclusive services, which have already served 70 children with development difficulties
 
Catarina Pereira
 
By addressing inclusive day care centers, the president of the Institute of Social Action (IAS) revealed that the body plans to “establish an operational model of support and monitoring of children with developmental difficulties for day care centers, with a view to implementing it progressively on all Macao day care centers”. However, Hon Wai was no use details about the plan.
The information arises in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Lei Chan U, who had questioned whether the “day care center development plan for the years 2026 to 2030” would be reinforced inclusive services to support needy families.
On the other hand, law chan u asked how many day care centers provide inclusive services to children with slight special needs and what is the point of situation about this support. In this context, the president of IAS indicated that there are currently in Macau three subsidized day care centers who provide inclusive services, having already served 70 children with development difficulties.
“These services allow children with developmental difficulties to receive day care cautions together with other children of the same age, promoting their happy growth and, at the same time, helping to alleviate parents' pressure on their children's care,” explains Hon Wai.
Regarding the “day care center development plan for the years 2026 to 2030,” he says he aims to “provide adequate child care for families”, “support parents in the participation of child care and education” and “establish a quality day care management system”, in order to “further improve day care care services, relieving pressure on family care and encouraging young people to have children”.
Currently, IAS is “summarizing the experience” of implementation of the plan that began in 2023 and ending this year, “presenting to the sector the conceptions of the next phase of the plan and collecting opinions, with the aim of finalizing the plan during the year 2025”, read.
In written interplies, law chan u also wanted to know how authorities will reinforce personnel formation and resource allocation in this area. At this point, Hon Wai states that, since 2023, the body he directs has been training both to professionals and parents of children. "By the end of 2024, about 220 day care professionals and 250 parents completed the training," he said, adding that during this year they will continue to allocate resources to make approximately 500 training vacancies.
"In the future, training and support actions will be developed according to the needs, aiming at the continuous improvement of the day care center service system," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DSAT wishes “prospective vision” in new bus contracts</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dsat-deseja-visao-prospectiva-nos-novos-contratos-de-autocarros/</link><description>The study on the new bus service contract has already begun, in which a “comprehensive review” will be made to the careers of buses, the transfer between buses and the meter, to financial assistance, between several aspects, DSAT said. Ensuring that this study will incorporate the opinions collected over time, the body has revealed that it aims to “establish a contract with prospective vision, reinforcing its practical applicability and the ability to surveillance”.
 
The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) has already started the study related to the new contract for the provision of bus services. In this study, “a comprehensive review of contractual clauses will be made based on the services currently provided, namely regarding bus careers, business management, business management, financial assistance, overflow between buses and the light meter, among other aspects,” he said in response to a written interpretation of Deputy Ron Lam.
According to DSAT, the study "will incorporate the opinions that, over time, have been collected from the various sectors of society on the bus service, aligning with the course of Macao's development." At this point, he stressed that the objective is to “establish a contract with prospective vision, reinforcing its practical applicability and the enforcement capacity”.
It is recalled that the two bus companies, TCM and Transmac, signed concession contracts in 2021, lasting six years, so they will end at the end of 2026.
At the interpetement, Ron Lam requested the increase in the number of rapid careers circulating from the modal transport centers of the peninsula and the mud, passing through the Ká-Hó tunnel to the Ká-Hó care home. According to DSAT, after the collection, with the management entity of this home, the opinions of the visitors about the bus service, from June 7 this year, the special career matches 15s1, at times coincident with the most demanding periods. In addition, the body has ensured that "it will continue to closely follow the situation, proceeding to adjustments whenever necessary."
The deputy also pointed out that, according to some residents, during the Golden Week of May, many careers between the border stations and the tourist areas were already full while passing through the central zone, so they could not take buses in the center at the hours of exit of school and work. Citing some elderly people, Ron Lam lamented that there are buses to the Kiang Wu Hospital from Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro and Manduco Beach, but there is no back "which makes it difficult for the elderly and people with small mobility difficulties."
In response, DSAT reiterated that, to distribute the flows of different groups of public transport users and enhance the efficacy of flow, bus companies “highlight, depending on the actual situation, additional matches”. In addition, he added, "they are preparing in advance for the creation of seasonal careers on festive and holidays, in order to offer a more directed service, effective in terms of turnover and with relatively direct routes, ensuring greater convenience for passengers."
On the other hand, questioned by Ron Lam about whether to change the main careers that pass through the village of Taipa to stop at the Modal Transport Center of the village of Chun Su Mei, in order to increase their efficiency and relieve pressure from public roads in this old neighborhood, then DSAT director, Lam Hin San, said that the body will improve the waiting environment in the respective parts, in the respective stops, in Articulation with the integrated development of the village zone of Chun Su Mei.
In addition, careers will be reviewed that serves the zone and their scale stops, for the introduction, in due time, of optimizations and necessary adjustments, he added.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Banks Operational Profit Up 52%</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lucro-operacional-dos-bancos-sobe-52/</link><description>The Macao Bank Sector closed the first semester with operational gains of 6.3 billion patacas, 52% more than in the same period of 2024. According to data from the monetary authority, the Malparado credit registered the third sequential descent in four months, but remains at a very high level
 
The results of exploration of the sgw sector ascended to about 6.34 billion patacas in late June, which reflects an increase of 52% over the same month of 2024, the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM) revealed.
In the same temporal interval, banking institutions benefited from an increase from 60.1% to 6.10 billion patacas in bank services and operations and a 60.1% rise in financial investments (756.2 million) income. Already the amount derived from the margin of profits decreased 7.8% to 7.31 billion patacas.
Financing costs ciphed at 8.08 billion patacas, maintaining virtually the same level recorded at the end of June 2024. In the operating expenses chapter, the 6.1% increase in personnel costs (2.21 billion) was highlighted.
It is recalled that, in the general calculation of 2024, banks' operational profits reached 4.01 billion patacas, marking an annual decline of 21.3% and the lowest value since 2010. The results of 2024 marked the fourth successive descent, after 12 years, including 10 consecutive records, starting in 2011.
According to AMCM data, bank activity loans totaled 1,035.2 billion patacas in June, which represents a monthly rise of 4.2% and an annual breakage of 4.8%. Hong Kong dollar loans continue to dominate (44.1%of the total), surpassing a large margin those called Patacas (21.4%), US dollars (20.0%) and Renminbis (11.2%).
Internal loans to the private sector ciphed at 512.64 billion patacas, translating a monthly growth of 2.8% and an annual decrease of 3.8%. In turn, foreign credit advanced 5.5% in a month to 522.59 billion, but fell 5.8% within one year.
Regarding internal private credit, loans related to “restaurants, hotels and the like” and “production and distribution of electricity, gas and water” increased 34.3% and 18.6% in the second quarter, respectively, compared to the previous three months. On the other hand, the credit granted to the sectors of “Grosso Trade and Retail” and “Construction” fell 11.7% and 1.2%, respectively.
 
Malparado dropped to 55.6 billion
The amount of loans with more than 90 days late in banks is still very high in the territory, but recorded three sequential descents in four months. At the end of June, the “non -productive” or overdue credit (NPL, in the English acronym) totaled 55.57 billion patacas, which corresponds to a monthly decrease of 1.1% or 638 million.
On the other hand, the NPL grew 14.7% or 7.11 billion patacas compared to June 2024 and 20 times compared to 2.77 billion accounted for in late 2019, ie before the pandemic. In February of this year, the Malporado credit reached the highest value since AMCM began compiling these statistics in 1990 by settling at 57.62 billion.
In the period under analysis, the expired credit corresponded to 5.4% of bank loans, less 0.3 percentage points than in the previous month, and more 0.8 points in the annual comparison. The total NPL includes 34.08 billion unresident clients (61.3% of the total) and 21.49 billion residents, illustrating racings of 6.5% and 4.2%.
Official statistics also indicate that public sector deposits in banks reached 219.69 billion patacas, highlighting increases of 1.6% and 8.1% in monthly and annual terms, respectively. Resident deposits (803.76 billion) grew by 1.1% in a month and 10% on an annual base, while non-residents (373.86 billion) increased 6.5% compared to May 2025 and 8.8% for June 2024.
In general, deposits of bank activity totaled 1,397.3 billion patacas, more 2.6% than in the previous month and 9.4% more than in the same period of 2024.
The resident loan/deposits ratio grew from 49.3% in late May to 50.1% in the following month, and in the case of non-residents, it advanced from 73.0% to 74.1%. According to AMCM, current currents to calculate based on one month and three months against liabilities were 67.3% and 56.6%, respectively.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Picasso virtuosity “seduces” Grand Lisboa Palace visitors</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/virtuosismo-de-picasso-seduz-visitantes-grand-lisboa-palace/</link><description>For its “Special Exhibition”, SJM invited Mario Virgilio Montañez to organize the show “Picasso: Beauty and Drama”, patent on the Grand Lisbon Palace until October. To the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the curator spoke about the curatorship process and the relevance of Pablo Picasso today



































Pedro Milheirão
The Jornal Tribuna de Macau spoke to the curator of the show “Picasso: Beauty and Drama”, and responsible for the “Museo Casa Natal Picasso”, Mario Virgilio Montañez, regarding the “Special Exhibition” of SJM. Montañez was in charge of selecting the 143 works on display in Greater Lisbon Palace, from a collection with a thousand works by Pablo Picasso. For the show, Montañez resorted to his 36 years of experience with the artist's legacy, to compose the seven theme galleries that portray different periods of Picasso's career and his connection to Andalusia.
The principle that unites the chosen pieces is a combination of “beauty” and “a dramatic element that originates from melancholy or the intense emotions of bullfighting”, according to the curator. "From the intimate story of his childhood pieces, the humble and emotion -filled objects that we show outside of Europe, for the first time, to the presence of Greek and Romans, Malaga, with three thousand years of history, was Phoenician, Carthaginian, Roman, Byzantine, Visigotic, Arab and Christian."
“The city has been a cauldron of cultures and influences that are also evident in Picasso's fascinating work,” adds Montañez. Like the Andaluza city, “Macao is the perfect example of this mixture of cultures, between China and Portugal, a sister nation with whom Spain shares the Iberian Peninsula. The commercial vocation [of Macao], with commercial routes with Malaca, Goa and Japan, is similar to that of Malaga”, explains Montañez.
Of the pieces displayed, the curator highlights four drawings of Picasso, which dates from 1907 and were produced during the artist's first trip to Asia. In these pieces, is represented Raymonde, a nine-year-old girl Picasso adopted for three months before she surrendered to a hospice. “The emotion and delicacy of this portrait, full of melancholy, is truly moving,” says Montañez.
In an era dominated by digital technologies and the advent of artificial intelligence, the curator believes that “Picasso remains the best-known and most questioned artist, as when he was alive. He generates admiration or rejection, depending on the spectator's taste. But always inspires fascination, regardless of the opinion of the audience is positive or negative. When confronted with a peak, the look can never be passive. underlines.
Mario Virgilio Montañez hopes that the public will be "seduced by Picasso", noting that the artist was known to be a "great seductive". “Calmly observing each work in the exhibition, from the simplest to the most elaborate, the viewer is amazed by the virtuosity of Picasso, his perfect rule of line and trace, his imagination and courage,” he says.
Montañez is a writer, poet, researcher and art critic. He graduated in Hispanic Philology from the University of Malaga, having worked as a music critic for “Diario 16” between 1989 and 1993, and art critic for the “Sur” newspaper, from 2004 to 2011. He was also a director of “Vivir La Cultura” and “Territories de La Cultura”.
In addition to the “Hucha de Oro”, he raised awards in the “rehearsals about Ernesto Sabato”, “Jauja” and the “Exhibition of Young Literature”. He also gave lectures and organized several exhibitions around the world. Currently, Montañez is head of the Public Agency's Cultural Promotion Department for the management of the place of birth of Pablo Ruiz Picasso and other museum and cultural facilities, including the “Museo Casa Natal Picasso”.
The 143 original works by Andaluz artist will be patent in Greater Lisbon Palace, until October 26, and include paintings, impressions, ceramics, illustrations and manuscripts of the Spanish artist. SJM's “Special Exhibition” is one of the highlights of the Macao International Art Biennial program.
The exhibition is open to the public from 11h00 to 19h00, Monday to Thursday, between 11h00 and 21h00 Friday and from 10h00 to 21h00 to the weekends. Guided tours are available in English, Cantonese and Mandarin.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan wants to “lead global efforts” to a world without nuclear weapons</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/actual/japao-quer-liderar-esforcos-globais-para-um-mundo-sem-armas-nucleares/</link><description>EPA12285475 Doves are release during the peace memorial ceremony on the 80th anniversary of the atomic bombing of hiroshima at peace memorial park in hiroshima, japan, 06 August 2025. Nagasaki on 06 and 09 August respectively, Killing more than 200,000 People.  EPA/Franck Robichon



The Prime Minister of Japan said yesterday that Tokyo should “lead global efforts” for humanity to reach a world without nuclear weapons, the day the 80th anniversary of Hiroshima's atomic bombing was signaled. "Leading the international community to reach a world without nuclear weapons is the mission of Japan as the only country that suffered the atomic bomb in war and applies the three non -nuclear principles," said Shigeru Ishiba, speaking at the ceremony at Hiroshima Memorial Park, where, on August 6, 1945, the US released the first atomic pump in history, causing the death of about 70,000 causing the death of about 70,000. people. Ishiba referred to the principles of not producing, not possessing and not allowing nuclear weapons in their territory, which have been respected by all executives in the country, since they were declared in 1967 by then Prime Minister Eisaku Sato, and subsequently ratified by Parliament. Ishiba also highlighted the “deepening of international community divisions” regarding nuclear disarmament and “worsement of the security environment”, a context in which it is more necessary to “achieve a world without nuclear weapons” through initiatives of nuclear non -proliferation (NPT), he said. "We will appeal to all countries to make the most of this spirit of dialogue during the meeting of next year's NPT initiative," he said, also appealing to the "search for concrete measures" for denuclearization, including both countries that do not have such weapons and atomic powers. "The basis for achieving a world without nuclear weapons is the correct understanding of the fact of the atomic bomb," Ishiba said at the ceremony, in which survivors of bombing, the mayor of Hiroshima, Kazumi Matsui, and diplomatic representatives from 120 countries and territories, record record. On the other hand, at a press conference after the ceremony, Ishiba rejected the possibility of sharing US nuclear weapons. "There was some confusion about sharing nuclear weapons means having them, but I do not consider any of these options based on the three non-nuclear principles," he said, however, the need for Japan to "study" a "strengthening of the credibility of nuclear dissuasion," in reference to the American nuclear shield that protects the Asian country.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mand “won” 1,551 societies until June</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-ganhou-1-551-sociedades-ate-junho/</link><description>Between January and June, 2,020 societies were created in Macao and dissolved 469, which translated a net growth of 1,551, about 9% less annually
 
In the first semester of this year, the number of companies consisting of Macao decreased 12% to 2,020, compared to the same period from 2024, while dissolution cases decreased by 20.9% to 469, the Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) said. Thus, a net growth of 1,551 companies, 152 or 8.9%, was registered than in the first six months last year.
Between January and June, the share capital of new societies settled at 303 million patacas, less 53 million or 14.9% in the annual interval.
In the second quarter of this year alone, 1,107 societies were created (6.1% less than between April and June 2024), and most belongs to the branches of activity of thick and retail trade (380) and services provided to companies (326). On the other hand, 283 societies were dissolved (less 22.5%), leading to net growth of 824 (plus 1.2%).
According to the DSEC, the capital of the companies constituted between April and June totaled 98 million. Capitals originating from the interior of China (33 million patacas) and the MSAR (42 million), accounted for 34.1% and 43.3% of the total, respectively
Social capital from China's interior cities in the Greater Bay region was 12 million Patacas, with Zhuhai to “regret” 45.3% in this geographical set, and that of Hong Kong stood in 19 million.
The same data show that 791 societies constituted in the second quarter (71.5% of the total) belonged to the equity of less than 50 thousand patacas and the respective capital reached 20 million patacas (20.8% of the total). There were also 12 societies with a stock capital equal to or greater than one million patacas, involving 39 million, or 39.4% of the total.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Tour tours reveal history and culture</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/passeios-turisticos-revelam-historia-cultura/</link><description>During this month and all over the city, a series of tourist activities will be held that will show the history and culture of neighborhoods and temples
 
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) proceeds with the encouragement of local associations to carry out diversified activities or tourist projects, with a view to boosting the community economy. The activities aim to encourage visitors and residents to visit the community neighborhoods of Macao.
During this month, the “Temple Tracking Cultural &amp; Creative Market” is held every Saturday and Sundays until the 24th, from 17h00 to 21h00, at Largo do Pagoda do Bazar. During this period, every Saturday, from 16h00 to 18h30, there will be a tour of the Temple of Na Tcha.
According to STD, participants, accompanied by guides, will be able to visit the old sidewalk temple and the TCA temple, experience a shadow theater and a cultural and creative fair, as well as get consumer coupons to use at the fair and stores in the area adherent to activity.
Makmak &amp; Amazetar Coastal Immersive Puppet Theater for Families ”creates an immersive puppet theater experience that integrates interaction between parents and children, story theater, sea tour and cultural guided tours, with eight sessions on 9, 10, 16 and 17 August.
Participants will board the Barra da Barra bridge and return from the Coloane-CAIS Bridge. On the way, a puppet play will have “love”, local original intellectual property, and “Mak Mak”, Macau Tourism Mascot, as protagonists. Participants will visit the land on the Coloane-CAIS Bridge, where they will accompany the group's head on a visit to historic sites, will learn about Macao stories and “will conclude interesting interactive missions, obtaining memories and discount coupons” from stores in the old area of Macao and Coloane.
In turn, the Play Fun North District - IAO Hono ”includes the“ Iao Hon Play Fun Market ”, which will take place on August 22-24, from 2:30 pm to 7:30 pm, in the Iao Hon market garden. The content includes the theme tents and workshops in the North Zone and“ The Voice of Iao Hon ”.
The program also includes the “Enjoy A Leisurely Stroll at Iao Hon Market - Internet Celebrity Food Tour”, which will take place on August 9, 10, 16 and 17, from 2:30 pm to 4:30 pm. In this context, Macao digital influencers will be invited to travel to the Iao Hon market garden to share photographs strategies, guide participants in tasting typical delicacies, and explore the stories of community neighborhoods.
Between August 9 and 31, the “Qixi Festival Summer Experience in San Kio 2025” will carry out activities with community and festive characteristics in the San Kio area, including an exhibition of knowledge about the festivities, creative fair, traditional night, visiting the Community neighborhood and guidance of St. Chinese Valentine, “guiding participants to discover the old San neighborhood Kio ”.
On the other hand, participants who meet consumer requirements in the San Kio area can participate for free in the workshop or in the summer aquatic experience that will take place on Hac Sá beach.
Part of the activities require pre-registration and payment to participate, the STD said.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Anima receives donations from MGM and Melco</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/anima-recebe-donativos-da-mgm-melco/</link><description>MGM and Melco Resorts Entertainment donated a total of 160,000 patacas to the Macao animal protective society to "support the animal cause." The donations will serve for daily expenses and medical care for hundreds of animals housed by the anima
 
MGM and Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment gambling operators each donated 80,000 patacas to the Macau Animal Protective Society (Anima). Donations will serve to support the daily expenses and medical care of more than 700 animals sheltered by Anima, who shared on his Facebook page a thanks to both dealers for “supporting the animal cause”.
In June this year, the association's president, Zoe Tang, told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that the anima had, at the time, debts worth 1.9 million patacas, regarding animal food expenses, veterinary treatments and employee salaries.
"Due to the general economic situation of society, it is very difficult to raise donations. We can only maintain operations with donations from the founding of Macao and a small number of individuals," explained Zoe Tang. "We put 136 donations boxes in different locations, including two banks, the" Tai Fung "bank and the National Bank Overseas. However, it regretted the fact that the number of donations was not" as high as in previous years. "
At the same time, and despite having about 1,500 registered volunteers, most of them have a main job, which prevents the association from obtaining help at fixed times and their operating period, between 09h00 and 18h00. In February, Zoe Tang explained to this newspaper that another of the association's main problems was the sanitation of the facilities, whose work would start in July, with a predicted cost of 460,000 patacas.
On the last occasion he spoke to the Macao Tribune, Zoe Tang said that an advance of 200,000 Patacas had already been made to an engineering company, with which he was dealing with the process of submission of the documentation, waiting for a response from the direction of soil services and urban construction.
Since 2003, the Association has been dedicated to taking care of abandoned and mistreated animals, conducting monthly adoption campaigns and other activities. According to the Institute for Municipal Affairs, in the first half of this year, 228 animals were adopted or claimed, 99 adoptions than in the same period last year (327), and nine were returned to the body. In the same period, eight animals were also abandoned, three more than in the first semesters of 2024 (3) and 2023 (2).
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Dicj authorized game machine inspired by the “Squid Game” series</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dicj-autorizou-maquina-de-jogo-inspirada-na-serie-squid-game/</link><description>The Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ) approved for the Macao market the 'Light &amp; Wonder' slot machine inspired by the controversial South Korean series "Squid Game," said the Gggrasia portal. The machine features Netflix's iconic theme -based games, such as "Red Light, Green Light", "Tug of War" and "The Glass Tile." Although it is not yet known when and where the machine will be available, the product is in accordance with the second version of the Electronic Game Machine (EGM, in the English) of MSAR and the first version of Jackpots Technical Standards. Last year, the owner of Squid Game's Slot Machine debuted the machine on “Yaamava”, resort and casino located in southern California, and is also available in the Philippine market. The Netflix series debuted in 2021 and focuses on a group of individuals, without money, trying to gain a fortune surviving several deadly challenges alluding to children's games. The third and last season of the drama was aired in June this year. It is recalled that in 2021, the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) appealed to children and adolescents to not see the South Korean series, for containing “a lot of violence, blood, frightening elements and distorted values”. "If children and adolescents see the violent and bloody parts of the drama, they will be psychologically affected and can even imitate violent behavior," DSEDJ explained.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy takes Macau cinema to Venice</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/galaxy-leva-cinema-de-macau-veneza/</link><description>The Venice International Film Festival will have a set of events designated “Macao Day” in late August, in a partnership with the Galaxy short film event
 
The “Giornate Degli Author” section of the Venice International Film Festival will hold the “Macao Day” event series on August 29 and 30, in a collaboration with the Galaxy Entertainment International Film Festival (GEG). (IC), will be presented to the professionals of the film industry and the international public, the “cultural uniqueness of Macau”.
GEG's partnership with “Giornate Degli Authors” aims to “raise the profile” of the operator's initiative, injecting “a new vitality to the Macao film culture” and highlighting the “unique charm” of the “East Asia City City”. In addition, it will provide a “greater international visibility” to Macao's film works, “creating opportunities for emerging filmmakers to reach the global stage”.
According to the IC, “collaboration marks a significant connection” between the GEG festival and the “Giornate Degli author”, driven by the efforts of its artistic director, Gaia Fundo, and Giorgio Gosetti, Delegate General. In addition, “he highlights the shared commitment of both events to discover new cinematic talents and promote diversity and inclusion, surpassing age barriers, gender and geography through concrete actions”.
“Giornate Degli Author” is a parallel section of the Venice International Film Festival, which is dedicated to promoting independent films and emerging filmmakers. It is one of three official programs of the festival, along with the Venice International Film Festival and the International Week of Venice Crime Criticism.
The “International GEG Short Festival Festival”, co-organized with the IC, “seeks to discover and promote local and international outstanding shorts, foster the exchange in film culture and provide an exhibition platform for emerging filmmakers”. For the second year in a row, GEG “reaffirms its commitment to support the sustainable growth of Macao's cinematic talents and to facilitate the development of cultural events of international influence throughout the city”, can be read.
The Cultural Institute also intends that this collaboration promotes “the diversified development of the Macao film and television industry, offering local filmmakers opportunities for in -depth exchange with global professionals and audiences”.
The GEG Festival will take place in September, in the Galaxy theaters, at the Galaxy International Convention Center, at Andaz Hotel and Cinemateca Passion.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Physical Exhibition” improves integrated resort image</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/exposicao-fisica-melhora-imagem-dos-resorts-integrados/</link><description>"A high quality physical exposure has a positive impact on brand image, client experience and participatory behavior," concluded a study by academics at Macao Polytechnic University (UPM), published by the Journal of Destination Marketing &amp; Management. The investigation resulted from the collaboration between academics from the Pedagogical and Scientific Center in the areas of Game and Tourism of the Macao Polytechnic University (CJT-UPM) and the Beijing Technology Institute in Zhuhai. According to UPM, study results provide “an important reference for the elaboration of integrated resort marketing strategies”, which can improve customer printing on brands and contribute to the high quality development of MSc tourism. The investigation team, which included assistant professor Zhou Jinquan and assistant Ryan Ho of CJT-UPM, evaluated the “physically exposed elements” of integrated resorts such as architectural design, inner decoration, quality of facilities and employee image. The results offer scientific support for the “construction of intelligent tourist cities” and a new perspective for the theories of environmental psychology and “servicecape”, the UPM statement says.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Malay Buffet at Studio City until the end of August</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/buffet-malaio-studio-city-ate-final-de-agosto/</link><description>Sutdio City is welcoming, again, the Buffet “The Flavor of Malaysia”, until August 31, indicated Melco, reinforcing the position of Macau as a creative city of UNESCO's cuisine. At the start-up ceremony, Malaysian Consul General in Hong Kong and Macau, Muzambli Markam, said the initiative “promises an irresistible selection of Malay dishes,” pointing out that reflects the “richness of Malaysian cultural diversity”. Already Vice President Senio and General Manager of Studio City, Kevin Benning, said that the venture "is committed to offering world class experiences in Macao", and ensuring that it will continue to "offer international culinary experiences", in line with the policies of the Government of MSc. In addition to presenting seasonal shellfish, such as fresh oysters, and Sashimi “premium”, the buffet “has become a paradise of malaia cuisine”, with specialties divided into seven iconic flavors: Nyonya de Malaca cuisine, traditional grilled meats, Ipoh street food, Kuala Lumpur specialties, Malay Thinking Village dishes, Penang Street Snacks and Nyonya and Durian Desserts. The price per adult is 628 patacas, while children (from six to twelve) pay 318 patacas. The buffet opens at 18h00 and extends until 10 pm, daily.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2449/</link><description>Car crashed into a bus and stuffed in a store
According to the Fire Department, a car collided with a public bus on Rua do Regrador, Taipa, yesterday afternoon, at 17h00. The car then clashed in a store that sells dry shellfish, damaging the establishment's entrance facilities and several iron seals. A 60 -year -old bus passenger suffered minor injuries and was transported to the hospital. On the other hand, a non -resident worker of the store was also sent to the hospital because he felt damaged after the occurrence. Police will continue to investigate the cause of the accident. According to the Chinese language press, the vehicle was severely damaged.
 
SI LEG LAW Named Vice President of ID
The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture has appointed, in Service Commission, Law Si Leng to hold the position of Vice-President of the Institute of Sport (ID). According to the order published yesterday in an official bulletin, the appointment produces effects from August 21 and for a period of one year. Law Si Leng began as a technique of the organizing committee of the 4th edition of the Macao East Asia Games, having entered the ID that same year.
 
STD has over 10 million followers on social networks
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) currently has 28 official accounts on social networks, which exceeded in July “the barrier of 10 million followers in total, increasing the effectiveness of disclosure” about Macau, the body led by Helena de Senna Fernandes. STD states that it will “continue to promote online and face -to -face work” to “consolidate the Greater China market” and “continue to expand the sources of international visitors”.
 
Conditioning to traffic remains on Central Street
The second phase of the tubing work work of the building building of the court building on Avenida da Praia Grande is underway, and its conclusion is foreseen on the 10th of this month, then starting the third phase. "At that time, the road circulation on Avenida da Praia Grande will resume to normal, maintaining traffic conditioning on Central Street, and the ban on parking meter for light cars and in places for motorcycles located on Central Street with Plaza Victory," said the management of public works and the direction of service to traffic issues.
 
Detained by trafficking cocaine evaluated in four million
A 38 -year -old maid of Indonesian nationality will have helped a drug trafficking transfrontic network to receive and treat postcan packages containing cocaine. A mulher foi detida e foram apreendidas 2.160 gramas de cocaína avaliadas em cerca de quatro milhões de patacas. The PJ revealed that the network sent drugs to Macao from a West African country, and the postal package arrived in the territory on Monday and the suspicion was intercepted on the same day. No pacote, foram encontrados 144 pequenos frascos de produtos cosméticos, cada um com 15 gramas de cocaína. According to the PJ, despite being aware of the crime, the suspect agreed to help the criminal group receive the studded and tried to send them to voices. Foi encaminhada para o Ministério Público.
 
Three shopkeepers circumvented banks at 3.5 million
Three local shopkeepers were arrested, aged 34 to 39, on suspicion of local banks. According to PJ, data from foreign credit cards will have been used to make false transactions at the PA terminals equipped in their stores, as well as raised money from injured banks through these illegal operations. The cases involved 2,611 suspicious transactions, whose total amount exceeded 3.5 million patacas. The suspects claimed that they did not know each other and denied having committed the crime, but police believe they are related to the same criminal group. According to PJ, two banks warned police in mid -2024. Later, a sudden and abnormal climb was discovered in the volume of transactions of stores in question. Credit card data involved are from the US, Belarus, France and Indonesia, and the cards were issued by the same bank.
 
Junkets number has been the highest since the beginning of 2023
The total number of licensed games promoters in Macau is 30, since July 28, the highest value since the beginning of 2023, according to official data, reported the Gggrasia portal. But the total junkets is still 40% below the maximum limit of 50 established by the government. According to the list of inspection and coordination of games, five more promoters were added compared to the data available in May.
 
Contest offers 79 vacancies for medical residency
Enrollment for the competition of the medical integrated competencies evaluation procedure, for admission to this year's medical residency, announced the health services. In total, there are 79 vacancies that cover 33 specialties categories. The admitted ones will have systematic training in service for six years, including two years of basic training and four of complementary training, which will take place at the Public Hospital, the Community Health Care Department, the Center for Disease Prevention and Control, the Kiang Wu Hospital, or the Island Health Care Complex.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Steven Knight will write new James Bond movie</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/steven-knight-vai-escrever-novo-filme-de-james-bond/</link><description>Steven Knight, creator of the “Peaky Blinders” series, will write the new and long -awaited James Bond movie, the Amazon MGM studio announced. The shotie will work with the already announced Franco-Canadian director Denis Villeneuve (“Dune”) to bring the most famous British spy of fiction back to the big screen after a long absence.
The film will have executive production by Tanya Lapointe, who worked with Villeneuve in the films "Dune", while Amy Pascal and David Heyman will be the producers.
In 2022, Amazon acquired MGM, which includes a vast catalog with over 4,000 films, including espionage, but, according to specialized means Variety, had only 50% of the franchise.
In March this year, Amazon MGM Studios completed a new joint -venture with Barbara Broccoli and Michael G. Wilson. The terms of the agreement stipulate that Amazon MGM Studios will assume the creative control of James Bond's intellectual property rights.
Now the joint venture advances quickly to put the franchise in production, one of Hollywood's most profitable. James Bond's last movie was “In Team to Die”, released in 2021.
Knight is known to be the mind behind "Peaky Blinders," a series about a British criminal group set in the industrial age in the early twentieth century, which became a global success. With six seasons, and a Netflix movie on his way, “Peaky Blinders” gave his protagonist's career new, Cillian Murphy, as well as a star-filled cast with figures such as Tom Hardy, Anya Taylor-Joy and Kingsley Ben-Adader.
Steven Knight also contributed to the creation of the television contest “Who wants to be a millionaire?” And wrote four novels. Other titles by the writer from Birmingham, England, who also worked as a producer and director, include “Taboo”, “See”, “This Town” and “All the Light We Canot See”.
James Bond films, based on Ian Fleming's novels in the 1950s, raised more than seven billion dollars at international tickets since their debut in 1962.
It is not known what will be the release date or the title of the 26th edition of the saga. Despite the frantic speculation between the fans, there was also no ads about the actor that will replace Daniel Craig in the lead role. Before him, stars like Pierce Brosnan, Sean Connery and Roger Moore also played the legendary spy.
Among the names mentioned are Aaron Taylor-Johnson, Tom Holland, Harris Dickinson, Jacob Elordo and Ben-Adad, however, for now, Amazon MGM has refused to reveal the franchise's best-kept secret.
 
Died the first Mi5 head that inspired Bond's “m”
British agent and writer Stella Rimington, known for being the first woman to head the MI5 (British Information Service), died at age 90 in London, her family announced. Nicknamed “First Lady of Spying” when she took office from 1992 to 1996, she was considered as the main inspiration for the character of the "M" boss, played by Jud Dench in the James Bond movie series.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>