<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Only three sectors benefited “significantly” from visitors</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/apenas-tres-sectores-beneficiaram-significativamente-dos-visitantes/</link><description>Over the past two years, economic recovery driven by external demand "has not effectively spread by more than half of the sectors," concluded a study of elements from the monetary authority's investigation and statistical department. The game sectors, hotels and restaurants were the ones that “benefited significantly” from the arrival of more visitors to the territory. In this sense, the authors argue that “although efforts to boost external demand remain crucial, equal attention should be paid to the stimulus of internal demand” to ensure “a balanced economic recovery”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
More than half of Macao sectors have not rendered the result of tourism recovery in the last two years. A study by three elements from the Macao's monetary authority and statistics department reveals that only three areas benefited “significantly” from the increase in the number of visitors.
The analysis by C. K. Leong, C. K. IO and H. Y. Huang about the unequal economic resum in the territory points out that “the asymmetrical economic recovery of Macao stems from imbalances between external and internal demand”.
Despite the “excellent overall performance” of the local economy in the last two years, the authors note that “only three sectors: game and junkets activities; hotels and similar activities; and similar restaurants and activities have benefited significantly from the resurgence of visitors.” "This suggests that an economic recovery prevailed predominantly by external demand has not effectively spread to more than half of the industries," they marked in the document, consulted by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao.
The banking sector, insurance and pension funds, real estate activities, construction, education, health and social assistance, as well as the transforming industry, “did not benefit significantly from tourism growth”. "Coincidentally they have a significant positive relationship with the median monthly employment income, suggesting that the growth of these sectors is driven by internal demand," they observe.
In this sense, they consider that "although efforts to boost external demand remain crucial, equal attention should be paid to the stimulus of internal demand, accompanied by continuous analysis of the determinants of growth in all sectors in order to ensure a balanced economic recovery."
In the case of the retail trade sector, it is stated that “despite the rapid recovery in the number of visitors and the local economy in aggregate terms, double pressures to decrease per capita spending on visitors not related to the game and the environment of high interest rates are weighing on the prospects of small and medium -sized businesses (SME)”.
In other words, "SME's performance is more sensitive to the per capita spending of visitors not linked to the game than to the number of visitors." Thus, it is necessary to “look beyond the numbers of visitors arrivals”, so that examining the preferences of constantly evolving consumers in the postpandeia era would help to elaborate “effective policies” and directed to support small local companies in adapting to these changes.
"Our analysis (…) reveals that there is a substantial heterogeneity in the sectoral dynamics of Macao. Notably, an economic recovery predominantly driven by external demand did not effectively spread over half of the sectors," the trio reiterates.
Given that Macao is “a small open economy, where the integrated industry of tourism and leisure is a fundamental pillar”, the authors say that it is natural that the evolution of external demand raises more attention, but underline that it is necessary to “evaluate the short and long term dynamics of different economic variables and their specific implications for each sector”.
The study also underlines the importance of “promoting synergies between external and internal demand to solve growth disparities, which would help guide Macau's economy to a more sustainable development path in the context of adequate economic diversification”, it can read.
It should be noted that service exports represented about 80% of the contribution to actual GDP growth in 2024, and Macao's economic recovery was mostly driven by external demand.</description><pubDate>2025-07-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sign 10 had never been issued anytime soon</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sinal-10-nunca-tinha-sido-emitido-tao-cedo/</link><description>Sign 10 Due to the “Wipha” typhoon became the earlier since it has been registered in 1968. This was, moreover, the fifth tropical cyclone since 2017 that forced the issuance of the highest tropical storm signal, according to meteorological and geophysical services. For the next few days it is expected "unstable" time, despite the removal of "Wipha". The Secretary for Security praised the “efficient” cooperation and the response “timely”

Catarina Pereira
 
Typhoon “Wipha” has been the fifth tropical cyclone in the last nine years since 2017, forcing signal 10 in Macao, observed the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG). Moreover, since there are records in 1968 that the highest sign of tropical storm had not been lifted anytime soon. It is necessary to retreat on July 24, 1991, when the “Brendon” passage to find the record of a 10 sign at this time of year.
In a balance over the typhoon, the SMG report that, after entering the Southern Sea of China, the Wipha went directly to the coast of the Pearl River estuary with typhoon intensity, eventually passing about 30 kilometers southwest of Macao.
"The 10 -minute sustained winds registered in the four bridges reached level 12, with maximum gusts of 14, during the term of Tropical Storm signal 10," says the body.
After entering the northern part of the Southern Sea of China, the development of the typhoon "accelerated significantly", even resulting in the formation of the phenomenon known as "Hot Tower" as it approached the coast of the Pérola river estuary. “In the satellite image, an upward cloud appears like a tower at the top of a cloud,” the SMG indicates.
The body says the phenomenon represents "a sudden movement" near the eye wall of a tropical storm. "The height of the cloud summit can reach the top of the troposphere, accompanied by lightning, which means that the tropical storm is intensifying rapidly," he adds.
Although the “Wipha” typhoon has gradually removed and weakened, time in the region will remain “unstable” in the coming days, with thunder and thunderstorms due to the influence of associated cloud bands. “Squirers are expected to decrease and the sky will be not cloudy later this week,” says the SMG, appealing to the population to pay attention to the latest meteorological information.
 
Compliments to the civil protection structure
In a balance sheet, the secretary for security and joint action commander, Wong Sio Chak, considered that all members of the civil protection structure "fulfilled their duty, performed their duties and, according to emergency plans, were able to warn and prevent in time." He also praised the “efficient” cooperation, under the coordination of the Civil Protection Operations Center.
Wong Sio Chak recalled that Macau is still at the time of typhoons and said he hopes that members of the civil protection structure will not lower the guard, continuing to perform and optimize all tasks based on this response, "in order to ensure the safety of citizens' lives and goods."
According to him, around 6:30 pm on Sunday, the forces and security services sent personnel to all areas of the territory to remove fallen trees and obstacles on the roads, "ensuring the fluidity of traffic in the main arteries of Macao."
The “state of immediate prevention” in the territory was declared extinguished from 10:30 pm on Sunday, when signal 3 was lifted. Thus, the circulation of public transport was resumed and the maritime bridges of the territory reopened. The border posts that connect Macau and Zhuhai had already reopened at 17:00, when the tropical storm signal dropped to 8.
The passage of “Wipha” left five slight injuries in the territory and 139 people rode to the shelter centers. In addition, hundreds of occurrences were recorded.
Specifically, during the passage of the typhoon there were 163 occurrences, involving 98 cases of “removal of plaster, complaint, window, awning or other objects with risk of fall/overthrow” and 54 cases of “construction/lamp/tree removal with risk of fall/overthrow”. There were also nine situations involving “removal of scaffolding or other facilities in workshops with risk of falling/overthrowing”, a case of “retention in the elevator” and another of “fire”.
The Institute for Municipal Affairs indicated that after cleaning and security assessment, more than 80% of parks, 90% of leisure zones and all dogs ride zones were reopened yesterday afternoon.
The telephone support line, in turn, received 123 calls. The Public Security Police Corps also carried out an operation, and intercepted two cases of taxi drivers and four cases of unlicensed vehicles.</description><pubDate>2025-07-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hengqin can welcome more universities in Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/hengqin-podera-acolher-mais-universidades-de-macau/</link><description>The DSEDJ has revealed that the government has already communicated with Hengqin authorities to reserve “sufficient land” near UMA Campus in Hengqin for the construction of facilities from other public higher education institutions in Macau
 
In addition to the new campus of the University of Macau (one) in Hengqin, which is expected to operate in 2028, the Government of MSAR has already communicated with the Cooperation Zone Executive Committee, “in order to reserve sufficient land near the UMA Campus in Hengqin for the construction of new campuses of other public higher education institutions,” said the direction of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ), in response to a response to a response Deputy Leong Hong's Written Interpelation
DSEDJ has ensured that the government gradually plan and promotes the development of projects from other higher education institutions that meet the necessary conditions.
As for the Campus of UM in Hengqin, included in the first phase of construction of the city (university) of International Education of Macao and Hengqin, whose area will be over 370 thousand square meters, DSEDJ revealed that planning and conception have already been completed. Construction is expected to begin later this year, he pointed out, describing that this campus will integrate medical schools, science and technologies of information and design, among other new units of UM, which plans to cooperate with higher education institutions abroad.
Also for the purpose of “university city”, higher education institutions will be encouraged to strengthen the construction of bases for industry-inmade-enclosure, as well as cooperating with companies, added the body led by Kong Chi Meng.
The Institute of Scientific and Technological Research in Zhuhai and the UM HENGQIN Institute of Advanced Research, created more than 150 research projects commissioned by companies. In total, 19 joint laboratories were created to guide research and integration between industry and education, according to DSEDJ.
 
Renewed scientific cooperation with Portugal
On the other hand, according to the same answer, the Fund for Science and Technology Development (FDCT) is in negotiations with the Portuguese Science and Technology Foundation for the renewal of the Cooperation Agreement. In general, the FDCT promised that it will continue to review and optimize work in terms of financing and activities and to support the development of macao's state -of -the -art science and technology.
In addition, the government is studying the search for appropriate land in Macao to build an industrial park for research and development of science and technology that satisfies future development needs. "The park concerned will become a space to host and attract the subjects of international level innovation and provide complementary conditions and facilities appropriate to the development of the science and technology industry," he said, citing the direction of economy and technological development services.
In addition, this park “will have as its nuclear strategy the capture of medium and high and quality technology companies that have a high and high levels of research and development and development of the middle of professional work opportunities and offering a development platform for science and technology staff,” said the body.
According to stressed, the park “will have a deep connection with local higher education and scientific research institutions”, through “multiple ways”, including the creation of joint laboratories and research and technology transfer centers.
In addition, according to the answer, the government will actively participate in the preparatory work and the construction of the Technology Transfer and Transformation Center of Higher Education Institutions in the State of the Great Bay, promoting the integration of industry-academia-investigation.</description><pubDate>2025-07-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Offenses committed by taxi drivers rose 168%</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/infraccoes-cometidas-por-taxistas-subiram-168/</link><description>In the first half of this year alone the irregularities practiced by taxi drivers already exceeded the total of last year. According to data from the Public Security Police Corps, there were more offenses related to improper charges and refusals of service
 
Pedro Milheirão
The irregularities practiced by taxi drivers rose again and have already exceeded the total of cases recorded throughout the last year. According to data consulted by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, between January and June, the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) reported a total of 1,154 cases of offenses.
In the same period last year, the authorities accounted for 430, which translates into an increase of 168.4%. Throughout 2024, there were 870 cases, only 284 less than in the first half of this year. Thus, it is observed that there was an increase of about 33% between January and June compared to the total of infractions recorded last year.
Situations of “abusive collection” have more than doubled (118.2%) until June, when compared to the 2024 homologous period. There were 24 cases in which taxi drivers improperly charged passengers, while last year there were 11. The “transport refusals” also increased considerably (+72.5%). The taxi drivers denied service on 257 occasions, against 149.
At the same time, the number of cases in which taxi drivers did not wait for the order of customers in taxi squares fired. Between January and June 2024, CPSP reported only 117. This year, there were 719 (+514.5%) occasions when taxi drivers disrespected the arrival order.
In addition, taxi drivers used “inadequate speed” 27 times, compared to the 24th of the first half of 2024. There were still 60 “other irregularities”, plus 18 in homologous terms. Of the total cases registered by CPSP, 282 were delivered to the Directorate of Traffic Affairs Services (+77.4%).
Road accidents involving pedestrians also increased in the first half. 312 occurrences were recorded, plus 72 (+30%). There were more situations involving women (161) than men (151). However, cases with male pawns grew 38.5%, more than those involving female people (+22.9%).
Overall, the roads of Macao accounted for 7,331 road accidents until June. On the other hand, there is also a considerable number of people who “cross the roads without complying with traffic rules” (4,680), only slightly higher than the first six months of last year (4,614).
In the first half, CPSP also blocked 398 more public road vehicles (+38.2%), than in 2024. A total of 1,441 cases, 1,118 were cars (+49.5%) and 323 motorcycles (+9.5%). In addition, vehicles blocked in parking places, charged or with parking meters, rose 70.5%.
Police also registered 98 drivers “without driving”, an increase of 17 (+21%) in relation to the same period of 2024. 492 drivers exceeded the red sign (+24.1%), than last year. Of the 2,530 that did not respect the signaling, 1,559 drove cars and 971 motorcycles.
Regarding infringements related to the road traffic law and the Road Code regulation, 365,199, a slight descent in homologous terms.</description><pubDate>2025-07-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cuts in Western aid give in ground to China in Southeast Asia</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/actual/cortes-na-ajuda-ocidental-cedem-terreno-a-china-sudeste-asiatico/</link><description>China is ready to expand its influence on the development of Southeast Asia as the Trump administration and other western donors reduce help, according to a study by an Australian Think Tank. The region is in an “uncertain moment”, facing Western funding cuts for development, as well as “especially punitive” trade tariffs from the US, the Sydney -based Lowy Institute said. "The decline of western aid runs the risk of giving up a larger role to China, although other Asian donors also gain importance," the study says. Total official financing for Southeast Asia's development - including donations, low interest rate loans and other loans - grew “modestly” to $ 29 billion by 2023, according to the annual report. But US President Donald Trump suspended about $ 60 billion in development assistance-most of the US foreign aid program. Seven European countries - including France and Germany - and the European Union announced cuts of $ 17.2 billion in helping to implement between 2025 and 2029, according to the report. And the UK is reducing annual aid by $ 7.6 billion, redirecting public money to the defense. Based on recent announcements, the official general financing for Southeast Asia will fall by more than $ 2 billion by 2026, according to the study. "These cuts will harshly affect Southeast Asia," he said. "The poorest countries and the priorities of the social sector, such as health, education and the support of civil society, which depend on bilateral help financing, will probably be the ones that will lose the most." Countries with higher income already capture most of the official financing for the development of the region, the “Asian Aid Help Map” reports. Poor countries, such as Timor-Leste, Cambodia, Laos and Myanmar, are being left behind, creating an increasing division that can undermine stability, equity and long-term resilience, warns the report. Despite substantial economic development in most of Southeast Asia, about 86 million people still live with less than $ 3.65 a day, according to the study. “The center of gravity of the Southeast Asia development scenario seems to be moving to east, especially to Beijing, but also to Tokyo and Seoul,” he says. With the weakening of commercial ties with the US, the development options of Southeast Asian countries will be able to shrink, the study says, leaving them with less power to negotiate favorable conditions with Beijing. "The relative importance of China as a development actor in the region will increase as Western support for development decreases," he says. Beijing's financing for the development of the region rose $ 1.6 billion, reaching 4.9 billion in 2023-mainly through major infrastructure projects, such as rail connections in Indonesia and Malaysia, according to the report. At the same time, China's infrastructure commitments quadrupled, reaching almost $ 10 billion, largely due to the resuming of the Kyaukphyu deep water port project in Myanmar. In contrast, Western Alternative Infrastructure Projects have not realized in recent years, the study says. "Likewise, western promises of supporting the transition to clean energy in the region have not yet translated into more projects into practice - a global concern, as Southeast Asia, coal -dependent, is an important source of rapidly growing carbon emissions."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-07-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>433 Interest Bonus Requests for SMEs</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/aprovados-433-pedidos-de-bonificacao-de-juros-para-pme/</link><description>_Cuva



More than 400 small and medium -sized businesses got interest bonuses under the plan launched in April. According to DSEDT, bank credit involves about 1.1 billion patacas while bonuses reach 130 million
 
The Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) received, between April 22 and July 16, a total of 581 interest bonus requests under the Bank Credit Interest Bonus Plan for Small and Medium Enterprises (SME). Of these, 433 were approved, or 74.5% of the total, “involving bank credits worth about 1.1 billion patacas and bonuses worth 130 million patacas,” the body said.
According to the information available, in the same period, more than 1,300 loans related to this plan were submitted.
DSEDT ensures that "it continues to collaborate closely with licensed banks to streamline the loan approval process, with the aim of facilitating companies, supporting their sustainable development and safeguarding the employment of the population."
The plan aims to help SMEs reinforce the flow of capital, promote the stable development of companies and increase their confidence in business exploration.
Qualified SMEs may require the credit interest bonus through banks, provided that they obtain, between April 22, 2025 and April 22, 2026, the credit authorized by a Bank licensed in Macao designed to finance the company's Candidate Management Background, says DSEDT.
It is recalled that the maximum amount of credits to be granted to each commercial entrepreneur is five million patacas, with a maximum bonus period of three years and the maximum limit of the annual bonus rate is 4%.
In a statement, DSEDT also states that, in collaboration with the banking sector and associations and institutions, it has already organized more than 10 clarification sessions, having presented in detail the contents related to the plan, such as the form of bonus, application requirements and appreciation procedures.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-07-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sinch celebrates agreement with Banco da China</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-celebra-acordo-banco-da-china/</link><description>The Government of MSar and the bank of China signed a cooperation agreement, with a view to “accelerating the high quality development of modern finances in Macao”. The chief executive expects to “provide better quality financial services to residents”
 
Secretary for Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP, and China's vice president, Wu Jian, signed a "global strategic cooperation agreement between Banco da China and the Government of Masters." The meeting between both parties took place in the in -depth cooperation zone and was attended by Sam Hou Fai, head of the Executive, and Ge Haijiao, chairman of the Banco da China Board of Directors, according to a statement of the media.
Sam Hou Fai expects Banco da China to “contribute to accelerate the high quality development of modern finances in Macao, promotes financial innovation and articulation with international standards and participates deeply in building the great bay”. The aim is to create “a higher level opening platform, and provide better quality financial services to residents”, he said.
The Chief Executive also thanked the bank "for supporting the economic growth of the territory over the years" and for the help in the "active promotion of the proper diversification of the economy and the development of the cooperation zone." Sam Hou Fai noted that Banco da China “has been deeply rooted in Macau 75 years ago” and stressed the contribution of the financial institution to the development of the region.
The leader of the Government of Manders met with Ge Haijiao before the signing of the agreement, according to the statement. Both exchanged impressions of the deepening of cooperation and the role of the financial sector in the service to the “real economy” of Macao.
At the meeting were Vong Sin Man, substitute president of the board of directors of the monetary authority of Macao, the chief of the chief executive, Chan Kak, and Jia Tianbing, president of the Macao branch, among others.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Job Fair attracted more than 1,000 young people</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/feira-de-emprego-atraiu-mais-de-mil-jovens/</link><description>More than a thousand participants were present on the first day of the “Job Fair for Youth”, which took place at the Macao Tower to apply for more than 1,100 vacancies in various activity sectors
 
The first day of the “Young Employment Fair”, organized by the Directorate of Services for Laboral Affairs (DSAL) and the Macao New Youth Association, registered 1,006 participants at the Macao Tower Convention and Entertainment Center. Under the theme “Professional Guidance, Preparation for the Future”, the initiative was attended by more than 50 companies from hotel, tourist and leisure, financial and information technologies, among others, which provided more than 1,100 vacancies, according to DSAL.
A professional evaluation service was also launched to assist young people to “understand their vocational interests and discover their professional potential”, according to the statement. The launch was accompanied by a personalized consulting service, organized on site by specialized trainers, whose aim was to help participants understand the “degree of compatibility” with the available places and facilitate the planning of their professional careers.
The fair continued with thematic lectures on employment in the industries of 'Big Health', state -of -the -art technology, environment and cybersecurity. Representatives of different industries were also invited to share professional experiences. DSSA also organized 'Roadshows' and exhibition stations, with other publicly bodies of the MSAR, the Directorate of Subsistence Services in the Hengqin and Business Cooperation Zone on the sectors of activity of the two regions.
Dsal's director Chan Un Tong has assured that "the government has always defined youthful employment as one of the priorities of governance actions." Chan also encouraged young people “to be open to new experiences, to actively strive to learn, to increase their professional competitiveness, to accompany the evolution of labor market trends, and to discover their course of professional development according to their interests”.
The inauguration of the fair was chaired by Tai Kin IP, Secretary for Economics and Finance, and by the department of the Department of Education and Youth Affairs of the Central Government's connection, Shucheng. It was also attended by Chan Chou Weng, subdirector of economics and technological development services, Wong Ka Ki, subdirector of education and youth development services, among others. “The government will continuously follow the employment market and the situation of the employment of the youth of Macao,” can be read in the statement.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“A trip to the land of the crocodile” presents 25 photographs</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/uma-viagem-a-terra-crocodilo-apresenta-25-fotografias/</link><description>It is today inaugurated, at the Rui Cunha Foundation, the exhibition “A Travel to the Land of Crocodile in the year of the serpent”, with photographs by Cristiana Figueiredo and texts by Bibi Ain. The show will be patent until August 2

























He is entitled “a trip to the land of the crocodile in the year of the serpent” and is a photographic exhibition about Timor-Leste, by Cristiana Figueiredo (photos) and Bibi Ain (texts). It will be inaugurated today, at 18:30, at the Rui Cunha Foundation.
Resulting from a journey of discovery, to Cristiana Figueiredo, and from reunion, to Bibi Ain, the show, under the subtitle "people. Places." Things "presents 25 photographs that" visually reveal what texts describe about emotions impregnated in the small details of the journey. "
“In early 2025, we embarked on a trip to Timor-Leste. For one of us, it was the discovery of home roots, the hug of the loved ones, the reappearance of sweet and fragile memories. To the other, he went to a history book and feel the welcome of the unknown,” says the authors, cited in a statement.
The trip was “an intimate and inspiring lift” in Timor-Leste, “where apparently disparate perspectives came together to create new perspectives, about the people and places of this wonderful small country,” reveals the pair of travelers in his manifesto.
“Behind the lens, I witnessed the transformation of shy behaviors into generous tropical smiles that revealed intimate and fleeting glimpses. I found a landscape that surrendered to the capture of the windy car on a bumpy road, or a quiet moment with the feet buried in the hot sand, caressed by the sound of the waves. Of love to Timor-Leste, ”says Cristiana Figueiredo.
The author's life is a three -year -old tapestry. He was born in Angola, passed the years of training in Portugal. “In quiet afternoons after school, flipping through parents' art encyclopedias aroused her passion for the arts, an early fascination that inspired her to take several short courses in the history of art, design and painting, and to dedicate herself to photography, throwing the foundations for her creative path,” she can read.
After completing the degree in Sociology at the University of Porto, Cristiana's life brought her to Macau, where, in the last 23 years, she has been a local entrepreneur in the food and drink, having her creativity turned to graphic design, branding and interior design. Recently, it has become full-time visual creator.
In turn, Bibi Ain's life is a woven tapestry between three countries. Born in Timor-Leste, he spent the years of training in Australia. Studied Art, History of Art, Cinema and Television, English and Italian literature, architecture, business management and, finally, tourist management. It served your country as a diplomat in the last thirty years. Bibi Ain, stage name, derives from the word tetum “bibi” (goat) and “ain” (foot). “Like a goat who jumps everywhere with enthusiasm in search of a new adventure, my family dubbed me to reflect my thirst to travel,” he explains.
The images and texts will be displayed until August 2, being free admission.</description><pubDate>2025-07-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Wynn inaugurates the largest immersive ceramic exhibition in Jingdezen</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/wynn-inaugura-maior-exposicao-imersiva-de-ceramica-de-jingdezhen/</link><description>As part of the “Special Exhibition” of the Macao International Biennial, Wynn opened the “Hello China, Hello Macau - The Odyssey of Porcelain Jingezen” project. It is the first large -scale jingedens ceramic immersive exhibition in the world. The show will be evident at Wynn Palace until October

Wynn Palace inaugurated the exhibition "Hello China, Hello Macao - the Porcelain Jingezen Odyssey: a patrimonial journey from Macao to the world." This is the “first large-scale immersive art exhibition of the world with porcelains of Jingezen”, according to a Wynn press release. The show belongs to the “Special Exhibition” section of Macau's International Art Biennial.
Until October 19, the exhibition will be evident to the public on the “Palace Reserve Club Gallery” from 11h00 to 19h00, with free admission.
The project includes a digital display that "recreates elements such as the history of ceramics, the silk sea route in Macao and masterpieces of the Qing Dynasty, with 360-degree immersive projections." This shows the role that Jingezen played in ceramic production techniques around the world.
The exhibition also features Master Chang Shana's “Dove of Peace”, as well as other artwork from more than 30 contemporary handcrafted masters, including Lu Ru, Ning Gang, Liu Wei, Huang Jingzang and Liu Wenbin. Four ceramic varieties will be presented, including porcelain “Clark”, which reflects “traces of sino-Portuguese cultural exchange”. Similarly, the Buccleuch vessels, a Wynn art collection, is another “epic set of masterpieces that incorporates the fusion of oriental and western art”.
Master Chang Shana was invited to serve as the main aesthetic counselor of the exhibition. Renowned Chinese artist and educator, Chang was one of the main designers of the Great Hall of the People, chaired the Central Academy of Arts and Crafts and was recognized by the Chinese Federation of Literary Circles and Art.
A feast was also held to mark the beginning of the Biennial, promote the culture of Jiangxi and build a bridge that connects the treasures of this culture to the rest of the world. Also organized was the Seminar Seminar of the Silk Route - New Chapter of Macao ”to celebrate“ The Mutual Exchange and Appreciation between Chinese and Foreign Civilizations ”.
Han Xingwen, manager of Jiangxi Media Group, reflected on the moment a Portuguese ship, loaded with porcelain "Clark", left Macao, becoming "a cultural symbol for understanding Europe over China."
In turn, the president of the Cultural Institute, Leong Wai Man, highlighted the “pioneer initiative in the scope of the Government of the Government of the Government 'collaboration' model to promote Chinese culture in an innovative way”. Leong added that the MSAR is "a base of exchange and cooperation where Chinese culture is the dominant current and coexist various cultures."
Linda Chen, president of Wynn Macau, explained that the exhibition “offers residents and tourists a new perspective with an immersive experience” of Qing dynasty treasures. The operator's new cultural brand, "Wynn Culture", adheres to three fundamental principles, prepared Linda Chen, namely "defending integrity and innovation, dialogue with the world and transmitting traditions, and rooting in Macao."
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>"Hush!" open to proposals for artists and curators</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/hush-aberto-propostas-de-artistas-curadores/</link><description>By the end of this month, bands, musicians and curators of local artistic facilities will be able to submit proposals to participate in the “Hush!” Festival, which will take place in October at Praia de Hac-Sá
 
The Cultural Institute (IC) will accept, until July 31, proposals of bands, musicians and curators of local artistic facilities interested in participating in the event “Hush! Concerts on Praia 2025”, scheduled for October 18 and 19 at HAC-Sá Beach.
This musical marathon on various stages will also include a series of extension activities from 11 October, namely communities shows, music workshops, thematic musical development projects, artistic installations, children's recreation areas, online activities, among others. The organization will also combine recreational and sports activities outdoors in the sea and on land, in order to “create a large interdisciplinary musical festival”.
During the “Hush!” Festival, which focuses mainly on pop music, the bands will be divided into three categories (“Hot Wave”, “Music Chill” and “Hush! Kids”) and at least half of the songs and songs performed must be original compositions. In addition, special performance projects are programmed, such as the “Upbeat Power” concert, “Macau Cruise Concert” and “Extra shows in communities”.
Songs and songs to be played in the “Hush! Kids” category may not be original. According to the IC, it will also be welcome to participate bands or groups of adults who have songs intended for children.
With the purpose of promoting the diversification of pop music activities, this edition was launched an invitation to present projects of “artistic facilities”. These should have the beach of HAC-Sá and the adjacent forest zone as places to plan, conceive and produce outdoor artistic facilities that fit the theme of the event. THE
Already the “project of themed musical development” allows the bands, musicians and curators to show their creativity in the production of shows. In turn, the “music workshops” will admit, on their own or third party recommendation, the participation of instructors to convey knowledge about pop music.
The regulation and registration report for the presentation of proposals for bands, musicians and curators of local artistic facilities and extra activities for “Hush! Concerts on the Beach” are available on the IC website and on the “Hush Full Music” page on Facebook.</description><pubDate>2025-07-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Influenza cases tripled between May and June</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/casos-de-influenza-triplicaram-entre-maio-junho/</link><description>Close up of unrecognizable Doctor Vaccinating Child in Medical Clinic, Copy Space



Health services (SSM) reported 1,616 cases of mandatory statement diseases in June, with influenza infections representing 78.1% of the total. There are currently 45 types of diseases in Macao that require mandatory statement in the framework of monitoring of transmitted diseases. According to the SSM, compared to the previous month, diseases with more significant changes in the number of cases were enterovirus infection (rising 182.5%), influenza (increase of 214.7%) and Salmonella (plus 22.2%). In June, 1,262 cases of influenza were declared, which corresponds to a 30.5% rise compared to the 967 registered in the same month of 2024. The incidence of influenza, highly contagious acute respiratory disease, is predominant in winter and spring (from January to March) and summer (from June to August). In Macao, the most frequent types are flu A (H1N1 and H3N2) and flu B. On the other hand, cases of enteroviruses, which are more frequent in summer, descended 86.2% to 153 in June in the annual comparison. Salmonella cases grew 37.5% to 22 in annual terms. Most Salmonella infections occur between July and October.</description><pubDate>2025-07-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Technological industry “will inject new impetus” into the economy of the</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/industria-tecnologica-injectara-novo-impeto-na-economia-da-raem/</link><description>The chief executive believes that "the growth of the technological industry will inject a new momentum into the economy of Macao", creating "high quality jobs" and providing "a stage for Macau young people to pursue their dreams and aspirations." In speaking at the first plenary meeting of the Science and Technology Council, he stressed that "the technological industry will be a relevant chapter for Macao's future development." Since cutting -edge technology is one of four priority industries under the “1+4” plan, Sam Hou Fai has stated that the government “is intensifying efforts to continually improve the system and the scientific and technological innovation mechanism”. He also recalled that in the lines of government action it was announced that support and financing will be increased to diversified industries. To better achieve the objective of “attracting, retaining and stabilizing” companies and staff in this area, it has argued that it is necessary to “emancipate the mindset”, but also to work on strategic planning, namely “policy system, incentive mechanism, resource platform, and support services, to transform, in practice, the institutional advantages of Macau”, in order to help companies and talents that are established in the field. It also stated that it is “indispensable” to congregate social consensus and form a strong synergy to promote the conversion and modernization of the economy. In this sense, it pointed out that it is necessary to coordinate six “fundamental relations”: balance between the short -term response and long -term planning; Positive interaction between evaluation of difficulties and reinforcing trust; Articulation of market vitality with government orientation; Resource reserve development and growth optimization; Promotion of economic growth and improvement of quality of life; and coordination between high quality development and internal safety guarantee.</description><pubDate>2025-07-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lisbon National Library more digitized and open to the community</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/biblioteca-nacional-de-lisboa-mais-digitalizada-aberta-a-comunidade-ana-mendes-henriques/</link><description>A user consults a book in the National Library, during a report on the institution that has the Portuguese Bibliographic Heritage in Lisbon, July 15, 2025. The National Library of Portugal (BNP) wants to receive students from secondary education and lower from 18 to 16 years old access to the institution, guardian of more than three million books. (Accompanies Lusa text on July 19, 2025). António Pedro Santos/Lusa



Ana Mendes Henriques*
The National Library Amphitheater will be restored with funds from the Plan of Recovery and Resilience (PRR), through an endeavor to launch in the coming months, which should be completed in less than a year. "We managed, through two projects we already had in a portfolio, to go to the last phase of the PRR of works," the Director General of the National Library of Portugal (BNP), Diogo Ramada Curta, told Lusa.
At this time, the last review of the projects takes place. “We have told in the coming months to launch the venture, which we have to execute until the middle of next year and we will recover, on the one hand, the amphitheater and, on the other, a reserved room,” where rare and manuscript books are found, the official said.
One million and one hundred thousand euros is the value of PRR intended for works in the amphitheater and in the other room, through a “small reimbursement” of the library.
"We have to fulfill, we are committed to this fulfillment," said Diogo Ramada Short, by doing accounts.
The amphitheater, with access to the outside of the building, will be open to the community. The endeavor includes the arrangement of adjacent spaces, for years unused.
BNP is also in the phase of compliance with a PRR for conservation, digitization and cataloging, worth seven million euros. "We have had this impulse given to us by the PRR and we are in a good phase of execution. It has already been digitized and we are now advancing to the next phase, which is fundamentally the availability of this material," said the director.
“When I arrived at the library [in April 2024] 11% had been executed. At this time, we are about 60% and we will comply with all this PRR,” said Diogo Ramada Curta.
The library has a large collection of rare books, as well as all the current Portuguese bibliographic production, which is in the legal deposit, distributed by 15 floors.
Special collections are made up of rare and old books. "We have the largest collection of Portuguese books since the fifteenth century to our day ... and one of the greatest collections, if not, I think it is the largest, the country's collection of ancient music," he said.
"These are the treasures we have and we are looking to rendict," he said.
Restoration workshops have been one of the main concerns about preserving heritage to the BNP custody, according to Diogo Ramada Short: "One of the essential fundamental aspects is restoration, conservation, binding. We are particularly committed. We have an extraordinary team there. It is a very dedicated team and we are dynamizing these workshops."
In the BNP workshops are restored posters, printed books and manuscripts, in a lengthy work, which requires milutia and expertise. A common restoration can take between three weeks to a month. Rare volumes, such as parchment manuscripts, leather and wood pieces require six months of attention.
A seventeenth -century manuscript with these characteristics is now among the relics awaiting intervention in the workshop.
BNP treasures include Fernando Pessoa documents found after the poet's death. “Fernando Pessoa's so -called ark is with us, but there are many other spoils we have here and we will try to make available by creating digital platforms, which seems to be the fundamental leap that we are trying to develop,” explained the historian.
“We are particularly committed to creating two pilot projects, the first of a digital Camonian and, secondly, in the construction of a digital person,” said Diogo Ramada Curta.
The project related to the work of Luís de Camões is being developed in collaboration with the mission structure for the celebrations of the 5th centenary of the birth of the poet. "We hope soon will have results to present this digital Camonian," he said.
The two projects will give new visibility to the special collections that BNP has seen growing from writer and intellectual spoils. “Let's go to about 230 spoils,” said the director-general.
 
JTM/LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-07-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>