<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Masters want “more inclusive and effective” international exchange platform</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-quer-plataforma-de-intercambio-internacional-mais-inclusiva-eficaz/</link><description>The Chief Executive has secured, at a reception of the general consuls at MSAR and Raehk and to representatives of international organizations, which is committed to building an international exchange platform “more inclusive, more convenient, and more effective”. Defending that “openness and inclusiveness are in the genes of Macau”, Sam Hou Fai assured that the territory is willing to “share” development opportunities “with all countries and regions, widening the 'circle of friends' international”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Macao “is committed” and will work “for the construction of a more inclusive, more convenient, and more effective international exchange platform”, promised the executive head at a consules-general reception dinner at MSAR and Raehk and representatives of international organizations. "Opening and inclusiveness are in Macao genes. It was China's Foreign Commerce Port in the 16th century, and is today 'a center, a platform, a base'," said Sam Hou Fai, during the speech he gave.
"We are deeply aware that only embracing the world we can achieve the future. We will take initiative to articulate with the strategy of national development, and, having as its driving force the innovation of legal regimes and the optimization of policies, we will coordinate the common progress of government and market, from Macao and the world," he continued.
In this sense, Sam Hou Fai has expressed the expectation that the general consuls and representatives "continue to play the role of bridge", presenting mashes to other countries. "Macao is small in physical space, but with an extended ambition. We are an important connection city within the initiative" a track, a route ", and we have always striving to build an international cooperation platform," added the chief executive.
"In the future, we will build a high quality opening platform, and expand the international routes network," said Sam Hou Fai, saying that Macao's "advantage" will be taken advantage of, "where Chinese and Western cultures meet, to promote international exchange between people with different worlds and make it an important window for mutual exchange and learning."
In the same speech, the leader of the MSAR has ensured that the government is committed to “fostering the development of the proper diversification of the economy”, striving to boost the construction of the deepened cooperation zone. In this field, he argued that "" Macau + Hengqin "is assuming itself as the new example of enriching the application of the principle" a country, two systems ", the new level driving the construction of the great bay and the new platform to realize the opening of the country of high quality abroad."
Starting from a general and long -term perspective, Sam Hou Fai recalled, the executive plans to launch a set of "iconic works", hoping that they "have driving effects." The Chief Executive spoke of the University City of International Education of Macao and Hengqin, which is being promoted in a phase in the international tourist and cultural neighborhood, in the International Air Transport Hub, and the Science and Technologies Industrial Research and Development Park.
That said, the highest leader of MSAR has ensured that "Macau is willing to share development opportunities with all countries and regions, widening the 'circle of friends' international to achieve increasing cooperation."
Sam Hou Fai invited the companies and talents of "all countries" to "accompany the evolution of the times" and even said that "investing in China is investing in the future." "The Great Bay, including Macau and the Hengqin cooperation zone, will provide unlimited possibilities to global partners with the best policies and services, both for high quality manufacturing, development and research industries, and for green financial innovation, and other industries," he added.
“Macao shines more and more with its multiculturality and internationalization, which makes us proud,” said the chief executive.
 
Apply “a country, two systems” in the “right direction”
It also stressed that the “one country, two systems” principle is “the biggest advantage for Macao's development”. And at this point, he recalled the words of the Chinese President Xi Jinping: “The splendid successes achieved by Macau after his return to his homeland have proven to the world that 'a country' has a distinct institutional force and great vitality. It is a good system that sustains prosperity and lasting stability of Hong Kong and Macau. System for the guarantee of peaceful coexistence and the cooperation of shared gains between different social systems.
Thus, Sam Hou Fai pointed out that “it is necessary to continue to execute accurately and firmly, and broadly, the principles 'a country, two systems', 'Hong Kong ruled by their people' and 'Macau ruled by their people' with a high degree of autonomy, and ensure their unalterable and unshakable implementation, without any deviation or any deformation”.
On the one hand, he said it was “imperative” to persist in the fundamental politics of “a country”: to place sovereignty, security and development interests in the country above all, to ensure the defense of “a country”, implement the full power of governance of central government and not deviate from this commitment under any circumstances. On the other hand, he stated that it is necessary to persist in the policy of “two systems”, that is, “fully guarantee a high degree of autonomy of Macao, keeping the capitalist system and their way of living, its status of Porto International and Autonomous Customs Zone, and the Macao European Law System in Macao”.
The leader of the MSA promised, therefore, to ensure the defense of "a country", persist in the politics of "two systems", and boost the stable and lasting application of the principle "one country, two systems" in the "right direction".
Over the past three years, organizations such as the United Nations and the European Union have shown concerns about actions by the Macao authorities, arguing that they have contradicted the basic principles enrolled in Basic Law; An example of this is the exclusion of candidates for elections in the Legislative Assembly or the prohibition of demonstrations. Criticism has always been denied by local authorities.
The reception where Hou Hou Fai spoke was attended by representatives of consulates-generals of about 50 countries and international organizations. Also present were the Commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs at MSAR, Liu Xianfa, Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, Secretary for Security, Wong Sio Chak, Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, and Chief Executive Chief Chan Kak.
 
Chief Praise Reinforcement of Transfronho Consumption
Noting that the great bay "is one of the most open regions, with strong economic vitality and the largest consumer market in China," the chief executive said that the change in the consumption model after the pandemic has reinforced "the transionic consumption by residents," which described as "unprecedented enthusiasm." For Sam Hou Fai, this new scenario “injects a new dynamic to revitalize consumption and boost high quality consumption in the large bay, further broaden the internal demand market and even promote high quality development” in the region. The leader of the sgas spoke, in a virtual format, in the ceremony that began the activity “Purchases in China - consumption in the great bay”, saying that it will “attract even more tourists from the interior of China and abroad to consume in Macao, and constantly enrich the image of Macao as the world center of tourism and leisure”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Firefighters make “triplet” in the tank top boats</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/bombeiros-fazem-triplete-nas-regatas-de-barcos-dragao/</link><description>The Fire Department teams dominated the first two days of Macao's dragon boat tank tops, triumphing into three male categories. In women's tests, highlighting the “Tong Law Engineering &amp; Construction” and “Association of Macao Youth Development”, respectively in large and small vessels. SJM Golden Jubilee was the fastest in the mixed class debut



















Victor Rebelo
 
The Fire Department and the Association of Macao Youth Development were the winners of the main tank tops of the first two days of the Macao International Schedule of Boats ”, which took place in the waters of Lake Nam Van, in the Nautical Center of Praia Grande.
In the Open category competition, intended for large vessels, a distance of 500 meters, the Fire Department lived up to the superiority manifested several years ago and hit its most direct rival, Dong Roan Dragonboat Team for more than two seconds. The "Peace Soldiers" vessel made the time of 1 minute, 55 seconds and 936 thousandths, against 1,58,030 of the opponent.
The SJM Golden Jubilee team occupied the last place in the podium (1.58.286). Soon after, Wynn, Sands China and MGM were positioned.
In the ladies' final, the game operators teams, considered the main favorites to the title, were surprised by the formation of Tong Lei Engineering &amp; Construction, which recorded the mark of 2,14,812. More slowly almost two seconds, SJM Golden Lotus was second and Wynn Third. Sands China failed better than fourth place, leaving the last places for Galaxy Pearl and Macao Youth Canoe Club.
In yesterday's last race, the news class, this year's news, the triumph was up to SJM Golden Jubilee, ahead of Tong Lei Engineering &amp; Construction and Sands China.
However, on Saturday, the events intended for the smaller boats of 12 athletes (10 rowers, an element to the rudder and a drummer), with competitions of 200 meters away.
In the open category (Open), the Fire Department team stood out in the qualifiers and semi-finals, reaching the discussion of the title as a favorite. In the final, the main rivals hit the two formations of SJM in the immediate place. Prosperous was in second place and Golden Jubilee in third.
Firefighters, who repeated the 2024 triumph, reached the time of 48,856, more than two seconds of advantage over the SJM Prosperous vessel. The remaining participants in the final were Tong Lei Engineering &amp; Construction Co. Ltd, Wynn Glory and Dong Rong Dragonboat Team, who qualified in the same order from fourth place.
In the female class, there was superiority of the Association of Macao Youth Development, which, like firefighters, repeated last year's title.
The winning boat recorded the 58,605 mark, against Wynn Elegance's 1,00,630. This was followed by SJM Golden Lotus-A, ahead of Tong Lei Engineering &amp; Construction, Sands China and SJM Golden Lotus-B.
Also in the small vessels, but in the race for higher education students, the University of Macao team (one) - defended her the 2024 triumph, winning with the time of 51,372. Macao Polytechnic University - was second and one - B in third.
In the race of the Macao Government Departments, the victory belonged to the Fire Department, followed by the Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs - A and Institute for Municipal Affairs - A.
On the 31st, Saturday, Tung NG holiday, international tests will be held by invitation, Open category, ladies and university, all at a distance of 500 meters. The continent, Hong Kong, Thailand, Singapore, Philippines, Malaysia and Egypt participate, along with Macao representative teams. This year, the races received the registration of 139 teams.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>437 proposals for 20 stalls in the mud market</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/437-propostas-para-20-bancas-mercado-da-taipa/</link><description>The public tender for the operation of 20 lights of light meals, coffee shop and cultural and creative articles in the mud market was in adhesion, with the AI ​​register the entry of more than 400 proposals
 
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) received 437 proposals under the public tender for the exploitation of 20 stalls in the mud market. In addition to maintaining the sale of fresh and living food products and traditional trinkets on the market floor, 19 light and creative and creative meals on the first floor, and a coffee shop on the terrace.
Under the management regime of public markets, AMI Angaria Rentaries through a public tender. In this concrete case, the body has intended to attract young operators and “new concepts of exploitation”, contributing to introduce the “gastronomy + cultural creativity” to the mud market, which society has been proposing, in order to boost the “transformation of traditional markets” and make available “more diverse purchasing options for residents”.
In the process of appreciation of proposals, competitors will be evaluated based on five main criteria, including the strategy of operation, experience and qualification, and the diversity of the typology of goods. Thus, AMI intends to “inject a new vitality in the market”.
According to the announcement of the contest, whose deadline for delivery of proposals ended on Friday, the "competitor's operation strategies" have a weight of 60% in the evaluation of the proposals. Here are “diversity of goods typology” (20%), “daily bank exploration time” (10%), “competitor experience and qualifications” (5%) and “convenience of payment instruments” (5%).
With a view to the good use of public resources, the contract term is three years. During the exploration period, the stalls exploration situation will be the target of inspection and evaluation, ensured AMI, warning that those who violate the law or do not comply with the standards may see the respective contracts terminated.
The competition regulation establishes that the daily opening hours of the newsstands cannot be less than eight hours, and the daily operation between 10h00 and 18h00 is mandatory.
After the evaluation committee evaluate all the documentation delivered by the competitors, the priority list of the newsstands will be prepared and published. Stands are scheduled for the fourth quarter of this year.
 
Sá Kong Cemetery will have at 2026 plus 10,000 gray drawers
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) plans to expand the gray deposit facilities at Sá Kong Municipal Cemetery in Taipa. The idea is to do a work in three phases, to be started in the 3rd quarter of this year. After the completion of the works, more than 10,000 gray drawers will be available, which are expected to operate in the 1st semester of 2026, the body indicated in response to an interpellation of Deputy Ella Lei. According to AMI, until April this year, there were about 1,000 drawers of 1st class and 2nd class ossaries available. As for gray drawers, the 1st class were all leased in July 2024, and only 2nd class gray drawers are currently available, with about 1,100 drawers. The expansion of the cemetery facilities aims to “meet social development needs”, stresses the body.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>East Line requires budgetary allocation by 2031</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/linha-leste-requer-dotacao-orcamental-ate-2031/</link><description>Although the east line of the light meter is expected to be scheduled for the second half of 2029, it will be necessary to have a budget allocation by 2031, due to the circulation system, as happened with other recently completed lines, DSOP said. The body also ensures that it has supervised the progress of the work and that there is no delays so far
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The eastern line of the light metro is expected to go into operation within four years, however, it will be “necessary to have a budget allocation by 2031”, due to the circulation system, “since some works will continue to be performed after the entry into operation”, revealed the direction of public works (DSOP) services. According to the body, the works are advancing as expected.
Beginning in the third quarter of 2023, it is expected that the construction works of the East Line will end in the first quarter of 2028. But later, commissioning and testing of the circulation system will be performed, “being the east line project to advance towards the objective of gathering the conditions for its entry into the 2nd semester of 2029”.
"Like the bar line, the Hengqin line and the Pai Van Seac line, which were recently completed, after the conclusion of the construction works, were still subject to the completion of the installation of the circulation system and the tests to have conditions of operation. Taking as reference the conclusion, within the time and without delay, of the three lines of the light subway, the Line Line Works Plan," communication.
The total value of the award of the construction works of the southern and northern east line is 9.281 million patacas, an amount being paid according to the progress of the year's work. “Since the work projected for 2024 were completed in advance, it was necessary to transfer allocation to payment purposes,” explains the body.
DSOP guarantees that “it has been strictly overseeing the quality and progress of the work, in order to achieve the objective of gathering the conditions for operating entry” in the second half of 2029. The works related to the circulation system have already begun, while the construction work of underground stations, the tunnel with tuning and the mud line viaducts “are also in accordance with the plan. planned ”.
According to he said, the work of some compulsory goals were even “completed in advance”. In two days, the southern segment tunnel will begin. "At this stage, there is a completion of the global project by about 41% and its progress and budget are as expected," he said.
The body recalls that, with the approval for the use of the “Vit in the form of V”, ES1 station will be moved west, which may reinforce the convenience of the connection between the siege gate border post and the light meter. Despite the increase in work, "the deadline for completion will not be, for now, affected," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DSEDJ supports students affected by the dispute between Trump and Harvard</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dsedj-apoia-alunos-afectados-pela-disputa-entre-trump-harvard/</link><description>In addition to providing counseling and assistance to the affected, DSEDJ urged Macao universities to provide “convenient transfer” methods to local students who are studying at Harvard University after the Trump administration has blocked foreigners registration
 
The Macao government has offered help to young places studying at Harvard University after US President Donald Trump suspending foreign students enrollment at the institution.
The Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) reported on Saturday that it contacted Macau students at Harvard "to provide permanent counseling and assistance." In a statement, DSEDJ said it "is closely following the last developments," but stressed that "circumstances are still changing."
Still, the body encouraged Macao universities to provide "convenient transfer" methods to those affected to "protect students' rights to continue their studies." "Any concrete measure will be decided by each university in accordance with the actual conditions," said the DSEDJ.
On the other hand, he promised to “continue to promote Macao universities and attract exceptional students from around the world” to promote the internationalization of higher education in the territory.
On Friday, a University of Hong Kong had already promised to facilitate the registration of students from Harvard University. Hong Kong University of Science and Technology has announced "unconditional offers, simplified admission procedures and academic support to facilitate a soft transition."
The proposed benefits include “accelerated admissions, credit transfers and personalized support” in visa and accommodation assistance, according to a statement.
On the same day, the China Ministry of Foreign Affairs considered that the decision to ban Harvard University to enroll foreign students undermine the US image and credibility. "The educational cooperation between China and the United States is mutually beneficial," said Foreign Ministry spokeswoman Mao Ning, stressing that Beijing "is firmly opposed to the politicization of educational exchanges" and "rejects unfounded attacks and defamations against China."
The spokesman also assured that China will "firmly protect the legitimate rights and interests of Chinese students and academics abroad."
The statements were made after the US internal security department cited alleged university ties with the Chinese Communist Party to revoke the Harvard's foreign student and visitors program. Beijing rejected the accusations as unfounded and criticized Washington's measures, considering them illegal, appealing to his withdrawal as soon as possible.
Harvard, one of the most prestigious universities in the world, welcomes about 7,000 international students of which approximately 20% are Chinese citizens, according to some estimates. The measure affects both new candidates and current students, who may lose their legal status in the country if they are not transferred to other institutions.
The university, the most prestigious in the US, responded to the Executive with a judicial action, leading a federal judge in Boston, Massachusetts state, to temporarily block the Trump administration measure. Judge Allison D. Burroughs accepted Harvard's temporary suspension of the revocation of permission to welcome international students, representing a quarter of the institution's total students.
"Harvard has shown that without a request to temporarily restrict [the Order of Trump], it will suffer immediate and irreparable damage," the judge noted.
The magistrate scheduled an audience about the case on May 27, which will be attended by representatives on both sides.
Harvard sued the republican government in April to recover his frozen federal financing of $ 2.6 billion for alleged anti-Semite behaviors.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Inflation closer to zero</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/inflacao-mais-perto/</link><description>The annual inflation rate slowed again in Macau, reaching 0.42% in April, according to official data
 
The average consumer pricing index (IPC) at MSAR registered a 0.42% rise in the annual cycle ending in April compared to the immediately preceding 12 months, the most used interval by economists to calculate the annual inflation rate. The percentage, released by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services, confirms the IPC deceleration trend after reaching 0.48% in March, 0.57% in February, 0.70% in January this year.
Following the same temporal goal, official statistics show that the April IPC advanced 0.4% in level A, which encompasses about 50% of family aggregates with monthly expenses between 11 thousand and 35,999 patacas, and 0.44% in category B, which integrates 30% of families with average spending between 36 thousand and 71,999 patacas. In general, DSEC highlights additions to the indices of “various products and services” (+2.47%), “education” (+2.21%) and “health” (+1.62%).
In the general calculation of recent years, the inflation rate in Macau retreated from 1.04% in 2022 to 0.94% by 2023 and 0.74% in 2024. In 2021, it dropped to 0.03%, compared to 0.81% noted in the previous year, after Macau registered nine months in deflation, a situation that had already happened between 2000 and 2003, with negative rates of rates of 1.61%, 1.99%, 2.64%and 1.56%, successively.
According to new DSEC data, the General IPC rose 0.23%compared to April 2024, stimulated by the sections of “Leisure, Recreation, Sport and Culture” (+2.47%) and “Miscellaneous Products and Services” (+1.82%), which encompasses personal care, insurance, jewelery, goldsmiths and watches. Homologous increases extended to “food products and non-alcoholic beverages” (+0.48%) and “housing and fuels” (+0.21%), contrasting with the descents in “information and communication” (-3.01%), “clothing and footwear” (-2.35%) and “transport” (-1.67%).
On the other hand, the IPC increased 0.16% compared to March this year, especially the section of “Leisure, Recreation, Sport and Culture” (+2.6%), due to the increase of hotel room prices. DSEC also emphasizes monthly additions in “Clothing and Footwear (+0.78%) and“ Transport ”(+0.42%), and the descents in“ Information and Communication ”(-0.07%) and“ food products and non-alcoholic beverages ”(-0.04%).
In the first four months of 2025, the average General IPC grew 0.17%, in annual terms, essentially due to “food products and non -alcoholic beverages”, whose index rose 0.63%.
The General IPC covers all household aggregates, and expenses with higher weights in the calculation of inflation are those of housing and fuels, food products and non -alcoholic beverages and transportation, with considerations of 34.47, 29.47 and 8.33, respectively.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Awarded 17 “green” hotels</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/premiados-17-hoteis-verdes/</link><description>Seen Hotels were awarded by the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services, under the “Hotel Green Macau 2024 Award”. The replacement of artificial light with natural light or the installation of electric vehicle charging equipment have been some of the measures adopted by the sector
 
A total of 17 hotels were rewarded by the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA), as part of the “Hotel Green Macau 2024 Award”. In the hotel group, MGM Macau, Nüwa, Morpheus, Sands, Okura and Hotel Contagem decreased by the Golden Prize, while the Silver Award was awarded to the Hotel Imperial and the Broadway Hotel.
Riviera Macao, Legend Palace, Hotel Waldo and Crowne Plaza received the bronze award, while the Merit Award went to the Yoho Treasure Hotel Island Resorts World and City Viva Hotel. With regard to the category of economic accommodation, the Green Pension Award was delivered to Holiday Inn and Hotel I Fu, and the City Pension got the certificate of basic measures.
For DSPA, winning establishments “have been able to effectively reduce operating costs and improve their environmental image”, implementing systematic environmental management measures. Several hotels have calculated emissions and prepared decarbonization strategies, materializing “energy conservation and reducing emissions”, read in the statement.
Some award -winning hotels reorganized the distribution of interior spaces to “maximize natural light entry” or minimize the need for artificial lighting, allowing a decrease in electricity consumption.
In the same vein, several award hotels also gradually installed charging equipment for electric vehicles, in order to promote the development of green transport and to contribute to the reduction of carbon footprint.
In the context of “double carbon target” and to encourage more hotels to adhere to the cause of environmental protection and carbon reduction, DSPA has encouraged the implementation of ecological measures and states that the hotel sector and the Government of MSA have actively contributed in terms of environmental policies.
The body organizes the “Hotel Verde Macau Award”, in collaboration with tourism services and the support of the Hotel Association, the Hotel Association, the Technology Productivity and Transfer Center and the Hotel Industry Employee Association.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Start-Up Recycles Tea Waste</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/start-up-de-macau-recicla-residuos-de-cha/</link><description>The “Zence Object Holding”, a Macao company founded in 2023, has been betting on the transformation of tea plantation waste in China, to create various types of products, including furniture
 
A Macao-based 'start-up' has created a business based on tea plantations in China, which recycles on paper, shopping bags, glasses, toothbrushes, electronic and even furniture sheets.
Zence Object Holding already has more than 20 active projects in areas such as interior decoration, beverage packaging, among others, which develops with various customers, who are also partners, namely restaurants, hotels and conference centers.
Every year, China produces about 100 tons of tea waste, which end in the trash, according to the China's annual report of China in 2023. On the other hand, the country produces about 200 million tons of plastic waste annually, according to a UN report by 2023.
Zence has seen in the need to “solve global waste problems” an opportunity, seeming perfectly the idea of ​​turning tea waste into recycled ecological materials. The company founded in 2023, with a capital of six million patacas, expects to reach the return on investment next year and be profitable in 2028.
"A ton of tea waste can give rise to 10 tons of tea-based bioplastic, flexible and versatile like plastic," the company's co-founder explained to Lusa, Bob Lei Hou Keung.
The same weight of tea residue can make 150 table tops, or cluster panels with size 120x60x1.8cm, which can be used in the “direct replacement of the majority of wood panels”, with the “triple of the hardness of cement”, added the entrepreneur.
About a ton of tea waste per month, coming directly from a tea plantation from Fujian province, one of China's largest tea -producing provinces, is sent to two Zence factories in Guangdong Province, Lei said.
The industrial process integrates technologies of modification of biological -based plastics and mixture of vegetable fibers, biomaterial modification, production and manufacture.
"After gathering the tea residues, we process them, sterilize them, we begin to turn them into a grain-shaped tea-based bioplastic, which after melting is shaped by a machine," the businessman explained.
Law stressed that tea waste “can be decomposed 100% naturally”, “without formaldehyde” and “carbon neutral”.
A cup of coffee, for example, contains 10% pure tea leaves with vegetable polymers and polyhydroxialcanoates (PHA)-natural biodegradable polymers, “buried in the ground, and can completely decompose within 60 to 90 days,” he said.
The fragile side of the project has to do with the final cost of biodegradable products, at least for now. The cost of tea -based materials produced by “Zence” is 30% more expensive than plastic. Keeping the example of coffee cup, "each one costs 100 patacas in the market," he added.
“I hope that tea residues can completely replace plastic in 2030” in the set of products to which Zence is looking, the businessman said, in reference to the date set by the UN in the sustainable development objectives.
In September 2020, Chinese leader Xi Jinping stated, in the general debate of the 75th United Nations General Assembly, that China will adopt more vigorous policies and measures, and strive to reach the peak of carbon dioxide emissions by 2030 and try to achieve carbon neutrality by 2060.
The set of materials that are being used as biological alternatives to conventional plastics are increasing, such as starch based bioplastics, cellulose materials (wood pulp, cotton, agricultural waste), chitosan (crustaceous carapaces), alginate (brown algae), mycelium -based materials, or casein (milk protein).
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism promotion in Kuala Lumpur focused on Muslim markets</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/promocao-turistica-em-kuala-lumpur-focou-se-nos-mercados-muculmanos/</link><description>Cooperation between Macao and Malaysia tour operators, in the context of Southeast Asia's markets, was the purpose of another STD campaign directed to attract Muslim visitors
 
The Malaysian capital, Kuala Lumpur, was the place chosen for another campaign to promote Macao's “Tourism + Conventions and Exhibitions” products, with the aim of boosting the exchange and cooperation between the tour operators on both sides. In addition, the seminar served to explore business opportunities in the Southeast Asian market and expand the sources of international visitors.
During the seminar, the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) presented the new points of attraction of MSAR, the rich and diverse resources and events, and addressed “especially aspects intended for Muslim visitors,” as a statement from the body indicates.
The Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment of Macao and the six integrated tourism and leisure companies presented information on conventions and exhibitions and the tourist services provided.
In addition, tourist operators made a contact scholarship to explore business opportunities together and conceive of “new scripts and tourist products” from Malaysian to the Malaysian market, “thus increasing the desire to visit Macau during summer holidays and in the second half of this year,” says the same note.
In her speech during the seminar, STD director Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes said Macau is committed to becoming “a high quality tourist destination,” which includes the creation of a friendly environment for Muslims, “seeking to attract Islamic visitors and around the world”. According to the statistical data, "the desire of Malaysian visitors to visit Macau has increased continuously," he said.
Together with Fat Tea, a Macaense food restaurant in Kuala Lumpur, STD also presented 13 Malaysian Digital Influencers Gastronomy and Macao sights, with a view to “taking advantage of its influence to promote the image and charm of Macao as a creative city of gastronomy and world tourism and leisure center”.
Until April this year, Malaysian visitors in Macao reached 80% of the levels of the same period of 2019. Malaysia currently occupies fourth place in the international visitors of Macao and the seventh at the general level.
This year, STD plans to conduct a large -scale street campaign in Kuala Lumpur to continue to explore the visitor markets of Malaysia and Southeast Asia.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Boss praises progress of a</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-enaltece-progressos-da-um-2/</link><description>The University of Macau “has improved the quality and scale of its teaching,” said the chief executive at the undergraduate ceremony of more than 1,600 students
 
More than 1,600 graduates from the University of Macau (one) completed their courses at the various colleges of the institution. Of these, 70 are students from the College of Honor who have completed the certification program.
The undergraduate ceremony was chaired by the Chief Executive, who highlighted the progress of UM in recent years. The university “has closely aligned its efforts on the needs of the country and Macao, consistently improving the quality and scale of its teaching, while actively promoting integration between Macau and Hengqin,” he said.
These efforts “significantly increased the reputation and international influence of one, starting an era of unprecedented development,” he said.
Sam Hou Fai, who had by his side the secretary for social affairs and culture, LAM, was confident that a "will play a significant role in developing an international center for high-level talents." In addition, he encouraged graduates to remain "determined" and to face challenges with "young energy, innovation and concrete actions."
Meanwhile, the rector, Yonghua Song, said that one has kept "faithful to his original missions and is entitled to the trust in it." In addition, he expressed three hopes for graduates: to develop Macao with “pure passion and play their role in national rejuvenation”; take advantage of the opportunities “with vision” and face the challenges “with resilience”; and they may enter "unexplored territories with the spirit of innovation."
Prior to the ceremony, the chief executive visited the facilities of UM and traveled his three state key laboratories, namely the quality investigation in Chinese medicine, analog vlsi and mixed signal and the Internet of things to intelligent cities.
The university informed it on “the research strategy and its achievements in the field of collaboration between industry and the academy”, points out a note from the media of social communication.
 
V. R.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 3,200 talents graduated from UCM</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-de-3-200-talentos-graduados-pela-ucm/</link><description>More than 3,200 graduates received the Certificate of Conclusion of Studies from the University of Macao. The secretary O LAM highlighted the “vital role” of higher education institutions in the “cultivation of innovative talents”
 
At the undergraduate ceremony of the University of Macau City (UCM), which took place at the TAP Seac Polydestive Pavilion, more than 3,200 graduates received certificates, including about 400 doctoral students, more than 1,500 masters and more than 1,300 undergraduate students.
The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture stated that the Government of MSAR has attributed great importance to the “life role” of higher education institutions and highlighted the continuous efforts of the government to promote the development of the Macau-Hengqin International Education City of International Education. The LAM also referred to UCM's continuous efforts in the implementation of “serving Macau, integrated in the Great Bay” philosophy as a key pillar of local higher education.
Highlighting the recent developments in the academic structure, the “cultivation of innovative talents” and the promotion of joint laboratories and artificial intelligence science platforms, the secretary also said the university “continues to nourish exceptional talents with patriotism and love for Macau”.
The rector of UCM, Jun Liu, congratulated the graduates and highlighted the university's commitment to align with national strategy to make China in a “leading country in education”, highlighting government strategies to establish an academic ecosystem, humanities and social sciences, with an artificial intelligence as a central engine for an innovative interdisciplinary development ”.
Jun Liu also highlighted this year's creation of the Institute of Urban and Sustainable Development and the Academy for Seniors, in response to the demands and development of society.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Confirmed restrictions on mobile phones in schools</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/confirmadas-restricoes-telemoveis-nas-escolas/</link><description>Close Up of Elementary Student Typing Text Message on Smart Phone While Sitting at the Desk in the Classroom.



The use of mobile phones or other electronic apparatus by students will be restricted from next school year in all non -higher education schools, confirmed the DSEDJ director, ensuring that the measure was well received by the establishments that participated in a pilot program
 
About half a hundred schools in the course of schools already have cliffs to store students' mobile phones during school hours, a measure that will be extended to all not higher schools from the school year 2025/2026, confirmed the director of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ). Students will have to put their mobile phones in cliffs or scholarships in schools and can only collect them after classes.
Schools will be able to adopt specific solutions, depending on space limitations, said Kong Chi Meng, quoted by “or Mun Tin Toi” on Friday.
According to the same responsible, the initiative was well received by the schools that participated in a pilot program on mobile phone management. Authorities intend, above all, to avoid the excessive use of mobile phones in the school context.
In March, Leong I on, head of the Division of Secondary Education, had already advanced that the DSEDJ will launch "guidelines" so that schools and guardians are aware that mobile phones taken by students to schools must be subject to management measures. He explained, the "guidelines" will explicitly define when and on what occasions can students or not use mobile phones or other types of electronic devices.
Exceptions for emergency cases or pedagogical needs, namely educational activities with teacher guidance will be foreseen. At the same time, Leong I on exemplified that it is common to use electronic products in schools to search information or do group reports.
DSEDJ already provides school guidelines on the use of information technology and the Internet through the school's operating guide. These guidelines indicate that the “proper” average time of internet use by students is one hour a day, and that students should rest after 20 minutes of use of electronic products.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>TSI maintains a doctoral sentence that tried to bribe</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/tsi-mantem-pena-de-doutorando-tentou-subornar-professor/</link><description>The Court of Second Instance rejected the appeal of a student who was convicted of “active corruption” of his doctoral thesis advisor. Thus the six-month imprisonment is maintained and the payment of 15,000 patacas to suspend the execution of the sentence determined by the Base Judicial Court
 
The Court of Second Instance (TSI) rejected the appeal of a doctoral student, convicted by the Base Judicial Court (TJB), for active corruption. According to the office of the President of the Last Instance Court (TUI), the forming tried to bribe the advisor, intending to achieve "approval, with economic benefit, of the proposal of thesis with offense to the common criteria of appreciation."
The student will have hidden an 8,000 -pataca red envelope in a book that put in the teacher's office mailbox. After discovering the book, the teacher scolded the forming and returned the aforementioned envelope. The case happened at the University of Macao, according to information previously published.
The TJB became aware of the case and sentenced the student to six months in prison, with suspended execution for two years, and the payment of 15 thousand patacas “as a duty to suspend the execution of the sentence”.
Disagreeing, the student turned to the TSI, arguing that “he offered the red envelope only to obtain more academic guidelines, and there is no intention of bribery”, and requesting the replacement of conviction with a lighter one.
The TSI collective court claims that it has existed “manifest non-disabilities between the student's various justifications” about the reason for the envelope offering, as sometimes he claimed to have done him to apologize and other times to get more guidance from the teacher.
He also indicated that the conduct of the doctoral student was “adverse to academic integrity and in disharmony with the rules of experience”, having noted that “evaluate the qualification, proposal of thesis and defense of the students' dissertation according to the specialized criteria” is an act resulting from the duties of the advisor's functions.
There is no direct expressions such as “active corruption” or “bribery” to the collective court, the registration of conversations between the student and his mother indicated that “the form of money delivery” was discussed to the teacher and the “sufficiency or not of value”, sufficient to reveal the intention of active corruption.
The TSI pointed out that the facts and evidence of the case was sufficient to prove that the student offered a pecuniary benefit with the intention that the teacher violates “the common criteria of appreciation” and lower the “requirements for assessment of the doctoral thesis proposal” for its approval.
The student only began discussing with the teacher the theme of the thesis in March 2023, after being notified by the university that he was obliged to complete and obtain approval of the thesis proposal until May 19, 2023, and the draft presented by the student "never satisfied the requirements".
According to the office of the president of Tui, shortly after entering the course, in 2020, the student tried to offer the same monetary value coupons, and the teacher expressly refused them and warned the student about the likely illegality of the act.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Iranian Panahi's ‘A simple accident’, he wins Golden Palm in Cannes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/um-simples-acidente-iraniano-panahi-vence-palma-de-ouro-em-cannes/</link><description>EPA12132077 Iranian Filmmaker Jafar Panahi Poses During the Winners 'Photocall after Receiving The Palme d'Or Simple Accident' at the Closing and Awards Ceremony of the 78th Annual Cannes Film Festival, In Cannes, France, 24 May 2025. The Film Festival Runs From 13 To 24 May 2025. EPA/Guillaume Horcajuelo



The 78th edition of the Cannes Film Festival granted on Saturday night the Golden Palm to Iranian dissident filmmaker Jafar Panahi with “It Was Just An Accident”, in a policy ceremony in which the Brazilian film “The Secret Agent”, by Kleber Mendonça Filho, took the best performance and actor awards.
After a journey of a certain nervousness by a blackout in the city, due to a sabotage of the electric network, the ceremony was normally, with a room delivered to Panahi's humility and firmness, a director who was persecuted, tortured and arrested by his country's government.
"It was just an accident", filmed in clandestinity, tells the fortuitous encounter of a man who believes to recognize his torturer on the streets of Tehran.
"I think this is the time to ask all Iranians, in Iran or in the world: let's set aside […] all the problems, all the differences, the most important now is the freedom of our country," said the 64 -year -old filmmaker, receiving the award from the hands of actress Cate Blanchett.
Arrested twice in his country and persecuted by the government, Panahi was finally able to attend Cannes for the first time in 15 years to receive the prize, along with all his actors and acts.
Panahi said he will soon return to his country. Asked if he feared the return after taking the maximum prize by a film contrary to the power of the Ayatollah and filmed in a clandestine way, the filmmaker replied: “Absolutely no. Tomorrow let's go.”
The Brazilian feature film “The Secret Agent”, a political thriller set in 1977, had the awards for best director and direction, which were received by director Kleber Mendonça Filho himself. The actor Wagner Moura, who plays a teacher who faced corruption in his city, Recife, and where he returns despite all dangers, was absent at the ceremony.
At 56, Kleber Mendonça Filho is part of the select circle of filmmakers whose presence is usual in Cannes, with a cinema that is based on both magical realism and political militancy. “The Secret Agent” is his third film to compete in Cannes after “Bacurau” in 2019 and “Aquarius” in 2016.
“I think Cannes is simply the cinema cathedral on this planet,” he said.
At 48, Wagner Moura is one of the best known faces of Brazilian cinema around the world for his role as Captain Nascimento on the acclaimed "Elite Troop", and participations in international productions such as the series "Narcos" and the movies "Civil War" and "Elysium".
With these two awards in Cannes, Brazilian cinema lives a year of glory, in which it also won the history Oscar for best international film with “I'm still here”, by Walter Salles.
On the other hand, at a festival that gave a broad space to the female protagonists, the French Nadia Melliti, just 23, received the award for best female interpretation in “La Petite Dernière”, by director Hafsia Herzi, in the debut movie in the seventh art. Physical Education and Discovered Student in a cast -actor test, she plays Fatima, a 17 -year -old Muslim of Paris suburbs who gradually discovers her attraction to women.
Other highlights were Norwegian sentimental Value Joachim Trier, who tells the story of a filmmaker who seeks the reunion with his daughters and got the Grand Prix, as well as “Sirat” by the German Mascar Schilinski's “Sound of Falling”, who divided the jury's award.
“Jeunes Mères”, from Belgian brothers Dardenna, who portrays a group of teenage single mothers, took the best script award, while the abstract “Resurrection” of Chinese Bi Gan was laureated with the special award.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>