<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>In a decade, only 1,298 Portuguese asked for permanent residence</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/numa-decada-so-1-298-portugueses-pediram-residencia-permanente/</link><description>In the last ten years, only 22.76% of the requests for permanent resident status have been made by Portuguese. According to the direction of identification services, 5,702 non -permanent residents presented requests to become permanent residents, of which only 1,298 were Portuguese. Of these, 13 saw the requests denied
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Within a decade, only 1,298 Portuguese nationality citizens made the request to acquire the status of permanent resident in Macao, which is equivalent to about 130 Portuguese per year. According to official data provided by the Directorate of Identification Services (DSI) to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the number represents 22.76% of the total requests.
According to DSI statistics, between November 2014 and November 2024, a total of 5,702 non -permanent residents presented requests to become permanent residents. The JTM asked the government organism the number of requests received and how many were rejected, per year, in order to realize if it is possible to draw any trend, but the DSI indicated not being able to provide the data in this way.
The DSI said only that, in the general calculation, during the ten years under analysis, 361 people saw the application be "rejected", making 6.33% of requests made. Of these, only 13 were Portuguese citizens, representing 3.6% of requests to which green light was given.
The rejections were due to "mainly, that interested parties do not usually reside in Macao or to the impossibility of confirming their intention to have their permanent domicile in Macao." The DSI also added, in the response to this newspaper, that, in case of non -compliance with the result of the assessment, citizens may always have challenged with the administration and the courts, in the legal terms.
JTM also tried to know with DSA the nationalities of citizens who made the remaining requests of permanent residence in the Masheries, but until the closing of this edition the body did not respond. On the other hand, it pointed out that, since some requirements are still in the follow -up phase, statistics may change.
In a few years, it is likely that the requests for permanent residence made by Portuguese will drop even more, because, it is recalled, Macau has not accepted, since August 2023, new requests for residence for Portuguese for the “exercise of specialized technical functions”, allowing only justifications from family reunion or previous connection to the territory.
The guidelines eliminate a practice signed after Macao's transition in 1999. The alternative for a Portuguese to secure the BIR now undergoes an application to recent qualified frame capture programs. Another hypothesis is the issuance of “Blue Card”, authorization limited to the labor bond, without the benefits of residents, namely at health or education level.
According to recent data reported by the Macau channel of TDM, the number of residence requests made by Portuguese and approved fell by 2024, in annual terms. Migration authorities were referred to 20 requests, of which 13 (65%) were approved, the Public Security Police body said. A break from 2023, when the number of orders totaled 56, and was given green light at 52 (92%).</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MP asks for incentives to captivate nurses</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/deputada-pede-incentivos-para-cativar-enfermeiros/</link><description>The reservation of nursing professionals in Macau health services is worrying Song Pek Kei. The deputy considers that the current pace of increased nurses, less than 10% annually, is insufficient for needs, taking into account the aging of the population
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Noting the current reality of aging the aging of the population, Deputy Song Pek Kei understands that the government should pay more attention to medical services that are made available to those who need them. Thus, the increase in demand for medical services in Macao and the need for the government to retain cadres in the nursing area to ensure the future were approached by the deputy in a written interpellation.
Song Pek Kei speaks specifically about the issue of nursing staff, considering that the increase in professionals recorded in recent years fall short of needs. Between 2013 and 2023, therefore over a 10 -year period, "the number of nurses in Macau increased only 1,126, a volume that cannot respond to population growth and the evolution of medical services," said the hemiciclo member, adding that the increase of less than 10% annually "is below the expectations set by the executive."
In 2023, according to the Statistical Yearbook, Macao had 2,980 nurses, ie 4.4 per 1,000 inhabitants, yet one climb compared to 2013, when there were 3.1 per 1,000 people.
In this sense, Song Pek Kei points out that there was the expectation, created by the authorities, that it would be possible to introduce ward assistants, “to relieve the pressure of nurses”, intending to know if the implementation of this measure is a reality.
According to the latest data from statistics and census services last year, the elderly population (65 years or older) stood at 100,200, corresponding to 14.6% of the total population. The proportion of elderly grew 0.6 percentage points in annual terms.
The trend of population aging remained, and official data even reveals that the aging rate reached 116.6%, plus 10.5 percentage points in annual terms, the highest since 1990 and marking the 28th consecutive year of growth. Also the dependence rate of the elderly grew 0.8 percentage points to 20%, also marking the highest since 34 years ago.
On the other hand, to face the search for the Islands Hospital for Health Professionals, also the vice president of the Macau Institution of Macau Alliance recalls that the government "had stated that the number of nursing professionals would record an increase of 10 to 15% annually." However, he observes, "currently the growth rate nor reached 10% and the increase of nurses obviously cannot achieve the purpose of reserve frames for the sector."
Therefore, Song Pek Kei questions the executive about whether to launch more incentive measures in the future, "with a view to captivating and retaining more nursing paintings and promoting the sustainable development of territory medical services."
In addition, in its interpellation, the deputy urges the government to periodically disclose data related to the demand of society by nursing professionals. In his view, "this data have never been updated so far and would serve to provide a database to adjust the number of personnel and better collaborate with the evolution of medical services."</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CCPPC adopts resolution on “one country, two systems”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ccppc-adopta-resolucao-sobre-um-pais-dois-sistemas/</link><description>EPA11953045 Chairman of the Chinese People's Political Consultive Conference Wang Huning (2-R) Speaks During the Closing Meeting of the Third Session of the 14th Chinese People's Political Consultive Conference (CPPC) Beijing, China, 10 March 2025. China's Major Annual Political Meetings, Known As The 'Lianghui' Or 'Two Sessions,' Began on 04 March with the Opening of the Chinese Policing Consultive Conference (CPPCC), While the National People's Congress (NPC) OPENED ON 05 MARCH.  EPA/WU HAO



A political resolution was approved yesterday by CCPPC at the closing session. Regarding the MSAR, according to the resolution, it is necessary to full, precise and unshakable pursuit of “a country, two systems”, “Macau ruled by their people” and a high degree of autonomy
 
The closing ceremony of the 3rd session of the 14th Political Political Conference of the Chinese People (CCPPC) was held yesterday. At the time, the CCPPC unanimously approved (2,082 votes in favor), a political resolution that requires the full, precise and unshakable pursuit of the “a country, two systems”, “Macao governed by their people”, “Hong Kong ruled by their people” and with a high degree of autonomy.
In addition, according to the resolution, it is necessary to "advance unshabble with the large cause of the reunification of the homeland and consolidate and develop the widest possible patriotic front."
After the ceremony, several MSAR vowels at CCPPC have asserted that they will “transmit well” the spirit of the “two sessions” in Macau. According to the Chinese language press, for example, Leonel Alves stated that the professional sector will transmit, above all, the content related to the right mentioned in the “two sessions”. In addition, he considered that Macau can take as reference the development of artificial intelligence in the judicial system of the interior of China.
Prior to the closing ceremony, in an interview organized by CCPPC, Ho Ion Sang, a member of the permanent committee of this political advisory body, stressed that Hengqin is a “ideal” place of combining the advantages on both sides of the border. He also emphasized that the “integration between Hengqin and Macao” conjuncture "proved, with facts, with the world that" a country, two systems "is not only viable, but also implementable and recognized by the population."
 
More proposals around Lusophony and Hengqin
On the other hand, in Beijing, the deputy of MSAR at the Popular National Assembly (ANP) Dominic Sio submitted a proposal in the hope that the Ministry of Chinese trade will extend Macau's “Syno-Musso Platform” function to the countries of the Southeast Asian Nations Association (Asean), taking advantage of the role of mashes to promote the connection of the Asean block to the Lusophone market. Specifically, he suggested creating by the Lusophone countries from a transfrontic electronic trade platform between China, Portuguese -speaking and ASEAN countries.
Also within Lusophony, Lao NGA Wong, a member of the CCPPC Permanent Committee, proposed an international soccer training center established by Hengqin and Macau. In his opinion, this “center” could take advantage of MSAR to introduce the “good quality management system” of strong football countries and explore the development “football + finance” through the issuance of “sports titles” and the creation of a “soccer players growth fund”.
In addition, they were delivered to more proposals focused on hengqin. The delegation of Macao representatives at ANP proposed the quick confirmation of the fast train “Hengqin” station and the extension of the macao light meter to this station, where the “Integral Border Inspection” model is applied. It is thus intended to realize the connection without interruption between the Macao meter and the fast train.
Lam Lon Wai, a vowel at CCPPC, suggested intensifying the frequency of large-scale cultural activities co-organized by Macau and Hengqin.
Another CCPPC vowel, Li Amber Jiaming, advocated the realization of “efficient and easy” transfrontic circulation of biological samples between Macau and Hengqin, such as blood samples, human cells and organs. In turn, representatives at ANP Si Ka Lon and Chui Sai Peng proposed that Hengqin and Macau investigate stem cell treatment products.
On the other hand, Kou Hoi In, a member of the ANP permanent committee, suggested to the central government to support the creation of a permanent mechanism for issuing state debt securities and local governments in Macao, as well as promoting the application of digital pataca in Hengqin and a reinforced connection of “e-mop” to Renminbi Digital.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mental health professionals complain of ambiguous norms</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/profissionais-da-saude-mental-queixam-se-de-normas-ambiguas/</link><description>Deputy Lam Lon Wai calls for more human resources in the area of ​​mental rehabilitation services in the community and the improvement of notification and referral rules of patients with mental health problems. As I said, there are professionals in the area to complain about “obstacles”
 
Notification or referral of patients with mental health problems have been facing “obstacles”, complaining professionals in the area, cited by Lam Lon Wai, who asked the government to optimize these procedures. The deputy also considers that it is necessary to define "more refined" measures in relation to human resources.
According to data released by the authorities in January, there were 177 registered social workers from the scope of rehabilitation services, which represented 12% of the total of social workers. Already based on information from the sector, Lam Lon Wai indicated that, currently, in the context of mental rehabilitation services in the community, “each worker has to provide services to 30 people”, a ratio more or less equivalent to the registered in New Zealand and Australia. However, “with the rapid socioeconomic evolution of Macao, there will be more and more cases of mental problems in the community,” he warned of written interpellation.
Thus, the deputy intends to know if the authorities will take advantage of the opportunity to elaborate the new decenate rehabilitation services plan to “define more improved measures regarding the provision of human resources or the long -term support network mechanism”. "For example, they can adjust the personal-patient ratio and the referral mechanism to the hospital to mitigate the pressure of the front line staff and to improve the treatment steps of high risk cases," he said.
On the other hand, "according to the professionals in the area, in some urgent cases, staff have faced many difficulties and obstacles in the procedures of notification or referral of patients [with mental illness] to the hospital, because the rules are relatively ambiguous." In this sense, it asks if, in the future and in relation to “high risk” cases, the authorities intend to optimize the rules and criteria of the referral process of these patients to the hospital.
In concrete, Lam Lon Wai questions whether the government will optimize interdepartal coordination or define “more perfected” guidelines, with the aim of “solving these difficulties”.
The deputy also noted that, by the end of September 2024, there were 3,600 people with mental disabilities, representing 19.43% of the total people with disabilities. Specifically, there were 1,766 mental disabled over 55 years, making 49% of the total.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Initiative of Casa do Mandarim seen as “innovative case” by UNESCO</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/iniciativa-da-casa-mandarim-vista-como-caso-inovador-pela-unesco/</link><description>《文化遺產保護法》生效 10 周年系列活動 - 世遺走走看



The World Heritage Institute for Training and Research in the UNESCO Asia Pacific region in Suzhou has selected the activity “Come and Casa de Mandarin's Heritage Set better as one of China's 10“ innovative cases ”over the past year. The Cultural Institute emphasizes that this is “important recognition” about the work of youth education related to the World Heritage
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The initiative of youth education entitled “Come and know our world heritage better”, from Casa do Mandarin, was selected by the UNESCO's Institute of World Heritage for Training and Research in the Asia-Pacific Region (Whitrap), and located in Suzhou as one of China's 10 “innovative cases” in 2024. According to the Cultural Institute (IC) Scope of Youth Education on World Heritage ”.
Since the conclusion of the restoration work of that space and the opening to the public, in early 2010, “IC has actively used the Mandarin House to organize various cultural promotion activities with young people, so as to guide them in understanding the value of world heritage, making them know the cultural characteristics of the Chinese and Western cultures in Macao, cultivating a sense of patriotism, strengthening self-confidence and disseminating the traditional Chinese culture ”.
It is recalled that it was in 2018 that the same institute gave the title of “Youth Education Base on World Heritage” to the Mandarin House. The body led by Leong Wai Man refers, in a statement, that to enhance the role of the Mandarin House as a "base" organized several editions of the activity now distinguished, "which intends to encourage creative thinking and cultivate cultural innovation and creative young people." All this through “innovative and fun experiences, including namely Chinese painting, sculpture, ceramic, design, 3D printing, building blocks and other artistic and educational activities, with the historic center of Macao as the main theme”.
In addition, the IC has produced and launched an online session of cartoon short films on the historic center and other didactic resources, in conjunction with the “Special Interactive Exhibition of the Macao Historic Center” at the Mandarin House. Last year, the body promoted, for the first time, a local study visit called “visits to world heritage”, in order to widen the historical and cultural horizons of young people from multiple perspectives and to cultivate awareness and the meaning of responsibility for cultural heritage.
Reiterating that the selection by Whithrap, “is an important recognition of the IC's work in the context of youth education on world heritage,” the body adds that this year will be added to a new group reserve service to groups. For Macao primary schools registered in the government or non -profit groups of Macau will be free.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>A bet on exchange with English universities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/um-aposta-intercambio-universidades-inglesas/</link><description>A delegation from the University of Macau traveled to the United Kingdom for the purpose of establishing cooperation agreements with higher education institutions in different scientific areas in order to reinforce their role in the international context
 
Led by Vice-Rector Rui Martins, a delegation from the University of Macao (one) moved to several top universities in England, with the purpose of fostering bilateral cooperation. The strategy involves areas such as exchanges of students and teachers, double -graduation programs and joint research projects.
According to a statement from the institution, Rui Martins described the visit as “an important initiative for reinforcing his partnerships with the higher education institutions of English -speaking countries”, “effectively” their “strategy of internationalization” and “establishing a solid basis for substantial cooperation” in the domains of teaching and scientific research. Thus, it expects to "further increase your international profile and cultivate high -level talents with a global perspective for masters and the big bay."
At the University of Warwick, “several agreements” were established and elaborated “plans to establish undergraduate and postgraduate exchange programs, double title programs and visiting academics programs in areas such as engineering, social sciences and education, as well as the holding of academic seminars”.
The delegation of UM also visited the University of Leicester, where he discussed cooperation in “Computer Science, Engineering and Materials Science”, and on double -graduation programs, student exchanges and research in research. The two universities agreed to sign a memorandum of understanding to promote cooperation and disciplinary exchange.
On the other hand, at the University of Nottingham, discussions focused on “important disciplines”, such as education, Portuguese studies, social sciences and engineering, with plans to systematically promote students' exchange, double title programs and academic conferences. With the University of Sheffield, issues focused on electronic and electric engineering, mathematics, physics and education were addressed, and an initial consensus on the creation of student exchange programs, co-organization of academic forums and the development of “innovative” research projects were achieved.
Already at the University of Leeds, the delegation of UM discussed the reinforcement of collaboration in electronic and electrical engineering, chemistry, material science and education. The two institutions, which maintain a longstanding partnership, have launched a double master's degree in English studies this academic year and admit to launching more programs of the genre in other subjects.
The English ride also included, among other institutions, a visit to the University of Manchester, where the two parts reached an “initial consensus” about the launch of double -graduation programs.
In addition to Rui Martins, the delegation included Sun Handong, associate director of the Institute of Applied Physics and Materials Engineering, and Sin Sai Weng, deputy director of the Institute of Microelectronics.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Decrease complaints about rats in public spaces</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/diminuem-queixas-sobre-ratos-em-espacos-publicos/</link><description>The complaints filed by the population about the appearance of rodents in public spaces have been decreased in the last five years, around 36%. According to the Institute for Municipal Affairs, the results of the investigations reveal that the control of rats is at an acceptable level
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) revealed that, between 2019 and 2024, there was a decrease in about 36%in the number of complaints related to the presence of rats in public spaces. Last year, there were 711 complaints made by the population to the authorities compared to the 1,113 verified five years earlier.
In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Ron Lam, AMI clarified that an investigation, carried out by an academic institution in the interior of China about the number of rodents in public spaces of Macao, had as main points the markets, parks and gardens, green zones and leisure, peripheral dikes and public roads in the buildings of various neighborhoods. With as reference the national criteria, the assessment focused on observing the traces of rat movement, including waste, holes, bites, living or dead rats, among other aspects.
In the response document to Ron Lam, signed by the president of IAM, Chao Wai Ieng, the body ensures that it has reinforced in recent years the work of eliminating rodents by placing boxes with bait in public spaces. The number of fixed traps on the streets registered a rise of about 200 in 2017 to about 1,400 at this time, with a coverage of all Macao zones.
“Specific personnel proceed to collect and periodic analysis of trap data at inspection to understand the trend of rodents in various neighborhoods and take the measures due to their prevention and control,” says the text.
In addition to the placement of fixed traps, AMI has divided the entire territory into 25 zones to periodically develop deratization work, focusing on launching baits to eliminate rats into flower beds, green zones, dikes, sewage mouths, among others.
AMI considers that the results of investigations in recent years show that control of rodents in public spaces of Macau is at a "acceptable" level.
Since 2024, regional rodent elimination works have gone from two to at least three times a year in each area, and also in these places “intensive elimination work” is done lasting five weeks. 27,000 boxes with baits were placed during the year.
The response to Ron Lam's interpellation concludes that rat proliferation prevention and control is long -term work, and prevention from the source is even more important. "Its effectiveness depends on the active collaboration of the entire population of Macao, thus realizing the joint participation of all in the prevention and collective control for the improvement of environmental hygiene," said AMI.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Next week brings cold and heat</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/proxima-semana-traz-frio-calor/</link><description>Noting that the time in the first week of March was hot with fog, followed by rain and cold, meteorological and geophysical services (SMG) predict that “the meteorological conditions of alternation between cold and heat return and that time in the region is moist”. For now, these are the conjectures for next week. Already this night, Macao should be “gradually” influenced by a maritime air stream. According to the body, "relative moisture will rise again" and, with the weak wind, "it is likely to occur fog and rain in the coastal regions of Guangdong, so the visibility will be low." According to the latest predictions, a cold front will reach the coast of Guangdong on Saturday, predicting that it can bring thunder and thunderstorms into the province. "However, the occurrence of this year's first thunderstorm in Macao depends on the intensity and position of the cold front to arrival," said the SMG. “Regardless of the possibility of thunderstorms in Macao, it is expected that the sweeteners will increase,” reads a note, with the body to appeal to the population to continue to pay attention to the latest weather forecasts. On the other hand, with the Cold Front pass through the coast of Guangdong during the weekend, another Northeast Monsoon will affect Macao, "and with the increase of the northern quadrant wind, the temperature will come down again." Thus, next week, time in the region should mark by meteorological changes of alternation between cold and heat. "In addition, given the occurrence of fog, the visibility will be low, so it appeals to the population to pay attention to changes in atmospheric conditions and driving safety," warns the SMG.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CCAC and Singapore join efforts to combat corruption</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ccac-singapura-unem-esforcos-combate-a-corrupcao/</link><description>The Commissioner Against Corruption (CCAC) received the director of the Singapore Corruption Investigation Office, Sam Tee, to share ideas on the fight against corruption in Macao and the city-state. To the CCAC Commissioner Ieong Seog, he stressed that, despite having distinct cultures and legal systems, the two territories share the same view of what constitutes a full society based on a rule of law, according to the CCAC statement. The commissioner added that both parties maintain “an attitude of zero tolerance” and the application of “severe and firm sanctions” in combating corruption acts. In turn, the director of the Singapore Corruption Investigation Office has recognized that the visit can “promote the exchange and cooperation between the two parties”, agreeing with the Ieong Seong proposals in terms of joint personnel formation, according to the same note. The CCAC team also made a presentation on investigated cases and investigation procedures, followed by an exchange of opinions in the context of preventing and combating corruption. In addition to the Ieong Seong and Sam Tee, the deputy CCAC commissioner and director of corruption services, Wong Kim Fong, advisor, Fong Pak Ian and Leong Leong, head of the 2nd Department of Investigation of the Directorate of Corruption, were present.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Companhia Bai Li Integra Ipor</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/companhia-bai-li-integra-ipor/</link><description>Companhia Bai Li Group was recently integrated into the associative structure of the Portuguese Institute of the East (IPOR), following a deliberation adopted at the General Assembly. “Recognized for its excellence in the international trade area, especially in the wine distribution sector,” the company “has sought to position itself as a Sino-Portuguese commercial platform in Macao, investing over the years in a series of projects and activities”, with the aim of using Macau as a “connecting vehicle for the placement of Portuguese products in the Popular Republic of China,” says an IPOR statement. This strategy, it accentuates, aligns with the principles and objectives of IPOR, since it is “complemented” with initiatives to promote tourism, culture and Portuguese language. The same note also points out that the entry of Companhia Bai Li in IPOR demonstrates, on the one hand, “the recognition of the work developed in the preservation and diffusion of Portuguese language and culture in the Asia-Pacific region” and, on the other, “the identification and commitment” of the company to reinforce the mission of the institute and the narrowing of relations between the Lusophone countries, the mashes and the interior of China. The new member thus joins a group of associates that includes the Oriente Foundation (founder of IPOR), Camões - Institute of Cooperation and Language, BNU, Quinta da Marmeleira and the Macao Tourism and Tourism Society. "This cooperation is, in this sense, another step towards the affirmation of the role of IPOR, not only as a disseminating agent of the economic and global value of the Portuguese language, but also of cultural cooperation and promoter of interculturality," the statement.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MGM and Art Basel award distinguishes emerging artists</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/premio-da-mgm-art-basel-distingue-artistas-emergentes/</link><description>The winner of the first edition of the “MGM Discoveries Art Award” will be revealed during Art Basel Hong Kong on March 28th. The reward highlights the originality and innovation of emerging international talents in the art world. The award was created by MGM and Art Basel Hong Kong to support talents of all ages and nationalities “in exploring the infinite possibilities of art, raising its influence on the world of international art and infringing a new energy on the global art scene,” according to a game operator statement. MGM hopes to introduce state-of-the-art artistic trends in the city, inviting award-winning artists to Macau and inspiring the younger generation to engage in artistic creation. Three candidates will be evaluated, namely Shin Min, represented by Seoul's P21, Kayode Ojo, Sweetwater de Berlin and Saju Kunhan, from Tarq de Mumbai. The jury is composed of five experts from the international artistic and cultural sphere, including Aaron Cezar, founding director of Delfina Foundation, a non -profit organization that promotes artistic exchanges in the United Kingdom; Antonia Carver, director of Art Jameel in Dubai; Christopher K. Ho, Executive Director of Asia Art Archive; X ZHU-NOWELL, Executive Director and Chief Curator of the Rockbund Art Museum in Shanghai; and Sam Sungho Park, president of the Parkseobo Arts and Culture Foundation in Seoul. The winner will receive a $ 50,000 prize. In addition, the three artists will have the opportunity to perform an exhibition and participate in exchanges in Macao and in the area of ​​the Great Bay.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Game recipes remain “stable” in early March</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/receitas-jogo-continuam-estaveis-inicio-de-marco/</link><description>The gross revenues of Macau casinos cipher at about 5.75 billion patacas in the first nine days of this month, corresponding to a daily average of 638 million, yesterday the JP Morgan investment bank said yesterday. Billing remained “stable” compared to the 644 million per day in the first two months of the year, “which is encouraging for an intermediate month as March”, highlights the report signed by analysts DS Kim, Selina Li and Mufan Shi. Between March 1 and 9, the revenues of the mass market and the VIP segment will have reached 110% respectively and just over 20% of the pre-covid level. The Investment Bank believes that this month's accounts will be able to terminate around 19 billion Patacas, a amount close to that registered in the same period of 2024 (19.5 billion). In this scenario, the accounting of the first quarter will also remain “stable” in annual terms, despite the “relatively difficult comparisons,” added the trio of analysts. Benefiting less demanding comparative bases, revenues could rise 5% in the second half, “resulting in a modest growth from 3% to 2025”, anticipates the JP Morgan team. According to data from the Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate, casinos revenues totaled about 38 billion patacas in the first two months of this year, reflecting a 0.5% residual increase compared to the same period of 2024. In February, revenues reached 19.74 billion, which translates up 8.2% and 6.8% per month, respectively, and equivalent to 77.8% of the 2019 level.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2356/</link><description>Brief
Hospitalized elderly after fire in social housing
A fire in block 4 of the Lok Kuan building, social housing in Colaane, caused a poor disposition to two residents, one 70 years and the other 90, which were eventually transported to the hospital. The fire occurred in a fraction on the 11th floor and was caused by a short circuit. According to the Fire Department, the elderly people live on other floors and one of them felt heart discomfort. In addition, 24 residents left the building by the foot itself.
 
Compensation for work accidents
The government has decided, "in the assumption of the balance of the rights and interests of workers and employers, to maintain the boundaries in force of compensation for damage resulting from occupational accidents and occupational diseases," the services reported to work. The limits of compensation must be reviewed annually. The analysis by the executive corresponded to 2023 and included data on the economic situation and the labor market, and the insurance sector and representatives of workers and employers were heard.
 
12 thousand have not done proof of life
There are 168,000 beneficiaries of the pension to the elderly or the disability pension, and about 12,000 have not yet done the proof of life. Pointing out that they can do so by the end of March, the Social Security Fund recalls that the procedures can be done in person or through the single account. The fund also reiterates that it does not send messages with links, asking citizens to warn of attempts at fraud.
 
More than 100 job openings in technological companies
An employment conjugation session will provide more than a hundred vacancies in certified technology companies. The initiative of the Directions for Services for Laboral and Economics and Technological Development affairs is held on March 29, with registrations between today and the 26th. A total of 13 companies, which act in areas such as information technologies or artificial intelligence, offer vacancies in 67 categories.
 
Free Cancer Tracking Consultation for Women
Health services launched the “Reminder Program for the tracking of cervical cancer” in collaboration with non -profit medical institutions. The objective is to raise awareness of the residents of the MSAR, between 21 and 65 years old, to make a free tracking consultation in one of the 14 places to provide this service, including health centers and association clinics. In addition to a reminder call call they will receive, residents can use “single account” for more information about the health services program.
 
COVID infects five users of the HOA Care Home
Five users of the Ká-Hó care home of the Workers' Federation of Associations were diagnosed with Covid-19. The establishment has already applied infection control measures and isolation standards for infected users, indicated health services (SSM), adding that they are in a “stable state” without serious complications. SSM also ensure that they continue to organize support measures for high -risk groups, such as remote consultations or sending health professionals for proximity services.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Women's rights back on a quarter of countries, warns UN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/direitos-das-mulheres-retrocedem-em-um-quarto-dos-paises-alerta-onu/</link><description>Political polarization, new technologies, conflicts and climate emergency threaten the rights of women, who will be settled in one in four countries by 2024, a report from the UN Women Organization warned.
"The weakening of democratic institutions has been hand in hand with a violent reaction against gender equality," warns the authors of the report that analyzes women's rights 30 years after the declaration and platform of Beijing's action in 1995, adopted by 189 countries.
Actors contrary to gender rights "are actively undermining longtime consensus on key issues." "When they cannot completely reverse legal and political progress, they try to block or slow their application," says the report, published about International Women's Day.
“Almost a quarter of the countries reports that the reaction against gender equality is making it difficult to implement the Beijing agreements.
“Political polarization is increasingly exacerbating the risk and reality of the violent gender reaction,” warns the report.
To this are added conflicts and crises, which got worse from the covid-19 pandemic that broke out in 2020, climate emergency and new digital technologies, especially artificial intelligence.
"Women and girls' rights face an unprecedented scenario of increasing threats worldwide, from higher levels of discrimination to weaker legal protections and reduced financing for programs and institutions that support and protect women," the UN agency says.
"Women and girls are demanding changes and deserve nothing less," said UN Women's director Sima Bahous.
A total of 63% of women between 25 and 54 years old have paid work compared to 92% of men. More than 772 million women work in the informal economy, have no social protection and their jobs are the most threatened in case of crisis.
Since 2022, cases of conflict -related sexual violence have increased by 50%, and 95% of victims are women and girls. By 2023, 612 million people lived 50 km from one of the 170 armed conflicts that occur on the planet, 54% more than in 2010.
In every 10 minutes, a woman or girl is killed by her partner or a family member, and a third suffers physical and sexual violence at home and outside her.
The document points out that, in recent years, gender equality has been achieved in girls education, maternal mortality has been reduced in one third, female representation in the more than doubled parliaments and many countries abolished discriminatory laws. However, women still have 64% of the rights men enjoy and this despite the fact that “when women's rights are fully defended in countries where they live, families, communities and economies prosper,” says the report, which also includes the new Beijing+30 program, with six initiatives to complete pending tasks.
This includes ensuring egalitarian access to technology, eradicating poverty and violence, egalitarian decision making, peace and safety and climate justice.
“We could be the first generation to live in an egalitarian world,” says the authors…
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>