<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Macau lawyers want to bet on Hengqin and Big Bay</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/advogados-de-macau-querem-apostar-em-hengqin-grande-baia/</link><description>The economic conjuncture of the territory has an impact on the activity of lawyers, acknowledged the Macao Lawyers Association, which considers crucial "to take advantage of opportunities" in Hengqin and the Great Bay, where, said Oriana Pun, the association's secretary general, the causes of the territory "can play a very important role." In the presentation of the activities of the lawyer day, there was still no progress in the protocol with the Portuguese Bar Association, noting that, for this “there has to be a mutual will”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Macao Lawyers Association (AAM) admits that the sector is impacting the new economic environment, but is willing to work to take advantage of the opportunities arising from the development of Hengqin. At a press conference held yesterday to present the activities of the lawyer's day, the association's secretary general, Oriana Pun, spoke specifically in the fall of the purchase and sale of houses in the MSAR. "There is some impact, but as there is in other sectors," he noted.
"In fact, lawyers who are more linked to private notaries, who make purchasing deeds and real estate sales ... Just see the number of deeds or purchases and sales to know that, for sure, has an impact," said the lawyer.
Therefore, he said, "we have to take advantage of the opportunities, following the measures announced in the government lines of action, be aware, follow economic development and seek these opportunities."
In this respect, he focused on the case of Hengqin. "We have lawyers in the great bay that can play a very important role in this development and can help foreign investors bet inside China and vice versa, as well as bring the continent's entrepreneurs to Portuguese-speaking countries," he said.
Oriana Pun said that "this is where we are trying to develop our work, looking for opportunities to provide these services." In the Great Bay there are about 90 lawyers to perform functions. At this time, Macau has 457 registered lawyers.
Regarding the spectrum of interns lawyers, Oriana Pun indicated that they are currently close to 180. "The number has been stable in recent years," he said. He said, annually there are about a hundred students who are completing the law degree and who take admission examination, of which 20 to 30 pass the assessment and are recognized as interns.
As for the possibility of being restarted the protocol with the Portuguese Bar Association, Oriana Pun was peremptory in stating that "there has to be mutual will and not only on our part."
The lawyer indicated that on the visit of an AAM entourage to Portugal in 2024, this issue was not spoken at the meeting maintained with the Portuguese order. "They don't seem so willing to talk about it," he said.
It is recalled that the protocol between AAM and the Bar Association existed for a while, having as its main purpose the mutual recognition of the qualifications of lawyers from both parties. The deal was suspended about 10 years ago and has never been reactivated.
 
Legal Consultations and Forum on Professor's Day
Regarding the activities planned for lawyer day, free legal consultations are once again one of the strengths of the program, which starts this Saturday with sports events in the University of Science and Technology Stadium fields (UCTM). In the competitions will participate, in addition to lawyers, interns, and workers of the Directorate of Justice Services, also students from the universities of Macau, Macao, UCTM and São José.
In the event list, highlight the possibility that the general public has once again to receive legal consultations for free, an initiative that AMM has been making over the years.
Fulfilling what had been announced in 2024, consultations will have a wider scope this year. "This initiative will have a special focus, as we will be able to count on the presence of representatives of Hong Kong and the interior of China," said Vong Hin Fai. May 17 and 18 will take place between 10h00 and 20h00, at the Tourist Information Center of the Tourism Services Directorate.
Another highlight is the holding of a conference entitled “Integrating the interior and abroad - Forum on the Development of High Quality Legal Services under the“ One Rota ”initiative”, on May 16, between 14:30 and 17:30, at the Celebrity Tower Ballroom of the Studio City Hotel.
In the Forum, they will intervene, in addition to Macao lawyers, professionals from the continent, Hong Kong and Southeast Asia. In the same place, at 6.30 pm, the opening ceremony of the lawyer day will follow. "In this official opening we will have representatives of the government and the Greater Bay region, as well as those who participate in the forum," said the president of AMM. The traditional cocktail and commemorative dinner will take place about 7 pm.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>233 can vote for the consulate for Portuguese legislatures</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/233-podem-votar-consulado-para-legislativas-portuguesas/</link><description>From a universe of 55,789 voters registered in the territory, only 233 people are registered to vote in person, on May 17 and 18, for the legislative elections of Portugal, the Consul General told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. As for correspondence vote, Alexandre Leitão called for the bulletins to be sent as soon as possible. However, today the anticipated vote ends
 
Catarina Pereira*
 
There are only 233 people who will be able to vote in person in Macao for the legislative elections of Portugal, in a universe of 55,789 voters registered in the territory, the consul General of Portugal revealed in Macao and Hong Kong, in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. Alexandre Leitão also appealed to the vote and asked that, in the case of correspondence vote, the bulletins be sent as quickly as possible.
In the territory, citizens can exercise the right to vote in person at the consulate's facilities, on May 17 and 18, Saturday and Sunday, throughout the day, between 08h00 and 19h00. There will be only one vote table.
As for the voting reports, the Portuguese ambassador said he was informed by the Macao Post Office Director that voters are already receiving the electoral correspondence.
"People, as soon as they receive [the voting report], and I think many have already received, vote and go to the Post Office, because, of course, the sooner the vote will leave, the more guarantees it is to arrive at Portugal. On the side of Macao Post Office there is a commitment to give an immediate referral," said Alexandre Leitão, to make the CTT always have an opening stance in this scope.
However, census citizens in Portugal and who are abroad on May 18 can vote to this day at the consulate in Macao. Voters who are displaced in public or private functions can do so, representing national selections, as well as students, researchers, teachers and research pockets, as well as patients undergoing treatment. According to the consul, in this modality "there are not many people to vote".
Alexandre Leitão noted that "abstention is usually high", but not so much in the face -to -face [votes], "noting that by 2024 it was 33%." In voting bulletins could frankly decrease, "he said.
In this sense, he recalled that the vote is a right and a duty. "In Portugal it is not an obligation in the legal sense, we have to respect the individual freedom of each one. However, our political system is based on the choice of citizens from whom they governs them and, therefore, it is natural and understandable that I appeal to that everyone uses this faculty that the law can choose who will be deputies to the Assembly of the Republic in this case and, therefore, indirectly, who will govern Portugal."
 
*With Vítor Rebelo</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Al condemns “acts” of journalists from “All About Macau”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/al-condena-actos-de-jornalistas-all-macau/</link><description>The "acts" of two journalists from "All About Macau" were convicted by the Legislative Assembly, which says "much of the legitimate right of the media and journalists to do interviews and reports", but that this right "must be exercised within the limits established by law"
 
The Legislative Assembly (AL) condemned the "acts" of the journalists of the "All About Macau", which, according to the police, will have committed the crime of disturbance of functioning of masters, specifically the legislative body. The case, which took place on April 17, was sent to the prosecutor. “The handle and condemns the acts (…) of journalists,” can be read in a statement.
It is recalled that, according to the online newspaper, two journalists of the publication were taken by police while trying to enter the AL hall to attend the presentation of the 2025 Governing Action (LAG) lines for the Secretary's Guardianship for Administration and Justice, André Cheong. In a video published by the newspaper on social networks, it is possible to observe employees of the public security police body trying to remove one of the journalists from the entrance of AL.
On social networks, the newspaper, which has a monthly edition on paper, wrote that the journalists' request to enter the plenary session was refused, and the police were called to remove the two professionals, "claiming they were suspected of" disturbing the operation of the authorities "from Macao and" illegal video recording ".
Still inside Al, the newspaper indicated, the journalists received a 'blue card', which forces to watch the session in another room, through television broadcast - something they refused. "Apparently there were still vacant places" for the media in the main hall, according to the "All About Macau".
The legislative body, in turn, has another perspective. First of all, it argues that “reasonable measures have been adopted regarding assistance to meetings by journalists from the media and public bodies”. Then he says that "as there was a great influx of journalists" during the LAG, and "since the space for interviews, as well as the places available in the plenary room is limited," Al "allowed journalists who had not been able to access the plenary room after the necessary filming, could watch the broadcast."
"Regrettably, journalists of a particular publication did not comply with these reasonable measures during the three days of the meetings held on April 14, 15 and 17, shouting and pushing the security lines, which severely disturbed the order of the functioning of plenary meetings," reads. In this sense, "to cease the situation and to avoid its aggravation, the staff of the support services to the ALCATED the police to assist, on April 17, with the same removed the journalists from the AL, in order to ensure the effective continuation of the plenary." That day, the journalists remained in police custody until 21:00, still according to the "All About Macau" on social networks.
In the same note, AL ensures that “it has given great importance to the public information of the public about the work done” and that “it respects the legitimate right of the media and journalists to do interviews and reports”. However, he stresses, "this right must be exercised within the limits established by law." "As for acts that severely disturb the normal functioning of AL, it adopts, under the law, the appropriate measures to suppress them," he adds.
The Macao Journalists Association (AJM) said to “deeply” lament the detention of reporters, including Association President Ian Sio Tou. The AJM had expressed, days before, concern about the increase of official events without coverage of the media and “discriminatory practices” with the sector.
Already the president of the Portuguese and English Press Association of Macau reacted to Lusa, saying that "the unprecedented situation is sad and worries us, because we consider that it opens a precedent-at least-embarrassing." José Miguel Incarnation asked the MP “that there is a consideration in the evaluation of the facts, so that there is no greater consequences”.
 
Newspaper refuses “biased accusations”
All About Macao newspaper said it "deeply regrets the statements and biased accusations" of the Legislative Assembly (AL) against the two journalists expelled from Parliament, also criticizing the fact that the legislature has issued "an response to the incident" only "after more than a month of silence." In a statement released on social networks, he said that the AL prevented "repeatedly All About Macau journalists from doing their normal reporting work under false pretexts." He also accused the "ignoring the provisions of the Press Law and Article 94 of his regiment." The article states that "they are reserved to representatives of the media, duly accredited, own places in the meeting room." The newspaper also regretted the one that was "the first incident in Macao's history in which journalists who covered the ALS were taken by police for investigation - and even face criminal proceedings."
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Francis Lui warns of challenges that threaten Macau's competitiveness</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/francis-lui-alerta-para-desafios-ameacam-competitividade-de-macau/</link><description>The lack of hotel rooms could threaten Macau's competitiveness as a global tourism and leisure center, warned the leader of Galaxy Entertainment. For Francis Lui, the MSAR has also to respond to structural challenges such as the scarcity of human resources, the aging of the population and the increase in operating costs
 
"As Macau changes to a more mass-focused model, the issue of hotel rooms should also be addressed," Galaxy Entertainment president Francis Lui Yiu Tung yesterday warned, in an opening speech by the Global Gaming Expo Asia (G2E Asia), an event that runs until Friday at Venetian.
The game's mass market generated 74.9% of casinos gross revenues in the first three months of this year, reaching 43.20 billion patacas, more 10.9% than in the same period of 2019, according to data from the inspection direction and game coordination. Already the revenues of Backed Vip cipher at 14.46 billion, reflecting climbs of 3.3% and 0.5% in quarterly and annual terms, respectively, however, fell 61.1% compared to the first quarter of 2019.
"If we cannot adequately address the issue of accommodation of accommodation, Macao's competitiveness as a game -related destination, not only at the regional level, but also globally, will decrease," said Francis Lui.
The president of Galaxy Entertainment recalled that Las Vegas received 42.5 million visitors in 2019, before the start of the pandemic, and currently has "more than 155,000 hotel rooms." "This is more than three times higher than Macao," he lamented, although the territory received more than 34.9 million tourists last year.
According to official data, Macao's hotels and pensions had, at the end of March, with 44,000 rooms, 5.8% less than in the same month of 2024. The number of guests fell 5.4% in the first quarter and about 59% of visitors arrived in organized excursions and spent less than one day in the city.
"Given that the search for accommodation will continue to overcome the offer in the coming years, we must unite as an industry to protect Macau's premium positioning-not competing in prices, but in customer quality and experience," said the Galaxy leader.
According to data from the Macao Hotel Association, which brings together 47 local establishments, the average prices of the rooms fell 9.7% in homologous terms to 1,287 patacas in March.
Francis Lui admitted that the scarcity of land in Macau is a challenge and pointed out as a possible “greater integration” solution with the in -depth cooperation zone in Hengqin. "We must also consider the adoption of a strategic approach that emphasizes the differentiated and complementary development with other cities of the Great Bay," he argued, pointing to the exploration of an event strategy with Hong Kong, with complementary offers within the concept "One Visit, Two Cities".
The same responsible considers it still necessary to improve the Regional Transport Network. "It is still possible to make improvements to increase the number of vehicles using the [Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau] bridge, as well as improve immigration efficiency and policy," he said, suggesting the implementation of a large bay unified entrance system, supported by advanced technologies.
 
Structural challenges
In his speech, Francis Lui also noted that Macau faces several structural challenges, such as the scarcity of labor, the aging of the population, the aggravation of operating costs and the limitations in terms of terrestrial resources, without forgetting increasing regional competition.
On the other hand, he considered that the 2025 government lines of government reflect a “clear” orientation for both the population and the economy in general and for the particular game operators. "Diversification has been and will continue to be the way for the sustainable growth of the Macao game industry," he said, taking the opportunity to highlight the fact that Galaxy Macau already hosted nearly 900 events after the opening in 2023 of its arena and the International Convention Center.
With regard to the development of phase 4 of Galaxy Macao, Lui said this phase of expansion "promises to be a big leap for hospitality and luxury entertainment around the world." "We are also planning an immersive, high -tech theme park," he added, convinced that these facilities will offer guests "a state -of -the -art resort experience."</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China wants "sincerity" and "justice" in conversations with USA</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/china-quer-sinceridade-justica-nas-conversacoes-eua/</link><description>China yesterday appealed to the US to demonstrate “sincerity in commercial conversations” planned for the weekend, stressing that it accepted the meeting based on its interests and expectations of the international community. "The US should demonstrate sincerity in conversations, correct their wrong practices, find a balance with China and solve mutual concerns based on equality and respect," the Chinese Ministry of Commerce said in a statement.
The ministry stressed that “all dialogue and negotiation should be based on the principle of mutual respect”, in reference to meetings that the vice-minister He Lifeng-China's main commercial negotiator-will have US Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent on Saturday and Sunday in Switzerland.
“In recent times, US guardians have been circulating information on possible adjustments to their tariffs and transmitted this intention to China by different channels, manifesting openness to dialogue,” reads in the statement. "Given global expectations, China's interests and US industry and consumer demands, China has decided to accept talking," he added.
The Ministry has accused the US of adopting, since the return to Donald Trump's power, "unilateral, illegal and irrational tariffs," which will "severely affect bilateral economic and commercial relations, disturbed international order and created serious obstacles to global economic recovery." "To defend its legitimate rights and interests, China has taken firm countereds. Our position is consistent: either in the confrontation, and in dialogue, China's determination to safeguard its development interests will not change, as it will not change its commitment to equity, justice and multilateralism," he said.
The Chinese government reiterated that it maintains the door open to dialogue, but warned that the US must recognize "the negative impact of its unilateral tariffs," respect international economic standards and hear "the rational voices of all sectors." But if the US "say one thing and do another" or resort to "coercion and blackmail under the disguise of negotiations," this is something Beijing "will never accept," he said, vigoring that "China will never sacrifice its principles or international justice in exchange for an agreement."
China has reiterated that it will continue to work with other countries to "reinforce coordination, resist jointly to unilateral protectionism and hegemonic intimidation, defend free trade and multilateralism, and promote inclusive and beneficial economic globalization."
Since Trump has reacted the trade war in early April, the US has imposed up to 145% tariffs on Chinese products. Beijing answered with rates of up to 125% on imports from the US.
On Tuesday, Trump stated that there would be negotiations "at the appropriate time". In recent days, Washington has indicated that there have been previous contacts and Trump claimed to have spoken with Xi Jinping - something Beijing has denied and that the White House did not clarify.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Fines and travel agencies downloaded</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/baixadas-multas-para-guias-agencias-de-viagens/</link><description>The proposal of the activity of travel agencies and the tourist guide profession provided that the guides were sanctioned with a fine of 10,000 to 20 thousand patacas, if they did not use the profession card in the visible way. However, after some deputies of the 2nd Permanent Commission of the Legislative Assembly (AL) pointed out that the value was “too high”, the government dropped the amount to 2,000 to 10,000 patacas.
According to the Chinese language press, Chan Chak Mo, chairman of the commission, said the proposal also included a warning measure, which means that, in the first non -compliance with the rule, the offender will not incur a fine.
Other changes include a reduction in the fine of 150,000 to 400,000 patacas following the illegal exercise of agency activity to 150,000 to 300,000 patacas, as well as the relief of the fine for changing licenses to 2,000 to 10,000 patacas, and this fine varied between 50 thousand and 70 thousand patacas in the initial version of the proposal.
According to Chan Chak Mo, government representatives explained that the initial version of the proposal was prepared before the pandemic, but the guide market has changed, with the number of excursions decreased by the pre-pound period, so the executive decided to lower some fines.
On the other hand, the law proposal defines that travel agencies can exercise intermediation activities in selling tickets for shows, large events, amusement parks and places of tourist interest, as well as dining meal valleys. Given the doubt of deputies regarding the risk of selling high price tickets being considered as speculation, citing the government, Chan Chak Mo explained that, unless tickets are by boat or by plane, other types, such as concert tickets, will not be considered illegal, provided that prices are clear and accepted by customers.
In addition, according to Chan Chak Mo, the law provides that, within two years, transfers can be enrolled in a course of the University of Tourism of Macau, and will receive the guide card issued by tourism services after the completion of the training program. Citing the government, the deputy noted that, in the last five years, 39 people have taken a transfered course, and there are currently 19 transferrs in Macao.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Malparado in credit cards reaches 74.5 million</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/malparado-nos-cartoes-de-credito-atinge-745-milhoes/</link><description>The total amount of the debt for paying more than three months in credit cards issued by Macau banks was 74.48 billion patacas in late March, which represents an annual increase of 3.3% and a quarterly decrease of 4%, indicates data released by the Monetary Authority (AMCM). Already the debt with delays between three and six months reached 13.48 million patacas, or less 16.2% in a year and more 1% in the quarterly interval.
In the first quarter, the unpaid debt ratio, measured based on arrears for more than three months against debt balance, retreated 0.1 points to 2.9%, compared to the same period last year.
The credit limit relative to cards (50 billion patacas) grew 1.1% in annual terms and 0.2% in three months, with the balance of debts settling at 2.6 billion at the end of March. Rollover's balance (773.4 million) equivalent to 29.7% of debts receivable.
According to official statistics, the amount of credit used in the first three months of 2025 totaled 5.9 billion, illustrating down 0.2% and 5.3% in annual and quarterly terms, respectively. The advance of cash (153.7 million) corresponded to 2.6% of the credit used.
The number of credit card transactions (11.8 million) grew 9.7% within one year, but lowered 7.1% over the fourth quarter of 2024. The amount of refund (6.1 billion), including interest and expenses, fell 1.6% and 0.5% in the same comparative bases.
In debit cards (excluding cash surveys), the number of transactions (about 1.2 million) increased by 40.3% in a year, but dropped 3.2% in three months. The value involved (464.9 million) decreased 45.4% and 15.9% in annual and quarterly terms, respectively.
 
Mobile payments downloaded in quarterly terms
On the other hand, between January and March, the number of transactions with mobile MSAR payments decreased by 9.6% to 90.4 million compared to the previous three months, although it rose 11.6% in annual terms.
According to AMCM, the value of transactions reached 7.9 billion patacas, translating a quarterly descent of 3.8% and an annual increase of 8.7%. The average value per transaction was encrypted at 87.8 patacas in the quarter under analysis.
At the end of March, 108,749 devices accepted mobile payments and “QR code” supports in Macao, representing a 6.5%annual growth.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Wynn suffers from 38% in operating results</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/wynn-sofre-descida-de-38-nos-resultados-operacionais/</link><description>Wynn Macau yesterday announced $ 127.1 million operating results (about 972.5 million patacas) in the first quarter, less than 38.3% than in the same period of 2024. According to the controlling company, Wynn Resorts, which follows US accounting standards, EBITDA (results before interest, taxes, fees and depreciation) of WYNN Macau dropped 25.8% to $ 252.1 million in annual terms.
Between January and March, the Macau operator registered revenues of $ 865.9 million, a 13.3% drop compared to the same period of 2024. Bets on Wynn Macao and Wynn Palace casinos were responsible for the company's most of the company's $ 720 million in revenues, except 12.2% than in the first trimester of last year.
Craig Billings, executive director of Wynn Resorts, said in the same statement that the great gamblers were more lucky than normal in the first quarter, something that "negatively affected the results."
In this segment, known as the VIP game, the bets decreased only 1.25% in the two Wynn Macau casinos, but revenues fell much more, 34.4% in homologous terms, to $ 120.2 million. On average, casinos manage to raise at least 3% of bets on the VIP game, but this amount fell to 1.09% in the first three months of the year, in the case of the Wynn Macau casino.
The mass market continued to be from afar the main segment for the operator, representing revenues of $ 710.9 million between January and March, 6.9% less than in the same period of 2024.
Wynn Resorts, which is building a Casino hotel in the United Arab Emirates, said it continues to "explore opportunities to develop more business or related games in the domestic and international market." In a teleconference with analysts, after the announcement of the results, Billings acknowledged that the company could compete for new concessions for casinos in Japan, but only "if the conditions were adequate."
Billings also gave as an example Thailand, a country that is discussing the legalization of casinos and described as "an incredible market, with air transport, infrastructure, tourism, etc. unbelievable."
On the other hand, he said he did not expect any impact on Wynn Macao from the trade war created by US -imposed tariffs on imports from China.
On Tuesday, the Financial Notation Agency Fitch Ratings considered that the trade war could damage play operators in Macau, which are “subject to retaliation” and vulnerable to Chinese economic slowdown.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Poetry in the Garden” celebrates diversity of the Portuguese language</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/poesia-jardim-celebra-diversidade-da-lingua-portuguesa/</link><description>“Poetry in the Garden” wants to transform Seac Pai Van park “into an outdoor literature gallery, accessible to the entire population”, with the aim of making known poets of Lusophony. The show, which is inaugurated tomorrow, at 17h00, has 10 poems - nine of Portuguese -speaking countries and one from Macao. Portugal will be represented with Alberto Pimenta's “Praise of Kitsch”, while the MSar will feature the poem “Mei Chit Lai”, by Carlos Marreiros
 
Catarina Pereira
 
He calls himself “Poetry in the Garden” and is a show that aims to celebrate the Portuguese language and Lusophone cultures. The initiative, which emerges under the celebration, on May 5, from World Portuguese Language Day, is organized by the Portuguese Institute of the East (IPOR), and has the support of the House of Portugal in Macao and the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries.
It is in the Pai Van Seac Park, at 5 pm tomorrow, that the exhibition will be inaugurated, being evident to the public until May 31. “With this project it is intended to transform a garden of Macau into an outdoor literature gallery, accessible to the entire population, thus making known the poetic work of authors of nine countries and the region where Portuguese is one of the official languages,” explains Ipor.
The show consists of eleven panels suitable for external environment and includes 10 poems, “nine of whom (…) to Angola, Brazil, Cape Verde, Guinea-Bissau, Equatorial Guinea, Portugal, Mozambique, Sao Tome and Principe and Timor-Leste, who joins a poem in representation of the mashes”. Each panel includes the Portuguese version, with its traditional Chinese translation and simplified Chinese.
"And as poetry should not only be read, but also heard, the visitor will have the opportunity to listen to the declamation of the poems in the three languages: Portuguese, Mandarin and Cantonense." The audio will be made available through a QR code. In addition, it will also be included "a brief biography of the writer in both languages."
According to the information made available to this newspaper by IPOR, the poems will be the poems “Evolution”, by José Luís Mendonça (Angola), “Dona Doida”, by Adélia Prado (Brazil), “Vertical Construction”, by Armenio Vieira (Cape Verde), “Traces in Time”, by Emílio Tavares Lima (Guinea-Bissau), and “Mother” Evuna (Equatorial Guinea).
Representing Macao, in turn, will be the poem “Mei Chit Lai”, by Carlos Marreiros, while Mozambique will be shown through Mia Couto's poem “Identity”. Also present will be the poems “Praise of Kitsch”, by Alberto Pimenta (Portugal), “True Friend”, by Carlos Cardoso (Sao Tome and Principe) and “Oh! Freedom!” of Xanana Gusmão (Timor-Leste).
The celebration of World Portuguese Day, through poetry written in Portuguese, is, for Ipor, “a way of demonstrating the beauty that exists in the cultural diversity of countries and communities that speak, think and write in this language”. “After all, this outdoor exposure allows for a meeting with the various ways of reading and writing in Portuguese, in honor of its history and all those who have it as their own,” can read.
Currently spoken by more than 265 million people, the Portuguese language is a means of communication shared by peoples of the most diverse geographies, and therefore, “an indispensable resource for the construction of a plural community, with its own varieties
of those who chose it as a language of communication. ”
 
Camilo Castelo Branco focused on Book Day Session
The Reading Club of the Association of Friends of the Book in Macau, in collaboration with the Portuguese Institute of the East, celebrates today World Book Day, at the Camilo Pessanha Library, at 18:30. "Fanny Owen", by Agustina Bessa-Luís, is the book chosen for analysis and discussion. “The main reason for this choice was the creator of Camilo Castelo Branco, whose bicentennial of the birth, we are also celebrating,” explains the organization. At the session, Pedro D 'will speak of his experience in approaching Camilo Castelo Branco's work with Chinese students, where he can be assisted by Wang Suo Ying, who translated “The Love of Perdition” and “The Fall of an Angel” to Chinese. Shee will try to understand man through his biographers and admirers such as Agustina Bessa-Luís, Manuel de Oliveira and Mário Claudio.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao and France artists explore “invisible fabric of reality”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/artistas-de-macau-franca-exploram-tecido-invisivel-da-realidade/</link><description>The Sino-Francesa exhibition “Déjà Vu” will be evident in Parisian until the end of June, exploring the ideas of “memory” and “perception”, through multimedia facilities, video and artificial intelligence



















Under the “May French” Arts Festival, the Parisian will host the “Déja Vu” exhibition, a sino-frank project that sets “a bridge between Sino-Franceses cultural dialogues through art” and plunges “in the philosophical intersections of time, memory and perception”.
Co-organized by “Art for All” (AFA), “Avant-Garde’ Innovative Multimedia Art Association ”and with the support of the Culture Development Fund and Sands China, the exhibition will open on May 14 and will be open to the public until June 28, every day between 12:00 and 19:00.
According to a statement from AFA, the theory of the “Déjà vu” of Frenchman Henri Bergson reveals “the simultaneous split between perception and memory” and a coexistence of the present “real” and his “virtual” mirrored image. Macao Alice Kok and Catherine Cheong artists and Frenchman Robert Cahen transform this abstract philosophical concept “into tangible sensory experiences”, using multimedia facilities, video and images generated by artificial intelligence.
According to AFA, the keywords of the project, "Mirroring", "looping" and "Generating", reflect the artists' techniques and recognize "how memory and technology weave the invisible fabric of contemporary reality."
Robert Cahen and Alice Kok will also organize “Video Postcards” MasterClass on May 18, in which participants will have the opportunity to enter “Coloane's natural and historical landscapes”. With techniques such as “slow camera, overlap and sound design”, artists will transform sensory experiences into unique “memory cards”. The workshop will include on-site filming, post-production orientation and a final display, indicates AFA.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Golden Week attracted 51 thousand international visitors</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/semana-dourada-atraiu-51-mil-visitantes-internacionais/</link><description>During the five days of Labor Day holidays (May 1-5), Macau received about 850,000 visitors an increase of 40.7% over last year's same period, with a daily average of 170,000, exceeding 158 thousand visitors per day in 2019 and reaching 107.5% of this year's daily average. According to data from the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), during this period, the territory received 51,000 visitors from international markets, equivalent to 6% of the total. As usual, the majority, 679,000, came from the interior of China (80%), followed by Hong Kong visitors, totaling 111,000 (13%) and Taiwan, which totaled 9.1 thousand. Also according to the STD balance and taking into account the data provided by the hotel sector operators, during these holidays, the average occupancy rate of hotel establishments was 94.1%, an annual increase of 5.0 points. The highest occupancy rate was registered on May 2, with 98.1%. On the other hand, the Grand Prix Museum received from 4,255 visitors, representing a 4.11%homologous increase. According to the body led by Helena de Senna Fernandes, during this period eight cases suspected of illegal accommodation of accommodation were detected. The open line for tourism received 61 requests for information and nine complaints of visitors, mainly related to concert tickets and services at border stations, among others, and 11 residents complaints, related to the illegal benefit of accommodation.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Launched the latest edition of “The Books and the City” about “Reading and Sport”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lancada-ultima-edicao-de-os-livros-cidade-sobre-leitura-desporto/</link><description>The 39th edition of “The Books and the City”, published by the Public Library of the Cultural Institute (IC) and dedicated to the theme “Reading and Sport”, is already available. This new edition covers “thematic articles from various perspectives” and offers “a unique reading experience” with “practical suggestions” to establish “reading and sports habits,” the IC said. In the “Reading Landscape” section, the “Reading Program for Babies and Children” is addressed to encourage families to “cultivate the habit of joint reading in the growth process”. Already in the section “Speaks the Author”, readers are brought “to the world of the author's mind” from the illustrated book of cognitive psychology “The Butterflly That Wasn´t Painted Gold”, in the sense of knowing the concept and history of the creation of the work. Readers will also find information regarding the legal deposit regime of Macao, in the “Library Manual” section, for “a deeper understanding” of the functioning of the local cultural conservation. The public can also find “a vast selection of recently published books and magazines” in the “New Launches” section, as well as 10 “succinct and clairvoyant” book reviews in Portuguese, Chinese and English. The 3,000 copies are available for free survey at IC dependent libraries, in higher education institutions, in various bookstores, TAP Seac Gallery and other cultural spaces in the city. The digital version can be consulted on the IC Public Library website.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Xia Baolong starts today visiting inspection</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/xia-baolong-inicia-hoje-visita-de-inspeccao-a-raem/</link><description>Hong Kong and Macau's workst a director of the China Communist Party Central Committee, Xia Baolong, starts a six -day visit to Macau today, “to find out of the local situation, and with the purpose of knowing Macao's socioeconomic current and the governance work of the new Government of MSAR”, according to an official note from the Social Communication Office. Executive Chief Sam Hou Fai, thanked, cited in a statement, “the attention and support provided by the central government”, welcoming the visit of the Hong Kong and Macao Macao Cabinet Director. “The government will be committed to the appropriate provisions to ensure the full success of Xia Baolong's visit,” said Sam Hou Fai. It is recalled that the last time Xia Baolong was visiting the MGA was in May last year. At the time, the High Chinese leader said it was necessary to work for Macao's “Golden Business Card” “shining even more as an international metropolis”, which this was an expectation for the future development of the territory. Xia Baolong then visited institutions and health care industries, Big Health, state-of-the-art technology, education and young people, and the deepened cooperation zone is still moved to find out the work of implementing the first phase objectives and tasks. This time, the visit ends next Tuesday, May 13.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Increases chickens in the US because of increasing egg price</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/aumenta-aluguer-de-galinhas-nos-eua-por-causa-aumento-preco-dos-ovos/</link><description>Frustrated by increasing egg price and rationing in supermarkets, Yong-Mi Kim decided it was time to rent chickens.
A US Aviary Influenza crisis has cost eggs in recent months. While many chose to raise their own animals, this university professor who lives in the La Crescenta, California community preferred to rent them.
“I want to try this and see if I like it or not,” he comments. "I know people who have chickens at home, but they do a lot of work. They had to adapt the garden." "I think renting a chicken is a good start."
Chicken rental began to gain strength in the US over a decade ago, when Jenn and Phil Tompkins created the “Rent a Chicken” project in Pennsylvania. The service has expanded to about 40 cities by farmers and has gained even more popularity in recent months.
“From the pandemic we have seen more interest than usual, but it was especially greater this year. I would say that three to four times more than we saw at the same time last year,” Victoria Lee, who serves the Los Angeles region on her farm in the Agua Dolce community, told AFP.
At the peak of the crisis, the Americans even paid more than $ 10 for a dozen eggs, which, depending on the city, used to cost between three to five dollars.
The supermarkets began to ration the carton packaging, and the issue infiltrated the 2024 presidential campaign, when Donald Trump promised to reduce the cost of food, including eggs as soon as he took office.
But the Republican politician is the current president and the product is up to the rise. In March last year, egg prices rose 1.2% compared to the previous month and were 60.4% more expensive, according to the US Department of Agriculture.
Although raising chickens at home is no cheaper than buying eggs on the market, Lee explains that this improves quality.
"When they arrive at the store, eggs have, on average, 48 to 60 days. Over time, egg protein begins to decompose," he says.
On the other hand, the garden eggs last the time their owners take to collect them.
“Rent the chicken” offers different packages that, depending on the location and number of chickens, range from about $ 500 to $ 1,000 for six months. The rental includes the bird, food, drinking fountains and feeders, a guide on how to take care of chickens and the key element of the proposal: the mobile chicken coop.
It is a kind of mini pit, individual for each chicken, fully closed by grids and transportable, with wheels at the bottom. This protects animals from predator and, being portable, ensures that birds live in a natural environment without much space.
“Every day, customers raise the chicken coop and move it to another location, so that chickens have access to fresh herb daily in a seven-day cycle,” explains Lee.
"So chickens have the experience of being in an open area, with new stimuli, new insects to look, new grass to dig, but in a safe environment."
The practicality of the chicken coop is what makes your rental to people like Kim attractive. The 52 -year -old teacher received the chickens at home with great enthusiasm.
“Free eggs!” He exclaimed when Lee came to his home to deliver the kit, which included a dozen fresh eggs put by animals last week.
A client with two chickens can wait up to 14 eggs a week, explains Lee.
Kim, whose son is athlete and consumes eggs often, says that although the supply crisis has led her to rent the chickens, "it's something deeper than that." "I wanted to learn (that) as a way of life and also compare the taste of eggs."
Proof that the US continues to be the land “of opportunities”…
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>