<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Taxi drivers committed almost 2,000 offenses last year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/taxistas-cometeram-quase-2-000-infraccoes-ano-passado/</link><description>There were almost 2,000 infractions committed by taxi drivers over the past year, according to data revealed by the Public Security Police Corps, a volume that illustrates an annual increase of 118%. According to the information, 71% of the cases concerned taxi drivers who did not wait in order of arrival for customers in the territory's squares.
 
CATARINA PEREIRA
 
Irregularities committed by taxi drivers more than doubled last year, with the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) recording 1,898 cases, a volume that reflects an increase of 118.16% compared to 2024. The data, made available by the corporation on the official Facebook page, reveals that the vast majority of cases were related to taxi drivers who did not wait in order of arrival for customers in the territory's squares. Specifically, 1,110 situations of this type were recorded, that is, 71% of the total, having registered an annual increase of 306.59%.
There were also 428 cases of refusal to transport, 56.2% more than a year before, and 110 cases of obvious route deviation, with this type of infractions rising by 2.8%. With regard to abusive charging, 43 cases were detected, an annual increase of 72%, while 52 cases of inappropriate speed were recorded (+1.96%). The number of other types of offenses committed by taxi drivers also grew by 36.67% to 90 cases.
Conversely, the number of cases of price negotiation fell by 7.14% to 14, while situations in which taxi drivers did not activate or deactivate the meter decreased by 47.22% to 123.
To strengthen inspection of the taxi sector, the CPSP may request data on terminals installed in vehicles from the competent authorities, after receiving related complaints and to “execute the law fairly”. In this sense, and according to the statistics presented, in 2025, the CPSP requested information from taxi terminals for a total of 3,247 cases, an annual increase of 142.68%.
On the other hand, 7,651 people were charged with illegal crossing, an increase of 2.56%. The CPSP recalls that notices have already been installed in some areas of the city, such as Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro, Rua do Campo, Rua de Beijing, Rua de Ferreira do Amaral and Avenida do Comendador Ho Yin.
Overall last year, there were 14,638 road accidents on the territory's roads, representing a drop of 5.62% compared to the total of 15,510 recorded in 2024. The three main causes of accidents were failure to maintain a safe distance (3,087 cases, minus 2.59%), uncontrolled speed (2,024 cases, minus 1.27%) and lack of be careful when turning (1,892 cases, 3.44% more).
Furthermore, the CPSP revealed that there were 4,578 road accidents that caused injuries, translating into an annual increase of 0.68%. Regarding serious road accidents, the number remained stable, although there were four road accidents in which seven deaths were recorded, representing a drop of 20% compared to the five cases recorded in 2024. For the corporation, the data demonstrate that “road safety in Macau remained at a good level last year”.
With regard to drunk driving, 141 cases were recorded (-17.06%). According to the CPSP, there were 86 criminal cases of drunk driving, an annual drop of 23.21%, and 55 cases of driving under the influence of alcohol, a decrease of 5.17%. In 2025, out of every 10,000 people who were tested for the presence of alcohol in their blood, 30 were detected with excess alcohol. This rate represented a decrease of 27.21% in annual terms. On the other hand, there were also three cases of driving under the influence of drugs (+50%).</description><pubDate>2026-01-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Consulate in Macao recorded increase in voter turnout</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/consulado-na-raem-registou-subida-da-afluencia-eleitoral/</link><description>The presidential elections in Portugal brought 2,374 voters to the polls installed at the Consulate General of Portugal in the Macao SAR, including 1,178 on Saturday and 1,196 on Sunday. With 57,748 registered voters in the territory, the participation rate reached 4.11%, more than double the 2.03% recorded in 2021, during the pandemic, when 1,424 of the 70,134 registered people voted. In 2016, 15,977 people were registered and 526 voted (3.29% of the total).
 

The official results of the vote in Macau will only be published at 9 am today, when the Consulate General's services open, said Consul Alexandre Leitão. As he explained, the results could only be released after the polls close in the Azores, that is, at four o'clock in the morning in Macau.
During yesterday, voters generally waited a short time to exercise their right. The day before, some periods, specifically in the late morning and early afternoon, had long queues, with waiting times of around 45 minutes.
For David Morais, the process was easy. “We arrived at the Consulate, spent two or three minutes to find out which section we were in and within 10 minutes it was resolved,” he told Jornal TRBUNA DE MACAU.
Regarding the campaign for these elections, the professor admitted to having seen the summaries of the debates. “I think that the parties are interfering a lot in the election of their candidates, but unfortunately that is what we have”, he said.
Regarding the importance of voting to elect the President, even when living a long distance from Portugal, he stressed that “our Head of State is our representation across borders, he is the one who stands up for us”.
Sofia Alcântara said that it is “important that we exercise our right and responsibility to vote, even if it is blank, which is not my case”. “It is important for us to truly honor what a democracy is, whether or not we live in Portugal, because it is our homeland”, he stressed, adding that “people do their best to express their opinion so that the country goes in the right direction”.
The dentist by profession said she was enlightened by the campaign, despite the high number of candidates. “I think that from the moment they meet the necessary signatures, and as we live in a democracy, there should be as many numbers as we want”, he indicated, hoping that the new President “will give Portugal the right direction”.
Regarding whether electronic voting would make the process more comfortable, faster and more efficient, he confessed that “I had never thought about it, but it would be interesting”. In fact, “it was more convenient, but that shouldn’t be what stops us from coming and exercising our right and duty to vote”, he reinforced.
Ana Pinto, in turn, said that the process was “well organized, calm and super-fast”. Even so, he considered that electronic voting might be better. “With new technologies it would be a good solution and would provide greater speed”, he argued.
The Venetian worker hopes that the new Portuguese President will be “innovative and take a little care of our country, which is a little down”.
José António Carion Júnior, Macanese, retired about 10 years ago, only waited around 15 minutes to place his ballot in the ballot box, but understands that there should be more than two polling stations, “to provide a faster process”.
As for the future, he stressed that the new President “has to know Macau well, because sometimes there are things that Portugal forgets”. “Therefore, you should be a little more concerned about those who are living abroad, of which there are many throughout the world”.
Carion, who lived in Toronto (Canada) for a few years, only exercised his right to vote in Macau, “because the distances here are much smaller”, he notes, stating that he noticed that many Chinese people with Portuguese passports went to vote. “In the past, they didn’t care, but now they have a better idea”, he points out.
Rui Oliveira, who had just left the premises, confirmed the speed of the process. “I didn’t have a long wait,” he pointed out.
Regarding the election itself, he noted that, even from a distance, “we continue to be part of Portugal, we are all Portuguese, hence there is every interest in guaranteeing and participating in the electoral process for a figure who, despite not being politically the one who has the greatest weight over governance, is the one who has the greatest weight over the institutions”.
The lawyer considers that “this was one of the best presidential campaigns, because the debate was of better quality”. Despite there being several candidates, “there was a debate of ideas and content, and not just about personal issues”. It was, therefore, “a very positive and very enriching campaign for Portuguese democracy”, he concluded.
 
Participation rate in Portugal exceeded 21% by noon
Voter turnout in Portugal for the election of the next President of the Republic reached 21.18% until 12:00 yesterday (20:00 in Macau), according to data from the General Secretariat of the Ministry of Internal Affairs. In the last presidential elections, on January 24, 2021, and at the same time, voter turnout was 17.07%. In the 2021 presidential elections, the abstention rate reached 60.76%. The polls for the presidential elections opened at 08:00 (16:00 in Macao) in mainland Portugal and Madeira and an hour later in the Azores due to the time difference, closing at 19:00 (03:00 in Macau). When polling stations opened across the country, starting at 8:00 am, the National Elections Commission (CNE) did not record any incidents, according to its spokesperson, André Wemans. More than 11 million voters were called to choose the new President of the Republic, who will succeed Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, who reached the term limit, with 11 candidates accepted, a record number. If one of the candidates obtains more than half of the votes validly cast, he will be elected head of state. Otherwise, there will be a second round, on February 8th, with the two most voted candidates in the vote.
 
Victor Rebelo</description><pubDate>2026-01-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>VIP gaming recovery accelerated in late 2025</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/recuperacao-jogo-vip-acelerou-final-de-2025/</link><description>While remaining far from pre-pandemic levels, VIP baccarat gross revenues rose by almost a quarter by 2025 year on year, outpacing overall average casino growth. According to official data, the recovery gained new momentum between October and December, with revenue linked to high rollers increasing by 45.2% in annual variation, corresponding to around 31% of the total
 
SERGIO TERRA
 
Overall last year, VIP baccarat generated gross revenues of approximately 67.99 billion patacas, a value that represents an increase of 24.14% compared to 2024, according to data released by the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Department (DICJ) on its website. In the space of a year, the weight of VIP gaming in the revenue structure of Macau casinos increased by 3.3 percentage points to 27.48% of the total, a result that is still far from the 46.24% in 2019.
Data from the DICJ show that the room's business for high rollers grew above average, taking into account that total revenues from games of chance registered an annual increase of 9.09% to 247.40 billion patacas, reaching 84.60% of the level of 2019, the pre-pandemic year. Revenues from VIP baccarat were only equivalent to 50.27% of the 2019 level, however, the percentage of this comparison accelerated again, compared to the 40.5% recorded in 2024.
The recovery of VIP gaming was most notable between October and December 2025, with gross revenues from this segment amounting to 20.31 billion patacas, illustrating a pre-covid recovery rate of 62.85% and increases of 45.17% and 20.29% in annual and quarterly terms, respectively. The general performance of casinos in the fourth quarter (66.06 billion) resulted in increases of 15.04% and 5.58% on the same comparative basis.
In the fourth quarter, the proportion of VIP gaming in total revenue reached 30.75%, reflecting a growth of 6.38 points compared to the same period in 2024 and an increase of 3.76 points when compared to the previous three months.
It should be remembered that, after having dominated the sector for many years, the VIP game suffered severe blows following the arrests of Alvin Chau and Levo Chan, former leaders of the main “junket” companies (Suncity and Tak Chun), in November 2021 and January 2022, respectively. In recent years, the activity of gambling promoters has also come to comply with several legal restrictions within the framework of the Government's new strategy for an industry that continues to be the territory's largest economic engine.
In turn, gross revenues from the mass market, including tables and slots, grew 4.30% to 179.42 billion patacas between 2024 and 2025, corresponding to 75.52% of the total. Comparison with 2019 also reveals a 14.12% increase in revenue volume.
Baccarat in the mass segment alone contributed 142.65 billion, 3.44% more than in 2024. In gaming machines, revenue increased 7.33% to 13.87 billion.
According to official data, between October and December, revenue from the mass game amounted to 45.75 billion patacas (69.25% of the total), marking a quarterly increase of 0.15% and an annual increase of 5.33%.
 
Bets fall on football and rise on basketball
DICJ statistics reveal, on the other hand, that betting on football games generated a gross income of 386 million patacas last year, signaling drops of 3.26% and 27.72% in relation to 2024 and 2019, respectively. On the other hand, revenues derived from basketball betting (223 million) rose 3.72% in annual terms and 5.69% compared to the pre-pandemic era.
Including casinos, racing betting and lotteries, Macau's gaming industry ended 2025 with gross revenues of 248.03 billion.</description><pubDate>2026-01-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief demands greater government efficiency</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-exige-maior-eficiencia-governamental/</link><description>The leader of the Macao SAR said he hopes that the management of public bodies will be able to recognize “insufficiencies”, in order to increase the “efficiency” of government work. During a meeting with several Government officials to review the work carried out last year and plans for 2026, Sam Hou Fai also once again highlighted the importance of “boosting economic diversification”.
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
Sam Hou Fai instructed the directorates of public services to increase “governance efficiency and boost diversification”, in a meeting that took place on Friday afternoon, at the Government headquarters, to present the assessment of the work carried out in 2025 and the government plans for 2026. According to a statement from the Social Communication Office (GCS), the Chief Executive “underlined the importance of being more aware of the shortcomings and the need for them to be verified as the work is carried out”.
The Macao SAR leader noted that “existing mentality and thinking must be released to break habitual mental patterns” and work must be planned “in a timely manner”. He also mentioned that the work must be carried out with “courage and responsibility” and that government actions must be implemented “with precision”.
In addition to giving priority to services for residents, in favor of “social well-being”, Sam Hou Fai also urged leaders to be aware of the risks and to remain “alert even if you are in a safe situation”.
When taking stock of 2025, the Chief Executive praised the work carried out, highlighting that the “good start” of this Government's mandate “proceeded in a stable, successive and calm manner, with reforms, innovations, advances and results”.
According to the GCS, the person in charge demonstrated “a high appreciation for public services”, for having taken “the fundamental interests of the Country and the integral interests of Macau as the starting point to install a global mentality that firmly guarantees the sovereignty, national security and development interests of the Country”.
For the Head of Government, regarding next year, “all departments and services must unify the same thinking, make every effort and collaborate proactively, with a sense of responsibility and mission and thus create an enormous force to work and advance together”.
Another of the priorities that Sam Hou Fai highlighted is based on the need to “insist and improve the predominance of executive power, maximizing the central role of the Chief Executive and the Macao SAR Government in the governance system”. Furthermore, the Secretary for Administration and Justice must “effectively fulfill his duties and responsibilities, strengthening coordination and cooperation to ensure that the Macao SAR Government assumes its central governance functions with professionalism and pragmatism”, added the Government leader.
The solution will involve “creating a governance structure with interconnection between higher and lower levels and a synergy of cooperation between services, and promoting positive interaction between the executive and legislative powers that cooperate, support and promote reciprocally, at institutional, political and operational levels”, defended the Chief Executive.
In this sense, the Government will move forward “with the nine essential works presented in the Lines of Government Action”, having presented “the main work plan for each tutelage, based on the instructions and demands of President Xi Jinping”, and in line with the 15th National Five-Year Plan and the Third Five-Year Plan of the Macao SAR.
The Chief Executive also added that the annual work review meeting for holders of key positions and directors of public services will be held regularly, “to improve their institutional development and increase the efficiency of governance”. He also asked those responsible for caution and entrepreneurship, in favor of the “long-term development of Macau”.
More than 70 officials were present at the meeting, including the Secretary for Administration and Justice, Wong Sio Chak, the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, the Secretary for Security, Chan Tsz King, the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, and the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, among others.</description><pubDate>2026-01-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Liu Xianfa left MNE Commissioner in the Macao SAR</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/liu-xianfa-deixou-comissariado-mne-na-raem/</link><description>Liu Xianfa stepped down as commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs in the Macao SAR after completing his term
 
On Friday, Liu Xianfa, commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs (MNE) in the Macao SAR, concluded his term in Macau. On the same day, he left office and returned to Beijing with his wife, Li Ping.
According to information published on the website of the MNE Commissariat in the Macao SAR, in recent days, Liu Xianfa said goodbye to the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, the vice-president of the Chinese People's Political Consultative Conference (CPPCC), Edmund Ho, the former Chief Executives of the Macao SAR, Chui Sai On and Ho Iat Seng, the main heads of legislative and judicial bodies, among other figures from different sectors.
At the farewell meeting, Liu Xianfa expressed his gratitude to the Government of the Macao SAR and all sectors of society for the “great support continuously given to the work of the Commission”, expressing himself “honored” to have participated in “a series of great, important and happy events” of the Macao SAR and witnessing the “new development, new advances and new achievements of the successful practice of ‘One Country, Two Systems’”.
Recalling that this year marks the beginning of the 15th National Five-Year Plan, while the Macao SAR Government “is actively developing” the preparation of the 3rd Five-Year Plan for the city, Liu promising.”
“The MNE Commissionerate will resolutely implement the decisions of the Central Government, carry out, with full commitment, the functions and responsibilities in accordance with the Basic Law, and continue to create a good external environment for the economic and social development of Macau”, assured Liu Xianfa.
Sam Hou Fai and Edmund Ho praised the “innovation” and “pragmatism” of the MNE Commissionerate under the leadership of Liu Xianfa over the past five years. The Chief Executive and Vice-President of the CPPCC also highlighted that, under the leadership of Liu Going deeper into Hengqin, widening the opening to the outside…”.
Furthermore, they recalled that the Commission “committed itself to guaranteeing the rights and interests of Macau’s compatriots abroad, put into practice the principles of ‘diplomacy in favor of Macau’ and ‘diplomacy for the people’, through concrete actions, as well as made positive contributions to the lasting prosperity and stability and the adequate diversification of Macau’s economy”.
Sam Hou Fai and Edmund Ho stated that Macau will fully take advantage of its unique advantages to deepen exchanges and cooperation with Portuguese-speaking and neighboring countries in the economic, commercial, cultural and educational fields, and to better integrate and serve the national development situation.
It is recalled that Liu Xianfa was appointed commissioner of the MNE in the Macao SAR in February 2021, several months after the departure of his predecessor Shen Beili. Currently, Liu is 62 years old.</description><pubDate>2026-01-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Voluntary demolition of illegal works continues to grow</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/continua-crescer-demolicao-voluntaria-de-obras-ilegais/</link><description>The voluntary demolition of illegal works continues to grow, having reached a maximum last year, at least since 2020. In total, 241 illegal works were demolished, voluntarily. DSSCU initiated 776 cases, an annual decrease of 8%. In addition, it concluded 10 processes regarding the treatment of illegal works together, with cases being resolved in around 260 fractions
 
CATARINA PEREIRA
 
Over the past year, the Directorate of Land and Urban Construction Services (DSSCU) opened 776 cases due to illegal works, representing an average of around 64.6 per month. The data illustrates a decreasing trend that has been observed over recent years, with a decrease of 8% compared to 2024, when 844 were registered.
Since 2019, the annual number of cases initiated only grew between 2022 and 2023, going from 723 to 1,114. The recent breaks will be associated, in large part, with the impact of the legal regime for urban construction, which came into force in 2022, increasing fines and expanding the means for enforcing the law, including the introduction of criminal liability, endorsement in the land registry and suspension of the supply of water and electricity.
Last year, offenders in 94 cases were notified of the final decision, 46 more than a year before. These are cases in which the owners can now proceed with the demolition of illegal works, within a stipulated period. If the order is not complied with, DSSCU itself carries out the demolition, the expenses of which are borne by the transgressor.
Voluntary demolitions have been growing over the last few years and reached a maximum in 2025 since at least 2020. Last year, there were 241 cases of voluntary demolition, three more than the 238 in 2024. In 2020 and 2021, these cases had been below 80, while in 2022 they rose to 98 and in 2023 they increased to 129.
It is worth noting that, with a view to encouraging offenders to cooperate with the Government in implementing the law, if the requirements are met, the law provides for measures to reduce or exempt fines for those who carry out voluntary demolition.
In a statement issued yesterday, DSSCU reported that last year it concluded 10 processes regarding the treatment of illegal works together, with cases of illegal works being resolved in around 260 units. Among the cases observed, 15 were clandestine constructions that existed on the terrace of a building. “After receiving the demolition order issued by DSSCU, interested parties requested voluntary demolition and carried out the works within the same deadline, in order to restore the terrace in accordance with the project”, it can be read.
Since last year, the organization began to reinforce the joint treatment of several illegal works with similar characteristics in the same building in order to increase the efficiency of the work. In situations where there are illegal works with similar characteristics in the common spaces of a building, such as terraces, podiums or corridors, DSSCU collectively initiates demolition processes and orders.</description><pubDate>2026-01-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>RAE expands border crossing facilities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/rae-alargam-facilidades-na-passagem-fronteirica/</link><description>Starting today, the authorities of Macau and Hong Kong will expand the scope of facilities at the border crossing between the two regions. On the one hand, the minimum age for using automatic passage channels from another region for permanent residents increases from 11 to 7 years old, on the other hand, non-permanent residents aged 18 or over will also be able to start using these channels. Furthermore, iris recognition at border crossings will be extended this year to non-resident workers and foreign students
 
The authorities of Macau and Hong Kong continue to optimize measures to facilitate border crossings between the two regions, under the “General Planning Guidelines for the Development of the Greater Bay Area”. In a new phase, which begins today, the minimum age for using automatic passage channels in another region will be lowered, while non-permanent residents will also be able to have access to this passage.
According to a statement from the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP), the Identification Services Directorate and the Macau Security Forces Services Directorate, which are working with the Hong Kong Immigration Department, permanent residents of the SAR between the ages of 7 and 10 can register at counters to use automatic passage channels located at border posts in the other region, as long as they are accompanied and carry the necessary documents with them. Minors can start using the channels around 30 minutes after registering.
At the same time, access to Macau's “automatic full inspection channels” and “iris recognition crossing channels” will be extended to Hong Kong permanent residents aged between 7 and 10, “which will allow them a faster and more convenient border crossing experience”. Specifically, minors from Hong Kong, who use their Permanent Identity Card and the Safe Conduct to and from Mainland China of residents of Hong Kong and Macau, including those of non-Chinese nationality, can use the channels at the Hengqin and Qingmao Border Posts and the Zhuhai-Macau Inspection Room of the Delta Bridge Border Post.
At the same time, with the registration for Macau's automatic pass-through channels, they can register to use the iris recognition channels. Once registrations are complete, you can use the iris recognition channels at Portas do Cerco, Ponte do Delta Border Post, maritime terminals at Porto Exterior, Porto Interior, Taipa as well as at Macau Airport.
As for non-permanent residents of both regions, aged 18 or over, they can register through the self-service kiosks and start using the other region's channels after around three hours. They can not only register to use Hong Kong e-channels at the registration counters of the HKSAR Immigration Department, but also at the self-service kiosks in Macau and Hengqin.
On the other hand, non-permanent residents of greater age, who use the HKSAR Permanent Identity Card and the “Hong Kong Special Administrative Region Document of Identity for Visa Purposes” valid for more than 90 days, in addition to being able to register at the counters in Macau, can use the self-service kiosks at the designated checkpoints or at each “Registration of Persons Offices” in Hong Kong. Non-permanent residents of the SAR aged between 11 and 17 can register in person at the counters.
Meanwhile, iris recognition at border crossings will be extended this year to non-resident workers and foreign students with extended stays in the Macao SAR. According to the CPSP, there are currently 152 automatic channels with iris recognition in the territory.
Last year, around 330 thousand residents completed the registration of this system, with 26.28 million passages recorded through these channels in 2025. As for permanent residents of Hong Kong, who have been able to enter the Macao SAR through this method since June last year, there were almost 400 thousand registered, with more than 1.4 million passages.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2026-01-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Promised “full” follow-up of residents’ suggestions</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/prometido-acompanhamento-integral-das-sugestoes-dos-residentes/</link><description>“Health Promotion, Decentralization of Resources and Anticipation of Disease Intervention” was the theme of the first session of the “Esplanada: Conversation on social issues and culture”, held at the Ilha Verde Health Center and attended by more than 70 people.
The events aim to materialize the principle of “better serving the citizen”, as established in the Government Action Lines and implement government guidelines in the area of ​​social affairs and culture, “aiming to monitor the lives of the population and capture public opinion”, according to a statement from the Health Services (SSM).
The event itself was preceded by an interactive exchange, in which the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture highlighted that the conversations seek to “create a platform for direct dialogue with residents”, collecting opinions on topics related to the lives of the population, such as students' school fees, storage in libraries, sports facilities and SSM.
Lam committed to “recording and fully monitoring” the suggestions presented by residents, paying attention to problems, “even those whose resolution is complex in the short term”.
Together, he highlighted, “a phased improvement” will be promoted, with the expectation that the team will adopt an attitude of “listening more, reflecting more and paying greater attention”, responding to the population’s questions. Several residents then presented their opinions and suggestions on health, social issues and culture.
From January of the current year, the activity became part of the range of regular interactive exchange events in community neighborhoods.
This activity, which focuses monthly on different themes, aims to “achieve social consensus and continue to improve the various works”, emphasize the SSM, adding that the process aims, “above all, for residents to feel more benefited and contribute, together, to the achievement of the government's vision for the construction of a 'happy Macau'”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2026-01-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New association wants to promote the study of Law</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/nova-associacao-quer-fomentar-estudo-direito/</link><description>The Association of Legal Studies of Macau and Portugal was created to give life to a mega undertaking, the publication of the annotated Macau Civil Procedure Code, and, later, of works “outside the most popular topics”
 
David Sá Machado, a Portuguese lawyer working in Macau, is the ideologue of what will be the first annotated version, published in full, of the territory's Civil Procedure Code.
The three volumes, with the contribution of around 60 authors, including “lawyers, magistrates, academic professors, advisors and other jurists from Portugal and Macau”, should see the light of day later this year, the person responsible explains to Lusa, noting that they are in the review phase. “If there are changes to the code planned, we may delay a little”, he adds.
To facilitate the publication of the work, “an added value” that aims to be a “contribution to law in Macau”, the Association of Legal Studies of Macau and Portugal was created.
“Other projects will emerge later”, says Lusa Sá Machado, president of the association, indicating the intention of, in the future, organizing “more pedagogical and didactic initiatives”.
Still talking about this project of around three thousand pages and coordinated by two women – Maria José Capelo, associate professor at the Faculty of Law of the University of Coimbra, and Teresa Leong, retired judge from Macau – the lawyer notes that it will be produced in Portuguese, although a Chinese version is also planned, as “the target audience is jurists from Macau”.
“An annotated code should serve to clarify the reader of the various interpretative meanings of the norms and, perhaps, add something from the point of view of the right to be constituted”, he indicates. “I think it always enriches any legal system”, he adds.
Macau has annotated versions of the Civil Code, the Penal Code and the Code of Criminal Procedure, and between 2006 and 2008, the first two volumes of the annotated and commented Code of Civil Procedure were published, authored by Cândida da Silva Antunes Pires and Viriato de Lima. The work, however, remained unfinished, recalls the lawyer.
Sá Machado, also one of the authors, defends the importance of the project: "We are always using Portuguese codes, Portuguese notes. We are left with something of our own."
Still talking about the work, which will be published in Portugal by Edições Almedina – after making “some approaches in Macau, informally” -, the lawyer says that “I would like it to be a reference work”.
“Having as many people associated as we do, who have a reputation, who have technical quality, who have a lot to offer, from Macau and Portugal, this is a beautiful project”, he considers.
The president of the new association, who studied at Macau High School in the 1990s and returned to the territory to work in 2017, believes that there is more that can be done locally in terms of legal studies.
“With what would be desired for a territory like Macau, where there is a very dynamic functioning of justice, and now there have been several legislative changes, reforms, this part should be encouraged more”, he argues.
The Portuguese notes that it is still the association's intention to dedicate itself to other types of publications in the area of ​​local law, outside of “the most popular topics”, such as “mediation, arbitration and Greater Bay Area”. “Maybe more traditional, classic themes, or even different themes, but trying to avoid these common places”, he says.
And he gives examples: “Mechanisms related to evidence, issues related to procedural assumptions, but there are also always current topics that are of interest and that can be mixed with these, such as artificial intelligence, civil liability, biomedicine”.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Two local chefs will participate in UN program</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dois-chefs-locais-vao-participar-em-programa-da-onu/</link><description>Macau will be represented by two chefs in a United Nations Food and Agriculture program. Daniel Chio and Safa Rodas are among a dozen chefs from around the world selected to participate in the World Food Forum. The initiative aims to empower young chefs to play a leading role in transforming agri-food systems through culinary practices in their communities.
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
Two local chefs were chosen to participate in a program by the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO), an initiative that aims to educate cooks between the ages of 18 and 35 to become promoters of sustainable practices.
After a selection process, Daniel Chio Ka Kin, 30, from Galaxy, and Safa Rodas, 33, from City of Dreams, received approval from the World Food Forum to participate in the Young Chefs Program. The duo is among just 10 chefs selected worldwide, this being the first time that Macau will be represented.
The program aims to empower young chefs to play a leading role in transforming agri-food systems through culinary practices in their communities.
During the Forum's activities, representatives of the territory will participate in online classes led by experts from FAO and partner organizations on topics such as nutrition, food security and promotion of values.
Those selected will also be paired with mentors from the World Association of Chefs Societies network and will design projects to implement sustainable consumption, strengthening food security and biodiversity in their communities. The chefs will also have the opportunity to present the results of their work at the main event of the World Food Forum, in October this year.
According to a statement from the Tourism Office (DST), the participation of the chefs “will help expand efforts to develop Macau as a Creative City of Gastronomy”, as well as support the training of the next generation of “culinary leaders” in the Macao SAR, ensuring a “more sustainable future for the food industry and related sectors.
On the other hand, highlights the DST, the participation of local chefs will boost the development of Macau “as a place for the aggregation of outstanding international qualified professionals”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Balance between professional and personal life is “key” to boosting birth rates</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/equilibrio-entre-vida-profissional-pessoal-e-chave-para-impulsionar-natalidade/</link><description>Macau should legislate equal parental leave, promoting gender equality and balance between personal life and work, an academic told Lusa, arguing that they are essential factors in reversing the drop in birth rates.
“Work-life balance is a key factor in boosting the fertility rate,” said Lok Cheng, an academic at Macau Polytechnic University who studies public policy.
Lok's research, which compares Macau's parenting policies with those of countries such as Germany, Sweden and the USA, supports this conclusion.
Macau recorded the lowest birth rate in the world in 2024 and the lowest number of births in almost 50 years in 2025, said, at the beginning of the year, the deputy director of Macau's public hospital, Tai Wa Hou, quoted by TDM's Chinese-language channel.
This decline has persisted despite a revised budget approved last year to strengthen social supports, including subsidies for parents with children up to three years old, increases in birth benefits and marriage subsidies.
Macau currently offers 70 days of maternity leave and only five days of paternity leave for workers in the private sector (in the public sector it is 90 days for mothers and five for fathers), recalled the expert: “Less than the 98 days recommended by the International Labor Organization”, she said.
This disparity, argued Lok, reinforces the idea that women have the main responsibility for newborns, which also has an impact on their professional career. “We have tacitly accepted that women have a greater responsibility for caring for newborns, and this is reflected in the workplace,” he continued.
In contrast, the expert, who is also a civil servant, points to European policies. “Sweden has a well-established parental policy and saw an increase in the birth rate in the early 2000s,” he said. “Both Germany and Sweden provide longer maternity leaves and are actively promoting father participation”, he reinforced.
Lok explained that Sweden offers more than 300 days of shared parental leave, with 90 days reserved exclusively for the father.
“Macau currently has no relevant regulations regarding fathers”, noted the academic, suggesting that the region could learn from this model to implement equal parental leave and “promote gender equality in the workplace”.
Such a policy, he said, would help families share childcare and “eliminate gender bias that places women as the main caregivers”. “This prejudice is harmful to women’s professional development”, he assessed.
According to the latest official data from the Macau Women's Database, the average monthly salary of the female population in 2024 was 16,800 patacas, lower than the 19,300 patacas earned by men.
Lok explained that many women are hesitant to have children, fearing increased family duties and career stagnation. But when childcare is shared, “this can increase the desire to have children and reduce the associated costs”.
Such a change would also benefit women professionally, he added. If parental duties were distributed more equally, “companies would be less concerned about gender when hiring women of childbearing age, and women would be able to pursue careers on an equal footing.”
Look acknowledged that it may be a challenge for Macau to adopt a system like Sweden's, but it is necessary to “move forward gradually”.
“The first step is to increase maternity leave to 98 days, in accordance with international standards”, he concluded.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Shao Jiang beats champion in the opening of the Elite League</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/shao-jiang-bate-campeao-na-abertura-da-liga-de-elite/</link><description>The defending champion of the Macau Football Elite League, Must Ipo, was defeated by Shao Jiang, 3-2, in the first round of the competition. In Saturday's game, held late in the afternoon at the Taipa Stadium, Jesus Piñero's men, runners-up in 2025, started the match well and scored after five minutes, through Venezuelan Luis Gonzalez. The opponent, coached by fellow Spaniard Jordi Alonso, tied at 16, through Portuguese Vítor Almeida. Before the break, Shao Jiang returned to the advantage, with a goal from Jeim Gomez, from a penalty, and increased their score at the beginning of the second half, at 50, again by the Colombian striker. Must Ipo pulled one back with 10 minutes left, through Paraguayan substitute Ronaldo Cabrera. In the other challenge of the inaugural round of the I Division, G. Universe, champion of the II Division, beat Benfica 7-2, after having been losing 1-0, with a goal scored in the seventh minute by Niki Torrão. At half-time, the new first division leaders already had the advantage, having scored by Boly Mohamed Keira (at 33) and Peter Johnson Mikimba (39). In the second half, G. Universe consolidated the unexpected triumph, with goals from Boly, Mikimba, San Kou Pak, Ieong Cheang Hon and Hou Cheong Peng. On the 23rd, Ching Fung and Hang Sai will play.</description><pubDate>2026-01-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>STAFF AT HOSPITAL DAS ILHAS WILL INCREASE 27% BY THE END OF THE YEAR</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pessoal-hospital-das-ilhas-aumentara-27-ate-final-ano/</link><description>_cuva



Currently having around 710 employees, Hospital das Ilhas will increase the number to 900 (an increase of around 26.8%) by the end of this year, and the new hires will mainly involve doctors and nurses, said Lei Wai Seng, deputy director of the hospital complex. According to the Chinese-language press, the official also revealed the hospital's goal of reaching 1,200 employees before the end of 2027. Lei Wai Seng highlighted that mainly residents will be hired. Furthermore, he stated that, if the tests to be carried out this week go smoothly, Hospital das Ilhas will operate emergency services from the end of this month. The current operating model of the Ilhas Emergency Station will be maintained identically, with the hospital providing 24-hour outpatient emergency services 24 hours a day, but will not receive ambulances. The official explained that many emergency services at the Macau Medical Center of Peking Union Medical College Hospital are not yet perfected. On the other hand, the most recent and advanced robotic orthopedic system, called Stryker Mako, was introduced for the first time in Macau, in a recent knee arthroplasty operation. Hospital das Ilhas received many appointments, with professionals able to perform two to three operations per week. Furthermore, by January 5th of this year, flu vaccines had been administered to more than 187 thousand people in Macau, a year-on-year increase of 13.7%. The vaccination situation is “satisfactory” among high-risk individuals, noted Lei Hong Mui, head nurse at Areia Preta Health Center.</description><pubDate>2026-01-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Rio de Janeiro expects eight million for Carnival mega show</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/rio-de-janeiro-espera-oito-milhoes-para-mega-espectaculo-carnaval/</link><description>Rio de Janeiro Carnival, Brazil's most emblematic festival, is expected to attract around eight million people this year, including residents and tourists, providing a significant economic boost to the city, according to official sources.

“Last year, Carnival generated 5.7 billion reais [about 919 million euros] for Rio's economy and the expectation is that this number will be even higher” in 2026, said Bernardo Fellows, president of Riotur, the city's tourism company, at a press conference held at City Hall.
The expectation is that the Carnival street parades alone will attract around six million people, who will be in the streets to the rhythm of music, dance and revelry during more than a month of celebration. The street party will feature 460 groups who, from the weekend until February 22nd, will bring joy and color to the neighborhoods and main avenues of Brazil's most emblematic city.
For 2026, the municipality received 803 applications from groups known in Brazil as “blocks”, 118 more than last year. However, for logistical reasons, priority was given to traditional groups, although there was space to include 35 new groups in the parades.
The center of Rio will host the largest number of performances and parades, followed by the city's main tourist area, which includes the world-famous neighborhoods of Copacabana and Ipanema.
The program includes options for different audiences, from children and families to large traditional gatherings that attract more than a million people, such as Cordão da Bola Preta, or the renowned “megablocos” (street parties) organized by famous artists, such as Anitta, which also attract crowds.
According to the City Council, the other two million people expected in the city are those who will watch the majestic parades at the Sambadrome, which take place during Rio Carnival week, from the 13th to the 22nd of February.
 
Special operation with 1,100 agents
The Municipal Secretariat of Public Order (SEOP) and the Municipal Guard of Rio (GM-Rio) set up a special urban planning and patrolling operation. The operation began at the weekend, and includes preventive patrolling and inspection of the main street blocks. Approximately 1,100 agents (including municipal guards and SEOP employees) will use 70 vehicles – including trailers, motorcycles and vehicles – in the actions. The teams will monitor the concentration, the route and also the dispersion of the blocks with urban planning actions and inspection of irregular street commerce (street vendors, stalls and kiosks), with special attention to the seizure of glass bottles that are prohibited and can cause accidents, and coercion of crimes.
Municipal guards will also monitor and inspect traffic to minimize possible impacts on traffic and speed up the opening of roads after the end of the events. There will be inspection of taxis, app and transport cars, in addition to monitoring and assistance in the closure of official blocks.
The Municipal Health Department has prepared a special pre-hospital care scheme in areas with the highest concentration of public with seven medical posts that will support a total of 55 blocks, including the 10 megablocks.
In total, 566 health professionals are on duty throughout the popular festival. All stations will have advanced ambulances to transfer the most serious cases that require hospital support to units in the municipal urgency and emergency network.
Also important, a mega cleaning operation is prepared for before, during and after the passage of all blocks in the city. The cleaning work will be carried out on the main roads along which the blocks parade and in the entire surrounding area, with a workforce of 13,714 workers, 13 thousand containers.
During the period, the company will have 1,507 vehicles, including compactor trucks, satellite trucks, dump trucks, electric carts, large sweepers, mini-sweepers, tractors and 180 blowers.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2026-01-19 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>