<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Operators exempt from paying 150 million due to foreign bettors</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/operadoras-isentas-de-pagar-150-milhoes-devido-apostadores-estrangeiros/</link><description>Gaming concessionaires were exempt from paying approximately 150 million Hong Kong dollars in 2024, taking advantage of the exemption of up to 5% on gaming tax for operators that attract international players. Ip Sio Kai, president of the 2nd Permanent Committee of the Legislative Assembly, also highlighted the fact that operators have increased non-gaming investments by 170 million patacas
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
In 2024, the six gaming concessionaires benefited from a reduction in contributions equivalent to around 150 million Hong Kong dollars, under the Gaming Law, which grants an exemption of up to 5% on gaming tax on revenue generated by international players, revealed Ip Sio Kai, chairman of the 2nd Standing Committee of the Legislative Assembly, citing Government representatives. The amount of revenue corresponded to around three billion Hong Kong dollars.
During a Commission meeting, where the 2024 Budget Execution Report was discussed, Ip Sio Kai also highlighted, cited by the Chinese-language press, that the reductions and exemptions do not refer to taxes, but to contributions other than taxes. As 2024 was the first year of implementation of the respective legal provisions, there is no data for a comparison with the same period in the previous year, explained the deputy.
Furthermore, he indicated that data shows that the six concessionaires increased their investments in government projects unrelated to gaming activity by 170 million patacas, according to the contracts. The Government stressed that this amount does not represent the operators' total investment in non-gaming projects, since the majority of these initiatives other than gambling are carried out by the companies themselves, and are not included in the Government's accounts.
On the other hand, according to Ip Sio Kai, by the end of 2024, the outstanding balance of loans from the Bank Credit Interest Subsidy Plan for Small and Medium Enterprises was around 1.886 billion patacas, with outstanding payments exceeding 200 million.
Ip Sio Kai said that the Government will compile the data and calculate the late payment rate based on the total amount of loans, which exceeds five billion patacas. Ip also revealed that he was concerned about the financial situation of the Retirement and Survival Scheme, highlighting the fact that the number of retirees has increased at a time when fewer contributors are counted, putting pressure on the system.
Furthermore, the deputy pointed out that, with the adjustments in tuition fees and the increase in the number of students, the University of Macau, the Polytechnic University and the University of Tourism all saw an average increase of approximately 30% in revenue in 2024.
According to him, the opinion on this diploma will be signed next week.
 
“Stable” start to the year for casinos
In the first 11 days of January, casino gross revenue amounted to 8.05 billion patacas, which corresponds to a daily average of 731 million, according to the JP Morgan team of analysts. According to the investment bank, the “stable” trend should “alleviate investors’ concerns” about a possible slowdown in revenues, taking into account that, at the end of last year, the daily average was between 620 million and 630 million patacas. For DS Kim, Selina Li and Lindsey Qian, the slowdown in demand at the end of last year was due to the “bad luck of VIP players” and seasonality leading up to the long New Year holiday. The JP Morgan team expects the game's gross revenue to grow at least 15% this month, and 13% in the first quarter, year-on-year. For the overall year 2026, it expects revenues to rise between 5% and 6%, driven by annual growth of 7% to 8% in mass market tables and slots. The sector's profits are expected to increase between 6% and 7%. On the other hand, JP Morgan analysts believe that the VIP segment could fall by 5%, in annual terms, given the “high” basis of comparison last year.
 
Wynn and Galaxy announce salary increases
After Sands was the first to announce salary increases, Wynn and Galaxy followed. According to a press release, Wynn will introduce a salary increase of 2% for employees who receive more than 16,000 patacas and 3.1% to 4.5% for an additional 500 patacas, for those whose salary is equal to or less than 16,000 patacas. The salary increase will come into effect on March 1, covering 98% of the current workforce of 11,803 employees, excluding administration employees. Linda Chen, president, vice-president and executive director of Wynn Macau, Limited, stressed that “the company's success depends on the tireless efforts and dedication of each team member”. In turn, Galaxy Entertainment Group announced that all eligible team members with the position of senior manager and below will receive a salary increase from April 1, with around 98% of employees benefiting. Also in this case, those who receive a monthly salary of 16,000 patacas or less will receive an additional 500 patacas, while those with higher salaries will have an increase of 2%.</description><pubDate>2026-01-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Kennels may have new spaces for animals</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/canis-poderao-ter-novos-espacos-para-animais/</link><description>The Institute for Municipal Affairs intends to optimize the facilities and equipment of the two municipal kennels, including the construction of new animal warehouses. Furthermore, it has plans to improve the interior and exterior areas, with a view to improving the reception environment. Meanwhile, it rules out the possibility of expanding external consultation services for pets
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The construction of new warehouses for pets and the optimization of indoor and outdoor areas for animal activities and additional ventilation and thermal insulation facilities are projects that the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) intends to implement in the future.
In response to a written question from deputy José Pereira Coutinho, the IAM states that it intends to add more spaces in the warehouse area, in the form of prefabricated houses, which it created in 2023 to accommodate abandoned dogs and cats, with the aim of alleviating the prolonged situation of overload of municipal kennels.
On the other hand, says the organization, it continues to promote the “capture, sterilization, open adoption” measures, providing appropriate and free medical assistance and care to abandoned dogs and cats. This support included medical examinations, vaccination against rabies, introduction of a microchip, among other services, as well as making those who “are healthy and friendly available for free adoption, after sterilization”.
The deputy alerted the Government to the need to implement access to basic animal health services at lower prices, as a way of “preventing animal abandonment”. Regarding the matter, the IAM's response, signed by the deputy chairman of the Board of Directors for Municipal Affairs, Mak Kim Meng, states that, “as veterinary clinical care belongs to a personalized service, the service fee is mainly influenced by the species of animal, size, among other factors”. Therefore, he adds, “prices are defined and adjusted by the sector itself”.
At another point in the interview, the member of the Legislative Assembly asked whether the Government has plans to expand the current public shelters by transforming part of the spaces of the former Jockey Club of Macau into an Animal Welfare Center. In its response, the IAM said that “due to the limited resources of the Public Administration, it is not possible to extend the services mentioned”.
The IAM mentions that, under the terms of the “Animal Protection Law” in force, the owner of a pet who cannot raise it can hand it over to the IAM. “From January to November 2025, a total of 30 animals were sent to the Institute, which represents a significant drop of 64.3% compared to the same period in 2024”, he informs.
However, in a “Ou Mun Tin Toi” program, the IAM ruled out the possibility of expanding external consultation services for pets provided in municipal kennels, associating the decision with existing human resources and diagnosis and treatment. As he explained, municipal kennels need to provide medical, sterilization, quarantine and monitoring services for sheltered animals and emerging rescues.
On the same program, a listener pointed out that currently outpatient consultation services for pets are only provided in the morning on weekdays. In this sense, he asked for the extension of opening hours until 5 pm and the increase in vacancies.
According to the IAM, the kennels provide a total of four places for external consultations per day, during the week, and to reduce waiting times, they adopt an appointment mechanism to use the respective services. The organization explained that, if there are vacancies available, they can also be opened without booking.</description><pubDate>2026-01-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Speech and occupational therapy with less waiting time</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/terapia-da-fala-ocupacional-menos-tempo-de-espera/</link><description>The average wait time for the first appointment at the Pediatric Joint Assessment Center is about two weeks. In terms of rehabilitation, children may have to wait between one and four weeks to receive speech or occupational therapy sessions, revealed the Health Services. The organization says it will create a “green lane” so that the waiting time can be “even further reduced” in serious cases and children in urgent need of therapy
 
CATARINA PEREIRA
 
The waiting time for early childhood intervention decreased within a few months. The Health Services (SSM) revealed that the average waiting time for the first consultation at the Pediatric Joint Assessment Center, aimed at children aged six years or less, suspected of having growth and development disorders, is around two weeks, compared to around three weeks in July last year.
“After the evaluation, the waiting mechanism for classifying cases will be adopted, in order to carry out occupational therapy and speech therapy at the Pediatric Rehabilitation Center”, said the agency's deputy director Cheang Seng Ip, in response to a written question from deputy Wong Kit Cheng.
As for the pediatric rehabilitation phase, the average waiting time is one to four weeks. "All very urgent cases do not require waiting time. For urgent cases and general cases, the average waiting time for occupational therapy is around one to four weeks, and for speech therapy it is around two to four weeks", it can be read, with the SSM stressing that "these deadlines represent a significant reduction compared to the 12 to 18 months of waiting before the creation of these centers".
Note that in July last year, the waiting time for occupational therapy was three to six weeks, and for speech therapy it was five to six weeks.
Cheang Seng Ip also indicated that “a green lane” will be created, according to which serious cases and children in urgent need of therapy, upon assessment, “will be directly subjected to rehabilitation and therapy, in order to further reduce the waiting time”. Regarding children with developmental disabilities aged three years or less, referred to the Institute of Social Action (IAS) by the Pediatric Joint Assessment Center, “they will be monitored by one of the four early intervention equipment, according to the results of the assessment”.
Generally speaking, these children will receive physical therapy, occupational therapy or speech therapy services within three weeks, with one session per week. “Currently, vacancies for these services are, in general, sufficient to meet needs”, argues the deputy director of the SSM.
At the same time, it is said that, in response to the social changes in Macau, “the IAS has been analyzing the needs relating to human resources and services of social facilities, reviewing the allocation of personnel in these facilities, as well as developing the respective response measures”. By October 2025, there were 121 speech, occupational and physiotherapy therapists in social facilities supporting the elderly and rehabilitation in Macau, which represented an increase of 28.72% compared to the number recorded in 2020.
“In the future, the IAS will continue to communicate and collaborate with social facilities, in order to constantly improve the distribution of human resources in social services, according to their respective plans and needs”, guarantees Cheang Seng Ip in response to the question.
 
“Indispensable role” of guardians
To ensure that the effectiveness of early intervention can be extended to the family's daily life, “parents play an indispensable role”, highlights the deputy director of the SSM. Therefore, public services cooperate with early intervention institutions to provide caregivers with comprehensive training support and flexible services.
SSM also introduced the “Cloud Platform for Cognitive Language Rehabilitation Training through Artificial Intelligence”, which serves as an effective complement to speech therapy services, so that children can receive training at home, in the company of their parents, increasing their language skills.
In addition to the guidance given to parents in external consultations, the Pediatric Joint Assessment Center also organizes weekly training sessions for parents, given by doctors, therapists, nurses, representatives of the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) and the IAS.
DSEDJ, in turn, annually carries out training activities for guardians under the theme “Global Support for Child Development” with the aim of improving skills in understanding, caring for and guiding children with special educational needs.
In order to support guardians of students in need, “the aforementioned parental actions were further optimized in 2025”, and activities with diverse themes were launched within the scope of “SEN parental education”. Furthermore, in addition to therapy services, the IAS helps early intervention equipment in the development of other services for children with developmental difficulties, namely initial training, auditory rehabilitation, temporary day care, parental counseling, parenting training and parental support.</description><pubDate>2026-01-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Combating fraud excludes interception of communications</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/combate-as-burlas-exclui-interceptacao-de-comunicacoes/</link><description>The Government has ruled out, for now, resorting to message interception technologies, in the context of combating fraud, as it puts “individual rights, such as the secrecy of communications” at risk. The Secretary for Security believes that young and old are better prepared to defend themselves against fraudulent schemes
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
The Secretary for Security considers that “there are no conditions, at the moment, to proactively issue alerts to all users”, within the scope of the Judiciary Police (PJ) mini anti-fraud program. In a response to a written question from Chan Lai Kei, Chan Tsz King's chief of staff, Lam In Sang, explained that the technology needed to intercept fraudulent messages “involves individual rights, such as the secrecy of communications”, which would require “obtaining a broad consensus from society” and “a lot of caution”.
Between January and November 2025, the PJ managed to block 519 phishing sites, through a cooperation mechanism established with local telecommunications operators in 2023. Furthermore, the Anti-Scam Coordination Center “completely integrated the data collected on phishing connections, communicating them to application platforms, domain providers and service providers”, in order to eliminate these connections.
For the Secretary for Security, the elderly and young people are more aware of fraud, and there has been a decrease in the number of cases. From January to October last year, the number of fraud victims aged 60 or over decreased by 11.3%, compared to the same period in 2024.
To this end, the PJ has reinforced awareness-raising activities and sent staff to markets, gardens and tea houses, to “explain to the elderly the ‘modus operandi’ of scams, the measures to prevent them and teach them how to use the mini anti-scam program”.
As part of the “Campus Anti-Scam Vaccine Program”, in the first nine months of 2025, the number of students who failed the “Police, Prosecutor and Court” exercise fell by 42.6%, year-on-year.
On the other hand, in recent years, authorities have noted an increase in investment fraud, affecting “many qualified professionals with extensive life experience and higher education”.
Since “telecommunications fraud and cyber fraud have a cross-border nature”, the PJ maintains proactive communication “with the police services of neighboring regions and other countries, participates in the bilateral or multilateral police collaboration mechanism” and “establishes cooperative direct communication channels with anti-fraud units in Mainland China, HKSAR and Singapore”. In addition, the PJ also joined Interpol's global rapid payment blocking mechanism and takes part in the “Frontier+” cooperation platform.
“The PJ will continue to monitor the evolution of fraud, scientifically and precisely optimizing the work to prevent fraud, helping high-risk groups to face the new methods used in fraud crimes”, assured Lam In Sang.</description><pubDate>2026-01-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Portugal and China play in Guangzhou in the Davis Cup play-offs</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/portugal-china-jogam-em-cantao-play-off-da-taca-davis/</link><description>epaselect epa12140616 Nuno Borges of Portugal hits a backhand during his Men's 2nd round match against Casper Ruud of Norway at the French Open Grand Slam tennis tournament at Roland Garros in Paris, France, 28 May 2025. EPA/YOAN VALAT



Nansha, in Guangzhou, was the venue chosen to host the play-off of Group I of the Davis Cup, in tennis, between Portugal and China. The challenges are scheduled for the weekend of February 6th and 7th. The Portuguese team tries to avoid relegation to Group II. Tiago Pereira is the big news in the team led by Rui Machado

VÍTOR REBELO
 
The teams from Portugal and China will decide in Nansha, in the city of Guangzhou, who will remain in the elite group of the Davis Cup, in tennis, or go down to the lower division. The play-offs will be played on the 6th and 7th of February.
After being eliminated in Group I by Peru (3-1), Rui Machado's men face the Chinese team, who have the home advantage in their favor, in matches that will take place on a fast surface in Guangzhou, a fact that could lead some Portuguese to travel to the capital of the province of Guangdong to support the Portuguese team.
Portugal currently occupies 27th place in the Davis Cup rankings and was seeded third in the draw, while China is 59th on the list.
In case of victory in the first confrontation in history with China, Portugal will return to compete in Group I in September 2026, but, if they lose, they will play in Group II at the same time, in which they have not been since 2015.
In 2025, the Portuguese team also competed in the Group I play-offs, in which they eliminated Monaco, also out, before losing to the Peruvians, thus failing to qualify for the finals.
Just like Portugal, which has Nuno Borges (46th) as the highest ranked tennis player in the rankings, China only has one player in the world's top 100, Yunchaokete Bu, who occupies 74th place in the hierarchy. Furthermore, China's team should feature Aoran Wang, 259th in the world and the Chinese number one, in pairs.
Regarding those called up for the meeting to be held on the Continent, Tiago Pereira is an absolute debutant. The 21-year-old from Algarve joins Nuno Borges, Francisco Cabral, Henrique Rocha and Jaime Faria.
Justifying the bet on the young man who occupies 265th place in the ATP singles ranking and 182nd in doubles, the coach pointed to the quality that the tennis player has shown playing in both variants. “Tiago Pereira has been improving a lot and, in recent months, he has obtained good results not only in singles but also in doubles, which makes him an option for both variants”, he said, quoted by the Portuguese Federation of the sport.
Rui Machado adds that Tiago Pereira is “an excellent element to take to China as one of the youngest players on the team and I believe he will integrate very well”.
After a great season in 2025, where he climbed several levels to finish in 267th place, in a season where he had started in 515th place, the young man from Faro now earned the trust of the national captain for the trip to the Asian continent.
Remember that, in addition to the great rise in singles, Tiago Pereira won three doubles titles in 2025, the last of which was at the Maia Open.
As happened in all qualifiers played since 2022, Portugal will play away again, but this situation does not scare the coach.
“In the last experience, we lost against Peru in conditions that were not favorable, but we have also shown that we are capable of winning as visitors”, remembering that Portugal won on a hard surface in Austria, two years ago, with most of these players in the competition. “I feel that the team will have the opportunity to reach the Group I play-offs in good shape”, he concluded.</description><pubDate>2026-01-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Zone A with shops before the Lunar New Year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/zona-lojas-antes-ano-novo-lunar/</link><description>Commercial activity spaces in economic housing buildings in Zone A will open their doors before Chinese New Year. Some bus routes will also be extended to Zone A before then, and a temporary line will be added during the festivities
 
The Government said that commercial spaces in economic housing buildings in Zone A of the New Landfills will be opened before the Lunar New Year. According to “Ou Mun Tin Toi”, the spaces located on the ground floor of the Tong Chong Building are intended for a restaurant, a bank, a supermarket and a store, while the one in the Tong Kai Building will be used for the operation of a pharmacy.
At the same time, public transport conditions are also being reviewed, taking into account the entry into operation of facilities in Zone A and the successive move of residents to that area. The Executive mentioned that bus lines 101X, 102X and 103 currently run between Zone A, the Peninsula, Vila da Taipa, COTAI and the Hengqin Border Post.
Authorities will try to extend some existing bus routes to Zone A before the Lunar New Year. In addition, route 101XS will be temporarily added during holidays to ease the flow of passengers.
In addition to the Lot B9 health center already being operational, the Government is monitoring other projects to support cultural, recreational and social facilities in the area, which will be successively opened to the public, in order to meet the needs of residents in a more comprehensive way. The formalities relating to the receipt of house keys from buyers of residential units in the Tong Seng, Tong Chong and Tong Kai Buildings are also ongoing.
As of January 9, 2,214 qualified households in the economic housing competition opened in 2019 had already chosen their units. Of these, 1,636 families had completed the formalities to receive house keys, 717 of which were for the Tong Seng Building, 507 for the Tong Kai Building and 412 for the Tong Chong Building.
Furthermore, 46 families had already been notified to complete the formalities and 532 mortgage loan applications were still pending, according to data from the Housing Institute.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2026-01-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Banking experience program broadened students’ vision</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/programa-de-experiencia-bancaria-alargou-visao-dos-estudantes/</link><description>The Macau Monetary Authority (AMCM), in conjunction with the Macau Banks Association, continued the “Program – Banking Experience”, which ran from October until this month. The initiative allowed higher education students interested in entering the banking sector, through direct experience, to learn about the daily work in the “front”, “middle” and “back office” departments of a bank and also to communicate with senior management at the banking units.
The sessions held helped students “to learn, at an early stage, about the practical operations and development guidelines for different functions, broadening their career vision and planning their future professional path”, according to a statement from AMCM.
Upon recommendations from the five local higher education institutions, through the Advisory Board of the Macau Financial Training Institute, the program attracted close to a hundred students. The activity was developed through the combination of various forms of participation, such as sharing experiences, group presentations and observation of professional activities in the workplace.
In the first week, the “Financial Masterclass” took place, during which sector leaders and experienced bankers communicated with participants, sharing career experiences and perspectives on the sector. In the second week, and according to the AMCM note, students gave group presentations on current topics in the modern financial sector, “with a view to deepening their knowledge of the local banking sector, while contributing to strengthening their thinking and expression skills”.
The presentations were evaluated by a panel made up of representatives from AMCM, experienced professionals and representatives from the Financial Training Institute. Participants from the teams that obtained an “Excellent” rating were involved in the “Observation of professional activities in the workplace” session, which took place in a bank, in the third week of the program.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2026-01-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief recognizes FARM’s “core” role in social “stability”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-reconhece-papel-fulcral-da-faom-na-estabilidade-social/</link><description>Safeguarding the legitimate rights and interests of workers in general and maintaining social stability were issues discussed at the Chief Executive's reception of the new leaders of the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau. During the meeting, Sam Hou Fai highlighted the “fundamental” role of FAOM in strengthening the foundations of love for the country and Macau
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The Chief Executive received at the Government headquarters a delegation of the new leaders of the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau (FAOM), with whom he exchanged views on safeguarding the rights and legitimate interests of workers in general, maintaining social stability and encouraging the Macao SAR to reach a new phase of development.
During the meeting, Sam Hou Fai praised the FAOM for having constituted “a pivotal force” in strengthening the foundations of love for the country and for Macau, contributing to the Macao SAR implementing the “one country, two systems” principle “unshakably” and better integrating itself into the context of national development.
On the other hand, the Government official highlighted the “proactive role in uniting and serving workers in general and maintaining the stability of society”, thanking FAOM for its work over the years, within the scope of safeguarding labor rights and interests, for its efforts in “building harmonious labor relations”, and for its “firm support for the governance of the Macao SAR in accordance with the law”.
Sam Hou Fai also recalled that, during his recent visit to Beijing, on an official mission, President Xi Jinping and the Central Government fully recognized the results achieved by the Macao SAR Government in leading and uniting the efforts of different social sectors last year, which counted on the “significant contribution” of FAOM.
The Chief Executive argued that, in the last year, the Government united and led the various social sectors in the in-depth implementation of the spirit of Xi Jinping's “important speeches”, always based on the concept of “Working with an entrepreneurial spirit and moving forward together, persisting on the right path and investing in innovation”, and striving to promote the continuous development of Macau's various industries.
Quoted in a statement by the Social Communication Office, Sam Hou Fai said he hopes that, under the leadership of the new board members, FAOM “will continue to unite workers from all sectors, especially young workers, “comprehensively increasing their professional competence through specialized training, and positively guiding society”.
The meeting was attended by the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, the head of the Office of the Chief Executive, Chan Kak, and the director of Labor Affairs Services, Chan Un Tong, in addition to the directors elected for a new term at FAOM, including the president of the general assembly, Lam Lon Wai, the president of the board, Kong Ioi Fai, the person responsible for the Supervisory Board, Ho Sut Heng, and other members of the list of managing bodies.</description><pubDate>2026-01-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Eight health and wellness stations created</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/criadas-oito-estacoes-de-saude-bem-estar/</link><description>Eight health and wellness stations were launched, which will be expanded in the future to a total of 12, said Health Services (SSM). These spaces, which provide “regular health promotion services”, making resources available in an “easy and immediate” way, are made up of three elements: cultural nutrition, scientific movement and health information.
The first phase of the health and well-being station's activity runs until March 31, from Monday to Friday, except holidays, from 8:00 am to 10:00 am and from 4:30 pm to 6:30 pm. The stations are installed in Dr. Sun Yat Sen Municipal Park, Jardim de Luís de Camões, Leisure Area of ​​Jardim Lok Ieong, Jardim Vasco da Gama, Leisure Area of ​​Alameda da Tranquilidade, Parque Dr. Carlos d’Assumpção, Jardim de S. Francisco and Leisure Area of ​​Avenida Olímpica da Taipa.
All stations are equipped with a banner and workers use pins to facilitate resident identification, the organization explained. The Cultural Institute, Sports Institute and the SSM will also distribute “cultural disseminators”, “gymnastics instructors” and “health promoters”, who can provide the population with guidance and information on cultural activities, personalized sports guidance based on scientific data, free blood pressure measurement, health information and assessment, as well as support in booking appointments at health centers, including disease screening, vaccination and psychological assessment.
At the inauguration ceremony, the director of the SSM, Alvis Lo, stated that the Government has been implementing the national development strategy with priority to health, with the health of the population as the center and promoting the decentralization of resources.
He also recalled that the “Healthy Community” program was launched in March last year. With interdepartmental cooperation, around 200 activities were carried out, through the Community Health Consultation Post and the Community Health Flash Post, with the participation of around 140 thousand residents. “These activities received positive feedback from residents”, he added.
On the other hand, on the sidelines of the ceremony, Alvis Lo reported that, last year, there was an increase in the number of people diagnosed with hypertension and diabetes in Macau.</description><pubDate>2026-01-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM explores planning for new campus</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/upm-explora-planeamento-novo-campus/</link><description>Marcus Im, dean of UPM, and Lam Chan Tong, director of the Faculty of Applied Sciences, visited the Architectural Design and Research Institute of South China University of Technology to learn about the results of the new campus in Hengqin
 
The rector of the Macau Polytechnic University (UPM), Marcus Im, and the director of the Faculty of Applied Sciences, Lam Chan Tong, visited the Architectural Design and Research Institute of the South China University of Technology (UTSC), as part of the construction of the University City in Hengqin and promoting the creation of the UPM campus. According to a note from UPM, “both parties had an in-depth approach to the planning and design of the campus”.
During the meeting, Marcus Im gave a presentation on the progress of UPM's pedagogical operations in the Deep Cooperation Zone. According to the presentation, “at this moment, with the general coordination of the Macao SAR Government, UPM is carrying out the various works in an orderly manner”.
In the first phase, this year, a temporary post will be installed in the Cooperation Zone to begin postgraduate teaching activities; while in the next phase, construction, works are expected to begin in 2027 and be completed in 2030. At that time, the headquarters in Macau and the UPM campus in the Cooperation Zone “will embrace new opportunities for teaching activities in cross-border, international and regional areas”.
In turn, the deputy director and deputy chief architect of the UTSC Architectural Design and Research Institute, Huang Jun, presented the Institute's design and results. As a “prestigious design institution”, led by academic He Jingtang, who has completed landmark projects such as the University of Macau Campus in Hengqin, the Institute “has accumulated extensive experience in integrating cultures, innovating functions and seeking sustainable development”.
Participants shared opinions in response to the transformation of the modern education model and the creation of a space to promote academic exchange, the statement read. With this meeting, “UPM gained a deeper understanding of cutting-edge ideas in campus planning, which will serve as a valuable reference for subsequent work.”
UPM also says that it will “actively raise” resources from all parties and constantly promote the construction of the campus in the Cooperation Zone, “with the aim of cultivating more qualified professionals for the country and for Macau, helping Macau to become a place for aggregating outstanding international qualified professionals”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Huawei certified AI course attracts 30 participants</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/curso-em-ia-certificacao-huawei-atrai-30-participantes/</link><description>There are 30 participants from certified technology companies who are participating in a training co-organized by DSEDT and Huawei focused on Artificial Intelligence
 
The “Practical Training Course in Artificial Intelligence (AI) with Huawei Certification under the Digital Training Program for Macau Technology Companies for Transformation with Artificial Intelligence (AI)” attracted 30 participants from 16 certified technology companies, said the Economic and Technological Development Services Department (DSEDT), co-organizer of the training with Huawei Services Society (Hong Kong) Lda. – Macau Branch.
The director of the government body, Yau Yun Wah, stated that “AI is currently an important driver for upgrading global industry”. In this sense, he said he hopes that the three-day course can train more talents with essential AI skills in Macau, “helping technology companies to accurately seize the golden opportunity of AI training in the industry, integrating new quality productive forces in product development, process optimization and service innovation”.
Yau Yun Wah stressed that the objective is to promote “a deep integration between technological innovation and industrial innovation”. The course will provide professional training in AI technology, covering content such as core AI technology fundamentals, AI business practices and related industry applications. The idea is for participants to “understand in depth” the latest AI technologies and development directions and help local companies use AI to improve business competitiveness.
The training, which ends today, took place at the Economic and Commercial Services Center between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries in the Deep Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin. At the same place, the launching ceremony of the “Hengqin International Talent Training Base in Digital and Intelligent Transformation” was also held.</description><pubDate>2026-01-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>World skate experts come to the “Battle of Champions”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/especialistas-mundiais-de-skate-vem-a-batalha-dos-campeoes/</link><description>Extreme sports, through street skateboarding, return to the territory for the second edition of the “Battle of Champions”. The event that will take place at Studio City, between March 13th and 15th, will feature the world's leading practitioners, including Juni Kang, from South Korea, and Hong Yun, from China. The organization will present a new park, inspired by the cinematic theme of the integrated resort

As principais figuras do skate mundial vão marcar presença na segunda edição da “Batalha dos Campeões”, integrada no Festival Internacional dos Desportos Radicais (FISE), que regressa ao Studio City depois da realização das competições em 2025.
For the three-day exhibitions, between March 13th and 15th, the presence of two renowned experts has already been confirmed, both from the women's sector, the South Korean Juni Kang and the Chinese Hong Yun, who stood out at the FISE stage in Shanghai, in October last year, thus automatically guaranteeing qualification for the Macao SAR event.
The remaining skaters have not yet been announced, which should happen soon, according to a note from Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment.
The track where the event will take place will be installed by Melco. The new park will adopt a new creative direction inspired by the cinematic theme of the integrated resort. “This year's event will take skaters and fans on a nostalgic visual journey through the retro cinematic culture of Macau and Hong Kong, combining neon aesthetics, iconic landmarks and vintage influences into a unique skateboarding experience,” the statement read.
As preparations “accelerate”, excitement “continues to build around what promises to be one of the most memorable action sporting events of 2026”, adds the company.
The street skate festival is organized by FISE, in collaboration with Melco Resorts, Rakuten Sports and Hurricane Group.
Senior Vice President and General Manager of Studio City said, “This high-energy competition will captivate urban sports fans and extreme sports enthusiasts with elite skateboarding and non-stop action.”
Kevin Benning emphasizes that “the road to Macau is open”, believing that the event will allow resort guests to “experience world-class skateboarding”, whilst “discovering the vibrant culture” and unique offerings of Macau and Melco, “contributing to the city’s economic diversification”.
Based on the success of the “intense battles of the last event”, the 1v1 tournament format “is back and ready to offer another round of high-level action, energy and creativity”, concluded the official.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2026-01-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Matteo Ricci's journey remembered on 33 canvases</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/viagem-de-matteo-ricci-recordada-em-33-telas/</link><description>Doctoral students from the University of Macau present 33 paintings that recreate the pilgrimage of the Italian priest Matteo Ricci, who traveled from China to Italy in the 16th century. “No Trilho de Matteo Ricci” is on view at the Rui Cunha Foundation gallery until January 24th

























The Rui Cunha Foundation yesterday presented 33 works from the exhibition “No Trilho de Matteo Ricci”, produced by doctoral students from the Department of Art and Design at the University of Macau (UM). As peças, patentes na Exposição de Arte Colectiva até ao dia 24 de Janeiro, resultaram de uma viagem de estudo de 18 autores, que repetiram o itinerário do padre jesuíta italiano, uma das figuras fundadoras das missões católicas na China, há mais de 400 anos.
The works, in Indian ink and color, portray Ricci's journey, which left Macau towards Italy, passing through cities such as Guangzhou, Zhaoqing, Shaoguan, Rome, Macerata, Genoa, Venice, Milan and Florence, according to a press release. According to Li Ranqing, one of the exhibition's curators, the choice of Macau as the location for the exhibition was based on the fact that the city constitutes a “spiritual anchor” for the artists.
“Each work embodies the hesitation, transformation and repercussion of experience.” The paintings on display “retain a large part of the ‘in situ temperature’”, can be read in the press release. “The wind-blown cracks in the Xuan rice paper and the street dust on the edges of the pastel paintings are not imperfections, but natural extensions of the Chinese painting philosophy of ‘observing things through inner vision,’” explains the curator.
The use of brush and ink of traditional Chinese painting as a “historical pen” served to complete a “transtemporal search to the roots”, explains Li. “As a curator, I imagine this project as a practical fieldwork of contemporary Chinese painting, woven around the 400-year-old route of cultural exchange”.
“Just as Matteo Ricci introduced Western knowledge to China, through Chinese translation centuries ago, we used the language of Chinese painting to try to transform this trajectory through mountains and seas, into a continuous dialogue between civilizations”, says the curator. “When you see the sunset over ancient Rome in watercolors and the corner of an alley in Lingnan in pastels, you are faced not just with landscapes, but with a soft touch between two civilizations created through art”, he describes.
With free entry, the exhibition, organized by UM's Center for Chinese History and Culture, was curated by artists Li Ranqing and Lei Meihang. The work was supervised by the Center's director and teacher Zhang Yan, from the city of Zhaoqing, one of the places visited by the Italian missionary at the end of the 16th century.
The project was supported by the Guangdong Provincial Center for International Cultural Exchange and the Guangdong Artists Association, as well as the participation of the China Artists Association of the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area Artists Alliance and the Greater Bay Area Landscape Painting Art Committee.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2026-01-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Pessoa's unpublished works and new voices mark the bets of the Penguin editions for 2026</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/ineditos-de-pessoa-novas-vozes-marcam-apostas-das-edicoes-penguin-para-2026/</link><description>Renowned international authors making their debut in Portugal, unpublished texts by Fernando Pessoa and Roberto Bolaño, and new books by Afonso Cruz, José Gardeazabal and Patrícia Reis are some of the new features of the Penguin group for the first half of 2026.
By June this year, Penguin Random House Portugal will launch almost 400 books, in what is a big commitment by the publisher to use “beauty against the barbarism” of the times, according to Clara Capitão, director of the editorial group, who presented the news, at Casa do Comum, in Lisbon.
Penguin Clássicos brings one of the biggest news, which is the publication of “A History of Portuguese Literature”, by Fernando Pessoa, with editing, organization and introduction by Nuno Ribeiro, who publishes here unpublished texts, among the many that are still to be discovered in the poet's famous vault of manuscripts. Of the various projects that occupied him, Fernando Pessoa had the idea of ​​writing a history of Portuguese literature, centered on the main Portuguese-speaking authors of the last five centuries, whose texts now take shape in this collection.
Another of the books highlighted at Alfaguara is entitled “Everything in nature just continues”, by Chinese writer Yiyun Li, who debuts in Portugal, has lived in the USA for decades, writes in English and does not allow her books to be published in China. A widely awarded author, she was a finalist for the National Book Award with this memoir centered on her survival of the suicide of her two children (one aged 16 and the other aged 19) seven years apart, written from that dark place into which she plunged.
“The summer in which my mother had green eyes” is another of the debuts under the same banner, in this case by the Romanian-speaking Moldovan writer Tatiana Tibuleac, a novel that won the 2019 Cálamo Prize in Spain, which has as its protagonist a painter in creative block who the psychiatrist advises to remember the last summer he spent with his mother, still as a child, and to relive the emotions that dominated that distant time.
Also debuting at Alfaguara will be the Italian author Maria Grazia Calandrone, with the novel “Written with blood in the water” about the story of her origin, which she only discovered in adulthood: In Rome in the 1960s, a baby is abandoned in a garden and the parents commit suicide together. That baby was the author and this is the story of her roots, which she investigated using her journalistic flair.
Alfaguara will also publish “Audição”, a novel shortlisted for the Booker Prize, by Katie Kitamura, a writer already published in Portugal but now debuting in the Penguin catalogue, as well as new books by Lara Moreno, Alba de Céspedes, Jamaica Kincaid and Leila Slimani – from the latter, a compilation of literary, social and political reflections, written over time and started after the attack on the Bataclan Theater in 2015.
Patrícia Reis returns to romance, with “The place of uncertainty”, making her debut at Companhia das Letras with this story about faith and the human abyss.
Bruna Dantas Lobato is another new author in Portugal who has now reached the national book market with “Blue Hours”, an autobiographical work about a young Brazilian woman who moves to the USA to study literature and maintains a connection with her mother, who stayed in Rio Grande do Sul, through computer conversations, deceiving herself from a distance.
“Blue Hours” is her first novel and was originally written in English and published in the USA – where it was critically acclaimed – and only later translated into Portuguese and published in Brazil, as Bruna Dantas Lobato is a translator, having won the National Book Award for the English translation of “A Palavra Que Resta”, by Stênio Gardel.
Another Brazilian author making her debut in the Companhia das Letras catalog is Vera Iaconelli, psychoanalyst and columnist for the newspaper Folha de São Paulo, who publishes “Análise – Notas do divã”, in which she psychoanalyzes herself, delving into her complex family history.
Still under the new seal in Portugal, “Apparent Death”, Carolina Fulcher's debut novel, about loneliness, destiny and love, and “Esse place”, by Galician writer Berta Dávila, on the theme of motherhood, will be published.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>