<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Sustained economic growth “dependent on increased productivity”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/crescimento-economico-sustentado-dependente-aumento-da-produtividade/</link><description>Structural policies and reforms that support the growth of long -term productivity - this is Isabel W.T. Choy of the monetary authority's investigation and statistics department to respond to population aging in the territory, which, warns, is a challenge and could limit the economic growth of masters. With the prospects for decreasing the active population in the coming years, the labor market will be affected by decreasing productivity. Sustained economic development will be “dependent on increased productivity”, points out
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Population aging could be an obstacle to the economic growth of Macao, as it will impact the productivity of the labor market, warns Isabel W.T. Choy, from the Macao Monetary Authority Research and Statistics Department (AMCM). “A fundamental challenge for Macao medium -term growth prospects is the aging of the population, due to the low birth rate and increased life expectancy. This demographic trend is likely to slow down the active population growth rate, ”says the economist in a study entitled“ Estimation of Potential Output and Output Gap of Macao ”.
According to the projections of the population of Macau 2022-2041, which is based on the results of the latest censuses, carried out in 2021, the rate of labor participation should have a decreasing trend, decreasing 2.0 and 5, 7 percentage points (men and women, respectively) in 2041 compared to 2021. “Active population growth should slow down,” says Isabel W.T. Choy, pointing out that a slowdown was already registered after 2010.
"Even from the principle that the growth in labor productivity will remain stable, the prospects for growth in the medium term of Macao in the next decade will be inevitably limited by the tendency to decrease the active population's growth rate," He argues, adding: "The weak growth of labor will affect the growth of per capita GDP in the future."
In Isabel W.T. Choy, for a “sustained growth” in the territory, is necessary to explore “increasingly productive” ways to use “production factors”. According to it, "the main source of medium -term sustained economic growth will necessarily provide for increased productivity."
“Although it is not as important as the growth of labor productivity, employment increases that it has contributed remarkably to the development of Macao over the last three decades. In prospective terms, the aging of the population will slow down the growth of labor, thus limiting the potential for economic growth from employment, ”he notes.
According to the projections of the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services, for the next twenty years, it is expected that the proportion of elderly (65 years or older) over the total population continues to rise, from 12.2% in 2021 to 20.9% in 2041. The numbers point to the oldest layer of the population to increase from 83,200 people to 164,400 in 2041, at an average annual growth rate of 3.5% - “considerably higher” than the population Total (0.7%).
The proportion of the adult population in relation to the total will decrease. The number of adults (15-64 years) will increase, but the growth of the adult population (+7.7%) will be “much lower” to that of the elderly population (+97.6%), as “it is dragged by the fall Continuous of the young population (under 14 years or equal to or equal), which in the future will expand the adult population. ” The proportion of the adult population will continually decrease, and it is foreseen to descend from 73.3% (500,600) by 2021 to 68.6% (539,000) by 2041. In this sense, the total dependence index will be increased, so “ sustaining seniors will become a greater weight. ”
To counteract the challenges imposed by demographic changes, Isabel W.T. Choy considers that "medium -term growth strategies should be oriented to stimulate greater productivity growth." In this sense, political priority should be given to “reaching resources for more productive uses, including relocation within each sector and between sectors”.
“In addition, the current tendency of digitization in Macao would facilitate these relocations. These structural reforms would be well aligned with the strategic objective of diversification of Macao's economy in order to release new sources of productivity growth and support Macau's growth in the medium and long term, ”he may read.
Stressing that the analysis he has revealed revealed “a more pronounced volatility of production in the last decade, even excluding the pandemic period”, the author adds that Macau, being an open economy, “is highly susceptible to external shocks, which emphasizes the importance of the budget reserve to safeguard macroeconomic stability ”. "Budgetary reserves allow you to resist the amplification of shocks and facilitate quick disbursement for emergency and recovery efforts in the sequence of serious shocks," he says.
“The challenges placed by population aging require structural reforms to support long -term productivity growth. In particular, reform priorities should be aligned with Macao's strategic objectives established in the proper diversification plan of the Mashed economy (2024-2028). In the future, progressive political measures are needed to trigger a new growth in productivity and to achieve a more balanced and high quality growth trajectory, ”he argues. In short, "sustained economic growth will depend on increased productivity."
 
“Capacity” to recover from negative deviations
In his analysis, the economist states that Macao "recorded five episodes of negative production deviations in the last three decades, the most serious of which it occurred during the Covid-19 pandemic." The longest, which lasted six years, began in the late 1990s, during the Asian financial crisis. However, "in terms of magnitude, the economy recorded its lowest point during the Covid-19 pandemic between 2020 and 2022, representing the worst negative deviation during the sample period."
Three other episodes of negative production deviations were also recorded, but which were “eliminated” within two years, as the economy recovered and effective production levels returned to its potential.
On the other hand, the economy recorded the largest positive deviations between 2013 and 2014, followed by 2017-2019. “The economy dived abruptly in the negative zone with the start of the pandemic in 2020. In terms of duration, the longest positive hiatus lasted four years in 2010-2014,” he says.
With regard to economic recovery after pandemic, the results suggest that “the economy has been robustly recovering from the great negative deviations during the crisis, and it is estimated that production in 2023 returned to its pre-standard tendency, effectively closing the tendency. production gap ”.
Given the observed results, Isabel W.T. Choy points out that "in terms of duration, most negative deviations were eliminated within two to three years in Macao, which partly reflects the capacity of the economy to gradually return to its potential level."</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Animal species and plants proliferate in ecological zones</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/especies-de-animais-plantas-proliferam-nas-zonas-ecologicas/</link><description>Animal species and plants in the ecological zones of Cotai continue to grow. Last year, 2,105 types were counted, including algae, mosses, fetuses, zooplankton, insects, fish, mammals, among others. DSPA stresses that the “richness of food resources” in that area of ​​the territory has brought to the place 198 species of birds to feed or rest there
 
Cotai ecological areas have attracted new visitors, judging by increasing the number of animals and plants. Currently, ecological zones I and II, whose total area extends by about 55 hectares, already gather more than two thousand species. The data released by the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) reveal that by the end of 2024 the ecological zones already gathered 2,105 types of animals and plants.
In concrete and regarding plants, by the end of last year, ecological areas had a total of 773 types, including 327 algae species, four moss, 22 fetuses, 11 gymnosperms and 413 angiosperms. Looking at the statistics of the previous year, we can see that new species of algae and angiosperms were found, since in 2023 had been accounted for 319 and 406, respectively.
As regards animals, 1,328 species were recorded, including 143 of zooplankton, 176 of benthic animals and 654 of insects. There are also 118 fish species, five amphibians, 22 reptiles and 12 mammals. In this case, new types of insects and fish were found, compared to the previous year, when 652 and 116 species were known, respectively.
"The richness of food resources available there has led 198 bird species to choose the ecological zones as a resting place or to feed, among which the black-barreter (Platalea Minor), one, is included," ave rara integrada na Lista Vermelha da União Internacional para a Conservação da Natureza e dos Recursos Naturais (IUCN), salienta a DSPA, na sua página electrónica.
Ecological Zones I and II of the Cotai were completed at the end of 2003. In the middle of the following year, the Macao authorities hired a consulting company to ensure the management and maintenance of these environmental spaces, which is systematically collecting it data on data The bents, plants, birds, water quality and the surrounding environment.
DSPA asserts that "it has been striving to optimize the ecological environment of ecological zones, in order to provide a habitat and an environment of ideal food for migratory birds that come to winter in Macao." In this sense, and taking into account opinions collected from academic institutions, annual works have been developed on the banks of the ecological zone I outside the time of migration of birds.
These works involve, for example, “the dredging of channel's slams, the removal of herbs and reeds on the lake banks, the control of reed growth and the widening of the margin area, as well as the improvement of the environment of boundary birds, Bentonic animals and fish ”, underline environmental protection services, adding that, in recent years, the number of migratory birds that have been winter in the territory has kept a“ stable level ”.
Located Northeast of the Lotus Flor Bridge, the Ecological Zone I, which occupies 15 hectares, is an area of ​​conditionally open management. Two bird observatories were installed in the south dike of this zone, where aquatic shrubs, sugarcane fields and trees can be found, as well as water channels that connect the Shizimen channel.
The open management zone II is located on the west coast of Cotai, with the south of Coloane's WWTP and bordering the north with the Broadway Macau complex. It covers an area of ​​about 40 hectares, where three artificial islands and a slope for visits were built in the mudflasses, being rich in fauna and flora of the mangal, namely gray mangrove, mangrove “kandalia obovata”, “aegiceras corniculatum”, “acanthus ilicifolius ”, called-Maré and lodaded jumping.
 
Vao Hoi Ieong is again subdirector of DSPA
The Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, appointed, in Service Commission, Vai Hoi Ieong for the position of Deputy Director of the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA). The information, which was published yesterday in an Official Report, indicates that the appointment has effects from February 17 and for a period of one year. Vai Hoi Ieong had already held the same position, between June 2009 and June 2015, and was even director of the same organism (June 2015 to March 2016), and also went through the weather and geophysical services, so far as date . Degree in Chemical Engineering (University of Calgary, Canada), and Master in Environmental Engineering (Hong Kong Polytechnic University), Vai Hoi Ieong, who began his career in the civil service in 1999, also has a master's degree in Public Administration (National Institute China's administration).
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau won 5,881 tnr in a year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-ganhou-5-881-tnr-num-ano/</link><description>Within a year, the number of TNR in Macao grew 5,881 to a total of 182,542. If we look at the end of 2019, when the TNR peak was reached, with 196,538, the numbers represent about 93% of the labor then accounted for
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Macao had, at the end of last year, with 182,542 non -resident workers (TNR), an increase of 5,881 compared to the end of 2023, when 176,661 were counted, equivalent to an annual rise of 3.32%, show the data from the Public Security Police Corps, released by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL). If we look at the end of 2019, when the TNR peak was reached, a total of 196,538, the numbers are still below, but already represent about 93% of the labor then accounted for.
Compared to January 2023, when authorities ended the covid zero policy, there was an increase of 30,664 workers. This month, the labor coming from abroad, including from mainland China, had fallen to less than 151,878 TNR, the lowest number since April 2014.
Returning last year, statistics point out that a large slice of TNR (66%) originates from the interior of China, totaling 121.161, followed by the Philippines (30,912 or about 17% of the total), Vietnam (8,261 TNR ), Indonesia (7,418), Myanmar (4,314), Nepal (3,776) and Hong Kong (2,228).
The sector of hotels, restaurants and the like accounted for 53,948 TNR at the end of last year, representing 29.55% of the total imported labor. Used, the number did not reach the volume of 2019, when there were 54,749 TNR in this sector. In the end of 2023, hotels, restaurants and the like hired another 4,561 TNR. This had been the area most affected by loss of labor in the Covid-19 years, during which more than 17,600 TNR have been dismissed since the end of the pre-pound year.
The second sector that hired the most was that of families with maids, which won 1,678 TNR, rising to a total of 27,435 (15% of imported labor). For the area of ​​cultural and recreational activities, another 1,418 workers were imported, with the sector to finish the year with 11,372 TNR. This area includes casinos, and in this case there was an increase of 913 workers to 4,446.
 
Construction lost more than 4,500 tnr
On the other hand, the construction sector lost, within a year, more than four thousand TNR. At the end of 2024, Macao had 25,641 workers from abroad in the construction area, less 4,568 than a year earlier. Still, the sector is third in terms of the “weight” of imported labor, representing 14% of the total.
In fourth place is the area of ​​real estate activities and services provided to companies, representing 13% of total TNR, with 23,647 workers. Also in this case, there were 1,023 at the end of 2023. In the opposite direction, the thick and retail trade-which equals 12% of the universe of labor from abroad-raised 725, with counting on counting on 21,279.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Bank exploration results decreased by 21% last year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/resultados-de-exploracao-dos-bancos-diminuiram-21-ano-passado/</link><description>Macao banks operational profits fell more than one fifth by 2024 to four billion patacas, marking the fourth consecutive homologous descent and the lowest value since 2010. Breaking break has derived essentially from the 18.3% reduction on margin of fees
 
The Macao bank sector ended the 2024 accounts with total operational profits of 4.01 billion patacas, which has been the lowest since 2010 and represents a decrease of 21.3% compared to the 5.09 billion accounted for in 2023. According to the statistical data released by the Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM), the results of bank exploration thus suffered the fourth consecutive annual break, contrary to 12 years of growth, including 10 successive records from 2011.
The decrease in profits by 2024 was essentially due to a drop of 18.3%to 16.1 billion patacas on the interest margin, the difference between loan revenues and deposit expenses. This after the AMCM approved three descents of the main reference interest rate in the last three months of 2024, the last of which a 0.25 percentage points, introduced on December 19, following the US Federal Reserve.
On the other hand, after several months up, the bank sector operating costs eventually dropped 6.8% in the general calculation of 2024 to 21.41 billion patacas. Provisions for bank credit impairment, which represented 45.6% of operating costs, decreased 16.3% to 9.76 billion.
The loans, the main source of revenue from the worldwide banking, decreased 7.2% compared to the end of December 2023, settling at 1.01 billion of patacas. On the contrary, deposits with Macau banks increased 4%to 1.27 billion of patacas in late 2024.
As reported yesterday the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the “non-productive” credit (NPL, in the English acronym) in local banking institutions was 56.07 billion patacas at the end of last year, illustrating an annual increase of 30, 3% or 13.04 billion and reaching a new record in the territory, according to AMCM data. The NPL, which includes loans with delays of over 90 days, grew more than 20 times or 53.30 billion compared to the end of 2019, the pre-pound year, and recorded increases in 21 of the last 22 months.
Overdue loans accounted for 5.5% of Macao banks loans at the end of 2024, plus 1.6 percentage points within one year, and the percentage rises to 6.9% if we consider credit to institutions or individuals only to consider credit to credit or individuals non-residents. The European Banking Authority, the EU regulatory agency, for example, considers that banks with at least 5% of bad loans have “high exposure” at risk and should establish a strategy to solve the problem.
Still, the NPL ratio in Macao is far from the 25.3% record reached in mid -2001, in the world's economic crisis caused by the outbreak of the speculative bubble of companies linked to the internet.
In the first “Monetary and Financial Stability Review” report of 2025, AMCM's Department of Studies and Statistics stressed that “Macau's financial system has shown continuous resilience, supported by solid capital and liquidity positions”. "Capitalization and the liquidity position of the bank sector remains solid, providing robust support to financial stability and sufficient resources to respond to future demand for credit," he says, recognizing, on the other hand, that "uncertainties about rhythm FROM FOMC FUCKING CUTS FOMC [US Federal Reserve Federal Market Committee] require vigilant credit risk management by Macao banks and an agile response to changes in macrofinance conditions. ”
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump “No haste” to talk to XI</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/trump-sem-pressa-para-falar-xi/</link><description>ERIE, Pennsylvania - July 29: Form U.S. President Donald Trump Enters Erie insurance Arena for a Political Rally While Campaigning for the Gop Nomination in the 2024 Election on July 29, 2023 in Erie, Pennsylvania. (Photo by Jeff Swensen/Getty Images)



O Presidente dos EUA garantiu que não tem pressa em falar com o seu homólogo chinês, Xi Jinping, no primeiro dia da guerra comercial entre os dois pesos pesados da economia mundial. “I will talk to him when the height comes. I'm in no hurry, ”said Donald Trump in the White House.
Trump also asserted that he is not concerned about China's tariffs on certain US imports from February 10, after the entry into force of additional 10% taxes by Washington on Chinese products.
“Let's go out very well against China and against everyone else. At this time, they are taking advantage of the Biden government as we have never seen before, ”he said in statements in the Oval Hall. Accusing China of using US money "to strengthen his army," Trump criticized Biden for allowing him to happen.
"The good news is that we are very well," he insisted, emphasizing that the US is "again respected as a nation, perhaps at a level that people have not seen for many, many decades."
Since midnight yesterday an additional 10% rate on its exports to the US, Beijing retaliated, announced on Tuesday the application of 15% rates on coal and liquefied natural gas (LNG) rates on Tuesday. and 10% of oil and agricultural equipment from the US. "The unilateral imposition of customs rights by the US seriously violates the rules of the World Trade Organization," the Chinese Ministry of Finance said in a statement announced the imposition of retaliatory tariffs.
Beijing reiterated yesterday that resolutely opposed to increasing customs imposed by the US and appealed to dialogue. "What we need now is not a unilateral increase in rates, but a dialogue and discussions based on mutual respect," Lin Jian, spokesman for the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, told a press conference.
"The measures taken by China are a necessary action to defend their rights and legitimate interests," he added.
Asked about a possible future conversation between the two leaders, Chinese diplomacy spokesman did not give details.
Washington's decision against China contrasts with the situations of Mexico and Canada, in which both nations obtained a postponement from the imposition of 25% per month, after reaching separated agreements with Trump.
 
Rubio promises to support Costa Rica before Chinese "blackmail"
In turn, the US Secretary of State offered a "frank support" from the US to Costa Rica, before what he called China's "blackmail" on his first trip abroad since his inauguration. "Under the president [Donald] Trump, we have a foreign policy where we support our allies," Marco Rubio said at a press conference in San José, alongside Costa Rica President Rodrigo Chaves.
A country “deserves support” when it is confronted “with non -secure companies that are supported by governments such as China, who like to threaten, sabotage and use economic coercion,” he added.
Costa Rica effectively banned Chinese giant Huawei from submitting proposals to its fifth -generation (5G) network in 2023, due to Beijing's refusal to sign an international cybercrime agreement.
“Dealing with companies like this has its consequences: blackmail, threats, attempts to infiltrate government agencies. You have been very firm and we will continue to support them in this area, cybersecurity, a problem we also face in the US, ”Rubio added, announcing the continuation of financial aid to Costa Rica.
 
US postal service suspends packages from China and Hong Kong
The US Postal Service (USPS) has announced that it will “temporarily” to accept orders from China and Hong Kong “to New Order” at a time when the Washington and Beijing trade war intensifies. USPS clarified that the measure does not affect “the flow of cards and normal mail”, but only orders for low value products that previously benefited from exemption from rates. An order from Donald Trump has eliminated an exemption for products of less than $ 800, purchased directly by consumers and sent through postal service. The measure can block or delay orders made through Chinese Electronic Trade Platforms Shein and Temu, but also from the American Amazon. Although the MSAR was not targeted by USPS, the CTT of Macao yesterday suspended the sending of small packages and orders by surface mail to the US, as well as the Express Commodities Service (EMS), but in this case only for the state from Illinois. The remaining US postal services "for documents, letters, air mail (including small packages, orders and EMS) continue to work normally."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Record of suspicious transactions attributed to the resuming in casinos</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/recorde-de-transaccoes-suspeitas-atribuido-a-retoma-nos-casinos/</link><description>The number of suspicious transactions recorded in Macao casinos reached a new record by 2024 due to the recovery of the economy and tourism, the Financial Information Office (GIF) told Lusa.
According to data released in January by the GIF, the six casino operators in Macao submitted, totaling 3,837 suspicious transactions of capital bleaching or terrorism financing in 2024, 11.8% more than the previous year. Game operators were thus responsible for 73.2% of total reports submitted over the past year.
"This increase was mainly due to economic recovery and the significant increase in the number of visitors arrivals in 2024," said the GIF in a response to Lusa questions.
The cabinet also mentioned the "continuous investment of resources from entities complaining in the detection of suspicious transactions."
In 2024, the game sector in Macau raised a total of 226.8 billion patacas in gross revenues, more 23.9% than the previous year. The territory last year received 34.9 million visitors, 23.8% more than in 2023.
Casinos denounced transactions involved questions such as “conversion of chips without or with minimal play activities, the conversion of tokens in the name of third parties [or] the exchange of money/cash conversion,” added the GIF.
In 2023, almost 1,300 cases of suspicious transactions involved file exchange without or with reduced game activity, appearing as the “most common feature” of the processes analyzed by the GIF and overcoming the situations of “irregular upstream survey”, according to the annual report of the cabinet. The money exchange and frequent use of ATM boxes for deposit and cash operations have also generated concerns this year.
In the general 2024 calculation, the Financial Information Office received 5,245 reports on suspicious transactions, a number that translates an annual climb of 13.7% and is the highest since the beginning of the records in 2006. In addition to casinos, reports of Financial institutions and insurance companies rose 23.7% to 1,097 (20.9% of the total) and the stakes made by “other institutions” grew about 5.1% to 311 (5.9% of the total) in the space of A year.
Under the law, the referenced sectors, such as casinos, are required to communicate to the authorities any transaction equal to or greater than 500 thousand patacas.
Of the total of 5,245 appearances, the GIF last year 142 suspicious transactions to the prosecutor for investigation, 26 more than in 2023. Asked by Lusa about the reasons that led to discarding the overwhelming majority of suspicious transactions, the GIF did not do any comment.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese costumes to try at a new year event at the hostel</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/trajes-chineses-para-experimentar-em-evento-de-ano-novo-albergue/</link><description>CAC - Circle of Culture Friends and the SCM hostel will mark the Chinese New Year with the Lunares lanterns festival. The event scheduled for the next 12th includes a 16 -piece “Cheongsam” exhibition, traditional Chinese clothing, as well as an accessory workshop and other celebration activities of the year of the serpent



















Victor Rebelo
 
The first night of the full moon of the year, which takes place on the 15th day of the first month of the lunar calendar and marks the beginning of a new cycle and the rebirth of nature, will motivate the holding of a party that will take place in the outer space of the hostel of Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macao, on February 12, Wednesday, between 18:30 and 21h00.
Since people celebrate this occasion as part of the new year's festivities, the Culture Circle (CAC) promotes the “Chinese New Year's celebration”, which also serves to mark the Lunares lanterns festival in the scenery Parish of St. Lazarus. The festivity will have as its theme the “serpent”, continuing tradition with a selection of festive snacks and activities for the public.
The event integrates “an inheritance of seductive beauty: Cheongsam Chinese exhibition”, which consists of the display of traditional Chinese, male and female clothing. It is a costume that dresses by the body and, as such, should be done by measure.
The 16-piece Cheongsam show of different periods will include classic handmade models by Master Yan Ka-Man, as well as innovative pieces reinterpreted through modern design. According to CAC, the exhibition presents nostalgic scenes and offers participants the opportunity to try traditional shirts for photographic opportunities.
In order to “inherit and promote traditional Chinese culture”, CAC collaborates with the Hong Kong Design Institute to host the exhibition “an inheritance of seductive beauty: Chinese Cheongsam exhibition”.
This costume show will be evident to the public until March 16 this year, opened every day from 12h00 to 20h00, and on Monday from 15h00 to 20h00 at Gallery A2 of the Albergue.
The commemorative activities program also includes a “DIY FROG Button accessory workshop”, which will take place from 15h00 to 20h00, with a total of eight sessions, each lasting half an hour. The workshop will show the ability to create frog buttons accessories, adding brackets for earrings, necklaces or rings in the double binding. Participation in the workshop is free and works in order of arrival.
In addition, the CAC invited the famous Macau Caligraph, Master Choi Chuen Heng, to attend the event, where he will publicize his handwriting, conveying to citizens since New Year's Eve votes. At the same time, it will present the “Chinese Calligraphy Art Exhibition 2025” in order to promote traditional Chinese culture and celebrate the Moon Festival.
This exhibition, which enhances the essence of Chinese culture and the exquisite art of handwriting, can be visited until February 23, at Pavilion D1, at the same times as the clothing exhibition.
The organization of all events is sponsored by the Macau Foundation and the institutional support of Albergue, the Hong Kong Design Institute and its fashion file, as well as the Tai Fung Tong Art House.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Military Club welcomes Guzheng and Erhu Repair</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/clube-militar-acolhe-concerto-de-guzheng-ehru/</link><description>The traditional Chinese instruments Guzheng and Ehru will be focused on another session of the musical journeys, promoted by the Military Club. Next Sunday's concert will feature the action of artists Pui Ian Chan and Fang Teng
 
A duo of artists from Macao will act in another edition of the Military Club's “Musical Days”, at a concert scheduled for next Sunday, February 9, at 17:00, called “Elegance in Harmonia”. Pui Ian Chan and Fang Teng will play Guzheng and Erhu, traditional Chinese instruments originating from the Tang Dynasty.
They will be heard in this show, to be held in the Stanley Ho room of the Military Club, excerpts from various composers, such as Deng Yuhsian, Liu Tiahua, Lou Shuhua, He Zhanhao and Huang Haihuai.
Pui Ian Chan studied Guzheng at the Macao Conservatory of Music and was awarded the “Elite Performative Arts Award” twice. In 2022, he ranked first among foreign students in the masters admission exam at the Central Music Conservatory.
Its awards also include first place in the professional youth group of the International Arts Festival Guzheng “Liangjiang Cup”, 12th World Shangoi Youth Arts Festival, China-Japan Youth Arts Festival and the 8th exhibition selection. National Youth Instrumental Instrumental Education achievements (WENHUA Cup). He was a jury in several art contests for youth and cultural events.
In 2021, he played at the Beijing National Stadium at a large -scale event to celebrate the 100th anniversary of the Communist Party of China and, in 2024, held another Guzheng recital at the Cultural Center, which had great media coverage. In the same year, he was invited to act again on the 25th anniversary of the MSar, at President Xi Jinping's welcome banquet.
Fang Teng was admitted in 2015 at the Central Music Conservatory (CCOM), where he studied with Professor Tian Zaili, renowned Erhuista and Pedagogue. It has a bachelor's degree and a master's degree in execution of ERHU, having been a professor of this instrument at the CCom Faculty of Continuous Education and a guest musician of the Macao Chinese Orchestra. He is currently a member of the Hou Kong Secondary School faculty.
Recognized for his talent, Fang accumulated several awards, highlighting the gold medals at the 31st Binhai Sound Music Festival and the 6th International National Instrumental Music Contest of Beijing “Dunhuang Cup”. In addition, he won the special gold medal in the first vocal and instrumental music contest for young people from Zhuhai-Hong Kong-Macau.
The musician was invited by the Chinese orchestra of Macao to act in various national and international digressions, including Portugal, Bahrain and some cities in China. In July 2018, he participated at the Atlantic Mimo Music Festival in Portugal, where he acted as an Erhu soloist at Chang Hong concert.
Fang Teng is currently dedicated to the promotion of the teaching of traditional Chinese music in Macao and, over the years, has taught Erhu to thousands of students in Hou Kong Secondary School.
Tickets for the concert cost 120 patacas, with cocktail included. Anyone who also wants to participate at dinner after the concert at the Military Club restaurant will have to shell out 330 patacas.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Creative challenged to participate in Hong Kong Fair</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/criativos-desafiados-participar-em-feira-de-hong-kong/</link><description>The Cultural Institute (IC) will organize the participation of the Macao Cultural and Creative Industries sector at the Hong Kong International Licensing Fair, which will take place in late April. The IC will install a “Macao Creative Pavilion” to publicize original local intellectual (PI) brands and promote industry cooperation and development. Registration for participation in the event will take place until February 19. All interested parties and companies dedicated to the Intellectual Property Industry (PI) in Macau are invited to register. IC will select participants based on criteria such as the content inherent in PI licenses, uniqueness, market potential and target audience base, multimedia and multicultural adaptability, as well as the cultural relevance of their intellectual property content. This fair at Raehk is one of the leading licensing events in Asia, providing a unique platform to connect possessors of global licenses, brands, licensing agents and traders. Thus, IC encourages industry professionals to take advantage of the “Macao Creative Pavilion” to promote original territory intellectual property licenses in global markets, increase their visibility and recognition.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM and SJM promoted emblem design contest</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/upm-sjm-promoveram-concurso-de-design-de-emblemas/</link><description>???????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????? ???????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????? ???????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????? ???????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????? ???????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????? ???????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????? ???????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????? ???????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????? ???????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????? ?????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????



Providing an exchange and exhibition platform for designers of the new generation was the purpose of organizing an emblem design contest, carried out together by the Macao Polytechnic University (UPM) and the Small and Medium Business Institute of Society Macau Games (SJM), with the support of the Commercial Association. The competition received many works presented by teachers and UPM students, highlighting creativity and design techniques. After professional evaluation, the best works were selected, with the first prize to be attributed to Cao Wei. The works of Zhou Xiaoyu and Xu Jiali were followed, ex-aequo in second place, and cui jihao, third. Honorable mentions were also granted to three teams, led by Li Xinlua, Cao Wei (another work), Wang Tai and Wang Ruier. In a statement, UPM points out that the contest “demonstrated the artistic talent of students and also highlighted the university's result in the formation of high quality frames for cultural and creative industries”. Organizing entities hope that, through this contest, it is possible to “inherit and promote the local characteristic culture”, jointly cultivating the brand “Made in Macao”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 1.3 million visited Macau in the Chinese New Year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-de-13-milhoes-visitaram-macau-ano-novo-chines/</link><description>During the Golden Week of the Chinese New Year, which took place between January 28 (the eve of the first day of the Lunar New Year) and 4 February, more than 1.3 million visitors entered the MSAR, according to data from the Board of Directors Tourism Services (STD), which represents a daily average of 163,696 and an annual decrease of 3.5%. In the first three days of the golden week there were somewhat marked annual breaks, up to almost 35% in one of the days, so even with the positive results recorded in the last five days - on February 1 there were almost 12% of visitors to The previous year -the truth is that, in the general calculation, there was a decrease in tourist flow during this festive period. STD statistics also show that about one million visitors arrived from the interior of China (less 3.2% annually) and 231,058 (8.9% less) came from neighboring Hong Kong. The preferred border post continued to be the siege gates, with 38% of visitors (503,589), however, the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau bridge was also well positioned, having absorbed 24% of the total tourist flow (314,488). Thirdly, the Hengqin border post was, where 213,382 visitors or 16% of the total came in. According to preliminary data from the Public Security Police Corps, between January 25 and February 4, there were more than 6.8 million border movements, and almost 1.7 million visitors entered the territory.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2337/</link><description>Executive and Al want “more effective” communication
At the Government headquarters, the leader of the MSAR Meeting with the President of the Legislative Assembly (AL), Kou Hoi In, and the members of the table. According to a note from the Social Communication Office, the parties “exchanged impressions on mutual support between the executive and legislative bodies in compliance with their skills according to the law, and the creation of a more effective communication mechanism”. Moreover, as it can be read, they agreed that it is “necessary to establish jointly a legislative coordination between the executive and legislative bodies”. Also present were the Secretary for Administration and Justice, the vice president of the AL, Chui Sai Cheong, the first secretary, Ho Lon Sang, and the second secretary, Si Ka Lon.
 
Chief present at the opening of the Winter Asian Games
The head of the Executive of the MSAR moves to the city of Harbin, in the province of Heilongjiang, between today and Saturday, to be present at the opening ceremony of the 9th edition of the Winter Asian Games 2025, which is held tomorrow. According to an official note, Sam Hou Fai will have a meeting with the leaders of Heilongjiang province. During the absence of Sam Hou Fai, the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong will interim the functions of Chief Executive.
 
Adjustments in the work of elevator station in the interior port
The sealing area on a stretch of Rua das Lorchas in front of Macau Masters Hotel will be adjusted again from next Saturday, in articulation with the execution of the rainwater drainage work of the third phase of the rainwater lifting station work and Drainage in the south of the inner port. The directions of public works and services for traffic issues, however, rely on the circulation of vehicles in two lanes towards Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro, and in a lane towards the square of Bridge and vegetable garden, in order to maintain road circulation in the area.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Bosses and workers keep discord over a minimum wage</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/patroes-trabalhadores-mantem-discordia-sobre-salario-minimo/</link><description>For the employment part in the Permanent Council of Social Concertation, it is a point that the minimum wage must be increased this year, with the representative saying that it would be “optimal” that there was an indexing mechanism to the value of inflation. But there is discord: the bosses do not welcome a possible salary climb, arguing that the economic situation in the MSAR is not yet stable and that the measure may affect "some sectors." If the decision is advancing with the increase, the employer considers that there must be a period of transition and tax benefits. The Director of Services for Labor Affairs, in turn, did not want to compromise with a date for the completion of the report
 
Catarina Pereira
 
In what was the first plenary meeting of this year's Permanent Social Concertation (CPCs) Council, it was very clear that there is discord with regard to the eventual increase in the minimum wage. If, on the one hand, for workers it is a point that should be advanced with the climb, for the bosses the ideal is not to happen. The government will reassess this year the amount of the minimum wage, but the director of services for labor affairs (DSAL), Wong Chi Hong, did not want to compromise yesterday with a date for the report to be finalized.
“Regarding the minimum wage and also the compensation resulting from occupational accidents and occupational diseases, they are guarantees to workers. We suggest increases and that these increases may, for example, be indexed to the value of inflation, ”said Fong Ka Fai, representative of the work side at the CPCS after the meeting. Also vice president of the Workers' Federation of Associations reiterated that it would be "optimal" to have a minimum wage indexing mechanism to the value of inflation, but stressed "dialogue and reach a consensus."
Fong Ka Fai continued, saying that "the important thing is how we can improve and develop our economy." Then he added: "We, as workers, of course we will support the government and make our efforts to promote the economy of Macao because we have the pandemic and now efforts are needed from all over."
On the other hand, Vong Kuok Seng, representative of the patronage and subdirector of the Macao Commercial Association, argued that "the median of salaries should not be identical to the minimum wage." “The minimum wage is the minimum. If it's the minimum, it's not the most, ”he said.
According to argued, "there will be an overload for some sectors, namely those in which the worker earns according to what he does," if "a very high minimum wage" is fixed. By way of example spoke in the areas of retail and restoration sale.
"These workers urge what they do and [the minimum wage increase] can affect these workers," he said, adding: "Those who in the old days do more to be able to earn more, they won't want to do so much because those who do less do not need to do so much to earn more ”. Vong Kuok Seng noticed then that in Macao there is “great competitiveness”, namely in the tourist sector. “In our view, we should not change the minimum wage,” he reiterated.
But if the decision is this, the associative leader argues that "there has to be a period of transition and should provide the employer some tax benefits." In addition, it will be necessary to take into account some long -term service contracts. “But if the minimum wage is increased, we have to take into account if these contracts are still valid, and are not completed or labeled, the service provider can earn this difference from the amount or is according to what is foreseen In the initial contract? ”He asked.
For Vong Kuok Seng, "the economic situation in Macau is not very stable yet." “There are more tourists, but the number of tourists has no direct correspondence on consumption or a stabilization of the economy. Macau is small, but there are many areas where trade is not yet well. We believe that the government should do more, build a more balanced, stable economy, a community economy, ”he said.
On the sidelines of the Plenary Meeting, the DSAL Director indicated that “there is a lot of information and data” that is still being collected. Without committing to a date for the completion of the report on the minimum wage revision, Wong Chi Hong has ensured that the government will “try to speed up” work and then forward the document to CPCs and discuss the issue.
Regarding the limits of compensation, the boss representative, Vong Kuok Seng, recalled that last year were reviewed and that the decision was to maintain the values. In this context, he appealed that there may be a flexibility in relation to the annual review. “We reviewed last year, we have to review this year, but the economic and social situation is basically identical. Therefore, I ask if it is necessary to review these amounts annually, ”he said, considering that if there is a review of the legislation this should be an aspect to change.
“For review work it is necessary to obtain a lot of data, a lot of information, to study it, to examine it and it is a job that we have to do every year. In an economic conjuncture where there are no major changes, we question why to do it annually, ”he reiterated.
On the other hand, the labor part, represented by Fong Ka Fai, understands that the government must consider "more training for workers, so that they can raise their abilities and competences." In addition, it will continue to insist on increasing maternity leave to 98 days and vacation days.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Show with 200 singers and musicians celebrates Carlos Paredes in Coimbra</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/espectaculo-200-cantores-musicos-celebra-carlos-paredes-em-coimbra/</link><description>A concert with 200 singers and musicians, designed around the Portuguese guitar, celebrates the 100th anniversary of the birth of Carlos Paredes, in Coimbra, in a tribute that was born from the desire of two friends, Bruno Costa and André Varandas.
Scheduled for the 15th, the inaugural concert of the “100 Paredes” project (which is also a documentary with Carlos Paredes audiovisual collection, conceived by artistic director André Varandas), will have on stage, in the São Francisco Convent, in addition to the Portuguese guitar of Music director and guitarist Bruno Costa, a choir and community orchestra, in a total of 200 participants.
Speaking to Lusa agency, Bruno Costa noted that the tribute was born from the will of the two friends to celebrate Carlos Paredes's 100th anniversary.
To the original idea of ​​release of an album, an LP that is already recorded, the tribute conceived by the two friends “extended to a multidisciplinary program designed in the Master's hometown,” added André Varandas, about an initiative that eventually gathered to University and the municipality of Coimbra, in addition to 15 partner municipalities at national level and other entities.
"It is a wide program that will have about 80 events and initiatives, in the national and international circuit in 2025," he said.
André Varandas highlighted the “work and incredible legacy” of the master of the Portuguese guitar and his multidisciplinary vocation, since, besides the music, Carlos Paredes worked with theater, cinema or dance and with various influences, from classical music to popular music.
The programmer, which specializes in socio -communion artistic intervention projects, stressed that “100 walls” was conceived in Coimbra, highlighting this particularity: “Carlos Paredes was the first of the first to achieve and universalize the school of Coimbra da Guitar. He took this language out, and to Lisbon, but it is clearly Coimbra that is in his music. ”
Specializing in creating shows very focused on the identity of the territory and material and immaterial heritage, André Varandas recognized that he was 'on his beach' when working in the life and work of Paredes.
"What I do is create the shows in terms of artistic direction, that is, add the languages ​​of other people and give them an aesthetic meaning and a story."
According to those responsible for the artistic and musical direction of the “100 Paredes”, the show brings together, under the leadership of conductor Artur Pinho Maria, a large community corpore and large orchestra, born of collaboration and integration with artistic collectives of each municipality, from cultural associations Philharmonic bands, going through music schools and theater groups.
“The project is a tool for the inclusion of local communities, creating new and various audiences. This was the primordial point, ”noted André Varandas.
Also counting on new exclusive arrangements by Brazilian composer Rodrigo Morte, the artistic programmer stressed that in the show the work of Carlos Paredes "will gain a great contemporaneity, pushing everyone to think the future without crystallizing".
Asked by Lusa about whether this means that one can have an electronic walls, Bruno Costa denied this scenario: “Carlos Paredes's work will be fully respected, and obviously even by the orchestrations and the dynamics of the show itself, there may be some Changes, not the piece, but the way it is brought to the public. ”
"The show will be very dynamic, very rich, and people will hear and realize that it is a great thing, but it respects, in full, what was the master's work."
The project “100 Paredes” is part of the national program “Variations for Carlos Paredes”, created to mark the 100th anniversary of the birth of the musician who was born in Coimbra on February 16, 1925 and died in Lisbon on July 23, 2004.
 
JTM/LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>