<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>“Young people are more motivated, but more stressed”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/os-jovens-estao-mais-motivados-mas-mais-stressados/</link><description>Children are “too busy” and do not have time for themselves, to recharge, consider the director of the Faculty of Health Sciences at the University of São José. In an interview with the Jacky Ho Jacky Journal argued that there should be changes in the education system, returning to “origins” and helping students develop the talents with which they identify the most. In their perception, "young people are more motivated, but more stressed," the fruit perhaps from expectations to achieve "success." The college leader since 2022 also suggested that he is introduced into schools an hour of nap, a time to take breakfast and daily physical education classes. As for the use of mobile phones, it considers that only the restriction of their use will not have lasting fruits; What is necessary is to teach children and young people to control the use of these devices and make them realize that there are much more tools beyond technologies

Catarina Pereira
 
-The number of suicides in Macao has been increasing in recent years. Last year, 90 people ended life, a number that reached a peak. From your perspective, what is you failure?
-In addition, when we talk about this type of incidents, people immediately focus on recent events. But when we talk about this kind of questions, we have to ask where it all started. After the transfer of Macao in 1999, the casinos were in full expansion, there was a very fast development. After these 25 years, we may have to reflect on how we build the value system of young or general generations. It is alarming that, due to this economic growth, the people's value system has become more oriented to objectives or somehow build success in terms of how much money they have, how much wealth they have. Life is not like that. We want to teach our young generations to have a more balanced view. We want them to be happier and less stressed. But the truth is that we encourage our young people to be more diverse in terms of development, we want to be "successful." And maybe we should ask young people: is this what they want?
People may think it is the fault of COVID-19-I have no data on it. But, I'm sure it is not just because of the pandemic. This system of values ​​that I speak has to be cultivated. We can see that young people are more motivated, but at the same time they are stressed. And they are spending less time with their family - so we heard during the pandemic where families had to spend more time together, who could not deal with each other. When we have not spent time with our family for 10 years, and then we are put in this environment, parents still see their children as children, but they have become teenagers; And children also have to learn to deal with their parents.
There are multiple variables that contribute to the results we see today. Regarding this theme, I feel that the construction of our values ​​system is different and young people need some guidance.
 
How can this value system be built?
-I was talking about the same subject with a group of friends -some of them focus on the development of adolescents, others in mental health -and we have come to the conclusion that the government invested many resources to expand the learning platform of young people. They participate in different programs, can be sent abroad to participate in this and in that, and are a great success. All young people who arrive at the university, when they are interviewed by us, have a history of medals or awards.
But the point is that if we want our young people to feel that they are being taken care of, efforts from different interveners are needed. For example, how can we encourage business culture to allow more time or more flexibility in terms that parents can effectively assume the role of parents and educators?
As for schools, I know that some have already adjusted the curriculum. They intend to go from purely academic learning to something more diverse, which is great. But the children are too busy. There are no time alone taking care of yourself or focusing on you. Why before they lie down go to the mobile phone and social networks? Children and young people wake up at six or seven hours, go to school before eight, they have all day. They end around four thirty and have to go directly to piano, sports, explanations. They arrive home, have dinner and when they can sit have to do their homework. When do they have free time? Before the time to lie down. They are human. We as adults want our time, they also need it. Of course we don't want our children to spend five to six hours on the mobile phone, but we may have to think about why they need it. In the middle of the filled day-to-day agenda, they don't even have time to concentrate or recharge. These are the conclusions of a study we did recently. So I question: Is our current form of organizing education really beneficial for all the development of our children's general well-being?
 
-What argue that there should be changes in the education system?
-Yes, there should be changes in the education system. In some schools abroad, children do not only learn on paper. They teach them how to build skills of understanding and problem solving in different areas of knowledge. For example, they can take them to a national park, where they ask them to identify plants and at the same time ask the chemical composition of the ground that can help the plant grow. Perhaps we should think of returning to the origins of education and allowing our children to develop their own talents. We know that the government wants to bet on science and technology, it is great. But not everyone would like to follow this direction. There are children and young people who can have a way for arts, theater, dance.
 
Do you consider that society and the authorities be prepared for these changes?
-It have some people from the government understand, because they have consulted a lot of people, hear opinions. But as a government institution it is very difficult to promote a new political direction. It is not a question of saying that we will change a particular book on a particular subject. We are talking about changing the whole paradigm of the way we face education. This will require some courage. And how does the community react? I spoke to some friends who are also in the education sector and told me that they want to reduce the number of homework and testing, which is good. But then they also heard some comments from parents who said, "Why?" They begin to compare with other schools, think their children will be affected.
 
-Rescently, the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services has announced that next school year will launch guidance on the restriction of mobile phone use in schools. How is it seen this measure?
-The technology, the Internet of Things, Artificial Intelligence (AI) will be part of our lives, we cannot avoid it. However, as far as we should integrate these elements in the current education system and what we want to achieve, some schools are already thinking of teaching students to use different AI tools, I think this is good. But simply turn everything into digital formats and then ask young people to spend five, six hours a day in front of a computer…
Having a student accessing the internet, doing research and finding information is no problem. But can we limit the proportion of the number of hours or the number of content that must be involved in this process? I believe we should focus more on the fact that, after all this information, they must have a discussion enriched with teachers about this specific topic. And teachers have to be prepared for it. Technology is a way of helping us, but it cannot replace all interaction.
 
-And in relation to these mobile guidelines?
-I hope this is not the only step to help our young people take control of mobile phones. If it's just one step to prevent them from using it, I don't know if the effects will be lasting. While we are restricting, we should also be able to give them something that makes them realize that if I have to learn this, I have “n” different tools available, I don't need to do so only through the mobile phone. If I want to communicate with people, I can do so through various means, not just through the mobile phone. The mobile phone is a convenient way, but not the only one. Perhaps it is better to help our children browse and explore the different tools available rather than restricting them to a single moment. We must think about the lasting effects.
 
-I need to teach how to manage time ...
-Yes yes. Or managing the way the problems solve. Nowadays people use mobile phones as a map. I am sure that our young people do not know how to use a real map, but no problem, the world is changing. And if one day the internet is down, how are you going to do? (…) Perhaps we should think of having a program that allows students to land their mobile phones and then give them some challenge, making them learn to address different issues and solve the problem and have a sense of success.
 
-Relatively to young people, as I said, are more anxious, stressed, and there have also been cases of suicide. What signs should families be aware of to realize if anything goes on?
-Parents have to be aware and realize if their children are having interactions, say normal, with colleagues, or suddenly become very closed. Or if for example they are very proactive, they have objectives, and suddenly change their behavior or their desire for these things are reduced. At the same time, we must think that if our children suddenly lose interest in the things they were doing, we also have to be aware. And of course, along with some physical signs, such as stomach pain, sensation of pressure, lack of attention and liveliness. These are the physical signs that tell us that the child is having a problem or facing some stress. Therefore, we have to take care of the physical and mental aspect. And I also encourage parents to get involved with their children's colleagues, at least they should know that so-and-so is my son's best friend; or they can plan activities that involve friends.
 
-Most times the use of mobile phones restless their parents in the sense of not knowing what they are doing or seeing. How can you deal with this?
-The internet is feeding the kids with many adult content inappropriately. It is something we have no control over. Of course, some mobile phones have a parental control function that limits certain content, but the truth is that these contents are available everywhere, so as restrictions as we put in the mobile phone these contents can reach them. (…) The underlying reason why children focus on the mobile phone and do not interact with each other is because parents are always on the phone too. We have to teach by the example or it is very difficult to convince our children. Therefore, the question is: we have a mobile phone, now let's exercise control; Let's teach you how to do this control. Perhaps we should have some kind of group of activities to explain to parents how to teach the exercise of control over these devices.
 
Mental health issues have been more addressed in recent years. Soon will be announced the lines of government action for 2025. What mental health related policies should be implemented?
-It is my conviction that there are three [important] elements. If we can turn them into a more sustainable program and integrate it into our educational system, our curriculum, our way of life, we can relieve or reduce the impact of mental health problems. Prevention is the key - this is also one of the main political strategies of governments in terms of health care. The three elements are nutrition, exercise and sleep. Kids do not have adequate nutritional intake, which is the central element that gives energy and aid to growth. If we have a good base in terms of body physiology, we are preparing it to face challenges and to react to stress. Then exercise helps to develop a sense of resilience: studies show that people who practice regular physical activity also have benefits in terms of mental state due to the release of endorphins because they feel a sense of accomplishment because they are setting goals. But at the same time, they also help to reinforce the sense of resilience and this also prepares them to face the challenges of life. Finally, we have sleep, which can help the body regulate all stress factors and eliminate the waste we accumulate every day. If we sleep well, we will also have a good mood and a clear mind to deal with everyday challenges. What I am suggesting is that instead of training the brain to be increasing, perhaps we should think of putting these three elements of intervention in schools.
 
-In practical terms, how can this be done?
-First, reintroduce the nap in the afternoon. Because children are waking up early, they are learning, the brain is reacting to all these stimuli. The brain needs to rest in the middle. I am talking about all ages. Studies show that nap time helps regulate the mood, there is better academic performance and can help improve attention and concentration in classes. They absorb more and at the same time make everything better and more beneficial in terms of learning. Therefore, one suggestion is to introduce the time time at all ages at school. Then we have to make sure they have hours of exercise every day, because they are not doing enough exercise.
 
-In Macao do you think children and young people do not exercise much exercise?
-In the current school system, we are not fulfilling the ideal amount of physical activities for young children. They are sitting in a classroom for six or seven hours, then they have explanations, etc., but they are not learning about their body. This is why we see that there is a development of health problems earlier and earlier. Therefore, I argue that we should introduce physical education classes every day, at least an hour. Third, we have the issue of nutrition. There are workshops, lectures and shares in the school context and that's good, it's a starting point. But how do they turn it into practice? They have no choice. Probably breakfast will seek anything from the bakery and run to school, chewing anything while entering the classroom. This is not how we should deal with the human being - and especially with children. So we can, for example, mark a 30-minute session before class so that all students can have time to take a proper breakfast. I know it is very difficult to implement these suggestions that I give, there will be arguments from all over. But this is reality, it is the scientific evidence. The truth is that our children are not getting healthier and we want them to be, because it is aligned with the policies of Macao and China. In mainland China, the central government has been considering this for a long time. They started by reducing the number of homework, then many explanation centers were closed and some schools already have chairs that can be reclined so that students can sleep in the middle of the day.
 
-February dates indicate that there were 104 mental health professionals, of which 43 in the public sector. It seems reasonable to you this number?
- All I can say is that the depth of dealing with people with mental health problems requires effort and time. Despite working 8 or 10 hours a day, they are not limited to taking patient counseling sessions, but they also have to do analytical work on the reasons why they are looking for them and why they are in the state they are in… if we are talking about the current prevention of mental health in the school system, I would say that we should have more professionals, because we want problems to be identified earlier. And one or two school counselors or counselors in a 510 school system, 1,000 students, I do not think they are able to do so. And I also hope that these professionals will be introduced at workplaces, they must be present in various contexts. Regarding existing professionals, perhaps an inquiry could be done to know how many are thinking of abandoning the profession or how many are able to stay in the middle years before they realize they are already with a burnout. I would like to see a more systematic way of training mental health professionals, but at the same time allowing current professionals to remain and support themselves on the ground and are able to offer more services to support early intervention in various contexts.
 
-In relation to the Faculty of Health Sciences, how many students expect in the next school year?
"We are still collecting the number, but we hope to get at least 15-20 for the degree program and for the master's program." Students and professionals want to know more about mental health and so we are planning two new programs in the area.
 
-Do you be going to be next year? Can you give details about these new courses?
-Yes, we are planning and the idea is that they start next academic year. The first is a master's degree in Social Work, specializing in mental health. The other is a master's degree in counseling psychology. Thus, we hope the two programs will be able to win more impetus at the reception of candidates. We already have many requests for information.
 
-For the coming years, what are the priorities for college?
-First, with the new direction of the program, we hope to be able to promote and train professionals ready to be put on the ground. Secondly, we are thinking about developing more programs, perhaps one that train therapists.
 
"When do you leave students from college, do you think they are ready to go to the ground?"
-Our training is not only in the classroom. We also get involved with the community. Our students have to understand that there is a path, steps. If they do not understand, even if, in terms of knowledge, know how to evaluate the patient, they will not be able to maximize help within the community. Therefore, our program is aligned with these two elements: academic and practical. However, are all our students able to deal with complicated cases? I would say no, because complicated cases need to be under supervision and accumulate sufficient experience. But I am sure that our students are able to deal with users, evaluate them, know how to find the resources and networks suitable for supporting them. And then along the way they accumulate experience. But I believe Macau needs supervisors for health professionals. Both junior and senior professionals need supervision-this will help them develop professionally. Macao needs to put into practice supervisor training strategies in the areas of Psychology, Social Work, in health professions.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Employee Companies Incomed Increasing Number of Vehicles</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/companhias-de-autocarros-instadas-aumentar-numero-de-veiculos/</link><description>In order to meet the predictable growth of passenger flow in the future, the two public bus companies in the territory were bound by DSAT to increase the number of vehicles and drivers. Similarly, Transmac and TCM should bet more and more on buses powered by new energies
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) will require the two public bus companies in Macao to reinforce vehicle fleets and, consequently, the number of drivers. According to the head of DSAT Transport Management Division, the objective of the measures is to face the prediction of growth in the number of passengers in the future.
The body also aims that companies use more electric buses, or moved to new energies. Transmac and the Macao Collective Transport Society (TCM) have said they will try to correspond to the government's wishes, putting in operation, as soon as possible, this type of "Friends of the Environment" buses.
Speaking of a “or Mun Tin Toi” program, Lau Nga Hong recalled that last year, public buses carried about 227 million passengers, almost equivalent to the 229 million accounted for in 2019, which is a record.
On the other hand, the DSAT leader stressed that this year, the body and the two companies will consider adjustment and optimization of bus careers, "especially in the face of their capacity situation, considering the search for the entry into the city's new zones."
At the same time, companies will also collaborate with the light meter, “in order to increase the operational efficiency and quality of bus services, as well as the entire road transport network,” said Lau Nga Hong.
In the same program of the Chinese language radio, TCM's deputy general manager Chan IAT, clarified that the company operates a total of 548 buses, with a daily frequency of 5,900 exits, numbers that exceed 10% the basic periodicity defined by the authorities.
Transmac's director of operations, Un Kuan Ngai, stressed that last year, the company concluded the replacement of all buses with new energies, totaling 410, which are subject to a daily frequency of more than 4,200 exits. The number exceeded the basic level of 15 to 20%.
Regarding the possibility of more stops in the vicinity of Alameda Carlos D 'Assumpção, at Nape, Un Kuan Ngai assured that "the company will study if there is conditions to do so."
Meanwhile, the information was given that, for 2024, the number of passengers using fast careers, “X”, accounted for about 9% of total users. As for the capacity problem, DSAT intends to open fast or special careers.
Faced with the suggestion of a “or world tin toi” listener to cancel reverse seats inside the buses, Transmac's operations director considered that the idea may not result. "If these places are canceled, the total number will reduce and this will also make it impossible to increase the number of passenger seats that stand," he noted.
 
Taxi radio company wants license extension
The Macao Taxi Radio Services Company asked the government to extend the license for the operation of 100 “blue” vehicles, whose deadline expires on September 30 this year. Chan Un Kuan, general manager of the company, said that "both sides will consider the time to use the respective taxis, analyzing whether these vehicles will still be suitable to continue operating," adding that the company will collaborate with government planning. The official indicated that, in 2024, the number of requests for service registered by the company reached 22.46 million, among which 4.25 million were successfully met, representing almost 20% of the total. He also pointed out that if the 100 “blue taxis” ceases to circulate, the company's transportation capacity will lower one third. On the other hand, as there are five of these barriers without barriers, predicted that this will affect the displacement of residents and tourists. On 1 April, the day the Radio Taxi company will organize an activity to celebrate the 8th anniversary, all 12 vehicles without barriers will provide free services, "giving priority to elderly passengers or with difficulty in mobility." The company estimates that it will ensure about 300 services at no cost to users.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hospital das Ilhas with procreation center in the 2nd semester</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/hospital-das-ilhas-centro-de-procriacao-2o-semestre/</link><description>In the second half of this year, a medically assisted procreation center will be inaugurated at the Islands Hospital, which will also have a hemodialysis center. On the other hand, Hospital das Ilais revealed that the daily number of markings for external consultations specialized recorded a 50% increase compared to the volume verified at the beginning of operations
 
The Islands Hospital has already opened the public assessment service for procreation and initial external consultations for access to the medically assisted procreation service (PMA). At the same time, it has prepared the acquisition, installation and testing of equipment, as well as the formation of staff, providing that the PMA Center of the Hospital of the Islands may go into operation in the second half of this year, to give the public “comprehensive options” of PMA.
In addition, in a statement, the Hospital Complex anticipated the opening of the hemodialysis center later this year.
On the other hand, he noted that the number of external consultations specialized by the Islands Hospital increased to 52, while the daily amount of markings for external specialty consultations reflected a 50% increase in the initial volume of hospital operations.
At the same time, the volume of computed tomography exams already occupied a quarter of public services of the genre. The Islands Hospital has provided radiotherapy services 277 times to cancer patients. He said, two cyberknife treatment systems were installed, which are in the testing phase. It is expected to be placed in operation in the middle of this year.
On the other hand, since January of this year, the hospital's integrated wards began to receive hospitalized patients and the hospitalization of acute patients from the Conde de São Januário hospital center, recalled in the statement, also pointing out that it began to be regularly carried out painless gastrointestinal endoscopy in February. In the next phase, several surgical projects will be opened.
The hospital also concluded that, according to situations observed in external consultations specializing in the last half year, there are many elderly patients with chronic diseases in Macau, some of which are complicated.
In this sense, it indicated that it plans to launch a project of chronic heart failure management and establish a referral system for diagnosis and treatment that encompasses community centers and local public medical institutions. The idea is, through educating and encouraging patients to use electronic monitoring equipment, improve the self -management of teachers with heart failure, to analyze the factors that influence them and present suggestions for improvement.
In addition, the Islands Hospital has gradually provided private medical services at the International Medical Center, with the operation of the Health Management Center to be activated and international medical hospitalization services to be opened later this year.
Also about the Hospital Complex, in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Lei Chan U, health services (SSM) revealed that, in this year, in addition to further expanding the supply of aesthetic and vaccination medicine projects, will introduce new specific external consultations services such as external consultations for weight loss and cancer prevention. It also aims to expedite the process of digitization regarding health management, in favor of optimizing the medical care experience. Given the future, the services of private ward will also be in operation, SSM said.
In the answer, the body also said that it will, in the short term, make public consultations on the “legal regime for the exercise of activity of private institutions providing health care”, in order to gather, more broadly, the consensus and opinions of society, to optimize the licensing and operation regime of the medical institutions of this nature.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>EPM without “whimper” during MNE visit</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/epm-sem-choradeira-durante-visita-de-mne/</link><description>The president of the founding of the Portuguese School of Macao (EPM) told Lusa yesterday that the institution "has nothing to have closed" to the Minister of Foreign Affairs (MNE), Paulo Rangel, who visits the masters tomorrow. "There is no whimper, we have nothing to do, we have nothing to demand, everything is normal," he said.
Jorge Neto Valente said he hoped Rangel "take a correct perception of the school, for what is the ones, the goals he has." "It's always good to have direct knowledge, it's much better than in the papers," he said.
"We have to account that the school is fulfilling the role that it is expected to play," he added, recalling that the Portuguese State holds the majority of EPM foundation capital.
At the end of December, Neto Valente said the founding of FEPM is in danger of running out of money if the Portuguese state no longer contributes to school financing. At an event at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center in Lisbon, the lawyer said that EPM expenses should reach eight million euros in the school year 2024/2025, with the Portuguese state financed only 10%.
"The [budgetary] deficits have been verified in recent years have been covered by FEPM, and if not stopped, the risk of seeing its capitals in the medium term is exhausted," said Neto Valente, quoted by Jornal Hoje Macau, adding that the school "lives mainly from the support of the government of Macau, without any interference."
A week earlier, the Portuguese Ministry of Education, Science and Innovation stressed the commitment to “drastically reduce the number of students without classes” abroad, but recalled that it is necessary to take into account “the lack of teachers in Portugal”. In a note sent to Lusa regarding criticism of the EPM Parent Association, the ministry detailed the reasons for rejecting the request to replace several teachers and Vinca that in other cases the requests to teach in Macao were accepted.
 
Miguel de Senna Fernandes insists on Cantonese
The president of the Macanese Instruction Promotion Association (Apim) suggests that Chinese teaching at EPM, where Mandarin and not Cantonese is taught, is approached on Rangel's visit. "I have always advocated that Cantonese must have status. Because students, when they leave school, are in a singing world. This with all the merit that can have teaching in Mandarin," said Lusa Miguel de Senna Fernandes.
"It must always be approached," he replied, when asked if the theme should be taken to MNE, which has the tutelage of the EPM. "It's an issue that should be asked. It's a delicate question, because we are talking about an official language," he added, referring to Mandarin.
The also vice president of the EPM foundation admits that this is not a question that generates consensus -"many parents do not agree with this vision" -but stresses that the learning of Cantonese "is a vehicle of integration" as it is the dominant language in the territory.
Despite defending the teaching of Cantonese, Senna Fernandes recognizes the importance of Mandarin learning - "It's a desiderate, therefore noble, absolutely valid, I have no doubt."
Doubts raise, however, regarding the results of the bet, since in the “contact with some students”, they reveal difficulties, he added. "Those who are not aware of Chinese arrives here and learn Mandarin. ... There are students who are exceptional for languages, I am not in question, but in most cases it does not happen. Why? Because the environment does not speak mandarin, although now it is started to hear more," he said.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Amelia António exhorta mne to “explain” Portugal's position in relation to China</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/amelia-antonio-exorta-mne-explicar-posicao-de-portugal-em-relacao-a-china/</link><description>The president of the House of Portugal in Macao (CPM) defended, in anticipation of tomorrow's visit to the Portuguese Foreign Minister to the territory, the importance of Paulo Rangel clarifying the Portuguese community about the government's position on China.
"We are here, we suffer the consequences of these relationships [between Portugal and China], good or bad. We had very close relations for a long time, which changed with Covid. I have not seen things to be as they were, and I think it was important that the minister explains what is the position," Maria Amelia António was told that Portugal does not have to "align faithfully with all that is said in Europe and above all." USA, ”he said.
Before the pandemic, he recalled, there was “permanent communication” and “much exchange” between the Portuguese and Chinese authorities. Today is noticeable a “hardening regarding the Portuguese” in macao immigration, Maria Amelia António declared, but not being able to affirm categorically whether the position is related to “this removal” between China and the West.
Macao authorities have not accepted new requests for residence in the territory for Portuguese for the “exercise of specialized technical functions”, allowing for justification of family reunion or previous connection to the territory. The guidelines eliminate a practice signed after the transition from Macao in 1999. The alternative to a Portuguese national guarantee the resident identity ticket (BIR) undergo an application to recent qualified frame capture programs. Another hypothesis is the issuance of a 'Blue Card', a limited authorization to the work bond, without the benefits of residents, namely at health or education level.
These limitations have affected CPM in hiring professionals to integrate the School of Art and Crafts. Mentioning the strategic relationship between China and the Portuguese -language universe and Beijing's interest in the Portuguese language, the associative leader mourned the “slightly contradictory” stance.
"We can not make omelets without eggs, we who are here and who work with the Portuguese culture and the Portuguese language, we have a hard time having people who replace those that went out. Many Portuguese from Macao, and working in these areas with these qualifications] is very complicated," he said.
Also the president of the Macanese Instruction Promoting Association (Apim) considered the new obstacles to the Portuguese residence “an important question”, although he admits that history is not guaranteeing “special status”. "As Portuguese, person in Macau, of course I would like my patricians to be treated well and, of course, that the residence in Macau is always facilitated," said Miguel de Senna Fernandes.
The president of Apim noted that the difficulty of hiring had an impact on the Portuguese school (EPM), under the protection of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Portugal. It is expected, he said, that the Portuguese State “always continues to pay special attention” to the EPM.
Senna Fernandes, also vice president of the EPM foundation, stressed, however, a “distant attitude” of the Portuguese authorities “in relation to Macao things”. The trip from Rangel to Mand, believes, will bring few changes. "It's a pro-form, because, unintentionally being pessimistic, I don't see that it makes a lot of difference. But of course, it's always good for the Foreign Minister to visit Macau. (…) It never made a difference. In fact, no politician or minister in Macau has made some difference," he said.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Defended benefits of electronic vote</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/defendidos-beneficios-voto-electronico/</link><description>Leaders of Portuguese matrix associations in Macao told Lusa to agree with a transition to the electronic vote, stressing embarrassment in the current options for emigration.
"As long as it is not advanced without being tested, I am fully in agreement. The future is this and we have to point out there," said the president of the House of Portugal in Macau (CPM), Maria Amelia António.
In legislative elections, the Portuguese abroad have the possibility of exercising the right of vote in person or postal, while in the presidential and European, the vote is in person. In choosing correspondence, the government sends the address indicated in the census notebook the voting report and two envelopes, one of green and one white, which must be returned to the Ministry of Internal Affairs after filling.
According to data from the Portuguese Consulate-General in Macao and Hong Kong, in the last elections for the Assembly of the Republic last year, 213 voters were registered to vote in person in this diplomatic representation and 48,645 were qualified to exercise the postal voting right. In the last estimate given to Lusa, the consulate pointed to the existence of about 155,000 people with Portuguese passport between the residents of Macau and Hong Kong.
The electronic option “can offer greater security”, defended Maria Amelia António. He realized: “With the consulates to work badly, in order to have few employees, with their work, and in countries where they are far from the sites where people live, it is very difficult for people to vote personally. There has also been a lot of flaws in the guarantees of receiving vow [via mail],” he added.
Also the president of the Macanese Instruction Promoter Association (Apim), noting that “the Post Office problem is very complicated,” he admitted that if the electronic vote ensures greater participation in the electoral act, then it is a won bet. "On top of that, [when] from Portugal, the country of emigrants, who want to follow the matters of the country," he said.
The electronic choice is a longstanding claim of the Portuguese Communities Council (CCP). Rui Marcelo, president of the Regional Council of the Portuguese Communities of Asia and Oceania, who has a meeting scheduled this Friday with Portuguese Foreign Minister Paulo Rangel told Lusa that the “theme is already part of the agenda” of the CCP “a few years ago and has been approached several times and with various governments”.
"With the advancement of technology and the possibility of implementing security systems that can ensure vote safety - which happens today through the provision of services in other areas of the government also - the conditions are created so that we can eventually evolve into a situation where it can obviously be a complement, but not a substitute," he noticed.
In February, Parliament approved a resolution proposed by the PSD to test the electronic vote in emigration. The President of the Republic suggested, in December, an electronic voting pilot experience in the circles of emigration.
The applicability of electronic vote was also the subject of the first panel of the annual meeting of the Regional Council of Portuguese Communities in Europe, which took place last week at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs in Lisbon. Also then the European counselors expressed the desire to rely on this possibility of vote, taking into account the distances that sometimes have to be traveled to vote for the voting assemblies and the constraints that the postal vote has revealed.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Land of Coloane Market reversed to the state</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/terreno-mercado-de-coloane-revertido-para-estado/</link><description>After the Coloane market ended in mid -December last year, the land and the building were now reversed to the state
 
The land where the former Coloane market is located, next to President António Ramalho Eanes, was integrated into the state's private domain. The lot, “including the building built on it”, was reversed “free of burden or charges” to the State, after the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) gave up from the free granting of the land, as it can be read in a order signed by the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam.
It is recalled that the Coloane market, the only one on that island and that went into operation in 1893, ended the public on December 16 last year. Coloane's evolution, the change in the demographic structure in the village and the modification of resident consumption habits were pointed out as factors that contributed to the continuous decrease in the flower flow of that space - and which led to their extinction.
According to the order published yesterday in an official bulletin, the terrain, with an area of ​​299 square meters, has a value of about 23.2 million patacas. When AMI announced the closing of the market in November last year, the body revealed that it started studying the revitalization and reuse of space, after considering, “comprehensively”, the development of Coloane's development, the distribution of fresh and living food offering points in the area and the effectiveness of market service functions in recent years, as well as the opinions of the Coloane community.
In concrete, the body indicated that the revitalization of the original construction of the Coloane market would be considered, and the proposal would later be presented to the public. This newspaper questioned yesterday the AMI about if there is already a decision for the future of that space in Vila de Coloane, however, until the closing of this edition did not receive an answer.
After knowing the plan, the residents of Coloane began to discuss the matter, and their opinions were collected, for example, by the Industrial and Commercial Federation of the islands of Macao. At the time, the association's president, Yeong Keng Hoi, suggested in statements to this newspaper that the space would welcome a terrace and a multifunctional enclosure.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Financial Reserve grew 5.3 billion in January</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/reserva-financeira-cresceu-53-mil-milhoes-em-janeiro/</link><description>The value of the capital's financial reserve capital reached about 621.51 billion patacas in late January this year, reflecting a monthly increase of 0.9% or 5.3 billion, according to data from the monetary authority (AMCM) published yesterday in the official bulletin.
According to the synopsis of AMCM's active and passive values, the basic reserve was approximately 164.17 billion patacas, more 7% than the previous month, while the extraordinary dropped 1.2% to 457.3 billion. The basic reserve is equivalent to 150% of the appropriations of core services expense, while the extraordinary corresponds to the remaining balances of the financial reserve after the satisfaction of the basic, and can be taken to provide financial support to a possible budgetary deficit of MSAR, as well as the necessary financial resources to favor socioeconomic development.
By 2024, the financial reserve grew 6.2% or 35.74 billion to 616.21 billion patacas, in annual terms, with the basic and the extraordinary reserve to be encrypted at 153.4 billion and 462.8 billion, respectively. After increasing 4% between 2022 and 2023, the financial reserve thus accelerated postpandeia recovery, although something distant from the record of 663.56 billion recorded in February 2021 was maintained.
According to AMCM, the Financial Reserve registered investment benefits in the order of 31 billion last year, corresponding to a profitability of 5.3%. The results of 2024 surpassed those of 2023, when the income was 28.98 billion and the profitability of 5.2%, and marked a return to profitability of 5.3% registered in 2020, the year in which investment income was recorded (31.06 billion).
In a report yesterday released in the official bulletin, the Financial Reserve Inspection Committee praises the strategies adopted by AMCM. "The members of the Financial Reserve Inspection Committee unanimously understood that, in 2024, despite the fluctuations still verified in global financial markets, investment management strategies were adopted appropriate to the financial reserve, achieving an ideal return on investments, while effectively controlled the risks," says the opinion.
Looking at 2025, the commission notes that while stabilizing the economy of mashes and improving public finances, the geopolitical environment remains “complex”, with “major variations in financial and monetary policies between countries”, which increases “potential risks in global financial markets”. In this sense, he stresses, “it is appropriate for AMCM to maintain the investment card in a diverse manner, with emphasis on controlling any risks in the descendant sense, and, in parallel, ensure the liquidity and safety of the investment portfolio, adjusting the allocation of assets in accordance with the evolution of the market, in order to achieve the objective of preservation and appreciation of assets, in the medium and long term, reserve, reserve. financial ”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Man who stabbed shopkeepers in psychiatry</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/homem-esfaqueou-lojistas-internado-na-psiquiatria/</link><description>The man who stabbed two employees from a store in Travessa dos Anjos is hospitalized for psychiatric treatment and evaluation. According to the authorities, the suspect will have mental problems. The knife he used in the aggression was bought in a supermarket near the store concerned
 
A 41 -year -old resident who stabbed two employees from a telecommunications store in Travessa dos Anjos, near Rua do Campo, is hospitalized for psychiatric evaluation and treatment, Judicial Police (PJ) said yesterday. According to the authorities, man will have mental problems, however, has no history of treatment for mental illness.
After a preliminary assessment of the doctor, added the PJ, the man needs to receive psychiatric treatment and be the target of new evaluations "to realize the mental state when he committed the acts." Authorities also await the psychiatrist's final evaluation report.
The case occurred late Tuesday afternoon, when the man entered the telecommunications store and began by stabbing one of the employees, also assaulting a second when he tried to prevent the situation. According to the authorities, one of the employees then managed to escape and ask for help from people on the street.
As for the injured, they are both residents. One of them registered an 18 -centimeter neck injury, so it had to take 100 points. Still, and according to the authorities, the nerves, vital organs and blood vessels were not injured. The other recorded lacerations on the arm. Both are stable, but hospitalized for observation.
According to information provided by the Telecommunications Company, there is no registration of complaints or conflicts involving the suspect and the company's employees. Both the injured and other staff of the store claimed to be unaware of the suspect and denied conflicts.
The PJ considers that there are strong evidence that the case involved attempted murder and severe offense to physical integrity. On the afternoon of the incident, and before heading to the telecommunications store concerned, the man will have wandered in several areas until he reached the vicinity of Rua do Campo. The perpetrator, who is unemployed, used a 22 centimeter knife he bought in a supermarket near the store.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IC intends to create more places for street artists</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ic-pretende-criar-mais-locais-para-artistas-de-rua/</link><description>Busking, a very popular street artists' performance in various cities around the world, has been arousing greater interest from associations and groups of Macao. Given the growing request for licenses for this purpose, the Cultural Institute promises to study the creation of more spaces, pointing mainly to community areas. About 1,800 authorizations have already been issued
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The street is often the first stage for many artists and the so-called Buskers, or performers, spread around the world, showing themselves mainly in large urban centers, where the number of visitors reaches greater flow. In Macao, this concept is not yet very widespread, especially at the level of solo artists, but may change, since, according to the Cultural Institute (IC), there has been a growth in the number of licensing requests.
Until 2024, about 1,800 copies of Busker Card were issued and the number of points for artistic tours continues to increase.
In response to a deputy interpellation to the Legislative Assembly, Ella Lei Cheng I, IC President Leong Wai Man, says that the government and integrated tourism and leisure companies will continue to study more measures, seeking to create conditions favorable to public participation in the development of community areas. ”
Almost 10 years ago, the IC launched the “Ticket Program for the Arts”, with the aim of “stimulating public appreciation and participation in culture and arts, revitalizing community neighborhoods, creating a cultural environment and more performance platforms for Macao artists”.
According to the body's president, “the number of points for artistic tours went from three, at the beginning, to eight, currently,” as a result of the increase in interest on the part of associations and artistic groups. Leong Wai Man stresses that “zones open to the public are available for different types of shows,” including Taipa Houses, Fortaleza do Monte, the former Panchões IEC Long factory and Lai Chi Vun Naval Shipyards.
The IC also recalls the launch of the “Financial Support Plan for the Revitalization of Historical Zones”, with the purpose of “supporting the various sectors of society to fully take advantage of the special resources of these places and to participate in the exploration of shows and activities with their own characteristics”.
It is further in the use that "will continue to review and study the optimization of the" Program Ticket for the Arts ", as well as to continuously increase the points for artistic tours according to the situations, in order to facilitate exhibitions and exhibitions of artists."
In addition, it goes on, “IC takes advantage of several artistic programs in community neighborhoods to offer local arts and culture workers platforms, including the 'International Parade' and the 'Fringe Festival of the city', among others”.
These events “seek to promote dance, theater and street performances, among other shows, to synergically combine artistic groups and respective entities, aiming at the enrichment of the artistic and cultural environment”.
The response to Ella Law adds that, in the future, “with the use of different artistic and cultural programs”, the IC will continue to study the creation of more acting platforms in community neighborhoods, “providing society of great quality cultural and artistic activities”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Meeting” promotes more than 350 Lusophone products</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/encontro-promove-mais-de-350-produtos-lusofonos/</link><description>Tomorrow and Saturday, the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment (IPIM) will hold the “Meeting”, an initiative that aims to provide the public the opportunity to experience “the unique charm of the products and culture of Portuguese -speaking countries (PLP)”. The event, to be held at the Exhibition Pavilion of the Service Platform for Commercial Cooperation between China and PLP, will present more than 350 “quality and affordable products”, from Café do Brasil and from Timor-Leste to Vinhos and Cortiça Boutiques from Portugal. It will also be held 10 workshops, alcohol tasting courses and culinary demonstrations, as well as product promotions. On Friday, alcoholic products will be promoted, bringing together a variety of PLP wines, and culinary demonstrations, where Macau cooking chiefs will cook Portuguese delicacies such as Portuguese chicken and potato pasties. The next day, the IPIM will launch “Lusophone Alcohol Workshops”, with wine specialists sharing knowledge about wine tasting. Other workshops will also take place, open to the public, such as painting and collage of Portuguese ceramic, sardine rope braid and hand painting of tiles. Consumers who make purchases from an amount can exchange a wine classified for only one level, until the stock is over, or getting a reminder of the “Pou Kong Ieng” mascot, which will make a surprise flash. The public can also participate in the guided tours of the pavilion to "know the results of Macau's work as the Sino-Portuguese platform." IPIM reports that during the event, the pavilion parking lot will be open to the public, with limited places and operating in order of arrival.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Completed sending of 177 horsepower of the Jockey Club to the interior of China</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/concluido-envio-de-177-cavalos-jockey-club-para-interior-da-china/</link><description>The process of sending 177 horsepower of the Jockey Club to the interior of China is already completed. Doumen's customs in Zhuhai announced that on the afternoon of the 20th of this month 41 retired jockey club horses, which were part of the fifth group of animals sent by the company to the neighboring city, completed 30 days of inspection and quarantine. It was the last group of horses to be sent to the continent. According to later, these animals will be transferred to subject themselves to systematic training in the interior of China, "in order to inject a new momentum into the equestrian sports industry of the Great Bay." After the last horse race at Jockey on March 30 last year, horses had to be transferred abroad by the end of this month. At the closing date of the space, there were 289 horses in the Jockey Club. On the other hand, in relation to cats, the Macao Animal Protective Society (Anima) announced yesterday that the Jockey Club will subsidize the 22 adopters, worth 5,000 patacas per cat. This is because it became aware that some of the adopted cats have developed health problems that require medical treatment. However, the horse racing company lamented the death of two cats that had also been welcomed. According to Anima, the allowance will be issued through a cross check directly by Jockey to adopters, and checks will be entrusted to the association for delivery to each person. The Institute for Municipal Affairs has also participated in the coordination of the process.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2368/</link><description>Neto Valente leaves TDM Fiscal Council
Lawyer Joaquim Jorge Perestrelo Neto Valente was replaced by António José Dias Azedo in the presidency of the Macao Teledifusion Fiscal Council (TDM), according to the official bulletin. The same order from the Chief Executive renews the nominations of Lam Bun Jong and Iong Weng Ian as members of the same fiscal council of the company that ensures the public radio and television service in the territory. The mandates for the performance of the functions mentioned began on March 22 and last for one year.
 
"Kaifong" plan clinical and new center for the elderly
The General Union of Residents Associations (“Kaifong”) will seek to open a community clinic on Verde Island and a new elderly center, highlighted Chan Ka Leong, director of “Kaifong”, in a first life with the media. In addition, it revealed that the association will perform surveys about population aging, hoping to help the government better respond to related problems. At the same time, he promised that the Kaifong will organize more activities that aim to stimulate the development of the community economy.
 
118 veterinarians obtained certification
Since late February, 118 certified veterinarians have been issued in Macao, the institute for municipal affairs (AMI) have been issued. According to the body, in recent years “the search for the veterinary clinical care sector has been growing at a rapid pace”, so the law on veterinary clinical care came into force in April 2024. Recently, representatives of AMI and the Council of Veterinary Medicine participated in the 2nd Conference of Veterinary Doctors in Guangdong. The event included visits to the Clinical Skill Training Center, the Veterinary Hospital and the drug research and development companies.
 
Named Subdirector of Justice Affairs
Ng Chi Kim was appointed, in a service committee, to hold the position of subdirector of the Directorate of Justice Services (DSAJ), for a period of one year, from 1 April. The order released in an official bulletin was signed by the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong. Ng Chi Kim joined the civil service in 1999, having had several positions, including head of the Secretary's Office for Administration and Justice between December 2019 and July 2020. Since April 2023, hengqin's executive cooperation zone has been, since April 2023.
 
Shun Tak with 12% growth in 2024 revenues
Shun Tak Holdings saw its 2024 revenues grow 12% in terms annually to over $ 4.5 billion from Hong Kong, according to a company announcement. However, the year also increased the group's loss by 22%to 824 million HKD. The group quoted on the Hong Kong Stock Exchange said it had generated a 918 million profit last year with real estate promotion. However, as far as hotel and leisure are concerned, this business segment recorded a loss of 180 million, compared to 74 million the previous year. As for the area of ​​transport, it suffered a shared loss of 8 million.
 
Activities mark 32 years of the promulgation of the Basic Law
Under the theme “Rule of Law in Macao - Participation of All”, the Macao Basic Law Disclosure Association, Matter Services, Institute for Municipal Affairs and Youth Education and Development Services will perform a series of activities, in celebration of the 32nd anniversary of the promulgation of the Basic Law of Masters. Today, at the Center for Science, an “Academic Seminar on New Journey of the Implementation of the Principle‘ One country, two systems ’in Macau” will take place with guests from Macao and the interior of China. On Sunday, at Tap Seac Square, there will be the Legal Disclosure Festival - “on the way with the law”, with stage performances and games related to legal disclosure.
 
Benjamin Chan exit from the Value Deposit Center
Benjamin Chan was dismissed, at his request, to the exercise of the chairman of the Board of Directors of the Macao Society Limited Society of Macau, from 1 April. This is what an order signed by the chief executive and published yesterday in an official bulletin. It is recalled that, as the Tribuna de Macau newspaper found, Benjamin Chan is expected to be replaced by the chairman of the board of the monetary authority by Henrietta Lau, current administrator for the banking area. Yesterday, in the chief's order it is also said that Wu Jianfeng and Ho Chi Hou are also exonerated, at his request, from the administrators of the Board of Directors of the same deposit center.
 
42 suspects of illegal work detected in February
In February, authorities detected 42 suspects of illegal work in operations developed individually by the Public Security Police Corps and the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs, but also together between both and with other services. In total, 367 locations were inspected, including construction shipyards, private buildings, commercial and industrial establishments, among others.
 
2023 health valleys valid until April 30
Health services remember that the deadline for the use of electronic health valleys, awarded in 2023, ends on April 30. Health valleys, in the amount of 600 patacas, can be used to pay expenses in establishments where professional health functions who have adhered to the “Health Care Reimbursement Program for the year 2023”. The consultation and transmission of the valleys can be made on the “single account”, in self-service service kiosks, or at a support counter of the Mashel of the Islands Services Center or in the black sand.
 
15 suspected cases of alcohol sales to minors
Since the implementation of the “Alcohol Consumption Control Law”, in November 2023, health services (SSM) have detected 70 cases of suspected violation of the law, 15 involved “the sale or availability of alcohol to minors”. The services intend to sensitize establishments that have not posted the prohibition of sales to minors, an infringement to which the fines can reach 200 thousand patacas. Distics can be obtained in the Office for prevention and control of smoking and alcoholism, health centers, the SSM website services center.
 
“Power Banks” only in the hand luggage
The airlines that operate at Macau airport advise passengers to store the power banks in their hand luggage, and their use is prohibited during the flight or to store them in the basement or in the upper compartments. In a statement on the latest regulations on the use of these devices, the Macao Airport society also indicated that poor Power Banks can be lying out at control points.
 
Open 25 vacancies to visit the Environmental Center Alegria
Registration is open for the guided tour of the Alegria Environmental Center in Mong-Há. The visit is free, and only 25 vacancies are available, and will be held on April 5, at 10:30 am, with an estimated duration of two hours. Interested parties can apply to the environmental protection services website. If adverse weather conditions or insufficient number of participants are verified, services may cancel the visit.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump changes oval room decoration, with golden tones and various ornaments</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/trump-muda-decoracao-salao-oval-tons-dourados-varios-ornamentos/</link><description>Donald Trump has promised a new “golden age” to the US. In the White House Oval Hall, at least it has already fulfilled this promise, with a change in decoration that highlighted the golden tones and many ornaments.
The Republican decorated the presidency sanctuary with golden trophies and cup holders with his name, and filled the walls with portraits of his predecessors.
Almost every day, the president brings something new, and seems to be more interested in the decoration of the space now, than during his first term, from 2017 to 2021.
“President Trump plays Donald Trump's role very well,” said Peter Loge, director of the media school at George Washington University. "The show is important. Part of it is ostentation. It would be surprising if Trump did not transform the oval hall into a TV studio that reflected his brand."
Behind the change is also a political message. The Oval Hall is a symbol of American power, a scenario of press conferences and meetings with foreign leaders shown on TV. Therefore, it was not by chance the inclusion of the president of the nineteenth century, James Polk, to the presidential portrait gallery.
Under Polk's mandate, the 11th president, the US lived the largest period of territorial expansion, representing a message, as Trump alarms allies when claiming the Panama Canal and talking openly about the possibility of attaching Greenland and taking control of the Gaza Strip.
Each president gives the oval hall a personal touch, and the contrast between the Republican and his predecessor Democrat Joe Biden could not be greater.
"Do you think Joe Biden would do this? I don't think so," Trump said recently as he opened the curtain that protects from light a copy of the Declaration of Independence during an interview with Fox News's "The Ingle Angle" program. He pointed to the newly installed gold cherubim above the doors: "They say angels bring luck."
Biden's Oval Hall was sober, with five portraits around the famous fireplace, including one of the president in times of war Franklin D. Roosevelt. Trump installed nine, not to mention others placed near his table, including one of the Republican Ronald Reagan.
Biden had put on the shelf above the fireplace a plant that allegedly dated from John F. Kennedy. Trump exchanged it for seven golden objects, some of them over 200 years. It also added to the salon a bust of former British Prime Minister Winston Churchill.
The ostentation should not be surprised, as a man who announced the first candidacy for the presidency on a golden escalator of Trump Tower in New York. The billionaire prints his name in everything he can, from buildings to Bible, and rarely fails to promote both his brand and the image of strength that was fundamental to his political career.
Trump also plans to pave the famous White House rose garden to give her the appearance of her residence courtyard in Mar-lago, Florida. "The grass doesn't work," because "it gets soaked," he said in the interview.
One of the things that the Republican is most proud of is a unconventional portrait hanging near the images of their illustrious predecessors. Outside the Oval Hall, in a golden frame, is still the police photo taken from Trump in 2023, in Georgia, referring to the judicial case where he was accused of attempting to interfere with the 2020 elections. To remember his opponents…
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>