<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Burlas surpassed a sixth of inquiries opened by the MP</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/burlas-ultrapassaram-um-sexto-dos-inqueritos-abertos-pelo-mp/</link><description>Last year, the prosecutor registered a "record" of inquiries charged since the creation of the MSAR-15,840, having observed an annual increase of 13.70%. Of these, 14,722 were completed, and 3,671 accusations were deduced and 10,622 filing orders were issued. The agency warns of the “proliferation of the cases of circumvents, notwithstanding repression”, pointing out that the surveys filed by burlas “surpassed a sixth” of all. Analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the work report perspective still the year 2025, with the MP saying that it will intensify the conscience of magistrates for national security. In addition, it also indicates that it has already presented to the Executive the opinion to “restart negotiations around judicial cooperation in criminal matters with the interior of China”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The Public Prosecution Service (MP) found an “evident increase” in the number of inquiries assessed over the past year. Within a year, 13.70% have grown to a total of 15,840, reaching a “record” since the establishment of the MSAR and “denoting a relatively manifest sign of promoting the practice of criminal activities”, it can be read in the annual report of the body.
According to the document analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, 14,722 were completed, representing about 93% of the total; In this field, there was an 18%increase compared to 2023. Among these inquiries, and after investigation, 3,671 accusations (plus 8.19%) were deducted and 10,622 filing dispatches (plus 20.59%), based on grounds such as “manifestation by the offender not to desire criminal proceedings, insufficient crime practice or non-identification”.
From 2023 to 2024, 7,460 inquiries were transferred, an increase of 32.15% compared to the previous period. On the other hand, after new evidence has been discovered, the MP reopened 264 archived inquiries, translating a decrease of 23.70% in annual terms.
The five crime groups with the most inquiries assessed included the crimes against property (such as theft, theft, damage), with 4,946 inquiries (plus 17.12%); against heritage (various types of circumvents, extortion), with 3,152 inquiries (plus 9.79%); offense to physical integrity, with 1,696 (more 22.10%); against the road traffic law, registering 999 inquiries (plus 11.25%); and computer crimes, with 981 inquiries (plus 83.71%).
The most frequent crimes, such as slopping, theft, illegitimate appropriation of founding and computer crime, "registered a more evident increase," while there was also a climb in game surveys related to the game, "which directly led to an increase in the total amount of inquiries."
The MP considers that the “proliferation of circumvents, despite repression” deserves “attention”. "The number of burla surveys has been increasing, reaching 2,770 inquiries charged [in 2024], which has exceeded one sixth of all charged surveys, consecutively occupying first place since 2021, which evidences a high dangerousness," he warns.
Alongside this, it also warns that caution is needed taking into account the trend of increasing game crimes. By way of example, it indicates that 262 usury inquiries related to the illicit game (114.75%), 23 -requirement or acceptance of identification document (plus 35.29%) and 55 hijacking crime (plus 89.66%), “representing an obvious increase”.
"Given the importance that the integrated tourism and leisure industry is covered by the economic development of MSAR, [and] the trend of increased criminal activities alluding to the game sector (…), it is necessary to reinforce and intensify prevention and control work, with a view to eliminating potential risks and ensuring a healthy and ordered development environment," says the MP.
The report also recalls three "relevant" cases that were in the courts: "Sunity Group", "Vip Tak Chun" and former directors of the Directorate of Soil, Public Works and Transport Services. "The results of the judgments of the three cases demonstrate the solid guarantee of the MSAR Judiciary System in relation to the rule of law, the integrity and healthy development of the MSAR GAME sector. At the moment, the executions of decisions are being ordered in an ordained manner," he can be read.
Regarding the last year, it is also said that the MP's “computerization work” was accelerated and a “internal data connection and sharing based on the application of digitization and administration systems of internal work” was accelerated.
 
“Intensify consciousness” from magistrates on national security
By prospecting the year 2025, the MP stresses that "the magistrates' awareness of national security will be intensified and their domain over the legal system will be intensified, with the aim of achieving better results in practical work." In addition, it also states that it will “strengthen the mechanisms” intended to comply with responsibilities “in the safeguard of national security, including the implementation of internal rules regarding criminal jurisdiction and cooperation with the competent services in the interior of China”.
By the way, it argues that it is “indispensable” to raise the “modernization” of the Macao legal system, “with the aim of adapting to the positioning and demands of the development of both the Great Bay (…) and in the in -depth cooperation zone in Hengqin”. "The Public Prosecution Service, as a judicial body of the Misrees, which performs judicial functions, will reinforce the connection with administrative and legislative services, with a view to boosting and improving, under the terms of law, the modernization of the legal system of MSAR," he adds.
It also reveals that it has already presented to the Government of the Misrera "the opinion to restart negotiations around judicial cooperation in criminal matters with the interior of China, promoting in timely legal progress in the area concerned between masters and the interior of China."
The MP binds after "it will seriously implement the spirit of President XI's important speeches." At the same time, he stresses that he “performs his duties and fulfills his responsibilities autonomously and independently, without any interference” and undertakes to bet on staff formation. It also promises to continue to comply with the principle “a country, two systems” and the basic law.
On the other hand, it ensures that "it will improve work mechanisms and internal operation, optimize procedural procedures and reinforce the construction of the team." In this field, he even says he will “enhance the strengths and perfect the weak” as well as focus on “increasing judicial effectiveness”. It also guarantees that "it will adopt a more active attitude, will raise transparency in your work and improve the mechanism of dissemination of information."
 
Defended reinforcement of the fight against prostitution exploitation
In the 2024 work report, the Public Prosecution Service (MP) points out that there was a decrease in sexual crime surveys against minors, but an increase in serious sexual crimes. Those related to minor pornography descended “dramatically” (90%) to 15 surveys. At the same time, inquiries linked to crimes such as sexual abuse of children and rape have “a decrease in different levels”. On the other hand, 52 violation crime surveys were charged, plus 36.84%. "There is no excluding the possibility that most of the crime of violation crime inquiries can be caused by prostitution," says the MP, adding that 26 inquiries related to proxenetism (44.44%) were opened. "In the light of the foregoing, there is certainly the need to continue to reinforce measures to combat prostitution exploitation and related illicit activities, in order to purify the social environment," he says.
 
More than 82 million in compensation for harmed workers
Over the past year, the prosecutor supported 1,050 workers, who eventually received a total compensation of 82 million patacas. Cases include workers from the “Suncity Group”, and also related to employers who violated the rules of criminal law and who fled in bad faith to pay debts in matters. Still in the work field, 277 new processes of occupational accidents and occupational diseases (less 3.48% in annual terms) were registered, with 285 conciliations and 13 actions were made because they did not agree; As well as 103 new common labor processes (less 36.81%), with 84 conciliations and 30 actions brought because there is no agreement. The conciliations involved 368 workers (minus 21.37%).</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>World Return Motorf World</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mundial-de-motosurf-de-regresso-hac-sa/</link><description>For the second year in a row, the waters of HAC-Sá beach are expected to be the scene of the fifth and last journey of the Motosurf World Championship in November. The International Union of the sport has put Macau on this year's calendar, only missing official confirmation by Melco, which sponsors and organizes the competition, in conjunction with the local association. As last year, the race could decide on the territory the winners of another season of this nautical sport, dominated by the Czech Motorcyclists
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The International Union of Motonautics (UIM) has returned to Macao in the calendar of the Motosurf World Championship, scheduling the final journey of the current season for the weekend of November 21, 22 and 23. This will be the second consecutive time in which the territory welcomes the competition, to compete in the waters of the beach of HAC-Sá.
Official confirmation will be known soon, as talks, “very advanced,” according to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau, between Uim and Melco Entertainment, which sponsors and organizes in conjunction with the local association of modality.
Following the results verified in the previous rounds, Macau may, as in 2024, decide the champions in the various categories, highlighting the elite, in which Czech Matyas Novotny is the holder of the title.
The time of 2025 is already running, having been held two days in the United Arab Emirates, in the city of Fujairah, and in Türkiye (çesme). Two tests will be followed in October in Italy (Manfredonia) and Croatia (Zadar). In half, there are world games in Chengdu (China), in which the motorcycle and female races were included for the first time.
The current general classification of the main class, Elite, is led by Lukas Zahorsky of the Czech Republic, with 107 points, ahead of compatriots Alex Lukscheider (95), Matej Kozisek (91) and Matyas Novotny (90).
The World Cup encompasses six more categories, namely Stock (American Antony Squire commands the table), Stock R-Merlin Plus (Adam Kolar, Czech), Masters (Kim Down, South Korean), women (Eliska Matouskova, Czech), Men's Junior (Matyas Narvyk, Czech) and Junior Burdova Junior (Ellen Burdova, Czech).
The athletes of the Czech Republic are the great dominators of the sport worldwide, especially the elite class, calling itself the main titles.
In the 2024 edition held at Hac Sá Beach, which also served as qualification for the World Games, the races encompassed 120 motorcycles from 20 countries or regions, including Macao that already has some athletes competing in proofs abroad, especially on the continent.
The motorcycle is a water sport that involves the use of a motorized board to slide over the water. It is a relatively new modality that combines elements of traditional surf with the technology of an engine, allowing practitioners to maneuver and enjoy speed in various aquatic conditions, without necessarily depending on waves. The boards are equipped with combustion or electric engines that drive the board through the water.
Motosurf was made official as a sport by UIM in 2019 and has great popularity in recent years, conducting championships and events in several countries.
As in 2024, Macau should count on the presence of the big names in the sport.</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More than one million patacas in fines for illegal works</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-de-um-milhao-de-patacas-em-multas-por-obras-ilegais/</link><description>In the first half of this year, the number of illegal works processes established by the Soil Services Directorate and Urban Construction, 441, representing more than half of the total of 2024. The total value of the fines applied exceeded one million PATACA
 
The Directorate of Soil Services and Urban Construction (DSSCU) filed 441 processes related to illegal works, between January and June, representing more than half of the total cases verified throughout the last year (844). In the first six months of this year, 38 resulted in fines that rose to about 1.1 million patacas. In five cases, the fines were not paid within the stipulated period and will be subject to a coercive collection by the government, says a statement.
In addition, 100 processes filed in the first half of 2025 are related to cases of voluntary demolition, according to DSSCU. The body recalls that, after the entry into force of the new legal regime of urban construction, the fines to be applied were increased, and new fines have been added to those who do not comply with the demolition orders. In order to encourage cooperation by infrastructors, the new legislation introduced "a measure of reducing and exemption of encouraging character under the sanctioning procedure."
If the owners require the voluntary demolition of the illegal work during “the period of hearing”, they are totally exempt from the payment of the fine, assuming that the application has been accepted and the demolition of the confirmed work. However, the owner must first submit the request to DSSCU and only after receiving permission can demolish the illegal construction. "Otherwise, a fine may be applied for violating other provisions provided for in the legal regime of urban construction," explains the body.
Regarding the established processes, he notes that "a number of commercial spaces did not" prior communication "or requested the work leave for the execution of remodeling works." The lack of notice, as well as the license, may result in a fine, and the amount of fees due to legalizing the construction may triple.
It should be noted that during the first six months of the year, offenders of 50 cases were notified of the final decision, two more than throughout 2024. These are cases where owners can already demolish illegal works within a stipulated period. If the order is not met, DSSCU itself performs the demolition, whose expenses are the responsibility of the transgressor.
In the same period, 59 cases were filed, more than half of the total of 2024 (102). The body "gives priority to cases of new illegal works, renewal of illegal works, constructions in ruin state and cases of illegal works located in buildings whose license of use was issued after the entry into force of the new law."
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Dialysis Center already works at Hospital das Ilhas</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/centro-de-dialise-ja-funciona-hospital-das-ilhas/</link><description>The Dialysis Center of the Islands Hospital is already in operation, which can, in the initial phase, serve residents sent by the SSM. It is expected that the center provide monthly routine dialysis services to 1,200 people/times, by the end of this year
 
Officially entered the Dialysis Center of the Hospital das Ilhas, which, in the initial phase, provides treatment of maintenance hemodialysis to residents sent by health services (SSM). According to the Islands Hospital, the Center is expected to provide monthly routine dialysis services to about 1,200 people/times, by the end of this year.
Quoting data from statistical and census services, the hospital pointed out that in 2024, dialysis treatment services were provided to 131,635 people/times in Macao. The hospital noted that the search for dialysis treatments has increased continuously as the population is increasingly aged and chronic kidney diseases are more frequent among younger people.
The hospital is convinced that the creation of the Dialysis Center will contribute to providing more comprehensive support services, and geographically more convenient dialysis treatment services to Cotai who previously used public medical services.
With an implementation area of 1,400 square meters, the dialysis center has advanced medical equipment in the large bay and a “welcoming and comfortable treatment environment,” says the Islands Hospital, ensuring an intelligent information platform that allows the electronics management of medical records and medical prescriptions.
Led by “Peking Union Medical College Hospital” (PUMCH) experts, the team working at the Center can provide hemodialysis, hemofiltration, among various modes of dialysis, as well as performing and maintaining access to dialysis to meet the treatment needs of patients at different phases. Generally speaking, the Center provides “One Stop” diagnostic and treatment services, integrating dialysis treatment, disease monitoring, complication management and access maintenance, taking advantage of PUMCH.
The hospital unit has promised to continue adding medical equipment, widening the scale of diagnostic and treatment services, and actively relieves the pressure of the public sector's medical system.
 
Proposal on “Day Hospital” will be submitted to AL this year
The director of the SSM, and also chairman of the Council for Medical Affairs, said that the proposal for the exercise of activity of private institutions providing health care will be submitted later this year to the Legislative Assembly. At a meeting of the Council, Alvis Lo also presented the final report of the public consultation on the said legal regime, which provides for the creation of day hospitals. In addition, he explained the guidelines regarding the regulation of medical advertising, with a view to collecting vowel opinions. According to he stressed, the opinions collected generally support the legislation for the “day hospital”, and the SSM absorbed some suggestions. Alvis Lo stated that he expects to improve and further promote the legislation.</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Portuguese summer course joins 406 students in a</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/curso-de-verao-de-portugues-junta-406-alunos-na-um/</link><description>Organized by the Department of Portuguese of the Faculty of Letters of the University of Macau (UM), the Portuguese Language Summer Course has this year with 406 students enrolled, the Higher Education Institution said. The 39th edition attracted students from various countries and regions, including mainland China, Macau, Hong Kong, Taiwan, Australia and Timor-Leste.
The students have already started classes, and for many this was the first contact they had with the Portuguese language, highlights one, adding that, “through an intensive program of three weeks dedicated to language and culture, participants will deepen their knowledge of the Portuguese language and experience the Lusophone culture”.
At the opening ceremony, the Vice Rector for Global Affairs, Professor Rui Martins stressed that this is the oldest course of UM, with almost four decades since its inauguration in 1986. Rui Martins “encouraged all participants to fully enjoy the richness of the Portuguese language and Lusophone culture, as well as immersing them in the academic life of the University of Macau”, says the same note.
With the support of the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services, Macao Foundation, Post Office and Tourism Services, the Summer Course aims to “provide participants with a thorough knowledge of the Portuguese language, a awareness of their variety, richness and cultural complexity and their growing and invaluable value around the world”. The linguistic, historical, social, economic and political dimensions of Macau and the Lusophone countries will be addressed during the course, whose program integrates topics on linguistics, literature and translation, cultural activities such as visits to relevant spaces of Macau, and clubs that encompass theoretical learning and practice of domains as capoeira, folkloric dances, the culture of countries Lusophone and topics of contemporary Portugal.</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Authorities made a great simulacrum in casino</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/autoridades-fizeram-grande-simulacro-em-casino/</link><description>Several police units co-realized an exercise that simulated a bomb threat and a robbery at different properties of SJM. The simulacrum lasted about an hour and was attended by over 200 people



















This week, the exercise “capture of the wolf” took place, which simulated a bomb threat and armed robbery in different SJM facilities. The exercise lasted about an hour, had 209 participants and "the results obtained fulfilled expectations," according to a statement from the Unit Police Services (SPU).
The SPU guarantee that they will continue to make efforts to achieve the three police concepts presented by the Secretary for Security, fulfilling the motto “better to prevent remedy”, through the performance of various police operations and joint exercises.
Upon describing the scenario of the year, the SPU indicates that a criminal group claimed to have placed a bomb at the Grand Lisbon Palace and demanded $ 100 million from Hong Kong in cryptocurrencies. The SJM immediately reported the case to the Judicial Police (PJ) and the Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate. The PJ highlighted staff for the scene and coordinated with the Public Security Police (CPSP) the monitoring of the other properties of the operator.
However, the bomb threat would have only served to divert attention from the authorities, since the intention of the criminals was to “perform an armed robbery” in a SJM casino in Cotai. The robbers set themselves on the run and ended up intercepted by the PJ, culminating in the detention of one of the criminals. A second was arrested by CPSP on the public road.
Another robber took two hostages in one of the rooms. The PJ began the “Operation TRAQUINAS” and installed a command center on the ground. CPSP, PJ agents, and customs services mobilized cars, drones and quick boats to patrol the city, coastal areas and border stations, requesting the help of Zhuhai authorities.
The Fire Department provided first aid to the injured and the CPSP highlighted two special groups to the site. In the casino, PJ negotiation experts managed to release a hostage. The CPSP Special Operations Group eventually stopped the criminal and rescues the last hostage. The PJ also stopped the last suspicion, and author of the bomb threat, which had been disguised as a client.</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Joe Chan disillusioned with electoral exclusion</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/joe-chan-desiludido-exclusao-eleitoral/</link><description>Joe Chan Chon Meng, one of 12 candidates excluded from the Legislative Assembly (AL) race for lack of patriotism, was outraged by the decision. The Macao State Security Defense Commission (CDSE) has excluded all candidates from two lists, including synergy power, which includes Joe Chan. In a statement, CDSE explained that when a candidate is excluded for lack of patriotism, all others on the same list are also removed.
"I can't believe it. I never heard of this system around the world. Basic law said I had the right to vote or be voted. This is how to get back to the cultural revolution," Joe Chan told Lusa.
"I was deprived of my political rights for no reason," he said, admitting that the decision represents, in practice, a lifetime prohibition to return "to participate in any election."
The new electoral law, which came into force in April 2024, states that people who have been considered “not defenders of the basic law or non -faithful to the Special Administrative Region of the Macao of the Popular Republic of China” in the five years prior to the vote.
Joe Chan manifested himself angry and disillusioned that the reasons that led to exclusion and demanded an explanation and disclosure of evidence by the Electoral Commission was not communicated. "They can provide evidence, guidelines or advice so that I can improve the situation," he questioned the activist.
On Tuesday, the chairman of the Legislative Assembly Electoral Affairs committee assured that the binding opinions of the CDSE, of which it is not possible to appeal, "have a clear and sufficient legal basis" and were elaborated "taking into account the facts." However, Seng Ioi Man refused to reveal the facts that led to exclusion, arguing that "the works and documents of the State Security Defense Commission are confidential." The disclosure of these “may represent certain risks to national security, and should not even be published their content,” added the judge.
Joe Chan, who is also environmentalist and educator, said that the only reason he can find is that sometimes he "talks against them," referring to the MSAR authorities.
For decades, Chan has been dedicated to the protection of the environment in Macao. "If the government wants to build an ecological island and do something against pollution, I can often talk and even be a little critical," he admitted.
The ecological island is the name given by the Macao government to an island for garbage deposit, planned to South Coloane - a plan against which Joe Chan launched a petition. "This is why I'm not loyal enough to the government to support their policies," the environmentalist asked.
The power list of synergy is led by the current deputy Ron Lam U Tou, who in the last elections in 2021 had been the seventh most voted, with 8,764 votes. Ron Lam, one of the few critical voices of the executive at AL, said on his Facebook page that he had not yet received any official notification, but admitted that the exclusion "was very sudden." “I'm in a quiet conscience. My initial intention to Macau will not change. I believe the sun always comes after the wind and the rain!” Added the former journalist.
Exclusion also covers the list “Popular Liveliod Force in Macao”, led by social worker Alberto Wong, who first competed in AL.
In 2021, it was the Electoral Commission to exclude five lists and 21 candidates-15 of which pro-democracy.
With Tuesday's decision, they will compete for the elections of 14 September six lists for direct suffrage, less than in 2021.
Thirty -three deputies are part of AL, 14 of which are elected by direct suffrage, 12 for indirect suffrage through associations, and seven are later appointed by the head of the local government.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SSM Attentive to Foshan Outbreak of Chikungunya fever</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ssm-atentos-surto-em-foshan-de-febre-chikungunya/</link><description>After nearly five hundreds of chikungunya fever cases in Foshan, health services say they are aware of the outbreak and call for caution to the population
 
Health services (SSM) are “closely monitoring” the chikungunya fever outbreak detected in Foshan, guangdong province, associated with an imported case, which has about 500 confirmed infections. The body led by Alvis Lo guarantees that "will take response measures in timely time."
At the same time, SSM ask the population to pay attention to the prevention of infectious diseases and to take steps to clean the standing water and prevent mosquitoes. Clinical manifestations and disease transmission methods are similar to those of dengue, explains in a statement.
According to data from the Department of Health of the district of Shunde, in Foshan, an imported case of chikungunya fever was identified as cause of a local outbreak. Until July 15, 478 cases have been confirmed, which focus mainly on the villages of Lecong, Beijiao and Chenncun. According to the authorities, they are all “light cases”.
According to SSM infectious diseases monitoring data, Macau registered, in 2013 and 2019, two and three imported cases of chikungunya fever, respectively, all from Southeast Asian countries. There were no serious cases or deaths. This year, Macau has not yet registered a case, the authorities assure.
Chikungunya fever is an infectious disease transmitted by the Aedes aegypti mosquito or aedes albopictus. Clinical manifestations, transmission methods, prevention and control of chikungunya fever are similar to those of dengue.
According to the SSM, the incubation period is two to 12 days, usually three to eight days, and the main manifestations are fever and intense joint pain. Other common symptoms include: muscle pain, headache, nausea, fatigue and rash, which are usually slight and last several days. Authorities also report that serious and fatal cases are rare, and that there is no prevention vaccine.
The body ensures that it will continue to monitor the prevalence of chikungunya fever in neighboring regions. It also appeals to citizens who, if they travel to Southeast Asia and other regions where the disease is prevalent, reinforce precautions and adopt measures against mosquitoes.</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New Coffee celebrates Legacy of the Great Prize</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/novo-cafe-celebra-legado-grande-premio/</link><description>A coffee was inaugurated at the Macau Grand Prix Museum, inspired by the sports event. The theme of space and menu is alluding to elements such as the guide circuit and the “Triumph Tr2” car. Until next Wednesday, promotional activities take place
 
The Macao Grand Prix Museum (MGPM) inaugurated this week a coffee that offers “themed food and drink” inspired by the sports event, announced the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD). The body expects space to provide “an immersive experience in the cultural atmosphere of race”, both residents and tourists. The new establishment fits the concept “Tourism + Sport + Culture and Creativity”.
The interior of the coffee has representative elements of the guide circuit and “a table that recreates on a real scale” “Triumph Tr2”, the winning car of the first Macao Grand Prix (GPM), held in 1954. The menu itself has options such as “gallon with coffee ice, wheel -shaped ice cream and ice cream,” says the statement. Several cultural and creative products of Macao are also available.
Until July 23, “customers who share on social networks taken on coffee or their products will be able to receive free GPM thematic ice cream,” says STD. Under the inaugural week, “special discounts” are also available, whose details can be consulted in the establishment. Coffee is in operation every day, between 08h00 and 21h00.
The company responsible for managing the establishment was selected in a public tender of STD, in 2024. The opening ceremony was chaired by the director, Helena de Senna Fernandes, the subdirect of the Department of Advertising and Culture of the Central Government connection, Ba Bing, IP Sio Kai, member of the Executive Board and by other guests.
Situated in Nape, the museum has several elements that make up “History, Sport, Science and Technology, Cultural and Creative Industries”. Its mission is to “develop entertainment, leisure, knowledge and learning functions” and promote “education with fun”, reinforcing “culture dissemination and preservation” associated with the great award. The MGPM is open to the public from 10h00 to 18h00, every day except Tuesday.
The museum continues “committed to enriching its exhibitions and interactive elements” as well as improving support facilities. At the same time, it has collaborated with different sectors “to integrate cultural, creative and leisure components”. Interested parties can consult more information regarding the museum as well as purchase online tickets.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sands and Red Cross distributed 1,500 emergency kits</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sands-cruz-vermelha-distribuiram-1-500-kits-de-emergencia/</link><description>Under the usual “Emergency Response Response Kit”, 38 Sands Cares ambassadors packed 1,500 “kits” at the Macao Red Cross headquarters, which were distributed to “local schools vulnerable to storms in the low areas of Macao”. According to Sands, the "kits" contain personal safety and disaster response objects, such as a waterproof case, a first aid package, disinfecting wipes, a whistle, a rain poncho, masks, a glass protection towel, a flashlight emergency radio, a blanket and a leaflet with useful information. In addition, workshops were organized, driven by the Red Cross in various schools. Wilfred Wong, vice president of Sands China, thanked the volunteers, the Red Cross, as well as the Institute of Social Action and the Education and Development Services for support, adding that the program has benefited 7,400 families since 2019. Owen Wong, deputy director for assistance to the Red Cross Cross disasters, said the initiative allowed the initiative to build a field. "More resilient and safe."</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao on the tropical storm</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-na-rota-de-tempestade-tropical/</link><description>According to the expected trajectory, a tropical depression located east of the Philippines, which continued to intensify yesterday, will enter the area of 800 kilometers from Macau at the beginning of tomorrow, the meteorological and geophysical services (SMG) informed that at this time will be issued signal 1 of tropical storm. In a forecast released at 5:25 pm yesterday, the SMG also mentioned that the tropical storm is expected to move towards the west coast of Guangdong. Due to the “uncertainties in the storm's trajectory and intensity”, the SMG guaranteed to be closely monitoring their development and movement, appealing to the population to pay attention to the most updated information. In addition, they anticipated that time in the region will be very hot between today and tomorrow, and the yellow alert has been issued. In turn, the Hong Kong Observatory has announced that it will issue signal 1 as early as tonight, admitting to raise the alert to level 3 on Saturday. On Sunday, more intense typhoon warning signs may be issued, depending on the storm distance from the Rio das Pearl estuary and the changes in local wind conditions, the observatory explained. Since the beginning of the typhoons, Macau has been affected by three tropical storms, although without significant approximations and always with low alert levels.</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2435/</link><description>Suggested greater scope in temporary accommodation
Three specialized groups held a meeting on temporary housing and eligibility for their assignment. According to the Council for Urban Renewal, they proposed that people affected by other reconstruction projects, in addition to those of the “seven sets of buildings in the Iao Hon neighborhood”, are housed in temporary housing, serving as an example and contributing to the promotion of urban renewal work.
 
Looking for overcame national obligations
China's Ministry of Finance issued national obligations of 6 billion Renminbis (RMB), among which 3 billion two -year, at a interest rate of 1.43%; 2 billion with a period of five years and 1.55%; and 1 billion with a period of 10 years, at a interest rate of 1.72%. "The present issue was well accepted by the market, having recorded an excessive subscription," said the monetary authority of Macao. The accumulated volume of obligations issued by the Ministry of Finance in Macao has already reached 21 billion RMB.
 
Seized 1,008 packs of illegal cigarettes
1,008 packages of cigarettes with labels were seized that were not in accordance with the law, in a total of 20,160 units, after a complaint to the cabinet for prevention and control of smoking and alcoholism. The action of inspection to the convenience store in ZAPE was performed by customs services. According to health services, the convenience store also failed to present the import documents. The establishment may be fined up to 200 thousand patacas; illegal objects will be confiscated and destroyed.
 
STD wins PATA AWARD IN MARKETING AREA
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) triumphed in the marketing category of Pata Gold 2025 awards, announced the Asia-Pacific Tourism Association (PATA). STD was distinguished by the “Experience Macao Limited Edition” campaign, an interactive game that invited the site users to explore virtually Macao, while competing for exclusive and limited edition travel experiences. This year, 20 winners were recognized in two major categories - marketing and sustainability and social responsibility. STD director Helena de Senna Fernandes said that "the winning initiatives of the Pata Gold prizes are a breath of fresh air for the tourism industry."
 
Creative presents two colloquiums
Creative Macao will host this Saturday the lectures “Politics of Aesthetics and Aesthetics of Politics” and “Critical Inventories as an artistic research method”, by researchers Sofia Lopes Borges and Stéphane Blumer, respectively. The two colloquiums will be held in English, between 15h00 and 4:30 pm with free admission. This initiative is organized by the Macao European Studies Institute.
 
UPM will host education conference
The “IEEE Tale 2025” Education Conference, which will take place from December 4th to 7th at Macao Polytechnic University (UPM), invites academics and professionals from around the world to the submission of articles. The IEEE (IEEE Education Society) Annual Conference in Asia-Pacific will focus on Steam's engineering, technology and interdisciplinary education, exploring the innovative application of digital technology in learning, teaching and evaluation. The idea is to promote academic exchange and the sharing of practical experiences in the area of educational technology, UPM said. The period of submission ends on July 25. All complete articles, short articles and in -course investigation will be published in the text collection of the “IEEE Tale 2025” conference and submitted to the IEEE XPLore Digital Library.</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New regime will allow resort hospitals in resorts, hotels and commercial zones</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/novo-regime-permitira-hospitais-de-dia-em-resorts-hoteis-zonas-comerciais/</link><description>The government intends to allow “commercial zones, resorts, hotels, among others, which meet technical conditions” function as a “day hospital”, under the new “legal regime for the exercise of activity of private institutions providing health care”, whose report of the public consultation has already been released. The idea is to “fully develop the advantages of software and hardware of integrated leisure companies and to boost the coming to Macau of more tourists,” according to the document. On the other hand, the idea of health valleys can be used in hospitals of the day. Health services “the generality of opinions supports” legislative work, with disagreement opinions to be always less than 5.7%
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Under the new “legal regime for the exercise of activity of private health care institutions” -which aims to “promote the Big Health industry and the development of 'health + tourism'” -the government intends to allow hospitals to be created in game operators. This is what it states in the final report of the public consultation, consulted by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao.
There were several aspects addressed during the 30 days of consultation, including the location of the private health care institutions. According to the document, "most opinions suggested that hotel establishments were included in the legal scope of choice of location, indicating that hotels, in conjunction with medical services, can create" health + tourism "synergies."
According to participants, the “innovative model” can be applied, for example, to physical exams, medical beauty and postoperative rehabilitation, “which not only increases the convenience of visitors, but also allows the development of high value added business to the hotel sector”.
“To fully develop the advantages of software and hardware of integrated leisure companies and to drive Macao from more tourists because of health care, after the integration of opinions and under the premise of ensuring the public health and safety of sick, in principle, commercial establishments, namely commercial zones, resorts, hotels, among others, who gather the technical conditions, may be authorized to function as hospital of Day, ”said the government in the answer.
In addition, he adds that, through the "Preliminary Technical Meeting" mechanism, authorities may "provide suggestions on technical and administrative formalities in choosing the site to investors wishing to establish private medical institutions."
The executive also dismissed the hypothesis that health valleys, currently in a value of 700 patacas, can be used in hospitals. During the consultation, there were those who suggested that the amount be increased and that the government would consider widening the scope of its use until hospitals.
In the response on the subject, health services (SSM) remind you that the objective of the health care reimbursement program is to “promote the family medicine system”, “reinforce cooperation between the public and private sector”, as well as “support the development of private doctors”. And they refuse this idea: "Since day hospitals mainly provide specialized medical services in some hospitals, being different from the promotion of family medicine (…) health valleys will not be applicable at this stage."
During the consultation period, the SSM received 892 opinions or suggestions from health professionals, associations and medical institutions, civic associations, commercial sector, game operators, residents and academic institutions.
According to the SSM, "the generality of opinions supports the present legislative work, considering that it actively contributes to the promotion of the development of the Macao Health sector." Of the opinions presented for the various sub-themes, those who expressed opposition always remained below 5.7%, with the rest showing “agreement” or “partial agreement”.
 
Hospitals are not required to have obstetrics and neonatology
After the analysis, the SSM “welcomed some opinions”, in particular on licensing requests, the adjustment of the hospitals of day hospitals, the widening of the location of establishments for the installation of medical institutions, the adjustment of the requirements of the basic functional areas of hospitals, the widening of the content of medical advertising and the recipients of proximity services, as well as the optimization of transitory provisions of hospitals, hospitals, It can be read in the conclusions.
Regarding hospitals, the idea of the government was that the existence of an obstetrics and gynecology service, and a neonatalogy service was mandatory. However, heard the opinions, and given the birth rate, among other factors, the creation of these services becomes “flexible”.
Regarding the transition of hospitals, after hearing the opinions of the sector, "since some hospitals have been working for many years and are an integral part of the health system, in order to ensure the stability and continuity of medical services rendered to the public, the emergency service will be replaced by the creation of an external 24 -hour consultation."
The security, in turn, is intended to allow hospitals and hospitals of the day, in case they do not comply with the responsibilities, they can use as compensation. As for the value -and despite the opinions in favor of a lower or lower value -the government intends to keep it at 5 million patacas to the hospital and 1.25 million to the day hospital, and "the value will be increased according to the services to be developed."
There were also those who showed fears about the risks of “advanced therapies”. At this point, the SSM consider that "the hospital and the day hospital have facilities, monitoring equipment and specialized medical teams, which can effectively respond to any adverse complications or reactions during the treatment process."
In the report it is also said that the SSM will define, more flexibly, through guidance, the scope of telemedicine. On the other hand, and in view of the aging problem, anticipating greater demand for proximity medical services, the authorities indicate that “the scope of these services will be clearly defined. In particular, “chronic diseases management, wound treatment, among other low -risk items”.
Authorities consider that the legislation "provides complete legal protection for advanced therapies, telemedicine and proximity medical services, in articulation with existing industrial support policies of the Government of MSAR, further promoting the mutual complementarity of the advantages between public and private medical institutions."
Regarding the license period, that of hospitals will be one year, contributing to “the timely review of its operation”, while the day's hospital will be valid for two years. As for clinics, whose nature of services is relatively simple and with lower risk level, the expiration date will be three years.</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Changes in cannabis rules leave farmers in a difficult situation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/mudancas-nas-regras-da-canabis-deixam-agricultores-em-situacao-dificil/</link><description>When it became the first nation of Southeast Asia to decriminalize cannabis in 2022, Thailand triggered a “green race”, quickly remodeling the economic panorama and challenging ancient cultural norms.
Cannabis dispensaries proliferated in urban centers such as Bangkok, reaching more than 10,000 across the country. But agricultural communities of the lush rural northern countryside are perhaps the ones that benefit most from the expanding sector - assuming that the government does not close everything.
In the mountains of northern Thailand, blessed with an ideal climate and fertile soil, generations of HMong and other ethnic minorities have long cultivated the earth, preserving a deep knowledge of indigenous plants and practices of sustainable cultivation. Historically, these communities were linked to the illicit cultivation of opium, before moving to healthier cultures such as corn, tea and vegetables from the late 1960s.
Cannabis Legal, an industry that moves more than 1,000 million US dollars a year in Thailand, has offered them a profitable opportunity in recent years. Now the sector plunged into chaos after the Thai government announced an abrupt retreat in the legislation at the end of June.
The country decided to restrict the use of cannabis for medicinal purposes, requiring medical revenues and limiting volumes to a 30 -day customer supply. Committed to repressing the increase in cannabis tourism, smuggling and recreational smoke by minors, Thailand authorities should also prepare rules that require each dispensary to have a doctor on site and can even reclassify the herb as a category 5 narcotics.
With tighter controls of sales and distribution in sight, mountainous communities and sponsors of operations are preparing for real difficulties, from the lowest demand to widespread unemployment in the country. Some HMong farmers are afraid of resorting to less profitable and more polluting crops, such as corn, where farmers traditionally burn the fields after harvesting, contributing to the worsening atmospheric pollution in northern Thailand.
Still, Mrs. Chokwan Kitty Chopaka, president of Writing Thailand's Cannabis Future, a defense group, is hoping that agricultural communities do not completely abandon the practice.
“The Hmong people have always been the guardian of the seeds,” says Chokwan Kitty Chopaka. “I hope they continue to keep them safe,” he emphasizes.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>