<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Year of the Horse “unfavorable” for economic activities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ano-cavalo-desfavoravel-para-actividades-economicas/</link><description>Characterized by an “extremely strong Fire energy”, the Year of the Horse will bring challenges to some sectors in Macau, such as gambling, but also potential for growth in other areas, such as real estate and education, predicts local “Feng Shui” master Mickey Hung. Consulted by the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU on the occasion of the Chinese New Year, Mickey Hung also described, through Chinese nomenology, the luck at work and the health of the Chief Executive and the five Secretaries of the MSAR

The year 2026 is the “Year of Bing Wu”, generally marked by an “extremely strong Fire energy”, since both the Celestial Trunk and the Earthly Branch of the Pillar of the Year are of Fire (one of the “Five Elements”), begins by analyzing Mickey Hung, local master of “Feng Shui”, who once again made predictions to the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper at the time of the Lunar New Year, about the luck and misfortune of the MSAR in another cycle of the Chinese zodiac.
"It is called 'Year of the Red Horse'. Fire has a dry and hot nature, symbolizing splendor and ostentation. However, without the Wood element to generate it, Fire becomes unstable and is accompanied by a state of impatience and change", describes the master. Still, it rules out a significant impact of this phenomenon on “Water element industries”, such as the entertainment and tourism sectors, because “Macau is located in southern China, supported by Mainland China, with the Pearl River Delta on three sides”.
Still, Mickey Hung warns that “attention should be paid to industries with the Wood element, such as those linked to tea and furniture, which may face greater obstacles”.
Specifically, the soothsayer predicts that, in the Year of the Horse, the economic performance of the gaming industry “may be relatively modest compared to other sectors”.
"Macau entered the 9th Cycle of 'Feng Shui' in 2024, a cycle lasting 20 years. The 9th Cycle is a cycle of Fire. The gaming industry belongs to the Water element in the 'Five Elements'. Fire and Water (entertainment and gaming) are incompatible. Furthermore, as 2026 is the Year of the Horse (Yang Fire), there is a compound effect, that is, of adding more fire to the fire. Therefore, the Macau gaming sector may not perform very well this year”, he projects.
"With increased competition in the sector and variables in the international tourism market, the attractiveness of gaming offers may be affected. In particular, high-end gaming establishments and facilities will face stiff competition from other regions and countries. The industry needs to seek innovation, explore new gaming models and improve customers' travel experiences, to face market challenges", suggests Mickey Hung.
Regarding the economy in general, the “Feng Shui” expert points out that the “Horse” will bring “a year with a strong influence of the Wood and Fire elements”, which “will be unfavorable for economic activities”. “In other words, the economy, finances, among others, may be relatively stagnant”, he warns.
"Those involved in industries related to the Fire element need to redouble their efforts. On the other hand, for industries not related to Fire, such as retail sales, it is advisable to integrate technological elements into various aspects of business. For example, opening online stores and using artificial intelligence elements", he advises.
According to his analysis, in the first half of 2026, Macau's economy will be “really affected by the strong fire”, which “will lead to stagnation or even a downward trend”. “Significant growth in the economy and the real estate market is expected to gradually emerge in the second half of the year”, he anticipates.
Conversely, the “Feng Shui” expert believes that the “Horse” will offer “new opportunities” to the local real estate market. "'Real estate' belongs to the Earth element in the 'Five Elements', and the Year of the Horse belongs to Fire. However, this nature of Fire is quite empty, that is, without roots. Empty Fire needs Wood to generate it and Earth to protect it. Earth acts as the furnace for Fire", he explains.
In his opinion, with the Macao SAR Executive implementing, since January 1st of this year, policies that aim to boost the real estate market, these government actions “will help to increase the desire of residents to buy houses and attract the attention of investors from other regions, further increasing the potential for appreciation of real estate in Macau and the promising returns on investment”.
As for the education sector, Mickey Hung also makes positive predictions. "In the theory of the 'Five Elements', education is considered 'Earth', mainly because the Earth nurtures talents, just as the soil cultivates human resources. This year is a year of Fire, the element that generates the Earth", he observes.
In this logic, the soothsayer understands that, during the Year of the Horse, the Macao SAR Government must introduce new reforms in education. At the same time, schools and educational institutions must also adopt new teaching philosophies and methods, improve teacher training and optimize the allocation of educational resources, in order to increase the competitiveness of talents.
“As Macau does not have a unified entrance examination system throughout the territory, and this is a year of Fire generating the Earth, education services will have new plans”, he further predicts.
 
Warning about “frequent” scams
On the other hand, Mickey Hung highlights the area of ​​public security, warning that cases of fraud “will likely remain frequent” in the Year of the Horse, as “the energy of Bing Wu (Fire Horse) is strong in the Year of the Horse, and the Internet (belonging to Fire) will see a growing ‘empty fire’”.
"Old alcohol in new bottles is a particularly effective strategy for deceiving mentally vulnerable citizens. This phenomenon also warns the Government and law enforcement authorities to intensify actions to combat fraudulent activities and improve public safety awareness," it continues.
Generally speaking, the “Feng Shui” expert also used the “Ba Zi” (the Four Pillars of Destiny) of the establishment of the Macao SAR to predict the opportunities and crises that the territory will face in the Year of the Horse. In this theory, the Macao SAR's “Ba Zi” is composed of “Ji Mao” (year), “Bing Zi” (month), “Bing Wu” (day) and “Wu Zi” (hour).
According to reports, the Beginning of Spring (Lichun) for this year is February 4, 2026, at 4:03 am. In this context, “according to the ‘Ba Zi’ of the Macao SAR establishment, the Master of the Day is Bing Fogo, born in the month Zi (Rat)”.
"Zi is the official month, but unfortunately, the 'Official Star' lacks a 'Star of Wealth' to generate it. Furthermore, it suffers the impact of 'Wu' (Horse) and a penalty from 'Mao' (Rabbit). The gaming industry belongs to Water, while the Horse corresponds to Fire. Water and Fire clash, so the challenges that the gaming industry will face should not be underestimated", he emphasizes.
"The clash pattern between Water and Fire could make the gaming sector weak, with the stability of capital chains worrying. Especially under intensified market competition, the risk of a financial crisis will increase significantly", he emphasizes in the same forecasts, but in another form of analysis.
Also based on “Ba Zi”, the real estate sector could see improvements, predicts the soothsayer, adding that “market demand for properties could increase, which will lead to higher transaction volumes and bring impetus to economic prosperity”.
“At the same time, the development of the health industry will benefit from technological advances, with the fruits of scientific research gradually gaining recognition, which will further drive market expansion in traditional Chinese medicine, medical services and healthcare”, he highlights.
 
Cooperation with the PLP requires “active measures”
On the other hand, this time, Mickey Hung also made specific projections regarding the Macao SAR's fortunes and misfortunes as a Sino-Lusophone platform and in cooperation with Portuguese Speaking Countries (PLP).
"According to 'Feng Shui' analysis, Portugal is located north of Macau. In the Year of the Horse, the corresponding direction is associated with the 'White Star Six', symbolizing controversies and disputes. Therefore, in the Year of the Horse, Portuguese politics may see many disputes. This may not only affect Sino-Portuguese cooperative relations, but also cause conflicts of interest, hindering friendly development", warns Mickey Hung.
To “mitigate these potential conflicts”, the “Feng Shui” master suggests that the Macao SAR Government take “active measures”, such as “organizing cultural forums or study trips” to “increase cultural exchange between the two parties”. “Initiatives of this kind can promote intellectual exchange, deepen mutual understanding, help build more stable cooperative relationships and effectively reduce misunderstandings and conflicts”, he maintains.
In this area, Mickey Hung also mentions that the current President of the Portuguese Republic, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, whose term is coming to an end, is a Head of State “oriented towards people with very good relations with China”. “From his ‘Ba Zi’, he has positive energy”, he highlights, stressing the conviction that Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa “can maintain good Sino-Portuguese commercial relations”.
 
Pressure, challenges and overcoming for Macao SAR leaders
Mickey Hung also once again analyzed the work luck of the Chief Executive and the five Secretaries of the Macao SAR, but this time using “Chinese esoteric nomenology”.
In relation to the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai (岑浩輝), whose Chinese zodiac sign is the Tiger, the master begins by describing, “from a naming perspective, the character ‘Sam’ (岑) belongs to Earth, ‘Hou’ (浩) to Water and ‘Fai’ (輝) to Fire”.
“The ‘Five Elements’ of this name form a pattern of Earth restricting Water and Water restricting Fire, that is, a configuration of consumption, implying significant work pressure that requires personal involvement”, highlights the diviner.
Specifically, it indicates that, in the Year of the Horse, the energy of Fire will be “extremely strong” for people born in the Year of the Tiger. "The clash between Water and Fire will intensify. Therefore, [the Chief Executive] needs to pay attention to cardiovascular and eye health", he advises.
"Strong Fire generates Earth, while Earth is the 'Official Astro', beneficial for exercising authority. However, excessive Fire can lead to impulsive decision-making. It is advisable to face challenges firmly", he highlights. Furthermore, he predicts, in terms of “luck at work”, that Sam Hou Fai's leadership capacity will “increase”, but warns that his subordinates “will be likely to get involved in problems”. In this sense, he recommends “more coordination and communication”.
In turn, the Secretary for Administration and Justice, Wong Sio Chak (黃少澤), has the Monkey as his sign. According to Mickey Hung, from a naming perspective, the character “Wong” (黃) belongs to Earth, “Sio” (少) to Gold and “Chak” (澤) to Water. "This is a very ideal flow pattern. The 'Five Elements' of this name follow a productive sequence, indicating intelligence, flexibility and good adaptability", he analyzes.
Regarding health, Mickey Hung suggests the Secretary for Administration and Justice to “pay attention to lung and respiratory health”. As for work, he considers that “excessive Fire and Earth can result in an increase in the workload”. However, he predicts that “the Earth-Gold-Water productive sequence can dissolve the pressure, allowing overcoming through professional skills”.
In general, he considers that, for Wong Sio Chak, judicial and legal matters are areas in which work results “will be easily achieved” in 2026. However, he anticipates that “details may provoke disputes”, recommending the Secretary to be careful with “lapses in documentation”.
Regarding the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip (戴建業), whose zodiac sign is the Monkey, according to Chinese nomenology, “Tai” (戴) corresponds to Fire, and both “Kin” (建) and “Ip” (業) belong to Wood. For Mickey Hung, this combination “forms a bright pattern between Wood and Fire, indicating a strong career motivation and pioneering ability”.
"The Fire of the year is strong. The Wood and Fire of this name become excessively flaming, easily causing problems with liver fire and sleep problems", he points out. Por outro lado, o adivinho sugere a Tai Kin Ip que “aproveite a força da equipa e evite decisões autocráticas”. “As decisões durante este Verão requerem cautela especial”, sublinha.
In his analysis of the Secretary for Economy and Finance, the “Feng Shui” master also points out that “Fire is the ‘Star of Wealth’, beneficial for promoting economic policies”. However, as “strong Fire restricts Gold, with Gold being the element of the Monkey sign”, the diviner argues that this ruler needs to “prevent the impact of international financial fluctuations on the local economy”.
Regarding Chan Tsz King (陳子勁), Secretary for Security, whose sign is the Dog, from a naming perspective, “Chan” (陳) belongs to Fire, “Tsz” (子) to Water and “King” to Wood, a combination that “forms a pattern of simultaneous production and restriction”, says Mickey Hung.
"The Fire of the year is strong, intensifying the clash between Water and Fire within this name. It is necessary to pay attention to kidney and urinary system health. On the other hand, as strong Fire generates Earth (Earth Xu) and Earth generates Gold (Geng Gold), the area of ​​security may encounter sudden incidents, but can overcome dangers through discipline", he notes, considering that teamwork is "fundamental" for Chan Tsz King this year. For the master of “Feng Shui”, the Secretary for Security must “avoid internal conflicts” and will see his luck become “softer” in the Autumn, “when Gold is strong”.
For her part, the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam (柯嵐), has the Tiger sign. Mickey Hung also made an analysis based on Chinese nomenology, according to which “O” (柯) belongs to Madeira and “Lam” (嵐) to Earth, constituting “a pattern of Madeira restricting Earth, indicating overcoming in the midst of competition”.
"But, it is necessary to prevent interpersonal friction. Furthermore, the strong Fire of the year drains Wood (Jia Yin) and generates Earth, slightly alleviating the conflict between Wood and Earth, which will be beneficial for the implementation of cultural and educational policies. On the other hand, Fire is the 'Star of Talent', full of inspiration. However, excessive Fire can result in excessively rapid execution of plans. It is advisable to advance in stages", he proposes.
In the health chapter, the master states that the Secretary must “pay attention to problems of the spleen, stomach and digestion”. “As the Wood restricting the Earth is moderated by the Fire of the year, the general health is stable” for O Lam, he predicts.
As he describes, also in the Year of the Horse, the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam – Tam Vai Man (譚偉文), whose zodiac sign is the Rat, will see the “moment of the ‘Five Elements’” in his “not soft” name. This requires the Secretary to prevent “communication barriers”, points out the diviner, explaining that “Tam” (譚) is associated with Fire, “Vai” (偉) with Earth and “Man” (文) with Water.
For the “Feng Shui” master, Raymond Tam should “pay attention to blood circulation and kidney health”, since “the strong Fire of the year generates Earth, while Earth will seriously restrict Water”.
"The year Geng Zi meets Bing Wu, constituting a clash between Zi and Wu and conflicts between the Pillars of the Year and Destiny. Consequently, the areas of works and transport will be likely to experience delays or sudden situations, requiring advance contingency plans. Furthermore, the pressure will multiply, but Fire and Earth generate Gold (Geng Gold), thus allowing crises to be resolved through experience", projects Mickey Hung, when analyzing the luck of the Secretary for Transport and Public Works in the Year of the Horse.</description><pubDate>2026-02-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Retail sector “optimistic” for the holiday period</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sector-retalho-optimista-para-periodo-de-feriados/</link><description>The tourism sector believes that both the flow of customers and the volume of business “will be higher than in the previous Chinese New Year”, said Yeong Keng Hoi, president of the Industrial and Commercial Federation of the Islands of Macau, to the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper. Although consumption in the retail sector may be “modest”, as noted by Penny Wan, from the University of Tourism, the truth is that Yeong Keng Hoi said he is “optimistic”, especially because the number of visitors has been increasing. In his opinion, the tourist segment from Mainland China “will not save on costs”. Economist Henry Lei does not go that far, pointing out that in general tourists remain “cautious”, but believes that there are three factors that “could bring a slight increase in ‘per capita’ expenditure”

Catarina Pereira
 
The tourism sector expects greater spending power from visitors during the Chinese New Year festive period, which began yesterday and runs until February 23, said the president of the Industrial and Commercial Federation of the Islands of Macau, Yeong Keng Hoi, to the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper. Economist Henry Lei also believes that during the Lunar New Year there will be greater demand for consumption. However, the retail sector is expected to be the least strong, pointed out Penny Wan, professor at the Macau Tourism University (UTM), something with which Yeong Keng Hoi agrees.
“I believe that the spending power of visitors will be better during Chinese New Year, taking into account the current economic situation in Mainland China,” said Yeong Keng Hoi in statements to this newspaper. As Macau “continues to be very attractive” for visitors from Mainland China, he continued, “I believe that this group of visitors will not save on costs”.
The association leader predicted that the visitors' consumption model will continue, pointing out, for example, that in the restaurant sector they will continue to prefer “light food and street cuisine”. On the other hand, he noted, some restaurants will choose to close their doors during the festive season. “As for the restaurants that will keep their doors open, business will be very good,” predicted Yeong Keng Hoi.
“However, compared to the restaurant sector, retail establishments may suffer more significantly from the impacts caused by various internal and external factors”, noted the president of the Industrial and Commercial Federation of the Islands of Macau.
It should be noted that per capita spending by visitors to Macau fell by more than 7% between 2024 and 2025, suffering the third consecutive annual drop. In absolute terms, excluding gambling, total expenditure exceeded 80 billion patacas, an increase of around 6% resulting from the increase in the number of visitors.
Henry Lei noted that in the fourth quarter of last year, “per capita tourism expenditure stabilized.” “Therefore, I expect the value to remain stable in the first quarter of 2026, or with a slight increase due to the Chinese New Year and the consequent greater demand for consumption”, he added.
“Overall, tourists remain cautious, but the appreciation of the RMB, together with the festive atmosphere and the expected increase in prices, may bring a slight increase in tourists’ per capita expenditure,” said the economist.
Listing a series of reasons for more conservative consumption, Henry Lei spoke of the negative effects on wealth faced by property owners in China, given the huge adjustment in property prices. Furthermore, “despite achieving real GDP growth of 5% in 2025 in China, this value is still lower than the level of 6.8% and 6.1% in 2018 and 2019”, which, together with “geopolitical uncertainties” leads to people being “reluctant to spend as they did a few years ago”.
“Last but not least, as it has become much more convenient to travel to Macau and multiple entry is also allowed for tourists from Hengqin, expenses per trip will decrease,” he added.
Still, Henry Lei says that “recently, many tourists visit Macau to do their shopping and prepare for Chinese New Year, for example, they buy items needed for the festivities and gifts for friends and family”. Furthermore, during the Lunar New Year, “they tend to spend money on fireworks for good luck, before going to the casinos”.
Penny Wan, for her part, pointed out that “hotel occupancy rates will certainly increase, restaurants in tourist areas will be full, especially since many of them are not open during the holidays, but non-tourist areas will not benefit much”. As for integrated resorts, “they will benefit most”, while “retail could benefit, but modest consumption is expected”.
In Yeong Keng Hoi's view, however, the retail sector is confident. "I think that, compared to the same period last year, both the flow of customers and the turnover [in general] will be higher than in the previous Chinese New Year. This is because, recently, the number of visitors has increased compared to last year, and the volume is on an increasing trend. Therefore, the retail sector is optimistic about this period," he explained.
Looking at the last weekends in the territory, the association leader recalled that there has been “a high number of visitors”. As for the Lunar New Year, he stressed that, both on the Peninsula and on the Islands, there will be pedestrian areas, which, “will certainly attract a large flow of visitors”. It is recalled that the director of Tourism Services, Helena de Senna Fernandes, predicted that Macau should receive between 1.4 and 1.5 million visitors during the Chinese New Year period. On Saturday, 146,964 visitors entered the territory.
The possibility of the weather being cold at this time of year “may make the willingness of residents of Mainland China to visit uncertain”, said Yeong Keng Hoi. For now, the days have been hot, but according to forecasts from the Meteorological and Geophysical Services, from Tuesday onwards, the minimum will drop from 19º Celsius to 17º Celsius, while the maximum will drop from 26º Celsius to 22º Celsius.
In the luxury segment, however, Yeong Keng Hoi noted that “Macau faces competition from Hainan Province”, which is why this sector “takes a relatively cautious attitude” towards the Chinese New Year. “In this segment, I think it would be satisfactory if the stores were able to maintain the same turnover recorded in the same period last year”, he stated.
 
Customers need “more” incentives to buy
Stressing that “during Chinese New Year, integrated resorts are certainly the ‘must-see’ destinations for visitors, while casinos are the most visited points of interest”, economist Henry Lei noted that “the market expects a good record of gross gaming revenues and, perhaps, another new record after Covid”.
“This tends to bring linking effects and benefits for restaurants, retail stores and luxury brands, especially when tourists are able to win at casinos, as they tend to have an even greater incentive to buy”, he continued.
In Lei's opinion, retail establishments must differentiate themselves, establishing “strong points of sale” and offering something “unique” to attract visitors. “Meanwhile, unlike in the past, purchasing power is not very strong and retailers must set reasonable prices for their products, taking into account the price level of similar products in China, otherwise it will be difficult to attract spending from tourists,” he concluded.
Penny Wan agrees. Admitting that “it is quite difficult” for the retail sector to attract more consumption, since many things can be purchased online, the UTM professor emphasizes that “customers need more incentives to buy here, such as bigger discounts, shopping at outlets, fast courier and delivery services”.
"Retail companies can do more partnerships, such as collaborating with Macau's old shops - for example, a partnership between an ice cream shop and a branded clothing store to encourage cross-spending. Instead of just encouraging spending, this will help strengthen the city's cultural heritage resources, allowing our customers to get to know Macao's old shops, history and culture," he proposed.
In this way, he stressed, “another type of experience is offered to customers”. In Penny Wan's opinion, businesspeople and the Government need to join forces when it comes to “innovation”. “Government support for small businesses – especially those in non-tourist areas – is essential”, he argued.
The professor noted that “nowadays, tourists who come to Macau want to get ‘experiences’”. “Many young people dress up in traditional costumes to enjoy street food, explore local alleys, streets and neighborhoods, take photos and post them on social media,” he added.
In this sense, he considers that the retail sector should pay attention to the younger generation, especially from mainland China, to understand what type of experiences they are looking for. “For example, it is necessary to understand young people dressed in traditional costumes, whether they come to attend concerts, what their itineraries are, behaviors and consumption patterns, etc., to design services and products that attract this younger segment that is looking for different and new experiences”, he further argued.
 
Occupancy rate in hotels must exceed 90%
The director of Tourism Services (DST) said that, “according to previous experience”, the hotel sector estimated that “the final occupancy rate will exceed 90%” during the festive period. Helena de Senna Fernandes, who spoke on the sidelines of the Chinese New Year Parade blessing ceremony, said, on the other hand, that “until now, hotel room prices are at the equivalent of the level seen in the same period of previous years”. He also stated that the authorities have already warned the sector to pay attention to situations on social media, pointing out that, “if abnormal situations are discovered, or drastic increases in hotel room prices, DST will monitor the situation on developed platforms”.</description><pubDate>2026-02-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Party city~</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cidade-em-festa-2/</link><description>Several activities will mark the arrival of the Chinese New Year, with emphasis on two Parades, which are expected to attract close to 80,000 spectators. Furthermore, there are fireworks shows, an exhibition of traditional flowers at Tap Seac and singing, dancing and magic displays at ZAPE
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The first of the two parades scheduled to celebrate the arrival of the New Year of the Horse is expected to have between 70,000 and 80,000 spectators along the route, according to estimates from the Tourism Services Directorate (DST).
The organization's director, Helena de Senna Fernandes, presented these numbers during the blessing ceremony that serves to wish the event success, revealing that preparations “are progressing at a good pace”.
The processions are scheduled for two days, the first being next Thursday, February 19th, starting at Praça do Lago Sai Van, and the second, on Saturday 28th, in the North Zone of the city. Both start at 8pm.
17 floats will participate together with around 1,300 artists from Macau, Hong Kong, Mainland China, Portugal, Spain, Italy, Philippines and Korea. The decorated platforms will pass through Dr. Sun Yat-Sen Avenue and the Science Center, arriving at Fisherman's Wharf.
The DST allegory will come into play at the end, when the main stage will host artists celebrating Cantonese pop music and elements of K-pop. Following the exhibition, there will be a “show” starring drones with fireworks. A total of 3,888 remotely piloted aircraft will join the fireworks.
The floats will be on display at Doca dos Pescadores, between the 20th and 27th of February, and at Praça do Tap Seac, between the 1st and 8th of March, and the light installations will be switched on daily between 5pm and 10pm.
On the third day of the Lunar New Year, between 5:30 pm and 8:00 pm, there will be dance, singing and magic displays on Rua de Cantão/Shanghai and ZAPE.
In addition, ZAPE will host, until March 1st, the “Gala a gallop” event, in the area between Rua de Cantão and Rua de Beijing, with installations characteristic of the festive season. The objective, according to DST, is “to increase the festive atmosphere and tourist attraction, attracting people to community neighborhoods, in order to promote consumption and achieve a good interaction between tourist promotion and community development”.
The thematic zone activity will involve the participation of ZAPE traders, with a view to launching exclusive benefits, also offering additional prizes, including accommodation in starred hotels, restaurants and film coupons.
During the Chinese New Year celebrations, which will take place throughout the city and islands, residents and tourists will also be able to watch the golden dragon parade, lion dances and themed traditional flower fairs, large-scale floral art exhibitions and decorative illuminations at Tap Seac Square (until 1 am on the 17th).
Two more fireworks shows are also scheduled, in addition to the “show” with drones on the 19th, now in Macau Tower Bay (23rd February and 3rd March), a “Sports Festival” in Iao Hon (19th), a “Motorcycle and Classic Car Parade” (22nd) and the cultural event “Albergue Wishing Well and Love Tree” in Albergue da Santa Casa da Misericórdia, in São Lázaro.
 
“Mercado da Sorte” will liven up Barra
Until February 26th, Barra will host Chinese New Year celebration activities, organized by MGM. “Barra Lucky Blessing Market” will present new retail, entertainment and creative culture experiences. The program includes a multi-brand store, nostalgic game booths, festive themed installations and craft workshops, in addition to the “Poon Choi Banquet”, which brings together more than 400 guests from community groups, partners and neighboring communities. There will also be a lion dance show, a “God of Fortune in Andas” parade and calligraphy gifts with Spring couplets.</description><pubDate>2026-02-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Drops in investment and domestic demand 'stopped' GDP growth</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/quebras-investimento-na-procura-interna-travaram-crescimento-pib/</link><description>The value of domestic demand fell slightly in 2025 and lost weight in the Gross Domestic Product, having been offset by the increase in net exports of goods and services. According to official data, in a year in which Macau recorded economic growth of 4.7%, the total volume of investment also fell by 7.8%, despite the increase in the public sector
 
SERGIO TERRA
 
Service exports made a positive contribution of 4.2 percentage points to the overall growth of 4.7% in Macau's Gross Domestic Product (GDP) in 2025, in real terms, compared to the previous year, detailed official data shows. According to the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC), which had already released preliminary results at the beginning of this month, the value of GDP reached 418.04 billion patacas, corresponding to 89.6% of the economic volume of 2019.
GDP per capita registered an annual increase of 4.3% to 607,263 patacas, while the implicit deflator of Gross Domestic Product (100.7), which measures global price variation, rose 0.5%.
After growing 7.8% between 2023 and 2024, according to data now updated by DSEC, Macau's economy suffered a slowdown in 2025, but exceeded the expectations of the International Monetary Fund, which had anticipated an increase of 2.6%, in a downward revision published in October, six months after projecting an increase of 3.6%.
In 2025, service exports increased by 5.0% year-on-year, driven by the 14.7% growth in the number of visitors. Specifically, exports of gaming services and “other tourist services” rose by 10.0% and 0.1%, respectively. Thus, the weight of net exports of goods and services in the formation of GDP reached 45.4%, 3.1 percentage points more than in 2024.
On the other hand, domestic demand fell 0.5% in terms of value, to 228.12 billion patacas, and saw its weight in GDP drop 3.1 points to 54.6%. The decline was even more noticeable in gross fixed capital formation, taking into account that the weight of investment fell 1.8 points and its volume decreased 7.8%, driven by the 14.1% drop in the private sector, which contrasted with the 4.2% rise in the public sector.
With regard to the private sector, investments in construction and equipment fell by 19.1% and 5.1%, respectively. In the public sector, investment grew 5.6% in construction and fell 2.9% in equipment.
Among the main economic indicators, the 1.3% growth in private consumption expenditure stands out, the weight of which in GDP decreased by 1.0 percentage points compared to 2024. According to DSEC, household final consumption expenditure in the local market and abroad increased by 1.0% and 6.0%, respectively.
In turn, government final consumption expenditure increased by 3.0%, however, its weight fell by 0.3 percentage points. In this area, the organization highlights that employee remuneration and net purchases of goods and services rose by 2.4% and 3.8%, respectively.
Conversely, in foreign trade of goods, exports and imports of goods decreased by 5.0% and 5.3%.
DSEC also confirmed that GDP grew 7.6% to 115.72 billion patacas in the fourth quarter of 2025, in real and annual terms, equivalent to 94.1% of the level reached in the last three months of 2019. Between October and December, the highlights were increases of 9.8% in service exports, 2.1% in government final consumption expenditure, 0.7% in private consumption expenditure and 1.3% in gross fixed capital formation.
The organization also reviewed data from the remaining quarters of 2025, now pointing to a year-on-year contraction of 1.5% between January and March, an increase of 5.2% in the following three months and an increase of 7.3% in the period between July and September.</description><pubDate>2026-02-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Parents fear the effect of electronic payments on children's savings concept</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pais-receiam-efeito-pagamento-electronico-conceito-de-poupanca-das-criancas/</link><description>A survey carried out by the General Union of Residents' Associations reveals that almost 50% of a total of 813 parents of children aged between seven and 12 give their children allowances through electronic payment. However, more than 60% believe that the use of electronic payments is weakening children's concept of money, while 36% are concerned that this form of payment may make it difficult to create the habit of saving.
 
In order to understand the current situation regarding the allocation of allowances to children, the General Union of Residents' Associations of Macau (“Kaifong”) surveyed 813 parents of children aged between seven and 12 years old. As revealed by the “Kaifong”, the survey shows that, in general, almost 50% of those interviewed give their children allowances through electronic payment. However, more than 60% believe that the use of electronic payments is weakening children's concept of money.
Furthermore, more than 50% of respondents expressed concern about consequences such as “difficulties in mastering real wealth” and “unlimited spending”. On the other hand, 36% of guardians are afraid that electronic payments “will make it difficult to create the habit of saving” among children.
According to the Chinese-language press, the survey also shows that, currently, Macau children aged between seven and 10 still receive mainly cash allowances, with only between 25% and 38% of parents of children in this age group giving their children allowances through electronic payment.
However, among children aged 11, more than half receive allowances in electronic payment, while this percentage reaches 71% among children aged 12.
On the other hand, more than 80% of respondents usually plan how to use their allowance with their children. Furthermore, when children have spent their entire allowance, more than 50% of parents “will review the expenses together with their children”, while 30% “do not immediately add” more allowance.
In conclusion, the association highlighted that the period between the ages of seven and 12 is crucial for the formation of children's views on money, and therefore appealed to parents to take advantage of the allowance to promote financial education.
Furthermore, the “Kaifong” suggested that the concept of physical money be established among children as early as primary school and that electronic payment tools should only be gradually introduced as children's age increases, with these tools having to have a monitoring function.
Understanding that the allocation of allowance must be subject to a fixed day and amount, the association also hopes that the Government will include financial education for children in school curricula.</description><pubDate>2026-02-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Wynn made more, but made less profit</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/wynn-facturou-mais-mas-lucrou-menos/</link><description>Wynn Macau's profitability fell by almost 16% in 2025, despite operating revenues registering residual growth to around 30 billion patacas, according to data released by the Wynn Resorts group
 
SERGIO TERRA
 
Wynn Macau closed the 2025 financial year with operating profits of 566.54 million US dollars (around 4.56 billion patacas at the current exchange rate), a value that deducts non-monetary expenses linked to depreciation and amortization, and reflects an annual decline of 15.7%. According to Wynn Resorts, the majority shareholder of the Macau operator, earnings before interest, taxes, amortization and depreciation (EBITDA), which comply with American accounting standards, fell 7.7% to US$1.09 billion (8.73 billion patacas).
The drop in profits contrasted with a residual improvement in operating income. Throughout 2025, the company's operating revenues rose 1% to almost US$3.72 billion (29.93 billion patacas), including US$2.31 billion at Wynn Palace (up 4%) and US$1.41 billion at Wynn Macau (minus 3.7%).
Between October and December, the company's EBITDA fell 7.5% to US$270.95 billion (2.18 billion patacas) and operating revenues increased 4.4% to US$967.77 million (7.79 billion patacas). According to Craig Billings, CEO of Wynn Resorts, the fourth quarter results showed “significant growth” in the volume of bets in the company's casinos in Macau, however, the retention rate was “exceptionally low, both in the VIP segment and in the mass segment”.
At Wynn Macau, ‘house’ success rates fell, in the space of a year, from 5.01% to 3.49% in the VIP segment and from 17.9% to 17% at mass market tables. Wynn Palace experienced a similar scenario, recording drops from 3.51% to 2.84% and from 26.0% to 21.8%, respectively.
The drop in the retention rate of VIP bets “cost us a little more than 16 million dollars in EBITDA in the quarter”, highlighted Billings, in a conference call with analysts to discuss the financial results, also pointing to the increase in operational expenses as another factor that affected profits. “Furthermore, there hasn’t really been any fundamental change in the business,” he assured, stressing that “the VIP segment can be incredibly unstable.”
In general, Billings was satisfied with the performance of the Wynn Resorts group, which ended the year with net profits of 327.33 million dollars (down 34.7%) and revenues of 7.14 billion (plus 0.1%). “The fourth quarter results reflect continued strength across all businesses and steady progress in our global development initiatives,” he said in a statement, highlighting again the “substantial increases” in gaming business in Macau, both in the VIP and mass market sectors.
During the conference call, Billings also stated that “the good momentum” in Macau extended into 2026, with trading volume in January “slightly above” the fourth quarter of 2025. “Looking ahead to the rest of 2026, following the sustained double-digit growth in gross gaming revenues across the market in the second half of 2025, we remain optimistic about the future of Macau,” he declared, noting that the operator is “always well positioned” in the ‘premium’ segment, which “continues to lead the market”.
The CEO revealed, by the way, that the Macao SAR Government authorized Wynn Palace to reopen, in time for Chinese New Year, the “Chairman’s Club”, a premium gaming area, whose area has now tripled to almost 9,290 square meters. “The space includes gaming areas, along with various amenities, such as sophisticated restaurants and bars, entertainment areas, a cigar lounge and a bar,” he added.</description><pubDate>2026-02-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Melco “secures” City of Dreams Manila</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/melco-segura-city-dreams-manila/</link><description>Melco will maintain its participation in City of Dreams Manila, revealed Lawrence Ho. After an “evaluation of strategic alternatives”, the group’s executive director felt that none of the options “would allow us to fully exploit the value and potential” of the resort
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
In a turnaround regarding its investments in Manila, Melco decided to hold its 50% stake in City of Dreams located in the Philippine capital, after an “evaluation of strategic alternatives”. During a conference call with investment analysts, Lawrence Ho, executive director of Melco, explained that the group “did not feel that any of the options would allow us to fully realize the value and potential of the property”. He also stated that he was confident “that the business will recover”, promising a future reassessment of the situation.
It is recalled that, last year, Melco had initiated contacts with “potential buyers” of the gaming operator's stake in the City of Dreams Manila resort, whose financial results were being affected by an “intensified competitive environment”.
On the call, Lawrence Ho also spoke about the “strong start of 2026 in the Macau market”, with an annual increase of 24% in terms of gross gaming revenues, and with “a growing market share in the first quarter so far”. He also noted that this year's Chinese New Year looks strong compared to 2025. He also mentioned that the company's efforts to improve the customer experience "have proven to be a successful strategic focus."
Melco's CEO also presented a status report on the concessionaire's plans for 2026, "whose biggest project is the opening of the renovated 'Countdown Hotel'", closed since 2021, with a planned investment equivalent to 100 million US dollars. Lawrence Ho pointed to the reopening of the hotel development for the third quarter of this year, with the expectation that it will “introduce a truly distinctive experience and establish a new benchmark in Macau”, and that it will feature approximately 150 high-luxury suites.
According to Ho, Melco plans to invest around US$450 million throughout this year, with the majority of the funds going to the three resorts located in Macao. Lawrence Ho mentioned that the company has started the “renovation of the retail area of ​​Macau’s City of Dreams” and plans to “improve” the restaurant offering in the complex.
Melco recorded net profits of 185 million US dollars (1.49 billion patacas at current exchange rates) in 2025, four times more than in the previous year. Earnings before interest, taxes, amortization and depreciation (EBITDA) grew 17.2% to 1.43 billion US dollars. “In Macau, EBITDA grew 25% year-on-year, reaching US$1.23 billion in 2025, driven by more robust gaming revenues and margins”, highlighted Lawrence Ho.</description><pubDate>2026-02-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MICE expanded economic impact</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mice-ampliou-impacto-economico/</link><description>With the number of conventions and exhibitions growing by 22% and participants and visitors rising by 11%, revenue generated by events in the MICE sector for non-gaming areas increased by 16% to almost 6.3 billion between 2024 and 2025, according to official data
 
Revenues from Macau's non-gaming sectors of economic activity derived from convention and exhibition events (MICE) reached around 6.28 billion patacas in 2025, a figure that represents an annual increase of 16.4%, announced the Statistics and Census Bureau (DSEC). The annual growth was due to events promoted in the fourth quarter, a period in which these revenues increased 86.6% to 2.58 billion in the year-on-year comparison.
According to data released by DSEC, non-gaming per capita expenditure made by visitors to conventions and exhibitions was estimated at 4,821 patacas in the fourth quarter and 4,572 patacas in the general calculation of 2025, reflecting increases of 17.6% and 5.8%, respectively.
In 2025, Macau hosted 1,861 conventions, exhibitions and incentive events (337 more or 22.1% than in 2024), with around 1.47 million participants and visitors (10.7% more). In the year under review, 1,737 meetings and conferences were held (22.1% more), with 218,300 participants (19.2% more) and an average duration of 1.2 days. In terms of exhibitions, 65 events took place (6.6% more), with almost 1.25 million visitors (10% more), according to information provided by the organizing entities. In addition, there were 59 incentive events (47.5% more), with 7,700 participants (42.7% less).
The exhibitions attracted 7,369 exhibitors (3.9% more) and 82,241 professional visitors (56.2% more) in 2025. According to DSEC, 387 exhibitors (60.6% more) and 680 professional visitors (166.7% more) came from Portuguese-speaking countries.
In the fourth quarter of 2025 alone, 564 conventions and exhibitions were held (an increase of 21.3%) with 487 thousand participants and visitors (an increase of 50.4%).</description><pubDate>2026-02-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>AL will analyze “failures” in digital integration with the Government</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/al-vai-analisar-governo-falhas-na-integracao-digital/</link><description>Some deficiencies in the integration of e-governance platforms will lead the Monitoring Committee for Public Administration Affairs to analyze the issue with the Government. The decision follows a consultation with associations linked to areas such as social services, education, culture and sport
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The Monitoring Committee for Public Administration Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (AL) held several internal meetings to monitor the integration of e-governance applications and services and will call on the Government to analyze failures in the digital integration of applications and services.
In order to collect opinions on the user experience and suggestions for improvement for the aforementioned services, the Commission hopes, “through monitoring and collaboration, to promote the global integration and ease of use of electronic services, in order to accelerate the digitalization of governance, deepen the reform of public administration and effectively respond to society's requests”, according to the President of the Commission, Ma Chi Seng, cited in a statement.
The first session served to define the issues to be monitored this year by the specialized groups, namely, “measures to optimize passage at the Hengqin Border Post” and “integration of e-governance applications and services”.
Regarding the “integration of electronic government applications and services”, the Commission created a specialized group, coordinated by deputy Kou Kam Fai, which has already requested the presence of association members from different sectors, namely social services, education, culture, sport, liberal professions and youth, “in order to study solutions to promote the ease of use of electronic services”, says the AL note.
According to the elements present at the meeting, the Government has invested in promoting electronic governance, and achieved good results. However, they detect some gaps with the widespread application of artificial intelligence, considering that “electronic governance must be improved, as there are public services that are not yet provided online and some of them are not integrated into the Single Account or the Platform for Companies and Associations”.
The representatives hope that the Government and the competent services will continue to improve the experience of using electronic services, “pursuing the philosophy of administrative simplification and making life easier for the population”.
In the next stage, the Commission will hold specific meetings with representatives of the competent services, to learn about the implementation of policies on electronic governance, difficulties and planning, and jointly analyze improvement measures.</description><pubDate>2026-02-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UM launches Robotics Laboratory with Hong Kong Polytechnic</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/um-lanca-laboratorio-de-robotica-politecnica-de-hong-kong/</link><description>Strengthening collaborative innovation in higher education and scientific research in the Greater Bay Area was the basis for the creation of the Robotics and Embedded Intelligence Laboratory, established between the University of Macau and the Hong Kong Polytechnic University. The project joins the launch of another program on cutting-edge technologies and high-level talent development
 
The University of Macau (UM) and the Hong Kong Polytechnic University (PolyU) signed an agreement to create the first joint project, which aims to strengthen collaborative innovation in higher education and scientific research in the Greater Bay Area.
The Joint Robotics and Embodied Intelligence Laboratory brings together UM's strengths in interdisciplinary research, artificial intelligence and engineering with PolyU's expertise in applied sciences and engineering practice.
The established agreement “will promote fundamental research and technology transfer in cutting-edge areas, such as intelligent robotics and embedded artificial intelligence”, according to the UM rector at the launch ceremony.
Yonghua Song added that the partnership will continue the long-standing collaboration between the two universities in the field of research, serving as a “strategic platform for training high-quality innovative talents”.
On the same occasion, UM and PolyU announced the creation of a dual doctoral program with joint supervision by faculty members from both sides, “marking a significant step in collaboration on cutting-edge technologies and the development of high-level talent.” The program is now open for applications.
The four-year double doctorate is jointly supervised by faculty members from those institutions and students will have the opportunity to study and carry out research in Macau and Hong Kong, receiving doctoral degrees upon graduation.
The initiative aims to harmonize efforts to leverage the disciplinary and technological strengths of both institutions and establish an internationally competitive doctoral training model for the Greater Bay Area, “thus supporting China's high-quality development and world-class research centers,” said Yonghua Song.
In turn, PolyU President Teng Jin-Guang said that the launch of the laboratory and the dual doctoral program “reflect the common vision of UM and PolyU to promote cutting-edge innovation in robotics and embedded intelligence, strengthen cross-border collaboration in research, and train high-caliber talents for the development of the Greater Bay Area.”
After the agreement was signed, the laboratory was formally inaugurated, with faculty members from both universities soon presenting the initial collaborative projects.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2026-02-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SME bad debt reaches 5.3 billion</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/malparado-das-pme-atinge-53-mil-milhoes/</link><description>At the end of 2025, small and medium-sized companies in Macau accumulated around 5.3 billion patacas in non-performing loans, according to official data that reflect an annual decline of 1%
 
The total value of unpaid loans by small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) in the Macao SAR amounted to 5.29 billion patacas at the end of 2025, which is equivalent to an annual decrease of 1% and a semi-annual drop of 6.3%, according to data revealed by the Monetary Authority (AMCM). Between 2023 and 2034, non-performing loans for SMEs, which involve payments of interest and/or principal that are more than three months late, had risen by 83.2%.
Despite the improvement seen in 2025, unpaid debts remain at a very high level, especially when compared to the pre-pandemic period. According to AMCM data, outstanding loans grew 32 times or 5.21 billion compared to the end of 2019.
The unpaid debt ratio – the proportion of loans with outstanding payments in relation to the total credit granted to SMEs – stood at 7.9% at the end of 2025. This percentage represents a semi-annual increase of 0.3 percentage points, an annual increase of 1.1 points and a growth of 7.7 points compared to 2019.
AMCM took the opportunity to reiterate that “it encourages the banking sector to negotiate flexible repayment plans with SMEs, under the principle of prudent risk management and in accordance with its own credit policies, continuing to provide credit support to customers with liquidity difficulties”.
At the end of the second half of 2025, the new credit limit approved by banks reached 4.52 billion patacas, marking a drop of 8.4% compared to the first half of the year and a year-on-year increase of 35.3%. The guarantee ratio, that is, the proportion of credit limit with promised tangible assets, stood at 25.7%, corresponding to decreases of 36.5 percentage points in six months and 51 points in the space of one year.
On the other hand, the used balance of loans to SMEs (67.32 billion) fell by 9.7% and 13.9% in half-yearly and annual terms, respectively. Between June and December 2025, loans granted to the wholesale and retail trade sector increased by 4.3%, while the restaurants, hotels and similar and construction sectors recorded declines of 12.5% ​​and 8.7%, respectively.
The utilization rate – proportion of the balance of outstanding credits in relation to the approved credit limit – grew 0.2 percentage points to 85%, compared to the previous six months. The annual comparison translates into an increase of 1.4 percentage points.
 
S.T.</description><pubDate>2026-02-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Credit cards register increasing use</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cartoes-de-credito-registam-crescente-utilizacao/</link><description>stack of multicolored credit cards on black background



Credit used with payment cards in Macau exceeded 6.5 billion patacas in the last quarter of 2025, illustrating an annual increase of 5.6%, according to official data. Non-performing credit on cards fell 3.6% to 69.5 million
 
The value of credit used in the fourth quarter of 2025 amounted to 6.55 billion patacas, marking an annual increase of 5.6% and a quarterly increase of 3.5%, reveal data from the Monetary Authority (AMCM). Cash advances (147.7 million) fell by 6.2% in the space of one year and were equivalent to 2.3% of the credit used between October and December.
The number of credit card transactions (13.97 million) increased by 6.4% in three months and 10.2% in annual terms. The reimbursement amount (6.34 billion), including interest and expenses, fell by 1.6% and 2.9%, respectively, on the same comparative basis.
On debit cards (excluding cash withdrawals), the number of transactions (1.94 million) grew by 62% and 11.1% in annual and quarterly terms, respectively. The amount involved (520.67 million) fell 5.8% in one year, but rose 9.4% in three months.
AMCM statistics also reveal that the total value of outstanding debt for more than three months on credit cards issued by local banks amounted to 69.51 million patacas at the end of December, signaling an annual decline of 3.6% and a quarterly drop of 3%. Even so, bad credit remains well above the 48.13 million recorded at the end of 2019, the pre-pandemic year.
Debt with arrears of between three and six months reached 11.18 million, falling 16.2% in one year and 24.6% in relation to the previous quarter.
Between October and December, the unpaid debt ratio, measured based on amounts outstanding for more than three months against the balance of debts, dropped 0.2 points to 2.5%, compared to the end of September.
The credit limit on cards (50.86 billion) increased by 1.9% in annual terms and 0.7% in three months, with the debt balance standing at 2.80 billion. The rollover balance (775.78 million) was equivalent to 27.7% of debts receivable.
 
Almost 104 million mobile payments
On the other hand, between October and December, the number of mobile payment transactions in Macau (103.8 million) grew 3.8% in annual terms and 7.4% in quarterly terms.
According to AMCM, transactions involved 8.9 billion patacas, representing an annual increase of 7.5% and a quarterly increase of 5.4%. The average value per transaction reached MOP85.4 in the quarter under review.
At the end of December, 111,223 devices accepted mobile payments and “QR Code” support in Macau, representing an annual growth of 2.1%.
 
S.T.</description><pubDate>2026-02-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Patrick Dumont named CEO of Las Vegas Sands</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/patrick-dumont-nomeado-ceo-da-las-vegas-sands/</link><description>Patrick Dumont will assume the role of president and executive director of Las Vegas Sands (LVS) from March 1st, succeeding Robert G. Goldstein, who will serve as the company's senior consultant until March 2028, confirmed the North American group, which holds around 75% of Sands China's capital. Dumont, 51 years old, son-in-law of Sheldon Adelson, the group's late founder, was also named president of Sands China. “It is a true honor for me to serve as president and CEO of this iconic company founded by one of the industry's greatest visionaries,” said Patrick Dumont in a statement, stressing that, “under the leadership of Sheldon Adelson and Rob Goldstein, Sands has reached extraordinary heights.” Dumont joined LVS in 2010, was appointed president and chief operating officer in January 2021 and has been a member of the board of directors since 2017. He is responsible for the company's new venture in Singapore, an $8 billion Marina Bay Sands expansion project that began construction in July 2025. In March last year, the LVS board of directors had already indicated that Dumont would be the likely successor to Goldstein, who had led the group since January 2021, following Adelson's death.</description><pubDate>2026-02-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Storms in Portugal damaged more than 120 museums and monuments</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/tempestades-em-portugal-danificaram-mais-de-120-museus-monumentos/</link><description>Em Portugal, mais de 120 museus e monumentos sofreram danos causados pelas tempestades nas duas últimas semanas, com cinco equipamentos da Rede Portuguesa de Museus e quatro do património classificado, como o Convento de Cristo, em Tomar, a apresentarem “danos graves”.
De acordo com o Ministério da Cultura, Juventude e Desporto, sofreram “danos graves” o Museu da Ciência da Universidade de Coimbra, o Museu de Arte Pré-Histórica e do Sagrado do Vale do Tejo, em Mação, o Museu Municipal de Santarém – Casa-Museu Anselmo Braamcamp Freire, o Museu da Imagem em Movimento, em Leiria, e o Museu Municipal de Ourém. Na área do património classificado, apresentam “danos graves” a cerca do Convento de Cristo, em Tomar – monumento classificado como Património da Humanidade da UNESCO -, a Casa Museu Afonso Lopes Vieira, em São Pedro de Moel, Marinha Grande, a Capela de Nossa Senhora da Encarnação, em Leiria, e a igreja matriz de Cernache do Bonjardim, na Sertã.
In this balance, in the archives area, for now, the Leiria District Archive is also marked with “serious damage”.
In the Portuguese Museum Network (RPM), with “moderate damage”, there are the Santos Rocha Municipal Museum, in Figueira da Foz, the Francisco Tavares Proença Júnior Museum, in Castelo Branco, the Central do Caldeirão museum nucleus of the Carlos Reis Municipal Museum, in Torres Novas, the Ílhavo Maritime Museum and the Museum of the Roman Villa of Rabaçal, in Penela.
From RPM, according to the published list, the Ourém Municipal Museum, the Anselmo Braamcamp Freire House-Museum, in Santarém, the moving image museum, in Leiria, and the museum nucleus of the Carlos Reis Museum, in Torres Novas, are closed to the public. The Science Museum of the University of Coimbra is “partially closed”.
Of the approximately two dozen pieces of RPM equipment flagged by the Ministry of Culture, there are also the National Railway Museum, in Entroncamento, the Almedina Tower of the Coimbra Municipal Museum, the Marrazes School Museum, in Leiria, and the Cantanhede Stone Museum. These equipment, according to the report, have “slight damage”, requiring intervention, and are open to the public.
The Santa Joana Museum, in Aveiro, the Leonel Trindade Municipal Museum, in Torres Vedras, the Wool Museum, in Covilhã, and the Batalha Municipal Community Museum, with no damage to the buildings, are open, most without access restrictions.
In the list of classified heritage, Leiria has the largest number of buildings with “moderate damage”, including the Castle, the mansion and garden of the viscount of Barreira, the Chapel of São Pedro, the Church and Convent of São Francisco, the Cathedral, including cloister, surrounding churchyard, bell tower and bell ringer's house, the Church of Misericórdia, the convent and the former seminary of Santo Agostinho, the church of Pousos, the sanctuary of Senhor Jesus dos Milagres, the Chapel of S. João Batista de Monte Real and the Lagar Velho Shelter. In the district of Leiria, the Fábrica Lusitana de Vidros Angolana and the former Stephens residence, in Marinha Grande, the two choirs and the cloister of the Church of the Convento do Louriçal, in Pombal, the Castle of Ourém and the church of Urqueira, in the same municipality, are also marked with “moderate damage”.
In Coimbra, there is “moderate damage” to the church and cloister of Misericórdia (Colégio Novo), the New Cathedral, the Botanical Garden and its surroundings, the Church of São Bartolomeu, with “all its integrated heritage”, the churchyard and staircase of the Church of Santa Justa, the old Laboratorio Chimico, currently the Museum Center of the University’s Science Museum, and the Monastery of Santa Clara-a-Velha, which remained submerged by the Mondego River. In the Coimbra region, “moderate damage” is also reported at Penela Castle and, in this location, at the churches of S. Miguel and Santa Eufémia, at the Adães Bermudes School and at the Convent of Santo António, including its fence.
In the district of Santarém, the city walls, the Fortaleza de Abrantes, as well as the chapels of Piedade, São Lourenço and the standard of D. João I, in Tomar, are highlighted. In Sertã, in the district of Castelo Branco, the Seminário das Missões Ultramarinas is marked, also with “moderate damage”, while in Torres Vedras, in the district of Lisbon, there is the Monastery of Varatojo.
With less serious damage compared to these buildings, but in need of intervention, there are close to 60 monuments, such as the monasteries of Alcobaça (including the tombs of Pedro and Inês) and Batalha (tombs of João I and Queen Filipa de Lencastre), both classified by UNESCO. The Monastery of Jesus and the tomb of Santa Joana, in Aveiro, the Ceramics Museum, in Caldas da Rainha, the Paço de Mallorca in Figueira da Foz, the Mercado de Santana, in Leiria, the Monastery of the Poor Clares in Monte Real, the Roman City of Eburobrittium, in Óbidos, and the Roman Forum of Tomar are other buildings that require restoration work.
Likewise, the Palace Hotel do Buçaco and the surrounding forest are highlighted, “including chapels and hermitages, Cruz Alta and everything it contains of historical and artistic interest, together with the Convent of Santa Cruz do Buçaco”, and different areas of the Battle of Aljubarrota Military Field.
On Tuesday last week, for a first assessment of 50 monuments damaged by Storm Kristin, the Minister of Culture, Youth and Sports, Margarida Balseiro Lopes, admitted the need for investment of 20 million euros in recovery works, during a visit to affected areas in the Central Region.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>