<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Health services want to wage use of alternatives to tobacco</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/servicos-de-saude-querem-travar-uso-de-alternativas-ao-tabaco/</link><description>Alternative products to traditional cigarettes may be prohibited, as well as possession of electronic cigarettes. At least, these are the recommendations of health services, in the context of evaluation to the regime of prevention and control of smoking between 2021 and 2023. As for the streets of the city, in some areas with greater concentration of people, such as the cases of the Siege Portas and the São Paulo Ruins Zone, may be allowed to smoke only in certain places, and smoking to walk. All these issues are being studied by the authorities
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Heavy hand is what is expected in the near future in relation to alternative products to traditional cigarettes, with the government to argue that it is necessary to study the change in the law to prohibit these new tobacco products or other non -tabs, but considered equally harmful to health. As for electronic cigarettes, regulation will also be reinforced, including the prohibition of possession of these products. These and other measures were proposed by health services (SSM) in the report on monitoring and evaluation of the smoking prevention and control regime between 2021 and 2023.
Noting that in recent years “new products have emerged on the market”, such as herbal cigarettes or so -called “nicotine bags”, the body points out that “contain toxic substances that harm health”. Regarding water pipes, also known as Shisha, consumption in Macau is prohibited in places where smoking is interdicted, but is not illegal elsewhere. SSM report that restaurants and bars provide “personalized flavors” and showy pipes to attract customers, “especially young people”.
In this sense, and “to prevent herbal cigarettes, nicotine bags and water pipes from becoming popular in Macau and damage public health, their prohibition is advisable as soon as possible”, read the document. Authorities will control these new types of products by reviewing the law, according to Lam Chong, director of the cabinet for prevention and control of smoking and alcoholism to Chinese radio.
Electronic cigarettes - whose manufacture, distribution, sale, import, export and transportation at the entry and exit of the MSAR are prohibited - will also be the target of more limitations. But not for now, since the last review of the law happened in 2022, Lam Chong said. At the time, the possession of electronic cigarettes was not prohibited to “give time” to consumers from consuming the products already purchased, but SSM report that the study “on the timely launch of measures to reinforce the control of electronic cigarettes will be done, including the ban on their possession”. This is, by the way, a request that has been made in society, namely by deputies and considering that more and more young people seem to be consuming these products.
According to the results of the study of tobacco consumption by young people of Macao in 2021, the tobacco consumption rate attributed to young people aged 13 to 15 years is 3.8%, with the study that “the consumption of electronic cigarettes by students is particularly accentuated”. In concrete, the consumption rate of electronic cigarettes among students increased to 4.0%, representing a significant increase over the rate of 2.6% in 2015. A trend that "cannot be ignored."
Another measures suggested in the evaluation report now disclosed include the introduction of “simple packaging” to tobacco products - something that the World Health Organization encourages and has been implemented in 25 countries. In Macao, the authorities consider that there is room for improvement. According to a study cited by the SSM, for example, compared to smokers with normal cigarette packaging, 81% of simple packaging smokers are better able to stop smoking at least once a day, and considering that stopping smoking is something important in life.
Continue to reinforce the promotion of smoking cessation services, as well as raise the effectiveness of services, and to define as the main objective of prevention and control of smoking health promotion, with the dissemination of information about harm with women and young people are other measures indicated in the document.
 
Smoking prohibition can reach the ruins and doors of the siege
SSM also suggest “study the application of the smoking prohibition measure in some streets and squares”. In recent years, "society has expressed the desire for the government to extend areas of outdoor smoking, namely, prohibiting smokers smoke while walking," a request that has been "pressing".
In this context, the report refers to the cases of Singapore, where, since 2019 has been prohibited smoking in the public zones of the famous Orchard Road commercial zone; And from Japan, where in the streets of some cities there are their own cabins to smoke.
Now, in the case of Macao, the streets "are narrow, which makes it difficult to install smokers or large areas for smokers on the tours." Thus, "the most viable solution would be to study the possibility of, in some streets, being allowed to smoke only in certain places, and smoking is prohibited to walk."
This solution can be implemented “experimentally, on the streets and squares with greater flow of people, and after the accumulation of experiments, it can be reviewed and considering the widening of its scope”, the document says.
Regarding the study of the feasibility of delimiting exclusive areas for smoking in streets or places where there is a large concentration of people, Cheang Seng IP, SSM subdirector, spoke, by way of example, from Square Praça do Serco and the São Paulo Ruins Zone. According to said, the body is coordinating the issue with other public services.
Noting that society “is very attentive” to the conduct of smoking when walking, Cheang Seng IP has stated that, since the issue is “urgent”, the authorities hope to achieve the goal of “controlling smoke” even before reviewing the law through the coordination mechanism with other public services.
However, exposure to passive smoke does not only happen in the streets of the territory. According to official data, in 2023, the proportion of the local population exposed to tobacco tobacco at home was 13.8%; Already in restaurants and closed spaces of the workplace was 7.5% and 6.1% respectively. In addition, that year, 64,700 people over 15 years old (11.6% of this population group) consumed tobacco and such products, a 31.4% reduction compared to 16.9% in 2011.
In 2023, yet, the consumption rate of tobacco and related products registered the first increase after the law entered into force in 2011. The general rate of tobacco tobacco consumption and the tobacco consumption rate between men decreased by 2022, while among local women “increased slightly”. An increase that SSM attribute “especially non -resident workers and non -resident students living in Macao”.
 
Casino Kampek is the most targeted in the accusations
Between 2021 and 2023, Health Services (SSM) and the Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ) made 1,732 inspections to the casinos, and 442 accusations were deducted due to infringements of the law. Of these, those made in Kampek Paradise Casino occupy the highest percentage (156 cases, 35.3%), followed by Venetian (44 cases, 10.0%) and City of Dreams (43 cases, 9.7%). Most offenders are tourists (69.5%), and Macao residents occupy 29.4%and workers not resident 1.1%. The SSM deduced 315 accusations, followed by DICJ with 93 and the public security police body with 34.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>International parade enchanted a crowd on the streets of Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/desfile-internacional-encantou-multidao-nas-ruas-de-macau/</link><description>Colorful, animation, enthusiasm both on the side of the participating groups, both of the people waiting for the long procession, marked another edition of the Macao International Parade. The route traveled yesterday afternoon several arteries in the city center, from the ruins of Sao Paulo to the SAP Praça Van, passing through the Leal Senate. 1,800 artists from various countries or regions have filled the festival, which is already a tradition in














































Victor Rebelo
 
There are already 11 editions of the Macao International Parade and every year the enthusiasm grows in view, evaluating for thousands of people, residents and tourists who yesterday afternoon clustered along the course to witness the procession. Those who could not occupy the front line, next to the corridor outlined by the organization, could hardly see the show of the carnival genre, which, lasting about three hours, wandered through several streets of the territory.
On a sunny afternoon, the parade ripped into the former ruins of Sao Paulo, down the street of the same name and passing through Largo de São Domingos, where the groups interacted with the population, before heading to the Leal Senate, following the Roquete Travessa.
In this central area of ​​the city, thousands of people joined, many of which went to occupy the front places about an hour in advance. "Otherwise we had no chance of seeing the parade correctly," some spectators told the Tribuna de Macau newspaper. Others spoke of “impressive crowd on the streets”, little viewed in the since of an outdoor cultural event.
The procession has not faced expectations and provided unique moments of diverse artistic performance, with the 1,800 artists showing their work, including 23 groups from 15 countries or regions of Asia, Europe and South America, who joined 60 local participating groups.
In addition to serving as a celebration of the 26th anniversary of the Macao Return to the Fatherland, it constituted at the same time the opening ceremony of the “East Asia City - Macao, China” program, promoting the spirit of “symbiosis, innovation and harmony”.
The outdoor event, which promoted the artistic exchange and highlighted cultural interaction, caused many smiles and reactions of astonishment of the public, accompanied by endless photographs, for the originality of the performances.
We recall groups that played theater, dance, acrobatics and other performative arts representing Cebu (Philippines), Artfusion (Portugal), Gipsy puppets (Bosnia Herzegovina), Circus (Germany), Taiti (Polynesia), Torrevieja (Spain), Kamakura (Japan), Aneong (South Korea), Tanoura (Egypt), Bubble Wonderwalks (Italy), Agendance (Argentina) and several comedians of Chinese cities, including Fujian, Anzhi, Wuzhou, as well as the refinement of Hong Kong drums.
From Macao, highlight to the giant “bandstand” of Casa de Portugal, Brazilian Capoeira Dance, various arts schools, many of which with children, philharmonic orchestras, Indian associations, Philippines, among others.
The traditional dance of the “drunk dragon” closed the parade that, for those who witnessed it in the same place on the route, spent about an hour and a half to watch the passage of the entire show.
The parade also went through old alleys from the historic center and finished at Largo Sai Van, where the closing party unfolded, near 19h00. The organization belonged to the Cultural Institute, along with the six concessionaires of the game in Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Revitalization of the mud market completed in the fourth quarter</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/revitalizacao-mercado-da-taipa-concluida-quarto-trimestre/</link><description>The mud market will be the target of revitalization, with the conclusion of the optimization works of the space to be pointed out to the 4th quarter of the year. The idea is to introduce cultural and creative elements as well as light food, and 20 newsstands will be launched for this purpose. Authorities expect to “inject a new vitality in the traditional markets”
 
The mud market revitalization plan, which aims to introduce elements of gastronomy and cultural creativity in that space, will be set this month. The works should be ended at the end of the year, with the space to go into operation at that time.
Located at Rua do Regrador, the Taipa Market is a large concentration zone of residents and tourists, and "is surrounded by popular sights and large flow of people." Last year, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) launched a competition directed to higher education institutions, to realize that it is to give to traditional markets.
To better enjoy the spatial disposition of that market, and after listening to vendins, restaurants, youth and cultural and creative associations, he realized that, in addition to maintaining fresh and living food products, a space could be created to introduce elements of “gastronomy + cultural creativity”.
In this sense, and with regard to markets in general, the body will adjust the distribution of newsstands, unify some vacant newsstands and, at the same time, beautify the facade of these spaces, “further optimizing the facilities and the outside”.
As for the mud market, 20 light food stalls and cultural and creative products will be launched to contest. After the “optimization”, on the ground floor of the market, the sale of fresh and living food products and traditional goods will be held, while on the first floor are the two dozen stalls that go to contest. These newsstands have a minimum area of ​​8.1 square meters and a maximum area of ​​30.9 mere square. On this same floor, there will still be a meal zone. According to AMI, a terrace will also be installed on the terrace “to provide a leisure and comfort environment”.
The Evaluation Committee will consider proposals according to the competitor's exploration, experience and qualification strategy, banking daily opening hours, diversity or uniqueness of product types, convenience of the means of payment, among other criteria. With a view to good use of public resources, the contract term is three years, and during the exploitation period there will be supervision and evaluation of the exploration situation. AMI also warned that if the law is violated or the contract is not complied with it may be terminated.
For now, AMI points to the conclusion of the optimization work for the 4th quarter of the year, and it is expected that the entry into operation of the newsstands posed by the contest, as an experimental way, also at that time.
The body hopes that the project for revitalization and development of creative industries and gastronomy “can inject a new vitality in traditional markets”.
Remember that, a few years ago, and in order to respond to the needs of social development, AMI has expanded the mud market. In concrete, installations without architectural barriers and conditioned air were introduced.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Electronic governance conquers more 21% of users</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governacao-electronica-conquista-mais-21-de-utilizadores/</link><description>Government online users increased one fifth between 2023 and 2024, reveal official data, which also highlight the climb of purchases over the internet. Last year, the internet penetration rate rose to 94% in general terms, with the elderly to record the highest growth
 
Sérgio Terra
 
The development of a digital society in Macao has gaining strength in 2024, with the number of online service users growing on virtually every front, both in the public sphere and in the private sector. Data from the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), based on the results of the annual inquiry into the use of computer technology by household aggregates, show that the government continues to appear among the main engines of this trend, along with the bank sector.
Over the past year, the number of users who resorted to online public services increased by 21% to 338,200, compared to 2023, in line with the continuous generalization of electronic governance. According to DSEC, most used online government services to “consult personal information” (about 212,200 people), generate the “border passage QR code” (182,100), “obtain public information” (168,500) and “make payments” (108.100)
Options provided by public services on the Internet include “submit information or filling online forms” (66,300), “request certificates, documents or subsidies” (42,100), “make marking or download forms” (30,500), “registration in activities or rental of facilities and equipment” (23,700) and “search for employment and recruitment” (9,600).
Overall, most users on the MSar continued to access the internet for “communication or access to social networks” (578,600), 1.6% more than in 2023. Regarding purposes, “entertainment” (547,300) and “online banking services or mobile payments” (457,400), with annual additions of 20.3% and 1.8%, were followed. respectively.
At the same time, the number of people who made online shopping (245,500) grew 3.3% within one year, especially the “Take-Away services of food and drinks” (151,900) and “clothes, luggage, accessories, etc.” (140,200). The median online shopping expense was in 1,800 patacas in the fourth quarter of 2024, illustrating an annual increase of 20%, with the acquisition of “tourist services” far above average (5,000 patacas).
 
Almost 98% of families use internet
By 2024, the internet was used by 200,200 household aggregates, which corresponds to 97.3% of the total and represents an annual rise of 0.4 percentage points, and 99.4% appealed to the mobile network (plus 0.6 points) and 93.4% to the home band (plus 3.0 points). The total number of Internet users on MSAR has grown 2.2% or 13,000 to 610,300 compared to the previous year.
The internet penetration rate (94.0%) was estimated at 94.0%, more percentage points than in the preceding year, exceeding 99%among users aged 15 to 54 years. However, the highest growth (+3.5 percentage points) occurred at the rate of individuals with 65 or more years (81.3%).
Inquiry data also indicate that 91.4% of users accessed the internet daily and the median daily time remained 3.5 hours.
At the individual level, 607,100 mobile phone users (plus 1.4%) and 397,400 computer (plus 12.7%) were accounted for, which is equivalent to penetration rates of 93.5% (+0.5 points) and 61.2% (+6.4 points), respectively.
The inquiry sample involved 2,100 accommodation units and the statistical object covered individuals aged three years or over. Among the samples, there were 1,969 occupied accommodation units, of which 1,604 completed the interviews, thus obtaining a response rate of 81.5%.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Expectations for renovation and innovation in Hengqin</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/apresentadas-expectativas-para-reforma-inovacao-em-hengqin/</link><description>At the ninth meeting of the deepened cooperation zone management committee in Hengqin, the chief executive made reference to various development expectations, one of which aims to “make more efforts to reform and innovation”. Sam Hou Fai also pointed to the “convergence of rules and mechanisms, to overcome the restrictions on hengqin development”
 
The co-chiefs of the deepened cooperation zone management committee, which includes the head of the Executive of the MSAR and the governor of Guangdong, chaired the body meeting in Hengqin. Among other topics, at the meeting was presented the “Working Report of the Executive Committee of the 2025 Deepened Cooperation Zone”. In the analysis were also the report on the execution of the budget for 2024, the budget proposal for 2025, the “government investment plan” this year and the “Industrial Development Plan of the Zone”.
At the meeting, Sam Hou Fai indicated that the various works have reached positive progress in the last three years, adding that the level of integration between Hengqin and Macao has gradually improved and the role of “sustaining diverse development of Macao's economy is becoming increasingly evident”.
The leader of the MSAR also stressed that “both parties better clarified work ideas for the second phase of the construction of the cooperation zone” and stressed the need to achieve a maximum consensus to proceed in an orderly and pragmatic manner to hengqin work.
Regarding the next phase of development of the cooperation zone, the Chief Executive presented several expectations, one of which aims to make “more efforts to reform and innovation”, exploit “with courage to innovative policies and the convergence of rules and mechanisms, to overcome the restrictions on hengqin development”. On the other hand, it stressed that it is important to "promote diligence, responsibility and pragmatism and create a work environment gathering wills and efforts to achieve advances."
Sam Hou Fai recalled that the government created the leadership group to promote the in -depth cooperation zone with the aim of increasing policy support, legislation, personnel and resource allocation. It has revealed that a series of specific measures focused on the adjustment of laws and rules around the development of industries and the well-being of the population, the synergy of policies between Hengqin and Macao and the guidance of Macau's public and social capital to invest in the projects of the cooperation zone.
The governor of Guangdong Province considered that the two parties should strive to develop the “four new” industries and reinforce the promotion of preferred policies and the planning and introduction of industrial projects, as well as attract the agglomeration of more qualified frames with innovative ideas, capital, companies and residents of Macao “to animate the cooperation zone business environment”.
On the other hand, at a Guangdong Spring reception, Sam Hou Fai stated that the neighboring province and Macao “communes from the same roots and is united by fraternal ties” and that the “first and strategic priority” of the "is always" to reinforce cooperation with the neighboring province. He further reiterated that this is “a crucial year” not only by marking the beginning of the sixth government of MSA, but also for starting the construction of the second phase of the cooperation zone in Hengqin.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Inflation retreated in February</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/inflacao-recuou-em-fevereiro/</link><description>Inflation in the MSAR translated at a rate of 0.57% in February, reflecting monthly and annual descents in the consumer price index, according to official data
 
The inflation rate in Macao was estimated at 0.57% in February, taking into account the variation of the average consumer price index (IPC) in the annual cycle ended in the reference month, compared to the immediately preceding 12 months, the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) announced. After reaching 0.74% in the general calculation of 2024, inflation had already dropped to 0.7% in January 2025.
Considering that comparative interval, the February IPC advanced 0.54% in category A, which encompasses about 50% of household aggregates with monthly expenses between 11 thousand and 35,999 patacas, and rose 0.59% in level B, which includes 30% of families with average spending between 36 thousand and 71,999 patacas. In the presentation of February data, DSEC highlights the additions to the indexes of “education” (+2.84%), “various products and services” (+2.54%) and “health” (+1.97%), and the decrease in “transport” (-3.19%).
Regarding February 2024, the General IPC fell 0.16% due mainly to the “high comparison base” as the Lunar New Year celebration propelled the prices of some goods and services, DSEC observed. In annual terms, the most significant decreases occurred in the categories of “Leisure, Recreation, Sport and Culture” (-5.03%), “Transport” (-4%), “Information and Communication” (-2.83%) and “Clothing and Footwear” (-1.98%), contrary to “various products and services”-including personal care, insurance, jewelery, and yields and yields of watches - (+2.05%), “alcoholic and tobacco beverages” (+2.03%) and “education” (+1.17%).
More moderate were the additions to the indexes of “food products and non-alcoholic beverages” (+0.69%) and “Housing and Fuels” (+0.31%), attributed to the increase of meals acquired away from home, “take-angoy”, breads and cookies and home lace.
The IPC General of February also retreated 0.19% compared to January, with the “Leisure, Recreation, Sport and Culture” section to record the highest break (-3.6%), due to the descent of excursions and hotel rooms after Lunar New Year's holidays. In the monthly comparison there were also declines in the categories of “transport” (-1.64%) and “clothing and footwear” (-0.93%), in contrast to increases in “alcoholic and tobacco drinks” (+1.1%) and “education” (+0.46%).
"The price index of the section of food products and non-alcoholic beverages, one of the sections to which the population is most attentive, has also grown 0.15%, in monthly terms, thanks essentially to the increase in the prices of meal acquired away from home and take-soway," says DSEC.
In the first two months of this year, the average IPC grew 0.2% compared to the same period as 2024.
The General IPC covers all household aggregates, and expenses with higher weights in the calculation of inflation are those of housing and fuels, food products and non -alcoholic beverages and transportation, with considerations of 34.47, 29.47 and 8.33, respectively.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Detained for attacking, coercing and kidnapping the ex-wife</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/detido-por-atacar-coagir-sequestrar-ex-mulher/</link><description>A 39-year-old unemployed resident was arrested on suspicion of coercion, kidnapping and domestic violence, in a case where the victim is the ex-wife. In addition, the man will also have stolen goods from the victim.
According to the Judiciary Police (PJ), the suspect used a knife to resist detention, which caused injuries to two criminal investigators, who had to be transported to the hospital.
Investigation data indicate that after the end of the marriage, which lasted more than a year, until December 2024, the suspect will have attacked the former spouse in January this year. As a result, it was prohibited by the Public Prosecution Service (MP) from contacting the victim.
However, the individual continued to move several times to the fraction where the old wife lives, giving her and threatening her with a knife for her to raise money on an atm machine. On the other hand, he will have kidnapped his ex-wife twice in that fraction for 31 and 15 hours, respectively, and stolen a suitcase evaluated at 9,000 patacas.
Accompanied by friends, the victim warned the police last Thursday. On the same day, when the PJ conducted an investigation at the victim's house, he found that the suspect was wandering near the offended fraction. After noticing the agents' presence, the suspect tried to escape, but was eventually detained.
According to the PJ, various results of the investigation and analyzes point to physical and mental abuse caused by the suspect to the victim and the existence of strong evidence of the practice of six crimes, namely possession of prohibited weapon, theft, sequestration, resistance and coercion, severe offense to physical integrity and domestic violence.
The detainee was sent to the MP.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mandate and Portugal consolidate cooperation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-portugal-consolidam-cooperacao/</link><description>A delegation from Macau was in Portugal to consolidate cooperation in several areas. UCTM signed two agreements with the New University of Lisbon
 
The Secretary for Economics and Finance went to Europe with a delegation of MSAR, having passed through Lisbon, where he took the opportunity to “negotiate the consolidation and deepening of cooperation” with Portugal in areas such as science, technology, economy and commerce. The aim was to “better develop the role of Macao as a platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”.
In concrete, Tai Kin IP met with the Secretary of State for Economy, João Rui Ferreira, and the Secretary of State for Education, Alexandre Homem Cristo. He also passed by Banco de Portugal, where he met the administrator, Luís Morais Sarmento.
During his stay in Portugal, and according to a statement, the delegation met with China's ambassador to Portugal, Zhao Bentang, “having exchanged impressions on the deepening of cooperation between Macao and Portugal”. He also participated in the unveiling ceremony of the “Sino-Portuguese Laboratory of Artificial Intelligence and Public Health Technologies”, constituted jointly by Higher Education Institutions of Macao, Canton and Portugal.
Visits to institutions of higher education and scientific research: Portuguese Catholic University, New University of Lisbon and Institute of Nanostructures, nanomodellation and nanofabrication were also unfolded. The idea was that Macau became known the latest development of scientific research in Portugal.
During the visits, a memorandum of understanding was signed between the University of Science and Technology of Macao and the New University of Lisbon in cooperation of cooperation in scientific research and personnel exchange. Another signed agreement aimed at the creation of a joint research center.
“Through the promotion of the development of more industry-university-investigation cooperation between organisms of the two parties, the development of the Science and Technology Cooperation and Exchange Center between China and the Portuguese-speaking countries will be reinforced.
In this visit led by Tai Kin IP, which aimed to “further extend international calls and explore opportunities for cooperation”, the delegation also passed through Spain, Belgium and Monaco.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Carlos Ortiz wins “Golf Series” in Coloane</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/carlos-ortiz-ganha-series-de-golfe-em-coloane/</link><description>Mexican Carlos Ortiz hit the entire competition and won the Macau's “International Series” golf tournament after the rivalry with the American Patrick Reed until the last day of the race held on the “Macau Golf and Country Club”, in Coloane.
Ortiz, 33, born in Guadalajara, closed the competition with 64 strokes, 22 below the field pair, three in front of his opponent, ie, 67. Reed, also a veteran (34 years) had dominated the first rounds, but could not sustain the excellent recovery of the Mexican, also allowing, at the end of the event, that his compatriot Jason Kokrak in second position.
The three players secured the qualification for the "Major" "The Open Royal Portrush", Ireland do Norte, to play this summer, as the Macao Tournament was part of the Open Qualifying Series.
Another of the main candidates for the title in Coloane was the Spaniard Sérgio Garcia, who made company to Reed in the fight for first place in the first hours, ending in fourth post, with 65 strokes.
Garcia, already 45, may complain about having failed a short-distance shot to "Birdie" in the last hole, which would have led him to draw with Kokrak and secure third place in Open through decreasing count based on its best worldwide classification.
In the fight for the first place of Macao's “International Series”, champion Carlos Ortiz began the day to share the Reed lead, but immediately moved forward with “Birdies” in the first and third and another in the eighth. It was two ahead at the turn before throwing pair 5 of the 12th.
The Mexican reached a five -foot "Fairway Wood" and made the "Putt de Eagle", which meant two strokes in front of the rival and three from Kokrak, who made Birdie in the 12th. A "Birdie" in the last hole, gave Ortiz the victory.
The winner of this second consecutive edition at the MSAR ASIAN TOUR test, sponsored by Wynn Resorts, was pleased with its performance. "I think I did a good job, having best managed my game, which is important in this Macao field," he said, adding that he took advantage of the five pairs and some of the four shorts. He also mentioned that "most problems arise from the TEE, so as soon as the driver is in play, everything opens from there."
Foi a 10ª vitória na carreira do mexicano, que igualmente conquistou um título na LIV Golf League e no PGA Tour. O jogador subiu ao topo da Ordem de Mérito do “Asian Tour” e do “The International Series Rankings”.
Macao representative Kelvin Si ended in the top 18 of the classification, with eight fewer strokes than the field pair.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macanese and Luso-Asian in San Francisco surpass those who live in Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macaenses-luso-asiaticos-em-sao-francisco-superam-os-vivem-em-macau/</link><description>A study released last week by a Chinese researcher concludes that, currently, the population of Macanese and Luso-Asiatics residing in the São Francisco Bay area is larger than that of Macao.
"There are about 70,000 macanese and Luso-Asia to reside in San Francisco, which is more than the number in Macao," researcher Leong Wong Un NA said in Lusa, who presented on Thursday at the University of Macao the book "Macanese and Luso-Asian-Asian Bay Area" from 1940 to 1950, a title that results from his doctoral thesis.
According to the latest censuses held in Macao in 2021, only 13,021 residents in Macau had Portuguese ancestry, representing 1.9% of the total population. The data also reveal that even less, 6,668, 1% of the total population, had Chinese and Portuguese descent, characteristics normally used to define the Macanese community.
According to Leong, the Macanese, some of which had left for various regions of Asia in the nineteenth century, Luso-Asian and the Portuguese in Asia, emigrated to the US from Macao in the twentieth century, due to political and economic reasons, choosing as the main destination of the São Francisco Bay, California.
Leong Wong Un NA, a Chinese who grew up in Macao and says maintaining a close relationship with the Macanese community, has many family members resident in San Francisco, including parents and siblings.
The immigrated macanese and Luso-Asiatic-symatic-symatics, he concluded Leong, were not soon recognized as Portuguese when they arrived in the US and were even discriminated against for decades by the Portuguese community itself.
At the same time the Communist Party was taking power in China, “the macanese and the Luso-Asiatics, when they immigrated there [San Francisco], could not participate in the organizations created by the Portuguese of Portugal,” said Leong Wong Un na. "Some of the descendants of Portuguese who came from Asia did not speak fluent Portuguese, so the Portuguese from Portugal said that if they did not know Portuguese, they were not Portuguese," he explained.
Leong describes in his book not only how the community of Macaenses and Luso-Asia that is currently living in the area of ​​São Francisco Bay, such as the origins and cultural traits of the Portuguese community there and even the architectural characteristics they have imprinted on the urban surroundings.
The researcher concluded that the Macaenses and Luso-Asia of San Francisco "maintain habits still very alive in Macau, such as the Macaense cuisine and the Catholic religion."
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau could face between five and eight tufts</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-podera-enfrentar-entre-cinco-oito-tufoes/</link><description>Between five and eight tropical storms can affect Macau this year, a number that oscillates between the “normal” and “relatively high”, “any of them can reach the level of severe or higher typhoon,” anticipated meteorological and geophysical services (SMG). Scheduled to start in June, the tuft time “will end in October or after,” the body said in the forecasts published on its electronic page. Given the latest data on maritime observations and predictions, SMG stresses that the phenomenon “La Niña” is gradually slowing down and will be able to return to the “neutral” state in late spring, so the temperature of surface water in downtown and east of the Pacific Ocean will be returning to “normal state”. On the other hand, SMG expects the average rain -time temperature (April to September) to vary this year between “normal” and “relatively high”, while accumulated rainfall will be “normal”, although “extremely strong” rain is also likely. Reflecting the impact of global warming, the average annual temperature in Macau was 23.6ºC in 2024, which equaled 2019 as the hottest year since 1952. The SMG also recall that, with the gradual development of the state of “La Niña” in November 2024, a rare phenomenon of “four tropical storms at the Ocean” was registered in the noroes. Pacific, three of which entered the Southern Sea of ​​China and affected Macao, establishing a record for November in the territory.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More than a thousand candidates for the second phase of the capture</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-de-mil-candidatos-a-segunda-fase-da-captacao-de-quadros/</link><description>There were 1,043 valid application for the 2nd phase of qualified frame capture programs. According to data released by the Development Commission of Qualified Tables, until February 28 this year, 105 individuals were included in the list of capture -proposed staff. Among these proposals, 50.5% have a doctorate diploma. On the other hand, 58.1% have academic degree conferred by one of the 100 best institutions in the world or one of the 20 best institutions in the interior of China. In terms of the age group, 56.2% are aged between 31 and 40 years, while 31.4% are in the age group of 41 to 50 years. On the other hand, eight were included in the funding list in the highly qualified framework, while 97 are associated with the program for advanced level professionals. However, in this 2nd phase, among the 16 requests for high quality qualified paintings, none has been proposed. Of among the 1,043 candidates, 373 ran for the program for highly qualified tables and 654 in advanced level professionals. The data also show that among the 105 proposed candidates, 44 belong to the “cultural, sports and other industries”, 27 to the “modern finance industry”, 19 to the “state -of -the -art technology industry” and 15 to the “Big Health industry”. Regarding the first phase of the fundraising programs, until February 28, of the 1,036 valid requests, 470 individuals were included in the list of qualified frames proposed for capture.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2365/</link><description>UM Fair offers 3,000 job openings
The University of Macao Multifunction Hall will host the career and internship fair, on Wednesday, from 11:00 to 17:30. The fair will have over 110 companies and organizations, offering over 3,000 job openings. The event aims to assist finalist students to seek job opportunities and summer internships. The fair also offers an online job search guide, recruitment lectures, workshops and counseling services.
 
BOCELLI CONCERT WITH ADDITIONAL PLACES
The organization of the concert Andrea Bocelli will perform at the Galaxy Arena next Saturday at 20:00, launched a limited number of additional places at the price of 320 patacas, announced the Galaxy Entertainment, stressing that the show woke up “a race to tickets”. Tickets are on sale on Galaxy Ticketing, Damai, Maoyan, Uutix, Trip.com, Ctrip, Mpay and Macao Ticket, offering fans a last opportunity to watch the performance of one of the world's most famous tenores. In this return to Macao, almost nine years after acting in the opening gala of Wynn Palace, the Italian singer will star in a special duet with his son Matteo Bocelli.
 
Wynn Palace will launch gastronomic zone in April
Wynn Palace will open on April 29 the “Gourmet Pavillion”, a space that will reinforce the gastronomic offer of the resort located on Cotai with several restaurants and a “food hall”. According to the Wynn Palace website, the "Gourmet Pavillion" will provide an "extraordinary gastronomic adventure that extends from the nyonya style of Singapore and the aromatic spices of India to the delicate art of China and the abundance of fresh mountain foods from the mountains and seas of Japan."
 
Simulated fire response at the Hovion Factory
The Fire Department (CB) made a simulacrum at the Hovione factory. The exercise simulated a fire originated by the escape of a pipeline solvent. The factory's emergency team called the CB and adopted the internal response measures, evacuating the site. The CB highlighted nine emergency vehicles and 39 firefighters for the occurrence. For almost an hour, about 160 individuals participated in the exercise, which, according to CB, reached "the expected goals and results."
 
Hotel MGM Reserve opens in May in Zhuhai
MGM Reserve, a new hotel brand, will enter May in the mainland market, with the opening of a venture in Zhuhai, reported the Gggrasia portal, citing information from Diaoyutai MGM Hospitality, promoter of the project. This company is a joint venture between Diaoyutai State Guesthouse from China and MGM Resorts International, MGM China's majority shareholder. In addition to guest rooms, the hotel will have Villas, three restaurants and banquet spaces. However, MGM China has announced that its board of directors proposed the payment of a final dividend for 2024 of 0.251 HKD, which will result in the distribution of almost 954 million HKD to the shareholders, corresponding to about 20.7% of last year's profits.
 
Died 54 -year -old man found in fire
A 55-year-old man died who had been found without heartbeat in a fraction in the siege gates, where a fire was registered on Thursday. According to the Judicial Police, no suspicious injuries were found or caused by criminal acts, and the case was considered as a corpse discovery. Three people were transported to the hospital, the PJ added, pointing out that the fire will have started in a fourth of the fraction.
 
Reservoir in design phase for expansion
The Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs Services (DSAMA) is performing the preliminary design for the expansion of Seac Pai Van reservoir, revealed the director of the body, predicting the introduction of solar panels, among other elements of environmental protection and renewable energy. At TDM, Susana Wong also stated that the first phase of the recycled water station, next to the Coloane WWTP, will enter into 2026. Dsama hopes to conclude this year the revision of technical provisions on the distribution of recycled water. The official spoke in the scope of the “World Water Day”, which Dsama signaled with several initiatives between 16 and 22 March.
 
Detained seven suspects of burla with false tokens
The Judicial Police (PJ) has detained seven men from the interior of China, aged 24 to 41 years, suspected of integrating a mockery network that resorted to fake gambling. There were 128 chips of 10,000 hkd, whose appearance, size and weight are similar to the true. According to the PJ, since mid -2024, the network has six times sent members to Macao, injuring 17 people, all not residents, including some illegal money chambers. The damage totaled 1.2 million HKD.
 
“Macaupass-China T-Union” can now be used on MTR
Since Saturday, Macaupass-China T-Union cards can be used on MTR in Hong Kong, where machines show the “China T-Union” logo. According to Macau Pass, the user must ensure that the balance of his electronic wallet in Renminbi on the “Macaupass-China T-Union” card is not less than 50 Renminbis. This type of cards already covers more than 300 cities in the interior of China and the RAE public transport network.
 
“Legionella” leaves tourist in critical condition
The Conde de Saint Januario Hospital Center diagnosed a case of “Legionella” infection, involving a 58 -year -old foreign nationality tourist with chronic diseases. According to health services, the patient is in critical condition, requiring fan to assist breathing. This is the second case of “Legionella” detected in Macau this year. The patient was in the interior of China and arrived in Macau on the 19th of this month.
 
39 thousand have not yet paid circulation tax
The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) reminded the owners of vehicles that the deadline for payment of the circulation tax ends on March 31. Until 09:00 Friday, more than 39,000 had not yet settled the tax. DSAT calls for payment to be prioritized through the electronic service of services, mobile application or “Macao Single Account” website, or the “Macao Smart Go” application.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Japanese widow Aum Shinrikyo speaks 30 years after attack on the metro</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/viuva-culto-japones-aum-shinrikyo-fala-30-anos-apos-ataque-metro/</link><description>Just seven years after her marriage, Yuki Niimi first touched her husband-a morgue, where she collected her body after her execution, and kissed him in a coffin. Prior to that, a glass screen always separated her from her husband, Tomomitsu Niimi, a notorious member of the final judgment Aum Shinrikyo who for 30 years orchestrated an attack with a nervous agent in the capital of Japan.
On March 20, 1995, members of AME released Sarin in five Carriages of the Tokyo Metropolitan, killing 14 people and leaving thousands sick. "Until the end, he did not apologize to those who died. He did not regret what he did."
Yuki herself is a former member of an Aum's successor group that, despite her denials, has already been convicted of using intimidation to try to recruit an acquaintance for the sect. Given the magnitude of her husband's crimes, she believes that the death penalty was "inevitable" and that "paying refund" is the only way that the cultures of AM can do.
Under the domain of rebel -haired guru and almost blind Shoko Asahara, Aum's devotees believed that the Armageão was coming and saw the massacres as an altruistic way of raising souls to a superior kingdom.
Unhappy young people in Japan, including doctors and engineers who later manufactured toxins, found comfort in Asahara's doctrines. Among the most loyal pupils was Tomomitsu, which was behind bars when he met Yuki and when they got married in 2011.
His relationship consisted of letters and 15 to 30 minutes of conversation, almost every day, under the supervision of a guard. It all ended with its execution in the summer of 2018, along with 12 other AMA members, including Asahara.
After her death, the widow Yuki stroked the still hot body of Tomomitsu, whose neck was wrapped in a ligation to hide the mark left by the loop. He then spent the next three days, to the cremation, lying next to him at home. "He didn't seem to have suffered anything. He seemed to be sleeping," she said.
Tomomitsu, who died at the age of 54, is sometimes called Aum's “bloodiest” disciple - having helped perpetrate all seven deadly attacks on the group, including the previous strike of the meter in which he served as a driver.
The AUM cultists, who wasolated and were incommunicable in the pre-internet era, "believed in everything," Asahara said, and "honestly thought they were helping their act of salvation," Yuki said.
However, about a month before Tomomitsu's execution, she felt that her loyalty to the leader was finally crumbling. “He called him only 'Asahara'-this had never happened before in the 12 years or more we were together.
Then, in his diary, “in the last days of his life, he clearly expressed that 'I will not follow him anymore'” realizing that Asahara's teachings over Karma were a fallacy, Yuki said.
Also, despite Tomomitsu's lack of remorse, "I asked why Aum had performed the gas attack on the meter, and my husband clearly told me that the guru was sick, mentally ill," he added.
The poisoning in the metro shocked the world and led to an adjustment of accounts with extremism in Japan, with a repression of the Asahara Empire, which has had more than 10,000 followers.
Its successor groups continue to operate and recruit, with estimated numbers of 1,600 in the domestic market. Two of these groups, Aleph and Hikarinowa, openly operate in Japan, which, according to some experts, makes them easier to monitor.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>