<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>161 cases of illicit game until March</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/registados-161-casos-de-jogo-ilicito-ate-marco/</link><description>In general, crime in Macao decreased 7.3% in the first three months of this year, but, on the other hand, the game -related crimes were increased mainly by the illicit game (161 cases), illegal exchange exploration (132) and slips (152). Authorities justify the scenario with the entry into force of the illicit play crimes and the improvement of other provisions related to game crimes. Moreover, the crimes of burla, computer crime and violent crime recorded a decline
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Crime generally recorded “a decrease” in Macao in the first quarter of this year, with the situation of public security to remain “stable and favorable”, the secretary for security, Wong Sio Chak, said yesterday. Even the crimes of burla and computer sciences "have begun to record a decrease trend." On the other hand, compared to the first three months of 2024, there was an “increase in crimes related to the illicit game”, according to the balance of crime.
Between January and March, 3,289 criminal inquiries were established, representing a decrease of 260 cases and a declining of 7.3% in annual terms. It should be noted that the “crimes against the person” slightly rose to 565 cases, most of which (293) were of simple offense to physical integrity. There are also five cases of child sexual abuse, more than in the previous year, “mainly involving the practice of voluntary sexual acts between people of the same age and the diffusion of photographs and pornographic images”; In addition to 10 cases of violation, four minus.
In the context of cases of domestic violence, 26 (two more) were preliminarily recorded. However, until May 12, after investigation and confirmation, only four were actually classified as crimes of domestic violence. In addition, 12 were qualified as offense crimes to physical integrity, two such as other crimes and eight remain under investigation.
Against the heritage, 1,949 cases were registered, a break of almost 11%. Regarding the circumvents, there were 555 cases, a decrease of 15.4%, while computer crime decreased by 14% to 160 cases.
As for the game, 567 inquiries were established for crimes related to the sector, plus 216 cases or 61.5%. Authorities reported 161 illicit play cases, plus 145 or 906.3% over the same period of 2024, and justify the numbers with the entry into force of the illicit play crimes in late October, which added the crime of exploitation of illicit exchange exchange rates and the improvement of provisions related to other illegal game crimes.
Only processes related to illicit exchange exploration for game were 132, occupying more than 60% of the number of increased cases related to the game, and representing 23.3% of the total. Game -related crimes also had “high occurrences”, growing from 76 to 152 cases, equivalent to 26.8% of the total.
In the balance sheet, the secretary also said that between January and March, police detained 251 people for the practice of illegal money exchange in various police actions, 1,041 individuals and a decrease of 80.6% over last year's same period.
Under the game, cases of usury (51), theft (46), illegitimate appropriation (38), disobedience (21) were also counted. Authorities also note that "the number of tourists entering Macao has increased by 11.1% over last year's same period, which brings to the Macao Society more uncertain factors affecting security."
In general, there were 56 cases in the scope of violent crime, minus 21 cases or a break of 27.3% in annual terms. Faculture, homicide and severe body offenses "continue to keep a zero rate or a very low occurrence rate."
The secretary also announced that, from the first quarter of this year, data on crimes of "slavery" and "trafficking in persons", provided for in the Penal Code, as well as some crimes provided for in the law of terrorism prevention and repression of terrorism, are included in the statistics of violent crime, so that they are "more scientific and logical". For now, there was no records regarding these crimes.
 
Wong Sio Chak says journalists “are no exception” to the law
The Secretary for Security stressed yesterday that journalists “are no exception” to the duty to comply with the law after the arrest of two reporters in the Legislative Assembly in April. "It's not for your profession that you don't have to comply with what is in the law," said Wong Sio Chak, when asked about the incident involving the "All About Macau". "It is important, we have to comply with the law. No profession is exception," added the manager, recalling that "the police ... During the execution of the law, it is monitored by the judicial body, the prosecutor." Asked by Lusa, the office of the prosecutor, Chan Tsz King, said on Tuesday that he had no "information to disclose at this time" about the progress of the process.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Government “injected” 678 million in Metro last year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-injectou-678-milhoes-metro-ano-passado/</link><description>default



Government's financial support to the Metro Light Society decreased in annual terms, but still represented 88% of 2024 revenues, a total of 678 million Patacas. The number of passengers increased by 117% to 5.37 million, but not even that helped: overall, revenues fell about 3.5 million, with MLM justifying that it had fully assumed the contract that had been awarded to MTR, related to the operation and maintenance of the subway. With total expenses to increase 2%, the financial year closed with net income of 17.4 million, registering a break to almost half of the 2023 value
 
Catarina Pereira
 
In the financial year of 2024, the Macao Light Metro Society (MLM) obtained a positive balance before taxes in the order of 23.6 million patacas, an annual decrease of 40.5% or 63.3 million, according to the report yesterday published. In net terms, profits suffered a break of almost 49% or 16.7 million patacas, totaling 17.4 million.
Although last year the company has requested less financial support from the government, it is still represented most of MLM revenues. In concrete, the amount granted by the executive was 678 million patacas, less 3.88% or 27.3 million compared to 2023.
According to the data analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the financial assistance of the MGA represented 88%of the revenues of the company of the Metro, observing a reduction in its "weight" over the previous year (91.2%), 2022 (96.8%) and 2021 (98.1%).
Overall, the company's revenues totaled about 770.4 million patacas, noting a decrease of more than 3.5 million, ie less 0.5% in the annual comparison. Exploration revenues rose about 94% to 39.9 million patacas, equivalent to 5.1% of the total, but still remained short of interest rates (52 million), which grew by 9.7%, making 6.7% of the total. The revenues generated by “other sources” not detailed, in turn, decreased almost 9% to 314 million patacas.
Regarding exploration revenues, the box office represented 69% of the total, with 27.7 million patacas. This value reflects an annual climb of 105%, driven, the increasing daily average passenger and the entry into operation of the Pai Van Seac line and the Hengqin line. Last year, the light meter made about 129,000 trips and was used by more than 5.37 million passengers, an increase of 117% annually.
The number of passengers using the slight meter “has grown stable”, and in December 2024, the daily average exceeded 23.1 thousand, “marking the first time the daily passenger number exceeded 20,000 since the charging of the mud line,” says the report.
In turn, revenues derived from the lease of spaces ascended to 4.1 million patacas (plus 112%) and those generated by the lease of parking parks reached 1.3 million (plus 119%). Already other sources not discriminated contributed with 6.7 million (plus 49%).
“Despite the continuous rise of the daily average passenger average in all lines, which resulted in significant growth (…) in ticket offices and the addition of alternative revenues for the sale of tickets by about 72% (…), the full assumption of the 'service of service service and maintenance service contract has led to a substantial reduction in the associated cost. Consequently, the request for the financial support of this company to the Government of the MSAR decreased on 27,369,485.00 Patacas, equivalent to a decrease of 3.88%, resulting in a decrease in total revenues compared to the year 2023 ”, read in the report.
 
Increasing expenses
Already the expenses totaled 746.8 million patacas by 2024, with an annual increase of 1.7% or 12.7 million. Generally, spending had an increase in the amount of 12.6 million patacas, in relation to the year 2023, corresponding to a climb of 2%. "This growth is mainly due to the preparation for the full assumption of the 'contract for the provision of services to the operation and maintenance of the macao macao system mud line', as well as the entry into operation of the Seac Pai Van line and the Hengqin line," explains MLM.
The costs related to the operation - due to the full assumption of the contract and the work and maintenance work required by the new lines - increased 93 million patacas (plus 89%) to a total of 198.1 million.
On the other hand, the cost associated with the contract registered a significant reduction from 54% to 232.6 million patacas, since in 2024 the services were fully assumed by MLM progressively. "However, in global terms, the reduction of the cost of MTR's contract (Macau) was not enough to completely compensate for the increase in other expenses," the company justifies.
The contract entered into with MTR (Macau) expired last year, with the expenses of the services to be paid for settlement at the end of 2024. According to the report, the contract, awarded by the Government of MSAR in 2018, had an initial value of 5.88 billion Patacas and a period of 80 months. "Until its conclusion, it is estimated that the total amount of the services to be paid has been about 3.34 billion patacas," says the document, with the MLM that is still pending "a small portion of the expenses", so the amount does not yet correspond to the final, actually paid.
It was in 2021 that MLM began to assume the operation and maintenance of the Metro, and until last year, a cost of approximately 460 million patacas. In total, the global value of the contract is about 3.8 million -3.4 million to pay for MTR (Macau) and about 460 million supported by MLM -“representing a reduction of approximately 2 million patacas (less 35%) compared to the originally awarded value”.
 
They went up spending on the workers
At the same time, spending arising from personnel expenses have been increased by 181.2 million patacas (plus 157%) to 296.3 million as a result of the increase in the number of workers. In late 2024, MLM had 855 employees, a substantial increase compared to the 247 at the end of the previous year. Last year alone, 550 MTR workers (Macau) were hired.
"In order to gradually create a transport team on local local carris, MLM has driven the hiring of Light Local Metro workers and has offered them opportunities for professional ascension," he says, adding that so far the percentage of local workers throughout the operating team has exceeded 95%.
In order to effectively raise the professional capacity and safety awareness of workers and train specialized technicians, the Metro society gradually started a series of training courses. In the last year, 122 training sessions were held, with a total participation of 512 workers and 1,862 representatives of the sub-unexplaces.
In the report's findings, the company is peremptory: “After reaching autonomous operation, MLM aims to strengthen professional techniques and management skills, actively seeking advances in operational efficiency, personnel management, revenue expansion not coming from activities and service optimization”.
With the gradual increase in the number of passengers in the light meter, MLM hopes to “look for more revenue sources, in order to gradually increase the quota of revenues not coming from ticket sales and reducing the operation's financial charges”. Having full notion that, as the metro network expands, "society's expectations" continue to grow, MLM is always committed to following the principle of service of "security and convenience".</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Secretary says demonstrations can affect national security</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/secretario-diz-manifestacoes-podem-afectar-seguranca-nacional/</link><description>The Macao government said yesterday that demonstrations may threaten national security, but denied that police pressured an association to cancel a protest on Labor Day.
"Manifestations can bring conflicts to society, state security," said the secretary for security at the Crime Balance Press Conference in the first quarter of the year.
"This has to do with the well-being of our country. We cannot, due to a person's interest, harm our people," Wong Sio Chak told journalists.
During the pandemic, security forces refused to approve the course of any protest, invoking reasons for “order and safety” or public health. Authorities raised anti-standard restrictions at the end of 2023, but the protests did not return to the city streets.
These prohibitions arrived at the UN Human Rights Committee, which in 2022 evaluated "an increasing number of information of improper restrictions on the exercise of freedom of peaceful manifestations."
Wong Sio Chak reiterated the respect of the government of masters for the right to manifestation, but stressed that "it cannot impact society."
According to the “All About Macau”, Macao's Power Power Group canceled a May 1 demonstration for “police pressure”, which claimed that the protest could violate the National Security Act. The online newspaper also indicated that the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) confirmed that it had received a demonstration notification for the Labor Day, but said that the organizer voluntarily removed it.
However, Wong Sio Chak assured that "the police did not cause him pressure." "We have a negotiation of public order, as earlier, because a demonstration has to occupy public space and can also have many people to participate," he said.
Macao's Popular Power Association said it expected 20,000 participants in the May 1 protest, which would require the reduction in the number of migrant workers.
Wong Sio Chak gave as an example an alleged police decision in Spain, which was confirmed by the court, to prohibit a demonstration "involving two religious groups that could lead to conflict and disorder."
Asked if the Macao police had reason to fear that the Labor Day protest could lead to physical clashes, the secretary did not respond directly. However, Wong stressed that "all police are afraid of conflict, aggression."
On May 1, a resident was taken to the squadron after screaming slogans with the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs against the “excess” of resident workers, the unemployment of local and the fact that they have to seek work in the Great Bay. Since "I had not warned in advance that it was going to be manifested," CPSP "made several warnings to the man, but had no effect," police said the police, considering that the conduct will have violated the meeting and manifestation law. Considering that a crime of disobedience was committed, the CPSP referred the case to the prosecutor.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New academic year at EPM starts on September 8</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/novo-ano-lectivo-na-epm-arranca-8-de-setembro/</link><description>The students of the Portuguese School of Macau will start the school year 2025/2026 on September 8th. As for the end, the dates depend on the calendar of national examinations stipulated by Portugal. At MSAR, schools dependent on education and youth development services begin to teach between September 1 and 5
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The next school year at the Portuguese School of Macau (EPM) will start on September 8, Monday, according to what is already defined by the educational establishment. Regarding the end of the third period, the days are still provisional - June 5 for students who will have to take exams (9th, 11th and 12th) and 26 for the remaining students.
Filipe Figueiredo, president of the EPM (APEPM) Parents and Parents Association (APEPM) told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that these dates, although not yet fully defined, "should not escape much of what is currently calendarized."
As EPM is a private educational institution, so not dependent on the regulation of official schools of the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ), the Calendar of the School Year has some differences. First of all because the Chinese schools have two school semester, unlike the EPM that has three quarters.
Educational establishments under the dependence of DSEDJ will have to start the school year 2025/2026 between September 1 and 5, according to the announcement published yesterday in an official bulletin. Then, the first period ends on February 13, while the second starts on February 25 and finishes July 9 to 15, according to the calendar released.
Regarding the EPM, the end of the first period, for Christmas and New Year, will be on December 16, while the second will start on January 4 and finishes on March 31. The start of the third and last school period starts on April 13.
In the announcement released by the DSEDJ, it is reported that it is responsible for each body of the respective official school to decide the start and end of educational activities and to communicate this decision, before July 1, 2025, in addition to “adapting the school calendar to articulate with the educational projects and the pedagogical plans of the school, as well as the real situation of the school semesters”.
The calendar made public also mentions the periods of interruption of teaching activity: from December 20 to January 1 (1st period) and from 16 to 24 February (2nd period).
As for the student evaluation period, DSEDJ reports that each school year has two evaluation moments, which occur after the end of each school semester. The first semester classification bulletin will have to be attributed within the 10 working days from the day following the beginning of the second semester classes, after ratifying by the director of the educational establishment.
The evaluation regarding the second semesters will have to be held within the 10 working days from the day following the ratification by the school principal.
“The school calendar for special education is equal to the one established for regular education,” says DSEDJ in the announcement signed by the director, Kong Chi Meng.
Remember that schools that are not dependent on the DSEDJ, such as EPM, which is governed by teaching regulation in Portugal, have yet to meet some requirements imposed by Macao for private schools, such as the number of hours of academic times, which is about 190 annually.
In addition, there are subjects contemplated in the Macao curriculum that do not exist in Portugal, namely at the level of secondary education and are also taught at school. Filipe Figueiredo explains that “in Portugal, according to the Portuguese system, there is at the end of the 9th grade a choice of areas by the students and, therefore, who goes to humanities has ceased to have math, who goes to science, ceases to have history, etc.”.
In Macao, the APEPM official, “is intended to be regardless of choice, is that there are disciplines, namely history, mathematics, arts and music, which are common to all branches, and even secondary students end up having these subjects, most of them until the 12th grade, which do not exist in Portugal”.
Then there are differences from academic times. "In Macau there is a great preponderance to the teaching of foreign language and so English has more academic times than in Portugal," says the associative leader, adding that "computer intelligence and artificial intelligence as well, so they are adapted according to local legislation."
The EPM should count on the next school year with a slight increase in students, such as JTM recently advanced. Currently the school has 780 students, a number that may exceed 790, thanks to the improvements that are being made in some classrooms. Regarding the hiring of two teachers to teach mathematics and geography from September, the process of candidacies also follows, and should soon begin the selection and the interviews.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Six insurers cover “disasters” of the SMEs</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/seis-seguradoras-cobrem-desastres-das-pme/</link><description>EPA08612339 A MAN WALKS ON AN FLOODED STREET AFTER TROPICAL STORM HIGOS HADD VERY CLOSE TO MACAO, CHINA, 19 AUGUST 2020.  EPA/TATIANA LAGES



Subscriptions to property insurance against large disasters for small and medium enterprises and their financial support plan received the adhesion of six local insurers. The program is intended to alleviate the charges of merchants. Candidates may submit requests until December 31 this year
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The subscription of the “assets insurance against large disasters for small and medium enterprises” (SMEs) to 2025, opened yesterday the candidacies, which can be made until December 31 this year, and the industrial and marketing fund continues to implement complementary measures such as the financial support plan to be granted at the same scope.
The objective, according to a joint statement from the Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM) and the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), is to relieve the financial charges of traders. In order to facilitate subscription, the number of local insurers who joined the program increased this year to six.
SMEs can subscribe to a “large disasters insurance” for each commercial establishment, within this program, there are safe amounts to the choice of candidates, namely 100,000, 200,000, 300,000 and 500,000 patacas.
On the other hand, it will be continued to grant discounts on prizes to traders who have never filed compensation when insurance renewal, and discounts of 20, 25 and 30% for the first, second and third years of renewal, respectively.
Regarding renewals to be made in the fourth year or in the following, discounts of 35%will be granted. The plan establishes that, in the case of a merchant, during the period when it enjoys a reduction of 25% or higher, submitting a claim for compensation, it will benefit from the following year of a 20% discount on prizes when renewing the respective policy. The maximum discount to be granted will be limited to 35% on an annual basis when insurance renewal, if no further compensation is submitted.
The document widespread by AMCM and DSEDT stresses that the government “will continue to grant, through the industrial development and commercial development fund, the financial support of the large disasters to qualified SMPs, and the amount equals 50% or 30,000 patacas of the total annual of the standard award, in order to reduce financial charges. Traders can rise up to 2.25% of the total original awards, depending on their own situation, if it is acquisition or insurance renewal.
The “insurance against large disasters” was launched in 2019, aiming to solve the problems of small and medium -sized companies located in the city's low areas, regarding the absence of any insurance coverage of the losses caused by business assets. Following the continuous optimization of the program, coverage will be given to the commercial patrimonial losses caused by severe climatic phenomena, namely the sign of tropical storm No. 8 or higher, the red or higher “storm” alert, the black rainfall, issued by meteorological and geophysical services.
On the other hand, within the scope of the program, the franchise amount, no compensation limit of goods, was set, as well as discounts on prizes when the insurance renewal are granted.
At the same time, with the financial support of the industrial and marketing development fund, traders will be encouraged to subscribe to this insurance, continuously, thus ensuring the proper management of risks.
Since the implementation of the plan, 101 policies with financial support have been issued, and the subscriber traders come from sectors such as restoration, retail trade, rude trade trade, as well as retail and thick electrodomers, among others. The total value of coverage was on 14.9 million patacas.
In order to facilitate the processing of formalities concerning the acquisition of “insurance against large disasters” and the request for financial support, “in one place”, by interested traders, insurers can help collect and transfer the documents from the order.
At the same time, given the premise and difficulties with which traders confront, after large disasters, insurers promise to accelerate procedures with a view to the rapid payment of compensation.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Moody’s” maintains evaluation on the MSAR</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/moodys-mantem-avaliacao-sobre-raem/</link><description>The financial notation agency "Moody's Investors Service" has decided to maintain the long -term credit rating "AA3" attributed to the MSAR. According to Moody's criteria, the notation “AA” refers to a high investment degree and a risk of extremely low credit failure.
The rating “AA3” “reflects our assessment that [Macao] maintains strong credit points, including a very high per capita income and the absence of pending public debt,” the agency reiterated, anticipating that the financial reserve should continue to be high to “short and medium term”.
The “AA3” classification, the fourth highest on the “Moody's” scale, is based on the “stable situation of public finances and external payments of MSAR,” says a statement from the Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM). "In addition, the absence of charges with debt by the Government of MSAR continues to give a strong ability to resistance to potential external shocks," he adds.
"Despite the complex challenges and multiple uncertainties that the global economy currently faces, MSar's economy has shown a solid recovery trend. In the first quarter of 2025, the dimension of the local economy reached 85.2% of the level recorded in the same period of 2019," said AMCM. At the same time, the body adds, with the support of the central government, the Executive of the MSAR is promoting “the development of the proper diversification of the economy and regional cooperation, further reinforcing the sustainability of economic growth” of the territory.
However, "Moody's" maintains a negative perspective on the evolution of the local economy above all due to the dependence on the continent and the recipes of the game. "The game sector continued to represent about half of economic production by 2024 and about 80% of the government's total revenue," he noted, recalling that the casinos' businesses are "widely driven by Chinese tourists, representing about two thirds of the total visitors in 2024."
In this context, “politics changes in mainland China have direct implications for Macao's growth, on their tax and external reserves, as the impact of China's anti-corruption campaign in 2015-2016, which led to prolonged slowdown in the Macao game sector,” recalls the agency, further expressing skepticism about the fruits of short-term economic diversification strategy.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Praise driver who assaulted police can be a crime</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/elogiar-motorista-agrediu-policia-pode-ser-crime/</link><description>Following the case of a driver who has assaulted a public security police officer, Wong Sio Chak warned that praising a criminal may be a crime. On social networks, some residents tried to excuse the driver's acts
 
The secretary for security warned yesterday that comments on social networks to support a heavy driver who allegedly assaulted a police officer may be a crime. "Regarding the support manifested on social networks to the aggressor, when a person is praising a criminal, it is inappropriate," said Wong Sio Chak during the crime balance press conference.
"As for being a crime, I remember that there is an article in the Penal Code on the compliment of criminals," added the manager when asked about the incident.
The Penal Code, approved in 1995, provides for a prison sentence of up to six months for the “public apology of crime”. The article applies to those who "reward or praise someone else for committing a crime, properly to create danger of the practice of another crime of the same species."
This crime implies the apology made “in a public meeting, through a means of social communication, for writing or another means of technical reproduction”, says the Penal Code.
On social networks, some residents tried to excuse the driver, seeing in the aggression a symptom of social discontent and growing economic pressure.
The driver was arrested on Sunday, after what was an assault with a metal bar to a public security police officer who was fine for illegal parking, an incident that was filmed by passers -by and shared on social networks. Wong Sio Chak stressed that "any police aggression is a very serious case."
"The traffic agent is executing the law, maintaining the order and the population must collaborate. This has nothing to do with the application of the law," said the secretary. "Only if the police have done something wrong, then the citizen may later file a complaint."
The driver was arrested, but eventually left by decision of the criminal instruction judge, the prosecutor said. Still, the 60-year-old resident was forced to pay a security and to present herself periodically to the police, and is still forbidden to abandon Macao. This is because the judge concluded that there were “strong evidence of the crime of aggravated injury, the crime of damage, the crime of resistance and coercion, and the crime of unjustified arrest”.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Boss and Health Commission discussed 'Big Health'</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-comissao-de-saude-debateram-big-health/</link><description>The development of the 'Big Health' industry and the training of health professionals were some of the subjects addressed by the head of the Executive of Mashera in a meeting with the Deputy Director of the National Health Commission. Cooperation in the area of ​​clinical practice for health students of Macau also deserved discussion in the dialogue between Sam Hou Fai and Cao Xuetao
 
The Chief Executive met at the Government headquarters with the Deputy Director of the National Health Commission, Cao Xuetao, for an exchange of impressions on the development of the 'Big Health' industry and the training of health professionals.
According to a note from the Social Communication Office, Sam Hou Fai said that the government continues to optimize the structure of different sectors and to focus on promoting the 'Big Health' industry. He also stressed that Macau will deepen the synergies in the Great Bay in this domain, with the objective of “jointly promoting a high quality development of this sector”.
On the other hand, Sam Hou Fai emphasized cooperation with the National Health Commission, aiming to reinforce clinical practice for Macao health students, as well as the intensification of medical education and the exchange of qualified staff, and improving the level of Macao health services in all aspects.
During the conversation with Cao Xuetao, the Chief Executive thanked the Commission for supporting Macao health work over the years, adding that, since the transfer of sovereignty, the Executive of the MSAR, “has committed to continuously improving medical services, with the aim of improving the health and well-being of the entire population”.
In addition, he indicated that the completion and entry into operation of the Islands Hospital (Macau Union), “a major project related to the life of the population”, aims to boost better development of work in the area of ​​health, as well as “reflect the attention and importance of the country to the well-being of the population of Macau”.
Also present at the meeting, among others, the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, the LAM, the Director of Health Services, Lo Iek Long, the director of the Islands Hospital, Wu Wenming, the Office Subdirector for Hong Kong, Macau and Taiwan and 1st Class Inspector of the National Health Commission, He Zhaohua, and the Department of the Department of the Department. Medical of the National Health Commission, Li Dachuan.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sold 34% of houses in the new neighborhood in Hengqin</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/vendidas-34-das-casas-novo-bairro-em-hengqin/</link><description>default



The annual report of the Urban Renewal Society indicates that only 34% of the apartments in the deepened cooperation zone were sold by the end of 2024. The data show that more than 2,500 residents of Macao moved to the new neighborhood
 
Between November 2023 and the end of 2024, only 1,388 of the 4,070 apartments from the new Macau neighborhood of Hengqin were sold, according to the annual report of the Urban Renewal Society (Mur, in the English acronym), quoted by Macau News Agency, which represents only 34% of the total units.
The purchase of parking places has also slowed, indicates the report, with only 462 (11.6%) were sold out of a total of 3,973 seats. According to Mur, more than 2,500 residents have moved to the new neighborhood, with over 80% of supermarkets, restaurants, banks, shops, barber shops and laundry services to be operated by Macao traders.
Seen as a project to deepen the ties between Macao and China, it is expected that between 12,000 and 15,000 residents of MSAR will end up moving to the new residential complex. The project, intended for residents of Macao, consists of 27 residential blocks with units of two and three bedrooms, to 30 thousand Renminbis per square meter.
According to Macau News Agency, a subsidiary of Mur said the number of residents moving to the complex continues to "grow constantly" with "completely operational" public services. Most retail stores have opened doors, forming a “full circle of life of 15 minutes”, with vitality, commercial activity and atmosphere to reach “new levels”.
Together with traders, Mur intends to create “a habitable community that meets the needs of all social groups” and encourages “Macao's small and medium-sized companies to integrate into the great bay and bring more brands”.
To stimulate sales, Mur relieved purchase restrictions twice in 2024. In May, it eliminated the rules that required buyers to be owned by Zhuhai real estate and had no more than an apartment in Macao. He raised the age requirement, set in 18 years, and removed the five -year resale restriction.
Efforts to improve the habitability of the in -depth cooperation zone include educational services and infrastructure. A primary school opened last year and a secondary school is being built, which is scheduled for 2026.
In the first quarter of 2025, the average price of houses in Macao descended to 71,859 patacas per square meter, a 15.5% reduction compared to last year's same year period and 31.2% compared to the period prior to pandemic.
Mur reported net income of 483.48 million Renminbis by 2024 after a year with losses of 12.54 million Renminbis in 2023.
In April, the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, reiterated that the development of Hengqin and the integration with China is one of the priorities of the Government of Masters.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Open registrations for “unique” travel to Italy</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/abertas-inscricoes-para-viagem-unica-italia/</link><description>The Culture Circle is organizing a trip to Italy in September, whose registration is open until June 2. The trip includes visits to cities like Venice and Milan as well as prestigious art shows
 
Until June 2, registrations are open for a trip to Italy, organized by the Culture Circle (CAC) and will be held from 21 to 29 September. For CAC, it is a “unique opportunity” for architects, designers, engineers and artists. The association promises not only to be a professional development opportunity, and is also a journey through the “vibrant culture of Italy”.
One of the highlights of the trip will be a visit to the Venice Architecture Biennial, which serves as a platform for sector professionals to display their work and share ideas about contemporary architecture and design, says CAC.
Participants will also have the opportunity to visit the Triennial of Milan, a “prestigious display dedicated to design, architecture and arts”, with every three years in that Italian city. According to CAC, the event features innovative work by international designers and artists, which enhance trends and developments in the fields of design and visual culture.
The trip will also include visits to iconic places in Venice, Milan and other nearby cities, "offering a rich cultural context for discussions about architecture." Participants will be able to experience workshops and lectures by experts throughout the journey, and know “contemporary and historical architectural wonders” that define cities.
The participation rate is 13,000 patacas, and includes flights between Hong Kong and Italy, transport between cities, six nights of accommodation and biennial tickets.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Guaranteed conclusion of works before the beginning of classes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/garantida-conclusao-de-obras-antes-inicio-das-aulas/</link><description>The execution period of the works carried out near the schools will have, according to the government, “a strict control”. The measure aims to complete the work before the beginning of classes
 
The adoption of measures to shorten the deadlines of the works that are done near schools was one of the determinations that came out of the “Coordination Group to optimize road works”, chaired by the secretary for transport and public works.
Given that, this summer, eight joint works of great wingspan will be carried out, seven of which are in places close to educational establishments, Raymond also requires that the members of the “working group” will proceed “rigorously to control the execution period of the works, with a view to the beginning of the classes and the normalization of traffic”, supervising the builders so that “they move punctually and in each phase. of construction ”.
At the same time, he said, "it is necessary to ensure adequate management of workshoars to minimize the impact on citizens' lives."
In addition, according to a note from the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT), measures should be adopted to shorten the deadlines, ensuring the safety of the works, especially in places near schools, where normal traffic should be restored before the beginning of the school year, in order to relieve congestion in class return.
In parallel, the “working group” will have to ensure that all contractors have an adequate disposition of temporary signaling and equipment, both in quantity and location, in order to minimize the impact on citizens' travel.
DSAT also indicates that the anticipated installation of pipes and the reserve of binding pipes also constitute one of the priorities: “Through the reservation of pipes, future development projects can make their connections only within the limits of the construction area or occupying small areas of tours, thus minimizing the impact on traffic”.
The “Working Group” asks these channeling companies to evaluate the needs provided for the sections where they intend to intervene over the next three years, making the installation of reserve conduct during the excavations.
It also encourages the application of “three news” of technology: new equipment, new materials and new techniques, namely the use of non -destructive methods, such as the installation of pipes or the horizontal perforation directed in places with adequate conditions, for water repair works or installation of electric cables. These include the use of non -destructive methods on the busiest roads of Afonso de Albuquerque Street, Resto Road and Avenida de Demétrio Cinatti.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Digital Education Standards Launched</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lancadas-normas-de-educacao-digital/</link><description>Marcus Im, dean of the Macao Polytechnic University, was present at the World Conference on Digital Education in Wuhan, where guidelines for the “standard” application of digital technologies in education in the “intelligent era” were launched at the “standardized” application.
 
Macao Polytechnic University Rector (UPM), Marcus Im was in Wuhan, to participate in the World Conference on Digital Education, which served to launch the “Initiative for building an international framework for the Digital Education Standards System” and the “General Reference Framework for Great Education Models”.
Under the theme “Development and Change in Education: The Intelligent Era”, several academic experts exchanged impressions about the innovation of digital technology and education, in response to the United Nations “on global change in education in the intelligent era,” says UPM. The initiative is a project to establish global standards for digital education and provide “clear guidelines” for the development of subsequent rules of the World Digital Education Alliance, as well as a standard application of digital technologies between its members.
The “General Reference Framework for large models of education”, in turn, aims to provide “systematic guidelines” about the conception, development and implementation of large models of education “in various scenarios”, says the university statement.
According to Marcus IM, in recent years, UPM has promoted “global sustainable development based on interdisciplinary scientific research in‘ Artificial Intelligence +’”, with the contributions of the Engineering Research Center in Automatic Translation and Artificial Intelligence of the Ministry of Education, the Drug Discovery Center driven by Artificial Intelligence and the Set Research Laboratory for Intelligent Cities.
The university guarantees to be committed to “developing the application of artificial intelligence technologies in various domains”, such as intelligent education, environmental protection, drug discovery or medical imaging, among others, and in fostering qualified pictures in scientific and technological innovation, with the help of global partners, promoting a “sustainable development” of the planet.
The event was organized by the Ministry of Education of the Popular Republic of China, the China National Commission for UNESCO and the Hubei province government.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese Doctors Association celebrated 80th Anniversary</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/associacao-de-medicos-chineses-celebrou-80o-aniversario/</link><description>The Association of Chinese Doctors and Medicines of Macao held a commemorative ceremony of its 80th anniversary, with the presence of representatives of the central authorities of that sector. During the event, the association's president, Jorge Kuan, again underlined the importance of strengthening Chinese medicine and traditional medicines worldwide, namely in Portuguese -speaking countries in the context of a “spirit of collaboration” and “obedience to the directions of the central government of China”. The celebrations were also marked by the signing of various cooperation agreements between the local association and mainland China, including the Canton Study and Technology Institute, the Hong San (Canton) group, the Chinese drug group Tái Kek, Kam Hông (Hengqin), Tong Yun Technology and Tung Yun Medicine (Canton) Zhuhai, linked to drug drinks.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Türkiye discovers and reproduces bronze age bread</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/turquia-descobre-reproduz-pao-da-idade-bronze/</link><description>In the early days of the Bronze Age, a piece of bread was buried under a newly settled house in the current Türkiye. Five millennia later, archaeologists had managed to dig it up, studied, and helped a local bakery recreate the recipe.
"This is the oldest roast bread discovered in an excavation and has largely preserved its form," said Murat Türkteki, archaeologist and director of the excavation of Küllüoba, near the city of Eskisehir in the center of Turkey.
"A bread is a rare discovery in excavations. Usually we only found crumbs. But here it was preserved because it was burned and buried," he told AFP.
Küllüoba, round and flattened bread as a host about 12 centimeters in diameter, was discovered in September 2024, charred and buried around 3,300 before Christ.
A piece was torn before the bread was burned and buried when the house was built. "This forces us to recognize that it has been a ritual of abundance," said Türkteki.
In the absence of written evidence, the mystery pointed to the Anatolian civilization of Küllüoba and its customs, such as burying the houses before moving to another place or building new housing over older structures, thus forming hills.
At the age of the bronze, the Hatianians, a people of Anatolia who preceded the Hittites, lived in the Eskisehir region.
"Küllüoba was a medium -sized urban agglomeration with commercial, handcrafted, agricultural and mining activities. It was evident the existence of a certain family and social order," explained archaeologist Deniz Sari.
Several analyzes showed that the bread was made with grossly ground lentil seeds and flour, an old variety of wheat. The leaf of a plant still being determined was used as yeast.
Carbonized bread has been on display at the Eskisehir Archaeological Museum since Wednesday. "This discovery excited us a lot. While talking to our excavation director, I wondered if we could reproduce this bread," said Ayse ünlüce, mayor of Eskisehir.
To follow the original recipe as faithfully as possible, and since wheat Farro no longer exists in Turkey, the city decided, after analyzing bread, using Kavilca wheat (a similar variety), bulgur and lentils.
At Halk Ekmek's facilities (‘People's Bread’ in Turkish), a local bakery at low prices, employees make 300 küllüoba loaves every day since last week.
"The combination of ancient wheat flour, lentils and bulgur produces a rich and full -bodied bread, low with gluten and no preservatives," said Serap Güler, director of Halk Ekmek in Eskisehir.
The first Küllüoba breads, sold in packaging of 300 grams for 50 Turkish liras, sold out in a few hours. “I ran because I was afraid of nothing left. I was curious to know what the taste of this old bread was,” explains client Suzan Kuru.
“These lands have preserved this bread for 5,000 years and gave us this gift. We have a duty to protect this inheritance and transmit it,” says ünlüce.
Eskisehir province, once rich in water resources, now suffers from drought. "We are facing a climate crisis, but we still cultivate corn and sunflower, which requires a lot of water. Our ancestors have taught us a lesson. We should, like them, focus on cultures that require less water," the mayor emphasizes.
One of its objectives is to revive the cultivation of Kavilca wheat in the region, which is resistant to drought and disease. "We need very strong public policies for this issue. Cultivating ancestral wheats would be a symbolic advance in this regard," he said.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>