<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Malpated SME credit grew 14% in a year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/credito-malparado-das-pme-cresceu-14-num-ano/</link><description>The debt loans are still growing unpaid by small and medium enterprises, having already reached 5.64 billion patacas at the end of the first half of this year. Malpated credit has risen 14% in a year and about 27 times since the same period of 2019, according to official data, which is the highest amount since there are records. AMCM recalls that it has been encouraging the banking sector to negotiate “flexible refund plans, under the principle of prudent risk management”, to provide support to customers with “liquidity difficulties”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Debt loans not paid by the Small and Medium Enterprises (SMEs) of the territory cipher at 5.64 billion patacas at the end of the first half of this year, noting an increase of 14.4% or almost 705,000 patacas within one year. When compared to the end of the second half of last year, the bad SME credit rose 5.6% or about 302,000 patacas, according to data released by the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM).
Unpaid loans, involving interest and/or capital payments with delays of more than three months, thus performed two and a half years of consecutive climbs, having recorded the ninth semester increase since 2020. Official data show that liquidation debts grew 26.8 times, or 5.43 billion patacas, compared to the end of 2019. It is the highest value since 2008.
“Due mainly to the drop in the balance of debt loans granted to SMEs”, the non -paid debt ratio - proportion of loans with delayed settlements compared to the total credit granted to SMEs - advanced to 7.6% at the end of June 2025. This percentage represents a semiannual rise of 0.8 percentage points, an annual increase of 1.4 points and a growth of 7.4 points to the period Pre-Covid.
According to AMCM, in the first six months of this year, the new limit of banks approved by 47.7% to 4.93 billion, in relation to the previous six months, and rose 11.8% in annual terms. The warranty ratio, which illustrates the proportion of credit limit with promised body assets, set at 62.2%, corresponding to a decrease of 14.5 percentage points compared to the last semester of 2024 and a 15.4 points in annual terms.
Regarding the balance used of the loans granted to SMEs (74.34 billion patacas) suffered a semiannual decrease of 4.7% and an annual break of 7.2%. Between January and June this year, loans to the “Transport, Storage and Communications” sector increased by 14.1%, while attributed to “Grosso and Retail Trade” and “construction” decreased by 9.9%and 2.8%, respectively.
The use rate, defined as the proportion of the balanced balance sheet for the approved credit limit, grew 1.2 percentage points to 84.8%, when compared to the rate registered at the end of 2024. In addition, it increased by 3.8 points compared to the end of June 2024.
In a statement, AMCM recalls that "encourages the banking sector to negotiate with Flexible Reimbursement PMEs, under the principle of prudent risk management and in accordance with their own credit policies, continuing to provide credit support to customers with liquidity difficulties."
Recently, the president of the Macao Banks Association, IP Sio Kai, revealed that since the launch of the Bank Credit Bottle Plan for SMEs in mid -April, banks received 2,000 loan requirements, including 80% involving new loans. According to it, if all these requirements receive “green light”, they will involve more than three billion patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New consumer plan launched on September 1</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/novo-plano-de-consumo-lancado-1-de-setembro/</link><description>Between September 1 and November 30 this year, the Government and the Commercial Association will release the great award for consumption again, in order to “revitalize the confidence of the consumer market”. This time, the total amount to be assigned in the form of consumer benefits rose to 485 million patacas
 
The big consumption award will be held back in Macao, between September 1 and November 30, with a duration of 13 weeks and a total amount of 485 million patacas to be attributed to consumer benefits, "in order to give an injection of the community economy," the Macao Commercial Association (ACM), organizers of the initiative, announced.
At a press conference to announce the activity, entitled “Strength of National Games - major consumption award in community zones”, the objectives were highlighted: “boosting the continuous and stable recovery of Macao's economy during the usual tourist season about to arrive”, “responding to the enthusiastic environment of national games” and “revitalizing the confidence of the consumer market”.
The president of the ACM board, Frederico MA, said that in this edition, the association will continue to sponsor pecuniary awards expecting to increase attractiveness. He pointed out, all the promotional activities organized by the ACM and the government "were effective in attracting client flow and expanding clientele to small and medium local traders, encouraging residents to consume in Macao, increasing the confidence of the commercial sector and establishing a solid base for this initiative."
The director of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), Yau Yun Wah, said that the edition promoted between March and May “obtained remarkable successes”, pointing out that an inquiry shows that residents and commercial establishments expressed satisfaction with the initiative model, considering that it produced a positive effect on the encouragement of local consumption.
According to the Chinese language press, the official noted that the initiative budget was elevated from 295 million to 485 million patacas, representing an increase of 65%. In addition, he stated that he took into account the government's “cautious” analysis and consideration of Macao's current economic situation.
At this point, Yau Yun Wah said the government has noticed that some traders continue to face economic pressure, needing more time to adapt. "Budget reinforcement fully reflects the government's determination to actively respond to society's needs in the current economic environment, and support the local economy," he said.
The attribution of electronic benefits through mobile payments will maintain the usual model.
Throughout the activity, from Monday to Friday, when the electronic portfolio user, with real name authentication, make a mobile payment in the eligible stores in the amount of not less than 50 patacas for each transaction, can get three opportunities to earn discount coupons, which expire at midnight immediately.
Cups (with value of 10, 20, 50, 50, 100 and 200 patacas) should be used on Saturday and Sunday immediately following more than 20 physical stores, and the amount actually paid in each transaction should be equal to or higher than triple of the nominal value of the coupon. If you have several coupons in the same electronic wallet, they will be “exchanged” automatically in a single transaction as long as the requirement of “triple the value of the coupon” is satisfied.
In addition, on Saturdays and Sundays, beneficiary consumers can automatically participate in the luck. We will be drawn weekly three winners who can receive 8,000 patacas each in cash.
Organizers encourage and appeal to the most merchants to launch additional offers.
However, the initiative involves two perfected aspects, according to the government. The first is the increase in the value of the “immediate discount for the elderly” to 500 patacas, while the second is the assignment of a “social care card” with 500 patacas for immediate discount benefits to the holders of the Disability Evaluation Registration Card (CRAD).
According to DSEDT, 50% of the purchase value will be deducted directly from the amount of discount awarded (equivalent to 50% off), while the remaining 50% will be charged. In practical terms, holders of both types of cards may purchase goods or services in the total amount of 1,000 patacas using only 500 patacas of their money.
All 65-year-olds until November 28 may travel to more than 100 service posts designated to obtain the benefits by loading the Macau Pass card to the elderly. On the other hand, since yesterday, more than 40 institutions coordinated by the Institute of Social Action (IAS) began notifying and assisting users in surveying the social care card. The other CRD holders will be able to raise this card from September 1 in the five social action centers at the IAS General Rehabilitation Evaluation Center.
This group of beneficiaries covers individuals who have requested CRD until August 21 and approve by November 28. According to DSEDT, it is not possible to enjoy the two types of benefit simultaneously.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Visitors rose 14.5% in July</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/visitantes-subiram-145-em-julho/</link><description>In July, Macau had 437,177 visitors' entries, in relation to the same month as last year, translated into an increase of 14.5%, according to official data. In homologous terms, there were also 4,791 international visitors. In the first seven months of the year, the number of visitors has exceeded more than half of the government's predictions to 2025, which pointed to between 38 million and 39 million people
 
Pedro Milheirão
 
The MSAR registered 3,458,366 visitors in July, 14.5% more than in the same month of last year (3,021,189). In the first seven months of the year, the Board of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) accounted for 22,676,906 entries, plus 14.9% compared to the same period of 2024. There was also an increase in terms of international visitors, from 172,983, in July 2024, to 177,774 (+2.8%), the same month of this year.
The number of visitors in the first seven months of the year has already made more than half of the total planned by the director of tourism services, Helena de Senna Fernandes, at the beginning of the year, which announced that government expectations pointed to between 38 million and 39 million people over 2025.
In the month under review, the number of visitors from Portugal from Portugal grew 35.4%from 611 in 2024 to 827 this year. The amount of tourists from Thailand fired 48.9%, in annual terms, to 12,352, the 14,884 visitors from Indonesia corresponded to an annual increase of 9.7%and those from Singapore grew 2.9%to 5,836. The 15,796 entries of people from the US represented an increase of 6.2%.
In the opposite direction, the visitor entrances of the Philippines fell 11.8%to 37,912, while from Malaysia down 9.6%to 8,102, comparing July 2024 and 2025. In the same time interval, the entries of India decreased 12.2%to 6,167, and those of South Korea and Japan fell 1,6%and fell 1,6% 0.4%, respectively, to 32,288 and 8,743.
2,563,212 visitors from the interior of China registered in July correspond to an annual growth of 17.4%. Of these, 1,225,642 came from the large bay, translating a 23%annual increase, especially the growth of visitors from Zhuhai (+56.8%). In the same period under analysis, visitors to Hong Kong (625,343) and Taiwan (92,037) increased 6.2% and 21.4%, respectively. In the general calculation, the number of tour has grown 24.1% to a total of 1,980,732, and tourists increased 3.7% to 1,477,634.
The average time of permanence of visitors was 1.2 days in July. The tourists were, on average, 2.4 days in the masters. In turn, the tour remained 0.2 days. In the first seven months of 2025, the average permanence period of visitors was 1.1 days, less 0.1 than in the same interval of 2024. According to DSEC, this variation was due to “increasing the proportion of tour in relation to the total visitors”.
Earthly entrances (2,881,243) accounted for 83.3% of the total and an annual increase of 19.5%. The number of visitors to the siege doors rose 20.1%, while those by the Hengqin border post increased 43.2%in annual terms. The 323,296 maritime entries and 253,827 by air were 9.3% and 7.3% of the total, respectively, decreasing 2.6% and 8.6% compared to July 2024.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai began to hear opinions for lag elaboration</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sam-hou-fai-comecou-ouvir-opinioes-para-elaboracao-das-lag/</link><description>The Chief Executive heard opinions and suggestions of elements of various quarters of society, as part of the elaboration of the Governing Line Report for the Financial Year 2026. Some of the questions raised point to greater development of intelligent governance, the improvement of the platform function between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries, the impulse of the modernization of the legal system, the development of the economy of the neighborhoods and the support for small businesses and medium businesses.
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Opinions and suggestions from Macau deputies to the Popular National Assembly (ANP) were presented to the Chief Executive, as part of the preparation of the Governing Action Lines Report (LAG) for the financial year of 2026.
At the meeting that took place at the government's headquarters, members of the APP PERMANENT COMMITTEE and Macao deputies to that organ raised several issues, including a greater development of intelligent governance, the creation of sovereign funds, the improvement of the platform function between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries and the impulse of the modernization of the legal system of Macao.
In addition, they also addressed reinforcement of the boost of the economy of the neighborhoods, the continuous optimization of the civil protection mechanism, the improvement of the mechanism and system of the in -depth cooperation zone, the improvement of traffic management, the inspection of artificial intelligence, the response to the low birth rate, the support of schools in improving the conditions of its operation and the use of young people.
The government was also proposed to create a team of experts (Think Tank), in order to “provide scientific and strong foundations in political decision -making and continues to optimize the increasingly frequent, and more frequent meteorological events, as you can read in a statement of the social communication cabinet.
Several participants also drawn attention to issues about the development of the economy of neighborhoods, suggesting to the government the organization of more activities that benefit consumption, attracting greater flow of people. In response to the proposals of the elements linked to ANP, Sam Hou Fai has guaranteed that it will forward them to the various tutelage “to be studied and analyzed”.
He also pointed out that the government will take into account the general situation and will adopt “a proactive and innovative approach, to deepen administrative reform, reinforce coordination, strive to promote and revitalize the economy of neighborhoods, launch various measures and organize activities according to the singularities of the neighborhoods”, giving as an example, in the latter, the “Zape with flares” events, and the requests of the Esplanades license, who have obtained license positive effects ”.
With the same objective -the preparation of the LAG report -Sam Hou Fai received the members of Macao in the National Committee of the Chinese Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC) and CCPPC members in the Macao instance.
At the meeting, there was talk of the impetus of the proper diversification of the economy, the increase in the use rate of the Hengqin Border Post, the construction of the Macao International Education City, the revitalization of the economy in the neighborhoods and the housing policy.
Analyzed were also other matters, such as the reinforcement of business and investment capture, the use of young people, the policy of non-resident workers and the optimization of transport infrastructure.
Members proposed to the government to build more low -cost hotels to streamline visitors consumption and the economy of the neighborhoods, as well as continue to make the initiative of the “large consumption award in community zones”, in order to stimulate local consumption and support SMEs.
The opinions and suggestions presented "will be analyzed and will serve as a reference," said the chief executive, indicating that the government gives "high importance" to community development and the improvement of the population's well-being. "The competent services will continue to improve the work based on the opinions of merchants and residents, collected in the neighborhoods," he said.
The Secretaries for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, and for transport and public works, Raymond Tam, were present in both sessions, having responded to subjects related to their guardianship.
 
Of tourist experience to civil servants
Representatives of the industrial, commercial and financial sectors also presented proposals to SAM Hou Fai, aiming at the elaboration of LAG. Elements linked to 16 associations participated in the meeting, which spoke, among other subjects, about the promotion of “silver economy”, the acceleration of urban renewal, the development of the seafront, the sector of higher education, and the incentive to the transformation and update of the convention and exhibition sector.
It was also pointed out that in order to increase Macao's full competitiveness as an international tourism city, the government must raise the travel experience of tourists through the development of the concert industry, the support for local cultural and creative intellectual property and the improvement of public transport network measures, attracting tourist flow to promote the development of the economy of the neighborhoods.
Concretely with regard to SME support, the head of the governing team of MSA has promised to adopt various measures to increase the flow of people in the neighborhoods and guide the market in its transformation to new consumption models.
Also representatives of six civil service workers associations moved to the government's headquarters. Proposals have been fundamentally focused on protecting workers' rights and interests, continuous improvement of training for public administration personnel, optimizing the subsidies regime, increasing the effectiveness of inter-departmental work, in the study of the proper adjustment of the seniority prize, in the revision of the retirement regime of civil servants, as well as a higher requirement for the quality of management and head.
Some members also suggested improving the internal mobility mechanism, as well as increasing the relevance between the formation and the functions of civil servants in order to support the modernization of the system and governance capacity of Macao.
Sam Hou Fai stated that it will be promoted, “stable”, the reform of the public administration and “the increase of consciousness and the quality in the provision of services in general”.
He added that the government "gives high importance to the quality of management and leadership staff and that the recent conclusion of the discussion of the" Amendment to Administrative Regulation "project will also" reinforce the proactivity of civil servants and improve government efficiency. "
In these two meetings were the secretaries for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP, for transport and public works, Raymond Tam, for administration and justice, André Cheong, and for security, Wong Sio Chak.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Brightness of the East” brings together musicians from China, Japan and Korea</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/brilho-oriente-junta-musicos-da-china-japao-coreia/</link><description>Twelve musicians from China, Japan and South Korea will participate in the starting concert of the new season of the Macao Chinese Orchestra, entitled “Brightness of the East”, in a celebration of the East Asian Culture City. The show is scheduled for August 30, at the large auditorium of the Cultural Center, and tickets are already on sale
 
Titled “Brightness of the East”, the opening concert of the 2025/2026 season of the Chinese Macao Orchestra is scheduled for August 30, at 8 pm, at the Great Auditorium of the Cultural Center. Under the baton of the musical director and main conductor, Zhang Lie, the concert will feature the debut of the Symphonic Suite of Traditional Chinese Music “Brightness of the East”, jointly composed by composers of China, Japan and South Korea, “in a creation that celebrates cultural integration and the artistic synergy of the three countries in the Cultural Culture Program”, indicates the cultural institute ” (IC).
The concert will also include a selection of ordained works and classic pieces of regional inspiration, adds the body, indicating that tickets are already available through the Macao online ticket office.
To celebrate the designation of Macau as “Culture of East Asia 2025”, the Chinese orchestra of Macau also invited Chinese composer Zhao Lin, young composer Luo Maishuo, Japanese music master Kaoru Wada and Korean composer of traditional music park bum-hoon, to collaborate in the creation of the traditional symphonic suite music suite Chinese “brightness of the east”.
The work will be interpreted by 12 musicians from the three countries, who will play traditional musical instruments such as Chinese Pipa and Zhongruan, Shakuhachi and Japanese Shamisen, and Haegeum and Gayageum Koreans, "revealing vividly revealing the ethnic characteristics and musical essence of the three cultures, promising a unique and surrounding action."
The Chinese orchestra of Macao will also play “Macao Night”, a work commissioned to Singapore Cultural Medal, Eric Watson, as well as other prominent regional pieces, with a view to sharing with the audience “The Vibrant Cultural Identity of Macau through music”.
The 2025/2026 Concerts Season of the Macao Chinese Orchestra is organized by the Culturale Institute, co-organized by the Macao Orchestra Society, limited, and is supported by Banco da China (Macau).
Tickets for the opening concert are available at the Macao online box office at 120, 180, 250 and 380 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Government wants to use road facilities on ZAP</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-quer-optimizar-instalacoes-rodoviarias-zape/</link><description>The chief executive visited the “Zape with flavors” fair and acknowledged that the convenience of road and transport facilities is “crucial” to facilitate the circulation of residents and attract more visitors to that area of ​​the city. On the other hand, he encouraged traders to inject a new dynamic for the sustainable development of the community economy
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The “Zape with Flavors” event, which took place for 10 days and yesterday ended, is considered by the government as a pilot project that aims to revitalize the business environment, combining elements such as gastronomy, cultural and creative products and game trends.
Visiting the scene, the Chief Executive stained with the situation and business exploitation, as well as the flow of people who rode the event, and said that a synthesis of the results obtained to identify the aspects that must be improved will be prepared.
Sam Hou Fai encouraged traders to develop more distinct elements of consumption attraction, collaborating with the government in the constitution of the “Zape” brand and the “injection of a new dynamic for the sustainable development of the community economy”.
The official rode from the scene of the fair to Avenida da Amizade, where the secretary for transport and public works, Raymond Tam, presented the ideas about the optimization of road facilities surrounding Zape, including measures that will facilitate the crossing of Avenida da Friendship by the passers.
The entourage then moved to NAPE through the public parking park nearby, and was part of the parking conditions of vehicles with the Zape and the current situation when it walks between the two areas.
The chief executive stressed that the convenience of road and transport facilities is “crucial” to facilitate the circulation of residents and attract more visitors to Zape. Thus, according to a text released by the Social Communication Office, has already instructed the competent services to ponderate, “from a global perspective”, the connection of the pedestrian paths of the different zones, including the creation of better conditions for pedestrians to easily walk between Zape and Nape.
Also present at the site, the Director of Tourism Services (STD) stressed that “this activity has had a more satisfactory effect than expectations”, noting that throughout the event the immediate hotels “were encouraged” to provide discounts to customers, and the sector has received positive reactions.
Helena de Senna Fernandes revealed, on the other hand, that STD is studying the hypothesis of installing on the streets of Cantão and Shanghai parallel spaces for the “International Festival of Cities of Gastronomy”, scheduled for March next year.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Inflation rate continues to retreat</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/taxa-de-inflacao-continua-recuar/</link><description>In the annual cycle ended in July, Macau registered a 0.28% rise in the General Index of Average Consumer Price (IPC) compared to the immediately preceding 12 months, falling short of 0.34% marked in June, according to the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services. The percentage of IPC increase in this comparative base, the most used by economists to calculate the annual inflation rate, has continually decreased since August 2024.
In the same time window closed in July, the IPC rose 0.25% in level A, which encompasses about 50% of family aggregates with monthly expenses between 11,000 and 35,999 patacas, and 0.30% in category B, which includes 30% of families with average spending between 36,000 and 71,999 patacas. In general, the increases in the indexes of the sections of various products and services (+2.29%), education (+1.29%) and leisure, recreation, sport and culture (+1.22%) and decreases in transport (-2.72%) and information and communication (-1.85%).
The General IPC rose, on the other hand, 0.12%compared to July 2024, with the largest variation to be focused on the leisure, recreation, sport and culture section (+3.21%), contrary to the descents in information and communication (-3.00%) and clothing and footwear (-2.54%). The DSEC also states that the price index of the section of food products and non-alcoholic beverages grew 0.30%, "thanks mainly to the climbing of dining prices acquired away from home and" Take-Away ", while housing and fuels rose 0.22%," due to increased home rents. "
In addition, the CPI rose 0.11%in the monthly comparison, with DSEC highlighting variations in the leisure, recreation, sport and culture section (+2.03%), “due to the increase in hotel tours and rooms”, and transport (+0.72%). In the opposite direction, that of clothing and footwear decreased 0.87% and that of various products and services (such as personal care, insurance, jewelery) decreased 0.18%.
In the first seven months of the year, the average General IPC grew 0.18%, compared to the same period last year. It is noteworthy that the price index of the section of food products and non-alcoholic beverages increased 0.46%. IPC-A and IPC-B, both average indices, rose 0.13% and 0.21%, compared to the identical period of the previous year.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Game with more workers and greater salaries</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jogo-mais-trabalhadores-maiores-salarios/</link><description>The average remuneration of the workers in the game sector rose 2.4%in the first half of the year, in relation to the same period of 2024. There was also an increase of 380 workers, in homologous terms
 
In the first six months of this year, the average remuneration of workers in the game sector was 27,390 patacas, 2.4% more than in the first half of 2024, according to official data. Until June, salaries earned by residents registered an average value of 27,340 patacas, plus 2.4%. In particular, the average salaries of directors and leading staff were the ones that increased the most, about 1,830 monthly patacas (+2.78%), from 65,760 to 67,590. In reverse, the average remuneration of experts from intellectual and scientific areas fell from 43,490 to 41,730 patacas (-4.05%).
In addition, the inequality between genres was accentuated in terms of remuneration. Male workers registered an average salary increase of 3.5%, in annual terms, considering that by the end of June, men earned an average of 29,770 patacas per month, and in the same period last year this value was 28,750. Women, in turn, began to earn an average salary of 25,690 patacas (+1.4%).
At the end of the first half of the year, there were more women than men to work in the sector. Of the staff at service, 30,856 were female, in view of 22,042 men. In general, there were 52,898 full -time workers at the end of the second quarter, 380 more than those registered in June last year (52,518), according to the direction of statistics and census services.
Executive staff and directors were those that increased. At the end of the first semester there were 3,183, more 390 (13.96%) than in the same period as 2024 (2,793). The amount of croupiers also increased from 23,467 to 23,500. On the other hand, the number of administrative employees registered a slight decrease, from 41,366 to 41,274, translated into a loss of 92 workers.
In addition, there were 190 employees of treasury, files and boxes, heads and boards of bank and betting operators, among others. At the end of June, 14,707 of these professionals were accounted for, compared to 14,897 of the same month last year. Banking and game room chiefs also decreased at the same time interval from 3,671 to 3,581. Similarly, banking assistants and “croupiers” supervisors went from 8,503 to 8,360.
Most workers (41,924) continued to operate in large establishments, with more than five thousand employees. The number of vacancies also fell to more than half. There were 208 places available at the end of June, and at the end of the second quarter of last year, there were 498.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Summer Paradise” in CCM Square</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/paraiso-de-verao-na-praca-ccm/</link><description>The Macau Cultural Center Square will be the scene of numerous activities within the scope of the “Micaf Fun Day” Arts at Party, Closing Program, the International Children's Arts Festival. This activity began this weekend and will happen again next, indicated the Cultural Institute (IC), which organizes the initiative with Sands China.
According to the body, this year were installed large -scale, 10 meters high, sprinklers and a container zone, which allow you to "turn the square into a fantastic summer paradise." In addition to the “Foam Festival” and “Aquatic Fun Festival”, the event will feature a gastronomy zone, a children's costume zone, behind -the -scenes visits, workshops and games.
But there is also room for shows such as the Master of Andas Master, street dance played by children, acrobatics on a single -cycle, freestyle rope, belly dance, cheerleading performance, clowns and other interactive events.
The IC reported that the “Talent Show” session will be added, where children will be able to show their talents, and will also be presented a program of local and international outdoor animation shorts. In this context, the topics covered will be the valorization of life, child innocence and the worlds of fantasy.
On the other hand, on August 30 and 31, at 6 pm, Sands China will invite the Macao Band Regent Association to present two concerts to the free air, namely the “little musicians”-concert of the new stars of the wind instruments and “the beginning of a dream”-Disney classic concert. During the two days of the event, there will also be room to “exchange one book for another”, where the public is invited to bring their books and make the exchanges.
The Micaf mascot and “Mak Mak”, as well as the “Xiyangyang” and “Lerongrong” mascots of the National Games will also be present to live with the children.
Registration for the second week's sessions (August 29-31) of the “Talent Show”, “Adventure Behind the Scenes”, “Foam Festival” and “Aquatic Fun Festival” can be made from 12:00 pm on August 27th through the official page of the International Arts Festival for Macao Children. The IC indicates that there will be a limited number of places available for registration on site, which will be assigned in order of arrival.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Retail trade contracts 9%</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/comercio-retalho-contrai-9/</link><description>The turnover of retail trade establishments was 33.55 billion patacas in the first six months of the year, which corresponds to a decrease of 9%in annual terms. Between April and June, the volume was 15.97 billion, 1.4% less than in the same period of 2024 (16.2 billion), and a 9.3% decrease over the first three months of 2025 (17.58 billion). According to the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), in the first half of the year, leather and cosmetic and hygiene products registered breaks of 15.8% and 14.3%, respectively, compared to the first half of 2024. On the other hand, the volume of car businesses and the pharmacies grew 3.6% and 4.5%, in annual terms. Between April and June, adult clothing descended 21.5%over the previous quarter, and Chinese foods and sweets dropped 18.1%and supermarkets fell 8.9%. During the second quarter, clocks and jewelery represented more than one fifth of the total turnover (22.3%), followed by leather (19.9%) and warehouses and trinkets (13.9%). The sales volume rate, in turn, fell 11.4%from 124.31 to 110.19, compared to the first semesters of 2024 and 2025. According to DSEC, 40%of retailers predict that the sales situation decreases in the third quarter, and the majority (54.7%) expects the situation to stabilize.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UTM records record of new students</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/utm-regista-recorde-de-novos-estudantes/</link><description>The University of Tourism of Macau (UTM) welcomed 1,000 new undergraduate and postgraduate students, which is the highest number of enrollment in the history of the educational establishment. At the mud campus, the dean, Fanny Vong, said that the recent renewal of the Yiu Tung building and the educational residence will provide “more complete educational and training facilities”. On the same day of the reception to students, the UTM took effect, dealing with the “intellectual property rights and combating illegal trafficking”, oriented by customs employees, “cybercrime and fraud prevention”, taught by the Judiciary Police, and “disclosure of labor laws”, with representatives of services for work affairs. Also the Macao Polytechnic University (UPM) received 3,000 students who will attend the undergraduate, master's and doctoral courses in the new academic year. The students come from Macau, the Great Bay, the interior of China and the Portuguese -speaking countries. At the opening and launching ceremony of the orientation activities 2025/2026, the rector, Marcus Im, emphasized the inheritance of the spirit of “Love for the Fatherland and Macao”, and the contribution of wisdom and energy to the development of the country and masters. Chinese Olympic champions Jiao Liuyang and Zhang Yangyang spoke on behalf of the new students, affirming their conviction of integrating "the combative spirit of athletes in their academic careers." UPM added to this year several postgraduate courses, including PhD in Applied Sciences of Language and Physical Education and Sports Sciences, and Masters in Environmental Intelligence and Technology and Innovation in Sport.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Revelation” at the Porto Book Fair</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/apocalipses-na-feira-livro-porto/</link><description>The artistic book “Revelation”, a joint project of local anthropologist Cheong Kin Man and Polish artist Marta Stanisława Sala, integrates, until September 7, the Greta Lisbon Bookstore stand at the Porto Book Fair, after traveling Singapore, Kuala Lumpur, Nuremberg, Berlin, Lisbon, Słupsk, Katonia (Poland) and Junction. Inspired by science fiction, the work narrates the tension between natural humans and artificial beings endowed with extreme intelligence. Originally designed for the Macao Biennial in 2023, the artist book includes 60 pages and hundreds of fictitious ideograms. This initial version is still available in independent bookstores from Berlin, such as Hopscotch and Encounters Bookspace. The 720 -page expanded edition, launched in June at the Goethe Institute of Lisbon, was sponsored by the Oriente Foundation (FO). Produced in limited circulation, with numbered specimens and signed by the artists, the volume adds more than 500 new signs to the initial book. The supplement resulted from an exhibition project carried out in 2024 in Bavaria, in cooperation with the municipal councils of Krakow and Nuremberg and the Confucius Institute, which also had support from FO. In June, the book also accompanied Macao's literary and musical events in Lisbon, and was presented at Atelier Artery, the Goethe Institute and the Hangar - Artistic Research Center, as well as at the Soares dos Reis National Museum in Porto, according to the Krakow Chamber in a note to the international press. Colombian curator Lorena Tabares Salamanca, who was part of the recent show of the duo at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center in Lisbon, emphasized, in a statement to the public, the book by the way “navigates the critical character of multiple languages ​​and cosmogeographies”, using “artistic and relational tactics, which, in its ability to convene the gesture and the gesture and the gesture Act, invite us to participate in the “deconstruction” of meanings.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2461/</link><description>Resident arrested for mistreating cats
A 30 -year -old resident man will have mistreated two cats, claiming that they had bitten his shoes. It was the suspect's own girlfriend, to whom the pets belonged, who made the complaint. To realize aggression to felids, the individual will have used a broom three times and a range. The tests performed by the Institute for Municipal Affairs revealed that the cats suffered injuries to the paws and eyes. The suspect was sent to the prosecutor, accused of crime of cruelty against animals.
 
Heater explosion hurts five people
An instant water heater exploded inside a fraction near the siege doors. The accident caused light injuries to passersby, three men and two women, aged 52 and 87 years. Four were transported to the hospital while another rejected receiving medical treatment. According to the firefighters, the case was caused by a mechanical damage. The explosion also reached walls and doors of two nearby housing. According to soil services and urban construction, a preliminary evaluation was performed to the structure of the building, and the hypothesis of danger was ruled out. In turn, the Institute of Social Action has provided temporary accommodation, emotional support and other services to one of the affected people.
 
Detected 8th imported case of chikungunya fever
Health services (SSM) were notified of an imported case of chikungunya fever, the 8th this year. This is a nine-year resident, who studies in the interior of China and lives permanently in Zhuhai. The patient had visited family members in Canton, finding himself currently at his home in Zhuhai, in a stable state. The SSM were also notified for an imported case of dengue fever and one of Legionella. As for the case of dengue fever, the 10th of this year involves a 33 -year -old TNR, which traveled to Malaysia. The patient is hospitalized in a stable state.
 
Young man broke down windows with simulated air pistols
A 20 -year -old local college student used three simulated air pistols, causing damage to windows of two housing fractions. According to the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP), some victims heard glass sounds to break and warned the authorities. The young man was intercepted the next day, and, despite admitting the crime, did not explain the reasons. The owners of the two fractions claimed losses of 5,000 and 2,000 patacas. CPSP has confirmed that the pistols have an import license.
 
Discovered 87 suspected cases of illegal work
Operations to combat illegal workers, carried out in July, indicate that 546 locations were inspected, with 87 suspicious cases. The actions developed individually, or together, by the Public Security Police Corps and the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs, as well as other services, took place in construction shipyards, private buildings and commercial and industrial establishments.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt reveals traces of submerged city with over 2,000 years</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/egipto-revela-vestigios-de-cidade-submersa-mais-de-2-000-anos/</link><description>Egypt has presented this weekend traces of a submerged city in front of the coast of Alexandria, including buildings, tombs, fish tanks and a quay, all over 2,000 years old.
According to the authorities, the site, located in Abu Qir Bay, can correspond to an extension of the ancient city of Canopo, an important center of the Ptolemaic dynasty - which ruled Egypt for almost three centuries - and later from the Roman Empire, which remained there for about 600 years.
Over time, a series of earthquakes and the increase in sea level submerged the city and neighboring port of Heracleion.
Now this weekend, large cranes have removed several statues. "There are many elements under water, but what we can recover is limited; they are only parts selected according to strict criteria," said Tourism and Antiques Minister Sherif Fathi.
"The rest will remain as an integral part of our underwater heritage," he added.
The findings include limestone buildings that would have served as places of cult, houses or commercial and handcrafted structures.
Rock deposits and tanks were also identified, intended for both aquaculture and water storage for domestic consumption.
Among the most notable pieces are real statues and sphinxes prior to the Roman period, including a partially preserved Ramesses II.
Also found were a merchant ship, anchors of stone and even a port crane where a 125 meter pier was used as port for smaller vessels during the Roman and Byzantine seasons.
Site of great archaeological wealth, Alexandria is currently threatened by the same waters that submerged canopy and heracleion.
The coastal city sinks more than three millimeters per year and is among the areas most vulnerable to climate change and increased sea level.
Even in the most optimistic scenario elaborated by the UN, a third of Alexandria will be submerged or uninhabitable in 2050, which will be a disaster for what is still left of the founded city, in 331 BC, by one of the great generals ever, the Greek Alexandre Great. This city that was built on a piece of land already occupied by a small Egyptian village between the Mediterranean Sea and Lake Mareotis (Mariout Lake) is undergoing climate change.
For those who do not know, even today are iconic places to their great library, the largest in the ancient world, and the Lighthouse of Alexandria (Pharos), one of the seven wonders of the ancient world, and the catacombs of Kom El Shoqafa are now considered one of the seven wonders of the Middle Ages.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>