<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Taxi drivers defend fare adjustments similar to those on the Mainland and Hong Kong</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/taxistas-defendem-ajustes-das-tarifas-similares-aos-continente-hong-kong/</link><description>In 2026, representatives of the taxi sector will be able to submit a new request to DSAT to increase taxi fares, revealed the director of the General Union of Taxi Drivers to the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper, assuming that he expects adjustments similar to those adopted in Mainland China and Hong Kong, which vary between 10% and 15%. Tony Kuok also argued that the Government should be “cautious” in the plan to increase the total number of taxis to 2,000, suggesting that authorities start by granting 300 new licenses next year. From his perspective, the issue of labor is worrying and it is important to take into account the impact of fleet expansion on traffic
 
The director of the General Union of Taxi Drivers of Macau revealed that he will discuss increasing taxi fares and may submit a formal request to that effect to the Traffic Affairs Services Bureau (DSAT) next year.
Speaking to the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper, Tony Kuok said that he will take as a reference the adjustments adopted in Mainland China and Hong Kong, to propose increases of between 10% and 15%, at checkout, and in charges after checkout based on travel distance, among other fees, in order to ensure a general increase in fares in the sector.
It is worth remembering that, in February 2024, taxi fares in Macau rose from 19 to 21 patacas, reflecting an increase of 10.5%. At the same time, two patacas were also charged for every 220 meters after the checkered flag, whereas previously the amount covered 240 meters. The value of the additional fee for taking a taxi, for example, at the Airport or Ponte do Delta, was also revised upwards.
On the other hand, the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, recently announced that 800 new taxis will be launched, which will bring the total number in Macau to more than 2,000. However, Tony Kuok considers that the Executive must be “cautious” in implementing this plan.
"I believe it will be difficult to implement the plan of 2,000 taxis in a space of one or two years. A supply of that level is viable, but a lot of preparations will be needed for the vehicles to start circulating on the roads. I suggest that the authorities first launch 300 new taxis next year, instead of adding everything at once, because it is necessary to hire drivers, who will also watch the business and the profits. If business is not good, they may leave the sector. It is better to do this with calm down”, he analyzed.
For the association leader, a sector size of 2,000 taxis “should already be the maximum”. First of all, he warns, the issue of labor is worrying, especially if there is a notable expansion in the fleet, especially because “old taxi drivers will gradually retire”, and “many young taxi drivers may leave the sector just one to two months after working”.
But why? According to Tony Kuok, the taxi driver profession is just “one of two or three occupational options” for these local young people, who may give up as soon as they find other opportunities. “In addition, the Government is now appealing to young people to develop in Hengqin”, he pointed out, attributing the “relatively high” abandonment rate in the sector also to this trend.
As noted, following the closure of satellite casinos, the taxi sector welcomed “a little more people to drive”, however, its possible continuation is, realistically, linked to the ability to profit in this sector, reiterated the association leader.
Kuok's concerns also extend to the possible worsening of traffic congestion. Taxi drivers usually provide services departing from San Ma Lo or around the Delta Bridge, where they already face this problem, he warned.
In recent years, the problem of traffic jams on the roads has already contributed to a “slight decrease” in the number of kilometers traveled by taxis, said the same official.
 
Taxi business “is nothing special”
In general, the sector's businesses “did not register significant increases” this year, guarantees Tony Kuok. "Although more and more visitors are coming, consumption models are already different. Therefore, with the exception of holidays, our business is nothing special", he highlights.
By reviewing the Regulations for the Transport of Passengers in Light Rented Cars or Taxis in 2026, the Government also intends to create favorable conditions for the introduction of the taxi hailing service via online platforms. Expressing support for this legislative guideline, Tony Kuok revealed that the Government has already started discussing the matter with the association, which currently manages a mobile application designed to call taxis online, as well as other platforms, such as Gaode, a company that provides digital maps, navigation and location services for Mainland China.
In this regard, the association leader understands that taxi drivers who collaborate with future online platforms “must be holders of a taxi driver identification card”, because these services must be provided by “well-standardized drivers”.
Furthermore, Kuok believes that it will be possible to implement an additional fee for taking taxis called through the respective platforms. "It is necessary to charge an additional fee, because the development and maintenance of an application or platform has costs. The Government can discuss with the Legislative Assembly the online call fee charged for each service, to find an appropriate value", he indicated.
"There are rules about taxis, vehicles and drivers. Now we have everything. So it will be very easy. DSAT told us that [the platforms] will be launched soon", concluded the director of the General Union of Taxi Drivers.
It is recalled that, in the debate on the Lines of Government Action for 2026, the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, announced that, in the short term, 100 new taxis will be added.
Recently, in response to a written question from MP Lee Koi Ian, DSAT stated that the “public tender” scheduled for the short term will involve “a new series of general taxi licenses”. Specifically, it will include licenses for “black taxis”, with the aim of “replenishing the number of taxis (both regular and special) whose licenses expire”.
According to DSAT, “in this tender, with a view to facilitating the mobility of people in vulnerable situations, clauses relating to the introduction of accessible taxis will be included”. In this regard, Secretary Raymond Tam has already announced the intention to increase the number of accessible taxis from seven to 28 and for new barrier-free taxis to begin operating successively in 2026.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Xi Jinping praises Sam Hou Fai</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/xi-jinping-enaltece-sam-hou-fai/</link><description>The Chief Executive of the Macao SAR was received yesterday in Beijing by the Chinese President as part of the presentation of the Government's work during this year and the main points of the Lines of Government Action for 2026. At the meeting, Xi Jinping stated, from the outset, that “Sam Hou Fai has scrupulously fulfilled his responsibilities”.
Furthermore, he said that Sam led the new Macao SAR Government in “firmly defending the country’s security sovereignty, rights and development interests, with an entrepreneurial and pragmatic spirit”.
Xi highlighted the smooth holding of elections for the Legislative Assembly (LA), as well as the promotion of public administration reform, the Macao SAR's “active participation” in the development of the Greater Bay Area, the “new results” obtained in the adequate diversification of the economy and the “new progress in various causes”.
“The Central Government fully recognizes the work of Sam Hou Fai and the Government of the Macao SAR”, stressed Xi, stressing that Macau must “proactively articulate” with the 15th National Five-Year Plan, “integrating and better serving the national development situation”.
Sam Hou Fai, in turn, considered that, with the “full support” of Beijing, the local government “led sectors of society to deeply comply with the spirit of the important speech given by President Xi Jinping”, on the occasion of the 25th anniversary of the Macao SAR.
He also argued that the system of predominance of executive power “has worked well”, also highlighting the “success” of the elections for the AL and the holding of the 15th edition of the National Games, in a joint organization of Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau. At the same time, he said that “the social situation has maintained harmony and stability, with Macau’s economic and social development achieving new progress in a stable scenario”.
Sam Hou Fai promised to “in-depth study and implement” the spirit of the 4th Plenary Session of the 20th Central Committee of the Communist Party of China and “closely coordinate” with the 15th National Five-Year Plan, through the 3rd Five-Year Plan of the Macao SAR. The aim is to boost economic diversification, accelerate the construction of Hengqin and create a broader development space for Macau, he added.
Xi also received the Chief Executive of Hong Kong yesterday, also praising the work of John Lee and his administration, and once again expressing his condolences to the victims of the fire in Tai Po. Lee “led the HKSAR government with courage and responsibility, safeguarding national sovereignty, security and development interests,” said the Chinese leader.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Request mental health survey every five years</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pedido-inquerito-sobre-saude-mental-de-cinco-em-cinco-anos/</link><description>A comprehensive survey on the mental health of the entire population carried out every five years is what MP Ho Ion Sang calls for, who considers that “the absence of regular large-scale surveys of the population prevents an accurate assessment of the real distribution of mental health problems”. Furthermore, the parliamentarian calls for the publication of other types of statistics, such as the types of diseases treated in the field of Psychiatry, service usage rates and waiting times
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Ho Ion Sang argues that authorities should launch a mental health survey every five years. Furthermore, the deputy considers that there is a lack of information and statistical data on the subject. Although he admits that the Government publishes statistics on the volume of services provided in daytime external consultations, among others, Ho Ion Sang points out that these data do not allow us to understand “the true nature of demand”.
Noting that, in 2024, the number of outpatient psychiatric consultations in Macau reached 50,597, the deputy states, in a written interpellation, that “this number not only reflects the urgency of service needs, but also highlights the serious challenges that the existing service system faces”. “With the fast pace of society and the increasing pressures of daily life, the demand for mental health services among Macau residents has shown a persistent upward trend,” he added.
For the deputy linked to the education sector, “there is a lack of detailed categorization” for key indicators, such as the distribution of types of patients, prevalence rates of mental illnesses and rates of use of public services. “This makes it difficult to precisely identify the specific needs of different groups and limits the precision of service provision”, he argued.
On the other hand, it also considers that “the absence of regular large-scale surveys of the population prevents an accurate assessment of the real distribution of mental health problems in communities”. In his view, “this data deficiency easily compromises the effectiveness of the ‘four-level joint prevention’ mechanism”.
Therefore, Ho Ion Sang questioned the Government about whether the Health Services (HHS) can launch a comprehensive survey on the mental health of the entire population every five years. “This would allow the systematic collection of essential data on the prevalence, incidence and risk factors of mental illnesses, allowing these analytical conclusions to serve as a basis for decision-making in service planning and resource allocation”, he explained.
He also asked whether the authorities will improve the data collection mechanism, “for example, by adding detailed classifications, such as the types of diseases treated, service use rates and waiting times” in this area. Furthermore, the deputy also wants to know how the authorities intend to improve data analysis and application capabilities.
It should be noted that the Health Services stopped publishing statistical data on suicides in Macau and, more recently, the Office of the Secretary for Security also stopped publishing information on suicides and parasuicides within the scope of crime data.
Asked by this newspaper why this data was not published now and asked to reveal the numbers on suicides and parasuicides in the first nine months of this year, Chan Tsz King's Office said only that the information on crime was presented last Friday for public information. JTM insisted again, but so far has not received any further response.
Remember that, last year, 90 people ended their lives in Macau, according to SSM monitoring data compiled by this newspaper. The number not only represented an increase of 2.3% compared to the previous year but was also the highest in at least the last 11 years.
Until June, and according to statistics previously published by the Security Authority, 41 people committed suicide in Macau: one was between 5 and 14 years old, five were between 15 and 24 years old, and nine were between 25 and 34 years old. There were also five people who ended their lives aged between 35 and 44, followed by nine more (45-54 years old), five (55-64 years old), five (65-74 years old) and two aged 75 or over.
Suicide attempts in the first half of the year were 101, with 14 cases in the age group from 5 to 14 years old and 30 cases from 15 to 24 years old.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Vice-rector of UCM defends reinforcement of studies on PLP</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/vice-reitor-da-ucm-defende-reforco-de-estudos-sobre-os-plp/</link><description>To deepen the functions of the Sino-Lusophone platform, the vice-rector of the UCM, Ip Kuai Peng, considers it essential to reinforce systematic studies dedicated to Portuguese-speaking countries. From his perspective, this will be effective in accurately conveying China's stories abroad. Furthermore, he advocated the intensification of financial cooperation with Portuguese-speaking countries, the attraction of scientific innovation projects from China and the PLP to establish themselves in Hengqin and the training of interdisciplinary bilingual staff through the development of higher education in Hengqin
 
The vice-rector of the City University of Macau (UCM), Ip Kuai Peng, considers that, given the “profound changes” in the global panorama and the entry of the “One Belt, One Road” initiative into a “new phase of high-quality development”, the Macao SAR needs to further enrich the functions of the Sino-Lusophone platform. Particularly through new achievements in the fields of international communication and regional studies.
In a speech given at a thematic lecture on studies of regions and countries, held at the School of Foreign Languages ​​of the Harbin Institute of Technology, Ip Kuai Peng highlighted that, in the context of the current international situation, it is necessary to intensify and carry out in-depth systematic studies focused on Portuguese-speaking countries (PLP), among other relevant regions, in accordance with the rules of international communication. In his view, this can help the Macao SAR to effectively play the role of a Sino-Lusophone platform.
According to Jornal do Cidadão, the director of the Institute for Research on the PLP argued that “only with a deep knowledge of the history and culture, social structure, spiritual values ​​and preferences of the public of the target countries will it be possible to achieve an accurate transmission [of China's stories]”, increasing the affinity and effectiveness of China's external communication.
In this sense, he called on the academic sector, the Government and companies to make joint efforts to “deeply integrate” the studies of regions and countries into the practice of international communication, so that the “voices of China” are truly heard, understood and recognized.
 
More interdisciplinary bilingual talent
Furthermore, the UCM vice-rector pointed to three approaches in creating the Sino-Lusophone platform. Firstly, he suggested that, focusing on the area of ​​“finance+”, the authorities make good use of the Macao SAR's internationalized financial resources, in order to attract foreign investment to Macau's physical economy, as well as resort to financial cooperation to deepen mutual trust with Portuguese-speaking countries.
He also highlighted the importance of promoting the construction of the “Science and Technology Exchange and Cooperation Center between China and the PLP” and of attracting scientific innovation projects to be established in the Deep Cooperation Zone, with scientific innovation as the driving force.
On the other hand, Ip Kuai Peng wants to see the acceleration of the formation of interdisciplinary cadres who master Chinese and Portuguese, with the support of space and preferential policies in that area, in order to provide intellectual support for the sustainable development of the platform.
In general, the academic stressed that, in the future, the innovative institutional advantages of the Cooperation Zone must be fully utilized, to make it an exemplary area of ​​open cooperation for the PLP. At the same time, he called for the participation of more Spanish-speaking countries to be encouraged in the construction of “One Belt, One Road”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>National Special Games promoted “mutual integration”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jogos-especiais-nacionais-promoveram-integracao-mutua/</link><description>Another edition of the National Special Olympic Games has concluded, with Macau hosting the badminton event. The closing ceremony, held in Shenzhen, was marked by the inclusive relationships between the athletes. In her speech, the Macao SAR Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture said that the joint organization demonstrated the “powerful synergy” of the Greater Bay Area, in terms of “walking together for the same will and promoting mutual integration”.

VÍTOR REBELO
 
The National Special Olympics Games came to an end, with a closing ceremony held at night at the Shenzhen Sports Center Pavilion, which was attended by hundreds of athletes who participated in the competitions in the three organizing locations, Macau, Hong Kong and Guangdong province.
According to a statement from the Preparatory Office for the Organization of the Macau Competition Zone, the closing show “took a simple and interesting form, conveying warm relations of inclusion between people with and without disabilities, unity in the Greater Bay Area and joint cooperation, as well as the sporting spirit of self-improvement, solidarity and tireless struggle”.
The Macao SAR was officially represented by the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, who, in her speech, began by presenting “the most sincere thanks and respect to all the workers who contributed to the success of this edition of the National Games for the Disabled”.
Lam then said that the collaboration and coordination between the three regions demonstrated the “powerful synergy” of the Greater Bay Area, in terms of “walking together for the same will and promoting mutual integration”. He added that athletes from all over the country, “with perseverance and sweat, lit their dreams and their will inspires us with the courage to overcome challenges and promote the harmonious development of society”.
The official stressed that “Macau will take advantage of the opportunities” and, in conjunction with efforts “with all sectors of society”, promote “the full development of services for people with disabilities”.
At the ceremony, O Lam, together with officials from Hong Kong and Guangdong, as well as Chinese sports officials, received the flags of the National Games for People with Disabilities and the National Special Olympics Games, which in turn were handed over to the Permanent Member of the Hunan Provincial Committee, Wang Daoxi, representing the province organizing the next edition, in 2029.
Before the event that concluded the competition for disabled athletes, the coordinator of the Preparatory Office for the Organization of the Macau Competition Zone was present at the debriefing press conference, also held in Shenzhen. Pun Weng Kun said that Macau “offered guarantees” to more than 500 participants and technicians from 28 delegations, “in various aspects”, such as organization, collaboration and provision of services, among others, and said that 1,500 volunteers received systematic training to provide full support to the event.
“The Macao SAR will take advantage of this opportunity to continually deepen the concept of inclusion, promote the diversification of barrier-free facilities and reinforce the regular development of sports for people with disabilities”, contributing to the synergistic development of services for people with disabilities in the Greater Bay Area”, he highlighted.
Regarding the results obtained, the territory's athletes obtained a total of 145 medals, including 34 gold. In general terms, from the races held in Macau, Hong Kong and Guangdong, 15 world records and 156 national maximums were recorded.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Program for doctors launched in the Greater Bay Area</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lancado-programa-para-medicos-na-grande-baia/</link><description>Young doctors can apply for a training program in the Greater Bay Area. This may last for three, six or twelve months, with professionals being entitled to a monthly allowance worth MOP10,000.
 
The “Professional Training Program for Young Doctors in the Greater Bay Area”, organized by the Health Services (SSM) and four hospitals in the Greater Bay Area (1st Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University, 5th Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University, Nanfang Hospital, Southern Medical University, Hengqin Branch of No. 1 Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University), together with the Health Professionals Council, will open registration from December 19th.
The objective is to “raise the technical and professional capacity and professional competitiveness of young doctors in Macau and expand the space for development”, with the SSM considering that it can “better support their integration into national development and promote the progress of medical techniques in Macau”.
The recipients are individuals from Macau who hold an accreditation certificate in the field of medicine, dentistry or traditional Chinese medicine; aged 35 years or younger.
According to the SSM, there are 25 vacancies, with registration lasting until January 5th of next year. Tomorrow there will be an information session, between 6:00 pm and 7:30 pm, “so that all interested parties can learn the details of this program”.
Candidates can choose to complete, at the same institution, a maximum of two training periods (1st option and 2nd option), according to the training periods and contents provided by the designated medical institution, in addition to having to submit a CV, with photograph, academic and professional experience.
According to the organization led by Alvis Lo, all approved and eligible candidates will undergo clinical training in hospitals, lasting three, six or twelve months, during which they will be entitled to a monthly allowance worth 10,000 patacas. It is expected that the list of admitted candidates will be published by the Health Professionals Council on January 26, 2026.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>In 10 months, DSAL placed 785 people in construction</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/em-10-meses-dsal-colocou-785-pessoas-na-construcao/</link><description>Between January and October, the Labor Affairs Services Directorate helped 785 people find jobs in the construction sector. According to Chan Un Tong, the Government has paid “continuous attention” to the issue of priority hiring of residents. The director of DSAL also mentioned that several construction projects are “about to start”
 
In the first 10 months of the year, the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) helped place 785 individuals in the construction sector. In response to a written question from Leong Pou U, the organization's director, Chan Un Tong, said that, until the end of October, 283 valid jobless candidates applied for this sector of activity, corresponding to 7.9% of the total number of unemployed people looking for work.
Chan highlighted that “human resources needs in the construction sector and the employment situation of residents have received the Government's continued attention”. In this sense, the Executive has given particular attention to residents in need of employment, through the Working Group for the Promotion of Employment Coordination and interdepartmental collaboration.
Furthermore, the Government has “continuously collected data on the demand for labor for various types of work in public works and other major works”.
In this context, the director listed the projects whose work is either “in the design phase or about to start”. These include the “superstructure” of the New Central Library, the planning of the land along Avenida Norte do Hipódromo, the Sports Garden for Citizens and the creation of several temporary open fields, among others.
Reiterating the importance of prioritizing residents when hiring workers, Chan Un Tong recalled that the Government “implemented in the public works tender processes, the principle of priority hiring of resident workers, stipulating in the tender documents the obligation to give them priority”, further clarifying that “the percentage of resident workers” is one of the evaluation criteria.
The Working Group continuously monitors the application of the priority of hiring residents in the public award processes for works and services, “requiring that the awarded suppliers increase the proportion of resident workers”.
The director of DSAL promised that the Government “will continue to pay attention to the employment and professional development needs of local construction workers, actively promoting professional matching”, through “specific employment support measures, in order to guarantee the continued employment of residents”.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Majority of young people in favor of revitalizing markets</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/maioria-dos-jovens-favoravel-a-revitalizacao-dos-mercados/</link><description>A survey by the New Chinese Youth Association reveals that 67.2% of a total of 644 young people in Macau have a favorable opinion on the transformation and revitalization of traditional municipal markets. On the other hand, 69.1% expressed support for the use of unoccupied land to hold fairs
 
In October this year, the New Chinese Youth Association of Macau surveyed 644 local young people aged between 18 and 44, with the aim of understanding their opinions regarding traditional municipal markets, open-air fairs and the concept of “market economy”. The survey found that 67.2% of young people surveyed expressed support for the transformation and revitalization of markets, while 56.1% are satisfied with Macau's traditional markets.
On the other hand, 30% of respondents expect to see spaces for restaurants, leisure and other experiences in municipal markets.
From another angle, young people justified their main motivation for going to open-air markets with the desire to “enjoy a relaxing and unique atmosphere” (32.4%), while 31.5% highlighted the intention of “tasting street snacks and characteristic drinks”.
In the description of an “ideal Macau fair”, 33.9% of respondents consider that it should have “strong support for young entrepreneurs and new brands”. Furthermore, 32.3% want “comfortable public leisure spaces and an atmosphere of social interaction”.
On the other hand, 71.1% of those interviewed argue that resources should be channeled towards the launch of “youth-led” fairs, which focus on the participation of young people and correspond to the fashion and values ​​of the new generations.
Furthermore, this study indicates that 69.1% of young people were in favor of using unoccupied land to hold fairs.
Based on the results of the study, the association proposed promoting the updating of functions and the revitalization of traditional municipal markets, in accordance with the principle of “each market having a unique characteristic”, and the introduction of diversified restaurant elements, with the Coloane Municipal Market as a pilot project.
Furthermore, it recommended the launch of themed fairs for a limited time in unoccupied spaces in the territory, as well as the creation of “youth-led” fairs with Macau brands and pet-friendly spaces in future initiatives of the kind.
 
Taipa Market gastronomic area opens
The “gastronomy + cultural creativity” Zone at Taipa Market was inaugurated yesterday, in a ceremony presided over by the Secretary for Administration and Justice, Wong Sio Chak. This area is located on the 1st floor and on the terrace of the 2nd floor of the Market. The 1st floor has 19 gastronomy stalls and cultural and creative items and an indoor dining area, while the terrace on the 2nd floor has a terrace and an outdoor dining space. Chao Wai Ieng, chairman of the Board of Directors of the Institute for Municipal Affairs, revealed that more than 400 applications were received for the “gastronomy + cultural creativity” Zone, with all 20 local young people selected. According to him, in the future, IAM will continue to listen to society's opinions and maintain close cooperation with vendors, to boost the transformation and sustainable development of municipal markets.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Secretary defends global initiative for dialogue between civilizations</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/secretaria-defende-iniciativa-mundial-para-dialogo-entre-civilizacoes/</link><description>Stressing that the territory played a pioneering role in the “harmonious coexistence” between peoples, Secretary O Lam proposed the launch of a “Macau Initiative” to foster dialogue and cooperation between civilizations
 
The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, yesterday defended the launch of a global initiative to promote dialogue and cooperation between civilizations. O Lam's appeal came during a speech at the opening ceremony of the inaugural edition of the International Forum for Civilizational Exchange, which for two days brings together 40 experts and leaders from a dozen countries.
Guests include academics from Portugal, mainland China, Egypt, Indonesia, Tunisia, Italy, Germany, the United Kingdom and Canada. The program includes interventions by the president of the China Observatory, Rui Lourido, and Maria José de Freitas, an architect who works in Macau and president of the scientific committee of the International Council of Monuments and Sites (ICOMOS) on shared built heritage.
Lam issued a challenge to the Forum participants: “launch a ‘Macau Initiative’, looking at all civilizations equally, promoting dialogue and cooperation”.
The Secretary argued that the city, which for more than 400 years was under Portuguese administration, “was a pioneer in dialogue and integration”, as well as in “harmonious coexistence” between civilizations. Lam rejected the ‘clash of civilizations’, a theory by the influential American academic Samuel Huntington (1927-2008), and argued that world history proves that “progress is never separated from mutual learning”.
Also at the opening ceremony, the president of the Cultural Institute, which organizes the forum, reiterated “the commitment” of the territory “to participate in the global dialogue between civilizations”. Leong Wai Man argued that the region has the potential to “build a platform for dialogue that transcends borders between nations”.
The leader highlighted that Macau “has always had an open and inclusive attitude to accept the positive influences of foreign civilizations”, giving as an example the Portuguese sidewalk in the historic center of the city.
The Forum also marks 20 years since the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO) classified the Historic Center of Macau as a World Heritage Site in 2005.
The Chinese Vice Minister of Information also pointed to “the marks of more than 400 years of fusion and coexistence” of civilizations that turned Macau into a “cultural bridge that connects China to the world”. Wang Gang said that, in addition to respecting differences, civilizations must “learn from common values”, among which he highlighted freedom and democracy.
Although China is, in practice, a one-party regime, since 2019 the Chinese Communist Party has defended the political concept of 'popular democracy throughout the entire process'. Beijing claims that this concept promotes continued citizen participation in China's governance, even in the absence of universal suffrage and direct election of the country's leadership.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“The Last Bet” won Short Film Festival</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/the-bet-venceu-festival-de-curtas/</link><description>A film of love and dark humor, entitled “The Last Bet”, by German director Meike Wustenberg, won the Best Film award at the Macau International Short Film Festival. It is a story focused on the lives of an elderly couple who use the last chocolate as a bet to see who will die first. “Nuptial Flight”, by Chan Chon Sin, won in the local category



















VÍTOR REBELO
 
“The Last Bet”, produced in Austria, under the responsibility of German director Meike Wustenberg, won the Best Film award at the 16th edition of the Macau International Short Film Festival. The script focuses on the lives of an elderly couple, Emst and Leni, who use the last chocolate as a bet to see who will die first, revealing a deep bond of love, albeit with dark humor.
The 14-minute film, which featured Dany Sigel and Wolfgang Hubsch as the main actors, received the highest score from the competition jury, which took place over a week at the Teatro Capitol.
During the award ceremony to the winners, Meike Wustenberg reacted, via a video message, to the title achieved. He highlighted his satisfaction with the fact that the public “identified” with his film's representation of the “annoyance and subtle love” of an elderly couple. “I will truly value this award”, stressed the filmmaker, praising the festival. The value of the monetary prize was 16,000 patacas.
The cinematographic event included awards in 15 categories, with the Best Documentary being awarded to “Our Voices Can Bring Change”, produced in Kenya, directed and composed by Carline Brillians, who also participated as an actress alongside Craig Morgan and Nick Gaglia.
“After being elected class president by her classmates, teenage student Carline uses her voice to abolish physical punishment at her school in Mombasa, Kenya”, can be read in the film’s “storyline”.
Meanwhile, Best Fiction was awarded to “The Sentry”, produced and directed in three locations, Cambodia, USA and Norway, by director Jake Watchel.
The film is an irreverent dismantling of spy film clichés and a love letter to Cambodia. “The Sentry” follows a Western agent who expects yet another routine death. It is an action and comedy tale that “mixes genres about the extraordinary lives we are trained to ignore”, says the synopsis.
At the event's final gala, highlights also included the Best Local Film awards for producer Chan Chon Sin, with “Nuptial Flight”, shot in Macau and Taiwan, and Macau Cultural Identity, with “Developing Macao”, by Zhang Linliang.
Portugal won Best Song, an award given to composers Zeca Baldeiro and Larissa Malty, with “Sea-Heart”. As for Best Animation, it went to “Free the Chicken, a Slovak film by Matur Vizar, while, in the student category, first place would be achieved by “Solos”, directed by Chinese director Yuang Zhong.
The remaining award-winning films were “Burning Sun”, by Nodar Nozadze, Georgia (Edition); “Morpheus”, Tao Xiong, China/Macau (Visual Effects); “Grotto el Truffan”, Lukas Holocsy, Czechia (Sound); “Bobby Beauty Parlor” by Vistal-Chayan, India (Music); and “In The Orbit Without You”, by Leong Hou Wang, Macau (Prémio Audiência).
The Best Director of the festival was Karlim Huu Do, with “Ne Me Quitte Pas”, from Spain, and the Best Cinematography went to “Towards the Sun, Far from the Center”, by Pascal Viveros, (Chile/Spain).
The shorts festival this year received a record number of submissions of 6,361 films, from 123 countries and regions, with the jury selecting 122 works, 25% of which were produced by directors from Mainland China and Macau. The event was sponsored by Creative Macau, Fundação Oriente and Banco Nacional Ultramarino.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sporting wants to support Hengqin in training footballers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sporting-quer-apoiar-hengqin-na-formacao-de-futebolistas/</link><description>Sporting Clube de Portugal has shown interest in collaborating with Hengqin in training young footballers, authorities at the Guangdong-Macao Deep Cooperation Zone in Hengqin said.
A delegation from the Executive Committee of the Deep Cooperation Zone was in Europe at the beginning of the month. In Portugal, the delegation visited Sporting Clube de Portugal, described as “a powerhouse of European football”, and “investigated the youth training system” of the Cristiano Ronaldo Academy.
According to the statement, the Portuguese club “expressed its availability to introduce a high-level youth football training system” in Hengqin.
In April, the Macau Government said it wants to hire a European team to provide football training to younger people, in a bid to develop this sport in the territory. “This year, we will try to expand football training for young people, we will try to hire a team from Europe to train young people”, said the then president of the Sports Institute, in the Legislative Assembly (AL).
Without providing details about this European team, Luís Gomes also said that other football events are about to be launched: “young people from cities in the Greater Bay Area will be invited to play” in Macau and a “Hengqin-Macau cup will be created to promote sport among young people”.
In March, deputy Eddie Wu Chou Kit defended cooperation with the Portuguese Professional Football League (LPFP) to organize friendly games with “top European teams” in Macau. In an intervention at the AL, Eddie Wu proposed “establishing [a] deep cooperation” with the LPFP to create, “together, a permanent training base”.
The deputy explained that the objective would be “to attract top teams from Europe to train and hold traveling games, promoting sporting and cultural exchange at an international level”.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Studio City celebrates 10th anniversary with cinematic “wonders”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/studio-city-celebra-10o-aniversario-maravilhas-cinematograficas/</link><description>Until January 4th next year, Studio City presents a series of events dedicated to cinema, in celebration of 10 years of activity in Macau. The program includes themed experiences and sensory festivities, all free of charge. One of the attractions is the “Celebrity Wax Gallery”



















A themed celebration of Cinematic Mastery, titled “Make Every Scene a Success,” jointly marks Studio City’s 10th anniversary and the holiday season. The program covers a series of free activities that will run until January 4th.
The entertainment complex, operated by Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, transforms into a “fantastic kingdom of wonders” dedicated to cinema, revealing a “captivating program of three themed experiences and sensory festivities”, according to a statement from the operator. Visitors are invited to “embark on an immersive cinematic adventure and revel in the timeless charm” of “Fun Never Ends.”
The first experience is located in the main atrium. “Movie Wonderland” allows entry into the “Make Every Scene A Hit Light Tunnel”, with three zones, namely “Star Wax Figures”, “Magic Carpet” and “Super Strength Movie Scene”.
The public can take photos with wax figures from the Madame Tussauds Hong Kong museum, “fly across a science fiction horizon” on a magic carpet surrounded by LED screens and animated effects, or enter “a super-powered action movie scene and become a hero who saves the world”, highlights Melco.
In addition, film enthusiasts can experience a professional virtual CGI film shoot (available daily from 12:00 to 20:00) and a film production studio, where they have the possibility to transform into a jewel hunter or a secret agent, completing a series of scenes in a professional studio with green screen, special effects backgrounds and dubbing.
In the “Celebrity Wax Gallery” there are 11 figures of movie stars such as Marylin Monroe, Audrey Hepburn, Bruce Lee and Brad Pitt on display.
In “Frozenland”, located in the resort’s “Times Square”, a nine-meter-high Christmas tree lights up the square. The space features Eskimo-style igloos, an ice fishing experience, an icebreaker photo booth, a husky figurine and a 3.5 meter high ice slide.
Studio City Macau's attractions, such as the world's tallest figure-eight Ferris wheel, the “Golden Reel”, the only water park in the territory with a constant temperature of 30 °C all year round, the “Studio City Water Park”, and the multi-themed indoor amusement park, the “Super Fun Zone”, offer exclusive privileges for Melco Beyond members. Until January 4th, guests who purchase a standard ticket can add a second ticket for just 10 patacas.
In addition to these events, the resort prepared festive gastronomic experiences, with the launch, in several restaurants, of menus appropriate for the Christmas season.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Young Portuguese visit Macau for two orchestra concerts</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jovens-portugueses-visitam-macau-para-dois-concertos-de-orquestra/</link><description>This month, the Church of Nossa Senhora de Fátima hosts a concert by the Colégio Moderno String Orchestra, conducted by maestro Frederico Projecto, during which Italian works will be performed. In January, the ensemble will join the Macau Youth Orchestra for a New Year's Eve performance at the Macau Cultural Center. The initiative “marks a new chapter in musical exchange between young people from China and Portugal”

The Colégio Moderno String Orchestra will perform a concert at the Church of Nossa Senhora de Fátima, on December 29th, at 8 pm, according to a press release. The group will also participate in the “18th Macau New Year Concert”, organized by the Macau Youth Orchestra, at 8 pm on January 3, 2026, in the Grand Auditorium of the Macau Cultural Center. The initiative “marks a new chapter in musical exchange between young people from China and Portugal”.
The program of the “Concerto da Orquestra de Cordas do Colégio Moderno Português”, whose entry will be free, includes a revival of the “Stabat Mater”, which was presented in the inaugural edition of the Macau International Music Festival. Works by Italian composers will be performed, under the baton of maestro Frederico Projecto and with the participation of soprano Sílvia Sequeira and mezzo-soprano Rita Coelho, both winners of the Cascais Opera International Competition.
In the New Year's show, a line-up of 100 musicians from the Macau Modern and Youth College String Orchestras will be led by maestro Aleksei Mikhaylenko. This performance will include excerpts from classic operas, such as Reinecke's “Flute Concerto in D Major”, Kalliwoda's “Oboe Concerto” and famous pieces by the Strauss family.
The concert will also feature the special participation of two former members of the Macau Youth Orchestra, namely Hio Ian Cheng, on oboe, and Ao Ieong Wai Teng, on flute, for a “true audiovisual feast that brings together youth musical talents from China and Portugal”, says the note.
Frederico Projecto began studying guitar at the age of eight, at the Setúbal Regional Conservatory. In 2006, he entered the Singing course at the School of Music at the National Conservatory of Lisbon. Graduated in Choral Conducting and Musical Training from the Escola Superior de Música de Lisboa. He also studied Orchestral Conducting with Jean-Marc Burfin, at the Academia Nacional Superior de Orquestra, and also worked with the Orquestra Académica Metropolitana.
His concert experience includes “a wide range of works from the symphonic orchestral and choral repertoire”. Furthermore, he performed on some of the most important national stages, such as the Teatro Nacional de São Carlos or the Grande Auditorium of the Centro Cultural de Belém.
He interned with maestro Sebastian Bereau and, in 2013 and 2014, he was Assistant Choir and Orchestra Conductor at the “Les Musicales de Grillon” festival. He was a member of the Gulbenkian Choir from 2008 to 2023, where he collaborated with several renowned conductors. In 2017, he took over as conductor of the Orchestra of the Escola de Música do Colégio Moderno.
Last summer, the Macau Youth Orchestra was invited to participate in the Mafra Music Festival “Filipe de Sousa”, where they performed a joint concert with the Colégio Moderno Orchestra. Both established “a strong friendship” and “solid foundations for future collaborations”, which motivated the Portuguese orchestra to come to Macau.
The Portuguese school, founded in 1936 by João Lopes Soares, father of the former President of Portugal Mário Soares, has musical education as “one of its fundamental pillars”.
The delegation that will visit the territory will be led by the school's director, Isabel Soares, and by Adriano Jordão, founder and first musical director of the Macau International Music Festival, “which constitutes tangible proof of the Macau Youth Orchestra's continued commitment to promoting international cultural exchange”.
Tickets are on sale at “Macau Ticket”, for 250 and 300 patacas.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism in Osaka suffers strong impact as tensions between China and Japan rise</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/turismo-em-osaka-sofre-forte-impacto-aumento-das-tensoes-entre-china-japao/</link><description>Denryu Lin, who manages around 80 vacation rental properties in central Osaka, has seen his business evaporate since late November as tensions between Tokyo and Beijing rise. More than 600 reservations, involving more than a thousand Chinese guests, were canceled by the end of the year, he said.
“Everyone I know in the real estate and tourism sector is suffering,” he said, highlighting a general feeling of stress in the sector, which could turn into an even bigger crisis if the downturn continues.
Osaka, Japan's second largest economic hub and one of the clearest symbols of the country's dependence on Chinese tourism, is suffering the strongest impact of tensions. Kansai International Airport has seen the biggest flight cuts across the country, while hotels, retailers and restaurants face waves of cancellations.
Chinese tourists are the biggest spenders in Japan, accounting for a fifth of the country's tourism revenue. His sudden withdrawal – triggered by Beijing's warning following Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi's statements about Taiwan – threatens one of the few bright spots in the Japanese economy.
Travel bookings from China to Osaka, with departures in winter and early spring, fell between 55% and 65% – a steeper drop than the national average, with Kansai Airport recording a disproportionate share of cancellations, according to market research firm China Trading Desk. Spending on luxury items by Chinese tourists in Osaka is expected to drop by approximately half, to US$40 million to US$60 million per month, according to the company.
Japan's economic losses could reach 1.2 billion yen in 2026 if the travel freeze persists, said Hiromu Komiya, an economist at the Japan Research Institute (JRI), adding that a rapid easing of tensions could limit the damage to around 500 billion.
The reversal comes after Osaka recorded a nearly 50% increase in Chinese tourist arrivals in early 2025, driven by the six-month World Expo, which boosted tourism across the region.
Now, local reports and social media posts point to a decline in visitors to Shinsaibashi and Shinsekai, once favorite destinations for Chinese groups, with tour buses disappearing and restaurants reporting fewer customers. Some hotels report cancellation rates of 50% to 70%, with Namba, a major transportation and leisure hub in Osaka, being the most affected area, according to the Osaka tourism office.
The pressure is expected to increase further with the arrival of the Lunar New Year, said Mr. JRI's Komiya, adding that winter destinations such as hot springs and ski resorts could suffer from the crisis.
China ordered the country's airlines to reduce flights to Japan until March 2026. Even if routes resume after this period, the Japanese market may not fully recover. The market share of Chinese tourists is shrinking as they turn to South Korea and Southeast Asia, said Subramania Bhatt, executive director of China Trading Desk.
“Japan could recover perhaps half to two-thirds of the lost Chinese tourist volume in the next 12 to 18 months,” he said. “But the era of treating China as a surefire growth engine for Japanese tourism, and for places like Osaka in particular, is over for now.”
This shift is forcing Japan to rely more on other markets to fill the gap.
At the Stargate Hotel Kansai Airport in Osaka, the number of Chinese guests is down 20 to 30 percentage points from pre-pandemic levels, said Jiro Kobayashi, director of accommodation. The hotel is looking at Southeast Asia, Taiwan and South Korea to offset demand, he added.
Kyoto cosmetics chain Yojiya reported a 10% drop in sales to Chinese tourists at the end of November, but offset the losses with domestic demand.
Since post-pandemic reopening, Japan has encouraged its regions to diversify the profile of visitors. Progress is uneven but visible.
In Gifu, Chinese tourists now represent 10% of stays, a drop from the 41% recorded in 2019, according to government data. In Shizuoka, the proportion fell from 71% to 45%.
Retailers are adapting too. Matsuya's flagship store in Ginza saw a drop in duty-free sales of around 15% in November year-on-year, although overall sales fell by just 1.2%. Takashimaya suffered a 3.1% drop in duty-free sales, but total revenue increased by 3.5%.
Drugstore chain MatsukiyoCocokara &amp; Co, which derives around 6% of its total sales from foreign tourists, said it has not yet felt a major impact and remains focused on domestic demand.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>