<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>AMCM anticipates “resilient” economy but with “weaker impulse”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/amcm-anteve-economia-resiliente-mas-impulso-mais-fraco/</link><description>By the end of this year, the MSAR economy should continue to show resilience and then a "trajectory of recovery", although to a "weaker" rhythm due to "external challenges," the monetary authority foresees. In the second “monetary and financial stability review” report of 2025, the body anticipates “moderate” inflationary pressures and “favorable” conditions in the labor market, and reiterates its optimism on the impact of economic diversification and measures to foster consumption in old neighborhoods. On the other hand, despite some mixed signs in the sector, it stresses that local banks recorded “improvements” at liquidity and profitability
 
Sérgio Terra
 
Despite the persistence of “external opposite winds”, “constant economic expansion” within China, “supported by moderately accommodary proactive tax and monetary policies, will reinforce consumer confidence” on the continent and, consequently, “promote a more favorable environment for Macau service exports”, considers the monetary authority of Macau. In this context, “Macao's economy is expected to remain resilient, although with a weaker impulse in the face of world economic uncertainty”, anticipates the body in the latest report of “Review of Monetary and Financial Stability”, the second relative to 2025.
"In the internal level, the Government of MSA has intensified efforts to revitalize the older neighborhoods and implemented support measures, such as reward programs for consumption, to streamline local economic activities. Such initiatives should reinforce Macao's recovery trajectory in the rest of 2025, despite the external challenges," says the document, which comes into available statistics and information until July 7.
In the previous study bulletin, published in late January, the optimistic tone was a little more incisive, with AMCM's Department of Studies and Statistics to maintain that the MSAR was “prepared for greater economic recovery, driven by sustainable tourism and the increase in game -related investment”, without forgetting “strong” external demand.
According to preliminary data released by Statistics and Census services, Macau's Gross Domestic Product (GDP) descended 1.3% in annual and reais terms in the first quarter of this year, reaching 99.78 billion of patacas, which corresponds to 85.2% of the economic volume of the same period of 2019. Official data that can still be reviewed, marking the sixth consecutive quarter of slowdown.
In the two reports prepared in 2025, AMCM has no numerical predictions about the evolution of GDP throughout the year. The international monetary fund reduced, in April, estimates of the economy of Macao, pointing to a growth of 3.6% in 2025, half of the projection announced in October, and an increase of 3.5% next year.
According to AMCM, the “challenging scenario” of the global economy is characterized by “high political uncertainty” and “contained growth”. "Although the global economy has shown resilience in the midst of a robust post-standard recovery, concerns about commercial tensions and recurring policy changes can undermine consumers' feeling, damage investment and potentially trigger an abrupt repracification of assets," he warns, stressing that the pace of growth of the American economy should slow "due to policies of commercial protectionism", with the "effects", with the "effects", with the "effects", with the effects ", with the" effects ", with the effects", with the "effects", with the "effects", with the "effects", with the "effects", with the "effects", with the "effects", with the effects " adverse tariff policies ”to undermine the confidence of families and companies.
Moreover, the body admits that in Macao the "business sentiment" has become "prudent" in the face of "economic uncertainties." The number of newly created companies, after deduction of dissolved, descended 24.7% to 887 in the first four months of this year, in homologous terms, after retreating 15.9% in the same period of 2024.
 
“Modest” inflation and stable employment
On the other hand, he believes that "inflationary pressures will be moderate" until the end of the year at MSAR, where "labor market conditions are expected to remain favorable."
"Given the sustained impetus of Macao's economic recovery, it is expected that inflation measured by the IPC [average consumer price index] increases modestly in 2025. At the same time, it is expected that the resilience of the labor market is intact. Imported workers, who are intended to complement the offer of local labor, will provide sufficient protection for political adjustments," the document consulted by the document consulted by the newspaper document consulted by the document consulted by the newspaper document consulted by the newspaper document consulted by the document consulted by the newspaper document consulted by the newspaper document consulted by the document consulted by the newspaper document consulted by the newspaper document consulted by the newspaper From Macao.
In a more dilated preview in time, the financial sector regulatory entity argues that the “acceleration of appropriate economic diversification and deeper integration into the national strategy will put Macau in a sustainable development trajectory”. In this context, it recalls that the government lines for 2025 are part of four major infrastructure projects conceived to boost the “1+4” economic diversification strategy, including the (university university) establishment of Macao and Hengqin International Education, “which will develop talents and file gaps between higher education and industrial needs”, allowing at the same time “expanding to expand at the same time expanding the international reach of the city is to generate a new momentum for the integrated industry of tourism and leisure ”.
At the same time, the new changes to the narrowing agreement of economic and commercial relations between the interior of China and Macau (CEPA), which since March 1 this year has expanded liberalization measures in sectors of high technology, finance and other services, will “create a more favorable business environment for local companies” and reinforce the efforts of “adequate economic diversification”. “Taking advantage of these initiatives, Macau is well positioned to reinforce its platform role between China and Lusophone countries, actively contributing to the development of the large bay area,” reaffirms AMCM.
 
Banks with “improvements” in liquidity and profitability
The report reiterates, on the other hand, that the monetary stability of the MSAR has been supported by a “credible” exchange system and the “strong budget discipline”. "Macao's currency reserves remained enough level to fully cover the monetary responsibilities of Pataca and provided a robust reserve to cushion the external shocks" in the financial system, Vinca, emphasizing that "continuous accumulation of the fiscal reserve" and "the strong budget position" guarantee "a broad political space" to "anchor macroeconomic stability, maintaining" simultaneously your debt -free status. ”
Although credit demand remains "relatively weak in a context of still high interest rates," Macao banks "witnessed improvements in terms of liquidity and profitability, the latter being driven by positive growth in income, while maintaining strong capital adequacy." In the insurance sector, the solvability ratios of life and general insurers are “far above the minimum legal requirement”.
The results of exploration of local banks increased 31.6% to 5.81 billion patacas in the first five months of 2025, in homologous terms, after they went down 21.3% to 4.01 billion in the overall calculation of the past year. On the other hand, the quality of banks' assets has' weakened ', something that is reflected in the highest ragged rather than high credit (NPL). At the end of May, the total NPL grew 16% in homologous terms to 56.2 billion patacas, leaving the rally ratio of 5.7%, plus 1.3 points in the annual variation.
In turn, the “solvability indicators” of the banks reflected “divergent trends,” notes AMCM. At the end of March, the consolidated capital adequacy ratio of locally constituted banks, including the government's post -owned postal Caixa, rose 1.3 percentage points to 15.5%, compared to the previous year, reaching a level “far above the minimum legal requirement” of 8%, however, the ratio between provisions and capital increased by 5.8 points to 29%.</description><pubDate>2025-07-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>"Wipha" motivated signal 10 and left five injured</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/wipha-motivou-sinal-10-deixou-cinco-feridos/</link><description>"Wipha" forced the authorities to lift sign 10, the highest of all. Two years ago there were no signs of such high storm. By passing through the territory, the typhoon caused at least five injured and hundreds of occurrences. Macau entered “immediate prevention state” at four in the morning of Sunday



































Catarina Pereira
 
Macau was in “immediate prevention state” due to the passage of the “Wipha” tropical storm - the highest sign of all, was issued at 12:30 pm yesterday, with the center of the storm crossing “a very close point” of the territory. By the morning, it was a distance of 30 kilometers, according to data from the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG). At the same time the wind exceeded 118 km/h, having been "accompanied by strong gusts." By the end of yesterday afternoon, there were at least five injured to record and more than a hundred occurrences. As for the number of users who rode to the emergency reception centers, there were 139.
About two years ago, such high signs of tropical storm were not issued. According to the data compiled by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the last signs 9 and 10 issued on the MSAR were on September 1 and 2, 2023, respectively, with the passage of the storm “Saola”. On the other hand, since October 5, 2024, the sign 8 was not lifted, at that time due to the "Yagi" storm.
Sign 1 of Tropical Storm due to “Wipha” was issued at 5:00 am on Saturday and at 5:30 pm on the same day rose to signal 3. At dawn yesterday, at 4:00 am, the authorities raised the sign 8 - at which time the immediate prevention state was declared - and later, at 11:00, signal 9. For four and a half hours, dropping to sign 8 at 17:00 and to level 3 to 22:30.
According to the SMG, at 20:00 yesterday, "Wipha" was about 140 km from Macau, continuing to move towards the west coast of Guangdong. However, the organism predicted that the thunder and thunderstorms would continue at night.
In some areas of the territory there were “slight” floods and, yesterday afternoon, the blue warning of “Storm Surge” was issued, with the authorities to provide for the possibility of flooding in the low zones today, and the water level reaches values below 0.5 meters.
According to the Civil Protection Operations Center (COPC), 161 occurrences were registered until 20:00. There were 96 cases of “removal of plaster, claim, window, awning or other objects with risk of fall/overthrow”; 54 cases of “construction/lamp/tree removal with risk of fall/overthrow”; Nine situations involving “scaffolding removal or other facilities in workshops at risk of fall/overthrow”; and still a case of “retention in the elevator” and another of “fire”.
The Cultural Institute, in turn, said it was accompanying the state of Tin Hau's temple, since during the Typhoon passage, trees were recorded and collapse of a platform ”next to the temple. The body ensured that “the temple's main structure is not damaged”, and the administrator confirmed that there were no victims to register.
 
Closed borders, open casinos
With the approach of the Wipha, the authorities suspended public transport and ended the public parking parks and border posts that connect the territory and Zhuhai. Serco doors, Qingmao and Transfronho Industrial Park ended at 6:00 am, while Hengqin's post ceased to operate from 11:00; Everyone returned to work from 17:00.
The sea connections were suspended and, with the sign of signal 9, the only connection between the peninsula and the mud - the lower board of the SAI Van bridge - was also closed. Thus, the four bridges that connect both sides were impassable. Also the lower board of the SAI Van bridge resumed the operation in the late afternoon.
Despite the storm, the direction of inspection and coordination of games kept the casinos open, justifying the need to “prevent potential risks derived to closing” spaces. The body has ensured that it has communicated with the operators of play, in order to take action against the typhoon and to ensure the protection of workers' rights.
Hundreds of flights were canceled and some people were retained in the territory. For example, at the Delta Bridge border post were 40 drivers who carry fresh food to the territory and tourists, which were eventually helped by the authorities.
 
Chief Executive asked for a quick response
At a working meeting at COPC, the Chief Executive asked all members of the civil protection structure and services to remain “always on alert” and to accompany changes in the tropical cyclone and “potential threats”. He said, most importantly they react “quickly” and prepare plans to restore normality.
On Saturday, Sam Hou Fai had already made an inspection visit to the interior port areas. Considering that "Macao has constantly improving civil protection mechanisms and typhoon and flood prevention facilities," he said believed that the impacts caused by the typhoon could be "largely reduced."
In general, he considered that all members of the civil protection structure "coordinated appropriately, in advance, human and material resources." The secretary for security reiterated that the COPC should always "keep warning", following with "high attention" the changes in "Wipha".
 
Fined for crossing Noble Carvalho
Two tourists were fined after walking at the Noble Bridge of Carvalho yesterday morning, the Public Security Police body said. The behavior “violated the sign of prohibition of pedestrian circulation placed on site”, thus infringing the road traffic regulation. In a shared video on social networks, two people could walk with a suitcase, despite the rain and strong winds.
 
At least three people died in the Philippines
At least three people died and three were injured in the Philippines due to the Wipha. The typhoon also caused the trip of about 43,000 people in the country, according to EFE. On the other hand, in Hong Kong, the observatory dropped the typhoon sign to number 3 at 19:40 yesterday. Sign 10, which prevailed almost seven hours, was replaced by 8 in the afternoon. At least 21 people upheld to hospitals, more than four hundred flights were canceled and there was a record of more than 300 trees.</description><pubDate>2025-07-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Certain order of the lists candidates for elections for al</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/determinada-ordem-das-listas-candidatas-as-eleicoes-para-al/</link><description>According to the draw to attribute the order of candidacies in the voting report for the elections of the AL, the Association of United Citizens, linked to Fujian countrymen, is the one on top. On the other hand, Caeal did not accept to review the decision on the deletion of Alberto Wong's list, but agreed to return the value of the deposit of 25 thousand Patacas
 
The draw was concluded to determine the order, in the voting report, of the six lists of candidacy for direct suffrage of the elections for the Legislative Assembly (AL) and two to the indirect suffrage in the labor sector.
In direct suffrage, the first list is the Macao United Citizens Association, linked to the Fujian countrymen, whose head-to-head is Mrs Song Pek Kei. In second place appears the new hope, led by José Pereira Coutinho.
The third is the list of the promoting union for progress, linked to the general union of residents' associations and led by Leong Hong Sai. In turn, Joey Lao leads the number four list, Macao-Guangdong Union, team linked to Jiangmen countrymen.
The union for development, which represents the Federation of Workers' Associations, will appear as list number five. Ella Law is number one on this list. Finally, the Good Home Alliance, linked to the Women's Association and led by Wong Kit Cheng, is in sixth position.
As for the indirect suffrage, in the work sector, the first list is the union of workers' associations led by Leong Pou U, while the second is the joint commission of the candidacy of employees associations, led by Lam Lon Wai.
Before the draw, the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) held, with the Commissioner against Corruption (CCAC), a working meeting with the representatives and representatives of the definitive candidates. Emphasizing that this year's elections are “great importance”, the president of Caeal has ensured that the commission will continue to “strictly comply with the provisions of the electoral law” to proceed with the various electoral issues and high quality, creating better conditions for qualified voters to “actively participate” in the elections.
Seng Ioi Man said he hoped all lists will support and cooperate with work from the Commission and other competent entities to safeguard the electoral order. The objective, he stressed, is that residents witness to “orderly” and “success” of the elections for al and that they take place according to the law “in a fair, impartial and whole environment”.
CCAC Deputy Wong Kim Fong warned that if activities with the attribution of social benefits involve electoral propagated, it may constitute a crime of electoral corruption. In this regard, it remembered candidates and legal persons who must declare, under the law, the activities intended to assign benefits that are not electoral propaganda. The violation of this duty will incur sanctions, situations that have already occurred in previous elections.
According to the same responsible, CCAC will continually reinforce the actions of inspecting the execution of the law, in order to combat electoral corruption and other unlawful acts.
 
Excluded candidate attempted inadmissible appeal
On Friday, Caeal posted in the Public Administration building the complete list of candidacies definitely admitted to the identification of the candidates, already refused to accept an “alleged request for 'appeal',” in a letter sent by one of the disqualified lists of the electoral race.
The Commission reiterated that the Electoral Law for the Legislative Assembly clearly stipulates that it is up to a complaint or litigation of the Caeal decision that an individual does not have the ability to be a candidate, based on the binding opinion of the State Security Defense Commission.
Alberto Wong, leader of the “Popular Liveliod Force” in Macao, one of two excluded lists, filed a request for review of the decision and demanded the return of an electoral deposit of 25,000 Patacas. In a written response, shared by Wong with Lusa agency, Caeal reiterated that he could not accept the request, but agreed to return the deposit value to Wong. Still, the social worker expressed frustration in the face of the situation and uncertainty about the future.</description><pubDate>2025-07-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sought two residents victims of human trafficking to Cambodia</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/procurados-dois-residentes-vitimas-de-trafico-humano-para-camboja/</link><description>Two residents of Macao are missing after being victims of human trafficking to Burla centers in Cambodia, the Judiciary Police said
 
The Macao Judicial Police (PJ) announced that two residents disappeared after they were victims of human trafficking to dedicated mockery and extortion centers using telecommunications and the Internet in Cambodia.
"For now, there are two cases of people who have been attracted to Cambodia and we continue to investigate with the continental [from China] police and, through international cooperation, we hope to find them," PJ spokesman Ka Wo said during a press conference on Friday.
Asked by Lusa, the PJ refused to provide more details on the two victims.
At the same press conference, the PJ announced that it had intercepted four men on Thursday, from the neighboring Guangdong province, between 20 and 29, who would work in centers dedicated to the Burla and extortion in Cambodia.
The PJ said she had received a call from a family member, saying her son was about to board a plane at Macau airport to Cambodia, "and suspected that the son had been enticed to participating in illegal activities abroad." “As it turned out that there were also three Chinese traveling with him,” police took them back to the squad for investigation, the spokesman added.
According to the PJ, men were enticed to Cambodia with an offer of a monthly salary of 10,000 Yuan and a high commission, allegedly performing investment customer service functions.
"In fact, they would work for organized crime groups to commit crimes in centers dedicated to online fraud and extortion," the spokesman explained.
"Criminal groups asked them to catch Macao flights because of the mainland China to have more stringent exit authorization requirements for the people traveling to Cambodia," PJ said.
Hundreds of thousands of people, most of whom Chinese have been the target of human trafficking for Southeast Asia centers, where they are forced to defraud compatriots through the Internet, according to a United Nations High Commissioner report. According to the non -governmental organization “International Justice Mission”, in recent years thousands of people from more than 60 countries have been victims of traffickers, attracted to burla centers with high wage promises announced as white collar jobs located in Thailand or other countries in the region.
"In most cases, criminal groups deceived people to travel to Thailand in search of apparently legitimate jobs, then being trafficked through the Border to Myanmar and forced to work under exploration conditions," the spokesman explained.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-07-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Inaugurated “Main Exhibition” of the Macau Biennial</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/inaugurada-exposicao-principal-da-bienal-de-macau/</link><description>The Macao International Art Biennial has already started and runs until October. During the three months, the “main exhibition” will have about 30 exhibitions, distributed by 20 spaces from the Museum of Art. Portugal will also be represented at the “Vila Franca de Xira Pavilion”, which will be inaugurated in September

The “main exhibition” of Macau's International Art Biennial was inaugurated on Friday and will be patent until October, in the first three floors of the Museum of Art (MAM). According to the Cultural Institute (IC), the exhibition, distributed by 20 MAM spaces, goes from “out of place” to “space” and uses unconventional exposure areas, such as corridors and bathrooms, “so visitors can participate in art creation without realizing it”. About 30 exhibitions will be held during the three months of the event.
The show includes a project by Bart Hess, which uses "clients waxed to capture subtle contact between fashion and the human body." Gregor Schneider, in turn, "reformulates the physical laws of spatial perception through architectural facilities." Tobias Rehberger “explores the dialectical relationship between humans and the physical environment through the systematic construction of social spaces,” while Xu Bing uses images of lakes captured by artificial satellites to reflect on human civilization.
In the MAM there are also patents several interactive works. In "Neither a question, no answer," Song Dong requires the public to "follow" entry "procedures before entering the exhibition." In the "treatment room", "how to make an ocean" of Kasia Molga presents an artificial intelligence robot, who "invites the audience to try to pour tears and make a" ocean "bottle." Through the main show, “the curatorial team innovates the traditional artistic narrative of the biennials,” says the statement.
The “main exhibition” has about 80 works. According to the IC, the works of 46 artists from 13 countries and regions break “the limits of traditional exhibitions” and underline “the close relationship between art and life”. At the same time, they provide “a series of artistic landscapes” of different dimensions, presenting “the beauty of the coexistence of multiple aspects”.
About 200 artists were invited to participate in the opening of the Biennial, chaired by Leong Wai Man, President of the IC, the Substitute Director of Tourism Services, Cheng Wai Tong, Patrícia Nheu Quaresma, Deputy Consul for Education and Culture of the Consulate General of Portugal, by Feng Boyi, the main curator, and several executives of the six gaming operators, among other official guests. The inaugural ceremony took place in the small auditorium of the Cultural Center.
 
Vila Franca de Xira Pavilion
Under the “Pavilion of the City” section, the “Vila Franca de Xira Pavilion” and the “Jinan Pavilion” will be inaugurated from September. In addition to the “main exhibition” and the “City Pavilion”, the “Public Art Exhibition”, another of six sections of the Biennial, will present five projects, created by eight renowned local and foreign artists.
Under the theme “Waves and Paths”, the works include the “Community Co-Creation Project and Mutual Aid San Mei On”, a “Bairro's Living Room” built by Jason Ho in the North Zone. The other four exhibitions will be presented successively in public and community spaces. Projects will lead “residents to reexamine the local landscape of their lives,” read.
The six works selected for the “Local Curator Project” are “Behind the Oriental Garden” by Cheong Weng Lam, “Under the Wang and Wong Mei Teng Wang Meng“ Genetic Duration ”Peninsula; “Jacone Tower”, by Feng Yan and NG Sio Ieng; “He Jun Yan and Zhang Ke and“ an enunciable position for women ”by Cheong Cheng We and Wang Jing.
The “collateral exhibition” presents proposals for works, collective and individual, teachers and students from various higher education institutions. These last two sections aim to “promote dialogue between local creativity and international context” and boost “broadly” the art of Macao. Finally, the six special exhibitions organized by operators “are the largest on scale and the most diverse” compared to previous editions.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Launched Anti-Innundations in Coloane</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lancadas-obras-anti-inundacoes-em-coloane/</link><description>The project of flood protection works and improvement of drainage in the marginal zone on the west of Coloane is already underway
 
Macao authorities have launched a series of works to reinforce Coloane's resistance ability on the impacts of flooding caused by storm tides and heavy rains. According to the Directorate of Public Works Services (DSOP), with the objective of mitigating the problems of flooding on the west side of Coloane, flood prevention equipment will be built and water drainage systems in dikes and Shizimen channel will be built.
The flood prevention pattern of this project is based on a period of return of 200 years, with the corresponding tide level projected to another 3.85 meters. Already the planned standards for drainage and the pumping station are based on periods of return of 50 and 20 years, respectively. Flood prevention dikes will have a global length of about 1,200 meters.
The works were awarded to NAM Kwong Union Commercial and Industrial by 566 million Patacas and are completed until August 2027. Among other contracts related to the endeavor, the project management services, attributed to Pal Asia Consultants (20.85 million patacas), the supervision, by Macao-Professional Services (14.86 million), and the choice of CCC-GEDI Macai as projectist (12.89 million).
The works extend from the northern end of the Lai Chi Vun road from Colaane to the downstream area of the Tam Kong temple, covering the surroundings of Avenida de Outubro, Rua dos Navegantes, Cais de Coloane and Lai Chi Vun Naval Shipyards.
The first phase of the project encompasses the construction of flood prevention dikes, comports for the passage of water and the provisional watershed station, among other water -related interventions. The main content of the works includes the construction of dikes in the sections of Lai Chi Vun and Avenida de October, the work of four waterproofs that cross the dikes and the removal of sludge in the two landscape lakes of Lai Chi Vun and that avenue, in addition to the respective watersheds and the work of environmental protection and supervision, inspection and tests.
According to DSOP, all work of transport materials related to the project will be carried out at sea.</description><pubDate>2025-07-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Three more countries in automatic passage channels</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-tres-paises-nos-canais-de-passagem-automatica/</link><description>From this Monday, the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) will widen the traditional automatic passage channels at the borders of mashes to French, Malay and Spanish tourists. Thus, the countries are now covered by this measure that already benefits the passport holders of Australia, South Korea, Portugal, Brazil, Singapore and Germany.
Citizens in these older countries can register for automatic passage at the migration posts of different borders and in the PAC ON migration services building, where they will have to present their passport, valid for at least 90 days. Minors aged between seven and 17 years must be accompanied by the father, mother or tutor in the registration, and display the original birth certificate, as well as the identification document of the father/mother or tutor. In the case of a tutor, a proof of the legal relationship must be presented.
In addition, the new measure of passage in vehicles at the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Hong Kong Border Post, launched on June 9, also applies to the nationals of the nine countries mentioned.
In the same statement, CPSP promises to articulate, in an active way, with the government lines of action to continually launch measures at border posts to “facilitate the circulation of tourists”. “CPSP will persist in the philosophy of 'continuous improvement' and 'reform and innovation', continually develop and implement facilitating measures and improvement for border passage, offer tourists a safer and more convenient border passage and, committed to committed, efficient circulation of people, all to inject dynamics in the construction and development of the great Guangdong-Hong Bay Kong-Macau, ”he says.</description><pubDate>2025-07-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2436/</link><description>Hid in cannabis underpants for trafficking
The Judiciary Police (PJ) stopped at the airport a couple from the interior of China from Thailand on suspicions of drug trafficking. According to the PJ, the 42 -year -old husband hid 655.7 grams of cannabis flowers and parts of cannabis plants in his underwear. In addition, in the couple's luggage, 3.6 pounds of cookies and gums containing cannabis were found. The drugs are evaluated at 654 thousand patacas. The PJ believes the detainees intended to traffic drugs from Thailand to mainland China. The couple came to Macau with their minor son.
 
First imported case of chikungunya fever
The 1st imported case of chikungunya fever in Macao was detected this year. This is a 61-year-old resident who lives on Avenida do Conselheiro Borja and visited family members in Foshan. The patient is stable and will be hospitalized for treatment. For now, who lives with the patient does not record symptoms. Health Services (SSM) will inspect the source of reproduction of the disease in the patient's accommodation and reinforce the removal of stagnant water in the area. Warning that the risk of mosquito -transmitted diseases is increasing, SSM have renewed appearance appeals.
 
153 suspects of illegal worked in June
The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) detected 153 suspected cases of involving illegal workers in June. CPSP, the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs and other services have supervised 387 locations, including construction shipyards, private buildings and commercial and industrial establishments, among others.
 
AMCM warns population to fraudulent pages
Aia International warns the public to be careful with false insurance -associated pages, “with the aim of avoiding situations of burla and unexpected damage”, according to the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM). The company was established by AMCM to publish a warning on the official website, after verifying the circulation of fraudulent phishing pages. AMCM recalls that if private data or transactions are requested through suspicious “links”, the persons involved must immediately contact their institution and alert the Judicial Police.</description><pubDate>2025-07-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Burlas surpassed a sixth of inquiries opened by the MP</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/burlas-ultrapassaram-um-sexto-dos-inqueritos-abertos-pelo-mp/</link><description>Last year, the prosecutor registered a "record" of inquiries charged since the creation of the MSAR-15,840, having observed an annual increase of 13.70%. Of these, 14,722 were completed, and 3,671 accusations were deduced and 10,622 filing orders were issued. The agency warns of the “proliferation of the cases of circumvents, notwithstanding repression”, pointing out that the surveys filed by burlas “surpassed a sixth” of all. Analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the work report perspective still the year 2025, with the MP saying that it will intensify the conscience of magistrates for national security. In addition, it also indicates that it has already presented to the Executive the opinion to “restart negotiations around judicial cooperation in criminal matters with the interior of China”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The Public Prosecution Service (MP) found an “evident increase” in the number of inquiries assessed over the past year. Within a year, 13.70% have grown to a total of 15,840, reaching a “record” since the establishment of the MSAR and “denoting a relatively manifest sign of promoting the practice of criminal activities”, it can be read in the annual report of the body.
According to the document analyzed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, 14,722 were completed, representing about 93% of the total; In this field, there was an 18%increase compared to 2023. Among these inquiries, and after investigation, 3,671 accusations (plus 8.19%) were deducted and 10,622 filing dispatches (plus 20.59%), based on grounds such as “manifestation by the offender not to desire criminal proceedings, insufficient crime practice or non-identification”.
From 2023 to 2024, 7,460 inquiries were transferred, an increase of 32.15% compared to the previous period. On the other hand, after new evidence has been discovered, the MP reopened 264 archived inquiries, translating a decrease of 23.70% in annual terms.
The five crime groups with the most inquiries assessed included the crimes against property (such as theft, theft, damage), with 4,946 inquiries (plus 17.12%); against heritage (various types of circumvents, extortion), with 3,152 inquiries (plus 9.79%); offense to physical integrity, with 1,696 (more 22.10%); against the road traffic law, registering 999 inquiries (plus 11.25%); and computer crimes, with 981 inquiries (plus 83.71%).
The most frequent crimes, such as slopping, theft, illegitimate appropriation of founding and computer crime, "registered a more evident increase," while there was also a climb in game surveys related to the game, "which directly led to an increase in the total amount of inquiries."
The MP considers that the “proliferation of circumvents, despite repression” deserves “attention”. "The number of burla surveys has been increasing, reaching 2,770 inquiries charged [in 2024], which has exceeded one sixth of all charged surveys, consecutively occupying first place since 2021, which evidences a high dangerousness," he warns.
Alongside this, it also warns that caution is needed taking into account the trend of increasing game crimes. By way of example, it indicates that 262 usury inquiries related to the illicit game (114.75%), 23 -requirement or acceptance of identification document (plus 35.29%) and 55 hijacking crime (plus 89.66%), “representing an obvious increase”.
"Given the importance that the integrated tourism and leisure industry is covered by the economic development of MSAR, [and] the trend of increased criminal activities alluding to the game sector (…), it is necessary to reinforce and intensify prevention and control work, with a view to eliminating potential risks and ensuring a healthy and ordered development environment," says the MP.
The report also recalls three "relevant" cases that were in the courts: "Sunity Group", "Vip Tak Chun" and former directors of the Directorate of Soil, Public Works and Transport Services. "The results of the judgments of the three cases demonstrate the solid guarantee of the MSAR Judiciary System in relation to the rule of law, the integrity and healthy development of the MSAR GAME sector. At the moment, the executions of decisions are being ordered in an ordained manner," he can be read.
Regarding the last year, it is also said that the MP's “computerization work” was accelerated and a “internal data connection and sharing based on the application of digitization and administration systems of internal work” was accelerated.
 
“Intensify consciousness” from magistrates on national security
By prospecting the year 2025, the MP stresses that "the magistrates' awareness of national security will be intensified and their domain over the legal system will be intensified, with the aim of achieving better results in practical work." In addition, it also states that it will “strengthen the mechanisms” intended to comply with responsibilities “in the safeguard of national security, including the implementation of internal rules regarding criminal jurisdiction and cooperation with the competent services in the interior of China”.
By the way, it argues that it is “indispensable” to raise the “modernization” of the Macao legal system, “with the aim of adapting to the positioning and demands of the development of both the Great Bay (…) and in the in -depth cooperation zone in Hengqin”. "The Public Prosecution Service, as a judicial body of the Misrees, which performs judicial functions, will reinforce the connection with administrative and legislative services, with a view to boosting and improving, under the terms of law, the modernization of the legal system of MSAR," he adds.
It also reveals that it has already presented to the Government of the Misrera "the opinion to restart negotiations around judicial cooperation in criminal matters with the interior of China, promoting in timely legal progress in the area concerned between masters and the interior of China."
The MP binds after "it will seriously implement the spirit of President XI's important speeches." At the same time, he stresses that he “performs his duties and fulfills his responsibilities autonomously and independently, without any interference” and undertakes to bet on staff formation. It also promises to continue to comply with the principle “a country, two systems” and the basic law.
On the other hand, it ensures that "it will improve work mechanisms and internal operation, optimize procedural procedures and reinforce the construction of the team." In this field, he even says he will “enhance the strengths and perfect the weak” as well as focus on “increasing judicial effectiveness”. It also guarantees that "it will adopt a more active attitude, will raise transparency in your work and improve the mechanism of dissemination of information."
 
Defended reinforcement of the fight against prostitution exploitation
In the 2024 work report, the Public Prosecution Service (MP) points out that there was a decrease in sexual crime surveys against minors, but an increase in serious sexual crimes. Those related to minor pornography descended “dramatically” (90%) to 15 surveys. At the same time, inquiries linked to crimes such as sexual abuse of children and rape have “a decrease in different levels”. On the other hand, 52 violation crime surveys were charged, plus 36.84%. "There is no excluding the possibility that most of the crime of violation crime inquiries can be caused by prostitution," says the MP, adding that 26 inquiries related to proxenetism (44.44%) were opened. "In the light of the foregoing, there is certainly the need to continue to reinforce measures to combat prostitution exploitation and related illicit activities, in order to purify the social environment," he says.
 
More than 82 million in compensation for harmed workers
Over the past year, the prosecutor supported 1,050 workers, who eventually received a total compensation of 82 million patacas. Cases include workers from the “Suncity Group”, and also related to employers who violated the rules of criminal law and who fled in bad faith to pay debts in matters. Still in the work field, 277 new processes of occupational accidents and occupational diseases (less 3.48% in annual terms) were registered, with 285 conciliations and 13 actions were made because they did not agree; As well as 103 new common labor processes (less 36.81%), with 84 conciliations and 30 actions brought because there is no agreement. The conciliations involved 368 workers (minus 21.37%).</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>World Return Motorf World</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mundial-de-motosurf-de-regresso-hac-sa/</link><description>For the second year in a row, the waters of HAC-Sá beach are expected to be the scene of the fifth and last journey of the Motosurf World Championship in November. The International Union of the sport has put Macau on this year's calendar, only missing official confirmation by Melco, which sponsors and organizes the competition, in conjunction with the local association. As last year, the race could decide on the territory the winners of another season of this nautical sport, dominated by the Czech Motorcyclists
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The International Union of Motonautics (UIM) has returned to Macao in the calendar of the Motosurf World Championship, scheduling the final journey of the current season for the weekend of November 21, 22 and 23. This will be the second consecutive time in which the territory welcomes the competition, to compete in the waters of the beach of HAC-Sá.
Official confirmation will be known soon, as talks, “very advanced,” according to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau, between Uim and Melco Entertainment, which sponsors and organizes in conjunction with the local association of modality.
Following the results verified in the previous rounds, Macau may, as in 2024, decide the champions in the various categories, highlighting the elite, in which Czech Matyas Novotny is the holder of the title.
The time of 2025 is already running, having been held two days in the United Arab Emirates, in the city of Fujairah, and in Türkiye (çesme). Two tests will be followed in October in Italy (Manfredonia) and Croatia (Zadar). In half, there are world games in Chengdu (China), in which the motorcycle and female races were included for the first time.
The current general classification of the main class, Elite, is led by Lukas Zahorsky of the Czech Republic, with 107 points, ahead of compatriots Alex Lukscheider (95), Matej Kozisek (91) and Matyas Novotny (90).
The World Cup encompasses six more categories, namely Stock (American Antony Squire commands the table), Stock R-Merlin Plus (Adam Kolar, Czech), Masters (Kim Down, South Korean), women (Eliska Matouskova, Czech), Men's Junior (Matyas Narvyk, Czech) and Junior Burdova Junior (Ellen Burdova, Czech).
The athletes of the Czech Republic are the great dominators of the sport worldwide, especially the elite class, calling itself the main titles.
In the 2024 edition held at Hac Sá Beach, which also served as qualification for the World Games, the races encompassed 120 motorcycles from 20 countries or regions, including Macao that already has some athletes competing in proofs abroad, especially on the continent.
The motorcycle is a water sport that involves the use of a motorized board to slide over the water. It is a relatively new modality that combines elements of traditional surf with the technology of an engine, allowing practitioners to maneuver and enjoy speed in various aquatic conditions, without necessarily depending on waves. The boards are equipped with combustion or electric engines that drive the board through the water.
Motosurf was made official as a sport by UIM in 2019 and has great popularity in recent years, conducting championships and events in several countries.
As in 2024, Macau should count on the presence of the big names in the sport.</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Dialysis Center already works at Hospital das Ilhas</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/centro-de-dialise-ja-funciona-hospital-das-ilhas/</link><description>The Dialysis Center of the Islands Hospital is already in operation, which can, in the initial phase, serve residents sent by the SSM. It is expected that the center provide monthly routine dialysis services to 1,200 people/times, by the end of this year
 
Officially entered the Dialysis Center of the Hospital das Ilhas, which, in the initial phase, provides treatment of maintenance hemodialysis to residents sent by health services (SSM). According to the Islands Hospital, the Center is expected to provide monthly routine dialysis services to about 1,200 people/times, by the end of this year.
Quoting data from statistical and census services, the hospital pointed out that in 2024, dialysis treatment services were provided to 131,635 people/times in Macao. The hospital noted that the search for dialysis treatments has increased continuously as the population is increasingly aged and chronic kidney diseases are more frequent among younger people.
The hospital is convinced that the creation of the Dialysis Center will contribute to providing more comprehensive support services, and geographically more convenient dialysis treatment services to Cotai who previously used public medical services.
With an implementation area of 1,400 square meters, the dialysis center has advanced medical equipment in the large bay and a “welcoming and comfortable treatment environment,” says the Islands Hospital, ensuring an intelligent information platform that allows the electronics management of medical records and medical prescriptions.
Led by “Peking Union Medical College Hospital” (PUMCH) experts, the team working at the Center can provide hemodialysis, hemofiltration, among various modes of dialysis, as well as performing and maintaining access to dialysis to meet the treatment needs of patients at different phases. Generally speaking, the Center provides “One Stop” diagnostic and treatment services, integrating dialysis treatment, disease monitoring, complication management and access maintenance, taking advantage of PUMCH.
The hospital unit has promised to continue adding medical equipment, widening the scale of diagnostic and treatment services, and actively relieves the pressure of the public sector's medical system.
 
Proposal on “Day Hospital” will be submitted to AL this year
The director of the SSM, and also chairman of the Council for Medical Affairs, said that the proposal for the exercise of activity of private institutions providing health care will be submitted later this year to the Legislative Assembly. At a meeting of the Council, Alvis Lo also presented the final report of the public consultation on the said legal regime, which provides for the creation of day hospitals. In addition, he explained the guidelines regarding the regulation of medical advertising, with a view to collecting vowel opinions. According to he stressed, the opinions collected generally support the legislation for the “day hospital”, and the SSM absorbed some suggestions. Alvis Lo stated that he expects to improve and further promote the legislation.</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More than one million patacas in fines for illegal works</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-de-um-milhao-de-patacas-em-multas-por-obras-ilegais/</link><description>In the first half of this year, the number of illegal works processes established by the Soil Services Directorate and Urban Construction, 441, representing more than half of the total of 2024. The total value of the fines applied exceeded one million PATACA
 
The Directorate of Soil Services and Urban Construction (DSSCU) filed 441 processes related to illegal works, between January and June, representing more than half of the total cases verified throughout the last year (844). In the first six months of this year, 38 resulted in fines that rose to about 1.1 million patacas. In five cases, the fines were not paid within the stipulated period and will be subject to a coercive collection by the government, says a statement.
In addition, 100 processes filed in the first half of 2025 are related to cases of voluntary demolition, according to DSSCU. The body recalls that, after the entry into force of the new legal regime of urban construction, the fines to be applied were increased, and new fines have been added to those who do not comply with the demolition orders. In order to encourage cooperation by infrastructors, the new legislation introduced "a measure of reducing and exemption of encouraging character under the sanctioning procedure."
If the owners require the voluntary demolition of the illegal work during “the period of hearing”, they are totally exempt from the payment of the fine, assuming that the application has been accepted and the demolition of the confirmed work. However, the owner must first submit the request to DSSCU and only after receiving permission can demolish the illegal construction. "Otherwise, a fine may be applied for violating other provisions provided for in the legal regime of urban construction," explains the body.
Regarding the established processes, he notes that "a number of commercial spaces did not" prior communication "or requested the work leave for the execution of remodeling works." The lack of notice, as well as the license, may result in a fine, and the amount of fees due to legalizing the construction may triple.
It should be noted that during the first six months of the year, offenders of 50 cases were notified of the final decision, two more than throughout 2024. These are cases where owners can already demolish illegal works within a stipulated period. If the order is not met, DSSCU itself performs the demolition, whose expenses are the responsibility of the transgressor.
In the same period, 59 cases were filed, more than half of the total of 2024 (102). The body "gives priority to cases of new illegal works, renewal of illegal works, constructions in ruin state and cases of illegal works located in buildings whose license of use was issued after the entry into force of the new law."
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Authorities made a great simulacrum in casino</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/autoridades-fizeram-grande-simulacro-em-casino/</link><description>Several police units co-realized an exercise that simulated a bomb threat and a robbery at different properties of SJM. The simulacrum lasted about an hour and was attended by over 200 people



















This week, the exercise “capture of the wolf” took place, which simulated a bomb threat and armed robbery in different SJM facilities. The exercise lasted about an hour, had 209 participants and "the results obtained fulfilled expectations," according to a statement from the Unit Police Services (SPU).
The SPU guarantee that they will continue to make efforts to achieve the three police concepts presented by the Secretary for Security, fulfilling the motto “better to prevent remedy”, through the performance of various police operations and joint exercises.
Upon describing the scenario of the year, the SPU indicates that a criminal group claimed to have placed a bomb at the Grand Lisbon Palace and demanded $ 100 million from Hong Kong in cryptocurrencies. The SJM immediately reported the case to the Judicial Police (PJ) and the Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate. The PJ highlighted staff for the scene and coordinated with the Public Security Police (CPSP) the monitoring of the other properties of the operator.
However, the bomb threat would have only served to divert attention from the authorities, since the intention of the criminals was to “perform an armed robbery” in a SJM casino in Cotai. The robbers set themselves on the run and ended up intercepted by the PJ, culminating in the detention of one of the criminals. A second was arrested by CPSP on the public road.
Another robber took two hostages in one of the rooms. The PJ began the “Operation TRAQUINAS” and installed a command center on the ground. CPSP, PJ agents, and customs services mobilized cars, drones and quick boats to patrol the city, coastal areas and border stations, requesting the help of Zhuhai authorities.
The Fire Department provided first aid to the injured and the CPSP highlighted two special groups to the site. In the casino, PJ negotiation experts managed to release a hostage. The CPSP Special Operations Group eventually stopped the criminal and rescues the last hostage. The PJ also stopped the last suspicion, and author of the bomb threat, which had been disguised as a client.</description><pubDate>2025-07-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lisbon National Library more digitized and open to the community</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/biblioteca-nacional-de-lisboa-mais-digitalizada-aberta-a-comunidade-ana-mendes-henriques/</link><description>A user consults a book in the National Library, during a report on the institution that has the Portuguese Bibliographic Heritage in Lisbon, July 15, 2025. The National Library of Portugal (BNP) wants to receive students from secondary education and lower from 18 to 16 years old access to the institution, guardian of more than three million books. (Accompanies Lusa text on July 19, 2025). António Pedro Santos/Lusa



Ana Mendes Henriques*
The National Library Amphitheater will be restored with funds from the Plan of Recovery and Resilience (PRR), through an endeavor to launch in the coming months, which should be completed in less than a year. "We managed, through two projects we already had in a portfolio, to go to the last phase of the PRR of works," the Director General of the National Library of Portugal (BNP), Diogo Ramada Curta, told Lusa.
At this time, the last review of the projects takes place. “We have told in the coming months to launch the venture, which we have to execute until the middle of next year and we will recover, on the one hand, the amphitheater and, on the other, a reserved room,” where rare and manuscript books are found, the official said.
One million and one hundred thousand euros is the value of PRR intended for works in the amphitheater and in the other room, through a “small reimbursement” of the library.
"We have to fulfill, we are committed to this fulfillment," said Diogo Ramada Short, by doing accounts.
The amphitheater, with access to the outside of the building, will be open to the community. The endeavor includes the arrangement of adjacent spaces, for years unused.
BNP is also in the phase of compliance with a PRR for conservation, digitization and cataloging, worth seven million euros. "We have had this impulse given to us by the PRR and we are in a good phase of execution. It has already been digitized and we are now advancing to the next phase, which is fundamentally the availability of this material," said the director.
“When I arrived at the library [in April 2024] 11% had been executed. At this time, we are about 60% and we will comply with all this PRR,” said Diogo Ramada Curta.
The library has a large collection of rare books, as well as all the current Portuguese bibliographic production, which is in the legal deposit, distributed by 15 floors.
Special collections are made up of rare and old books. "We have the largest collection of Portuguese books since the fifteenth century to our day ... and one of the greatest collections, if not, I think it is the largest, the country's collection of ancient music," he said.
"These are the treasures we have and we are looking to rendict," he said.
Restoration workshops have been one of the main concerns about preserving heritage to the BNP custody, according to Diogo Ramada Short: "One of the essential fundamental aspects is restoration, conservation, binding. We are particularly committed. We have an extraordinary team there. It is a very dedicated team and we are dynamizing these workshops."
In the BNP workshops are restored posters, printed books and manuscripts, in a lengthy work, which requires milutia and expertise. A common restoration can take between three weeks to a month. Rare volumes, such as parchment manuscripts, leather and wood pieces require six months of attention.
A seventeenth -century manuscript with these characteristics is now among the relics awaiting intervention in the workshop.
BNP treasures include Fernando Pessoa documents found after the poet's death. “Fernando Pessoa's so -called ark is with us, but there are many other spoils we have here and we will try to make available by creating digital platforms, which seems to be the fundamental leap that we are trying to develop,” explained the historian.
“We are particularly committed to creating two pilot projects, the first of a digital Camonian and, secondly, in the construction of a digital person,” said Diogo Ramada Curta.
The project related to the work of Luís de Camões is being developed in collaboration with the mission structure for the celebrations of the 5th centenary of the birth of the poet. "We hope soon will have results to present this digital Camonian," he said.
The two projects will give new visibility to the special collections that BNP has seen growing from writer and intellectual spoils. “Let's go to about 230 spoils,” said the director-general.
 
JTM/LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-07-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>