<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Only three convicted of the crime of trafficking in persons since 2013</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/apenas-tres-condenados-pelo-crime-de-trafico-de-pessoas-desde-2013-2/</link><description>In a report sent to the UN on the convention against torture, Macao indicates, based on data from the last court office, which in 12 years - between 2013 and 2024 - only three people were convicted of the crime of trafficking in persons. Authorities justify that in the vast majority of suspected cases there is no evidence that fully fill the elements of the crime. Regarding the number of victims, 60 were identified, most of which report to the years between 2013 and 2017
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Macau sent the United Nations (UN) a report on the convention against torture and other cruel, inhuman or degrading treatments or penalties. The delivery date was scheduled for 2019, but the document only arrived at the international organization in February 2025. Consulted by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the sixth periodic report, which is still in Chinese language, reveals that the number of convictions is poorly expressive. According to information sent, based on data from the Last Instance Court (TUI), between January 1, 2013 and May 31, 2024, only three people were convicted of human trafficking. As for the number of victims, this is much higher: 60 (59 women) were detected, of which 32 were smaller.
In the general calculation, over the period under analysis, 54 suspected cases of human trafficking were investigated, and the Public Prosecution Service (MP) decided to investigate 49 effectively by this crime, according to data from the Secretary for Security Office included in the report. Of these, 42 were eventually filed, corresponding to 85% of the total.
The largest number of human trafficking victims refers to the years between 2013 and 2017, a total of 55. Since 2018, according to data submitted to the UN, zero victims have been found in much of the years. The exceptions occurred in 2021 and 2022, when authorities discovered four women and a man victims of the crime of human trafficking, respectively.
According to the commission of monitoring the distressing measures of trafficking in persons, in 2021, police instituted a suspected case of trafficking in persons, which was referred to the prosecutor (MP), who decided to effectively classify him as this crime. It involved two defendants, one of which was accused of three crimes of trafficking in persons. He was sentenced to a four -year prison sentence, but for the commission of only one human trafficking crime and two prostitution exploration crimes. The other accused, who was accused of three persons of persons, was acquitted.
Regarding the case detected in 2022, the committee's data reveal that no one was convicted despite the existing victim.
In the period under analysis, and in addition to the condemnation verified in 2021, only two more people were convicted of human trafficking, according to the data from the Tui Office. In 2015, a lawsuit was sent for trial, in which the man was charged with two crimes of trafficking in persons, and was sentenced the following year to eight years in prison for each crime. The other case, which began in 2016, also involved a man, accused of two persons of persons, who the following year was sentenced to five years in prison for each crime, could be read in the report.
Over the years, there have been several cases suspected of human trafficking, but which would be tried and convicted of other crimes. According to data from the follow -up committee, there were at least 14 situations in which this happened. "Since the vast majority of cases suspected of human trafficking do not fully fill the elements of the crime based on the evidence seized during the judicial process, the authorities accuse and judge these cases for linociness, organized crime or other crimes," the authorities justify the report sent to the UN.
The commission's latest statistical data also reveal that in 2023 a case of human trafficking was registered, with no data on victims or defendants. Already in 2024 police instituted a suspected case of trafficking in persons, however, the MP decided to qualify it as a “crime of receiving illegal immigration people”, so zero cases were recorded. In 2025, specifically until February, there was also no record of any situation of the genre.
 
Resolute combat
In the report, Macao guarantees the UN that "the public security agencies of the MSAR have resolutely and continuously fought the crime of trafficking in persons." He states that, to combat the crime of trafficking for sexual exploitation purposes, “regular inspections and surprise in potential black points are made,” such as saunas, massage houses, karaoke bars, cybercafés, discos and illegal hotels. Regarding trafficking for labor exploration purposes, “surprise inspections are performed in conjunction with the direction of services for labor issues in specific places, such as construction shipyards, hotels, restaurants and employment agencies”.
At the same time, authorities underline that strict control is exercised at borders, with special attention to tourists or foreign workers from “high -risk countries”, as well as random controls and questionnaires to passengers who reach the territory, especially women aged 18 to 35.
"To combat sex tourism, police are interrupting the sex business supply chain, dismantling prostitution networks, including the repression of illegal activities, such as the organization of sexual transactions through mobile applications and the processing of people who distribute pornographic leaflets," the document says.
Assistance to victims is a function of the Institute of Social Action (IAS) that also helps “potential” victims. In all, between 2013 and 2018, 51 victims were assisted, of which 33 were children. It should be noted that in 2013, a total of 20 cases involving minor victims and potential victims were received from which one returned to the place of origin by his will. Between 2019 and 2024, all IAS data point to zero victims helped.
Last year, about 7,592 participation in training actions related to the fight against human trafficking were registered. Among the services that organized the sessions were the Public Security Police Corps, the Directorate of Services for Affairs, Customs Services, IAS, the Legal and Judicial Training Center, the Judiciary Police and the operators, as well as the Macao Security Forces School.
 
Commission for Refugees received
four requests and all were rejected
The Macau Refugee Commission received four requests for refugee status between 2013 and May 2024. According to the report sent to the UN by MSAR, “all applicants were male from Liberia (2015), Congo (2016), Pakistan (2017) and the United States (2023)”. As for the applicant of Congo "he was rejected because he had obtained the refugee status in other countries", while the rest were rejected "due to insufficient information and evidence." "None of these requests was based on torture or abuse, and no applicant appealed to the court," the authorities underline.</description><pubDate>2025-07-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Casino GrandView closes doors tomorrow</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/casino-grandview-fecha-portas-amanha-2/</link><description>The first casino-satellite to close doors is GrandView, in the mud, already tomorrow. The SJM ensures the continuity of employment for the 159 workers who had prominent for that space, as well as opportunities for the seven employees hired by the casino-satellite itself. DICJ has said it will be following the whole process to ensure that the game dealership meets the promises made
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The Grandview Casino in Taipa will end tomorrow at 11:59 pm, announced the SJM Resorts, indicating that "all the game tables currently operating on site will be transferred to other casinos of the company." As for employees, the game operator assured that “it gives great emphasis to the protection of local employment”, having already prepared measures to ensure the continuity of the employment of those professionals.
The Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ) has ensured, in turn, that it will “strictly inspect” the closing procedures of the casino, ensuring that it is “stable and ordered” and that “all legal procedures are being properly fulfilled”.
According to the gamekeeper in a statement, "all local employees employed by SJM will remain employees and will be transferred to other SJM casinos to assume game -related functions, according to operational needs."
Regarding those who work at the GrandView Casino and who are not employed by SJM, "they will be invited to apply for related vacancies within the group, with priority in hiring equal circumstances." SJM ensures that "they will receive the necessary support, depending on the actual situation, to facilitate a quiet transition."
In this context, the DICJ states that it will maintain a “close communication” with the direction of services for labor affairs, in order to ensure strict compliance with the commitments made by the SJM, “namely the proposal previously presented, as regards the remuneration, perks and working conditions of its 159 workers” highlighted in the GrandView.
At the same time, he stressed that the game operator pledged to provide opportunities for employment to the seven workers recruited by the casino-satellite himself, "in order to ensure employment continuity."
On the other hand, the DICJ states that it will designate employees to oversee the closing process, ensuring “the proper treatment of cash and game sheets stored in the treasury, unused cash coupons and the exchange of play cards, among other procedures”.
Regarding customers who have cash deposits or cash discounts in the GrandView casino and who have not been redeemed, SJM indicated that, after closing, they can go to the Casa Real casino deposit box, on Dr. Rodrigo Rodrigues Avenue, to schedule the subsequent treatment from Thursday, July 31. “The company will ensure that all customer rights are properly respected,” reads the press release.
It is recalled that in June the government announced that the 11 satellite casinos under SJM, Melco and Galaxy will close doors before the end of the year, given that the three-year transition period granted to these game spaces ends on December 31, 2025.
However, SJM intends to “rescue” two of these spaces through the acquisition of the properties of hotels where Ponte 16 and Le Royal Arc casinos are located. For now, it is not yet known what the point of situation about negotiations and then it will be necessary for the concessionaire to apply to the government to direct these casinos.</description><pubDate>2025-07-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>There are 79 slopes with average risk</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/existem-79-taludes-risco-medio/</link><description>Currently, there are 284 slopes at risk, and 79 are “average risk”, according to information given by the DSOP director. Lai Weng Leong also said that there are no high -risk slopes
 
The Director of Public Works Services (DSOP), Lai Weng Leong, revealed that of the present 284 at risk slopes in the territory, 79 are of “average risk”, with high risk classifieds “being eliminated through the inspection and monitoring mechanism”. In response to an interpellation of Deputy Ella Lei, the same leader points out that in the source of the government's responsibility “the competent services continue to perform, in an orderly manner and according to the degree of urgency, the respective maintenance work”.
He also pointed out that, in relation to the inspection and monitoring work of the slopes, in addition to having been responsible for the Macao Civil Engineering Laboratory to proceed to the monthly inspection, he has also been developing interdepartal security assessment work, “proceeding to the consolidation and planning of slopes at risk at a successively and depending on the degree of urgency”.
For its part, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) said that "it has been conducting continuous supervision, as well as maintenance, repair and stabilization works for public slopes under its competence, which are at risk of medium or higher level." In addition, it has established an inspection mechanism to examine slopes before and after bad weather, "in order to detect problems as soon as possible and take preventive measures, ensuring the safety of the public and its goods."
Asked about the slopes that are simultaneously on land land and private property, the director of DSOP indicated that the government distinguishes responsibility depending on the location of the area to be repaired: if it is within the state land, the reparation will be in charge of the government; If, on the contrary, it is located within the private property, the responsibility falls on the owners.
In these cases, if the area is the responsibility of AMI and it is necessary to develop repair work, the body will, before the start of the work, notify the owners and the direction of soil services and urban construction (DSSCU), and take into account the location and real area of public and private land, as well as the disposition of surrounding facilities, road circulation and access conditions, to perform coordination and collaboration with the owners, if necessary.
According to the provisions of the legal regime of urban construction, the maintenance of slopes located on private land is the responsibility of the owners, who must periodically proceed to their inspection and maintenance. With regard to slopes located on private land already submitted to the assessment of the State of Security, DSSCU notifies them to do maintenance and consolidation work. It should be noted that the legal regime provides for the total exemption of rates for the projects of repair and maintenance works.
In response to the deputy, Lai Weng Leong also says that DSSCU will continue, along with other public services, to monitor and monitor cases regarding slopes located on private land to ensure security conditions.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-07-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Melco presents “moonlight” of the Haas brothers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/melco-apresenta-luar-dos-irmaos-haas/</link><description>Melco inaugurated, at “City of Dreams”, the project “The Haas Brothers: Clair de Lune”, within the Macao International Biennial. Patent until September, the operator's “special exhibition” intends to guide the public for a “dream landscape to the moonlight”
 
The "City of Dreams" received the show "The Haas Brothers: Clair de Lune", one of the highlights of the Macao International Biennial program. The exhibition is inspired by the childhood memories of Simon and Nikolai Haas about Austin's “moon towers”, the hometown of the twin brothers. Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment invites "art lovers" to embark "on a journey where memory and emotion converge." The “Special Exhibition” will be evident until September 12th.
Towers, tall structures used to illuminate the city at night, became a symbol that deplete “the line between the real moon and an artificial moon”, according to a game operator note. The six pieces on display “build a poetic and imaginative world in the moonlight”, and the whole show unfolds as a “dream landscape to the moonlight”, can read.
The works “a street light called Desire”, “there is street light”, “a light on the streets” and “crazy in the sheets”, “approval lamp” and “light to remain silent” arouse a “reflection on topics such as desire, recognition and silence”. The sixth piece, "Reach-Able Moment", features a small monkey that symbolizes the search "for love, patience and devotion", both evoking a "silent and philosophical reflection on the meaning of existence."
The “Clair de Lune” project reflects the “consistent creative philosophy” of the Haas brothers and is also based on the namesake of composer Claude Debussy. For the two artists, the moonlight serves as a "metaphor for emotional migration, with the flow of light representing the two -way journey of" come and come ". The shadow and light game invites viewers to perform "a journey of perception, reflection and emotional exploitation."
The Haas brothers explained that "the moonlight is fleeting but powerful. It changes everything that plays. Transforms the common one into the fantastic." "If we can take the viewer to a quiet, humorous and reflective world, then we did our work as artists," they concluded. Throughout their careers, Simon and Nikolai have worked in the areas of fashion, cinema, music and design, having developed “a distinct multidisciplinary artistic language” and an “anthropomorphic approach”.
Lawrence Ho, President of Melco, said the exhibition "Fundery Emotional Resonance with Artistic Imagination." At the launch ceremony were also Ba Bing, a subdirector of the Department of Advertising and Culture of the Central Government's connection cabinet, Leong Wai Man, president of the Cultural Institute and Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, director of tourism services, among others.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Thailand and Cambodia accept “unconditional” ceasefire</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/tailandia-camboja-aceitam-cessar-fogo-incondicional/</link><description>EPA1268018 Malaysia's Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim (C) Speaks During a Press Conference Next to Cambodia's Prime Minister Hun Manet (L) and Thailand's Acting Prime Minister Phumtham Wechayachai Cambodia in Putrajaya, Malaysia, 28 July 2025. Thailand and Cambodia's Leaders are due to meet for pedace talks on 28 July, as the territorial feasting dispute their shared frontier dragged into a fifth day of open compabat.  EPA / MOHD RASFAN / POOL



The governments of Thailand and Cambodia agreed yesterday in Malaysia to declare a “immediate and unconditional” ceasefire from midnight after five days of border clashes that made 35 dead. Malaysian Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim announced the agreement as president of the Association of Southeast Asia Nations (Asean), of which Bangkok and Phnom Penh are members, at the conclusion of a meeting between the heads of the governments of Thailand and Cambodia, Phumtham Wechayachai and Hun Manet, respectively.
"An immediate and unconditional ceasefire in force from midnight on July 28. This is a first vital step for the distension and restoration of peace and security," Anwar said alongside Cambodia and Thailand leaders. He also stressed that the meeting resulted in positive discussions that culminated in a commitment to restore peace and security in border zones, where about 300,000 people were removed last week due to hostilities.
To promote this understanding, Anwar continued, at least two bilateral meetings will be held, starting with one this Tuesday among military leaders and another scheduled for 4 August.
In his speech, Hun Manet thanked US President Donald Trump for his mediation on this issue, as well as China for his participation, who joined these negotiations as an observer. The meeting was attended by US and China ambassadors in Malaysia, Edgard D. Kagan and Ouyang Yujing.
The Cambodian leader expects this agreement to be able to restore diplomatic channels, which were reduced after both countries have called on their ambassadors for consultations in the face of the escalation of the conflict. “May our bilateral discussions return to normal in the relationship,” said Hun Manet.
In turn, Phumtham Wechayachai, who acts as an interim prime minister due to the suspension of Paetongtarn Shinawatra, thanked Anwar and the parties for mediation and highlighted the agreement as a peaceful resolution to protect people's sovereignty and lives.
After weeks of border tensions, last Thursday broke out fighting between the armies on both sides. They accused themselves mutually from starting the attacks, in which they used F-16 fighters and Rockets BM-21, among other artillery weapons.
The conflict left at least 35 dead: 22 on the Thai side (14 civilians and eight military) and 13 on the Cambodian side (eight civilians and five military), according to the latest official data. In addition, dozens of people have been injured and about 291,000 are housed in evacuation centers and temporary fields, over 156,000 in Thailand and about 135,000 in Cambodia.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-07-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SJM confirms Hotel project in Hengqin</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sjm-confirma-projecto-de-hotel-em-hengqin/</link><description>SJM - SJM SJM Holdings subsidiary, yesterday celebrated an agreement with Zhuhai Hengqin Shun Tak Property Development Company, a company fully detained by Shun Tak Holdings, to purchase properties that will be turned into a three -star hotel, inserted into a 'lifestyle' pole composed of residential, commercial and village spaces nearby from Hengqin's border post. This plan, which had already been announced in December 2024, aims to expand the hotel presence of SJM in the Great Bay, support the integrated development of the deepened cooperation zone, reinforce the role of Hengqin as the “fundamental driver of economic diversification” of Macau and contribute to the continuous integration of the territory in the country's “global development strategy”, said the operator in a reported statement.
"This project represents more than an expansion of our hotel portfolio. Reflects our strong alignment with national strategies to deepen the integration between Hengqin and Macao, and the firm conviction in the long-term growth potential of tourism and transfronist cooperation," said Daisy Ho, president of SJM Holdings and SJM Resorts.
With this investment, focused on the mass market, the company believes it is playing an “active role” in the construction of the great tourist future of the Great Bay, anchored in the “Force de Macao” as the World Center for Tourism and Leisure.
The total value of the acquisition rises to approximately 724 million Renminbis (816 million patacas to the current exchange rate), excluding taxes. According to SJM, the business was referenced an estimated market value of 660 million Renminbis to the property and 108 million in conversion costs, and will be settled in seven phases.
The property integrates 12 floors of fractures of condominium title and a retail unit, with a total gross area of 19,781 square meters. Conversion and renewal works are expected to be completed within 24 months, “paving the way for broader diversification” of the group's revenues in the Tourism and Hospitality of the Great Bay.
The SJM is convinced that the venture “is exceptionally well positioned to capture the sustained demand of transionic travelers”, given the fact that he is near the Hengqin Border Station, the Interurban Railroad Cantão-Zhuhai and the Macao Light Metro Transfer Station.</description><pubDate>2025-07-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Guangdong Macau Fair involved almost 400 contact bags</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/feira-guangdong-macau-envolveu-quase-400-bolsas-de-contacto/</link><description>This year, the Guangdong and Macau Province Product Products Fair featured 389 contact scholarship sessions, 51 of which involved health care services and the third age, home support services adapted to the elderly. For the event, where two dozen agreements were signed, more than 50 thousand people passed
 
The Guangdong and Macau 2025 Province Products Fair (GMBPF, in the English acronym), co-organized by the Institute for Commerce and Investment Promotion (IPIM) and the Guangdong Province Trade Services, focused on current industrial trends, providing “a platform for the expansion of markets”. During the three days of the event, 389 contact scholarship sessions were organized, 51 of which involved health care and welfare services of the third age, home support services adapted to the elderly population, among other areas.
According to IPIM, on the first day, several Guangdong and Macau business associations signed three cooperation agreements. "These agreements aim, in particular, the joint realization of investment promotion activities in the Great Bay, the promotion of the internationalization of companies in the regions of Guangdong and Macau, the reinforcement of coordinated industrial development and the establishment of the first" Macao Companies Support Post "in the city of Jiangmen," explained Ipim. On this day, there were 23 agreements signed on products from the silver economy sectors, cuisine and national trends.
The event was attended by 1,829 professional buyers and was attended by 292 purchasing representatives from over 13 sectoral associations, in guided tour sessions for buyers, the body said. “These numbers are proof of GMBPF's positive role as a contact platform and cooperation for exhibitors,” read the IPIM statement.
Keeping the “An Event, Two Locations” model, this edition of GMBPF organized, in Macao and Hengqin, several professional forums, with the aim of guiding the development of the sectors involved. For example, in Macao, a total of 60 entrepreneurs were present at the Economic and Commercial Cooperation Forum and cultural exchange between countries covered by the initiative “a track, a route”.
In addition, the 2025 Stem and Smart Care Economy Forum recorded 85 people, offering a thorough debate on industry trends.
In addition, in the in-depth cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin, the Forum on Innovation in the Silver Economy and Big Health was held. Under the “Knowledge sharing-contact scholarships-visits to the site” model, the participation of 103 experts and business representatives of the sector was coordinated in a total of 139 directed contact scholarship sessions and four guided tours of exhibition spaces, “thus taking full party from the Hengqin-Macau synergy effect”.
Until 14h00 on the third day of the GMBPF, the accumulated number of visitors exceeded 50 thousand, of which 29,000 people visited the fair on the first day open to the public. According to Ipim, more than 100,000 gifts were distributed on the spot, "and visitors who participated in the games had the opportunity to win large awards such as smartphones, smart sports watches, motorcycles, televisions and vacuums."
According to Ipim, the Xiguan Cultural Corridor, in the section of the Lichia Canal, integrated in the exposure zone of national trend products, "became the most sought after point to take pictures." The intangible national cultural heritage masters made demonstrations of techniques on site, attracting more than 7,000 people.
In turn, in the experience space “Beco No. 72 of Guangdong and Macao”, actors Wu Jiahui and He Zhifeng, who played the 369 and 258 papers on the television series “Seventy -Two Tenants”, presented the original play “Luz da Macau on Macao”. In addition, the young transmitters of the Cantonesa opera performed flash performances throughout the pavilion.
In the gastronomic tasting room, 14 culinary demonstration sessions were presented by Chinese chefs and renowned western. In addition, the workshops for parents and children, where they were able to prepare traditional dishes of intangible cultural heritage, "enriched the experience of visitors."</description><pubDate>2025-07-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Regime of medical devices in force on 1 July 2026</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/regime-dos-dispositivos-medicos-em-vigor-1-de-julho-de-2026/</link><description>The “Supervision and Administration Regime of Medical Devices”, which was published yesterday in an official bulletin, will come into force on July 1 next year. Through the implementation of “Integral Supervision”, the Institute for Pharmaceutical Supervision and Administration (Isaf), which is the supervisory entity, considers that “it will be possible to ensure its quality, effectiveness and safety, defending and promoting public health”.
"At the same time, the implementation of this supervision will provide a legal basis for the development of industry regarding medical devices in Macao, boosting the diversified development of the Macao Big Health industry," read the press note.
The regime prepared by the government is based on the situation of Macao, as well as the combination of comparisons and references of regimes of supervision and national and foreign administration and countries/neighboring regions. In addition, he also took into account and incorporated the opinions and suggestions of the professional associations and the Macao sector, as well as the competent government services.
According to the new legal regime, medical devices are classified into three main classes according to their potential risk level, including class I (low risk), class II (average risk, subdivided into low-risk class III and high average class III (high risk) class IIB, applying the “registration” or “registration” regime depending on the risk level. Only medical devices that have been approved for registration or have been registered can circulate in the Macao market.
The scope of business activities related to medical devices includes manufacturing, importation, exportation, thick sale and retail sale. For the manufacture of medical devices, it is necessary to obtain the “manufacturing license”, it is stipulating that their manufacturers must comply with the “good practices of manufacturing medical devices”.
The law also defines criminal and administrative liability, introducing provisions regarding criminal sanctions for the exercise of counterfeit medical devices in order to better protect public health. The new regime also establishes periods of transition, "to allow a transition without startling to existing establishments."</description><pubDate>2025-07-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2442/</link><description>Elderly woman found dead in a building house
An elderly resident was found dead in the house of the management office of a building on Rua do Almirante Costa Cabral, yesterday morning. According to the Judicial Police, no criminal injuries were detected or caused by acts of violence. The causes of death will be determined by autopsy examination.
 
Two suspects of “Ice” trafficking
The Judiciary Police (PJ) stopped at the airport on Sunday afternoon, two people from Hong Kong, specifically a 51 -year -old man and a 63 -year -old woman who will have helped a network traffic out abroad, making a scale in Macao. In the operation, about one kilo of “Ice” was seized evaluated in three million patacas. According to the PJ, the two detainees do not know each other, but admitted to having received instructions from a trafficking network to transport the drug to Macau and later send it to a designated destination. According to PJ, the suspects entered Macao on the morning of that day, through the border of the Delta Bridge, and moved to the airport to leave the territory.
 
Health services warn of hyperthermia risk
Health services (SSM) warned the population to the risk of hyperthermia, taking into account the emission of a yellow warning for high temperatures by meteorological and geophysical services, which predicted that time will remain hot in the coming days, with thermometers could reach 33ºC or more. The SSM have recommended that preventive measures be taken, including avoiding outdoor activities for a long time while the weather is hot, and wearing a hat, umbrella, wearing loose, light and breathable clothes.
 
“Macao Smart Go” encompasses 12 parking parks
The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) launched the new version of the “Maca Smart Go” application, which joined information on vacancies available in 12 parks, including three more, namely at the airport, the University of Macao and the Galaxy Macao. The new version of the “Macao Smart Go” application also combines car routes, on foot, bus and taxi, offering integrated mobility solutions. According to DSAT, traffic alerts were improved, with a specific filter for changes in driving examination.</description><pubDate>2025-07-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 70% of secondary students feel stressed with studies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-de-70-dos-alunos-secundario-sentem-se-stressados-os-estudos/</link><description>This year, 40% of a total of 1,017 macau-respondent students in respondents showed a slight level of anxiety disorder, while 6% demonstrated average signs to the serious of this pathology, reveals an inquiry developed by the General Association of Students Chong Wa, along with the University of São José. More than 70% are stressed due to studies.
 
The General Association of Students Chong Wa de Macao and the University of São José released the results of an investigation into the mental health of the secondary education students of the territory, referring to 2025, which had a total of 1,017 respondents from seven schools. According to the Chong Wa Students Association, 40% of the students inquired revealed slight symptoms of anxiety disorder, while 6% show medium to serious signs of this pathology.
In addition, 54% do not suffer from anxiety disorders. As for pressure, according to the study results, more than 70% of students interviewed are stressed “due to studies and people and related subjects”, and more than 40% have emotional reactions such as irritability, anxiety and depression when facing pressure. Some of them had even thought of resorting to self-mutilation.
Studies continue to constitute the main source of stress. More than 50% of respondents associated stress with classes, exams and study of studies, while almost 30% attributed the problem to communication with family members and interpersonal relationships.
To deal with pressure, most students prefer to rest, distract themselves with entertainment or talk to friends. However, students who chose to directly solve the problem represent a very low percentage. More than half consider friends and family members as the main features that help them solve stress. However, very few respondents sought professional help.
Another conclusion is that, in terms of various psychological indicators, such as the degree of satisfaction with life, anxiety, personal resilience, and cohesion of life, boys highlights a generally better level than the interviewed students. In addition, male students also have “more satisfactory” sleep quality than girls.
According to the study's findings, students sleep an average of seven hours a day, with 34.6% sleeping daily less than six hours. For 28.5% of respondents recently, the state of sleep has been “unsatisfactory” or “very unsatisfactory”. In addition, 24.6% even stated that sleep problems have already disturbed their daily lives.
In general, 70% of respondents consider that a good sleep help them relieve pressure, which, for the research team, shows that the quality of sleep greatly influences the degree of happiness of secondary school students.
Based on the investigation conclusions, the team suggested reducing simulation tests and increasing rest and exercise time. At the same time, researchers expect schools and families to promote mental health education and the training designed to identify crisis, as well as encourage students to express their feelings more, distribute their rest time well and ask for help to professionals.</description><pubDate>2025-07-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Launched 2nd Children's Arts Festival</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lancado-2o-festival-de-artes-para-criancas/</link><description>第二屆澳門國際兒童藝術節 線條魔法-塞吉 布洛克的繪本遊樂園親子模特兒



The second edition of the International Arts Festival for Children of Macao has already begun. During the opening ceremony, several outdoor artistic facilities were presented, “The Paradise of Little Micaf” and the exhibition “Magic of the Lines”







第二屆澳門國際兒童藝術節 開幕式







第二屆澳門國際兒童藝術節 光影劇場《波力波拉》總綵排




The 2nd International Arts Festival for Children of Macau (Micaf, in the English acronym) was inaugurated on Friday. At the time, outdoor artistic facilities were presented, organized by the Cultural Institute (IC) and Sands China, the weekend parties of “The Paradise of the Little Micaf”, in the Praça do Cultural Center of Macau (CCM), and the exhibition “Magia das Lines” by Serge Bloch, co-organized by IC and MGM.
The facilities are patent under the theme of the festival mascot and include “large -scale inflatables” as well as “a 10 meter high micaf mascot” for photographs. During the ceremony, the Macao Conservatory of the Cultural Institute (IC) and the South Korea Push Theater also performed “spectacles full of innocence and vitality,” says the IC statement.
The inauguration was chaired by the Substitute President of the IC, Cheang Kai Meng, the subdirector of the Department of Advertising of the Central Government's connection office at MSAR, Ba Bing and the Director of Macao Tourism Services, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, among others.
Cheang stressed that "this year Macau was honored to be selected as" East Asia Culture City "and that this year's Micaf incorporates rich Asian elements." He continued, saying that "children will have opportunities to see a broader world, to experience cultural diversity in the arts, to learn respect and inclusion, and to practice acceptance and sharing, launching the basis for the construction of a harmonious society in the future."
The Substitute President of the IC also assured that "the festival also brings together fantastic ideas of international artistic groups and local artists, which will stimulate local cultural and artistic creation for children and inject a new vitality in the Macao cultural industry."
The Serge Bloch Show is available on “Art Space”, on the 1st floor of CCM, until October 7, and in the Barra Zone, in Naval Workshops No. 1 and 2, until September 14. The three sections, with free admission, allow visitors to "enter the creative space built by the French illustrator." The weekend parties, which began earlier this month, have several collective competitive games and facilities with sports elements, corresponding “to the spirit of the 15th edition of the National Games”. In the last two weekends of August, the “Micaf Fun Day” will bring programs under the theme “Aquatic Fun and Art”.
In addition to the return of the “Foam Festival” and the “Aquatic Fun Festival”, there will also be street dances, handicraft workshops, outdoor movie screenings and food stands. The "Snow Show", "A Astronaut's" theaters and the "whispering the zodiac" are also scheduled.
Tickets for MICAF activities are available at the “Enjoy Macao” ticket office, with discounts for families. Tickets for the Children's International Film Festival are on sale at Cinemateca Paixão and their online reservation platform.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>National Games open in Canton and end in Shenzhen</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jogos-nacionais-abrem-em-cantao-terminam-em-shenzhen/</link><description>The 15th edition of the National Games will start in the city of Cantão, and end in Shenzhen, with the participation of more than 20,000 athletes. The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM, said that the organization also intends to extend the visa period to visitors of the MSar people who intend to attend competitions
 
Pedro Milheirão
More than 20,000 athletes will participate in the final phases of the 15th edition of the National Games, which will be inaugurated in Canton, on November 9, and will end in Shenzhen, on the 21st of the same month. National games include 34 large and 419 small scale competitions. Half of the 68 test competitions has already been completed. To date, the authorities have been finalizing the remodeling of the sports pavilions for competitions, and the calendar for them has already been announced.
The MSar will host competitions of four modalities and a competition for the public. Raehk, in turn, will organize eight -sport competitions and a sports competition for viewers. The National Games will be held in a total of 19 cities. Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau will also organize a celebration activity, 100 days from the opening ceremony, "to show the results of the preparations of the three regions."
According to the organization, the event will be held according to the principle “Focus on Guangdong and priority to RAE”, taking into account “the urban characteristics and advantages” of the different host cities. He also stressed that he will "fully respect the desire of Hong Kong and Macau."
At a press conference, LAM, secretary for social affairs and culture, said that organizing committees have been trying to prolong the visa's term "for visitor to the national games spectators." He also said that the five Macau test competitions were held “successfully”.
The secretary also pointed out that Macau will make "good use" of the transport network, near the sports pavilions, as well as the diverse options for accommodation and restoration, in the sense of "meeting the needs of viewers of different origins." LAM has continued, saying that the MSar authorities will take advantage of the national games “to develop activities to disseminate patriotic education”.
Already Tong Lixin, vice president of the General Administration of the State, said that "the realization of games must fulfill the ideas of the organization of the games" green, sharing, open, integrity "and the organization requirements with" simple, safe, wonderful ". Tong said he also hoped that the sports event will promote “regional integration, national development and the well-being of the people”.
In turn, Wang XI, assistant coordinator of the organizing committee of the National Games and member of the PCC Guangdong Province Committee, greeted “the close coordination with Hong Kong and Macau in terms of competition organization and customs measures, as well as general services work” and “the promotion of community neighborhood optimization work”.
Raehk's secretary for administration Chan Kwok-Ki believes the games "will further promote the approach between residents of Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macao." The event will deepen "cooperation and sports exchange and in various areas in the Great Bay, streamlining transfronic tourism and generating new economic opportunities," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-07-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Confiscated meat and less illegal clothing</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/confiscada-mais-carne-menos-roupa-ilegal/</link><description>During the first half, customs services have already seized more than half of the meat confiscated in the total of last year. Conversely, seized clothing items have diminished in recent years
 
Pedro Milheirão
In the first six months of the year, customs services (SA) seized 7,771 pounds of pork, 2.008 chicken meat, duck and goose and 7,717 of other types of meat. This means that the 17,496 kilos of meat seized this year are already more than half of the total meat confiscated in 2024 (29,737). From January to December last year, 13,956 pounds of pork, 3,610 chicken, duck and goose and 12,171 of other types of meat were seized, according to data consulted by the Jornal Tribuna de Macau.
Still in relation to non -inspected food products, in the general calculation of last year, 16,118 kilos of illicit vegetables were also registered. In the first half of this year, there were 6,372 pounds, ie 39.5% last year. During the first three months of this year, four bottles of wine were also seized, and throughout 2024, the SAs did not confiscate any. In 2023 44 illegal bottles were registered, in 2022 were 10 and, in 2021, the SAs seized 721.
Between January 2021 and June 2025, authorities seized a total of 10,888 pieces of clothing, bags, watches, glasses, accessories and illegal shoe pairs. However, the data reveal that there is a decreasing tendency, if we consider that only 195 garments were confiscated in the first half of 2025, compared to 1,362 of the year 2024 and 1,809 of 2023.
Until last June, 10 bags were also seized, against the 39 recorded between January and December 2024. On the other hand, 19 clocks were confiscated between January and March this year, three more than in the set of 2022, 2023 and 2024 (16). It should be clarified that data on 2025 is not available on the number of pairs of footwear, accessories and glasses.
In terms of daily needs products, in the first half of the year, 501 units were seized, an increase of 3478.6% compared to 2024, the year in which the authorities confiscated only 14. On the other hand, in the year 2023 were seized 2,811 products. Between January and June, the authorities also arranged 496,401 cigarettes without custom customs paid, less 57.3% than in the full year of 2024 (1,161,912).
Between April and June 2025, authorities intercepted 2,631 illegal medicines, 1,800 capsules of an unknown pill with ephedrine and 161 Zolpidem medicine capsules.
In terms of electronic products, authorities confiscated only one, in the second quarter of 2025, the same amount registered between 2021 and 2024. During these four years, 10 mobile phones were also confiscated.
 
27 brought to court for illegal immigration
Until June this year, eight illegal immigrants were arrested, according to customs services. The same data also indicates that the authorities detained 69 people in 2024 for this reason, 187 in 2023 and 69 in 2022. In the first six months of the year, 27 “individuals who provided assistance”, or who illegally reached in the territory, were sent to court, about half of 2024 (53). In 2023 and 2022, the authorities refered 81 and 35, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-07-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>The photographer and university professor Maria José Palla died</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/morreu-fotografa-professora-universitaria-maria-jose-palla/</link><description>Photographer Maria José Palla, 81, died in Lisbon, a family member told Lusa. Maria José Palla, who was a jubilated teacher at the New University of Lisbon, died three days before she was 82.
Photographer, researcher, specialist in Languages and Literature, History and Arts, Maria José Palla lived in Paris, where he was exiled during the Portuguese dictatorship, and PhD at the University of Sorbonne, in the area of Languages and Romanesque Literatures, with a thesis on the symbolic costume of the work of Gil Vicente, after a master dedicated to “Les Objects of Civilisation Dans L'Oeuvre de Gil Vicente ”, under the direction of Linguist and Lusitanist Paul Teysier (1912-2002).
In the French capital, Maria José Palla studied photography and cinema with filmmaker Jean Rouch (1917-2004), at École Pratique des hautes Études, after completing the course of the Institut Français de Photography, and attending the Ecole National de Potographie de Paris (Ecole de Vaugirard), which led her to an internship at RL Dupuy, RL, RL, RL, in the 1960s.
Graduated in Art History, by École du Louvre, in Paris, is the author of several books and articles about Gil Vicente, the 16th century theater and the Portuguese painting of Renaissance. Among his works are “dictionary of the characters of the theater of Gil Vicente”, “from the essential and the superfluous-lexical study of the costume and adornments in Gil Vicente”, “Costume and Painting-Grain Vasco and the altarpiece of Viseu”.
As a photographer, an art to which he has dedicated himself in the last 40 years of life, held several exhibitions in Portugal and abroad, such as "Archive", in which he revisited the four-decades work at the Appleton Cultural Association in Lisbon, in 2022, and "Maria José Palla: self-portrait as a no-dead nature", the most recent in the individual name in the Frei National Museum Manuel Cenacle, in Évora.
Among its many exhibitions, brought to different parts of the country, Europe and Macao (Macau), are “fragments of a discourse” (2013), “Le Temps” (2010), “The Wheel of Time” (2006), “Anatomy of a Face”, “Facials of Melancholy” and “The Woman Without Shadow” (2001), “Poet Portraits” (1998), with great plans of Portuguese literature ” Contemporary, by António Franco Alexandre and Mário Cesariny, Nuno Judice and Sophia de Mello Breyner Andresen, Eugénio de Andrade and Pedro Tamen.
The artist, who used in particular the portrait as a means of expression-and self-portrait about herself-to the Évora show last year at the Friar Manuel do Cenacle Museum, chose to combine photographs and objects, in a substantiated action in the title of the show: “Maria José Palla: self-portrait as a red-hatred-a retrospective”.
Maria José Palla, who traveled the history of theater, Portuguese literature, French literature, Literature of the Renaissance and Literature and other arts - Photography, at the Faculty of Social and Human Sciences of the New University of Lisbon, was also translator of “Free de Cuisine de L'Afante Maria du Portugal”, for the Institute of Medieval Studies.
With Manuel Villaverde Cabral translated “Hiroshima, My Love” by Marguerite Duras, for the European-Americ (1963), “Life of Miguel Angelo”, by Romain Rolland, for the publisher Presence of Man (1967), and “Camus for himself” by Morvan Lebesque, to the Portuguese Publishing (1967).</description><pubDate>2025-07-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>