<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Licensed 29 “junkets”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/licenciados-29-junkets/</link><description>Gambling Hand Holding Poker Cards and Money Coins Chips



The universe of “junkets” for this year has 29 professionals qualified to operate in the territory, according to data from the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Department. It means that the number of gaming promoters corresponds to 58% of the maximum limit set for 2026
 
Catarina Pereira
 
There are 29 gaming promoters that are authorized to operate this year, according to the list recently updated on the website of the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ). Compared to the beginning of last year, when 24 “junkets” were authorized to practice in the territory, the increase was five professionals or 21%. In relation to the previous update of the list, in mid-December last year, there is only one less “junket” compared to the 30 then recorded – the highest number since the beginning of 2023.
However, the total number of gaming promoters corresponds to only 58% of the maximum limit of 50 established by the Secretary for Economy and Finance for the year 2026.
According to the limits, published on the DICJ website, Venetian Macau and SJM Resorts continue to stand out as the concessionaires that can collaborate with the largest number of “junkets”, totaling 12 each. This is followed by eight gaming promoters for MGM Grand Paradise and another eight for Melco Resorts, while Galaxy Casino and Wynn Resorts have just five each. Gaming promoters will have to sign a contract with one of the six concessionaires.
For this year, the DICJ also maintained the maximum limit of junket employees at 250. According to the latest update, at the beginning of January, 12 gambling promoter employees were licensed in Macau, making up just 4.8% of the total set for 2026.
The new Gaming Law, which came into force in January 2023, defined that “each gaming promoter can only carry out gaming promotion activities at a concessionaire” and prohibits “junkets” from “sharing – in any form or agreement – ​​with concessionaires, revenue from casinos, or the exclusive exploitation of areas reserved for casinos under contract”.
Furthermore, junkets were prohibited from issuing credit to players, with gaming concessionaires having exclusive power, further narrowing their scope of action.
Although they remain far from pre-pandemic levels, it is worth remembering that gross revenues from VIP baccarat rose by almost a quarter in 2025, in annual terms, surpassing the general average growth of casinos. Specifically, overall last year, VIP baccarat generated gross revenues of approximately 67.99 billion patacas, a figure that represents an increase of 24.14% compared to 2024, according to official data.
In the space of a year, the weight of VIP gaming in the revenue structure of Macau casinos increased by 3.3 percentage points to 27.48% of the total, a result that is still far from the 46.24% in 2019.
According to DICJ data, business in rooms for high rollers grew above average, taking into account that total revenues from games of chance registered an annual increase of 9.09% to 247.40 billion patacas, reaching 84.60% of the level of 2019, the pre-pandemic year. Revenues from VIP baccarat were only equivalent to 50.27% of the 2019 level, however, the percentage of this comparison accelerated again, compared to the 40.5% recorded in 2024.
The recovery of VIP gaming was most evident between October and December 2025, with revenues from this segment amounting to 20.31 billion patacas, reflecting a pre-covid recovery rate of 62.85% and increases of 45.17% and 20.29% in annual and quarterly terms, respectively. The general performance of casinos in the fourth quarter (66.06 billion) resulted in increases of 15.04% and 5.58% on the same comparative basis.
For this 2026, the estimate, according to the Budget proposal, is that gross gaming revenues will total 236 billion patacas, 3.5% more than the forecast for 2025, with the Government considering that the tourism sector will continue to grow.</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hearing problems already affect more than 6,000</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/problemas-auditivos-ja-afectam-mais-de-6-000/</link><description>Between the end of the first half of 2024 and the same period of 2025, the number of individuals with hearing problems rose from 5,465 to 6,087, now representing 31.5% of holders of the disability assessment registration card. Virginia Kong, director of the Hearing and Language Center at “Widex Macau”, explained to this newspaper that, despite some progress, greater awareness about hearing health is needed

PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
At the end of the first half of 2025, 19,283 people held a disability assessment registration card, according to data from the Social Action Institute. Of these, 6,087 suffered from a type of hearing impairment, representing 31.57% of the total. In the same period of 2024, out of 18,178 cardholders, 5,465 suffered from hearing problems, corresponding to a proportion of 30.06%, which means that there was an increase of 1.51 percentage points.
For Virginia Kong, director of the Hearing and Language Center at “Widex Macau”, the growing trend of cases is mainly due to the aging of the population, as she explained to Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU, anticipating the reopening of the Center’s renovated facilities.
Even so, the official noted that, regarding rehabilitation services, 77 of the 82 long-term measures stipulated in the Ten-Year Plan from 2016 to 2025 were fulfilled. Virginia Kong also stated that, currently, the health care available in the territory “is extensive”, giving the example of the existence of 12 day centers with capacity for 13,069 people or rehabilitation bus services.
On the other hand, he recognized that there are still gaps, particularly in sign language interpretation and in the hearing health system. “There are other hearing healthcare services in Macau, but not on this scale”, he noted, referring to “Widex Macau”. “We’ve been here longer than others”, he highlighted.
“Widex Macau” resulted from a partnership between “Widex of Denmark”, “Widex Hong Kong” and “Bond Medical”, a company founded in 2002 by Virginia Kong’s father, who accumulated more than five decades of experience in the area of ​​pharmaceutical distribution and medical services.
"Due to his work, he was always in contact with local doctors and health professionals. He felt there wasn't as much awareness or a place where people could get professional help. At the time, there were only over-the-counter hearing aids, which were less advanced than in Hong Kong. People on a limited budget needed to travel to Hong Kong. It was inconvenient, especially for the elderly and children," he recalled.
"Everyone over 50 years of age should undergo a hearing test as part of their annual routine exams. We need to monitor our hearing health. People in Macau don't pay as much attention as they do to their eyes or blood pressure. We should really value our hearing", reinforced Virginia Kong.
In this sense, the director left a warning. "Once your hearing starts to deteriorate, you can't recover it, because once the hair cells die, they don't recover. Therefore, we have to pay more attention to preventative measures. When a person feels they are losing hearing, they should seek help, because, as the brain is not as stimulated, other problems can arise."
Some of the most common first signs of deterioration in hearing capacity in older people are, for example, "when they start to answer questions wrong or when family members complain that their cell phone or television is playing too loud. This tends to be one of the most common complaints", he noted. Or when they become “moody” or “more sensitive”. If the person “is not actively social with friends or family, they may develop dementia or some cognitive disorder in the future”, he warned.
 
Government and population more aware
The Center's mission also aligns with the Executive's health plan, said Virginia Kong. "[The Government] also wants to control and prevent the occurrence of long-term illnesses. Dementia and cognitive disorders are long-term illnesses that society wants to prevent, as the costs are very high, because of the caregivers and the medicines needed."
According to the IAS, in October 2025, 13,648 people received an annual disability allowance, the value of which was 10 thousand patacas per individual, while another 5,752 people received support of 20 thousand patacas, corresponding to a total public expenditure of more than 251 million.
For the person responsible for “Widex Macau”, “in recent years, the Government has paid more attention to hearing loss. Conde de São Januário Hospital is slowly increasing the services it can offer. Despite not offering hearing aids or other rehabilitation products, they are trying to make more tests available”.
In the director's opinion, technological progress has also benefited the cause and helped to combat stigma. "Hearing aids have become smaller. They are also more aesthetically pleasing. People used to be very insecure. [The devices] were heavy and unintuitive. They were not as comfortable", he concluded.
Over the years, the Center has gained “strong recognition from the public”, through various community awareness activities and events on rehabilitation and hearing protection. As the years passed and an increasingly aged population, the original space became insufficient to meet growing demand.
 
New space to respond to greater demand
In response, Virginia Kong decided to acquire the commercial unit next to the Center, where “Widex Macau” operates until the renovation works are completed and the old space is reopened. "This site had been vacant for two years. It used to be a veterinary hospital. We felt that the other space needed to be optimized." “More and more people are seeking hearing care.” "We are not very big. We are small, but I am planning to expand because demand is growing", he assured.
“Because of the limitations of the small fraction, people didn’t have a good place to sit and wait comfortably.” “We used to have some elderly customers who stopped here just to take a blood pressure test and read the newspaper,” he said, stressing that he also intends to offer a more community experience.
"We have people of all ages. In addition to the pilots I mentioned just now, we also have individuals who work in construction. By law, they are required to have hearing tests every two years."
"In the old space we only do pure tone tests and impedance audiometry. We want to add more pediatric services and some advanced auditory services like Auditory Brainstem Response, in which the patient is asleep and we collect more accurate data", said Virginia Kong.
The Center has also focused efforts on public health education. The director hopes that the new space will allow regular seminars on health and activities in collaboration with non-governmental organizations.
Looking ahead to the next decade, Kong hopes the new Ten-Year Plan will “emphasize hearing health, greater subsidies for devices and regular publications of specific data for better transparency and monitoring”.
In addition to the inauguration of the new facilities, scheduled for this Saturday, “Widex Macau” is already preparing activities for World Hearing Day.</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Passenger volume at the Airport could rise to 8.14 million in 2026</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/volume-de-passageiros-aeroporto-pode-subir-para-814-milhoes-em-2026/</link><description>The Airport Society predicts that during the current year the volume of passengers could reach 8.14 million. In the balance of airport activities for 2025, the president of the CAM Executive Committee indicated that revenues amounted to around 1.35 billion patacas, a drop of 8.5% in annual terms. He also highlighted that the various ongoing projects have injected “new impetus” into aviation logistics in the Greater Bay Area
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The volume of passengers at Macau International Airport could reach 8.14 million this year, which, if expectations are confirmed, would mean an increase of 8.2% compared to the previous year, when 7.52 million were recorded. The 2025 number meant a slight decline of 1.6% compared to 2024.
In estimates for 2026, those responsible for the Macau International Airport Society (CAM) also foresee a total of 63,000 flight movements, 110,000 tons of cargo volume and 1,200 executive aviation movements.
Speaking at the spring lunch, the president of the CAM Executive Committee said that the Society intends to launch more multimodal transport ports, as well as update services to meet passenger travel demand.
Simon Chan Weng Hong highlighted that there are plans to implement suspensions of night flights from the fourth quarter of this year, “in order to move forward with the recovery and expansion of the landing and take-off runway and the respective platform, as well as building a new taxiway bridge, at the same time as repair and improvement works on the runway are planned”.
In 2026, “more new airlines will join Macau”, highlighted the official, adding that several others have increased the frequency of flights to existing destinations and that the main project of the Airport Development Plan – Expansion and Recovery Project “progressed steadily” in 2025.
He added that this project includes the construction of temporary dikes and embankment, foundation work with piles for the material conveyor belt, work near the taxiway bridges carried out during the suspension of night operations and environmental and flood prevention monitoring, in accordance with the established plan.
Meanwhile, construction of the Hengqin Upstream Cargo Terminal Project is progressing “comprehensively”, with acceptance testing expected to be completed by the end of 2026 and operations to begin in the first half of 2027.
“CAM continues to deepen collaboration with relevant parties to promote the development of an international air cargo hub on the west bank of the Pearl River, in Macau”, stated the CEO of the entity responsible for the development, financial operation and commercial exploitation of the Airport.
Speaking about the balance of 2025, he highlighted that the volume of international passengers increased by 8% compared to the previous year and that the volume of cargo exceeded 109,000 tons, registering a growth of approximately 1% in annual terms, while executive aviation movements reached 1,165, an increase of 2%.
Total revenue in 2025 amounted to around 1.35 billion patacas, a drop of 8.5% compared to the previous year.
 
Terminal with improvements to security channels
Regarding improvements to terminal facilities and services, infrastructure optimization was carried out “in an orderly manner” last year, mainly including “hardware” upgrades for smart security channels integrated with biometric recognition and digital identity technologies “to improve efficiency and security experience”, noted Simon Chan.
As the first overseas user of the National Traffic Flow Management System, the Airport “has achieved a transformative shift from ‘manual coordination’ to ‘system collaboration’, with on-time flight performance constantly improving”, he noted.
In the same vein, he pointed out that “the Airport has actively integrated regional transportation resources with three major service centers established in 2025 to promote regional connectivity and the benefits of ‘Flying via Macau’, while also offering convenient information about flights, ticketing and immigration assistance.”
In terms of optimizing the travel experience, “the signage system will be fully updated and the commercial area will be renovated, including the food kiosk in the restricted area of ​​the northern extension of the terminal, which is expected to open in the 2nd quarter of 2026, bringing a completely new experience to travelers”, he said.
Simon Chan said that CAM will continue to adhere to the fundamental principle of “Safety, Efficiency and Effectiveness”, keeping in line with the Government's objectives of strengthening and improving the advantages of the integrated tourism and leisure industries. The objective, he assures, is to further deepen the integration and cross-border development of “tourism+” and expand the sources of international tourism, injecting a “new impetus” into air logistics in the Greater Bay Area.
In the same presentation, the person responsible spoke about the implementation of smart technologies and improvements to the passenger experience. “Services have been updated and optimized to further improve operational efficiency, while diversifying shopping, dining and relaxation options to create a more premium and convenient travel experience for passengers.”
 
MGM Cotai offers check-in option
Hotel guests now have access to an additional check-in service, which will benefit travelers traveling to Macau, Hong Kong and Zhuhai airports. The latest option is available at MGM Cotai and opened yesterday. “The launch is a significant milestone in strengthening cross-border aviation services and collaboration in intermodal transport between Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau,” MGM said in a statement, adding that the aim is to strengthen “mutual connectivity” within the Greater Bay Area. Last week, the Airport announced new check-in services at Holiday Inn Express and Crowne Plaza Macau.
 
Surveillance in aviation called for due to Nipah virus
The Health Services (SSM) indicated that currently, and according to the World Health Organization's risk assessment, the impact of the Nipah virus for Macau is “relatively low”. Even so, they organized a lecture on the subject, aimed at representatives of the Civil Aviation Authority, the Airport Society and airlines. Representatives from the Center for Disease Prevention and Control of the SSM explained in detail the epidemiological situation of Nipah virus infection, the transmission routes, clinical symptoms and important points of personal protection, among other aspects, with a view to increasing the prevention capacity of frontline staff. More than 100 managers were present. During the meeting, it was highlighted that the border post constitutes the first line of defense against the importation of serious infectious diseases. To protect the health of residents, the aviation sector “must remain vigilant and take precautionary measures, as well as ensure sufficient reserves of protective equipment, through regular checks”, they stressed. So far, Indian authorities have announced that the number of cases of infection is low and limited to the State of West Bengal, with transmission taking place mainly within hospitals.</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Uber raises concerns about data and oversight</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/uber-gera-preocupacoes-dados-fiscalizacao/</link><description>After Uber once again offered transport services in Macau, deputy Leong Sun Iok defended clarifications on where passenger and taxi driver data collected by the platform will be stored. In the same vein, a member of the Traffic Advisory Council warned of inspection problems
 
Reacting to the return of Uber services to the MSAR with the availability of new services for requesting taxis and booking cross-border transport between Hong Kong and Macau, MP Leong Sun Iok acknowledged that booking taxis online has already become a general trend. However, he warned that, with the lack of specific legal provisions regulating this type of service, it will be difficult to protect the rights and interests of passengers or drivers.
Specifically, it is important to clarify where the passenger and taxi driver data collected by Uber will be stored, said the deputy, warning that, if they are transferred abroad, the process must comply with the relevant regulations, otherwise it could violate the law. In this sense, the location of Uber's data server constitutes a focus of attention, highlighted Leong Sun Iok.
According to the newspaper “Ou Mun”, the deputy added that, currently, the four online taxi booking platforms in operation all have their servers installed within the country.
In general, Leong Sun Iok urged the Government to speed up the review of the legal regime for passenger transport in rental cars, to strengthen guarantees for both passengers and drivers. As he exemplified, there are cases in which the passenger did not use the service after booking online, however, the taxi driver was unable to recover the losses, or the passenger did not have the rights and interests protected by law when faced with the taxi driver's no-show due to problems on the platform.
Furthermore, he regretted that some platforms charged additional fees to passengers, thus renewing the call for authorities to complete the review of the law as quickly as possible to implement the supervision of online taxi request platforms.
On the same subject, Lei Chong Sam, member of the Traffic Advisory Council, also warned of “problems that require attention”, including the inspection of the online booking platform, terminals installed in vehicles, drivers, the order distribution mechanism and additional charging.
Quoted by the newspaper “Exmoo News”, the member also warned about the lack of supervision by the law, noting that, currently, private online platforms basically operate under self-management, in a “semi-public and semi-hidden” state. In his opinion, the essential step is to clarify which Government service will be responsible for monitoring, that is, “who can enter the system and manage the mobilization of vehicles”, since “currently some taxi hailing platforms seem to present problems such as difficult scheduling and no-shows”.</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Art Museum will host major exhibition dedicated to Vieira da Silva</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/museu-de-arte-de-macau-vai-receber-grande-mostra-dedicada-vieira-da-silva/</link><description>Exhibitions dedicated to Rui Sanches, João Paulo Feliciano and Lourdes Castro, and a large international exhibition by Maria Helena Vieira da Silva in Macau are part of the activity plan for 2026 at the Arpad Szenes Museum – Vieira da Silva, in Lisbon.

Organized in three cycles, the exhibition program in Lisbon will also host exhibitions, among other artists, by Teresa Segurado Pavão, Frida Baranek, Vasco Futscher, Carlos Noronha Feio, Mariana Caló and Francisco Queimadela, according to the program now released.
Contacted by the Lusa agency, the director supervised by the foundation with the same name highlighted that the new program will continue to value the work of the founding artists and promote dialogue with contemporary creation, alongside investing in the international circulation of the institution's “rich, broad and diverse” collection.
The first exhibition cycle, which opens on February 10th, includes the exhibition “Arpad Szenes and Vieira da Silva: nuclei of the collection”, bringing together fundamental works by the two artists, “organized in a diachronic and thematic reading that highlights the evolution and main lines of their productions”.
In the same period, “Essays in Immobility and Secret Movement” will be presented, which brings together sculptures by Rui Sanches and Teresa Segurado Pavão, in an unprecedented collaboration between the two artists.
“There are two artists who have this happy coincidence – like Vieira da Silva and Arpad Szenes – of being a couple, Rui Sanches dedicated to sculpture and drawing, and Teresa Pavão to ceramics and textiles”, pointed out Nuno Faria, highlighting that, according to the invited authors, “this unprecedented partnership between four hands will be unrepeatable”.
The exhibition brings together wall sculptures that combine wood and ceramics, proposing a contemporary approach to the still life genre, described Nuno Faria, who took over the direction of the museum at the beginning of 2024, following an international competition.
The first cycle also includes the exhibition “Desafios/Defiances”, by Brazilian sculptor Frida Baranek, composed of wall, suspended and floor sculptures, in which the artist works with materials associated with construction and architecture, exploring the relationship between body, scale and spatial perception.
“Broken Mile”, by Vasco Futscher, with ceramic pieces located between sculpture and painting, which cross references from architecture, decorative arts and art history, also enters this cycle.
Asked about the internationalization plan, Nuno Faria indicated that the foundation is preparing a large exhibition dedicated to Vieira da Silva at the Macau Museum of Art, built from works from the institution's collection, integrating “in a context of growing international interest in the artist”.
“We were challenged by our partners to hold a large exhibition in Macau with works from our collection and other collections, and we are working on this exhibition, which will take place at the end of the year and will coincide with the Arpad Szenes anthology in Lisbon”, said the person in charge.
According to Nuno Faria, the recent exhibitions of Maria Helena Vieira da Silva's work “raised a very visible interest in the retrospective exhibition at the Guggenheim Museum in Bilbao, which shed new light” on the Portuguese artist's work.
“This will be the first major exhibition by Vieira [da Silva] in China”, said the director of the museum opened in 1994 in the former Fábrica das Sedas, in Amoreiras, Lisbon, following the creation of the Arpad Szenes – Vieira da Silva Foundation, in 1990, intended to house and publicize the estate of the two painters.
It is also planned to present at the Embassy of Portugal, in The Hague, in the Netherlands, an exhibition dedicated to the graphic work of Vieira da Silva, bringing together a significant nucleus of the foundation's collection.
The museum's second exhibition cycle, between May 21st and September 13th, includes a new presentation of the cores of the Arpad Szenes and Vieira da Silva collection, deepening the reading of the work, and an exhibition dedicated to Lourdes Castro (1930-2022), with unpublished initial drawings, works and documentation from the 1950s and 1960s, developed in partnership with MUDAS – Museu de Arte Contemporânea da Wood.
The project revisits the initial period of the Madeiran artist's production, and highlights the personal and artistic connections she maintained with Vieira da Silva and Arpad Szenes.
Also part of this cycle is the exhibition “Da Capo”, by João Paulo Feliciano, bringing together recent paintings in dialogue with early works influenced by the pictorial language of Vieira da Silva, and “Reflexo deador”, by Mariana Caló and Francisco Queimadela, with installations that use light projections on silk fabrics, creating immersive environments that cross painting, cinema and installation.
An exhibition by Carlos Noronha Feio is also planned, composed of works that articulate images printed on silk and light, developed from research into the foundation's collection and archive.
The third cycle will be dedicated almost entirely to an anthological exhibition of the work of Arpad Szenes (1897-1985), based on in-depth research into his pictorial and graphic production, with the aim of presenting new readings of the artist's work and promoting the international circulation of the project.
“This is perhaps the most challenging exhibition we are going to do this year”, said the museum director to Lusa, adding that the entire museum space will be dedicated to Arpad Szenes.
The anthological exhibition “will give the public the opportunity to revisit the work of Arpad Szenes, which over the past year aroused a lot of curiosity among museum visitors, and will be a way of looking in depth at his first works until the end”, he added.
Still on dates to be defined, an exhibition of Vieira da Silva's graphic work in the Azores is also planned for this year.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DICJ guarantees “rigor” in the analysis of revenue generated by foreigners</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dicj-garante-rigor-na-analise-de-receitas-geradas-por-estrangeiros/</link><description>Ng Wai Han, director of the DICJ, assured that “strict standards” are established regarding the analysis of gross revenue generated by foreign players. As he explained, there is a “daily check” of these recipes
 
The Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ) guarantees that it has established “strict standards” regarding the identification measures for customers from foreign countries and the gross gaming revenues generated by them. “Specifically, concessionaires are obliged to establish standard operating procedures and internal and regular audit mechanisms”, says the director, Ng Wai Han, in response to a question from deputy José Pereira Coutinho.
The objective, he continues, is “to ensure that all transactions and gaming activities of customers from foreign countries are carried out by foreign visitors in accordance with what is defined, effectively verifying the updating, accuracy and integrity of records regarding gross gaming revenues”.
Furthermore, Ng Wai Han stated that “the standard operating procedures and the audit mechanism must be approved in advance by the DICJ”, in addition to that, “after the approval of the standard operating procedures and the audit mechanism, the DICJ will continue to carry out daily assessment and verification of the gross gaming revenues generated by customers from foreign countries”.
The leader of the organization also states that, when the concessionaire submits the request for the reduction or exemption of contributions, the DICJ “will also check the supporting documents and information presented by the concessionaire, as well as carry out the audit, including the random verification of the players' identification data and gaming records, etc., in order to verify whether the gross revenues from the game come from foreign visitors in accordance with the definition”.
It is recalled that in 2024, the six gaming concessionaires were exempt from paying approximately 150 million Hong Kong dollars, under the Gaming Law, which grants an exemption of up to 5% on gaming tax on revenue generated by international players. Also according to information provided by the president of the 2nd Permanent Committee of the Legislative Assembly, operators increased non-gaming investments by 170 million patacas.
Deputy José Pereira Coutinho had asked the Government about how many requests for reduction or exemption of contributions had been analyzed and how many had been approved since 2023 and to date, a question that remained unanswered.
Furthermore, he also asked what type of concrete documentary evidence is required from gaming concessionaires to demonstrate that it was through their promotional or business actions that they effectively attracted foreign players “and not generic and fortuitous factors such as the reopening of borders”.
In the response, Ng Wai Han highlights that, in the application for the public tender for the granting of concessions for the operation of games of chance in casinos, “the concessionaires clearly presented their commitments and plans regarding the expansion of customer markets in foreign countries, the contents of which were incorporated into the concession contract”. “And the Macao SAR Government has continued to monitor compliance with contractual obligations”, he assured.
In another context, and in response to another question also from Pereira Coutinho, Ng Wai Han indicated that the DICJ “is carrying out review work, in order to analyze the fulfillment of social responsibilities by [gaming operators], as well as the promotion of adequate diversification of the economy and sustainable development, among other aspects”.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Women's Association calls for screening for more cancers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/associacao-das-mulheres-pede-rastreios-para-mais-cancros/</link><description>Taking advantage of World Cancer Day, the General Women's Association called on authorities to be aware of new trends in the incidence rate of cancer. Among other measures, it suggests screening programs for cancers with a rising incidence rate, such as thyroid and prostate cancer. Furthermore, it hopes that diagnostic and treatment technologies and medicines will be improved
 
On the occasion of World Cancer Day, celebrated yesterday, the General Women's Association of Macau called on authorities to pay attention to new trends in the incidence rate of cancer and continually reinforce prevention and treatment work.
Women's Association vice-president and congresswoman Wong Kit Cheng and the association's Women's Medical Center doctor Chen Kin Ian suggested launching pilot screening programs for cancers with an increased incidence rate, both in community medical services and in healthcare. Specifically, they requested blood collection services to screen for thyroid and prostate cancer.
At this point, they warned that, according to the Macau Cancer Report for 2023, the standardized incidence rate of prostate cancer registered a significant increase of 79% from 2019 to 2023, and the same happened with thyroid cancer among women, which increased by 46%, compared to the rates recorded between 2014 and 2018. In this sense, they consider that these trends require joint attention from society.
For the two association leaders, authorities must expand the means of evaluating and screening cancers and improve diagnostic and treatment technologies and medicines. In terms of treatment, they hope that the advantages of Hospital das Ilhas and the medicine assessment and approval system will be taken advantage of, so that more cancer treatment technologies and advanced medicines can be introduced and used in Macau.
On the other hand, Wong Kit Cheng and Chen Kin Ian asked authorities to develop specific awareness-raising actions about cancers with incidence rates rising significantly in recent years. In this aspect, they defended more intensified community cooperation in order to increase residents' awareness of self-management of health. “Through health lectures and diverse publicity, the work can allow more residents to learn about the risks and symptoms of cancer”, they highlighted.
According to the aforementioned report, the relative survival rate of cancer patients rose from 59% to 62% between 2013 and 2023, “standing among the highest levels in the world”. Meanwhile, the mortality rate in cancer patients shows a decreasing trend in the Macao SAR, having fallen by almost 18% in the space of 10 years.</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief wants to strengthen connection with MNE Commissioner</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-quer-reforcar-ligacao-comissariado-mne/</link><description>The Chief Executive met with the new commissioner of the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs in Macau, at the Government Headquarters. In his welcome speech to Bian Lixin, Sam Hou Fai highlighted the Macao SAR Government's intention to “strengthen communication and connection” with the Commissioner
 
Sam Hou Fai stated that the Macao SAR will continue to “strengthen communication and liaison” with the Commissariat of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs (MNE) of China in Macau, according to a press release. The Chief Executive received Bian Lixin, the new MNE commissioner, at a meeting at the Government Headquarters, during which both parties shared opinions on the Macao SAR's external affairs and the implementation of the “one country, two systems” principle.
It is recalled that Bian Linxin arrived in Macau at the end of January to replace Liu Xianfa. The Government leader said he hoped that the Commission “will continue to support and contribute to the long-term prosperity and stability of Macau”, according to the Social Communication Office.
The Chief Executive stated that the “Government is determined to leverage Macau’s position as a ‘center, a platform and a base’ and to “fully utilize its advantages in connecting domestic and international markets and in the fusion of Chinese and Western cultures”. In this sense, the Executive intends to “actively promote the strategy of ‘outward expansion and investment attraction’ and constantly increase its international competitiveness and influence”.
During his welcome speech, Sam Hou Fai recalled that, since the MSAR was established, the Chinese MNE Commissionerate “has provided strong support to the territory”, helping Macau “to respond to various internal and external challenges”.
Furthermore, the Commission “has fully supported Macau in valuing its unique advantages, expanding exchanges and cooperation with abroad, expanding external contacts, strengthening its capabilities in governing external relations, fully protecting the rights and interests of Macau residents abroad, promoting the development of adequate diversification of the economy and helping Macau to better take advantage of the institutional advantages of the ‘one country, two systems’ principle”, highlighted Sam Hou Fai.
Projecting “a new situation of high-quality development”, the Chief also recalled the visits abroad, which are scheduled for this year, as well as the “plans for the establishment of an economic and commercial delegation in Southeast Asian countries”. These plans aim to “further expand the tourist market and consolidate Macau’s position as a global tourism and leisure center”, he argued.
Present at the meeting were Chan Kak, head of the Chief Executive's Office, Derek Loi, director of Government Headquarters Affairs Services, and Cheng Lei, deputy commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs in Macau, among others.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Imperatori publishes research on innovation in architecture</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/imperatori-divulga-pesquisas-sobre-inovacao-na-arquitectura/</link><description>Marco Imperatori's experience in the world of architecture and his research projects will be highlighted in a lecture that the Italian professor will give today at the University of Science and Technology
 
The Faculty of Human Sciences and Arts of the University of Science and Technology of Macau (UCTM) and CAC – Círculo dos Amigos da Cultura de Macau will organize the 280th Distinguished Artists Lecture “Architecture for Humanity” and “Innovative External Systems for Architecture”, given in English by Marco Imperadori, professor at the Polytechnic of Milan, Italy.
The seminars, which are part of the Continuous Professional Development (CPD) program and will be conducted in English, are scheduled for this Thursday, from 3:30 pm to 6:30 pm.
On the theme “Architecture for Humanity”, the professor and researcher will address very difficult post-disaster, emergency or difficult situations for social or economic reasons, reporting on his experiences and that of his VeluxLab team from the Department of Architecture, Built Environment and Construction Engineering of the Italian institution.
In the second part, in “Innovative External Systems for Architecture”, he will present the innovation he designed with different companies and which generated an industrial following. All the prototypes presented were used for public social or cultural purposes in different locations, as highlighted in a note from the CAC.
Marco Imperadori is a full professor and researcher, holding the chair of Technological Design and Innovation. His work focuses on high energy efficiency buildings, structural/envelope building systems and sustainability. With a master's and doctorate in Civil Engineering, he combines knowledge of architecture and engineering.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM and University of Bologna with double doctorate</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/upm-universidade-de-bolonha-duplo-doutoramento/</link><description>As part of the construction of the Macau and Hengqin International Education (University) City, the Macau Polytechnic University signed an international agreement with the University of Bologna on the award of double doctorates
 
The rector of the Macau Polytechnic University (UPM), Marcus Im, signed the International Academic Agreement on the Award of Double Doctorates, together with the rector of the University of Bologna, Giovanni Molari, as part of a visit to renowned Italian universities. “This agreement marks a consensus reached between the two universities on cooperation in joint scientific research and the cultivation of qualified high-technology staff”, says the local higher education institution in a statement.
For UPM, this agreement “further” reinforces academic cooperation between China and Italy, “bringing together innovative international resources for Macau and the Greater Bay Area and promoting the internationalization of the International Education (University) City of Macau and Hengqin, with fruitful results”.
At the agreement signing ceremony, which took place at the Rector's Building of the University of Bologna, Marcus Im recalled that that institution was founded in 1088, “enjoying the reputation of ‘Alma Mater Studiorum’”. “Since the launch of the double doctorate academic degree course in 2022, the two universities have continued to deepen the cultivation of qualified staff in the field of cutting-edge technology”, he added.
“The signing of this agreement is one of the key projects to promote the construction of the University City”, continued Marcus Im, saying that, in conjunction with UPM’s “Artificial Intelligence +” scientific research strategies, “it will focus on the joint training of doctoral students in cutting-edge fields such as applied computer technology and artificial intelligence, improving the mechanisms of bidirectional mobility and joint guidance”. The objective, he stressed, is to train more “high-level qualified staff with an international vision and capacity for innovation”.
Giovanni Molari, for his part, and also in accordance with the UPM statement, stated that the two parties have achieved great results in many areas based on the solid strategic cooperation established over the years. He also noted that the signing of this agreement is based on “the shared academic vision and deep mutual trust that has been built over a long period of time, helping to expand high-level scientific research collaboration and strengthen exchanges between students and faculty members in the future”.
“With the new opportunities resulting from the construction of the University City, cooperation between the two parties will be expanded to a deeper and broader level in the future”, he argued, hoping that “the advantages and resources of both institutions will continue to be integrated, exploring innovative academic paths to face global challenges and contributing to the advancement of knowledge and social development”.
During their stay in Italy, the UPM delegation visited the Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, where they were received by the deputy rector of Global Affairs, Edilio Mazzoleni, and his academic team. The two parts covered topics such as artificial intelligence, data science and linguistic technology. They also explored “future collaboration projects”.
Marcus Im presented the development of UPM in the field of applied sciences, especially the development focus and interdisciplinary advantages in artificial intelligence and data technology. He also hoped that, based on the cultivation of existing qualified staff, the two universities will continue to develop diversified cooperation.
In turn, Edilio Mazzoleni highlighted that the two parties have similar concepts and complementary advantages in promoting the integration of technological innovation and social application and that they have “broad perspectives for cooperation”, and hoped that, in the future, “international cooperation would be deepened and progress would be made in joint scientific research, exchanges and visits by academics and the cultivation of qualified staff”.</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Korean pop culture in focus in Lisbon</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cultura-pop-coreana-em-foco-lisboeta/</link><description>Various K-pop themed activities and interactive experiences to promote South Korean pop culture, including dance performances and guest participation segments, will liven up the Lisbon Macau hotel on Sunday. The event is also part of the “Gen K-pop Battle”, a competition whose winner will be rewarded with professional dance training at a Korean dance studio
 
Next Sunday, the Lisbon Macau hotel organizes “Do it! H853 K-Wave FanFest”, a fun event that integrates a variety of K-pop themed activities and interactive experiences to celebrate the global appeal of South Korean pop culture.
The initiative, which has the support of the Tourism Services Bureau, includes dance performances and guest participation segments, with the aim, according to the organization, “to further support cultural tourism in Macau and expand diverse entertainment options for younger generations”.
“Fanfest” will offer a variety of K-pop themed activities and interactive experiences to celebrate the global appeal of Korean pop culture, highlighted by creative dance performances, which will engage and participate in pop culture entertainment such as the World Tourism and Leisure Center and the City of Performing Arts.
The “H853 Fun Factory” space in Lisboeta will also host the “H853 1st-6th Gen K-pop Battle”, whose registrations are now open, with the winner being awarded with professional dance training at the renowned Korean dance studio, “offering participants a unique opportunity to delve into the heart of K-pop culture”, says the note.
"DO IT! H853 K–Wave FanFest" focuses on K-pop music, dance, trending culture and fan communities. K–Pop random dance challenges will provide a platform for dance lovers to connect and showcase their talent. In addition to professional dance training at the studio in South Korea, the first place winner will also be entitled to round-trip tickets, “providing broader opportunities for learning and growth”, highlights the statement.
The event will take place between 2pm and 5pm, at the “Lisboeta Macau H853 Fun Factory”, with free entry.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Remote consultation certificates should now be valid</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/atestados-de-consultas-a-distancia-deverao-passar-ser-validos/</link><description>The Government wants certificates of illness, recovery and licenses issued through remote medical services to have the same validity as certificates from in-person consultations, according to Wong Kit Cheng, president of the First Standing Committee of the Legislative Assembly. The Commission yesterday discussed the proposed law on the activity of Private Institutions Providing Health Care (IPPS) that restricts the provision of remote medical services to hospitals. The Commission questioned whether these certificates would be recognized by employers and public services. Wong Kit Cheng stated that the Government will communicate with the Labor Affairs Bureau and other public bodies to ensure the recognition of certificates issued remotely. In addition, the creation of a 'one-stop' service was also discussed, to shorten the application time for opening integrated clinics, as well as the introduction of an evaluation committee. Applicants will be able to submit a request to the Health Services through the Platform for Companies and Associations, which will be forwarded and assessed by different government departments. The adoption of a registration mechanism for clinics with a single health professional was also discussed. Clinics with an area of ​​more than 120 square meters that need to carry out structural works and integrated clinics with more than two healthcare professionals will be subject to the licensing regime, which can be processed in the 'one-stop' service.</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Businesspeople visit Portuguese-speaking countries in the 2nd quarter</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/empresarios-visitam-paises-lusofonos-2o-trimestre/</link><description>The Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment (IPIM) will coordinate “a delegation made up of businesspeople from Macau and the Cooperation Zone to Portuguese and Spanish Speaking Countries for economic and commercial exchange activities in the second quarter of 2026”, revealed Jacinto Luiz, deputy president of the organization. According to him, through presentation sessions, signing of cooperation protocols and contact grants, IPIM hopes to “strengthen cooperation with these countries in the areas of technology and big health, etc.”. The idea is to “better play Macau’s role as a ‘precision interlocutor’ between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries, as well as continue to reinforce and optimize the ‘China-PLP Trade Conduct’ service, helping companies to expand their business abroad”, he added, in response to a question from Lee Koi Ian. Furthermore, he indicated that IPIM will hire market-oriented professional consultancy teams, “in order to reinforce the cooperation network in terms of attracting investments in the markets of Mainland China and Portuguese- and Spanish-speaking Countries”. Through collaboration with the Center for Economic and Commercial Services between China and Portuguese/Spanish Speaking Countries, initial support services will be provided to companies in international business expansion, “effectively playing the role of the Macau platform in internal and external communication”.</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Book of jokes about Picasso reveals visions of friends and enemies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/livro-de-anedotas-sobre-picasso-revela-visoes-de-amigos-inimigos/</link><description>A woman is silhouetted as she walks past a copy of Spanish artist Pablo Picasso's "Guernica" at the 'Skulpturenmuseum Glaskasten' in western city of Marl November 17, 2006. A new exhibition opens November 19 in Marl, marking the 125th anniversary of the painter's birth.  REUTERS/Ina Fassbender (GERMANY)



A book that brings together, for the first time, anecdotes published about Pablo Picasso reveals how his contemporaries saw the artist born in Málaga and the opinions that his art provoked, both among friends and enemies.
"These anecdotes capture the way journalists at the time saw Picasso. There are, for example, many jokes about Cubism, because when the artist began to be famous, he was not appreciated by the press from the beginning", explains Rafael Inglada, author of this book published by the Museu Casa Natal de Picasso, in an interview with the EFE agency.
With a preface by the Catalan journalist Lluís Permanyer, recently deceased, “Pablo Picasso. Livro de Anecdotas” is part of a tetralogy that began with “Pablo Picasso. Livro de Conversas” (2023), which will be followed by two more volumes dedicated, respectively, “to statements to the press and defenses, the latter of a more political nature”, explains Inglada.
Compiling these more than 260 anecdotes required thorough research in newspaper archives. The vast majority of texts were published in France, with only a few in Spain. According to the author, the texts sometimes reveal “a lot of malice, but also, at other times, a lot of kindness and an approach to the topic”. According to Rafael Inglada, “through the press, a new Picasso is revealed, seen by his contemporaries”.
“These are anecdotes that appear in articles and rarely appear in biographies, therefore, this is a way of publishing an unpublished book, something increasingly difficult to achieve when it comes to Picasso”, he highlights.
The French press dedicated many more pages to Picasso than the Spanish press during the Franco regime, with an approach that encompassed “everything”, since “sometimes a certain irony or malice on the part of the writer shines through in the texts”.
“This is a book that can be opened on any page, with brief anecdotes, organized chronologically, ranging from 1910, at the height of Cubism, to 1973, the year of Picasso's death”, highlights Inglada.
In its pages, you discover, for example, how the Malaga artist reacted when asked to explain his work. A woman who had just bought him a drawing asked: “What does this represent, master?”, to which Picasso replied: “Exactly 3,000 francs, my lady!”
Another buyer boasted to Picasso that he owned paintings by Degas, Cézanne and other painters, purchased for considerable sums. He stated that works by deceased masters “had to be paid for at exorbitant prices.”
When Pablo Picasso asked him for 5,000 francs for his painting, the buyer was surprised, and the Malaga artist explained: “It's my posthumous price, sir.”
About the beginning of the artist's career, it is said that Picasso wanted Rodin's opinion on his first futurist work. He showed it to Rodin before signing it, as he wanted an authoritative opinion.
Rodin picked up the painting, turned it over several times and said to Picasso: “In any case, boy, I advise you to sign it, so at least we will know how to hang it.”
On another occasion, a press photographer visited the artist, who received him in a large, empty room. There, the visitor was surprised to find none of his paintings. "Nowadays, a Picasso costs more than 500,000 francs. It's a luxury I can't afford," said the artist from Malaga.
Resuming the interpretation of his works, Picasso took the opportunity to needle critics. At the opening of an exhibition, someone asked him what those paintings represented and he replied: “You'll read it in tomorrow's newspapers”.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>