<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>TSI expects “more lawsuits” but faces “scarcity of judges”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/tsi-espera-mais-processos-mas-enfrenta-escassez-de-juizes/</link><description>Now that there are more judges in the courts of the first instance and that social and economic activities are resuming, more cases are expected to be admitted to the second instance court, however, it faces "scarcity of judges." To “improve the efficiency and quality of judgment”, it is necessary to “put more judges in the sections of proceedings”, says the report of the last year judiciary. On the other hand, it warns that the Base Judicial Court will face “a lot of pressure” on human resources, specifically to court officials
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The number of cases admitted to the Second Instance (TSI) is expected to “increase even more in the future”, given that social and economic activities “return to normal” and that new magistrates who have completed the formation were appointed judges of the first instance courts in October last year. However, “TSI is (…) facing a scarcity of judges,” says the report of the last year.
In this sense, and “in order to deal with increasingly complex cases, it is considered to put more judges in the process sections in the future, with a view to improving the efficiency and quality of proceedings judgment”, can be read in the document.
In 2023/2024, TSI had eight judges, including President Tong Hio Fong. According to the list of judges published on the website of the courts of MSAR, it is currently nine, more than then, which is Seng Ioi Man. It should be noted that it is in this instance that is also one of the only two judges hired in Portugal: Rui Ribeiro.
The document suggests, on the other hand, that the “external exchange activities” are reinforced to “improve the professional level and vision of judges”, as well as communication about the judicial system of the interior of China. The idea will be “closely the rhythm of national development”, with special emphasis on exchanges and collaboration with the great bay and the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin.
In the period under analysis, they entered TSI 998 cases, and by joining those of the previous year total 1,371. Of these, 1,012 were completed, with a resolution rate of 101.40%, an increase of 5.53% compared to the number of processes in the year immediately before. Thus, 359 lawsuits went to the following year, less 3.75% compared to the previous year.
In relation to the Base Judicial Court (TJB), and as in the previous judiciary, the report warns that “it is predictable that several court officials will fulfill retirement requirements in the coming years and the possibility of some court officials cannot be excluded for other services”. These factors will “necessarily cause a lot of pressure to the Human Resources of the TJB”.
In the report, it is also said that the Legal and Judicial Training Center held a new qualification course for entry into the careers of Judicial Justice Officer and the Public Prosecution Service in April 2024. "It is expected that this can supply as soon as possible human resources in the TJB, in order to relieve the insufficiency of personnel that occurs successively in process sessions," he adds.
According to statistical data, the courts of first instance currently have 41 judges, specifically 36 in the TJB, including Jerónimo Santos (one of the nine presidents of collective court), three in the court of criminal instruction and two in the administrative court. In 2023/2024, the lower court courts had 33 judges, one of which Carlos Carvalho, who left roles in late August last year.
Despite the issue of court officials, “the global functioning of the lower court courts was good” in general terms. But to “further reduce the volume of work” of staff and “improve work efficiency, first instance courts will continue to optimize the process management platform”.
It is also mentioned that the TJB began “inspection” to judicial employees who gathered the conditions, expecting to “detect, as soon as possible, potential problems and disabilities at work, in order to issue guidance and make time improvements”.
 
“Strengthen” knowledge with the public
On the other hand, there was “a significant increase” in the number of cases admitted by the criminal court, which totaled 6,436, plus 1,173 or 22.29%, compared to the previous judiciary. In this case, 6,624 were completed, representing an increase of 1,235 processes (+22.92%) and a resolution rate of 102.92%. Pendants were 2,403, a decrease of 7.26% or less 188 processes.
Although “a certain number of criminal instruction proceedings” related to “lack of knowledge of the parties” -since they “wrongly believed the instruction was the necessary pre -judgment procedure, so they required the opening of instruction to have a faster judgment” -the situation was that the situation “improved” compared to previous years.
The report also tells that "some parties, because they are not familiar with the judicial process, did not intend the instruction process, missing the opportunity to ask the court to revise the decision of the investigation." In order to avoid the “wrong intervention” in the instructional processes of the procedural parties that want to obtain the outcome of judgment sooner, among other cases, it is said that the knowledge of the public regarding the instruction process should be “reinforcing the better revelation of judicial impartiality”.
In addition, it was also recorded “a slight increase” (eight or an increase of 9.09%) in the number of administrative proceedings entered into the Administrative Court (TA), which totaled 96. In the TA, 83 lawsuits were exceeded, less 13.54%or 13 cases, having been pending 99. The resolution rate was 86.46%.
"In response to the trend of socioeconomic development, the number of processes may increase further, in particular those involving the government's government infrastructure measures, population subsistence policies, administrative supervision and sanctions, etc. However, with adequate adjustment to judges' work, it is believed that the number of pending cases will maintain a reasonable level," says the document.
 
TUI JUDGES SEE PRAISE WORK
The superior body of the Hierarchy of the Courts of MSAR, in turn, "continued to ensure its normal and effective functioning", as well as to ensure "the independent judicial power." The number of cases admitted and concluded “diminished slightly” in the last court (TUI): 132 (2.94%less) were entry and 135 (less 3.57%) were ended. The resolution rate was 102.27%, not far below the one registered in the previous year. On the other hand, fewer processes were pendants, a total of 70, with a decrease of 4.11%.
In order for Song Man Law, president of TUI -who succeeded Sam Hou Fai -could inspect the first instance judges, the Council of Judicial Magistrates took steps to advance with the trial of some cases in his hands. In this situation, Judge José Dias Alado gave “great support and assistance”. Also the work of Song Man Lei is praised, since he judged, "in accumulation of functions, most of the processes that were distributed to him without delaying the judgment of the proceedings to which [was] responsible." "All this was due to the incessant efforts of the two TUI judges, who struggled their best to ensure the effective functioning of Tui.
As for the use of the two official languages, it is said that the courts of the three instances "have continued, as always, to implement the promotion of the use of the Chinese language." Having as assumed not to affect the functioning of the courts, ensure the quality of judicial decisions without delaying the judgment of the cases and taking into account the language that the procedural parts dominate, “both Chinese and Portuguese languages ​​or one of them used to perform procedural acts as the case of a specific case”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Anima debts increased to nearly two million</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dividas-da-anima-aumentaram-para-quase-dois-milhoes/</link><description>Anima's debts continue to grow, having reached a value of 1.9 million Patacas, according to the president of the executive committee of the Association to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. The difficulty in raising donations is due to “the general economic situation of society,” explained Zoe Tang. On the other hand, sanitation improvement work will start next month
 
Pedro Milheirão
The General Assembly of the Macao Animal Protective Society-Anima met on Sunday to discuss and vote on the account report, among other matters. Speaking to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the Association's executive committee chairman Zoe Tang said the anima accumulates debts worth 1.9 million patacas, regarding animal food expenses, veterinary treatments and employee wages.
"Due to the general economic situation of society, it is very difficult to raise donations. We can only maintain operations with donations from the Macau Foundation and a small number of individuals," said Zoe Tang. "We have placed 136 donations boxes in different locations, including two banks, the Tai Fung bank and the National Bank Overseas. We also observed that the number of donations is not as high as in previous years," he lamented, compared in particular with the period preceding the Covid-19 pandemic.
It is recalled that in February, the association's debts reached about 1.5 million patacas, as this newspaper reported at the time. In addition, the budget for 2025 will be 8.6 million patacas, plus 300 thousand patacas than the amount provided at the beginning of the year.
Regarding the association's sanitation problems, the work will start at the beginning of July. In February, Zoe Tang had said that this problem was one of the "pending questions" and unresolved in sight. The anima has already advanced a payment of 200 thousand Patacas to an engineering company, and the total cost of the project will be 460 thousand patacas.
Currently, the responsible company is also helping the association in the process of submission of the documentation, while waiting for the authorization of the soil services and urban construction.
 
Need for a TNR program
Asked about the government's actions regarding the TNR (catch, sterilizing and returning) program, the association's leader said that the "government currently has no direction for the program." The system, applied in many countries, prevents species such as highly fertile cats from multiplying, being an alternative to slaughter.
According to data provided by the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM), in the first quarter of this year 289 animals were sterilized, an increase of 27.9% for the same period of 2024. In addition, more cats (102) and fewer dogs (29) were adopted, compared to the first quarter of 2024 (97 and 68, respectively). A cat and a dog were returned to AMI between January and March.
In Tang's opinion, the lack of government developments is due to the fact that it is "very difficult to find appropriate places to carry out TNR, which involves resource problems and requires the assistance of many volunteers."
“Anima has about 1,500 volunteers registered, but as they have a main job, we do not have volunteers present at fixed times” during the operation period of the association, between 09h00 and 18h00. Currently, the association houses 400 dogs, 300 cats, 26 turtles and three hamsters.
Since 2003, the Association has been dedicated to taking care of abandoned and mistreated animals, having monthly adoption campaigns and other activities planned for this year. Within a year, the anima will have elections for the regulatory bodies.</description><pubDate>2025-06-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Electoral Commission Alert on Campaign Prohibition rules</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/comissao-eleitoral-alerta-sobre-regras-da-proibicao-de-campanha/</link><description>The beginning of the campaign ban for the elections for the Legislative Assembly, which will take place between June 27 and August 29, motivated an alert from the Electoral Affairs Commission so that candidacies, support teams and the general public do not violate the provisions of the law. For a better understanding of the campaign inhibition period, Caeal launched a collection of questions and answers yesterday. About the case of the only candidacy, the led by Wong Wai Man, the committee chairman says he did not receive any appeal. Regarding the five people accused of electoral corruption, Seng Ioi Man again mentioned that the investigations and inquiries “are autonomous”, so Caeal “will not know details” about this issue
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) warns that applications, mandates, support teams and the general public pay maximum attention to the provisions of the law and comply with what is stipulated for the campaign ban, which will take place from next Friday, June 27, until 29 August.
The president of Caeal recalls that, during this period of almost a month, "no one can campaign", otherwise "will violate the provisions of the electoral law" and can be punished with a fine between 2,000 and 10,000 patacas.
Seng Ioi Man appeals to compliance with the law so that “illegal propaganda acts are avoided”, thus safeguarding the electoral order and that “we can all work together to guarantee elections that take place within legality, justice, impartiality and integrity”.
At a press conference held yesterday morning, the official reaffirmed that "during the period of prohibition of advertising, neither candidates nor anyone can advertise for any means." According to the law, he stressed, "electoral propaganda means any and any way of drawing public attention to one or more candidates and expressly or implicitly suggesting to voters who vote or fail to vote for one or more candidates."
Prohibitions include calls made by message, phone, email, applications, electronic mail or other means.
Prior to the beginning of a prohibition of advertising, the transmission of news about elections, or on the constitution of a commission of application, presentation and candidacies, "are not considered as illegal propaganda," said the president of Caeal.
He added that this news that "is already on public platforms do not need to be withdrawn," but during the prohibition period "no content related to electoral propaganda should not be published, as well as the top, or in a prominent place, previous news, under penalty of being considered electoral propaganda."
According to Seng Ioi Man, deputies "can continue to perform their duties, participate in public activities, give interviews, comment on matters of today, take stock of their work as deputies in the latest legislatures," but are prevented from making electoral propaganda, "how to talk about their political program or electoral affairs."
 
Collection released on the electronic page
The official also released the launch, from yesterday, on the CAEAL Electronic page, of a collection, "for a better understanding of the provisions regarding the period of prohibition of advertising, with questions and answers." The careful reading of the compilation of useful elements about elections and specifically on the prohibition of advertising is advised by Seng Ioi Man, in order to “avoid inadvertent violations of the law”.
He added that Caeal has been discussing the presentation of the statement of electoral propaganda material to use by candidacies, including the obligation to submit separate statements. He gave the example of advertising materials to be distributed to the public, articles to supporters during campaign sessions, or the materials used by workers.
With the approach of the elections, scheduled for September 14, the commission underlines that it has been reinforcing the dissemination work. From August, video production will focus more on information about the consultation of the voting site, such as voting, or the vote secret.
A simulated voting assembly will also be installed before the elections, so that the public can know their operation, predicting the organization of visits and voting simulations for students "with a view to cultivating their civic consciousness."
In the period of questions and answers, Seng Ioi Man said he was not aware of any appeal presented by the only list rejected so far - the led by Wong Wai Man, also known as "Captain Macao". Regarding whether Caeal requested information from the prosecutor or the commissioner against corruption in the case of five people accused of electoral corruption, reiterated the separation of competences. "Research and inquiry activities are performed autonomous form and are subject to judicial confidentiality," so the commission "will not know details about this issue," he concluded.
It is recalled that, until yesterday, 12 lists of candidates to the elections, distributed in equal number (six) by the direct and indirect suffrage, lacking the realization of two of the direct suffrage.</description><pubDate>2025-06-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Catholic Association leads pilgrims to know four historical churches</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/associacao-catolica-leva-peregrinos-conhecer-quatro-igrejas-historicas/</link><description>The “Pilgrims of Hope” initiative of the Catholic Association has already started and takes place by the end of August. Participants will have the opportunity to visit four historic churches of Macao and meet sacred relics

Pedro Milheirão
The “Pilgrims of Hope: Pilgrimage of Macao's Pilgrims of Hope” of the Macao Catholic Association of Macao has begun and runs until August 31st. The script includes visits to four historical Catholic churches in Macao: the Church of the Seminary of St. Joseph, the Church of St. Lourenço, the Church of St. Anthony and the Cathedral Church. The pilgrims will have the opportunity to know the sacred relics of St. Francis Xavier, St. Lourenço, Saint André Kim, Santa Madalena de Canossa, St. Peter, Sao Paulo and Vera Cruz, among others.
In addition, during the event period, participants will be able to collect a “pilgrimage passport” in one of the four churches. In each place pilgrims will be able to collect an official seal and rescue, in the Dream Corner, a free copy of the book “Pilgrims of Hope: The Life of the Hundred Santos”, a recent publication of the association, after completing the set of stamps.
The book invites the public "to contemplate the courageous testimony of the saints to Christ and their unshakable hope in the midst of suffering" to strengthen and illuminate readers and make them "true pilgrims of hope."
In addition, the “passport” includes QR codes that refer to exclusive guide videos for each of the churches. Participants will be conducted on virtual visits narrated by a specialized guide who will present “rich stories and cultural traditions” of the Macao World Heritage Sites.
The videos, subtitled in Chinese and English, are based on the series “City of the Name of God of the Association”, funded by the Culture Development Fund. Since it was released, the video series has been having over 500,000 views and is “widely appreciated both locally and internationally,” according to the organization.
The Catholic religion arrived in Macao over 400 years ago, and has always been “an important meeting point for Chinese and Western cultures,” says the statement. MSAR has “many centuries of history and religious customs that are not only an important cultural heritage, but which have greatly contributed to local communities,” giving the Catholic Church into Macao “distinct characteristics”.
In line with new communication technologies, the organization has launched an online digital resource platform to “integrate the historical characteristics of Macao's Catholic culture into the modern culture of new media” and promote “the popularization and sharing of Catholic cultural resources”.
Created in July 2018, the Association aims to publicize the “rich Catholic historical culture” with “two thousand years of tradition”. Moreover, it supports the preservation of Catholic architecture and cultural relics that characterize the Church, as well as its "precious history."
The organization also edits and publishes materials and also organizes various activities of Catholic cultural promotion, with local and international organizations, to establish “friendly cultural exchanges with the community and other religious groups”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump locks new attacks from Israel against Iran</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/trump-trava-novos-ataques-de-israel-contra-irao/</link><description>EPA12194389 US President Donald Trump Speaks to the Media As He Departs The White House for the Nato Leaders Summit, In Washington, DC, USA, 24 June 2025. The President Answed Questions About Accusions of Ceasefire Violations in the Iran-Israel Conflict.  EPA/JIM LO SCALZO



Israel “refrained” yesterday to make new attacks against Iran after Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu had a telephone conversation with US President Donald Trump. According to Netanyahu's office, the beginning of Trump's ceasefire had been defined at 7:00 am (16:00 in Macau), and at 03:00 Israel still attacked Terraão targets and, at 07:06, Iran launched a missile against Israeli territory.
Quoting an employee of the White House, the Associated Press agency indicated that Trump spoke to Netanyahu from the “Air Force One”, on the way to Nato's Summit in The Hague, and “had no half words”. It was "exceptionally firm and direct" with the Israeli Prime Minister about "what it was necessary to do to support the ceasefire," he added.
Shortly before, the US leader was disillusioned with Israel for “launching bombs shortly after the ceasefire agreement” sealed with Tehran and the Israeli government. "We need Israel to calm down because they left on mission this morning. They need to calm down now!" He exclaimed in the White House gardens as he prepared to board the "Air Force One."
"They [Iranians] raped [the ceasefire], but Israel also violated," he told reporters. "I am not satisfied with Israel," he stressed, while a message from his on social networks required Telavive to make his riders return to the house: "Israel. Do not launch these bombs. If they do, it is a serious violation. Bring your pilots home."
"Basically, we have two countries that fight so much and so hard that they no longer know what they are doing," Trump said, regretting that Israel has released "many bombs" because "he felt violated by a rocket that has reached nowhere."
On board the presidential plane, he guaranteed, contrary to what he said in the weekend, that he does not want to see a "change of regime" in the middle of the conflict with Israel. "A change of regime leads to chaos, and ideally that we don't want to see so much chaos," he said.
On Monday night (yesterday in Macao), Trump had surprised the world by announcing that Israel and will agree to a total ceasefire to be implemented within 24 hours. "Congratulations to all! It was fully agreed between Israel and the Iran that there will be a complete and total ceasefire," said on the social network "Truth".
Trump's publication was made at a time when Iranian news agencies reported powerful explosions in downtown Tehran, which followed an Israeli warning of imminent bombing, and while Iran launched an alert for Ramat Gan evacuation, around Telavive, threatening to attack. "Starting from the principle that everything will work as it should be, what will work, I would like to congratulate both countries, Israel and will have the resistance, courage and intelligence to end what should be called 'The 12 -day war'," he said.
Iran retaliated by the “midnight hammer operation”, US bombardment at the weekend to its uranium enrichment facilities and nuclear fuel production in Isfahan, Natanz and Ford. Iranian news agency Irna, quoting a revolutionary guard statement, said Iran has reached an American base in Qatar with the "same number of bombs the US has used to attack Iranian nuclear facilities."
The target, Al udeid, is the largest US base of the Middle East, located on the outskirts of Doha and housing about 10,000 soldiers, which had previously been removed.
The Pentagon stated that there was no registration of American casualties in the Iranian attack on the air base. Trump thanked Iran for "warning in advance" of the "very weak" attack that he did to Al Udeid. According to the US president, they were fired at the base at Qatar 14 missiles, of which 13 were slaughtered and one followed in a "non-threatening direction."
The Israeli government was the first to officially accept Trump's ceasefire and said it had “eliminated an immediate existential double threat: nuclear and ballistic” by Teerão. "Israel will react hard against any ceasefire violation," added the text published after Trump's announcement.
Although Iran has not officially confirmed the ceasefire, the country's National Security Council released a statement in which he cites "a victory that forced the enemy to regret, accept defeat and unilaterally cease his aggression." But he also pointed out that the country "remains on alert, with fingers in the trigger, ready for a decisive response that will cause the regret of those who start an aggression."
 
Beijing insists on the “peaceful dialogue”
The Chinese government said yesterday that “the facts show that the military way does not bring peace to the Middle East, after US President Donald Trump announced a ceasefire and requesting the parties to respect him. Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakun has transmitted his hope that “peace will be reached as soon as possible” and stated that "the peaceful dialogue is the right way to solve problems." "We exhort the parties involved to resume the right way to a political solution as soon as possible," added the spokesman, ensuring that China "is willing to collaborate with the international community to make efforts to maintain peace and stability in the Middle East" and "doesn't want tensions to intensify."
 
Asian bags closed on the rise
The main Asian scholarships ended yesterday, stimulated by the ceasefire agreement between Israel and the Iran announced by US President Donald Trump. In mainland China, the Shanghai and Shenzhen bags rose 1.15%and 1.68%, respectively, while the Hang Seng Kong Index registered gains of 2.06%. The Seoul Stock Exchange reference index, Kospi, rose 2.96% and exceeded the 3,100 points barrier for the first time in three years and nine months, after reducing concerns with the potential impact of conflict on the Middle East on the country's economy, which is particularly dependent on the region's oil imports. In Japan, the main index of the Tokyo Stock Exchange, Nikkei, which brings together the 225 most representative actions on the market, advanced 1.14%. In Southeast Asia, Thailand led the gains, with the set up 3.5%, while the Singapore and Indonesia bags rose 0.65%and 1.21%, respectively.
 
JTM with Lusa and International Agencies</description><pubDate>2025-06-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing wants justice of mashes with “national vision” and “conjuncture”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pequim-quer-justica-da-raem-visao-nacional-conjuntural/</link><description>A delegation of the MSAR courts, headed by Song Man Lei, was in Beijing. High leaders said they hoped "the judges of the Mand will possess a" national vision "and a" conjunctural vision "and" understand deeply and implement the spirit of the important discourse given by President XI Jinping. " The president of Tui assured that the spirit of the Chinese leader's speech will be implemented
 
The president of the Last Instance Court (TUI), Song Man Lei, headed a delegation visiting Beijing and Liaon to “deepen exchange and cooperation in the judiciary”. High leaders of the Popular Republic of China "fully recognized the developed efforts and the role played by the Fasome Courts in the full and correct implementation of the" country, two systems "principle, in the safeguarding of the constitutional order of the Macao and Basic Law", as well as in the maintenance of social and stable social development of Macao.
Among the senior leaders were the Director of the Cabinet for Hong Kong and Macao of the Council of State, Xia Baolong; the director of the Macao Basic Law Commission of the Permanent Committee of the National Popular Assembly, Shen Chunyao; and the president of the Supreme Popular Court, Zhang Jun. Also the permanent vice-prosecutor of the Supreman Popular Attorney, Tong Jianming, and the Minister of Justice, He Rong, were in the meetings with the delegation of MSAR.
They said, they expect "the judges of the Mand to have a" national vision "and a" conjunctural vision "and" to understand deeply and implement the spirit of the important discourse given by President XI Jinping. " They should also safeguard the sovereignty, security and interests of the country's development, according to a statement from the TUI president's office, as well as “firmly” to “firm” the judicial function and improve the judicial system.
Representatives of the various organs in Beijing also requested that the judges of the MSAR “contribute to the promotion of the proper diversification of the economy of Macao and its integration in the conjuncture of national development, as well as enjoy the advantages of Macao in exchange and cooperation with the abroad”. The idea is that they can write "a new chapter in the successful implementation of the principle" a country, two systems "with characteristics of Macao."
Song Man Law, in turn, thanked China's interior bodies for the “great support provided to the courts of Masters over the years” and spoke about the situation of exchange and judicial cooperation between the courts of Masters and those of the continent, as well as about labor priorities.
He also ensured that "the courts of Macau will deeply understand and implement the spirit of President XI Jinping's important discourse," as well as "firmly defending sovereignty, safety and interests of the country's development, fully safeguarding the order of the rule of law and the legitimate rights and interests of masters residents."
For the future, Song Man Lei said it will continue to “deepen exchange and cooperation between the mashed courts and the judicial organs of the interior of China, as part of the formation of personnel and judicial cooperation”. He also argued that MSAR courts should “seek alternatives and innovations, learning from the continent's experiences”, “especially with regard to the successes obtained in the diversified resolution of disputes and computerization”, in order to “further increase judicial efficiency”.
The delegation of the MSAR included, among others, José Dias Alado, Judge of Tui; Tong Hio Fong, President of the Court of Second Instance; and Io Weng San, president of the lower court courts. During their stay in Beijing, they also visited the second traveling court of the Supreme Popular Court, the Beijing Court of Finance, the first historic archive of China and the Exhibition Museum on the History of the Communist Party of China.</description><pubDate>2025-06-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Boss points to the “new stage” in cooperation with Cantão</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-aponta-nova-etapa-na-cooperacao-cantao/</link><description>Canton was the last stop of a three -day visit from the Chief Executive to six cities of the Great Bay. In the capital of Guangdong Province, Sam Hou Fai exchanged ideas with local authorities on the continuous improvement of the cooperation mechanism, the deepening of exchange in various areas and the organization of national games
 
The chief executive closed a tour of six cities in the Great Bay in Canton, with cooperation and exchange the common denominators of conversations with local authorities.
During a meeting he maintained with the member of the Guangdong Provincial Committee of the Communist Party of China (CCP) and secretary of the Cantão Municipal Committee, Guo Yonghang, Sam Hou Fai addressed the continuous improvement of the cooperation mechanism, the deepening of exchange in various areas and the joint commitment to the organization of national games, among other topics.
Considering that Canton “has achieved success in its development in various areas”, the leader of the MSAR said that, in recent years, the cooperation mechanism between the two cities has worked “effectively”, reaching new “pragmatized advances in various branches”, which remain “constantly deepened”.
On the other hand, it has been hoping that Canton continues to support the governing action of MSAR and, along with the consolidation of the existing good cooperation base, allows further collaboration in all aspects, such as technology, economy and commerce, culture, tourism, education, among others, “in order to propel bilateral cooperation in turn to a new stage”.
Taking advantage of the opportunity for Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau co-organize the 15th edition of the National Games and National Games for people with disabilities, Sam Hou Fai stressed that the two cities can make joint efforts to collaborate more in the area of ​​sport, “injecting a new dynamic in diversified cooperation”. According to a note from the Social Communication Office, the ruler stressed that all parties involved in the competition should be devoted to the preparation work to achieve organizational success, serving as a reference to test tests, in order to perform a “spectacular” sports event, which “reflects the advantages of the system, demonstrate the characteristics of the great bay and show the Lingnam style”.
Before the meeting, the Macao entourage, which included the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin Yip, visited an urban air transport technology company and the “Guangzhou Metro Group”, to find out about the development of that city's transport technologies.
Under the stage of the Great Bay, the Chief Executive was also in Dongguan, having debated with the Secretary of the Municipal Committee of the CCP, Wei Hao, aspects of cooperation in technological innovation, humanities and education, among others. He expressed that the MSAR intends to deepen cooperation with Dongguan under “the good base already existing”, noting that the two cities have maintained close connection in domains such as economics, education, humanities, science and technology.
He made votes that in the future, both focus on promoting cooperation in the field of science and technology, widening the space of existing cooperation and taking full advantage of the complementarity of the advantages for the proper diversification of the Macao economy. ”
The Chief Executive also visited two scientific and technological innovation projects in Dongguan.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-06-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM Colloquium addressed Sino-Lusophone Education</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/coloquio-da-upm-abordou-educacao-sino-lusofona/</link><description>The Polytechnic University of Macau organized the lecture “Conversations with Sino-Lirophones personalities”, in which Professor Carlos Ascenso André as the main speaker participated. The teacher highlighted “the great potential of Macau as an exchange platform”
 
The Faculty of Languages ​​and Translation and the Pedagogical and Scientific Center of the Portuguese Language of the Macao Polytechnic University (UPM) co-organized the 5th lecture of “Conversations with Sino-Madphones Personalities”, under the theme “University and Culture in Multicultural Context: China and Lusophony, but not only”. The Colloquium addressed “The Interactions and References between China and Portugal” and provided “new ideas” to the promotion of Sino-Lusophone academic cooperation, according to a statement.
UPM Honorary Professor Carlos Ascenso André was invited as the main speaker to talk about the “importance of exchange and integration” between civilizations to “the development of higher education from a global perspective”. Using several examples, also president of the Scientific Council of the Lisbon Academy of Sciences presented “the unique values ​​and practical paths of mutual learning between China and Portuguese -speaking countries (PLP)”. The teacher also analyzed "the cultural similarities between China and PLP" as well as "the great potential of Macau as a multicultural exchange platform."
Several teachers and students participated in the event, discussing with the guest on topics such as “mutual learning of cultures and language teaching”. According to the UPM, "the cozy academic environment" contributed to extend the international view of students and teachers of the university, as well as deepen the "understanding of Chinese and Portuguese cultures".
With this event, UPM intended to “promote deep integration between culture and sino-illusopone education”, supporting the construction of the “Sino-Misophone Platform” and the “Bilingual Qualified Staff Training Base in Chinese and Portuguese” at the MSAR. The lectures “Conversations with Sino-Lusophone Personalities” aim to invite renowned experts and academics to share “avant-garde knowledge”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Signed agreement with RPC on inert materials</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/assinado-acordo-rpc-sobre-materiais-inertes/</link><description>The authorities of Macao and the interior of China signed an agreement for the interregional treatment of inert materials resulting from the demolitions and construction of Macau projects
 
The Government of MSA has signed, with the Ministry of Ecology and Environment of the Popular Republic of China, a “Cooperation Agreement for the management work of inert materials resulting from Macao demolitions and constructions in the areas of the interior of China”.
It was thus established “a long -term efficient mechanism for the disposition of inert materials resulting from masters of demolitions and constructions” in the maritime areas of the interior of China, in accordance with national standards. Memorandum will allow “to ensure the continuous advance of large infrastructure projects related to the life of the population of Macao”, can be read in a press release.
The agreement “will be the first success case in the interregional treatment of inert materials resulting from macao demolitions and constructions”, contributing to “relieving pressure” in landfill for construction materials waste.
In a statement, the Secretary's Office for Transport and Public Works recalled that the construction works of the East Line of the Light Metro are underway and that a tunnel drilling machine will be used to dig the soil below the sea surface and the underground at a depth of about 20 to 40 meters or more.
"Considering that soils to excavate with this type of perforator come from the depths of the subsoil and have a relatively simple composition, and considering that the only landfill for construction materials in Macau is already saturated, the problem of the destination to give to soils arises," he says.
Secretary Raymond Tam's office even says that "if this problem is not resolved as soon as possible, it will have a serious impact on the progress of the main subsistence infrastructure projects in Macao."</description><pubDate>2025-06-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Uniform Nursing Career Uniform Regime</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/afastado-regime-uniformizado-da-carreira-de-enfermagem/</link><description>The director of health services dismissed the uniformity of the nursing career, arguing that "it must be the institution itself to define its regime of personnel, remuneration and perks." Alvis Lo also said that the Nursing Specialties Commission will, “in timely time”, review the internship regime, currently six months
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The government has removed nursing career standardization - a measure requested by Wong Kit Cheng, which argues that it would optimize career progression and professional development; In addition, the deputy also suggested the definition of salary indices or at least the reduction of differences in terms of remuneration. The Director of Health Services (SSM), Alvis Lo, in turn, considers that "it must be the institution itself to define its regime of personnel, remuneration and perks."
It justified the position with factors such as the recipients of the services provided by medical institutions and social work institutions, the content of the work and the degree of risk of nursing care. "With regard to nurses from the private sector, the Government of MSAR is supporting private medical institutions through three ways, including financing and acquisition of services, which can indirectly create more employment opportunities for health professionals," added Alvis Lo.
With regard to nurses' remuneration and perks, the promotion mechanism and compensation in the civil service are regulated by the nursing career regime.
On the other hand, the SSM director stated that the government “has reinforced nursing formation and the development of specialties”, in order for nurses to “constantly raise” the professional level. In addition, he recalled that the legislative production of the legal regime for the exercise of activity of private institutions providing health care is underway, and private medical institutions may develop the new model of “home nursing care”.
Wong Kit Cheng had also questioned the executive about if he would exempt the six -month stage to nurses. In this context, Alvis Lo stresses that the objective of the internship requirements provided for by law is to “provide interns opportunities for clinical practice and deepen knowledge about the present situation of the Macao health system”, thus being able to prepare for the beginning of career. Still, it indicates that the Nursing Specialties Commission (EEC) “will globally consider the course of the course and the internship, reviewing, in due time, the current internship regime”.
It is also said that since the creation of the EEC in 2022, two specialized nursing formations have been held in the territory, with a total of 32 graduates. Next September a new formation will begin. "In the future, this training will be organized progressively in order to raise the specialized knowledge of nursing staff," added Alvis Lo.
 
Perks for the social service team
Recalling that in 2024 the Institute of Social Action (IAS) proceeded to an increase of 3% for financial support to grant subsidized social equipment workers, alvis lo, ensures that the body has been “encouraging” social equipment to “properly increase personnel 'perks, with a view to consolidating the social service team. Alongside this is also containing subsidies for the double maturity of the year and for the non-compulsory central pension regime. For the director of the SSM, all “is able to effectively ensure perks and ensure protection in the reform of subsidized social work workers”.
According to until April this year, health professionals from the standardized social equipment subsidized by IAS performed a total of 228, of which about 65.5% are nurses. In addition, the total number of several categories of health professionals increased by 4.5% compared to the same period last year.</description><pubDate>2025-06-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Continent students show paintings in Ká-Hó</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/estudantes-continente-mostram-pinturas-em-ka-ho/</link><description>The Hold on To Hope project will receive, for the first time, an exhibition of students from students from universities on the continent seeking to expose their works in Macau. On July 6, a show of oil paintings from six students attending the master's degree from the Faculty of Fine Arts of Huaqiao will be inaugurated

Victor Rebelo
 
An oil painting exhibition of six students from the Faculty of Fine Arts of the University of Huaqiao, Fujian Province, will be inaugurated on July 6, at 4 pm at the “Hold on To Hop” Gallery (H2H), from the Macao Toxicode Rehabilitation Association (ArtM).
This is the first exhibition of the genre, integrating students from the continent, in what “may be the beginning of a greater connection to this University and others from the continent, for the dissemination of artistic work,” according to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau Andreia Bento.
The H2H project coordinator stated that the initiative belonged to the Faculty of the Interior of China. "Students of Fine Arts look for places where they can expose their work and have contacted us, so this will be the first exhibition dedicated to students of Chinese universities that our association will lead to."
“Chasing Dreams Under The Stars” features more than 30 paintings performed by master students, including John U, Fong Hio Wa, Rosa, Madonna and Ho Cheng Wa. “Through their individual experiences and perspectives, artists express their thoughts and feelings about the world around them through art,” says the synopsis of the event, which will publicize a diversity of styles and themes.
The exhibition “reflects varied creative techniques and inspirations, telling stories of hope, dreams and the pursuit of passion through works”, underlines the “Hold on to Hope”, hoping that the audience “is captivated by the colors and techniques of each painting”.
The organizers of the show consider that "Chasing Dreams Under the Stars" is "more than an art exhibition", which is a "celebration of creativity and power of self-expression", allowing "art and emotions to meet and transform dreams into reality."
The exhibition of the works of the students of the Faculty of Huaqiao will be evident in the gallery located in the village of Nossa Senhora in Ká-Hó until July 27.
The University of Huaqiao, which has two campuses, one in Xiamen and one in Quanzhou, is directly dependent on the Chinese Chinese Affairs Office of the China State Council and is considered to be the National Base for Teaching Chinese Language and Culture, hosting a wide number of foreign students, but also from Macau, Hong Kong and Taiwan. It has over 35,000 students and full -time graduates, including about 9,000 students from over 100 countries and regions.
Hold on to Hope has already programmed other exhibitions with the same higher education establishment as the continent.</description><pubDate>2025-06-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“The Universe in millimeters” by Chan Hin Chi in 245 drawings</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/o-universo-em-milimetros-de-chan-hin-chi-em-245-desenhos/</link><description>A total of 245 Chan Hin Chi Drawings will be exhibited at the Rui Cunha Foundation until July 5, under the individual show “The Universe in millimeters”



















A exposição “O Universo em Milímetros”, de Chan Hin Chi, que foi ontem inaugurada na Fundação Rui Cunha, vai ficar patente ao público até 5 de Julho. Reunindo trabalhos do artista inspirados nas paisagens e lugares visitados e eternizados entre 2017 e 2025, a mostra individual exibe “uma imensa colecção” de 245 peças, com 56 desenhos de tamanho médio e 189 pequenos esboços nas dimensões de um postal de viagem.
"The works result from the visual and affective impressions of Chan Hin Chi through the places where he has spent in recent years, such as messages drawn and sent to posterity," the foundation says in a statement. Although most represent images of streets, buildings, corners, details and memories of the old and modern Macao, the works also reveal seen from other cities in China -Chengdu, Foshan, Doumen, Harbin and Beijing -, Taiwan, Japan, Germany, Switzerland, France, Spain and Portugal.
Chan Hin Chi style “outlines a three -dimensional visual world, in a paper design that does not exceed the size of a postcard, where you see the big one from the small,” says the preface to the exhibition, adding: “In this limited space, intertwine lines and colors to create an infinite and fascinating visual world”.
Chan Hin Chi is "born in a foreign country, moved with his family to Macau when he was small in order to fix residence in the 1960s of the previous century." He is a jurist and dominates the Portuguese and English (Mandarin and Cantonese) languages, while dedicating himself to the study of Luso-Chinese languages ​​and cultures, as well as legal research and teaching.
According to the biographical note, Chan Hin Chi loves the practice of drawing as an amateur artist, and has been interested from childhood by the pen ink. “Over the course of time, it was improving its art with the delicacy and patience necessary for its formation in the studies of law and linguistics,” can be read.
For the author, “to draw is to have subjective confidence to sketch the world or represent a specific scenario,” which depends on many uncontrollable external factors. Therefore, "each drawing is a self-decline" in search of balance, and "every challenge can be a meditation on life." Chan Hin Chi argues that "the practice of drawing and law activities are, respectively, emotional and rational, but inclusive and combinable."</description><pubDate>2025-06-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM company operates project with revenues of one million</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/empresa-da-upm-opera-projecto-receitas-de-um-milhao/</link><description>Created on November 13, 2024, the technological innovation of the Macao Polytechnic University (UPM) Limited Unipessoal Society, a 100% detained public capital company, is operating a new project to provide scientific consulting and research services to Government Bodies of MSAR, within 24 months. According to the company's report for 2024, this project allows to generate total revenues of over one million patacas. In addition, UPM's technological innovation signed, by the end of 2024, a scientific research cooperation project, which should be able to generate revenues of 640,000 patacas this year, the report points out. As the company was in the initial phase of operations, the expenses were mainly used to cover the expenses necessary for the establishment of the company and the initial operations, the document says. Assuming has found challenges in the early stages, the company ensures that this year will, based on UPM academic resources and power of innovation, to achieve technology -oriented social and economic benefits, thus injecting a new driving force to the diversification of Macao's economy.</description><pubDate>2025-06-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brad Pitt, Javier Bardem, Lewis Hamilton… When F1 and Cinema met</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/brad-pitt-javier-bardem-lewis-hamilton-quando-f1-cinema-se-encontraram/</link><description>"I really felt that F1 and the cinema have met," said Lewis Hamilton, wrapped in front and behind the Camaras in Joseph Kosinski's new movie, with star Brad Pitt as a retired rider who returns to the tracks and Javier Bardem as the owner of a team.
Following the huge success of Netflix's documentary series “Drive to Survive”, Formula 1, which seeks to expand its audience, especially in the United States, completely opened the doors to Hollywood to a movie that plunges the viewer in the world of the maximum motorsport category with ultra-realistic images.
“F1” tells the story of a fictional team, APX GP, in serious difficulties in the World Championship and whose owner, played by Bardem, uses Pitt, who plays Sonny Hayes, an former F1 prodigy whose advance was interrupted 30 years earlier by a serious accident that almost cost her life.
Since his arrival at the team, Hayes must face the distrust of his young teammate, Joshua Pearce, played by British actor Damson Idriss.
Rivalry will quickly reach its peak, but gradually Hayes takes a mentor role for his boxer and helps him score points, playing with the regulation, but without breaking it, as the real F1 teams would do.
Kosinski, director of the blockbuster “Top Gun: Maverick”, who raised impressive $ 1.5,000 in 2022, dedicated four years to achieve the ambitious project, convincing F1 to join this adventure.
With Superrestrela Brad Pitt and Jerry Bruckheimer, one of the most recognized American producers, the project has also been involved since the seven times world champion Hamilton (Ferrari).
A big fan of cinema, the Briton is also producer of the feature film through Dawn Apollo Films, a producer he founded in 2022, in collaboration with Apple TV+, which also joined the project.
"We needed Lewis for the technical aspects and to ensure that we were faithful to reality. For a scene in Budapest, it was he who told us that such an event could only occur in such a curve, or that at that point the car should be in the first march and not on Monday," explained Bruckheimer.
Stefano Domenicali, the F1 CEO, quickly saw the business opportunity and considered it was an opportunity to make Formula 1 even more popular, especially in the United States, where “Drive to Survive” has exponentially increased interest in the category.
The United States currently receive three major awards from the F1 season (Austin, Miami and Las Vegas). Before the Netflix series, it had only one.
The F1 authorized the feature film team to shoot for 10 races around the world from Silverstone (United Kingdom) to Suzuka (Japan), through Budapest and Abu Dhabi. APX GP's white and gold cars, F2 vehicles - the second category - disguised as F1, rolled in these circuits during Formula 1 free training sessions.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-06-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>