<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Air connection between Lisbon and Macau will be “difficult” under the current management of TAP</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ligacao-aerea-entre-lisboa-macau-sera-dificil-na-actual-gestao-da-tap/</link><description>The possible launch of flights between Lisbon and Macau was discussed by the Portuguese Government's Secretary of State for Infrastructure in an interview with the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper. Hugo Espírito Santo says it is “difficult” for this to materialize in the current management scenario at TAP. However, privatization “could help TAP to grow and evaluate the possibility of this route, if it proves to be economically profitable”. On the other hand, the Secretary of State for Tourism recalled that “Beijing Capital Airlines” operates flights between Lisbon and Hangzhou
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
“TAP does not currently have an aircraft that can fly directly to Macau (…) Therefore, it is clearly impossible to make a direct flight from Lisbon to Macau, at least through TAP”, said the Secretary of State for Infrastructure of Portugal, in an interview with the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU.
Hugo Espírito Santo highlighted, however, that if there is another company interested, “and so we manage to resolve the issue of slots, this could be a possibility”. In this sense, the project “could continue to be considered, in the long term, and even together with the private shareholder who will begin to participate increasingly in the management” of TAP.
According to the official, who came to Macau to participate in the Congress of the Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies, the Government's idea is that “the future private investor has the capacity to influence management”, and “from then on he will also be able to help TAP grow and evaluate the possibility of this route, if it proves to be economically profitable”.
Asked about the need for this air connection, the holder of the Infrastructure portfolio recognizes that there is a large Portuguese community in Macau and that Portugal attracts many Asian tourists. “We have a lot of ‘sex appeal’ from a tourism point of view for Asians, but we are still admittedly ‘scratching the surface’, as the English used to say”, he highlights.
Taking into account that there are “many indirect alternatives”, Hugo Espírito Santo insists that it is “difficult” to create a direct alternative. “The truth is that leaving this Delta region, there are many airports with connections to several international hubs, which is why “it becomes complicated to create and create this alternative from an economic point of view”, he asserts.
In fact, he adds, “it was the same reason why the route that TAP operated was also deeply necessary”. Therefore, “it is not worth anticipating, especially because the realities in the aviation sector change very quickly”, he pointed out, maintaining that “it is obvious that TAP has to continue looking at this market, but it will in fact depend on who its next shareholder is and its priorities”.
In turn, the Secretary of State for Tourism, Commerce and Services, Pedro Machado, recalled, in the opening speech of the event, that “Beijing Capital Airlines” currently connects the cities of Lisbon and Hangzhou, with two weekly flights, to which, soon, “possibly in December”, a third direct flight may be added on Tuesdays”.
“Just the day before yesterday, in a more or less informal discussion with the Secretary of State for Infrastructure and the Consul General of Portugal, we discussed the possibility of, in the not too distant future, being able to evaluate new and desirable connections”, he said.
Regarding other issues that are part of the program, some of which concern the importance of Macau as a platform for developing tourism in this region, Hugo Espírito Santo highlighted that Portugal must look “very carefully” at its relations with Asia, considering that the continent is currently “by far” the fastest growing.
“Portugal must also recognize this fundamental role, where we had a historical pioneering role in the past and, therefore, bring closer and continue to work on these relations between Portugal and Asia, including Macau and China”, he stressed.
Asked to explain what unites infrastructure and tourism, the Portuguese government official indicated that “we [infrastructure sector] are a bit the annoying uncle of tourism, because, in truth, tourism is glamorous, immediate, fast, easy to adjust”. On the other hand, “we are a bit like Chinese culture, ancient, which takes time”.
From his perspective, what is being done in Portugal, namely the new airport, the new crossing over the Tagus, the high-speed network, the high-speed fuel network, the investments in the road network, is “perfectly symbiotic” so that “tourism has room to continue growing and that it is what the country's own development is, from an economic and social point of view, so that a balance is guaranteed between the development of the needs of the Portuguese population, with the needs of tourism”.
As for TAP, the Government decided to start the privatization process. According to Hugo Espírito Santo, the first phase of the privatization process points to 49.9%, “of which up to 5% can be attributed to workers, if they so wish”. From there, the remainder will be sold to a single entity, which must be an airline, or an entity that has an airline, with more than five billion in revenue.
Three companies presented expressions of interest.
 
Portugal, Macau and China in a “virtuous triangle”
For his part, the Secretary of State for Tourism, Commerce and Services told this newspaper that his presence at the congress “means the deepening of a historical relationship with Macau, of what it represents for Portugal and which we want to maintain, strengthening ties and commercial exchanges”.
Speaking of “symbiosis”, he highlights that there is a virtuous triangle” between heritage, history, the bilateral relationship between Portugal, China and, in particular, Macau”. Furthermore, he reinforces, a symbiosis “between the capacity we have today to want to implement and attract tourist flows, with China, in particular, being our main Asian market”.
Macau as a platform for the development of Portuguese tourism in Asia, “assumes an important role” due to what it represents in the “strategic and geographic georeferencing” in which it is located, with its proximity to Hong Kong and other cities, says Pedro Machado. “This, in essence, makes possible a broader, more open market, of several tens of millions of potential consumers, of potential tourists to Portugal”, he observes, also highlighting the relationships with culture. “We know that there is a very strong cultural and social history here, which we want, deep down, to intensify”, he emphasizes.
Pedro Machado says he feels that “there are more and more Portuguese people who also want to rediscover the territory, and from Macau, especially because there is an affinity with the language, the architecture, the surroundings, and I would say almost this ecosystem that exists in Macau, which is very much ours, which has a lot to do with what normally exists in Portugal, and nowhere else in the world, which we call saudade, and this is very present in this connection”.
Without coming to Macau for eight years, the Secretary of State uses the adjective “impactful” to highlight, “on the one hand, the development and growth it has had, but, on the other, associated with this, almost the size, the monumentality created around this space, in a territory that we know is small, but which, in fact, has an experience and a dynamic that is remarkable”.
Portugal's commitment to relations with Portuguese-speaking countries also deserves mention. “Three, four weeks ago, our country opened in Cabinda, Angola, the first hotel and hospitality school outside of Portugal, which means a strong investment in the relationship, in cooperation with Portuguese-speaking countries, but materialized”, he guarantees.
Pedro Machado also spoke about the consequences for the tourism sector of the existence of political and diplomatic tensions, wars and other constraints. “Tourism is, essentially, from people to people”, he points out, adding that “factors such as security, health, connectivity, mobility are absolutely critical for the ability of countries and markets to cross paths”. Therefore, “it means that, today, this insecurity and unpredictability is an aspect that mitigates and conditions tourist flows”.
In conclusion, it augurs a bright future for the tourism sector, predicting that Portugal could enter the ranking of the 10 most competitive countries in the world, finding itself in 12th place, ahead of Switzerland and Canada.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Portugal is one of the priority markets for Macau”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/portugal-e-um-dos-mercados-prioritarios-para-macau/</link><description>Helena de Senna Fernandes stressed yesterday that, within the scope of the diversified development of the economy and with regard to the focus on “tourism+”, “Portugal is one of the priority markets for Macau”. At the opening of the 50th APAVT Congress, which has a record number of participants, Pedro Costa Ferreira spoke of an “exciting reunion” with the “common history” of Portugal and Macau, which will allow us to look at the “challenges of the future”. The Secretary of State for Tourism, Pedro Machado, highlighted the good relations between Portugal and China
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The 50th National Congress of the Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies (APAVT) kicked off yesterday in Macau, attended by more than a thousand professionals from the sector, a record number, according to the president of the association, Pedro Costa Ferreira. At the opening ceremony, the director of Tourism Services (DST), Helena de Senna Fernandes, highlighted that it is an “honor” for the territory to have been chosen to host this forum, in the year in which the association celebrates 75 years, and stated that the Portuguese market is one of the priorities for the Macao SAR.
“Hosting, for the sixth time in four decades, the APAVT Congress, reinforces good relations between Macau-China and Portugal, and boosts joint work in tourism – a central industry for our economies”, stated Helena de Senna Fernandes, adding that the event also serves to “show delegates Macau’s potential for the Portuguese tourist industry to open new horizons in the East”.
Senna Fernandes said that, within the scope of development as a global center for tourism and leisure, Macao SAR is committed to diversifying the economy, through the “1+4” strategy. "This new direction that we are following implies a strong commitment to deepening the intersectoral integration of 'tourism +' in other sectors to diversify the range of iconic offers and attract international visitors of different profiles. Portugal is one of the priority markets for Macau, and we want to continue working with partners like APAVT to boost tourist flows in the various segments", he stressed.
“To expand our tourism cooperation we also have the added value of being able to take advantage of Macau’s role as a ‘platform’ to connect Chinese and Portuguese tour operators, as will happen at this congress, in the China-Portugal session”, continued the director of DST, also remembering that Portuguese travelers benefit from visa exemption in Mainland China. From his perspective, Macau can also enhance “Portugal's good relations” with Spain, Europe and Portuguese-speaking countries to continue creating synergies in terms of the flow of visitors and hosting of events.
The director of DST also pointed out that, with the “strong support” of the Central Government, Macau has been developing “with its unique profile and advantages”, also functioning as a “precision interlocutor” between China and abroad, “where tourism and the relationship with the Portuguese-speaking world occupy a leading place”.
“Assuming a position as ‘one center, one platform’, that is, as a global tourism and leisure center, and as a service platform for economic and commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, Macau has equipped itself with infrastructures and policies that create a new framework for relations with the Portuguese tourism industry to continue to evolve in this new era”, he argued.
 
Reunion with “common history”
In turn, Pedro Costa Ferreira described Macau as “vibrant” and “safe”, a place “where East and West have always met, a showcase of a brave new world, a fantastic example of a culture of service and respect for the consumer, a solid model of economic development, a gateway to the largest issuing market in the world”.
He then recalled the last congress held in the Macao SAR, in 2017. "Shortly afterwards, we were plunged into the worst crisis in our history, a pandemic that affected us all equally, and equally violently. Today, in front of around a thousand people, it is difficult to believe how it was possible for us to rise again with this strength and vitality, as well as it is difficult to internalize the extent of the fantastic work we have done in recent years", he considered.
“Today, in this congress, we involve the entire Portuguese tourism sector, in an exciting reunion with our common history, looking at the challenges of the future”, he continued, adding that APAVT’s desire is that this congress “represents, much more than an end of cycle, a bridge towards a renewed ambition to do more, better and closer”.
Pedro Costa Ferreira also criticized the evolution of tourist taxes in Portugal, accusing them of being “an attack by weak politicians on strong markets”. "A brief but important note about the shameful evolution of tourist taxes in Portugal. Shameful, above all, due to the scam. They are not taxes because they do not have any service as a visible counterpart, they are not tourist taxes, because they are paid by those who are working in the country, increasing the contextual costs even further", he argued.
To Lusa, he explained that the strategy of approaching the world's main tourist source market, China, was one of the reasons for choosing Macau. Furthermore, “there has been work for years and years with Macau, which, when it goes well and becomes more intense from year to year, ends up naturally ‘asking’ for a congress to take place, as happened this year”, he stated.
In turn, the Secretary of State for Tourism, Commerce and Services, Pedro Machado, emphasized relations between Portugal and China, remembering, among other moments, the recent trip of the Prime Minister, Luís Montenegro, to China, where he was received by Xi Jinping, as well as his visit to the Macao SAR.
“China is the largest source of tourists from Asia to Portugal, it is probably one of the most relevant in terms of long haul and, probably, the one with the greatest potential for growth in the long term”, said Pedro Machado, adding that, according to statistical data until August, Portugal will be very close “to reaching the 2019 indicators: 390 thousand guests who generated more than 600 thousand overnight stays”.
The estimate is that tourist revenue could reach 200 million euros and that, as an export of services, “it will help to mitigate the chronic trade deficit we have with China”, he continued. Another important indicator in the relationship with China is air connectivity, as you also mentioned [see page 3].
The Secretary of State also mentioned “the work that was returned with regard to citizens holding a Portuguese passport no longer needing to issue a visa prior to their travel for stays of less than 30 days, which certainly contributed to greater dynamics”.
 
Tourism sector is experiencing sustainable growth
The president of the Portuguese Tourism Confederation admits that the sector is entering a phase of sustainable growth, after record years, with a 2025 more dependent on national tourists, but with foreigners creating more value. Francisco Calheiros, who was speaking at the opening of the 50th Congress of the Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies (APAVT), began by considering that we are experiencing “another positive tourist year” in Portugal. "If the first months already predicted it, the data already known from the summer confirms it. But let's not fool ourselves, we are entering a phase of sustainable growth. There is no stagnation, of course not, but there is greater stability. Something that was already anticipated, after very strong growth in the post-pandemic years", he stated. On the other hand, the president of APAVT considered that tourism is more competitive than the national economy. "Tourism, and tourist distribution, so attacked by the prevailing mediocrity, certainly constitute a zone of resistance to this entire situation. It has allowed growth, where everyone stagnates, it has given a chance to territorial cohesion, where everyone centralizes, it has made it possible to welcome immigrants, giving them training and decent conditions, when others defend them on the streets, to better house them in layers, as if they were human scum", explained Pedro Costa Ferreira to Lusa.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Metro extension to Coloane will be “relatively easy”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/extensao-metro-coloane-sera-relativamente-facil/</link><description>The Government intends to extend the Seac Pai Van Line to the town of Coloane, said the Secretary for Public Transport, promising that he will try to implement the plan as quickly as possible. Raymond Tam even considers the work to be “relatively easy”. The government official also gave details about the other lines proposed in a study on Light Rail development strategies and promised that a public consultation will be launched
 
Catarina Pereira
 
A study on the development strategies of the Light Rail “suggests the extension of the Seac Pai Van Line to the edge of the town of Coloane, that is, the Coloane market side”, revealed the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam. The government official believes that it is possible to carry out the extension of the Seac Pai Van Line in the short term, because, as he said, “the work will be relatively easy”.
“If it is possible to connect the Metro Line to the town of Coloane, it will be very beneficial for the residents of Coloane and for tourism in Macau”, he stressed, which is why he promised that he will try to implement this plan as quickly as possible. Raymond Tam was speaking to deputies as part of the presentation of the Lines of Government Action under his authority.
The Secretary also spoke about other lines that the study proposes. For example, the Taipa North Line, and in this case, the idea is that it starts from the ES6 station, in Zone E, passing through Zones D and C of the New Landfills, and also through the Oceano station on the Taipa Line.
The Southern Line will be able to connect the Macau border post at Ponte do Delta to the ES5 station in Zona A dos Novos Aterros, passing through NAPE, lot A9 in Nam Van, Sai Van and Barra. In turn, the study also suggests the West Line starting at Doca do Lam Mau and ending in Barra.
Raymond Tam mentioned that, in relation to the West Line, which will connect the Qingmao station to Barra, with passages through the Fai Chi Kei area and the Inner Port, the section between the Qingmao station and Fai Chi Kei is the one that can be completed sooner. In general, this project will be implemented in phases.
Since the section of the Inner Harbor will involve reorganization, it will be necessary to carry out landfill work, which means it is necessary to wait for approval from the Central Government to move forward with the plan, added the Secretary.
As for the Southern Line, “the conditions are relatively mature”, said Raymond Tam, explaining that the pillars for the metro station at the border post at Delta Bridge have already been built. He also revealed that the Southern Line could be underground to guarantee 24-hour operation.
Regarding the Taipa Line, the Secretary for Transport and Public Works said that during rush hours, sets of four carriages per trip can be used. However, as there are still no connections between the carriages, remodeling work is being carried out to make this connection, in order to increase transport capacity. He also assured that when new carriages are purchased, the issue of interconnection will be taken into consideration.
At the session, Raymond Tam also announced that he will restart studies on the construction of the 5th connection between the Peninsula and Taipa, through a tunnel that will connect the NAPE Zone to Zone D of the New Landfills. As he explained, the 5th connection will include lanes for car circulation and the Metro will run underneath, “which will connect to the Taipa North Line and reach the Jockey Club lot”. The Secretary also assured that a public consultation will be held on the study of development strategies for this means of transport.
 
Passengers on the Metro reach almost the level of 2019
In November, the Light Rail recorded a daily average of 32,600 passengers, according to statistics provided by the Metro Society. The number is the highest this year and is very close to the record recorded in 2019, when this means of transport was inaugurated and travel was free. At that time, there was a daily average of 33 thousand passengers. It should be noted that, throughout this year 2025, the volume of passengers on the Metro has been recording a growth trend since June.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Closing of Casino Fortuna affects 553 workers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/fecho-casino-fortuna-afecta-553-trabalhadores/</link><description>Next week, Casino Fortuna, part of SJM, will close its doors, with the gaming operator providing job guarantees for the 553 affected workers. Meanwhile, Kam Pek Paradise has already closed, with the DICJ indicating that the process went according to plan
 
Casino Fortuna is the next to close its doors, on December 9th, at 11:59 pm, SJM Resorts, S.A. announced yesterday, leaving guarantees in terms of employment for affected workers. The gaming operator has assured that all local employees employed by SJM will be transferred to the company's other casinos to perform gaming-related duties in accordance with operational needs.
As for residents who are not employed by SJM Resorts, they will be invited to apply for related vacancies within the group, “with priority in hiring under equal circumstances, and will receive the necessary support, depending on the actual situation, to facilitate a smooth transition”, can be read in the press release.
According to the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ), 553 Casino Fortuna workers are involved. The organization also says that it will maintain “close communication” with the Directorate of Labor Affairs Services, in order to ensure remuneration, benefits and working conditions, as well as employment opportunities.
In this sense, and to ensure that the process takes place in accordance with the proposal to close the satellite casino defined by SJM and presented to the Government, the DICJ will send personnel to supervise the closure of the space.
SJM also states that “all tables and gaming machines currently operating on site will be transferred to other company casinos”. Additionally, customers who have accumulated chips, deposits or cash rebates at Casino Fortuna that have not been redeemed after the closure can visit other casinos operated by SJM Resorts from December 10th to monitor the situation.
Eight of the 11 satellite casinos have already closed. The last to close its doors, on Monday, was Kam Pek Paradise, with almost 600 employees. In this context, the DICJ indicated that the closure of Kam Pek Paradise, also allocated to SJM, took place in accordance with the established procedures.
During the closure, DSAL sent staff to the site to provide clarification to the workers concerned, and they were provided with information about an open line for further consultation. The personnel of the Public Security Police Corps and the Judiciary Police have, in turn, preserved public order at the site and in the surrounding area.
In a statement, the DICJ indicates that it will continue to ensure the coordination established with concessionaires operating games of chance, and the competent services, promoting the healthy and orderly development of the gaming sector in Macau.
 
C.P.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>International Short Film Festival with record participation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/festival-internacional-de-curtas-recorde-de-participacoes/</link><description>This year's Macau International Short Film Festival has seen a record number of entries since its inception. Of the 6,361 films submitted, 122 short films were selected, of which more than a quarter were made by filmmakers from China. For the festival's president, Paulo Canelas de Castro, the participation rate is a demonstration of the event's “growing prestige”
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
This year, the 16th edition of the Macau International Short Film Festival received 6,361 films, a record number of submissions, Professor Paulo Canelas de Castro, president of the initiative, announced yesterday during a press conference at Teatro Capitol. For the professor, this “exceptional” number is indicative of the festival’s continued growth and the “attention it attracts from the majority of filmmakers, both in Macau and in Mainland China and the world in general”.
Of the projects submitted, the jury selected 122 short films, with “more than 25% of the films coming from Mainland China and Macau”. This edition had the participation of representatives from 123 countries and regions, “who delivered productions of their experiences, their films, their creativity, in the different categories of the festival”, noted the president.
Paulo Canelas de Castro considers this participation to be “testimony to the growing prestige of the event and the worldwide explosion of interest in the short film format”.
At the same time, "having sustained this event for 16 consecutive years is a testament to the enduring passion for films and culture that thrives within the community. It speaks volumes about Macau's unwavering commitment to the arts. This festival leverages its unique position, offering a platform where diverse cultural narratives converge and interact," he stressed.
For his part, João Francisco Pinto, TDM consultant and involved in the festival “for more than a decade”, stated that “there has been a notable improvement in the local film industry”. "Two years ago, many of the documentaries, for example, were basically produced by communication students, undergraduate or master's students. Obviously, they lacked a certain depth in the cinematography they presented", he noted.
However, "over the years, the quality has improved a lot. And not just in documentary terms, but also in fiction. The quality, the ability to tell stories, video editing, cinematographic competence has grown tremendously", he highlighted.
João Francisco Pinto stressed that “Macau is moving in the right direction in terms of cinema”. "We now have a considerable number of filmmakers. Many of them studied abroad and brought new ideas to the local scene." “Some of these great films, and documentaries too, will be shown at this festival.”
Cosmo Wong, a local artist and member of the jury, explained that the responsibility of choosing the films is “not easy”. “In the process, we respect all participants and select films based on several key dimensions, such as structure, narrative, whether it is artistic, original and whether it has social value and, finally, emotional strength”.
For the artist, “it is important that the festival continues”, that it “brings images” and that it “continues to be seen, heard and appreciated”. In turn, Julia Patey, director and also member of the festival's jury, considers that the work of “watching so many films in sequence is an inspiring experience”.
Menn Chow, director of the festival, stated that "in an era of content saturation, the short remains a powerful antithesis. It demands full attention and delivers a profound impact in minutes. The future of stories is here and it is brilliantly concise." “We invite you to slow down, immerse yourself and discover the transformative power of short films”, he concluded.
The event runs until December 10th, at Teatro Capitol, with more than 15 prizes for a total amount of 84 thousand patacas, sponsored by Creative Macau, Fundação Oriente and Banco Nacional Ultramarino.
Since its inception, the festival has served as “an affirmation of the strength of bold, artistic vision against commercial power,” according to the organization.
In 2015, the festival evolved into an international platform, with the introduction of the “Shorts and Volume” competitions. In recent years, it has established itself as “a crucial platform for creative exchange”. The initiative “connects Macau’s unique cultural environment with global cinematic voices, fostering dialogue and lasting professional partnerships”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Full review” defended to reinforce fire prevention and rescue</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/defendida-plena-revisao-para-reforcar-prevencao-resgate-em-incendios/</link><description>Deputy Nick Lei called for the creation of a regular review mechanism in relation to failures detected in fire prevention inspections. Furthermore, he defended specific rescue plans for different areas, in order to guarantee “more targeted and operable” rescue work, as well as the introduction of advanced equipment, to fully increase rescue capacity in cases of fire.
 
Considering that the serious fire that occurred in Hong Kong represents an “alarm” for Macau, deputy Nick Lei argued that it is important to “carry out a full review of construction safety supervision, rescue plans in the face of major disasters and public education on fire prevention, preventing risks”.
In a written statement, he pointed out that, although the Government quickly initiated specific inspections of scaffolding works, “a single inspection is not enough to eliminate hidden risks”. From his perspective, it is necessary to create a regular review mechanism in relation to flaws discovered during inspection work, in order to ensure that construction materials meet fire prevention standards and to fundamentally improve the situation of access roads blocked by objects.
Furthermore, he warned that “large-scale rescue work faces many challenges” in Macau, given the high population density, small distance between buildings and narrow streets in the territory.
In this context, Nick Lei argued that, in addition to the general rescue plan that the authorities currently adopt, specific rescue plans must be drawn up for each area, depending on the population density, type of construction and environmental characteristics of the different areas, thus ensuring “more targeted and operable” plans.
For the deputy, these plans must take into account the support capacity of the medical system, rescue equipment and available human resources. “At the same time, it is necessary to clarify standard procedures for initiating regional rescue collaboration in order to ensure timely obtaining of support from neighboring regions during the occurrence of serious incidents,” he continued.
Furthermore, Nick Lei called on the Government to carry out specific reorganization actions for low-rise buildings in old areas and buildings without management entities, in order to increase the efficiency of emergency evacuations.
On the other hand, the deputy linked to the People's Institution Alliance highlighted that advanced equipment is important to increase the efficiency of rescue in cases of fire. In this sense, he urged the Government to introduce advanced technology equipment to assist in rescue work, in order to fully increase the rescue capacity in cases of fire occurring in tall buildings and old and narrow neighborhoods.
“It is necessary to review, following the highest standards, and effectively reinforce the execution efficiency in eliminating safety risks, supervising works and responding to disasters... avoiding similar cases in Macau”, emphasized Nick Lei.
 
IAM warns about fire prevention in nature
Pointing out that, with the arrival of Autumn and Winter, “the weather is very cool and pleasant, making it a good time for citizens to take walks outdoors”, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) warns that, as precipitation decreases and the weather becomes dry, “the risk of forest fires increases”. In this sense, the organization appealed to citizens to be alert and prevent the occurrence of fires. With dry winds and low humidity, “if fallen leaves and withered branches in nature come into contact with a flame, they are likely to ignite within a short period of time, causing an uncontrollable forest fire”, highlighted the IAM, also asking that during walks the population does not light a fire to cook in places not intended for barbecue, nor smoke or throw cigarette butts on the ground.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Prize competition launched for qualified staff</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lancado-concurso-de-premios-para-quadros-qualificados/</link><description>Until the end of March 2026, residents who have obtained certifications in language skills, career guidance and qualifications in finance or information technology, throughout 2025 from designated entities, are eligible to compete for the Qualified Personnel Development Commission's awards program
 
Applications for the “Program to Encourage Training and Accreditation Exams for Qualified Personnel”, co-organized by the Qualified Personnel Development Commission (CDQQ) and the Macau Foundation, are open until March 31, 2026. In a statement, CDQQ informed that the prizes awarded to successful candidates relate to certifications in foreign languages and sectoral orientation as well as professional qualifications in finance or technology of information.
The Commission explained that “in conjunction with the needs of social development” and “after listening to the opinions of the sectors”, the co-organizing entities decided to expand the coverage of the award catalogs for this year's various programs.
Aimed at Macau residents who have obtained certification in 2025, the awards relating to foreign languages ​​and sectoral orientation include 450 places and cash prizes worth 1,000 patacas.
The institutions whose exams are covered by the catalog of language skills assessment awards are the Center for Assessment of Portuguese as a Foreign Language, the “Alliance Française”, the “National Institute for International Education”, “The Japan Foundation” and the Chinese Foreign Language Publication Administration.
Regarding sector-oriented certifications, the awards are aimed at qualifications at different levels and in multiple sectors of activity, namely restaurants and hotels, construction, management, commerce, social services and exhibitions and conventions.
Within the scope of the “Program of Awards for Professional Certification of Qualified Staff in Modern Finance”, four categories of awards will be available, for a total of 310 places, with monetary values ​​of 1,000, 3,000, 6,000 and 8,000 patacas. The awards relate to certifications relating to training in management, corporate finance, anti-money laundering and prevention of financial crimes, among others.
In turn, the “Program of Awards for Professional Certification of Qualified Personnel in Information Technologies” has two categories of awards, for a total of 290 places, worth 3,000 and 4,000 patacas. These awards reward certifications of different levels provided by entities such as Cisco, Huawei, Alibaba, Tencent, Baidu or Linux, covering areas such as cloud computing, cybersecurity and the management of Internet systems.
Applications can be submitted using the Single Account or the CDQQ online application system.
The purpose of this program is to “encourage residents to participate in accreditation exams and reach a specific level, promote and provide different techniques in different fields, with the aim of increasing their professional qualities and individual skills, as well as creating a reserve of technical-professional staff in different sectors for the development of adequate diversification of the economy”.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Visual Arts Exhibition presents 61 works</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/exposicao-das-artes-visuais-apresenta-61-obras/</link><description>The Cultural Institute received hundreds of works of art to be part of the Visual Arts Exhibition, however, after selection by the jury, 61 remained. These are the pieces that the public will be able to see between today and January 8th at the Tap Seac Gallery
 
Held for several years now, the Annual Visual Arts Exhibition once again promotes “the safeguarding, innovation and sustainable development of traditional Chinese painting and calligraphy”. The exhibition, which presents works precisely in the category of Chinese painting and calligraphy, can be enjoyed by the public between now and January 8th at the Tap Seac Gallery.
The Annual Visual Arts Exhibition includes 61 pieces/sets of artworks with different themes, including epigraphic transfers that represent urban memories, works that interpret Taoist philosophy with ink and brush, ink painting works that integrate elements of intangible cultural heritage, and calligraphy works inspired by styles from the Song and Ming dynasties, indicated the Cultural Institute (IC).
“Works that express lyrical reflections on life through the representation of objects and innovative representations of natural landscapes with ink and brush will also be presented, clearly demonstrating the creative advances of Macau artists in the fields of traditional Chinese painting and calligraphy, as well as the vibrant exploratory spirit of their creative activity”, adds the organization's note.
The process of collecting the works began in May this year, with requests for works of traditional Chinese painting, calligraphy, seal engraving and experimental ink art. The initiative received an “enthusiastic response” from local artists, with 161 works received from the same number of candidates.
After selection by the jury, 61 works were chosen to be included in the exhibition, 10 of which were awarded the Prize for Exceptional Works. The award-winning artists are: He Guohong, Ho Weng Chi, Mok Hei Sai, Chang Cheng Cheng, Vong Mio Ngo, Wong Monica Wondlarm, Ye Jiehao, Liu Yuqu, Lu Shaoyi and Im Hok Lon.
The exhibition will be on view at Galeria Tap Seac daily, between 10:00 and 19:00 (including public holidays), with free entry. During the month of December, guided tours will be offered in Cantonese and Mandarin at 3:00 pm and 4:00 pm, respectively, on Saturdays, Sundays and public holidays, as well as on the 22nd, 23rd and 26th of December.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Banks without fluctuations in international activity</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/bancos-sem-flutuacoes-na-actividade-internacional/</link><description>The international activity of Macau banks continued in the third quarter, continuing to focus on Asia
 
The share of financial investments in international markets in the total assets of the Macau banking system was 84.5% at the end of September, remaining the same as at the end of June, according to statistics from the Monetary Authority (AMCM). At the same time, international liabilities in the total liabilities of the banking system also remained at 81.3%.
At the end of the third quarter of this year, the pataca represented just 0.8% and 0.6%, respectively, of total international financial assets and liabilities. The shares of the Hong Kong dollar, US dollar, renminbi and other foreign currencies corresponded to 28.3%, 43.0%, 21.8% and 6.1%, respectively, of total international assets and 38.3%, 37.6%, 18.0% and 5.5%, respectively, of total international liabilities.
According to AMCM, the international assets of the Macao SAR banking sector amounted to 2,153.6 billion patacas, 3.2% more than in the previous quarter, with foreign assets (1,630.4 billion) and local assets in foreign currencies (523.3 billion) growing by 1.9% and 7.7%, respectively. In turn, loans from non-bank entities abroad, which constituted the majority of international assets, grew 4.0% to 584.7 billion.
Statistics also indicate that the international liabilities of the banking sector reached 2,073.7 billion, reflecting an increase of 3.2% in quarterly terms. During this period, liabilities abroad reached 1,042.8 billion, a decrease of 0.5%, while domestic liabilities in foreign currencies grew by 7.3% to 1,030.9 billion. Deposits in foreign currencies of the Macao SAR Government and Macau residents in local banks continue to represent the main component of total international liabilities, which increased by 1.9% to 780.5 billion.
Macau's international banking activity continues to be mainly focused on Asia. At the end of September, the Macau banking system's credits in Mainland China and Hong Kong were equivalent to 35.8% and 23.9%, respectively, of total foreign assets. However, credits for Portuguese-speaking countries and countries included in the “One Belt, One Route” initiative occupied 0.6% and 14.8%, respectively.
Regarding liabilities abroad, shares of 47.2% were recorded for Hong Kong, 35.7% for Mainland China, 6.9% for countries included in the “One Belt, One Road” initiative and 0.4% for Portuguese-speaking countries.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Eight artists evoke the journeys of Fernão Mendes Pinto and Xu Xiake</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/oito-artistas-evocam-viagens-de-fernao-mendes-pinto-xu-xiake/</link><description>Eight artists from China and Portuguese-speaking countries, including the Portuguese Carla Cabanas, will present 28 works, at Casas da Taipa, under the theme “Spiritual Narrative”. The exhibition is based on the travels of Fernão Mendes Pinto and Xu Xiake, in the 16th century

The Casas da Taipa Exhibition Gallery opens tomorrow, at 6:30 pm, the “Spiritual Narrative – Annual Arts Exhibition between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries”. The exhibition brings together 28 works by eight artists from China and Portuguese-speaking countries, including Portuguese artist Carla Cabanas, and is inspired “by the experience of two legendary travelers from the 16th century”, Fernão Mendes Pinto and Xu Xiake, explains the Cultural Institute (IC) in a press release.
The installations and works of painting, sculpture and video reveal “a mosaic of the cultural contexts of China and Portuguese-speaking Countries” as well as a “rich artistic vocabulary”, can be read in the statement. The remaining artists are Wong Hio Chit and Cosmo Wong, born in Macau, Cao Yu and Tong Wenmin, from Mainland China, Délio Jasse, from Angola, Eugénia Mussa, from Mozambique, and Juliana Matsumura, from Brazil.
The exhibition uses “artistic creation instead of physical travel”, through “a visual feast”. The IC states that “entering the exhibition space will be like following in the footsteps of a traveler, beginning an artistic tour of self-reflection and exploration of the world”.
The choice of the two travelers was based on the fact that they both measured “the world with their own steps, transforming their observations and travel experiences into philosophical reflections on life”.
Open until March 1, 2026, the public will be able to visit the exhibition free of charge, between 10am and 7pm, from Tuesday to Sunday, at the Exhibition Gallery and the Casas da Taipa Nostalgia House. Guided tours in Cantonese and Mandarin will also be available this month, at 3pm and 4pm, respectively, on weekends and holidays and between the 23rd and 26th.
The exhibition is part of the program of the 7th Meeting in Macau – Festival of Arts and Culture between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Paper art from recycled textiles</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/arte-em-papel-partir-de-texteis-reciclados/</link><description>“Waves of Influence: Foreign Materialities” by Elizabeth Briel is an exhibition that celebrates the unique qualities of paper art created from textiles. It will be open to the public from today at “Taipa Village Art Space”



















VÍTOR REBELO
 
This year's artistic closure of the Associação Cultural da Vila da Taipa will be marked with the exhibition “Waves of Influence: Foreign Materialities”, by the North-American Elizabeth Briel. The exhibition highlights the uniqueness of paper art created from recycled textiles, a rare artistic medium that is imbued with the concept of environmental sustainability.
As a versatile artist, Elizabeth Briel has experience in architecture and heritage, “which aligns perfectly with the initiatives of the Associação Cultural da Vila de Taipa to integrate contemporary art, architecture and design in innovative ways”, says a statement from the organization of the exhibition that will open to the public this Wednesday.
With the support of the association, the “Ondas de Influence” exhibition was completed this year and is being mounted together with selected works from a previous series by the author, entitled “Impressions: What Lies Beneath Paris &amp; Hong Kong”, a Greater Bay Area project developed in a paper art center in the Guangzhou region and which will be exhibited in “Taipa Village”.
The exhibition will feature an artistic installation created from recycled denim and t-shirts, transformed into a fluid wall of blue and white Macau tiles. The work of art, engraved and silkscreened with acrylic, graphite, copper foil and ink on cotton paper made from post-consumer denim and pre-consumer textile scraps, features around 250 tiles, each measuring 30 x 30 cm, which together “cover an impressive 250 square feet in a unique mix of sustainable materials and complex artistic techniques”, highlights the association.
Elizabeth Briel is a painter and printmaker who works primarily with paper in response to where she lives, printing directly from architecture, making paper from linen and cotton, and creating large-scale modular paper installations. His work begins with materials imbued with meaning, i.e. paper beaten by typhoons or made from military uniforms and bone and lead paints.
Born in California and raised in Minneapolis, the artist earned a Bachelor of Fine Arts in painting from the University of Minnesota. After living in New York and Boston, he left the USA in 2003 and lived in Asia for two decades before moving to Paris on an artistic and cultural “Passport Talent” visa in 2024. He has exhibited in Europe, Asia and Australia, and returns to the Asian continent for annual projects.
The concept for this exhibition in Macau is the result of hours of work on and around his studio table, inlaid with hand-painted blue and white Chinese porcelain, created for the export market and brought by Americans to Hong Kong. He traced the intricate designs on the porcelain, remembering the Portuguese tiles in Macau and the way this art connects disparate cultures, from China to the West.
“These blues are the art of empires that, like paper and denim, were intertwined across continents and centuries through migration, trade, power and conflict, transformed by people from all levels of society as they were incorporated into their lives”, the note can also read.
For the Taipa Village Association, “what particularly interested Briel were the cultural interactions between the Chinese empires, the Mediterranean caliphates and the Iberian powers that catalyzed the artistic means of paper and blue and white porcelain during the last millennium”.
At the launch of the exhibition, Elizabeth Briel says that, in Macau, she explored tiles with Portuguese motifs in municipal structures and 20th century tiles depicting the South China Sea. “When translating these drawings onto denim paper made from blue jeans, I studied the individual brushstrokes to understand the decisions made by their creators”, he highlights.
To deepen his understanding, he traveled to Portugal and China to experience the tactile and sensory aspects of painting and enamel. “These challenges include working with metallic enamels and the intense conditions of high-temperature firing,” he explains.
The exhibition curator and president of the association, João Ó, states that “although paper is often seen as a fragile material, the artist's work challenges this notion, showing its true power and resistance, as she transforms the delicate paper into a stunning and sustainable medium that captivates and inspires”.
The exhibition will be on display until February 4th, from 12pm to 8pm.
The Cultural Association, created in 2016, aims to highlight the uniqueness of Taipa Village's heritage, raising awareness of its attractions and reinforcing its position as a distinct community “that benefits the entire Macau region”. According to the association, several initiatives were planned to “preserve, strengthen and improve the town's position as an unmissable tourist and cultural destination”, including a diverse range of artistic and cultural attractions “that allow current visitors and future generations to enjoy a unique experience of authentic Macau”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Oil paintings reflect society and social networks</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pinturas-oleo-reflectem-sociedade-redes-sociais/</link><description>Oil painting works by artist Sunny Sit Ka Kit are on display at the Rui Cunha Foundation Gallery. The author explores the reverse side of the mirror, in the way society and social networks understand the role of modern man






























The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) yesterday opened the oil painting exhibition “Shaping.Viewing the Scene”, by Sunny Sit Ka Kit, an artist who focuses his work on psychological changes and the ethical balance of male identity. At the same time, “it explores the reverse side of the mirror, in the way society and social networks understand the role of today's man”, says a note from the FRC.
The exhibition includes 15 highly impactful works, where Sit Ka Kit uses oil painting as a medium, drawing experiences as a husband and father, reflecting themes of “identity formation” and “the responsibility to see”.
According to curator Kit Tam Chon, in contemporary arts, the introspective writings of male artists have often been forgotten. “Although women's art courageously addresses themes of identity and social power, men's psychological experiences and ethical reflections when faced with family, emotions and social responsibilities are often hidden beneath rationality and silence”, he highlights.
The exhibition is made up of two series: “Private Space” and “Public Space”. The former illustrates the “psychological transformations of men” in the context of the family, while the latter observes “social events from a spectator's perspective, reflecting ethics and public consciousness”. Both “resonate to build a double mirror structure” where “the self and the world intersect”, reveals the artistic manifesto.
In “Private Space”, the author uses family experience as a starting point for his narration, where “through calm and measured brushstrokes”, he captures on screen the “tension of fatherhood, responsibility and freedom”, mentions Kit Tam Chon.
In “Espaço Público”, the artist departs from social networks and public events, giving his “spectator” perspective to explore themes such as ethics, public pressure and the state of existence. “With an objective lens and without imposing personal feelings, Sit Ka Kit thus tries to encourage a reassessment of the “ethical scenario” in which we live”, says the FRC statement.
Born in Macau, the artist is currently studying for a PhD in Fine Arts. He obtained a master's degree from the Guangzhou Academy of Fine Arts in 2019 and was an exchange student at the Faculty of Fine Arts of the Seoul National University of Science and Technology in 2017.
He was invited to participate in the artistic creation project “Macau Elegance Reborn – Fine Depiction of Mountain, Sea, and City Images” by the National Art Fund of China, as well as in the Young Artist Creation Program of the National Art Fund of China and in the third collateral exhibition “Macao International Art Biennial”, in 2023. He received nominations and awards in the Greater Bay Area, having held solo exhibitions in places such as Guangzhou and Zhongshan.
He is currently deputy director of the Youth Art Association and director of the Association of Fine Arts Artists, both in Macau, and also holds guest professorships at the City University of Macau and the Polytechnic University.
Co-organized by the FRC, the Macau Youth Art Association and the Macau Fine Arts Artists Association, the exhibition will be open to the public until December 13th.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Consular residence hosts exhibition commemorating 500 years of Camões</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/residencia-consular-acolhe-mostra-comemorativa-dos-500-anos-de-camoes/</link><description>The Consulate General of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong and the Instituto Português do Oriente (IPOR) will present tomorrow the exhibition “Camões Cinco Zero Zero”, by Victor Hugo Marreiros, after having been on display at Galeria Passevite, in Lisbon. The inauguration ceremony will take place at 6:30 pm, in the Gallery of the Official Residence of the Consul-General of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong, and will remain open until December 27th. In this simultaneously nostalgic and creative project, the figure of Camões is reinterpreted “with graphic freedom, humor and critical spirit”, can be read in a press release. Victor Hugo Marreiros was based on an original idea by designer Henrique Silva, known as “bibito”, to propose “a contemporary and symbolic reading of the poet's figure” through the posters that he himself has created over more than thirty years in commemoration of June 10th. The exhibition that now arrives in Macau “symbolically closes the cycle of a project that unites the two margins of Portuguese heritage and celebrates the dialogue between art, history and Portuguese-speaking identity”. During the exhibition period, a special silkscreen edition numbered and signed by the artist and an official exhibition catalog will be available, the note states. The project has the support of Banco Nacional Ultramarino, Quinta da Marmeleira, Fidelidade, Ginja do Senado, and the Amagao and Passevite galleries. After the opening of the exhibition, the Alvorada concert “Regresso” will be held, dedicated to the memory of Artur Paredes and Carlos Paredes.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Young customers “travel back in time” to ancient China</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/jovens-clientes-viajam-tempo-ate-a-china-antiga/</link><description>Women in long wigs and ornate traditional costumes wandered through a stone courtyard, stopping to take photographs beneath a pavilion, while the melodious sound of the Chinese zither played in the background.














These customers paid to, for a few hours, “travel back in time” to ancient China in an experience offered by a recently opened themed restaurant in the center of Beijing, which offers clothing services and an eight-course dinner.
Although the world's second-largest economy has suffered from weak domestic demand, many young people still spend on experiences and goods that give them satisfaction – a trend recently dubbed in China as “emotional consumption”.
Consumers born after the 1990s often buy things to “please themselves”, driving purchases with a strong emotional charge in the country, specified the “China Daily” newspaper.
These purchases include Labubu dolls, which quickly sold out on shelves in China. “New forms of consumption… (and) new trends,” such as dolls with toothy smiles, could help boost China’s economy, Commerce Minister Wang Wentao said in July.
Before dining, diners choose their outfits in a room filled with traditional hanfu, or Han clothing, headdresses adorned with fake jewelry and accessories.
Wearing a red silk blouse printed with dragons, Zhuang said he was happy to spend money on a new experience. “It’s not about being blindly frugal, it’s about living in the moment,” the 27-year-old told AFP.
 
Willing to spend
On the second floor, women sat in front of dressing tables while makeup artists applied powder to their faces and blush delicately to their cheekbones.
After being made up, Wu Ke, 22, dressed in a flowing lilac hanfu and matching cape, said she was drawn to this restaurant because of her interest in ancient Chinese culture and clothing from the Song and Qing dynasties.
The presenter said that although people have tightened their belts in China, they are still willing to spend on certain things and experiences.
“If, in our daily lives, we are a little more economical with things like food – for example, eating more simply – and opt for public transport when we leave, the money we save will certainly find another destination,” Wu told AFP.
Outside, Huang Jing smiled as he watched his nine-year-old daughter posing for photos with a parasol on a small wooden bridge in the middle of a misty garden.
Huang paid at least 900 yuan for his daughter to dress in traditional clothes for dinner and have professional photographs taken.
The restaurant was “immersive”, different from ordinary restaurants, and had a cultural element, highlighted Professor Huang.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>