<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Retreat at the Church of Ká-Hó served as a test for restarting activities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/retiro-na-igreja-de-ka-ho-serviu-de-teste-para-reinicio-de-actividades-2/</link><description>The Church of Our Lady of Sorrows, in Ká-Hó, will reactivate its religious and pastoral activities as early as March, after a period of little dynamism. On the weekend, Friday, Saturday and Sunday, will take place three masses, whose times are not yet defined. In addition, the Diocese of Macau will highlight a priest to daily serve the faithful for confessions and guide the worship of the Blessed Sacrament. The first experience of revitalizing the chapel and the surrounding area was done through a retreat that had more than 70 people. Some participants consider that the site has all the conditions to become a kind of "sanctuary" and a reflection space. Father Daniel Ribeiro stressed to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau that “formerly Ká-Hó took care of sick with leprosy and physical problems”, and “now will work the soul of people”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The first experience by the Diocese of Macao to revitalize religious and pastoral activities in the Church of Our Lady of Sorrows in Ká-Hó, Coloane, was considered a success. The retreat, in Portuguese, held last Saturday, from morning until late afternoon, brought together more than 70 faithful, many of which belonging to the Congregation of Our Lady of Sorrows, who participated in a mass presided by Father Daniel.
In addition to the religious act, which took place at 16h00, the retreat had periods of formation, prayer, via sacred and worship of the Blessed Sacrament. One of the objectives was also to provide healthy conviviality among the people who responded to the diocese's call to mark the restart of activities, beyond a Christian reflection that was associated with him, on a day of spirituality.
From mid -March, the revitalization of events in the church and the surrounding area will be a reality. The activities will take place every day, with the presence of a priest-still named by D. Stephen Lee, bishop of the Diocese-who will receive every morning the faithful who want to confess from Monday to Friday, so How will the worship of the Blessed Sacrament guide.
On the weekend, from Friday to Sunday, three masses will be held, one of which may be in Chinese language, with times that will be defined by the end of February.
“We are studying the best times, that is, those who can have more people,” Father Daniel Ribeiro told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau.
In addition, pastoral activities will be organized in the nearby institutions, both at the Rehabilitation Hospital and at the Santa Ana Sisters Convent, or at the Hold on To Hope. “In the latter case we have not yet failed with the Macao toxicode dependent Rehabilitation Association), but it is one of our ideas for making events more often, which will have the responsibility of the congregation of the Fathers of the Sacred Heart of Jesus (Dehonians), ”says the priest.
However, remodeling works are being done in the house adjacent to the church, which should end at the end of March. In this housing, essentially oriented activities will be developed.
 
Some emotions
among the faithful
Father Daniel Ribeiro recalls that "formerly Ká-Hó took care of sick with leprosy and physical problems and now it will be a place where the soul of people will work," those who have depression, fear, who feel alone. " Therefore, “the place will be open all day,” he reinforces.
About the retreat, the vicar considers it to have been very positive, with good adherence from people, and states that "Ká-Hó is a very pleasant place where Macao people have a very large respect and consideration." In this context, he notes, "many of those who were thrilled there."
The ecclesiastical believes that this revitalization of activities, especially the presence of a priest every day and the accomplishment of masses to the weekend, will constitute "a source of blessing for many people in Macau".
One of the faithful who participated in the retreat confided to JTM that the space of Ká-Hó “has all the conditions to become a kind of sanctuary and reflection”, since it is in a quiet zone, involved in nature.
Another similar retreat is already scheduled for March 15th.
 
Dedicated church
to the protector of the sick
The history of the Church of Our Lady of Sorrows is indissolibly linked to the lepers who lived in Ká-Hó and Father Gaetano Nicosia, rising on the slope of the Ká-Hó hill on Coloane Island.
Built in 1966, during the bishopric of Dom Paulo José Tavares and was supported by Pope Paul VI, the government of Macao and the local diocese, it was intended to serve the religious needs of the village of Ká-Hó, where, at that time, They lived the families of healed lepers and some new patients with this terrible illness. Hence, the Church was dedicated to Our Lady of Sorrows, the protector of the sick.
The Nossa Senhora das Dores Church was the first projected in Macao according to the new concepts of religious architecture introduced after the Second Vatican Council (1961-65), so its inner space reflects the changes of the liturgy implemented during this Council , being conceived as a large hall, with the high altar positioned to the center of the assembly and focused on the faithful, as an amphitheater, establishing a closer relationship between these and the priest.
It has the shape of a great tent and, by the desire of Father Nicosia, has 13 doors that symbolize Jesus Christ and his twelve apostles. Its conception, in a modernist style, was by Italian engineer and sculptor Francisco Messina, and also had the contribution of Leopoldo Goffredo Acenci, another transalpino sculptor and his construction of contractor Oso Acconci.
As it turned out before, your altar is not placed in the back of the church, but on one side, so that it had seven doors on one side and six on the other. It is therefore known as the 'odd -doors church'.
In turn, the coverage consists of eight sets of diagonal beams that, in addition to structural function, symbolically divide the Church into seven sections, evoking the 'Seven Pain of Our Lady of Sorrows'. Outside his north door has a magnificent bronze crucifix, by Francisco Messina, who also conceived the church's bronze bell.
Construction is an authentic logistics challenge. In fact, the materials had to be transported by boat to Coloane, as there were no terrestrial roads that made the connection with the Macau Peninsula and, in addition, the church zone was separated from the village, because the workers, many of which They lived in Ká-Hó during the construction, were afraid that the lepers approach.
The church is classified by the Macao government as a building of architectural interest.
 
Father Nicosia improved
THE LIFE OF LEPEROS
About Father Gaetano Nicosia, undoubtedly one of the great workers of the work done at Ká-Hó leprosy, the ecclesiastical began his mission in Hong Kong in 1935 when he was only 20 years old. Eleven years later, he was ordained a priest at the São José Seminary Church in Macao, joining the Society of St. Francis of Sales (Salesians). He began to preach in China, but wanted his mission to be among the poorest, including lepers, as he had promised Jesus Christ when he was young.
His superior Salesian then intended to send him to a leproseria in Colombia, when the bishop of Macao asked for help from the leper colony on Coloane's island.
He definitely moved to Macao in 1958, having lived in the village and Ká-Hó between 1963 and 2011. Under the proposal of Gaetano Nicosia, the place of leprosaria was called the 'village of Our Lady'.
When he arrived at the leper colony in Ká-Hó, the priest came across a catastrophic situation. Due to the serious illness that they suffered and the almost total abandonment they were targeted, the suicide rate among the lepers was high, there was no drinking water or electricity, hygiene was virtually nonexistent, only from time to time received a visit from a visit Doctor and the foods were few.
The Italian developed all efforts to improve the living conditions of the lepers of Ká-Hó and, thanks to their long and continuous work for 48 years, has achieved many of them recovered and reinstated in society, despite the associated social stigma To this disease, having become known as the 'Angel of the Leperstos'.
In Macao, the lepers were welcomed in a hospice in the São Lazarus neighborhood (Macau), built by Bishop Dom Belchior Carneiro, in the mid -16th century and was funded by the Holy House of Mercy of Macao.
Already in the late nineteenth century, in view of the expansion of the city of Macao, a separation of lepers was made, and men were taken to a 'leper deposit' in Pac Sá Lan, on the island of São João (today , Mountain Island or Hengqin), initially being in very fragile dwellings that were destroyed by a typhoon in 1883, and then, more solid houses were built to your welcome.
Despite the stigma of leprosy, this was not an impediment for the sick to be a frequent target of pirate attacks that stole their little belongings, such as rice and coins.
 
Disease separated
Men of women
In 1885, women with leprosy were placed in the five homes that were part of the Ká-Hó hospice. It was neither a simple nor peaceful process, and the authorities changed their plans several times, as the places chosen, both on the island of macao and in the Macau Peninsula (near the siege doors), were rejected by the populations of these places.
Even the Portuguese authorities of the time referred to leprosy as 'that disgusting disease' and, on behalf of public hygiene, direct medical assistance to lepers was very limited. In the 1930s, the doctor only visited Ká-Hó once a week and even less frequent were the medical visits to Pac Sá Lan.
The treatment of leprosy wounds was left in the hands of the smartest and most polite patients, and the construction of a building on the Macau peninsula for the treatment of some of the patients has even happened, but this never happened.
In 1929, the government began the expansion of the Ká-Hó leprosy. The new buildings, including five pavilions and a chapel designed in an eclectic architectural style, were completed in 1930, defining a road on the slope facing the sea. The pavilions were characterized by large, classic, large -inspired balconies that opened on the landscape.
The new leproseria had a capacity of 90 patients and received weekly visits from medical teams, as well as the assistance of religious organizations, including the Canossian charity sisters who settled here to provide care to the sick, as well as the inhabitants of Vila de Ká -Hó.
In 1950, men with leprosy who were in Pac Sá Lan were also taken to Ká-Hó, since there was an intention to expand the village on the island of São João, but this did not occur, because the builder of Work also contracted leprosy and disappeared to never being seen again.
The couples were not allowed to cohabitation, but, of course, the members of the couples exchanged correspondence between them. The leper community cultivated vegetables, thus being autonomous. He also received food from Macao that was left in a small beach located in the area.
Apart from these sporadic trips, they were not visited by anyone else, being the leper treated as animals and chained for fear of contagion. In the leprosy of Ká-Hó then lived about 100 lepers, abandoned to their luck and urgently need medical care.
The situation only changed with the arrival in Macao do Father Nicosia in 1958. This, with a boundless dedication, never refused to deal with these sick, despite the high risk of contagion. From there, the lepers began to receive more frequent medical assistance and the village was slowly free from leprosy.
In 2011, all inhabitants of the leprosy colony were declared healed and many of them returned to work as teachers, workers or exercising activity as independent professionals.</description><pubDate>2025-02-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Coutinho available to continue in the presidency of ATFPM</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/coutinho-disponivel-para-continuar-na-presidencia-da-atfpm/</link><description>José Pereira Coutinho is available to continue the place of president of the Macao Public Service Association, a position he has held for over 25 years. The leader explained to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that the elections for the Association were postponed to 26 October so as not to coincide with the campaign period for the electoral act of the Legislative Assembly
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The availability for José Pereira Coutinho to remain at the head of the Macao Public Function Workers Association (ATFPM) “is total,” the associative leader of the Jornal Tribuna de Macau told. However, it caveat, "the list is not yet formed."
Coutinho states that "there is a long time to prepare the list of managers that will be sent later for approval of the ATFPM Board." The leader considers that, at this moment, the elections of the association “are not the priority”, but those of the Legislative Assembly (AL), “which is the most important”.
The proposal to postpone the Electoral Act of the ATFPM was unanimously approved at a general meeting held for days, during which it was also decided that the current structure of the Board and the Fiscal Council will remain until December 31, 2025, in order to ensure the daily operation of the association.
“If we account for exactly the end of the three years of office, this would come into incompatibility with the AL, which will be held in September,” says Pereira Coutinho, stressing that “this would undermine the maintenance of the stability of our process of work".
The ATFPM leader raises the veil from the program and the expectations he intends to see in terms of future action, stating that the intention is to try to increase young paintings in the composition of managing bodies. “We have been doing this as far as possible, little by little, to manage difficulties, because nowadays, due to the social and cultural diversity that exist, which allow young people to have other attractions, this prevents them from being available To contribute voluntarily to society, ”he says.
Regarding the elections for AL, Coutinho guarantees that nothing is still defined as to the elements that will integrate the top of the list of candidates. “Both I and Rita Santos can move forward, but that has not yet been defined,” he reiterates. The important thing, it goes on, "is that we will continue to have at least one elected deputy, since two will be a complicated task, due to the very strong competition that we will find from other associations."
In addition to the decision to postpone the elections to the ATFPM bodies, the General Assembly addressed some issues that Coutinho classifies as urgent in the current panorama.
According to a statement, the partners expressed the hope that continuity will be given to the struggle, with the government, to ensure the basic claims of the members. "Given that members are mostly under -base workers reported that, currently, the cost of living in Macau is extremely high, being forced to reside inside China to be able to survive," says the notice. Hence they suggested that the index value of the civil service be adjusted from 94 to 97 patacas.
In addition, they expect the rulers to understand the difficulties faced by the elderly: "With the constant increase in the prices of essential goods, the current amounts of the pension and the subsidy for the elderly are insufficient to cover daily expenses." Therefore, they suggest that these values ​​rise to 4,500 and 10,000 patacas, respectively, and that the pension payment is changed from quarterly to monthly.
On the other hand, they propose the distribution of at least another round of electronic consumer cards in the amount of 8,000 patacas, taking into account the current high cost of living environment.
Stressing that ATFPM has received and heard an average of 50 people a day, Coutinho asserts that some cases have been resolved. "Some of them are very sensitive, having to do with bullying, suicides, unequal treatment, economic and social issues, housing, public health, diseases, among other problems," he adds.</description><pubDate>2025-02-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Price of houses sold down 9% in Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/preco-das-casas-vendidas-desceu-9-em-macau/</link><description>Between 2023 and 2024, there was a progress in the volume of the real estate sector in the MSAR, however, the average price of houses decreased. The data released yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) also point to a slowdown in the sale of fractions in the last quarter of the year.
Official data, based on seal tax charged, reveal that 3,380 housing autonomous fractions (plus 501 or 17.4%, in annual terms) were transacted in Macao, during the year 2024, for a global amount of 20.33 billion. of patacas (+11.1%). Comparison with 2019 shows a decrease of about 60% in the number of alienated houses, as at the time it was 8,277, and also in the total amount, which in the pre-pound year was 51.05 billion.
Business closed in 2024 involved 3,023 housing fractions in built buildings and 357 in buildings under construction, for the values ​​of 18.48 billion and 1.85 billion patacas, respectively.
Regarding the average price per square meter (service area) of the apartments, it was encifted at 85,114 patacas in the general calculation of 2024, representing a 21% break compared to 2019. In the peninsula (78,751 patacas), the price fell 12.5%, in mud (93,896) decreased 3.6% and in Coloane (99,617) 7.3%.
DSEC data also point out that the average price per square meter of houses in built buildings (83,126 patacas) decreased 10%, while in buildings under construction (124,323) grew 1.2%.
Between October and December last year, 884 homes were sold, less than in the previous quarter, for 5.08 billion patacas (-3.5%). In concrete, 782 (39) housing fractions in built buildings were transacted by 4.51 billion patacas (-7.8%) and 102 in buildings under construction (+26), for the value of 575 million (+51 , 8%).
The average price per square meter of housing units (76,071 patacas) also fell 12.1% between the third and fourth quarters, including a decrease from 11.4% to 75,076 patacas in the already built and a decline from 10.7% to 118,424 in the houses under construction. According to DSEC, between October and December, sales focused mainly on the “Baixa da Taipa” areas (131), “New Black-Natap sand landfills” (81) and “Black Sand and Iao Hon” (64 ), for the average prices of 81,905, 83,563 and 57,983 patacas, respectively.
On the other hand, in the quarter under analysis, there were 97 housing fractions with emitted use license, of which 82.5% were studio type and 13.4% had two rooms. There were also 26 with authorization for execution issued, and "they were all located on the Macao Peninsula and were the studio."
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-02-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Advocated revision of the “five -scales housing” policy</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/defendida-revisao-da-politica-de-habitacao-em-cinco-escalas/</link><description>Representative Lo Choi In Exhorted the government to review the “five -scales housing” policy and to launch a public consultation about the relief of the application for economic housing, change to the definition of price, as well as an “proper enlargement” of investment nature of economic fractions
 
Given the reduction of birth rates, population aging and “lack of confidence” in the market, the government must review the entire “five -scales housing” policy, considers Lo Choi In. For the deputy, it also matters to make an appointment to perceive public opinions about economic housing, mainly considering relaxing the application requirements, changing the pricing and “properly widening the nature of invest ”in economic housing.
Convinced that the current housing policy “cannot correspond to social needs and development in the future”, the deputy anticipated that, even if the authorities increase the proportion of T2 fractions of economic housing with the aim of encouraging birth, the effect "It will not be very significant."
Quoted by the Citizen Journal, Lo Choi in argued that, to review the Economic Housing Law, a “broad public consultation” must be organized, taking into account the actual conjuncture of society. The deputy understands that it will be necessary to discuss various possibilities, namely “whether the nature of investing and the flexibility of economic housing should be extended, if it is necessary to eliminate or relax the application requirements and the restrictions implemented after purchase, and should be changed The target audience of the Economic Housing Law, in order to lead this legislation to return to its original intention to contemplate the purchasing power of residents. ”
In this respect, Lo Choi In emphasizes that “it is not necessary that the costs spent on economic housing are supported by buyers”, because this type of housing covers other public facilities, such as stores and parking parks, which can generate additional revenues for the government .
Regarding the aim of encouraging birth, the deputy proposed that some families willing to have the first baby or about to have the second child are included among priority candidates to exchange to a larger house. In addition, it suggested that adjacent T1 fractions be converted to T2 or T3 fractions for these families.
On the other hand, the deputy linked to the Jiangmen Country Association expressed support for the request of a real estate association for the government to perform land auctions to build housing for exchange in urban renewal. Lo Choi in believes that such cooperation between the Urban Renewal Society and Real Estate Prosecutors may create conditions for the “healthy and sustainable development” of the private real estate market ”, so it suggests that this matter is included in the public consultation content regarding Housing Policy.
In turn, Deputy Nick Lei urged the executive to study as quickly as possible to revise the economic housing law, especially the typology of houses, a mechanism that allows exchanges depending on changes in family structure and an authorization for aggregates with only a person may require larger fractions than T1.</description><pubDate>2025-02-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>XI encourages technological companies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/xi-incentiva-empresas-tecnologicas/</link><description>The Chinese president yesterday held a symposium with business leaders in the country, including the main technological groups, in a demonstration of support for a sector that has been in the eye of the hurricane in recent years due to the authorities' regulatory campaigns. During the event, Xi Jinping asked technological companies to strive to “promote healthy and high quality development in the country's private sector,” said state news agency Xinhua.
“The private sector enjoys broad perspectives and great potential. This is a privileged moment for private companies and entrepreneurs make the most of their abilities, ”said Xi, at the Great People's Hall in Beijing. He also stressed the importance of "reaching a consensus" and "reaffirming trust to promote healthy and high quality development of the private sector."
Prime Minister Li Qiang and two other members of China's Communist Communist Party Permanent Committee, Wang Huning and Ding Xuexiang, were also present at the meeting. The South China Morning Post newspaper identified the CEO of Xiaomi, BYD and Huawei among the entrepreneurs present, as well as Jack Ma, founder of the Electronic Trade Giant Alibaba, in an apparent sign of reconciliation after years of problems between the government and the man which was once the richest in the country. Bloomberg also mentioned that the founder of “Deepseek”, the latest sensation in the Global Sector of Artificial Intelligence (IA), joined the guest list.
Jack Ma founded Alibaba in 1999 and turned it into one of China's most recognized and dominant private companies. However, in recent years has reduced public appearances, especially after the authorities had canceled in 2020 the initial public offering of Ant Group, Alibaba's subsidiary, after a speech of MA in which he criticized regulators. Ma no longer occupies executive positions in Alibaba, but analysts believe it is still an important shareholder of the company, whose value has increased more than 40% since the beginning of the year.
The meeting between Xi Jinping and the business leaders took place at a time when China faces a slowdown in its economy, affected by a real estate crisis, the reduced level of consumption and the high rate of unemployment among young people.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-02-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>"Kaifong" director calls for new incentives for consumption</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/director-dos-kaifong-pede-novos-incentivos-ao-consumo/</link><description>Before the public knows the government lines for the present year, the government should launch another round of the “great consumption award in Macao,” suggested Chan Ka Leong, director of “Kaifong”. It also argued that it is time to discuss the optimization of the beneficiaries of the monetary reimbursement, asking for public consultations on the matter
 
The Director of the General Union of Macao Residents Associations (“Kaifong”) predicted that the Governing Action Lines (LAG) to 2025, which will be announced between March and April, will understand measures aimed at encouraging economic development in residential areas and Support Small and Medium Enterprises (SME). Still, Chan Ka Leong hopes that, before the lag, the executive bid again, and as soon as possible, the “great consumption award in Macao”.
In your opinion, associations and commercial establishments should continue consumer promotion activities in various community neighborhoods, as it believes that only the combination of the two consumer incentive aspects will be able to support SMEs in residential areas within a short period of time. However, Chan Ka Leong considers that the hypothesis of launching consumer cards should still be studied.
Regarding the optimization of the beneficiaries of pecuniary reimbursement, according to the Chinese language press, the associative leader argued that it is time to discuss the issue. "You can no longer be delayed," he said, suggesting consultations with the public, associations or the Legislative Assembly (AL) on the matter, in order to unite the consensus of the public and to make the beneficiaries of the checks “recognition público, precisos, de pouca controvérsia e focados no incentivo ao consumo em Macau”.
Nevertheless, Chan Ka Leong predicted that LAG for this year will not contemplate these changes, as uniting social consensus must "request some time."
In the long run, the Kaifong director has suggested to the government to help SMEs solve problems related to the opening of establishments, administrative procedures, the change of consumption model and the attraction of tourists to the community neighborhoods.
On the other hand, in the face of a case recently revealed by customs services, in which a woman tried to bring Hong Kong an electronic cigarette containing “ethomidate”, the executive board member expects authorities to study legislation to control the substance and to ponder even more emerging sourwitts. Chan Ka Leong believes that, if necessary, the Executive Council and Al will, in an urgent process, the legislative work.</description><pubDate>2025-02-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Macau in my heart” shows photos of Alex Chao</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-meu-coracao-mostra-fotos-de-alex-chao/</link><description>A collection of 30 photographs by Alex Chao, which exploit the city of different angles, will be on display from today in the Rui Cunha Foundation gallery. “Macau in my heart” shows, through the artist's lens, the transformations of the territory over the years

The changes that have marked Macau's face over the years have been the starting point for the conception of 30 photographic works by local artist Alex Chao, who will be released to the public at the Rui Cunha Foundation Gallery (FRC) Show with scheduled inauguration for 18:30.
The exhibition “Macau in My Heart” is the mirror of the photographic journey of decades when the photographer was a teenager, having used the lens “how a poet uses a pen”, transforming “such deep emotions into visual language”, according to the artist in the artist exhibition manifesto.
The images captured illustrate the architecture of the old and recent city, the urban movement, the sparkles and the colors, the rhythm of the population. “Here, the Portuguese historical architecture and the modern high buildings complement each other, while traditions and innovation go hand in hand,” says the artist.
Alex Chao Io Chong, a professional photographer for over 30 years brings together images from various parts of the city, exploring different topics, styles and approach techniques. The works record distinct moments such as the transformation of the city, from a fishing village in a prosperous international city, and compile poetic images “by intertwining history and modernity”.
The artist considers that the rapid economic development "brought prosperity to the city" and also made Macao "a tourist attraction and a worldwide entertainment center." Throughout this process, the photographer witnessed many important moments, such as “the opening of international casinos, the construction of new milestones and the annual fireworks”, records that are part of some examples that can be observed in the show, Which is curated by David Sit, art critic, painter and university professor.
Alex Chao graduated from the Polytechnic University of Macao, with specialization in Visual Arts (Artistic Education). In the early years, he studied and dedicated himself to professional photography and visual arts education. He was a professional photographer at the former Hotel Mandarin East in Macao, for many years, and also director of the photography studio at the then Polytechnic Institute of Arts of Macao, with decades of research and practice in the development of photography. It also has a vast experience in the areas of visual design, book editing, printing, multimedia and exhibition planning.
The show will be evident until March 1st. However, with the same title “Macau in My Heart” in the English translation, Alex Chao will also present a seminar on photography on February 20, Thursday, at 18:30 , only in Chinese language (Cantonese). The entrance is free.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-02-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DIQUE CONSTRUCTION IN COLAANE PURSUE IN BRIEF TERM</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/construcao-de-dique-em-coloane-arranca-breve-prazo/</link><description>The first phase of the flood prevention work in the marginal zone on the west of Coloane will begin, the first phase of the public works of public works (DSOP). This step, which will take place in the water, includes the construction of the flood prevention dike, about 1,200 meters long, the four floods and the watershed station on the hengqin side in Zhuhai, among others. "The first phase of the work will be executed only at sea, so it will not impact the coastal environment and residents and traders," says DSOP. Recently, the body presented the work to the residents of Colaane, in a session that was attended by about 60 people, including the Director-General of the General Union of Macao Residents Associations (“Kaifong”) and responsible for Coloane's associations . This is one of the medium -term projects of the disaster prevention and reduction plan in Macao. It is recalled that last year were completed the preliminary conception, the various thematic studies and geotechnical prospecting, and the opinions of the experts of the Hydraulics and Environment of China were also heard, and the project was “optimized”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Improved pedestrian environment next to Ferreira do Amaral Square</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/melhorado-ambiente-pedonal-junto-a-praca-de-ferreira-amaral/</link><description>The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) began the third phase of the works of optimization of Ferreira do Amaral Square and surrounding roads, with the aim of improving the pedestrian environment, through the repair and beautification of the surrounding underground tours. The endeavor “consists of widening and repairing the surface of tours, placing tiles with images that articulate with the peripheral environment, adjust and increase green spaces, install banks for citizens and tourists rest, and optimize street lighting installations ”Explained the body in a statement. In addition, "it aims to beautify the ceiling and repair the situations of lower passage to pawns between Yoho Treasure Island and Wynn Macao, with a view to creating a broader and more comfortable pedestrian environment." The works will be developed by zones and phases, and is expected to be completed in the second quarter. AMI warned the public to pay attention to provisional sealing measures to avoid any accidents.</description><pubDate>2025-02-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>This year reviewed solid waste management plan</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/revisto-este-ano-plano-de-gestao-de-residuos-solidos/</link><description>This year, the government will charge “a professional study institution” to review the implementation situation of Macau Solid Waste Management Planning (2017-2026), the director of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) said in response to An interpellation of Deputy Ngan Iek Hang. "Given the new conjuncture of social development, as well as the social situation, public opinion and also referring to the experiences of the neighboring regions, will define plans and directions that correspond to the reality of Macao," added IP Kuong Lam . 2016 to 1.48 kg by 2026. In the answer, IP Kuong Lam said only that "following social development in recent years, the general environment of Macao has undergone major changes compared to the launch period of the plan." On the other hand, the DSPA director has ensured that the government “will continue to optimize the network and community recycling services, and to encourage the population to put into practice the reduction and recycling of waste through the various plans in force, with a view to Raise society's global environmental awareness to jointly promote the work of waste reduction ”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>International Parade attracts 90 team candidacies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/desfile-internacional-atrai-90-candidaturas-de-equipas/</link><description>Marked on March 23, the “International Parade of Macao” aroused almost 90 candidates, revealed Leong Wai Man, president of the Cultural Institute (IC), highlighting the desire that more associations and local schools can participate in this cultural event. According to the evaluation criteria and plans, the IC will select between 50 and 60 local teams and, after that, choose artistic groups abroad for the “international parade”. On the other hand, the body continues to receive candidacies for new large shows, which will be held in the outdoor shows area, in Cotai, between next month and May. According to Leong Wai Man, many proposals were presented, including some scheduled for May or subsequent months. Regarding the six revitalized historical areas, he explained that, for now, the IC will maintain these spaces, but intends to gradually transform some short -term activities in these areas into medium or long term programs. The implementation of the respective revitalization projects completed almost two years. According to the scope of collecting information about the projects, the IC has also heard opinions, hoping that this policy will benefit residents, small and medium -sized companies and artistic groups. Generally speaking, IC intends, together with other government services, promoting cooperation programs in community neighborhoods, including old zones, through culture and art, in order to improve the life environment in neighborhoods and the community economy, He highlighted Leong Wai Man.</description><pubDate>2025-02-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MICE generated revenues of 5.5 billion for areas without game</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mice-gerou-receitas-de-55-mil-milhoes-para-areas-sem-jogo/</link><description>The recipes of the branches of economic activity not playing Macau derived from Convention and Exhibition events (MICE) cipher at about 5.48 billion patacas in 2024, a value that translates an annual break of 8.2%, reported Yesterday the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), based on preliminary estimates. According to official statistics, Macau welcomed 1,524 conventions, exhibitions and encouragement events over the past year, which reflects an annual increase of 31.4% or 364 initiatives compared to 2023. However, participants and visitors at events MICE decreased 17.1% to 1.33 million, mainly due to the descent of one fifth in the number of exhibition visitors. Overall, 1,423 meetings and conferences were held (32.2% more than 2023), with 185,000 participants (plus 8.2%), and 61 exhibitions (minus three) with 1.13 million visitors ( minus 20.5%). Exhibitions attracted 7,093 exhibitors (1.5%less) and 52,651 professional visitors (less 12.1%), with those from outside representing 51.9%and 51.5%, respectively. In turn, incentive events doubled to 40 in annual terms and had 13,000 participants (plus 22.5%). According to DSEC, most convention and exhibition events focused on “commerce and management” (640), corresponding to 42% of the total, followed by the themes of “computer technology” (164) and “Health” (154), which equivalent to 10.8% and 10.1%, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-02-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sentenced to one year in prison for fire put to the MP and PJ</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/condenado-um-ano-de-prisao-por-fogo-posto-junto-ao-mp-pj/</link><description>The Court of Second Instance (TSI) has reduced to a year of imprisonment to the penalty of a man who set fire to objects with the Judicial Police (PJ) and the Public Prosecution Service (MP) buildings, after appeal by both parties. The Base Judicial Court had applied a sentence of one year and three months in prison. The case happened in January 2024, with the man pouring kerosen under a police car with the PJ and putting newspapers to burn, and then followed to The MP, where he poured the remaining kerosene in the gate and set fire to a tissue towel. The defendant said he acted this way for being “dissatisfied with the file decision” of a case by the MP. The TSI understood that the man practiced “no doubt” two crimes: fire and qualified damage in the attempted form.</description><pubDate>2025-02-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>"Parasite" director presents in Berlin new movie about space race to cum musk</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/realizador-de-parasita-apresenta-em-berlim-novo-filme-sobre-corrida-espacial-gozar-musk/</link><description>South Korean director Bong Joon Ho, known for his award-winning movie “Parasite”, presented on Saturday at Berlinale “Mickey 17”, a comedy about the space race that satirically criticizes the ambitions of billionaires like Elon Musk.
The long-awaited production was shown out of competition during the Berlin Festival after its world debut on Thursday in London. The comedy will hit theaters on March 5.
"It's a story that takes place in the future, but it could also happen in the present or past," said Bong Joon Ho on Saturday at a press conference before the screening in Berlin.
The film is starring Robert Pattinson, an idol of the saga "Twilight" and currently one of Hollywood's most sought after British ("Batman", "Tenet"), in the role of Mickey, a young man without money.
To escape his problems on Earth, he becomes voluntarily in a guinea pig in a spaceship sent to colonize another galaxy. A billionaire reminiscent of Elon Musk's style, brilliantly played by Mark Ruffalo (“Avengers”), also participates in the expedition.
At the press conference, Bong Joon Ho stated that he did not have a specific inspiration for this character, but allusions to the US technology gurus and 'trump like' are evident.
Mickey, hired as a "disposable" passenger, is on the basis of the ship's social hierarchy. Therefore, it is sent to all the most dangerous missions and experiences, but thanks to a machine, it can be "reprinted" and rise whenever it dies.
“Parasite”, Bong Joon Ho's masterpiece, a golden palm winner in Cannes and the best Oscar movie in 2020, tells the story of a poor family that infiltrates the house of a very rich family, being a satire of the South Korean society and its inequalities.
Bong Joon Ho says he suspects "advertising" movies and said he wanted to do something spectacular and fun.
“All the things that happen to Mickey, his situation and the way he is treated in the movie are political. He talks about how we treat and respect (or not) a human being, ”he said.
“It's a science fiction movie where people travel to extraterrestrial planets in a spacecraft, but they are ridiculous people. It is not a great space adventure where people throw lasers in each other. These are ridiculous losers. The movie is full of adorably ridiculous people, ”he concluded.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-02-18 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>