<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Government launches childhood subsidy and increases support to the most vulnerable</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-lanca-subsidio-para-infancia-aumenta-apoios-aos-mais-vulneraveis/</link><description>Policies for encouraging birth and increased support for the elderly and people with disabilities - these are the biggest highlights of the presentation of the governance lines for 2025 by Sam Hou Fai. The Chief Executive was yesterday at the Legislative Assembly, where he also announced a support plan for small and medium enterprises, which he said, “constitute an important force” for the territory. The leader of the Misrera foresees “opportunities and challenges”, saying that the perspectives of the economy face “uncertainties”, so it is necessary “prudence”

Catarina Pereira
 
Sam Hou Fai presented yesterday the first lines of government action (lag) as chief executive, stressing that 2025 will bring "opportunities and challenges, as well as some pressure and renewed motivation." "It should be noted that the current perspectives of Macau's economy are facing uncertainties, with a single source of financial revenues and high rigid financial expenses. Thus, we must use the financial resources in the best way possible," he said, adding that it takes "prudence".
First of all, pecuniary checks are maintained, but changes in the form of attribution in the near future are anticipated. On the other hand, the incentives for birth and support for the most vulnerable groups, such as the elderly and people with disabilities, were highlighted. In addition, the leader of MSAR has taken over once again that there is a "loss of consumers" and that "the impact caused to small and medium enterprises (SMEs) is very large, even though there are many visitors," because they have also changed consumption patterns. In this sense, it also announced measures to support small businesses.
The pecuniary reimbursement plan, launched in 2008, will remain, with the usual 10,000 patacas for permanent residents and 6,000 for non-residents, however, residents must be “qualified” and have to fill the “requirements”-something that in previous years was not mentioned. Sam Hou Fai said that, after hearing the opinions of “all sectors of society”, he will proceed “in time to the improvement of the pecuniary reimbursement regime, using savings in expenses to increase resident welfare and promote the development of the community economy”.
Asked about this aspect at the Press Conference after the LAG presentation to the deputies, at the Legislative Assembly, the Chief Executive argued that, since it has passed 17 years since the implementation of the plan, it is time to change, so as to be “fairer”. “The plan is regulated by administrative regulation, it is not a law, that is, it is different from the elderly subsidy, for example. It is a measure of support. Macau works like this, we have different temporary measures, I know that the population would like to be regular… but, I notice that in society there are voices that consider that the plan is not fair, that it is necessary to change, for example, the conditions of distribution are more accurate, to be fixed or restricted, as the mode of restrictions, as well as the mode of restrictions Distribution, ”he said.
"I think we can have consensus that it is necessary to optimize the plan, it is not to cancel plan," he continued. Weaving some considerations on the subject, spoke in the form and value of distribution, days of stay in Macao, whether or not the person has contact or connection with Macau, whether in the great bay. “As for the details, I would like to have consensus,” he continued. As for the date for checking the check, Sam Hou Fai was no use details, saying that it is still necessary to deal with the administrative regulation.
Like previous years, the 200-patacas electricity payments are maintained in payment of electricity and water. The health care reimbursement program, a measure that reaches only permanent residents, rose from 600 to 700 patacas.
 
Incentives for birth
The scenario of the low birth rate in the territory has been concerned and, in this sense, the chief executive announced policies yesterday that they intend to encourage couples to have more children. An unprecedented measure is the so -called “childhood assistance subsidy”, which provides for the assignment of a monthly support of 1,500 patacas, totaling 18,000 patacas per year, for permanent babies and resident children under three years old.
In addition, the birth allowance, which was once 5,418 patacas, will move to 6,500 patacas and can be required by both progenitors. As for the increase in the number of days of maternity leave, the government will start a study, ensuring that the idea is to improve labor legislation.
"We will elaborate a project to develop day care centers in order to ensure the continuity and quality of services, to reduce the pressure of families from working couples with dependent children and to foster an environment conducive to child care for families with children," added Sam Hou Fai.
In addition, the reimbursement program in the treatment of medically assisted procreation will be launched, which will provide free “limited services” in this context.
In the same vein, the marriage subsidy also suffered a slight increase from 2,122 to 2,200 patacas, in which case it may be requested jointly by the spouses.
For students there will continue to be annual subsidies for the acquisition of school manuals, in non -higher education, in the values ​​of 2,400 patacas (kindergarten), 3,000 patacas (primary education) and 3,550 patacas (secondary education). Already for students of families with economic difficulties are foreseen subsidies of bribes, ranging from 4,000 to 9,000 PATACAS depending on the level of education, food allowance (3,950 patacas) and support for school supplies.
 
Great Bay: The Destiny of Young people
The head of the executive stressed that the government puts the works related to young people “in an extremely important position” and, in this sense, said that the boost of employment and entrepreneurship of this layer of the population is one of the goals. In this field, it revealed that a support plan will be launched for young people who move to work in the Great Bay.
This plan “aims to attribute to young people, aged 35 years or less, higher education graduates who are discouraged to work in the companies indicated in the nine cities of the Great Bay and in the hengqin cooperation zone, a monthly allowance of 5,000 patacas, for a maximum period of 18 months during employment”, explained during the presentation of lag.
In addition, he promised to make more internship opportunities available, “increasing the number of internship vacancies in the companies indicated in the interior of China and raising to 520 vacancies in the internship program in China for Macao Higher Education students, attributing to those who complete the internship, a subsidy worth 5,000 patacas”.
It is also foreseen the extension of the internship vacancies of the “Macao Youth Professional Development Plan”, as well as studying the possibility of extending the application of the “Internship Plan to create better work prospects” and the “Young Entrepreneurs Support Plan” to Macao young people who are developing careers in the interior of China.
 
Help to the elderly and disabled
On the other hand, also for the elderly and people with disabilities, adjustments were announced on the supports. The subsidy for the elderly rises from 9,000 to 10,000 patacas per year, while the pension increases from 3,740 to 3,900 patacas per month, totaling 13 installments per year.
The boss also said that continuity of the elderly database will be given isolated or couples in which the two elements are already elderly. In this context, he said the technology will be used for care. Another aspect mentioned was the study of the widening of the “Peng on Tong” teleassistence service, “reinforcing the guarantee of safety of the elderly”.
In addition, and in response to early treatment and care in the homes, the creation of an early treatment installation in the North Zone with 44 early treatment vacancies, a day -to -day special care center and an integrated area of ​​rehabilitation services in zone A, with 40 daytime care vacancies for the elderly and 100 rehabilitation services.
Regarding people with disabilities, normal disability allowance will rise from 9,000 to 10,000 patacas per year, while the amount of special subsidy grows from 18,000 to 20,000 patoes also annually. As for the disability pension, which was 3,740 patacas, it will be 3,900, a total of 13 installments per year.
 
Interest Bonus Plan for Small Business
The chief executive yesterday again stressed that "the SMEs constitute an important force for the socioeconomic development of Macao," so the government will act with a long -term perspective in the face of the global conjuncture, making efforts to revitalize the community economy and to stimulate SMEs to "raise quality development."
Thus, Sam Hou Fai announced the launch of the Bank Credit Interest Bonus Plan for SMEs, which provides each commercial entrepreneur who fulfills the requirements, “a maximum amount of the five million bonus credit, with a 4% interest bonus for a period of three years”. The maximum limit of the total amount of bank credits is fixed at 10 billion Patacas, “with the aim of relieving the burden interest on SMEs, reinforcing their liquidity and mitigating their financial financing pressures,” he explained.
On the other hand, it also addressed the launch of the three -level support plan, which had already been announced. Based on the current “Plan of Stores with their own characteristics”, the “Plan of Stores with specialized and delicate characteristics” will be launched, seeking, over the next three years, selecting 100 companies with potential that have innovative ideas, “especially the favorite of young clients”.
Support will also be given to commercial associations in the new edition of classification of “typical Macao brands” to select “typical brands” and “centenary brands”, “seeking to cultivate a group of old and famous stores and companies with great development potential, high competitiveness, greater social influence and rich cultural characteristics”.
 
Eye on operators
On the other hand, and with regard to the Pillar sector of Macao's economy, the game, Sam Hou Fai has ensured that the government will “carry out the coordination work and contingency plans to respond to the end of the transition period of exploration of satellite casinos, which will happen in the near future”.
As for non-play investment projects, he said that operators will be exhorted to “invest more resources in priority industrial projects in Macao and Hengqin, as well as brands that support the elevation of Macao's overall competitiveness” as well as “establishing the effectiveness evaluation indicators of non-game investment projects, and periodically reviews the global situation of compliance with concession contracts”.
Pointing to the promotion of the game's healthy development, he added that the intelligent and digitized management of the sector will be improved and the promotion of the responsible game will be promoted.
The chief executive stressed yesterday that he hopes that there is a consolidation of economic recovery, a development of community economy and maintenance of GDP growth. Alongside the optimization of the welfare of the population, Sam Hou Fai also aims to maintain the low unemployment rate in the territory and the stability of price.
 
Budget for this year will be reinforced
The chief executive admitted yesterday at the press conference that the 2025 budget will have to be reinforced, as tax revenues should be below expected. "If we do not reach the goal [of 93 million revenues from casinos] will have an impact on the budget base. We will make budget reinforcement for this year to launch measures and plans," said Sam Hou Fai, adding that authorities will continue to "evaluate" the impact of the world conjuncture on Macao situation. According to said, the trade war between the United States and China could impact Macao, especially if there is a devaluation of Renminbi, which will have consequences in the consumption of Chinese tourists.
 
Mand will create representations in the Southeast and Northeast Asia
Continuing to attract international tourists is also one of the government's objectives for this year, with particular emphasis on the Northeast Asia markets, Southeast Asia, South Asia and South America. international, ”announced Sam Hou Fai. He has also ensured that the MSar will “widen the airport's flight network, to promote the coming of tourists from countries or regions that do not have direct connections with Macau through neighboring regions and attract more international tourists by discounting airplane tickets, transfronhetic transport benefits among other measures”.
 
Pecuniary
Stay in 10,000 Patacas
for permanent residents
and 6 thousand for non -residents
 
Childhood subsidy
1,500 patacas per month
Children under three years
 
Birth subsidy
Up from 5,418 to 6,500 patacas
 
Subsidy for the elderly
Grows from 9,000 to 10,000 patacas
 
Pension for the elderly
Up from 3,740 to 3,900 patacas
 
Disability subsidy
Normal: It goes from 9,000 to 10,000 patacas
Special: rises from 18,000 to 20,000 patacas
 
Disability pension
Increases from 3,740 to 3,900 patacas
 
Health valleys
Rise from 600 to 700 patacas</description><pubDate>2025-04-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Cluster” of medical industry and “university city” in hengqin</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cluster-de-industria-medica-cidade-universitaria-em-hengqin/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai dedicated a considerable part of the government lines to approach the development of Hengqin, saying that he intends to create “a cluster of the medical and health industry” in the deepened cooperation zone. The chief executive is also betting on developing a “university city of international education” on the other side of the border
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Hengqin's support in the diversification of Macau's economy is still "short of expectations" and the masters should "align with the national strategies to achieve better development," said the chief executive yesterday. In the presentation of the government lines, Sam Hou Fai stressed that the development of macau-hengqin cooperation is one of his missions.
In this context, Sam Hou Fai indicated that the government will “carefully introduce technologies and medical concepts at the international level, building a series of high -level specialized medical institutions”. The idea is to attract “the establishment of a series of high quality health technology companies in the deepened cooperation zone, creating a cluster of medical and health industry with characteristics of Macao and Hengqin”.
Alongside this, he said that the “Macao Registration + Hengqin Production” model will be adopted to promote the “integrated and deep development” of the Macao and Hengqin Traditional Chinese Medicine industry. At the same time, Sam Hou Fai has promised to be committed to “optimizing the multifunctional free trade account system, boosting the participation of macao-qualified banks in the cooperation zone pilot project, and the promotion of transfrontic flow of capital between Macau and Hengqin”.
In addition, the Chief Executive is also betting on creating a “university city of international education” in Hengqin, highlighting “the advantages of Macao Higher Education Institutions”. According to the LAG report, the idea is through the “internationalization of qualified paintings, scientific research and scientific and technological exchange”, to carry out promotional actions of integrated development between Macau and Hengqin in the scope of education, science and technology and qualified staff.
“The Government of MSA will proceed to the coordination work so that local higher education institutions to recruit students from the interior of China for undergraduate courses, (…), use the pedagogical extension model“ a university, two zones ”, perform preparatory work to create the new university campus in the cooperation zone, with the aim of creating a pedagogical environment that is uniform with Macao, and configuring a macao, and to configure a macao Macao integration pilot project with hengqin in the scope of higher education, ”he said.
Sam Hou Fai also said that "efforts to obtain authorization to build more reference laboratories in the state will also be" taught. The University of Macao (one) will be the first to implement the pedagogical extension model in the cooperation zone. The leader of the MSAR said yesterday that, although one already has the land, has no money to start building, which is also one of the reasons why the budget for 2025 needs to be reviewed.
Regarding Hengqin, the boss also said that more workers of the Public Administration of Macao will be highlighted to work on the Executive Committee and various work structures. Sam Hou Fai also stressed that the Misrem will “proactively promote” the Macao Judges Pilot Project to perform non-permanent judges in the Hengqin Courts.
 
More Lusophone Products in the Great Bay
In the presentation of the government lines, the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, ensured that the government will promote “the access of more products from Portuguese -speaking countries to the Greater Bay market”. According to said, it will be maximized, “full”, the function of the “exhibition pavilion of the service platform for commercial cooperation between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries”, turning Macao into a “starting point” for Lusophone products in the access to the Great Bay market. Sam Hou Fai also said that various types of conventions and exhibitions will be held, "in order to create more scenarios for the deepening of connectivity between the nine cities of the great bay and the Portuguese -speaking countries."</description><pubDate>2025-04-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Planned study on the extension of the metro network on the peninsula</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/planeado-estudo-sobre-extensao-da-rede-de-metro-na-peninsula/</link><description>The government will do a study of the extension of the lightweight meter network on the peninsula, the chief executive said yesterday, without, however, to advance details. According to this year, this year will also be made an interleaved assessment of the execution of the Metro contract. On the other hand, in relation to public housing said the policies will be perfected. Regarding the land, Sam Hou Fai indicated that the government will revise the calculation basis of the concession award
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Later this year, the government will “elaborate a preliminary study regarding the extension of the light metro network on the Macao Peninsula,” said the chief executive yesterday. Not long ago, it should be recalled, it was known that the study on the viability of the extension of the East Line to the Qingmao border post concluded that the project is viable, despite the various challenges. Sam Hou Fai did not go into detail yesterday on the subject.
However, and still in relation to the light meter, the leader of the MSAR added that also throughout this year will be made an interchange evaluation on the execution of the metro contract. Since the issue of transport is a concern for Sam Hou Fai, the chief executive said he will reinforce the regulation of bus services and optimize careers. "We will provide special bus service service in major festivities, in order to drain the flow of visitors and relieve transportation pressure," he said.
As regards taxis, he said the number will be increased “depending on transport needs”, and will be studied “the feasibility of introducing the online transport service”.
On the other hand, and in relation to housing, Sam Hou Fai said the policies will be perfected. "We will review and optimize housing policies, adjusting the plans to offer different types of housing, in order to better respond to the housing needs of residents with different levels of performance. We will rationally try to balance the relationship between supply and demand in the real estate market, in order to promote their stable and healthy development," he said.
As for social housing, it provides that the construction in lots A5, A6, A10 and A11 of Zone A of the new landfills is completed in 2026 and 2027. In this context, it has promised that the government will strive to “reduce the average waiting time”.
Regarding the economic housing of lots A1, A2, A3, A4 and A12, also in Zone A, estimates that phaseously completed in 2025 and 2026, while those of lots B5, B7, B8, B11 and B12 are planned for 2027 and 2028. As, evaluate the feasibility of the economic housing exchange regime, ”he said. At the press conference, Sam Hou Fai said he had a "open" stance on this issue of the exchange of economic houses.
Sam Hou Fai also played on the issue of residence for the elderly. In this context, it indicated that "the admission of the candidacies for the use" of the residence will be regularized, which "will be provided to the qualified elderly, in an orderly manner." In addition, "the long -term demand will be studied for private housing for the elderly."
 
Urban planning and land use
On the other hand, he said he intends to “reinforce the management” of Macau Urban Renewal, S.A., as well as accelerate the promotion of existing transformation projects. In this field, the chief executive also said that the revision of the legal regime of urban renewal is planned.
In the report, it is possible to read that, as for urban planning, it will be continued to promote the elaboration of the various zones of the Director Plan, as well as the planning work of the community neighborhoods. The government will also seek “to conclude as soon as possible, the study of updating on the Urban Plan of Seac Pai Van, Coloane (east side).
Regarding the “rational use of land and improving land management”, Sam said that this year the government will “review the concession award base, rationally adjusting the cost of land use”.
 
Mandar will have “International Tourist and Cultural District”
In order to “further enrich the content of the World Center for Tourism and Leisure, boost the construction of 'a base',” the government will strive to build an “integrated tourist and cultural neighborhood, establishing cultural facilities of relevant, international influence, high and iconic patterns”. In terms of its nature, the neighborhood "is characterized by being an area where high quality cultural complexes are concentrated at the international level." According to the reporting lines of government action, with regard to configuration, "it should be noted that it will include several iconic cultural complexes." As for the function, it will integrate cultural, tourist and commercial elements, “highlighting the Macao National Museum of Culture, the Macao International Center for Performative Arts and the International Museum of Contemporary Art”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Rejoice for social benefits but “we need to discuss other topics”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/regozijo-pelos-beneficios-sociais-mas-e-preciso-discutir-outros-temas/</link><description>The lines of government action released by the chief executive generally pleased deputies and members of associations. However, they consider that there are domains in which government intervention will have to be more effective, and it is necessary to discuss in more detail other topics, such as employment
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Generally speaking, reactions to lines of government action (LAG) are satisfactory, although for some of those who spoke to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the benefits have not fully reached the ambitions they advocated.
The issue of increasing the monthly pension of the elderly, which went from 3,740 to 3,900 patacas, as well as the improvement of the annual subsidy, which is now from 10,000 patacas for the same age group as the population, deserves a positive analysis of the President of the Association of Retirees, Reformed and Pensioners of Macao (Apomac). Jorge Fão is said to be "surprised by the positive" with the lag, recognizing that "did not tell that the chief executive of almost everything the elderly needed."
However, it points out that Apomac's aspirations were a little higher. "Of course, what we wanted in all and that we consider to be ideal for a better life of the elderly has not been obtained as a whole, but I am generally satisfied with what was achieved, which means we were not forgotten," he stresses.
Jorge Fão points out that it was a good start to the mandate of Sam Hou Fai, "because naturally older people are grateful."
Nick Lei, deputy to the Legislative Assembly, says LAG focused on benefit measures for the population, public administration reform, industrial diversification and development of the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin.
In the balance of the lag announced by Sam Hou Fai, the deputy believes that, for local society, what caught the most attention was the part related to social benefit measures. But, it notes that "the proportions of increase have a disparity in relation to public expectations."
For Nick Law, the executive "must have pondered this year's financial revenues, which have so far also have a disparity over forecasts," so "he has tried to establish a balance between the financial situation and the improvement of social benefits."
The deputy argues that "there are still many points that should draw more attention, such as employment, for example." "LAG reported that it is necessary to monitor and control the number of non -resident workers, or performing jobs, but in this part I do not see new measures," he notes.
Generally speaking, Nick Law admits that "the content of LAG includes balanced aspects", however, he considers that "we need to discuss in detail other topics in the next debates, such as the satellite casinos and the workers in the active."
The director of the Institute of International Academic Investigations (Macao), stressed that "it is positive to increase social benefits for the well-being of the population", hoping that the government will continue to improve these aspects, "relieving the difficult commercial situation."
However, Kou Seng Man warns that “many residents consider that the level of reinforcement of measurements is not sufficient”, giving the example of the monthly subsidy of 1,500 patacas for children's care. "This will not be enough to encourage birth, while the proportion of increased marriage allowance is very reduced," he says.
Regarding the SMEs, which benefit from a 4%interest bonus, the academic questions the reason for no kind support for citizens who have to pay their mortgage loans. “The government did not explain why,” he attests.
Analyzing the increased prices of essential goods and housing, Kou Seng Man expects the government to readjust the amount of social benefits, "in order to provide precise help to women, children, young people, the elderly and groups of the most vulnerable population, thus promoting social inclusion."</description><pubDate>2025-04-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CCAC “articulated” with Beijing in the fight against corruption</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ccac-articulado-pequim-combate-a-corrupcao/</link><description>The authorities of Macao and the interior of China must firmly promote cooperation in the anti-corruption struggle, defended the commissioner against corruption, to Ieong Seong, on a visit to Beijing-centered on the exchange of the construction of a full society and the rule of law
 
Macao cannot be a “paradise of refuge” for the corrupt, he stressed the commissioner against corruption, to Ieong Seong, at a meeting in Beijing with Deputy Minister of Public Security, Chen Siyuan. In this sense, “the authorities of Macao and the interior of China must firmly promote cooperation in the context of corruption,” he said, according to a statement issued by his office.
In turn, the Deputy Minister of Public Security stressed that the interior of China has “strict demands” regarding case investigation procedures, and the whole process is subject to proper supervision, and will strive to combat transionic crimes. Chen Siyuan also promised to continue supporting Macao's Commissioner against Corruption (CCAC) in exchange and training with the public security agencies in the interior of China.
This meeting was inserted in the context of the visit that a CCAC delegation held Beijing, to foster the exchange in the context of the construction of a whole society and the rule of law.
The program includes a meeting with the Office Subdirector for Hong Kong and Macau affairs with the Council of State, Nong Rong, which encouraged the MSar to respond to President Xi Jinping's “high expectations and demands” with “concrete and entrepreneurial actions”. According to the same note, Ieong Seong asserted that the CCAC staff will always keep in mind the spirit consecrated in the important speeches of Xi Jinping, "firmly fulfilling their attributions in the context of combating corruption and the provision of justice." According to the Commissioner, CCAC has also proceeded to an early planning for the next elections for the Legislative Assembly and “is well prepared”, to ensure the effective implementation of the “Macao Patriots” principle, as well as justice, impartiality and the integrity of elections.
In another meeting, with Zhang Jun, president of the Supreme Popular Court, Ieong Seong expressed the desire to maintain a close connection with the judicial organs of the interior of China, namely at the level of combating corruption and capturing fugitives and recovery of assets, and promised commitment to the area of ​​courts, in order to raise administrative efficiency and level of governance in the field.
The fight against corruption was once again approached at a meeting with the National Supervision Commission subdirector, which was willing to cooperate with CCAC and made a presentation on the measures adopted on “control of formalism, bureaucratism, hedonism and extravagance”, without forgetting “the current situation of investigation and simultaneous correction of antitetic practices and corruption problems”. In turn, Ieong Seong said CCAC "will articulate with the homeland to promote the policy and objective of fighting corruption -" no one dare, can and want to be corrupt. "
In general, these ideas were also underlined in a meeting with Supreme Popular Attorney Attorney General Ying Yong, who said he expects to reinforce the exchange with CCAC in combating transionic crimes and the punishment of corruption, providing a stronger legal guarantee for socioeconomic development in the interior of China and Macao, namely the large bay.
The CCAC delegation also visited the Government Services Center of the Municipality of Beijing, to find out the situation of the centralized treatment of the administrative formalities of the entire Municipality and the functioning of the electronic services that make life easier for citizens.</description><pubDate>2025-04-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Government will deliver eight proposals to the</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-entregara-oito-propostas-de-lei-a-al/</link><description>This year will receive a total of eight law proposals submitted by the government, including a change to the cultural heritage safeguard law. In addition, it was revealed that priority will be given to the beginning of the revision of the Code of Administrative Procedure and the Code of Civil Procedure
 
Throughout this year, the government plans to submit a total of eight bills to the Legislative Assembly (AL), the executive head, Sam Hou Fai, revealed in the presentation of the Governing Action Lines (LAG) to 2025.
Among the planned diplomas, there is a proposal to change the law of safeguarding cultural heritage. In addition, two other proposals aim to amended to the Law on the Creation of the Institute for Municipal Affairs, the General Staff of Teaching Personnel of Private Schools of Non -Superior Education and the Statute of Private Schools of Non -Superior Education.
Already the list of new legal regimes that should arrive this year to the hemiciclo includes the regime for the regulation of certain activities; the Restoration and Beverages and Related Establishments Law; Advertising Acting Law; Gold and Platinum Commercialization Law; and the legal regime for the exercise of activity of private health care institutions.
On the other hand, during the presentation of the lag, Sam Hou Fai said that this year, there will be priority to the beginning of the review work of the Code of Administrative Procedure and the Code of Civil Procedure. "With the use of professionals' participation, different specialized groups will be created to study the revision of codes," he said.
In addition, according to the Chief Executive, in addition to reinforcing judicial cooperation and exchange with the interior of China and Hong Kong, the authorities will celebrate with Kazakhstan the “agreement on the transfer of convicted persons”, the “agreement to the delivery of escape” and the “agreement to mutual judiciary in criminal matters”.
At the same time, the Government will strive to complete the negotiation and conclusion of agreements on these articles with the Philippines and Angola, as well as to promote negotiations with Vietname regarding a agreement on mutual judicial aid, Sam Hou Fai revealed.</description><pubDate>2025-04-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief confirms visit to Portugal after May elections</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-confirma-visita-portugal-apos-eleicoes-de-maio/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai confirmed yesterday that the first visit as Chief Executive will be to Portugal, and that it will happen after the legislative elections, which are scheduled for May 18
 
The head of the executive said yesterday that he will visit Portugal after the legislatures of May 18, but did not offer any solution to restrictions on the Portuguese residence, saying only that there were no changes to the law and that the rights of the Portuguese remain consecrated in the basic law.
Sam Hou Fai said he will visit Portugal, “during the first half, after the elections, when the situation is already stable”, in reference to the formation of the new Portuguese government. Remember that Foreign Minister Paulo Rangel said after a meeting with Sam Hou Fai in Macao that the chief executive would visit Portugal "immediately before August or in September."
Yesterday, at the Press Conference after the presentation of the Governing Action Lines, Sam Hou Fai stressed that the visit to Portugal will be the first trip to foreigners since taking office. “It is a testimony of the good and long relationship between Macao and Portugal,” said Sam Hou Fai, the first leader of the mandate that dominates the Portuguese language.
At the end of March, when asked about restrictions on the Portuguese residence, Rangel said he spoke to Sam Hou Fai "on all the issues that are relevant to the relationship between Portugal and the MSAR." "But, as it is a dialogue that is underway, I have a duty to give the opportunity we can, with the questions that have been raised from one part and the other, now we have space and time to build solutions," he added.
Rangel said that the “follow-up of dialogue” enacted with Sam Hou Fai will take place at a meeting of the Portugal-Raem Joint Commission, “which will be organized in principle in the second half” in Macao.
Macau has not accepted since August 2023 new requests for residence for Portuguese, for the “exercise of specialized technical functions”, allowing only justification of family meeting or previous connection to the territory. The guidelines eliminate a practice signed after Macao's transition in 1999.
The Portuguese remains the issuance of a “Blue Card”, limited authorization to the labor bond, without the benefits of residents, namely at the level of health or education. The only alternative to guarantee BIR now has a candidacy for recent qualified frame capture programs, admitted Sam Hou Fai.
"Whatever nationality, if they meet the requirements of law, they are always welcome," said the chief executive. Still, Sam Hou Fai has promised to evaluate the programs, "optimize and find qualified pictures suitable for Macao's needs."
The 2021 censuses indicate more than 2,200 people born in Portugal living in Macau. The last estimate given to Lusa by the Portuguese Consulate-General pointed to about 155,000 Portuguese passport people between residents of Macau and Hong Kong.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-04-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Photographs with memory at António Leong's “Déjà Vu”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/fotografias-memoria-deja-vu-de-antonio-leong/</link><description>About two and a half dozen black and white photographs will be displayed by António Leong at Creative on April 22. The show “Déjà vu” intends, according to the author, “give the feeling that things in Macau have changed a lot, but the memories remain”. The images were captured between 2020 and the first months of this year, fundamentally portraying everyday life
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Memories of Macao, landscapes and everyday life, fill the exhibition “Déjà Vu” by local artist António Leong, with about two and a half dozen works produced between 2020 and the beginning of 2025.
With his works, the author intends to "bring that feeling that things have changed a lot, but memories remain," he said to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, adding that "in an instant we have a click as if we had seen a certain image for some time."
The photographs are all in black and white, which happens for the first time in António Leong's exhibitions. "Without color, the sensation is stronger, because in my opinion the color diminishes this feeling of the 'déjà vu', and so I try to remember something," he stresses.
The exhibition will take place between April 22 and May 12 and the inauguration ceremony will take place on April 24, Thursday, between 18:30 and 20:30.
In the presentation of the show, Creative - Macao Creative Industries Center, which will be the place of exhibition, states that “photography plays a key role in the documentation of reality with the least prejudice, but the aesthetics of an image is significantly shaped by the perspectives and angles of various photographers”.
Of the “intricate details of their architecture to the vibrant tapestry of people's daily interactions, images can incorporate both familiarity nostalgia and the excitement of the city's discovery”, stresses the same note, adding that in António Leong's exhibition, “each photograph acts as a portal, capturing fleeting and stagnant moments that resonate with the macao essence”.
Creative tells these images "bring us memories of past incidents, encounters and personal narratives in which Macau serves as a backdrop, fostering dialogue not only among exhibitors, but also with the public."
Thus, “Déjà vu” is interpreted as “a feeling of phenomenon, as if we were finding something we have already witnessed before, and which is uninterruptedly evoked in this exhibition through the clicks of the photographer's Chamber Lens shutter”.
Each photograph of this collection captivated the artist's attention for long periods, "inspiring a deep feeling of admiration and calm." “The lines, shapes and silhouettes used aim to convey the supernatural nature of these themes in the context of our contemporary world,” says António Leong.
The author, born in Macao, fell in love with photography for many years, capturing the sole Chinese and Western culture of this city through the objective. António began to share his work in 2012 and created the “Antonius Photoscript” page on Facebook.
Through this page, the photographer participated in various photographic exhibitions that promote Macao tourism worldwide, as well as cooperative with different charity organizations and artists in various types of photographic activities, serving as an instructor and speaker to share their techniques and photographic experiences.
In 2021, António Leong and the Macao Cultural Catholic Association presented jointly the exhibition “discovering the beauty of everyday life”, and in 2024 the “via pulchritudinis: Macao Catholic World Heritage”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ballet “The Adventures of Alice” on display at Grand Lisboa Palace</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ballet-as-aventuras-de-alice-em-exibicao-grand-lisboa-palace/</link><description>The show “The Adventures of Alice” is on display at the Grand Lisboa Palace, with double sessions scheduled until May 4. Choreographed and directed by the Artistic Director of the Hong Kong Ballet (HKB) Septime Webre, the production features a new and lively score by composer NG Cheuk-Yin, Cirque Du Soleil's costumes, special stage effects and an intimate audience participation.
The “Show” is inspired by the acclaimed Ballet of Webre “Alice (In Wonderland)”, 2018. Since its debut in Hong Kong, has been invited to act in Beijing, Singapore and USA.
Now, the organization, by the Macau Game Society (SJM), presents a version inspired especially for Macau, on a totally immersive 360 ​​-degree stage at the 1st -floor atrium of Grand Lisboa Palace, with state -of -the -art lighting, “surround” sound and projection effects.
To support this production in residence, SJM held several open auditions earlier this year to recruit Macao dancers and the vicinity of the Great Bay. "The initiative not only provides vocational training, experience of action and development of skills to aspiring artists, but also encourages new talents for the region's ballet, further contributing to the cultural vitality of the area," said SJM.
The next shows of “The Adventures of Alice” will take place on the 18th, 19th and 20th of this month and May 2, 3 and 4, always with two daily screenings, at 14h00 and 16h00.
The public can also explore the maze and picturesque outdoor secret garden with the facilities of “Alice’s Enchanteed Garden”, opened on the 3rd floor of Grand Lisboa Palace. On the other hand, by June 30, Alice -inspired cakes and drinks will be available on the resort's “Lounge Lounge”. “Extravagant characters, such as Alice and Queen of Cups, will make special appearances throughout the resort and will interact with the guests in joyful parades,” SJM said.</description><pubDate>2025-04-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM and Galaxy celebrate creative view of the new generation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/upm-galaxy-celebram-visao-criativa-da-nova-geracao/</link><description>“The Star Scrolls” is the name of an open exhibition to the public in the Galaxyart space, which results from a collaboration between Galaxy and the Macao Polytechnic University (UPM) and which brings together creative teachers, current and alumni at the School of Arts and Design of the educational institution. The show presents works of art from more than two dozen authors and will take place until April 25, portraying an artistic trip that unites traditional aesthetics with contemporary expression.
The Chinese title of the exhibition, "Xinghan", is a poetic term for "The Galaxy", symbolizing the cosmos without limits of artistic creativity. "Visitors will watch a charming interaction between the rich textures of oil paintings and the fluid dynamism of paint salpics, as well as an inspiring dialogue between traditional Chinese landscape painting and avant -garde digital art," according to a statement by Galaxy Entertainment.
The same note adds that the exhibition "is an immersive journey that invites viewers to explore evolutionary interpretations of cultural heritage through the eyes of contemporary artists of Macao."
Galaxyart will also organize thematic workshops on Saturday afternoon. In addition, also on April 19, a special session will be held “Share about Star Trinks”, in which former UPM artists will talk about their creative philosophies and the vision of the evolution of the mashed artistic industry.
Simultaneously to this exhibition, another local artist, Cristina Vinhas, releases the joblery collection “Nature, My Muse - Art Jewellery”. Inspired by the splendor of nature, Cristina Vinhas creates pieces that mix western design contemporary with eastern elegance.
With a career of over two decades, the artist created nearly ten series of jewelry, decorations and pieces of glass art.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-04-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Anime” inspires street promotion in Tokyo</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/anime-inspira-promocao-de-rua-em-toquio/</link><description>Macau tourism services will launch a street promotion on Thursday at the famous Akihabara commercial zone in Tokyo
 
The expansion of international markets is based on another street promotion of Macau Tourism Services (STD), now in the capital of Japan. The event includes a seminar, contact bags and exchange visits and aims to stimulate the interest of the Japanese to visit Macau.
The campaign will be held for four days, from April 17 to 20, in Akihabara, the famous center of electronic products and the “Anime” comic book culture of Tokyo. Akihabara's transformation into a “Macao Pop-Up Zone”, with the combination of “Anime” culture, special travel promotions, limited joint brand products and Mak Mak memories, among others, will be able to wake up to visit Macau, believes STD.
The promotion has as its starting point the "anime", with the collaboration of intellectual property designers (PI). Tou Chon Wai, creator of the Macau Tourism Mascot, will be present to unravel the history of the Black Householder “Mak Mak”.
STD also cooperates with Macao cultural and creative designers and Macau Pass, along with the famous Japan PI team “Ghost in the Shell SAC2045”, to be part of the main stage design of the event and launch a Macau Pass card version with thematic animation elements.
The promotion will also integrate an exhibitor dedicated to the classic Japanese comic book character “Kamen Rider”, where he will not miss his iconic motorcycle. "Toei Company", creator of "Kamen Rider", and a company from Macao will also launch an official wine with the brand "Kamen Rider".
So that customers can feel the environment and customs of Macao, until May 30, the building agency Histo Japan, in Ginza, Tokyo, is fully decorated with the theme of Macao: Portuguese -style tile walls, iconic points and decorations of Rooster Barcelos de Portugal.
In addition to the street campaign, and along with the Institute for Commerce and Investment Promotion, tour operators and the International Airport Society, STD will stimulate cooperation with Japan's tour operators tomorrow through a presentation session on “Tourism + Conventions and Exhibitions” and contact bags.
It is also scheduled, with tourist operators from Macau, a visit to the city of Kamakura, with the aim of deepening the exchange and cooperation with the places of the “East Asia Culture City” in Japan.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-04-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Open new phase of support for community tourism</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/aberta-nova-fase-de-apoio-ao-turismo-comunitario/</link><description>A Direcção dos Serviços de Turismo abriu uma segunda fase de candidaturas ao programa de apoio para o turismo comunitário. As entidades interessadas podem concorrer até 25 de Abril
 
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) launched a second phase of applications to the 2025 Financial Support Program for Community Tourism “Traveling by Macau”, which takes place until 17:30 on April 25. Candidate projects must be held between July 1 and December 31. Services provide for a response to the appreciation of requests in June.
Applications can be submitted through the user account of the Platform for Companies and Associations, on the website of the Financial Support Program for 2025 of STD. Each requesting entity may submit up to three requests, with the requests submitted by the same entity between August and September 2024.
According to the services, the Tourism Fund has established specific evaluation criteria for each financial support plan, based on the principle of selecting projects “deserving subsidy”, assessing and carefully analyzing all requests.
STD aims to “encourage associations to plan innovative and diverse tourist activities”, says the statement, “to further promote tourism and consumption in community neighborhoods”. The program aims to take advantage of the various tourist resources, combining “cultural, sports, festive, entertainment and exhibitions”, in order to support the development of “tourism+”, through the active participation of traders, and to guide tourism consumption to community neighborhoods.
The first phase of applications for the 2025 Financial Support Program for Community Tourism “Traveling by Macau”, Gastronomic Promotion “Macao Flavors” and Maritime Tourism “Fun on the Coastal Waterfront” took place between August and September last year. Of the 43 approved projects, which include guided tours, fairs, gastronomic production and boat tours, six have been completed until March 31, and the rest will be launched successively later this year, STD said.</description><pubDate>2025-04-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Banco Citic launches scholarships for students from business schools</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/banco-citic-lanca-bolsas-para-alunos-de-escolas-de-negocios/</link><description>In partnership with the Macao University of Science and Technology (UCTM), the Banco Citic International China (CNCBI) Macao branch (CNCBI) announced, in celebration of its 20 years of existence, the creation of a scholarship program, worth 150,000 Patacas to assign over three years. According to the bank's statement, the agreement aims to “reward five students from academically solid business schools”, recommended annually by a UCTM selection panel. Each selected student will receive 10,000 patacas. CNCBI's vice president said this joint initiative illustrates an "effort to demonstrate the bank's support to education in Macao, as well as its social responsibility commitment." Li Haixia stated that, through industry-academia collaboration, the bank seeks to motivate aspiring students to explore the financial sector and “contribute to the driving force behind the" fintech "advances, throughout the great bay. In turn, Joseph Hun-Wei Lee asserted that UCTM "is committed to cultivating global talents with an international perspective." The university president assured that “collaboration with CNCBI will provide students with more opportunities and practical resources”, strengthening research and industry-academia integration for proper and diversified development of Macau's economy.</description><pubDate>2025-04-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Latin America Exalts Vargas Legacy Llosa</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/america-latina-exalta-legado-de-vargas-llosa/</link><description>EPA12031162 (File) Peruvian-Spanish Mario Vargas Llosa poses for pictures in the Library of the French Academy (Academie Francaise) In Paris, France, 09 February 2023 (Reissued 14 April 2025). Nobel Prize-Winning Author Mario Vargas Llosa Died at the Age of 89 at His Home in Lima On 13 April 2025, His Children Reported Through Social Media.  EPA/TERESA SUAREZ



Several current and former heads of state of Latin America expressed regret for the Peruvian-Spanish novelist Mario Vargas Llosa, who died at the age of 89, highlighting the legacy of the Nobel Prize in 2010. Vargas Llosa died on Sunday in Lima, where they lived since 2022, they informed their children on social networks, adding that, respecting the father's desire, there will be no ceremony. public ”of farewell.
Peruvian President Dina Boluarte expressed deep regret for the death of Vargas Llosa, describing him as a "universal and distinguished writer of the Nobel Prize for Literature." "Its intellectual genius and its vast set of works will remain an eternal legacy for future generations," said the presidency of Peru.
The Peruvian Congress expressed similar feelings, sending its "deepest condolences to family, friends and readers of the Nobel Prize winner."
One of the first Latin American political leaders to react to the writer's death was former Uruguayan President Luis Lacalle Pou (2020-2025), for whom "Vargas Llosa has left his mark in many aspects of life, always remaining faithful to himself." Personally, Pou said that he always liked the generosity of Vargas Llosa.
The ancient Colombian presidents Álvaro Uribe (2002-2010) and Iván Duque (2018-2022) also said goodbye to the novelist, whom they called "Master." “Leave us your work, your admiration and your example. Leave us a way for the future,” added Uribe, on the social network X. “Mario Vargas Llosa's death fills me with sadness. I had the honor to enjoy your friendship and share unforgettable moments, listening to your encyclopedic knowledge, your overwhelming simplicity and refined humor,” said Duque.
Venezuelan opposition leader María Corina Machado expressed solidarity with the writer's family and highlighted her “unmatched legacy” in the defense of freedom in Latin America and the world.
The Gabo Foundation, founded by his friend and later rival, Gabriel García Márquez, also lamented the author's death, who described as "a master of the Spanish-language narrative and a key figure of Latin American literature."
Born in Arequipa, on March 28, 1936, Jorge Mario Pedro Vargas Llosa, was also a politician, journalist, essayist and university professor. He was one of the main writers of his generation, to the point that some critics consider that he had an impact and an international audience like no other of the Latin America boom.
Early on, he began to engage politically, first as a supporter of Fidel Castro and the Cuban Revolution, later as a defender of the most conservative, capitalist liberal democracy, even running for Peru's presidency in 1990 for a center-right coalition against Alberto Fujimori (1990-2000).
However, despite his political and social involvement, Vargas Llosa confessed a day that he would like to be remembered by writing and work. He began in writing influenced by the existentialism of Jean-Paul Sartre and his fame was soon projected with his second novel, “The City and the Dogs”, edited in 1963, which added other hits such as “The Green House” (1966), the monumental “Conversation N'A Cathedral” (1969), “Aunt Julia and the Write” and “The Festa de Chibo” (2000).
The Nobel Prize jury of the 2010 literature justified Vargas Llosa's choice for being the holder of a writing that “cartography of the structures of power” and a work that reveals “scathing images of resistance, revolt and the failures of the individual”.
In addition to novels, including comedy, mystery, history and politics, Vargas Llosa also wrote theater, rehearsal, memories, literary criticism and journalistic texts, collaborating with newspapers such as Spanish El País, Brazilian Estadão and France Presse. Some of his literary works were adapted to the cinema, as is the case of "Aunt Julia and the Writer", "Pantaleão and the Visitors" and "The Chibo Festival".
 
JTM with Lusa and International Agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>