<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Family debts in the Macao SAR generate “concern” and require “prudence”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dividas-das-familias-na-raem-geram-preocupacao-exigem-prudencia/</link><description>At the end of 2024, the debt rate of Macau households corresponded to almost 82% of the Macao SAR's GDP, according to a study released by the Monetary Authority. Despite having recovered from a rate of 167% in 2022, economist António José Félix Pontes told this newspaper that the value remains “worrying”. In turn, Carlos Cid Álvares, president of the BNU Executive Committee, said that the indicator “requires prudence”, although he does not consider it at an “alarming” level. In the study, interest rate variability is identified as the main vulnerability of the Macao SAR financial system.
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
The debt rate of Macau families fell from 166.8% to 81.8% of the MSAR's GDP between 2022 and 2024, according to a study released by the Macau Monetary Authority (AMCM). To the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, economist António José Félix Pontes described this value as “worrying”. Carlos Cid Álvares, president of the Executive Committee of Banco Nacional Ultramarino (BNU), said he considers that the “level is not alarming in absolute terms, but requires prudence”.
“Above 80%, 90%, means that we are approaching dangerous, alarming levels”, warned Félix Pontes, recalling the 2008 financial crisis. “Household debt in Portugal was close to 100% of Portuguese GDP and, in the USA, this indicator exceeded 95% of GDP”.
In the “Econometric Analysis of Household Debt in Macau and its Implications for Financial Stability”, H. Y. Huang, from AMCM's Research and Statistics Department, points to interest rate variability as the greatest vulnerability of Macau's financial system.
"The pataca, as we know, is indexed to the Hong Kong dollar, which, in turn, is linked to the US dollar. Any changes in the exchange rate or US monetary policy will have an impact on the financial stability and liquidity of Macau banks, with the real margin for Macau being small, in terms of exchange rate fluctuations and capital outflows", explained Félix Pontes. On the other hand, “the relative good news is that interest rates are in a downward phase”.
Carlos Cid Álvares also recognizes that US monetary policies and, subsequently, interest rate changes “do not always reflect local economic reality”. “But, in an increasingly globalized world, economies inevitably end up influencing each other, leading to identical economic cycles”, he says.
In contrast to countries that adopted the euro and “lost the sovereignty to define their own monetary policy”, the Macao SAR can still take “specific measures, such as increasing the amount of money in circulation, to mitigate local effects”. “However, these measures are not sustainable in the long term, because the peg to the US dollar creates a structural limit”, explained the BNU CEO.
 
Critical indicators
Regarding a first warning sign, regarding the household debt rate, for Félix Pontes, “there is no magic number”. “To make an adequate assessment, several factors must be taken into account, such as the rate of debt growth, the ratio of ‘debt service’ and ‘disposable income’, the savings rate and the ‘bubbles’ of certain assets”, such as real estate, argued the economist.
Cid Álvares pointed to “the increase in payment delays” as a potential initial trigger for a worsening of the economic situation. However, he guarantees, “banks closely monitor default ratios in home loans, consumer loans and credit cards”. Furthermore, “the banking system has reinforced control mechanisms, such as the debt center, which allows responsibilities to be assessed before new concessions”, he highlighted.
"At a macroeconomic level, the evolution of non-performing loans, combined with indicators such as unemployment, inflation and expectations of rising interest rates, constitute factors that could impact an increase in defaults. A simultaneous increase in these factors has impacts at an economic level and possible deterioration of families' ability to manage debt", warned Cid Álvares.
Félix Pontes also believes that “the main systemic risk for Macau's financial sector lies in a combination of interconnected external shocks, such as, for example, the occurrence of a liquidity crisis, associated with a serious recession in the gaming sector, if there is a new pandemic, and disruptive geopolitical measures, as has been happening with the new American administration”.
From his perspective, “a situation of this type would exceed the response capacity of local authorities, the Central Government and the financial sector”. “This systemic risk for local banks may also result from the contagion effect arising from a crisis of confidence in the financial system of the Greater Bay Area”, he warns.
The economist also pointed out the exposure to the real estate market in Mainland China, “whose situation is still in doubt”. Félix Pontes also outlined other hypothetical scenarios such as a regional liquidity crisis due to the application of geopolitical sanctions, problems arising from a high concentration in the gaming industry and resulting from a major slowdown, cyber attacks and the continuous loss of qualified professionals.
“In reality, the current stability that results from the reading and interpretation of Macau’s macroeconomic data may ‘mask’ some problems or weaknesses in the banking network, typical of a small economy such as Macau, open to the outside and with a high concentration in the gaming industry”, summarized Félix Pontes.
 
Savings grew and loans contracted
In the latest Macau Monetary and Financial Stability Review report, AMCM indicated that Macau's savings rate rose 2.6 percentage points to 59.5%, in the first three quarters of 2025, compared to the same period of the previous year. This value represented more than double the global average of 26.2%.
"In Macau, as in Hong Kong, the family savings rate has always registered high values ​​and above the global average. This is a very interesting issue and one that can translate into an ambiguous symptom. It can be a sign of responsible financial planning, but it can also reflect some fear and distrust regarding the future of the economy", acknowledged Félix Pontes.
“The household savings rate must be analyzed together with other indicators, namely the unemployment rate, the evolution of bank credit and the global macroeconomic context”.
Conversely, loans decreased by 0.4%, compared to the end of December 2024, standing at 1.02 billion patacas. For Carlos Cid Álvares, the drop in credit granting resulted “more from a lack of demand than from an excessively prudent stance on the part of banks”.
As he explained, “there are several elements that explain this retraction”, including “the uncertainty of families and companies, which tend to postpone investments, the fall in the real estate market, with little supply of new units, the difficulties of small and medium-sized companies (SMEs), the conclusion of large tourism and leisure projects and the scarcity of new structuring projects by the private sector”.
 
Latent effects of the pandemic
Data from AMCM indicate that non-performing loans fell 11.6% over the last year, to 49.7 billion patacas. “In short, part of the current bad credit is still a reflection of the pandemic, but there are additional economic factors that worsen it”. “Today the economy has already recovered and unemployment has returned to levels similar to the pre-Covid period”, stated Cid Álvares.
"However, this recovery is uneven. SMEs, as well as sectors focused on local consumption, face strong competition from Zhuhai and Hengqin, where prices are more competitive and online shopping habits are growing. This could weaken local entrepreneurs and workers", he warned.
For Cid Álvares, another factor to take into account is the real estate market. "Before, families in difficulty could more easily sell assets to alleviate financial pressure. Now, with low demand and falling prices, this solution has become less effective."
"The good news is that Macau's banks have already set up adequate provisions to cover potential losses. The expectation is that, in the medium and long term, the default ratio will decrease", he projected.</description><pubDate>2026-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>6 million border crossings expected for Chinese New Year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/esperadas-6-milhoes-de-passagens-nas-fronteiras-ano-novo-chines/</link><description>Between the 15th and 23rd of February, during the Lunar New Year holidays, Macau could see a daily average of more than 670,000 border crossings, the CPSP predicts, anticipating that the peak of entries and exits will occur on the 19th. With plans to respond to the flow of people ready, the authorities also guarantee that they will reinforce inspection personnel in the most touristic places

The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) forecasts for the nine days of Chinese New Year (from 15 to 23 February) are that the borders will register between 6 million and 6.21 million entries and exits, that is, a daily average of more than 670 thousand border crossings. This was what the deputy head of the CPSP Operations Planning Department said yesterday.
Lei Tak Fai also highlighted that the corporation estimates that the 3rd day of the lunar calendar (February 19) will mark the “peak” in the volume of entries and exits at the borders. On that day, there could be around 780 thousand entries and exits. According to him, the police authorities “have already prepared several measures to control the flow of people to be applied at the main borders”, at the same time, logistics personnel will be mobilized to support frontline work.
The same CPSP official also indicated that several counters will be opened to increase the efficiency of border crossings and divert the flow of people.
The Police also defined contingency plans, together with the customs inspection authorities of Mainland China and Hong Kong, continued Lei Tak Fai.
With regard to the city, the authorities have also defined specific action plans and several measures, “including the reinforcement of inspection staff, who will closely monitor the flow of people in popular tourist spots”. Lei Tak Fai said, on the other hand, that taking into account the implementation of pedestrian zones in the old town of Taipa and Rua de Nossa Senhora do Amparo, the police will reinforce the level of patrol and implement measures to control the flow of people in a timely manner, “in order to guarantee good order in the flow of people and vehicles”.
Regarding large-scale celebration activities, he indicated that the CPSP will create a command center at the activity sites to “ensure the smooth and safe execution” of the various initiatives.
At a conference, Chan Weng Hei, deputy head of the Customs Inspection Department of the Border Posts of the Customs Service (SA), stated that the Macau and Hengqin authorities have already determined a joint operations mechanism. Specifically, at the Hengqin Border Post, a space with temporary border crossing facilities will be activated during peak hours.
On the other hand, Chan Weng Hei said that the SA and CPSP have defined contingency plans, such as opening more lanes for vehicles during peak periods.
 
Strengthening transport capacity
On the same occasion, Un Kit Ling, deputy head of the Transport Management Division of the Traffic Affairs Services Directorate (DSAT), called on taxi drivers to “support diversified payment methods, including electronic payment”.
Furthermore, he stressed that traffic diversion measures will be reinforced. He also indicated that, in total, eight daytime routes (3, 21A, 22, 23, 26A, 32, 33 and MT4) will extend service hours from February 16th until 01:00 in the morning of the following day. Routes 3X and 50, in turn, run until 1am the following day between the 17th and 19th.
The two bus operators will continue to operate seasonal routes: 3BX, 17T, 21AT, 26AT and 101XSo, while route 25AX will operate on holidays and extend the timetable.
To improve the waiting environment at the “Praça das Portas do Cerco” stop, an adjacent fenced space will be provisionally made available until February 22nd for the expansion of the waiting area, thus facilitating the circulation and accommodation of passengers.
On the part of the Directorate of Tourism Services (DST), Tam Si Weng, deputy head of the Public Relations Division, noted that the authorities encourage tourists to check the status of the flow of people at 114 tourist attractions, through the page “Intelligent application for forecasting the flow of visitors”.
Tam Si Weng also recalled that DST organizes, in addition to the Parade, drone and fireworks shows, the “Gala a galop no ZAPE” initiative, which will take place in the area between Rua de Cantão and Rua de Beijing. Between today and March 1st, there will be facilities for taking photos, shows and games, as well as promotions in stores in the area.
On the other hand, the organization coordinated with a sea tour operator to launch a night tour at sea during the period of the Year of the Horse Celebration Parade (19th and 23rd February, and 3rd March).
A representative of the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM), in turn, revealed that to make it easier for citizens to purchase flowers for personal use in Mainland China, it will install, between tomorrow and the 16th, a temporary landscape phytosanitary inspection post at the Portas do Cerco border post, providing the inspection service free of charge. The IAM warns citizens that, if they do not have a certificate and license for endangered species issued by the Economic Services, they cannot transport plants included in the “Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora”.
 
Increases amount of waste treated by CSR
CSR Macau – Waste Systems Company revealed that in recent days the amount of waste treated registered a year-on-year increase of 30%, with large waste being the ones that increased most significantly. The company predicted that at peak time, that is, during the weekend, the volume of large waste to be treated will increase from the daily average of 17 tons to almost 40 tons. Domestic waste could increase from around 1,000 tons to around 1,200 tons per day. It should be noted that the Institute for Municipal Affairs has installed 136 large garbage collection points, as of February 16th.
 
Beijing guarantees “stable” food supply
Representatives from the Chinese Ministry of Commerce visited Macau in recent days to learn about the work on supplying agricultural products. According to what was said, the Ministry has already issued orders to guarantee the “safe and stable supply” of agricultural products to Macau during the Lunar New Year. The authorities also recalled that, last year, Mainland China supplied 420 thousand tons of agricultural products to Macau, with the volume of supply of live pigs, live cows, chicken and fruits, fish and seafood products, and alcohol registering increases. The volume of supply of vegetables and cereals remained stable.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2026-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Request for maternity leave benefit for TNR</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pedido-subsidio-na-licenca-de-maternidade-para-tnr/</link><description>The president of the Macau Property Management Association, Paulo Tse, hopes that the authorities will extend the subsidy measure for maternity leave remuneration to non-resident workers as well, to mitigate the human resources costs of property management companies.
 
Despite understanding that the increase in maternity leave and the number of annual vacation days “may be more in line with the general interests of Macau and the well-being needs of the population”, Paulo Tse, president of the Macau Property Management Association, expressed concern about the resulting steep costs for companies in terms of human resources.
According to the Chinese-language press, in this sense, Paulo Tse hopes that the Government will extend the subsidy measure to the remuneration paid for maternity leave also for non-resident workers (TNR). The objective, he stressed, is to alleviate the operating costs of property management companies, thus preventing expenses from being transferred to owners.
The Government's idea is to continue the “implementation of the supplementary subsidy measure to the remuneration paid during maternity leave, granting small and medium-sized companies a subsidy of up to 20 days in relation to the enjoyment of maternity leave by resident workers”, according to the public consultation document.
However, the association leader pointed out that the property administration sector actually covers three areas, namely management, security and cleaning, with the sector employing around 28 thousand workers, of which TNR represent 85%.
In his opinion, as the property administration sector depends on non-local labor, it will face considerable operational pressure, following the increase in maternity leave and the increase in annual leave depending on seniority.
Furthermore, Paulo Tse highlighted that 60% of the property management fees charged to owners come from labor costs, warning of the consequent increase in the property management fee and the quality of service worsening due to the inability of companies to hire workers.
On the other hand, on the same matter, Frederico Ma, director of the Macau Commercial Association, suggested that the aforementioned subsidy measure become permanent. He also proposed that the proportion of this subsidy be increased appropriately.
It is recalled that, within the scope of the revision of the Labor Relations Law, the Government proposed to increase maternity leave from 70 to 90 days, of which 30 can be taken “in full or in part, before or after childbirth, by decision of the worker”. At the same time, it intends to continue granting a subsidy to small and medium-sized companies.
Regarding annual vacations, the Executive intends to implement a seniority mechanism, so that workers are entitled to one more working day of vacation for every two years they spend in the same company, up to a maximum of 12 working days annually.</description><pubDate>2026-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Caritas Macau raises funds to help Portugal and Spain</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/caritas-macau-angaria-fundos-para-ajudar-portugal-espanha/</link><description>Two vehicles were destroyed after a house collapsed due to bad weather in Arruda dos Vinhos, Alenquer, February 10, 2026. Fifteen people have died in Portugal since January 28 following the passage of depressions Kristin, Leonardo and Marta, which also caused many hundreds of injuries and displacement. ANTÓNIO PEDRO SANTOS/LUSA



For three months, Caritas Macau will collect funds to support victims of the storms that have affected Portugal and Spain. Paul Pun highlighted the “special bond” between the territory and the Portuguese people

Civil Protection elements and firefighters rescue people from Reguengo do Alviela, in Santarém, February 6, 2026. Eleven people have died in Portugal since last week following the passage of depressions Kristin and Leonardo, which also caused hundreds of injuries and displacement. ANTÓNIO PEDRO SANTOS/LUSA

Caritas Macau is raising funds for those affected by the storms in the Iberian Peninsula, mainly due to the “special connection” between Portugal and the Macao SAR, the institution's secretary-general told Lusa yesterday.
"Macau residents include Portuguese citizens. Our colleagues are Portuguese, our neighbors are Portuguese, our partners are Portuguese. Maybe our teachers are Portuguese," said Paul Pun Chi Meng.
The 2021 census indicates more than 2,200 people born in Portugal living in Macau. The latest estimate given to Lusa by the Consulate General of Portugal pointed to around 155 thousand Portuguese passport holders among residents of Macau and Hong Kong.
“When we see and understand that there is suffering there [in Portugal], we can help”, explained the secretary general of Caritas Macau.
In a note published on social media, the Catholic organization lamented the “devastating storms” that caused “catastrophic floods” and landslides in Portugal and Spain, destroying infrastructure and homes. "Thousands of people are homeless and urgently need water, food and medical care. Local teams are working tirelessly, but the recovery will be long and challenging", warned Caritas Macau.
Paul Pun expressed hope in the solidarity of the population of Macau, especially as the Lunar New Year approaches, the most traditional Chinese festival, which this year falls on February 17th.
The fundraising campaign was launched on Tuesday and will run for three months, said the Caritas leader. Details about the donation process are available on the Caritas page on the social network Facebook.
In the end, the money raised will be sent to Caritas Spain and Caritas Portugal, with whom Caritas Macau has long had a partnership, recalled the secretary general. Caritas Macau was founded in 1951, still during the Portuguese administration of the territory.
On April 17th, Paul Pun will visit Portugal, in a trip already scheduled “half a year ago”, to discuss how to “join financial resources” to help the most disadvantaged, not only in Portugal, but also in other Portuguese-speaking countries.
At least 16 people have already died in Portugal following the Kristin, Leonardo and Marta depressions, which also caused many hundreds of injuries and displacement. The sixteenth victim is a 72-year-old man who fell on January 28th while repairing the roof of a family member's house, in the municipality of Pombal, and who died on Tuesday, at the University Hospitals of Coimbra.
The total or partial destruction of homes, businesses and equipment, the fall of trees and structures, the closure of roads, schools and transport services, and the cut of energy, water and communications, floods and floods are the main material consequences of the storm. The Centre, Lisbon and Vale do Tejo and Alentejo regions are the most affected.
The Government extended the calamity situation until Sunday for 68 municipalities and announced support measures of up to 2.5 billion euros (around 24 billion patacas at the current exchange rate).
In Spain, the southern region of Andalusia was the area most affected in recent days by heavy rains that caused flooding and the displacement of more than 11 thousand people, with more than eight thousand already able to return to their homes. Yesterday, the Basque Country was under red alert (extreme danger) for waves up to 10 meters high and yellow alert (low danger) for strong winds. Another 14 regions were also under orange or yellow alerts, due to one or more of these weather conditions, in addition to melting ice and rain.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao SAR reinforces its dominance in the Forbes Travel Guide</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-reforca-dominio-guia-de-viagens-de-forbes/</link><description>Forbes published the 68th edition of its Travel Guide, which includes more than 80 establishments in the Macao SAR, with four and five stars. In the luxury segment, Macau has 28 hotels, 26 restaurants and 18 spas, more than any other destination, in each of the categories. Melco was the resort operator that achieved the most five-star ratings in Macau, with 17
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
Macau once again topped Forbes magazine's Travel Guide, which distinguishes the cities with the most five-star establishments, thus marking the Macao SAR's fourth consecutive year of dominance. The North American publication awarded the maximum score to a total of 28 local hotel projects, four more than in the previous year.
Forbes also highlighted a new trend in the Macao SAR's elite hotels, indicating a greater inclination towards “more exclusive luxury stays”. Among the new entries on the five-star list, the recently opened “Capella” at Galaxy Macau, the “Paiza Grand” and the “Palazzo Versace Macau”, for example, offer “a hotel experience within a hotel”, inserted in an integrated resort. The “St. Regis Macao” was the fourth to make the list.
In addition to these four, the list is made up of the “Altira Macau”, the “Banyan Tree Macau”, the “Emerald Tower” and “Skylofts” from MGM Cotai, the “Encore Macau”, the “Epic Tower” and the “Star Tower” from Studio City, the “Four Seasons” and the “Grand Suites”, the “Galaxy Hotel Macau”, the Grand Lisboa and the Grand Lisboa Palace, the “Okura”, the “Karl Lagerfeld”, the “Londoner Court” and the “Londoner Hotel”, the “MGM Macau”, the “Morpheus”, the “Nüwa”, the “Paiza Lofts”, the “Raffles”, the “Ritz-Carlton”, the Wynn Macau and the Wynn Palace.
Macau hotels had already led in 2015, 2018, 2023, 2024 and 2025, independently, in addition to having shared first place with Hong Kong, New York and London (2014) and Paris (2016 and 2017). In this 68th edition, the British capital occupies second place, with 19 five-star hotels, one less than in the previous two editions. Among the cities with the most luxury developments are Dubai (14), which surpassed the Maldives (13), and Paris (11).
Mainland China has 12 five-star hotels on the Forbes list, spread across Beijing (4), Shanghai (4), Guangzhou (2), Chengdu (1) and Shenzhen (1), while Hong Kong has seven establishments listed.
In the ranking of four-star establishments, the Macao SAR is represented by the hotels “Andaz Macau”, “Conrad Macao”, “Grand Hyatt”, “JW Marriott” and “Mandarin Oriental”, and by the spas at “St. Regis Macao” and “Bodhi Spa”. The eight restaurants awarded four stars were Chiado, by Henrique Sá Pessoa, “Drunken Fish”, “Lakeview Palace”, “La Chine”, “Pin Yu Xuan”, “Saffron”, “Vida Rica Restaurant” and “Teppanyaki Shou”.
 
26 luxury restaurants
The MSAR also once again dominated the ranking of luxury restaurants, with 26 establishments, one more compared to the previous edition, with “Sushi Kissho de Miyakawa”, in “Raffles” at Galaxy Macau, now appearing on the list.
In addition to Mesa by Portuguese José Avillez, the five-star restaurants classified by the magazine include “8 1/2 Otto e Mezzo BOMBANA”, “Alain Ducasse”, “Aurora”, “Chef Tam’s Seasons”, “Don Alfonso 1890”, “The Eight”, “Five Foot Road”, “The Huaiyang Garden”, “Imperial Court”, “Jade Dragon”, “Lai Heen”, “Mizumi”, “Palace Garden”, “Pearl Dragon”, “Robuchon au Dôme”, “Sushi Mizumi”, “SW Steakhouse”, “Tenmasa”, “Wing Lei”, “Yamazato”, “Ying”, “Yí”, “Zi Yat Heen” and “Zuicho”.
On the other hand, Macau now has one fewer five-star spa on the Forbes list, compared to the previous edition, and still holds the first position in this category, with 18.
Among the six gaming concessionaires, Melco was the operator that achieved the highest number of five-star ratings, with a set of 17 establishments distinguished in Macau and two in Manila. Lawrence Ho, CEO of Melco, said, “Achieving the most five-star awards globally among integrated resort operators is testament to our team’s unwavering commitment to excellence.” “These results highlight our dedication to operating world-class integrated resorts that offer superlative design and guest experiences,” he added.
Forbes says its ratings "are objective, independent and data-driven. Unidentified inspectors pose as ordinary guests, checking into hotels, boarding cruises, trying spa treatments and eating at restaurants."
“While the quality and condition of facilities remain vital, exceptional service counts for 70% of an establishment’s rating, reflecting the human element at the heart of luxury,” the publication states.
 
Michelin Guide of the RAE will be presented at the Grand Lisboa Palace
The presentation ceremony of the 18th edition of the Michelin Guide for Macau and Hong Kong will take place on March 19th, at the Grand Lisboa Palace, in the same year that the iconic Michelin Star celebrates 100 years. According to a statement, the ceremony will pay “a great tribute to the century-old legacy that continues to inspire cooks, visionary chefs, and passionate gourmets around the world”. Furthermore, the “Bib Gourmand” selection will be announced a week before, on March 12th, highlighting restaurants that offer “good quality” and “good value cuisine”. This selection will be published via the Michelin Guide's official website and mobile application. All establishments are chosen according to five criteria: the quality of the ingredients used, the mastery of the kitchen and culinary techniques, the harmony of flavors, the expression of the chef's personality in the kitchen and consistency over time and the menu. Establishments are evaluated by anonymous Michelin inspectors.</description><pubDate>2026-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Meteorologists discussed cooperation in the Greater Bay Area</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/meteorologistas-discutiram-cooperacao-na-grande-baia/</link><description>Meteorology seminars discussed developing high-quality services in the Greater Bay Area. Representatives from Macau, Hong Kong and Guangdong took stock of the results of cooperation over the previous year and established collaboration plans in areas such as developing forecasting techniques and response mechanisms to climate change
 
Representatives from Macau, Hong Kong and Guangdong discussed, in two conferences, the development of high-quality meteorological services in the Greater Bay Area, events that served to mark the 30th anniversary of meteorological cooperation between the three regions of the Pearl River Delta.
During the meeting of the “Conference on Operational Cooperation in Meteorology”, the three parties took stock of the results of cooperation in the previous year and established collaboration plans in the areas of developing forecasting techniques, integrated observation, building information systems and meteorological services to respond to climate change.
Thus, according to a statement from the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG), the three parties defined the strategic guidelines for meteorological cooperation for the next year, “continuing to strengthen meteorological security in the construction of high-quality services in the Greater Bay Area”.
The director of SMG, Leong Weng Kun, stated that, over these 30 years, Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau have always maintained the spirit of cooperation “Building meteorological dreams and pooling efforts for the future”, achieving “significant results” in various areas, such as “sharing meteorological data, coordination in forecasting and warning, responding to extreme weather conditions and the application of innovative technologies”.
In the future, he said, “we will continue to deepen cooperation, promoting collaborative innovation and joining efforts to create a meteorological service system in the Greater Bay Area that is more flexible and intelligent.”
At the “Meteorology Technical-Scientific Seminar”, experts held an exchange on the application of radar and observation technologies, the use of artificial intelligence and “machine learning”, predictions and warning of adverse weather conditions.
A case analysis and technical discussion on tropical cyclones were also carried out, “contributing to strengthening the meteorological forecasting and warning capacity in the bay through technological innovation”, says the SMG text.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2026-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Government allocated 8 million to “exceptional” athletes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-atribuiu-8-milhoes-aos-atletas-excepcionais/</link><description>Athletes and coaches from different sports who demonstrated “exceptional performance” in international competitions, held during the year 2025, were distinguished by the Macao SAR Government, which awarded monetary checks worth a total of more than eight million patacas. At the awards ceremony, the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, said that the Macao SAR will continue to increase investment in training elites, introducing teams specializing in scientific training and rehabilitation
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The Macao SAR Government distinguished 140 athletes and coaches from nine sports with monetary prizes that exceeded eight million patacas, for achieving “exceptional performance” in 12 competitions. At the same time, around 400 practitioners and technical support staff from 22 sports received certificates of merit.
The most prominent sport was wushu, whose representatives from Macau raised more than two million patacas, thanks to the results obtained in the Asian junior championship, in which they achieved one gold, four silver and four bronze medals.
The focus was also on the dragon boats, which brought a second place and two third places from the Brandenburg World Cup, in Germany, and also the Asian Dragon and Lion Dance competitions, in Jakarta, capital of Indonesia, where Macao SAR athletes won five categories.
The remaining sports included were roller hockey, the men's sector, which finished third in the Asian Championship, which took place in Jecheon, South Korea, as well as karate, bowling, fencing and bodybuilding.
When it comes to competitions aimed at athletes with disabilities, veteran Hoi Long, gold medalist at the Olympic Games for the Deaf, in Tokyo, shone. The same athlete achieved silver in the National Games for People with Disabilities and Special Olympics, while Wong Peng Kuong was ranked third.
At the awards ceremony, organized by the Sports Institute, the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture stated that the Government will continue to increase investment in the training of elites, introducing teams specialized in scientific training and rehabilitation”.
Lam also highlighted that the Executive will also coordinate mechanisms to support entry into higher education, providing flexible admission policies and scholarship schemes. Furthermore, it will create a “platform” for post-career transition, linking it with international courses in sports science and employment opportunities in companies, so that athletes, with the spirit of “never giving up”, can also shine in their own lives.
He also highlighted the intention to promote population well-being, with the continued improvement of community sports facilities and the organization of Sports for All activities, in order to integrate sports into everyday life.
In 2026, Macau will participate in major multi-sport events, including the Asian, Para-Asian, Asian Beach and Asian Indoor and Martial Arts Games, among others.</description><pubDate>2026-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MIECF will focus on low carbon and zero waste</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/miecf-focara-baixo-carbono-residuos/</link><description>This year's edition of the International Environmental Cooperation Forum and Exhibition will take place at Cotai Expo, between March 26th and 28th, with the theme “Low Carbon and Zero Waste Cities”. According to the organization, MIECF has been enriching its “core contents” and reinforcing the “influence of the green platform”
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
Encouraging international exchange and cooperation in the field of environmental protection between governmental, industrial, academic, research, consumer and financial entities are once again at the forefront of the objectives to be achieved by the Macau International Environmental Cooperation Forum and Exhibition (MIECF).
The 2026 edition will take place between March 26th and 28th, at Cotai Expo, and has the theme “Low Carbon and Zero Waste Cities: Embarking on a Global Collaboration”, focusing on the green development of tourism and leisure and the four main industries.
As a professional exhibition accredited by the Global Association of the Exhibition Industry, the MIECF promotes coordination between companies and the supply and demand of the international environmental protection market, through green contact exchanges.
The fair has been enriching its “core contents” and reinforcing the “influence of its green platform”, according to a statement released by the event’s organizers. As a result, he adds, the MIECF now asserts itself as an annual event of relevance for exchange and cooperation in the field of environmental protection, at a regional and even international level, “where national and foreign exhibitors and buyers have access to global opportunities”.
To highlight the objectives and results of the latest editions of the Forum, MIECF officials highlighted reactions from present exhibitors, giving the example of the Technological Center for the Textile and Clothing Industries of Portugal. The entity that participated for the first time in 2025 “considered that one of Macau's main strengths lies in the concentration of cooperation resources between industry, universities and research institutions, “which create favorable conditions for the exchange of knowledge, the development of projects and the conversion of results from institutional cooperation”.
In another example, coming from Malaysia, with five years of experience at the fair in the territory, it is said that the exhibitor “raised the visibility of the institution and expanded its network of associates, as well as boosting the implementation of environmental cooperation projects in that Southeast Asian country”.
In turn, a local recycled materials company took advantage of the Forum as a “green springboard” to establish partnerships with listed companies from both SARs. “This collaboration enabled the supply of environmentally friendly materials and technical support for large-scale engineering projects, resulting in potential orders exceeding ten million renminbi”, highlights the MIECF organization, adding companies from Zhejiang and Hengqin to the list of exhibitors.
MIECF 2026 is co-organized by the governments of the provinces and regions that make up the Pan-Pearl River Delta, with the collaboration of the National Commission for Development and Reform and the Ministries of Science and Technology, Industry and Information Technology and Ecology and Environment of China. Its implementation is also coordinated by the Trade and Investment Promotion Institute and the Macau Environmental Protection Services Department.</description><pubDate>2026-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM signs AI agreement with Pui Va Secondary School</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/upm-assina-acordo-sobre-ia-escola-secundaria-pui-va/</link><description>An agreement between UPM and Pui Va Secondary School will allow “the sharing of educational resources, teacher training and curriculum development, in order to train qualified staff with knowledge in AI and innovative capacity”
 
Macau Polytechnic University (UPM) and Pui Va Secondary School signed a cooperation agreement, with the aim of strengthening cooperation between higher education and basic education, on the occasion of UPM's 45th anniversary, the school's 30th anniversary and the beginning of the 15th National Five-Year Plan. The signing marked the official start of cooperation in “education driven by Artificial Intelligence (AI)”.
“This agreement marks the beginning of in-depth cooperation between the two parties in areas such as sharing educational resources, teacher training and curriculum development, in order to train qualified staff with knowledge in AI and innovative capacity, injecting a new impetus into the educational and technological development of the Greater Bay Area”, can be read in a statement from the higher education institution.
The rector of UPM stated in his speech that the signing of the agreement “constitutes the continuous implementation of UPM’s ‘Rooted in Macau’ educational philosophy, and the training of highly qualified staff in conjunction with all sectors of society”. Marcus Im also added that the university has “actively promoted” the “acceleration of self-sufficiency and self-strengthening in high-level science and technology”, “encouraging research in ‘AI+’ through the creation of interdisciplinary academic degree courses”.
Regarding the platform built in cooperation with Pui Va Secondary School, Marcus Im indicated that “students will learn to explore AI+, collaborate and take responsibility, improving their comprehensive skills”.
The director of Pui Va Secondary School, Lei Chao Lam, said that, currently, with the deep integration of AI technologies into social life, “Greater Bay needs talents with scientific-technological thinking and innovative capacity, making integration between basic education and higher education imperative”.
Defending that UPM has “a solid capacity for scientific research in the field of AI”, Lei Chao Lam added that the school he heads stands out in the educational area, having won the National Teaching Merit Award in the field of professional education. He also noted that the school has worked towards integration between industry and education, providing students with learning opportunities in real business environments.
“This cooperation with UPM will contribute to the creation of an educational environment of ‘basic education-higher education-industrial demand’, opening students a window into the future of AI, supporting the professional growth of teachers, and training more qualified staff with innovative capacity”, considered Lei Chao Lam, cited in a statement.
The agreement signing ceremony took place at UPM and was attended by more than a hundred teachers and students from both institutions.</description><pubDate>2026-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC displays “visual journey” of Sino-Lusophone art</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/frc-exibe-viagem-visual-de-arte-sino-lusofona/</link><description>Until March, the Rui Cunha Foundation has exhibited 26 works from its collection, signed by Chinese and Portuguese artists. The exhibition “The Gallop of the Year of the Fire Horse” is free to enter and “proposes a visual and cultural journey through different artistic expressions”



















The exhibition “The Gallop of the Year of the Fire Horse” is on display at the Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) until March 7th, with free entry. According to a press release, the exhibition presents 26 “eclectic” works from the FRC collection and was organized in collaboration with the Poetry Association of Friends of Jardim da Flora, “which dedicated calligraphed verses of good auspices to this event”.
As part of the Moonlight New Year celebrations, the exhibition “proposes a visual and cultural journey through different artistic expressions, such as calligraphy, painting, sculpture and ceramics, exploring themes such as movement, energy, spirituality and renewal, values ​​intrinsically linked to this ancient celebration”, it can be read.
The works displayed represent “the dialogue between cultures, traditions, artistic languages ​​and different materials, highlighting the fusion of this symbolic richness associated with the festive season of the lunar calendar”.
The “diverse set of works with oriental influence, signed by Chinese and Portuguese artists” includes names such as Paulo Valentim, Arlinda Frota, Rui Calado, Vasco d’Orey Bobone, Lei Iat Po, Natalie Lao, Lee Chau Ping, He Jianguo, Liu Shengli, Wilson Lam, Li Jinxiang and Meng Li, among other artists “who passed through the Gallery over almost 14 years”.
The initiative is a demonstration of the Foundation's commitment “to the dissemination of art and to promoting meetings between local artists from different cultures”, says the note.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2026-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Grand Prix Museum offers signs alluding to the races</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/museu-grande-premio-oferece-disticos-alusivos-as-corridas/</link><description>Visitors to the Grand Prix Museum will be able to use rollers with templates to print auspicious blessings or racing-themed designs on lai si couplets and envelopes. The activity “Horses at Full Steam, Fortune at a Gallop”, will take place between the 17th and 23rd of February
 
The Grand Prix Museum (MGPM) will present for a week, between 17 and 23 February, a special Chinese New Year celebration activity, allowing visitors to print, on rolls with templates, auspicious blessings or racing-themed designs on handmade lai si couplets and envelopes.
To this end, two interactive stands will be installed with features alluding to the Lunar Year festivities, namely, “Couple Printing Station” and “Lai Si Rolling Printing Station”, as part of the “Horses at Full Vapor, Fortune at Gallop” activity, promoted by the Tourism Services Directorate (DST).
On the other hand, two special exhibitions at the museum will accompany the public during the Chinese New Year: the tire-themed exhibition “Macau Grand Prix Museum
To take advantage of the festivities, the souvenir shop at MGPM launches Chinese New Year and Lantern Festival promotions until March 31st, also offering gift packages and product sales with a 30% discount.
Meanwhile, the MGPM Café provides a special restaurant experience, offering themed meals, also including a full-scale dining table for taking photographs inspired by a champion racing car, “so that customers can immerse themselves in the Grand Prix environment”, says a note from DST, highlighting that the space, opened in July 2025 after renovation, “has become a popular tourism spot integrated with sport and cultural and creative industries”.
DST guarantees that it has made efforts to promote and publicize the Grand Prix culture in the museum, having continued to increase the interactive multimedia exhibition items, the GPM scenery display installations, the racing cars and related objects. Likewise, it has adopted barrier-free facilities and other facilities, with a view to providing Macau residents and visitors with an “education and fun” experience, showcasing the diversity of “tourism +” and contributing to increasing Macau's tourist attractiveness.
MGPM will be open during the Chinese New Year holidays, daily from 10am to 6pm, including the rest day, Tuesday (17th), especially as it is the first day of the Lunar New Year.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2026-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Business Awards with two new categories</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/premios-empresariais-duas-novas-categorias/</link><description>The ninth edition of the Macau Business Awards, which recognize entrepreneurs and institutions that have contributed to the city's development, will take place on May 12, at Studio City. This year the initiative has two new awards, “Sustainability” and “My City – My Brand”
 
The Studio City Grand Hall will host the 9th Macau Business Awards Gala Ceremony, on May 12th. Among 11 categories, the highlight goes to the two new awards for “Sustainability” and “A Minha Cidade – A Minha Marca”. In a statement, the “Business Awards of Macau” states that “around 250 renowned executives and professionals” will be present at the ceremony.
The “Sustainability” award distinguishes “those who stand out for helping Macau become more sustainable, acting in a ‘greener’ way in the sectors of transport, construction, energy, tourism, waste management, education and public policies”. The distinction “My City – My Brand” rewards “the contribution of those who, for generations, kept an idea, a business, or a dream alive, often facing economic and social challenges”, it can be read.
The remaining categories include the awards for “Leadership by Example”, “Entrepreneurship”, “Young Entrepreneur”, “Great Bay”, “Leadership in Entertainment”, “Innovation”, “Small and Medium Businesses”, “Non-Profit Organization” and the highest honor, the “Grand Award of Merit”, “which recognizes the highest level of overall contribution to the community”, says the statement.
All participants shortlisted for the final phase will be invited to the awards ceremony. “The finalists with the highest scores will be recognized as ‘Gold Winners’ in their respective categories, while the rest will receive the ‘Excellence’ award.”
Paulo Azevedo, president of the Macau Business Awards, believes that “this enormously prestigious annual program will continue to celebrate the notable achievements of institutions, companies and individuals who exceptionally contribute to the city's development”.
Applications for this edition are open until March 31st. Voting will take place during the month of April.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2026-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New vaccine against covid-19 available</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/disponivel-nova-vacina-contra-covid-19/</link><description>The Health Services (SSM), in accordance with the recommendations of the World Health Organization, purchased the Comirnaty LP.8.1 monovalent mRNA vaccine against the disease caused by the SARS-CoV-2 virus for people aged six months and over. The objective, the authorities emphasize, is “to reduce the risk of serious cases and death associated with infection by the new type of coronavirus”. According to the SSM, the appointment system is now accessible, and vaccination will be available from today. People aged 12 and over can get the vaccine at the health centers in Ilha Verde, Jardins do Oceano, Areia Preta, Praia do Manduco, Nossa Senhora do Carmo-Lago, Seac Pai Van and at the Covid-19 Vaccination Center at Kiang Wu Hospital. The health centers in Ilha Verde and Jardins do Oceano, in turn, can administer the vaccine to people aged between six months and 11 years. Vaccination is free for all residents, non-resident workers, prisoners and students legally authorized to stay in Macau. Non-residents who are legally authorized to stay in the territory can also administer the vaccine, in which case it costs 150 patacas for each dose. The SSM recommend vaccination to the elderly, patients with chronic illnesses or people with a weakened immune system, as they “present a significantly higher risk of developing serious symptoms or fatalities in case of infection with the new type of coronavirus”.</description><pubDate>2026-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Indonesian president orders Bali beaches to be cleaned</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/presidente-indonesio-obriga-limpar-praias-de-bali/</link><description>Bali has launched a major beach cleaning initiative in response to Indonesian President Prabowo Subianto's recent criticism of the island's growing trash problem.
Hundreds of Bali police and local military joined students and volunteers to collect trash at two of the island's most popular tourist beaches: Kuta and Kedonganan, in the Badung region. Additional cleaning operations were also carried out on the beaches of Delod Berawah in the Jembrana region and Saba in Gianyar, resulting in the removal of several tonnes of rubbish.
Bali Police spokesperson Ariasandy said authorities invited the public to participate in this beach cleaning program because community involvement is crucial to preserving the island's marine ecosystem.
“The activity aims to raise awareness about environmental protection and create clean, healthy and welcoming beaches for visitors”, highlighted Ariasandy. “Keeping beaches clean not only benefits the environment, it also supports economic activity and has a positive impact on tourism,” he added.
The governor of Bali said that a special force will be created to deal with the problem at Kuta beach, following Subianto's criticism. “We appreciate the President’s attention to the issue of litter on Bali’s beaches, especially Kuta Beach,” said Wayan Koster.
"We will immediately create a dedicated force on Kuta Beach to respond quickly whenever marine debris arrives from outside the island of Bali. The aim is for the beach to be clean again within an hour", explained the governor.
In addition to this intervention group, Koster emphasized that regular community clean-up activities will be carried out on Kuta beach. These initiatives will actively involve residents and students, ensuring that the beach remains clean and welcoming for visitors.
During a meeting with regional heads in Bogor, West Java, on February 2, the Indonesian President expressed concern about the growing garbage problem in Bali. "I recently met with several foreign leaders in South Korea, and they shared their criticisms about Bali's beaches. They told me: 'Your Excellency, I just returned from Bali. The beaches are very dirty now. Bali is not so beautiful anymore.'
Bali has faced a growing waste crisis in recent years, with rubbish often contributing to environmental problems such as flooding, even in tourist areas.
In 2024, the island generated 1.2 million tons of waste, most of it coming from tourist hubs such as Denpasar, Gianyar and Badung. The governor previously noted that almost all of Bali's landfills have reached capacity, with single-use plastics accounting for the majority of waste.
A 2019 study revealed that only around 48% of Bali's waste is managed properly through recycling or landfill. A significant portion of the waste collected never reaches recycling facilities or the island's 10 official landfills, resulting in an estimated 33,000 tonnes of plastic entering Bali's waterways every year.
To address the growing waste problem, Koster launched several initiatives in 2025, including a ban on single-use plastic bags, cups, straws and Styrofoam in companies, public offices, schools, hotels, restaurants, markets and places of worship. The production and distribution of water bottles with a capacity of less than one liter were also banned.
Companies, public offices, schools, hotels, restaurants, markets and places of worship are also required to separate waste, treat organic materials and recycle inorganic waste, either independently or through outsourcing services, so that only solid waste ends up in landfills. Bali plans to build its first waste-to-energy plant, with construction scheduled to begin in March and operation scheduled for 2027.
Following the President's criticism of Bali's trash problem, Tourism Minister Widiyanti Putri Wardhani announced that the ministry will expand beach cleaning initiatives to popular tourist destinations across Indonesia.
“The Ministry of Tourism has been implementing the Clean Tourism Movement since 2025. Now, the program is being reinforced and elevated as part of the President's priority agenda”, he highlighted, cited by the Indonesian news portal Kompas.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2026-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>