<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Limit for housing credit will increase to 80%</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/limite-para-credito-a-habitacao-vai-aumentar-para-80/</link><description>When purchasing housing units, local buyers will see the maximum mortgage loan percentage ceiling raised from 70% to 80%, the Government revealed yesterday, during the LAG discussion.
 
In addition to exempting the payment of stamp tax on the transfer of properties to qualified residents when purchasing housing units up to six million patacas, the Government proposes to raise the maximum limit on the mortgage loan percentage from the current 70% to 80% for local purchasers of housing units. The idea is for the two measures to be in force at the same time, said Vong Sin Man, deputy president of the Monetary Authority (AMCM), yesterday.
According to the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, regarding the acquisition of a housing unit whose price exceeds six million, the excess part will be taxed at a rate of 3%.
In the discussion of the Lines of Government Action (LAG), within the scope of Economy and Finance, deputy Kevin Ho suggested the exemption from payment of stamp duty for commercial units. However, the Secretary stressed that it is necessary to observe the implementation of the new measures to later evaluate this issue, warning that housing projects in tourist areas and those in community neighborhoods present significant differences.
Asked by several deputies how the Government intends to support small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) and the community economy, Tai Kin Ip assured that the authorities will reinforce “political support in multiple aspects, including dissemination and promotion, customer acquisition, training, brand building and financial support, to assist SMEs in their innovation and conversion, increasing their competitiveness”. They will also encourage SMEs to explore markets through cross-border e-commerce and live streaming sales.
Most commercial establishments in low-lying areas have already completed the installation of lifting platforms to prevent flooding, according to the director of Economic and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), Yau Yun Wah. Regarding SMEs not yet equipped with this installation, in 2026, the Government will reinforce the level of financial support and consider increasing the level of financial support within the scope of property insurance against major disasters for SMEs, in order to encourage companies to transfer the risk of flood prevention through the insurance market.
According to the same official, 1,438 of a total of 1,537 requests received this year for interest subsidies on bank credits for SMEs were approved, involving 3.34 billion patacas. Furthermore, in 2026, tax incentives will be added for treasury centers of qualified companies.
On the other hand, the Secretary promised that the Government will continue to optimize the business environment in community neighborhoods, supporting the carrying out of different types of activities with different characteristics, reinforcing interconnection with large-scale events, and providing incentives to encourage participants to visit and consume in these areas. Furthermore, the Government hopes, through the “first store economy” program, to attract foreign brands to open their first store in the neighborhoods.
Specifically, he revealed that the Executive plans to improve transport in ZAPE, beautify this area of ​​the city and introduce more activities, such as festivals. According to him, ZAPE will host typical Christmas activities at the end of this month and in December.
Regarding the Grand Prize for Consumption, Tai Kin Ip stated that the two rounds launched this year achieved a consumption boost effect of more than four times. Faced with a request from Chan Lai Kei to extend this type of measures to holidays, the Secretary stressed that consumption benefits should be concentrated on weekends, a period when many residents will consume outside the territory. For the government official, the local consumer market has a certain level of support on weekdays.
In turn, the director of Tourism Services said that the number of international tourists exceeded 2.14 million in the first 10 months of this year, an annual increase of 13% and equivalent to 83% of the 2019 level, highlighting, in this regard, the goal of recovering the annual volume of three million. Noting that traditional sources of international tourists are no longer necessarily the guideline to follow to attract tourists, Helena de Senna Fernandes mentioned that she intends to invest in emerging markets, such as Central Asia. The idea is to establish, in 2026, economic, commercial, tourist and cultural delegations in Southeast Asia and Northeast Asia.
Furthermore, he highlighted that tourism products will be optimized, the content of large-scale activities will be updated, the financial support program for community tourism will be expanded, cooperation with airline, bus and boat companies will be extended and improved, as well as the emerging tourism markets, such as sports-related, senior citizens and family tourists, will be explored in a precise manner.
On the other hand, the Secretary said that a financial support plan will be launched to help the local food industry in the packaging, design, translation and certification of halal food products.
 
Reinforced intensity in attracting investments
In the presentation of the LAG, the Secretary warned that local economic development “will continue to face incessant challenges from the external environment”, while “the recovery of some sectors and neighborhoods is at a relatively slow pace, with the situation of imbalance and insufficiency in Macau's economic development persisting”. “At the same time, the structural problems that condition Macau’s long-term economic development remain”, he added, stressing that “all these scenarios impose increased demands” on the tasks under his supervision.
In this sense, Tai Kin Ip argued that “the achievement of more substantial progress in the adequate diversification of the economy” must be promoted, while the intensity and proactiveness in attracting business and investments will be reinforced.
Che Weng Keong, president of the Trade and Investment Promotion Institute (IPIM), revealed that he has already received more than 500 inquiries via telephone call about the “first store economy” program, 70% of which were related to the desire of local companies to introduce brands from abroad in the Macao SAR. Several requests were submitted, including some made by Portuguese brands, he said.
According to the Secretary, the Government will be committed to promoting “pragmatically” exchange and cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries in the economy, trade, finance and technology, mobilizing the sector's forces to support Mainland Chinese and local companies in expanding international markets and attracting more companies and investment projects from Portuguese-speaking countries.
“The internationalization of traditional Chinese medicine will be promoted through the model of introducing medicines through medical treatments, taking Portuguese-speaking countries as a starting point”, he added. In this context, it announced an “Incentive Plan to Promote the Modernization of the Traditional Chinese Medicine Industry”.
The substitute president of AMCM said that preliminary studies on the creation of the government fund for industries and the guidance fund have been completed, and AMCM will present proposals regarding the management, structure, risk management, investment guidance and operational model of these funds.
Furthermore, he revealed that, so far, more than 10 investment fund companies, with the potential to establish themselves in Macau, have contacted AMCM. In parallel, its strategy is to urge financial companies that currently help AMCM manage assets to open branches in the territory. However, he predicted that implementing this strategy would take a long time.
Regarding the securities law, Vong Sin Man said he has started legislative work, adding that AMCM hopes the law will be inclusive and operable.
As he highlighted, by the end of September, the value of capital in the Macao SAR's Financial Reserve stood at 658.7 billion patacas, and investment revenues worth 34.9 billion were recorded, reflecting an annual increase of 12.76% and a rate of return of 5.6%. This year, the Government began to include gold in the Financial Reserve's investment options.
Furthermore, the Secretary predicted that the merger between DSEDT, the Fund for the Development of Sciences and Technology and the Consumer Council will be completed at the end of next year.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>TNR quotas gradually reduced in the retail and construction sectors</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/quotas-de-tnr-reduzidas-gradualmente-nos-sectores-retalho-construcao/</link><description>The Secretary for Economy and Finance stated yesterday that the authorities have redoubled their efforts to promote the gradual reduction of TNR quotas in the areas of retail sales, administrative personnel and construction, which has already borne some fruit
 
This year, 8,700 residents got jobs with the help of the Government, of which 50% are under 34 years old and the other half are middle-aged residents, the Secretary for Economy and Finance said yesterday. In addition, around 48 thousand residents participated in 1,600 professional training courses launched this year.
In the field of employment, Tai Kin Ip also highlighted that the Working Group for the Coordination of Employment Promotion has carried out reviews of the situation of non-resident workers (TNR) and the job vacancies that each sector can provide. As he highlighted, the Government has intensified efforts to promote the gradual reduction of TNR quotas in the areas of retail sales, administrative personnel and construction.
"In the construction sector, the number of residents waiting for employment has gradually decreased. As for civilian personnel, [the Government] has tried to provide more opportunities for resident employment, while in the financial area, it has taken measures to gradually reduce TNR, freeing up vacancies", he continued, stressing that, with efforts, the unemployment rate has fallen in recent months.
In the same vein, he stressed that, to obtain financial support under the “first store” program, candidate companies must hire a certain number of residents.
Deputy Chan Lai Kei warned of the emergence of illegal workers working as photographers, makeup artists and artists. The Secretary assured that the fight will be further strengthened. However, he warned that it was necessary to assess the degree of punishment for self-employed workers, including the issue of reentry of the respective individuals, so additional measures would be needed.
Furthermore, Tai Kin Ip promised to try to secure the employment of around 3,200 employees at the four satellite casinos that will close by the end of the year. As specified, one will close its doors at the end of this month and the others will stop operating in December, including Fortuna, which closes on the 10th. According to the Secretary, the line open to support satellite casino workers has already registered “29 cases of information consultation”, but “no case has been received that requires the support provided by the Government”.
As confirmed, after the closure of six satellite casinos, 1,600 workers have already been reinstated in the gambling concessionaires' staff. “We will continue to work, step by step, for a smooth transition of satellite casino workers,” he added.
Regarding the sector in general, Tai Kin Ip highlighted that the operation of the concessionaires will be strictly supervised, in accordance with the law, and the fulfillment of investment commitments in the game and extra-game. Operators will be guided to invest in projects with socioeconomic benefits that contribute to improving the image of Macau's brand, supporting, more effectively, the development of industrial diversification.
 
Residents will have a “skills passport”
The Secretary also revealed that 800 people have already used the Integrated Professional Training Platform, which offers 70 courses and is open free of charge to all residents. Chan Un Tong, director of Labor Affairs Services (DSAL), indicated that the Platform already includes training courses from DSAL, the Center for Productivity and Technology Transfer and the University of Tourism.
The person in charge said that he plans to launch, on the Platform, a function called “skills passport”, for residents to “upload” and show, in this digital “passport”, the certificates obtained, in order to make it easier for employers to understand the skills of job candidates.
At the same time, the courses available on the Platform will be aimed directly at companies' specific “requests”. In other words, courses will be added according to companies' needs in relation to certain professionals, said Chan Un Tong.
Furthermore, the Secretary revealed that he had already completed preliminary studies on increasing the number of days of maternity leave and annual leave. “The Government is organizing the information, intending, based on consensus, to move forward with the review of the law for the respective increases”, he stated.
Tai Kin Ip stressed that experience proves that large companies are capable of taking longer maternity leave, with some having already adopted better benefits in this regard. As he assured, adjustments to maternity leave and annual leave will be promoted under the principle of shared responsibility between the labor and employer sides.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Male chauvinism” still prevails despite women’s progress</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chauvinismo-masculino-ainda-prevalece-apesar-dos-progressos-das-mulheres/</link><description>Between January and June, 27 suspected cases of domestic violence were investigated, including, among the victims, 12 children and 10 women. As part of the International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women, TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper spoke with the director of the Centro do Bom Pastor, Debbie Lai, about the evolution of society, the progress made by women in recent decades, as well as the work carried out by the center in recent years
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
In the first half of this year, the Central Domestic Violence Case Registration System of the Institute for Social Affairs (IAS) detected 27 suspected cases of domestic violence, which involved violence against 12 children, 10 wives, a husband and four other family members. In most cases, 71% of the attackers were men and, in the 11 cases of domestic violence in particular, 10 of the attackers were male.
In 2024, 55 suspected cases of domestic violence were registered in the territory, which corresponds to an increase of 37.5%, compared to 2023, confirming an upward trend that has been observed since 2022, according to the Central Domestic Violence Case Registration System. On the occasion of the International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women, which is marked today, the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper spoke with Debbie Lai, director of the Centro do Bom Pastor, about the evolution of society, and women in particular, over the last 30 years.
For Lai, the increase in the number of cases of domestic violence “may indicate that victims are becoming more aware of the need to protect themselves and their children”, “in the hope of being able to live a safe and dignified life, which motivates them to report to the police and seek help”. On the other hand, “economic factors” continue to be “one of the reasons why [victims] are not willing to report violence”.
Data from this year's semi-annual report from the Central Registration System also indicates that 52% of the aggressors were unemployed and did not earn any type of income, while 22% had “unknown” income. In the case of victims of domestic violence, four (36%) out of 11 did not have any income.
"Some [of the victims] are unaware that there are resources to help them in society or perhaps they do not have the motivation to seek help. Others do not want to depend on the Government or even family service centers from non-governmental organizations", observed the director. “If you find yourself in this situation, you can try to apply for the IAS social grant to solve short-term financial problems and take care of your children”, warned Lai.
"Another reason may be fear of retaliation, harassment or intimidation from other family members. Some victims fear that their children will lose a complete family, and feel ridiculed or embarrassed by the possibility of becoming a single-parent family", he pointed out.
 
Three decades of social progress
Debbie Lai, with more than three decades of experience working at the center, recognizes that "currently, women are much more capable. They have equal opportunities and the right to personal development. Most company directors are also women. They can choose their career, their partners, study in higher education, take on leadership positions.
“However, many women arrive in Macau to marry residents and, as new immigrants, some have a low [social] status”, in addition to other family problems, explained Lai. However, according to data from the report, in the first half of the year, only four of the registered victims were not permanent residents.
“Male chauvinism, gambling, drug abuse or poor communication” are other prevalent problems that afflict women, believes Debbie Lai. "The husband has to control everything and the wife must listen to him. Typically, victims “lack self-esteem”, which leads to “arguments, conflicts and even violence becoming more frequent”. “These types of problems still occur today and affect the psychological and physical development of children”.
Among the aggressors, 41% suffered similar experiences in childhood or witnessed situations of domestic violence, the report indicates.
 
Fewer donations to the Bom Pastor Center
Currently, the institution run by Lai houses eight people, including six women and two children. The length of stay can vary between two weeks and a year and a half, according to the director. In addition to providing legal assistance and advice, the center also organizes educational and prevention activities for victims.
"Regular financial support from IAS remains the main source of funding for the center. Other donations are unpredictable. Monetary assistance has decreased this year compared to last. Donations are not limited to money. Benefactors also donate material and [offer] sponsorships", explained the director.
"Since 2002, in addition to helping women in crisis, we began to focus our attention on the quality of family life in Macau. Especially for this purpose, we organize seminars, workshops and public exhibitions aimed at raising awareness about the problem of family violence and promoting skills to foster a harmonious family life. Every year, we organize different educational activities for the public," he added.
In 2024 and 2025, the Center promoted “Non-Violent Communication” in primary and secondary schools, hoping to reduce conflicts between teachers and students and parents and children, improving their relationships. The initiative included lectures, exhibitions and games.
"Last year, the other program focused on women's rights and we organized a training session for social workers and school counselors. The aim was to improve participants' empathy in helping victims of domestic violence and make them more sensitive about what they need and how they experience physical and psychological trauma," he said.
In conclusion, Debbie Lai appealed to the public to improve good communication within the family and “to fully take advantage of community resources”. “Please do not hesitate to seek help if you are faced with emotional or family problems”, warned the director. “Actively participate in activities that are beneficial to your physical and mental health and work together to build a harmonious family life.”
According to the United Nations, violence against women and girls remains one of the most prevalent and widespread human rights violations in the world. Globally, almost one in three women have been subjected to physical or sexual violence, by partners or non-partners, or both, at least once in their lives, according to the UN.
For the organization, the focus of this year's International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women campaign is digital space. “Violence against women on online platforms is, today, a serious and rapidly growing threat that seeks to silence the voices of multiple women, especially those with a strong public and digital presence in areas such as politics, activism or journalism.”
The date of November 25th was chosen to honor the Mirabal sisters, three political activists from the Dominican Republic who were brutally murdered in 1960 on the orders of the country's then leader, Rafael Trujillo.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>22 imóveis patrimoniais foram restaurados ou revitalizados em 2024</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/22-imoveis-patrimoniais-foram-restaurados-ou-revitalizados-em-2024/</link><description>O Instituto Cultural restaurou ou revitalizou 22 edifícios patrimoniais no ano passado, envolvendo um total de 26 projectos. Furthermore, according to the organization's annual report, the University of Macau can now study data obtained by the World Heritage Monitoring Center to analyze general changes in heritage constructions, under a bilateral cooperation agreement.

Last year, the Cultural Institute (IC) completed 26 restoration or revitalization projects for 22 heritage buildings, according to the organization's latest annual report. According to the document consulted by the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, 16 projects involved restoration work, including the repair of the exterior walls of the Clube Militar building and Farol da Guia, repair of the wooden doors and windows of the Albergue da Santa Casa da Misericórdia, partial restoration of facilities at the Teatro Dom Pedro V, the Ancient Walls next to Estrada de São Francisco and the exterior walls and the surface of the roof of the Fundação Oriente headquarters.
As part of the revitalization, the 10 projects targeted the Old Iec Long Panchões Factory, Zona da Barra around Doca D. Carlos I, Rua da Felicidade, Fortaleza do Monte, 23º and 25º jetties of Porto Interior and Kun Iam Ecumenical Center.
The IC highlights that, in 2024, it continued to use the World Heritage Monitoring Center to generally supervise changes in the structures of heritage properties and their surrounding environment, having centrally managed and comprehensively analyzed monitoring data. “The objective is to analyze more precisely the trends of physical structural change in the respective constructions, in order to make scientific decisions and adopt appropriate and timely protection measures, further improving the monitoring and protection of World Heritage”, highlights the report.
In this regard, he recalls that, in order to make better use of monitoring data, the IC and the University of Macau (UM) signed a cooperation agreement last year. As part of this collaboration, UM can now study the data obtained by the Monitoring Center to analyze general changes in heritage buildings.
Over the past year, the IC carried out safety inspections of 165 classified properties, involving more than 600 heritage buildings, as well as carrying out 231 inspections of temples, within the scope of fire prevention.
In the same year, it installed the termite prevention and monitoring system in 68 heritage sites and commissioned the Macau Civil Engineering Laboratory to carry out structural safety monitoring in 10 heritage sites, including the Ruins of São Paulo, Fortaleza do Monte, Casa do Mandarim, Teatro Dom Pedro V, Capela de Nossa Senhora de Penha and Igreja de Santo Agostinho. In addition, the changing situation at the Ilhas Verde Retreat House, among other heritage spaces, was analyzed through 3D scanning and aerial photography.
Also in the sphere of cultural heritage protection, the IC issued 891 opinions in 2024, mainly related to construction projects and advertising signs.
With regard to intangible cultural heritage (PCI), the document reveals that the IC concluded, last year, investigations into 20 items, which will serve as a reference for updating the PCI Inventory in the future. At the same time, the organization photographed and filmed 14 items, having completed the production of promotional videos on six PCI items.
 
Fewer visitors to the Ruins of São Paulo
The report also points out that, among the heritage buildings that serve as tourist attractions, the Ruins of São Paulo, the Museum of Sacred Art and Crypt and the Church of S. Domingos were the most visited last year, registering 4.05 million, 2.09 million and 1.56 million visitors, respectively. The Museum of Sacred Art and Crypt registered a significant increase of 2.47 times in the number of visitors, compared to the previous year, while the Ruins of São Paulo showed a decrease of 10.3% in that chapter.
Lou Kau House, Guia Fortress, Na Tcha Temple Exhibition Hall, Sir Robert Ho Tung Library and Former Iec Leong Panchão Factory also proved popular in 2024, with 420 thousand, 197 thousand, 190 thousand, 174 thousand and 171 thousand visitors, respectively. In the context of the historic box office performance of the Chinese animated film “Nezha 2”, released last year, the Na Tcha Temple Exhibition Hall also recorded a notable increase of 48.8% in the flow of visitors.
Last year, 582 films were shown at Cinemateca Paixão, attracting a total of 22,736 spectators.
 
Almost 300 requests for filming approved
The report also reveals that the IC received 338 requests for filming in Macau, an annual increase of 52.3% and an increase of 36.8% compared to 2018. The IC understands that, with the boost of the “double anniversary” and a series of policies that support filming in Macau, there was a clear increase in film production activities in the territory, with requests submitted by teams from abroad growing by around 2.3 times compared to the previous year. The percentage of requests made by non-local teams thus rose from 26% to 46% between 2023 and 2024.
In total, 292 filming requests were approved, 62.2% more than in 2023, including 130 from local teams, 59 from Mainland China, 19 from Hong Kong, 12 from South Korea and five from Taiwan. Additionally, Japanese, American, Singaporean and Thai film crews have also submitted applications in 2024.
Statistics indicate that, among the 239 cinematographic works produced in 2024, the categories of television programs (43 cases), feature films (35), advertising and online programs (33) and promotional videos (27) stood out. Meanwhile, six microfilms were captured in the territory, however, with no record of production that year. The average time for considering applications was 3.8 days.
In turn, the Cultural Center hosted 1,266 shows or activities in 2024, 300 more than in the previous year, with more than 302 thousand spectators/times. In parallel, 84 entities benefited from discounts worth a total of MOP979 thousand when renting the Cultural Center.
The Dom Pedro V Theater served as the stage for 63 shows and activities, mainly musical, which were watched by 6,306 people/times. As a tourist attraction, the theater attracted more than 80 thousand visitors last year.
In museums, the number of visitors increased by 64.3% to 4.58 million, compared to 2023. The Museum of Sacred Art and Crypt was the most frequented, while the Macau Museum recorded an increase of 22.2% in the volume of visitors. Furthermore, local art museums received 1.28 million, an annual growth of 33.2%.
In another area of ​​the cultural world, at the end of last year, the Macau Conservatory had 1,087 students enrolled in continuing arts education courses and 76 registered in secondary education courses. Specifically, the Dance, Music and Theater Schools had 265, 678 and 144 students, respectively, enrolled in continuous artistic education.
 
Public library users increased by 9%
More than 2.77 million people/times visited public libraries in 2024, reflecting a year-on-year increase of 9.1%, according to the Cultural Institute. According to data from the latest annual reports, around 10.4% of public library users (289 thousand people) borrowed books. Compared to 2023, the number of people requesting to borrow books fell by 2%. In total, libraries lent 570 thousand books. On the other hand, there was a 19.3% increase in the number of clicks on public libraries' electronic resources, to 1.18 million. In addition, more than 83 thousand people used the advance booking service to borrow books, an increase of 8.5%. Through this service, 106 thousand books were loaned.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Historic areas with new revitalization model</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/zonas-historicas-novo-modelo-de-revitalizacao/</link><description>The revitalization of the six historic areas, which was the responsibility of gaming operators, together with the Government, will now involve one more element: associations. As explained by the Secretary for the Economy, associations will be responsible for planning events and activities. The Executive also intends to create a “Zone Development Center”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Starting next year, the Executive will adopt a new model for the revitalization of the six historic areas of Macau, revealed yesterday the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip. “The Government will supervise and coordinate, the gaming concessionaires will invest resources and the associations will prepare and plan activities”, he explained, in the presentation of the Lines of Government Action under his authority.
“We are going to take advantage of the strength of the associations, because they have knowledge and ideas”, he stressed, adding that the objective is to create a “Zone Development Center”, to “carry out activities and improve the image of historic areas”.
The revitalization plans undertaken by the concessionaires, remember, were formulated as part of the non-gaming investment requirements under the new law. The six areas include the Lai Chi Vun Shipyards, Rua da Felicidade, the Barra area, piers 23 and 25 of Porto Interior, Avenida do Almeida Ribeiro and Rua de Cinco de Outubro, as well as the Iec Long Panchões Factory, each corresponding to one of the gaming operators.
Regarding the investment by the six large companies, deputy Ip Sio Kai asked the Government whether it could not be extended to other areas of the city. At this point, the Secretary only noted that evaluation work has been carried out on compliance with gaming operators' commitments in the context of investments beyond gaming. “In the future we will see if there is the possibility of having more revitalization zones”, he added.
The deputy insisted again asking whether “the methods and scopes” within the scope of the contracts could not be reviewed. “We can adjust and invest in other areas other than these six…”, he said.
In the reply, Tai Kin Ip said that the operators made “small adjustments” to investments in non-gaming elements, but “remained within the original scope”. He also admitted that, taking into account the experience gained in recent years, and considering the operational and social benefits of the projects, “some investments in areas not related to gaming may not have performed as expected, which requires appropriate adjustments”.
“It was always the Government's idea that gaming concessionaires could create more non-gaming investments, but other Macau companies also participate in this work”, he stressed, denying that these investments could restrict other industries.
On the other hand, in relation to NAPE, where many satellite casinos have been closing their doors, Tai Kin Ip admitted that the transformation of the area will take time. Pointing out that there are thousands of hotel rooms available there, the Secretary said he believes there will be new customers, such as families and young people. He also guaranteed that new products will be developed to attract tourists to that area.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Two possible locations for Science Park</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/duas-localizacoes-possiveis-para-parque-das-ciencias/</link><description>The Secretary for Economy and Finance revealed yesterday that there are two locations in mind for the Macau Science and Technology Park: in front of the Airport or in Zone E1 of the New Landfills. The project will be in public consultation from Thursday
 
The Macau Science and Technology Research and Development Industrial Park project, which will be presented to the public this Thursday, as part of the launch of the public consultation, has two possible locations, the Secretary for Economy and Finance said yesterday. "The first proposed site, located in front of Taipa Airport, on Wai Long Avenue, has an area of ​​approximately 80,000 square meters. The second site, located in Zone E1, between Macau Bridge and Friendship Bridge, has an area of ​​177,000 square meters", explained Tai Kin Ip, in the presentation of the Government Action Lines.
As he told deputies, the park's positioning aims to “leverage the scientific research base accumulated by Macau in recent years”, giving priority to the introduction of high-quality technological companies in four key sectors: integrated circuits, biomedicine, digital technology and aerospace technology. “It will also target other promising fields such as smart robotics and new materials,” he added.
The facilities, scale and spatial design of the Science and Technology Park are still in a preliminary phase, stressed the government official, saying that the Government seeks to obtain a “broad contribution” from all sectors of society.
Before the Park is launched, however, the Executive intends to establish the Macau International Center for Scientific and Technological Industry next year. “As the construction of the park takes time, the former Macau Youth Business Incubation Center at NAPE will be vacated to accommodate this center, which will occupy approximately 2,000 square meters,” said the Secretary. “Although modest in size, this space will serve as a temporary installation to host technological projects that intend to establish operations in Macau”. As for the Business Incubation Center for Young People, it will be transferred to the central area.
Tai Kin Ip highlighted that the Hengqin-Macau Innovation Industrial Park “complements” the Macau Science and Technology Research and Development Industrial Park. "Macau is positioned to focus on research and development, while Hengqin is designated for production. Construction of the Hengqin-Macau Innovation Industrial Park is expected to be completed between the end of next year and the beginning of the following year, with investment promotion activities already underway," he clarified.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Carga fiscal na China “ajuda” ourivesarias locais</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/carga-fiscal-na-china-ajuda-ourivesarias-locais/</link><description>The Macau Goldsmiths Association told Lusa yesterday that the recent cut in a tax exemption for the purchase of gold in Mainland China could benefit the territory's market.
As of November 1, the Chinese authorities reduced the exemption from Value Added Tax (VAT) on certain gold purchases made by companies from 13% to 6%, and the new policy does not cover Hong Kong and Macau.
“This is good news for the industry,” said the vice-president of the Macau Goldsmiths Association.
“The price difference between mainland China and Macau has widened, leading to an increase in business with visitors who now buy gold here out of necessity,” added Lei Cheok Kuan.
Lei acknowledged that there has not yet been an immediate increase in business volume, “due to some people from mainland China not being able to come to Macau immediately”.
However, Lei noticed a clear trend: “among those who have long been interested in gold jewelry or invested in the metal, the price difference is a significant factor in their purchasing decisions when visiting Macau”.
The policy change is already affecting the Mainland China market. The “World Gold Council” noted on social media that Chinese gold jewelry manufacturers and wholesalers implemented widespread price increases, “with the increase reflecting the additional tax burden borne by companies”.
Jewelry group Chow Tai Fook announced on November 3 that it has “adjusted the prices” of some products and is “proactively managing the impact of increased costs in the acquisition and production of gold”.
Chow Tai Fook, one of the largest Chinese jewelry groups, closed more than a thousand retail stores in Mainland China in the first nine months of 2025, maintaining a network of 5,663 establishments.
However, the “World Gold Council” clarified that investors in gold bars and coins who purchase investment products directly from members of China’s main gold exchange, the “Shanghai Gold Exchange”, “will not be affected in any way”.
The Chinese province of Gansu (northwest) announced the discovery of a new large gold deposit in the Qianhongquan-Heishanbeitan area, in the municipality of Yumen, with reserves estimated at more than 40 tons, Chinese state television CCTV reported in October.
 
The price of gold, historically considered a safe haven asset in times of uncertainty, was falling 0.52% yesterday, at 3:41 pm, with an ounce (equivalent to 31.1 grams) being traded at 4,094.5 dollars, far from the historical maximum, 4,347.86 dollars, set on October 20th.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Reinforced sports cooperation in Greater Bay Area</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/reforcada-cooperacao-desportiva-na-grande-baia/</link><description>A quadripartite agreement was signed between the SAR, Guangdong and the State General Administration of Sports, with a view to promoting the development of sports in the Greater Bay Area
 
An agreement signed between the State General Sports Administration, the People's Government of Guangdong Province, Hong Kong and Macau reinforces sports cooperation in the Greater Bay Area. Focusing “on strengthening sports cooperation and promoting integrated development”, the quadripartite agreement “represents a document with important results that synthesizes, in a profound way, the experiences acquired in the joint organization of the 15th edition of the National Games”.
Aiming to promote, “on an ongoing basis”, the integrated development of sport between Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau, it also allows “an exploration with practical actions to maximize the unique functions and pluralistic values ​​of sport, and thus better serve the construction of the Greater Bay Area” and the principle of “one country, two systems”, says the statement from the Social Communication Office.
Thus, the signing of the agreement “will comprehensively strengthen exchanges and cooperation” between Mainland China and the regions of Hong Kong and Macau in various areas. Namely competitive sport, sport for all, sports industries, youth sport, international sports governance, sports sciences and technologies, sports culture and legal issues in sport.
“The agreement, through encouraging the implementation of joint pilot projects in the Greater Bay Area, aims to achieve the sharing of resources, the use of facilities, the organization of competitions, the training of qualified staff, the growth of industries, the creation of science and technology and advancement at the sporting level, boosting the integrated development of sport between the three locations, at a higher level, in a broader scope and with a broader vision, serving the State's global strategy”, highlights the press release.
According to the statement, Macau will “fully implement the content of the agreement, vigorously supporting the development of sport and promoting cooperation in the sector”. It also intends to “seize opportunities, using competitions as a link in order to continuously deepen collaboration and synergy with Guangdong and Hong Kong in the areas of culture and sports, achieve closer regional cooperation, create a more dynamic industrial ecology and promote a stronger cultural identity”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Checo renews motorbike surfing world title in Hac-Sá</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/checo-revalida-em-hac-sa-titulo-mundial-de-motosurf/</link><description>Motorsurfers from several countries competed in Macau in the final round of the World Cup. In the main category, Elite, Czech Matyas Novotny repeated the title achieved in the previous edition. The tests took place over three days in the waters of Hac-Sá
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
Czech Matyas Novotny once again secured the title in the Elite category of the Motosurf World Championship, which closed the season in the waters of Hac-Sá Beach, in Coloane.
The 19-year-old won the Macau round, the last of the season, totaling 276 points, compared to 248 from second place, compatriot Lukas Zahorsky, and 244 from third place, also representing Czechia. The “duel”, which had already been fought in 2024, was repeated between the two main figures of the sport.
Czechia continues to be the most dominant country in motorsurfing, having completely filled the “top 10” of the final table of the Elite competition, after the five rounds held since April this year, which took place in the United Arab Emirates, Turkey, Italy and Croatia.
The championship includes other categories, which also decided the titles in the Macao SAR event and had more motorsurfers from other countries fighting for the top spots. The list of winners includes: “Stock” (Antony Squire, USA); “Stock R – Merlin Plus” (Mike Michaelides, Cyprus); “Masters” (Down Kim, South Korea); Women (Eliska Matouskova, Czechia); Junior men (Matyas Barvyk, Czechia); Female juniors (Ellen Burdova, Czechia) and “Electric Challenge” (Yano Vankersbilck, Belgium).
The Macau round took place over three days, always with good weather and waves favorable to good races, whether in the qualifiers or finals, with 80 athletes taking part, from 19 countries or regions, including the Chinese Zhang Maozhu, who won the silver medal at the 2025 World Games in Chengdu. He competed in Stock “Class”, where he was ranked ninth.
This was the second consecutive time that Hac-Sá hosted the World Cup, organized by Melco Resorts, with the support of the Macau Motosurf Association and the supervision of the International Motorboat Federation (UIM).
This year, the event presented a new activity, called the Coastal Market, which took place along the Hac-Sá promenade, offering local culinary products, interactive workshops and a sand sculpture performance. “The initiative enriched the spectators’ experience, while deepening the synergy between ‘tourism + sport’, in line with Macau’s broader development strategy”, highlighted the organization.
MotoSurf Racing was created in Czechia in 2012 and is officially recognized by the International Olympic Committee. The World Championship is open in terms of a plurality of manufacturers. In both the combustion engine and electric engine categories, any manufacturer that complies with the valid UIM rules is admitted.
Motorsurf racing is known for its ecological approach, thanks to the advanced technologies used in motorized surfboards. Boards in the combustion engine categories are designed according to the latest technologies and are officially classified as the lowest emission personal watercraft.
The electric category is contested on fully electric motorized boards, with zero impact on emissions, being the first fully electric racing class in the world of motorboating.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mozambique hosts Sino-Lusophone meeting of businesspeople in 2026</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mocambique-recebe-encontro-sino-lusofono-de-empresarios-em-2026/</link><description>The 2026 edition of the Businessmen's Meeting for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries will take place in Mozambique. “The meeting will be held in Mozambique next year,” said the president of the Institute for Trade and Investment Promotion (IPIM), Che Weng Keong. This year, the business meeting between China and Portuguese-speaking countries took place for the first time in Malabo, capital of Equatorial Guinea, for three days, at the end of July. The annual event has been held on a rotating basis in Portuguese-speaking countries since 2005, however, it was suspended for four years during the pandemic. The meeting returned in 2024, having taken place in Macau and coinciding with the sixth ministerial conference of Forum Macau, which included the signing of the organization's action plan until 2027. Che Weng Keong also defended the actions of the China-Portuguese-Speaking Countries Cooperation and Development Fund, saying that “it has encouraged [Chinese] companies to develop operations in these countries”. Yesterday, during the afternoon session, deputy Song Pek Kei highlighted that Portuguese-speaking countries “are a base for Macau to play the role of a connecting platform”. “We have to reinforce our proactive attitude”, defended the deputy, adding: “Can we communicate more with Portuguese-speaking countries so that they have a greater desire to settle in Macau?”. Song Pek Kei also noted that, in the territory, there are consulates of several Portuguese-speaking countries and asked that this also be a reality in Hengqin. In the reply, the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, said that he will “work” on this matter, but noted that “it also depends on the will of the consulates”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>TDM promotes conference with Portuguese-speaking countries</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/tdm-promove-conferencia-paises-lusofonos/</link><description>TDM is promoting today a conference on the integrated production and transmission of information, with the participation of representatives from television stations from Portuguese-speaking countries, namely RTP, TPA-Televisão Pública de Angola, RTTL-Rádio e Televisão de Timor-Leste and TGB-Televisão da Guiné-Bissau. João Nuno Nogueira, who worked at TDM in the 80s and 90s and is currently a consultant to the RTP Board of Directors, will address the project under development at RTP, “Casa de Notícias”, which aims to create a multiplatform news production center, can be read in a press release from the public station. The deputy director of TPA, Amândio Caweie Cafuanda, the director of information and current affairs at RTTL, Horácio Babo, the administrative and financial director of TGB, Adulai Demba Baldé, and the director of Information and Chinese Information Programs at TDM, Grace Lao, will also participate in the conference. The initiative will be moderated by TDM's director of information and Portuguese programs, Gilberto Lopes, at the Fórum 2 studio. Tomorrow, six documentaries produced by Chinese stations will be delivered to Portuguese-speaking countries, in an initiative by the Chinese Foreign Affairs Commissariat in Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>iRad at Studio City enters into agreement with Hong Kong Sanatorium</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/irad-studio-city-celebra-acordo-hong-kong-sanatorium/</link><description>iRad Hospital, located in Studio City, announced the signing of a cooperation agreement with Hong Kong Sanatorium &amp; Hospital. “This partnership launches complete cross-border medical assistance services, reinforcing the Macau Government’s ‘1+4’ economic diversification structure and supporting Macau as a medical tourism destination”, says Melco in a statement. The “strategic alliance” enables “seamless connectivity” of medical services between the two regions, providing patients with access to expanded specialized medical resources through iRad Hospital. “Combining Hong Kong Sanatorium &amp; Hospital’s 103-year legacy of comprehensive medical excellence with iRad’s more than 20 years of professional medical experience and resort-integrated healthcare model, this partnership establishes an unprecedented healthcare network covering the Pearl River Delta region,” he adds. The healthcare program “facilitates integrated care coordination, efficient interfacility scheduling, and personalized treatment plans utilizing resources from both institutions.” Lawrence Ho, CEO of Melco, highlighted that this collaboration demonstrates the group's commitment to enriching the health tourism offer in Studio City, aligning with the Government's strategies.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>BRIEF</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2504/</link><description>18 deputies are part of the Chief’s Electoral Committee
The Electoral Affairs Committee of the Chief Executive published the list of new representatives of the Legislative Assembly in the 4th sector of the Electoral Committee of the Chief Executive, “elected by the new deputies to the AL, through internal suffrage, resulting from the change of legislature”, it is mentioned in the Official Bulletin. In total, the representatives are 18: Ho Ion Sang, Song Pek Kei, Nick Lei, Ella Lei, Lam Lon Wai, Iau Teng Pio, Joey Lao, Ma Chi Seng, José Pereira Coutinho, Kou Ngon Seng, Cheong Weng Chon, Angela Leong, Leong Sun Iok, Chan Hao Weng, Wong Kit Cheng, Ip Sio Kai, Che Sai Wang and Ngan Iek Hang.
 
Parking lots with half-hour charge increase
From December 3rd, the Directorate of Traffic Affairs Services will extend the facilitation of half-hour charging to a further seven public car parks. Thus, the total number of public car parks that adopt the half-hour pricing model will increase to 22. The new parks are those in Parque Central da Taipa, Rua da Ponte Negra, Ferry Terminal for Passengers in Taipa and buildings in Lago, Iat Sang, Chun Su Mei and Iat Fai. The daytime fare for light vehicles will be 3 patacas per half hour, and the nighttime fare will be 1.5 patacas. For motorcycles and mopeds, the fares will be 1 patacas per half hour (daytime) and 0.5 patacas (nighttime).</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Dramatic adventure” dictated the end of the Portuguese Revolution 50 years ago</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/dramatica-aventura-ditou-fim-da-revolucao-portuguesa-ha-50-anos/</link><description>Portugal experienced, 50 years ago, the “dramatic adventure” of the 25th of November, which pitted far-left and “moderate” military personnel against each other and dictated the end of the Portuguese revolution and the democratic normalization of the country. The expression “dramatic adventure” comes from General Costa Gomes, the President of the Republic who, from the Belém Palace, in Lisbon, negotiated with all the barricades to avoid a confrontation that could have dragged the country into a civil war.














On one side was the military left, influenced by the extreme left and communists, divided between “gonçalves”, close to former prime minister Vasco Gonçalves and the PCP, and “otelistas”, supporters of the 25 de Abril strategist and head of COPCON (Continent Operational Command), supporters of the “revolutionary path”. On the other were the “moderates”, bringing together military personnel and forces to the right of the PCP – including the PS of Mário Soares, the PSD of Sá Carneiro and the CDS – and who ended up having the support of Costa Gomes.
A year and a half after the Carnation Revolution, on April 25, 1974, which overthrew Europe's oldest dictatorship of almost half a century, the revolution was on the streets. Banking and insurance had already been nationalized and agrarian reform in Alentejo and Ribatejo was at its peak.
Since July 1975, in the North and Center of the country, bombs destroyed PCP headquarters. In the streets, people shouted cheers for popular power, the revolution and “down with the communists”. That summer of 1975 went down in history as the hot summer that lasted until November.
Since 1974, there have been coups and counter-coups, the 28th of September, still in 1974, the 11th of March, in a country governed by a Council of the Revolution.
In the newspapers, during this hot autumn and with an almost daily cadence, coups and more coups were announced. Left and right.
Then November arrives. The barrel has heated up and is ready to “explode”.
The “trigger” was the choice of Vasco Lourenço, from the Group of Nine, the moderates, as commander of the Lisbon Military Region, replacing Othello, who the revolutionaries saw as a leader for the socialist revolution.
Events come to a head on November 20th. Days after the siege of the Assembly of the Republic by striking construction workers and the kidnapping of the Prime Minister, Pinheiro de Azevedo, the Government goes… on strike. Pinheiro de Azevedo's outburst saying that he didn't like being kidnapped will go down in history: “It upsets me”!
And if the “trigger” of November 25th was the replacement of Othello, the “spark” was the paratroopers’ entry into action. The unit raised weapons in protest against the threat by the Air Force Chief of Staff, General Morais da Silva, to dissolve the regiment, a decision that the “paras” do not accept.
The result is an uprising by paratroopers, who occupy the bases of Tancos, Monte Real, Montijo and the Air Region Command, at Monsanto, in Lisbon.
This revolt served to justify the advance of the “moderate” military group, which, for months, had been preparing a military plan to respond to a possible coup by the radical left.
In addition to Melo Antunes and Vasco Lourenço and the operative Jaime Neves, at the head of the Amadora Commandos, the name of a soldier who would become President of the Republic (1976-1986) then appears: Ramalho Eanes. He would be the operator of the plan that gave victory to the moderates.
In Belém, the “moderates” try to convince Costa Gomes to support their military plan. The general President is postponing and negotiating to calm things down: with the “revolutionary” military, with the PCP, so as not to take to the streets and not support the “adventure” of the paratroopers.
Otelo Saraiva de Carvalho is called to Belém. And there he stays. Held back and unable to communicate with his “troops” in the COPCON barracks.
But it took two days to control the situation.
On the afternoon of November 25th, a state of siege was declared in Lisbon – an exceptional regime. The rebels threatened to kill General Pinho Freire, in the Air Command at Monsanto, Lisbon, but he was detained in a room with a telephone, which was used to communicate what had happened to the Group of Nine.
At night, the commandos occupy the Monsanto base and free Pinho Freire. The clashes take place the following day, November 26th. Commandos surround the Military Police facilities in Lisbon, occupied by the rebels. The shooting resulted in three deaths – two commandos and a military police officer.
The years have passed, but there are still some aspects that are less clear. Who gave the order to the “paras” to occupy the bases? And did the PCP approve the decision? Othello denies it was him. Ramalho Eanes considers that it was Othello who gave the order or that he “covered”.
Raimundo Narciso, leader of the PCP at the time and responsible for the party's links to the military, later a PS deputy, states that the order came from the military left and “had the approval of the PCP”.
This last version, however, is denied by Álvaro Cunhal, historic leader of the PCP, 25 years after the revolution, in the book “The Truth and the Lie in the April Revolution”, published in 1999.
 
Celebrations revive historical fractures between left and right
The celebrations of the 50th anniversary of the 25th of November, equated to those of the 25th of April, revived historical fractures in national politics, with the left accusing the right of intending to rewrite History and downplay the Carnation Revolution.
After, last year, there was, for the first time, a solemn session dedicated to the 25th of November in the Assembly of the Republic, this year the Government took a step forward and, in August, after a Council of Ministers, announced the creation of a commission to organize the celebrations of the 50th anniversary of the 25th of November.
In addition to a solemn session in parliament, whose ceremony will be similar to that of the 25th of April, the anniversary will also be marked with a military parade in Praça do Comércio, in Lisbon, as happened in the celebrations of the 50th anniversary of the Carnation Revolution, in 2024.
The almost total equality in the celebration of the two dates - with the exception of the fact that the 25th of November has not yet been consecrated as a national holiday - was unanimously criticized by the left, who accused the right of wanting to diminish the 25th of April and argued that the two dates are incomparable.
This divergence manifested itself in particular at one of the last conferences of leaders in the Assembly of the Republic, in October, in which all left-wing parties opposed the IL proposal, supported by CDS-PP and Chega, so that the 50th anniversary session of the 25th of November in parliament would have, like the 25th of April, outdoor banners and the same number of floral arrangements – which will end up happening.
On the eve of the celebration of the anniversary, all left-wing parties, with the exception of the PS, indicated that they will not be present at the military parade in Praça do Comércio. The PCP also refused to participate in the formal session at the Assembly of the Republic, similar to what happened last year.
The PS, despite participating in the military parade, announced that it will organize its own program to commemorate the event and refused to join the commission created by the Government, considering that it hides “the central role” of Mário Soares and has the purpose of “creating a narrative of confrontation and polarization”.
“The PS cannot follow this resolution of the Council of Ministers, nor this commission that separates the 25th of November from the 25th of April 1974, and it does so not only because it hides the central role of Mário Soares and the PS, but it also does so because, to a large extent, it intends to rewrite history”, accused the parliamentary leader of the PS, Eurico Brilhante Dias, in August.
With the PS's refusal, this commission, chaired by Lieutenant General Alípio Tomé Pinto, was only made up of right-wing parties (PSD, Chega and IL), one of the reasons that led one of the protagonists of 25 de Novembro, Colonel Vasco Lourenço, to consider it “a joke”. "They have the nerve to say that it is an independent, non-partisan commission, but who are they kidding? And, as I say, look in the mirror and be ashamed of the face you see reflected in the mirror. (…) They are not good people", he accused.
Despite this criticism from the left, the anniversary will be celebrated with practically the same honors as the 50th anniversary of the 25th of April. According to the Minister of Defense and leader of the CDS-PP, Nuno Melo, these celebrations allow the State to fulfill “its obligation in relation to a fundamental date for the consolidation of democracy and freedom”.
"The 25th of November returned the 25th of April to its original purpose. The 25th of April allowed the change of the regime with the intention of handing over power to the people, and the 25th of November put an end to the totalitarian drift and confirmed the democratic regime", said Nuno Melo in August, when he announced the creation of the commission relating to the 25th of November.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>