<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Support from the Building Repair Fund rose 19% in one year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/apoios-fundo-de-reparacao-predial-subiram-19-num-ano/</link><description>Support granted by the Building Repair Fund to help owners repair their properties increased by almost 19% in 2025, in annual terms, show statistics analyzed by the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper. Specifically, 66.05 million patacas were allocated to around 500 buildings. Since it was created in 2007, this Fund has channeled more than 714.3 million patacas towards various types of works
 
Catarina Pereira
 
In the space of a year, support granted by the Building Repair Fund increased by 18.58% to 66.05 million patacas, an amount that was channeled towards the repairs of a total of 507 buildings. The Housing Institute (IH) points out, however, that of the total number of buildings, 15 obtained approval for more than one Fund plan, meaning that, in reality, applications relating to 492 buildings were approved.
These IH data refer to the period between January 1 and December 31, 2025, which also indicate that 662 requests for support were granted, while three were rejected – two for not falling within the scope of granting support and one due to the price. The government body also indicates that 20 dropouts were registered, according to statistics consulted by the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper.
In 2024, remember, support was granted in a total amount of more than 55.7 million patacas, while in 2023 aid worth more than 62 million had been granted.
The largest share of subsidies allocated by the Building Repair Fund throughout 2025 is made up of support under the Financial Support Plan for Repair of Common Parts of Class P and M Buildings. In this field, more than 41 million patacas (more than 62% of the total) were channeled to 294 buildings in the territory. Specifically, the amount was used to repair the entrance and exit gates of buildings, general electricity, water supply and sewage installations, to repair the covering of interior walls, stairs and corridors, as well as the covering of external walls and replacement of windows in common areas, as described by IH.
This was followed by almost 19 million patacas (29% of total support) in financial support for the repair of 42 buildings, under the Financial Support and Interest-Free Credit Plan for Building Repairs. In this case, the main approved projects concerned external walls, expansion joints on the platform floor, elevators, waterproofing of the terraces, water supply and sewage installations, fire protection system, renovation of the tiles on the atrium walls, repair of the balusters in the common areas, as well as the repair of the ceiling of the elevator corridor.
Still within this plan, the Building Repair Fund allocated 5.2 million patacas in interest-free credit, in four situations, all referring to projects related to the repair of exterior walls.
On the other hand, more than 421 thousand patacas were granted to convene general assemblies of condominiums in 163 buildings, through the Financial Support Plan for Building Administration. The Financial Support Plan for Inspection of Common Parts of Buildings provided almost 320 thousand patacas for the development of building repair projects for four buildings.
Since it was created in April 2007, the Building Repair Fund has already channeled more than 714.3 million patacas in financial support for a total of 7,253 applications submitted. Since 481 of the 4,521 buildings received approval for more than one plan, applications for 4,040 buildings were actually approved.
The Financial Support Plan for the Repair of Common Parts of Class P and M Buildings is the one that has granted the most money, amounting to more than 510.7 million patacas (more than 71% of the total) over 19 years.
The Building Repair Fund aims to provide financial support for carrying out conservation and repair works that contribute to the safety and environmental health of private buildings in the Macao SAR, operating alongside IH.</description><pubDate>2026-01-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CTM has already started reducing tariffs</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ctm-ja-comecou-reduzir-tarifas/</link><description>Companies, public services and individual customers can now benefit from discounts on CTM tariffs, with the company putting into practice the plan agreed with the Government
 
The Macau Telecommunications Company (CTM) began implementing the tariff reduction plan, benefiting users who subscribed to the company's relevant services until September 30th. Through this initiative, the telecommunications operator intends to support small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs), large companies, government departments and individual customers.
Eligible individual customers using residential broadband services are entitled to a 10% discount on the net monthly fee during the months of January, April, July and October 2026. Furthermore, from this month onwards, the price of additional mobile data drops from 13 to 8 patacas per gigabyte (GB), corresponding to a reduction of 38.5%.
In turn, according to CTM, SMEs can benefit from a 20% discount on common broadband services during the months of January, April, July and October. The monthly fixed telephone service plan for ordinary commercial customers will fall to 140 patacas from this month onwards. Customers who simultaneously subscribe to common commercial broadband services will be able to enjoy a discounted rate of MOP112 per month.
Large companies and government departments can receive a 20% discount on the net monthly fee for commercial broadband services in January and July, respectively, and a 10% reduction per month on Direct Internet Access (DIA) and local and international private circuit service.
In a statement, CTM highlighted that customers do not need to sign up or register to benefit from this program, as the corresponding amount will automatically be reflected in their invoices.
The new price plan follows a request from the Executive, to “respond to society's concerns”, as stated in September by the director of Postal and Telecommunications Services (CTT), Derby Lau. “With the Government's policies regarding the diversified development of the sector, we will create more spaces and conditions to allow Macau to be a city with the most advanced technologies in the world, offering quality services, at reasonable and attractive prices”, said the company's CEO, Vandy Poon at the time.
In October, Ebel Cham, vice-president of commercial operations at CTM, stated that these measures aim to “support the Macao SAR Government in creating a more favorable environment for business, and improve citizen satisfaction”.
According to data released by the CITIC group, which owns 99% of the local operator, CTM expanded its dominance in mobile telecommunications in the Macao SAR in 2024, controlling 53.3% of the market, with the number of 5G users reaching almost 760 thousand. CTM currently has one competitor in 5G services (China Telecom) and three in the 4G network (China Telecom, Hutchison and Smartone).
Throughout 2024, CTM's sales revenue increased by 9.8% year-on-year to approximately HK$2.62 billion, including handsets, equipment and mobile services. Revenues from mobile services alone grew 12.7%, to 1.09 billion, compared to the previous year, due to the increase in the number of mobile customers and mobile market shares, as well as the 5G penetration rate.
Business has also advanced in the internet domain. As of December 31, 2024, CTM held 96.8% of the Macau broadband market.
 
S.T.</description><pubDate>2026-01-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Government will create a system to assess the psychological well-being of residents</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-criara-sistema-para-avaliar-bem-estar-psicologico-dos-residentes/</link><description>The Health Services revealed that they will create a system for evaluating physical and mental health indicators, as well as a database, to assess the psychological well-being of residents. At the same time, they report that they have collected data on outpatient psychiatric consultations, number of hospitalized patients, patient diagnostic categories, rate of use of services and waiting time, information that will serve as scientific foundations for defining policies, resource management and optimization of services
 
The Government will create a system for evaluating physical and mental health indicators and a database, and in this system, the psychological well-being of residents will be evaluated based on five physical and mental health indicators from the World Health Organization, said the Health Services (SSM).
In response to a written question from deputy Ho Ion Sang, the body led by Alvis Lo further explained that this assessment system and database will be created based on the results of the “physical condition assessment” of the Sports Institute and the “health assessment” of the SSM.
According to him, at the same time, a scientific measuring instrument is also used to understand the state of psychological disturbance of residents, in order to understand the physical and mental state of the population in different aspects, which can also support the definition and correct improvement of subsequent policies.
In the interpellation, Ho Ion Sang suggested a comprehensive survey on the mental health of the entire population carried out every five years, even pointing out that “the absence of regular large-scale surveys of the population prevents an accurate assessment of the real distribution of mental health problems”. Furthermore, the deputy requested the publication of statistics on the types of illnesses treated in the field of Psychiatry, service usage rates and waiting times.
At this point, the response states that the SSM have been systematically collecting data on outpatient psychiatric consultations, number of hospitalized patients, patient diagnostic categories, rate of use of services and waiting time, among others. As revealed, this data will be integrated and analyzed to provide scientific foundations for defining policies, managing resources and optimizing services.
 
Elderly mental health concerns Ho Ion Sang
In another written statement, Ho Ion Sang warned that, “with the heightened severity of population aging problems in Macau, mental health problems among the elderly have become evident”, such as anxiety, depression, loneliness and insomnia.
In this sense, the deputy urged the Government to adopt “diversified strategies” to mitigate the psychological challenges that the elderly face. Specifically, he suggested “personalized psychological support” for the elderly that combines exercise therapy, intelligent monitoring, remote medical services, artificial intelligence and mega-data.
Furthermore, it considers that authorities should encourage companies, financial institutions and social service providers to launch retirement planning and support services, in order to reduce the likelihood of elderly people having mental health problems after retirement.
On the other hand, to mitigate the challenges of loneliness, Ho Ion Sang advocated long-term digital skills training plans, with a view to helping senior citizens actively integrate into smart life, establishing contact with society and other people.</description><pubDate>2026-01-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Public consultation on expansion of the Light Metro starts this month</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/arranca-este-mes-consulta-publica-sobre-expansao-metro-ligeiro/</link><description>Between January and February, the Government will collect opinions on the Light Rail expansion plans. The public consultation will serve to assess the feasibility of the work and the travel needs of residents and tourists. The optimization of the connection between bus services and the Metro and the introduction of other means of electronic payment will also be considered.
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
The Government will hold a public consultation between January 23rd and February 28th, to gather opinions from the population and professional sectors on the development of the Macau Light Rail. According to a statement from the Public Works Services Directorate (DSOP), the initiative aims to make society aware of the planning and construction work relating to the expansion of the Light Rail.
As this is “an important project of the Macao SAR Government”, the Executive will commit itself “to exploring the extension of the Light Rail service to areas not yet covered, namely, to the western and central areas of the Macau Peninsula, the northern area of ​​Taipa and some areas of Coloane”, says the DSOP.
In this sense, the Government prepared a general plan that contemplates “strategies for the future routes of the Light Rail, its general effectiveness, the technical feasibility of construction and the travel needs of residents and tourists, among other preliminary ideas”.
According to a response to a question from deputy Chao Ka Chon, the Office of the Secretary for Transport and Public Works indicated that the Southern Line will extend from the Macau Border Post of Ponte do Delta to Estação da Barra, passing through Zone A of the New Landfills, the New Landfill Zone of the Outer Port (NAPE) and lot A9 of Nam Vam Lake.
The West Line will connect Qingmao Border Post, Fai Chi Kei and Barra Station, while the Taipa North Line will cross Zones D and C, from Zone E's ES6 station to Oceano Station. The Seac Pai Van Line will be expanded to the edge of Vila de Coloane.
Citizens will be able to consult information regarding planning on the DSOP website and fill out the opinion form on the same page. Terão também a possibilidade de apresentar as suas opiniões por outros meios, como correio, fax, telefone e correio electrónico.
 
Optimization of connections between buses and Metro
In turn, Chiang Ngoc Vai, director of Traffic Affairs Services, said, in response to a written inquiry from Wong Kit Cheng, that the organization intends to negotiate with the two bus service operators, to promote “a plan of benefits for correspondence between buses and the Light Rail”.
Chiang stated that “technical coordination, passenger needs and the operational efficiency of the system will also be considered in an integrated manner”. In this context, the Light Metro Society also intends to collaborate with the Government in order to introduce electronic payment methods and optimize the “mobility environment in public transport”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Review of the Educational Guardianship Regime removed</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/afastada-revisao-regime-tutelar-educativo/</link><description>There has been a certain stability in the criminal recidivism rate of young offenders in the last three years, which does not exceed 5%, according to the Institute of Social Action. According to the organization, there are no plans to change the Educational Guardianship Regime
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
Extending the length of confinement “may lead to institutionalization problems”, that is, “cause a negative impact on the connection of young offenders with their family of origin and society”, considers the Institute of Social Action (IAS) in response to a written question from Lam Lon Wai.
In this sense, the organization led by Hon Wai adds that the extension may “not favor” the social reintegration of young people when they spend long periods of time at the Instituto de Menores (IM), “even if the family visits them regularly during institutionalization”.
The deputy questioned whether the Government intends to carry out legislative changes and revisions regarding the Educational Guardianship Regime for Young Offenders, including considering extending the duration of short-term educational supervision measures from one to two years, “in order to accommodate the correction and therapy time necessary for high-risk cases, thus establishing a more effective educational supervision mechanism”.
In the response, the IAS justifies its intention not to do so with data. Between 2022 and 2024, the rate of replacement of placement in a temporary residence unit with other, more stringent measures was 9.7%. On the other hand, based on records relating to recidivism in the commission of offenses or crimes by young offenders during two years after the end of the period for applying the measures, compliance with which is supervised by the IAS, the recidivism rate in the last three years remained only between 3% and 5%.
IM statistics reveal that the recidivism rate of young people admitted from 2018 to 2022, who left the institution, was zero.
“This shows that educational guardianship measures are effective in correcting the deviant behavior of young offenders”, he says, adding that, in the future, the Government will remain “attentive” to the state of play of the Educational Guardianship Regime and will continue to listen to the opinions of all sectors of society. At this moment, he guarantees, “there are no proposals to change the regime in question”.
In the text signed by the substitute president, Tang Yuk Wa, the IAS highlights that, due to the differences that exist with regard to the nature of all educational protective measures and the deadline for their implementation and monitoring, “a certain flexibility is granted in their application and replacement, in order to have a positive impact on the lives of the young people being monitored”.
In 2026, the IAS plans to develop parental education services for the families of these young people and launch a new support program, called “Effective Parenting”, with which it intends to “deepen support for parental education and reinforce education and legal awareness”, in addition to the provision of existing services, with the aim of “insistently improving family and community support for young offenders”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Charging electric vehicles will become cheaper</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/carregamento-de-veiculos-electricos-vai-ficar-mais-barato/</link><description>As part of promoting green mobility, the Government will reduce the cost of public charging of electric vehicles by around 10%. The tariff update will come into force from next month, according to an order from the Chief Executive
 
The Government will lower charging rates for electric vehicles by around 10%, according to an order from the Chief Executive, published yesterday in the Official Bulletin. Within the scope of the “Electric Vehicle Promotion Plan in Macau”, the reduction in tariffs will take effect from the 1st of February. In addition, the nominal output powers of slow and fast charging will be adjusted.
At slow charging points, the energy cost will go from 2.15 to 1.94 patacas per kWh, between 09:00 and 20:00, and from 1.42 to 1.28 patacas from 20:00 to 09:00. Average charging points will now cost MOP2.68 per kWh. Fast charging points will cost MOP3.1 per kWh.
Furthermore, the Government intends to “increase, in a timely manner, the number of charging facilities at different speeds and standards and battery exchange facilities in public parking lots or neighborhoods that meet the appropriate conditions for this”, according to the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) in a statement.
DSPA also assured that the Government “will urge the electricity concessionaire to optimize the electricity charging management platform, ensuring the provision of high quality charging services”.
According to the organization, these measures aim to achieve the national “Double Carbon Target”, the continuous improvement of a system that guarantees green mobility and the promotion of the use of electric vehicles.
Remember that, in 2024, the Executive had already reduced public electrical charging rates for medium and fast charging and extended the lowest cost hours for slow charging.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2026-01-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 160 infiltration cases remained unresolved in 2025</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-de-160-casos-de-infiltracoes-nao-ficaram-resolvidos-em-2025/</link><description>The Interservice Center for the Treatment of Water Infiltration in Buildings recorded 2,082 cases of infiltration in 2025, the majority of which (1,918) were completed. However, in 164 situations, the owners “did not fulfill their responsibility for repairs or their duty to collaborate”, indicates the Housing Institute
 
Last year, the Interservice Center for the Treatment of Water Infiltration in Buildings recorded 2,082 cases of infiltration, but not all of them were resolved. The data made available by the Housing Institute (IH) and analyzed by the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper reveal that in 164 cases, that is, 7.88% of the total, “after coordination, the owners did not fulfill their responsibility for repair or the duty of collaboration”.
On the other hand, in 1,854 situations, after coordination, “the owners have already carried out repairs or monitored the cases in accordance with the inspection reports”, while in 64, after coordination, “the people concerned or the managers monitored and dealt with the cases on their own initiative”.
The IH also indicates that it was monitoring a total of 294 cases, of which 284 related to 2025 and 10 to the previous year. The public works services were assisting 435 cases of water infiltration in buildings, 419 of which were from the year in question and 16 from the previous year. Six interdepartmental joint actions were also carried out in this context.
In another context, IH indicates that it received 2,184 cases of clarification regarding the administration of common parts of buildings, all of which were resolved. There are also 2,109 requests for “the provision of favorable information for convening the general assembly of the condominium and the administration of condominiums”, of which 1,909 were resolved.
The organization also dealt with 1,110 situations regarding the availability of the list of owners, of which 1,075 were resolved. The IH also received 412 requests for certificates, 315 for the deposit of a copy of the minutes, 12 relating to strengthening communication on the administration of the common parts of buildings and one case on collaboration in resolving disagreements/emerging conflicts on the administration of the common parts of buildings.
Furthermore, by the end of last year, there were 850 private buildings and 76 affordable housing buildings with active administration and records deposited, including sub-condominiums of buildings under complex administration.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2026-01-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Requests for more nursing homes to fill the lack of vacancies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pedidos-mais-lares-de-idosos-para-colmatar-falta-de-vagas/</link><description>Waiting for a place in nursing homes “takes around two years or more”, says José Pereira Coutinho. The reception of older people in nursing homes led to a written question from the deputy, in which he questioned the Government about what measures could be adopted to combat the problem and resolve it in the short term.
 
The need to admit the elderly to homes, due to families' difficulties in caring for them at home, leading to an increase in demand for reception spaces, public or private, is a topic raised by José Pereira Coutinho.
In a written interpellation, the deputy alerts the Government to the fact that the household is getting smaller, couples have fewer and fewer children and even these, he says, “most of them are active in the job market, showing a noticeable lack of family members to take care of the elderly”.
Considering that in Macau the waiting time for a place “takes around two years or more to be admitted and the waiting list increases rapidly with more new elderly people registering, also increasing the waiting time”, the member of the Legislative Assembly wants to know what measures will be implemented in the short and medium term to reduce the “queue” to enter public or private nursing homes, but subsidized by the Government. He also questions what is being thought of to build more nursing homes or homes for the elderly in the Macao SAR, in order to “address the lack of vacancies” and solve this “serious problem”.
José Pereira Coutinho also wants to know whether the Government is planning and executing actions to solve the problems of elderly people on the waiting list for a place in homes.
The deputy recalls that with the increase in population aging, greater life expectancy and the drastic reduction in births “have created enormous pressures on families” in terms of caring for their relatives in their old age, “especially those who are victims of Alzheimer's, cardiovascular accidents and strokes with irreversible consequences or with serious orthopedic problems and who are immobilized or bedridden”. Therefore, he talks about the “need for more places” in homes or beds in long-term care in the public sector.
“Over the last three years, our Citizens Assistance Office [of the Public Service Workers Association] has received many requests for support from family members who have difficulty caring for their elderly relatives themselves, especially those who, after being admitted to hospitals, are asked to recover at home”, states the member of the Hemicycle.
“In many of these cases”, he states in his question, “the financial conditions of the family and the type of relationship between parents and children also greatly influence the choice between institutionalizing or caring for the elderly at home”.
On the other hand, he adds, “elderly people, many of them disabled, live alone or with family members who need to work, and are unable, for reasons of force majeure, to take care of their parents or elderly relatives”, he concludes.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2026-01-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Double exhibition celebrates 160 years of Guia Lighthouse</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dupla-exposicao-celebra-160-anos-farol-da-guia/</link><description>The Maritime Museum created an online version of the commemorative exhibition “A Century of Vigilance – 160 years of the Guia Lighthouse and 10 years of the Management of Maritime Areas”, which has registered a “high influx” of visitors since its inauguration, on October 11 of this year, informed the Directorate of Maritime Affairs and Water Services (DSAMA). In order to facilitate access and improve the public's experience, the Maritime Museum decided to present diverse information from this exhibition through virtual reality technology and digital technology.
Through the virtual visit, the public will have the opportunity to learn about the evolution of maritime management, hydrographic surveys, nautical charts and navigation support equipment over the last century in Macau, as well as the history and documentation on the development of the Guia Lighthouse. The online exhibition is available in Chinese, Portuguese and English on the Maritime Museum's website (www.museumaritimo.gov.mo).
Managed by DSAMA, the Guia Lighthouse is considered the first modern in the Far East, and its configuration and internal structure have undergone several changes since it came into operation in September 1865. In this exhibition, models of the Lighthouse's lamps and their evolution are displayed, as well as nautical charts from the last century, hydrographic survey tools, old tide tables, maritime signal lamps, among others. Furthermore, at the exhibition site, a hand plumb provides an interactive experience.
Recalling that the various navigation support equipment, from lighthouses to maritime beacons, played an important piloting role in the last century in Macau, DSAMA emphasizes that “the safety and management of maritime areas constitute permanent concerns for port cities”. In this sense, the organization highlights that it has carried out various works within its competences, namely in the areas of maritime services, port management, vessel registration, dredging, maintenance of channels and maritime beacons, hydrographic survey, production of nautical charts, among others.
The exhibition is free to enter and runs until June 8th, but the online version will continue to be available after that date. The Maritime Museum is open between 10am and 6pm, every day except Tuesdays).</description><pubDate>2026-01-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sands gives bonuses and salary increases</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sands-da-bonus-aumentos-salariais/</link><description>Sands China will pay a bonus equivalent to one month's salary to its eligible full-time workers on February 6, the gaming operator said. The bonus is for all employees who are not part of the management team and who have been with the company for more than a year. For members of the management team, the bonus will be paid based on individual performance, the company's Management Incentive Plan and financial results. Additionally, Sands China will increase salaries for eligible workers from March 1, benefiting 99% of its approximately 28,000 team members. Eligible full-time employees earning monthly salaries of up to 16,000 patacas (before tax) will receive a salary increase of 500 patacas, resulting in a salary increase of between 3.1% and 4.0%. For monthly salaries above 16,000 patacas, the increase will be 2.0%. In a message to workers, Grant Chum, executive director of Sands China, stated that “2025 was a remarkable year” for the operator, highlighting “team collaboration and execution”, which is why the bonus and salary increase appear in recognition of their “efforts”. “Looking to the future, I hope the team continues to strive for excellence and reach even higher heights,” he added. Sands was the last of the six operators to announce bonuses to workers this year.</description><pubDate>2026-01-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Subsidizing tariffs in the “Novo Bairro” requires “exhaustive consideration”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/subvencao-de-tarifas-novo-bairro-requer-ponderacao-exaustiva/</link><description>The extension of water and electricity tariff relief to the “New Neighborhood of Macau” in Hengqin requires “exhaustive consideration, in conjunction with the general political orientation of the Macao SAR Government, the reasonableness in the application of public funds and the actual situation of society”, defended the deputy director of the Finance Services, Ho In Mui, in response to a question from deputy Leong Sun Iok. It is worth remembering that, since 2008, the Government has been establishing the “Subsidy Program for the Payment of Electricity Tariffs to Housing Units”, aimed at providing financial support to local housing units. The implementation of this program is now in its 18th phase, with each housing unit being able to benefit from a monthly electricity subsidy, with a maximum amount of 200 patacas. At the same time, the Government grants water tariff subsidies to both local and non-housing housing units. On the other hand, in the same response it is said that, since its opening a year ago, the “Novo Bairro” Health Center “has operated satisfactorily”. Cervical cancer screening services, flu vaccination, as well as laboratory tests are provided. Currently, 545 Macau medicines are available across the border, while the Health Services maintain “continuous collaboration with the competent services in Mainland China, aiming to promote a pharmaceutical policy that facilitates the population's access to medicines”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CCTV DOCUMENTARY MARKS 20 YEARS OF WORLD HERITAGE</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/documentario-da-cctv-assinala-20-anos-patrimonio-mundial/</link><description>To celebrate the 20th anniversary of the inclusion of the Historic Center of Macau on the UNESCO World Heritage List, the Cultural Institute (IC) and China Media Group produced the documentary entitled “Macau: Open-air Museum”. According to the IC, this documentary was broadcast for the first time on December 19th, on the CCTV-9 television channel, and is available on the website “cctv.com” and on the YouTube platform for global viewers to watch. Having as its main axis the stories of several characters, the documentary shows the journey of safeguarding and the process of inheritance of Macau's World Heritage, in a “real and three-dimensional” way, through the perspectives of a series of characters with close ties to the Historic Center, including residents, young students, heirs of intangible heritage, historians, restoration specialists, Macanese artists, architects and cultural heritage conservators. According to the IC, this production not only recalls the “challenging World Heritage nomination process” 20 years ago, but also focuses on the “rich and innovative” practical experiences that Macau has accumulated in the areas of protection, revitalization and inheritance of cultural heritage since the inclusion of the Historic Center on the World Heritage List. At the same time, it “delicately describes” how different generations of the local population conceived unique cultural heritage items in the context of exchanges and clashes between Eastern and Western cultures, further revealing how these heritage elements deeply integrate and influence the daily lives and spiritual world of contemporary people in Macau.</description><pubDate>2026-01-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>BRIEF</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2526/</link><description>Fast train between Xiamen, Fuzhou and Zhuhai
On the 26th of this month, the first direct fast train line between Xiamen, Fuzhou and Zhuhai will be opened. The Tourism Services Bureau (DST) will place advertisements online and at high-speed train stations with Macau's tourist information. Furthermore, it will encourage the MSAR's tourism sector and Fujian's major international travel agencies to launch signature “Macao+Fujian” itineraries, which highlight the history and culture of that province and Macao's eastern and western characteristics. According to DST, between January and November 2025, the Macao SAR welcomed 600,000 visitors from Fujian, representing 2.5% of the total.
 
Fifth connection studied in the form of a tunnel
The Government is studying the feasibility of building the fifth Macau-Taipa connection in the form of a tunnel, in conjunction with the public transport network, said Lam Wai Hou, director of Public Works Services, in response to a written question from Leong Pou U. The director also mentioned that a “comprehensive analysis of the NAPE road network and the surrounding area” is being carried out, promising to release more information “in a timely manner”.
 
Extended support period for eye patients
The Ou Mun Newspaper Readers' Charitable Fund and the Kiang Wu Charitable Association yesterday renewed the deadline for the Vision Recovery Plan to 2028. According to the institutions, in the last 31 years, the Plan has financed 2,711 surgeries for people with eye diseases. Tina Ho, president of the Charity Fund, said that the fund has already channeled more than 25 million patacas towards vision recovery projects. It also revealed that the fund's annual financing for this plan increased from 1.5 million to 1.8 million patacas.
 
Two injured in accident on Sai Van bridge
Traffic on the Sai Van bridge was restricted yesterday afternoon, after five cars collided and caused two injuries. According to firefighters, the cause of the accident is being investigated.</description><pubDate>2026-01-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brazil makes history at the Golden Globes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/brasil-faz-historia-nos-globos-de-ouro/</link><description>epa12644043 Brazilian actor Wagner Moura poses in the press room with the award for best performance by a male actor in a motion picture - drama for 'The Secret Agent' during the 83rd annual Golden Globe Awards ceremony at the Beverly Hilton Hotel in Beverly Hills, California, USA, 11 January 2026. The Golden Globe Awards recognize outstanding achievements in the global film and television industries.  EPA/CHRIS TORRES



Brazilian cinema made history by winning two statuettes at the Golden Globes, with the film “The Secret Agent” being considered Best in a Non-English Language and Wagner Moura being distinguished as Best Actor.
“The Secret Agent is a film about memory, the lack of memory and generational trauma,” said Wagner Moura, upon accepting the Golden Globe. “If trauma can be passed from generation to generation, so can values”, he continued, dedicating the award to those who continue to “defend their values ​​in difficult times”.
It was the first time that the Golden Globe for Best Actor was awarded to a Brazilian. Moura, who won in a category that also included Michael B. Jordan, Dwayne Johnson, Joel Edgerton, Oscar Isaac and Jeremy Allen White, ended his speech speaking in Portuguese to everyone in Brazil who attended the ceremony.
“I dedicate this to young filmmakers”, director Kléber Mendonça Filho had said, minutes before, upon receiving the Golden Globe for Best Film in a Non-English Language. “This is a very important moment in history to make films, both here in the USA and in Brazil”, he stated, in English.
“The Secret Agent” was also nominated for Best Dramatic Film, but lost the statuette to “Hamnet”, the period film directed by Chloé Zhao about the private life of William Shakespeare.
The director recalled words from the protagonist, Paul Mescal, who told her that the most important thing in an artist is to be vulnerable enough to be seen as he really is. “So many of you have become strong and soft at the same time,” Zhao said, addressing the filmmakers in the room. “Let’s let them see us,” he added. The film's protagonist, Jessie Buckley, also took home the Globe for Best Actress in a Motion Picture Drama.
The big winner of the night, which marked the 83rd edition of the awards, was “One Battle After Another”, which took home the statuettes for Best Musical or Comedy Film, Best Screenplay, Best Director for Paul Thomas Anderson and Best Supporting Actress for Teyana Taylor. “Purpose always finds its moment,” said the actress, who was the first winner of the night in Los Angeles. “Our light does not need permission to shine,” she said, addressing the “sisters and girls of color” who saw her triumph at the ceremony.
In the Musical or Comedy category, Rose Byrne was Best Actress for “If I had Legs I’d Kick You” and Timothée Chalamet was Best Actor for “Marty Supreme”.
Stellan Skarsgard emerged victorious as Best Supporting Actor for “Sentimental Value”, an independent film spoken in Norwegian that became one of the year's favorites.
But one of the most rated, “Sinners”, ended up taking home just two Golden Globes: Best Soundtrack, written by Ludwig Göransson, and Cinematic and Box Office Achievement.
The Netflix phenomenon “Adolescence” dominated the Golden Globes in the television categories, with four awards, followed by the medical drama “The Pitt” and the comedy “The Studio”, which won two awards each.
The series about a 13-year-old boy called Jamie, arrested for the murder of a classmate, won the award for best mini-series, while British actors Owen Cooper and Stephen Graham repeated their Emmy success, taking home the Golden Globes for best actor and best supporting actor, respectively. Erin Doherty, who plays the psychologist in the third episode of the series, also won the award for best supporting actress.
 
JTM with Lusa and international agencies</description><pubDate>2026-01-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>