<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Apomac goes to elections with continuity plan</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/apomac-vai-eleicoes-plano-de-continuidade/</link><description>The Macao's retirees, retired and pensioners association goes to elections on Friday with only one competing list, under the motto "We are elderly but energetic." Francisco Mannão will remain president of the Board and Jorge Fão as leader of the General Assembly. Napoleon Assisi is the only new face for the three -year term. The current leaders intend to continue the work for the elderly, that is, “solve their problems”. On the other hand, improving canteen management is one of the priorities
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Most of the current managing bodies of the Macao's retirees, retired and pensioners (Apomac) association will remain for the next three years of office. This is because only one list competes for elections, scheduled for Friday from 15h00.
The main managers of the Association, Francisco Mannão, president of the Board, and Jorge Fão, number one of the General Assembly, will remain in the positions, with only a significant change, with the entry of Napoleon Assis to vowel. The new member is linked to some associations and his work is already known to the current leaders.
"We recruited this new element, which has agreed to work with us, which is not always possible to assure this type of volunteering mission, which requires a lot of dedication and immense work to solve a number of problems with which our members are faced, such as the proof of life," Tribuna de Macau Jorge Fão, in office, told the foundation of Apomac in 2001.
The 78 -year -old leader confirms the existence, once again, of only one list, as has been found since the association's foundation. "If there was another list, I would take it, as long as a serious person appears to take my place and do not environmental interests, other than serving the association."
Apomac's social bodies' application list for the 2025-2028 triennium, we are based on the motto "We are elderly but energetic." “Although elderly we are energetic, and thereby voluntarily contribute to the energy that still remains to support those who need, offering our services and know,” explains Francisco Mannão.
The leader acknowledges that "volunteering practically does not exist in a capitalist society like ours, where everything negotiates", hence the association wants to continue the work started "how far and when possible".
In the program for the ninth consecutive mandate, Marnão states that Apomac seeks to monitor the government's policy and the Macau Foundation with a view to adjusting the needs to the “action program” for the next three years.
"We will continue to provide the necessary support to associates so that they can enjoy the benefits awarded by the government and other official entities, as well as support them with the Portuguese Retirement General and the Macao Pension Fund," he says.
Regarding other activities, which are usually held throughout each year, the candidacy program points to the “promotion of more lectures on well-being and health” and the “organization of sightseeing tours to mainland China, making known its culture and success”. In other points of the manifesto, in focus, also the promotion of more coexistence, "thus allowing members to come periodically join," and the intention to "improve, whenever possible, canteen management."
In addition, Apomac, which next year celebrates the 25th anniversary, thus celebrating the silver jubilee, intends to "continue to support national politics" a country, two systems "for Macao to always be our paradise."
Francisco Mannhão, who has been with Jorge Fão since the early years of Apomac, has, in terms of the future, a dream. “I liked to build a satellite city, because it would be good to host all the elderly people, offering them a number of conditions in which they could live, have sites to read the newspapers, shopping in a mini-market space, among others,” he advocates.
The chairman of the 75-year-old Apomac says he will not give up on this idea, being concerned about the safety conditions of the elderly. “I think the government builds buildings for older people, but do you put them on very high floors, which probably is not your liking, will it be the best solution?” He asks.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Panda visits rose 189% compared to 2019</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/visitas-aos-pandas-subiram-189-face-2019/</link><description>Pandas Jian Jian and Kang Kang, and their parents Xin Xin and Kai Kai, seem to be attracting more and more visits-last year, more than 372,000 went to the Pandas Pavilion to see these animals, an 189% increase over the pre-pound year, according to data from the institute for municipal affairs. Currently, the body deals with about 300 animals, including birds, mammals and reptiles, in various areas of the city

Catarina Pereira
 
Jian Jian and Kang Kang, the first giant pandas born in Macau, as well as their parents, Xin Xin and Kai Kai, have received more visits in recent times. The family of giant pandas seems to be attracting the curiosity of increasingly places and tourists since, in 2019, the Giant Panda Pavilion recorded 128,508 visits and, last year, attracted 372,164 - an increase of 189%. The data were nominated for the Jornal Tribuna de Macao by the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI), which also mentioned that in 2023, the year the territory reopened after three years of pandemic, the pandes were visited by 289,715 people.
The twin brothers, both male and whose names said together they mean “health”, were born in June 2016 and are children of Pandas offered by China to the masket. They will complete, next June, nine years of existence.
Jian Jian has “round head, cute hair and hair, round and straightforward ears, wide cup, large nose, strong paws”. The older brother is also described by AMI as a "traquins and fun" animal, while the youngest is "affectionate". Kang Kang, in turn, features "a pointed head, narrow and long muzzle and folded ears forward."
As for the mother, Xin Xin, was born at the base of study of procreation of Chengdu giant pandas. With "round face, short paws and chubby body", is "cute and shy," according to AMI. Kai Kai, his father, was born in the same place in Chengdu. It is "corpulent" and has "long paws", being "very curious and fun".
Pointing out that the Giant Panda Pavilion, located in Seac Pai Van Park, is a place of conservation of these animals outside its habitat, the AMI stresses that “its main role consists in playing the function of preserving the species and, at the same time, transmitting important information about the conservation work of giant pandas”.
The pavilion consists of two interior spaces of 330 square meters, intended for panda activities, and by an outdoor garden of 600 square meters. There is also an information center on the giant panda, equipped with a multimedia room, exhibition zone, reading space, among others.
Panda is an animal with a special symbolism for China, also playing a role in the level of diplomacy, as the country has the tradition of sending these animals to foreign zoos gardens. China has developed important means to preserve the animal's species and habitat, which led the International Union to the conservation of nature to remove, in 2016, the giant panda from the list of most endangered species.
According to AMI, there are currently about 300 animals to be raised at Seac Pai Van Park, Garden of Flora and Granja do Óscar, under the management of this body, including birds, mammals and reptiles. In recent years, in the optimization of gardens and leisure zones, "AMI has considered the balance between the various functional areas, in order to provide the public and animals a comfortable space for leisure and life," he said in response to this newspaper.
 
New Leisure Zone in Seac Pai Van
The new leisure zone of Alameda da Harmonia, between the Lok Kuan and IP Heng buildings, in Seac Pai Van, is already open, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) said. Outdoor facilities are suitable for different age groups, with separated zones depending on the ages of children and adults. The space, with a total area of ​​about 2,730 square meters, includes climbing elements and proper challenges “so that children can increase the sense of coordination and balance”, reinforcing their physical fitness. The dedicated area to adults also takes into account the needs of young people, adults and the elderly, “with rich and diverse facilities,” says AMI. The opening hours of the children's fun zone is from 07:00 to 22:00 and the dedicated area to adults remains 24 hours a day. AMI hopes to respond to the needs of residents of the Seac Pai Van community neighborhood, through the use and reordering of existing public spaces, creating “a rich and diverse leisure environment”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MIECF brings together exhibitors from 40 countries or regions</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/miecf-reune-expositores-de-40-paises-ou-regioes/</link><description>DCIM100GOPROG0039927.JPG



Macau's International Environmental Cooperation Forum and Exhibition starts tomorrow's Cotai Expoi EXPO focused on the ecological transformation and with the presence of exhibitors from 40 countries and regions. The event will have as its theme “Innovation and Green Development - Solutions for the Construction of Beautiful Cities” and has, in parallel, three sessions of the “Green Forum”, which will bring together experts and academics
 
Victor Rebelo
 
This year's edition of the Macao 2025 International Environmental Cooperation and International Exhibition (MIECF) will feature exhibitors from 40 countries or regions, bringing together renowned experts and academics from the interior of China, Southeast Asia, Europe, Hong Kong and Macau, which will jointly explore new opportunities for international exchange and cooperation at the international level. Of between 60 foreign stands, 26 belong to exhibitors Lusophone, who bring Macau products related to new energies, waste management, wastewater treatment and environmental hygiene, according to the president of the Institute for Promotion of Trade and Investment (IPIM), Vincent U.
According to IPIM estimates, the number of international professional participants at the fair may record an annual increase of 23%. The number of international participants overall should grow about 17% compared to the 2024 event.
At the MIECF presentation press conference, which starts tomorrow and will take place until Saturday, the president of Ipim said that this year's edition focuses on the “debut economy”. In the exclusive exhibition zone for this theme, more than 20 new products or projects will be first launched, for example, a mechanical dog, automatic electric motorcycle parking technology and a new biodegradable material, among others.
"Contact bags will also be made for some products, in order to highlight the potential of debut economy," said Vincent U.
In turn, IP Kuong Lam, director of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA), stressed that the MIECF will host three sessions of “Green Forum”, centered on green transformation, technological innovation and exchange and cooperation in the environment of the Rio das Pearl Delta region. The last day of the exhibition, Saturday, is defined as the “Open Day”, in which citizens can visit the exhibition zone for free.
Meanwhile, the deepened cooperation zone will organize four sessions inserted in the activity “An Exhibition/Convention, two regions”. The MIECF will have as its central theme “Innovation and Green Development - Solutions for the Construction of Beautiful Cities”. Among the sessions to be held over the three days, highlighting the “green transition driven by new quality productive forces”, which will take place on Friday morning.
 
BIOSHOES4ALL DISCLOSES PORTUGUESE FOOTWEAR
The Portuguese footwear sector will count this year with an exhibitor at MIECF, with the aim of presenting the latest industry news through the Bioshoes4all project. The stand will be shared with the textile and clothing sector partners under the Beat Project, coordinated by Citeve.
The coordination of the trip to Macao from representatives of Portuguese shoes is up to the Portuguese Association of Shoes, Components, Skin Articles and their Substitutes (Apiccaps), after an invitation directed by the Portuguese Environment Association.
In a statement, and citing statements by Maria José Ferreira, from the Technological Center, the body states that “in practical terms, it is public that the cluster of footwear and fashion assumes as a vision to be an international reference in the development of sustainable solutions, reinforcing Portuguese exports based on a highly competitive national productive basis, based on knowledge and innovation”.
Determinant for the characterization of these objectives is the Bioshoes4all Project. “It is completely aligned with the goals advocated in Portugal's Economic Recovery Plan, involves 70 partners and an investment of around 60 million euros,” says Maria José Ferreira.
The project's head of the project stresses that it is divided into five pillars of intervention (biomaterials, ecological footwear, circular economy, advanced production and training technologies and promotion), and “has the ambition to induce radical change in materials, technologies, processes and products of shoes and Moroccan”.
Already Paulo Gonçalves, from Apiccaps, regrets that "90% of footwear production is focused on major Asian players", since "it is possible to produce in Europe of quality, lasting and fair prices." For this, “it is important to define new business models that are based on the sophistication and creativity of Portuguese supply, at the level of biomaterials, ecoproducts, digital and agile processes, and sustainable business models, thus betting on market segments on which the choice is based more on fashion and technicity than price”.
In this sense, it reinforces Apiccaps spokesman, “it is essential to ensure a resilient national productive base for positioning in the international market in which innovation, differentiation, rapid and effective response, service, product quality, training and promotion are competitive arguments that allow us to be superior to competition”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Flu Patient Consultations increased 38.5%</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/consultas-de-doentes-gripe-aumentaram-385/</link><description>Last week, the daily average of patients with flu symptoms in Macao represented a 9.2% increase in emergency and 38.5% at the Conde de São Januário and Kiang Wu hospitals compared to the previous four weeks. Health services therefore find that the respiratory tract virus is still active and advise vaccination again
 
Victor Rebelo
 
According to diseases surveillance data with flu flu to the hospitals of Conde de São Januário, last week the average daily number of emergency service users was about 1,333 consultations (including 313 children) compared to 1,221 in the previous four weeks, with an increase of 9.2%.
Meanwhile, also in the last seven days, the daily average of patients treated in those units was 108 (68 of which children), compared to 78 patients in the previous four weeks, which represents an increase of 38.5%. These data show that, at this moment, the spread of the respiratory tract virus in Macau is still active.
Regarding cases of collective flu infection, from January to date, 78 cases of collective infection of diseases with flu symptoms were reported, of which 13 were caused by Covid-19 and occurred in homes.
As for other collective infection situations, 29 cases caused by influenza A viruses were detected, five by influenza B and 13 by pathogenic agents of the respiratory tract. In the remaining 18 cases it was not possible to identify the pathogenic agent.
Only on March 21, health services (SSM) were notified of three cases of collective infection of the new type of coronaviruses, which took place at Home of Zidoso Fok Hoi, the Estrela do Mar School and the “Retribution” senior citizen support complex.
Since the beginning of the year, no serious case or death related to Sars-Cov-2 virus has not been registered in Macau. However, given that people of high risk, namely the elderly, patients with serious chronic diseases, people with weakened immune system are at greater risk of serious diseases or death, after infection, SSM recommend reinforcement of prevention and inoculation of JN.1 Vaccine against COVID-19 as soon as possible.
In a statement, SSM stresses that treatment with antiviral drugs against Covid-19) can prevent the reproduction of the virus and, the use of this type of medicine, within five days after infection, can effectively reduce the risk of severe cases and death.
For high-risk groups, “if they manifest suspicious symptoms of COVID-19, such as fever and other respiratory symptoms, they should submit to antigen testing,” the body stresses.
Given the numbers in recent weeks, and in order to reduce the influenza, Covid-19 infection, and other transferable diseases of the higher respiratory tract, SSM intend to sensitize, once again, residents for the adoption of various prevention measures, including annual vaccination against seasonal flu and Covid-19.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China wants to strengthen ties with Portugal</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/china-quer-fortalecer-lacos-portugal/</link><description>China is ready to work with Portugal to develop a “more stable, fruitful and dynamic” relationship and make the two countries “strategic partners of trust and mutual achievements”, the Chinese Minister of Foreign Affairs, a meeting in Beijing with the Portuguese counterpart, noted that this year marks the 20th anniversary of the establishment of the “comprehensive strategic partnership” between the two nations and the 50th of relations diplomatic between China and the European Union.
According to the Xinhua agency, Wang pointed out that China and Portugal have "a good tradition of respect" and "mutual support", and that "they have" properly resolved the issue of Macao with political wisdom. "
The minister also argued that the modernization of China offers greater opportunities to Portugal and other countries in the world. "Both sides should actively expand cooperation and exchanges between people, continue to play the role of Macau as a bridge and boost greater development of bilateral relations," he said, according to Xinhua.
In turn, according to the official Chinese agency, Rangel praised the success of the principle "a country, two systems" in Macao and ensured that Portugal attributes great importance to relations with China and "adheres firmly to the policy of one China." Recognizing that Chinese investment has played an important role in Portugal's economic and social development, it was also willing to strengthen cooperation with China in the fields of economics, trade, energy, health, finance, infrastructure and green transformation.
 
Relations in a “very positive” state
Speaking to the Lusa agency, the Portuguese minister stressed the “very positive” state of the relationship with China, devaluing the absence of visits in the last five years. "The fact that there was this hiatus did not slow down the interest that both countries have in their bilateral relationship," he said after meeting with Wang Yi at the beginning of a four-day visit to China, which will also include travel to Macau and Hong Kong.
Rangel justified the absence of visits with “some government instability in Portugal”, refusing any discomfort in relationships, despite the approach of Beijing to Moscow, in the context of Ukraine's Russian invasion, and Lisbon's decision to exclude Chinese suppliers from 5G networks, namely Huawei. "Our relationship with China is bilateral. It is not dependent on the geopolitical circumstances of each moment, even if they may be relevant, in terms of orientation changes, which we think they may have medium or long term impact, not just short -term," he said.
Regarding the possibility of the antagonistic position of US President Donald Trump in relation to the transatlantic alliance to revitalize the dialogue between Portugal and China, the Portuguese minister was clear: "The dialogue with China does not depend on the situation in the US." "The relationship with China is 500 years old. In the last 45 years he had great development, deepening and enrichment. Macao's transition model was an exemplary model. After that, this strategic relationship was created," he said.
On the other hand, he stated that Lisbon "does not review" in some of China's proposals to end the war in Ukraine, but pointed out that Beijing may play "positive role." "We do not review each other in some of the principles in this statement, but all the contributions of those who can play a positive role are welcome," he said.
 
Jtm with Lusa and Xinhua</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Education, leisure and social services absorb UPM newborn</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/educacao-lazer-servicos-sociais-absorvem-recem-graduados-da-upm/</link><description>According to UPM Vice-Rector, Education, Leisure and Entertainment and Social Services are the three sectors that most absorb the institution's newborns to work. On the other hand, more than 80% have already achieved jobs or decided to continue their studies
 
The most recent inquiry into the continuation of the studies and employment of newborns at the Macao Polytechnic University (UPM) indicates that more than 80% have already achieved employment or opted to continue their studies, Vivian Lei, UPM, on the sidelines of “Career Day 2025”, revealed.
The deputy dean said that the newly graded UPM already contracted earns an average monthly compensation of 16 thousand patacas, with education, leisure and entertainment and social services the three sectors that most absorb the students who leave the institution.
According to the Chinese language press, Vivian Law also indicated that Oxford University, Columbia University and the University of Lisbon are the most chosen institutions by graduates who decide to continue their studies.
As part of “Career Day”, UPM invited more than 130 local companies and institutions from the Great Bay, which provide 3,000 jobs or internship vacancies in the area of ​​Information Technology, Integrated Leisure, Finance, among others. At the same time, 10 lectures were given to help students know the employment environment and market demand information.
In a speech given during the event, Vivian Law stressed that globalization, support from the country and the training provided by the Government of MSAR and higher education institutions will bring new development opportunities for students. The UPM vice-rector expects students to take advantage of these opportunities, demonstrating their talents to actively integrate into the national development conjuncture.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Signed seven agreements between masters and heilongjiang</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/assinados-sete-acordos-entre-raem-heilongjiang/</link><description>The sgas signed seven memos and cooperation agreements with Heilongjiang, following a meeting between the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, and the secretary of the provincial committee of the CCP, Xu Qin.
According to an official note, Sam Hou Fai argued that the two parties "gather different advantages in resources and industries, so the perspective of cooperation will be wide." He also pointed out that they will reinforce cooperation in order to inject new dynamics in promoting the development of the diversification of Macau's economy.
In concrete, a memo of tourist cooperation was signed between the Heilongjiang Department of Culture and Tourism and the Macao Tourism Services, and another between the Heilongjiang Province Trade Department and the Institute for Promotion of Trade and Investment. Memorandum was also sealed among the education departments of the two locations and a strategic cooperation agreement in the area of ​​traditional Chinese medicine, between health services and the management of traditional Chinese medicine of Heilongjiang.
The Institute of Sport and the Sport Administration of that province also signed an Exchange and Cooperation Framework Agreement, while the Education and Development and Youth Services established with the Heilongjiang Youth Federation a memo of cooperation on the deepening of exchange.
Finally, an agreement was signed on the creation of the Heilongjiang Medicines Certification of Quality Certification and Product Innovation between the University of Macao and the Academy of Traditional Chinese Medicine of that province.
 
Forum reinforces “cultural and humanistic” exchange
On the occasion of the visit of the Heilongjiang delegation to Macau, a cooperation agreement was signed between the Macao Forum Permanent Secretariat and the Province Trade Department, in which “they will strengthen bilateral exchange, organize or jointly participate in economic and commercial and humanistic and humanistic exchange activities”.
The idea is to take advantage of Heilongjiang's “advantages” to promote China's forum action and measures to promote economic and commercial cooperation with PLP, as well as encourage the “opening of Heilongjiang”, develop the role of Macau as a sino-sidoponic platform and streamline “comprehensive mutual benefits” with PLP.
 
Boss participates in the Boao Forum
The chief executive leads, today and tomorrow, a delegation of the MSAR that will be in Haião to participate in the annual conference of the Boao Forum to Asia. Like what has been happening, the Commissioner of the China Foreign Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Liu Xianfa, is part of the delegation as a guest advisor. The conference focuses on promoting cooperation in a world in “rapid transformation”, how to rebalance globalization and how to explore the potential of artificial intelligence. The MSAR delegation is also composed by the secretary to the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP, and the chief of staff of the chief executive among others. In the absence of Sam Hou Fai, André Cheong will interim the functions of Chief Executive.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Total Harmonic Experience” in concert at the Military Club</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/experiencia-harmonica-total-em-concerto-clube-militar/</link><description>The Military Club will organize another classical music session, with the concert “Total Harmonic Experience - The Piano Trio”. Scheduled for Friday, the show will bring together pianist Robin Zebaida, violinist Meidaad Yehudayan and the cellist Si Won Park
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Concert “Total Harmonic Experience - The Piano Trio” is the title of another concert integrated in the musical journeys promoted by the Military Club. For the session on Friday, March 28, at 19:00, at Stanley Ho Salon, pianist Robin Zebaida, Violinist Meidaad Yehudayan and the cellist Si Won Park were invited.
The trio will interpret composers of recognized composers in the landscape of classical music such as Shostakovich (Andante, Allegro Con Brio, Largo and Allegretto - Adagio) and Rachmaninov (slow lugubre), as well as popular excerpts from Mozart (Allegretto), Schumann (Traumerei) and Schubert (Marche Militaire).
Meidaad -in -aisite violinist and conductor Yehudayan developed several solo and chamber projects with members of the Berlin, Israel and Hong Kong Philharmonic Orchestras, including performances from the White House in Washington to the World Peace Festival in South Korea. American Protégé ”in New York, was invited to the jury of various festivals, such as Viena, Chamber music Vanke Meisha in China and Hong Kong strings, and directed“ Masterclasses ”in California and the University of Indiana.
Meidaad Yehudayan was director of orchestra and ropes at the Hong Kong International School between 1999 and 2023. Under his guidance and as creator of the program, he had the privilege of educating thousands of students, creating and developing a world -class string and orchestra program and raising millions of dollars to school.
The musician obtained the bachelor's degree in music and the artist diploma at the Faculty of Performative Arts of the Academy of Music and Dance Rubin of Jerusalem, where he studied violin and viola with Samuel Bernstein. He then became the first Israeli student to be sent to the Moscow's Tchaikovsky Conservatory.
The South Korean Si Won Park began musical career at Carnegie Hall in New York, after winning the 1997 International Artists Contest. Active soloist and chamber music, she played in Asia, Europe and US in places such as "Alice Tully Hall" at Lincoln Center, "Walt Disney Concert" in Los Angeles, "Kumho Art Hall" in Seul and "Hong" Kong City Hall ”.
In recognition of musical experience and distinction, she was appointed cultural director of the Korean Chamber of Commerce in Hong Kong and received a prize, awarded by the Minister of Gender Equality and the South Korea family, for the role as responsible for the International Korean women in Raehk. SI WON PARK is part of the Board of Directors of the Advisory Board for Peaceful Unification.
The artist who will act at the Military Club has been distinguished in numerous regional and international contests, including the Marta Istomin award, "Westchester Suny" and "Korean Monthly Music Magazine Competition."
Robin Zebaida will be presented to the piano, an instrument with which he participated in concerts in the US, Canada, Central America, Europe, the Far East and Australia. For this year, there are concerts scheduled for various countries or regions of Asia, including China, Philippines, Thailand and Cambodia. It is often requested for lectures, preconce conversations and “masterclasses”, and regularly invited to serve as a member of the jury in the panels of various regional and international piano contests.
In a career that covers many aspects of music production, Zebaida, born in London and currently piano professor in Hong Kong, also acts as a accompanyor, camera music partner and soloist concerts. Its group “Classical Cornucopia” has shown on several thematic cruises of classical music.
Those interested in watching the concert will have to spend 120 patacas, with cocktail included. For those who want to participate at the club's post-concept dinner, the cost of the ticket is 330 Patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Cultural Promotion Month” provides 26 experiences</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mes-da-promocao-cultural-proporciona-26-experiencias/</link><description>?????????????? 0 ????????



Experience theater in Patuá, Cantonense Opera, “Being librarian for a day” and knowing the world heritage will be possible during April, which will be dedicated to “cultural promotion”. There are 26 activities divided into four themes
 
April will be the “Month of Cultural Promotion”, an initiative that aims to “mark the diverse dissemination and transmission of culture”, as well as “integrate art and culture in daily life”, explains the Cultural Institute (IC). Unfolding in four themes -“Craft Transmission”, “Space of Artistic Experimentation”, “In Contact with Art and Culture” and “Lecture on Aesthetics” -the event offers the public 26 activities of artistic and cultural experience “from various perspectives”, divided into a dozen sections.
In the context of “Craft Transmission”, participants will be able to try, for example, the theater in Patuá, the Cantonense Opera and the Tea Ceremony. According to the IC, the instructors will present the basic vocabulary and dialogues in Patuá through the theater, teach the basic movements and singing styles of the Cantonense opera, as well as guide the entire tea tasting process and incense appreciation, respectively. “Through close contact and experimentation, the public will be able to know the unique charm of traditional culture in a deepened way,” he adds.
Artistic creation activities will also be launched at the places of the World Heritage and other historical buildings, including “Come Get to Meet Our World Heritage”, “Japanese Floral Arrangement Workshop”, “3D Modeling Workshop” and “Facial Painting Activity”. These sessions, which intend to lead participants “to appreciate the beauty of architecture and art as they make creations”, are part of the field of “artistic experimentation space”.
In relation to the series “In Contact with Art and Culture”, an initial experience of artistic and cultural activities will be performed for parents and children. In concrete, including “being a librarian for a day”, participants can get to know the operation of libraries, as well as enjoy the pleasure of reading through an interactive experience of the services and resources of public libraries. On the other hand, the “choir of adults and children” is a “fun coral experience” for parents and children, says the IC, which will explore the potential and musical interests of children.
On the other hand, experts and academics will be invited to give lectures on aesthetics, “in order to observe, appreciate and enjoy beauty together with the public”. The event “Lecture on Aesthetics” aims to “inspire the public to have a greater perception of beauty in their daily lives,” according to the IC. The details about this session will be released later.
Entries can now be made through the single account. If the number of registrants exceeds the maximum provided for, the vacancies will be attributed by draw, being the participants admitted notified by message.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Activities for families celebrate Easter in Vila da Taipa</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/actividades-para-familias-celebram-pascoa-na-vila-da-taipa/</link><description>The Vila da Taipa Cultural Association returns the initiative “Easter Festive Fun” and invites the local community to participate in the activities of the festive period, on April 19 and 20
 
The “Easter Festive Fun” program of the Vila da Taipa Cultural Association is part of several family -oriented activities. In collaboration with local merchants, the association invites families to participate in a chocolate egg making workshop and an egg hunting, within the scope of Easter festivities.
According to the association, the workshop will be driven by Alberto Santos, head of the restaurant of Tapas de Portugal, where participants will have the opportunity to create Easter chocolate eggs with Portuguese curd filling.
On April 19, the two sessions of the workshop, one hour each, will take place between 15:00 and 17:00, in that restaurant, on Rua dos Clérigos. The price of participation is 450 patacas per family and includes ingredients for two chocolate eggs and a choice of drinks per person.
On the 20th, between 14:00 and 18:00, the Easter egg hunt will be held in the village of Taipa. The registration fee is 50 patacas per child and requires it to be accompanied by an adult. Each family will receive an egg hunting kit to complete missions in different control posts throughout the village of Taipa. Upon successful conclusion, each child will be rewarded with a gift.
The Association also invited the General Association of Macao Women to participate, on April 12, in an exclusive Workshop of Easter Chocolate Eggs.
The vice president of the Executive Board of the Taipa Village Cultural Association, Pamela Chan, justifies the return of the initiative “based on the tremendous success of the previous Easter festivities”, expressing the organization's enthusiasm for “reintroducing” a program “intended to promote connections within the local community”.
“Through partnership with local merchants and organizations, we endeavor to create an excited, cheerful and significant Easter experience for families, providing a fun opportunity to explore the vibrant history and unique heritage of Taipa village,” said Pamela Chan.
The Association, created in 2016, aims to highlight the uniqueness of the village of Taipa's heritage and reinforces its position as a community that benefits the entire territory. The organization has promoted numerous initiatives to preserve and improve the position of the village as a mandatory tourist and cultural destination.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>USJ reinforces partnerships in Hubei</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/usj-reforca-parcerias-em-hubei/</link><description>A delegation from the University of St. Joseph, led by Rector Stephen Morgan, visited Hubei universities, with the purpose of deepening academic cooperation between Macao and the Chinese province
 
The rector of the University of St. Joseph (USJ), Stephen Morgan, led a delegation that visited the University of Wuhan (WHU), the University of Science and Technology of Huazhong (Hust) and the Normal University of Central China (CCNU). The visits aimed to reinforce the academic collaboration between Macao and the three universities of Hubei, in the areas of humanities, social sciences, religious studies and philosophy.
On the first day of the tour, USJ representatives went to the Hust, where they were received by the institution's vice president, Zhang Yonghui, read in the USJ statement. The two parts performed “in -depth debates” about collaboration in the human and social sciences and, in particular, in philosophy. They planned the promotion of academic exchanges through conference co-organization and the reinforcement of academic visits.
Stephen Morgan stressed USJ's role as "a bridge between Chinese and Western cultures," highlighting its international resources. The rector of USJ also expressed the desire to collaborate with the Hust in favor of the development of the great bay.
The next day was marked by visiting CCNU, during which the two parts signed a memorandum of understanding. Peng Shuangjie, president of CCNU, underlined the importance of collaboration with the universities of Macau.
Morgan, in turn, expressed expecting this partnership to “create synergies” in student exchanges, academic visits and joint research, contributing “to the cultivation of high quality talent”. The discussions focused on collaboration in “inclusive education”, “family education” and “social services”.
On the last day of visits, Yu Vice-President Yuan Yufeng received the group led by the USJ dean, with whom he maintained "cordial conversations." Conversations about cooperation in philosophy and religious studies and student exchange culminated in signing a memorandum of understanding.
Yuan presented Whu's history and achievements in international collaboration and stressed "the importance of educational partnerships with Hong Kong and Macau." Morgan said that “USJ is committed to bridge between the interior of China and the international community,” in particular with Portuguese -speaking countries. The rector said he expects a “deeper cooperation” with the institution of Wuhan, in terms of academic investigation and the exchange of teachers and students.
Morgan has asserted that USJ will continue to “defend its internationalized education” and promote collaboration with universities on the continent, in an effort to serve as a “vital link” between China and the global community.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Renewed appeal to measles vaccination</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/renovado-apelo-a-vacinacao-contra-sarampo/</link><description>The predictable increase in the flow of people on the hollows of Cheng Ming and Easter, due to the displacement of many residents abroad, led Macao health services (SSM) to advise again to inoculation of measles vaccine at least two weeks in advance. The body considers that children who have not yet completed the two doses of the vaccine and pregnant women without immunity should avoid moving to regions with measles epidemic to reduce the risk of infection. Although Macau is not a region affected by a measles epidemic, as a tourist city, "the risk of importation and spread of the disease persists," the statement says. SSM recommend that minors should receive at least two doses of the measles vaccine for complete immunity and advise the inoculation of a dose of MMR vaccine at the 12th and 18th months of age respectively. As for the general population, aged 18 or over, suggest a dose of the MMR vaccine. The SSM appeals to residents that if they have suspicious measles symptoms, namely fever, rash and conjunctivitis, while traveling or after returning to Macau, they should turn to the doctor as soon as possible, informing the health professionals in detailed travel and contact history. People in need of vaccination, residents and non -residents authorized to stay in Macau for a long period can schedule vaccination at centers or health posts through prior marking. According to the World Health Organization, the measles epidemic has aggravated in some countries due to the low rate of child vaccination. In 2024, more than 127,000 cases were reported in Europe and Central Asia, with the highest number since 1997. More than 40% of cases involve children under five and more than half require hospitalization. Until March 6, 38 measles -related deaths were recorded in these regions of the world.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing for exchange in the black sand is already built</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/habitacao-para-troca-na-areia-preta-ja-esta-construida/</link><description>Situated in Lot P in the Black Sand, the Housing Project for Exchange called “Pearl Metropolitan” has already been completed, and inspection works are being carried out, Macao Urban Renewal S.A. (MRU) said. In addition, MRU opens on the spot visits to the applicants eligible to buy housing fractions for exchange, in order to allow them to know the conditions of the fractions. According to a statement from MRU, the exchange housing encompasses six blocks with a total of 2,064 fractions. All fractions have a balcony and electrodomers in the kitchen offered to owners. In addition, the windows are made with three-layer energy saving glass, effective in thermal and acoustic insulation, refers to MRU, adding that the venture adopts anti-faded steel cables to protect the safety of residents. On the other hand, each block has four elevators. Regarding parking, the change housing provides 1,873 places for light cars (all allow charging of electric cars) and 490 for motorcycles. In addition, the venture has a club, an outdoor pool, recreational and sports facilities, and landscapes of afforestation. In Lot P, there are also commercial spaces, a bus terminal, an exclusive pedestrian area, ambulance roads and two new 24 -meter -wide public roads, composed of four two -way bands and treadmills. Remember that, among more than 3,000 former owners of “Pearl Horizon”, only 1,932 requested housing for exchange, of which 1,899 saw their approved requests.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Nine -year -old tattoo artist causes surprise in Thailand</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/tatuador-de-nove-anos-causa-surpresa-na-tailandia/</link><description>Napat Mitmakorn is only nine years old, but already handles the tattoola pistol with great skill and without doubt that he wants to be a tattoo artist when he grows up.

“I want to be a tattoo artist and open my own studio,” says Napat, in a place where surprised visitors look at how his hands draw a long snake in his uncle's thigh.
“I like to draw, so I like to tattoo so much,” confesses the child.
Tattooing is an ancestral tradition in Thailand, where omnipresent studios propose all kinds of drawings, from the most traditional to the most modern and profane.
Napat's father Mitmakorn, Nattawut Sangtong, a passionate tattoo artist, says he began his son in the art of tattoo to distract him.
“I simply wanted to distance it from your mobile phone because I was addicted to the games and didn't have much concentration capacity,” says the 38-year-old man.
Like his father, Napat learned the work thanks to videos on Tiktok and before tattooing people trained in drawing leaves and then in pieces of artificial leather that simulate human skin.
At school, art was the favorite article of the young tattoo artist, who his father trains six hours per week to perfect the technique.
"It's not just tattooing, art has become meditation," said Nattawut Sangtong, who with his son manages an account with Tiktok on the topic called "The Tattoo artist with milk teeth."
In this account, he releases his tattoo sessions live, which attract thousands of viewers.
Recently, Napat Mitmakorn held his first public session in a studio in the Thai capital, tattooing a 20 -centimeter snake in his uncle's thigh.
So far, the father insists that the child works only with family and friends, as offering the child's drawings to other clients would require a more rigorous training in hygiene.
But Naruebet Chonlarachaisit, the little tattoo artist's uncle, was very quiet while the snake appeared in his left thigh. “I trust him and I believe it can only improve,” he says.
Napat Muangsawang, a visitor of the exhibition, stopped at the boy's stand to admire his art. "It's scary. Tattooing is not easy," he says. “It's not like drawing on a sheet of paper that can erase,” he adds, demonstrating his surprise to the child's ability.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>