<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Foreign visitors rose 14% in 2025</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/visitantes-estrangeiros-subiram-14-em-2025/</link><description>The flow of international visitors who traveled to Macau through the various border posts in 2025 translated into more than 2.75 million entries, an annual increase of almost 14%, according to the Public Security Police Corps
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
In 2025, the entry of foreign visitors to the Macao SAR recorded an annual increase of 13.7% to 2.75 million, who used the nine border posts, according to data from the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP).
Visitors from Mainland China naturally constituted the largest group, with more than 29 million, an increase of 18.5% compared to 2024. From Hong Kong came 7.31 million (+1.7%) and from Taiwan 996 thousand (+19.4%). In total, 40.06 million people visited Macau in 2025, 14.7% more than in the previous year.
Furthermore, during the New Year holiday period, that is, between December 31st and January 4th, authorities recorded a total of 766,240 visitors. On Sunday alone there were 99,631 visitors.
Statistics from 2025 indicate that all border posts registered 235 million crossings, an annual increase of 9.8% and a daily average of 640 thousand. Passages through land stations represented 93% of the total, while entries and exits through sea and air stations accounted for 7%.
On the other hand, border crossings by residents rose 10.1% to 85.78 million, year-on-year.
Also according to CPSP data, the policies of “one visa for multiple entries” for residents of the Deep Cooperation Zone and “one entry per week” for residents of Zhuhai led to almost six million tickets over the last year. The average daily number of tickets under the “one visa for multiple entries” policy was approximately 4,200, while the average under the “one entry per week” policy was around 11 thousand.
The CPSP assured that, in response to the growing demand for border crossings, it will collaborate with relevant services to explore more innovative crossing models, thus increasing the capacity of border posts and improving the crossing experience for visitors.
Since the implementation of iris recognition swiping, 329,000 residents have registered with the service. In 2025, this method represented approximately 42.6% of passes, totaling almost 17.5 million entries and exits, while the fingerprint system constituted 57.4%, with approximately 23.57 million movements.
Hong Kong residents have been able to register for the iris recognition ticket since June 11 last year. Around 394 thousand people in the HKSAR have already subscribed to this service.
Meanwhile, the Hengqin Border Port's “one-inspection” system introduced facial recognition on November 5, 2025. Around 167,000 people registered and carried out 1.1 million passes with facial recognition, representing 26.7% of the total.
The authorities also highlighted that on January 1st this year, the “Macao Vehicle Circulation in Guangdong” policy celebrated its third anniversary. Over the past three years, Gongbei Customs has supervised 4.393 million Macau unique vehicle registration passes through the Delta Bridge checkpoint. In 2025 alone, the number reached 1.741 million vehicles/times, 14.1% more compared to the previous year.</description><pubDate>2026-01-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UTM PHOTO…. UTM will recruit 1,300 students in the next academic year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/foto-utm-utm-recrutara-1-300-alunos-proximo-ano-lectivo/</link><description>In the next academic year, UTM will continue to increase the number of new students to a total of 1,300, said rector Fanny Vong. The institution plans to launch, also in 2026/2027, two courses: one for a master's degree in business management and the other for a degree in science in management and data science
 
In recent years, the Macau Tourism University (UTM) has increased the number of new students, having admitted a total of 952 students in the 2025/2026 academic year, said Fanny Vong, rector of the institution. According to him, UTM intends to admit, in the next academic year, around 1,300, including students who will take classes at the institution's temporary campus in Hengqin.
Quoted by the Chinese-language press reiterating that UTM's temporary campus in Hengqin will focus on master's programs, the dean predicted that there will be many international students interested in the respective courses.
Furthermore, Fanny Vong revealed that UTM plans to launch master's degrees in business management and bachelor's degrees in management and data science in the next academic year, with the aim of training interdisciplinary talents, equipped with business acumen and data-based skills, to face the new challenges of the era of smart tourism.
At the 2026 Open Day of the UTM Taipa Campus, held on Sunday, the rector highlighted, in a speech, that the Macao SAR Government is vigorously promoting major projects, including the “Macao International Integrated Tourism and Culture Zone” and the “Macao-Hengqin International University City”. According to him, UTM will make the most of these political opportunities, expanding its educational reach in Hengqin, innovating its programs and strengthening international collaboration to train “tourism+” professionals with a global vision and social responsibility.
According to the institution, during the Open Day activities, students, parents and the general public were able to learn the latest information about the admission process and course characteristics, as well as experience university life and campus culture.
“Some secondary school students reported having experienced the richness and diversity of degree courses and life on the UTM campus during the event, which helped them make important decisions about their future studies”, highlighted the university.</description><pubDate>2026-01-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Construction of drainage systems worries residents of Coloane</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/construcao-de-sistemas-de-drenagem-preocupa-moradores-de-coloane/</link><description>Dike construction work in Coloane, as a means of preventing floods, is generating some concern among residents near the Coloane Pier Bridge, fearing that the project could obstruct existing sea views and affect the coastal landscape. For the president of the Son I Charitable Association, the current construction is “closer to the coast than expected”
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
Residents of the area where works are being carried out, near the Coloane Pier Bridge, to build flood prevention equipment and reorganize water drainage systems in the dikes and the Shizimen canal, are concerned that the project could obstruct sea views and affect the coastal landscape.
The warning is given by the Son I de Coloane Charitable Association, whose president states that the current construction is closer to the coast than expected, “which actually affects the landscape”. In this sense, Yeong Keng Hoi intends to contact the competent authorities in the near future, in order to discuss and convey these concerns.
Quoted by Jornal do Cidadão, the association leader states that the initial plan proposed raising existing dikes to improve resilience to floods, but this “was rejected due to its serious impact on the coastal landscape”.
He adds that, “after extensive discussions”, the current “two lakes proposal” was finally adopted. “This involves the construction of new dikes that seek to balance the needs of flood control with the preservation of the landscape”, he points out, adding that “this optimized approach has obtained preliminary recognition from several interested parties”.
However, “as the project enters its preliminary phase and the initial construction takes shape, new concerns have emerged”, warns the president of the Associação de Beneficência dos Son I, for whom there are discrepancies between the current construction site and the project representations, with the actual location “closer to the coast than anticipated”.
Yeong Keng Hoi believes that if the dike is built in its current position, areas such as Avenida de Cinco de Outubro “will lose the view of the sea, significantly affecting the original coastal landscape”. On the other hand, it recognizes that the dike will be open to pedestrians after its completion, offering “potentially different views”.
The same official said that he will present suggestions to the Public Works Services Department on improving the landscape, such as the incorporation of recreational and fitness facilities in the dike area. The objective is, he notes, “to create a new landscape that combines practical functions of defense against floods and typhoons with aesthetic appeal”.
Furthermore, the association leader expressed the hope that stakeholders will consider public views during implementation, “meticulously optimizing landscape design while ensuring defenses against floods and typhoons, thus achieving the dual objectives of the “Two Lakes proposal”.
The same publication also heard from the owner of a café in the area, who expressed support for the flood prevention project in general, considering it to be “vital for the subsistence of riverside communities”, and maintaining that, in relation to the landscape aspect, it is premature to judge before completion. The cafe owner, surnamed Cheong, also noted that the dike “could offer new panoramic views, once accessible to pedestrians and cyclists”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Alice Costa presents paintings that combine the natural and abstract</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/alice-costa-apresenta-pinturas-combinam-natural-abstracto/</link><description>Former judge Alice Costa will exhibit solo for the first time, presenting more than three dozen works of abstract paintings, oil and acrylic on canvas. The works, according to the author, combine “the organic beauty of the natural world with the freedom and expressiveness of abstraction”. The exhibition will take place at Creative, with the opening scheduled for January 8th
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
An exhibition by Alice Costa will open on the 8th, Thursday, between 6:30 pm and 8:30 pm, at the Gallery of the Center for Creative Industries of Macau – Creative, in which the former presiding judge of the Courts of First Instance will present around 30 painting works.
The works consist of abstract paintings, oil and acrylic on canvas, and also “mixed media”, where the artist uses various materials such as clay, sand or pigments, to create textures.
Speaking to the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, Alice Costa explained that she uses abstract paintings of a “captivating genre”, combining “the organic beauty of the natural world with the freedom and expressiveness of abstraction”. He is inspired by landscapes, flora, fauna and natural phenomena, such as forests, oceans, mountains, sun or storms, and reinterprets them “through non-representational forms”.
The painter points out that she created the “Flow” series, making “organic shapes and fluid lines that flow into irregular shapes, imitating the spontaneity of nature”. He says he likes using textured and surface techniques, such as impasto, splashes or layers, which create “tactile depth, suggesting natural textures”.
According to the exhibition manifesto, a deep creative vocation led the artist to painting three years ago, where she now dedicates herself entirely to abstraction. “His work is a dialogue between the structured and the organic, translating the rhythms of the natural world, such as forests, oceans, storms and light, into non-representational forms”, can be read in the introduction to the event.
Ultimately, he adds, “Alice Costa’s paintings are sensory experiences”, asking the viewer, not to recognize, but to feel, with the aim of “connecting with the invisible emotions and primitive rhythms within the chaos and serenity of nature”.
For the exhibition's curator, the author's cultural and professional diversity gives her art a unique perspective. “She transmutes the precision of her legal training into the free expression of abstract painting” and her work “oscillates between chaos and calm, creating a dialogue between discipline and liberation”.
Menn Chow adds that the “Flow” series perfectly captures this balance, reflecting the “unpredictability of nature”, while also offering a peaceful space for meditation. Therefore, says the curator, Creative invites the public to “immerse themselves in this artistic current”, where art becomes “a channel for emotion, a witness to the invisible rhythms of nature and a record of creative transformation”.
The exhibition, the proceeds of which will be donated to ORBIS Macau, can be seen until January 31st.
Graduated in Law from the University of Macau in 1994, Alice Costa was appointed judge of the Court of First Instance in 1997. She left the service in 2017 for retirement purposes.
For this year, the artist is already preparing another exhibition of painting works, which will take place in March at the famous white horse temple in LuoYang, in Henan province.</description><pubDate>2026-01-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Deputy suggests subsidy for rates in the “New Neighborhood” in Hengqin</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/deputado-sugere-subvencao-tarifas-novo-bairro-em-hengqin/</link><description>To improve the lives of residents living in Hengqin, deputy Leong Sun Iok suggested subsidizing the payment of water and electricity tariffs in the “New Neighborhood of Macau”. In a written interpellation, he also argued that medical certificates issued by Hengqin hospitals must be recognized by Government services
 
One of the measures to alleviate the living costs of residents living in the “New Neighborhood of Macau” in Hengqin should include expanding social welfare benefit policies, for example, subsidizing the payment of water and electricity tariffs, considers Leong Sun Iok.
In a written interpellation, the deputy even urged the Executive to “encourage, with effective support, residents to live in the Deep Cooperation Zone, thus giving impetus to the integrated development of Hengqin and Macau”.
According to Leong, some public officials reported that the “New District” Health Post in Hengqin does not operate 24 hours a day and provides limited medical services. “Furthermore, Government services do not recognize medical certificates issued by Hengqin hospitals, which affected their medical appointments and rest”, he pointed out, stressing that the respective employees hope that this problem will be resolved.
In this sense, Leong Sun Iok urged the Government to speed up coordination, clearly defining opening hours for the health post, in order to improve medical services. Furthermore, he asked that public services begin to recognize medical certificates issued by Hengqin hospitals. On the other hand, he argued that the health post in the Cooperation Zone should try to provide, as quickly as possible, vaccination and blood collection services, as well as some after-hours services.
In his opinion, this way, residents living in Hengqin will be able to enjoy medical services similar to those they receive in Macau.
On the other hand, citing residents who live in that area, the deputy warned of the long waiting time and the phenomenon of “congestion” at the Hengqin Border Post during rush hours. Given the strong demand for crossing this border and the 24-hour operation of the same post, the Government was urged to take concrete measures to optimize public transport.
Specifically, Leong Sun Iok suggested the provision of more night public bus services between the centers of the Peninsula, Taipa and Coloane and the Hengqin Station, more fast routes, as well as extending the Light Metro's operating hours.</description><pubDate>2026-01-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Bank of China supports Loja Social for the 14th year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/banco-da-china-apoia-loja-social-pelo-14o-ano/</link><description>The Macau branch of the Bank of China (BOC) delivered on Saturday a donation of 300 thousand patacas to the Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macau Social Store (SCMM), to support the distribution of “food baskets” in the first month of 2026 to 373 low-income working families. In January, this program will benefit 300 households nominated by the Federation of Workers' Associations (FAOM) and the General Union of Residents' Associations of Macau (UGAMM), 48 from Santa Casa and 25 referred by the Association of Family Carers for the Mentally Disabled.

The donation was handed over by the president of BOC, Fan Yaosheng, to the SCMM Ombudsman, António José de Freitas, in a ceremony that was also attended by officials from both institutions, as well as from FAOM and UGAMM. Before handing over the check, António José de Freitas accompanied Fan Yaosheng and others on a visit to the premises of the Social Services Store and the Rehabilitation Center for the Blind.
According to SCMM, Fan Yaosheng confessed that he was very pleased to participate for the first time in the basket distribution activity and for the opportunity to learn more about the Social Store's services and the history and operation of the Blind Rehabilitation Center. Over the years, he stressed, BOC has actively fulfilled its social responsibility, namely through supporting education, culture, sports and charitable works in Macau.
Furthermore, BOC and SCMM are long-time partners. Since the creation of the Social Store in 2013, the bank has organized teams of volunteers to help distribute “food baskets” and hopes that Santa Casa will continue to provide assistance to more people in need.
António José de Freitas thanked BOC for its “continuous participation in the project”, for 14 years, in the first month of each year, assuming “a leadership role” and demonstrating “a lasting commitment” in supporting the most disadvantaged. The Provider highlighted that the constant support of the various sponsors allowed the distribution of the “food baskets” to remain uninterrupted and become a “gold brand” of local charitable initiatives, also praising FAOM and UGAMM for the rigorous monthly selection of beneficiary families.
He also emphasized that Santa Casa will maintain its initial purpose, continuing to promote social service work and support poor working families. António José de Freitas hopes that, in 2026, more companies and benefactors will be able to contribute to the regular functioning of the Social Store.
The Bank of China Volunteer Association mobilized more than 50 people to help distribute the baskets.</description><pubDate>2026-01-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Japanese singer's concert canceled</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cancelado-concerto-de-cantora-niponica/</link><description>Japanese singer Mika Nakashima announced the cancellation, “due to unavoidable circumstances”, of a concert scheduled for March 14 in Macau, at a time of tensions between Beijing and Tokyo.
In a statement published on Nakashima's official website, the artist highlighted that she is “in negotiations to reschedule the concert”, which was scheduled for the Londoner Macau hotel-casino, and thanks her fans for their understanding.
This concert would be the first of an Asian tour by the 42-year-old singer and actress, which continues to include visits to Bangkok (Thailand), Taipei (Taiwan), Kuala Lumpur (Malaysia), Seoul (South Korea) and Osaka and Tokyo (Japan).
On December 12, the Macau Government denied any interference in the cancellation of at least three concerts with Japanese artists scheduled for the region and assured that these were solely commercial decisions by the organizers. “I think different parties have their own considerations”, said the president of the Macau Cultural Heritage Council, Leong Wai Man, at a press conference.
"It is normal to have adjustments regarding concerts or different events. Situations of cancellation due to force majeure are common", added the leader of the Cultural Institute.
On December 9th, the Venetian Macau hotel-casino announced the cancellation of a concert by Japanese pop singer Ayumi Hamasaki, scheduled for January 10th. This is after the Hamasaki show in Shanghai, on November 29, was cancelled.
A day earlier, a Christmas show, scheduled for December 25th at Studio City, which included the female band Say My Name, which includes the Japanese Hitomi Honda, had also been cancelled. On the same day, a third show was cancelled, this time by the band Hi-Fi Un!corn, a group that includes Japanese artists, scheduled for December 21st at Galaxy Macau.
Asked by Lusa whether there were instructions from the Government not to hold cultural events with artists from Japan, Leong Wai Man assured that “this is a matter for the commercial sector, it is the organizer's decision”. “I have nothing more to add”, he stressed.
In November, Macau followed Beijing's example and advised against traveling to Japan, “given that since the middle of this year, the trend of attacks in Japan against Chinese citizens has been increasing”.
Days earlier, the Japanese Prime Minister spoke about a possible Japanese military intervention in a conflict between mainland China and Taiwan. Sanae Takaichi stated that if an emergency situation in Taiwan involved “the deployment of warships and the use of force, this could constitute a threat to Japan’s survival.”
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Comic book competition exalted cultural fusion and affective memory</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/concurso-de-banda-desenhada-exaltou-fusao-cultural-memoria-afectiva/</link><description>A biannual competition from Somos! – Portuguese Language Communication Association distinguished original works that celebrate the city's cultural identity, highlighting the Sino-Lusophone fusion. The winning story evokes Vila da Taipa, through the solitary dance of an elderly Portuguese man

The first edition of the biannual “BD-Macau” visual art competition, launched by Somos – Associação de Comunicação em Língua Portuguesa, challenged young residents, aged 15 to 25, to create original visual narratives, with a minimum of four panels, whose stories unfold in Macau, highlighting its sociocultural specificities, urban landscape and using one of the official languages ​​(Chinese or Portuguese).
The association received around a dozen applications, four of which “fully met all the stipulated criteria”. The jury, composed of Wesley Chan, president of the “Hyper Comic Society”, Rodrigo de Matos, a renowned cartoonist residing in Macau, and Natacha Fidalgo, representative of Somos – ACLP, selected the three award-winning works.
The first prize, worth 7,000 patacas, was awarded to Tse Wai Sam, aged 25, for the comic book “O Último Passo de Dança”, which evokes the “iconic set of Vila da Taipa, portraying, through the solitary dance of an elderly Portuguese man, cultural fusion and affective memory in urban transformation”. According to the author, the dance “symbolizes tradition and remembrance”, while the city’s lights “represent modernity, creating together the unique rhythm of Macau – between nostalgia and rebirth”.
The second prize, worth 4,000 patacas, distinguished Ng Ka Iam, aged 15, for the work “Um Dia do Gato do Barra”, which records the stories of visitors through the perspective of a cat that lives in the A-Má Temple. “The ‘cat’s unique’ ability allows him to see into each visitor’s past, presenting the ‘intertwined experiences and emotions of different characters in Macau’”, he said to Somos, adding that this comic “depicts moments from the first emigrants to the modern transformation, showing the ‘unique charm of Macau as a place of cultural fusion, while also exploring the sense of belonging and memories of individuals in the face of the city’s changes’”.
Tam Hio Tong, 17 years old, won third prize, worth 2,000 patacas, for his work “A-Muk and the Frog – Macau Chapter”. This comic describes the warm midday journey of the protagonist “A-Muk” and a little frog through Macau, highlighting “the dried cow meat from Ruínas de São Paulo, the coconut ice cream from Rua dos Ervanários, and even the unique motorcycle culture of Macau”. This work, made by a teenager, “proves that the cultural characteristics of Macau are already deeply rooted in the daily lives of the new generation”, argues Somos.
Parallel to the competition, a comics workshop was organized, taught by Wesley Chan and Rodrigo de Matos, on drawing techniques, character creation and narrative development.
With this competition, Somos – ACLP intends to “celebrate Macau, its architectural and historical richness, as a place of cultural confluence and a Sino-Lusophone base”, at the same time supporting the development of the area of ​​drawing and illustration. Although the number of participants was lower than expected, the organization understands that the “attendance was positive, considering it was the inaugural edition”.
“We managed to reach the Chinese public, which has been one of our biggest battles in the initiatives we have carried out”, emphasizes the note.
Marta Pereira, president of the association, believes that there is an “expanding market in Macau, however, “probably still with few opportunities”. Therefore, in the next edition, she wants to “invest in better marketing and promotion”, convinced that “the trend is towards growth”.
“In the next edition we will rethink the concept, perhaps involving other local associations dedicated to art, and/or inviting artists from Asia and other countries”, said Marta Pereira.</description><pubDate>2026-01-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SIX JUDGES Sworn in</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/empossados-seis-juizes/</link><description>. Six judges recently appointed to new roles by the Chief Executive were sworn in yesterday before the president of the Court of Final Instance (TUI), Song Man Lei, and the testimony of several guests, including the leader of the Macao SAR. The group of inductees included Choi Mou Pan, new president of the Court of Second Instance (TSI), Hoi Wai Neng (TUI judge), Lou Ieng Ha, Jerónimo Alberto Gonçalves Santos (TSI judges) and Io Weng San and Rong Qi (presidents of the First Instance Courts).</description><pubDate>2026-01-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>GOVERNMENT ADMITS TO EXPANDING ACCESS TO TEMPORARY AND EXCHANGE HOUSING</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-admite-alargar-acesso-habitacao-temporaria-para-troca/</link><description>The Macao SAR Government will deepen the study on expanding the scope of housing for exchange and temporary accommodation already completed, in order to ensure the rational use of existing resources, said yesterday the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, at a plenary meeting of the Council for Urban Renewal (CRU), the body he presides over. According to a note from the CRU, the three specialized groups presented the state of play on their respective work and discussed various issues, including “the long-term mechanism relating to housing for exchange and housing for temporary accommodation, the pragmatic promotion of urban renewal through administrative optimization, among others, as well as the dynamization of community neighborhoods through their beautification, with a view to improving the quality of life of residents”. Raymond Tam also reiterated that, in 2026, urban renewal work will be boosted, an area that constitutes a “priority” for the Government. In addition to continuing to promote the reconstruction of the “Seven Complexes of Buildings in Iao Hon Neighborhood”, the reconstruction of individual buildings will be reinforced, as well as public facilities in the old neighborhoods increased. It is recalled that, in November, in the presentation of the Lines of Government Action, the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, had already stated that, in order to meet the demand for affordable housing, “a plan to implement the exchange regime will be drawn up” and the formalities relating to the sale and occupation of the units allocated to households applying for affordable housing in the 2019 competition will be monitored.</description><pubDate>2026-01-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2523/</link><description>Four suspects arrested for fraud with fake tokens
Four individuals from Mainland China were detained by the Judiciary Police (PJ) for being in possession of fake gambling chips. They allegedly defrauded players of a total of 210 thousand Hong Kong dollars. According to the PJ, the tokens are very similar to the real ones and will be from the same batch as others detected in a similar case at the beginning of 2025. In the operation, 128 fake tokens worth 10 thousand HKD were seized. The detainees, aged between 22 and 35, were reportedly recruited by a criminal network to operate in Macau.
 
New DSF leaders took office
Ho In Mui and Kuok Iat Hoi were sworn in yesterday as director and deputy director of the Directorate of Financial Services (DSF), respectively, in a ceremony presided over by the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip. Ho In Mui committed to “guiding his action by the spirit of prudence, pragmatism and innovation and continuously leading the process of modernizing public financial management”. The new head of DSF holds bachelor's and master's degrees in Business Management, having joined the organization in 1995. Kuok Iat Hoi, a graduate in Business Management, joined DSF in 2002.
 
Vulnerable children with access to free childcare
Registration for the “Free Daycare Scheme for Children from Families in Vulnerable Situations” begins on January 12th, informed the Institute of Social Action (IAS). The program, which involves more than 30 subsidized daycare centers, aims, according to the IAS, to provide services, free of charge, to children from households experiencing economic difficulties and deprived of the means to be cared for by their families. Children must be residents of the Macao SAR under three years of age and come from single-parent families, with disabled members, chronically ill, made up only of grandparents and grandchildren or beneficiaries of the regular IAS subsidy.
 
Professional reintegration plan for women created
The Bureau of Labor Affairs (DSAL) and Sands China launched the “Professional reintegration plan for women” who left the job market for personal or family reasons. The program includes 29 job openings, mainly in the categories of “administration”, “customer service and sales” and “operation of integrated resorts”. Sands will provide support in a number of areas, such as helping to create a social network, and will assign specific personnel to regularly monitor the situation after induction into the role. The plan lasts six months. Interested parties can register online until the 16th.
 
Post office launches Year of the Horse stamp issue
The Postal and Telecommunications Services Department put into circulation an extraordinary issue of stamps called “Lunar Year of the Horse”, with a total of five models. The largest number of stamps (527,100) has a fee of 2 and a half patacas. A wallet with two series of eight stamps (5,000 in total) costs 40 patacas.</description><pubDate>2026-01-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ho Iat Seng and Kou Hoi In receive Macao SAR's highest distinction</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ho-iat-seng-kou-hoi-recebem-mais-alta-distincao-da-raem/</link><description>The Government will award medals and honorary titles to 28 personalities and entities that stood out in the political, social and sporting landscape. Highlights include the highest decoration awarded by the Macao SAR, the Great Lotus Medal of Honor, to Ho Iat Seng, former Chief Executive, and Kou Hoi In, former president of the Legislative Assembly. This distinction “is a collective victory”, said the previous Government leader. Also for Kou Hoi In, the medal is the result of the work of “everyone who contributed to the development of Macau”. The imposition ceremony will take place on the 30th of this month at the Cultural Center

VÍTOR REBELO
 
On the last day of 2025, the Government released the list of personalities and entities that will receive medals and honorary titles for having distinguished themselves through personal achievements, contributions to society or services provided to Macau. The distinctions, totaling 28, will be awarded at a ceremony to be held on January 30th, in the Grand Auditorium of the Cultural Center.
Among those awarded, suggested by the Appointment Committee, highlight is the highest decoration awarded by the Macao SAR, the Great Lotus Medal of Honor, which will be awarded to Ho Iat Seng, former Chief Executive, and to Kou Hoi In, former president of the Legislative Assembly (AL).
Through his Office, Ho Iat Seng thanked him for the important medal awarded to him and stated that the development of the Macao SAR “continuously advances on the foundations that are the achievements of the past”. Ho Iat Seng, who was also a member of the Standing Committee of the National People's Assembly and president of the AL, highlighted that the fifth Macao SAR Government “brought together all sectors of society to overcome challenges and achieve tangible results through pragmatic efforts”.
These results, he highlighted, “depend not only on the dedication and hard work of the government action team and all Public Administration employees, but also on the strong support and joint efforts of the community and all residents”.
The former head of the government team during a five-year term considered that this Medal of Honor is “a collective victory, which demonstrates the commitment of the entire society to promoting greater and better development for the Macao SAR”.
In the same note, he also expressed the firm conviction that the territory, “under the firm support of the great motherland”, will continue to “actively integrate itself into the context of national development, taking advantage of the significant opportunities arising from the construction of the Greater Bay Area and the Cooperation Zone in Hengqin”. In addition, he emphasized the commitment to continue upholding the fundamental values ​​of patriotism and love for Macau, promote the stable and lasting implementation of the principle of “one country, two systems” and contribute to the long-term prosperity and stability of the nation and the Macao SAR.
For his part, Kou Hoi In said he felt “deeply honored”, promised to continue doing his best for Macau and the country and recognized that the medal is the result not only of his work, but also “of all those who contributed to the development of Macau”.
The former deputy recalls having been elected in 1991, before the transfer of sovereignty, having served the Macao SAR for 34 years and witnessing the main historical changes and the success of the practice of the “one country, two systems” principle in Macau.
Finally, the current chairman of the TDM Board of Directors assured that, in the future, he will continue to “promote the values ​​of love for the country and Macau, defend the stable and lasting implementation of ‘one country, two systems’ and contribute to the long-term prosperity and stability of the country and the Macao SAR”.
 
Raimundo do Rosário receives “Golden Lotus”
The Golden Lotus Medal will be awarded to the former Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raimundo Arrais do Rosário, as well as to Ho Veng On, former Commissioner of Audit, and Vong Man Chong, former director general of the Customs Services.
Raimundo do Rosário, born in Macau, was also a member of the Drafting Committee of the Basic Law and the Preparatory Committee for the Establishment of Macau, deputy to AL and member of the supervisory board of Banco Comercial de Macau. Between 1999 and 2014, he headed the Macau Economic and Commercial Delegation, in Lisbon, and was also responsible for the economic and commercial delegations to the European Union, in Brussels, and the World Trade Organization, in Geneva.
As for Ho Veng On, who left his position as Audit Commissioner in 2024, after more than 20 years, in what was his longest tenure, he reacted to the decoration, remembering that in the past he also participated in the organization's work on awarding medals and helped the Chief Executive to move forward with the respective proposals. “I know, therefore, that this medal has great meaning”, he stressed.
Vong Man Chong, in turn, expressed that the medal also belongs to the long-term work carried out by the Customs Services. “I would not be able to achieve this honor without the solid foundation left by all the previous directors-general of the Customs Services, who always persisted in the governance guidelines and development guidelines of the Customs”, he asserted.
Looking to the future, he said he was “deeply convinced” that all Customs personnel will continue to defend Macau’s “core values” to “overcome difficulties and complete the tasks given by the Government”.
Closing the Medals of Honor, the Government awarded the “Silver Lotus” to the Macau Banks Association. Speaking to the newspaper Ou Mun, the entity's president, Fan Yaosheng, pointed out that there has been, over 40 years of existence, “an effort to maintain financial stability, promote the development of modern finance, and boost economic development and integration in the construction of the Greater Bay Area”.
The Medals of Honor, with the degrees of Great Lotus, Golden Lotus and Silver Lotus, aim to “distinguish individuals or entities for their notable contribution to the image and good name of the Macao SAR, both within and abroad, or for their contribution, in any field, of great relevance to the development of the Macao SAR”, can be read in a statement from the Social Communication Office (GCS).
 
“Dancing Water” distinguished with Tourist Medal
As for the Merit medals, they will be awarded to the Macau University of Science and Technology, Keang Peng School and Kao Yip School, in the educational sector, and to the team of the show “House of Dancing Water”, by Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, in this case in the Tourism sector.
These Merit distinctions comprise seven categories and are intended “to reward individuals or entities that stand out in the exercise of any professional activity, for their prominence and notoriety in the industrial and commercial domains, as well as for the contribution made to development in these areas”, highlights the GCS.
Sport was also distinguished, with the Nomination Committee nominating the Karate Team of the Macao SAR Sports Delegation to the 15th Edition of the National Games and the table tennis athlete Zhu Yuling. The list of merit badges also includes Chan Iok Lin (professional), Nam Kwong and Li Amber Jiaming Logistics Company (industrial and commercial), Macau Barra Maritime and Land Residents Chinese Opera Association, Lam Fat Iam and Chan Iu Pui (cultural) and the China-SAR International Medical Emergency Team (altruistic).
The Macao SAR Government also awarded Distinguished Service Medals to Tai Kam Un (Dedication) and the Macau Peng On Tung Tele-Assistance Service Center (Community Services), which highlight the performance of duties, participation in responses to incidents of a public nature or the provision of community services.
In addition, the list also includes honorary titles of Valor and Prestige, three of which are awarded to educational establishments (Salesian Institute of the Immaculate Conception, Pui Ching Secondary School and Lou Hau Secondary School) and another three to the teams present in the “Asian Elite Dance Competition 2024-2025”, in the 2nd Asian 3×3 Basketball Championship for Secondary Schools and in the 2025 Bowling World Cup, as well as Li In Iat.</description><pubDate>2026-01-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism on the rise at the end of 2025 and the beginning of 2026</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/turismo-em-alta-fim-de-2025-inicio-de-2026/</link><description>Macau registered 180,000 visitors in farewell to 2025, with December 31st still being marked by the concentration of 65,000 people in the countdown area on the “Cotai Strip”, according to police estimates. Macau tourism also started 2026 with robust results, registering more than 188 thousand visitors both on January 1st and the following day



















On the last day of 2025, 180,502 visitors entered Macau, reported the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP), revealing that the territory registered 188,036 visitors on January 1st, a number that set a daily record on the occasion of the Universal Brotherhood holiday.
According to the CPSP, also on January 1st, the volume of entries and exits across local borders reached 866 thousand, also setting a new daily record. On that day, residents accounted for 33% of border movements, while visitors and non-resident workers (TNR) accounted for 49.6% and 16.2% of entries and exits, respectively.
With a total of 147 thousand entries and exits, the Hengqin Border Post also registered, on January 1st, a new daily record for border crossings.
On January 2nd, the number of visitors to the Macao SAR reached 188,561. On the 3rd, it dropped to 109,510, which means that the three-day Universal Brotherhood holidays in Mainland China brought more than 486,000 visitors to Macau.
On the other hand, also according to CPSP data, until 5pm yesterday, the Macao SAR recorded 80,394 visitors.
 
65 thousand filled “Cotai Strip”
On December 31st, several areas of the city hosted New Year's Eve activities. At COTAI, Sands once again organized a special New Year celebration program, with outdoor music and a fireworks show, which attracted thousands of people.
On the other hand, at Lake Sai Van Square, a countdown concert organized by the Cultural Institute also brought together many people. Casas da Taipa were also the scene of celebrations marking the departure of 2025 and the entry into 2026, in a celebration dedicated to the theme of multicultural integration. The performances of singers, bands and different communities in Macau fascinated many spectators who almost occupied the entire audience.
However, according to the Chinese-language press, after the pyrotechnic display on the “Cotai Strip”, numerous groups of people were stranded in that location, which led to negative comments on social media about the traffic measures taken at the location and the “lack of clarity” in the instructions regarding the flow of people.
According to the Unitary Police Services, police authorities estimated that, at the countdown location on the “Cotai Strip”, there were around 65 thousand people at peak height, with the flow of passengers waiting for buses being basically completed by 04:00 in the morning.
Police consider that traffic order was generally normal and safe that night. Even so, he assured that he will review and analyze the relevant measures, including improving plans for dispersing the flow of people and traffic.
In turn, the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs revealed that, from midnight on New Year's Eve until the end of public transport services, the Light Metro made more than 170 departures, serving more than 12 thousand passengers, and there were almost 570 departures of public daytime buses, which means an annual increase of 18%.
 
Macau with annual record of 40.06 million visitors
The MSAR welcomed 40.06 million visitors in 2025, setting a new annual record that reflects an increase of around 14.7% compared to 2024. According to the CPSP, the annual record for border crossings was also broken in 2025, which reached 235 million, an increase of 9.8% compared to 2024. Among all border crossings, those for residents represented 36.4%, while 26.1% and 33.9% involved TNR and visitors, respectively. The most used borders in 2025 were Portas do Cerco (52.7% of the total), Qingmao (15.4%) and Hengqin (12.9%). Furthermore, according to the Zhuhai customs inspection authorities, during one year of implementation, the “one-entry visa per week” policy for Zhuhai residents and the “one visa, multiple entry” policy for Hengqin residents led 5.5 million holders of these documents to visit the Macao SAR.</description><pubDate>2026-01-05 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Writer Oníssimo Teotónio Almeida distinguished with Graça Moura Prize</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/escritor-onesimo-teotonio-almeida-distinguido-premio-graca-moura/</link><description>The writer and university professor Oníssimo Teotónio Almeida was honored this year with the Vasco Graça Moura Prize – Cultural Citizenship for his contribution to “the affirmation of the culture of the Portuguese language in the world”, it has now been announced.
“As a scholar and essayist, he has contributed decisively to the affirmation of the culture of the Portuguese language in the world, thus affirming cultural citizenship as an exemplary factor of expansion and development”, highlighted the jury, chaired by former minister Guilherme d’Oliveira Martins.
The jury justified the choice of Oníssimo Teotónio de Almeida “due to his persistent action as a prestigious professor and researcher with proven experience in the fields of study and consolidation of the Portuguese language, literature and culture, especially those of the United States of America”.
The author of “Na Senda de Fernão Mendes” (2013) has lived in the United States since 1972, where he went as a postgraduate student at Brown University and where he continues to teach, having helped create the Center for Portuguese and Brazilian Studies, currently a department at that university, which he directed from 1991 to 2003.
Onesimo Teotónio Almeida was born 79 years ago in Pico da Pedra, on the island of São Miguel, in the Azores, having studied at the Angra do Heroísmo Seminary and completed his bachelor's degree at the Catholic University of Lisbon.
As an author he has published in different genres – chronicle, short story, theater, poems and essays. His works include “José Enes – Filósofo, Pedagogue e Mestre” (2025), “Diálogos Lusitanos” (2024), “O Século dos Prodígios” (2018), “A Obsessão da Portugalidade” (2017), and “Despenteando Pararágrafos” (2015).
In a statement sent to the Lusa agency, Estoril Sol – organizer of the prize – highlights that “Oníssimo Teotónio Almeida is one of the greatest thinkers and prose writers, having more than a hundred essays and texts published in Portugal and abroad, namely in the United States, Brazil, France and England”.
The Vasco Graça Moura Prize – Cultural Citizenship, worth 20,000 euros, was awarded for the first time in 2016 to essayist Eduardo Lourenço. Since then, journalist José Carlos Vasconcelos, writer and researcher Vítor Aguiar e Silva, actress Maria do Céu Guerra, fado singer Carlos do Carmo, manager and jurist Emílio Rui Vilar, book publisher Zeferino Coelho, painter Graça Morais, historian José Pacheco Pereira and writer and researcher Helder Macedo have been distinguished.
In addition to Guilherme d’Oliveira Martins, the jury was made up of Maria Carlos Gil Loureiro, from the General Directorate of Books, Archives and Libraries, José Manuel Mendes, president of the Portuguese Writers Association, Manuel Frias Martins, president of the Portuguese Association of Literary Critics, Ana Paula Laborinho, director in Portugal of the Organization of Ibero-American States for Education, Science and Culture, by journalist José Carlos de Vasconcelos, and, also, by Dinis de Abreu, at the invitation of Estoril Sol.
The award winner was announced on the day that writer Vasco Graça Moura would have turned 84 years old. The award ceremony “will be announced in due course”.
 
JTM/Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>