<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Training qualified staff attracted 63% of Macau Foundation subsidies in 2024</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/formacao-de-quadros-qualificados-captou-63-dos-subsidios-da-fundacao-macau-em-2024/</link><description>•Œ¶‚§j¡x™∫´ÿøv



Last year, 63% of the 2.16 billion patacas in support from the Macau Foundation went towards training qualified staff, according to the organization's annual report. The amount allocated in the 2024 calculation was equivalent to more than double that granted in 2023, with increases also being recorded in approved applications, number of projects, activities or beneficiary people, scholarships and prizes awarded
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
Last year, the “training of qualified personnel” received the largest share of financial support from the Macau Foundation (FM), amounting to 1.37 billion patacas, which is equivalent to 63% of total subsidies, according to the organization's annual report. 413 million (19%) were channeled towards “improving the well-being of the population”. For the “academic studies” category, 234.4 million (11%) were transferred, while “exchange and cooperation” projects received 143 million (7%).
In the general calculation of 2024, and according to the report analyzed by the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper, the FM allocated 2.16 billion patacas in financial support, corresponding to more than double the 933.48 million patacas granted in 2023. Last year, the competent bodies of the FM approved 901 applications for subsidies, relating to 2,362 projects or activities, and awarded 13,459 scholarships and awards. These numbers correspond to 61 more applications, 200 projects or activities and 699 scholarships and prizes awarded than in the previous year.
The amount paid as financial support exceeded 626 million patacas, while the beneficiary entities had to return more than 19 million. As part of monitoring the financial support granted, the FM carried out 668 analyzes of financial reports and subsidized activities, having notified on 329 occasions the “application of consequences to non-compliant projects”.
“With the aim of supporting the carrying out of activities that help to reinforce community cohesion, to energize community neighborhoods, to promote the development of civil society, to improve the well-being of the population and to stimulate the improvement of associations”, more than 65 million patacas were allocated, for 1,238 activities.
In addition, FM also implemented the “Financial support plan for association operating expenses” for 2025, through which 62 association groups received 297 million patacas last year. In the plan with the same name, but relating to 2024, a single association received 1.74 million.
 
More than 11 million for scholarships
Regarding the “Financial support plan for academic studies”, 31 million patacas were distributed among 279 projects, in order to “support the implementation of academic projects in favor of the sustainable development of different sectors in Macau and studies on society, the economy, the legal system and public policies”, among others.
Regarding the awarding of scholarships, FM awarded more than 11 million patacas to 249 scholarship holders. Last year, 143 “excellent students” in higher education collectively received 1.59 million. Furthermore, 57 mobility students received more than one million, while more than nine million patacas were distributed to 47 students from abroad enrolled in Macau. There were also 31 scholarship holders from Portuguese-speaking countries who collectively received 5.6 million.
Under old study support programs, 74 awards or scholarships were granted or renewed, totaling more than eight million patacas. More than 2.8 million were distributed by students from Portuguese-speaking countries.
In November last year, remember, FM signed the “Cooperation Agreement regarding the granting of financial support to the University of Macau for the acquisition of land for educational purposes, in the In-depth Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau, in Hengqin”. The support will be 1.3 billion patacas, at most, “with a validity period until full fulfillment of the duties set out in the agreement”, according to the document.
In December 2024, the organization signed the “Cooperation Agreement between the Macau Foundation and the Economic and Technological Development Services Department regarding the granting of financial support for the ‘Macau Science 2’ satellite project of the Macau University of Science and Technology”, for a maximum amount of 203 million patacas, in force until December 31, 2030.
In relation to primary and secondary education, the FM awarded 12,325 prizes last year. Since 2014, the Macau Foundation has rewarded non-higher education students with the best academic achievement, in cooperation with the Education and Development Services Department and on the recommendation of local schools.
 
Special support for health
In the area of ​​health, the report highlights the granting of special financial support to the Kiang Wu Hospital Charitable Association, worth 19.68 million patacas, “for updating the computer network, communication equipment and for the acquisition of hospital equipment”, including more modern devices for different specialties, in order to “increase the quality of medical treatment to be offered to citizens”.
Furthermore, the FM approved the granting of a special subsidy to the General Union of Residents' Associations of Macau, “for renovation work on the integrated medical center of the Macau Residents' Welfare Association and for the acquisition of clinical equipment”, in the amount of 15.56 million.
In cooperation with the “Peking Union Medical College Hospital” (PUMCH), the Foundation also promoted the unprecedented “Financial support plan for pre-entry training of specialist doctors”, in order to provide 10 specialist doctors with the opportunity to receive specialized training at PUMCH, with a maximum duration of one year.
 
Foundation with a positive balance and “satisfactory” services
In the 2024 financial year, FM's actual revenues amounted to around 6.4 billion patacas, of which 4.4 billion relate to contributions from concession contracts for the operation of games of chance. Actual expenses totaled close to one billion, which means that the FM recorded a positive balance of approximately 5.4 billion.
As of December 31 last year, the Foundation's total assets were worth around 43.9 billion patacas, with a reserve of approximately 43.8 billion.
As stated in the report, “FM's financial resources come mainly from the contribution of 2% of the gross revenues of the Macao SAR's gambling and gambling concession companies, from allocations allocated by the Macao SAR Government, from local and foreign donations and from other revenues received under the terms of the law”.
In line with the e-governance vision, FM also updated the IT system, connecting services to the “Platform for Companies and Associations” application, for submitting applications and filling out forms relating to requests for financial support.
Furthermore, the Foundation carried out a survey on the population's level of satisfaction. According to the results, “public services within the scope of social action” had a score of 4.62, on a scale of zero to five, “with the mention of ‘satisfied’”. At the same time, respondents gave a score of 4.99 to FM's “general public services”, which essentially refer to the provision of facilities, “with the mention of ‘very satisfied’”.
At the end of 2024, FM had 119 employees, including managers, with individual employment contracts, excluding members of statutory bodies. Over the past year, there were 173 occasions in which workers signed up for 51 training courses, seminars and lectures, among various activities carried out by FM and other public and private entities.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Educational programs must integrate immersive heritage experiences</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/programas-educativos-devem-integrar-experiencias-imersivas-sobre-patrimonio/</link><description>A review of the curriculum plans for architecture and heritage subjects could contribute to better conservation and revitalization of Macau's historical heritage, indicates a recent study. In addition to traditional textual materials, researchers from the City University of Macau argue that immersive experiences should be integrated into educational programs, in order to bring students closer to historic buildings
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
Combining immersive experiences with local architectural heritage resources can contribute to expanding knowledge and increasing public awareness of protecting cultural legacy and safeguarding and revitalizing historic buildings, argue the authors of the study “Embodied Cognition and Education for Built Heritage: a case study of Macau's historic architecture”.
According to Junyi Zhao, Mengshun Lee and Xinyu Li, researchers from the Faculty of Innovation and Design of the City University of Macau, “by integrating historical resources into education, students understand and apply professional knowledge, cultural identity is reinforced, respect for cultural heritage is instilled and awareness of heritage protection increases”.
The aim of this study was to examine how immersive experiences, architectural atmosphere and the use of historic resources influence satisfaction and learning outcomes among students and teachers in architecture and heritage disciplines. To this end, the authors developed a questionnaire to evaluate the effectiveness of immersive classrooms.
The research group observed “a significant correlation between physical participation, immersion and effective learning”. The team therefore recommends an “integration of education incorporated into the core of architectural practice to effectively support the preservation and revitalization of heritage”.
Analysis of responses from 435 respondents indicates that "interactions between individuals and their environment play a crucial role in shaping spatial understanding and emotional investment. By allowing students to experience and interact with historic spaces in a meaningful way, it is possible to establish a deep connection with architectural heritage, thus providing an effective approach to revitalizing the cultural industry."
As the authors explain, "heritage constitutes the cornerstone of intercultural dialogue and social cohesion. Exposing students to the diversity of local cultures promotes the appreciation of tangible historical resources, a prerequisite for training professionals who have an international perspective and a deep connection with local traditions."
Combining “the preservation of architectural heritage with the integration of contemporary design practices helps to achieve sustainable cultural development in these regions”, they assert. The group of researchers also noted that “teacher support and student self-efficacy have partial mediating effects between learning experience and effectiveness”.
Furthermore, "strengthening professional understanding and enriching practical experience opens new avenues for collaboration between educational institutions, cultural tourism and heritage protection. The combination of theory and practice helps to bridge the gap between heritage protection and contemporary design and establishes a mutually beneficial model that supports cultural sustainability and economic development."
However, “the integration of multisensory experiences faces multiple challenges, including how to effectively incorporate heritage buildings into practical applications and academic courses, how to balance cultural values ​​and environmental sustainability in the material preservation process, and how to ensure that historic buildings can be smoothly integrated into contemporary urban life after restoration.”
Furthermore, “the current revitalization of historic buildings in Macau faces three major challenges, namely excessive commercialization, the disconnect between material and immaterial protection and the contradiction between the demands of tourists' experience and traditional exhibition methods”.
 
The multisensory experience of architecture
The senses interact with “materials, light, sound and aroma”, which “deepens perception and promotes emotional resonance”. This allows “participants to appreciate and preserve historic buildings.” At the same time, heritage education programs “reaffirm identity and promote mutual respect and diversity.”
"Architecture functions as a medium that provides individuals with sensations, identity and spatial orientation, creating a sense of place that strengthens affection and a sense of belonging. Studies on affection for a place indicate that individuals' emotional connection with a space arises from the interaction between social, cultural and material environments", the study reads.
Architects allow users to explore the potential of space through multi-sensory design strategies that involve multiple senses. Immersive, multi-sensory environments allow individuals to internalize the designer's intentions, promoting a deeper understanding of spatial narratives and values.
“Multisensory perception and environmental interaction reduce cognitive load, allowing individuals to acquire experiential knowledge and develop cognitive skills through embodied movement and direct spatial experiences, rather than relying on decontextualized knowledge”, emphasize the study authors.
“In the context of architectural heritage, students often resort to textual materials, which can limit their tactile engagement with the physical space”, they argue.
From their perspective, “greater student engagement with course content positively correlates with increased satisfaction with learning and better educational outcomes.” This form of education “promotes respect for cultural diversity” and “strengthens students’ personal identity and intercultural competence”.
"While modern technology offers multimedia resources, physical spaces, particularly those related to architectural heritage, provide invaluable experience that supports students' development and prepares them for future careers. Future education for architectural heritage must integrate digital technological skills and incorporate local practices of conservation and use of historic buildings into the curriculum", they emphasize.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Renovation of the IIM library will allow “more proximity to the public”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/remodelacao-da-biblioteca-iim-permitira-mais-proximidade-publico/</link><description>The Macau International Institute is about to complete the renovation work on the new wing of the headquarters building, where the library will play a very important role in contact with the community. The space, which should be open on Saturdays, will contain more than two thousand publications. In addition, the library will include the “IIM Bookshop” bookstore, will have a reading area for children and will host exhibitions. The official opening is expected to take place after Chinese New Year. António Monteiro, general secretary, told the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper that one of the objectives is to attract, “in addition to the general public”, students and scholarship holders “who want to use the books for work on the cultural identity of the territory”



















VÍTOR REBELO
 
The library of the International Institute of Macau (IIM), located in one of the wings of the headquarters building, is undergoing renovation work, which should be completed by the end of this year. However, the official opening is scheduled for after Chinese New Year.
The space will appear “clean-faced”, as the institution’s secretary-general said during a visit to the facilities by Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU. “Everything looks like construction, but already at an advanced stage, and with thousands of books stored and prepared to be placed on the new shelves”, António Monteiro began by explaining.
The existing library, named Joaquim Morais Alves, in honor of the outstanding member of the Portuguese community in Macau who carried out an intense civic, political and professional activity, had not undergone renovation work for 25 years, therefore since the beginning of the foundation. “There was some deterioration and, therefore, it needed to be renewed”, says the “right-hand man” of the IIM president, Jorge Rangel. “The solution was to completely remodel it.”
Having many books dedicated to Macau, on Macau studies, both in Portuguese, Chinese and English, “and even patuá is integrated here”, the idea was to have “a more dignified place, with better conditions, so that they could be shown and used by the public”, he highlights.
Thus came the decision for a total remodeling, which will make it possible to accommodate the more than 2,000 books that the IIM has. “After the official opening of the library, this will allow people, scholarship holders, university students, who want to use books to work on the cultural identity of the territory, to do so more frequently”, he expressed.
For António Monteiro, the library was and always will be a center of studies, “because IIM had, from the very beginning, the right to produce books, not only being a publisher, but also a reflection of Macau's entire legacy and cultural identity”. Therefore, he reinforces, “there is nothing better than a library to learn about this history, because it is all in the information in the books”. The intention also involves promoting activities and having “greater proximity to the public”.
“People come here and the aim is that they are not just reading a certain book, but that they use the space, and from there a general interest in reading can also be awakened, trying to also promote part of the older collections, despite the existence of other library spaces in Macau, such as at the University of Macau and the Central Library”, he highlighted.
The IIM's collection, in addition to the Macau study room, the Luís Gonzaga Gomes Room, with Macau editions, old magazines from the time of Portuguese administration, as well as the Revista da Cultura, also includes publications relating to China, Portuguese-speaking countries and Southeast Asia.
Once the main works are completed and following the “commitment made with the Macau Foundation, which sponsors almost all of the funds needed for the project”, the “most laborious” part and that will cause “the biggest headache” will be putting the thousands of publications in their proper places. “After everything is completed, I think the library will be in different conditions, with a more modern appearance, with a clean look, to welcome the public”, says the director, adding that the space will have other features.
“The bookstore, the ‘IIM Bookshop’, which has always operated next to the entrance counter, will also be located there, and from the moment the library is available, people can go to the new space, entering through the building’s stairs, via Rua de Paris, and access the place more easily to purchase books, carry out research and research studies that they deem necessary”, he highlights.
On the other hand, the library will allow exhibitions, photographic or artistic, to be organized inside and in the adjacent corridor in the future, “because there are conditions for this to happen in this multipurpose space, not only on our initiative, but also as a gallery open to the outside, to any entity that wishes to exhibit here”.
But the news doesn't stop there. The IIM intends for the library to open on Saturdays, as until now it has been open from Monday to Friday. It will be, according to António Monteiro, a good opportunity for “more people to come to our bookstore”.
 
If digital disappears, books will “always stay”
At a time when technology provides access to almost everything, and can replace physical books with digital ones, António Monteiro recognizes that digital “makes a lot easier”, but it could disappear. “If this happens, the books will always remain, so it is necessary to preserve them”, he emphasizes.
With regard to digitization, there are still many books to be subjected to this process, “especially the oldest ones”. As for the new ones, “they are all already in this format, in PDF, and then, with our ‘online bookshop’ system, which is linked to the website, people outside Macau can purchase our publications”.
Stressing that “what makes the IIM move is the book”, he considers that this “is the main product to promote Macau”. Regarding reading, he recognizes that the Government is “increasingly encouraging” this aspect and promoting reading “as a way of developing the cultural part of the territory”.
It would be very important, he argues, “in addition to the entry of books, which is already occurring at fairs in China”, that one day “these Macau publications could enter the market in Portugal, available, for example, at Bertrand or FNAC, but also in cultural centers or even in our collaboration with the Macau Cultural Scientific Center in Lisbon”. Otherwise, “it is a shame that we are always producing in Portuguese, only for the Macau market, which is very limited”.
It is an “ambitious” project, but at least “try to find a diplomatic way of doing it, for example, China and Portugal establishing joint intentions for the books to one day reach Portugal, because, although there is a lot already translated, and not just from IIM, there are many studies from China, Macau, even the Greater Bay Area, which is now being talked about so much, that are not translated, and there would be every interest in that”.
On the issue of translation, the secretary general states that “at the moment Portuguese is easier to translate into Chinese, because we also have many translators who are from China and who studied Camões' language”.
No entanto, “há, não só da parte do IIM, mas também do mercado de Macau, que encontrar vias, porque a tradução é cara”, constata, adiantando que “há poesias, ou estudos com características culturais muito próprias, que necessitam de pessoas que entendam a cultura e a história para traduzir esses trabalhos”. “This is still a very ambitious step that we hope to one day achieve.”
The IIM maintains links with Portugal and the Macanese diaspora, with close collaboration with the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center, in Lisbon, the Casa de Macau Foundation and the Jorge Álvares Foundation, in addition to universities and institutions with signed protocols.
 
Three new children's adventures at Livraria Portuguesa
On Saturday, Livraria Portuguesa will host the event “1, 2, 3 Books at Once!”, at 4pm, co-organized by Mandarina Books and the International Institute of Macau (IIM). Both institutions published the children's books “Na Escola” from the “Pequenos Exploradores” collection, “Na Memória” and “Vitória, Vitória – An episode of our history”, which will be presented by Pedro D’Alte, professor and specialist in children's literature, according to a press release. The three new adventures include “three worlds to explore and three excellent reasons to indulge in the pleasure of reading”. The event is also part of the Livraria Portuguesa Christmas Market, providing the “perfect opportunity to find that unique gift, full of meaning and imagination”, says the note. Mandarina Books and IIM are dedicated to promoting Portuguese culture and language through quality publications, with a special focus on creating a rich and diverse imagination for young readers.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau chosen to host World Choral Music Symposium</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-escolhido-para-receber-simposio-mundial-de-musica-coral/</link><description>The Macau Choral Art Association is preparing the World Choral Music Symposium, which will take place in August 2026. 14 groups are expected, from various continents, with a total of more than half a thousand people involved. Miguel de Senna Fernandes told TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper that it was “fundamental” to have the Cultural Center as a stage. “Music is a universal language and as we are always talking about harmony values, there is nothing more harmonious than a choir”, he highlights
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
Macau will host the World Symposium on Choral Music (WSCM) for the first time and is already in the process of organizing the shows and parallel activities that will take place between 23 and 28 August 2026. The responsibility for organizing the event, which will involve more than half a thousand people, lies with the Choral Art Association (AACM).
Under the motto “Reimagining the Future”, this musical event, promoted by the International Federation of Choral Music (IFCM) affiliated with UNESCO, will bring together the world's leading choirs, conductors, composers and choral music scholars.
“Macau’s unique symbiosis of Eastern and Western cultures, its vibrant cultural and artistic manifestation, and its rich unique heritage promise to create an inspiring environment where voices from all continents can truly converge”, says a note from AACM.
The president of the institution's general assembly told TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper that the territory “is the ideal place to host an event of this magnitude”.
So far, there is still no defined location to accommodate the many people who are expected to participate, as well as spectators. “We are in talks, raising awareness among entities, so that the Cultural Center (CCM) can be the stage for the symposium and we hope that it will come to fruition, since we need a place like the CCM to accommodate so many people”, reveals Miguel de Senna Fernandes.
From his perspective, the institutional part is paramount. “This is about the image of Macau and that is why we urge the Government to understand so that it is aware of the greatness of this symposium and that it has the same enthusiasm as when the World Choral Expo in Macau was held here in 2015”.
This event, remember, was a festival/exhibition, with a flexible format, which hosted several guest choirs with a wider range of participating ensembles and projects.
“What we are talking about is the World Symposium, IFCM's main large-scale artistic and professional meeting, conceived mainly as a global congress and high-level festival for conductors, composers and advanced choirs, being a place to hear the best ensembles, participate in specialized sessions and influence international choral discourse”, he points out, informing that it is the first to be held in all of China.
From gala concerts and workshops to academic forums and exhibitions, the WSCM, which takes place every three years, the last of which in 2023 in the capital of Turkey, will feature five days of international-level presentations and exchanges, with prestigious groups expected, such as the “Hamilton Children’s Choir” (Canada), “Madrigal Choir” (Philippines), “Vox Clamantis” (Estonia), “Crazy Singers Choir” (Hong Kong), “Shanghai Youth Choir” (China), “Ansan City Choir” (South Korea) and the “World Youth Choir”, among others. The AACM also invited Portugal to be represented by the Choir of the Gregorian Institute of Lisbon.
As the event takes place in Macau, local groups will have the opportunity to showcase themselves. “We still don’t know how many and who, but I think we can count on renowned school choirs, as is the case, for example, at the Pui Cheng School”, said the director, who would like to include the Patuá choir Dóci Pápiaçam di Macau.
For Miguel de Senna Fernandes, the message to be conveyed at an event of this kind “is very good”, considering that “music is a universal language, and, as we are always talking about values ​​of harmony, there is nothing more harmonious than a choir”.
In addition to the groups that will perform, the participation of 40 world-renowned speakers in masterclasses and workshops has been confirmed. “We are confident that this event will be truly spectacular, offering a valuable opportunity to increase cohesion and a sense of belonging among music enthusiasts, thus promoting the noble ideals of harmony and inclusion”, highlights the AACM statement.
“We thank the Diocese of Macau for its support, and we also hope to count on the collaboration of institutions from all sectors, both governmental and private, to jointly make this event the highlight of the year”, concludes the note.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IAM fined 293 violations of the “Animal Protection Law” until October</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/iam-multou-ate-outubro-293-infraccoes-a-lei-de-proteccao-dos-animais/</link><description>In the first 10 months of this year, the IAM fined 293 administrative infractions to the “Animal Protection Law”, which reflects an annual decrease of 23.9%. In response to a written inquiry from Loi I Weng, IAM also indicated that it will expand the area of ​​the dog park on Avenida da Ponte da Amizade and add several facilities in this space
 
Between January and October of this year, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) fined 293 cases of administrative infringement of the “Animal Protection Law”, which, according to what it noted, represents a decrease of 23.9% compared to the same period in 2024. The organization also highlighted that the number of cases fined for infringement of the same law has been decreasing every year.
In response to a written question from deputy Loi I Weng, the IAM highlighted that this demonstrates that “citizens' awareness of compliance with the law in the context of the protection and care of animal life has increased significantly”.
According to him, the body will promptly review the “Animal Protection Law” in accordance with the development of society, in order to improve animal welfare and reinforce legal effectiveness.
On the other hand, it found that, in recent years, the number of dogs and cats delivered to the IAM, due to the impossibility of breeding by their owners, registered a significant decrease. The total has gradually gone from a peak of around 600 dogs and cats per year to 84 by 2024.
The deputy called for measures to promote a pet-friendly environment. The IAM said that, in addition to improving the dog parks in the Colina de Mong-Ha Municipal Park and Travessa do Templo Lin Fong this year, it is carrying out design work for the work to optimize the dog park on Avenida da Ponte da Amizade.
According to the report, the area of ​​this space will be expanded, in addition to adding shade and seating facilities, and replacing the entertainment facilities for dogs. The execution of the work is scheduled for the beginning of 2026. Regarding the feasibility of introducing other complementary facilities in dog parks, the organization stated that it will analyze the current space and the usage situation of each park, as well as the management of equipment and the cost of maintenance, among other factors.
Furthermore, he assured that he continues to reinforce the management and supervision of the contracted companies in order to guarantee the cleanliness of the dog park facilities.
On the other hand, according to the IAM, the decision whether or not to allow the entry and exit of people who bring animals with them is up to the operator of each catering establishment.
 
TNR program scrapped
In another question, deputy Leong Hong Sai urged the Government to improve the current legal registration regime, to eradicate the problem of breeding stray dogs and cats. In this regard, the IAM has ruled out, at this stage, conditions to fully develop the “capture, sterilization and return” measures, also known as the TNR program, for stray animals in all areas of Macau.
The decision is related to the high population density, the external experiences taken into account, the influence on the lives of the population, the ecological environment of the forests and public health, explained the IAM, adding that “it will continue to study various viable methods to control stray animals, taking into account the feasibility and consensus of society”.
According to him, “palliative and definitive effects” were achieved, through the application of the law and fines, inspection and capture with traps, education for legal popularization, optimization of the facilities and equipment of the two municipal kennels, promotion of measures “capture, sterilization, open adoption”, among other actions.
In the interpellation, Leong Hong Sai also warned that, according to some residents of the Hac-Sá Village, there were those who welcomed around 70 dogs that make noise at night. According to the IAM, the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) received a letter from the Islands' Community Services Advisory Council, which referred to this problem.
After sending agents to inspect the area, the corporation found that, in an independent house, four dogs that had obtained the license were being bred and, so far, no traces of stray dogs or other abnormal situations were found, while the sanitary conditions of the public roads in the surrounding area are normal. The CPSP assured that it will continue to monitor this situation.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao SAR wants modern finance as “engine of growth”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-quer-financas-modernas-como-motor-crescimento/</link><description>The Government is moving forward with the creation of a fund for industries, having set up a working group to coordinate the preparatory work, according to the Secretary for Economy and Finance. Tai Kin Ip also said that, next year, he will continue to promote the role of modern finance as an “engine of economic growth”
 
Strengthening institutional mechanisms to support scientific innovation is one of the goals to be achieved in the short term by the Government, according to the Secretary for Economy and Finance. In a speech given during the 4th edition of the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area Financial Forum, Tai Kin Ip revealed that the Executive is moving forward with the creation of a government fund for industries and a guidance fund.
“Currently, a working group has been set up to coordinate the preparatory work related to the creation of these funds”, he indicated.
He added that, next year, which will mark the beginning of the 15th National Five-Year Plan and the 3rd Five-Year Plan of the Macao SAR, the Government will continue to promote the role of modern finance as an “engine of economic growth”, to boost the adequate diversification of the economy, “proactively assuming a more significant role in the development of the Cooperation Zone and the Greater Bay Area”.
Regarding the construction of the bond market, note that the Government is optimizing, in a phased manner, the Macau Central Securities Depository and deepening the network service and interconnection with Hong Kong.
At the same time, he adds, “we advanced with the preparatory work for the Securities Law, aiming to accelerate the creation of a bond market that serves as a bridge to Mainland China and creates connections with the international market, in order to better respond to the financing and investment needs of the Cooperation Zone and the Greater Bay Area”.
Regarding wealth management, the new Investment Fund Law will come into force next month, “further strengthening the legal foundations and development environment of the fund industry in Maca”, he noted, adding that the Government will continue to deepen cooperation mechanisms, such as “Cross-border Financial Management”, together with Mainland China and Hong Kong, promoting the integration of the wealth management markets of the three regions.
The Forum includes several thematic sessions and debates on the government fund for industries.
 
Integration into “One Belt, One Route” expands “development space”
The Government considers participation in the joint construction of “One Belt, One Road” as an “important path to integrate and serve the national development situation, expand Macau’s development space and accelerate the advancement of adequate diversification of the economy”. The statements were made by the Secretary for Economy and Finance at the 7th joint meeting between the National Development and Reform Commission and respective relevant services and the Macao SAR Executive on supporting Macau's comprehensive participation and collaboration in the construction of “One Belt, One Road”. Tai Kin Ip also declared that Macau will reinforce, among other aspects, its “platform functions”, focusing on the creation of “high-level projects with an emblematic and branded character”. The Commission, for its part, will support Macau in promoting a “more robust growth impulse”, in the expansion of “cooperation spaces with greater potential” and in the creation of a “more attractive” cultural image.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau and Hengqin attract four technology companies from Brazil</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-hengqin-atraem-quatro-tecnologicas-brasil/</link><description>Four Brazilian technology companies will establish activities in Macau and Hengqin, after their representatives participated in the “Global Exhibition of Artificial Intelligence Machines and Electronic Products”. According to the Directorate of Economic and Technological Development Services, the event also resulted in seven cooperation agreements, with the participation of 24 companies from Portugal and Brazil
 
During the participation of businesspeople from Portugal and Brazil in the “Global Exhibition of Artificial Intelligence Machines and Electronic Products” (AIE), four technological companies from Brazil completed the procedures to start operations in Macau and Hengqin, according to a statement. Three will operate in the Macao SAR, while the fourth will be located in the Deep Cooperation Zone. In addition, seven cooperation agreements were signed.
The group of companies coordinated by the Directorate of Economic and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) included 30 representatives from 24 companies in the technology sector, higher education institutions, incubators and associations from Portugal and Brazil. In fact, teams participated that won prizes in the “Innovation and Entrepreneurship Competition for Technology Companies in Brazil and Portugal”.
The visit began at the Economic and Commercial Services Center between China and Portuguese and Spanish Speaking Countries in the Hengqin Cooperation Zone. In this first moment, Portuguese and Brazilian companies deepened “their understanding of the development panorama and complementary policies of the scientific and technological innovation industry in that area”.
Company representatives also visited Zhuhai, Guangzhou, Dongguan and Shenzhen, visiting several technology companies in the region, roadshows and seminars.
On the occasion, the businesspeople established exchanges with several investment institutions, technology companies and higher education teams from Mainland China and internationally, in order to “strengthen collaboration” between China and Portuguese-speaking countries.
In general, the participating companies from Brazil and Portugal considered that “the itinerary of this visit was pragmatic and efficient”, which contributed to reinforcing confidence in expanding to the markets of Macau and Mainland China, indicated the DSEDT.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Three homes in Zone A begin operating between 2028 and 2030</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/tres-lares-na-zona-comecam-funcionar-entre-2028-2030/</link><description>There are three homes that will accommodate around 1,100 beds in Zone A of the New Landfills. According to the president of the IAS, they should come into operation between 2028 and 2030
 
Catarina Pereira
 
There are around 1,100 more beds in nursing homes that the new spaces in Zone A of the New Landfills will offer, at a time when population aging is the order of the day and is becoming increasingly accentuated. According to the president of the Institute of Social Action (IAS), Hon Wai, the Government's plan is to “create three homes for the elderly” in Zone A, which should come into operation between 2028 and 2030, as he said in response to a written question from deputy Song Pek Kei.
“In order to meet the needs of the elderly population at a community level, it is intended to create two day centers for the elderly, one in Zone [A] and the other on the Islands of Taipa and Coloane, as well as continue to improve community services for the elderly, through improvements and expansion of services”, added Hon Wai, without giving details.
He also recalled that at the end of this year a new special care center will come into operation in the Tong Chong Building, located in Zone A, with an increase of around 40 vacancies expected, making a total of around 540 vacancies for these services throughout the city.
Regarding reception and nursing services for elderly parents with elderly children and those with intellectual disabilities, the IAS coordinated with the elderly and rehabilitation homes in Seac Pai Van, giving priority to appropriate families in the use of services and thus maintaining family ties, according to what can be seen. In addition, it also coordinated with existing rehabilitation homes in Mong-Ha and considered placing eligible families made up of members of the same sex in the same home.
“In view of the needs for the development of homes for the elderly and rehabilitation, a rehabilitation home for people with intellectual disabilities with around 80 beds will be created in Zone [A], in order to support elderly parents with elderly children and those with intellectual disabilities, through this service model”, highlighted Hon Wai.
The president of the IAS guarantees that, in the future, “the Macao SAR Government will continue to address the feasibility of creating various social facilities, within the scope of the construction of public housing and the use of public land, depending on the needs of the population”.
In response to population aging and the development of services for people with disabilities, the Executive is carrying out preparatory work for planning the “Ten-Year Action Plan for Support Services for the Elderly 2026 to 2035” and the “Ten-Year Action Plan for Rehabilitation Services 2026 to 2035”, which, according to Hon Wai, should be officially published in the 1st quarter of 2026. Hope is that “these two ten-year plans establish a solid and sustainable basis for the development and systematic progress of quality services in the areas of elderly and rehabilitation”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Zhang Lanpo shows Chinese conceptual photography at the Hostel</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/zhang-lanpo-mostra-albergue-fotografia-conceptual-chinesa/</link><description>Photographs of contemporary Chinese art, by Zhang Lanpo, will be on display at the Albergue from today onwards. The artist considered one of the 20 best photographers on the Continent, stands out for his intellectual depth and broad investigation into the limits of human existence and consciousness






























“Acima do Abismo” is a solo exhibition of works by Chinese photographer Zhang Lanpo that will open today, at 6:30 pm, at Galeria A2 at Albergue da Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macau.
Recognized among the 20 best emerging contemporary photographers in China, the artist is considered one of the most representative figures in the field of Chinese conceptual photography. His practice is distinguished by its intense “intellectual depth and broad investigation into the limits of human existence and consciousness”, according to the manifesto promoting the exhibition, organized by the Círculo dos Amigos da Cultura (CAC) in commemoration of the 26th anniversary of the Macao SAR.
Going beyond “pure aesthetics”, Zhang Lanpo’s works “engage in critical and philosophical discourses” that position them at the center of the debate on contemporary Chinese art. His photography continues to be “focused on death”, with the aim of reconstructing a “vision of life”, highlights the CAC.
The artist's works have been exhibited at the China International Design Museum, and also at the YOUART museum in Suzhou, Arte Times de Chengdu and Arte de Guangdong, among other places.
The exhibition consists of 16 works, in a collection that includes photography and painting pieces. “Through his unique visual language, the artist takes the audience on a journey “floating above the abyss”. Named in English as “Above the Abyss”, the exhibition is not just a visual presentation, but a deep reflection on history, memory and humanity, critically re-examining the reality perceived by the public.”
The exhibition curator considers that Zhang Lanpo places his images “in a world that never completely descends, being fragments floating above a dark and viscous soil, emerging and sinking through layers of time, memory and death”.
Lion Ho adds that the artist does not restore history, but dismantles it. “Sacred forms merge with weapons, nerves become crowns of thorns, ruins intertwine with organs and divinity becomes involved in violence.”
The meaning “fragments” and the scale “collapses”, states the exhibition’s curator, for whom “floating above the abyss is the position he chooses and perhaps the position we share”, that is, “a threshold without ascension or escape, viscous, weightless, without resolution”. Here, “no truth is told, only images remain, waiting for the gaze that completes them”, he concludes.
The artist, born in the city of Lanzhou, has a master's degree in Fine Arts from the Guangzhou Academy of Fine Arts and currently resides in Zhaoqing, Guangdong province.
The exhibition, sponsored by the Cultural Development Fund and supported by “Art On Space” and Albergue da Santa Casa da Misericórdia, will be open to the public until February 15, 2026.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Images by Pedro Ramos highlight cultural traditions</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/imagens-de-pedro-ramos-realcam-tradicoes-culturais/</link><description>Photographic memories of the period between the transition and today are works of reflection and a personal look by photographer Pedro Ramos, on display at Galeria da Livraria Portuguesa. The artist shows images that document historic architecture and cultural traditions

“Macau’s Reflections – Now and then” is an exhibition of 74 works by photographer Pedro Ramos, which offers a deep and sensitive look at Macau at a decisive period in its history: from the transition from the end of Portuguese administration to integration into China, from 1999, to the present day.
The exhibition, whose opening ceremony is scheduled for 6:30 pm today, aims to provide a reflection and a very personal look at Macau.” Through a careful selection of the photographer's works, the exhibition captures the “essence of a city in flux, visually preserving its unique hybrid character”, according to a statement from 10 Marias Associação Cultural, which organizes the event.
The photographs function as a “portal to the past”, adds the note, documenting the historic architecture, vibrant markets, daily street life and cultural traditions that “defined Macau in the twilight of its previous status”. But they also function as a portal to a “colorful” future!
For those responsible for the exhibition, the work of Portuguese Pedro Ramos is not only “aesthetically captivating”, but also serves as a historical and cultural record “of inestimable value”, highlighting the delicate balance between tradition and modernity.
The images capture the soul of Macau “at a moment of historical turning point”, acting as a powerful reminder of the richness of our shared cultural heritage” and this exhibition aligns with our mission to preserve and promote the memory and cultural diversity of Macau”, highlights the Association.
The professional photographic artist and trainer, with an established career since 1998, has a personal connection to the territory, where he completed his primary and secondary education at the Liceu de Macau. He graduated from the prestigious Ar.Co school in Lisbon, and his vast experience covers areas such as commercial, portrait, fashion, architectural and travel photography.
His CV includes collaborations with entities such as Canon Portugal, FNAC Portugal or the Western Tourism Region, in addition to continuous activity as a trainer in institutions such as the Social Services of Caixa Geral de Depósitos.
This exhibition in Macau represents a “powerful synthesis of his technical vision and his intimate connection” with the territory, adds the document of the 10 Marias, a cultural collective based in Macau and dedicated to promoting and celebrating the territory’s cultural heritage.
The exhibition, subsidized by the Cultural Development Fund and supported by Casa de Portugal and the Associação Promotora da Instrução dos Macaenses, will be on view until the 30th of this month.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao SAR shows the ‘window of social inclusion’ in the Special Games</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-mostra-nos-jogos-especiais-janela-da-inclusao-social/</link><description>Badminton challenges for competitions aimed at disabled athletes at the National Games are already taking place at the Macau Dome. Macao SAR receives 28 teams, integrated into the motor and hearing disability groups. Secretary O Lam stressed that the territory has the opportunity to showcase “the important window of social inclusion in Macau”
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The National Games for People with Disabilities and the Special National Special Olympics Games have 46 disciplines and 1,876 small sports included in the sport for all category.
In the numbers released at a press conference held in Guangzhou, attended by the coordinator of the Macau side, Pun Weng Kun, it was mentioned that, after a rigorous classification, the games for the motor disability group and the hearing disability group occupy 26 large and 1,146 small modalities. 7,824 athletes from 34 delegations are registered, with a total size of more than 11 thousand people, which represents an increase of around 30% compared to the previous edition.
The Macao SAR is responsible for organizing badminton, the games of which started yesterday at the East Asian Games Sports Hall (Macau Dome). The competition will feature 28 teams, with a total of 500 members, including coaches, athletes and managers.
The games for People with Disabilities are divided into two categories: motor disability group and hearing impairment group, covering 26 small modalities, while the National Special Olympic Games group will have eight categories by age, covering 18 small modalities.
Meanwhile, the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture participated in the plenary meeting of the Organizing Committee of the event that will take place in Macau, Hong Kong and Guangzhou. The official highlighted that “this is the first time that the competition has been hosted in Macau, “which demonstrates the trust that the country places in the Macao SAR, as well as an opportunity to showcase the important window of social inclusion in Macau, contributing to the connection between the residents of the Greater Bay Area.”
Lam added that the Government has coordinated cooperation between various services and that venues and facilities have been refurbished and updated in accordance with the requirements of the Special Olympics Games for the Disabled, and the Gaode Accessibility Digital Map also covers Macau, “creating a more inclusive and friendly travel environment, improving the barrier-free travel experience”.
Regarding volunteers, 1,500 will receive specialized training, being able to offer comprehensive services and support in all jobs, as well as elements of sign language interpretation.
Border posts for official receptions opened exclusive corridors and buses to speed up the passage of participating delegations. Food, transport, medical assistance and public health and security are being provided to ensure that the races run smoothly.
Tickets can be collected free of charge, allowing a greater number of spectators at the games venues “to encourage athletes and promote social inclusion and the event environment”, highlighted the Secretary.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief gave orders to speed up work in the Cooperation Zone</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-deu-ordens-para-acelerar-trabalhos-na-zona-de-cooperacao/</link><description>The Chief Executive instructed the various branches of the Macao SAR Government to reorganize the upcoming work related to the Cooperation Zone, within the scope of the third meeting of the Leadership Group for Promoting the Construction of the In-depth Cooperation Zone in Hengqin. According to a statement from the Social Communication Office, Sam Hou Fai asked for the “main projects” to be implemented and promoted “in an orderly manner”, in addition to the fact that the various services should also “continue to select excellent public servants to participate in the construction of this Zone”. The meeting was attended by the five Secretaries. On the occasion, Sam Hou Fai said that the members of constituent leaders of the Management Committee and the Executive Committee of the Cooperation Zone, which underwent adjustment last month, will continue to perform leadership and coordination roles, “under the existing good foundation, striving to promote high-quality development”. He also highlighted that the construction of the Zone will continue to focus on “main aspects” such as innovative technology and industrial development, simplifying the lives and employment of Macau residents and promoting the efficient movement of people and goods between Macau and Hengqin. In this regard, the leader of the Macao SAR even said that “a series of policies and measures will be implemented, in a pragmatic way, in order to give greater impetus to the general development of the Cooperation Zone”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lecture focuses on cross-border issues about funerals and refugees</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/palestra-foca-questoes-transfronteiricas-sobre-funerais-refugiados/</link><description>Carlos Ka Nok Lo, assistant professor of Research at the Department of History at the University of Macau, will be the speaker at the lecture “Cross-Border Funeral and Refugee Issues: Macau during the Mid-20th Century”, which takes place today at Fundação Rui Cunha (FRC), at 7pm. The conference is part of the Cycle of Public Lectures on History and Heritage, the result of a regular partnership between the FRC and the Department of History and Heritage of the University of São José. Carlos Lo will speak on the topic that is the basis of his recent research and which should appear in his second monograph, entitled “Death and Funeral Practices in the Special Administrative Region of Macau, China”, to be published in 2026. In a press release, the FRC states that “from the mid-19th century, due to repeated coercive measures imposed by the Portuguese authorities in Macau, Chinese residents were prohibited from burying their dead on the Peninsula”. The Portuguese authorities then formally authorized the Kiang Wu Hospital, in 1881, to supervise Chinese burials and manage the Chinese Cemetery. “A unique pattern of cross-border burial was thus established between Macau and Xiangshan County (an area corresponding to the south of present-day Zhuhai), a practice that persists to this day”, explains the researcher, quoted in a statement. In the mid-20th century, the Japanese invasion of China triggered a mass migration to Macau, worsening the scarcity of burial space. “The great lack of land for burial led to the appearance of mass graves in the border area”, he adds.</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Architect Frank Gehry, master of deconstructivism, has passed away</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/faleceu-arquiteto-frank-gehry-mestre-desconstrutivismo/</link><description>Architect Frank Gehry, considered the master of deconstructivism and author of a series of emblematic works, from the Guggenheim Museum in Bilbao to the Walt Disney Concert Hall in Los Angeles, died last weekend. He was 96 years old.

Gehry was perhaps the greatest among the so-called “starchitects” (an elite group that includes Renzo Piano, Rem Koolhaas and Norman Foster, among others) and, although he enjoyed fame, he hated this label.
“There are people who design buildings that are neither technically nor financially good, and others who do the same,” he told The Independent in 2009. “There are two categories, simple,” he added.
His artistic genius and boldness shone through in complex projects, such as the large glass “sails” at the Louis Vuitton Foundation in Paris.
Gehry popularized contemporary architecture and became such a well-known personality that he even appeared on the television series “The Simpsons”.
“I work with clients who respect the art of architecture”, he declared in 2014, according to his biographer Paul Goldberger.
Born Frank Owen Goldberg in Toronto on February 28, 1929, to a Jewish family who moved to the US in the late 1940s, he changed his surname to Gehry to avoid becoming a target of anti-Semitism.
He studied architecture at the University of Southern California in Los Angeles, where he graduated in 1954 before enlisting in the US Army. He then continued his studies in urban planning at Harvard University, although he did not complete the program.
Between 1952 and 1966, he was married to Anita Snyder, with whom he had two children. He married again in 1975 to Berta Isabel Aguilera and had two more children.
His career began in the office of architect Victor Gruen, a pioneer in the design of shopping centers in Los Angeles. Afterwards, he moved to Paris to work with André Remondet. Back in California, he opened his own studio in the early 1960s.
The 1970s and 1980s marked the beginning of a long series of bold and innovative architectural projects, many of them in Southern California.
Close to the Californian “funk” art scene, Gehry's deconstructivist and experimental style is difficult to categorize. Many of his works (irregular metal facades that may resemble crumpled paper) could only be built thanks to digital design tools, which he adopted in a pioneering way.
One of the best examples is the renovation of his own house in Santa Monica, from 1978, where he lived for a long time. Here, corrugated metal surrounds the original 1920s structure.
Gehry ended the 1980s with architecture's highest honor: the Pritzker Prize, awarded in 1989.
Almost a decade later, he presented what is perhaps his most iconic project: the Guggenheim Museum in Bilbao, which earned him international recognition and fame. The work of limestone and glass, with curved walls covered in titanium sheets, is easily identifiable as a creation by Gehry. The American architect Philip Johnson even described it as “the best building of our time”.
The museum helped revitalize the city's former industrial heart, attracting visitors from all over the world and giving rise to the expression “Bilbao effect”, used to explain how architectural beauty can transform a region.
Many of Gehry's projects required complex calculations, which he pushed to the limit. For a long time, architects avoided rounded or curved shapes, as they created difficulties for engineers and drastically increased construction costs.
Gehry went against this logic and used 3D modeling software similar to those used by the aerospace industry. In this way, he was able to create unique shapes and keep costs within what investors were willing to pay for more conventional buildings.
The Lou Ruvo Center for Brain Health in Las Vegas—whose walls and windows appear to have melted in the desert heat—is a classic example of his innovative vision. "I love working. I love solving problems," he told The Guardian in 2019.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>