<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Suggested “special support” of the government for Macau-Portugal flights</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sugerido-apoio-especial-governo-em-prol-de-voos-macau-portugal/</link><description>CAM's marketing department director said there are some “difficulties” with regard to the creation of a direct flight between Macau and Portugal, but the company continues to try to encourage airlines to develop these routes. Eric Fong defended, in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, that the Government of MSAR should create a "special support." In addition, he said, he should try to negotiate the assignment of subsidies, together with the Portugal Civil Aviation Authority, to the company so that costs can be reduced
 
Macau Airport Society (CAM) “has driven airlines to develop direct or transferred routes to Portugal,” said Eric Fong, director of the company's marketing department, but is not an easy task. "We still strive to work on the aspect of direct flights," he continued in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao.
However, about this ambition, Eric Fong pointed out that “currently there is still a certain degree of difficulties” and a “very long incubation period”, given the “very high costs”, the market and other commercial considerations. According to noted, there are no carriers interested in launching this long distance connection.
"Therefore, we suggest to the Government of Misremine to create special support. And we also propose that [the government] and the Portuguese Civil Aviation Authority negotiate to provide subsidies to the airline [operator] and passengers, to ensure that the company reduces costs as possible before the launch of flights.
According to the official, some passengers from Macao resort to the Inheon Route (South Korea) - Lisbon, operated by Korean Air. In addition, he said that Cam has kept contact with Air Macao, hoping the Flag Company of the Mother China Air China, to make a connection between Macau and Beijing and the transfer of daxing to Europe.
On the other hand, Eric Fong said that Cam also bets on the “unique ticket with luggage transfer to the final destination”, mainly through several large carriers, such as China Eastern Airlines, China Southern Airlines, Korean Air, among others. Under this model, the flights depart from Macau to Beijing, Seoul, Taiwan, Kuala Lumpur, Singapore, or Bangkok, and then take passengers to Canada, USA, Europe, Australia, Egypt and India, he explained.
"There are many passengers from Macao to go to Canada, with the volume of passengers recorded a certain increase… In addition, we have constantly promoted this service [bay flights] in the Great Bay, so that tourists from the great bay or European or American countries can travel to Macau this way," he said.
This year, Cam also has made several negotiations with Australian and European airlines, "especially with Turkish Airlines", to promote medium and long distance charter routes in Macao, through cooperation with carriers and travel agencies, pointed out Eric Fong.
“Regarding charter routes, it will be a little difficult to promote this area to depend only on the population of Macau. So we have negotiated with some travel agencies and large charter companies in the interior of China, to realize if they are interested in promoting, along with Turkish Airlines and Australian airlines. Macau Airport can attract people in this part of the Great Bay -such as Jiangmen and Zhongshan -from Macau to move to the Middle East. Airlines have already expressed this desire if we can connect all the supply chains involved, ”said the official.
According to exemplified, Cam is “quite interested” on Turkish Airlines, wishing to promote connecting flights from Turkey and, using codes, then transport passengers to the interior of China, Southeast Asia and Northeast Asia with Air Macau planes. In this aspect, Eric Fong stressed that Cam "has been hardworking" and that negotiations "never stopped".
On the other hand, the Civil Aviation Activity Law will come into force on February 1 of next year. According to Eric Fong, so far, no airline has expressed a clear interest in providing passenger air transport services in Macao, but some carriers have asked CAM information on operational issues and requirements. Among the companies that contacted Cam, "there are some traditional and some foreigners," he said.
 
Service Centers in Shenzhen and Zhongshan
In addition, the official noted that the Macao Airport Service Center in Zhuhai went into operation on July 2 in Gongbei, having mainly served passengers from neighboring regions and providing airplane ticket and flying information consultation services and border ticket.
Eric Fong said that two more service centers of his gender should go into operation in the 4th quarter of this year in Shekou, Shenzhen, and in the port of Zhongshan, being "negotiating some details" and "proceeding to the decoration". According to it, these centers will provide information about flights, but also provide the maritime and air transport transfer service between these maritime terminals and Macao airport.
“We will promote a service that will allow passengers to leave the Shekou terminals and the Zhongshan Port, after arriving at the mud terminal, catching fast buses linked to Macau airport and using the" one inspection "service to go directly to Japan or South Korea, for example. 110 Patacas tax reimbursement and see luggage directly transferred to the destination. ”
The Campo and Air Transport Transfer Services Network will also include Wanzai Port, Zhuhai, and the Interior Porto Maritime Terminal, whose facilities and services were already ready in the first half of this year. ” However, the company currently continues to negotiate with China's interior authorities on “some details”, not providing a calendar for the launch of the service, in which the paid bus service of Macau airport will also be made available to passengers who reach the interior port terminal from the port of Wanzai. As this type of passengers enjoys tax refund, the service is “basically free,” notic Fong noted.
 
“Low-Cost” absorb 26% of passengers
Eric Fong also revealed that between January and July this year, 74% of Macau airport passengers caught flights from traditional airlines while 26% chose low-cost carriers. According to the same temporal interval, the “Low-Cost” flight occupancy rate exceeded 80%, while traditional airlines found an occupancy rate of about 75%. "Normally, low-cost airlines register a flight occupation rate between 80% and 85%," he added.
In addition, it also said that in the first seven months of the year, the total number of passengers at the airport registered an annual break of 4%, while the volume of flights was also below that verified in the same period of 2024. Regarding the origin of passengers, residents accounted for 11%, followed by those from the interior of China (57%), foreigners (17%), those of Hong Kong (1%) and those of Taiwan and those of Taiwan (14%). In this respect, he noted that the percentage of passengers on the Chinese continent fell two to three percentage points in annual terms. Still, he noted that the situation remained similar to the usual.
Eric Fong also said that in late September a route will be launched between Macao and the island of Phu Quoc, Vietnam, with two flights a week. And almost at the same time or early October, Macau will have a new connection to Sihanoukville, Cambodia, also with two flights weekly. In early November the Macau-Cheongju, South Korea, with four flights a week will be inaugurated.
In the interior of China, the official mentioned that, on September 10, flights will be started between Macau and Nanchang, capital of Jiangxi province, served by Comac C909 aircraft, with three flights a week.</description><pubDate>2025-08-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Launched contest for superstructure work of the Central Library</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lancado-concurso-para-obra-de-superestrutura-da-biblioteca-central/</link><description>The contest was launched yesterday for the construction work of the Central Library superstructure at the site of the former Hotel Estoril. The Directorate of Public Works Services states that this endeavor will have “immediate start” after the completion of the foundations and cellars. A base price was not defined, but as for the execution period is 620 days of work. The definitive security, in turn, is 5% of the total price of award. Proposals can be delivered until October 8
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The new Central Library, at the former Hotel Estoril, next to Tap Seac Square, will soon enter a new phase of construction. Yesterday, the Directorate of Public Works (DSOP) services launched the public competition of the construction work of the building's superstructure, whose project was the “Mecanoo” Dutch architecture office. Proposals can be delivered until 5 pm on October 8, and a base price is not defined.
In the announcement, published yesterday in an official bulletin, it is said that the maximum global execution period is 620 days of work, counted from the consignment of the work, with a mandatory goal: the completion of the coverage structure with a maximum period of 300 working days. DSOP states that "the work of superstructure will immediately begin, after the conclusion of the works of foundations and cellars."
For the assessment of proposals, DSOP will take into account several criteria, with the price of the endeavor to be the most weight (50%), followed by experience and quality in works (20%), execution time (15%), the execution program (10%) and the plan of the human resources program and the proportion of workers residing in management positions (5%).
According to the director of DSOP, Lam Wai Hou, “the award is made to the competitor with the highest total score and, if there is a tie in the higher total score, the award is made to the competitor with the lower price proposal”.
The announcement also informs that the provisional security is 7.8 million patacas, to be provided by cash deposit, bank warranty or insurance approved in the legal terms. The definitive security is 5% of the total price of adjudication, specifically, of the amounts that the contractor has to receive, in each of the partial payments, 5% to guarantee the contract, in reinforcement of the definitive security provided.
The new central library occupies an area of ​​land of about 2,960 square meters. According to the project, the library will have four floors in height, with a basement for storage purposes. The ground floor and top floors have an auditorium room, newspaper and magazine reading zones, adult libraries, children's library, youth library, meeting rooms, among other spaces.
Regarding the contest, there will be a visit to the place on September 3, at 10h00, being the meeting point the former Hotel Estoril.
It was three years ago, in March 2021, that it was known that the proposal of the office "Mecanoo" had been chosen for the conceptual project of the new central library, as it was "simple, rigorous, inspiring and multifunctional." It was the only one to support the change of symbolic mosaic to the interior of the library. The initial budget surrounded the 500 million patacas and at the time, it was expected that the space could open by the end of 2024, a goal that was already widely exceeded.</description><pubDate>2025-08-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>ID will adopt “Deduction of Points” in future awards</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/id-adoptara-deducao-de-pontos-nas-futuras-adjudicacoes/</link><description>Following CCAC suggestions, the ID has stated that it will introduce, in future public tenders, a mechanism for “downstream” in the evaluation criteria contained in the competition programs, appreciating the registration of ID -attached services to competitors in the last 24 months
 
In a case summary in the context of the “provision of justice”, the commissioner against corruption (CCAC) stressed that it is “an incomprehensible and unacceptable question” the fact that at the recently “ID) award in favor of a competitor in a contest without being subsequently rendered proper management and rescue service, and then was awarded, to have been awarded Competitor, again and in a short time, the provision of a similar service. ”
In this sense, CCAC considers that, in order to ensure the impartiality of public administration, in the future, it should be taken in advance measures adequate measures to the process of public tenders of the ID, in order to improve the items and evaluation criteria. It should be “above all to proceed with a broad assessment of the weaknesses and strong points of competitors, either regarding their performance and the quality of the services provided in the past”, stressed the CCAC, maintaining that “only then can the true quality of competitors be known, making the evaluations fairer”.
In response, the ID, in addition to stating that it agrees with CCAC's suggestions, has promised that “it will adopt adequate improvement measures in future public tenders, namely introducing a 'dowridden deduction' mechanism in the contest programs, and the registration of services awarded by the same institute in the last 24 months is appreciated.
According to it, if there is non -compliance with the obligations promised in the proposal, violation of contractual rules, irregularity subject to a fine, among others, a “deduction of points” will take place in the evaluation item related to the experience in providing service.
The case summary indicates that, during the treatment of a complaint, CCAC confirmed that a company obtained, in March 2024, through public tenders, awards of two services to ID, namely the outdoor pool management and rescue service and sports facilities with ID on the peninsula and identical service on the islands.
The service period was from April 1, 2024 to March 31, 2026. However, the company was unable to hire a sufficient number of salvator swimmers, not being able to fully fulfill the obligations assumed. In addition, it did not present the definitive security within the period indicated, so that the provisional security was confiscated and the expiration of the awards was declared.
In August last year, the ID reorganized the referred pools and held four more public tenders to provide similar services.
According to the CCAC, although all competition programs refer to various situations in which the potential competitors are considered as unqualified, including “having been punished with a fine or termination the contract by the award for breach of contractual obligations”, ID eventually concluded that there was no situation that allowed the company in question not meeting the requirements. Thus, he continued to apply the same evaluation criteria to decide the award again to the same company. This time, the service period began on December 1, 2024 and ends on November 30, 2026.</description><pubDate>2025-08-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Reinforced transport service for the start of the school year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/reforcado-servico-de-transporte-para-arranque-ano-lectivo/</link><description>Transmac and TCM will increase the frequency of buses of buses during periods of higher movement from September 1, when most schools start the new school year. Three public services are coordinating the implementation of transportation measures, including the detachment of additional personnel to manage the flow of people
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Most Macao educational establishments will start the school year 2025/2026 on September 1, so three public services are coordinating the implementation of transportation measures.
To respond to usual needs at this time of year, the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT), the Public Security Police (CPSP) and the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) collaborated to collect and share information about the beginning of the classes.
A working meeting was recently held with the two bus companies to plan transportation services. Almost 80% of secondary, primary and children's schools will start activities on the first day of next month.
All parties agreed to highlight additional staff to manage pawns flows during the initial period, increase bus and light meter services as necessary, and prepare contingency support measures. "These measures will ensure the safety and tranquility of students, staff and parents' travel," as you can read in a joint statement of those three services.
DSAT coordinated with the two bus companies and the Metro Ligeiro society to increase services during the end hours. In concrete, Transmac and TCM will increase the output frequency by approximately 10 to 15% during periods of higher movement.
At the same time, additional personnel will be highlighted to maintain order in the bus stops and manage passenger flow, while maintenance teams have received instructions to reinforce the maintenance of vehicles and carriages of the light meter.
Authorities will highlight additional agents, before the beginning of the academic period, to patrol the roads near schools, deal with illegal parking and drive traffic at busy crossings and entrances of educational establishments during peak hours.
For its part, DSEDJ also coordinated with schools the detachment of more employees, within its own facilities, to help with students reception.
In addition to mobilizing more personal, DSAT and CPSP will implement various measures to ensure the flow of traffic without obstacles and optimize the transport environment, ensuring that the main road works performed during the summer holidays have been completed, while others will end before the beginning of classes, "thanks to a close interdepartal coordination and reinforced supervision."
DSAT reports that it took advantage of the summer holidays to renew the treadmills, the pedestrian lanes and other facilities and traffic signaling around various school zones. In addition, he reinforces, "a new diagonal crossing system was installed at the intersection between the right street of the Hippodrome and the Hippodrome Avenue, near the schools."
Meanwhile, CPSP will designate certain parking spaces such as temporary passenger and passenger zones during the first week of classes to facilitate student collection by parents.
"Both parents and students should book enough time for travel, keep up with traffic and time updates and try to go on foot or use public transport," the document stresses, warning that "when private vehicles are used to take or pick up students from parks, parks of parking or designated stop zones should be used in order to avoid illegal parking and traffic obstruction."</description><pubDate>2025-08-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai wants to attract technology from the Lusófono block</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/sam-hou-fai-quer-atrair-tecnologicas-bloco-lusofono/</link><description>The chief executive wants companies of technology and science sectors from the Lusophone countries to be fixed in the region, the local government said yesterday. Sam Hou Fai pointed to the objective for the territory to “actively attract scientific and technological companies of excellence of Portuguese -speaking countries”, according to a statement.
The government leader stressed that these companies can establish operations in both Macao and in the in -depth cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in neighboring Hengqin.
On the contrary, Sam promised to “support the scientific and technological companies in the interior of China to expand abroad”, taking advantage of Macao and the four reference laboratories of the city based in the city.
The chief executive spoke at a meeting with Chinese Science and Technology Minister Yin Hejun, who came to Macau to mark the restructuring of the four laboratories.
Laboratories, based at the University of Macao and Macao University of Science and Technology, are dedicated to the areas of Chinese medicine, lunar and planetary science, microelectronics and the Internet of Things.
Hours earlier, Yin argued that the four laboratories should “take advantage of Macao's environment and advantages, namely the tradition of“ abroad cooperation ”to hire more“ international talents ”.
Remember that Sam Hou Fai will visit Portugal from September 16, at the first trip to abroad since taking office in December. The Chief Executive - the first leader of the territory to dominate the Portuguese language - will visit Lisbon and Madrid.
In May, Sam said the delegation sent by Macao to Portugal and Spain will include entrepreneurs from the region's industrial, commercial and financial sectors and "even certain companies in the interior of China."
At the same time, he argued that the territory has to “welcome foreign friends to invest in Macau and also to realize their dreams in Macau”, especially in the area of ​​advanced technology.
Sam stressed that "they can come from Portuguese and Spanish -speaking countries." "As long as they are in favor of economic diversification, they are always welcome," added the leader.
Sam argued that local entrepreneurs should "explore Spanish and Portuguese language markets and Africa markets and the Middle East."
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-08-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>"Two -digit" restaurants in business</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/restaurantes-quebra-de-dois-digitos-nos-negocios/</link><description>Due to several factors, including recent tufts, the Macao restoration sector has so far verified a “double -digit break” in the summer holidays, compared to last year's homologous period, said the subdirector of the associations of restoration and beverages owners' associations and beverage associations.
 
In this summer vacation, the local restoration sector registered a “double -digit break” in the turnover, compared to the same period last year, with the flow of customers decreased by the summer of 2024, Lo Kam Kuan, subdirector of the associations of Macao's restoration and beverages associations, revealed.
According to the Chinese language press, restaurants in residential areas have suffered a more significant break in recipes. The associative leader attributed the situation to bad weather, recent typhoons, as well as the consumption of residents abroad, the weakening of consumer power, the simplification of the eating habits of the population and the expansion of the food delivery model.
In addition, Lo Kam Kuan noticed that, following the climbing price of ingredients, the sector has been more stressed in operations, so it had to try to reduce human resources, adopt cheap menus and throw discounts through food delivery platforms.
From its perspective, the new round of the great consumption prize from September 1 will be beneficial to impulse community consumption, and the time to launch the measure is "adequate". Predicting that the sector's business can improve thanks to this measure, the associative leader called for restaurants that they do not take advantage of the consumer program to raise prices.
 
Stimulated consumption will be similar to the previous
On the other hand, the great consumption award was discussed yesterday on a “or Mun Tin Toi” program. Lau Kit Lon, head of the Department of Development of Economic Activities of the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), predicted that the plan will stimulate a total value of consumption equivalent to 4.2 times the amount attributed to consumers, similar to the ratio achieved at the last round of the program. It is recalled that the budget of this initiative was elevated from 295 million to 485 million Patacas.
Several listeners have asked that electronic consumer coupons can also be used on weekdays and holidays. However, this hypothesis was discarded by the DSEDT official. He explained, the essential objective of the initiative is to encourage residents to consume in Macao on weekends to support small and medium-sized local businesses. Thus, the measure could deviate from the original intention of the government, if it were extended to the working days, he pointed out.
At this point, Lau Kit Lon said that, according to data on previous editions, consumer benefits led to a 20% rise in the amount of Macao on weekends, which reflects that policy has achieved the goal. According to it, the use rate of consumer coupons with a value of 200 patacas reached 93%.
On the other hand, an inquiry carried out by an academic institution in charge of DSEDT shows that 73% of residents used to consume on the other side of the border said they increased the frequency of consumption in Macao because of the plan.</description><pubDate>2025-08-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Professional sector launched suggestions to the chief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sector-profissional-lancou-sugestoes-ao-chefe/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai, gathers with representatives of the expert group (Think Tank) and the professional sector to a hellish opinions and suggestions in the context of the elaboration of the Governing Action Lines Report



Think tanks representatives and professional sector associations launched suggestions to the Chief Executive in the context of the governance lines for 2026. Diverse topics discussed, including reinforcement in regional cooperation, optimization of the business environment and support for small and medium -sized companies
 
The Chief Executive continues the auscultations to various local groups and associations, in view of the preparation of the Governing Action Lines Report (LAG) for the Financial Year of 2026. This time, Sam Hou Fai received at the Government headquarters representatives of 16 "Think Tanks" and professional sector associations.
At the meeting were presented opinions on various aspects, including the enrichment of Macao as the World Center for Tourism and Leisure, the acceleration of the development of the main emerging industries, the reinforcement in regional cooperation, the optimization of the business environment, the support for small and medium enterprises for a better quality business and the revitalization of the community economy.
The stability of the use of residents and the acceleration of intelligent city construction were also under analysis, in a meeting where Hou Fai also heard suggestions on the improvement of urban planning, the optimization of the transportation system and the qualified staff regime, the work of young people, a greater safeguarding national security and the stability of Macao and the intensification in the construction of the deepened cooperation zone.
Several representatives have expressed that they expect the government to continue to bet on urban construction, further optimizing the housing environment, creating better development opportunities for residents and increasing the well-being of the population. Before the meeting, some of the associative leaders and experts of the Think Tanks handed over the boss's proposals in writing.
Sam Hou Fai stressed that he will study and analyze the opinions “seriously” to “pragmatically” the LAG report.
He stressed that, “in the face of the changes and complexity of the internal and external environment”, all social sectors of Macao “persist in the beautiful tradition of loving the country and masters”, having provided strong support in the development of society. He said he also believed that "the good base, if in the future it is necessary for the government to face deep social conflicts, will also allow to overcome the challenges and resolve them properly with the support of all sectors."
He also pointed out that, “when formulating policies”, the government must take into account “equity and sustainability” in the sense of “ensuring social stability and lasting and stable development of Macao”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-08-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Permanent show on “viable” patriotic education for the DSEDJ</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mostra-permanente-sobre-educacao-patriotica-viavel-para-dsedj/</link><description>The Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services considers it being feasible to install a permanent show on National Security Education
 
Teng Sio Hong, Substitute Director of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ), considers that the installation of a permanent exhibition on national security education is a viable proposal. However, in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Ho Ion Sang, the official explained that, in relation to the choice of the site, several factors must be considered, namely the “accessibility in transport”, the “convenience to the public” and the “adequacy of space”.
Recently, Deputy Ho Ion Sang questioned the government about the plans for the creation of “a permanent center of education on national security” and the organization of study visits and training on the subject. Teng Sio Hong has assured that DSEDJ will “promote education on the national conjuncture”, organizing the move of teaching and non -teaching staff, students and young people based on patriotism education to young people from Macao and the basis of education of education on the general perspective of national security for Macao young people in Shandong and Beijing.
The substitute director ensures that the body “continues to develop, organize and support associations in the realization of various activities, to deepen the feeling of love for the homeland and Macao of young people and students and their knowledge of national security”. In addition, DSEDJ will inaugurate a “Patriotic Education Exhibition Pavilion” in Seac Pai Van, in order to provide “diverse and rich learning experiences on the education of love for the homeland and Macau,” said Teng Sio Hong.
Under the recent anniversary of the Japan Resistance War, DSEDJ has organized study visits to historic sites, and also organized more than a hundred teacher training courses, which have focused on national security in the last three school years. In addition to the publication of the book “National Security Education”, various pedagogical activities, exchange actions and visits to patriotic education facilities and study posts in Macao and Hengqin were carried out, reiterated Teng Sio Hong, among other initiatives.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-08-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Rapper” Travis Scott includes Macao in Asian Turning</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/rapper-travis-scott-inclui-macau-em-digressao-asiatica/</link><description>Macao and Sanya are the two places in China where US musician Travis Scott will act in concerts integrated into the Asian tour, which also includes stops in India, South Korea and Japan. The performance of the “rapper” in the territory is scheduled for October 29 at the outdoor spectacles on the quota
 
Macao was chosen as one of the stops of the tour of the American “rapper” Travis Scott by the Asian continent, where he is expected to act in four other places: Sanya (China), Nova Delhi (India), Seoul (South Korea) and Tokyo (Japan). The concert at MSAR is scheduled for October 29, being the second large -scale event to take place at the outdoor shows on Cotai, with capacity to receive up to 50,000 spectators.
Those interested in watching the artist's show will be able to buy tickets from September 5, with prices between 459 and 7,599 Patacas. Macao residents will be able to purchase tickets through MPay or Macau Pass applications. Continent fans have the option of Damai online box office, while Hong Kong residents will be able to use the CityLine platform.
The show was not yet officially announced by the organization of the event in Macao, but the singer's coming is part of the program released by the official page of the “Circus Maximus” tour, which began in October 2023, and the five concerts in Asia was later added. Prior to the mashed show, the “rapper” will perform performances in India (October 18 and 19) and Korea (October 25) and then act in Sanya (November 1) and Tokyo (November 8).
The World “Circus Maximus” “tour”, which began in October 2023 in the United States, promotes its fourth studio album, “Utopia”, and is the top -box tour of ever -rappers, alongside Drake and Kendrick Lamar. Like the remaining albums of his repertoire, "Utopia" was well received by critics and fans and accumulated more than six billion streams on Spotify, highlighting the themes "Fe! N" and "I Know?".
Jacques Berman Webster II, better known by the stage name Travis Scott, is 34 years old and was born in Houston. He began his career at 17 as a music producer, focusing on hip hop production.
In 2012, Scott, who is also a composer, signed his first major contract with producer Epic Records, which followed in November of the same year, the connection to Kanye West producer, "Good Music" as part of his collaboration on the album "Cruel Summer."
His first full debut project was a “Mixtape” entitled “Owl Pharaoh”, released in 2013. He then starred in the second “Mixtape”, “Days Before Rodeo” in August 2014. His first studio album, “Rodeo”, was released only in September 2015 and the hit “Antidote” reached great success in the United States, figuring on top 20 from Billboard Hot 100.
The second album, "Birds in the Trap Sing McKnight", was released in September 2016, and the following year produced a album in collaboration with Quavo, entitled "Huncho Jack, Jack Huncho", signed by both with the name of the new duet, Huncho Jack. The third album of the "rapper" that debuts in Macao in late October was "Astroworld" in August 2018.
Travis Scott's concert is the second of an international artist at the outdoor shows after the presentation of DJ Alan Walker last June.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-08-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Art and aesthetics in focus in a lecture by Xu Bing</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/arte-estetica-em-foco-numa-palestra-de-xu-bing/</link><description>Xu Bing, Chinese contemporary artist will make a “lecture on aesthetics”, focusing on the theme “The Era without Coordinates has arrived!”. The session is integrated into the “Cultural Promotion Month” and will take place on September 7th at the Cultural Center. The Professor of the Central Academy of Fine Arts of Beijing will share the evolution of his thinking in recent years
 
Reflecting and judging in conjunction with the public of Macao the evolution of contemporary artist Xu Bing is the proposal of the Cultural Institute (IC) for one of the main events integrated into the activity “Month of Cultural Promotion”. The “Lecture on Aesthetics” will have as its central theme “The Era without Coordinates has arrived!”, Scheduled for 3 pm on September 7, in the conference room of the Cultural Center.
The Chinese teacher, currently teaching at the Central Academy of Beauja Belas (Cafa), is dedicated to widening the limits of art with his works, and is widely recognized as one of the main conceptual artists in the areas of linguistics and semiotic of today.
At the session, and in addition to talking about the evolution of his thinking, Xu Bing will focus on “exploring the limits and possibilities of art in the light of new technologies, through his animation in Stop Motion Satellite Lake, the first in the world filmed in space,” according to a text from the IC. The above work is exhibited at this year's International Art Biennial of Art.
In 1999, the artist received MacArthur Fellowship, the largest creative talent prize in the United States, in 2004 was distinguished with the Mundi Artes award, and in 2018 won the Xu Bei Hong award - Cafa Artistic Creation. His works have been exposed in various artistic institutions, including China's National Art Museums, New York Modern Art, Solomon R. Guggenheim, as well as multiple collections.
The lecture will be conducted in Mandarin, with simultaneous translation for Portuguese and English, being suitable for participants aged 15 years or over, with no places marked. Interested parties can apply through the “Activities Registration” option of the Single Account, until September 1st.
If the number of registrations exceeds the vacancies, admission will be made by lot. Admitted candidates will be notified by message and may enter the place with the message and the original identification document corresponding to the registration. The public who cannot participate in the place has the possibility to watch the transmission live through links from the Facebook page “IC Art” and official IC Wechat accounts: “Icmacao” and “IC_Art_Macao”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-08-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Maternity License Grant includes birthday births and involuntary abortions</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/subsidio-de-licenca-de-maternidade-inclui-partos-de-nados-mortos-abortos-involuntarios/</link><description>The complementary subsidy plan attributed to employers for the remuneration paid in the maternity leave began to cover cases of disgust and involuntary abortions, in pregnancies of more than three months and occurred between May 26, 2023 and December 31, 2026, according to the administrative regulation published in an official bulletin. It is recalled that the government has decided to extend the period of request for the salary payment grant in the maternity leave for another year, by the end of 2026. Employers, who fulfill the requirements and have paid salary to resident workers who had delivery within that period, may require, with the services for labor affairs (DSAL), a maximum support for 14 days of employee, second-time compensation explained the spokesman for the Executive Council and Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong. Chan Un Tong, director of Dsal, said the allowance is mainly intended for companies with less than 100 workers and indicated that a study was commissioned on the possibility of increasing maternity leave. According to 2024 UN data, Macau led the classification of countries and regions of the world with fertilities “ultrabalas”, with a rate of only 0.68 nados undead per woman.</description><pubDate>2025-08-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Launched 40th edition of “The Books and the City”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lancada-40a-edicao-de-os-livros-cidade/</link><description>The 40th edition of “The Books and the City”, published by the Public Library of the Cultural Institute (IC), is already available to the public. Dedicated to the theme “Macao Cultural”, this edition proposes to guide readers through books throughout an in-depth exploitation of World Heritage and Intangible Cultural Heritage of Macao, “unraveling the singular cultural DNA through the perspectives of experts, the revelation of secrets of world heritage and information about artistic and cultural events,” says the CI in a statement. The “Library Manual” section makes a retrospective on the moments of the “joint reading month throughout the city of Macau 2025” and presents an interview with participants who joined the activity “exchange one book to another”. Already in the section “Speaks the Author”, readers will enter the creative world of the Interactive Games Book “Small Explorers - A Place of Discoveries” and follow the guidelines for walking the streets and alleys of Macao and discovering a profusion of city stories, 2 lining the skin of small explorers. ” Chinese, Portuguese and English, presenting books from China, Japan, South Korea and Macau, and making known the cultural essence of the “East Asia City.” 3,000 copies are available.</description><pubDate>2025-08-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>30% of administrative staff has already been harmed in labor rights</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/30-pessoal-administrativo-ja-foi-prejudicado-nos-direitos-laborais/</link><description>An inquiry promoted by the Federation of Workers' Associations (Faom), in conjunction with the General Association of Macao Administrative Personnel, concluded that 30% of the 1,510 office workers had already suffered damage to their work rights, and 83% showed ignorance about MSAR work laws. In addition, the results report that almost a quarter considers that the salary level does not correspond to the amount of work they are taking, while 19% of the workers heard are dissatisfied with the current benefit regime. From a future perspective, 27% of administrative staff said he was optimistic. However, more than 405 said they feel stressed due to tight working hours, large amounts of work and lack of career ascension opportunities. The questionnaire also points out that 43% said that physical and mental health has already been impacted from pressure at work, noting that only 18% of companies provide psychological support to workers. As a suggestion, associations expect the government to create an inspection mechanism that also evaluates companies 'performance in protecting workers' mental health, in order to classify the situation and compliance with social responsibilities. Associations also ask the executive to clarify TNR's dismissal measures in the financial sector, considering that, according to government data provided by the end of June, there were 900 TNR to perform duties in this sector, of which more than 50% were unskilled employees. On the other hand, they propose a training mechanism that allows later career rise.</description><pubDate>2025-08-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Korea bets on culture in search of impulse for growth</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/coreia-aposta-na-cultura-em-busca-de-impulso-para-crescimento/</link><description>South Korean entertainment companies, which “surf” in the Korean wave, or Hallyu, are striving to widen global range, while Asia's fourth largest economy is betting on cultural exports at a time of growing protection barriers to traditional manufacturers.
Although it is growing rapidly from a low base, thanks to the substantial support of the government and the high visibility in the world landscape with some recent successes, the sector's contribution to the economy is still just a fraction of the transforming industry.
The Samsung and Hyundai Industry Giants House is delighting in the success of Boys Band BTS, the winning movie of a Oscar, “Parasite”, from the “Round 6” series “The Vegetarian”, whose author Han Kang won the Nobel Prize for Literature in 2024, and, more recently, the musical Maybe Happy Ending.
India, Latin America and the Middle East, in particular, are new promising markets for Korean cultural products that have been revealed global hits, said executives from major producers in interviews with Reuters.
“The Latin American region, recognized as the cradle of Latin music, is a key focus area,” said Jason Jaesang Lee, executive director of the K-Pop Hybe agency, who manages the BTS, featured his return planned for next spring.
The agency is also holding auditions in Latin America to release another boys Band, after the US -based Katseye group debut last year, whose six members come from four countries.
"It's time to re -examine Hallyu's definition," Lee said. "If the content is created abroad, but produced by a Korean company, or even by a foreign entity with Korean capital, I believe it should still be considered part of Hallyu."
Still, cultural exports are unlikely to replace the traditional transforming industry in the near future.
South Korea Intellectual Property Exports (PI), from music and movies to games, more than tripled over the past decade, reaching $ 9.85 billion by 2024, but representing only a fraction of goods exports, which increased by 13%, reaching $ 696.2 billion, according to Central Bank data.
Another company that is expanding the global business this year is CJ ENM, producer of “parasite”, which began to provide K-Damas for the Middle East and North Africa through a partnership with a regional streaming platform in June.
In the case of the Middle East, “we see this market as a promising long term, because Hallyu's popularity is high among the youngest generation,” said Sean Cho, executive vice president of the global business division.
In the main markets in Japan, Southeast Asia and the United States, the company is widening partnerships, more recently with Amazon Prime Video, to offer joint productions that combine Korean elements with local culture, Cho added.
For the game industry, a source of income that represents more than half of South Korea's intellectual exports and is famous for Krafton's award-winning PUBG: Battlegrounds, India promises to be the next growing market, although it represents only a tenth of the South Korean market.
"The India Game Market is still early in comparison with other advanced countries," said Sean Hyunil Sohn, executive director of Game Editor Kraftton India, which plans to explore growth potential, adding new genres and types of games.
President Lee Jae Myung has promised support and investment to make South Korea in a “great cultural power,” with the aim of expanding the market to 300 billion wons in value and exports to 50 billion wons by 2030.
"But we can't leave it in the hands of individual companies," he said in a recent talk show. "The government will play the role of establishing a solid foundation, and it begins now."
Big Five refer to music categories, dramas, webtoons, beauty and food products, which are key elements in President Lee's efforts to reposition South Korea as a cultural power.
For long -term success, sector experts and even the Central Bank have appealed to legislative structures to help national companies compete with global giants such as Netflix.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-08-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>