<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Government requires 183 days in the MSAR for pecuniary reimbursement</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-exige-183-dias-na-raem-para-comparticipacao-pecuniaria/</link><description>The residents of Macao who are living abroad will have to stay 183 days in the MSAR to benefit from the monetary reimbursement. However, there are several exceptions, such as being a student abroad or living inside China. As it enters into force today and corresponds to the situation in 2024, it will certainly affect large hundreds of Portuguese living abroad. The distribution of checks starts on July 15. André Cheong, Secretary for Administration and Justice and spokesman for the Executive Council, said that the amount that the government will spare the public purse, will serve to “various social supports, essentially aiming at the most vulnerable layers of the population”. Funds can also be used to “adjust pensions for the elderly” in the future
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Executive Board concluded the discussion about the project of Administrative Regulation on the “pecuniary reimbursement plan in economic development for the year 2025” and the changes introduced point to the requirement that residents are required to spend 183 days in the territory so that they can be beneficiaries of the check.
The new regime is similar to what is in force since 2017, to the non -compulsory central pension system, in which the government distributes a 7,000 patacas money to the residents, transferring the amount annually to the account of each of the beneficiaries.
From today, those who do not meet the requirements will not be covered by the pecuniary reimbursement, which has been applied, without interruption, since 2008.
Pursuant to the provisions of the Administrative Regulation, residents cumulatively gathering identity and permanence requirements in Macau may receive cash reimbursement, and each permanent resident will be assigned 10,000 patacas and each non -permanent resident 6,000 patacas.
According to the document released yesterday at a press conference of the Executive Council, chaired by André Cheong, spokesman for the agency and secretary for Administration and Justice, the identity requirements refer to the possession of the valid or renewable resident identity ticket on December 31, 2024, which is equal to the previous regime. The remaining requirements in Macao refer to the permanence in Macao at least 183 days throughout 2024, which constitutes a new condition established in the administrative regulation.
Despite having established new conditions of permanence in the territory, “to pay special attention to certain groups of persons”, the regulation provides that the three types of individuals who do not meet the 183 -day stay requirements in Macau are exempt from verifying this period in Macau, if they have not completed 22 years of age in 2024 and any of their parents are qualified to receive pecuniary reimbursement, and if on December 31, 2024, they are receiving the pension of or the disability allowance.
On the other hand, having as reference the provisions on extraordinary budget balance (non -compulsory central pension regime), it is indicated that those who are absent from Macao due to any of the eight reasons stipulated by the administrative regulation project are considered to have remained in the MSAR. One is the course of higher education, recognized on site, that is, students who are in foreign schools or universities will have to present enrollment test documentation.
Hospital hospitalization is another of the exceptions, as are cases of residents who have a domicile inside China as long as they have been 65 years of age or, being that age, health reasons justify it.
The provision of work outside Macao to an employer enrolled in the Social Security Fund is also one of the reasons for requesting the exemption of permanence of 183 days, as well as the provision of work outside the territory, when responsible for the subsistence of members of their household, who have a domicile in Macao, and the exercise of official functions.
Also included in the exceptions are the domicile in the in -depth cooperation zone, work on site or higher education course, recognized at the site, and work in the cities of the interior of China integrated in the Great Bay.
 
Distribution starts on July 15
To help interested parties to know the new plan determinations, the government will activate an open line of information (telephone: 28225000) and install 32 service counters in the five service centers spread across different areas of the city. On the other hand, since yesterday, residents can now access the single account or electronic page of the pecuniary reimbursement plan in economic development.
Individuals who meet the requirements will automatically receive the amount, according to the established calendar, through bank transfer or check, not requiring to submit the order.
According to the date of reception by automatic transfer or date of reception in Macao of the letter with the check, July 15 is the day intended for beneficiaries of the subsidy for the elderly, retired employees who receive retirement pension and beneficiaries of the survival pension. The next day, it will be the time of the reimbursement to reach people with pension and disability allowance, individuals who have registered the reception of the return of taxes or other payments to the direction of finance services by bank transfer.
On June 17, the recipients are those who enjoy economic support from the Institute of Social Action, while 18 checks go to teaching staff that has direct allowance or professional development allowance, and students who receive scholarships for higher education from the Educational Fund.
In the calendar for weeks, the first, from July 22 to 25, will cover individuals born until 1997, and the second, July 28 and 1 August, will be destined to residents who were born between 1978 and 2007. The distribution of checks ends in August to public administration workers who did not register the reception of tax return or other payments to DSF by bank transfer. Between the 4th and 8th checks are destined for those born between 2008 and 2017 and from 11 to 13 those born between 2018 and 2024.
 
Channeled funds for “various social supports”
At the end of the press conference held at the end of the morning at the government headquarters, and in the period of questions and answers, André Cheong said he had no estimate of how many people will no longer be beneficiaries of the monetary reimbursement, or how many are eligible to receive it immediately, remembering that last year were issued 735,000 checks, 162,000 of which sent abroad.
Asked where the amount collected with this new measure of 183 days will be channeled, the secretary stated that the funds will be intended for “various social supports, essentially aiming at the most vulnerable layers of the population”, adding that they could even “adjust the pensions for the elderly”. The government “will be able to save money from the public purse,” he emphasized.
Confronted with an issue about whether there is a certain discrimination, because there is a check to those who reside in the interior of China, to the detriment of those living in Hong Kong or abroad, the spokesman for the Executive Council denied. "It is not a matter of discrimination, but a political measure," he said, recognizing that the changes now introduced "will create impact and raise many doubts."
Regarding the decision to include, on the exemptions, residents living on the continent, the Secretary for Administration and Justice considered that "an incentive to the elderly to have the possibility of enjoying their reform within China."
André Cheong was flanked by Chan Pou Wan and Chong Seng Sam, respectively Substitute President of the Board of Directors of the Social Security Fund and the Subdirect of Finance Services.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau promises “more open” stance in Sino-Lusophone synergies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-promete-postura-mais-aberta-nas-sinergias-sino-lusofonas/</link><description>The MSar Embitiates converted to a “center of ideas” that brings together “wisdom and consensus”, and with an “even more open stance” to reinforce sino-illly-illly ties in various domains, stressed the secretary for social affairs and culture in a forum and reflection groups between China and Portuguese-speaking countries. At the event, the Commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of China in Macau argued that the Chinese political system can serve as a reference for the development of Lusophone countries

The University of Macau welcomed the “Think Tanks Forum between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”, an initiative that “covers extraordinary meaning” by providing a “new high -level platform for exchanges” between reflection groups, stressed the secretary for social affairs and culture in the opening speech of the event. According to LAM, this Forum, which has gathered Lusophone experts and academics from the interior of China and Macao, aims to “illustrate the concept of building a community of common destination of humanity, sharing with Portuguese -speaking countries the path of Chinese modernization”.
"At the same time, we also hope, using Macau as a link, conducting a debate with all experts on how to achieve a complementarity of mutual advantages and benefits, based on respect for the development trajectories of each country, as well as how to face the challenges of global development, using cooperation and innovation," he said.
Recalling that during his visit to the territory last year, President XI Jinping demanded that Macau becomes “a relevant connection of the country's high level for opening abroad” and “an important gateway to exchange and mutual understanding between Chinese and Western civilizations”, the secretary for social affairs and culture has ensured that the government is aware of the “significant responsibility” of this mission.
“We are willing to adopt an even more open stance to deepen the interaction between China and Portuguese -speaking countries in the domains of trade and investment, academic investigation, cooperation between" Think Tanks "and cultural exchanges, turning Macao into a" center of ideas "that congregates wisdom and consensus, in order to better fulfill the spirit of" two implementations "," he said.
LAM also considered that "as a witness, participant and beneficiary of Chinese modernization, Macau has the responsibility to spread the world of Macao and the history of China." "In 26 years since its return to the country, the significant achievements of Macao have not only witness their own development, but also highlight the robustness of the" country, two systems "principle, serving as a vivid example of the rich practice of Chinese modernization," he said.
 
The “wisdom” of the Chinese political system
In turn, the Commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of China in Macau argued that the Chinese political system can serve as a reference for the development of Portuguese -speaking countries. "Modernization with Chinese characteristics" is not only "the only right way" for the country, as "also provides wisdom for the modernization of humanity," he said at the Think Tanks forum.
Liu Xianfa stressed that "the Chinese people overcame numerous obstacles and challenges in the way of modernization with Chinese characteristics." China's political system “offers a strong institutional guarantee for modernization because it has many advantages,” said the diplomat.
"We are like a chess game, all with their efforts" to contribute to Chinese development, the commissioner explained, convinced that China and Lusophone countries can "learn from each other," namely using Macao as a platform.
For the Commissioner, since the transition from administration from Portugal to China in 1999, “Macao inaugurated the best development period in its history”.
At the same event, the director of the Institute of Industrial Economics of the Chinese Academy of Social Sciences admitted that the Chinese political system “has disadvantages or difficulties”. "We must not forget the harmful effects caused to nature" by China's rapid development in recent decades, "said Shi Dan, quoted by the Lusa agency, adding that" if we cannot solve pollution problems, we will never be a developed country. "
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Simplified Taxis Contest Procedures</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/simplificados-procedimentos-de-concurso-para-taxis/</link><description>Taxi licensing competition procedures will be simplified, and the Executive Board has already given green light to the project to change the administrative regulation. The idea, according to the spokesman, is to "optimize" the process. André Cheong said that, for now, there is no date for the launch of a new contest, nor information about the number of licenses to be made available. The discussion about the requirements, inspections and time of use of taxis was also completed
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The government aims to simplify the procedures of competitions for taxis, and the Executive Board has already completed the discussion of the project to change the administrative regulation on the procedures of public tenders for the assignment of licenses for the transportation of passengers in light rental cars. The idea is to “better optimize the procedures of public tenders for licensing,” said André Cheong, spokesman for the Executive Board.
According to the information, the regulation "simplified" the procedures, "reduced formal requirements and rationally separated the phase of assessment of the competitor's qualification documents and the proposals." All this in order to “raise the efficiency of sessions of the public act of the contest and admit more proposals, in order to better ensure the public interest”.
André Cheong, also secretary for Administration and Justice, explained that the regulation will extend the period of validity of proposals “according to real needs”, also requiring the award to “reinforcement of the security after the notification of award, to ensure compliance with obligations”. In case of expiration of the adjudication, the government will proceed to the adjudication “to the immediately following competitor, according to the order of classification, whose proposal is still within the validity period”.
Asked if there is already a calendar to launch a new taxi licensing contest and how many licenses will be put to contest, André Cheong said there is no information to move forward.
In the same context, it was also given green light to the project to change the administrative regulation on the requirements, inspections and time of use of light rental cars. The goal is to simplify and clarify the criteria and procedures of appreciation and approval, with a view to implementing the general planning of traffic and land transport of Macau (2021-2030), improving the quality of taxi service and meeting the needs of social development, said the spokesman.
First of all, “to encourage the renewal of vehicle fleets by the sector and improve the quality of service”, the regulation simplifies the taxis replacement requirements, and only requires authorization from the direction of services to traffic affairs. Thus, it will not be necessary to subject yourself to the requirement to “finally disapprove of inspection,” said André Cheong during the press conference.
Given that taxis are high mileage vehicles and have a degree of “relatively high” wear, and considering the “security of public transport”, the regulation clarifies that, “in the case of replacement of taxis that have been used for more than five years, the cancellation of its enrollment is necessary”. However, taxis that has been used for a period of less than five years may be altered for private use.
On the other hand, the regulation eliminates provisions on the propulsion engine and the taxis engine system. And since legally authorized vehicles to be imported have all engine systems whose functions adapt to the Macao road environment, the regulation eliminates the requirement that they are equipped with a cylinder cylinder equal to or greater than 1,500 cubic centimeters.
Also the requirement for the dimension of the luggage will be lowered, stipulating that it should allow at least two bags, each with the sum of the length, width and height of 158 centimeters.
Both regulations come into force the day after their publication.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Registered toxicode dependents increased 24% by 2024</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/toxicodependentes-registados-aumentaram-24-em-2024/</link><description>The total number of toxicode dependents included in the central registration system rose nearly a quarter to 148 between 2023 and 2024, including seven ages under 21 years. The most consumed drug was methamphetamine, followed by cannabis
 
The “Central Registration System of Macao Toxicode Pedestines” encompassed 148 people in 2024, which means a 24.4% increase over the previous year, the Institute of Social Action (IAS) said yesterday. Of this number, seven were young people under 21 years, representing 4.7% of the total.
Methamphetamine (Ice) is at the top of the drugs consumed, corresponding to 26.3% of the total, followed by cannabis, with a percentage of 11.1. With regard to consumer places, more than 80% of toxicode dependents have consumed drugs in Macau and more than 70% in “relatively hidden places, or their own or friends and hotels”.
The statistics were released during the 1st Plenary Session of 2025 of the Drug Fighting Commission (CLD), chaired by Hon Wai, vice president of the IAS agency and president.
The order of work included, among other issues, the balance of actions developed in 2024 and the presentation of the plan for 2025, the general situation of drug -related crime in Macao and data analysis of the “central registration system of toxicode dependents”. In addition, the meeting served to present the situation of the working groups to “monitor the problems of young drugs” and the “execution and monitoring of the Drug Fighting Law”.
The members also led to the resolutions of the 68th session of the United Nations (UN) and the respective coordination work.
Five young people were invited to attend the plenary session, with the aim of “strengthening the positive interaction between young people and the government and better auscultation of the opinions of this group,” according to IAS.
The work of revision and optimization of the “Central Registration System of Macao Toxicode Pedestines”, commissioned by IAS with a third entity, was completed in December 2024. In the future, according to the body, “at different levels, the actions of optimization will be developed, namely those that focus on the content of the questionnaire, participation system, collaboration of the periodic service units and the periodic realization of theme studies”.
In the analysis of previous meetings, the “Working Group to Monitor the Young Drug Problem” is aware of the promotional strategies of new drugs in Macao, having promoted “the participation of young people in national and international issues on the combat of drugs”, proposed to “continuous updating of data collection and collaboration mechanisms” of the central registration system of the toxicode dependents of Macau, and suggested the “reinforcement of the reinforcement of the reinforcement exchange and cooperation between private institutions and the cities of the great bay ”.
In turn, the “working group for the execution and monitoring of the Drug Fighting Law” paid attention to “vocational education and training for different groups of young people in the process of detoxification”, and suggested “reinforced communication and a greater articulation of detox services with the cities of the large bay”, as well as the continuous awareness of citizens for national anti -drug work.
In parallel, given that “society has been concerned about the harm caused to young people for the use of new drugs in electronic cigarettes”, this working group has invited health services to organize thematic sessions in order to profoundly address the change in smoking control law. Opinions, after organized and analyzed by the CLD, will be sent to the competent services as references to the amendment of the law.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing “rocks” US plan against Chinese students</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/pequim-arrasa-plano-dos-eua-contra-os-alunos-chineses/</link><description>Beijing reacted yesterday with indignation to the promise of the US government to revoke the visas of Chinese students, classifying the US offensive against foreign students such as "politics and discriminatory." On Wednesday, US Secretary of State, Marco Rubio, announced that the US will begin to “aggressively” the visas of Chinese students, including those who have connections to the Communist Party or study in critical areas.
Washington will also review visa criteria to reinforce controls on all future requests from China and Hong Kong, Marco Rubio said.
China's Ministry of Foreign Ministry spokesman, Mao Ning, considered that "the US has irrationally revoked the visas of Chinese students under the pretext of ideology and [protection of] national rights." "This political and discriminatory practice of the US has exposed the lies of the supposed freedom and openness that the US has always promoted, and has further damaged its own international image, national image and credibility," he added at a press conference.
Rubio intensified the measures against foreign students after China has already criticized his decision to temporarily suspend the processing of students from around the world. Before these measures, the Trump government had already tried to eliminate permission to all foreign students at Harvard University, which rejects the president's pressure.
Chinese students, who pay tens of thousands of dollars in enrollment, constitute one of the most important sources of revenue for US universities. More than 277,300 Chinese students were enrolled in the 2023-24 academic year, occupying second place, behind only the Indians, according to a report by the Institute of International Education supported by the State Department.
In his first term, Trump also aimed at the Chinese students, but focused on those who embraced careers considered sensitive or with army ties.
Marco Rubio has been widely criticized for revoking thousands of visas, most of foreign students who participated in protests against Israel. According to an internal memorandum signed on Tuesday by the head of American diplomacy, to which the AFP agency had access, the government intends to examine profiles on social networks of foreigners who want to study at American universities.
In the document, Rubio orders embassies and consulates that they do not allow "no student visa or exchange" until new guidelines are issued. "
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Secretary admits “challenges” in the context of high technology</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/secretario-admite-desafios-ambito-da-alta-tecnologia/</link><description>Under the science and technology development ceremony, Secretary Tai Kin IP admitted that high-tech development is still full of “challenges”, but it was confident that “progressive availability of political benefits”, these obstacles can be outdated
 
The Secretary for Economics and Finance stressed that "scientific and technological innovation is an indispensable way for the development of Macao," however, admitted that the development of high -tech industries is still "full of challenges". Tai Kin IP was spoken at the ceremony of Awards for the Development of Science and Technology of MSAR - 2024, reiterating that the government "will continually double the investment in scientific research."
This investment, he recalled, will materialize in the creation of a government fund for industries and a guidance fund for the transformation of scientific and technological results; in the planning and study of the construction of the Industrial Park for Research and Development of Sciences and Technologies; In the expansion of international cooperation in science and technology; and in the deepening of the “I&amp;D in Macau + Transformation into Hengqin” model.
"With the progressive availability of political benefits and the intensification of integrated development at the regional level, I am convinced that we will be able to overcome the restrictions and embrace an increasingly vast development horizon full of unlimited possibilities," he said during his speech.
Tai Kin IP stressed that the projects distinguished in this edition stand out “for their excellence”. Two projects that won the first prize "demonstrate a high degree of innovation and applicability," he added.
"The fundamental advances achieved in the development of new drugs derived from TRNA of traditional Chinese drugs and nanostructured cement materials significantly raise the technological level of their sectors and ensure their effective transformation and application," he said. The ruler stressed that these projects, "with vast prospects of use, will inject a new impetus to the development of the proper diversification of Macao's economy."
The ceremony in question aimed to recognize the contribution of the 83 workers of the scientific and technological sector to the development and innovation of technologies in the MSAR and, on the other hand, to allow the society to witness the abundant fruits achieved by the local scientific community.
The masters distinguished 22 projects with science and technology premiums, including the teams represented by the Deputy Rector of the University of Science and Technology of Macau, Jiang Zhihong, and the associate professor at Macao University, Sun Guoxing, received 1st place prizes. Thirty students received the scientific research and technological development prizes for postgraduates.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hospitality and Restoration have two thousand work vacancies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/hotelaria-restauracao-tem-duas-mil-vagas-laborais/</link><description>At the end of March, hotel and restoration sectors had about 84,000 full -time workers and had almost two thousand vacancies to fill. Average remuneration fell 1.9% in hotels and 0.7% in restaurants in the annual variation
 
Hospitality and restoration sectors jointly employed 83,863 full -time workers and available 1,963 vacancies at the end of the first quarter of this year, according to data revealed by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC).
In concrete, hotel establishments had 60,482 full -time workers (4,068 or 7.2% than in the first quarter of 2024) and had 839 job openings (less 616 or 42.3%). The mandarin dominance was required in 86.1% of these vacancies, given that the interior of China is the main market of visitors in Macao, and 63.6% required professional experience.
According to DSEC, hotel vacancies were mainly intended for staff of services and salespeople (275), unqualified workers (207) and administrative employees (186), representing 32.8%, 24.7% and 22.2% of the total.
Vacancy rates (1.4%), recruitment (3.8%) and workers' turnover (3.0%) retreated 1.1, 1.6 and 0.3 percentage points, respectively, in annual terms, showing that “the demand for labor gradually stabilized again,” according to DSEC.
The average remuneration (excluding irregular remuneration) of full -time workers from hotels decreased by 1.9% to 20,090 patacas, compared to the end of March 2024.
In turn, restaurants and similar establishments absorbed 23,381 workers at full time (less 624 or 2.6% in annual variation) and had 1,124 vacancies (less 401 or 26.3%), 86.6% of which only required the lower academic level or equivalent to overall secondary education and 70.6% implied mandarin domain.
In the field of restoration, vacancy rates (4.6%), recruitment (3.3%) and workers turnover (4.8%) descended 1.4, 1.9 and 0.6 percentage points, respectively, within one year. The average remuneration also fell 0.7% to 10,540 patacas.
Official statistics also include 303 vacancies in the transformative industries (less 229 than in the first quarter of last year), 38 in the elderly services (11 more), 13 in the production and distribution of electricity, gas and water (minus six) and 14 in day care centers (four).</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>An “guest” to train Guinean teachers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/um-convidada-formar-professores-guineenses/</link><description>The Rector of Amílcar Cabral University (UAC) said yesterday that the institution of Guinea-Bissau wants the help of the University of Macau (one) to have more teachers with a master's or doctorate. UAC has the ambition of, by 2030, to have at least 50% of teachers with a master's degree and 30% with a doctorate, Herculano Arlindo Mendes said.
"How are we going to do this if, even in Guinea-Bissau, we still don't have the master's or doctoral programs yet?" questioned the rector. "It is through partnership with our partners, that we can do this ambition," explained Arlindo Mendes, on the fringes of the "Think Tanks Forum between China and Portuguese -speaking countries", taking place until Saturday at UM.
“We are here available to explore the possibilities of partnerships that may arise,” said Arlindo Mendes, indicating that there were already ongoing negotiations with one and showing hope of signing a partnership agreement with the Macao institution during the Forum.
In addition to the training of teachers and the joint realization of international conferences and academic and scientific research projects, the University of Guinea-Bissau also aims to send students to one.
"We will try to request the support of the University of Macau, that is, through cooperation between China and Guinea-Bissau, so that we can have a significant number of scholarships," said Arlindo Mendes. This is because, admitted the rector, "from a financial point of view, the country, Guinea-Bissau, and the university in particular has a lot of difficulty in this regard."
Arlindo Mendes spoke in the forum about "the processes of modernization of Guinea-Bissau, the perspectives and the current challenges." "We also believe that we will learn from the experience of other countries that are present here," added the rector.
 
Learn from China Industrial Policies
The rector of Joaquim Chissano University (UJC) said that the institution of Mozambique will sign a partnership with the University of Technology of Southern China to train teachers in industrial policies. João Gabriel de Barros indicated that the agreement with the Chinese University Institute of Public Policy resulted from a visit to the Campus in Canton.
"It is different from what we have taught in public policy courses. They are industrial public policies, which aim for industrialization, (…) that even aim at the development in a concrete and direct way," explained the rector.
João Gabriel de Barros has lamented that in African countries, including in Mozambique, universities still “go too late” in areas with artificial intelligence and “others that are future formations”. “This all creates positive and necessary pressure. We have to learn and adapt all this to our contexts and not always go to the towing what globalization brings,” he said.
Barros explained that the partnership with the Institute of Public Policy will predict the sending of UJC teachers to receive training in industrial policies. “We will have to have our teachers there to be formed there, because the vision is totally different,” said the rector, who also came to participate in the Reflection Groups Forum between China and Portuguese -speaking countries.
The leader said that UJC will sign another memorandum of understanding with one, which extends the existing cooperation in teacher education and the exchange of teachers and students.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>AI Laboratory on Nutrition Junta UPM and Coimbra</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/laboratorio-de-ia-sobre-nutricao-junta-upm-coimbra/</link><description>Macao Polytechnic University (UPM) has announced the creation of a joint laboratory with the University of Coimbra that will use Artificial Intelligence (AI) to study the connection between nutrition and “healthy longevity”.
In a statement, the UPM said the laboratory dedicated to the nutraceutical will focus on applying AI in “health care, precision nutrition, chronic diseases prevention and health management”.
The nutraceutical is a combination of nutrition and pharmaceutical and studies the potential positive effects for the health of components present in food.
The new laboratory will “make the most of the advantages of the two universities in the areas of Artificial Intelligence, Health Sciences and Nutrition Technology,” said the UPM.
The agreement provides for interdisciplinary investigation with specialists from both universities to transform results into “state -of -the -art technical solutions” and “innovative applications”, he stresses in the statement.
UPM also assured that the laboratory will “form high -level talents for the Macao health industry [and] promote technology development through industry cooperation”.
The area of ​​health and well-being was pointed out as one of the four sectors in which the Macao government wants to bet to diversify the local economy, highly dependent on casinos and tourism.
On the other hand, the UPM stressed that the creation of the laboratory represents “a new milestone in educational cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”. The new institution will promote “scientific research and innovation in the area of ​​intelligent health in Macau and Portugal and support scientific and technological cooperation between China and Portugal,” he said.
The agreement for the creation of the laboratory was signed in Macao by UPM rectors, Marcus im Sio Kei, and the University of Coimbra, Amílcar Falcão.
In June 2024, Falcão told Lusa on a visit to Macau that the Portuguese institution and UPM had launched a double doctorate in information technologies. The PhD was born in the previous school year and "is starting to give the first results", with 18 students, "divided between Portuguese and Chinese," said the rector of the University of Coimbra.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Piano duet and cello at the Military Club</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dueto-de-piano-violoncelo-clube-militar/</link><description>The Military Club today receives the concert “The Great Romantics”, with the participation of pianist Clarence Lam and cellist Winca Chan
 
This Friday, the Military Club welcomes "The Great Romantics" for another night of the musical journeys, at Stanley Ho Salon. From 19:00, pianist Clarence Lam will play Franz Schubert's “Sonata in G, D 894” and, with the participation of Winca Chan on cello, “Sonata in G Minor for Piano and Cello, Op. 65 by Frédéric Chopin.
In addition to a musician, Clarence Lam is also an educator and examiner. Member of the Junior School of the Hong Kong Performative Arts Academy, the pianist has traveled masterclasses in renowned institutions such as “Eton College”, “Oundle School” and “Wells Cathedral School”.
According to the Military Club, his career as a concert career led him to give "captivating recitals" through Asia and Europe, having played with renowned orchestras such as "Athenean Ensemble", "RNCM Symphony Orchestra" and the "Rachmaninov Institute Symphony Orchestra". Clarence studied with Eleanor Wong at Hong Kong Academy for Performing Arts and was guided by reputable pianists like Gary Graffman, John Lill, Michel Béroff, Nelson Goerner, Pascal Deveoyon, Pascal Rogé and Stephen Hugh.
Winca Chan, on the other hand, graduated from the Vancouver Academy of Music, where he studied with Judy Fraser and received the Hong Kong, the cloonist, concluded his bachelor's degree in Otava and a master's degree in music at "Royal Northern College of Music." Throughout his career, Winca Chan raised several awards, such as the third prize in the Victoria Conservatory Concert Contest and first place in the provincial finals of the Kiwanis music festival.
Collaborated with different orchestras such as Royal Liverpool Philharmonic Orchestra, "Ottawa Symphony Orchestra", "Aspen Symphony Orchestra", "Hong Kong City Chamber Orchestra" and "Hong Kong String Orchestra", and several pop artists, such as Michael Bublé and Sammi Cheng, between others. He also participated in advertisements, films and events such as the 60th anniversary of Mandarin East Hong Kong, Cartier and Pandora.
Tickets, with cocktail, cost 120 patacas or 330 patacas if they include dinner.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hotel occupation reaches almost 90%</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ocupacao-hoteleira-atinge-quase-90/</link><description>The average occupancy rate of Macao hotels and pensions rose to 89.6% between January and April, 5.1 percentage points than in the same period of 2024, the Directors and Census Services directed. This variation results from a decrease of 3.2% in the number of guests (4.78 million) and the 4.3% decrease in total rooms (about 45,000) available from 147 hotel units that provided public accommodation services (plus 4, in annual terms) at the end of April. The average period of permanence of guests remained in 1.7 nights. Still, in April, the number of guests rose 3.4% to nearly 1.2 million, in annual terms, after two months of homologous falls. Last month, according to DSEC, guests from the interior of China (861 thousand) and international (106 thousand) increased 4.5% and 12.3%, respectively, compared to the same period of 2024. The body highlights the growth in South Korea guest numbers (3.1% to 25 thousand), India (64.4% to nine thousand), Thailand (28.4% to nine. thousand) and from Japan (5% to seven thousand). In the opposite direction, Malaysian guests dropped 3.1% and 0.1%, respectively, to about eight thousand, in both cases.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2407/</link><description>Registered earthquake from 3.5 to 206 km from the MSAR
An earthquake of magnitude 3.5 was registered on the Richter scale, 206 kilometers from MSAR, at 1:17 pm yesterday. According to the Directorate of Macao Meteorological and Geophysical Services, the epicenter was located next to the Southeast China coast, 10 kilometers deep.
 
Nuclear Center of Taishan had level 0 incident
The Taishan Nuclear Center, near the MSAR, registered a level 0 operational incident on Tuesday, according to the International Nuclear Accident Scale (from 0 to 7), the Macao Unit Police Services (SPU) reported, citing a communication from the Guangdong Nuclear Emergency Management Commission Office. According to the SPU, during the occurrence, the center "maintained the safe and stable functioning, with three intact safety barriers and no radioactive substance released abroad."
 
Opened sea route between Barra and Porto outer
SHUN TAK CHINA TRAVEL-Vessel Management Company (Macau) will start operating today the first Macao Cruise Route between the outdoor port passenger terminal and Barra-Cais Bridge. Initially, a round trip will be made, about 25 minutes, with the departure of the exterior port to be held at 10:30 and the trip from Barra at 17h00.
 
Simulated gas escape in the port of Ká-hó
The Fire Department (CB) and the Macao Fuel Terminal Management Society made a simulacrum at the Port of Ká-Hó fuel terminal. The one -hour exercise simulated high pressure GPL leakage and was attended by 140 people, having succeeded “successfully,” according to the CB.
 
DSAT adjusts public transport for summer
Career N3 will have its route extended to Hac Sá Beach, from June 1 to August 31, the services of traffic matters reported. From June 14 to August 24, the 26AT Seasonal Career will be operational and, between June 9 and August 3, careers 71 and 72 will have their intervals adjusted to 15 to 20 minutes, and 701xs will be suspended.
 
Residents surveyed on travel habits
The Government of MSar will conduct an online inquiry, from June 3 to 30, under the “Study of the Macao Origin Matrix”, to know the “habits and characteristics of travel of citizens”. Participants will be able to fill the questionnaire on the site (macautovelsurvey2024.com) and will be automatically registered in a draw, indicates the direction of services to traffic affairs.
 
Viaduct works require to end Basket field
The small field of basketball of the free field under the viaduct on Avenida do Comendador Ho Yin will be closed to the public between June 4 and 27. The Directorate of Public Works Services began the maintenance works of the viaduct, and the largest field and the gabel field will not be affected.
 
TRANSPORT ADAPTED FOR RACING DAYS
In the context of provisional traffic measures at the holidays of the Dragon Boat Festival, between today and tomorrow, an area for the "shuttle" of hotels and casinos, with space for wide queues, will be reserved to separate the outlet and passenger start. Between tomorrow and Monday, the shuttle that connect the Delta Bridge border post to the outdoor port maritime terminal will provide direct transportation service and 3BX, 17T, 21at and 26AT careers will have provisional changes, announced services to traffic affairs.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>161 cases of illicit game until March</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/registados-161-casos-de-jogo-ilicito-ate-marco/</link><description>In general, crime in Macao decreased 7.3% in the first three months of this year, but, on the other hand, the game -related crimes were increased mainly by the illicit game (161 cases), illegal exchange exploration (132) and slips (152). Authorities justify the scenario with the entry into force of the illicit play crimes and the improvement of other provisions related to game crimes. Moreover, the crimes of burla, computer crime and violent crime recorded a decline
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Crime generally recorded “a decrease” in Macao in the first quarter of this year, with the situation of public security to remain “stable and favorable”, the secretary for security, Wong Sio Chak, said yesterday. Even the crimes of burla and computer sciences "have begun to record a decrease trend." On the other hand, compared to the first three months of 2024, there was an “increase in crimes related to the illicit game”, according to the balance of crime.
Between January and March, 3,289 criminal inquiries were established, representing a decrease of 260 cases and a declining of 7.3% in annual terms. It should be noted that the “crimes against the person” slightly rose to 565 cases, most of which (293) were of simple offense to physical integrity. There are also five cases of child sexual abuse, more than in the previous year, “mainly involving the practice of voluntary sexual acts between people of the same age and the diffusion of photographs and pornographic images”; In addition to 10 cases of violation, four minus.
In the context of cases of domestic violence, 26 (two more) were preliminarily recorded. However, until May 12, after investigation and confirmation, only four were actually classified as crimes of domestic violence. In addition, 12 were qualified as offense crimes to physical integrity, two such as other crimes and eight remain under investigation.
Against the heritage, 1,949 cases were registered, a break of almost 11%. Regarding the circumvents, there were 555 cases, a decrease of 15.4%, while computer crime decreased by 14% to 160 cases.
As for the game, 567 inquiries were established for crimes related to the sector, plus 216 cases or 61.5%. Authorities reported 161 illicit play cases, plus 145 or 906.3% over the same period of 2024, and justify the numbers with the entry into force of the illicit play crimes in late October, which added the crime of exploitation of illicit exchange exchange rates and the improvement of provisions related to other illegal game crimes.
Only processes related to illicit exchange exploration for game were 132, occupying more than 60% of the number of increased cases related to the game, and representing 23.3% of the total. Game -related crimes also had “high occurrences”, growing from 76 to 152 cases, equivalent to 26.8% of the total.
In the balance sheet, the secretary also said that between January and March, police detained 251 people for the practice of illegal money exchange in various police actions, 1,041 individuals and a decrease of 80.6% over last year's same period.
Under the game, cases of usury (51), theft (46), illegitimate appropriation (38), disobedience (21) were also counted. Authorities also note that "the number of tourists entering Macao has increased by 11.1% over last year's same period, which brings to the Macao Society more uncertain factors affecting security."
In general, there were 56 cases in the scope of violent crime, minus 21 cases or a break of 27.3% in annual terms. Faculture, homicide and severe body offenses "continue to keep a zero rate or a very low occurrence rate."
The secretary also announced that, from the first quarter of this year, data on crimes of "slavery" and "trafficking in persons", provided for in the Penal Code, as well as some crimes provided for in the law of terrorism prevention and repression of terrorism, are included in the statistics of violent crime, so that they are "more scientific and logical". For now, there was no records regarding these crimes.
 
Wong Sio Chak says journalists “are no exception” to the law
The Secretary for Security stressed yesterday that journalists “are no exception” to the duty to comply with the law after the arrest of two reporters in the Legislative Assembly in April. "It's not for your profession that you don't have to comply with what is in the law," said Wong Sio Chak, when asked about the incident involving the "All About Macau". "It is important, we have to comply with the law. No profession is exception," added the manager, recalling that "the police ... During the execution of the law, it is monitored by the judicial body, the prosecutor." Asked by Lusa, the office of the prosecutor, Chan Tsz King, said on Tuesday that he had no "information to disclose at this time" about the progress of the process.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Türkiye discovers and reproduces bronze age bread</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/turquia-descobre-reproduz-pao-da-idade-bronze/</link><description>In the early days of the Bronze Age, a piece of bread was buried under a newly settled house in the current Türkiye. Five millennia later, archaeologists had managed to dig it up, studied, and helped a local bakery recreate the recipe.
"This is the oldest roast bread discovered in an excavation and has largely preserved its form," said Murat Türkteki, archaeologist and director of the excavation of Küllüoba, near the city of Eskisehir in the center of Turkey.
"A bread is a rare discovery in excavations. Usually we only found crumbs. But here it was preserved because it was burned and buried," he told AFP.
Küllüoba, round and flattened bread as a host about 12 centimeters in diameter, was discovered in September 2024, charred and buried around 3,300 before Christ.
A piece was torn before the bread was burned and buried when the house was built. "This forces us to recognize that it has been a ritual of abundance," said Türkteki.
In the absence of written evidence, the mystery pointed to the Anatolian civilization of Küllüoba and its customs, such as burying the houses before moving to another place or building new housing over older structures, thus forming hills.
At the age of the bronze, the Hatianians, a people of Anatolia who preceded the Hittites, lived in the Eskisehir region.
"Küllüoba was a medium -sized urban agglomeration with commercial, handcrafted, agricultural and mining activities. It was evident the existence of a certain family and social order," explained archaeologist Deniz Sari.
Several analyzes showed that bread was made with grossly ground lentil seeds and flour, an old variety of wheat. The leaf of a plant still being determined was used as yeast.
Carbonized bread has been on display at the Eskisehir Archaeological Museum since Wednesday. "This discovery excited us a lot. While talking to our excavation director, I wondered if we could reproduce this bread," said Ayse ünlüce, mayor of Eskisehir.
To follow the original recipe as faithfully as possible, and since wheat Farro no longer exists in Turkey, the city decided, after analyzing bread, using Kavilca wheat (a similar variety), bulgur and lentils.
At Halk Ekmek's facilities (‘People's Bread’ in Turkish), a local bakery at low prices, employees make 300 küllüoba loaves every day since last week.
"The combination of ancient wheat flour, lentils and bulgur produces a rich and full -bodied bread, low with gluten and no preservatives," said Serap Güler, director of Halk Ekmek in Eskisehir.
The first Küllüoba breads, sold in packaging of 300 grams for 50 Turkish liras, sold out in a few hours. “I ran because I was afraid of nothing left. I was curious to know what the taste of this old bread was,” explains client Suzan Kuru.
“These lands have preserved this bread for 5,000 years and gave us this gift. We have a duty to protect this inheritance and transmit it,” says ünlüce.
Eskisehir province, once rich in water resources, now suffers from drought. "We are facing a climate crisis, but we still cultivate corn and sunflower, which requires a lot of water. Our ancestors have taught us a lesson. We should, like them, focus on cultures that require less water," the mayor emphasizes.
One of its objectives is to revive the cultivation of Kavilca wheat in the region, which is resistant to drought and disease. "We need very strong public policies for this issue. Cultivating ancestral wheats would be a symbolic advance in this regard," he said.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>