<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/juros-das-obrigacoes-japonesas-disparam-para-niveis-recorde/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Deputies concerned about overload on public transport after large-scale events</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/deputados-preocupados-com-sobrecarga-nos-transportes-publicos-apos-eventos-de-grande-escala/</link><description>Several deputies complained about the inability of transport to respond to the concentration of crowds following events or festivities in Macau. Making reference to residents and tourists “stranded” in Cotai on New Year's Eve, several deputies argued that the Government must have a better plan for dispersing the tourist flow through coordination of traffic and border crossings.

The overload on public transport during festivities and events is worrying Macau's deputies, leading them to ask the Government for explanations about the deficiencies in the mechanism for dispersing the flow of people.
In written statements presented by Wong Kit Cheng, Leong Pou U, Nick Lei and Che Sai Wang, concerns about safety due to the concentration of people are mentioned, including the occurrence of accidents caused by stampedes, the impact on visitors' experience, as well as the failures of public transport to respond to daily life in the territory.
The issue was addressed mainly because of the recent chaotic situation in Cotai during New Year's Eve, where a large number of tourists and residents were stranded for hours after the celebrations due to difficulty in catching public buses or taxis, or walking to the Light Rail station.
It is worth remembering that around 65 thousand people attended the New Year's Eve event in Cotai. The wave of visitors may have been due to the cancellation of fireworks shows in Hong Kong this year. A series of posts on social media warned of the “bad experience” of spending the year in Macau.
“The crowd only gradually dispersed around 3 am, and the increase in visitors overwhelmed the Hengqin border post after the New Year,” said Wong Kit Cheng. The deputy linked to the General Women's Association also criticized the ineffectiveness of the Government's contingency and traffic organization plans.

RESPONSE FAILURE
 
According to the deputies, although the Government has already defined provisional traffic measures with the extension of service hours and an increase in their frequency, there was a lack of “timely and accurate forecasting” of the flow of people by the authorities. “It should be noted that this incident not only demonstrates the difference between prediction, execution, planning and reality, but also reveals systematic deficiencies in the dispersion mechanism in large events”, pointed out Nick Lei.
The legislator who is associated with the Fujian community defended that authorities should review and optimize the dispersion mechanism in large-scale activities, installing intelligent systems for alerting and guiding the flow of people at the activity sites, also reinforcing interdepartmental collaboration in real time and data sharing during the management of major events.
Nick Lei therefore suggested that the Government take as a reference the model of the Hong Kong “Easy Leave” website to disseminate, in real time, information about the waiting time and density of the flow of people for each dispersal route.
Che Sai Wang, deputy linked to the Association of Public Service Workers of Macau (ATFPM), urged the authorities to publish plans to respond to the organization of major events in Macau. He also asked the Government to implement, as quickly as possible, unified payment and matching benefits between the Light Rail and buses, with a view to facilitating passengers.
In turn, Leong Pou U, who is part of the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau (FAOM), considers it necessary for the Government to optimize the “early warning system for predicting the flow of people”, so that its function is extended to areas where major cultural and sporting activities take place, such as the open-air entertainment area, the Cotai area and traffic congestion black spots.
Leong, furthermore, highlighted that the Government must create a mechanism for interconnecting data from the aforementioned early warning system with the services responsible for coordinating traffic, so that they can take, in a timely manner, concrete measures to adjust transport capacity and optimize routes.
On the other hand, in Wong Kit Cheng's opinion, not only the Government, but also private entities and integrated leisure tourism companies should also contribute to better organizing large-scale festive events, since many of them are nowadays carried out by these companies.
In this case, to deal with these predictable large concentrations of people that require crowd management, security and traffic flow measures, the deputy urges the competent departments to coordinate with event organizers, formulating plans that cover crowd control, evacuation routes, public transport measures and security contingencies.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 23:47:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump invites China and Israel to join ‘Peace Board’</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/trump-convida-china-e-israel-para-integrar-junta-da-paz/</link><description>US President Donald Trump invited China and Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu to join the so-called 'Peace Board', a college of world figures to resolve conflicts, an official Israeli source told the Spanish news agency EFE yesterday. The Russian, Turkish, Argentine and Paraguayan presidents, respectively Vladimir Putin, Recep Erdogan, Javier Milei, and Santiago Peña, had already confirmed the receipt of a letter from Trump to the same effect. Sources close to French President Emmanuel Macron assured that a similar invitation was refused because the American leader's proposal went beyond the situation in the Gaza Strip and raised problems “about respect for the principles and structure of the United Nations (UN), which cannot be called into question”.
The 'Peace Board', an organization created by the White House to monitor the implementation of the Peace Plan for the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, was sanctioned by the UN Security Council, but there were different opinions from the international community that it could become a competing entity to the United Nations, with the aim of defending Washington's interests. Trump intends to preside over the aforementioned board, which will have an executive committee composed of the Secretary of State (MNE) of the United States of America (USA), Marco Rubio, the special American envoy for Gaza, Steve Witkoff, the businessman and son-in-law of the US leader, Jared Kushner, the former British Prime Minister Tony Blair, the director of the investment group Apollo Global Management, Marc Rowan, Trump's advisor Roberto Gabriel and the president of the World Bank, Ajay Banga. Invitations to the Prime Minister of India, Narendra Modi, the President of Egypt, Abdel Fattah al-Sissi, the King of Jordan, Abdallá II, the Prime Minister of Canada, Mark Carney, and the Prime Minister of Pakistan, Shehbaz Sharif, who was one of the great supporters of Trump's candidacy for the Nobel Peace Prize, have also been reported.
China confirmed this Tuesday that it received an invitation from the United States to join the Gaza Peace Council promoted by US President Donald Trump, although it avoided clarifying whether it would accept the proposal or who it would address within the Chinese leadership. At the daily press conference of the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs, its spokesman Guo Jiakun limited himself yesterday to stating that “China has received an invitation from the American side”, without offering further details about the content of the proposal or the steps that Beijing may take next.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 23:39:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Book by Arnaldo Gonçalves on the Chinese rise officially launched in Lisbon</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/livro-de-arnaldo-goncalves-sobre-a-ascensao-chinesa-oficialmente-lancado-em-lisboa/</link><description>Academic Arnaldo Gonçalves presents his latest geopolitical analysis, "China. The Imperial Dream", tomorrow, January 22nd. The launch of the book, which promises an in-depth discussion about China's rise as a superpower, is scheduled for 5:30 pm at the historic Grémio Literário, in Lisbon.
The event will feature a panel of notable guests, including RTP commentator and professor at Nova School of Law, Felipe Pathé-Duarte, and Major-General João Vieira Borges, president of the Portuguese Military History Commission. Entry is free, but requires prior registration due to limited places.
In the work, Gonçalves, a former consultant to the Government of Macau and professor of Political Science, traces the trajectory of Russian foreign policy over the last four decades. The book is structured into seven chapters that examine everything from economic transformation and the move away from isolation, through complex relations with the European Union and strategic duality with the United States, to the analysis of projects such as the New Silk Road and Chinese military strengthening.
One of the central focuses of the analysis is the paradox between the official peace discourse and the territorial and maritime assertiveness observed, particularly in the South China Sea. The author states that the motivation for this study arose from the perception that there is a scarcity of analyzes about China in Portugal that are not associated with specific commercial interests, explicitly positioning themselves from the point of view of the interests of Europe and the West.
The book arrives in bookstores amid renewed attention to China's role in the global order, offering a historical perspective that contextualizes Beijing's current actions.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Taiwan wants to build democratic AI supply chain with US</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/taiwan-quer-construir-cadeia-de-abastecimento-de-ia-democratica-com-eua/</link><description>Taipei expressed its intention to build a democratic high-tech supply chain with Washington and forge a strategic alliance around the development of artificial intelligence (AI), just days after a trade deal with the US.

The understanding, announced on Thursday after several months of negotiations, includes a reduction in tariffs on Taiwanese products from 20% to 15%, as well as a commitment by Taiwanese companies to invest $250 billion in the United States. As agreed, the Taipei Government also committed to guaranteeing an additional US$250 billion in commercial loans to facilitate new investments.
At a press conference in Taipei, local government official Cheng Li-chiun emphasized that the investment agreement with the United States “does not imply an externalization of the supply chain”, but rather seeks to strengthen the island's technological sector and consolidate “industrial capacity”. “This is not a transfer of the industrial supply chain, but rather an expansion of Taiwanese industrial capacity in the United States, with a supply chain built jointly by the two countries,” said the official, in statements released by the CNA news agency. “Before, we said ‘Taiwan can help,’ but we hope that in the future we can say ‘Taiwan and the US can lead,’” added Cheng, further arguing that the rise of artificial intelligence opens up the possibility of “creating a technological supply chain for the democratic field.”
When asked about future investments by TSMC — the world leader in the manufacture of advanced AI chips — in the United States, Cheng stated that such decisions “must respect the company's planning” and highlighted that the Taiwanese Government “has always supported TSMC and its associated industry”. “What we see is that the ‘protective mountain of the nation’ continues to strengthen in Taiwan,” highlighted Cheng, referring to the strategic importance of the semiconductor sector, considered a deterrent against a potential Chinese attack on the island.
Last week, the New York Times reported that the trade agreement between Taiwan and the US includes the construction of five additional TSMC factories in Arizona, a state where it has already invested 165 billion dollars, although the information has not yet been confirmed by the company.
Since returning to the White House, US President Donald Trump has insisted on the need to “bring back” semiconductor production to the United States, a country that for years depended on foreign manufacturers and fragile global supply chains. However, experts believe that replicating Taiwan's production capacity will not be easy, given the island's decades of experience, highly qualified workforce and a comprehensive ecosystem of suppliers and logistics that allows it to maintain high levels of efficiency.

More than 200 thousand “drones” through special defense budget

Taiwan intends to acquire more than 200,000 unmanned aerial vehicles (“drones”) through a special defense budget worth 1.25 billion Taiwan dollars (around 33,893 million euros), the local press reported yesterday.
During a clarification session held on Monday with deputies, Taiwan's Ministry of National Defense (MDN) revealed seven categories of weapons foreseen in this plan, designed to reinforce the island's defensive capabilities.
The project envisages the purchase of approximately 200,000 unmanned aerial vehicles – including coastal surveillance and reconnaissance “drones”, as well as attack “drones” –, more than a thousand unmanned vessels, “wandering” munitions such as the Altius-700M model and several “anti-drone” systems.
The formation of a vast fleet of “drones” has become one of the priorities for the defense of Taiwan, which sees the Ukrainian experience as an example of how technology can be used to face a possible attack.
Among the weapons that Taiwan intends to acquire are 82 HIMARS multiple rocket launcher systems, accompanied by 1,203 containers with precision projectiles and 420 tactical missiles, as well as self-propelled artillery – 60 M109A7 howitzers – and anti-tank missiles, including 1,050 Javelin and 1,545 TOW-2B.
These acquisitions would be financed through a special budget announced last year by Taiwanese leader William Lai, to run between 2026 and 2033, with the aim of consolidating armed forces capable of “permanently defending” “democratic Taiwan”.
The funds would also serve to support the development of the so-called “Taiwan Shield” (T-Dome), a layered air defense system, announced by Lai on October 10, inspired by Israel’s “Iron Dome” and the “Golden Dome” proposed by the United States.
However, the two main opposition parties – the Kuomintang (KMT) and the Taiwan People's Party (PPT) –, in favor of greater rapprochement between Taipei and Beijing, have blocked the budget's processing thanks to the legislative majority they hold, also accusing the Government of a lack of transparency in the spending plan. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 23:41:09</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 90% of Marques Mendes' votes in Asia and Oceania came from Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/mais-de-90-dos-votos-de-marques-mendes-na-asia-e-oceania-vieram-de-macau/</link><description>Despite coming in fifth place in all votes, Marques Mendes received the most votes in Asia and Oceania. Macau contributed to this in a decisive way: of the 1,174 votes that the candidate supported by the PSD had in this part of the world, only 101 did not come from Macau. Looking at the results of the Portuguese presidential elections in Asia/Oceania, it appears that Seguro won over voters in South Korea, Japan and Timor-Leste; Cotrim Figueiredo won in Qatar and the United Arab Emirates; Ventura was preferred in India, Israel and Australia.

Macau contributed overwhelmingly to Luís Marques Mendes being the most voted presidential candidate in Asia. In the first round of the Portuguese presidential elections, the candidate supported by the PSD received a total of 1,174 votes in the Asia and Oceania region. Of these, 1,073 were obtained in Macau, that is, the Macao SAR contributed 91% of the votes in Marques Mendes in this region of the world.
Despite the good result in Asia and Oceania, Marques Mendes had a result below expectations in the rest of the world. Overall, the candidate came in fifth place in the Portuguese presidential elections, with just 11.3% of the total votes.

INSURANCE CATCHES JAPAN, SOUTH KOREA AND TIMOR-LESTE

In the Asia and Oceania region, António José Seguro was the second most voted, having been the favorite of 842 Portuguese registered in this part of the globe, that is, 21.6%.
The candidate supported by the PS was the most voted by the Portuguese in Japan, with 12 votes (32.4%) of the 341 registered in that country. In Timor-Leste, Seguro won with 50 votes (40.3%) of the 1,586 Portuguese registered in Dili. The socialist also won in South Korea, with 8 votes (42.1%) of the total who went to the polls in Seoul.
Overall, Seguro was the most voted in this first round of the Portuguese presidential elections, with a percentage of 31.1%, and will go to the second round with André Ventura.

VENTURA PREFERRED IN AUSTRALIA, INDIA AND ISRAEL

André Ventura, second placed in the elections with 23.5% in total, was third placed in Asia and Oceania, with around 19.7%. The candidate supported by Chega received the most votes in Australia, Israel and India. In the consular posts of Sydney and Canberra, Ventura received 48% of the votes.
In Israel, it obtained 46.2%. Finally, in India, Ventura obtained eight votes, that is, half of the total number of Portuguese voters in Indian territory – all of them obtained at the Goa Consulate, and in New Delhi there was a tie between Seguro, Gouveia e Melo, Cotrim Figueiredo and Marques Mendes, with one vote for each of them.
India was, in fact, the country with the lowest participation rate in Asia and Oceania: only 0.1% of the 16,004 registered voters voted in these Portuguese presidential elections. India is also the second country in the region with the highest number of Portuguese registered, behind China, which has 58,125, of which 99.3% are registered with the Macau Consulate.

COTRIM FIGUEIREDO CONVINCED PORTUGUESE IN QATAR AND EMIRATES

João Cotrim de Figueiredo came in third place globally and fourth in Asia and Oceania, where he obtained 634 votes (16.2%). Even so, the candidate supported by the Liberal Initiative overcame the competition in four Asian countries: Qatar, the United Arab Emirates, Singapore and Thailand.
In Qatar, where 165 Portuguese went to the polls, Cotrim Figueiredo obtained 36.4% of the votes; in the Emirates, it won 52.1% of the 377 voters; in Singapore, it was 45.5%; and in Thailand he obtained six votes, that is, 30% of the 20 Portuguese who went to the polls.

FIVE-WAY DRAW IN INDONESIA

Indonesia, where there are 160 registered, was the country in Asia and Oceania with the fewest votes, only five Portuguese voted for the Jakarta Consulate, each of them voting for a different candidate. André Ventura, António José Seguro, Henrique Gouveia e Melo, João Cotrim de Figueiredo and Manuel João Vieira had one vote each.
One day after obtaining more than 60 thousand votes and 8th place in the global vote, musician Manuel João Vieira reacted with humor to the results: “Thank you very much to all the Portuguese men and women who voted for me and a special hug to the Portuguese from Indonesia who also voted for me”.
In the Asia/Oceania region, Saudi Arabia is the only country whose results are yet to be determined.


BOX
 
Second round of presidential elections: Portuguese can vote at the Consulate on the 7th and 8th of February

The second round of the Portuguese presidential elections, which will pit António José Seguro against André Ventura, already has a date set: voting abroad, including at the Consulate General of Portugal in Macau, will take place on the 7th and 8th of February, between 8am and 7pm. In Portugal, voting is only on Sunday, February 8th, also from 8am to 7pm. Remember that, according to Portuguese law, the candidate must receive an absolute majority of votes to be elected. If no candidate reaches a majority in the first round, a second round must be held between the two candidates who received the most votes in the first round. The next President of the Portuguese Republic will take office on March 9th this year. Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa will resign from his position ten years after taking office. According to the Portuguese Constitution, each presidential term lasts five years, with re-election permitted, but not for a third consecutive term.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 23:47:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Government wants to include residents living in Hengqin in the social security scheme</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/governo-quer-incluir-residentes-que-vivem-em-hengqin-no-regime-de-seguranca-social/</link><description>The period in which Macau residents working, studying or living in Hengqin will be considered as time spent in the Macao SAR under the social security system. This is what the proposed law presented by the Executive Council suggests, which aims to “strengthen the protection of the rights and interests” of residents on Ilha da Montanha.

O Conselho Executivo deu luz verde à proposta de alteração de lei para incluir, como excepções legais, os residentes de Macau que residem, trabalham ou estudam na Ilha da Montanha, para que, na avaliação dos requisitos dos direitos e interesses do regime de segurança social, o período em que estes se encontrem na Zona de Cooperação seja considerado como tempo de permanência na RAEM.
A proposta de lei, que prevê a alteração ao Regime da Segurança Social e ao Regime de previdência central não obrigatório, foi ontem apresentada por Wong Sio Chak, porta-voz do Conselho Executivo, e será submetida depois à apreciação da Assembleia Legislativa.
Segundo o também secretário para a Administração e Justiça, o Governo recorre actualmente a critérios de apreciação e autorização baseados em “razões humanitárias ou outras devidamente fundamentadas”, para, a título excepcional, apreciar os pedidos relativamente à contabilização do número de dias de permanência em Hengqin como se fossem dias em Macau.
Chan Pou Wan, chairman of the Board of Directors of the Social Security Fund (FSS), highlighted that, after the legislative review, cases will be evaluated by this Board, “thus streamlining administrative procedures”, he stressed.
According to data provided by Chan Pou Wan, last year, 2,341 Macau residents residing in the Cooperation Zone submitted an application to request contributions from the Non-Mandatory Central Pension Scheme. There were also 39 Macau residents who reside in Hengqin and requested, through an application, to enroll in the Optional Scheme Contributions.
The diploma in question also proposes to expand the scope of recognition of medical certificates necessary for applying for sickness benefit under the social security regime, so as to cover the Cooperation Zone. The Government, according to Wong Sio Chak, hopes to provide Macau residents with more favorable conditions for pursuing studies, employment and entrepreneurship, as well as for living in Hengqin, “creating an environment conducive to living and working that tends to be similar to that of Macau”. However, the Executive stated that the new policy should only be applied to Macau residents in Hengqin, ruling out the possibility of extending the measure to the rest of the Greater Bay Area.
The proposed law, in addition, envisages increasing, from once to twice a year, the possibility of withdrawing funds from individual accounts of the non-mandatory central pension scheme.
At a press conference, Chan Pou Wan was also asked about the progress in making the Central Pension Scheme mandatory. It is recalled that the FSS recently released the report of the “Study on the review of the current situation of the Non-Mandatory Central Pension Scheme and its development”, which suggests gradually implementing the mandatory central pension scheme.
Chan Pou Wan, in response, admitted that he had noticed a “robust recovery” in the local economy in recent years. “However, the pace of recovery among small and medium-sized companies has been unbalanced, and the FSS will continue to monitor” the matter, taking into account factors such as the level of economic recovery and the median salary, highlighted the person in charge.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 01:05:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Portuguese presidential elections: Marques Mendes wins in Macau, but those who go to the second round are Seguro and Ventura</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/presidenciais-portuguesas-marques-mendes-vence-em-macau-mas-quem-vai-a-segunda-volta-e-seguro-e-ventura/</link><description>António José Seguro (31%) and André Ventura (23%) were the most voted in the Portuguese presidential elections and will go to the second round, which will be held on February 8th. Luís Marques Mendes, who came in fifth place with just 11% of the total votes, was the winner in Macau, with a significant vote of 47%.

The results of the Portuguese presidential elections dictated that there will be a second round between António José Seguro and André Ventura, the two candidates with the most votes globally. In Macau, Luís Marques Mendes was the winner.
In the territory, the candidate supported by the PSD obtained 1,073 votes (47%). However, at a global level, Marques Mendes came in fifth place, behind Seguro, Ventura, Cotrim Figueiredo and Gouveia e Melo. Mendes got just 11.3% of the total votes.
O FINAL POINT asked António Bessa Almeida, representative of Marques Mendes' candidacy in Macau, how this discrepancy in Macau's results compared to global results can be explained. Bessa Almeida responded that Marques Mendes' “great victory” in Macau was the result of “good work” carried out in the region, with “maximum respect and transparency”.
Bessa Almeida also argued that the second round of the Portuguese presidential elections, from which Marques Mendes is absent, will be “a waste of time”, because they will “waste more money and more time”.

PARTICIPATION IN MACAU ALMOST DOUBLED

In Macau, António José Seguro came in second place, with 21% (477 votes). André Ventura came in third, having convinced 12.4% of registered voters in the Macao SAR (282 votes). João Cotrim Figueiredo was fourth (191 votes/8.4%); Henrique Gouveia e Melo in fifth (133 votes/5.8%); Manuel João Vieira came in sixth place (39 votes/1.7%); Catarina Martins came seventh (28 votes/1.2%); António Filipe in eighth (20 votes/0.9%); André Pestana da Silva came in ninth (14 votes/0.6%); in tenth place was Jorge Pinto (12 votes/0.5%); and lastly Humberto Correia (5 votes/0.2%).
For these elections, the number of voters registered at the Consulate General of Portugal in Macau was 57,748, of which 2,374 exercised their right to vote, that is, the participation rate was 4.1%. In the Portuguese presidential elections that re-elected Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa in 2021, the participation rate in Macau was just 2.1%.

SECOND ROUND ON FEBRUARY 8

Overall, António José Seguro was the most voted. The candidate supported by the PS obtained 31% of the total votes. André Ventura, supported by Chega, got 23.5%.
In this race for the position of President of the Portuguese Republic, Cotrim de Figueiredo came in third place with 16% of the votes; Henrique Gouveia e Melo had 12.3%; Luís Marques Mendes came in fifth with 11.3%; then Catarina Martins with 2%; António Filipe in seventh with 1.6%; Manuel João Vieira had 1%; Jorge Pinto 0.7%; André Pestana da Silva 0.2% and Humberto Correia got 0.08%.
The overall participation rate in this first round was 52.3%. In 2021, the participation rate was just 39.3%. Five years ago, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa was elected in the first round with more than 60% of the votes.
Remember that, according to Portuguese law, the candidate must receive an absolute majority of votes to be elected. If no candidate reaches a majority in the first round, a second round must be held between the two candidates who received the most votes in the first round. In this case, the second round is scheduled for February 8th.
The next President of the Portuguese Republic will take office on March 9th this year. Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa will resign from his position ten years after taking office. According to the Portuguese Constitution, each presidential term lasts five years, with re-election permitted, but not for a third consecutive term.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 01:06:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Price of recycled water in Macau will correspond to 85% of the value of drinking water</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/preco-da-agua-reciclada-em-macau-vai-corresponder-a-85-do-valor-da-agua-potavel/</link><description>The Government yesterday announced the new tariff system for the use of recycled water in Macau, which will come into force on March 1st with the start-up of the Coloane Recycled Water Station. Prices are calculated based on the tariff for using drinking water and range between MOP3.81 and MOP6.59 per cubic meter of water consumed.
Prices for recycled water consumption will be calculated based on the usage tariff established for each type of user, with values ​​ranging from 3.81 to 6.59 patacas per cubic meter. The information was published yesterday in the Official Bulletin, in a review of article 3 of “Fees and tariffs for the public water supply service”.
According to the new tariff system, which comes into force in March, the prices for recycled water consumption will correspond to 85% of the prices for drinking water consumption. In a statement, the Directorate of Maritime Affairs and Water Services (DSAMA) clarifies that, regarding residential use, for purposes such as flushing toilets, irrigating gardens and washing cars, the recycled water tariff “is not calculated by consumption brackets, but only according to the first bracket of the drinking water usage tariff” – that is, the cheapest. The price is therefore fixed at 3.81 patacas per cubic meter of water consumed.
With regard to the other two types of users, the new rules stipulate that 85% of the corresponding drinking water tariff is directly applied. This means that the base consumption of general non-residential water (intended mainly for industrial and commercial use, including schools and hospitals) is 5.13 patacas per cubic meter, while the base consumption of special water (gaming industry or civil construction, for example) is 6.59 patacas per cubic meter.
The new tariff comes into force from March 1st, with the start of the Coloane Recycled Water Station. In the initial phase, the system will cover public housing in Seac Pai Van and the University of Macau, intended for “flushing toilet tanks and irrigating green spaces”.
DSAMA says that, “after the supply of recycled water begins, users will be able to use it without needing to comply with other formalities”. The volume and price of water will appear detailed on the water invoice issued by Sociedade de Abastecimento de Águas de Macau (SAAM).
AUTHORITIES BET TO RAISE PUBLIC AWARENESS
Last Saturday, Macau authorities installed information posts in strategic areas of Seac Pai Van and the University of Macau, with the purpose of providing information to citizens about the recycled water system. The stations will remain in the same locations until April 29th, and at specific times employees will be designated to respond directly to any questions from the public.
DSAMA states that it has conducted several information campaigns among communities and families in Macau, in order to increase public awareness of the importance of recycled water in the territory. For example, several thematic lectures were held in collaboration with associations to clarify residents' doubts in person.
The next information session is scheduled for February 28th, with the “Recycled water publicity day” at the Official School of Seac Pai Van. In a statement, DSAMA agrees to opt for a “relaxed, diversified and interactive” approach, which allows citizens to “understand the importance” of the Coloane Recycled Water Station and “the start date of its supply, the supply areas, the purposes, water quality standards, identification methods, payment methods, observations and means of consultation, among others”.
It should be remembered that the supply of recycled water in Macau is scheduled to begin in March, initially covering public housing in Seac Pai Van and the University of Macau. The reservoir will allow the production of 2,500 cubic meters of recycled water per day, the quality of which will be tested daily by SAAM and subsequently detailed in reports published online.
The use of recycled water aims to promote the reuse of water resources and overcome the scarcity of fresh water in Macau, which is almost entirely dependent on inland China for raw water reserves.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 01:04:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau and Portugal maintain FIFA ranking in the first update of 2026</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/macau-e-portugal-mantem-ranking-da-fifa-na-primeira-actualizacao-de-2026/</link><description>The Portuguese football team remains in sixth place in the FIFA rankings, the first update of which for 2026 was released yesterday, in a hierarchy headed by European champions Spain. The Macau team remains in 193rd position, with 865.29 points.  For the third consecutive month, Portugal appears just behind the top 5, with the same 1,760.38 points it had in November 2025, when it qualified for the ninth time, and seventh in a row, for the final stages of the World Cup. The winners of the 2025 Nations League remain ahead of the Netherlands, ranked seventh, with 1,756.27 points, while the top five places continue to be occupied by Spain (1,877.18), world champion and two-time South American champion Argentina (1,873.33), France (1,870), England (1,834.12) and Brazil (1,760.46), respectively.
The top 10 now includes Morocco, eighth, with 1,736.57 points, after reaching, as hosts, the final of the African Cup of Nations (CAN), lost on Sunday against Senegal (1-0, after extra time). The recent African champions rose seven positions in the FIFA rankings, up to 12th place, while Nigeria (26th), Algeria (28th), Egypt (31st), Ivory Coast (37th), Cameroon (45th) and DR Congo (48th) were other countries benefiting from their performances in the CAN, played between December 21, 2025 and Sunday. If they overcome path one of the intercontinental play-off, in March, the Congolese will join Portugal in Group K of the World Cup, also formed by Colombia and Uzbekistan, falling from 13th to 14th place and from 50th to 52nd position in the FIFA hierarchy, respectively.
Of the Portuguese-speaking African Countries (PALOP), Cape Verde continues to be the best ranked, in 67th place, at a time when it is five months away from its debut in the main international competition for national teams. As for Portuguese coaches, Oman, coached by Carlos Queiroz, rose to 78th position, two above Guinea Conakry, led by Paulo Duarte, while Kuwait, led by Hélio Sousa, is 135th, São Tomé and Príncipe, led by Ricardo Monsanto, is ranked 189th and Timor-Leste, led by Zé Pedro, appears 198th.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 23:43:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Voluntary demolition of “low” risk illegal works may be exempt from licensing</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/demolicao-voluntaria-de-obras-ilegais-de-risco-baixo-podera-estar-isenta-de-licenciamento/</link><description>The Executive Council concluded the discussion of the change to the legal regime for urban construction, with a view to encouraging the demolition by citizens of relatively low-risk illegal works.
The diploma, which will be forwarded to the Legislative Assembly for consideration, suggests exemption from licensing and prior communication for the demolition of “illegal, relatively low-risk” works, which involve “building facades with a height of no more than nine meters, demolition projects lasting no more than five days and those of modest scale and complexity”, said Lai Weng Leong, director of Land and Urban Construction Services at a press conference held yesterday.
As established in the proposal, with regard to the prior communication of works on autonomous units with a gross area of ​​use not exceeding 120 square meters and which are not intended for housing purposes, as well as the request for a prior license for modification work, if they are presented via an electronic platform, prior communication will be immediately accepted and the prior license for work will be issued, allowing the works to begin the following day.
The Government considers that the new provisions will increase efficiency and promote electronic governance. Therefore, in order to guarantee the reliability of the electronic operation, the law also provides for sanctioning provisions in the event of inaccurate or erroneous information being provided.
The amendment to the law also proposes expanding the scope of application of the licensing exemption, to cover modification, conservation and repair works to be carried out in airport facilities, public maritime passenger terminals or the light rail system by the entities responsible for their respective operation.
In terms of works to be carried out by public services on real estate classified or in the process of being classified and in the respective protection zones or provisional protection zones, the diploma suggests that these works also do not require licensing, but without prejudice to the continued compliance with the provisions set out in the law on safeguarding cultural heritage.
Wong Sio Chak, spokesperson for the Executive Council, highlighted that the Government decided to move forward with the aforementioned review of the law taking into account the optimization of legal standards related to the business environment, as well as the simplification and increase in efficiency regarding the assessment and approval of projects.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 01:03:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan records record number of visitors despite sharp drop in Chinese tourist flow</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/japao-regista-recorde-de-visitantes-apesar-de-forte-queda-do-fluxo-de-turistas-chineses/</link><description>The country recorded 42.7 million visitor arrivals in 2025, surpassing the previous record of 36.8 million achieved in 2024. The weakening of the yen contributes to reinforcing the archipelago's attractiveness in the eyes of international tourists.
However, the number of Chinese tourists fell 45% in December from the previous year: just 330,000 visited Japan last month.
Relations between the two neighboring powers have deteriorated since Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi suggested in November before the Japanese Parliament that Tokyo could intervene militarily if China launched an attack on Taiwan. The statements sparked strong protests from Beijing, which a week later advised its citizens against traveling to Japan due to “significant risks” to their safety.
Beijing's recommendation triggered alerts in Japan's tourism sector, as China is the main source of foreign tourists, responsible for around 7.5 million visitors in the first nine months of the year, according to official figures, an increase of 42% compared to the previous year and a quarter of total foreign tourists.
Attracted by a weak yen, foreign visitors spent the equivalent of 3.3 billion euros in the third quarter.
The total number of visitors suggests that Japan has resumed the dynamics it demonstrated before the Covid pandemic, when the number of foreign visitors increased fivefold between 2012 and 2020.
In addition to Japan's attractiveness for its culture, gastronomy and landscapes, including Mount Fuji, this influx is also explained by the weakening of the yen, which has fallen against the dollar in the last three years, making the destination cheaper.
The Japanese Government has set an ambitious target: to reach 60 million foreign tourists per year by 2030, running the risk of fueling “excess tourism” in the most visited places in the archipelago and of inviting criticism from residents, particularly in the former imperial capital, Kyoto, which has increased the stay rate since January 1st to try to contain the phenomenon of mass tourism.
The archipelago, with 124 million inhabitants, continues, however, to receive far fewer tourists than the world's leading destination, France, which has 68 million inhabitants and received around 100 million visitors in 2023 and 2024. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 23:39:48</pubDate></item><item><title>VIP sector of Macau casinos grows in January</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/sector-vip-dos-casinos-de-macau-cresce-em-janeiro/</link><description>Preliminary data for the month of January reveal significant increases in the volume of bets and the number of “whales” (that is, players with a single bet of at least 100 thousand Hong Kong dollars). According to a Citigroup report, during this period there were at least six players betting between 500,000 and one million Hong Kong dollars in Macau casinos.

The volume of bets made by high-level players in Macau casinos increased by 72.3% this January, compared to the same period last year. The data was released in the most recent report from the brokerage firm Citigroup, which also shows a 16.7% increase in the number of “whales” in Macau, from 24 to 28.
According to the institution, these 28 “whales” – that is, players with a single bet in hand of at least 100 thousand Hong Kong dollars – contributed 8.1 million Hong Kong dollars to the revenues of the region's gaming industry. The average bet per player is estimated at around 290,000 Hong Kong dollars, an annual increase of 49%. In comparison, the amount collected in the same month of 2025 was 4.7 million Hong Kong dollars, as released by the Directorate of Gaming Inspection and Coordination (DICJ).
This January, during the period under review, analysts report seeing “several big bettors in Macau”, with emphasis on a “whale” who bet 1 million Hong Kong dollars on Galaxy Macau. There was also a gambler who bet 850,000 Hong Kong dollars on City of Dreams, managed by Melco, and another high roller who invested 640,000 Hong Kong dollars on Wynn Palace.
In total, analysts say they have detected “six ‘whales’ betting 500,000 Hong Kong dollars or more, compared to just two in January 2025”. According to Citigroup experts, this increase may be related to offers frequently given to prominent players, which include free tickets to nearby shows.
In January, cultural offers were diverse and abundant, with a calendar marked mainly by shows by singers Raymond Lam and Dylan Wang at the Venetian Arena and the Galaxy Arena, respectively. It is also important to note that Wynn Macau is currently giving free tickets to the South Korean Blackpink concert, taking place in Hong Kong next week, to premium players with the highest gaming volumes.
“We think it is safe to say that Macau has product offerings, both related and unrelated to gambling, that attract wealthy consumers from the interior of China, who remain willing to spend”, reads the Citigroup report, as cited by the GGRAsia portal.
As for the number of ‘premium’ players in the mass segment – ​​an intermediate sector between the mass game and the game played by VIP high rollers – there was a drop of approximately 11% compared to the number recorded in the same month of the previous year.
Even so, this layer of gamblers invested an average of 28,424 Hong Kong dollars in Macau casinos, an increase of 41% in annual terms. The bets for the month of January present, in fact, a value “comparable” to that of the Golden Week period of 2025, one of the biggest peaks in the influx of players from the Continent.
Although with a slight drop of 2% compared to January 2025, the Galaxy leads the January table for the 'premium' mass segment with a market share of around 25%. Melco, Wynn and Sands have respective – and close – shares of 20.9%, 20.3% and 20.2%.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 23:45:17</pubDate></item><item><title>China maintains reference interest rate at 3% for the ninth consecutive month</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/china-mantem-taxa-de-juro-de-referencia-em-3-pelo-nono-mes-consecutivo/</link><description>The People's Bank of China will maintain its reference interest rate at 3% for the ninth consecutive month. The central bank also announced that it will maintain the LPR for five years or more – used as a benchmark for mortgage loans – at 3.5%, also in line with market expectations.
The People's Bank of China (central bank) announced yesterday that it will maintain its reference interest rate at 3%, for the ninth consecutive month, in line with analysts' forecasts, which did not anticipate changes. In the monthly update published on its official portal, the central bank indicated that the reference interest rate for one-year loans (Loan Prime Rate, or LPR) will remain at that value for at least another month.
The LPR, created in 2019 as the main reference for market interest rates, directly influences the cost of new credits – especially for companies – and variable rate loans yet to be amortized. Its calculation is based on contributions from several commercial banks, including smaller institutions, which face higher financing costs and greater exposure to non-performing loans. The objective is to reduce the cost of debt and support the so-called “real economy”.
The central bank also announced that it will maintain the LPR for five years or more – used as a benchmark for mortgage loans – at 3.5%, also in line with market expectations.
The last interest rate reduction in China occurred in May 2025, when the central bank cut both rates by ten basis points: the one-year rate went from 3.1% to 3%, and the five-year rate or more from 3.6% to 3.5%.
At the time, in a context of economic slowdown in the second largest economy in the world, analysts considered the decision “obvious” and predicted further cuts throughout the year, which ended up not materializing.
In recent days, some experts have anticipated the possibility of a further reduction in the LPR after the central bank stated that it has room for additional cuts in 2026, although the first easing measures announced this year were considered “limited” and “low profile”.
According to analysts, the central bank has enjoyed, in recent months, room to cut rates without fear of a devaluation of the yuan, in part thanks to cuts made by the United States Federal Reserve (Fed). However, fears of a bubble in the financial markets or a worsening of industrial excess capacity prevailed.
Among the main factors that explain the weaker than expected economic recovery in China, economists point to the uncertainty of trade tensions with the USA, weak domestic and foreign demand, the risks of deflation, stimuli considered insufficient, the prolonged crisis in the real estate sector and the lack of confidence among consumers and the private sector. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 23:41:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Authorities call for reinforced measures against cold, wind and “discomfort”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/autoridades-apelam-ao-reforco-de-medidas-contra-o-frio-vento-e-desconforto/</link><description>The cold returns to Macau starting today. In the coming days, thermometers will drop to minimum temperatures of 10 degrees Celsius, which has already led to the publication of preventive measures against hypothermia by the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) and the Health Services (SS). The Winter Shelter Center opened its doors yesterday and will remain open every day, from 6pm to 8am, while the warning sign is in effect.

Temperatures will drop from today until at least next Tuesday. Authorities advise Macau residents to take protective measures against the cold, wind and health problems resulting from this abrupt change in weather conditions.
The “Decrease Temperature Alert” was issued yesterday on the official website of the Meteorological and Geophysical Services Directorate (SMG). This alert service, launched for the first time in December 2025, concerns situations in which “the minimum temperature in Macau will register a significant drop” within 24 or 48 hours, with the aim of “helping the population respond promptly to sudden changes in temperature” and minimize the risk of health impacts. At the same time, the “yellow alert for low temperatures” remains in force.
Today, temperatures should vary between 11 and 16 degrees Celsius, with relative humidity between 45% and 75%. The wind will intensify from today onwards, rising to levels 4 to 5 on the Beaufort scale (“moderate” and “fresh”) and with occasional gusts of level 6 (“very fresh”). Tomorrow, the day will be “very cloudy” and marked by even lower temperatures of 10 to 15 degrees Celsius.
There should be a slight recovery on Friday, when temperatures rise to between 11 and 17 degrees Celsius. The weather will continue to gradually warm up until next Tuesday, when thermometers register minimums of 17 and maximums of 23 degrees Celsius. Before that, “periods of light rain” are expected to occur on Monday.
In response to the changing weather, SMG launched a series of advice and preventative measures against the cold on its website. It begins by recommending that the public prepare additional clothing and try to dress “in layers” to avoid the cold, especially in the case of people with “more fragile constitutions” such as the elderly, children, pregnant women and chronically ill people.
The drop in temperature and the strong winds expected in the coming days could “cause physical discomfort” and even cause respiratory problems, joint pain, heart problems and gastrointestinal disorders. Wearing a mask and drinking hot water are some of the authorities' advice on this point.
Attention is also drawn to the possibility of the combination of multiple climatic phenomena, such as wind, cloudy skies and precipitation. In these situations, the thermal sensation (the temperature felt in the body) may be lower than the actual temperature.
Remember that the SMG page has, since the end of last year, a new service “Information on Felt Temperature”, which provides meteorological data in real time in order to more accurately reflect the thermal sensation interpreted by the human body. The various thermal indicators presented include temperature, humidity, wind speed and other meteorological factors that allow calculating the real thermal sensation experienced outdoors.

HEALTH SERVICES RELEASE ALERT

The Health Services (SS) also published a message yesterday reminding us of some of the measures to be taken to prevent hypothermia. In addition to the measures already listed by the SMG, the authorities emphasize that maintaining a warm and well-ventilated home environment should not be neglected. Particular attention should be paid to cold air currents and flammable materials, such as electric heaters – which, like hot water bags or electric blankets, should not be used by people with reduced thermal sensitivity.
Regarding food, hot and easily digestible foods should be preferred, such as soup, porridge and rice, avoiding meals rich in fat and cholesterol. Water intake should be doubled, unlike alcohol consumption: the warming sensation obtained by the dilation of blood vessels quickly gives way to a reduction in body temperature and dehydration.
Authorities recommend staying indoors as much as possible, while ensuring a daily dose of “moderate exercise” to generate heat and maintain an adequate body temperature.
In turn, the Institute of Social Action (IAS) announced that the Winter Shelter Center has been in operation since 6pm yesterday and as long as the yellow alert is in force. Daily reception hours are from 6pm to 8am the following day, at Rua Leste da Ilha Verde, no. 34, in the Edifício do Bairro da Ilha Verde E1. The facilities provide duvets, food and drinks to all users.
For more information, the IAS suggests contacting the Winter Shelter Center via numbers 28270939 (during office hours) or 63991963 (outside office hours).</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 23:45:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Frontline civil servants have little privacy, warns Che Sai Wang</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/funcionarios-publicos-da-linha-da-frente-tem-pouca-privacidade-alerta-che-sai-wang/</link><description>There are frontline civil servants who feel they have little privacy in the workplace, said Che Sai Wang. In a written interpellation, the deputy requests that changes be made to the work spaces of these workers to prevent them from being exposed to third parties.

Che Sai Wang is concerned about the lack of privacy of frontline civil servants. The deputy says he has received reports from workers who say they are exposed to the gaze of third parties for long periods of time.
In a written statement sent to the Government, Che points out that, in recent years, several public department workplaces have used closed circuit television systems, transparent or semi-transparent glass and monitoring tools that could harm the privacy of public employees. “We have received reports from frontline civil servants, indicating that the spatial design and monitoring arrangements in some government workplaces place employees on duty in the condition of being clearly observed by third parties for long periods”, says the deputy linked to the Macau Public Service Workers Association (ATFPM).
This, he explains, “includes situations in which external people can directly observe your behavior at work, operational processes, computer screens, and even private activities such as entering and leaving bathrooms”. According to Che Sai Wang, those involved stated that, after raising their concerns, “some of the response measures were limited to symbolic levels, such as placing anti-observation films”. “However, the design of the workspace itself and the resulting privacy risks have not been systematically rectified”, he points out.
For the deputy, the diplomas in force within the scope of personal data protection “do not establish clear, specific and binding legal standards for privacy risks not related to data processing, but of a continuous observational nature, which arise in government workplaces due to spatial design, visible structures or real-time observation arrangements”. Therefore, Che Sai Wang states that “regulation and consistency at a systemic level remain insufficient”.
The deputy elected directly asks, then, which “unified and specific privacy protection guidelines or regulations are applied to guarantee the necessary protection of the privacy of public servants in the work environment”.
Che also asks what initiatives the Government has taken to “carry out a comprehensive review of the design of workspaces and monitoring arrangements in current public departments, as well as to plan for privacy protection, especially in positions involving long shifts, intensive monitoring or high concentration”. “How does the Government intend to promptly reduce risks to privacy at the institutional and spatial design level, ensuring that frontline staff have a reasonably comfortable work space, thus leading by example in promoting privacy protection?”, he asks.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 23:46:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Seoul admits that surveillance failure allowed drones to be sent to North Korea</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/seul-admite-que-falha-e-vigilancia-permitiu-envio-de-drones-para-a-coreia-do-norte/</link><description>South Korean President Lee Jae-myung yesterday acknowledged a flaw in the country's surveillance system, following recent statements by a civilian who claimed to be responsible for the recent drone operation over North Korea.
“This means that there is a failure (in the surveillance system),” Lee said at an Executive meeting, in which he criticized the Ministry of Defense for not having detected the drones. The President classified the civilian's apparent actions as “unacceptable”, calling for “severe” sanctions, while the joint investigation by the Police and the Army progresses. Lee warned about the criminal seriousness of an infiltration with the aim of provoking a war, comparing the episode to “firing into North Korean territory”.
North Korea reported this month that drones from the South flew over its territory last September and again on January 4, and demanded explanations. Seoul denied that these were military devices and kept the possibility of civil action open.
Last week, a man in his 30s said in an interview with local channel Channel A that he operated the drones and that the aim was to measure levels of radiation and heavy metal contamination at a uranium factory near the Ryesong River, in North Korea.
At the same time, an investigation by the Yonhap news agency indicates that another man in his 30s, who has already been questioned by authorities, had participated in the manufacture of the devices.
Both suspects studied at the same university, founded a drone company in 2024 and worked in the presidential office under the administration of Yoon Suk-yeol, whose term began in May 2022 and ended in April last year, after being removed due to a failed attempt to impose martial law in December 2024.
Yoon himself, currently in pre-trial detention, faces a trial for alleged sending of drones to North Korea during his government, in addition to other complaints from Pyongyang about flights for propaganda purposes.
Kim Jong Un fires vice prime minister during ceremony
North Korean leader Kim Jong Un fired his vice prime minister during the inauguration of an industrial complex, state news agency KCNA reported on Tuesday (local time). “Kim Jong Un immediately dismissed Vice Prime Minister Yang Sung Ho from his position,” KCNA reported in the inauguration piece without specifying the reasons for the dismissal, which took place on Monday. Kim inaugurated the modernization of the Ryongsong Industrial Complex, on the outskirts of the capital, Pyongyang.
In his speech, he criticized “irresponsible, rude and incompetent economic policy officials”, blaming them for the project's delays, according to KCNA.
Kim Jong Un stated that the ruling party in North Korea clearly found “that the current economic guidance forces are poorly capable of carrying out the work of readjusting the country's industry as a whole and its technological modernization”.
In early January, North Korean authorities called for greater “discipline and loyalty” ahead of a crucial congress of the Workers' Party of Korea, the first to be held in five years, which will serve “to examine” the behavior of officials.
The appeal was made in an editorial published by the state-owned newspaper Rodong Sinmun, the country's largest daily, which states that “officials should face the congress with pride” because “it is the fruit of dedicated service to the North Korean people”.
The call for greater dedication and discipline at work comes at a time when North Korea is preparing for its 9th Party Congress, which aims to formulate a long-term political plan addressing diplomatic and economic issues in a context of growing tensions in the region.
At its last congress, in 2021, the party reaffirmed North Korean leader Kim Jong Un as general secretary, reinstating a position that had been abolished in 2016.
During the event, Kim acknowledged “the failure” of his economic policies, regretting that the goals set for the time had not been achieved. A day later, he defended the elevation of the country's military capabilities “to a much higher level”, arguing that this “defensive increase” was necessary to “protect the country's security” and provide a “peaceful environment for the construction of socialism”. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 23:40:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Recidivism rate of young offenders in Macau remains between 3% and 5%</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/taxa-de-reincidencia-dos-jovens-infractores-de-macau-mantem-se-entre-os-3-e-5/</link><description>Cases of recidivism among young people who have already committed crimes in Macau have remained low over the last three years, while young people who were admitted to the Instituto de Menores (IM) between 2018 and 2022 have a recidivism rate of zero. The data was released by the substitute president of the Institute of Social Action (IAS), Tang Yuk Wa, in response to a written question from deputy Lam Lon Wai.

The recidivism rate of young offenders in Macau has remained between 3% and 5% in the last three years, according to data recently released by the Institute of Social Action (IAS). As for young people who have been admitted to the Juvenile Institute (IM) of the Directorate of Correctional Services (DSC), the recidivism rate drops to zero.
The statistics were released in response to a written question from deputy Lam Lon Wai, in which he called for a review of the current Educational Guardianship Regime for Young Offenders and the reinforcement of monitoring of young people after their release from prison or temporary residences. In the message sent to the Government, the deputy argues that the regime in question, in force since 2007, “presents insufficiencies regarding education, supervision and subsequent support” for young offenders, especially those who suffer from emotional disturbances or who are part of dysfunctional families.
The ubiquity of the ‘internet’ and social networks makes these young people equally vulnerable to “scams”, “harmful information” and “precocious sexual behavior”, which is why the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) has already announced that it intends to “strengthen teacher training on legal education, sexual education and identification of psychological disorders”. In parallel, 151 lectures on crime prevention were held aimed at teenagers in the first three quarters of 2025.
Despite these initiatives, the deputy argues that there is still room to “improve educational protective measures aimed at young offenders, the model of homes, interdisciplinary cooperation and support after leaving homes”. He gives as an example the measure of placement in temporary residence units, whose maximum period of one year is often considered “insufficient” for young people to complete their rehabilitation and psychological treatment. Furthermore, there is still no specific home in Macau for young people suffering from emotional disturbances or mental illnesses, which makes it impossible for them to receive “treatment and management” suited to their needs.
With regard to recidivism, Lam Lon Wai relates this issue to “factors such as poor family functioning, insufficient parental skills, domestic violence and excessively strict or, on the contrary, too permissive educational methods”. The provision of continuous support by frontline professionals is, therefore, essential to ensure a reduction in the incidence rate and risk behaviors.

THERE ARE NO PLANS TO CHANGE THE CURRENT REGIME

In his response, the substitute president of the IAS, Tang Yuk Wa, begins by highlighting that “the authorities involved in the processes of educational protective measures” – namely, the judges, the IAS and the IM – “provide monitoring for young offenders in a staggered manner, taking into account the seriousness of the occurrences”. One of these measures involves placing young people in temporary residence units, which aim to “create a deterrent effect on the behavior of young offenders” over a period of institutionalization that can vary between one month and one year.
The head of the IAS explains that, when the result is positive, the judge can close the case within three or six months or apply other alternative protective measures; otherwise, the application of more stringent measures is considered, such as an inpatient service that can last from one to five years. The judge's decision is based on a social report prepared by IM every six months, referring to the evolution of young people.
In the most serious scenario, in which even after five years of internment the judge determines that the young people are still not able to participate in community life, the internment can be extended for a maximum period of three years. All things considered, the maximum duration of the internment measure is eight years. However, Tang Yuk Wa warns that extending the length of confinement could have negative impacts “on the connection of young offenders with their family of origin and society” and on their social reintegration.
IAS data for the period between 2022 and 2024 indicate that the rate of replacement of placement in temporary residences with “more stringent” measures was 9.7%. On the other hand, the recidivism rate in the two years after the measures were applied remained between 3% and 5% in the last three years. IM data also indicates that none of the young people hospitalized between 2018 and 2022 reoffended in situations of delinquent and criminal behavior.
In view of these data, the substitute president of the IAS considers that “educational protective measures are effective in correcting the deviant behavior of young offenders” and reveals that, for now, there are no proposals to change the regime in question.

NEW PARENTS SUPPORT PROGRAM IN 2026

Tang Yuk Wa also mentions the support programs launched by the IAS over the years, aimed at families of young people involved in judicial intervention. Of particular note is the support program “Carinhos e Amor da Família”, established in cooperation with non-governmental organizations with the purpose of “providing emotional support, family counseling and parental education services” to families, “helping guardians to reduce their psychological burden” and “recovering a healthy family life”.
This year, a new program aimed at the same population will be launched, called “Effective Parenting”, which aims to “deepen support for parental education and reinforce education and legal awareness”, while protecting and maintaining existing services. The release date of this program has not yet been revealed.
On the IM's part, “post-release counseling” services continue to be offered to all young people who have been hospitalized, in cooperation with the Social Reinsertion Department (DRS) of the IAS. Young people still in a hospital situation, but about to leave, can count on the “Education Support Program and the “Employment Support Program”, the result of a collaboration with the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ), to stay informed about school vacancies or job offers.
The IAS DRS's functions are to provide support to released minors, through the creation of temporary reception conditions and their integration into work, school, training and social work, acting in a first collaboration with the IM and the Macau Prison. The department has a team made up of psychologists, sociologists and social workers, who work together to monitor the minor's reintegration process into the family, school or professional environment, while also preventing criminal recurrence.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 01:05:53</pubDate></item><item><title>IC invites companies to submit proposals for catering services at an outdoor concert</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/ic-convida-empresas-a-apresentarem-propostas-para-servicos-de-restauracao-em-concerto-ao-ar-livre/</link><description>On the 7th and 8th of February, the Outdoor Performance Venue will host concerts and the Cultural Institute (IC) is inviting local companies in the restaurant industry to submit proposals to provide their services during the shows.
Local companies must submit proposals to provide light meal and beverage services during this event. Applications are free and are open from today until 5:45 pm on January 27th, and are open to all companies in the local catering sector.
The Macau Open Air Performance Venue is located at the intersection of Avenida do Aeroporto (to the northeast) and Rua de Ténis (to the north), in Cotai. Six containers are installed there, intended for providing light meal services during the concert. Each selected company will operate a container on those days, assuming sole responsibility for its own profits and losses and for applying for licenses, if any.
The IC explains that the selection will be made according to evaluation criteria such as the viability and integrity of the proposed operation, the harmony with the atmosphere of the outdoor shows, the diversity and reasonableness of the price of light meals and the compatibility of the menu with the event, the aesthetics and functionality of the venue's decoration and the team members' CV in relation to the experience of operating and managing catering establishments.
The application regulations are available on the IC website (www.icm.gov.mo). Candidates may present their application documents in person at the Cultural Institute Building during office hours or send them by post during the application period.
This venue, which began operating last year, is the largest outdoor performance venue in Macau, with a capacity for more than 50,000 spectators.</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 23:44:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Official distinction reinforces NAAM Thai Restaurant's legacy of authenticity at Artyzen</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/distincao-oficial-reforca-legado-de-autenticidade-do-naam-thai-restaurant-no-artyzen/</link><description>The tradition and authenticity of Thai cuisine in Macau has once again been recognized with an official public seal. NAAM Thai Restaurant, located at Artyzen Grand Lapa Macau, received the Thai Select 2-Star Restaurant distinction, awarded by the Ministry of Commerce of the Royal Thai Government. This is the third time that the restaurant has been honored with the Thai Select award, which now boasts a two-star rating, valid until November 2028.
The award, presented by the deputy director general of the Thai International Trade Promotion Department, Suparporn Sookmark, recognizes establishments that, globally, stand out for gastronomic excellence, memorable atmosphere, professional service and distinctive culinary character. The Thai Select program, which has already distinguished more than 1,610 restaurants in 65 countries, serves as a seal of trust for lovers of authentic Thai gastronomic culture.
For Rutger Verschuren, vice-president of Artyzen Hospitality Group and general manager of the hotel, the award is a reflection of the team's dedication and consolidates a presence of more than two decades in Macau's gastronomic scene. “As one of the first Thai restaurants in Macau, NAAM is valued for its relaxed atmosphere and genuine hospitality,” said Verschuren.
Executive chef Sutthaporn Chulavachana, who represented the restaurant together with the service and kitchen team at the ceremony, sees the award as motivation to remain faithful to its culinary roots. “Each dish at NAAM conveys the flavors, techniques and stories of Thailand,” said the chef, highlighting the “Authentic Thai Discovery” philosophy that guides the restaurant.
The restaurant’s identity is deeply linked to its name, “NAAM”, which means “water” in Thai. This concept is materialized in the decoration through an interior tank and in the views of the resort's pool and its tropical gardens. The space is designed to offer an immersive experience, where natural light fills the space during the day, creating an atmosphere of leisure that, at dusk, transforms into a peaceful setting of “discreet elegance”.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Japanese bond interest rates soar to record levels</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/20/juros-das-obrigacoes-japonesas-disparam-para-niveis-recorde/</link><description>Japanese interest rates soared to record levels yesterday, in a market haunted by the prospect of tax cuts and stimulus measures promised by Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi three weeks before early elections.

Japanese 30-year sovereign bond yields rose to an unprecedented 3.66%, and 40-year bond yields reached the 4% mark for the first time. Rates on 10-year bonds also rose, reaching a new high since 1997, at more than 2.32%.
This increase in rates reflects massive sales of securities and illustrates greater distrust on the part of investors, with yields moving in the opposite direction to demand, as more profitable yields are needed to convince buyers who have become more demanding and cautious.
This cooling of the bond market comes after a press conference by Sanae Takaichi on Monday, during which she announced her intention to dissolve the lower house of Parliament and call early legislative elections on February 8.
Takaichi, whose recovery policy with increased budgetary expenditure has already put Japanese debt under pressure since October, indicated, however, that he intends to pursue an accommodative budgetary policy.
Above all, the ultranationalist leader promised to eliminate the sales tax on food products for two years, a central measure in the electoral promises of the Liberal Democratic Party (PLD, in power for decades). The opposition also demands this tax reduction.
Given Takaichi's great popularity, the vote could reinforce the government coalition's parliamentary majority, currently very restricted, and consolidate the “proactive” spending program to relaunch activity. “With both the ruling and opposition parties advocating a reduction in consumption tax, the bond market is losing hope regarding fiscal discipline, and yields could continue to rise,” commented Ryutaro Kimura, senior strategist at AXA Investment Managers, cited by Bloomberg.
It is true that “Takaichi indicated that he wanted to ensure that these tax reductions could be implemented without resorting to issuing additional bonds”, but “the reduction in food tax will potentially represent a loss of revenue of around 5 billion yen per year (27 billion euros)”, agrees Michael Wan, from MUFG bank, cited by the EFE agency.
This fuels the concerns of the market, already cooled by the colossal recovery plan of 117 billion euros adopted at the end of 2025 and the prospect of a new record budget (equivalent to 665 billion euros) for the 2026 financial year.
This set of circumstances is fueling market concerns, already cooled by the colossal recovery plan of 117 billion euros, adopted at the end of 2025, and the prospect of a new record budget (equivalent to 665 billion euros) for the 2026 financial year, as well as threatening to further increase the country's already enormous debt, which is expected to exceed 230% of GDP in the 2025 financial year. that Takaichi publicly takes into account the markets' reaction, and budgetary concerns may ease over time as election-related uncertainty dissipates,” Wan says. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-20 23:40:17</pubDate></item></channel></rss>