<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/xia-baolong-inspeccionou-desenvolvimento-de-hengqin/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Visitors 'per capita' expense fell almost 15% last year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/despesa-per-capita-dos-visitantes-caiu-quase-15-no-ano-passado/</link><description>Last year, each visitor who entered Macao spent an average of 2,157 patacas, ie 14.6% less compared to 2023. In total, visitors' expense rose last year to 75.36 billion Patacas since there was a significant increase in the number of tourists last year.
 
The 'per capita' expense of visitors who entered Macao last year was 2,157 patacas, which reflects a 14.6% decrease compared to 2023, indicated the direction of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). Highlight for the 'per capita' expense of tourists (3,884 patacas) and that of the tour (691 patacas), which lowered 8.2% and 12.7%, respectively.
DSEC indicates that visitors have mainly spent purchases (45.4%), followed by expenses in accommodation (25.5%) and food (20.9%). Analyzing for the main reason for the visit to Macau, the 'per capita' expenses of visitors who came to attend shows/competitions (5,076 patacas) and participate in conventions/exhibitions (4,323 patacas) were the highest in 2024.
Analyzing the main origins of visitors, in 2024, the 'per capita' expenses of visitors from the interior of China (2,503 patacas), Hong Kong (1,009 patacas) and Taiwan (1,952 patacas) decreased 18.1%, 13% and 8.8%, respectively, compared to 2023. The 'per capita' expenses of South Korea visitors (2,405 patacas) and Japan (2,093 patacas) dropped 33.8%and 1.4%, respectively, in annual terms . The 'per capita' expenses of visitors from Thailand (2,598 patacas) and Malaysia (1,992 patacas) recorded respective decreases of 22.7% and 15%, compared to 2023, while the 'per capita' expense of Singapore visitors (2,834 Patacas) grew 6.6%.
In total, over 2024, visitors' expenses registered an annual growth of 5.8% to 75.36 billion patacas, as there was an annual increase of 23.8% of visitors. It is recalled that in 2024 Macau received 34.9 million visitors.
Looking only at the fourth quarter of 2024, the DSEC says that the total expense of visitors (19.15 billion of patacas) slightly descended 0.2%, in annual terms, observing a decrease of 0.7% in expense Total tourists (16.28 billion of patacas) and a 2.8% rise in the total expense of the tour (2.87 billion of patacas).
The 'per capita' expense of visitors (2,126 patacas) decreased 8.2%in annual terms, but rose 6.2%in quarterly terms. Analyzed by the origin of visitors, the 'per capita' expenses of visitors from the interior of China, Hong Kong and Taiwan ciphed at 2,548 patacas, 802 patacas and 1,494 patacas, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10T06:42:54+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong seizes three pounds of anesthetic linked to the new synthetic drug</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/hong-kong-apreende-tres-quilos-de-anestesico-ligado-a-nova-droga-sintetica/</link><description>Hong Kong police announced = seizure at the three -pound airport of an anesthetic used to produce a new synthetic drug, known as 'space oil', which will have caused three deaths in the territory. In a statement, the Chinese semi -autonomous customs said that the three pounds of Ethomidate had a $ 3.2 million market value from Hong Kong.
Ethomidate, an intravenous short action anesthetic, is mainly used in emergency services, anesthesia units, surgery rooms and intensive care units.
This chemical was found in a bag and a box of food inside an unspoken luggage from Malaysia on January 8.
Following an investigation, customs agents detained a 47-year-old man suspected of being linked to the case in Tuen Mun in northern Hong Kong, near the mainstream china border.
In early November, Hong Kong authorities confirmed suspicions that at least three deaths are related to 'space oil'.
At the end of December, the Hong Kong Security Secretariat told South China Morning Post that territory hospitals would establish more rigorous controls for ethomidate in 2025.
A spokesman for this secretary said the new protocols will involve more rigorous control not only about drug storage, but also on documentation and handling requirements.
Ethomidate is currently classified as a controlled substance, so the sale or illegal possession can lead to a two -year prison sentence and a $ 100,000 fine of Hong Kong.
At the end of October, Hong Kong Security Secretary Chris Tang Ping-Kung said the region was working to include the ethomyidate on the list of restrictions targeted by early 2025. “Illegal possession or Smoking, inhaling, ingesting and injecting 'spatial oil' containing ethomidate will be subject to a maximum sentence of seven years in prison and a fine of one million dollars from Hong Kong [118 thousand euros]. Trafficking or illegal importation of such a substance will be subject to a maximum life of life imprisonment and a five million dollars of Hong Kong, ”Tang added.
Macau also revealed in December that police have already detected four cases linked to this narcotic since the first case of 'space oil' found in a local school in October 2023.
This drug is known in Hong Kong as 'Zombie drug' because it can cause serious physical and mental damage, including dependence, memory loss, seizures, loss of consciousness and even death.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10T06:43:10+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing presents protest to Panama by departure from the initiative track and route</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/pequim-apresenta-protesto-ao-panama-por-saida-da-iniciativa-faixa-e-rota/</link><description>China presented a formal protest to the Panama Ambassador in the Asian country, Miguel Lecaro Bárcenas, by the Panamiana decision of not renewing Beijing cooperation in the track and route infrastructure project, the Chinese authorities said.
 
Chinese Foreign Deputy Minister Zhao Zhiyuan told Lecaro Bárcenas on Friday that Beijing "deeply regrets" the decision of the Central American nation, according to a statement issued on the Chinese Foreign Ministry portal .
In the context of the track and route initiative, the official noted, "the practical cooperation between China and Panama in various domains developed rapidly, achieved a series of fruit results and brought tangible benefits to the nation and the Panamian people." “Retrocede (…) goes against the expectations of Chinese and Panamian peoples and does not favor the vital interests of Panama,” said Zhao.
The leader emphasized that China "respects the sovereignty and territorial integrity of Panama and argues that all large or small countries, whether equal, respect each other and fulfill their promises." "China is firmly opposed to the United States efforts to deliberately undermine the relations between China and Panama," added Zhao, expressing hope that "Panama makes the right decision based on the general situation of bilateral relations and interests In the long run of both peoples, eliminating external interference. ”
Miguel Lecaro Bárcenas said, in turn, that Panama “attributes great importance to relations with China”, according to the Chinese diplomacy note.
The president of Panama, José Raul Mulino, officially announced the country's withdrawal from the lane and route on Thursday. The announcement was made shortly after the visit to the Central American country of the US Diplomacy Chief, Marco Rubio. Mulino said the Panama Embassy in Beijing "presented the document" to "announce the withdrawal with a 90-day pre-advice," as agreed between the part. Marco Rubio described Panama's decision as an “important step” to reinforce relations with Washington. At stake are US concerns about China's influence on the Panama Canal.
Hong Kong Landbridge Group companies and CK Hutchison Holdings currently operate ports at both ends of the channel. This presence arouses concerns about the possibility of double civil and military use and strategic maneuvers, given the increasingly profound presence of the Asian country in Latin America.
The track and route initiative includes the construction of ports, railways or freeways, creating new commercial routes between East Asia and Europe, Africa or Latin America.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10T06:43:13+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing Prices fall from 2023</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/precos-da-habitacao-caem-face-a-2023/</link><description>The global average housing pricing index retreated to 215.8 in 2024, at a 11.7% drop from 2023 numbers. The decrease was found both in the prices of built housing and the prices of housing under construction, which They suffered reductions of 11.3% and 6.1%, respectively.
According to the data provided this Friday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services, the housing price index fell 2% in the fourth quarter of last year, compared to the previous quarter. Still, it is possible to mark a slight growth in the last months of 2024. Between October and December, the housing price index ascended 0.1% compared to the period between September and November - especially the Macao Peninsula, which recorded a growth of 0.2% (200.8).
In parallel, in the same temporal window, the price rate of built housing (222.8) rose 0.2%, with growth of 0.1% in the mud peninsula and 0.5% in mud and coloane. On the other hand, the index related to the housing under construction fell 0.2%.
Considering the year of building the buildings, it is found that the dwelling price index belonging to the 6 to 10 years had the highest increase (2.6%), while the level of dwellings from the 11 to 20 years if It was a rise of 0.2%. Already the dwellings of 5 years or less than 5 years fell 2.1% compared to the previous period.
In terms of useful area, the dwelling price index of the level of 100 square meters of useful area has risen 3.1% from October to December, compared to the values ​​from September to November. In the same period, the level of the level from 75 to 99.9 square meters and the level of the level of less than 50 meters decreased 3.9% and 1%, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10T06:46:52+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Five Thai hostages released by Hamas return home</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/cinco-refens-tailandeses-libertados-pelo-hamas-regressam-a-casa/</link><description>Five Thai hosts released by Hamas arrived in Bangkok yesterday, 16 months after they were kidnapped by the Palestinian Islamite group in Israel, international agencies reported.
Agricultural workers were released on January 30, under the first phase of the ceasefire between Israel and Hamas, an agreement that aims to end the war triggered on October 7, 2023 by the Hamas attack on the soil Israelite.
Watchara Sriaoun, Pongsak Tanna, Sathan Suwannakham, Surasak Lamnau and Bannawat Saethao landed at Suvarnabhumi Airport from Bangkok at 07:30 (00:30 from Lisbon), according to France-Presse (AFP).
The group was received by family members and Thai Foreign Minister Maris Sangiampongsa, wrote the EFE news agency.
Speaking to the press, Sangiampongsa said the five are in good physical condition, although they continue to be evaluated. "Mental health is the next important issue," said the official, leaving thanks to the countries that contributed to the ceasefire in Gaza.
Sombon Saethao, the father of Bannawat Saethao, said he was “very happy” for being able to meet his son, who will dedicate a traditional Thai ceremony. "I don't think I want him to be away from home," he added.
On October 7, 2023, Hamas kidnapped 31 Thai, 23 of which were released before the end of this year and two declared dead in May 2024. It is believed that one last hostage of Thailand, detained in Gaza, is still alive.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10T06:51:57+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai highlights “Positive Trend of Cooperation” between Macau and Heilongjiang</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/sam-hou-fai-destaca-tendencia-positiva-de-cooperacao-entre-macau-e-heilongjiang/</link><description>The chief executive went to Harbin, in the province of Heilongjiang, to watch the opening ceremony of the 9th edition of the Winter Asian Games 2025. During the visit, Sam Hou Fai took the opportunity to meet the authorities of that province, underlining them narrower relationships between mashed and heilongjiang.
 
Sam Hou Fai was between Thursday and Saturday in Harbin, in the province of Heilongjiang, where he watched the opening ceremony of the 9th edition of the Winter Asian Games 2025. Qin, Secretary of the Communist Party Provincial Committee of the Communist Party of China (CCP), to address the reinforcement of cooperation between the two parties.
At the meeting, Sam Hou Fai stressed the “determination of the Government of Masters to take advantage of his own platform role between China and Portuguese -speaking countries to help the Province of Heilongjiang reinforce cooperation with Lusophone countries in order to serve the better form national development ”.
In a statement issued by the Government of MSAR, it is read that the parties considered that since the launch of the integration of eight more capital cities of the interior of China, including Harbin, in an individual visa to travel to Hong Kong and Macau , on May 27 last year, "the circulation of people between MSar and Heilongjiang is more frequent, just as the economic and commercial relationship is increasingly narrow, and there is also a positive trend of cooperation."
The chief executive wants Heilongjiang and Macau to “further reinforce collaboration” in areas such as education, tourism, sports and traditional Chinese medical industry, “with the purpose of creating a broader space of cooperation”.
The opening ceremony of the Winter Asian Games was held on Friday night. Macau sent a sports delegation, made up of 28 members, who participates in the men's ice hockey mode. Sam Hou Fai met this delegation in the ice hockey arena, leaving their incentive to athletes to “teach all efforts to demonstrate their ability, and take advantage of competitions, reinforcing the exchange with athletes from other countries and regions, and thus contribute equally to the promotion of Macau ”.
In Harbin, Sam Hou Fai also took the opportunity to visit the Harbin Institute of Technology Aerospace, which is the largest installation of aerospace thematic exhibitions among the country's higher education institutions and also “an important teaching base and an important space for promote to society and the public the education of national defense and the aerospace spirit ”.
On the visit, the Chief Executive and his entourage were accompanied by the Deputy Governor of Heilongjiang Province, Yu Jian, the Secretary of the Communist Party of the Harbin Institute of Technology, Chen Jie, and the dean, Han Jie, having visited several Exposure areas of the Aerospace Museum, namely the return capsule of the first recoverable satellite of China, “Jianbing-1”, the China's first-generation electronic recognition satellite, “Changkong-1”, and the command resolution of the first mission of manned aerospace flight.
Sam Hou Fai indicated that “this visit allowed to know, in the various points of view, the development of the aerospace industry, especially its arduous history of enterprise in China, which means that there was nothing before and has had a great development, As well as the important contribution of the Harbin Institute of Technology to the growth of the national aerospace industry. ”</description><pubDate>2025-02-10T06:44:27+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>ATFPM renews requests to increase salary index of civil servants to 97 patacas</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/atfpm-renova-pedidos-para-aumentar-valor-do-indice-salarial-dos-funcionarios-publicos-para-97-patacas/</link><description>The Association of Macao Public Function Workers (ATFPM) reiterates that the remuneration of the civil service must be updated and each index of the salary table should be valid 97 patacas. Inflation and increased workload are the reasons that ATFPM underlies in its request to André Cheong, Secretary for Administration and Justice. The association also urged the review of the law on the careers of public services workers, as well as the adjustment of various related subsidies.
 
Another request to the government for the salary increase for civil service workers. The Association of Macao Public Function Workers (ATFPM) argues that the value of each index of the Indian table must go from current 94 patacas to 97 patacas.
In a letter sent to the Secretary for Administration and Justice, ATFPM presented several suggestions to André Cheong regarding the lines of government action for this financial year. Proposing the adjustment of the salaries of civil servants, the association led by José Pereira Coutinho justified his request with continuous inflation in the territory.
"The increase in prices of first necessity goods in Macao in recent years deprived workers, especially those of basic level, much of their purchasing power and their ability to support the high prices of goods in Macao," he said. He stressed that the increase in consumer price index "forces [workers] to move to the interior of China" to live and buy goods at first need.
ATFPM also indicated that the workload of civil servants has increased, while the aspirations and demands of the public in relation to the government have increased in recent years. He added that all Macau game dealers have recently adjusted their staff's salaries in order to increase morale.
It is recalled that the salary table of civil servants was updated last year, with the value of each index adjusted from 91 patacas to 94 patacas, after three consecutive years without increased wages in the government due to the pandemic.
 
Career Law Review
 
In addition to updating the retribution to public servants, the Association requested the optimization of employees 'careers through the legislative revision of the public service workers' career regime, which "has been repeatedly postponed," he criticized.
"The Government of MSAR should not postpone the revision of the legislation for various reasons, as this creates injustices in the civil servant system and can lead to inefficiencies in services, causing social inequalities," he warned.
ATFPM has suggested several reforms on employees' careers, including the career adjustment of general clinic and nurses, asking for more opportunities to progression at work. According to explained, the salary of general practitioners, which starts with 560 points, can only increase to 600 points after years of service, unlike the 735 points that the upper technicians can reach and, on the other hand, the progression exams of the Nurses are "rarely realized".
It also aims to merge index careers 350 and 430, since “the daily functions of these careers are indistinguishable” and their salary difference can result in injustice.
 
Governing transparency
 
In terms of public administration reform, ATFPM has requested transparency on appointments to leadership positions and heads of departments. The entity said it had received “many complaints” from basic employees about the lack of transparency in nominations and their dissatisfaction because professional qualifications, technical knowledge, experience and performance evaluation are not considered factors for promotion in career.
It proposed to create an independent committee responsible for recruitment and promotion issues in government departments, which, according to ATFPM, evaluate the qualifications of candidates and clearly explain to the public the reasons for their change of office of leaders and bosses.
The association led by Pereira Coutinho also wants an increase in subsidies, residence, family and seniority for civil service workers. He asked for even more promotion of official languages. ATFPM expects a special subsidy to be created for public officials who dominate both official languages, encouraging them to learning the Portuguese language, in the case of maternal language employees in Chinese, and vice versa.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10T06:43:56+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lusophone exports to China fall 5.3% in 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/exportacoes-lusofonas-para-a-china-caem-53-em-2024/</link><description>Exports from Portuguese -speaking countries to China fell 5.3% in 2024 to $ 139.7 billion, according to official data released. In all, trade between Portuguese -speaking countries and China reached $ 225.2 billion last year, 2% more than 2023.
 
According to information from China's customs services, the descent was mainly due to the largest Lusophone supplier in the Chinese market, Brazil, whose sales fell 5.2% to $ 116.1 billion (111.7 billion euros) .
In addition, also the second largest Chinese commercial partner in the Lusophone block, Angola, saw exports decrease $ 6.7% to $ 17.6 billion (17 billion euros) by 2024.
On the contrary, Portugal's sales sales to China increased $ 8.9% to $ 3.17 billion ($ 3.05 billion), while Mozambique exports rose 1% to 1.81 billion dollars (1.74 billion euros).
Equatorial Guinea exports to the Chinese market dropped 28%to $ 981.7 million (944.3 million euros), while Timor-Leste sales (less 98.8%), Cape Verde (80 , 9%) and Sao Tome and Principe (less 74.8%) also fell compared to 2023.
Guinea-Bissau exports to China fell 43.4% in 2024, although the country did not sell more than a thousand dollars (about 962 euros) in goods.
In the opposite direction, Chinese exports to Portuguese -speaking countries increased 16.5% last year and reached a new record, $ 85.5 billion (82.2 billion euros).
This is the highest value as long as the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries (Macao Forum) began presenting this data in 2013.
The data reveal that Brazil was the largest buyer in the Lusophone block, with imports from China to reach $ 72.1 billion (69.3 billion euros), an increase of 21.9% in annual terms.
Second on the list in Portugal, which bought goods to China worth $ 6.11 billion (5.88 billion euros), 5.5% more than 2023.
Despite the new record of Chinese exports and the fall on the side of Portuguese -speaking countries, China registered a commercial deficit of $ 54.2 billion (52.1 billion euros) with the Lusophone block in 2024.
In all, trade between Portuguese -speaking countries and China reached $ 225.2 billion (216.6 billion euros) last year, 2% more than in 2023. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-10T06:43:14+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal point 2025.02.10</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/ponto-fatal-2025-02-10/</link><description>Exports from Portuguese -speaking countries to China fell 5.3% in 2024 to $ 139.7 billion, according to official data released. In all, trade between Portuguese -speaking countries and China reached $ 225.2 billion last year, 2% more than 2023.
 
According to information from China's customs services, the descent was mainly due to the largest Lusophone supplier in the Chinese market, Brazil, whose sales fell 5.2% to $ 116.1 billion (111.7 billion euros) .
In addition, also the second largest Chinese commercial partner in the Lusophone block, Angola, saw exports decrease $ 6.7% to $ 17.6 billion (17 billion euros) by 2024.
On the contrary, Portugal's sales sales to China increased $ 8.9% to $ 3.17 billion ($ 3.05 billion), while Mozambique exports rose 1% to 1.81 billion dollars (1.74 billion euros).
Equatorial Guinea exports to the Chinese market dropped 28%to $ 981.7 million (944.3 million euros), while Timor-Leste sales (less 98.8%), Cape Verde (80 , 9%) and Sao Tome and Principe (less 74.8%) also fell compared to 2023.
Guinea-Bissau exports to China fell 43.4% in 2024, although the country did not sell more than a thousand dollars (about 962 euros) in goods.
In the opposite direction, Chinese exports to Portuguese -speaking countries increased 16.5% last year and reached a new record, $ 85.5 billion (82.2 billion euros).
This is the highest value as long as the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries (Macao Forum) began presenting this data in 2013.
The data reveal that Brazil was the largest buyer in the Lusophone block, with imports from China to reach $ 72.1 billion (69.3 billion euros), an increase of 21.9% in annual terms.
Second on the list in Portugal, which bought goods to China worth $ 6.11 billion (5.88 billion euros), 5.5% more than 2023.
Despite the new record of Chinese exports and the fall on the side of Portuguese -speaking countries, China registered a commercial deficit of $ 54.2 billion (52.1 billion euros) with the Lusophone block in 2024.
In all, trade between Portuguese -speaking countries and China reached $ 225.2 billion (216.6 billion euros) last year, 2% more than in 2023. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-10T06:42:25+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Open applications for the TAP Siac Spring Craft Fair</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/candidaturas-abertas-para-a-feira-de-artesanato-de-primavera-do-tap-siac/</link><description>The Cultural Institute (IC) announces the opening of candidacies for the TAP SIAC Handicraft Fair in Spring, which will take place between April 24 and 27 and May 1 and 4, at Tap Siac Square. Registration for stands have already opened and run by February 26, while creative craft workshops can be submitted until February 19. Participation is free for all interested parties.
The TAP SIAC Craft Fair occurs twice a year, in spring and fall. The initiative aims to support creativity and innovation, promoting the insertion of Macao cultural and creative products in the market, and contributing to the exposure of the Great Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau Bay.
In this edition, the fair will feature more than 220 stands dedicated to handicrafts and creative cuisine, operating for four straight days in each of the two weeks scheduled. Registration for the stands will be available online for candidates from Macau, Malaysia and Singapore, through the “Stand Operator Database of the Craft Fair” on the official IC website. For stakeholders from the interior of China, Hong Kong and Taiwan, the specific form is also available on the fair's page.
The products to be presented must be of original design and include a minimum of ten models. In addition to the sale of artifacts, the inclusion of services of cultural and artistic experience is allowed. If the number of eligible candidates exceeds stand capacity, IC will hold a draw for their assignment.
At the same time, registration for creative craft workshops also open in the same period and can be sent by email or delivered at the reception of the Cultural Institute building. Workshops will be evaluated based on criteria such as viability, aesthetics, attractiveness, budget and experience of trainers.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Sands China Race International Macau 10k scheduled for March 16</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/corrida-sands-china-macau-internacional-10k-marcada-para-dia-16-de-marco/</link><description>This year's edition of the Sands China Macao International 10k race is scheduled for March 16, the organization said. 7,000 vacancies are available for the ten -kilometer race and another 3,000 for Fun Run, five kilometers. Registration for Fun Run opened yesterday and 10K started on Saturday morning.
10k will start at 7am and Fun Run at 7:45 am, in SAP Square Van. The 10K route will pass the Sai Van Bridge and the Cotai strip, ending at the Olympic Sports Center stadium.
The event is organized by the Sports Institute (ID), Sands China Ltd. and the General Association of Athletics of Macau (Agam). In the presentation of the details of the race, Luís Gomes, president of ID, said that the event has been hosted “with enormous support and enthusiasm since its creation”, having expressed the hope that “this great sports event can propel even more The development of the local sports sector, involving all quadrants of society and encouraging residents and tourists to participate in sporting events, at the same time boosting the growth of sports tourism and related sectors. ”
Wilfred Wong, Executive Vice President of Sands China Ltd., He said this is “a large sports event long awaited all spring”. Through the continuation of this event, Wong hopes to “promote sensitization for public health and widen the range of local sports events, inviting tourists from different countries and regions to experience Macao's charm as a world tourism and leisure center and raising the status. and the international influence of Macau ”.
The "The Funkiest custom Award" contest will continue to be held this year, being open to the participants of 10K and Fun Run. Dedicated to the theme "Ocean Run", this year's prize encourages athletes to incorporate oceanic elements into their clothing.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10T06:47:00+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea says nuclear weapons are not exchange currency for negotiations</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/coreia-do-norte-diz-que-armas-nucleares-nao-sao-moeda-de-troca-para-negociacoes/</link><description>North Korea said yesterday that the nuclear weapons it possesses are not a bargaining chip to negotiate, but a force to stop threats, and justified the reinforcement of weapons with the geopolitical aspirations of the West.
 
"Our nuclear force is not something we advertised to gain recognition of anyone or a bargaining coin to negotiate for some cents," the North Korean regime said in a statement released by state news agency KCNA, after the United States had defended “the complete denuclearization” of the Asian country.
"The nuclear force of our nation is of constant practical use to quickly detain any attempt to invasion by hostile forces that violate the sovereignty of the country and the security of its people, and threaten regional peace," he added to the statement.
The statement suggests that Pyongyang has no interest in returning to the negotiating table with Washington. In the first term as president of the United States (2017-2021), Donald Trump proposed to North Korea to end nuclear weapons in exchange for support in economic development.
The North Korean message also mentioned the recent statements of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) and the European Union, which reaffirmed that they will not recognize North Korea as nuclear power. Pyongyang accuses the West of being a destabilizing force of peace. "It is well known that the continuous expansion of the Ukrainian crisis and the vicious circle of war in the Middle East is the result of the shameless search for geopolitical interests from the United States and the West," said North Korea. "These old bands of thieves are now sniffing the Korean peninsula," he added.
Pyongyang, in addition, denounced the growing participation of NATO and European countries in military maneuvers around the Korean Peninsula, accusing them of seeking the confrontation and disarmament of the Asian country, not for safety reasons, but to “reach the ones their political objectives and impure military ”. "Precisely for this reason, the justification of our policy of reinforcing nuclear forces, which advance to stride without knowing limits, is even more impressive" and the hostile forces "feel intimidated," he said.
United States President Donald Trump expressed on Friday the intention to build bridges with Kim Jong-un's North Korean regime. “We will have relations with North Korea and Kim Jong-un. I got along very well with him. I think I stopped a war, ”said the US head of state at a White House press conference alongside Japanese Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba. “I think it's a great advantage for everyone that I get along with him. I like him, I mean, I get along with him, he gets along with me. And that's a good thing, it's not a bad thing, ”added the Republican.
Trump also said that "Japan likes the idea because its relationship is not very good" with Kim Jong-un and the United States can mediate between the two. "I think this is a tremendous asset for the world, not just for the United States," Trump said. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-10T06:51:58+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong complains to the WTO against US tariffs</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/hong-kong-apresenta-queixa-junto-da-omc-contra-tarifas-dos-estados-unidos/</link><description>Hong Kong will file a complaint with the World Trade Organization (WTO) in the face of the imposition of new tariffs by the United States to the products and services of the former British colony. "US measures are absolutely inconsistent with the relevant WTO rules and ignore our separate customs status," Hong Kong government spokesman said in a statement.
The territory executive "will formally initiate procedures in accordance with the WTO litigation resolution mechanism against US irrational measures to defend our legitimate rights," he added.
On Thursday, Hong Kong's Secretary for Economic Trade and Development, Algrenon Yau Ying-Wah, had already said the city was considering resorting to the WTO. Algrenon Yau condemned a radio program the imposition of an additional 10% tariff on imports from the territory, classifying the irrational measure. "It is a disrespect for the region status as a member of the WTO and Autonomous Customs Territory," he said. "Washington made a significant mistake by imposing these tariffs," he warned, installing the White House to "approach the decision with prudence."
The secretary said that over the past decade, the United States have registered a commercial surplus of more than $ 270 billion (260 billion euros) with Hong Kong, underlining the benefits of bilateral trade.
In addition, he said that exports from the former British colony to the country represent only 0.1% of the total, suggesting a limited impact of new customs rights.
Yau noted that in recent years, Hong Kong has diversified its markets, such as Middle East, Southeast Asia and Central Europe, to mitigate “the repercussions of geopolitics”, allowing local companies to adjust export strategies. China also took United States customs rights to the WTO and both parties now have the possibility of resolving the dispute through bilateral negotiations in the next 60 days.
After this period, the parties have the right to request the WTO the formation of a panel to resolve the commercial dispute. However, the decision of this committee may take months or even years, if one party appeals to it.
On Tuesday, Beijing announced the application of customs rights of 10 to 15% over certain US products, in retaliation of customs rights imposed by the United States to import Chinese products.
China has also announced new essential mineral export controls and has launched an investigation into monopoly practices against the Google US technological giant.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10T06:43:09+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Registered two cases of death by flu, the first of the year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/registados-dois-casos-de-morte-por-gripe-os-primeiros-do-ano/</link><description>Macao reported two cases of death caused by flu, whose victims were a 69 -year -old resident with several chronic diseases, and a 35 -year -old resident. Both had not been vaccinated against seasonal flu. Health services reiterate that the influenza virus is still active and so far seven serious cases in Macao have been found. More than 5,400 residents received anti-the flu vaccines this weekend.
 
Two residents of Macau died of flu complications, the first two dead cases for this disease this year. Health services have reinforced the service of the influenza vaccine administration and again appeal to the population for vaccination.
According to health services, the 69 -year -old victim of the first case was with several chronic diseases and had not been vaccinated against seasonal flu this year. The patient's influenza situation became severe last Tuesday and, due to the worsening of his state, was declared his death on Thursday, having been diagnosed with flu and pneumonia.
The second case of death was a 35 -year -old woman who belonged to a high -risk flu group and was not vaccinated against seasonal flu. According to the authorities, the resident expressed symptoms of fever and cough in late January, but had not resorted to doctors at the time. It eventually resorted to the Emergency Service of the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center on the 3rd of this month given the persistence of symptoms, and was diagnosed with flu, having received a prescription of the drug Tamiflu for medical treatment.
The patient, three days later, had symptoms of chest pain and, having considered the flu to and acute pericarditis, was admitted to the hospital. The state of the woman worsened on Friday and was administered intubation, with fan, to watch her breath. It was transferred to the Intensive Care Unit and died on the same day due to the influenza accompanied by acute myocarditis.
Thus, seven serious cases in Macao were in 2025, two of which were deadly. "Currently, the influenza virus in Macau is active and has already entered the peak of the epidemic, so it appeals to residents to reinforce prevention," they warn.
Health services, in a statement released last Friday, stressed that pregnant women, children, the elderly and those with chronic diseases, who have not yet been vaccinated against the flu, are “more susceptible to serious complications or death after Influenza virus infection ”, so they should especially resort to as soon as possible to anti -spripal vaccination.
 
5,400 residents vaccinated on the weekend
 
Authorities thus reinforced the anti-the-crepal vaccination services last weekend, and nine health centers and a health post have had influenza vaccine administration services on Saturday and Sunday in the morning.
More than 5,400 residents received flu vaccines this weekend. According to health services, more than two thousand residents were vaccinated on Saturday and on Sunday 3,400 were administered with vaccines.
Most residents who vaccinated (60%) moved to unmarked vaccination points and about 2,100 (40%) were previously marked. The whole process of vaccination was "quiet," he said.
The body recalls that residents who have not yet been vaccinated can mark online or go to health centers and health centers to vaccinate, while non-residents can go to the vaccination post at Hospital Kiang Wu, to the hospital University or the Macao Workers' Clinic in Rua do Bispo Medeiros, who have a cooperation agreement with health services, supporting appropriate expenses to receive the flu vaccine.
The final point consulted yesterday the online vaccination marking system of health services influenza, having found that the schedule for all health centers and health centers is already full for this week. The Preta Areia Health Center, the Fai Chi Kei Health Center, the Green Island Health Center and the Nossa Senhora do Carmo-Lago Health Center are the most chosen points by residents and have full marking for nearby Two weeks.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10T06:45:22+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Aero Dili starts year with a new air route that will connect Timorese Capital to China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/aero-dili-comeca-ano-com-nova-rota-aerea-que-vai-ligar-capital-timorense-a-china/</link><description>Timorense airline Aero Dili inaugurates next Friday the aerial route connecting the capital of Timor-Leste to the Chinese city of Xiamen, Lourenço de Oliveira, executive director of that private company.
 
Speaking to Lusa, at the company's headquarters in Dili, Lourenço de Oliveira explained that he decided to open the route because it “represents a large market”, taking into account the thousands of Chinese living in the Timorese territory.
But, he stressed, also because when he started flying to Bali, Indonesia, and then to Singapore, the Chinese community asked him to make a direct route. "The process was not easy," said businessman Timorese, but February 14 marks the beginning of the flight to Xiamen, the city of Fujian Province, southern China.
The connection between the two cities takes about 05:20 hours and the round trip will cost about $ 1.060.
Asked by Lusa about whether the expansion of the company includes air calls to Australia, Lourenço de Oliveira said he is already “submitting the documents”. "If they approve, I have plans to make the Dili/Darwin and Dili/Melbourne route," he said.
Lourenço de Oliveira also said that the company's future is successful, especially if Timor-Leste is admitted as a full member at the Association of Southeast Asia Nations, a process that the authorities expect to complete during this year.
Created in 2023, Aero Dili made its inaugural flight to Denpasar, Bali, in March of the same year, and currently flies every day to the capital of that Indonesian island.
Last year he started the connection to Singapore with a weekly flight and also has several weekly calls to Oecussi, Timorese Enclave located on the Indonesian side of the island.
The only financial support Aero Dili receives from the Timorese government is a monthly $ 50,000 compensation to fly to Oedusi. “Still, I also have to give a subsidy of $ 7,500” to keep ticket prices affordable, said Lourenço de Oliveira.
Asked by Lusa about if she has already asked for an increase in compensation to the government, Lourenço de Oliveira explained that she never asked, but stressed the route to Oecussi is running "very well". “But it is good anyway and has a good airport, it could be in Dili. If I could change the airport, ”he said, noting that works at Nicolau Lobato International Airport are“ very important ”, especially the increase in the track, which is small.
Aero Dili's executive director explained that it has conditioned operations because it cannot use larger aircraft.
Aero Dili has two aircraft, the second has arrived in March. "I need another plane to meet the criteria," said the businessman, stressing that for Singapore is planned to hold two weekly flights and awaits subscription of an air agreement between Timor-Leste and Thailand to start flying to that country as well.
The Timorese businessman said he decided to form Aero Dili, because after more than 20 years the country did not have a national flag airline, although before operating the air calls between the capital Timorese and Bali with 'charter' flights. “I started forming human resources and now we already have 22 two flights, three pilots, three more because of Airbus, which are now also flying, and I formed the government people in civil aviation, because if we have no inspector, we cannot collaborate ”Said Lourenço de Oliveira. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-10T06:43:11+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>We are promoting the religious diversity of Lusofonia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/concurso-de-fotografia-da-somos-promove-a-diversidade-religiosa-da-lusofonia/</link><description>A “We are! - Portuguese Language Communication Association ”announced the VI edition of the photography contest“ We are images of Lusophony ”, with the theme“ The Man and the Divine ”.
 
This Somos Contest! - Portuguese Language Communication Association ”(Somos - ACLP), which runs from February 10th to March 10th, aims to inspire participants to capture images that portray the different relations between human and divine, reflecting on various traditions religious and philosophies present in Portuguese -speaking countries.
With this initiative, Somos - ACLP aims to foster a greater understanding of the different ideologies, beliefs and religious practices cultivated in the various Lusophone regions, including Macao.
The registered photographs must capture the essence of devotion, contemplation and the connection between the human and the transcendent, allowing a true historical contextualization of the traditions involved. The diversity of beliefs that characterizes Lusophone space, including cults to multiple deities and traditions that integrate nature, offers a vast field for creative expression.
The Association also highlights the interconnection between religiosity, nature and ecology, enabling participants a broad reflection on the man-divindicar trilogy. This contest is an opportunity for photographers to explore not only the aesthetic beauty of sacred spaces, but also the cultural message that each photograph can convey.
Open to citizens of all countries and regions of Lusophony, as well as Macao residents, the contest will have a jury composed of photography professionals, who will evaluate the works based on criteria such as creativity, originality and relevance to the subject. The awards for the second and third place were extended, with 7,000 and 5,000 patacas respectively, while the first classified continues to receive 10,000 patacas, but now will be entitled to a trip to Macao, in order to participate in the inauguration ceremony of exhibition.
This exhibition, to be held in Macao, will include the winning photographs, as well as others selected by the jury for its relevance. The initiative reflects the intention of Somos - ACLP to project the cultural dimension of Lusophony and to reinforce the role of Macau as a meeting point between China and Portuguese -speaking countries.
For more information and consultation with the contest regulations, interested parties can visit Somos Virtual page.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Macau will not reach goal for electric vehicles, says environmentalist</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/macau-nao-atingira-meta-para-veiculos-electricos-diz-ambientalista/</link><description>Environmentalist Joe Chan states that the central government goal of 45% of electric vehicle sales in Macao by 2027 is “absolutely impossible” to be achieved. By 2024, only 31.4% of the new vehicles registered were electric, while fossil fuels still dominate the car fleet. Despite government initiatives to promote sustainable mobility and create loading points, the lack of a clear plan to eliminate highly polluting vehicles represents a significant challenge for a greener future in Macao, according to Chan.
 
Macau Green Student Union's environmentalist and president Joe Chan told Lusa that Macau faces huge difficulties in achieving the target established by the central government for the sale of electric vehicles. According to the new guideline, 45% of new car sales should be electric models by 2027, a goal Chan considers “absolutely impossible” to Macau.
The revision of the target for electric vehicles was announced by the central government in early January, raising it from previous 20% by 2025. This increase occurs in a context where, in the second half of 2024, electric vehicles have already represented more than half sales of new cars in mainland China, as revealed by the China Passenger Automobile Association. However, in Macao, only 31.4% of the new vehicles recorded in 2024 were electric, according to official data.
The Macao Auto Park, which accounted for 253,182 vehicles in late December, is still dominated by fossil fuel -powered models, representing 95.2% of the total. Joe Chan pointed out that despite government efforts to promote less polluting transportation, such as creating more electric vehicle charging points, the transition to a majority fleet remains “far away”.
The Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) reported that, by the end of 2023, Macau had 2,100 charging places for light car and 500 for motorcycles. In addition, a financial support plan to slaughter obsolete motorcycles was introduced by 2023, with a maximum value of 8,000 patacas for the acquisition of new electric models. However, data from the Traffic Affairs (DSAT) Services Board indicates that by 2024, only 3.5% of the 128,542 recorded motorcycles were electrical, revealing a modest growth of 1.4 percentage points over the previous year .
Chan proposed more rigorous measures, suggesting that authorities start efforts to restrict the circulation of heavy vehicles, especially those used in construction, as well as public transport.
Additional DSAT information indicates that they currently operate in the region 929 New Energy buses, which represent more than 92% of the fleet, reducing the proportion of traditional engine buses to about 3%. As for taxis, 210 are totally electric, about 11.9% of the total, while hybrid taxis make up approximately 86.2%.
However, Chan lamented the absence of a clear plane of the authorities for the progressive elimination of highly polluting vehicles such as trucks and heavy motorcycles. "[…] The authorities have not yet defined a calendar and a very clear deadline for their progressive elimination, so pollution [which causes] is high," concluded the environmentalist.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10T06:42:18+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Celebration stop of the year of the serpent took festive votes to the North Zone</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/parada-de-celebracao-do-ano-da-serpente-levou-votos-festivos-a-zona-norte/</link><description>The second parade of the serpent's celebration of the year was held in the North Zone, on Saturday night, having gathered 17 floats.
The parade began on the marginal road of Ilha Verde and followed the Avenida do Conselheiro Borja, Arco Road, Sand Black Road, Avenida de Venceslau de Morais, Quatro Rua da Areia Preta, Avenida da Longevity, Rua do Mercado de Iao Even to the garden of the IAO Hon market.
At the arrival of the parade, in the Iao Hon market garden, a cultural show was held that featured the performance of artists of Hong Kong Amy Fan and Alex Kwong, as well as the singers of Macau, Sean Pang and Kane to Ieong, among others .
The floats are on display at Tap Seac Square until February 16th. The luminous facilities of floats are linked daily between 17h and 22h. STD also launched the “Happy Chinese New Year-Golden Stars” hobby in the “interactive STD zone” of its mini-program at Wechat, whose promotion period is taking place and ends on February 12. By performing tasks in the game, the public will have the opportunity to participate in sweepstakes and earn awards, which stand up to 60,000.
In a statement, the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) recalls that the last Chinese New Year's Fire Show will take place this Wednesday, the day of the Lantern Festival, at 21h, in the riverside area in front of Torre from Macao. The 15-minute firefire will be shown under the theme of the Lantern Festival.
STD also points out that all information about this year's New Year's celebrations is available on the body's online portal.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Mobile and debit card transactions increase in the fourth quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/transaccoes-por-pagamentos-moveis-e-cartao-de-debito-aumentam-no-quarto-trimestre/</link><description>The number of transactions made for mobile payments and debit card, as well as their value, registered a growth in the fourth quarter of 2024 over the previous quarter.
According to statistics released by the Monetary Authority of Macao last Friday, between October and December 2024 1 billion transactions were made using mobile payment, observing an increase of 13.5% over the figures from July to September .
Also the average value of the movements was growth of 8.4% over the previous quarter, totaling 8.2 billion patacas (an average value of 82.4 patacas per transaction). By the end of the year, there were already 108,905 the devices that accepted mobile payment or allowed the reading of "QR code", which corroborate the growing popularity of these payment modes.
As for credit card operations, the trend is equally positive: 12.7 million transactions were accounted for, an increase of 8.1% compared to the previous quarter. In turn, movements made with debit cards (excluding cash survey) registered a value of 552.5 million patacas, with a total of 1.2 million transactions.
According to the same document, the credit limit granted by banks in Macao reached 49.9 billion patacas in December, an increase of 0.3% compared to the previous quarter. On the other hand, the unpaid debt ratio decreased from 2.8%in September to 2.6%at the end of the year.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10T06:46:50+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Xia Baolong inscribed hengqin development</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/10/xia-baolong-inspeccionou-desenvolvimento-de-hengqin/</link><description>Xia Baolong, director of the Hong Kong and Macao Work Office of the China Communist Party Central Committee and the Hong Kong and Macau Affairs Office with the State Council, was in the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin between Friday and Saturday to make an inspection. Beijing's guardian wanted to “find out, 'on-site', the situation of industrial development, construction and planning of the zone in question,” reads in a statement from the Government of the MSAR.
On Saturday morning, Xia Baolong heard a presentation by Tai Kin IP, secretary for the economy and finance, about the organization of the work of the Government of Masters to 2025 in the economic aspect, having exchanged opinions on the acceleration of the proper and diversified development of the economy From Macao, the promotion of the construction of Hengqin and a better integration of Macao in the Great Bay.
Tai Kin IP promised to “effectively promote the proper and diversified development of Macao's economy and improve the effectiveness of economic governance, with a more open mentality, greater responsibility and more realistic measures”, adding that their guardianship will “improve work Relative to the definition of political measures on industrial development, implementing general coordination, optimizing the business environment and striving to capture investment and providing business services, exploring and proactively adopting more innovative economic policies and Advisor, as well as supporting the development of diversified industries by increasing investment in financial resources and reinforcing human resources guarantees ”.
The secretary reiterated that the Government of MSar will reinforce the “alignment with important national strategies, in the deepening participation in the construction of the large bay, in the performance of the role of 'infallible contact agent' in cooperation between China and the countries of Portuguese Language, and in the simultaneous implementation of 'expand abroad' and 'attract foreign investment' 'initiatives.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10T06:42:26+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>