<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/tailandia-prepara-se-para-ter-terceiro-primeiro-ministro-em-tres-dias/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Social club to support for social causes</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/de-clube-social-ao-apoio-a-causas-sociais/</link><description>Brenda Histed was the first president of the International Ladies Club of Macau and the driver of her creation.
 
The International Ladies Club of Macau was created in 1982 to help integrate the women of foreign employees, who had just arrived in the territory, to work at the Macao Telecommunications Company (CTM). His first president, Brenda Hisd, tells the story to the end.
“At that time, there was very little entertainment in Macao, so we had to invent our own,” he recalls. Thus was born ILCM, which began to be a women's club, with social gatherings and some activities, such as Mahjong games, but quickly realized it could be much more. “Edith Jorge, Macaense, opened so many doors to us, presenting us, for example, the governor's wife,” he recalls. "We found an orphanage in Coloane, which at the time was considered very far [the orphanage of the Salesians] where 250 abandoned orphans and children, in extreme poverty, had only four nuns to take care of them and had no money," he recalls. Therefore, ILCM has transformed this into its main project.
They have regularly organized funds raising events to be able to support the orphanage more consistently. "Susana Chow [previous president of the Legislative Assembly of Macao, between 1999 and 2009] provided wool from her factories and knitted bedding to the children," he recalls.
But one of Ilcm's great friends at the time was Andrew Stow, who was a pharmacist. “He was amazing, supported everything. We used to go to the orphanage to play with the children and support,” he says, with a smile, remembering his adventure companion. With several initiatives to raise funds, Brenda recalls that they were able to renew the kitchen and build bathrooms. “The children used to bathe on the street,” he says. Events organized by the club include fashion shows. “The first was in 1983. Two ladies lived in Hong Kong and organized the parade for us,” he recalls.
Brenda eventually left the territory in 1986, returning only in 2012, for a short visit, on the occasion of the 30th anniversary of the ILCM, then recalling the days of yore. “Those [orphanage] children needed so much help; Andrew provided products such as shampoo and medicines, and one of our ladies, a nurse, even had to be delivered,” he says. "It was a lady who came from mainland China and was illegal, could not leave the place."
When Brenda returned to Macao to celebrate the 30th anniversary of ILCM, he came to know that baby, who, however, became an adult, a teacher at Dom Bosco College. “I loved those children, I hope I made a little difference in their lives,” he says.</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:26:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau loses golden opportunity called “Cristiano Ronaldo” and leaves the “city of sport” more isolated</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/macau-perde-oportunidade-de-ouro-chamada-cristiano-ronaldo-e-deixa-a-cidade-do-desporto-mais-isolada/</link><description>The previous executive's government lines proposed the construction of a 'city of sports', with the aim of enriching the development of the tourism and leisure industry through renowned sporting events.
Taking advantage of the rapid development of the game and tourism industry over many years, and consecutively hosted Asian Games, Lusophony games and ballrooms, Macau has infrastructures that can match other Asian and international cities, not lacking sports facilities with capacity to organize high quality events. In particular, game companies introduced a large amount of professionals and international networks, making Macau not only host the traditional major Macao awards and the World Women's Volleyball Championship, but also world -level table and billiard competitions. However, in intense regional competition, where the weaker are eliminated, the current development pace is still at risk of 'backwards if not advanced'.
Football, which I know well, is a clear example of this. Neighbor Hong Kong has inaugurated a stadium in Kai Tak and has already taken a rare opportunity: where Liverpool, Arsenal and Tottenham, from Premier League, and Serie A's AC Milan faced each other. The Saudi Arabia Super Cup will also be held in Kai Tak, and Manchester United visited Hong Kong again recently, with star Cristiano Ronaldo confirming that he will be present at the inauguration of his museum. The organizers promise series surprises, with airlines launching thematic planes to attract customers.
This lively summer in Hong Kong makes Macau's isolation even more evident.
Since the 2000s, Macau has successively invited the Portuguese team, Barcelona, ​​Manchester United and Chelsea to visit Macau, but due to administrative issues such as facilities management and financial investment, or lack of commercial forces connections, world -level soccer games have practically disappeared in recent years. The last one was the commemorative game of the return, before the pandemic, which was only attended by Southampton, which has now been relegated from the Premier League.
In April this year, a deputy revealed that the Cristiano Ronaldo Museum had been initially thought to be established in Macau, but was refused by one of the game companies, criticizing the ineffectiveness of government supervision for wasting a golden opportunity.
At the time, the secretary for the economy and finance countered that "there is not only one football star in Portuguese -speaking countries, there are many beyond Cristiano Ronaldo."
In fact, Cristiano Ronaldo is far above the football star level, even those who do not see and do not understand football knows him. In addition, the visit of Cristiano Ronaldo, who was born in Portugal, Macao would have an invaluable value to consolidate friendly cooperation between China and Portugal and increase the international visibility of Macao. If some civil servants continue with their limited vision and unchanged government attitude, the way to become a “city of sport” will not go far.
Moreover, I always considered that the 'city of sports' must be closely linked to the development of local sport. The 'city of sports' should not only serve tourism and foreign visitors, and Macao athletes should not just be a scenario of the 'city of sports'.
Although this is a small territory, the popularization of mass sport over the years has made the density of the sports population quite high, with citizens participating in various sports competitions and sports enclosures to be always crowded. Although it has not been able to get rid of the curse of 'amateurism' over the years, which has made it difficult to develop elite sport, support for athletes is still directed to individual modalities. In addition, due to accumulated historical factors, many sports federations are still far from modern, professional and transparent, and there are often controversies on affiliated club relationships, national team management, financial support and selection mechanisms.
Many professional athletes continue to fight the current, which makes them even more valuable.
It is essential to promote the involvement of the population of Macao, so that local athletes and sports professionals have fair opportunities to participate in high -level sports activities, contacting the first line with international stars and sports teams, progressing together with the world, which should also be an important objective of the 'city of sports'.
 
Sulu I am
Former deputy to the Legislative Assembly of the</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:27:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Diogo Jota dies in a road accident in Spain</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/diogo-jota-morre-em-acidente-de-viacao-em-espanha/</link><description>Portuguese footballer Diogo Jota, 28, and 26 -year -old brother died yesterday morning in a road accident at A52 in Cernadilla, Zamora, Spain. According to the investigation to EFE, the two footballers died following a car in the car on the highway Rias Baja, in the sense of Benavente, for unknown reasons, around 00:40 hours. According to the same sources, the car, a Lamborghini, may have had a burst of a tire during overtaking, which made him get off the road and set fire to. The fire that resulted, which spread to the surrounding vegetation, was erased by the firefighters, with the Civil Guard and the emergency medical services that could only confirm the death of the two footballers.
Diogo Jota was a Liverpool player, an emblem he represented for five times and in which he shone, especially in the second season, still with German Jürgen Kloop, with 55 games and 21 goals scored. The striker, who was part of the offensive trio with Mo Salah, in other seasons also with Roberto Firmino and Sadio Mane, was in the conquest of an English alloy, a cup of England, two cups of the league and a Super Cup. In his career, the player, who made the formation in Gondomar and Paços de Ferreira, also represented FC Porto for a time, on loan from Atletico Madrid, and who returned to give him to Wolverhampton, in which he eventually signed and playing for three times. In the selection, the footballer, who had appetions for the goal, was also a reference, not always the starter, but with 49 internationalizations and two leagues of the nations in the curriculum. From the accident in Spain also resulted in the death of André Silva, brother of Diogo Jota, an extreme representing Penafiel of the II Football League.</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:31:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Pop Mart Macao Citywalk initiative has already attracted more than 150,000 visits</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/iniciativa-pop-mart-macao-citywalk-ja-atraiu-mais-de-150-mil-visitas/</link><description>The “Pop Mart Macao Citywalk” project, which placed characters from characters such as Baby Molly, Crybaby, Dimoo and Labubu in different parts of the city, has attracted about 153,000 visits and generated 680 million patacas in commercial transactions, the direction of Tourism Services (STD) yesterday indicated. This initiative began on June 6 and ends on September 21st.
These facilities were placed on the sidewalk of São Lázaro Church, Luís de Camões Square, Largo de Santo Agostinho and in the leisure zone of Rua do Pai Kok da Taipa.
In the first phase, there were also about 11,500 shares on social networks published in exchange for limited edition thematic postcards at the points of the activity, which due to the high search often exhausted within the first hour of each day service. The Pop Station base, located in the Ritz building in Senate Largo, received about 73,000 visitors during this period.
STD began, before the event's opening, a promotion through its official social networks, such as Wechat, Weibo, Douyin, XiaoHongShu, Tiktok, Facebook and Instagram, in collaboration with the official Pop Mart platform. Partnerships were held with influentors from the interior of China to create content, including live broadcasts and publications with short images and videos. In total, 190 publications were generated that helped viralize the theme “Pop Mart Macao Citywalk”, reaching more than 36 million online views.
Users can participate in sweepstakes by making face -to -face payments in Macao through Mapay Macau, Alipay from Macao, Alipay from China, Alipay of Hong Kong, True Money from Thailand and Touch ‘N Go Ewallet of Malaysia. For each transaction of value equal to or greater than that defined (100 Mop for Macao, Thailand and Malaysia, 100 HKD for Alipay from Hong Kong and 100 CNY for Alipay from China), a draw that is likely to grant limited memories of “Pop Mart Macao Citywalk”.</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:31:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Study says that play prevents psychological problems and cognitive decline in the elderly</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/estudo-diz-que-jogo-previne-problemas-psicologicos-e-declinio-cognitivo-nos-idosos/</link><description>Participation in the elderly game can help reduce loneliness and prevent cognitive decline in old age, a study published by the Macao Polytechnic University concluded. According to the investigation, the rate of participation in the game between the elderly population is “very high”, taking into account their search for entertainment and socialization. Academics argue that Macau game operators should develop low -risk games that are suitable for the elderly population in the future.
 
A study by academics from the Polytechnic University of Macao (UPM) and Sun Yat-Sen University revealed the positive impacts of the game on the lives of the elderly, arguing that participation in the game can maintain social connections and relieve, or even prevent, psychological problems and the cognitive decline of older people.
"The main positive effects include the increase in social support, the decrease in loneliness and depression, raising subjective well-being and life satisfaction, and the improvement of cognitive functioning," said the thesis entitled "Gambling Participation Among the Elderly: Current Status, Trends and Policies", published in Studies in the Game and World Tourism, UPM publication, in which Introduction is justified in local gaming casinos suitable for the elderly.
In the investigation, Zeng Zhonglu, professor at the PEDAGOGICAL AND SCIENTIFIC CENTER in the areas of UPM Game and Tourism and President of the Association for Studies on Pacific Asia Game, and Yuan Zheng, Professor Sun Yat-Sen University, approached the high and growing rate of participation in the elderly, taking into account the elderly population, namely in China, where there are increasingly children whose children already have children They left home and living alone, with a proportion that reached 57.9% in 2021.
The academics analyzed data from elderly players from various countries and regions and concluded that the rate of participation in people of people aged 55 or over “is very high”, ranging from a minimum of 27% and a maximum of 76%.
In the case of Macao, according to an inquiry from the University of Macao, the rate of participation of said age group was 34% in 2019 and decreased to 28% in 2022. In the interior of China, “existing studies show that board and card activities, such as mahjong, which often involve bets, are one of the preferred activities of the elderly,” he said.
 
Emotional needs
 
According to Zeng Zhonglu and Yuan Zheng, the elderly participate in game activities not to make money, but "to have fun, socialize and meet psychological needs."
The research explained that the elderly manifests the highest demand for entertainment and fun activities, since the elderly today, compared to the past, are more “healthy, active and rich,” they take less parental responsibilities and have more leisure time. "Due to physical and economic restrictions, bets are an affordable and convenient way for the elderly," he said.
On the other hand, investigators emphasize that the game also responds to the need to combat geriatrics. In detail that, because of the reduction of social contact after the reform, the elderly population is more vulnerable than the general population to depression, loneliness, dementia, Alzheimer's disease and other psychiatric syndromes. The game, in this case, serves as a resolution for the maintenance of social participation and cognitive health.
 
Response Measures in Macau
 
The article raises the question about the lack of investigation into the elderly game, particularly in mainland China, despite the high number of senior players.
In the opinion of Zeng Zhonglu and Yuan Zheng, there are at the same time risks associated with playing activities for the elderly, especially the problematic game. They point out that, although the proportion of the problematic game between the elderly is relatively low, the elderly have, at the same time, low risk tolerance and negative impact.
Academics argue that the government and society must support the participation of the elderly in games, with a view to satisfying their search for their social participation, but also "adopting effective measures to prevent gaming problems." According to the study, suitable games for the elderly should be "those who have lower risks, where the amount involved is relatively low and that favors interpersonal relationships and are easy to participate."
Thus, in Western countries, this type of bets mainly involves bingo games, horsepower races and bet machines, while inside China involves Mahjong, card games and possibly blocking machines.
“Game operators, including the mainstreaming operators on the continent and the casinos in Macau, should develop low -risk and highly social games that are best suited for the growing elderly population in order to satisfy the growing market demand,” the study authors point out, specifying games that require expertise or analysis and thinking, rather than purely lucky and lucky.</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:29:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Of the Cape Verdeans Évora in Macao resists only one</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/dos-cabo-verdianos-evora-em-macau-resiste-apenas-um/</link><description>There were once a dozen Évoras in Macao, where they arrived in the 1940s, but only Mario Évora resists, with the family repeating the migrations that mark both Cape Verde and the Macanese.
 
"We have been between eight and ten Évoras in Macau," Sports Medicine expert Humberto Évora told Lusa from Lisbon, where he has lived since he renovated.
The maternal grandparents of Humberto (the last of the family to be born in Cape Verde) and Mário (the first to be born in Macau) arrived in the east in the late 1940s, with five of the couple's six children.
A year later, the daughter who had stayed with her husband in Cape Verde came to Macau, already with baby Humberto. The initial plan was for two years, but the couple ended up three decades and have three more children: Mario, Rui and Maria Helena.
In 1971 it was the turn of Humberto and Mário to leave to study medicine in Lisbon, but not without a great fright linked to the colonial war that had lasted a decade ago. "As we went to the university we could postpone military inspection, but the papers did not come from Macao and we risk being considered refractory," said Humberto.
The situation resolved, but Mario admitted to Lusa the fear of the mobilization. "We had this persecution, we had to go through the year not to go with the sides in the war," he explained.
Upon arrival in Lisbon, “we were soon welcomed and integrated into the Cape Verdean student community,” said Humberto, at a time of student agitation and politics. "There were periods when it was almost daily, manifestations of students against the regime, the shock police enter the canteen inside and give some suckling," said Mario. Humberto admitted that "it was a shock, for those who came from Macau, where there was little political culture and the colonial war was seen as a struggle against terrorists."
In a summer, the young man, who was integrated into a Cape Verdean group of intervention music, left with a friend "to the overseas ride out of guitar on his back." “I always remember the first time in France, that I saw the colonial war described on the contrary on television, the struggle for the liberation of a colonial power of occupation,” said Humberto.
When the two brothers finished the medical course, the independence of Cape Verde, on July 5, 1975, led them to the root return. "There was a movement of many of our colleagues to contribute to a new country, which was beginning to take the first steps," said Mario, then a formed cardiologist.
Especially because, recalled Humberto, some of the friends of Lisbon had however become members of the Government of Cape Verde. "There was this possibility, but the return to Macao, a place where it had spent so long, was natural," he explained. “I was born in Cape Verde, I spent part of my life in Portugal, I grew up in Macao, I am also Macaense. I am a citizen of the world,” said Humberto.
From the Évora brothers, Rui, engineer, left before the transition to Cape Verde, where he even worked on the project of the Macao Hotel David Chow built on the beach, but was inaugurated.
The younger sister, Maria Helena, expert in documentary sciences who has even worked in the historical archive of Macau, is currently in the City Hall of Oeiras.
The children “are all out” between the United Kingdom, Cape Verde and Portugal, said Mario. "Now the world is smaller and it is going where there are opportunities," he said. Humberto also faces migrations "as a natural process, not only for Cape Verdeans, but even to the Macanese." Nothing that has prevented the two brothers from keeping their ties with the archipelago.
Humberto divides the time between Portugal and Cape Verde, and has been the official doctor of Cape Verdean sports for decades to the main international competitions.
Mario was one of the founders-and president for ten years-of the Macau-Cabo Green Friendship Association. "We had here Ildo Lobo, Tito Paris, and my cousin," said the cardiologist, before taking a break and adds, with a smile: "Cesaria Évora." Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:28:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Launched bombs</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/bombas-lancadas/</link><description>In recent weeks, Donald Trump has continued to consolidate all departments and agencies of executive branch, personal and functions under his control, with the ultimate goal of becoming the first autocratic ruler of the United States. All their actions were conducted with this goal in mind. In foreign policy, Trump happily refused to enter “endless wars,” as in Iraq and Afghanistan. However, he launched sudden massive demonstrations of the American military power, more clearly visible in his recent attack on Iran's nuclear facilities. On internally, Trump continued his campaign to repression of dissent and resistance, ignoring federal and state laws, denigrating the orders of judges, destroying the constitution and telling the republican members of the Legislative power, the congress, the congress, to do what they do what they do what they do what the congress, to do what the congress, to do what the congress, to do what the congress, to do what the congress, to do what send or be "eliminated in primary".
During the past few weeks, Ukraine has witnessed a very slow advance of the Russian forces along its eastern front, but at a huge cost to Russian soldiers, as their daily lows ascend to about 1000 soldiers or more. So far, Russia has claimed four Ukrainian provinces: Luhansk, Donetsk, Kherson and Zaprizhyya, but has no control over the complete territory of any Ukrainian province. On July 1, Russia said it had finally assumed the total control of one of these provinces, Luhansk. They also captured, for the first time, a village in a fifth region, Dnipropetrovsk. However, negotiations for a ceasefire remain just that-negotiations. Convinced that he is winning the war, Putin wants to postpone any ceasefire as much as possible. Reinforcing Putin's argument, Donald Trump has suspended any new war supplies orders essential to Ukraine, including the valuable Patriot Air Defense Systems to stop Russian ballistic missiles, artillery projectiles, Mobile Rocket Artillery and Ar-Room.
Once again, the world's attention is focused on the Middle East, diverting the attention of the war between Russia and Ukraine, as well as other world seizures.  A war between Iran and Israel has suddenly broke out on June 13, when Israel launched a surprise air strikes against important military and nuclear facilities throughout Iran. The attack occurred in the midst of a new Israeli terrestrial offensive in Gaza, as well as growing terrorist attacks by Israeli colonists against unarmed bouncing in the West Bank. busy.  In the early hours of the attack on Iran, the air, terrestrial, and intelligence forces murdered some of Iran's most graduated military scientists, nuclear scientists and politicians. Israel has also damaged or destroyed Iran's air defense systems, as well as some of the country's nuclear and military facilities. Quickly, Israel gained total airspace control over Iran and was able to launch attacks at ease. In retaliation, Iran launched hundreds of missiles and drones against Israelite cities and military facilities. Although causing widespread damage and fear among the local population, aircraft, missiles and the US Air defense system have helped Israel overthrow many missiles and drones, maintaining the number of dead and injured at least.
On June 22, US air and naval units launched a major air strike against Iran, using giant pounds of 30,000 pounds, the most powerful conventional bombs in the world. American pilots severely damaged the three nuclear facilities of Iran, Fordow, Natanz and Isfahan. Donald Trump stated, without concrete evidence, that they were "totally destroyed."  On June 24, Israel and Iran agreed with a ceasefire. Since then, the heavens over Iran have been calm. The debate continues about the effectiveness of the American air strike at the three premises. Were they destroyed or simply damaged? Does Iran still have enriched uranium and sufficient centrifuges to rebuild a nuclear weapon industry?  We may not know the answers to these questions for months.
The war between Israel, the United States and Iran, though short, had a deep impact on the Middle East. Israel is clearly the consistent military power, having quickly defeated a once formidable enemy. Before the war began, since the October 7 attack, Israel broke into Gaza, killing much of Hamas's military and political infrastructure and leadership. The Gaza War triggered a new conflict between Israel and Hezbollah in September 2024. Soon, Israel beheaded Hezbollah's political and military leadership before Israelites troops invaded and occupy the southern Lebanon. In late 2024, in the neighboring Syrian enemy, the opposition military forces captured the capital, Damascus, causing the sudden fall of Bashar Assad's brutal regime, ending a thirteen -year civil war. Israel and its close ally, the United States, militarily dominate the entire region, which allows them to significantly influence any proposals for ceasefire and peace that arise from these wars.
While the world's attention was focused on a potentially important war between the US and Israel against Iran, the public's attention was diverted not only from the war in Gaza, but also from the attacks of the settlers to the villagers and Palestinian houses. The war between Israel and Gaza began when militants led by Hamas attacked southern Israel on October 7, 2023, killing 1200 people, mostly civilians, and taking 251 hostages to Gaza. About 21 months later, more than 56 500 Palestinians are dead, 135,000 are injured - mostly civilians, including women and children. Virtually the entire population of 2.3 million people has been displaced and reduced to misery and hunger. Much of Gaza is in ruins. To avoid full hunger, Israel and the United States have created a food help distribution scheme in Gaza. However, Israeli soldiers were filmed by killing and injuring more than 500 people who desperately sought food in these centers. On June 30, the Israelite army used a 500 pound bomb (230 kg) by attacking a crowded coffee by killing dozens of civilians, which probably constitutes a war crime. On July 2, Donald Trump announced that Israel agreed with the terms of a 60-day ceasefire in Gaza. He warned Hamas to accept the deal while the organization can still. However, the terms of this ceasefire are not known to the public and remain obscure. Hamas has not yet responded to Trump's "final proposal". Insists that it must remain in Gaza in some way. Israel insists that all Hamas combatants must be disarmed and exiled. For his part, Israel never defined what Gaza would happen on the 'next day'. Would the territory remain under Israelite military occupation or return to Palestinical Military and Political Control? These questions remain undefined, along with other questions.
In the busy West Bank, tensions have increased since October 7. Increasingly, it has become an open season for Palestinians in West Bank, who have been killed by terrorist extremist Jews. Essentially, these settlers openly invade Palestinian lands, burning plantations such as olive trees, houses and even whole villages, killing Palestinians with total impunity, which are only defending their lands, houses and plantations. The number of dead among Palestinians in the West Bank continues to increase. Since October 2023, nearly 1000 Palestinians have been killed by vigilant settlers or Israelite troops, who often help settlers in their illegality.
Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu will be speculated with a ceasefire in Gaza, in very favorable terms to Israel. All hostages, alive and dead, will be released. An indefinite number of Palestinian prisoners will also be released. The remaining political and military leaders of Hamas will be brought to exile. Then Netanyahu will probably hold early elections, claiming that he released the hostages, defeated Hamas, neutralized Hezbollah and weakened Iran. This is the same Netanyahu whose policies to fund Hamas, paying little attention to the Israeli border wall and their Israelite defenders, they helped cause Hamas's attack. Once reelected, he will get the multiple criminal accusations against him to be withdrawn and will continue his policy of attaching to West Bank and Gaza while shifting the Palestinian population.</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:27:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Palestine II - Land of someone</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/palestina-ii-terra-de-alguem/</link><description>On October 7, 2023, almost two years ago, Hamas, considered in the West as a terrorist organization, in coordination with other insurgent Palestinian groups made a foray into “Israelite territory” near the Gaza Strip from which more than a thousand Israelites killed and about 240 people were taken hostage and taken to Gaza. This attack, immediately classified as a terrorist by more than forty countries, perpetrated by about 6,000 Palestinians and accompanied by a discharge of more than 4,000 Israel rockets, was the deadliest attack that Israel has suffered since its foundation in 1948.
The next day, Israel declared the state of war, something that has not happened since 1973, when also then Israel was attacked by surprise, which triggered the Yom Kippur war.
This Palestinian foray into the Israeli territory caused astonishment and surprise, as it would not go through anyone's minds that Hamas had the ability to carry out such a company, as the Gaza Strip had been completely isolated from the world since June 2007, when the same Hamas took over the Gaza and Israel Palestinian Enclave government as retaliation, as retaliation, is completely isolated the territory. Since then Gaza has been described by many international humanitarian organizations such as an Open-Air also, ie an open prison, where no one can enter or leave without Israeli, who built a wall around the territory and blocks its maritime and air space. By the way, as early as 2001, as a form of punishment for the second intifada, Gaza International Airport - Rebotted Yasser Arafat International Airport -, inaugurated in 1998 and built with European money, nine and a half of euros donated by Germany, Spain and Sweden, was completely destroyed leaving the inhabitants of Gaza isolated and unable to get out of the territory or receive direct aid by road Air.
Israel's response to the attacks of October 7, 2023 was immediate and brutal. The target of the Israelite army was, as usual, the civilian population. Under the pretext that insurgents camouflage themselves among the civilians, the Israelites made the civilian population of Gaza feel all their military power. The Israelite Defense Forces (IDF) launched massive air strikes on Gaza followed by an unprecedented invasion of land. The Gaza Strip was completely destroyed by air attacks that transformed the buildings where the civilian population lived into hills of broken concrete and twisted irons. The military forces that entered Gaza with tanks and armed cars were destroying the little left.
Over the years, Israel has developed a policy of total complaint intolerance. According to this attitude of the Israelites, Palestinians have to eat and silence. Under a suffocating occupation, to use the words of Antonio Guterres, who denies them the most basic human rights, the Palestinians do not even have the right to complain, any complaint is immediately answered with retaliation to the civilian population. For example, in the West Bank, Jewish settlers can throw Palestinians to kill without anything, and if the Palestinian family killed by Jewish settlers complain to the courts, their members are arrested for insurgency. There is no wonder that in such a scenario this attack unprecedented by Hamas has deserved as excessive response as we still watched from the Israeli state today.
The attack on innocent civilians, for most women, children, pregnant women, the elderly and diminished people, was accompanied by something absolutely unbelievable. The Israeli soldiers who broke into the Gaza Strip began publishing in their social networks images, videos and memes where they enjoyed the situation of the Palestinians, filming alongside destroyed houses and sometimes even alongside Palestinian corpses they had just killed.
One of the things that most caught attention was the language used in these videos in which Israelite soldiers referred to Palestinians as subhumans, the same thing that the Nazis said about Jews, argument, which was used to justify the racial laws of Nuremberg by which Germany citizens who had a certain percentage of Jewish blood could not be considered German, and This way, it can end in concentration camps.
Although in completely different contexts from any perspective, except from the human point of view, the attitude of the Israelite soldiers who landed for photographs and videos alongside the bodies of their victims differs greatly from that of Nazi soldiers - these monsters - many of which committed themselves after being forced to participate in the collective killing of Jews. In fact, while Israeli soldiers proudly published in their social networks what they did to the Palestinians, the Nazis tried to hide the many atrocities that committed against the Jews at all costs. That is why the extermination fields were all located in Reich's most remote fringes.
The creation of these extermination camps, such as Treblinka, sorbibor or the infamous Auschwitz-Zwei, better known as Auschwitz-Birkenau, was partly an answer that Himmler had to give a problem that German generals brought to him. In the first part of the war, the Jews were shot by German army soldiers in dumped ditches in the woods and forests. This brought serious mental health problems to many of the soldiers who participated in these killings, many of whom eventually committed suicide, others fled and when they were caught had to be shot by desertion, while others tried to find peace of mind at the bottom of the bottle. The generals made the Himmler know that this was destroying the morals of the soldiers and that no war could be won with demoralized soldiers. Another problem was that these soldiers later counted on the barbarities practiced on the hidden. Hence the need to create a more effective form of extermination and with less participation of the Germans. Thus were created the extermination fields (Vernichtungslager), which are often confused with the concentration camps (Konzentrationslager). In the extermination camps, although they were directed by Germans of the SS, the cleaning of the gas chambers and the cremation of the bodies was in charge of the Sonderkommandos, who were Jewish workers of the extermination camps.
The disproportionate Israeli military response launched, not directly on Hamas, but about the Gaza's civilian population, along with the videos and memes that Israeli soldiers published on social networks, caused disgust and stupor to people who watched television as the Palestinians were indiscriminately laigated in a military operation that was nothing more than an attempt to a vengeance of a population over a population helpless. The reaction of the world, as usual, was classified from anti -Semitism by the Israeli authorities who remained impaired to their killing of innocent civilians in Gaza. The Israelites even accused the states that showed concern about what was happening in Gaza as being with Hamas terrorists.
In the face of the brutality of the attacks and the complete ineffectiveness of any attempt by the international community to end this situation, UN Secretary General António Guterres, former Minister of Portugal, dared to say that the attacks of Hamas 'Did Not Happen in a Vacuum', noting that 'Palestinian people have been subject to 56 years of suffocating occupation'. Guterres went further by stating that although 'the complaints of the Palestinian people cannot justify the terrible attacks of Hamas, these terrible attacks of Hamas cannot justify the terrible collective punishment of the Palestinian people'. Of course, as in the habit, the Israelites were offended and required the dismissal of the United Nations Secretary General.
Although António Guterres described the suffocating occupation of Palestinians as having lasted 56 years, the truth is that the Calvary of these people began when the Jews decided to occupy the land that did not belong to them, helped by the English who never lost their colonialist habit of disposing of the land that does not belong to them.
When the Jews began to reach Palestine in the late nineteenth century, Palestine was not anyone's land, its inhabitants had lived there by more than two millennia. As we will see, today's Palestinians are the direct descendants of the peoples who inhabited Palestine since the third millennium BC.
 
The political chess of British colonialism
All of this begins at the end of the nineteenth century when, animated by Zionist ideology, began to reach successive Jewish vacancies from different parts of the western world with the aim of fixing themselves in the territory, then part of the Ottoman Empire.
These emigration vacancies are known as ʿaliyâ. Three major Jewish migratory movements for Palestine are considered; The first, between 1882 and 1903, established the first Jewish colonates. The second ʿAliyan runs between 1904 and 1914, the year of the beginning of World War I and the third and most important runs between 1920 and 1948, the year of the Unilateral Declaration of Independence of the Modern State of Israel.
Until 1948, Palestine was inhabited almost exclusively by Muslims since, in 634, after the defeat of the Byzantines in the battle of Ajunadaim, this region was conquered by the Arabs. Three years later, in 637, the city of Jerusalem would fall under Islamic rule.
Prior to the conquest by Muslims, Palestine was part of the East Roman Empire, also known as the Byzantine Empire. From the conquest from 634 to 1920, Palestine has always been under Muslim rule, except from 1099 to 1187, when the Crusaders managed to conquer Jerusalem to the Moors and establish the Christian kingdom of Jerusalem.
Back in Muslim dominance in 1187 by the hand of Saladin, which inaugurates the period and the Dynasty Aiúbida, Palestine was conquered by the Turks in 1516 and became another territory of the vast Ottoman empire.
In World War I, the Ottoman Turks fought on the wrong side and came out defeated. Thus, since 1916, but especially since the capitulation of Türkiye, the Arab populations, which for centuries were under the tyrannical yoke of the Turks, began to rebel. This Arab rebellion was assisted material and intellectually by the English and the French who had territorial interests in the area.
At the end of the war, Syria, which at the time encompassed the territories now known as Syria, Lebanon, Jordan, and Palestine was divided into two protectors, one to the north, composed of Syria and Lebanon delivered to the French, and the then Transjantian, who were part of the British Protective, which lasted from 1920 to 1946. He only obtained the Nations League Protectorate in 1922, but since long before the English supported the Arab revolt against the Turks, hoping to obtain territories in the region to attach to their empire.
In 1917, the United Kingdom decided to support the creation of a Jewish state in Palestine what was formalized in the now known as Balfour statement, a letter from Arthur Balfour, Foreign Minister of Great Britain, addressed to Zionist leader Lord Rothschild on November 2, 1917.
The decision to support the creation of a 'national home to the Jewish people', as Arthur Balfour says in his estate, it was nothing more than a political cynicism operation to endowed the region to create the necessary conditions so that the English could satisfy their colonial interests, as Palestine was a strategic region between Egypt, with its Suez channel and the channel of Suez and Mesopotamia, both under British influence. In fact, the creation of the State of Iraq and its establishment as a monarchy, until its fall in 1958, was no more than the attempt to control the oil resources that abounded in the region. In fact, the two kings that Iraq had were but puppets in the hands of the English.
All of this is today of general knowledge because, however, the 1916 secret Sykes-Picot agreement between England and France to divide the Middle East with each other after World War I was no longer a secret.
In addition, the correspondence exchanged in the crucial years of 1915 and 1916 between Sharif Hussein Ibn Ali, Arab leader and Guardian of Saints of Mecca, and Sir Henry McMahon, the high British Commissioner in Egypt during World War I, demonstrate how the English were playing double play. At the same time they promised to help the Arabs so that they could independent themselves from the Turks, what the English expected is that the revolt against the Ottoman would lead the midfielder to complete chaos, chaos for which England, and possibly France, would be the best solution.
Support for the Jews, also secret at first, went against the promises made to the Arabs, but also it was intended to focus the region during and after the war. Moreover, the economic power of the Jews, and the influence that Questes had in the state-of-Unideal political class was also one of the reasons that led the English to promise them a homeland in Palestine.
Palestine has been since World War I have nothing more than a board of political-economic chess. In this game of cats and rats, at no time did the interests of local populations take into account. The situation of the Palestinians today is still a consequence of unbridled British colonialism that, for example, in North Africa designed borders with ruler and square without taking into account what this would represent for the indigenous populations that would become divided by the English lines in the libraries of their country houses.
 
The wars that created Israel
The First War in which Medie Israel was involved was the so -called War of Independence. After the end of the British Palestinian protective, the United Nations proposed the sharing of the Palestinian territory between Jews and Arabs based on the population distribution of the two communities. The Jews accepted, but the Arab countries rejected the proposal by claiming that that land belonged to the Arabs who lived there for centuries.
As it was not reached agreement, Israel decreed its independence unilaterally on May 14, 1948. The next day, an Arab countries formed by Egypt, Jordan, Syria, Lebanon and Iraq declared war on the newborn state of Israel. The War of Independence, also called the Israelo-Arab war ends officially on July 20, 1949, when Syria, the last country of the Arab coalition to do so, signs the Armistice with Israel.
As a result of this First War, Israel increased its territory and the first 750,000 Palestinians were displaced from their lands and transferred to refugee camps in Jordan and Lebanon where their descendants (over) live today.
In 1956, Israel attacked together with the United Kingdom and France the Egypt of Nasser after he nationalized the Suez Canal, hitherto controlled by the British and the French. Israel then invaded the Sinai Peninsula where he faced Palestinian militants. The Suez crisis, as it became known, was an idea poorly conceived by British Prime Minister Anthony Eden, and that in the end he would lead him to resign from office in 1957.
The Egyptians were able to resist the attacks of the English and, in the end, under pressure from the United States and the Soviet Union, the English and French had to retire from Egypt and Israel had to abandon the Sinai Peninsula. It was here that it was began to glimpse how dependent on the goods of the United States Israel is, for the Israelites did not want to abandon Sinai.
Tension in the region continued to increase and in 1967, Egypt and Syria mobilized their troops at the borders with Israel. This maneuver could only be another form of harassment, but Israel decided to prevent both countries preventively and Jordan in June 1967. The war that lasted only six days was the result of the invasion of the West Bank and East Jerusalem, which at the time were under Jordan administration, the Gaza Strip, thus occupying the entire territory of Palestine that from 1920 to 1946 was under the British protective and that should be divided between Jews and Arabs. This is where we begin the situation we are in today. Israel occupied all Palestinian territories under Jordan and Egyptian administration.
After the War of Independence in 1948, when Israel occupied a significant part of the territory that the United Nations attributed to the Arabs, Egypt was overwhelmed by the Gaza Strip and the West Bank was occupied by Jordan that eventually attached these territories in 1950. In addition to Gaza and the West Bank in 1967, Israel occupied the entire Sinai peninsula and Syrian Golhan hills, a strategic water source for the territorial interests of the Jews.
The six-day war that Israel launched against its neighbors completely altered the balance of forces in the region and the consequences are still felt today, as we recently had the opportunity to see in unilateral attacks and for no apparent reason against Iran. The other countries in the region could do absolutely nothing.
In 1973 Israel was last attacked. Egypt and Syria, in an attempt to recover the territories that Israel had occupied in the war of 67, attacked the Jewish state by surprise during the Yom Kippur religious holiday, hoping to catch the unprepared Israelites. Still, Israel managed to defend himself and this war ended in a military impasse because the territorial gains that Syria and Egypt succeeded at first were lost as Israel defended themselves.
This defeat led to Camp David's agreement in 1978, for which Israel would return the Sinai Peninsula in exchange for recognition by the Egypt of the State of Israel.
In 1982, Israel attacked Lebanon and occupied part of its territory until 2000, again attacking the south of this country, where the antique cities of Tire and Sidon, among others, were completely destroyed with the consequent loss of thousands of lives among the civilian population.
What we now watch with horror today is not after all new, it is just another chapter of the bloodthirsty history of Israel, a state that does not have a century of existence has.</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:27:26</pubDate></item><item><title>China's GDP growth is a focus on game recipes in Macao, says brokerage</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/crescimento-do-pib-da-china-e-fulcral-para-as-receitas-de-jogo-em-macau-diz-corretora/</link><description>More than investing in the non-game segment, China's growth growth is a key factor for Macau's game recipes to be sustainable in the future. The opinion was transmitted by the Investment Bank CBRE Capital Advisors in a report where it also says that it is not expected that the growth of revenues of the casinos operating in Macao remains above 15%.
 
The sustainability of the growth of Macao game recipes is linked to increasing the GDP in the interior of China, defends the Capital Advisors CBRE in a report quoted by the Gggrasia portal. According to the broker, the increase in revenues of the casinos operating in the region last month was due to stimuli caused by improving the economy in the country and not so much to non-game investments, such as the concerts of Jacky Cheung and G-Dragon, for example.
It is recalled that, according to data from the Directorate of Inspection and Coordination of Games (DICJ) released on Tuesday, in June, the game industry in Macao obtained revenues of 21 billion patacas, plus 19% compared to June last year. Looking at the game recipes since the beginning of the year, the casinos made 118.7 billion of patacas in the first half. This value reflects an increase of 4.4% compared to the first six months of 2024.
The CBRE stresses that it is not expected that the growth of game revenues will remain above the 15%mark, but emphasizes that "there is potential for Macao to return to consistent growth levels above the GDP [from the interior of China]," which is by far the main source of visitors in Macao. “The sustainability of the growth of game revenues will depend on the country's economic conditions,” observe the broker's analysts. In 2024, China's GDP registered an annual increase of about 5%. For 2025, the international monetary fund expects growth of almost 4%.
Regarding the Chinese economy, CBRE points out that continuous injections of liquidity in Banco Popular da China, retail sales and action market gains have helped raise consumer confidence and consumption, "what should be reverberated in Macao."
The banking institution also recalls that China "could intensify stimulus measures to boost domestic consumption in order to better face trade war between the US and China." Given this, the CBRE report says it is "optimistic with signs of economic stability in China and the acceleration of gross game recipes in Macao in recent months."
In the first budget for this year, the MSAR authorities predicted that gross casinos revenues rise to 240 billion patacas in 2025. However, the beginning of the year was short of expectations and, therefore, the government presented a review to the budget in which it reduces expectations and now foresees 228 billion game revenues.</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:27:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Academic de Macao debuts at the Chinese delegation at a meeting of the United Nations Commission</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/academica-de-macau-estreia-se-na-delegacao-chinesa-em-reuniao-da-comissao-das-nacoes-unidas/</link><description>Professor XU Yi, from Macao, was the first time the Chinese delegation who attended the United Nations Commission meeting for the peaceful use of the outer space. The event took place from June 25 to July 2.
 
The city of Vienna, Austria, was the stage chosen for the 68th United Nations Commission Meeting for the Peaceful Use of Outdoor (Committee on the Peaceful Uses of Oter Space, or Copuos, in the English acronym) was held in Vienna, Austria, between June 25 and July 2.
Professor XU Yi, from the National Lunar and Planetary Science Laboratory of the University of Science and Technology of Macao (National Laboratory), participated in the conference as the first member of MSAR in the Chinese delegation, “actively participating in the discussion of topics such as space and water, space and sustainable development”, can be read in a statement from the Chinese press.
During the conference, the parallel event “One Humanity, Infinite Frontiers” (a humanity, infinite borders), organized by China, was presented at the UN headquarters in Vienna. The parallel event focused on the exhibition of the achievements of the “20 years of the Chinese Lunar Project” and presented, for the first time to the world, the samples of the face and the hidden side of the moon collected by the Chang'e 5 and Chang'e 6 missions.
Professor XU Yi, as a guest of the discussion panel, shared the scientific work and the experiences of the investigation of the National Space Research Laboratory, which actively participated in the Lunar Chang'e project with the support of the National Space Agency. Laboratory researchers acted as chief scientists from various Chang'e missions and, based on lunar data, obtained several scientific results, discovering new lunar minerals through the analysis of Chang'e samples, and the opportunity to study “in depth” the erosion environment and the back of the moon.
In recent years, the National Research Laboratory has also conducted cooperation in scientific research with Chang'e data with research institutions from various countries, including the United Kingdom, Germany and Italy.
"The participation of Macao Academics at the United Nations Commission Meeting for the outer space reflects the support of the central government in the scientific and technological development of the MSAR and demonstrates the success of the practice of the" a country, two systems "in Macau. Professor XU YI said that the National Research Laboratory will continue to actively support China's spatial exploration and contribute to Macao's force for the country's scientific and technological development," says the same communication.
The National Laboratory of Lunar and Planetary Science (Macao University of Science and Technology) was approved by the Ministry of Science and Technology of China and officially inaugurated in 2018, being the only national laboratory of lunar and planetary science in the country.</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:26:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Urban melody: the phenomenon of mopeds in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/melodia-urbana-o-fenomeno-dos-ciclomotores-em-macau/</link><description>Absorbed in the complex and frantic urban fabric of Macao, a peculiar symphony echoes through the narrow alleys and busy avenues: the constant tinnit of mopeds that serpent agiles between cars, surpass long dexterity of public transport and feint pedestrians.
In this small region marked by contrasts and diversity, the bikes go beyond simple and economical transport vehicles, they represent a vital element of urban life, weaving in the city mesh inextricably.
The popularity of mopeds in China, in particular in Macao, can be attributed to a variety of factors. Accessibility and low maintenance cost make them an economic choice, especially in this region where space is increasingly disputed. In addition, the agility and ease of maneuvers make them ideal for navigating congested and narrow streets of the region, ensuring a rapid and efficient alternative to the dense and agitated urban environment.
Macao stands out in the security factor in relation to the countries of the Southwest Asia, where they see complete families to circulate in a single moped; Father in charge, mother in the rear and flock of children in sandwich. In Macao the scooters are limited to the transport of two people, and the use of helmet is mandatory.
Around four past four in the afternoon, finished another school day, it is the grandparents who traditionally assume the task of transporting grandchildren. In minutes the streets are filled with generational motorcycles: grandfather in front, grandson behind, embraced by a belt that (we pray) guarantees the child's stability and safety.
I admit that, still these days and with more than a decade of daily driving practice on the streets of the region, the tactic I use is quite defensive: when I am the first traffic light and, in a matter of seconds, I am surrounded by dozens of impatient mopeds, I breathe the signal to go to green and make a waiting compass so that the agiles and impatient canning can avoid a touch that provokes an apparent domino effect.
Despite the challenges and known dangers that accompany the use of mopeds in a very busy urban context, the swarm of scooters in Macau persists as an essential part of local landscape and culture. As notes in an urban melody, the bikes make up a dynamic narrative of mobility, freedom and self -expression, reinforcing the intense rhythm of the Macao region.</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:27:27</pubDate></item><item><title>SME association expects business growth in the second half</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/associacao-de-pme-espera-crescimento-de-negocios-no-segundo-semestre/</link><description>Sunny IP, president of the Macao Small and Medium -sized Development Alliance, provides for the business environment to “stabilize gradually” or even register a growth in the second half of the year, due to the continuous increase in the number of tourists in Macao, as well as the policies favorable to the interior of China for the territory.
Speaking to the newspaper or Mun, the association's representative, although optimistic, emphasized the need for small and medium enterprises to respond to changes in customer consumption habits, among other circumstances, exploit new products and create business conditions, “helping to promote industry development”.
"The market is becoming more stable. For example, the food and beverage sector is growing, but consumer preferences are constantly changing, consumers want healthy yet economic products, so companies have to make corresponding adjustments," he said.
Sunny IP has pushed concern about the business breakdown of local supermarkets following the popularity of online stores and the competition of traders in the interior of China, believing that the closure of supermarkets is a “individual case”, which is due to the change of commercial strategies and the introduction of business automation systems
Regarding the retrospective of the performance of the first half of this year, Sunny IP pointed out that there were different evolutions in various sectors in Macao, with trade in the tourist zones increased, while trade in physical stores in residential neighborhoods decreased, being the impact due to the influence of online sales.
Sunny IP noted that local traders can take as reference the operating strategies of the interior of China's e -commerce companies, highlighting the promotion and packaging of products, organizing promotional activities to attract consumer attention.</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:31:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Open registrations for entry at the Job Fair for Youth 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/abertas-inscricoes-para-a-entrada-na-feira-de-emprego-para-jovens-2025/</link><description>Registration is now open for the 2025 Youth Job Fair, to be held on the 18th and 19th of this month at the Macao Tower Convention and Entertainment Center. One of the news this year includes a professional assessment online test, now available on the Service Directorate page for Labor Affairs (DSAL), whose results will later be interpreted by instructors present at the fair.
 
This year's edition of the Young Employment Fair will take place on July 18 and 19, on the 4th floor of the Macao Tower Convention and Entertainment Center. The markings for the event, which will provide more than 1,000 job offers to newly graded young people in the territory, can be made from today and until July 16 on the thematic website created by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL).
Under the theme “Career Guidance, Alignment with the Future”, the event has the participation of more than 50 companies from different sectors, including Tourism, Hospitality, Information Technology and Bank and Finance. In total, more than 1,000 employment offers will be made available that cover various functions, such as that of seller for the convention and exhibition sector, VIP Service Agent, Specialist in Integrated Balcons Services or System Analysis Personnel, among others.
The initiative will also feature parallel activities such as sharing sessions and informative tents. In a statement released yesterday, Dsal reveals that “elite young people of the four main industries of Macao” - 'Big Health' of traditional Chinese medicine conventions, modern finances and cutting -edge technologies - will share their professional experiences with those present, “so that young people can gain valuable experiences” and feel encouraged to “leave the comfort zone and persecute their professional dream”.
At the same time, public services and companies from Macao and the Hengqin Cooperation Zone will set up 'roadshows' and on -site exposure tents so that, “through interactive exchange,” young people remain updated on the information of the sects of both territories and know “the current market needs and development trends”.
The big news this year is, however, the “The Self-Directed Search”, a initiative released on June 17 and will continue to be available online until July 19, the last day of the fair. This is a vocational evaluation test, designed by American psychologist John Holland, in which the end result produces a list of careers or study areas that align with the personality type and the interests of the participant.
DSAL advises young people who submit to the test to “keep the results and perform a prior marking for individual 'on -site' individual counseling services, where instructors will interpret the test results, support the analysis of personal advantages and provide proper professional guidance”. The objective, the organization refers, is to “support young people in exploring their professional potential and choosing a proper job”.
The event will have two entry times a day: one in the morning (between 11:00 and 13:00) and another in the afternoon (from 14:30 to 19:00, the last entry at 18:30). After the 'online' registration, interested parties will receive a mobile phone message that will work as 'check-in' for entering the site, where they should attend the Curriculum Vitae (CV) and the resident identity ticket (BIR).
The Dsal Fair is held in collaboration with the Association of the New Chinese Youth of Macao and the support of the General Association of Students Chong Wa de Macao and the Macau Youth Development Service Center.</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:26:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Running to the High House of Parliament in a new test to the government of Japan</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/arranca-corrida-a-camara-alta-do-parlamento-em-novo-teste-ao-governo-do-japao/</link><description>The July 20 election campaign for the Japan Alta House began yesterday, in a new test for the party supporting the minority government of the country's Prime Minister Shigero Ishiba.
 
The Liberal Democratic Party (LDP) pointed out as its objective to maintain the control of the Chamber of Counselors, which holds the coalition partner, Komeito, since the previous election, held in 2022. For this, the coalition needs to win at least 50 of the 125 places in these elections for the upper chamber, consisting of 248 members.
The campaign represents a new test for Ishiba, which rules a minority after losing control of the Baixa do Parliament, the Chamber of Representatives, in the early general elections of October.
This result forced the LDP, which widely dominated Japanese politics after World War II, to make opposition concessions, led by the Japan Democratic Party (CDP) of former Prime Minister Yoshihiko Noda.
A total of 519 candidates competes for elections, according to NHK public broadcaster, to fill the 125 seats. There are 152 women, almost 30% of the total, the second largest percentage in history, after the last elections. Of the total, 74 seats will be determined by electoral circle and the remaining 50 by proportional representation.
In Japan, half of the members of the House of Counselors elected every three years for a six -year term.
On June 22, LDP won a record number of places at the Tokyo City Hall Assembly, the most important regional elections in the country, usually considered as a national barometer.
Ishiba's mandate may be at stake if the opposition, although fragmented, conquers the majority of the Chamber of Counselors, namely through the Democratic Party for the People (Centro-Law) and the populist party of far right out.
Public discontent with the increase in cost of living, which salary increases could not resolve, is at the center of the campaign, with Ishiba promising to distribute 20 thousand yen (about 120 euros) to each resident.
The opposition has pressured the government to temporarily reduce or suspend consumption tax (equivalent to VAT in Portugal). The price of rice, which has doubled in the last 12 months, is one of the main concerns of the Japanese.
The Ishiba government has also been plunged into commercial negotiations with the United States of America, which threaten to impose tariffs on imports from the Asian country.
Ishiba, whose party traditionally has the support of agricultural groups and rural voters, promised not to sacrifice the agricultural sector, despite the US pressure for greater access to its agricultural products to the Japanese market. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:32:06</pubDate></item><item><title>ILCM: a new cycle after a nearly in May</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/ilcm-um-novo-ciclo-apos-um-quase-fim-em-maio/</link><description>After the Covid-19 pandemic and with the return of many foreigners to their home lands, the International Ladies Club of Macau was almost over in May. Businesswoman Sophie Law has again assumed the presidency and seeks to give her a new breath.
 
“Due to lack of interest, we are unfortunately forced to consider closing ILCM, which has existed since 1982,” read in a post published on the official Facebook page of the International Ladies Club of Macau on May 23rd. Initially created to welcome women from foreign employees hired to work at the Macao Telecommunications Company (CTM), the Association brings together members of different origins and has been responsible for thousands of donations to local charities.
This is the third time Sophie Lei assumes the position. “The first was in 2011 and then in 2017,” he says, explaining that his relationship with ILCM is already long. “I joined a first event in 1989. I was invited to one of the lunches at Macau Jockey Club at that time,” he recalls. He later became a member of the Association and, as a businesswoman, sponsored some of the draw awards. From 2008, he became more involved in the club, until, in 2011, he became president, for the first time. “I was invited to the Executive Committee, I took account of corporate relations, public relations and the relationship with the sponsors,” he says.
 
The club's objectives: from the beginning to the present day
 
The club began to work at the hands of Brenda Histed, an English woman whose husband was hired to work at CTM. As Sophie recalls, the initial goal was to create a support network for women of foreign professionals hired to work in the territory, without family and friends. "It was good to have a group of women, in similar situations, that could join and share information, know new environments and build some kind of friendship," he says. Gradually, considering that its husbands had professional positions of great responsibility, the club also became an important instrument “to give some return to society”, organizing events to raise funds for some charity organizations.
Sophie was the first Chinese president, born in Macau. “I know the local residents, I know the Macanese and I am friends with the expatriates who are working in different areas of Macao,” he says. Thus seeking to join everyone, the businesswoman considers that ILCM has an important mission "to gather people." And, on the one hand, for expatriates, it becomes an escape for those who want to learn more about Macao culture, for places helps to become more international, gaining friends from different countries. “Before, in Macao, they were all so closed in themselves that it was hard to have a club with all the nationalities,” he says.
For his current term, Sophie has some goals, but the main thing is to increase the number of associates. “When I took over the club, we had 42 members, but over the next six months I want to go up to 120,” he says. At the same time, there are some activities that want to resume, including social meetings every month and meeting among members, as well as Melbourne Cup Brunch, which is expected to take place in November. It is also in view of the organization of a Christmas bazaar and visits to potential patrons, along with the promotion of events in collaboration with other associations and local organizations or companies. Finally, the list of plans also includes a possible group for hobbies for members.
The ups and downs in the composition of ILCM
 
Since 1982 the ILCM associate numbers have not been lowered so much. So, in May, the warning came up and almost thought about an end. “With COVID-19, things have changed and everything went,” recalls Sophie Law. “People left Macau and were also very frustrated with the situation and more focused on their family, work and career,” he explains. The businesswoman, however, did not give up and offered to take over the presidency, also because, two years after the pandemic, the circumstances in Macau changed. “There are a lot of people to return to the House of Dancing Water and many expatriates are returning to the territory, there are new hotels to open and many good restaurants,” he says. “Until 2023, it was very difficult for the executive committee and there were only three people,” he says. Now Sophie has gathered 11 people again to join the Executive Committee. “I have 11 people really committed to helping me in the next 24 months,” he says. They are Portuguese, Canadian, Chinese and local, with different professions. They are entrepreneurs, lawyers, secretaries and accountants. “It's a good combination of committed, talented and intelligent people with a lot of experience,” he says.
To perform the presidency function for the third time, he says that it is now his last and assumes a very specific goal: to pass the testimony. “I have a very talented vice president, who is young and desired to help,” he says, referring to Nicole Massa Helm, the owner of Lax Cafe and Cuppacoffee. "It was not born in Macao, but it has spent much of your life in the territory, speaks English and Chinese and your children are growing," he says.
Therefore, as president, Sophie intends to lead and look for capable people who can continue to grow. “I want to spend my experience and my contacts,” he says. Now already with more than 60 members, including previous presidents and founding members, the current president wants to climb the number of members.
 
Always present
 
Eileen Stow is a known figure of the local and international community of the territory. Present almost since the start of ILCM, the president of the American Chamber of Commerce, which is also the Executive Director of Lord Stow’s Egg Tarts, has been, from the beginning, involved in the club. "It's an important and still important, but things have changed over the years," he says, explaining that "what needed to be, when the club has opened, has changed, however, and we have to adapt." At first, he recalls, it was a more club to create some cohesion among CTM employees. “At that time [1982], there was no supermarket, women went to Chinese stores and recognized nothing,” he says, explaining that adaptation to the international community was more difficult.
Brenda Histed then started with ILCM, always with the support of Eileen Stow's brother Andrew Stow, responsible for the creation of the famous Portuguese -style eggs. “He helped her a lot in the orphanage,” he reveals. “He was a person who worried a lot about the community,” he says, adding that his position as an industrial pharmacist was also crucial to helping young people from the Salesians orphanage, just in the start at ILCM.
On his side, Eileen began by helping to organize some dances, support and patronage. Regarding the club's activities, the businesswoman highlights philanthropic actions with needy individuals or local associations. “There are a lot of people depending on it,” he reveals. For example, since Andrew Stow's death in 2006, ILCM has been working on creating a fund established in its memory to help some students who have grown in the cradle of hope. "Most kids coming from there when they arrive at university need some extra financial aid," he says. Over the years, they have helped six young people complete their studies. "We had one, which was a huge commitment, because we helped him from the age of 11 to the UK degree," he says, adding that the goal is to ensure that they do not need to find part-time work. "Otherwise, they wouldn't have time to study properly," he says.
Looking at the composition of ILCM, Eileen says it has always been quite mixed, with international and local members. "Ana Maria Wong and Sónia Palmer have been from the beginning at the club and were fundamental," he says, explaining: "Without them, ILCM would not have been able to have the real introduction to local things."
Sónia Palmer was the fourth president of ILCM, between 1986 and 1987, and recalls that time well. “They needed local residents to help them guide in Macao,” he reveals. Contacted to join the club, it eventually recruited some women from the territory to help. "We had meetings once a month, and when more people came together, it was no longer just a CTM club and became more international," he says. Subsequently, it began to grow, with a more important weight in helping charity organizations. “Many Portuguese have joined too,” he recalls. Among the main activities of the time, it is also remembered the preparation of gifts for the children, at Christmas.
Given the possibility of ILCM ends, Eileen praises Sophie's intervention, which avoided closing. "The club needs new energy and Sophie has brought young girls to the team. It has a great position of society, it is in charge of its own time and it is always necessary such a person for these voluntary associations," he says.
ILCM is a non-profit organization that has been promoting funds raising events for charities and social activities for its members since 1982. Among the associations that currently helps include the cradle of hope, the Macao toxicode dependent rehabilitation, the Macao Caritarian School of the Good Shepherd, the Caritas de Macao School and the University of University Support Program. Saint Joseph.</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:25:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing reviews support model to startups and restricts the role of local governments</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/pequim-reve-modelo-de-apoio-a-startups-e-restringe-papel-dos-governos-locais/</link><description>Beijing is reformulating the way technological development finances, moving away from the model based on local governments, to an approach in which financial institutions and state funds play a growing role, the Gavekal Dragonomics "Think Tank" indicated.
 
The change, which emerges in response to the growing budgetary restrictions of local authorities and the recognition of ineffective investments in the past, aims to ensure a more efficient capital allocation to the strategic areas of technological innovation, the reflection group pointed out in a report.
“We propose a change from a budgetary logic to a financial logic,” said the Deputy Minister of Science and Technology, Qiu Yong last May, alluding to the transition from direct subsidies to more structured financing mechanisms.
According to the analysis of Hong Kong's Gavekal Dragonomics, the retreat of national and private -private capital since 2020 has left public funds as the main funding of emerging technology -based companies.
However, local governments - responsible for a significant slice of these supports - have been criticized for practices that have fed waste, excess capacity and disordered competition in sectors such as semiconductors and electric vehicles.
Since the 3rd Plenary of the Communist Party, in mid -2024, Beijing has intensified efforts to control out -of -budget spending, reducing subsidies and tax benefits. Some companies were really urged to return supports received. In 2024, state subsidies paid to quoted companies fell 12%.
The Ministry of Finance has also begun a process of restructuring and closing of local financing platforms (LGFV), entities responsible for much of the debt of municipalities, often based on future revenues of land sales. In 2024, Beijing absorbed 12 billion yuan of debt of these entities.
LGFVs, which in recent years had expanded their performance to risk financing, invested 519 billion Yuan in 2023, which fell 35% by 2024. The trend is for a continuous reduction in their role.
The so -called “orientation funds” - also public instruments, but with a more focused mission and professionalized management - are being reinforced. The central government this year issued new guidelines that require higher approval for the creation of these funds and reinforce the scrutiny of the budgetary funds involved.
The strategy also involves mobilizing new sources of capital, especially funds created by state companies and financial institutions.
The constitution of a “National Risk Capital Fund” is underway, focusing on initial investments in small companies that develop technologies seen as strategic, Gavekal Dragonomics said. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:29:13</pubDate></item><item><title>USA and China close agreement that provides for sending rare land and end of restrictions</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/eua-e-china-fecham-acordo-que-preve-envio-de-terras-raras-e-fim-de-restricoes/</link><description>United States and China formalized a commercial understanding reached last month in Geneva, which includes Beijing's commitment to resume rare land exports, US Secretary of Trade, Howard Lutnick said.
 
According to Lutnick, the agreement was signed two days ago and consecrates the terms negotiated between Washington and Beijing throughout this year after successive mutual accusations of violation of previous agreements. "They will give us rare lands and, when they do, we will raise our contracted," he said in an interview with Bloomberg.
Siemens AG, one of the world's leading semiconductor design software suppliers, has been released by the United States Department of Commerce from the need to request licenses to operate in the Chinese market, according to the German company in a statement.
Export restrictions had been imposed in May, as part of a package of measures adopted by the United States in response to Chinese limitations to export of rare land minerals.
Siemens has confirmed that it has restored full access to its software and technology for Chinese customers. The other two main world companies in the Electronic Design Automation Software sector (EDA) - Cadence Design Systems Inc. and Synopsys Inc. - have not yet responded to requests for commenting on if they received similar communications, according to Bloomberg news agency. The United States Department of Trade has not commented either, the agency added.
The rare lands are crucial materials used in the production of wind turbines, aircraft, semiconductors and advanced technology. Under the trade agreement last week, Washington has pledged to authorize the shipping to China from chip design, ethane and jet engine design as long as Beijing is promising to accelerate the approval of critical mineral exports.
An White House official confirmed that the two countries agreed with the terms necessary to apply the Geneva Agreement. The China Embassy in Washington refused to comment, while the Chinese Foreign Ministry did not respond immediately.
The signing of the agreement generated optimism in markets: Asian shareholders and European future rates have advanced, and a global stock index has reached a new historical maximum.
Lutnick indicated that US President Donald Trump intends to conclude, until July 9, a series of ten commercial agreements with the main US partners. "We will close the ten main agreements, organize them by categories, and the other countries will align after that," he explained.
Although he did not specify which countries involved, Trump suggested yesterday that the US is close to an understanding with India. The main Japanese negotiator, Ryosi Akazawa, also has scheduled meetings in the US capital, and reiterated that Japan "cannot accept" 25% tariffs on cars.
Trump has already stated that, in the absence of agreements until July 9, he will send "letters" to each country with the proposed terms, applying unilateral tariffs - the so -called "reciprocal tariffs", which may reach up to 50%. Most of these measures were announced on April 2, but suspended for 90 days to allow negotiations.
The actual scope of the agreements remains uncertain, as commercial pacts usually require years of negotiations. An earlier agreement with the UK, for example, continues with pending issues, including tariffs on imported metals.
The agreement now reached with China does not address more sensitive topics, such as fentanyl trafficking or full access to US companies to the Chinese market.
The first round of negotiations in Geneva resulted in a rate reduction by both parties, but was quickly followed by mutual accusations of non -compliance. After new talks in London this month, negotiators announced an understanding, subject to the approval of Trump and Chinese President Xi Jinping.
According to Lutnick, the survey of US counterfeit depends on the effective arrival of the rare lands. This week, the US Department of Commerce has already authorized ethane loading to China, although its landing remains conditioned on specific authorization. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:29:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Proposal to recognize Hong Kong Homosexual Union “Very Conservative”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/proposta-para-reconhecer-uniao-homossexual-em-hong-kong-muito-conservadora/</link><description>The founder of the non-governmental organization Hong Kong Marriage Equality yesterday told Lusa that the government's proposal to recognize same-sex union is “very conservative” and establishes unfair conditions. "The orientation is very conservative and we have a great concern with one of the conditions, which would require couples to first register the union abroad. We believe this is unfair," said Jerome Yau, co -founder of Hong Kong Marriage Equality (marriage equality). Yau spoke on the day the Legislative Council discussed a legal framework, proposed by the executive, which intends to recognize certain rights to same -sex couples legally married abroad. "If the proposal becomes law, what will be done essentially is to create two classes of same -sex couples, those who got married outside and those who are not married," said Yau, making a strangeness of having to "pay to travel" and marry.
The proposal follows a 2023 decision of the Superior Court of the Territory, which considered that the government violated the Hong Kong Rights Law by not providing for a legal framework for same -sex couples, such as civil unions. The court has given two years to the elaboration of rules that guarantee the “fundamental rights” of couples. In yesterday's parliamentary discussion, lasting about an hour and a half, most interveners showed opposition to the proposal. "The liberal party has opposed the legalization of same-sex relationships. We defend the traditional family values," said Deputy Lee Chun-Kung. "Political parties will not support what they are doing," said Deputy Priscilla Leung, addressing the Secretary for Constitutional and Continental Affairs, Erick Tsang. “This was done in a hurry,” accused Doreen Kong from the Pro-Pequim field. Despite underlining opposition to homosexual marriage, Reverend Peter Douglas Koon defended the proposal and asked for respect for "humanity and also for civilization."</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:29:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Thailand prepares to have a third prime minister in three days</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/04/tailandia-prepara-se-para-ter-terceiro-primeiro-ministro-em-tres-dias/</link><description>The king of Thailand, Maha Vajiralongkorn, yesterday gave the remodeled government yesterday, with a new interim prime minister in charge, the third in three days after a new political crisis centered on the Shinawatra Dynasty.
New Interior Minister Phumtham Wechayachai, 71, is expected to replace Suriya Jungrunggreangkit, who took office as an interim prime minister after the court suspended first-minister Paetongtarn Shinawatra on Tuesday.
Wechayachai, a local politics veteran who participated in the Communist Student Movement in the 1970s, is considered a loyal lieutenant of Thaksin Shinawatra.
The former prime minister and father of Paetongtarn Shinawatra is a charismatic billionaire, who radically changed the face of Thai politics in the 2000s, with a style between liberalism and authoritarianism, which was worth both the damage of rural zones and the hatred of the banguecoque elites.
Also on Tuesday, a trial in which Thaksin Shinawatra has been accused of defaming the monarchy in a trial. Hours later, the Thailand Constitutional Court suspended his daughter, Paetongtarn Shinawatra, until the completion of a lawsuit, which began after the disclosure of a telephone call with an former Cambodian leader.
According to a statement, the judges unanimously voted to accept a petition, presented by about 30 conservative senators who accuse Shinawatra of "serious ethical violation."
In mid-June, a conversation with former Cambodia Prime Minister and current Senate president Hun Sen was released in which Paetongtarn Shinawatra questioned the role of a high Thai army commander in the context of a border conflict between the two countries.
Despite tensions with Cambodia, the position of Defense Minister, who has so far been in the hands of Phumtham Wechayachai, will be vacant in the new government.
The judges also approved for seven votes in favor and two against Shinawatra's suspension, which will be effective “until the [final] decision of the Constitutional Court”, which may take several weeks or even months, according to the statement.
The leader will assume the position of Minister of Culture in the new government, which will allow her to continue to accompany state matters.</description><pubDate>2025-07-04 03:32:04</pubDate></item></channel></rss>