<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/novo-subsidio-vai-beneficiar-15-mil-criancas/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>China wants to repress “malicious” behaviors on short video platforms</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/china-quer-reprimir-comportamentos-maliciosos-em-plataformas-de-videos-curtos/</link><description>China authorities yesterday launched a campaign to combat what they consider to be “malicious” behaviors on short video platforms, such as the Chinese version of Tiktok, including dramatization and imitation.
Cyberspace administration said the initiative aims to create a “light and ordained” digital environment through “identification and correction of irregular behaviors” on video platforms such as Douyin, the Chinese version of the International Application Tiktok, which is blocked in China.
The campaign will focus on trends such as the deliberate creation of false content, such as the “staging of pitiful situations”, the falsification of identity or the “invention of for-profit melodramatic stories”, sometimes under the pretext of helping vulnerable groups or relieving poverty, the local newspaper The Paper reported.
Authorities have instituted platforms to perform detailed inspections and take control measures also against the dissemination of false information through techniques such as manipulated editing, the distorted presentation of facts or the improper use of artificial intelligence tools.
The content that violates the rules of public decency, such as verbal or physical harassment in public spaces, as well as the videos that contain sexual insinuations, will also be controlled or showing provocative clothes that seek to “induce vulgar interactions,” the regulator pointed out.
Authorities will focus on practices aimed at attracting visualizations considered “inappropriate”, especially those aimed at vulnerable groups. Among these practices, the regulator cited too sensational titles and the publication of fictional evaluations of products or services.
Short video video applications in China, including Douyin and Kualou, have about a thousand million users, according to the country's Internet and Networks Information Center.
In recent years, regulators have launched various campaigns against behaviors such as ostentation of wealth, “false information”, “inappropriate content” and “wrong values” on these platforms, leading to the closing of thousands of accounts.
China is the country with the most internet users in the world, but at the same time one of the countries with the most control over content. Popular services in the rest of the world like Google, Facebook, Twitter and Youtube have been blocked in the country for several years.</description><pubDate>2025-04-16 03:18:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Academic defends “systematic review” of birth policies</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/academico-defende-revisao-sistematica-das-politicas-de-natalidade/</link><description>Chan Kin Sun, a public administration researcher, urged the government to proceed to a systematic review and organization of all birth policies, as relevant policies are "fragmented." "It is difficult for the public to realize which subsidies the government grants to children in different age phases," he said.
The issue was raised yesterday on the Macao Morning Forum program, on the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, which addressed the theme of the government lines. Several residents called the program to ask for further support measures in child care besides the measures now proposed by the government, including the new childhood assistance allowance. A resident complained about the exclusion of children who have completed three years in this policy and requested to extend the scope of recipients of this measure for children up to six years.
Chan Kin Sun considers that the childhood assistance subsidy is an important innovation in local birth policy and reflects greater government commitment to encourage residents to have children. However, it indicated that their policy is fragmented and the population may not feel encouraged.
Also professor at the University of Macao (one) also mentioned that the content on integration in national development and the development of Hengqin occupies a "relatively high proportion" in LAG, which was "rarely observed in the past". It understands that the highlight on hengqin in local policies must be related to the international situation Macau faces and the need to promote economic diversification.
On the other hand, in the program, some residents were concerned that the increase in the amount of various subsidies can lead to price increases. Kwan Fung, academic in the economy, warned of the government's need to analyze the effects of policies in the market in depth.
He also recalled that the job market in Macau is difficult at this time, so “young people should adapt to market changes” in relation to salary levels and types of employment, in order to survive in the market.
Regarding the government's plan to support young people to work in the Great Bay, the academic said they did not agree with the possibility of Macao to decline as Hengqin develops. "The idea of ​​the government is just to increase the possibilities of employment of young people," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-04-16 03:17:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Rogério Puga explores the traces of Macau in one of the oldest US museums</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/rogerio-puga-explora-os-vestigios-de-macau-num-dos-museus-mais-antigos-dos-eua/</link><description>The Portuguese bookstore receives today, around 6:30 pm, the presentation of the book “Representations of Macau at the Peabody Museum”, by author Rogério Miguel Puga. The session will be presented and moderate by Joshua Ehrich, professor at the Department of History of the University of Macao, with the support of the Faculty of Letters of the University of Macao and the Luso-Asian Studies Research Center.
The book, originally published in 2023 and divided into two volumes, consists of a study on Macao's representation in the Peabody Essex Museum collections, located in Salem, in the US state of Massachusetts. Through the analysis of paintings, furniture, fans, photographs, designs and engravings related to Macau, Rogério Puga draws a portrait of the territory in the nineteenth century as a strategic commercial filed between Portuguese, Chinese and a huge variety of foreign traders.
The investigation project was funded by the Macau Foundation - also editor of the work and responsible for its bilingual publication in Chinese and Portuguese - and by the museum itself, one of the oldest in the United States of America.
The author has written about the history of Macau since 2009, when he launched the project "The World of Euphemism: Representations of Macao in the Work of Austin Coates: City of Broken Promises As Historical Novel and Female BildungsRoman." In the same year, he leaned over “the English presence and the Anglo-Portuguese relations in Macao” between 1635 and 1793. Four years later, in 2013, the book was published in English by the Royal Asiatic Society organization, with the title “The British Presence in Macau”.
Prior to the publication of the first research work on the territory, Rogério Puga assumed an associate professor at the University of Macao between 2007 and 2009. He is currently an associate professor at the Department of Languages, Cultures and Modern Literatures at the Faculty of Social and Human Sciences of the New University of Lisbon (FCSH/Unl), where he obtained the degree of doctorate in Portuguese Anglo-Portuguese states.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>In 2024, almost half of Europe had a record annual temperatures</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/em-2024-quase-metade-da-europa-teve-temperaturas-anuais-recorde/</link><description>Almost half of Europe registered annual temperatures record in 2024 and 60% of the continent there were more days than the average with at least “strong thermal stress” due to heat, a report released yesterday. The joint report of the Climate Change Monitoring Service of the European Union for Observation of Earth Copernicus (C3S) and the World Meteorological Organization (WMO) says that the number of days with strong, very strong and extreme thermal stress was “the second highest ever registered”. This meant, on average, “almost a month of at least strong thermal stress and about 12 tropical nights,” says a copernicus statement about the state of the European climate 2024. There is talk of thermal stress when the ability of the human body to regulate its temperature is difficult by the environmental conditions, too hot or cold. Copernicus had already informed that by 2024, the hottest year of which there was a record for the first time the 1.5 ° C (degrees Celsius) of global warming above the pre-industrial level, the desirable limit provided for in the Paris Agreement to combat climate change. The sea surface temperature (TSM) in the European region was equally the highest recorded, 0.7 ° C above average, 1.2 ° C in the case of the Mediterranean, and the same occurred in European lakes.
Regarding extreme weather conditions, the study refers to forest fires in Portugal, which in September 2024 burned about 110,000 hectares (1,100 square kilometers) in a week, which represents about a quarter of Europe's annual total area in Europe. "It is estimated that 42,000 people have been affected by forest fires in Europe," the statement says. At the same time, it is decreasing the European zone with temperatures below zero and last year the area with less than 90 days of frost was the largest record, while the Glaciers of Scandinavia had the highest annual mass loss rate. It was the “greatest mass loss of any glacier region in the world,” says the information released by the Copernicus program.
The report also emphasizes that Western Europe has had one of the ten fastest years since 1950 and the continent generally suffered further flooding in 2024 than since 2013. Almost a third of the river network has surpassed at least the flood bed, with storms and floods caused at least 335 deaths and affected about 413,000 people. In September, hundreds of thousands of people in Germany, Poland, Austria, Hungary, Czech Republic, Slovakia, Romania and Italy suffered the consequences of storm Boris, which caused flooding, massive cuts of electricity, disturbances in transport networks and led to mass removal in some areas. At the end of the following month, torrential rainfall caused devastating floods and deaths in the Spanish province of Valencia and neighboring regions. The damage caused last year in Europe by extreme meteorological phenomena (13.4 billion in 2023), 85% of which attributed to floods were calculated by 18.2 billion.</description><pubDate>2025-04-16 03:17:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing alerts for political manipulation after capturing Chinese combatants</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/pequim-alerta-para-manipulacao-politica-apos-captura-de-combatentes-chineses/</link><description>China yesterday asked to avoid political manipulation and media propaganda in the case of its two citizens captured in Ukraine after fighting alongside the Russian troops, according to Kiev.
The two alleged Chinese fighters appeared at a press conference in the Ukrainian capital on Monday, where they said they wanted to be changed and appealed to their fellow citizens not to follow their example. "We urge the parties involved to have a fair view of China's objective and impartial position and abstain from political manipulation and media propaganda," Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jean reacted. “Chinese authorities are checking the information and circumstances” involving these two citizens, he added.
Ukraine announced the capture of the two Chinese last week. Beijing denied any involvement in his recruitment by Moscow.
Dressed on uniform and handcuffed, the two men described in Mandarin as they were captured during the fighting in the Donetsk region of Ukraine, after being enlisted in the Russian army through online ads. "I hope China can bring me back," said one of them, identified as 26 -year -old Zhang Renbo.
The other, identified as 33 -year -old Wang Guangjun, appealed to his “compatriots who want to participate in the war in Ukraine” so they don't.
The two Chinese citizens spoke alongside armed Ukrainian soldiers with a hidden face, so it was impossible to know if they were intervening free will. "The position of the Chinese government is clear and unambiguous," said Lin Jian. "We have already issued security warnings on several occasions, asking Chinese citizens to move away from the conflict zones (…) and, in particular, to avoid participating in the military operations of either party," he said.
China regularly appeals to peace conversations and respect for the territorial integrity of all countries, including Ukraine. But it never condemned Russia for the invasion and reinforced its economic, diplomatic and military relations with Moscow since the beginning of the Russian invasion in February 2022.</description><pubDate>2025-04-16 03:18:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief Executive concerned with possible budget deficit</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/chefe-do-executivo-preocupado-com-eventual-defice-orcamental/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai was cautious yesterday in relation to public revenues, noting that if casinos do not generate monthly revenues of at least 15 billion patacas, the government will have a budget deficit-and this situation is not unlikely, the executive chief warned.
 
It is possible that this year's budget register a deficit, warned yesterday Sam Hou Fai in the Legislative Assembly (AL), explaining that it is enough for the casinos to make less than 15 billion patacas per month.
According to the accounts of the chief executive, if the gross revenues of the game operators are 15 billion patacas per month, this will cause management to lose 20 billion revenues from game tax this year, "and then the government will have a budget deficit."
Clarifying the deputies about the report of the lines of government action (LAG) presented yesterday, Sam Hou Fai warned that this scenario is not unlikely. However, so far, game recipes have been maintained between 18 and 19 billion patacas per month.
Cumulatively, in the first quarter the game industry reached revenues of 57.6 billion, which falls short of government objectives. The authorities put the goal for all this year in the 240 billion Patacas, which would imply that, every quarter, casinos fit 60 billion patacas. It is also recalled that tax revenues from the game industry represent more than 80% of all MSAR tax revenues.
"We know there is a risk, we have to have preventive measures," he said in AL, noting that there is an "imbalance in the structure of the finance" of the MSAR. "Between 2020 and 2022 there was the closure of borders, will this in the future happen again? We can never predict the risk in Macao," he said.
Already on Monday, during the presentation of the lag, Sam Hou Fai had warned that this year will be marked by the “coexistence of opportunities and challenges”. "Worldwide, we are living times of turbulence and transformation," said Sam Hou Fai, adding: "We have witnessed, in recent years, the aggravation of unilateralism and protectionism, the insufficiency of dynamics prone to world economic growth as well as the increase of unforeseen events and uncertainties."
In the lag presentation, Sam Hou Fai had also stated that, since Macao's economy is strongly turned abroad, the region would not be immune to impacts. "We should not underestimate any threats and challenges, before, we must always be aware of the risks and a sense of warning, so that we are prepared to act against all potential threats," Sam said.
At that time, the boss had also advanced that the government would probably have to make a budget reinforcement because tax revenues from the game industry could fall short of expectations.</description><pubDate>2025-04-16 03:20:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Seoul will support semiconductor industry with another 4.2 billion euros</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/seul-vai-apoiar-industria-de-semicondutores-com-mais-42-mil-milhoes-de-euros/</link><description>The South Korean government announced yesterday that it provides to inject 4.2 billion euros into the semiconductor industry, citing the “growing uncertainty” that the key sector faces in the face of US tariffs. "An aggressive investment plan has been planned to help local companies face increasing challenges in the global race to semiconductors," the Ministry of South Korean finance in a statement said.
South Korea exports a large part of the goods it produces for the United States, and its crucial semiconductors and automobile sectors would suffer a lot from 25% tariffs that US President Donald Trump threatens to impose.
The world giants of Samsung and SK Hynix chips, among others, are South Korean companies. "In order to promote a dynamic ecosystem, led by the private sector, focused on innovation and semiconductor growth, the government will increase its investment in the 26 billion sector from Won [16 billion euros] to 33 billions from Won [20 billion euros]," the ministry said.
On April 2, Trump announced a series of new rates against major business partners, including a 25% tax on South Korean exports, before suspending application for 90 days.
Nevertheless, “tariffs aimed at specific sectors, such as semiconductors and pharmaceutical products, remain on the horizon,” insisted the South Korean Minister of Choi Sang-Mok finance. "This postponement offers a crucial opportunity window to reinforce the competitiveness of South Korean companies, in a context of intensifying global commercial tensions," he added.
The package includes financing of infrastructure and human resources development.
The aid plan is part of a proposal to review the South Korean state budget, which increases it by 12 billion of Won (7.4 billion euros), which is expected to vote in Parliament.
The announcement of the tariffs, presented by Trump as a solution to the US commercial deficit, shook the stock exchanges around the world and increased concerns about global growth.
Last year, the US commercial deficit with South Korea was 58.16 billion euros in goods. Last week, the South Korean government had already revealed an emergency aid plan of 1.76 billion euros to help car manufacturers face the crisis.</description><pubDate>2025-04-16 03:18:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Ung Vai Meng offers “energy and strength” to the Rui Cunha Foundation with design exhibition</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/ung-vai-meng-oferece-energia-e-forca-a-fundacao-rui-cunha-com-exposicao-de-desenho/</link><description>The show “Lines. Sensation” shows, until May 3, more than two dozen Guilherme Ung Vai Vai works, including pieces specially created about the 13th anniversary of the Rui Cunha Foundation. Speaking to the end, the artist assumes that he “wanted to do special work for this occasion,” resorting to the strength and movement of the human body as inspiration.
 
The Rui Cunha Foundation inaugurated yesterday a design exhibition entitled “Lines. Sensation”, by artist Guilherme Ung Vai Meng, who will remain evident to the public until May 3. The entrance is free.
The UNG Exhibition Vai Meng fits in the Rui Cunha Foundation anniversary celebrations, which at the end of this month completes 13 years of existence. “I wanted to do a special job for this occasion, which evoked energy and strength,” acknowledges the artist, in conversation with the end point.
The three works specifically designed for the event obey this theme, when reconciling human traits and silhouettes with “strong and energetic” water marks, materialized with paint from China, in black and green shades. Overlapping of these different techniques is unprecedented to the painter's work, which confesses “never” to have experienced them throughout the extensive career in the domain of the arts.
The project is divided into three parts, the most “important” being the one that brings together the three illustrations created for the show. Another section consists of an outdoor sketches selection, made between the Asian and European continents in Beijing, Macau, Portugal and Italy. “I love to travel on the street, travel, in the park… Wherever go, the pencil accompanies me,” he shares.
At the end, the painter explains that the third section was also born from the interest in spontaneous sketches - but this time oriented towards interior spaces. The third part is, therefore, dedicated to representations of dancers drawn in the dark of the theaters, from the point of view of the audience, while the artists act.
“In addition to drawing abroad, I also like to draw inside theaters. While the artists are on stage, in Chinese operas, I'm always drawing in the notebook without knowing what the result will be. When the show ends and the lights come on, I finally see what I drew a lot. exceptional display.
In all, including the three parts where the show is divided, there are 21 drawings that the public can enjoy at the Rui Cunha Foundation until the first Saturday of next May.
Creativity Stories
Today, at 6:30 pm, the exhibitor artist will give a lecture on painting and linear design in the Auditorium of the Rui Cunha Foundation Road. The event will be conducted in Chinese and also in Portuguese, a language in which Ung Vai Meng is fluent.
More than a study of this artistic technique, it is intended to streamline an intimate conversation about stories and episodes of the painter's career. "I want to share stories about my creativity, divided into various parts. The passion for drawing and the preference for traditional style at the beginning ... Then I studied in Portugal and started to like the technique of the watery." Over the years, and regardless of the techniques chosen to externalize their creativity, the great constant remains the linear painting. “The core of my work and the central value of all my drawings and paintings are the lines,” he says.
Ung Vai Meng is an unavoidable name of contemporary art in Macao. He attended the Arte Arco School of Art and Visual Communication Center in Portugal, following the attribution of a scholarship of the Macao Cultural Center. In 1999, he distinguished himself as the first director of the Macao Museum of Art, when the inauguration of the space, later assuming the role of president of the Cultural Institute (IC).
He is currently a guest professor and a mentor of doctorates at the University of Science and Technology of Macau (M.U.S.T.) and a member of the Macao and CAC Association of Fine Arts and CAC (Circle of Friends of Culture). His art has already reached various parts of the world, having participated in exhibitions in Macau, Hong Kong, Portugal, Singapore, Malaysia, South Korea, Philippines, Taiwan, Sweden, Japan and Poland.
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>China orders airlines to stop accepting Boeing deliveries</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/china-ordena-a-companhias-aereas-que-deixem-de-aceitar-entregas-da-boeing/</link><description>China has ordered its airlines to stop accepting Boeing aircraft deliveries. According to Bloomberg, Beijing also asked Chinese airlines to suspend "any equipment purchases and planes of aircraft to American companies."
 
China has ordered its airlines to stop accepting Boeing aircraft deliveries in the midst of a tariff war with the United States (USA), yesterday Bloomberg, which cites sources close to the process.
According to Bloomberg, Beijing also asked Chinese airlines to suspend "any equipment purchases and planes of aircraft to American companies."
The US imposed a total rate of 145% on Chinese imports, while Beijing increased rates on US products to 125%.
In recent weeks, some analysts have pointed out the US aviation sector as one of the most affected by the tariff war, especially Boeing.
The Arlington -based company, Virginia, will be able to see the price of its aircraft increase compared to its two main competitors, European Airbus and Commercial Aircraft Corporation of China (Comac), which seeks to gain land in the domestic market with state support.
Boeing was spared tariffs during the last episode of the trade war during the first presidency of Trump (2017-2021), but their sales to the Asian giant have been falling since 2019.
By 2022, it was expected that 25% of Boeing's international deliveries would go to China, but by 2023 the number dropped to 9%.
On the other hand, experts believe that the climb of the trade war will make American companies in all sectors see higher prices for parts and raw materials that buy to China, which means they will face the double challenge of relocating part of their production and losing competitiveness in the Chinese market.
The trade war triggered by Donald Trump intensified on April 2, with the announcement of "reciprocal tariffs" to his business partners, a measure that reversed a week later, compared to the fall of markets and increased US debt financing costs. But while softened his offensive against most countries, applying a widespread 10%tariff, he decided to increase rates on Chinese products because he responded with retaliation.
The US has decided to leave several Chinese technology products without tax, but Trump said on Sunday that semiconductors rates will be implemented "in the near future."
China has asked Washington to completely cancel tariffs, stating that "no one wins in a trade war" and that "protectionism has no way out." Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-16 03:18:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Traditional associations manifest support for lag</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/associacoes-tradicionais-manifestam-apoio-as-lag/</link><description>Traditional Chinese matrix associations in Macao applauded the governing lines report for “having responded to the expectations of society and residents”. Several local pro-seystem associations issued communications shortly after the lag lag was presented by the chief executive Sam Hou Fai to show support to the government.
The increase in pension for the elderly and the creation of the childhood assistance allowance are the most praised measures by the associations. "Although tax revenues were not as optimistic as expected, the government has progressed in the welfare area of ​​the population," said the Federation of Macao Workers Associations (Faom).
Lee Chong Cheng, who leads Faom, said LAG predicts precise help to needy groups and show governance centered on residents of the present governing team. He also pointed out that Faom, while “one of the main patriotic associations” in Macau, will give firm support to the government and help improve vocational training and employment services for residents.
The General Association of Women also recognized the work of the government regarding the problem of low birth problem, through the revision of the quality of day care centers and the relief of charges for families in child care.
It is recalled that the executive announced the update of the amount of birth to 6,500 patacas and the launch of an annual subsidy of 18,000 patacas for each baby or permanent resident of Macao who has not yet completed three years of age. However, for the increase in the number of maternity leave days, which the community has been asking for, this year's lag indicates that the respective study would begin.
The General Union of Macao Residents Associations, represented by NG Sio Lai, said it was confident in the future development of Macau with Sam Hou Fai's leadership, taking into account its policies about national integration and the evolution of the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin.
The General Association of the Overseas Macao Chinese, in turn, said that it will follow the governing management to contribute to regional and international cooperation, in the current international situation “chaotic”, leaving criticism of the United States for the “irrational tariff conflict” that causes risks and unforeseen challenges worldwide.</description><pubDate>2025-04-16 03:17:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau, Hong Kong and Beijing accuse the USA of attacking China's survival</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/macau-hong-kong-e-pequim-acusam-eua-de-atacar-sobrevivencia-da-china/</link><description>Chinese Communist Party's main official for Hong Kong and Macao affairs, and the governments of both regions accused the United States of imposing tariffs to sabotage China. "The US has targeted our fares, they target our own survival," said Xia Baolong, director of the Hong Kong and Macau affairs, under the tutelage of the Council of State, the Chinese executive. “Although Hong Kong is the largest source of US commercial surplus, the United States still imposed high tariffs. This is extremely arrogant and blatant!” Sinced. "The US cannot tolerate Hong Kong's prosperity and stability and are the biggest sinister manipulator that undermines human rights, freedom, the rule of law, prosperity and stability in Hong Kong," the leader added.
Xia spoke in a pre-recorded speech, transmitted during the inauguration of an exhibition in Hong Kong, regarding the Day of National Security Education. “Whoever tries to lead us back to poverty and weakness is our enemy,” warned the leader. "Those who betray national interests and cheer for the enemy at critical times will never be tolerated," he added.
Xia's comments came a week after China's anti -monopoly regulator announced that he would analyze the agreement that Hong Kong Ck Hutchison had announced for the sale of two ports on the Panama channel. The business, valued at $ 23 billion, would see the concession move to the US asset manager Blackrock, something the US president greeted as a victory.
In recent months, Donald Trump has argued that the concession of ports to CK Hutchison means that the navigable road is under Chinese control.
In the same ceremony, Hong Kong's government leader John Lee accused the United States of, in a "wicked logic," imposing tariffs to protect his "unhealthy hegemony." "The United States oppose free trade, interrupt global trade and supply chains (…), severely damaging the multilateral trade system and the process of globalization," said John Lee.
The chief executive has assured that Hong Kong "will keep his status from Porto Franco with basically null fares" and will file a complaint against the United States to the World Trade Organization.
Also the Macao government leader criticized the United States for the "abusive imposition of customs taxes on all its business partners," including China, "under various pretexts." Also during the inauguration of an exhibition due to National Security Education Day, Sam Hou Fai said Washington “severely devastated the multilateral trade system (…) and impaired the stability of the world economic order.”</description><pubDate>2025-04-16 03:17:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Rupture of China-EU capital markets can cost up to $ 2.5 billion</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/ruptura-de-mercados-de-capitais-china-eua-pode-custar-ate-25-bilioes-de-dolares/</link><description>Dissociation between China and the United States capital markets can cost $ 2.5 billion in a “extreme scenario,” warned the investment bank Goldman Sachs yesterday.
 
US investors could be required to sell about $ 800 billion in Chinese actions traded on US scholarships in case of dissociation, bank analysts said.
China could settle its appearances in the US Treasury and actions, worth $ 1.3 billion and $ 370 billion, respectively.
The risk of dissociation between the world's two largest economies could go beyond trade, according to US Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent, who said the option to remove Chinese companies from the list of negotiated companies in US capital markets "is on the table."
Donald Trump's administration has already imposed a rate of 145% on products from China, while Beijing countered at a rate of 125% over all goods from the United States and another 25% over certain products. "In capital markets, investors in action are very focused on the renewed risk of exclusion from Chinese American depositary receipts," Goldman analysts said in the report.
If the threat will be realized, it will affect about 300 companies, including some of China's largest technology companies, which are quoted on the New York Stock Exchange (NYSE) or Nasdaq, with a joint $ 1.1 billion (970 billion euros) scholarship, according to the US-China Economic Analysis and Security Commission.
According to James Wang, UBS China Strategy Director Investment Bank Research, the exclusion of US Chinese companies could have significant fundamental implications, including reducing access to higher US capital volume, the potential reduction in multiple evaluation due to the loss of the investor base and less liquidity. "However, we note that the capital survey from ADRS [lots of shares of a non-American company traded in scholarships in other countries] has decreased in recent years, while the role of Hong Kong has increased," he added.
The Alibaba group is the largest Chinese company in the US, with a current $ 257 billion. PDD Holdings' e -commerce rival is the second, with a market value of $ 125. billion.
In 2022, five Chinese state -owned companies - Petrochina, China Petroleum and Chemical Corp, China Life Insurance, Aluminium Corporation of China and Sinopec Shanghai Petrochemical - were no longer quoted in the US due to an audit dispute.
The crisis was later resolved after the regulatory authorities of both parties have reached an agreement to allow audit inspections in Hong Kong.
Since then, many US-listed companies have sought to obtain secondary prices in Hong Kong or have become a primary double-quote status to avoid the threat of exclusion in the US. "We believe the potential admission to the Hong Kong quotation of these companies could probably catalyze a reassessment, given the flexibility of US investors to convert their ADR into Hong Kong actions," in the event of a disturbing liquidity event, Goldman analysts said. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-16 03:18:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Life of buildings and threats to twentieth century architecture in debate at the Rui Cunha Foundation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/vida-util-dos-edificios-e-ameacas-a-arquitectura-do-seculo-xx-em-debate-na-fundacao-rui-cunha/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation will receive the release of the book “How to Extend the Life of Buildings” on April 23, at 18:30. The panel will consist of architects Cecilia Chu, Bernard Brennan and Rui Leão, with the moderation of also architect and photographer Francisco Duarte.
According to a statement from the Docomomo Research Center, in which two elements of the invited architects are associated, the book focuses on the elements that make up the Trinity of “a good building”: functional materialization, durability and beauty. The question that gives the motto to the investigation - and the debate at the Rui Cunha Foundation - is this: "So what choices faces when its function is turned off or its durability is questioned?" In addition to experts and moderator, the public is also invited to respond to this reflection and to issue their perspectives.
 
In the note signed by Tiago Rebocho, president of the Research Center, it is read that the work results from continuous research work “about the most significant examples of modern architecture” of the twentieth century and the state of “threat” under which it has been in recent decades, due to the fact that “its original functions have changed substantially and their technological innovations have not resisted in long tensions term".
“After its life cycle, a building may be reborn with a new function, but for this to happen, it is necessary to allow its adaptation to happen through appropriate evaluations and partnerships with the relevant stakeholders,” says Tiago Rebocho.
Cecilia Chu, graduated in Urban History and with experience in design and conservation, is an associate professor at the Chinese University School of Architecture of Hong Kong. He is one of the founding members of Docomomo Hong Kong, having already served as president.
Bernard Brennan also belongs to the Docomomo working group in the same region, where he also teaches courses on architecture and conservation programs at the University of Hong Kong Faculty of Architecture.
The trio of guests is completed with the presence of Rui Leão, an architect who is dedicated to the teaching of architecture, the wording of editorial works related to the areas of heritage and urbanism and the development of projects of large infrastructure for the Macao government. Although it has studied in Portugal since 1996 that most of its projects are developed in Macao and mainland China.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Vietname and China sign 45 cooperation agreements during Xi Jinping visit</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/vietname-e-china-assinam-45-acordos-de-cooperacao-durante-visita-de-xi-jinping/</link><description>Vietnam and China signed 45 cooperation agreements in areas such as Artificial Intelligence (AI), agricultural trade and customs cooperation during a visit to Hanoi of Chinese President Xi Jinping, who is conducting a tour of Southeast Asia.
 
XI and Vietname's top leader, to Lam, Secretary-General of the Communist Party of Southeast Asia, witnessed the signature of the 45 agreements, according to the official press of both countries, who did not go into detail about the agreements.
Xi's visit to the neighboring country is loaded with symbolism and occurs at a time when both parties have considered options compared to the trade war launched by US President Donald Trump.
Beijing faces 145%rates, which he responded with 125%rates, while Vietnam is negotiating reductions at 46%announced and then temporarily suspended by Washington.
During his meeting with Vietnamese leaders, Xi said China, Vietname's largest commercial partner, is “ready” to receive more Vietnamese products and to encourage more Chinese companies to invest in Vietname, according to the local news agency.
The Chinese president stressed the need to reinforce cooperation in supply chains and expand collaboration in technologies such as 5G, IA, semiconductors and clean energy.
Lam proposed to make digital transformation one of the pillars of relations between the two countries and urged them to reinforce collaboration in critical technological sectors and attract high quality Chinese investments to Vietname, according to the Vietnamese news agency.
The meeting takes place at a time when US President Donald Trump threatens to impose rates on semiconductors, with Vietname established as a regional industry center.
China's loss of attractiveness for some investors due to the US commercial tensions during Trump's first term (2017-2021) made Vietnam, with a robust economy, the favorite alternative as a production center for large technological companies like Apple or Google.
Chinese offshooring helped boost Vietnam's commercial surplus with the US, which last year reached a record of $ 123.5 billion a year (109 billion euros), behind only China, the European Union and Mexico.
Trump said on Monday that the meeting between Xi Jinping and to Lam aimed to study ways to harm his country in the context of the current trade war triggered by Washington. "I don't blame China or Vietnam. I look at today's meeting and it's wonderful. It's a charming meeting, that is, it's as if we were trying to find out" how we hurt the United States, "he told the press in the White House oval room.
Xi then left for Malaysia to continue his tour of Southeast Asia, which ends later this week in Cambodia, and during which he seeks to introduce Beijing as a reliable partner in the face of Washington's fares. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-16 03:18:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing recognizes Sam Hou Fai's work in the elaboration of the lag</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/pequim-reconhece-trabalho-de-sam-hou-fai-na-elaboracao-das-lag/</link><description>Beijing addressed compliments to Sam Hou Fai's first report of the Government Lines (LAG), noting that the document is a “pragmatic and progressive” political agenda. The Hong Kong and Macao Cabinet Office of the Council of State and the Central Government's liaison office in MSAR recognized Sam's “accurate measures” in resolving issues that concern Macao residents such as employment and housing.
 
The central government says that the first report of the Government of Macao Government is “responding to society's concerns” and shows “Entrepreneurial Spirit”. Two Chinese government agencies compliments the lag presented by Sam Hou Fai on Monday, highlighting that the report is “pragmatic” and embodies the “spirit transmitted in the speeches” of Chinese President Xi Jinping during the visit to Macao.
"It is a profound implementation of the spirit of important speeches given by President XI Jinping during his visit to Macao in December last year, fully demonstrating the philosophy of reform and innovation, pragmatism and commitment," said the office for Hong Kong and Macao State Council affairs.
The body led by Xia Baolong stated that LAG imply a “greater determination and courage” of the Macao government to deepen reforms and increase the effectiveness of governance, as well as respond to the requests of Macao residents “with more accurate and pragmatic policies and measures”, namely in pension issues for the elderly, employment and housing, having outlined “a beautiful vision and a path of implementation and a path of implementation for one implementation and a path of implementation for one implementation and a path of implementation for one implementation and a path of implementation for a implementation and a path of implementation for one implementation and a path of implementation for one implementation and a path of implementation for one implementation and a path of implementation for a implementation and a path of implementation for one implementation and a path of implementation for a implementation and an implementation for one Macao governed by the rule of law ”.
In addition, the Hong Kong and Macau's affairs office understands that the present government “faces problems and challenges firmly” and demonstrates the commitment to seek change. He assured, in this case, that he will give full support to her development.
"The Chinese nation is advancing for a great rebirth at an unstoppable rhythm, and Macau is now enjoying the best period of development," the political body emphasized in a statement also released on Monday, saying that with the leadership of Xi Jinping and the support of the central government, Macau will take advantage of opportunities for progress.
The central government connection office on the MSAR, in turn, stressed that the LAG report is a “pragmatic and progressive political agenda” with “clear ideas and strong measures” that elaborates a “prospective plan on Macao's medium and long term development”.
According to the body, LAG for this financial year focuses on improving the effectiveness of governance and the work of reorganization of functions and organic structures of the civil service, providing for the guarantee of citizens' welfare with “precise assistance and resource allocation”, as well as “proactive alignment” with national development strategies.
Making a positive balance of the executive's work, the connection office also praised the “humble style” of the government of Sam Hou Fai to listen to public opinion, pointing out that the chief executive led employees from various political folders to collect suggestions from various sectors during the elaboration of LAG.</description><pubDate>2025-04-16 03:18:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan increases defense spending to 1.8% of GDP by 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/japao-aumenta-gastos-com-defesa-para-18-do-pib-em-2025/</link><description>Japan announced yesterday that it plans to increase defense expense this year to 9.9 trillion of yen (61.8 billion euros), equivalent to 1.8% of Gross Domestic Product (GDP).
 
Japanese Defense Minister General Nakatani said at a press conference that the government will reserve 8.5 billion of yen (52.3 billion euros) for the defense budget and 1.5 billion of yen (9.24 billion euros) for the current budget for the current fiscal year, which began this month and lasts until March 2026.
The announcement comes about a month after Donald Trump, the US President, Japan's largest ally, pressing Tokyo to support a larger cost of the costs of their safety and mobilization of US military forces.
In early March, in the first comments on the bilateral security pact between the United States and Japan since he returned to the White House in January, Trump told reporters: "I love Japan. We have a great relationship with Japan, we have an interesting deal with Japan we have to protect them, but they don't have to protect ourselves."
Japan reviewed the long -term defense strategy at the end of 2022 and set a goal of increasing defense -related expenses to 2% of GDP by the 2027 fiscal year.
It has represented the largest rearmament effort in the Asian country since the end of World War II (1939-1945) and includes the acquisition of “counterattack abilities”, such as hypersonic or long-range missiles, allowing it to directly attack enemy territory in case of direct threat to its safety.
The numbers detailed yesterday by Nakatani show that Japan's efforts to reinforce defense capabilities “are constantly moving forward” towards the goal of 2% of GDP, according to the minister.
Japan has chosen to increase expense in response to security challenges such as China's military reinforcement, North Korea's nuclear and missile developments, and Ukraine invasion through Russia, a country with which Tokyo has territorial disputes.
With a constitution that renounces the war and limits the capacities of the Armed Forces (officially called self-defense forces), Japan has long been limited to defense spending, keeping them in about 1% of GDP, or five yen billion (30.8 billion euros).
In early March, also Elbridge Colby, appointed by Trump to Undersecretary of Defense, urged Japan to increase the military budget to 3% of GDP.
Under the Japan-Eu ​​Security Pact, US military forces are parked in Japan, especially Okinawa, which is near Taiwan and Senkaku Islands in the East China Sea.
The Senkaku Islands, run by Japan but claimed by China, have been in the center of tensions between Tokyo and Beijing. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-16 03:18:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism sector agrees with government bets in the international market</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/sector-de-turismo-concorda-com-apostas-do-governo-no-mercado-internacional/</link><description>The tourism industry was pleased with the government's proposal in the “active exploitation” of international tourist markets, suggesting priority to cooperation with game concessionaires in the promotion of Macao abroad.
Wong Fai, president of the Macao Leisure Innovation and Tourism Services Association, marked the rich experiences of casino operators in international promotion, taking into account their network of visitor sources and the support of their mother companies. "The government can coordinate with game companies to promote their products in foreign markets, which increases global promotional attention and attractiveness," he said.
Speaking to the newspaper or Mun, Wong Fai understands that there is a need for the territory to attract more visitors from abroad, as “the volume of international arrivals is still far from the level prior to the pandemic”, although the tourism industry recovers as more and more visitors from the continent are registered.
The official also agrees with the government's plan to create economic, commercial, tourist and cultural representations of MSAR in Southeast Asia and Northeast Asia countries. It indicated that it is appropriate to prioritize the international market in Asia, proposing a collaboration with Hong Kong to promote tourism in the Middle East and Asean countries. It also requested the relaxation of visa restrictions or the introduction of the visa to arrive to Vietname visitors.
For aerial calls, Wong Fai suggested creating direct flights to facilitate India travelers, as well as accelerate the opening of aerial route franchises to create conditions for the introduction of potential competitors in the market and to enrich the network of routes traveling from and to Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-04-16 03:16:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai warns to “external forces infiltration”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/sam-hou-fai-alerta-para-infiltracao-de-forcas-externas/</link><description>The Macao government leader said Macau must be ready for the worst when defending China's national security, including "the infiltration of external forces."
 
"We have to increase our awareness of risks, persist in a prudent surveillance attitude to control and prevent any emergencies and be prepared for the worst scenarios," warned Sam Hou Fai.
The Chief Executive argued that it is necessary to “resolutely prevent and repress” the “different types of risks and challenges, namely interference and infiltration of external forces”.
Sam Hou Fai spoke during the inauguration of an exhibition on the day of national security education.
The ruler stressed that in 2024 the region “constantly improved the legal regime for the defense of national security and the mechanism of its application” to reinforce the Macao principle governed by patriots.
On Monday, Sam Hou Fai assured that, to consolidate this principle, from this year, all civil servants, including those of Portuguese nationality, will have to take an oath of loyalty to China and the territory. This according to two bills that are being analyzed in a Commission of the Legislative Assembly. In December, the local parliament approved the two proposals generally, unanimously and without any debate.
Also in December, the Secretary of State for Portuguese Communities told Lusa that the proposals were “an exclusive article from China”. "This is an issue that I do not comment, it is a matter of the Forum of the Popular Republic of China and the Macao authorities," said José Cesário, after a meeting with the Macao Public Function Workers Association (ATFPM).
The president of ATFPM said he had no concern about the proposals and recalled that since 2005, when he also became a deputy, who has to take a similar oath. “I never had a problem or [I felt] that this would cause pressure to pressure my activity,” said José Pereira Coutinho. The deputy said that the changes proposed by the government are positive, as "they come to demand more responsibility."
When the proposals were presented in November, the executive council spokesman warned that civil servants can be dismissed due to private conversations or comments published on social networks.
André Cheong stressed that the oath will be mandatory for all civil servants, including the Portuguese, but added that they could do it in Portuguese, one of Macau's two official languages, along with the Chinese.
According to the latest Human Resources report of the Public Administration, in 2023 the region had 34,311 employees. The document does not refer to how many have Portuguese nationality, mentioning only that 257 were born in Portugal. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-16 03:17:16</pubDate></item><item><title>New allowance will benefit 15 thousand children</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/16/novo-subsidio-vai-beneficiar-15-mil-criancas/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai was yesterday at the Legislative Assembly to give more details about the government lines for this year. One of the news is the subsidy for children under the age of three who, according to the executive head of the executive, will have 15,000 beneficiaries. Also within the scope of measures to stimulate birth, the chief executive said that the increase in the number of maternity leave days will be studied.
 
Following the presentation of the Governing Action Lines (LAG) for this year, Sam Hou Fai was yesterday to the Legislative Assembly (AL) to answer the questions of the deputies about the document. As medidas para fazer aumentar a taxa de natalidade foi um dos temas em destaque na reunião plenária de ontem no hemiciclo.
The LAG report already said that, in order to face the problem of low birth rate, the government will begin to grant a childhood assistance allowance, giving each baby or permanent resident of Macao under three years old a monthly amount of 1,500 patacas, making a total of 18,000 patacas per year. According to yesterday the chief executive, this support will benefit about 15,000 children.
During the session, Sam Hou Fai relativized the latest data from the United Nations Economic and Social Affairs Department (UNDESA), which said that the Macao fertility rate (0.68 births per woman) was the lowest in the world. The boss pointed out that this rate concerns all residents and not resident women in Macau. Sam suggested that if the accounts were made only to MSAR residents, the rate would not be so low.
Sam Hou Fai also commented that Macau has "many women [not residents] of very beautiful, very beautiful age, capable of having children," but "politics does not leave them." It is recalled that non-resident women pay a delivery fee of 2,925 patacas and the rates of delivery services are between 8,775 patacas and 17,550 patacas, respectively.
According to data from the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), there were 3,607 births in 2024, the lowest number for almost two decades. Health services also predicted that there should be less than 3,500 births in the region this year, a number that would be the lowest since 2004.
Still in the chapter of measures to increase the birth rate, the ruler highlighted the plan to start studying the increase in maternity leave, which will be in charge of an independent entity. In the LAG report presented by the government is plasmented: “Improve the laws and regulations on work, beginning, in particular, a study on the increase in maternity leave and annual holidays provided for in the Labor Relations Law”.
In addition, the marriage subsidy for 2,220 Patacas will also be increased and a project to develop day care centers “to reduce pressure from families from working couples with dependent children and foster an environment conducive to child care for families with children”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-16 03:19:17</pubDate></item></channel></rss>