<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/ponte-do-delta-com-transito-condicionado-no-sabado/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Galaxy's third-quarter profits rise 14%</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/lucros-da-galaxy-no-terceiro-trimestre-aumentam-14/</link><description>Gaming operator Galaxy Entertainment made profits in the third quarter of this year worth 3.3 billion Hong Kong dollars, which represents an increase of 14% compared to the same period last year. Gross revenues in this period reached 12.2 billion, also 14% more in annual terms.

Galaxy Entertainment yesterday released financial results for the third quarter of this year, which show that, in this period, profits rose 14% year on year to 3.3 billion Hong Kong dollars. Revenues also registered a 14% jump in annual terms to 12.2 billion. The group's adjusted profit for the last 12 months was HK$13.4 billion, which represents an increase of 14% compared to the previous year.
The document sent to the newsroom also says that Galaxy Macau's adjusted profits were US$3.1 billion, 20% more compared to the previous year and 8% less compared to the previous quarter. StarWorld Macau's adjusted profit was US$369 million, a 7% drop from the previous year and a 22% increase from the previous quarter. Finally, Broadway Macau's adjusted profit was US$1 million, compared to US$11 million in the third quarter of 2024 and US$4 million in the second quarter of 2025.
Galaxy's statement quotes the group's president, Francis Lui, who states that the balance sheet “remains healthy and liquid”. “Our solid balance sheet and operational cash flow allow us to return capital to shareholders through dividends, finance our development and pursue our international expansion ambitions”, said Francis Lui. In October this year, Galaxy paid provisional dividends of US$0.70 per share, which demonstrates “continued confidence in the long-term prospects of Macau and society”.
Francis Lui also highlighted that, in the third quarter, Galaxy held several mega entertainment events, including a show by Eason Chan and American comedian Jimmy O. Yang in Macau. In 2025, the group held approximately 260 entertainment, sports, arts and culture events and exhibitions and conventions, which contributed to a 41% increase in visitor flow at Galaxy Macau compared to the previous year.
In October, two popular singers, Luhan and Jackson Wang, performed at the Galaxy Arena, and world-renowned Chinese pianist Yundi Li made his debut with the Galaxy Music Gala at the Galaxy International Convention Center (GICC). Furthermore, the group promises to support the National Games by hosting its table tennis competition at the Galaxy Arena. A four-year strategic partnership was also signed with the Ultimate Fighting Championship (UFC) to bring UFC Fight Nights to Galaxy Arena and a three-year strategic partnership was renewed with TMElive (Tencent Music) to co-host popular music events.
Galaxy also says that, over the last 18 months, there has been a strong investment in technology, including the implementation of smart tables, the consolidation of data insights and the improvement of our data analysis capabilities. "The aim of these programs is to ensure that we better understand our customers and that we are in a position to provide the best service and experience to our valued guests. We want customers to make informed decisions based on concrete data and not hunches. We have already seen economic benefits from these investments and will continue to boost each business segment", highlights Francis Lui.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 23:41:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong Police Detain 80 People in Cryptocurrency Fraud Case</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/policia-de-hong-kong-detem-80-pessoas-em-caso-de-fraude-com-criptomoedas/</link><description>Hong Kong police announced the arrest of 80 suspects linked to one of the biggest cases of financial fraud, related to the JPEX cryptocurrency exchange platform.
Police have been investigating JPEX since September 2023, which the Chinese region's securities regulator accused of suspicious activities and promoting unlicensed products.
Since then, 80 people have been arrested, 16 of whom have already been charged with crimes such as “conspiracy to commit fraud”, the police said on Wednesday, adding that the others remain the subject of investigation.
This is the largest fraud case in Hong Kong in terms of number of victims and amount of losses suffered in recent years, police authorities noted at a press conference.
The police referred to the first use of the rules introduced by Hong Kong in 2023 to prosecute crimes related to the fraudulent encouragement of investment in virtual assets.
More than 2,700 complaints related to the case were received by the police, involving a total value of 1.6 billion Hong Kong dollars. Police classified the case as “very complex” and identified at least 14 key people. One of these people and two brains were abroad, the police said, adding that arrest warrants had been issued by Interpol.
Police have frozen assets worth more than 200 million Hong Kong dollars belonging to the suspects.
Questioned by the France-Presse news agency, the chief superintendent of the fight against crime, Ernest Wong, stated that the police authorities “will continue the investigation” and “cannot exclude the possibility of charging or detaining more people in the future”.
JPEX used advertising campaigns promoting high returns and low risks, in addition to promoting online influencers to encourage investors to deposit funds, according to police. The group transferred assets and laundered them through cryptocurrency wallets. Among those detained are social media influencers who helped with the promotion and holders of fictitious bank accounts.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 23:32:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Miguel Oliveira says goodbye to the Portuguese public at MotoGP</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/miguel-oliveira-despede-se-do-publico-portugues-no-motogp/</link><description>The Portuguese Miguel Oliveira (Yamaha) says goodbye to the Portuguese MotoGP public this weekend, as he participates for the last time in the discipline's Portuguese Grand Prix.

The 30-year-old driver from Almada is competing in his seventh season in the 'queen' category of speed motorcycling, having already planned to move on to the Superbike World Championship (on series-derived motorcycles) from 2026, with BMW.
This weekend, Miguel Oliveira says goodbye to the Portuguese public on a stage he knows well and where he won in 2020, a year of pandemic.
At the Autódromo Internacional do Algarve, stage of this 21st and penultimate round of the season, Miguel Oliveira has already 'ascended to heaven', with victory in the first time that the AIA hosted the Speed ​​World Cup caravan, but he has also 'descended to hell', with falls and injuries.
It was on the Algarve circuit, in Portimão, that, in 2023, he suffered his first injury of the year, after being hit at the start of the race by Spaniard Marc Márquez, who has already become MotoGP champion for the seventh time in his career, but who will be absent from the Portuguese race due to injury.
Despite being one of the routes he knows best and adapts well to, AIA is also one of the unluckiest for the Portuguese driver.
After the victory achieved in 2020, starting from pole position and leading every lap, achieving the fastest lap, he only achieved notable results again in 2022, the year in which he finished in fifth position, being the best KTM rider.
The Portuguese rider has already competed in 115 races in MotoGP, counting five triumphs (Styria, Algarve, Catalonia, Indonesia and Thailand), seven podiums and a 'pole position', precisely in the year of his victory in Portimão.
In 2021, the AIA hosted two championship events, the Portuguese Grand Prix and the Algarve Grand Prix. Oliveira was unlucky, falling to both.
Last year, when he was wearing Aprilia's colors, Miguel Oliveira was 12th in the sprint race, won by Spaniard Maverick Viñales, and ninth in the main race.
Now, the Portuguese rider arrives at the home race with new colors, representing Yamaha, after having already competed here with KTM and Aprilia.
Oliveira made his debut this year with Prima Pramac, a team that won the drivers' championship in 2024 with Spaniard Jorge Martin (also absent this year due to injury).
The year was a bad one for the Portuguese driver, who suffered a fall in the second race, in Argentina, which caused an injury to the ligaments in his right shoulder and ruled him out of the next three races (United States, Qatar and Spain), also affecting his performance in the first half of the season. This factor was fundamental for the Yamaha satellite team to activate the performance clause, which allowed the Portuguese rider to be released before the end of the contract, scheduled for 2026.
Miguel Oliveira is actually one of the four drivers who have already managed to win at the AIA. In addition to the Portuguese, only the Frenchman Fabio Quartararo (Yamaha), the Italian Francesco Bagnaia (Ducati) and the Spanish Jorge Martin (now with Aprilia, then with Ducati), defending champion, have won on the Algarve circuit.
The MotoGP Portuguese Grand Prix, which will be held between Friday and Sunday, will be the 21st of the 22 World Championship races. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 23:27:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Shao Jiayi is China's new football coach</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/shao-jiayi-e-o-novo-seleccionador-de-futebol-da-china/</link><description>Shao Jiayi is China's new football coach, replacing Serbian Dejan Djurdjevic, who held the position on an interim basis since June, the federation said yesterday in a statement published on its website. The organization states that when choosing Shao Jiayi, aged 45, in a process that included “several Chinese and foreign candidates”, “the experience and lessons learned from the appointment of other national team coaches” were taken into account. In June, the Chinese Football Federation (CFA) fired Croatian Branko Ivankovic, who had been hired in February 2024 after having led Iran to the 2006 World Cup and also for his experience in winning titles in China with the Shandong Luneng.
Branko Ivankovic's dismissal came following China's elimination from the 2026 World Cup, taking place in the United States, Mexico and Canada, and extended to 48 teams, after the 1-0 defeat to Indonesia. The elimination was a setback for Chinese football, which has not returned to a World Cup since its only participation in 2002, in South Korea and Japan, and, at the time, the then midfielder Shao Jiayi was one of the highlights of that team.
His performance at the World Cup caught the attention of Western clubs, and Shao ended up signing for Bundesliga side 1860 Munich that same season, where he remained until 2006. Shao then continued his career in Germany, playing for Energie Cottbus (2006-2011) and Duisburg (2011), before returning to his childhood club, Beijing Guoan, and retiring in 2015 as a legend. He later worked with China's youth teams, rising to the role of assistant coach before taking charge of Qingdao West Coast, his first experience as a head coach. It leaves the team in ninth place in the Chinese Super League, after recording nine wins, ten draws and ten defeats this season.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 23:27:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Biennial dance program concludes with show about maladjustment and social anxiety</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/programa-bienal-de-danca-conclui-com-espectaculo-sobre-inadaptacao-e-ansiedade-social/</link><description>The organization “Macau Space for Dance Idea” closes its biennial dancer training program with the show “Thanks for the Dance”, on the 13th and 14th of December, at the Macau Cultural Center. The play, inspired by the classic tale “The Ugly Duckling”, explores themes such as alienation and conflict in contemporary society through body language.

Two years of work culminate in a show that transforms a children's story into a reflection on the human condition. “Macau Space for Dance Idea” presents “Thanks for the Dance”, a production that marks the end of its Comprehensive Training Program for Dancers, an initiative that since 2023 has been training local artists through a contemporary pedagogical approach.
The play, conceived based on the famous story “The Ugly Duckling”, transcends the original narrative to address “the theme of alienation in the masses and feelings of anxiety, indifference and conflict” applied to Macau, as described by the organization.
Published in 1843 by Danish Hans Christian Andersen, “The Ugly Duckling” became one of the universal tales about resilience and self-discovery. The original story follows a duckling who is different from his siblings, rejected because of his appearance, until he discovers that he is actually a swan of incomparable beauty. This narrative about transformation and acceptance has been reinterpreted over the centuries as a metaphor about difference, bullying and the journey towards one's identity.
This new performance, under the direction of renowned local director Dicky Tsang and choreographed by Leong Iek Kei, represents the third phase of a creative process that has privileged Macanese life experiences as artistic raw material.
“The entire program has been running for two years, which has been challenging for both the members and me”, reveals Tsang, highlighting the particularities of transitioning from theater to dance. "As a theater director, dealing with dance direction is difficult; after all, the language of the stage differs greatly from that of drama. I needed time to think and consider how to translate the work into a physical language for the audience."
The training program, which has already presented two previous shows equally inspired by important works and local culture, now culminates with three participants embodying this choreographic exploration of dissonance within a group. The organization's fundamental premise is to develop dance creations that reflect the unique character of Macau, incorporating diverse artistic elements and using the multiple facets of the local lifestyle as a creative backdrop.
Tickets for the three performances are now on sale, with a base price of 180 patacas. The organization also offers special conditions for groups of two and three members, reinforcing its mission of making dance accessible to different audiences.
The “Macau Space for Dance Idea” thus consolidates its trajectory in promoting choreographic projects that explore styles that are still little represented in the local scene, establishing bridges between dance and other artistic expressions while maintaining an organic connection with the Macanese sociocultural context. “Macau Space for Dance Idea” is an organization dedicated to the development of contemporary dance in Macau since 2021.
“Thanks for the Dance” will be presented at the Macau Cultural Center on the 13th and 14th of December. Tickets are available on online platforms.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Suspect of electoral corruption allegedly solicited bribes on social media</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/suspeito-de-corrupcao-eleitoral-tera-solicitado-subornos-nas-redes-sociais/</link><description>Before the Macao SAR legislative elections, which took place on September 14, an individual shared messages on social media requesting money from third parties, promising to vote according to the indicated voting direction. The case was discovered by the Commissariat Against Corruption (CCAC), which accuses the man of electoral corruption.

The Commissariat Against Corruption (CCAC) reported yesterday that it detected two cases of infractions during the Macao SAR legislative elections that took place on 14 September. One of the cases has to do with a bribe request.
According to the CCAC, during the inspection of electoral propaganda activities, it was found that an individual circulated messages and posted comments on social media with the aim of publicly requesting money from third parties, promising to vote in accordance with the indicated voting direction. During the investigation, the individual in question admitted to committing the crime, claiming that he hoped, in this way, to obtain pecuniary advantages.
The voter in question is suspected of committing the crime of electoral corruption (soliciting a bribe) provided for in the electoral law for the Legislative Assembly, and the case has been forwarded to the Public Prosecutor's Office for due effects.
In a statement, the CCAC emphasizes that, under the terms of the law, whoever offers, promises or grants any type of advantage, in person or through an intermediary, so that voters vote according to the indicated voting direction, is punished with a prison sentence of up to eight years; Anyone who requests or accepts the respective advantages may be punished with a prison sentence of up to three years, with no suspension of the execution of the sentence in the event of conviction.
The other case detected by the CCAC concerns a suspected case of illegal electoral propaganda on election day. On September 14th, while carrying out inspections of electoral activities, the CCAC discovered that an individual used social communication software to send propaganda messages for a candidate list, with image and text, in several communication groups with more than a hundred members, appealing to members of these groups to vote for the respective candidate group.
The CCAC states that there is evidence that the act carried out by the individual in question constitutes electoral propaganda, and he is then suspected of committing the crime of propaganda on election day, which is punishable by a prison sentence of up to one year if convicted. The case was handed over to the Public Ministry.
It is recalled that the legislative elections on September 14th had a participation rate of 53.35% in direct voting, 11 percentage points more than in 2021. However, the participation rate was the third lowest among the seven legislative elections that have been held in the Macao SAR since 2001.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 23:42:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Panchão burning zone only in Taipa during Chinese New Year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/zona-de-queima-de-panchoes-so-na-taipa-durante-o-ano-novo-chines/</link><description>The area for burning panchons, fireworks and rockets, for the Lunar New Year season, will only be installed in Taipa, with the Macau Peninsula no longer available for the activity, announced the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM).
The panchão burning area in Taipa will have opening hours from February 16, 2026 (29th day of the 12th Moon of the lunar calendar) until February 21, 2026 (5th day of the 1st Moon of the lunar calendar).
The IAM had a tradition of designating two areas for the burning of panchões in Macau, namely on Avenida Dr. Sun Yat-Sen, and in Taipa during the Chinese New Year festive period. However, as the organization explained, with the start of work on the South Margin Green Corridor, “the surrounding areas are no longer suitable for the installation of the panchão burning zone”, explained the organization.
In this sense, the designated area for burning panchões will only be located on Estrada Almirante Marques Esparteiro, close to the seafront. The IAM assured that the space in the area will be expanded, with an increase in the number of tents selling panchons, fireworks and rockets, from four to six tents. There will be even more temporary parking spaces, in addition to improvements to facilities, in order to respond to the increase in people, said the IAM.
The IAM added that ten temporary stalls selling cigarettes and paper fans will be installed in Largo da Barra, during the Lunar New Year, whose operating hours will be from the 16th to the 23rd of February 2026.
Registration for the operating license for tents selling panchãos, fireworks and rockets, as well as for stalls selling pints and paper fans, is open from yesterday until the 19th of the month.
For the respective exploration license, a verbal tender will be opened, with the successful tenderer being obliged to pay, on site, the entire tender amount, in cash, by means of electronic payment or by crossed check. Interested parties can register at the IAM Service Center or at the Public Service Provision Centers in the different areas, collecting notifications of the competition information session and paying a deposit of 5,000 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 23:37:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Real wages in Japan fall for the ninth consecutive month in the face of rising inflation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/salarios-reais-no-japao-caem-pelo-nono-mes-consecutivo-face-a-crescente-inflacao/</link><description>The real wages of Japanese workers fell 1.4% in September, according to official data published yesterday, representing the ninth consecutive monthly drop in the country, at a time of rising prices for essential foods.

Nominal wages in Japan, which include base salary, overtime and other bonuses, increased by 1.9% compared to September 2024, according to a report released by the Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare.
However, real wages did not keep up with the general increase in prices.
In September food prices rose 7.6%, energy costs rose 2.3% and electricity costs rose 3.2%, according to the latest data from the Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications.
Japan's main inflation rate stood at 2.9% in September, above the BoJ's 2% target, driven by widespread increases in all essential goods, from food to service fees.
As a result, the average salary, which currently stands at 297,145 yen (1,677 euros), continues to be insufficient to offset inflation, causing real wages in Japan to show negative growth. These salary figures are the first to be released since Sanae Takaichi took over as prime minister of the archipelago at the end of October.
Japan's first female prime minister, representing the hard-line conservative wing of the Liberal Democratic Party, has vowed to curb persistent inflation and the erosion of real wages.
Meanwhile, Japan's largest union, known as Rengo, is demanding a wage increase of 5% or more for 2026, after successfully lobbying the Japanese government in August for a historic 5.25% minimum wage increase.
On October 30, the Japanese central bank improved Japan's economic growth forecast for 2025 by a tenth to 0.7%, warning of a slowdown caused by trade policies and falling corporate profits.
In the quarterly economic forecast report, the Bank of Japan (BoJ) chose, however, to maintain the inflation forecast for the current fiscal year at 2.7%, which will end on March 31, 2026, citing a relief from the increase in food prices, especially rice, which had been raising the index.
The Japanese institution decided to keep the remaining forecasts for the 2026 and 2027 years unchanged.
The BoJ highlighted that there are several risks that could influence the country's economy, including uncertainty surrounding economic activity abroad and the reaction to prices in trade and other policies in each jurisdiction. “It is necessary to pay attention to the impact of these developments on financial and foreign exchange markets, as well as on economic activity and prices in Japan”, indicates the text. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 23:31:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines declares state of emergency due to Typhoon Kalmaegi</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/filipinas-declaram-estado-de-emergencia-devido-a-passagem-de-tufao-kalmaegi/</link><description>The President of the Philippines, Ferdinand Marcos Jr., yesterday declared a state of emergency in the country, after Typhoon Kalmaegi left at least 142 dead and 127 missing, in the worst disaster to hit the country this year.

The declaration of a “state of national calamity” was made by Marcos, during a meeting with disaster response authorities, to assess the consequences of the typhoon.
The decision allows the Philippine Government to release emergency funds more quickly and avoid food hoarding and price speculation.
According to official data compiled yesterday by the France-Presse news agency (AFP), at least 142 people died and 127 are missing following the passage of Kalmaegi.
The Philippines' National Department of Civil Defense confirmed 114 deaths, in addition to 28 fatalities recorded by authorities in the province of Cebu, in the center of the country, AFP reported.
Most of the victims died by drowning or being hit by debris, following flash floods and landslides caused by the Kalmaegi, which also destroyed houses and swept away vehicles, said on Wednesday the deputy head of the Civil Defense Office, Bernardo Rafaelito Alejandro.
The army indicated that six soldiers died when an Air Force helicopter crashed in the province of Agusan del Sur, during a humanitarian aid mission.
The devastation caused by the typhoon affected nearly two million people and displaced more than 560,000 residents, including nearly 450,000 who were evacuated to emergency shelters, Civil Defense said.
Around 3,500 passengers were stranded in almost a hundred ports due to the navigation ban.
Authorities in Cebu province said years of mining and poor drainage works have worsened the impact of the floods.
As it passed through the central Philippines, Kalmaegi brought winds of 130 kilometers per hour (km/h) and gusts of up to 180 km/h.
After crossing the South China Sea, the storm is expected to soon reach the coast of Vietnam and cause intense rain in northern Thailand, according to meteorological services in the region.
While still dealing with the impact of Kalmaegi, authorities warned that another tropical cyclone coming from the Pacific Ocean could strengthen into a super typhoon, hitting the northern Philippines early next week.
Every year, around 20 storms and typhoons hit or come close to the Philippines, with the poorest regions of the country generally being the most affected.
 
Timor-Leste ready to offer support to the Philippines

The Government of Timor-Leste yesterday expressed solidarity with the Philippines, where more than 140 people died following the passage of Typhoon Kalmaegi, and said it was ready to offer all possible support. “Timor-Leste is deeply saddened by the scale of this tragedy and by the difficulties faced by so many families who have lost loved ones, homes and livelihoods,” said Prime Minister, Xanana Gusmão, in a letter sent to Philippine President, Ferdinand ‘Bongbong’ Marcos Jr. and cited in a statement released to the press.
The Timorese leader also highlighted that Timor-Leste “remains in solidarity with the Filipino people in this time of mourning and recovery”, reiterating regional friendship and cooperation.
In the same statement, the Minister of the Presidency of the Council of Ministers and Government spokesman, Agio Pereira, stated that the Philippines is facing a “tragedy of immense proportions”. "Our history and ties of regional cooperation mean that the Philippines' pain is also ours. We are ready to offer all possible support", added Agio Pereira. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 23:31:14</pubDate></item><item><title>The construction of a dictator: the United States and Donald Drump</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/a-construcao-de-um-ditador-os-estados-unidos-e-donald-drump/</link><description>One year ago, on Tuesday, November 5, 2024, Donald Trump was re-elected to the Presidency of the United States. Since then, the USA and the Presidency have been transformed. Donald Trump declared that he would be “dictator from day one” of his term. The media and experts declared that Donald Trump would be an “aspiring dictator”, a “would-be dictator” and a “potential strongman”. I believe that Donald Trump's actions over the past two weeks confirm that he is, in fact, a dictator. Two events confirmed this classification. One was the emptying of the East Wing of the White House in the week of October 20, without proper authorization from any planning agency or commission. The other is its ongoing war in the Caribbean and Eastern Pacific Ocean, decimating small, possibly ordinary, fishing vessels and killing everyone on board almost every day. Basically, the world learned that Donald Trump truly believes he can do whatever he wants. He said, "I have the right to do whatever I want. I am the President of the United States." To confirm these words, last year the Supreme Court ruled that he has absolute immunity for “all official acts”. With Trump, the United States is transitioning to a dictatorship, as stated by the New York Times in an excellent article that I will use in this text.

Trump began to stifle free speech and dissent. The United States restricted freedom of expression to a level not seen since the McCarthy Era in the late 1940s and early 1950s, but this political repression was orchestrated by an American senator, not an American president, who held all the powers of the presidency. The Disney Corporation was pressured to remove comedian Jimmy Kimmel from the air. Students critical of Trump's policy toward Gaza and Israel saw their visas revoked; leftist teachers were deported. Investigations have been launched against liberal nonprofit groups that fund Democrats, especially George Soros's Open Society Foundation and the Ford Foundation. Judges have been denounced for decisions that uphold the law. Fear has returned to hover over the American political landscape.

Trump sues his political opponents, whom he calls “enemies”. All opponents are discarded or delegitimized, being accused of suffering from “Trump Disorder Syndrome”. Trump calls the Democratic Party “the enemy of the people.” He promised to implement a retaliation program when he arrived at the White House, and he kept his promise. Attorney General Letitia James of New York; former FBI Director James Comey; and his own former National Security Advisor, John Bolton, were all charged. Criminal investigations were launched against other opponents, including Senator Adam Schiff of California; former special prosecutor Jack Smith; and others, including possibly the Clintons and Bidens. No opponent, whether high or low, is immune to prosecution and investigation. Trump is using the Department of Justice as an instrument of retaliation. There is no longer a rule of law in the United States, but rather government by law, at least in political matters. When it comes to his opponents, the law is what Donald Trump determines it to be.

Trump ignores and disregards Congress. It treats it with total disrespect, refusing to consult its members when required by law. Article I of the US Constitution clearly states that power over the budget belongs to Congress. Congress collects money through taxes and assigns where and when that money will be spent. Unilaterally, Trump has illegally raised billions of dollars through tariffs, which are taxes, and withheld funds authorized by Congress for foreign aid, libraries, museums, schools, universities, medical and scientific research, etc. During this current five-week government shutdown, Trump has illegally paid federal troops through private donations (at what cost to the country?). Congress has become essentially inert. The Senate does little beyond confirming Trump's nominees. The House of Representatives has not met for six weeks, refusing to perform even the basic functions of government.
Perhaps the most dangerous is Trump's use of the armed forces to exercise internal control. Trump mobilized the National Guard in Los Angeles and Washington, and tried to do the same in Chicago and Portland. Under the guise of “fighting crime,” the military has been used to implement Trump’s immigration policy and suppress dissent. Tear gas and pepper spray were used near schools and even during Halloween celebrations for children in Chicago on October 31st. Protesters were targeted by aerial fire. Many fear that these members of the National Guard and federal troops will be deployed next year in Democratic-run cities to suppress the vote in the November 2026 midterm elections, preventing a free and fair outcome.

Trump has defied federal judges and their rulings on several occasions and, on other occasions, has tried to circumvent orders rather than disobey them. Although he has so far not flouted any order of the Supreme Court, there are fears that he may do so following some critical decisions of the Supreme Court that will be delivered in 2026. To date, the Supreme Court has been reluctant to restrain him. In fact, even worse in his submission to his master.

Trump declares national emergencies under false pretenses when there are no emergencies. He manufactured an economic emergency to bypass Congress and impose tariffs. He used allegations of “invasion” to close the southern border and send the National Guard into cities. Trump used this fiction of an “invasion” to kill unidentified foreign civilians in international waters, violating numerous international and American laws.

Trump vilifies marginalized groups daily. Trump's immigration henchmen (ICE and Border Patrol agents) profile Hispanics to such an extent that many always carry their passports and have even stopped speaking Spanish. It vilified transgender Americans, essentially forcing them underground. Trump has removed women and people of color from positions of power in the military and federal government. It is trying to revise history by removing books about slavery, segregation and indigenous massacres from military libraries. Ultimately, Trump ordered the Civil Rights Division to investigate alleged discrimination against white Americans. In doing so, Trump suggests that only some American citizens are legitimate; Others are considered second-rate citizens, or even subject to denaturalization and deportation. Donald Trump is transforming the United States into a white Christian nationalist state.

Trump launched a personality cult, common to all dictators. His portrait hangs in government buildings. He held a lavish military parade on his birthday. Trump's cabinet meetings resemble those of other dictators, with ministers offering sycophantic and exaggerated praise. There are even rumors that his face will be carved on Mount Rushmore or minted on a coin next year. Plans to build a Trump Arch in Washington. It is building a huge gold-plated ballroom that will cost around $300 million, eclipsing the White House. Trump claims to have a unique ability to solve America's problems. “Only I can solve this” is a common refrain.

We could list many other actions that turned Donald Trump into a dictator. For example, his wars against universities, trying to overhaul American higher education, corruption on an unprecedented scale, raising the Trump family fortune from about $50 million a year ago to $3.4 BILLION now, and his attempts to control the media (CBS, NBC, PBS, Washington Post, TikTok, etc.) so that it positively presents Trump's fascist agenda and views. All of these events confirmed that the United States is a very different place than it was a year ago.
Next year — 2026 — will be a vital year. The Supreme Court will issue several critical rulings on voting rights, its signature tariff policy, the 14th Amendment, the legality of troop presence in cities, among others. These decisions, as well as whether the US midterm elections will be fair and free, will determine whether Trump's dictatorship is reversible. We should know the answer to this question in a year, maybe less. The 2025 midterm election, which has just been held, had an exceptionally good result for the Democrats. However, many observers fear that Trump will manipulate the law to remain in power indefinitely, essentially becoming a president for life.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 23:26:27</pubDate></item><item><title>The Durian Chronicle</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/a-cronica-do-durian/</link><description>In Asia, where the markets are an explosion of colors and aromas, there is one fruit that reigns supreme: the durian, the self-proclaimed queen of fruits. With a green, prickly shell, it looks like a hedgehog with medieval weapon aspirations. However, it is not its appearance that causes so much aversion, but rather its unmistakable smell. If I had to go out on a limb, I'd say it's a mix of raw onion, sewage and a teenager's sneakers. When it is very ripe, already fermenting, its odor becomes even more intense and even treacherous, resembling gas dangerously. In Malaysia, Singapore, Thailand and China, durian is a diva. There are those who pay fortunes for a perfect copy, describing its creamy pulp as “vanilla of the gods”. But, for every devoted fan, there are a dozen people who abhor its intense smell. Hotels, trains and elevators display signs prohibiting durian.
In 2018, a school in Melbourne, Australia, experienced an unusual episode: 500 students were evacuated because the smell of a durian, probably fermenting, was mistaken for gas. Alarms went off, kids screamed, firefighters arrived with their eyebrows raised. All for a smuggled fruit.
I myself was caught by the stinking queen, without ever having risked tasting her pulp. I was pregnant with my daughter, at the beginning of the pregnancy, when smell became a superpower. One Sunday night, I took advantage of being alone at home to sprawl out on the sofa and watch a series. At one point, I got up to go to the kitchen to get a glass of water and was suddenly surprised by a smell that screamed “gas!”. I ran to the stove but everything was off. I opened the door to the house and found that in the hallway on the floor the smell was even more intense. I knocked on the neighbor's door, who confirmed: her stove was immaculate. I called the doorman, opened windows, took a deep breath. Nothing. The smell persisted. Sleep approached, and I, afraid of falling asleep, resisted as best I could. Until, at eleven at night, already at the edge of panic, I called the fire department. Ten minutes later a fire engine, two ambulances and two police motorcycles appeared. Nine firefighters entered the house in mission mode, with combat boots, crowbars and state-of-the-art gas measuring devices. They searched the kitchen: nothing. The floor hallway: nothing. The neighbor's house: nothing either. Until they discover the culprit: a durian fermenting in the communal trash can, with a smell so convincing it sounded like a gas leak. Nine firefighters, an entourage of emergency vehicles and me, pregnant, full of shame and trying not to laugh at the durian's trap.
The durian is proof that, in Asia (and even in Australia), the throne is not won with beauty or delicacy, but with personality.
 
Note: The story of the school in Melbourne, in 2018, actually happened. As for my adventure with the firefighters? Also true, hilarious and without a single bite of durian!</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 23:25:06</pubDate></item><item><title>IAS removes increase in child care allowance</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/ias-afasta-aumento-do-subsidio-de-assistencia-na-infancia/</link><description>The Government has no plans to expand the scope of beneficiaries of the Child Care Subsidy, nor will it increase the amount allocated, which is now set at 18,000 patacas per year. The Social Action Institute assured that it is monitoring changes in the newborn population and the economic situation, reviewing the implementation of the plan. Furthermore, the Government promises to prioritize work over any increase in maternity leave and vacation time.

The Institute of Social Action (IAS) ruled out the possibility of expanding the Child Care Subsidy plan, launched four months ago, adding that it is not currently considering an increase in the value of the subsidy or expanding the age range of beneficiaries. The IAS statement follows a request from deputy Ngan Iek Hang in a written interpellation to inject even more financial support into families with children.
The Child Care Subsidy plan provides for the granting of an annual subsidy of 18,000 patacas to beneficiaries – babies and children under 3 years of age. The organization said it implemented the plan with the hope of encouraging birth rates and creating friendly conditions for raising children.
“To address the declining birth rate in Macau, and considering that families will face additional expenses due to child-rearing needs, such as powdered milk, diapers and other baby items, upon the arrival of a newborn, if it is possible to alleviate the expenses of families with children through subsidies, it will send a positive message to encourage birth rates,” he noted.
However, the IAS understands that babies and children will benefit from Macau's education, medical care and other relevant welfare policies as they grow, and therefore does not see the need to adjust the said subsidy plan.
The body reiterated that it will monitor factors such as changes in the newborn population and the general economic situation, summarizing the experience and effectiveness of implementing the plan to carry out a “comprehensive assessment and consideration” of relevant policies.
In the same response to the interpellation, the IAS also cited the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) to guarantee measures to protect the rights and interests of women in the workplace.
According to DSAL, priority is given to opinions on increasing maternity leave and vacation time, which received the greatest attention from society. DSAL stressed that it has already commissioned a third independent entity to carry out the study and investigation into the possible revision of the law.
DSAL, however, did not express a clear position on the deputy's appeal regarding the legal number of days for paternity leave or the creation of leave to accompany family members to medical appointments. He only stressed that the Government will listen to the public's opinions, since “the definition or review of other labor policies not only involves the interests of the labor and employer parties, but also the overall economic development of Macau and social interests”.

WOMEN'S DEVELOPMENT
 
On the other hand, the IAS, in its response, revealed that it is now moving forward with work on revising the text of the second Planning of the “Development Objectives for Women in Macau” (2026-2032), which aims to promote its development in several areas.
The IAS said that planning will focus mainly on physical and mental health, family-friendly measures, social participation and gender equality, which covers eight areas, including gender mainstreaming, public policy and management, education, healthcare, welfare and social security, legal protection, economy and employment, and technological development.
The Government also intends to create conditions to develop women's capacity for political participation, as well as their involvement in the field of technological development, in addition to “building a birth support system, promoting women's mental health and creating a family-friendly environment”, he noted.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 23:41:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Kong Chi insists on his innocence, but admits exchanging opinions with Ho Kam Meng about cases</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/kong-chi-insiste-na-sua-inocencia-mas-admite-troca-de-opinioes-com-ho-kam-meng-sobre-casos/</link><description>Former deputy prosecutor Kong Chi insists on his innocence in the face of the Public Prosecutor's Office's new accusations of corruption and malfeasance, but admitted in court to having discussed, in private, criminal cases with lawyer Ho Kam Meng, now one of the defendants in the case on trial. At the hearing, Kong Chi argued the alleged crimes relating to at least eight case filings that have already exceeded the statute of limitations.
Kong Chi, who is being retried on charges of a total of 79 crimes, has once again asserted his innocence and denied all charges against him, as in his previous court case for corruption and malfeasance. The former deputy prosecutor, who is accused of having received benefits to close certain criminal cases that he had followed, contested the prescription of criminal liability for some facts presented in the indictment.
At Wednesday's hearing session, Kong Chi, cited by Ou Mun Newspaper, argued that the crimes charged in relation to at least eight criminal cases he handled as deputy prosecutor have already had the right to legal action expired due to the passage of time.
The then magistrate, who was previously sentenced to 21 years in prison, argued that the completion of crimes should be counted based on his own acts and not those of third parties.
On the other hand, the deputy prosecutor responsible for the case, Kuok Un Man, justified the legality of the process and stressed that the Public Prosecutor's Office's accusation progressed in phases for reasons of procedural strategy, and is now in the “second phase”, and that the target of the criminal investigation continues to be the same group. Judge Choi Mou Pan, in this regard, said that the panel will analyze the aforementioned issues.
According to the prosecution's indictment, the then deputy prosecutor Kong Chi, lawyer Ho Kam Meng, businesswoman Choi Sao Ieng and lawyer Kuan Hoi Lon are suspected of, between 2008 and 2022, having formed a criminal group that received certain amounts to facilitate defendants investigated by the Public Prosecutor's Office, shelving cases or providing favorable decisions.
Ho Kam Meng, a lawyer who is currently suspended from his duties, according to the accusation, charged between tens of thousands and several hundred thousand patacas in “fees” to help in the alleged intervention and manipulation of criminal cases.
FRIENDS SINCE SERVICE AT MP
 
Faced with questioning from the Public Prosecutor's Office, Kong Chi admitted in court that he maintained a “somewhat special” relationship with Ho Kam Meng, acknowledging that he trusted Ho with the management of his private legal affairs and those of his family.
He also indicated that he had facilitated some procedures “within the limits of the law”, such as speeding up the processing of cases, but rejected any framing of a criminal organization or receipt of bribes.
Kong Chi said he met Ho Kam Meng at the Public Prosecutor's Office, where the lawyer worked as a senior technician for three years, until 2003. Kong also mentioned frequent meetings with Ho Kam Meng in Macau and in mainland China, where they discussed legal issues, insisting, however, that he responded only within legal limits.
The Public Prosecutor's Office showed in court the exchanges of messages between Kong Chi and Ho Kam Meng, in which the former magistrate revealed case numbers and case closure situations, and even suggested to the lawyer that the conversation records be deleted. In this case, Kong Chi justified that Ho was a lawyer appointed in the cases and that the comments were made “in good faith”, even though he admitted to having gone “a little further than necessary”. Kong Chi denied having helped Ho to close the cases, also ruling out any connection to illicit payments.
Furthermore, the Public Prosecutor's Office questioned the logic of Kong Chi's decision to close certain cases handled by Ho Kam Meng, accusing him of failing to fulfill his investigative obligations. In response, Kong Chi stated that he no longer remembers the specific decisions, but maintained that the reasons were already contained in the archiving orders.
At the hearing, he was again questioned about a document entitled “Subscription Register of the Hunan-Macau Mutual Fund”, which the Anti-Corruption Commissioner found on the defendant's computer at the Public Prosecutor's Office, which listed his alleged receipt of 5.8 million patacas between 2011 and 2015.
Kong Chi stated that he had forgotten most of its contents, but indicated that the vast majority concerned the activities of the Hunan Countrymen's Association in Macau, while the rest was “difficult to speak freely”, since certain contents “involved official institutions, exchanges and national security”, subjects that he “could not, nor did he want, discuss”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 23:39:45</pubDate></item><item><title>China's assertive foreign policy and APEC: implications and challenges</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/a-politica-externa-assertiva-da-china-e-a-apec-implicacoes-e-desafios/</link><description>The Chinese delegation led by President Xi Jinping at the APEC Summit in Busan and his meeting with US President Donald Trump illustrated not only the implementation of China's great power diplomacy, but also China's assertive and positive foreign policy, with important implications for international politics in general and Asian security in particular.
Firstly, the meeting between President Xi and President Trump resulted in a temporary truce between the two sides. While China agreed to buy soybeans and other agricultural products from the US and control the flow of fentanyl to the US, the US side decided to freeze 24% reciprocal tariffs on Chinese products for a year and reduce fentanyl-related tariffs from 20% to 10%. Furthermore, China decided to suspend its control over the export of rare earths for a year, while the US temporarily suspended Section 301 investigations into China's maritime affairs, logistics and shipping industry for a year. China agreed to begin the process of purchasing power and natural gas from Alaska, while the US froze its control over exports to China for a year. This is a brief truce, as both sides seek more time.
Although the news was received positively by American farmers, international stock markets did not react enthusiastically to the temporary rapprochement in US-China relations. Many investors around the world are probably already aware of the instability of US foreign policy, marked by the use of reciprocal tariffs since Trump's second term.
The Trump administration claims a victory, but in reality it is a Pyrrhic victory, given that US soft power has been rapidly declining following the intimidating and worrying use of tit-for-tat tariffs. While Donald Trump seemed to rant incessantly and hug Xi Jinping in public appearances, President Xi showed coldness and smiled in a polite but much more reserved manner – an indication that the Chinese side was quite dissatisfied with American actions since Trump's second presidential victory. President Xi Jinping openly told President Trump during the negotiations that both sides should move in a positive direction despite diplomatic differences between the two countries. The Chinese president's positive tone was evident, but China's foreign policy has been marked by assertiveness – a strong element that reflects the fact that contemporary China is affected by the long historical legacy of the decadent and fragile Qing dynasty, and that China under Xi Jinping is keen to avoid being seen as a weak state in relation to the US. In fact, the concessions made by both China and the US prove that the People's Republic of China (PRC) has already become a great power, on par with the United States, demonstrating confidence, assertiveness and positivity at the negotiating table – a notable phenomenon in the era of international politics, in which the US projects an image of hegemony and defense of unilateralism, and China is eager to oppose hegemonism and support multilateralism. China is no longer the “sick man of Asia” as it was during the Qing dynasty, and as such the US and other countries need to understand the historical foundations of China's current assertive foreign policy.
Second, China's great power diplomacy is clearly shaped by an emphasis on multilateralism, as demonstrated by President Xi's speech at the APEC meeting, an open economic environment, global supply chain stability and mutually supportive development. A closer reading of these emphases points to China's commitment to maintaining an economically liberal world order and a stable supply chain. This means that Beijing supports a liberalized economic order and attaches importance to a rules-based world, unlike the explicitly self-protective stance demonstrated by the Trump 2.0 administration. Maintaining a stable global supply chain implies that China's recent attempt to control the export of rare earths was actually a self-defensive approach, not an offensive one, as described by China's most hard-line critics, in response to US attempts to use reciprocal tariffs to coerce other countries into making substantial economic concessions.
Third, amidst China's foreign policy assertion, we find the ingredient of positivity. Positivity means that despite other countries' perceptions and misconceptions about Beijing, Chinese leaders and negotiators have been “steadfast,” in Trump's words, and yet positive in seeking solutions. It was reported that the Chinese side mentioned the Taiwan issue and that Japan should have a “correct understanding” of China's position on history and Taiwan (Sing Tao Daily, November 1, 2025). Japan, under new Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi, has also raised the issues of the Senkaku Islands (Diaoyu Islands in Chinese), rare earths and the export of Japanese agricultural products to China. Clearly, both China and Japan laid out their positions in the relatively brief 30-minute meeting. The positive attitude of the Chinese side can be seen in the way its diplomatic statements were made and the way it expressed to the other negotiating party the need to “understand” Beijing's position. Thus, assertiveness and positivity are the two pillars of Chinese foreign policy in the era of President Xi Jinping.
Similarly, this assertiveness and positivity can be observed simultaneously in the meeting of Chinese Defense Minister, Dong Jun, with his American counterpart, Pete Hegseth, in Malaysia, on October 31st. While the US expressed its concerns about Chinese military moves in the South China Sea and the Taiwan Strait, China reiterated that the US should take concrete measures not to contain China and that it does not seek conflict (South China Morning Post, November 25, 2025). The United States’ perception of an “aggressive” China is understandable; however, it may not fully understand traditional Chinese views on sovereignty — a perspective deeply rooted in Chinese history, which predates even the Qing dynasty.
Fourth, the rise of China and its assertive and positive foreign policy have benefited Hong Kong. Hong Kong Chief Executive John Lee was seen sitting next to President Xi Jinping and met with Asian leaders, projecting an effective “one country, two systems” image under which the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region (HKSAR) is empowered by the central government in Beijing to conduct its own external affairs. John Lee met with Singapore Prime Minister Lawrence Wong, expressing the view that the HKSAR is well prepared for its entry into the RCEP and that Singaporean companies can invest in the Northern Metropolis. The Chief Executive of Hong Kong also met with the Crown Prince of Abu Dhabi in the United Arab Emirates, Sheikh Zayed Al Nahyan, stating that Hong Kong's simple and favorable tax regime can provide a good business environment for capital and companies from the UAE and the Middle East to invest in the Hetao Shenzhen-Hong Kong Scientific and Technological Innovation Cooperation Zone (Hong Kong Government News, October 31, 2025). Clearly, the HKSAR has benefited not only from the “one country, two systems” principle, but also from the protection of China's assertive and, at the same time, positive diplomacy as a great power.
Fifth, China's emphasis on maintaining a liberal economic order in the world and in Asia has important implications for global and Asian security. Globally, China expects the continuation of the liberal and multilateral trade regime, emphasizing sustainable development and world peace. Regionally, China is eager to help create a regional free trade area within ASEAN and explore the possibility of developing a trilateral free trade area between China, Japan and South Korea. The creation of a free trade area with ASEAN can and will certainly benefit more Asian countries, while the development of any free trade bloc comprising China, Japan and South Korea will likely have a stabilizing role in maintaining peace in Northeast Asia, where North Korea has been warily watching the APEC Summit unfold. North Korea may not be very pleased with China's active participation in the APEC Summit in South Korea, and its missile tests before Donald Trump's arrival in South Korea appeared to be a gesture to demonstrate its military strength. Thus, an economic bloc composed of China, Japan and South Korea can and will be a pragmatic measure that will likely attract North Korea's participation eventually, especially if Trump is willing to intervene as an intermediary between the Koreas. Japan considers North Korea a genuine military threat. Therefore, the Trump administration will have to reopen dialogue with North Korea's Kim Jong-un for an in-depth discussion on Pyongyang's nuclear energy development in exchange for international inspections and oversight of nuclear facilities. Until then, if the free trade zone between China, Japan and South Korea gains strength, it will give Trump more “bargaining chips” to talk to Kim Jong-un in a more productive way. In summary, China's effort to maintain regional free trade blocs in Southeast and Northeast Asia can and will contribute to the development of economic pragmatism and regional security.
It is clear that China's peaceful rise faces enormous challenges. Those who do not fully understand Chinese history are vulnerable to the misperception that China is an “aggressive” country that threatens the security and economic interests of the West. This misperception is very common and it takes time for China's skeptics and critics to study and understand how the weaknesses of the Qing dynasty impacted the People's Republic of China's drive for economic and military modernization, and how China under the Xi Jinping era considered assertiveness and positivity as the two pillars of an effective and respectable Chinese foreign policy in a turbulent world marked by sudden changes in US foreign policy, hegemonism, regional conflicts and deep mistrust. After all, Chinese foreign policy has been reshaped, revitalized, and readapted in a way that is essentially self-defensive, but also responsive to the drastic shift in U.S. foreign policy, which has turned to tit-for-tat tariffs as a way of extracting concessions from Washington's allies and enemies.
The US has increasingly viewed China as a threat to national security, especially the bold way in which China has attempted to use its control of rare earth minerals to counterbalance US reciprocal tariffs. The US has begun a search for more rare earth sources through its G7 alliance, its agreement with Ukraine, its harmonious relations with Australia and its diplomatic relations with Malaysia, Thailand, Canada and Brazil. The US would also be collaborating with members of the Mineral Security Partnership, which includes countries such as Finland, France, Germany, Italy, Sweden, Norway and the United Kingdom, to secure and diversify supply chains for rare earth minerals. It will take time for the US to reduce its dependence on China for these minerals. However, the meeting between Trump and Xi in South Korea has already shown that China did not hesitate to use rare earth export controls as a response to Washington's use of reciprocal tariffs as a coercive mechanism to negotiate concessions. In short, the US should not wait for China to return to the era of the fragile Qing dynasty.
In conclusion, the way China behaved at the APEC Summit and the Xi-Trump meeting in South Korea demonstrated that assertiveness and positivity are the two pillars of Chinese diplomacy as a great power. Assertiveness and positivity are, without a doubt, the essence of Chinese foreign policy. China does not hesitate to assert its position on issues that it considers fundamental to national security, sovereignty and development interests. At the same time, when China faces other countries, including neighbors such as Japan, on issues of fundamental disagreement, its leaders and diplomats adopt a positive stance, hoping that other countries can truly understand the Chinese perspective and that all parties sincerely explore ways to steer their differences along a peaceful path through dialogue, discussions and finding solutions. From this Chinese perspective, contradictions are often seen as natural, as President Xi told President Trump at the start of the Busan talks, and the challenge lies in how China and other countries with divergent positions and opinions can agree to disagree, build mutual trust and pursue the path of peaceful development in a win-win situation.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 23:25:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Zone A health post opened</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/inaugurado-posto-de-saude-da-zona-a/</link><description>The Health Center in Zone A of the New Urban Landfills was inaugurated on Wednesday, which began operating yesterday. In the first phase of operation, the health post in question is equipped with six health professionals and administrative staff to provide services to the first batch of inhabitants in that area.
This health center is located on Avenida do Mar de Espelho, Edifício Tong Chong, 1st floor, in Zone A of the New Urban Landfills, with a total area of ​​approximately 1,066 square meters. This post will provide services from Monday to Friday, from 8:30 am to 1:00 pm and from 2:30 pm to 6:00 pm, closing on Saturdays, Sundays and holidays.
The Zone A station will provide holistic, comprehensive, coordinated and continuous medical services covering the entire life cycle, including healthcare for children, women and adults in general, unscheduled outpatient consultations, prevention and treatment of chronic diseases, health promotion, general nursing care, vaccinations and provision of basic medicines, fully meeting the daily healthcare and health preservation needs of residents.
There are currently nine health centers and four health posts, including the Health Post of Zone A of the New Urban Landfills, which provide free community health care and preventive health care services to the entire local population, “forming a fine-tuned network of community medical and health services, and playing a key role in the integrated system of medical services in Macau”, reads the statement from the Health Services, which points out that, nowadays, more than 80% of patients with diseases chronic patients in Macau opt for health centers to receive treatment, “which demonstrates that the objective of global health coverage has been preliminarily achieved”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 23:33:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Almost 60 companies achieved Certified Store status</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/quase-60-empresas-obtiveram-qualidade-de-loja-certificada/</link><description>The Consumer Council reported that, by the end of October this year, 59 companies had already obtained the status of Macau and Hengqin Certified Store through the mutual recognition mechanism.
The information came as part of an exchange session organized jointly by the Macau Consumer Council (CC) and the Consumer Association of the Guangdong-Macao In-depth Cooperation Zone in Hengqin, which took place on Wednesday, on Mountain Island.
In this session, a presentation was made on the “advantages of the policies, the registration of market entities and the food inspection guidelines, followed by another presentation by the representative of a renowned online commerce platform on the tactics of joining the popular platform and digitalization, as well as the sharing of Macau and Hengqin Certified Stores on the new consumption trend and the cases of providing services honestly”.
According to the statement, consumer organizations from Macau and Hengqin promise to continuously deepen cooperation, optimize the mechanism of mutual recognition of Certified Stores, promote the in-depth interconnection of the Certified Store rules of Macau and Hengqin, and promote the rapprochement of the two places in terms of evaluation criteria, management and supervision of Certified Stores.
Leong Pek San, president of the Consumer Council, said on the occasion that he hopes that companies can explore a broader cooperation space, inspire the dynamism and innovation of companies in Macau and Hengqin, and also encouraged Macau Certified Stores to join the Hengqin Certified Store system after establishing themselves in the Cooperation Zone, “so as to ensure that consumers enjoy quality services and are protected whether they are in Macau or in the Zone of Cooperation”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 23:37:36</pubDate></item><item><title>“I do not see and would not like to see a preponderance of the executive power over the judicial power”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/nao-vejo-e-nao-gostaria-de-ver-preponderancia-do-poder-executivo-sobre-o-poder-judicial/</link><description>Lektou law firm was founded in Macau 40 years ago. In an interview with PONTO FINAL, Frederico Rato, founding partner, recalls the initial challenges and the firm's growth process. Lektou, which is now also in Portugal, Shenzhen and Hengqin, wants to grow, but slowly, with “logic and harmony”. In the interview, Frederico Rato argues that the judiciary in Macau continues to be independent and highlights that the region's legal system “has worked with complete efficiency and justice”.

The Lektou law firm is celebrating 40 years. Founded in 1985 by Rui Afonso, Francisco Gonçalves Pereira and Frederico Rato, the office is now also present in Portugal, Shenzhen and Hengqin. “We are serious and qualified professionals and we want to reproduce this way of being in the profession not only here but also in Portugal and Greater Bay Area”, stated Frederico Rato, in an interview with PONTO FINAL, adding that the office’s future objective is “to grow, but slowly”. In the interview, the founding partner of Lektou argues that the judiciary in Macau is independent: “I don't see and I wouldn't like to see a preponderance of the executive power over the judicial power”. Especially because “the judiciary is always an independent power when we talk about the Rule of Law”. Rato also praises the territory's legal system, inspired by the Portuguese matrix, saying that “it has worked effectively and fairly over the last 25 years”.

Going back 40 years, what was the process of establishing the office here in Macau like?
In the first half of the 1980s, with the arrival of Admiral Almeida e Costa in Macau, the Portuguese government was aware that the so-called decolonization, which had already occurred in all territories where Portugal was established, would have to reach Macau. It was not a decolonization strictly speaking because Macau was not a colony, but rather a Portuguese administration in Chinese territory. The times demanded that a solution be found for this very special coexistence of a European country administering a small portion of Chinese territory. In this sense, it was clear that talks would have to be held with this objective and it would be necessary to give Macau a more modern and advanced face. The Macau that the Portuguese rulers found after the 25th of April was a Macau with very high basic needs and, with the prospect of it becoming the subject of discussions between the People's Republic of China and Portugal, it was necessary to improve the conditions of the people who were here. It was necessary to provide Macau with a minimum of infrastructure so that, when administration was handed over to the People's Republic of China, there would be a certain dignity that included the well-being, comfort and economic development of the territory. In this sense, Almeida e Costa felt the need to recruit staff to the Republic to develop recovery plans for Macau's economic fabric. Contract proposals began to pour in for staff to come and prepare and execute the Portuguese local government plan. In this baggage of qualified labor, jurists had to come. Although there were few, the vast majority of Macau's jurists were in law, but jurists were needed for the Public Administration, to observe the laws, to develop a new structure for a more sanitized and modern Public Administration. Therefore, in the first half of the 1980s, many jurists arrived in Macau to help give the territory a new face. In this group, Dr. Francisco Gonçalves Pereira, Dr. Rui Afonso – both my friends and my course colleagues in Lisbon – and myself came. Doctor Gonçalves Pereira came to the Inspection of Economic Activities of the Economic Services Directorate, Doctor Rui Afonso came to the Administration and Public Service Services and I came as a jurist and lawyer for the Macau Electricity Company. We were friends, we maintained contacts in Macau and, after two years of stay, we started to think that we could open our own office and, in some way, bring a more modern and participatory contribution to local law. That's how things happened. Looking at the existing offices and the surge in development resulting from the creation of infrastructure and some new investments in Macau, we thought that the creation of an office would also be a good investment in social, economic, financial and even linguistic development for Macau, which was going to be reborn. We opened the office with ten people.

Nowadays, what is the total size of the office?
Nowadays, in Macau, we are 36 people, including 15 lawyers, eight trainee lawyers, two jurists, ten people in administrative and financial coordination headed by a CEO.

What challenges did you encounter at the time of the foundation?
The first challenge was trying to find a central location in Macau that would allow us to open an office with maximum comfort for both those who work and the clients we were going to receive. We chose the Luso Internacional building, which was in fact very central, very modern, very accessible and expensive. Another challenge was the language because all three of us spoke very poor and incipient Cantonese, so we had to recruit bilingual secretaries and a translator-interpreter. Another challenge was to establish ourselves as providers of legal services with rigor and seriousness, showing ourselves to potential clients as serious workers in the legal field. Our establishment as a law firm ended up being successful, we gradually achieved professional success.

Highlight some of the most memorable key moments for the office?
The decision of the founders of this law firm to put into practice the “principle of continuity”, the political-diplomatic and doctrinal basis of the Joint Declaration. Another moment, extended over time, has been the coming together of our professionals and the combined efforts of everyone to preserve, improve and apply the legal-normative system of Roman-Germanic origin, warmly thanking everyone who works here and those who passed through here. Finally, another moment that gives us great joy and honor is that, over these 40 years, we have been a center for the training of independent legal professions, for example, judicial magistrates and the Public Prosecutor's Office, lawyers, jurists from the Public Administration and private companies and notaries, serving the second system, as a guarantor of the Rule of Law in the region.

40 years ago, did you think the office could become what it is today?
We had no idea. We thought we were going to stay at Luso Internacional for a long time, but after 12 years we ended up having to leave because there was no more space for more lawyers, trainee lawyers and assistants and we had to move here to Landmark and then we started to enjoy better conditions. It was a slow but considered and cautious growth. Obviously, at the time we didn't have the idea of ​​occupying a floor entirely at Landmark.

What plans do you have for the future? Are there any goals set?
Grow but slowly, grow on firm ground. Our growth process has been consistent, without taking high-risk steps. We also grew abroad, first heading to Portugal, in Lisbon and Porto. We also have two branches in Asia in Hengqin and Shenzhen. We want to develop them with logic and harmony. These are our plans for the future.

Could Lektou's development involve having more locations?
Not at this moment. We are in Hengiqn due to the existence of the Deep Cooperation Zone. Our presence in Shenzhen has to do with the dynamics that are beginning to emerge in the Greater Bay Area. Our objective is to maintain and improve, we have no intention of becoming a large international group, we are serious and qualified professionals and we want to reproduce this way of being in the profession not only here but also in Portugal and the Greater Bay Area.

Nowadays, what challenges do you face?
Some, namely the great technological advances and discoveries, which force us to always be up to date with what is being done. These advances in our profession must be monitored on a daily basis because they are always interfering with our daily practice. Now we have the great challenge of artificial intelligence, which is an extraordinary advance, it even has many substantial links to our profession, but we need to be careful. We are dealing with people, with people's heritage, with people's dignity and honor and with the exercise of people's rights. Artificial intelligence can be a double-edged sword, it can be a great factor in the development and advancement of the human condition, but it can also be an instrument of deception, fraud and greater slavery. You have to be very careful. Artificial intelligence is not the canon that should be accepted unconditionally, it is already being widely used in many professions, but in relation to law, law and justice, it is necessary to use and apply it with great criteria and discernment.

Here in the office, in daily work, are artificial intelligence tools used?
We already use it, although it is not regular use. It's exceptional. It is used with great care and great discretion. No artificial intelligence output comes out without being harshly reviewed, criticized, confronted and evaluated.

Are there other factors of concern for the future, besides artificial intelligence?
We are all living in a world in turmoil, threatened by major dissensions and conflicts over which we have no control and we do not know how they will develop. It is the challenge for peace and it concerns all of us. We can only live and work if we are in a peaceful environment. Our constitution as human beings requires the existence of peace, this is our great challenge both as citizens and as professionals.

Is Macau very different from what it was in 1985?
Macau's development over the last 40 years has been spectacular. In the first half of the 80s, Macau was a quiet village, a place of great placidity, where apparently nothing special happened. Today's Macau is completely different, fortunately with its historic center preserved. At its core and in its historic area, Macau remains preserved and there is a desire to maintain and improve its urban and historical hull, but the urban growth area, namely in Taipa and Coloane and Cotai, has radically changed its face. From an urban point of view, there are two Macaus: the old town on the peninsula, which has had improvements that enrich it; and there is the Macau of gaming operators in Cotai, which is the second heart of Macau, where its biggest source of reserves beats, which is gaming. Macau is a unique example of fraternization and multiculturalism and it is this Macau that we have to show.

Is the legal profession very different from what it was 40 years ago?
The legal practice that takes place in Macau today is much more internationalized. 40 years ago, the advocacy we did was much more internal, for businessmen, industrialists, builders and traders in Macau, and had a small international component. Today, this international aspect of commercial and financial contacts probably represents more than 50% of our activity. On the one hand, commercial and industrial activity has fallen drastically in recent years, on the other hand there has been a great development in Macau's relations with the outside world, which has meant that the type of law we practice today has an international component that exceeds half of our activity.

Does a Portuguese lawyer in Macau have as many conditions to work here as he did 40 years ago?
It doesn't, in fact. The entry of a Portuguese lawyer into the legal system of Macau as a professional of that same system and as a processor of the legal system is no longer so easy. 40 years ago we were under Portuguese administration, it is natural that the movement of Portuguese professionals would be much easier. With the resumption of sovereignty by the People's Republic of China, the legal profession evidently demonstrated that the influx of law graduates from Macau's universities became much greater. The production of Chinese mother tongue law graduates began to be much greater and evidently there was a reaction to the entry of new Portuguese lawyers into this socio-professional fabric. As a matter of self-defense, which is understandable, Chinese lawyers defend their positions of some predominance in the choice of clients whose clients are mostly Chinese-speaking. It is natural that there may be greater rarefaction and less facilitation of entry for Portuguese-speaking lawyers into the Macau Lawyers Association. Not only due to the pressure of the supply of Chinese lawyers, the laws on establishing residence and exercising professional functions have also been changed, both of which make it difficult for Portuguese lawyers to settle in Macau. The protocol that existed between the Macau Lawyers Association and the Portuguese Bar Association is suspended. This agreement provided for the equivalence of legitimacy for the exercise of duties by Portuguese lawyers in Macau and vice versa. If this agreement is suspended, it will become very difficult, under conditions of dignity and full exercise of their functions, for Portuguese lawyers to practice again in Macau. It's the reality we have.
PHOTOGRAPHY ANDRÉ VINAGRE
And does a lawyer who already practices his profession in Macau have the same conditions as he did?
I think so. Here the question of language arises again. The overwhelming majority of magistrates, whether judicial or from the Public Prosecutor's Office, speak Chinese as their mother tongue, but are bilingual. This means that the courts currently operate mainly in Chinese. For the Portuguese-speaking lawyer, today it is not the same as when there was some prevalence of the Portuguese language. Working conditions in terms of performance in courts of first, second and last instance and even in some pre-processes that may be carried out by the Public Administration, become more difficult depending on language proficiency. However, the use of the Portuguese language in any documents of a procedural nature is ensured and the translation and use of the Portuguese language in the arguments that lawyers present is also ensured. Evidently, this right can be fully exercised in the Portuguese language and we are convinced that this will be true until 20249.

Is the judiciary in Macau independent of the executive branch?
I would tell you, in an assessment without overly inflated comments, that the judiciary is independent of the executive and legislative powers. There is more and more talk about the preponderance of the executive power, but this preponderance of the executive power is more visible over the legislative power. I do not see and would not like to see a preponderance of the executive power over the judicial power. I want to continue to interpret the Basic Law as the source of three separate powers, judicial, legislative and executive, with executive preponderance but without intervention in the judicial function.

But at the opening of the judicial year, the Chief Executive asked the judicial bodies to protect the political system characterized by the predominance of the executive - the Chief Executive stated that "the administrative, legislative and judicial bodies are the indispensable pillars of the Macao SAR in terms of political power and governance; therefore, in addition to fulfilling the functions assigned by law, they must also safeguard the political structure characterized by the predominance of the executive power". Shouldn’t the independence of judicial bodies from the Executive branch also be a fundamental component of the Rule of Law?
Doctor Sam Hou Fai is not telling the judicial bodies, to which he belonged at the highest level, that the legislative and judicial powers are subordinate to the executive, but rather that the judicial bodies take into account the predominance of the executive power. This is my conception. He is telling the judicial bodies to take into account that in this political system there is a predominance of the executive over the legislative.

In your interpretation, what the Chief Executive says is that there is a predominance of the executive over the legislative, not necessarily over the judicial?
From my perspective, the judiciary is always an independent power when talking about the Rule of Law. The predominance belongs to the executive in relation to the political system, not in relation to the judicial system.

In 2020, the current Chief Executive and at the time president of the TUI suggested a reflection on the “challenges and problems” of applying the Macau legal system, which is inspired by the Portuguese system. Are there signs of a move away from Macau's legal system towards Portuguese inspiration?
I don't know exactly what he meant by that. What is certain is that the legal system in force in Macau, very inspired by Portuguese systems, has worked effectively and fairly over the last 25 years. One of the great interpreters of its application was doctor Sam Hou Fai.

How do you anticipate Macau’s future until 2049? Will there be a Portuguese presence until that date?
The Portuguese matrix will always be part of Macau. The next 25 years will be unknown. When Deng Xiaoping, following Zhou Enlai, enunciated the principle “one country, two systems” and then developed it from a doctrinal point of view and in practice, what I thought at the time was that in 2049, the second system would have infected the first system and the second system would bring about major changes in the first system, from an economic, financial, commercial and cultural point of view. At the moment I'm not sure, but I think that the recentralization of political power in the People's Republic of China is capable of giving a new interpretation and application of the concept “one country, two systems” and “Macau governed by its people”, so we look forward to seeing what the next generations that reach power can determine.

You mentioned that you thought there would be contamination of the first system by the second, but isn't the opposite happening?
What is happening now is a coexistence with a predominance of contamination in reverse.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Delta Bridge with restricted traffic on Saturday</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/06/ponte-do-delta-com-transito-condicionado-no-sabado/</link><description>Road traffic on the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge will be restricted tomorrow morning due to the men's individual road cycling event at the National Games.
Traffic restrictions will be implemented between 9:00 am and 12:30 pm on Saturday, affecting directions from Macau to Zhuhai, Macau to Hong Kong, Zhuhai to Hong Kong and Zhuhai to Macau.
According to the Traffic Affairs Bureau (DSAT), from 8am on that day, access for people and vehicles, including logistics and cargo, to the Macau Border Post Building and the traffic lanes of the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge will be prohibited. Control from Hong Kong to Zhuhai and Macau will be in effect between 7:30 am and 12:30 pm. The departure hall of the Delta Bridge Hong Kong Border Post Building and the border plaza for departing vehicles will be closed at 6:30 am on the same day.
During the control period, cross-border traffic, including golden buses, airport shuttle buses, cross-border buses between Hong Kong and Macau and intercity rental vehicles, will be temporarily suspended.
Regarding the provisional traffic and bus measures, part of the access roads of Macau Bridge and Wai Long Avenue will be closed to traffic from 2am on the same day, while some roads in the Pac On area and Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau South Border Avenue will implement traffic restrictions from 7am. It is expected that 11 bus routes will be affected. The measures should end at 10:30 am, depending on the progress of the race.
DSAT draws public attention to the aforementioned restrictions, recommending that the necessary time be reserved for travel or that, during the affected period, other border posts be used. In this case, DSAT suggests that citizens and tourists who intend to travel between Hong Kong and Macau may choose to use sea transport.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 23:33:49</pubDate></item></channel></rss>