<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/alunos-da-upm-ganham-premios-de-ouro-e-bronze-em-concurso-de-inovacao-medica/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Cultural Week of China and Portuguese-speaking countries will extend to Beijing and Zhongshan</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/semana-cultural-da-china-e-dos-paises-de-lingua-portuguesa-vai-estender-se-a-pequim-e-zhongshan/</link><description>The 17th Cultural Week of China and Portuguese -speaking countries will be held between the end of September and mid -November. One of the news of this edition is that the initiative extends to Zhongshan and Beijing.

The 17th Cultural Week of China and Portuguese-speaking countries will take place between September 26 and November 18 and, for the first time, will also extend to the cities of Beijing and Zhongshan, yesterday indicated the permanent secretariat of the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, which organizes the event.
The initiative will bring together cultural and artistic groups from nine countries, including China (Qinghai Province), Angola, Brazil, Cape Verde, Guinea-Bissau, Equatorial Guinea, Mozambique, Portugal, Sao Tome and Principe and Timor-Leste. There will also be a Craft Fair, culinary demonstrations and stands with products from Portuguese and Macao countries. The inauguration ceremony, which will take place at the fishermen's dock on September 26, will bring together Portuguese chefs and local catering companies to create special menus with delicacies with flavors from Lusophone countries.
On start-up day, the inauguration of the exposure and transmission of China-Portugal audiovisual works will be inaugurated at the Macao University of Science and Technology (Must). The event will include the display of a documentary that aims to “strengthen mutual learning between the Chinese and the Portuguese -speaking countries”.
The Macau Forum also highlights an art exhibition from Portuguese -speaking countries and the launch of a book on Lusophone Literature, which will take place in the Institute's Gallery for Municipal Affairs, on October 24, presenting works by artists from various Portuguese -speaking countries. The exhibition will take place from October 25 to November 18. In addition, during the cultural week, the book of the work “Is this book a novel?”, By Angolan author João Melo will be made. The book has been translated into Chinese and will be released simultaneously in mainland China and Macao.
For the first time, the event is not only held in Macau. In Zhongshan, in Xingzhong Square, music and dance performances will be held and an exhibition of works from Portuguese-speaking countries at the Xiangshan Commercial and Cultural Museum. Beijing's stage, headquartered at Beiped Shopping Park Plaza, will feature music and dance performances, as well as promotional activities of artistic groups.
This edition aims to “leverage the unique advantages of Macao as a platform for China and Portuguese-speaking countries, consolidating cultural week as a striking event that demonstrates the successful implementation of the" a country, two systems "principle, promoting integral exchange between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, spreading Chinese culture and promoting mutual learning between civilizations," the Macau Forum.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:28:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau rises a place in the FIFA ranking</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/macau-sobe-um-lugar-no-ranking-da-fifa/</link><description>The selection of Macao de Football went up a place in the FIFA ranking, now being in 191st position. The Portuguese football team also went up a position, but for fifth place in the ranking that was released yesterday and which has Spain as a new leader, while Argentina, world champion and previous commander, fell to third place.
Portugal climbed a position in the FIFA hierarchy, surpassing Brazil, after the qualification games for the 2026 World Cup, in which Armenia thrashed 5-0 and won Hungary 3-2, isolating himself in the leading of the FL Group of finding. The most significant change happened at the top, with Spain rising to first place -something that has not happened since 2014 -, dislocating Argentina, which was also outdated by France, a new second classified. Germany, which occupied the ninth position in the previous classification, published on July 10, was removed from the Top-10, having fallen to 12th, which allowed Croatia to rise to ninth place and the entry of Italy in the first 10 positions.
Of the African countries of Portuguese Language (Palop), Cape Verde is the best classified in 70th position, having climbed three, ahead of Angola (89), trained by Portuguese Pedro Gonçalves, and Mozambique (97). Oman, who has the Portuguese Carlos Queiroz as a coach, is 78.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 23:03:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Madeira Global Forum returns to Macau this year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/forum-global-da-madeira-regressa-este-ano-a-macau/</link><description>This year's Global and Sustainable Madeira Forum (GLSTF) will take place in Macao, between September 23 and 24, at MGM Cotai. This is the third consecutive year in which the forum takes place at MSAR.

This year's theme is “from Forest to Home-International Dialogue on Consumer and Innovation Trends in the Supply Chain” and the program includes close to 20 activities, including conferences, roundtables, exhibitions, B2B business meetings and launch sessions. "It is expected that the key actors of the forest, wood and domestic furniture industries, coming from over 40 countries, gather in Macao, looking for exchanges and high quality cooperation," says the press release released yesterday by the Institute for Commerce and Investment Promotion (IPIM).
This is an international forum of annual character that focuses on the worldwide forest and wood sector. GLSTF intends to “facilitate, based on Macao's convention and exhibition platform, the implementation of various international cooperation results and transnational action plans”.
This year's edition will focus on the search side, with the program of thematic conferences that cover the entire chain of the forest industry and the furniture and housing sector, from the management of forest resources to the consumer market, furniture and housing, exploring new guidelines in innovation and technological transformation.
Among the conferences, the following stand out: “Consumer Trends in the Global Industry of Madeira and Innovation in the Supply Chain”, “New Trends of Wood Products and Furniture and Decoration Industry”, “LEGALITY AND SUSTAINABILITY OF WOODS-Facing the uncertainties of Madeira's global commercial barriers”, “Sustainable Wood, Markets and Commerce-Innovative and Sustainable”, “Trends”, “Trends”, “trends” Market and development of the personalized home furnishings and decoration for the home - green and intelligent training, trends synergy ”and“ sustainable development of global forests and supply chain financing - forest supply chain financing and appreciation of ecological products ”.
In parallel, sustainable wood exhibition is also held, with about 30 stands available for companies, international organizations and wood and domestic furniture associations, from countries and regions such as Germany, Brazil, Indonesia, Malaysia, Thailand, Switzerland, Japan, Italy, various provinces and cities in China, as well as Macau. Forest and wood products will be exhibited, including blasts, sawn wood, furniture, wooden floors, wood derived panels, wooden doors and wooden crafts.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:26:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese Minister of Defense denounces “hegemonic logic” in the world</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/ministro-da-defesa-chines-denuncia-logicas-hegemonicas-em-curso-no-mundo/</link><description>Chinese Defense Minister Dong Jun guaranteed yesterday that the country is against the “hegemonic logics” that “are underway in the world” in a context of growing rivalry with the United States.

"History should serve as a permanent reminder to identify and oppose the hegemonic logic and the acts of disguised intimidation in a new form," said Dong, in front of several hundred military and civilian officers and Chinese and foreign experts gathered in Beijing for the Xiangshan Forum, the largest conference dedicated to China on defense and security issues.
The minister stressed that his speech coincided with the anniversary of the incident of Mukden, a false attack orchestrated by the Japanese Army in 1931 to justify the invasion of the northeast of Chinese territory. These events are seen in China as a historical humiliation.
The minister warned of the "new threats" who weigh on peace, in a context of geopolitical tensions and competition on all fronts with the United States. "The clouds that constitute a cold war mentality, hegemonism and protectionism have not dissipated," Dong said, without explicitly quoting the United States.
The minister addressed the defense of China's sea interests, at a time when former territorial sovereignty disputes and friction abound in regional waters in a context of competition with the United States Alliance System. "The alleged freedom of navigation defended by some countries outside the region and the alleged international arbitration invoked by some parts flagling the fundamental rules of international relations," he said.
By ensuring the safeguarding of its maritime and territorial rights and interests, China “firmly defends the postwar order and respect for international law,” he said.

Consensus to protect the international order

Dong Jun yesterday asked “consensus and union of efforts to protect international order” during the Xiangshan Forum in Beijing, the main annual military event of the Asian country. "Safety risks can be overcome through equality and mutual benefit, and together we can create a stable political environment for long -term peace and world stability," Dong said before defense delegates from various countries.
The Chinese minister urged, during the inauguration of the first plenary session of the Forum, to the implementation of "measures to manage safety tensions and achieve balanced development."
Dong highlighted the importance of “cooperation mechanisms” in the military level of what he described as “multiple security challenges” in the international context, while signaling that China is “willing to work with all peace-loving forces to firmly defend the achievements of victory in World War II and the international postwar order”.
Dong added that the country is willing to "help the armed forces of all countries strengthen their abilities to defend their legitimate rights and interests and jointly assume the historical responsibility of maintaining world peace."
The minister also highlighted the importance of “international consultations” and “clear norms” in “emerging areas such as artificial intelligence, marine depths and space” and their “risks and challenges”.


Taiwan belongs “unequivocally” to China

China's Minister of Defense stated that "Taiwan's historical and legal belonging to China is unquestionable," during the Beijing Xiangshan Forum. Dong Jun said before Defense Delegates from several countries that the popular liberation army (ELP, the Chinese army) "will never allow any separatist attempt to triumph in Taiwan.
During the inauguration of the first plenary session of the forum, the Chinese minister added that the ELP "has always been an invincible and powerful force in defense of the unity of the country."
Dong also indicated that China is “ready to thwart any external military interference,” a veiled reference to the United States, the Taiwan's main gun supplier and could defend the island in the event of a Chinese attack.
Beijing this week celebrates the Xiangshan Forum, the main annual meeting of Chinese military diplomacy, with delegations from more than a hundred countries, including Russia, France, Vietnam, Singapore, Nigeria and Brazil, and international organizations.
Under the motto “Maintain international order and promote peaceful development”, the program extends until this Friday. The agenda addresses global security, the relations between great powers, Asia Pacific, the political conflict resolution, the weaponry control, the new technologies, and the evolution of war, in a year marked by the 80th anniversary of the end of World War II and the UN foundation.
The forum arrives two weeks after the September 3 parade in Beijing, where the popular liberation army (ELP, the Chinese army) exhibited hypersonic weapons, unmanned air vehicles ('drones') and intercontinental ballistic missiles.
At the same time, the Chinese army crosses internal turbulence: Rocket Force recently suspended several experts and suppliers for irregularities in signings, while the Central Military Commission (the maximum military leading body) released guidelines to reinforce discipline and integrity after corruption scandals involving two former defense ministers.
The Xiangshan Forum aims to be the Chinese equivalent of Shangri-LA dialogue, the main meeting of its kind in Asia, organized annually in Singapore. About 1,800 guests from over 100 countries are announced in Beijing for the three days of conference until Friday. Most western countries are not represented at a high level. Representing the United States is the Defense Attachment of its embassy in Beijing. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 23:05:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Approved reconstruction of the former residence of CTT workers near the red market</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/aprovada-reconstrucao-da-antiga-residencia-dos-trabalhadores-dos-ctt-perto-do-mercado-vermelho/</link><description>The Council of Urban Planning (CPU) gave green light to the project to reconstruct the former residence of workers of the Directorate of Post and Telecommunications Services (CTT). The building, now with ground floor floor for the Red Market Library, is located between Avenida do Almirante Lacerda and Avenida do Ouvidor Arriaga.
According to the plant of urban conditions, the land in question has an area of ​​298 square meters and is not integrated into the cultural heritage protection zone.
The project, which was appreciated yesterday at the CPU plenary meeting for the second time, foresees the maintenance of the purpose of land such as housing, commercial or tourist and amusement soils, with a maximum allowed height of construction of 20.5 meters.
According to the opinion of services to traffic issues, in the lot, you should build an access to the superior passage to public pawns, which will connect to the Doca do Lam Mau zone. In this case, spaces are reserved for vertical communications, independent access and support components for upper pass for public pedestrians.
Quoted by Radio Macao in Chinese language, the Department of Urban Planning of the Directorate of Soil Services and Urban Construction (DSSCU) suggested the extent of that higher passage to Camões Shopping Center. It admitted, however, that the proposal would require the resolution of questions related to the 24 -hour operation and spatial modifications, requiring the consent of the property owner.
At yesterday's meeting, several CPU members were concerned about cultural loss if the building was demolished and rebuilt, taking into account its history and aquatectic values.
It is recalled that the former residence of CTT workers is the work of Portuguese architect Manuel Vicente from the 1960s. The members stressed that the building adopts a duplex residential structure, having unique characteristics such as “exploration of modernist architecture” to urban housing buildings.
The Department of Cultural Heritage of the Cultural Institute (IC), in the answer, pushed the concerns away. According to the body, although the building in question does not comply with the patrimonial standards, the authorities have been following the documentation of the works of renowned architects from Macao and "have already compiled the relevant information."</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:25:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing widens tax collection on income abroad</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/pequim-alarga-cobranca-de-impostos-sobre-rendimentos-no-estrangeiro/</link><description>China is intensifying the collection of income taxes abroad, widening the inspection to less rich citizens after last year, mainly focused on ultramionaires, the Bloomberg news agency yesterday reported yesterday.

According to sources cited by the agency, authorities are scrutinizing a wide range of offshore income, including investment gains, dividends and employee action options. These income can be taxed up to 20%.
In recent months, tax service providers have registered an increase in requests for clients with less than one million dollars in assets, in contrast to the 2024 campaign, which aimed at individuals with a heritage of over 10 million. Chinese residents with offshore investments, especially in actions in the United States and Hong Kong, are among the main targets, according to Bloomberg.
Beijing seeks to reinforce tax revenue and reduce a record budget deficit after intensifying the stimulus to counteract the effects of US tariffs. Local governments, pressured by the prolonged crisis of the real estate sector and the breakdown, could no longer count on the sale of land or the excessive resource for indebtedness.
Between January and April, the total revenue of the central government fell 1.3%in homologous terms, while the expense increased by 7.2%, causing the deficit to firing more than 50%, to more than $ 360 billion - the highest value ever for the period, according to Bloomberg calculations based on Ministry of Finance data.
At the same time, Chinese investors have transferred more wealth out of the country, given economic slowdown and increased inspection over the private sector. The policy of “common prosperity” promoted by Chinese President Xi Jinping also affected trust, although Beijing recently launched efforts to restore it among entrepreneurs.
This year alone, interior investors channeled about $ 658 billion from Hong Kong for Hong Kong -listed actions through the transionic connection mechanism, more than double the net exits recorded in the same period as 2024.
According to a source quoted by Bloomberg, the Ministry of Finance sees margin to increase revenue through a closer inspection on income subject to not declared or identified.
Several tax services in Beijing, Shanghai and Provinces such as Zhejiang issued warnings for residents to check their earnings abroad and submit statements by June 30, deadline for delivery of the 2024 performance.
Since March, local authorities have been coordinated after analyzing large databases have revealed residents who omitted offshore income. In some cases disclosed, the amounts charged in late taxes and fines were 127,200 yuan.
The new offensive follows China's adhesion in 2018 to the Common Reporting Standard (CRS), a global information sharing system designed to prevent fiscal dropout. Although the legislation has always stipulated the taxation of world income, last year alone the rule was more systematically applied. According to Bloomberg Intelligence estimates, personal financial assets in mainland China could reach $ 80 billion by 2030, with investments abroad to rise to 11% of the total, compared to 8% in 2023. Lusa.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 23:05:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Spanish tourist died by asphyxiation after robbery in Indonesia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/turista-espanhola-morreu-por-asfixia-apos-assalto-na-indonesia/</link><description>Matilde Muñoz, the 72 -year -old Spanish tourist murdered during a robbery at a hotel on Indonesia's island of Lombok, "died by asphyxiation," the autopsy confirmed. Authorities continue to investigate the case.

According to the police report, cited by the EFE news agency, the death by asphyxiation "reinforces the suspicion that [Matilde Muñoz] was the victim of violence." "The exam has revealed signs of head, cervical and thoracic trauma," added a statement from the Western Lombok Police.
María Matilde Muñoz Carzola's corpse, known as Mati, was found on 30 August buried on a beach located about 500 meters from the hotel where he was staying, about two months after being missed. Body has been changed by site several times until it was buried
The suspects-a 30- and 34-year-old former hotel employee-revealed that Mati's body was first transferred from his Bungalow at the Bumi Aditya hotel in Senggigi's area to divide the hotel generator, where he remained for four days.  Then the body was placed on the hotel rear and in August was taken to a vacant lot outside the hotel.
According to police, “the remains of the victim were transferred and buried on the beach” on August 24, after the authorities began to investigate the disappearance.
The suspects were arrested on the day the body was found by crimes of "qualified homicide and theft with violence." According to police, both confessed to the crime, but have been charged to each other.
Although the two men confessed to the crime, Mati's family believes there are more involved. "It's not just the two. There are more people involved, we firmly believe yes," Ignacio Vilariño told the Spanish news agency Efe.
Before the body was found, the family had already considered that a "classic crime" was at stake and asked Indonesia and Interpol authorities to intensify the investigations and listen to the hotel staff where they were hosted, believing they were "involved in everything."
According to Vilariño, hotel employees and managers presented "so evident contradictions that they leave no doubt" of a possible involvement.
By the time the disappearance was denounced in mid -August, Nurmala Hayati, an accommodation accountant, explained that the Spaniard was admitted for the first time at the hotel around “June 12” and “extended her stay” at the establishment on July 2 until the 20th of this month. The woman paid in advance and said she "went to the beach."  "After that, I never saw it again," he told Efe. "On July 5, the hotel staff told me that Matilde had not returned since July 2. I sent her a message through WhatsApp, but she didn't receive her. It was only on July 6 that she replied to say she was in Laos. I didn't send her more messages," Hayati added.
However, according to the nephew, the message sent to the hotel contained serious spelling errors, which were "atypical of her." A similar message was sent to your group of friends, but the family believes it may be an alibi for those involved.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 23:04:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Hengqin welcomes almost 30,000 workers and residents of Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/hengqin-acolhe-quase-30-mil-trabalhadores-e-moradores-de-macau/</link><description>Completing four years since its inauguration, the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin has almost 30,000 Macao residents living or working there, with a 23.8%annual rise. According to statistics, until July this year, 521 students from Macau are studying on Mountain Island, while the number of companies funded by Macau has increased to more than seven thousand.

Almost 30,000 residents of Macau have already moved to work and live in Hengqin. The number, according to the authorities, has been increasing in recent years. With a total of 29,216 people until July this year, the number of inhabitants and workers from Macau has a growth of 23.8% over the same period last year. The sum also represents 64.8% of the population registered in Hengqin.
The in -depth cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin has celebrated four years of birthday since its official opening.
According to data updated by the Directorate of Hengqin Statistics Services until July this year, the number of Macao residents living in Hengqin reached 24,439 people, with an increase of 26.2% in annual terms of 19,367 Natural inhabitants of Macao.
There are still 5,952 holders of the resident identity ticket of Macao working in Hengqin, a number that witnessed an increase of 16.8% in a year.
Regarding the transfronical crossing between Hengqin and Macao, from January to July, 16.13 million tickets were total, of which 3.45 million were made by Macao residents.
Already the number of business entities funded by Macau increased by almost 16%, in one year, to 7,461, including 7,303 companies with Macao capital. Macao capital entities represent 12.5% ​​of total business entities operating in Hengqin, ie an increase of 1.5 percentage points compared to the same period last year.
"There is a higher concentration of business entities with capital of Macao," said Hengqin authorities, adding that their quota part in the total of business entities in the cooperation zone "continues to grow".
It is recalled that the central government has promulgated the general project of construction of the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin on September 5, 2021, whose administrative organizations opened on September 17 of the same year. It was a project of Beijing that aims to “create conditions for diversified development of the industries of Macao” and “contribute to the [Macao] integration at the conjuncture of national development”.
The increase in Macao residents who have been living in Hengqin may be due to the great effort to promote the Macao government, including the Macao neighborhood of Macau in Hengqin and the school for Macao students on the mountain island. The policies launched by the Hengqin government offer benefits to medical and entrepreneurial professionals to develop their career.
Statistics indicate that the number of hong Kong and Macao resident professionals who exercise hengqin cross -border professions reached 1,647 individuals. This number includes 179 doctors registered in Macao, 769 tourist professionals, 461 construction experts, 95 design experts, 12 real estate management professionals, 63 lawyers, 11 social workers and 54 tax professionals.
On the other hand, until July there were 521 students from Macao who started studying on Mountain Island, an exponential climb of 90% compared to the same height last year, with 274 students. Among them, 186 are in kindergarten, 289 are in primary education, while 46 are in secondary education.
On Mountain Island, a school was inaugurated a school for students from Macao, the HENGQin school attached to Hou Kong school, which is currently making a kindergarten and a primary school available.
In its first year of operation, eight classes were opened with about 260 students. Already this school year, to satisfy the search for enrollment, ten classes were created for each level of basic and preschool, increasing the admission of students up to 600 people.
The school foresees the opening of a secondary education session for next year, with the estimate of creating six classes per school level.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:29:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau should be affected by two cyclones in just seven days</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/macau-devera-ser-afectado-por-dois-ciclones-em-apenas-sete-dias/</link><description>Two cyclones are approaching the coast of Guangdong, bringing the possibility of precipitation, thunderstorms, strong winds and floods between this weekend and next week. Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) warn of the “unpredictable” trajectory of systems and advise the population to remain attentive to the information issued by the authorities.

The Directorate of Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) has announced that two tropical cyclones are currently approaching Macao, and the former should require the issuance of alert signal No. 1 as of today. As a consequence, the time between this weekend and next week is unstable and with a strong possibility of thunder and thunderstorms.
The Mitag Tropical Cyclone - as it should be baptized - is the first to enter the area of ​​influence of Macau. Originating in the Philippines, the low pressure system evolved into tropical depression as it approached the eastern coast of Guangdong. The trajectory foreseen by the SMG indicates that the phenomenon will enter within 800 kilometers of Macao this morning, when the tropical storm signal should be issued No. 1.
The most proximity height of the Rio das Pearl estuary will take place between Saturday and Sunday, days that should be marked by a very cloudy sky, water, thunderstorms and winds that can reach level 6 on the Beauford scale (with the classification of “very fresh”). The accumulated precipitation will be “relatively high” and may give rise to potential floods, especially in low areas, so the population is advised to take preventive measures.
According to an informative note published yesterday by the authorities, the “small circulation” of Mitag suggests that it should slow after reaching the eastern coast of Guangdong, although there are “great uncertainties about the trajectory and development of intensity” of this tropical disturbance.

Second cyclone still with many uncertainties

This should not be the only storm to plague Macau in the coming days. Another weather phenomenon is currently achieving shape in the northwest of the Pacific Ocean, and it is expected to acquire the status of tropical cyclone “with wide circulation and high intensity”.
SMG estimates that the system should enter the Southern Sea of ​​China “early next week”, although “significant discrepancies” are found between numerical forecast models and projections of artificial intelligence models. Traditional models anticipate that the cyclone cross the area north of the Southern Sea of ​​China and Assole Macau - and the Guangdong coast - with "considerable winds." On the other hand, artificial intelligence models provide for the eastern coast of Guangdong to be the most affected.
Authorities warn that the influence of two successive tropical cyclones facilitates the occurrence of "overlapping weather disasters" and causes "atmospheric conditions to have immense fluctuations." This is, therefore, a time when the weather forecasts are still on “a high degree of uncertainty”, requiring continuous monitoring of the authorities and the in -time prevention of residents.
Between today and tomorrow, the region will remain on alert yellow for high temperatures, with maximums that will reach 32 degrees Celsius. By the end of Friday, thunderstorms and thunderstorms may already occur that will intensify on the weekend, accompanied by a slight descent from temperatures to 29 degrees Celsius. On Tuesday, after Mitag's passage and before the influence of the second cyclone (still unnamed), the sky will be unloved and the maxims will rise again to the 33 degrees Celsius.

It is recalled that in May, the authorities anticipated that Macao be plagued by about five to eight storms throughout the typhoons, usually included between June and October. Accounting these two new phenomena approaching Macao, the number of cyclones that occurred in 2025 rises to 11.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:30:06</pubDate></item><item><title>University of Macau promotes inclusion and diversity in the International Night 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/universidade-de-macau-promove-inclusao-e-diversidade-na-noite-internacional-2025/</link><description>The University of Macao Global Affairs Office (UM) held the “International Night 2025” on September 12, at a ceremony that brought together more than 250 students from 45 countries such as Portugal, Egypt, India or Sao Tome and Principe.
In a statement, the university says that "students and faculty members participated in a significant intercultural dialogue and shared ideas and practical experiences about studying abroad." Students from countries such as the interior of China, Brazil, Mozambique and Myanmar also had the opportunity to present a series of “cultural shows” representing their cultures - which deserved “enthusiastic applause”, tells one - and participate in a competition that attributed a prize to the “best costume”.
Speaking at the time, Vice Rector Rui Martins stressed that “internationalization” is a key element in the “development strategy” of UM, which has developed constant efforts to attract international students and promote exchange with other countries and cultures. "We invite all the" global village "members to write their unique history at UM. We encourage more students to take advantage of the university's foreign exchange opportunities to explore the world abroad," Rui Martins said, encouraging the students to "make the most of the diverse and inclusive environment" of the educational establishment.
In the same statement, a remember that has already established partnerships with more than 350 higher education institutions in 42 countries and regions and which provides students with exchange programs such as “Erasmus+” or “Ten Thousand Talent Program”.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:25:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong's social values ​​and the results of the Legislative Council votes</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/os-valores-sociais-de-hong-kong-e-os-resultados-das-votacoes-do-conselho-legislativo/</link><description>Judging by the behavior of legislators in the vote of three bills - partnership between same -sex people, basketball bets and tobacco control - at the Hong Kong Legislative Council (Legco) on September 10 and 11, 2025, we can infer from the results of the vote that Hong Kong is a conservative society regarding the same -sex partnership, but also characterizes a relatively liberal tolerance for bets legalized and more rigorous control over tobacco.

On September 10, the Hong Kong government bill to recognize the same-sex union was rejected by 71 legislators and supported by only 14-an action unprecedented by most pro-government legislators in a politically patriotic legislators, who opposed a government bill after the promulgation of the National Security Act at the end of June 2020. same sex was limited to people aged 18 or over and who had a civil union outside Hong Kong's territory. One of the couples had to be resident in Hong Kong. The government stated that the bill did not equate same -sex unions to marriage and that it would not mean that same -sex couples would be allowed to marry in Hong Kong. The bill was a government response to a decision of the Last Instance Court (CFA) in September 2023, which determined that the government would have to establish a framework for the registration of same -sex marriage, after a judicial review began by Jimmy Sham, who married his partner in 2013 and that contested the absence of any government action to recognize his union. The CFA gave the government two years, ie a deadline until October 2027, to implement the court's decision. The public consultation was held in July and the government received 10,775 written opinions, of which 80% expressed contrary opinions (Hong Kong Free Press, September 10, 2025).

Legco members' voting behavior was noteworthy. The table below shows that while six members of the Executive Council (Exco) supported the bill, six members of the new popular party also did, along with Paul Tse and Tony Tse. However, legislators who opposed the bill not only came from the Democratic Alliance for the Improvement and Progress of Hong Kong (DAB), Pro-Governo and Pro-Pequim, but also from the Federation of Unions (FTU), the Business and Professional Alliance (BPA), the Liberal Party and the Federation of Hong Kong and Kowloon Federation. It was rare to see DAB and FTU oppose a government bill so 'united'.

The absence of Stanley NG in the voting process was criticized by Exco coordinator, Regina IP, who asked him to explain himself to the Chief Executive, according to the principle of collective liability of the members of the Exco. In response, NG said he had requested a license from Legco. In retrospective, in the political history of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region, no Exco coordinator has publicly asked an Exco member to explain to the Chief Executive his absence in the Legco vote - perhaps an indication that the principle of collective responsibility has gone from a relatively flexible practice to a kind of constitutional convention that is expected to be more rigorously observed by the members of the Exco who are also members of the Legco.
The dominant atmosphere of social conservatism can be seen in the debate of the Legislative Assembly. Legislator Maggie Chan said the bill "shakes the foundations of the Hong Kong Monogamous and Heterosexual Marriage System" (Hong Kong Free Press, September 10, 2025). She added that if the bill were rejected, it would represent not only effective control and balance against the government, but also the end of the myth that the Legislative Council is only a body that approves everything. Priscilla Leung, another legislator, said before the vote that the Legislative Council would play a crucial role in the “separation of powers” ​​in Hong Kong's political system, suggesting that the legislature could disagree with how the government would implement the court's decision.

Legislator Junius Ho said the government should not have proposed the bill because there were same -sex ways to protect themselves, such as writing wills and naming each other as their prosecutors. In this way, Ho said, couples could protect and reinforce their rights. It was reported that, after the rejection of the bill by Legco, the government would consider the idea of ​​using administrative procedures to enforce the court's decision.

Interestingly, the legislators who supported the bill tended to adopt a more liberal social posture. Martin Liao reminded Legco members that many places in the world allow same -sex couples to marry, such as Canada, the United States, Argentina, Taiwan and Thailand. He added that the recognition of the same -sex partnership would bring justice in the treatment of society to same -sex couples. Tony Tse agreed with Liao and said the bill respected human rights and social diversity.

Following the rejection of the bill, Legco approved, on September 11, a government bill to legalize basketball bets (RTHK, September 11, 2025). The changes made to the betting tax law were supported by 77 legislators, while only two voted against and two others abstained. The quiet approval of the bill provides for the reinforcement of the role of Jockey Club as the only licensed betting operator, with a rate of 50% on net revenues of basketball bets. The Secretary for Internal Affairs and Youth, Alice Mak, argued that the legalization of basketball bets would help the government to combat illegal bets. However, Legislator Chu Kwok-Keung, which represented the Educational Functional Group, argued that allowing bets on basketball would offer another game alternative. His legislature, Tik Chi-Yuen, argued that the bill would even stimulate an increase in the number of citizens participating in bets. Both Chu and Tik voted against the bill.

Jockey Club welcomed the approval of the bill, stating that it would cooperate with the Hong Kong government to combat illegal bets. At the same time, it would use the operation of basketball bets to support the development of charity and sports work in Hong Kong.

On the same day, Legco approved a bill to strengthen smoking control, as tobacco control legislation (change) 2025 will prohibit the commercialization of alternative tobacco products such as electronic cigarettes and heated tobacco products (RTHK, September 11, 2025). The legislation also expands statutory areas to non -smokers to cover more public places and makes it illegal to provide or sell products to smoke to children under 18. The sale of cigarettes with different menthol flavors would also be prohibited. Seventy -four members supported the bill while one voted against and there were seven abstentions. Legislator Adrian Ho said he thought the new measures would not affect tourism, while Chu Kwok-Keung supported the bill to protect the health of young people. Given that the smoking rate in Hong Kong is about 9.1%, which means that there are 580,000 smokers in Hong Kong, the approval of the bill affects a minority of citizens.

Upon approval of the bill, the government will increase penalties for citizens who illegally smoke in public places. From January 1, 2026, citizens who smoke in public places will be fined HK $ 3,000 for smoking illegally unless they smoke in areas designated for smokers in public transport, cinemas, hospitals, clinics and day care centers.

Legco's voting results on the three bills - partnership between same -sex, basketball and tobacco control - have an important influence on the evolution of social values ​​in Hong Kong. Voting against the same -sex partnership bill means that Hong Kong's dominant society is not yet prepared to accept same -sex partnership. Thus, the government is likely to consider administrative measures that help implement the CFA decision. The vote of the Legislative Council against the bill also showed that, as regards a socially controversial issue such as same -sex partnership, Central Beijing authorities gave all legislators green to freely express their opinions. Thus, different pro-government and pro-pedimic groups showed varied voting trends, with the new popular party becoming the most vocal supporter of the bill, but all other pro-peak groups, such as DAB, FTU, Liberal Party, and FHKLU, tended to oppose it. Interestingly, the Hong Kong and Macao affairs office published a comment immediately after the rejection of the bill, stating that the result of the vote was proof of the proper functioning of brakes and counterweights in the Hong Kong political system. This comment suggested that the central authorities saw the debate in the Legislative Assembly and the result of the vote as a manifestation of how the judiciary, executive and legislative powers functioned very well in Hong Kong, with the proper protection of minority interests (Ming Pao, September 12, 2025, p. A2).

The support of the Legislative Board to the Basketball Betting Operation means that Hong Kong's dominant company overwhelmingly supports the legalization of bets - an indication that Hong Kong society has embraced the game's culture. As Hong Kong's legalized stakes are traditionally very popular and legalized football bets have been growing in popularity, it was not surprising that the basketball betting bill has been easily approved. Therefore, it can be said that Hong Kong's society is quite liberal in dealing with the issue of legalized bets, from football to basketball.

Legco's approval of more rigorous tobacco control points to a society that values ​​the need to protect public health, which is sensitive to the harmful effects of smoking and is aware of the environmental impact of smoking. With a small percentage of the population to smoke, the approval of tobacco control legislation was easy, reflecting Hong Kong's dominant value system in favor of more rigorous tobacco control. Specifically, the interests of the minority cannot harm the interests of the majority in society.

In conclusion, gathering the results of the voting of the three bills, with one being rejected and the other two approved, Hong Kong's social values ​​have evolved with the prominent characteristics of being quite conservative on the subject of same -sex partnership, but quite liberal in the context of legalized and relatively moderate and reasonable bets on tobacco control. If so, the Hong Kong society has already exhibited a hybridization of the values ​​of social conservatism in the issue of same -sex partnership, social liberalism in legalizing bets on basketball and social moderation on how tobacco should be controlled.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 23:01:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao, Hong Kong and Continent discuss air traffic management in the great bay</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/macau-hong-kong-e-continente-discutem-gestao-do-trafego-aereo-na-grande-baia/</link><description>In Macao, a meeting on the management and coordinated development of the Great Bay air traffic, a meeting of the leaders of the civil aviation authorities and the representatives of the guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau regions were present.
During the discussion, plans were heard of optimization of the large bay traffic coordination mechanism, including operating tests in case of large -scale meteorological situations. In a statement issued by the Macao Civil Aviation Authority (AACM), it is added that the Macao delegation presented the progress of landfill and expansion of Macao International Airport, which aim to solidify Macao Statute as “an Integrated International Tourism and Culture Zone”.
The three parts also addressed “coordinated control between drones and traditional civil aviation” and their challenges, in articulation with the objectives of developing the country's low altitude economy.
The civil aviation authorities of the three Chinese regions meet annually to “deepen technical cooperation, jointly study the elevation of traffic management efficiency and optimize the procedures of control operation”. The results of these meetings have been manifested in the conclusion of agreements or in the implementation of action plans-of which are the evaluation reports on the Great Bay Airspace Planning models-thus providing “a valuable view for planning and the implementation of regional airspace in the medium and long term”.
According to the statement, Macau also managed to reach a consensus with the administration of central and southern air control and the Zhuhai entry control center, to define three new flight control points west of the territory and thus contribute to “raising the efficiency and safety of helicopter transionic service on the western coast of the Pearls”.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 23:07:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Ipim announces financial support plan to the “first stores” of foreign brands</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/ipim-anuncia-plano-de-apoio-financeiro-as-primeiras-lojas-de-marcas-estrangeiras/</link><description>Applications for the first phase of the “Plan for Economic Development in support of establishing the first store in Macau” will be open from November 1st until January 31, 2026. The newly opened plan foresees financial support from up to one million patacas to international and inland China, Hong Kong and Taiwan, in order to encourage foreign brands to establish stores in Macao and and Macao and Macao and Macao and Macao and diversify the offer of local consumption.
The Press Center of the Complex Complex Service Platform for Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese -Speaking Countries welcomed a clarification session, in which approximately 120 representatives of commercial associations, associations of residents of various neighborhoods and local media were present.
At the time, the substitute president of the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM), Sam Lei, said that this program intends to streamline community economic development, promote local consumption, support the growth of small and medium enterprises and generate more employment opportunities, as well as reinforcing local market competitiveness through the introduction of new products and business models. He also ensured that IPIM will continue to encourage the development of market diversification and adopt new “quality products, typical dining and professional services”.
According to an IPIM statement, the plan is expected to attract more than 20 national and international brands eligible to establish their first store in Macau, provided they meet certain requirements. In the international plan, the company must be classified among the 100 largest in the world or the 500 largest brands in the world, with at least ten stores distributed in three countries. At the national level, the company must have been in operation for a minimum of five years and have been classified as one of the top ten brands in the interior market of China.
The plan will be split: Basic financial support includes a maximum amount of up to 500,000 patacas, while additional financial support is granted by scale based on criteria such as the location and area of ​​the store and the number of full -time resident workers. The joint amount of these two parts of the financial plan may ascend to a maximum of one million patacas.
The details about the plan, its recipients and the eligibility conditions can be consulted on the electronic page created for the purpose of the IPIM website, or by phone number 2871 0300.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 23:06:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Zone A: First houses delivered today</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/zona-a-primeiras-casas-entregues-hoje/</link><description>Today will be delivered the first keys of fractions of the economic housing in zone A of the new landfills. So far, 2,054 households have chosen the fractions.

As of today, the first promoting economic housing comploders in zone A of new landfills will be able to go to the Housing Institute (IH) to give them the keys to their fraction. First, the promising compliments will have to deal with formalities and pay the agreed amount.
The fractions concerned are located in the Tong Seng (bot B4), Tong Chong (lot B9) and Tong Kai (lot B10) buildings from the new landfills, which have a total of 3,017 economic housing fractions. The HI has organized the choice of fractions by family aggregates qualified from March 4 this year. By the past Monday, 2,054 qualified household aggregates have already chosen the fractions, IH said.
The HI is now notifying the promising economic housing comploders who gather the conditions-that is, those who have declared the full payment of the amount of housing or the completion of mortgage loans-to deal with the formalities related to the delivery of housing.
Promitent-compliances should then go to the Ilha Verde do IH neighborhood delegation with all the necessary documents, including the original identification document, the copy of the power-to-sales contract, the letter and the dwelling of the housing amount to pay the housing amount and the reception of the fraction keys.
Following the reception of the keys of the fractions, the promising economic housing compliments should go to the ports of buildings in the new landfills, to make the payment of the deposit, receive the access cards from the buildings and deal with the formalities related to the occupation of fraction.
As for the commercial spaces, the HI points out that the contracts have already been signed and the keys delivered. The body also says that the lender companies will accompany the conception of the remodeling works and deal with the formalities related to the exploration license.
"The HI will continue to evaluate the situation of occupation by residents, as well as the complementary facilities related to the quality of life of the population and the needs of everyday life of residents of this zone," say the authorities in the press release, adding that the public tender for the second phase public housing spaces will be started.
Recently, the government has also announced the opening of the leading access roads in Zone A of the new landfills - Tai On Avenue, a part of Doctor Ma Man Kei Avenue and Avenida do Mar de Mirror.
Zone A of new landfills, which is about 1.38 square kilometers, may receive 96,000 inhabitants.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:27:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Electronic payments in the restaurants reached almost 8 billion patacas until July</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/pagamentos-electronicos-nos-restaurantes-chegaram-quase-aos-8-mil-milhoes-de-patacas-ate-julho/</link><description>In the first seven months of this year, the volume of electronic payment transactions in the restoration area was 7.86 billion patacas, plus 2.5% compared to the same period last year. In July alone the volume of electronic payment transactions reached 1.12 billion, plus 5.8% in monthly terms.

Between January and July this year, the volume of transactions through electronic payments in the restoration sector reached 7.86 billion patacas, ie 2.5% more compared to the same period last year, the Board of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) said yesterday. The volume of transactions with electronic payment of both restoration and retail business branch represents about 70% to 80% of the revenues of each branch, the body indicates.
Observing only July, when electronic payments in the restoration sector reached 1.12 billion patacas, there is a monthly growth of 5.8%. Still, compared to July last year, there was a slight decrease of 0.9%.
In July, the volume of transactions of owners of all restoration sub-rides went up to June, “due to the effect of summer holidays,” explains DSEC, noting that the volume of transactions of fast food restaurants, the Chinese restaurants, as well as the Japanese and Korean restaurants increased 11.4%, 6.7%and 6.6%, respectively.
Compared to July 2024, the main sub-riras of the restoration recorded different variations. The volume of transactions of food and canjas food and soup stores, as well as the Chinese restaurants descended 2.3%and 1.4%, respectively, while that of fast food restaurants grew 14.8%.
DSEC also makes the accounts also to electronic retail payments, saying that in July, the volume of transactions of this kind was 3.93 billion patacas, increasing 5.4%, compared to June 2025 and the homologous variation (-1.1%) became tight. In the first seven months of this year, the volume of transactions was 28.98 billion Patacas, minus 9.1%, compared to the same period of 2024.
In July, the volume of transactions of most of the main trading sub-strokes the retail increased compared to the previous month, also "driven by the effect of summer holidays." The DSEC emphasizes that the volume of transactions of the shoes and the clothing for adults grew 16.9%and 15.2%, respectively, and only that of leather items decreased 4.2%. In July, the volume of clocks and jewelery transactions dropped 4.2%and 1.8%, respectively, compared to July 2024, since “the volume of transactions of the other sub-subsidates increased, namely, cosmetic and hygiene products significantly rose 13.5%”.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:27:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia promises to cut 62% greenhouse gas emissions by 2035</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/australia-promete-cortar-em-62-emissoes-de-gases-com-efeito-de-estufa-ate-2035/</link><description>Australia yesterday promised to reduce, by 2035, greenhouse gas emissions between 62% and 70% below 2005 levels. "We are listening to scientists and acting in the best interest of Australia," said Prime Minister Anthony Albanese, revealing the goal. For the head of the government, it is "a responsible goal, supported by science, a practical plan to achieve and built on proven technology," added the government leader. "It is the right goal to protect our environment, protect and promote our economy and jobs and ensure that we act in our national interest and in the interest of this and future generations," said Albanese.
The announcement follows after the release of a report that warned that climate change threaten the subsistence of more than one million people in the country.
A national climate risk assessment released this week revealed that increased temperatures will have “cascade, cumulative and simultaneous” effects on citizens' lives.
For example, more than 1.5 million from Australia's 27 million inhabitants live in areas that should be affected by rising sea level by 2050, according to the document.
Australia's previous goal was to reduce emissions by 43% by 2030 compared to 2005 levels.
Matt Kean, president of the Authority for Climate Change, which advises the government in the field of climate policy, said the Australian goal for 2035 demonstrated a "larger ambition than most other advanced economies."
The country's commitments are overcome those of Canada and New Zealand, but fall short of the UK, which are the most ambitious in the world.
Environmental groups advocated a reduction goal of more than 70%. But business groups warned that this would endanger thousands of millions of euros in exports and take companies abroad.
Global emissions are increasing, but they need to be reduced almost to half by 2030 to limit global warming to the levels set in the Paris Agreement, signed in 2015.
According to the agreement, each country should provide the United Nations a quantified goal to reduce greenhouse gas emissions by 2035, along with a plan to reach it. These goals should have been presented at the beginning of the year, but only 10 of the about 200 countries did, according to a UN database.
Australia has invested thousands of millions of solar and wind energy and promised to become a superpower in renewable energy. However, the country remains one of the largest coal exporters in the world and continues to strongly subsidize the fossil fuel sector.
Australia applied to host the UN climate summit in 2026, along with the Pacific's island neighbors, threatened by the rising sea level.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 23:04:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Industrial entrepreneurs "a little more optimistic" in the second semester</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/empresarios-industriais-um-pouco-mais-optimistas-no-segundo-semestre/</link><description>The Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) yesterday released the results of the conjuncture survey to the exporting industrial sector for the second quarter of this year, stating that the attitude of industrial entrepreneurs inquired for exports for the next six months became “a little more optimistic”.
According to the results of the investigation, 53.1% of entrepreneurs provided for a stagnation in the quarter under analysis, 32.3% over the previous quarter. In turn, 27.3% of respondents said they had an “optimistic perspective”, representing a growth of 0.4 percentage points compared to the first quarter of 2025. Businessmen who said they expect “a less favorable evolution” represent 19.6% of the total respondents - a 32.7% descent in quarterly terms.
The average duration of the order portfolio detained by the industrial entrepreneurs inquired was 2.7 months in the quarter under analysis. The orders portfolio detained by the sector of pharmaceutical products, which occupied first place, was 4.4 months, while the order portfolios detained by clothing and clothing sectors, electronic/electric equipment and other non -textile products were 3.2 months, 2.5 months and 1.2 months, respectively.
With regard to export destination markets, the European Union stood out as the market “which had a relatively better behavior”, with rates of 25.1%. Macao's main exported goods during the quarter under analysis were clothing and clothing, pharmaceuticals, electronic/electric equipment, alcoholic beverages and tobacco and metallic products. In the first quarter of this year, it is recalled, the region that revealed best performance was that of Asia Pacific (excluding data from the interior of China, Hong Kong and Japan).</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 00:24:28</pubDate></item><item><title>What should be done?</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/o-que-deve-ser-feito/</link><description>On September 3, I wrote an article in which he claimed that the United States, which was previously considered one of the world's most advanced liberal democracies, are undergoing a slow -chamber coup d'état on their way to becoming a totally authoritarian state.  Under his current regime, Donald Trump and his henchmen dismissed about 200,000 civil servants, purged the Armed Forces, the State Department, the Scientific and Medician intelligence agencies, replacing former career officials and superior officers with loyal people only Donald Trump. He also sent the Armed Forces this summer to Washington, DC, and Los Angeles, and spoke of sending troops to other cities, more recently, Memphis, Tennessee. Trump mentioned several times to arrest his political opponents and put them in prison. The objective of this repression would be to institute exclusive control over the executive branch and marginalize the legislature, the judiciary, states and individual cities. I finished the article with the following question, "What, if there is anything, can be done to prevent this process towards a totally personalized dictatorship?"
The founders, who wrote the United States Constitution about 250 years ago, did everything they could to prevent a new king from taking control of the United States. After all, they rebelled against Britain to overthrow the government of an alleged de-dispute, King George III, and establish a constitutional republic based on the rule of law. To this end, the founders were very aware of the need to institute in the government of the New Republic three equal powers (executive, legislative and judiciary), which could control and balancing mutually. For example, the president could appoint employees, but Congress should approve them. Congress approves bills and the president sanctions them, but the courts may declare these unconstitutional laws. Congress has full powers to allocate funds to finance agencies and execute laws, but the executive must spend the money allocated.
This process has worked reasonably well over the years, except for a few decades before and after the civil war between 1861 and 1865 to release black slaves. However, today the system is not working. The separation of powers, brakes and counterweights, the rule of law, the independent judiciary, and other safeguards instituted to protect US freedom and democracy have been seriously eroded in the eight months since the beginning of the Donald Trump regime on January 20. The president instituted a system of overwhelming tariffs (import taxes) without the approval of Congress, clearly violating the Constitution. The president refused to spend the money that Congress allocated to various projects, such as foreign aid, medical and scientific research, museums, education and other programs that did not fit Trump's 'agenda'. The Congress controlled by Republicans essentially ended his role of supervising Trump's questionable actions and his nominees, becoming marginalized and becoming essentially a 'discussion club'.
The judiciary has better defended the Constitution. The lower, federal, and state courts have stated that most of Donald Trump's decrees violated the Constitution and US legislation. These include their arbitrary tariffs, the cornerstone of their economic agenda, mass deportations, racial discrimination, citizenship by birth established in the fourteenth amendment, their mass layoffs and other decrees considered illegal and unconstitutional. However, the far -right Supreme Court reversed many of these lower court decisions, allowing Trump to take his illegal and unconstitutional measures. For example, last week, the Supreme Court ruled that police and troops can indeed perform magazines to people for no reason, based only on their color and tongue. This decision actually ripped the fourth amendment, which clearly states that "the right of people to security in their people, houses, documents and goods, against unjustified searches and seizures, will not be violated." The Supreme Court is considering whether the promulgation of tariffs, mass deportations and citizenship by Trump's right of birth is “constitutional”. Your decisions about these critical measures will be announced in the coming months. But Americans fear a lot that this Supreme Court ignores the constitution and American law, allowing Donald Trump to become a dictator with absolute power. The Republican Party itself became a totally authoritarian party, totally subservient to the whims and desires of a whimsical leader. He will not defend the Constitution or the Republic.
Opposition to Trump remains divided and without leadership. After the 2024 elections, the Democratic Party, which lost the presidency and both Congress chambers to Trump and the Republican Party, was demoralized. Unlike a parliamentary system, as in Britain, there is no opposition leader or shadowed cabinet. Democrats cannot decide how to respond to this attack on the Republic. Your leadership is very old and docile. Democrats managed to define the problems that afflict the US at this time, but could not prescribe any solutions. Therefore, the party remains very unpopular. There has been strong and active civil society in the US - universities, numerous organizations (NGOs), press and medium in general, etc. However, Trump's regime has attacked and weakened these institutions. He attacked universities of "elite", trying to make them purge teachers and promote the right-wing agenda of Trump, using federal funds as a pressure tool. The regime intimidated the media, in particular the National Public Radio and the Public Broadcasting System (similar to BBC), CBS, NBC and MSNBC. If your broadcast licenses are revoked, the only allowed television station will be FOX, a very conservative television network. Health and Science Agencies (CDC, NIH, NIS) and research financing for these agencies have also been quite restricted, making the US a less healthy and more dangerous country.
Last week, an important conservative young age and supporter near Donald Trump, Charlie Kirk, was murdered. Trump almost immediately blamed the "radical left", which includes any person or group opposing his fascist agenda - democrats, independent, liberal and socialist. He dubbed them "traitors", stating that they should be arrested or worse. Although the alleged young killer, Tyler Robinson, was white and had a conservative, Republican and Mormon formation, it was revealed that Robinson had a love relationship with a young man in transition to women. Many Americans fear that the president's words of hatred cause disorders against transgender people, putting many of them in danger. Charlie Kirk's critics have lost their jobs as Kirk supporters scour the internet for criticism on various social networks.
Given the failure of safeguards and US institutions to prevent this fall for autocracy, I believe it is up to the American people to challenge the regime. Donald Trump is a bully and, like most bullies, is cowardly and easily giving in to a real opposition. For example, due to the strong opposition of the governor of Illinois, the mayor of Chicago and the people of Chicago, Trump retreated from his threat of sending troops there. If US troops are sent to more democratic cities, as threatened, people in these cities should avoid soldiers - not smiling, not talking, doing nothing that shows approval for their arrival. It should be clear that soldiers are not welcome on American streets and opposed to the repression of this regime. Adopting the tactics of Mahatma Gandhi and Martin Luther King, Americans who oppose the regime should adopt civil disobedience. Under no circumstances they should resort to violence, as this would give the regime another excuse to intensify repression. I was very active during the 1960s in opposition to the Vietnam War and participated in two major demonstrations in 1967 and 1969 in Washington, DC, where about 500,000 people were present. The survival of the Constitutional Republic needs larger but absolutely non -violent manifestations, to force this intimidating self -ecratic to retreat and review its power calendar in the US.  After the murder of Charlie Kirk, the governor of Utah said that "this is a decisive moment." The escalation of political violence in the United States over the last year has placed the nation at the beginning of a dark period. We do not know where this political violence in a country flooded will stop.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 23:02:37</pubDate></item><item><title>The new era of muscular politics</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/a-nova-era-da-politica-musculada/</link><description>In recent years, the world has watched the worrying return of authoritarianism. Frequently leaders concentrate power, weaken democratic institutions, and restrict fundamental freedoms. Contrary to the classic dictatorships of the twentieth century, many of these regimes today wear an appearance of democracy: they organize elections without transparency, control the press and submit the courts to political power. The process varies from country to country, but the consequence is repeated: less space for contestation and a culture of fear that widens.
Examples multiply by several continents. In Russia, Vladimir Putin has been in power for over twenty years, jugulating rival parties, controlling the media narrative. For this it changed the constitution to stay in power by 2036. In Türkiye, Recep Tayyip Erdoğan remodeled the political system to establish an executive presidency, pursued critics with mass arrests and restricted press freedom. Especially after the coup attempt in 2016, when factions of the Armed Forces tried to overthrow the government. In Venezuela, Nicolás Maduro clings to office, despite the economic crisis and widespread protests, using security forces and imprisoning and even eliminating opponents. In Myanmar, after the 2021 military coup, the Armed Forces used lethal violence against pro-democracy protesters, resulting in hundreds of deaths.
This growth of authoritarianism is not limited to one region. It reveals a global trend fueled by disenchantment with the so -called failures of democracy. Populist leaders often present themselves as strong men, capable of restoring order and national pride, gaining the support of frustrated citizens with corruption, inequality or instability. However, this concentration of power often translates into more injustice-weakening control and balance mechanisms, restricting civil liberties and leaving ordinary people with less protection against state abuse. The result is a more muscular and unfair world, where the rule of law is awaited by the Law of Force.
In the last decade, political analysts have been observing a constant contraction of global democratic norms, a trend often described as “democratic setback. Polyotologist Marianne Kneuer of Kellog Institute explains that erosion or democratic setback is not an abrupt bankruptcy of democracy, but a slow death of democratic norms and practices. that democracy faces. It is possible to verify this democratic erosion in all regions of the world, both in older and recent democracies.
To end democratic erosion - notes Kneuer - it is essential to reflect on its own erosion and evaluate what is happening during this process. Most people think that stopping erosion is the solution, but stopping is not the same as inverting, nor does it imply the recovery of democracy, which often requires the reconstruction of democracy. It is not easy and requires the rebalancing of weakened institutions and the installation of new safeguards.
Recent examples confirm the continuity of this “democratic setback”. In Hungary, Prime Minister Viktor Orbán gradually transformed the country what he himself calls an "Iliberal democracy." It consolidated the property of the media in the hands of allies close to the government, changing the electoral rules and limiting judicial independence. India, once celebrated as the largest democracy in the world, has been the target of criticism for minority treatment, restrictions on press freedom and the use of generic laws to silence criticism of the opposition under Narendra Modi's government.
In the United States, the attack of January 6, 2021 to the Capitol exposed the fragility of democratic norms, when false allegations of electoral fraud undermined confidence in the electoral process.  Donald Trump manipulated the narrative of this attack in various ways which allowed him to regain support, reinforce the loyalty of followers and undermine the credibility of opponents. By turning the episode into a victim narrative, unfair attack and war against "The Elite," Trump has been able to reconfigure the public meaning of the event and use it all to his electoral political advantage.
Brazil, under Jair Bolsonaro, lived a marked polarization and attacks on democratic institutions, while Tunisia, for a long time considered the success case of Spring Arabic, retreated for authoritarianism under the presidency of Kais Saied as seen in the low participation of voters in the 2024 presidential elections. These examples show that democracy is not sustained alone; Without surveillance, transparency and responsibility, it can be emptied from within.
Alexis de Tocqueville wrote in "Democracy in America" ​​(1835) "therefore it is above all in democratic times when we are that true friends of freedom and human greatness should stand all the time to keep standing and ready to prevent social power from lightly sacrificing the particular rights of some individuals to the general execution of their projects." Time came to give it reason.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 23:02:04</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM students win gold and bronze awards in medical innovation contest</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/18/alunos-da-upm-ganham-premios-de-ouro-e-bronze-em-concurso-de-inovacao-medica/</link><description>Two teams from students from Macao Polytechnic University (UPM) won gold and bronze medals at the 11th edition of the National Medical Innovation Contest for University Students, whose awards took place at Shandong University.
The groups in question, composed of students from the Bio-Médic Techniques Sciences course at the UPM Faculty of Health and Sports Sciences, competed in two different categories: the international category and the category of Basic Clinic. During the preparatory period, the teams “obtained a solid base through a comprehensive training program” that included “the consolidation of innovative ideas, the optimization of experimental design and defense training,” according to a UPM statement.
The students representing UPM eventually stood out in the grand final, before the jury, for the “excellent performance of defense and teamwork” that revealed during the evaluation process. One of the teams won the Golden Award in the International Innovative Design category, for its project “Feasibility Study of Multi-Room Detection Integration for Liquid Biopsies using 'Stereo-Seq' Chip '”. The other team stood out in the basic innovative design clinic category with the “Study on Inhibiting Probiotics Activity Combined with dairy products against 'Helicobacter Pylori'”, which deserved bronze award.
As the statement points out, these were the best results achieved by the universities of Hong Kong and Macau at this year's event, which attracted the participation of 820 teams from 4,000 teachers and students and more than 200 guests and judges. This year, by the way, a double record was recorded at the ceremony celebration, both by the scale of the event and by the number of participants.
The National Medical Innovation Contest for University Students is one of the most respected medical discipline contests in the area, assuming itself as an important platform for the formation of qualified staff.</description><pubDate>2025-09-18 23:06:52</pubDate></item></channel></rss>