<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/26/escrutinio-ao-governo-nao-deve-ultrapassar-limites-defende-andre-cheong/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Sam Hou Fai promises greater bilateral openness of Macau with the outside world</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/26/sam-hou-fai-promete-maior-abertura-bilateral-de-macau-com-o-exterior/</link><description>The Macau Government commits to a “bilateral opening” to expand external relations, taking advantage of the city's advantages in internal and external connectivity and the fusion of Chinese and Western cultures.
The Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, yesterday assured of strengthening Macau's international presence, on the occasion of the reception that marked the beginning of duties of the new Commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the PRC in the Macao SAR, Bian Lixin.
In his speech, Sam Hou Fai assumed that the Executive will also promote multifaceted and reciprocal cooperation with Portuguese and Spanish-speaking countries, actively participating in the “One lane, one route” initiative, with a view to making the territory a relevant “gateway” for the country in opening up to the outside world and a privileged “window” for exchange and mutual learning between Chinese and Western civilizations.
The Government leader, in this case, assured that he will continue to strengthen communication and coordination with the Commission and count on its “guidance, support and assistance” so that “the Macao SAR implements its work more effectively, thus continuously strengthening Macau's international competitiveness and influence”, he said.
At the event, Sam Hou Fai welcomed new commissioner Bian Lixin, but also greeted outgoing commissioner Liu Xianfa. He highlighted that the Commissariat of the PRC in the Macao SAR has upheld the principles of diplomacy in the service of the people and diplomacy for the benefit of Macau, having “safeguarded national sovereignty, security and national development interests, defended the legitimate rights and interests of Macau compatriots abroad and made significant contributions to the promotion of long-term prosperity and stability Macao SAR deadline”.
The Chief Executive once again referred to the work carried out by the Government over the past year, pointing out that public administration reforms were deepened and that the effectiveness of governance was reinforced. “Macao’s economy and society have achieved stable development, accelerating the pace of adequate diversification of the economy,” he stressed.
For this year, the Executive reiterated the hope of defending and perfecting the system of predominance of executive power and “resolutely safeguarding” national security and social stability. It will, moreover, promote economic diversification and accelerate the development of Hengqin, further strengthening the “patriotic and pro-Macao forces” and raising the efficiency of Macau’s governance.</description><pubDate>2026-02-26 23:38:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Government promises new measures to restrict plastic use</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/26/governo-promete-novas-medidas-para-restringir-uso-de-plastico/</link><description>The Government will move forward with new measures to restrict the use of plastic “when the necessary conditions are met and there is social consensus”. The information was transmitted by the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) in response to a written inquiry presented by deputy Leong Hong Sai.

In the future, the Government will implement more measures to restrict the use of plastic, but only when “the necessary conditions are met and there is social consensus”, indicates the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) in response to a written question presented by deputy Leong Hong Sai.
In the interpellation, the deputy linked to Residents asked for details on measures to reduce the use of plastic in community neighborhoods and suggested the introduction of instructions on packaging used in retail and online commerce, for example.
DSPA responded that, together with the Directorate of Administration and Public Service Services and the Directorate of Finance Services, it has already drawn up instructions for eco-acquisition for public services, recommending the acquisition of products with less packaging, greater incorporation of recycled and biodegradable materials, which comply with environmental principles and are highly energy efficient. DSPA also prepared suggestions for ecological specifications for various products, to serve as a reference for society in general when purchasing goods, in order to encourage the priority use of environmentally friendly products.
The organization also recalls that, since 2019, it has successively implemented several measures to control the use of plastic, including the promulgation, in that same year, of the law on restrictions on the supply of plastic bags, which stipulates charges for plastic bags, and the phased introduction, from 2021, of bans on the import of disposable Styrofoam tableware and food trays, straws, drink stirrers, knives, spoons, non-biodegradable and disposable plastic forks, plates and cups, as well as cotton swabs, balloon sticks and disposable plastic inflatable sticks.
The Government's response to the question also states that “DSPA has been promoting environmental awareness among different sectors of society, through platforms such as the Macau Green Hotel Award, the Ecological Supermarkets Commendation Plan and the Eco-Schools Partnership Plan, publicizing environmental concepts such as waste and plastic reduction and reuse of resources, which are also considered important evaluation criteria”. Furthermore, the activity “Reducing plastic is very easy” encourages citizens to reduce the use of disposable tableware.
“These initiatives have contributed to the effective reduction in the use of single-use plastic products and the use of plastic packaging in fruits and vegetables, to the implementation of waste reduction and recycling measures and to the development of environmentally friendly consumption habits among citizens”, concludes the DSPA.</description><pubDate>2026-02-26 23:39:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Commissioner of the Chinese MNE says that Macau will reach “new horizons” and achieve “new glories”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/26/comissaria-do-mne-chines-diz-que-macau-alcancara-novos-horizontes-e-conquistara-novas-glorias/</link><description>Bian Lixin, the new commissioner of the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs (MNE) in the Macao SAR, is optimistic about Macau's future development. The official said yesterday that she hopes Macau will open “new horizons” and achieve “new glories”.

Bian Lixin arrived in Macau less than a month ago to serve as commissioner of the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs (MNE) in the Macao SAR, replacing Liu Xianfa. Yesterday, the Commissionerate organized a welcome reception for Bian Lixin and the new commissioner gave a speech in which she expressed confidence in the future of Macau.
The new commissioner began by pointing out that, in less than a month, she was able to see “clearly” that “the fusion of Chinese and Western cultures and the coexistence between different ethnic groups created a situation of harmonious coexistence, the love for the country and for Macau was rooted and passed from generation to generation”. Furthermore, he realized that “the practice of ‘one country, two systems’ with Macao’s characteristics has achieved remarkable achievements and Macao’s ‘golden business card’ shines even brighter in the world.”
Bian Lixin recalled that this year marks the beginning of the 15th National Five-Year Plan, as well as the 3rd Macau Five-Year Plan. This will make “Chinese-style modernization” enter a “more splendid phase in the next five years”, he predicted. Bian added that, “taking advantage of the country's efforts to build a great country and revitalize the Chinese nation, Macau will certainly open new horizons and continue to achieve new glories”.
“In the new journey, Macau will achieve greater success in promoting the development of adequate diversification of the economy by expanding exchange and cooperation with abroad”, stated the representative of Beijing, suggesting that Macau's role as “One Center, One Platform, One Base” be reinforced and promote the development of adequate diversification of the economy.
The commissioner believes that “Macau will, taking advantage of the results already achieved and moving forward with determination, expand and deepen international cooperation, proactively participate and contribute to high-quality ‘Belt and Road’ cooperation, accelerate the development of adequate diversification of the economy, create a platform for high-level openness to the outside world”.
Regarding Beijing's request for the Macao SAR to strengthen the executive branch over the legislative and judicial branches, Bian said that “Macau's practices since its return have proven that the predominance of the executive branch has an advantage in policy innovation and stability, and can effectively increase its competitiveness and international projection”.
In the commissioner's opinion, the principle of “one country, two systems” with “Macao characteristics” is a “good system that makes peaceful coexistence and win-win cooperation between different social systems a reality”. For Bian Lixin, the “values ​​of peace, inclusion, openness and sharing” that are part of the “one country, two systems” principle come from China and are shared by the rest of the world.
“We are convinced that, under the strong leadership of the Central Government and with the support of the motherland, under the guidance of the Chief Executive and with the efforts of all sectors of society, Macau, a shining pearl, will have an even more promising future”, he said, promising: “We will well tell the stories of Macau and the essential values ​​of ‘one country, two systems’, better safeguard the legitimate rights and interests of Macau patriots abroad”.
In his speech on the occasion, Bian Lixin also took the opportunity to highlight what he describes as the “historical successes” of the People's Republic of China, in the economy, technological innovation, the fight against poverty and diplomacy, for example.</description><pubDate>2026-02-26 23:41:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Annual profitability of the Macao SAR Financial Reserve reached a record of 6.9%</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/26/rentabilidade-anual-da-reserva-financeira-da-raem-atingiu-recorde-de-69/</link><description>Last year, the Macao SAR Financial Reserve recorded an investment income of 42.92 billion patacas, with its annual profitability reaching 6.9%, a new record.
The Macau Monetary Authority (AMCM) indicated that, by the end of last year, the value of the Financial Reserve capital amounted to 666.74 billion patacas, of which the basic reserve represented 167.29 billion patacas and the extraordinary reserve 499.45 billion patacas.
In a statement on the situation of Financial Reserve investments, released yesterday, AMCM says that, in the first half of last year, “tariff measures changed the panorama of global trade and geopolitics became more complex, leading to significant changes in international financial markets, with the main equity and bond markets undergoing adjustments”. Subsequently, “with progress in trade negotiations and the gradual reduction of tariffs, combined with the adoption of relatively more accommodative monetary policies in the main economies, complemented by expansionary budgetary policies to support the economy, and also the continued dynamism in the artificial intelligence sector, the prices of risky assets registered a recovery and a gradual rise”. “Throughout the year, the equity and bond markets generally presented a resilient performance,” says the organization.
This year “it is expected that the main global economies will continue to use various measures and policies to boost economic growth, with opportunities and challenges coexisting in the investment environment”. “The Financial Reserve will continue to strictly comply with the principle of safe, effective and stable investment, balancing return and risk through a prudent, flexible, diversified and balanced asset allocation, in order to achieve the medium and long-term objective of capital preservation and appreciation of reserve assets”, assures AMCM.</description><pubDate>2026-02-26 23:37:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Births decline in Japan for the tenth year in a row</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/26/nascimentos-diminuem-no-japao-pelo-decimo-ano-consecutivo/</link><description>The number of births in Japan declined in 2025 for the tenth year in a row, accentuating the challenges facing Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi. In total, 705,809 babies were born in the archipelago last year, according to preliminary data, a drop of 2.1% compared to 2024.

The number of births in Japan decreased in 2025 for the tenth consecutive year, according to data published yesterday by the Japanese Ministry of Health, highlighting the challenges faced by Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi. In total, 705,809 babies were born in the archipelago last year, according to preliminary data, a drop of 2.1% compared to 2024.
The statistics also include births to foreigners in Japan, as well as babies born abroad to Japanese parents.
More positive news is the 505,656 marriages, a number that represents an increase of 1.1%. The number of divorces decreased by 3.7% to 182,969 cases.
Data also reveals that Japan recorded 1,605,654 deaths, that is, 13,030 fewer than in 2024, a decrease of 0.8%.
According to the Ministry of Internal Affairs, the country's total population was estimated in February at 122.86 million inhabitants, a drop of 0.47% (580,000 people) in one year.
The world's fourth-largest economy has one of the lowest birth rates on the planet and a declining population.
This development is already causing a series of problems in the country, including labor shortages, increasingly heavy social security costs and a reduced number of tax-paying assets. It also contributes to worsening the country's high debt, which already has the highest debt ratio among large economies.
Figures published last year showed that the country had around 100,000 centenarians, of whom almost 90% were women.
Successive Japanese leaders, including Takaichi, the country's first female leader, have promised to halt falling birth rates, but with limited success.
Tokyo City Hall even developed a dating application, which requires users to provide documents proving that they are single and sign a letter certifying that they want to get married. “The falling birth rate and shrinking population constitute a silent emergency that will progressively erode the vitality of our country,” Takaichi said last week in parliament.
The Liberal Democratic Party (PLD), which the leader leads, obtained a two-thirds majority in the lower house of parliament in the February 8 legislative elections.
Turning to immigration would help reverse Japan's demographic decline and the resulting problems in the job market.
Under pressure from the anti-immigration Sanseito party and the slogan of this political formation “the Japanese first”, the ultra-conservative prime minister nevertheless promised to tighten immigration measures. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-26 23:30:21</pubDate></item><item><title>A century after his death, Pessanha is honored in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/26/um-seculo-depois-da-sua-morte-pessanha-e-homenageado-em-macau/</link><description>The centenary of Camilo Pessanha's death will be marked with two events at the beginning of March, which aim to rescue the memory and legacy of one of the greatest poets in the Portuguese language. The celebrations begin on the exact day that marks one hundred years since his disappearance, on Sunday, with a round table at Casa Garden. On the 3rd, it is IPOR's turn to host a discussion on the various dimensions of a man who, more than just a poet, was a professor, jurist and even a Chinese-Portuguese translator. He died in Macau on March 1, 1926.

Camilo Pessanha é um poeta tão grande que Macau inteiro não chega para seu túmulo, disse Eugénio de Andrade. Não basta, portanto, que o centenário do seu falecimento seja assinalado uma única vez. The life and work of the poet – one of the greatest figures in Portuguese-language literature – will be honored throughout the year 2026, starting with two sessions at the beginning of March.
The first round table is scheduled for Sunday, the 1st, when exactly a century will have passed since Pessanha's disappearance. The panel of guests will meet at Casa Garden, at 4pm, for a conversation between six speakers and moderated by Sérgio Sousa, full professor in the Department of Portuguese at the Faculty of Arts of the University of Macau (UM).
The names invited to this session are the poet, professor and essayist António Carlos Cortez, the writers and journalists Carlos Morais José and Christopher Chu, the UM professors Diego Giménez, Maggie Hoi and Yao Feng and the architect Carlos Marreiros. It is important to emphasize that all of these speakers have in-depth knowledge of Camilo Pessanha's work, being responsible for essays, critical reviews, cinematographic documentaries (in the case of Carlos Morais José) and even official translations of his only book of poems, “Clepsidra” (in the case of Yao Feng).
The event is titled “Going like this, on board a ship, without destination”, in allusion to the words that Camilo Pessanha addressed to his friend Carlos Amaro in a letter written in 1909, rocked by the waves that were taking him back to Macau. It is a reflection of the very unique identity of the poet and the man, both eternally seduced by the idea of ​​wandering aimlessly (and the constant threat of liberating shipwreck), and also a direct reflection on the path explored between Lisbon and Macau.
The relationship with Asian territory is dense, complex and ambiguous, seen in contemporary times as riddled with orientalism and prejudice. Arriving in Macau was not about seeing a lighthouse after a season on the high seas: it was about returning to the “unfriendly land of exile”, as he called it. In a text written in 1924 for the newspaper “A Pátria”, closed two years later, the general description that Pessanha gave about expatriate poets seemed to contain an auto-biographical character. “The few [poets] who wander and languish in distant regions, if they happen to write a verse, it is always to sing of the absent homeland”.
It is said that the poet voluntarily went into exile in Macau after a heartbreak, when Ana de Castro Osório refused his marriage proposal. The poem “Canção da Partida” suggests this, in which the poet alludes to the writer and activist’s engagement to Paulino de Oliveira, also a man of letters. A year later, he crossed the oceans towards Macau.

MAN OF MANY FACETS
 
The tragic-romantic version of the story insists on heartbreak, but the truth is that the departure for Macau was also supported by the need to find professional opportunities. This is how he ended up at the recently created Lyceum of Macau, where he taught different subjects: Philosophy, Portuguese Language, History, Geography, Political Economy, Commercial Law and History of China.
Camilo Pessanha's worldview was also reflected in the different jobs he held until the date of his death. In addition to being a teacher, he was a conservator, lawyer, judge, auditor and, with the exception of the last decade of his life, always a poet – perhaps the most unknown of his occupations to the local population, who interpreted him as eccentric and with a peculiar appearance (a perception exacerbated by his opium addiction).
The writer and researcher Danilo Barreiros, who became a contemporary of the poet, described him as follows in the work “The Testament of Camilo Pessanha”: “Slim, emaciated, with a shaggy beard, hair plastered to his forehead, half-naked on the bed, voluptuously inhaling the long pipe over the yellowish flame of the crystal lamp, which projected its disfigured shadow on the obscured walls, with the hypnotic expression of the opioid addicts.”
The literary recognition was posthumous and possible thanks to the efforts of Ana de Castro Osório, with whom he maintained a close friendship despite the failed romance. “Clepsidra” – a unique work in Camilo Pessanha’s repertoire, the greatest work in Portuguese literature – brings together the compositions that the poet created throughout his life and kept alive only in his memory, without putting them on paper. In later editions, the work would be expanded with poems discovered in the meantime.
The event on March 3rd at IPOR – Instituto Português do Oriente, scheduled for 6:30 pm, brings into focus the various facets of the poet. Doctor and writer Shee Vá, responsible for moderation, tells PONTO FINAL that the choice of each of the three guest speakers was intentional.
José Basto da Silva, member of the board of directors of the Fundação da Escola Portuguesa, will focus on the poet's teaching activity, while Frederico Rato, lawyer and notary from Macau, will explore his career as a lawyer and jurist. Finally, António Carlos Cortez – who will also be present at the day 1 session at Casa Garden – will focus on the field of poetry.
“I’m going to give you two themes to develop”, says Shee Vá. "The first, to find out if Camilo missed Portugal as much as is usually said. And whether or not this was reflected in his poetry, because, as we know, most of his work was written before coming to Macau – and in Macau he corrected, corrected, corrected".
A second area of ​​discussion focuses on the contacts he maintained with Portugal. "Camilo maintained correspondence with Portuguese newspapers and magazines, which were published there. He also sent many chronicles. Therefore, we will also question whether his prose writer aspect was reflected in his poems."
After the intervention of the trio of speakers, there will be space for a “reading club” in which poems will be recited, some of which have already been mentioned during the conversation. “In fact, the introduction I will make regarding Camilo’s life until he came to Macau will already introduce some of his poetic work”, explains Shee Vá. And it also reveals some of the other themes that may be mentioned throughout the conversation: Camilo Pessanha's side as a collector (“many works of art were sent to Portugal, and it would be interesting to know whether or not they have much value”) and his later years, marked by opium addiction and a slow degradation that culminated in his death at the age of 58.

RECOVER A DUSTY LEGACY

In the last decades of his life, Pessanha made successive trips to Portugal for medical treatments, where he met – and directly influenced – the members of the “Orpheu” magazine generation. He always returned to Macau. Macau, this territory that he described in 1916, in a letter addressed to Ana de Castro Osório, as a “very shy place – gossip and idiot – in all respects miserable”.
But Pessanha was a man of contradictions and paradoxes, and to focus on his (successive) criticisms of the territory would be to ignore the respect he demonstrated for local culture. He learned Cantonese, read Chinese poetry, collected antiques. He also dedicated himself to important translation work that included the “Eight Chinese Elegies” of the Ming dynasty, giving them visibility and relevance in the Portuguese-speaking world.
His vision of Macau seemed, above all, clouded by the umbilical longing for a homeland half a world away. The poet described it this way, in his essay on the Camões cave: “In Macau it is easy for the imagination exalted by nostalgia, in some pine forest less frequented by the Chinese population, to abstract from the vision of the Chinese buildings, the Chinese pagodas, the Chinese tombs, the mysterious Chinese inscriptions (…) and create, at certain times of the year and at certain hours of the day, the illusion of Portuguese land”.
Today, Camilo Pessanha is part of that same Portugueseness in Macau. His image is inscribed on a mural in the garden of the Consulate of Portugal, signed by the artist Vhils, or on the statue that represents him leaning on his cane, in the Jardim das Artes. Furthermore, in a territory where only 2.3% of the population says they are fluent in Portuguese, his verses circulate among a restricted group of poetry lovers. All of Macau is not enough for Pessanha's tomb, said Eugénio de Andrade, but his legacy is becoming dusty over the years – which now form a century. His simple grave goes unnoticed by those who stroll, inattentively or with other destinations, at the São Miguel Arcanjo Cemetery.
The initiatives scheduled for this year help to recover the memory of an unrepeatable poet, who elevated Symbolism in Portugal to its maximum expression. In addition to the two sessions already mentioned, IPOR intends to organize a series of activities related to the poet throughout 2026.
Speaking to PONTO FINAL, Patrícia Quaresma confirms that future events “are planned, but not yet confirmed, so we cannot say much about them”. He adds, however, that IPOR is “trying to study the possibility of bringing a bibliographic exhibition, together with the Camões Institute”, as well as carrying out “other activities about the poet, either in the library [appropriately called the Camilo Pessanha Library] or at Café Oriente”.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Macau's exports to the European Union fell 78.7%</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/26/exportacoes-de-macau-para-a-uniao-europeia-cairam-787/</link><description>The value of goods exported from Macau to the European Union in January was just six million patacas, that is, 78.7% less in annual terms. Conversely, Macau's exports to the interior of China registered an annual increase of 47.3%

The value of goods exported from Macau to the European Union in January was just six million patacas, that is, 78.7% less in annual terms. External trade data for January were released yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC).
Conversely, Macau's exports to the interior of China (76 million patacas) registered an annual increase of 47.3%. For Hong Kong, exports increased by 36.3% to 1.15 billion patacas. Exports to the United States of America also increased by 12% to 28 million patacas.
As for imports, the imported values ​​of goods produced in mainland China (4.75 billion patacas), Hong Kong (865 million patacas) and the European Union (3.72 billion patacas) increased by 50.4%, 33.1% and 8%, respectively, in annual terms. Analyzing by country or territory of origin, the value of imported goods from mainland China (1.98 billion patacas) and the HKSAR (10.59 billion patacas) rose 22.6% and 25.7%, respectively, compared to January last year.
In the month of January, a total of 1.46 billion patacas of goods were exported and 13.16 billion patacas of goods were imported, an increase of 29.2% and 24.6%, respectively, compared to the same month of 2025. Consequently, the total value of foreign trade in goods in January 2026 corresponded to 14.62 billion patacas and the trade balance deficit amounted to 11.71 billion patacas.

Portuguese-speaking countries imported record amounts of Chinese products in 2025

In 2025, Portuguese-speaking countries imported products from China worth US$88.1 billion, a year-on-year increase of 3.1% and the highest amount ever, according to official data released yesterday. The value, which corresponds to 74.8 billion euros, is the highest since the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-Speaking Countries (Macau Forum) began presenting this data, in 2013.
Brazil continues to be the largest buyer in the Portuguese-speaking bloc, despite imports from China falling 0.7% compared to 2024, to US$71.6 billion, according to information from the Chinese Customs Service. On the contrary, the second on the list, Portugal, purchased goods worth US$7.19 billion from China, an increase of 17.7%.
In the opposite direction, exports from Portuguese-speaking countries to China fell 1.4% in 2025, to US$137.7 billion, the lowest value since 2021, at the peak of the covid-19 pandemic.
The decline was mainly due to Angola, the second largest Portuguese-speaking supplier to the Chinese market, which saw exports decrease by 9.1%, to US$16 billion. Furthermore, sales of goods from Portugal – the third most important Chinese trading partner in the Portuguese-speaking bloc – also decreased by 10.2% to US$2.85 billion.
Five of the nine Portuguese-speaking countries saw their exports to the Chinese market fall. Mozambique's sales to China fell 11.9%, to US$1.59 billion, while Equatorial Guinea's exports fell 20.6%, to US$779.8 million.
Cape Verde's shipments to China decreased by 40.9%, although the country only sold around eight thousand dollars worth of goods. On the contrary, exports from Brazil – by far the largest Portuguese-speaking supplier to the Chinese market – rose 0.3% to US$116.4 billion.
The biggest increase was in Timor-Leste, whose sales soared, from just 881 thousand dollars in 2024 to 27.2 million dollars last year.
Exports from São Tomé and Príncipe more than tripled, reaching 54 thousand dollars, while sales from Guinea-Bissau went from one thousand dollars to eight thousand dollars.
Despite selling more and buying less, China continues to record a trade deficit with the Portuguese-speaking bloc, which reached US$49.6 billion in 2025.
In total, trade between Portuguese-speaking countries and China reached US$225.8 billion, 0.3% more than in the previous year.</description><pubDate>2026-02-26 23:39:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai highlights “stable recovery and continued development” of the economy</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/26/sam-hou-fai-destaca-recuperacao-estavel-e-desenvolvimento-continuo-da-economia/</link><description>The Chief Executive was present yesterday at the spring dinner hosted by the Macau Commercial Association. Speaking on the occasion, Sam Hou Fai said he hoped that the Macau Commercial Association “will continue to take advantage of the unique advantages and bridge functions it performs, bringing together the industrial and commercial sector, for greater integration in the context of national development and a better provision of services to the country”, can be read in a statement from the Executive.
Sam Hou Fai indicated that, in the last year, Macau's economy and society registered a “stable recovery and continuous development”, with the acceleration of economic diversification, managing to achieve “new advances in the development of the Deep Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin”. Furthermore, integration between Macau and Hengqin was strengthened, said the official.
He said that during his visit to Beijing in December last year, President Xi Jinping recognized the government's work and gave significant guidance. On the occasion, he indicated that the Government “will work with all sectors of society to effectively implement the development initiatives of the next phase” and, in this way, expressed five expectations to the Macau Commercial Association and the industrial and business sector: to be firm defenders of the principle of ‘one country, two systems’, to be “drivers” of adequate diversification of the economy, to be “pioneers” in the construction of the Cooperation Zone in Hengqin, to be “builders” of social harmony, and, finally, to be “guides”. for youth development. "It expects the industrial and commercial sector to collectively create opportunities for the younger generation to grow and develop, expanding their horizons and competitiveness through various channels. And together with the Macao SAR Government, promote an innovative and entrepreneurial environment that encourages the courage to renew, experiment and take initiatives, to support young people in realizing their ambitions and achieving success on the broad stages of Macau, Hengqin and the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area", concluded the official.</description><pubDate>2026-02-26 23:38:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Court building in Praia Grande with works completed</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/26/edificio-do-tribunal-na-praia-grande-com-obras-concluidas/</link><description>All works on the Court of Final Appeal Building in Praia Grande were completed, where the old court building and the former Judiciary Police facilities are located.
According to the Public Works Services Directorate (DSOP), the project is located on Avenida da Praia Grande and Rua Central, occupying a total area of ​​two lots of 3,524 square meters.
The contract was implemented in two phases, with the first phase of work on the foundations, basements and support of the external walls of the new building being carried out in October 2022 and completed in April 2024. The second phase of work on the superstructure of the front block was scheduled in March 2024 and that of the rear block was in April of the same year, and has now been completed.
According to the design, the old court building will be used to maintain and part of the space will be reorganized according to the new functions and, simultaneously, work will be carried out to consolidate the structure and remodel the interior. In addition, the facade of the east wing of the former Judiciary Police facilities along the street is maintained, and then a new building is constructed with a basement floor and three floors in height.
Information from DSOP shows that, in total, the contract for the new Court of Final Instance Building foresees a budget of 320.7 million patacas, including the budgeted amounts for project preparation, construction, supervision, quality control and quality control of electromechanical installations.
The Old Court Building, which is a classified property in Macau, with an eclectic style, was built in 1951. It was originally the Macau Public Offices Building, including the Macau Finance Office, the Civil Administration Services Office, the Central Economic Services Office, the Finance Office and the Court.
Later, due to lack of space, the aforementioned departments left the building. After the transfer of sovereignty, the name of the building was changed to the Base Judicial Court of the Macao SAR, and in 2003, the Base Judicial Court also left the building due to the identification of security decoys in the internal structure.
The building remained empty until 2007, when plans were initiated for alternative uses, including its temporary use as a performance venue for artistic groups. The Cultural Institute considered the possibility of converting it into the New Central Library, but this proposal faced public controversy and the Government decided to locate the new library in the space of the former Hotel Estoril, while the former court building was retained for judicial use.</description><pubDate>2026-02-26 23:36:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Merz announces Chinese order of up to 120 planes from Airbus in Beijing</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/26/merz-anuncia-em-pequim-encomenda-chinesa-de-ate-120-avioes-a-airbus/</link><description>The German Chancellor announced yesterday, in Beijing, an order for “up to 120” planes made by China to the European aircraft manufacturer Airbus”, meeting the Chinese President's desire for new progress in bilateral relations.

On the first day of the visit to Germany's main trading partner, increasingly seen in the country as a dangerous competitor for “Made in Germany”, Friedrich Merz did not provide details about the order, particularly regarding the type of equipment, but presented it as illustrative of the potential of the relationship with China.
"We have just learned that Chinese leaders are going to order more planes from the company Airbus. These are up to 120 additional aircraft", he told journalists, after meetings held throughout the day with Chinese officials.
Merz's announcement comes after Chinese President Xi Jinping told the German Chancellor, during a meeting in Beijing, that he expects “new progress” in bilateral relations. "It is a pleasure to work with you to enable the Sino-German global strategic partnership to continuously achieve new progress," Xi told Merz.
Xi, who has successively received foreign leaders in recent months, also reaffirmed his desire for “new advances” in the bilateral relationship. “The more troubled and complex the world is, the more important it is for China and Germany to strengthen strategic communication”, he stressed to Merz, who arrived accompanied by an important delegation of German business leaders.
In meetings with the Chinese Prime Minister, Li Qiang, and later with Xi, the head of the German Government defended a reinforcement of “fairer” cooperation with China and an open debate on the issues of divergence already highlighted before the trip.
These include the growing imbalance of trade in favor of China, distortions of competition, restrictions on access to markets and the security of supply of rare earths, a sector in which China holds a dominant position, as well as state subsidies to Chinese companies and the exchange rate of the Chinese currency. “There are challenges, but the framework in which we have evolved is remarkably good”, assured Merz during the meeting with Xi.
Merz is making his first visit to China since taking office in 2025. After the leaders of France, Canada and the United Kingdom, he is the most recent to visit Beijing, at a time when North American President Donald Trump has shaken the established order, with the imposition of customs tariffs and the review of traditional alliances.

Decisive visit for European strategy towards China

The visit of German Chancellor Friedrich Merz to Beijing is “decisive” for the European strategy towards China, between accepting the Chinese narrative of “stability” or moving towards a more assertive response to trade imbalances, according to the ECFR.
The director of the Asia program at the European Council on Foreign Relations (ECFR) think tank, Andrew Small, argued in an analysis report that one of Beijing's main political objectives is to preserve the status quo in relations with European countries which, faced with China's growing trade surpluses and non-market-oriented practices, could tighten trade protectionism measures.
For the analyst, the onus falls on Merz to make it clear that Chinese productive overcapacity, Beijing's willingness to exploit economic dependencies and support for Russian President Vladimir Putin are sources of instability for the German economy and European security.
The chancellor's trip is, therefore, “less of a bilateral tour” and more of a “defining moment” for Europe, in which the political signal sent by Berlin could influence whether the bloc opts for a firmer line or for maintaining the current model of economic relations. “Not changing the current trajectory of the relationship with China has a daily cost, translated into lost jobs, slower growth and the hollowing out of competitive industrial sectors,” wrote Andrew Small.
The implication is direct for Germany, whose export base faces increasing Chinese competition, from electric vehicles to machinery manufacturing. Europe's largest economy is under pressure from deindustrialization and loss of manufacturing jobs as Chinese manufacturers improve the quality of their products and maintain competitive prices.
During the visit, Merz asked Chinese President Xi Jinping for a “readjustment” of trade relations, pointing out the worsening German deficit, the restrictions imposed on German companies and the need to reduce risks in critical supply chains – in particular Europe's dependence on Chinese rare earths for sectors such as automobiles and defense.
“Competition between companies must be fair”, stated the German Chancellor, defending “transparency”, “reliability” and “compliance with common rules”. Merz also called for the reduction of “market-distorting subsidies” and industrial “overcapacity”, suggesting that greater domestic demand in China, supported by a moderate appreciation of the Chinese currency, could alleviate protectionist pressures in Europe.
Xi highlighted the importance of preserving the stability of the international order and strengthening European strategic autonomy, at a time of tensions between Beijing and Washington. The Chinese leader presented China and Germany as “defenders of multilateralism” and “free trade”, adding that Beijing “supports the self-reliance and strength” of Europe and hopes that the continent “works with China in the same direction”.
Despite the rhetorical hardening, Andrew Small considered that Merz “does not have a plan to face the deindustrialization of Europe caused by Chinese imbalances and practices that distort the market”.
The analyst argued that Berlin must promote an integrated European strategy to ensure equal conditions of competition. Although the European Union has advanced instruments such as industrial legislation, an economic security doctrine and investigations into foreign subsidies, these initiatives remain scattered.
According to the ECFR, these measures must be consolidated into a coherent and comprehensive strategy, capable of operating “at the speed and scale” required by the challenges posed by the Chinese economy.
Andrew Small further recommended informal coordination with other major economies facing similar challenges. “Diversifying trading partners can be useful, but it is insufficient if European companies face subsidized or state-supported Chinese competition in third markets,” he noted.
The third dimension is political: signaling a red line to Beijing, making it clear that Europe will defend its industrial future and will resort to instruments against coercion if China tries to block this strategy. For ECFR, European leaders have reiterated concerns in previous visits to Beijing without following up on them. Merz's visit therefore represents an opportunity to align speech and action and redefine European credibility in managing the relationship with China. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-26 23:31:34</pubDate></item><item><title>China's relations with Cuba under the US Sphere of Influence</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/26/relacoes-da-china-com-cuba-sob-a-esfera-de-influencia-dos-eua/</link><description>Recent developments in Sino-Cuban relations indicate that both countries have strengthened their bilateral relations immediately after the dismissal of former Venezuelan president Nicolás Maduro and also immediately after the US decision to stop the shipment of oil from Venezuela to Cuba, whose economy and society have been deeply affected by excessive dependence on Venezuela. The continued development of closer relations between Cuba and China shows that while Cuba seeks economic and political support from China, Beijing regards Havana as its socialist brother, whose economic needs and livelihoods must be immediately met.
After the removal of Venezuelan President Maduro by the US military on January 3, Washington interrupted the export of oil from Venezuela to Cuba, trying to force the socialist regime to implement economic and political reforms. The immediate impact on Cuba is the compromise of the livelihoods of ten million citizens, many of whom have been affected by energy, fuel and electricity shortages (CNN, February 18, 2026). Tourism in Cuba has also suffered. The United Kingdom and Canada have warned their citizens to avoid unnecessary travel to Cuba. Cuba's centralized economy was heavily dependent on subsidies from the former Soviet Union and the former Venezuelan government, under the leadership of Hugo Chávez and, later, Nicolás Maduro. Daily electricity cuts caused a crisis of subsistence and governance in Cuba, whose president, Miguel Díaz-Canel, called on citizens to adopt a war mentality in order to resist difficulties in a “creative” way. However, the reality is that many ordinary people complain about their basic needs and the difficulties of getting vegetables and other foods from the countryside to the cities.
On January 29, US President Donald Trump issued an executive order that not only declared a state of national emergency due to an alleged Cuban “threat” to American national security, but also imposed tariffs on countries such as Venezuela and Mexico, which sell or supply oil to Cuba.
Before the executive order was issued, several Venezuelan oil tankers heading to Cuba were seized and intercepted by US forces in the Caribbean Sea (Peoples Dispatch, January 23, 2026). Such actions clearly sent a warning message to the Cuban government.
On January 30, Guo Jiakun, spokesperson for the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs, told journalists at a press conference that China “resolutely opposes any inhumane actions and practices that deprive the Cuban people of their rights to subsistence and development” (Global Times, January 30, 2026). His comments were made in response to the US executive order threatening to impose tariffs on countries that sell oil to Cuba.
To worsen the problem of the US economic blockade, the Mexican state oil company Pemex “backtracked” on its plans to export oil to Cuba in January 2026. Although Mexican President Claudia Sheinbaum denied that Pemex's decision was a yielding to US pressure and even argued that the decision was “sovereign”, the Mexican company's action, coincidentally, worsened Cuba's energy crisis.
On February 10, China's Ministry of Foreign Affairs stated that there were no reports of Chinese citizens stranded in Cuba due to airlines running out of fuel and suspending their flights following the US blockade of oil shipments from Venezuela to Cuba (Reuters, February 10, 2026).
Lin Jian, another spokesperson for China's Ministry of Foreign Affairs, said China firmly supports Cuba in protecting its national sovereignty and security and opposes any foreign interference. He added that China would help the Cuban side “in the best way possible” (Reuters, February 10, 2026).
In response to US sanctions against Cuba, China announced, in January and February 2026, the shipment of 90,000 tons of rice to Cuba and the provision of emergency financial assistance. The first batch of rice arrived in Cuba on January 20, 2026. Clearly, China came to Cuba's rescue in the midst of the geopolitical struggle between Washington and Havana. Following the arrival of Chinese rice in Cuba at the end of January, Cuban Vice Prime Minister Oscar Perez-Oliva stated: “We deeply appreciate and are grateful for this assistance at a difficult time, when levels of aggression are increasing and the US economic, commercial and financial blockade against the Cuban people is intensifying in an unprecedented way” (Peoples Dispatch, January 23, 2026). At the same time, the Chinese ambassador to Cuba, Hua Xin, noted that Chinese aid represented the “deep ties of special friendship” between China and Cuba – a comment that points to the persistent ideology of socialist brotherhood.
In fact, the Chinese side sent six food shipments by air to Cuba before the last week of January 2026. In 2026, the PRC provided Cuba with solar lamps, roofing materials and mattresses, while President Xi Jinping approved financial aid worth 80 million dollars.
Both China and Russia apparently anticipated the harsher and imminent American sanctions against Cuba before Trump's executive order was issued. On January 21, Russian Interior Minister Vladimir Alexandrovich Kolokolssev traveled to Havana to talk to President Díaz-Canel and a Russian delegation. If Cuba is in the US' backyard, both Russia and China are eager to support Cuba economically and practically – an illustration of how geopolitical struggles have played out in Latin America.
In early February, Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi and Politburo Standing Committee member Wang Huning held separate meetings with Bruno Rodríguez Parrilla, special envoy and foreign minister of the Cuban government and the Cuban Communist Party (China Daily, February 6, 2026). Wang Yi stated that Cuba had already won wide respect from the international community due to its spirit of resistance to power politics and that the principle of China's foreign policy was to uphold equity and justice by providing support and assistance to Cuba. He further added that China attaches immense importance to strengthening the solidarity of the Global South and safeguarding regional and global peace. In fact, Cuba is an important socialist country in China's view, as it was the first country in the Western Hemisphere to establish diplomatic relations with the People's Republic of China in September 1960. On the other hand, China continues to be Cuba's second largest trading partner, which, in turn, is China's fifth largest trading partner in the Caribbean region.
Bruno Rodríguez Parrilla's visit to Beijing, at the beginning of February, was politically and diplomatically significant. This happened just one week after the issuance of the US executive order against Cuba. Parrilla expressed his gratitude for China's support for Cuba in opposing the blockade and external sanctions, as well as for rice exports and Beijing's financial aid to Havana.
The strong socialist connection between China and Cuba could be seen in President Xi Jinping's statements in September 2025, when both countries celebrated the 65th anniversary of their diplomatic relations. President Xi emphasized that China attaches immense importance to its relations with Cuba historically. Furthermore, for Xi, both countries must strengthen traditional friendship, increase mutual political trust and boost all aspects of comprehensive and strategic cooperation (Ming Pao, September 28, 2025). He also used the term “Sino-Cuban entity of common destiny” to refer to bilateral relations between the two countries – a term that reflects the strong bond under the ideology of socialist fraternity.
Strong ideological and historical relationships could also be detected in December 2024, when Cuba was affected by a blackout that interrupted the operation of schools and workplaces. In response to the blackout, China provided electrical infrastructure to Cuba in early 2025. In September 2025, both countries signed a memorandum of understanding on their cooperation in the development of basic infrastructure, exchange and sharing of information, standardization of measurements and quality control of facilities. In late October 2025, when Cuba was hit by Hurricane Melissa, which damaged many homes and crops, China provided immediate aid including food, solar lamps, furniture and building materials by air and sea (China News Agency in Hong Kong, November 17, 2026).
In terms of geopolitical rivalry, the US was reportedly concerned about China's attempt to install four intelligence gathering stations in Cuba as early as 2023 (TVBS News, January 9, 2026). Furthermore, the US was alarmed by the action of Chinese companies, such as Huawei, to build telecommunications networks in Cuba, which were reportedly used by Cuban authorities to disrupt communications between some Cuban protesters and dissidents internally (TVBS News, January 9, 2026). Above all, Cuba is located less than 100 miles south of Florida and is well positioned to conduct surveillance on US military installations (CSIS, December 6, 2024). Thus, Chinese operations in Cuba have been observed by the US in an alarming way.
On the other hand, although China has provided aid to Cuba, the latter's debt to the former is enormous and cannot be easily paid (RFA, October 30, 2024). Due to the instability of Cuba's financial situation, the increase in national debt represents a chronic payment problem for China. The “unfathomable” nature of Cuban debt could also mean that Cuba will likely have to experiment with Chinese-style market reforms for its economy to improve. Therefore, Chinese economic aid to Cuba should ideally be accompanied by constructive advice from China to Cuban authorities on how the overly centralized Cuban economy can be reformed in a more efficient, productive and effective way. In fact, the Joint Declaration signed by Cuba and China in September 2025 provides for cooperation in economic, social and political areas, which implies that Havana may seek Beijing's help to reform its excessively centralized economy.
However, the political will to reform the Cuban economy ultimately derives from its leadership. There are reports that President Díaz-Canel has already accelerated market reforms since 2018, legalizing small and medium-sized companies and boosting foreign investment. Still, large bureaucracy, financial restrictions and US sanctions became obstacles to Cuba's economic reforms. Most importantly, the US is committed to changing the Cuban regime. US Secretary of State Marco Rubio, a Cuban-American who immigrated from Cuba to Miami in 1971 and who remains interested in Cuban politics, reportedly held a secret dialogue with Raúl Guillermo Rodríguez Castro, 41, grandson of Cuban leader Raúl Castro (Axio, February 18, 2026). The younger Castro is seen as more business-oriented than other members of the Castro family. It remains to be seen how Cuban leadership will evolve. In any case, regime change is a fundamental geopolitical objective of the US in its foreign policy towards Latin America, as is the fate of Maduro in Venezuela. Maduro was detained by the US military and killed by Cuban security guards during the January 3 US attack.
Given the circumstances in which Cuba is under the US sphere of geopolitical and military influence, and considering Chinese economic influence over Cuba and Moscow's diplomatic relations with Havana, the American sanctions policy against Cuba naturally led to immediate diplomatic responses from China and Russia. The dispute between the USA, China and Russia for political-economic influence over Cuba still has to be observed.
In conclusion, the recent increase in American sanctions against Cuba has already provoked immediate reactions from China and Russia, especially since Beijing promptly provided financial and logistical assistance to Havana. China and Cuba remain friendly socialist brothers and, as such, the former's unconditional support for the latter is natural and understandable. The challenge for Cuba is to accelerate and deepen its market reforms following the Chinese path, while becoming more economically self-sufficient, instead of being overly dependent on regional and global powers, be they the former Soviet Union and Venezuela in the past, or China and Russia in the present. To protect and promote its geopolitical and military interests, the US naturally seeks regime change in Cuba – a consistent American foreign policy that nevertheless undermines the national security of the Cuban regime. In response, Cuba must seek more political-economic and diplomatic support from China and Russia. The times of the Bay of Pigs invasion in April 1961, when the US failed to overthrow Fidel Castro's regime, are behind us. Currently, the US seeks to promote regime change through much harsher economic sanctions than ever before. The US policy of seeking regime change in Cuba and Beijing's reactive policy of ideological-economic aid to Havana signal the intensification of rivalry between the US and China over Cuba – another battlefield following the collapse of the Maduro regime in Venezuela.</description><pubDate>2026-02-26 23:29:36</pubDate></item><item><title>DSAL and Galaxy provide 20 vacancies in the employment + training plan</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/26/dsal-e-galaxy-proporcionam-20-vagas-em-plano-de-emprego-formacao/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) and Galaxy will launch the “GEC elite development plan (operation in hotels)”, registration for which starts today and ends on March 12th.
This plan will provide a total of 20 job vacancies on a “first hire, then training” basis, with 10 vacancies for “agent (Front office)” and 10 for “agent (Buttler)”. Those admitted will receive professional and on-the-job training lasting 30 months. The training content covers integrated training before integration into the job market and technical training for the job, English conversation training course from Linguaskills General – Cambridge English Language Assessment, courses on basic and intermediate level management techniques, a workshop on service techniques from Forbes, among others, workers are also provided to obtain the professional qualification of master in the art of tea with national professional qualification, the Macao Occupational Skills Recognition System (MORS) certification and level 1 qualification courses and 2 in WSET wines.
Those who demonstrate good performance and have successfully completed the training will have the opportunity to progress to the position of assistant manager, with a salary adjustment.
“DSAL hopes that, through this plan, company resources can be effectively combined with Government policies, providing residents with a double guarantee of stable employment and increased skills, promoting the valorization of the local workforce structure and the development of adequate diversification of the economy”, highlights the organization in a statement.</description><pubDate>2026-02-26 23:37:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Old are the rags: The vibrant chapter of reform</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/26/velhos-sao-os-trapos-o-vibrante-capitulo-da-reforma/</link><description>Gone are the days when reform was associated with a silent epilogue. In the territory of Macau, reaching retirement age represents the beginning of a vibrant chapter, where time stretches between walks, park benches and get-togethers. With an average life expectancy of around 84 years, one of the highest in the world, Macau residents reach retirement with remarkably high levels of health. Factors such as access to quality medical care, a balanced diet and a strong emphasis on prevention and holistic well-being help many retirees maintain impressive vitality, defying stereotypes about aging. This longevity is not mere chance: it reflects a culture that values ​​balance between body, mind and community.
In Macau, the elderly do not retreat into oblivion; on the contrary, they breathe in the humid air of the Pearl River Delta, exalting a vitality that defies the years. The daily routine includes walks in traditional public gardens and parks, where the day begins with physical exercise to the sound of birds and the distant murmur of engines.
Macau's public gardens are true sanctuaries dedicated to health, designed with a sensitivity that integrates concepts of traditional Chinese landscape architecture with modernity, responding to the needs of different age groups.
Among the most popular attractions are the exercise machines installed in gardens, parks and squares throughout the region. These simple but effective pieces of equipment, such as ellipticals, stretching machines, and muscle-strengthening and balance stations, are designed to promote mobility, strength, coordination, and cardiovascular health without putting stress on your joints. Retirees of all ages use them daily, transforming exercise into a social and accessible routine.
Another characteristic element of the routine of local elderly people are the pebble stone paths, typical of the Chinese tradition of plantar reflexology. Walking barefoot on polished pebbles stimulates acupuncture points on the soles of the feet, according to the principles of traditional Chinese medicine, improving blood circulation, promoting the body's energy balance and contributing to longevity and vitality.
Although Macau is known internationally for its casinos, the locals' traditional games are mahjong and xiangqi (also known as Chinese chess) and it is quite common to see groups of elderly people gathered around stone tables in the public space playing games. More than just a pastime, studies have shown that this type of games stimulates the cognitive process, improves motor coordination, combats social isolation and significantly reduces the risk of dementia. They share laughter, discuss strategies and celebrate small daily achievements, transforming public space into a lively social event.
Renovation in Macau is a time of reconnection: with nature, with the community and with one's own body. Local seniors don’t just live out their retirement years; they celebrate it, inspiring new generations to age with grace, health and, above all, joy.</description><pubDate>2026-02-26 23:29:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Sands China expands paternal leave to strengthen support for families</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/26/sands-china-alarga-licencas-paternais-para-reforcar-apoio-as-familias/</link><description>Sands China announced yesterday the extension of paid maternity leave from 70 to 90 days and paternity leave from five to seven days, in a measure that covers more than 28 thousand workers. The decision, which comes into force on March 1st, reinforces the company's strategy to promote a family working environment and support employees during the period of welcoming new family members.

From March 1st, Sands China Ltd. will increase the periods of paid parental leave for its employees, in an administrative change that aims to provide greater balance and support for workers who become parents. According to the new policy, female workers with at least one year of service are now entitled to 90 days of paid maternity leave, while male workers are now entitled to seven days of paternity leave.
The operator's decision follows the proposal presented by the Government at the beginning of February to amend the labor relations law, which specifically provides for the increase in maternity leave from 70 to 90 days. The legislative change, which equates private sector workers to public servants, is currently under public consultation until March 16, with the Government also proposing a supplementary subsidy of up to 20 days for small and medium-sized companies to alleviate the financial pressure arising from the payment of licenses.
Paulo Cheong, senior vice president of Human Resources at Sands China, highlighted that the company, which currently employs more than 28 thousand people in the region, places the promotion of a family work culture at the heart of its strategy. "We follow a people-centered approach, and consider each employee as a valued member of our extended family. We remain committed to promoting their physical and mental well-being, family happiness and professional development, while maintaining a sustainable and supportive work environment," said Cheong.
This update to parental leave is part of a wider set of measures to support families implemented by the company in recent years. Since September 2025, eligible full-time employees are entitled to up to six days of paid childcare leave, allowing them to accompany children to medical appointments or vaccinations.
The company also offers a “parenting support shift” scheme, which allows workers to be absent for one hour a day for 90 consecutive days after the birth of their child. During this period, employees who work shifts can also be assigned fixed working hours, facilitating stability in the first months of the child's life.
In addition to these measures, the American-based operator grants days of paid annual leave above that required by law and allows workers to have up to six unused sick days from the previous year as compensatory rest days in the following year. The initiative, unprecedented in the sector, reinforces the company's commitment to the well-being of its employees, according to Sands China itself.
Another point that the operator highlighted in its statement was its human resources practice, which has been recognized internationally. The company was the first operator of integrated resorts in the Asia-Pacific region and the first company in the tourism and services sector in Macau to receive the “Top Employer” certification, awarded by the Top Employer Institute, based in Amsterdam, one of the most respected entities worldwide in the certification of human resources strategies. Sands China won this award for the second year in a row, joining a group of 2,500 certified companies around the world.</description><pubDate>2026-02-26 23:40:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Jimmy Lai wins appeal against conviction in Hong Kong</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/26/jimmy-lai-vence-recurso-contra-condenacao-em-hong-kong/</link><description>Former Hong Kong pro-democracy tycoon Jimmy Lai has won his appeal against a 2022 fraud conviction, just days after being sentenced to 20 years in prison for foreign collusion and seditious publication.

“We validate the appeals, annul the verdicts and suspend the sentences” in the fraud case, said Hong Kong High Court judge Jeremy Poon. Lai did not appear in court and remained in detention.
The decision represents a surprising victory for Lai, founder of the now 78-year-old Apple Daily newspaper.
The fraud case for which he was convicted in 2022 stemmed from a dispute over a lease and was unrelated to the charges he faced under the national security law. Jimmy Lai had been sentenced in this case to five years and nine months in prison for a “planned, organized and multi-year scheme”, as the first instance judge described it at the time.
During the trial, the prosecution argued that a consulting company operated by Lai in a personal capacity occupied offices that Apple Daily had leased for the newspaper's publishing and printing operations. Lai was convicted of violating the terms of the lease Apple Daily signed with a state-owned company, which the prosecution characterized as fraud.
Defense lawyers argued that the case should have been handled in the civil sphere and not in the criminal sphere, adding that the size of the locations in question was minimal.
Former Apple Daily executive Wong Wai-keung was also charged in the same case and sentenced to 21 months in prison.
On February 10, a Hong Kong court sentenced Jimmy Lai to 20 years in prison for foreign collusion and seditious publication. The sentence, handed down despite external pressure, is the harshest under the national security law imposed by China in 2020, following the sometimes violent pro-democracy protests that shook Hong Kong the previous year.

Hong Kong sentences activist's father to eight months for administering his daughter's insurance policy

A Hong Kong court yesterday sentenced the father of exiled activist Anna Kwok to eight months in prison for breaking national security law by trying to dispose of funds from his daughter's insurance policy. Kwok Yin-sang, 69, had been found guilty in early February of trying to raise financial assets in his daughter's name.
The court indicated during the preliminary trial that the defendant attempted to exchange a life and personal accident insurance policy taken out with AIA International in his daughter's name, worth 88 thousand Hong Kong dollars.
The prosecution argued that this operation constituted asset management by a fugitive, declared so by authorities in 2023 for her role as executive director of the Hong Kong Democratic Council (HKDC), a non-profit organization based in Washington, founded in 2019 by inhabitants of the former British colony during anti-government protests. The prosecution presented documentary evidence, including bank records and email, which demonstrated Kwok's knowledge of his daughter's legal status. The defense maintained that the father acted in good faith and denied any intent to benefit his daughter. Furthermore, he questioned the constitutionality of the rule, claiming that it does not imply a transfer abroad or support for subversive activities, and emphasized that Kwok considered the funds as family resources.
After the conviction, Anna Kwok said the accusation against her father was based on an “incoherent fiction”. “My father was condemned simply for being my father”, he added. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-26 23:36:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Escrutínio ao Governo não deve ultrapassar limites, defende André Cheong</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/26/escrutinio-ao-governo-nao-deve-ultrapassar-limites-defende-andre-cheong/</link><description>André Cheong, president of the Legislative Assembly (AL), reiterated yesterday that the legislative body must retreat before the executive branch, also defending that the chamber must “support the Government without omissions” and “supervise it without exceeding limits”.

At the spring lunch of members of the Legislative Assembly (AL) with representatives of the media, André Cheong insisted that the executive branch must have primacy over the legislative branch, also arguing that the hemicycle must not “exceed limits” in scrutinizing the Government.
The occasion served for André Cheong to recall that, last month, Xia Baolong, director of the Hong Kong and Macau Affairs Office of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China and the Hong Kong and Macau Affairs Office of the State Council, asked the Macao SAR to give greater preponderance to the executive power over the legislative and judicial powers. After this appeal, several Macao SAR entities promised to fulfill this aim, including AL.
The president of the AL, who took office in October last year after having been secretary for Administration and Justice, stated that since taking office, the hemicycle has “made efforts to implement the principle of executive primacy and promote positive institutional interaction between the executive and legislative powers”. “To this end, we have optimized legislative work procedures, intensified communication with the Government, and established closer connection mechanisms, promoting mutual understanding and regular cooperation, with the aim of consolidating a model of collaboration based on mutual trust”, he stated in his speech at lunch.
The person in charge said that, within the scope of legislative work, guidelines and working procedures were developed for the assessment of proposed laws. Regarding inspection work, “the operating rules of the three Monitoring Committees were improved and their responsibilities were clarified, making possible the eventual creation of specialized working groups”, he detailed. Finally, in the area of ​​internal management, a presidential office was created, internal rules for the assessment of proposed laws were also approved and, in addition, the distribution of human resources was optimized.
André Cheong also took the opportunity to provide an update on the analysis of the State Security Defense Commission's proposed law, which is being discussed in committee.  The AL “will intensify internal coordination and improve communication with the Government, ensuring the full performance of its functions, particularly with regard to the assessment of this proposed law and the consolidation of national security in Macau”, said the president of the legislative body. This proposed law, remember, will restrict the free choice of lawyers by defendants in national security cases. In these trials, lawyers will have to request special authorization and it is then the State Security Defense Commission, a body led by the Chief Executive, which will decide whether or not the lawyer can defend the accused.
“No futuro, a Assembleia Legislativa continuará a exercer com firmeza as competências que lhe são conferidas pela Lei Básica da RAEM, defenderá conscientemente o princípio da primazia do Executivo e apoiará plenamente o Chefe do Executivo e o Governo da RAEM no exercício das suas funções, nos termos da lei”, assegurou André Cheong, prometendo também reforçar a “interacção positiva com o Governo, tanto na actividade legislativa como na fiscalização”. “Pretendemos ajudar o Governo a identificar problemas, aperfeiçoar políticas e melhorar a eficácia da governação, assegurando assim a premissa de ‘apoiar o Governo sem omissões e de fiscalizá-lo sem ultrapassar limites'”, frisou.</description><pubDate>2026-02-26 23:41:55</pubDate></item></channel></rss>