<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/29/portugal-e-grande-baia-usam-musica-como-ponte-no-festival-luso-chines-de-musica-e-artes/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>More than cream pastels: butter shop wants to bring a slice of “Portuguese” to Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/29/mais-do-que-pasteis-de-nata-a-manteigaria-quer-trazer-uma-fatia-de-portugalidade-a-macau/</link><description>The butter shop opened four months ago in downtown Macao with the mission of revolutionizing the concept of “cream pastel”, so often associated with Egg Tarts Macanese who only resemble the Portuguese convent in the circular mold. Diogo Vieira, the brand manager, explains to the end point that the mission does not end there: beyond the “best authentic cream pastry”, only slightly retouched to adapt to Chinese palate, butter wants to provide macao an immersive experience of what it means to be Portuguese.
 
In the middle of Avenida da Praia Grande, one of the busiest arteries in the city of Macau, it is possible to return to Portugal only transposing a door. It is identified meters away by the unmistakable logo of the butter brand and a bell that sounds every few minutes, announcing a new batch of still stewardy cream pastels. Inside, the aromas the hot butter, cinnamon and coffee mix in an unusual atmosphere in Macao and refer to the typical cafes of the low Lisbon, where the cream pastel wants to be sweet and crash and always accompanied by the shit and the spout.
The Egg Tart is one of the most widespread symbols in Macau, simultaneously with the iconography of the ruins of São Paulo or the Mak Mak tourism mascot. At every corner, foods germinate foods that sell the famous soft -stuffed, similar to steam cooked egg yolks, wrapped in a brittle consistency mass. Despite the obvious differences in the texture and taste of the two varieties, some stores choose to label their products as “cream pastels” or “‘ Portuguese Egg Tarts ””, perhaps to give them an exotic sound. The authentically Portuguese cream pastel, with intense flavor to cream and butter and puff texture, is much rarer to find.
“I can't claim that we have the only authentic cream pastry in Macao, but we are guaranteed the best,” says Diogo Vieira, manager of the territory butter. He received the final point on the morning of the Thursday, the day they completed precisely four months since the inauguration of the space in January. There are competition stores a few minutes away, many of them with faithful clientele for decades and a lightweight, more sweetened and more focused egg than the Nata, designed carefully to the Asian palate. Still, the manager does not believe the butter was being integrated into a saturated market. On the contrary: in a region with such a little diverse offer, the Portuguese brand is distinguished by presenting the genuine flavor from the other corner of the world.
“Compared to the local offer, we are neither better nor worse,” he says. "We are different from what they offer. They call it 'Portuguese Egg Tart', which is not the correct denomination; it is a visually similar product, but it has a different consistency, like pudding, and a completely different taste than ours." Within the specific category of cream pastel, corresponding to the same standards of Portugal, Diogo Vieira is not aware of admitting: “There are other local bakeries that can even have Portuguese cream bakers, but they do not have the same recipe or quality of ours. Just see the comparison of criticism that customers leave 'online', both in Portugal and Macau”.
It is not only the cream pastel that came from the west European west. In the beverage menu, although American coffees and Lattes' are also very much appreciated locally, they are Expresso, Porto Wine and Ginja that solidify the colors of Portugal in the store and arouse the curiosity of customers, little used to this offer. "Our Ginja is a Portuguese product specifically produced to Macau by a local brand, Ginja do Senado. We want to partner with small local businesses, to encourage the spirit of community and ajuda." Alternatively, older clients to old habits can opt for homemade ginger, mint and lemon tea. "We try to have more localized drinks for this market, which meet Asian tastes and tea culture."
A customer enters the store and goes to the counter. Follow “good morning” and “how are you?” Exchanged from side to side, while the classic coffee and cream combination is served. Being Portuguese, note Diogo Vieira, refers to more than a cinnamon sprinkled pastry or a short and creamy express-is to exhale hospitality and welcome each client as a longtime friend, with their own characteristics that individualize it from the previous one. "We know that in pastries there is a long time to put the products on exhibitors and it is the customer who is serving on the board, and then go to the box to pay. This makes no direct interaction between the two parts," he laments. Buttering, as a stronghold of Portuguese culture in Macanese territory, seeks to stand out from the common self-service in pastries around with a very characteristic cordiality of southern European countries.
“We are trying to give a Portuguese experience of the best, including a Portuguese service. It is something that I try to instill in my team, even if employees are Philippines or Chinese: a genuine will to interact with the customer, ask how it is, how it was full and the line is great, people want to consume fast and leave. people. The intention is that the client, on the other side of the counter, mimicizes these cultural habits and returning them equally, starting with a "Hello" and ending in a "thank you."
 
Towards expansion in Asia, with 50% of sugar 
 
"Our production is open to the public. This area has been conceived exactly for the process to be in sight and so that customers can see our pastelers work. We have nothing to hide." Diogo Vieira and Pedro Quintaneiro, a pastry deputy, guide the end point until upstairs. There are no tables or chairs: although it is possible to consume in place, it is not so much a tasting zone as an occasion to stop and admire the method of making the Portuguese sweet since incipience. And perhaps to take a few photos for social networks.
The production of the sweets had to be divided into two floors, due to logistics limitations. “We can't put everything in the same space, as we do in Portugal,” explains the manager, pointing to the bottom floor where one of the most distinctive features will probably be a glass separator that allows the customer to follow the process to which pastelers call “opening, filling and cooking”. "This part down there is perhaps the most photographed, where you work with your hands opening the molds, fill the oven, take off the oven… because, here, it's a preparation process that is done at a specific time of day, in the morning. The rest of the work is focused below in the afternoon."
One of butter's main quality seals is the guarantee that everything is made at the moment at the hands of the pastelers, from the weighing of flour to cooking. "The process is every manual; nothing is automated. We have no machines to give us this support." The number of trays is managed according to the search for the day, ensuring that the time between oven exit and customer consumption is as small as possible. As Diogo Vieira explains, "the pastel sold in the afternoon was not cooked in the morning. We cook for periods of a hour or two, which gives us the possibility to do the stock of the day from eight in the morning until near eight in the night, when we close."
On the top floor, a pastry is working on the puff pastry and wrapping it in a thick butter block, which then goes to the refrigerators. Pedro Quintaneiro, responsible for the formation of pastelers since the beginning of the project, keeps his eyes fixed on what happens on the other side of the glass and occasionally enters to exchange a word or advice. Pedro was invited to join the team under one condition: he would have to spend almost three months in Portugal immersed in the world of butter, to receive training with pastel masters who included the creators of the brand's exclusive revenue. Return to Macao, he became the trainer of the local team and responsible for ensuring product quality, especially during the early two weeks of great adhesion-not only by the resident population, but consequently of the huge flow of Chinese New Year tourists.
"At the time, we had the reinforcement of two other Portuguese pastries, exactly because we already estimated that we would have a great demand at the beginning and did not have enough local labor to respond. Then things calmed down and they returned to the base," Pedro Quintaneiro remaining full time. If, at the opening in January, more than four thousand daily cream pastels were sold, the number came down to between 1,500 and two thousand, "depending on the days." Diogo Vieira discourages: “We opened very strongly, with a lot of tourism. The local community was curious, tourists have made queues… It's normal, in a opening phase. Now, as we can see, the city is calmer. We are waiting for an increase in May at the time of golden week”.
The official refers to the holidays of Labor Day in the interior of China, which coincide with the first five days of the month. The original recipe for cream pastels was, incidentally, adapted to correspond to the Chinese taste, less tolerant to sweet desserts than Portuguese. "Before we opened the project, we did tests with groups of local and Chinese clients to gauge the receptivity to Portuguese revenue. We conclude that the revenue we use in Lisbon is too sweet for the local market and had to make an adjustment to sugar level, with a 50%reduction." However: “the process and the ingredients remain the same. It was a good, quite balanced recipe”, without changing the essentials of what has popularized the conventual candy factory since the first house inauguration in Chiado over a decade. Even the ingredients are imported directly from Lisbon, except for those that can be bought in Macao without compromising the quality of the end result, such as sugar or lemon.
As the late morning approaches lunchtime, the movement of Portuguese customers and tourists increases on the floor. It's a day of celebration, but Diogo Vieira, plunged into the management of butter and projection of future plans, did not realize the date on the calendar. “Day 24, January… Yeah, it is,” he acknowledges, with an open hand in the four months that passed since the opening of the space. For the next handful of months, expectations are consolidating the brand range in the territory, attracting tourists and residents of Asian origin to a market of Portuguese clients who have already used to asking “a cream and a cream pastry, please” in employment breaks.
The most ambitious plans are scheduled for after summer, with the expansion of the brand to Rua do Cunha, in Taipa Velha - a zone with strong tourist attraction, great visibility and a strategic proximity with the Portuguese restaurant. Covered the "Macao's two main tourist areas", the next natural step will be to widen the brand to neighboring Hong Kong - region with their own gastronomic inheritances influenced by colonialism and an egg tarts tradition adapted from the Costard Tarts in flavor and texture. Anyway in the world, ambition is the same: create a kind of intact bubble of Portuguese within the store, regardless of the country that welcomes it abroad.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Largest opposition party in South Korea appoints Lee Jae-Myung for presidential</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/29/maior-partido-da-oposicao-na-coreia-do-sul-nomeia-lee-jae-myung-para-presidenciais/</link><description>The main opposition party in South Korea named the presidential presidential candidate Lee Jae-Myung, pointed out by the polls as a favorite, after the dismissal of Yoon Suk-Yeol.
 
In a television announcement on Sunday night, the Democratic Party announced that Lee won the presidential appointment with almost 90% of the primary votes that ended on Sunday, defeating two rivals.
"Now, the people and our party colleagues have given me the opportunity to regain the presidency and build a new and true republic of Korea [official name of South Korea]. Thank you! I will humbly implement this arduous and serious task," Lee said in Vitória's speech.
Lee, 60, who was governor of the province of Gyeonggi, the most populous of South Korea, and mayor of the city of Seongam, is the clear favorite to win the elections.
According to a Gallup Korea poll, released on Friday, 38% of respondents chose Lee, while none of the other potential candidates reached 10% of preferences.
The main conservative party, the Popular Power Party, currently in power, will choose the candidate next weekend.
This will be Lee's third attempt to run for presidency after losing the 2022 election to Yoon.
On April 10, Lee had announced the candidacy for party primaries, a day after leaving the position of president of political formation. "I am competing to create a real Korea," Lee said in a video, adding that he intends to be "the best tool" for the South Korean people in the face of the serious political and social crisis they have faced since former President Yoon Suk-Yeol has briefly declared the martial law in December.
Lee argued that the root of social conflict is economical and proposed the reactivation of the economy through public investment in technology and human resources training.
The leader rejected ideological positions, opting for an approach that ensured being pragmatic and defended, moreover, a foreign policy based on the national interest of South Korea.
The National Elections Commission has already started the registration of pre-candidates for the 21st presidential election of the country. The election campaign period starts on May 12.
Lee, 61, worked in factories since he was very young, having suffered a work accident that left him with permanent injuries on a arm. After getting a scholarship, he studied law and started working in a human rights law firm.
The Democrat's career has been marked by ambitious social programs, but also by allegations of corruption linked to an urban development project.
In January, he was the victim of an attempted murder and, on March 26, was acquitted of a conviction that threatened to disqualify him. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 04:28:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao Foreign Trade continues to break in the first quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/29/comercio-externo-de-macau-continua-em-quebra-no-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>Macau's foreign trade has a 4.5% drop between January and March this year, with a total amount of 33.82 billion of patacas. Despite the 6.1% increase in the exported value of goods, the importation of goods fell by 5.6% to 30.33 billion patacas, statistics and census services revealed.
 
Macau continues to record a break in foreign trade in the first quarter of this year, according to the statistics revealed by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). The total amount of foreign trade in goods was located at 33.82 billion patacas, a decrease of 4.5% compared to the 35.42 billion patacas registered between January and March last year.
DSEC yesterday revealed that the exported value of goods reached 3.49 billion of patacas, plus 6.1% in annual terms, highlighting that re-export of 3.15 billion patacas, and domestic export, of 345 million patacas, increased 6.4% and 3.5%, respectively. The imported value of goods corresponds to 30.33 billion patacas, which represents a homologous drop of 5.6%.
Thus, the trade balance deficit in the first quarter of 2025 was 26.83 billion patacas, two billions of patacas compared to the same quarter as last year, of 28.83 billion patacas.
Analyzing exports by countries or destination territories, exported goods for Hong Kong and the United States of America increased 14.0% and 7.0%, respectively, in annual terms to 2.69 billion patacas and 50 million patacas. On the contrary, the exported values ​​of goods to the interior of China (173 million patacas), the countries of “one track, a route” (66 million patacas) and to the European Union (56 million patacas) decreased 5.8%, 60.4%and 10.5%, respectively.
DSEC also advanced that, in relation to categories of goods, 357 million patacas of textile products and clothing and 3.14 billion of non-textile products were exported until March, registering annual growths of 4.3% and 6.3%, respectively.
On the other hand, regarding importation by countries or territories of origin, the amounts imported from goods produced in the European Union dropped 6.4%, and went to 9.45 billion of patacas. The breaking was also found in the amounts imported from goods produced in the interior of China (8.81 billion patacas) and in the countries of “one track, a route” (7.10 billion patacas) in 2.4% and 1.4%, respectively. However, the amount imported from goods produced in Japan (2.16 billion patacas) increased by 3.9%.
The statistics also consist of the analysis of countries or territories of origin of the products. According to the DSEC report, the amounts imported from the interior of China and Hong Kong fell 5.5% and 6.1%, respectively, compared to the first quarter of last year.
With regard to goods, 22.58 billion of consumer goods were imported in Macau, with a homologous decrease of 5.5%, it is highlighted that the imported value of clothing and footwear (3.17 billion patacas) and the golden jewelry (2.88 billion) dropped 8.1%and 8.9%, respectively.
However, the imported value of food and drinks rose 10.9% to 5.7 billion patacas. The imported value of fuels and lubricants (1.60 billion patacas) and mobile phones (553 million patacas) reduced 4.2% and 39.2%, respectively, while the building materials saw a significant decrease from 42.6% by March to 337 million patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 04:22:49</pubDate></item><item><title>China launches measures to stabilize employment, economics and foreign trade</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/29/china-lanca-medidas-para-estabilizar-emprego-economia-e-comercio-externo/</link><description>Chinese authorities yesterday revealed several measures to stabilize employment, economy and foreign trade, in the face of trade war with the United States, which increased uncertainty in the second largest economy worldwide.
 
Zhao Chenxin, deputy director of the National Development and Reform Commission, the country's leading planning body, explained that measures aimed at stabilizing China's foreign trade, which was shaken by the trade war began by US President Donald Trump, involving “specific and differentiated supports for each sector”.
The Chinese government "will help export companies avoid risks," Zhao said, adding that Chinese service companies will be encouraged "to expand internationally."
Foreign companies will also be encouraged to “reinvest” in China, noted the leader, quoted by the Chinese official news agency Xinhua.
Regarding consumer support, the ruler cited “the reinforcement of support for the elderly with disabilities”, “the expansion of consumption in the automotive sector” and “the construction of a salary distribution system appropriate to the skills of each worker”.
Zhao also emphasized the importance of “continuously stabilizing and becoming the capital market”, “increasing financial support to the real economy” and “consolidating the stability of the real estate market,” plunged into a deep crisis for years.
Regarding employment stabilization, the deputy director announced “an increase in vocational training” and “a reinforcement of public employment services”.
On Friday, the leadership of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) also called for measures to stabilize and stimulate the economy in order to mitigate the effects of trade war with the United States.
After a meeting, the CCP Politburo stated that, given the “growing impact of external shocks”, the Chinese government “will coordinate efforts to address the domestic economy in parallel with the challenges of international trade”. The powerful political body referred, not to mention specifically, to commercial disputes with the United States in recent weeks, which resulted in the mutual imposition of tariffs exceeding 100%.
Politburo has indicated that "it is necessary to further consolidate the foundations for China's sustained economic recovery", citing the importance of developing service consumption and "reinforcing the role of consumption as driver of economic growth."
Since the beginning of the trade war triggered by Trump, Chinese companies have focused on the domestic market. However, doubts still remain about the feasibility of this strategy, due to the weak internal demand of China, one of the main signs that affect the world's second largest economy.
In recent years, Beijing has refused to implement strong stimulus measures to prevent inflation that has reached western economies after pandemic, pointed out to the high public debt and the opposition of Chinese President Xi Jinping to the distribution of subsidies. Beijing said, however, that it will implement a cut in interest rates "at the right time."
In March, China was the goal for economic growth by 2025 in “about 5%” for the third consecutive year after growing 5% by 2024.
However, some international organizations have been shown to have cables for the country's ability to achieve the goal for 2025, taking into account the commercial disputes between Beijing and Washington.
The International Monetary Fund last week reduced the forecast of economic growth for China by 2025 by 0.6 percentage points to 4%, mainly due to tariff tensions, which cut the “positive impulse” of the last quarter of 2024.
 
China contradicts Trump and denies recent calls with Xi Jinping
 
China said yesterday that there were no recent telephone calls between Chinese President Xi Jinping and his American counterpart Donald Trump contradicting the Republican's statements.
The world's two largest economic powers are involved in a trade war, triggered by the White House leader.
Donald Trump imposed a 145% customs rates on most Chinese products entering the United States. Beijing retaliated, imposing his own 125% surcharge on US products.
In an interview published on Friday by Time magazine, the US President said he spoke with Xi Jinping on the phone, without specifying when or the content of the conversation. "As much as I know, the two heads of state did not speak over the phone recently," Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakun said at a press conference.
Trump also told Time magazine that discussions were taking place with China to try to reach an agreement and suggested that the process could be completed in the coming weeks. "I would like to reiterate that China and the United States have not been involved in consultations or tariff negotiations," said Guo Jiakun.
The growing commercial tension between Beijing and Washington has triggered uncertainties in markets and raised warnings from international organizations on its potential impact on world economic growth. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 04:28:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Executive expects hospital das Islands to remove 25% from São Januário pressure by 2027</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/29/executivo-espera-que-hospital-das-ilhas-retire-25-da-pressao-do-sao-januario-ate-2027/</link><description>The government estimates that by 2027 the Macau Union Hospital may remove 25% of the pressure from the Conde de São Januário hospital center. According to LAM, secretary for social affairs and culture, the Ilhas Hospital, inaugurated last year, will have 1,200 health professionals in two years.
 
LAM, Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, said yesterday that the government has a plan for the future development of the islands health care complex - Macao Medical Center of Peking Union Medical College Hospital (Macau Union Hospital), which provides that by 2027 the hospital will have more than 1,200 health professionals. Authorities expect two years from now, the new islands hospital remove 25% from the pressure from the Conde de São Januário Hospital.
In the presentation of the Governing Lines (LAG) of the Social Affairs and Culture Folder, the person responsible for the new hospital added that of those 1,200 professionals, 200 will be doctors and 150 specialist doctors. In addition, “we still have to have nurses, teaching staff, pharmacists, etc.,” he said, adding that recently graduated doctors have sought the Macau Union Hospital to work.
The LAG report says that "the collaboration between the Conde de São Januário hospital center and the Macau Union medical center will be reinforced to optimize the affectation of resources and the screening of patients, and to reduce the waiting time for imaging and endoscopic exams, among others." The government also intends to increase the capacity for specialized care in the new island hospital and "improve hospitalization services and the experience of residents in search of medical treatment in order to promote the development of public health care services."
The Macau Union Hospital, which is near Seac Pai Van, officially entered operation on September 16, 2024, currently providing external consultation services specialized for patients referred by health services, including medical examinations of ultrasound, computed tomography (CT) and X-ray and blood analysis services, as well as external consultation services, on the other hand, provides external services. In the areas of General Internal Medicine, Gastroenterology, Dermatology, Infectiology, Orthopedics, etc. In addition, online markings made by residents for external specialty consultations are also accepted. In addition, this hospital also serves to boost the Big Health industry.
At the session, LAM also said that the government will study alternatives to health valleys, as "the use rate is not very high." "The government will study the best way to use the balance not spent the valleys," said the secretary. The LAG report for this year, however, sets an increase in the value of these health valleys from 600 to 700 patacas. The beneficiaries of these health valleys are all permanent residents of Macao.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 04:24:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Putin thanks the North Korean troops for their involvement in the war</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/29/putin-agradece-as-tropas-norte-coreanas-pelo-envolvimento-na-guerra/</link><description>Russian President Vladimir Putin thanked the North Korean troops yesterday for the involvement in the fight against the Ukrainian forces in the Russian region of Kursk, after North Korea confirmed, for the first time, to send troops.
In a statement issued by Kremlin, Putin praised the heroism and dedication of the North Korean combatants: "Shoulder to shoulder with the Russian combatants, defended our homeland as if they were theirs," he said.
North Korea had confirmed yesterday, for the first time, the sending of troops to Russia to support the offensive against Ukraine, under the strategic partnership treaty signed with Moscow in June 2024.
North Korean state news agency KCNA has revealed that “armed forces subunits” in the country “participated in operations to release the occupied areas of Kursk,” following a direct order by leader Kim Jong-un.
According to KCNA, the soldiers' war effort "was completed victoriously."
On Saturday, Russia had announced that its troops totally recovered the Kursk region, taken by the Ukrainian forces, in a surprise foray last year. The Ukrainian authorities denied the claim.
US, South Korea and Ukraine secret services said North Korea sent between 10,000 and 12,000 soldiers to Russia in the last fall, in the first participation in a large armed conflict since the end of the 1950-53 Korean War. However, North Korea only yesterday confirmed the shipping.
The strategic partnership treaty between North Korea and Russia - considered the largest defense agreement between the two countries since the end of the Cold War - requires both nations to use all available means to provide immediate military assistance if any of them are attacked.
KCNA's statement quoted Kim Jong-un, stating that shipping aimed to "annihilate and eliminate Ukrainian neo-Nazi occupants and free the Kursk region in cooperation with the Russian Armed Forces."
The North Korean leader also announced that a monument will soon be erected in Pyongyang, to mark the Batalha de North Korean achievements and that flowers will be deposited in the dead soldiers' tombstones.
The North Korean statement does not specify how many soldiers the North Korea sent and how many died. But in March, the South Korean army stated that about 4,000 soldiers were killed or injured on the war fronts between Russia and Ukraine.
At the same time, the South Korean army also said North Korea had sent about 3,000 additional soldiers to Russia earlier this year.
North Korea to remove its troops from Russia, stating that support for Russia's Ukraine invasion represents a serious provocation to international security. Spokesman Koo Byoungsam said that sending North Korean troops was an “act against humanity” that sacrificed young soldiers in the name of his government.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 04:28:55</pubDate></item><item><title>China registers 70% rise in foreigners in the largest maritime bridge in the world</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/29/china-regista-subida-de-70-nos-estrangeiros-na-maior-ponte-maritima-do-mundo/</link><description>The Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge, the longest sea crossing in the world, recorded more than 172,000 foreign passengers until Sunday, an increase of 70% compared to the same period of 2024.
"This increase is largely due to the expansion of visa exemption policies by China, and Zhuhai's terrestrial border post is the only one in the Chinese continental territory that offers direct road access to Hong Kong International Airport," Chinese state news agency Xinhua said.
Until Sunday, the total number of trips through the bridge had increased by 18.9% in homologous terms, exceeding 10 million passengers, a goal reached 25 days earlier than in 2024.
According to Xinhua, residents of the Chinese continent increased 30.3% to 4.18 million, while the vehicle crossings recorded in Hong Kong and Macau for the Zhuhai border post rose 32.4% to almost 1.2 million this year, with a daily average of 10,000.
The bridge is the longest sea crossing in the world and was inaugurated in 2018. The construction of the bridge started in 2009, but was affected by delays, the death of more than 20 workers and budgetary skids. The final cost of the infrastructure is estimated at $ 16.4 billion, plus 25% of the initially expected.
The bridge has a length of about 55 kilometers, which include an underground tunnel of almost seven kilometers between two artificial islands to facilitate navigation in the Pearl River delta.
The infrastructure, which reduced the travel time between Macao and Hong Kong by about half, was pointed out by the government of China as an important symbol of the Great Guangdong-Hong Bay Integration Policy Kong-Macau.
The gross domestic product in the area that makes up the large bay, whose population is about 70 million, exceeds $ 1.5 billion, larger than the economies of Australia, Indonesia or Mexico, countries that make up the G20 bloc.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 04:28:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao is “the king”, but how long? Rui Cunha Foundation discusses threats to the game sector</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/29/macau-e-o-rei-mas-por-quanto-tempo-fundacao-rui-cunha-discute-ameacas-ao-sector-do-jogo/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation presented yesterday, at 18:00, a conference entitled "Higher Stakes: Macau's Gaming Industry Amid Rising Regional Competition" (translated as "High Betting: The Macao Game Industry within the growing regional competition"), regarding the challenges and changes in the game sector in Macau.
The panel was composed by specialists Ben Lee, shareholder partner of Igamix consultant; Niall Murray, President of the International Investment Society; Rosalind Wade, the executive director of the company expert in the winna media game sector; and José I. Duarte, economist and senior analyst of Macau Business magazine. The moderation of the session was in charge of José Carlos Matias, director of Macau Business and Macau News Agency.
“Macau remains the king of the game, but the regional panorama is changing,” the organizers wrote in a note published before the event. "After a two-year postpandbe recovery, the game's gross gross revenue growth parked by 2025." This stagnation, it is read, can be attributed to multiple factors, from the geopolitical tensions that China currently faces the intensification of regional competition, with Japan and Thailand joining Singapore and Philippines-two powers already established in the sector-as potential rivals.
At yesterday's roundtable, which was broadcast live on the Rui Cunha Foundation's Facebook pages and Macau Business TV (MBTV), guest speakers analyzed “as Macau can stay competitive, adapt innovation and ensure their place in the evolution of the game in Asia”, increasingly overloaded by new elements.
The conference was inserted in the Gaming Series Cycle of Macau Business, where debates and reflections on the game sector in the region are promoted.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 04:28:49</pubDate></item><item><title>China and Philippines display flags in a reef disputed in the Southern Sea of ​​China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/29/china-e-filipinas-exibem-bandeiras-num-recife-disputado-no-mar-do-sul-da-china/</link><description>Beijing said six Philippine citizens landed in Recife that both countries claim in the Southern Sea of ​​China, after photographs of Chinese Coast Guard officers appeared to show the Chinese flag there. A statement by the Chinese Coast Guard described the Philippine landing as illegal and said the Chinese officers had gone to Earth "to perform on -site checks and execution measures."
 
China said yesterday that six Philippine citizens landed in Recife that both countries claim in the Southern Sea of ​​China, after photographs of Chinese coast guard officers appeared to show the Chinese flag there.
Sandy Cay is the latest episode of a long dispute between the two countries about the Southern Sea of ​​China, which Beijing claims in its entirety.
A statement by the Chinese Coast Guard described the Philippine landing as illegal and said the Chinese officers had gone to Earth "to perform on -site checks and execution measures." It did not specify what these measures consisted of.
A statement from the Philippines stated that a joint team of the coastal guard, the navy and the maritime police, in rubber boats, had landed in the three sand banks that make up Sandy Cay, known as Recife Tiexian in Chinese.
Filipine Coast Guard spokesman, Comodoro Jay Tarriela, posted a message on social network with a video and photographs, including one that showed staff to display a Philippine flag in one of the sandbank. "This operation reflects the dedication and inabalable commitment of the Philippine government to defend sovereignty, sovereign rights and the country's jurisdiction in the Sea of ​​Western Philippines," read the statement, which refers to the name used in the Philippines for the Southern Sea of ​​China.
The measure was taken three days after Global Times, an official Chinese newspaper, published photos of Chinese Coast Guard officers in Tiexian Recife in mid -April, holding a Chinese flag and cleaning plastic bottles and other debris.
The Chinese Coast Guard's statement about the subsequent Philippine disembarkation said China has a "undisputed sovereignty" on the Spratly islands, including Tiexian Recife and surrounding waters.
Beijing claims sovereignty about virtually every uninhabited reefs and islets of the Southern Sea of ​​China for historical reasons, ignoring a decision of an international court of 2016 that considers there is no legal basis for Chinese claims. Philippines, Vietnam, Malaysia, Brunei and Indonesia have rival claims on this maritime zone of great commercial and strategic importance.
The situation has worsened in recent months. Several episodes of violence opposed Chinese ships to Vietnamese ships and Philippines in those waters. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 04:28:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Europe's team will help young people from Macau develop skills in football</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/29/equipa-da-europa-vai-ajudar-jovens-de-macau-a-desenvolverem-competencias-no-futebol/</link><description>Luís Gomes, president of the Sports Institute (ID), said yesterday that the government will hire a team from Europe to improve football training for young people in Macau. In the presentation of the Government Action Lines (LAG) for this year, the official also said that, in the soccer field, you will be invited young people from the various cities of the Great Bay to participate in some games and, in addition, a competition between Macau and Hengqin will be organized "to promote sports with young people".
The LAG report for this year already said that it will be “promoted to exploit more diverse sports and leisure elements, with the aim of fostering the ordered development of sports activities towards commodification, contributing to the development of the proper diversification of the economy”.
Macao's male selection, made up of amateur players, is currently classified in 193rd position in the FIFA world ranking, consisting of 210 teams. Only Timor-Leste is behind Macau-in 197º-among the countries or regions of Portuguese official language.
In March, Deputy Eddie Wu Chou Kit defended cooperation with the Portuguese Professional Football League (LPFP) to organize friendly games with “European top teams” in Macao. In an intervention in AL, Eddie Wu proposed "establish [a] deep cooperation" with LPFP for creation, "together, a permanent training base." The deputy explained that the goal would be to “attract top teams in Europe to train and perform itinerant games, promoting sports and cultural exchange at the international level”.
Extending the scope to Portuguese -speaking countries, Eddie Wu appealed to reinforce the “commercial collaboration (…) in the area of ​​football [and] introduce its famous high -level brands and competitions”. Wu argued that cooperation with the Lusófono block would allow "creating a platform of international events [and] attracting fans from East Asia to Macau to watch the games." The deputy, appointed by the previous leader of the local government, pointed out as a goal "to transform Macau into an important bridge for the exchange and cooperation between Portuguese -speaking countries and China at football."</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 04:28:07</pubDate></item><item><title>New Children's Support Plan should start in the summer</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/29/novo-plano-de-apoio-para-criancas-devera-arrancar-no-verao/</link><description>The government sees the fall in the birth rate as one of the main problems that affect Macao and, therefore, will launch a childhood assistance plan, whose applications should be opened in summer, according to the secretary for social affairs and culture. Yesterday, at the Legislative Assembly, LAM also warned that in 2041 a quarter of the local population will be elderly.
 
The low birth rate and the aging of the population of Macau dominated a significant part of yesterday's plenary meeting of the Legislative Assembly (AL), which served the secretary for social affairs and culture to clarify deputies on the lines of governing action (lag) of their guardianship. The LAM highlighted this issue as one of the main challenges that the mandate faces and said that the new childhood support plan should open the candidacies this summer.
This childhood assistance allowance provides for the attribution to each baby or permanent resident of Macao with less than three years of age a monthly amount of 1,500 patacas, making a total of 18,000 patacas per year.
In response to the various deputies who have raised issues related to the theme, LAM assumed that the region will enter 2029 at a stage of “super low birth”, which “will have implications for work force, teaching and distribution of resources”. The secretary even warned that in 2041 a quarter of the region's population will be elderly.
Macau registered, in 2024, a fertility rate of 0.58 children, the smallest always in the territory. Also according to the United Nations Economic and Social Affairs Department (UNDESA), Macao's fertility rate is the lowest in the world.
The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture said that this problem has to be approached in three strands: incentives for procreation, education and support for families. "We have to find politics in a scientific way to resolve these issues," he said.
"Support to procreation is the improvement of health care namely in the care of procreation," said the secretary. Regarding support for children at the age of the infantary, LAM stressed that the government wants “that children under the age of two can stay home to live in a family environment”, but many couples are working, so “public services are thinking how to support couples with children under two”, indicating that the executive also plans to implement measures to improve the functioning of day care centers. On the other hand, the government also promised to support vulnerable and needs families. It is recalled that in the LAG report for this year there is also mention of the increase in the amount of birth subsidy to 6,500 patacas and the increase in marriage allowance to 2,220 patacas.
Prior to the deputies' questions, in the initial presentation yesterday in Hemiciclo, the secretary for social affairs and culture had already mentioned that “the government and society in general must achieve consensus to take proactive, systematic and effective arrangements before a society with a 'super low birth rate' and a 'super aged population'”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 04:25:09</pubDate></item><item><title>European Commission without evidence of cybers after blackout that affected the Iberian Peninsula</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/29/comissao-europeia-sem-provas-de-ciberataque-apos-apagao-que-afectou-a-peninsula-iberica/</link><description>The executive vice president of the European Commission Teresa Ribera said yesterday there was no evidence of cyberatoque in the mass cut in the electric supply in the Iberian Peninsula, but in a "of the largest failures in the system" in the European Union (EU). "We are not discarding anything at the moment, but there is no proof of any kind of cybersecurity problem. We are aware of everything and the main priority is, obviously, to restore the electric system and to evaluate and understand what happened," said the guardian in the community executive by the clean, fair and competitive transition folder, Teresa Ribera, to the press in witches. According to the official, this was “one of the largest failures in the electric system that occurred in recent years” in the EU. Teresa Ribera said she was “accompanying what is happening” and in “Strait contact with the Spanish and Portuguese authorities, as well as the different services of the commission”, in a situation that she said, only affects the Iberian Peninsula and, perhaps by drag, perhaps a small part of southern France. "For now, what I can say is that we have to be prudent and patients so that the system can be restored as soon as possible," he said. According to Teresa Ribera, "in the case of Portugal, [national authorities] turned off their Electric System from the Spanish system so that they could recover little and little."
These statements from Ribera arise after the European Commission indicated to be in contact with the authorities of Portugal and Spain and the European operators network to understand the cause and impact of the mass cut on electric supply on the Iberian Peninsula. "We are in contact with the National Authorities of Portugal and Spain, as well as the EntSo-E [European Network of Electricity Transport Network Operators] to understand the underlying cause and the impact of the situation," the official source of the community executive told Lusa. "The commission will continue to follow the situation and make sure that the exchange of information between all relevant parties is processed without problems," said the same official source. Brussels also recalled there are “protocols to restore the operation of the system,” as provided for in the community legislation regarding emergency and restoration networks.
Yesterday, at 11:30, Lisbon time, several cities from north to south of Portugal were the target of an electricity failure, not yet replaced until the closing of this edition and also affected countries such as Spain and France. The blackout led to the reestablishment plans by power supply steps. REN - National Energy Networks said yesterday that it was impossible to predict when the supply of electricity would be normalized and warned of the complexity of the restoration operation of the service, which will be done gradually.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 04:28:10</pubDate></item><item><title>3.5 million border movements are foreseen during the golden week of May 1</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/29/previstos-35-milhoes-de-movimentos-fronteiricos-durante-a-semana-dourada-do-1-o-de-maio/</link><description>The government estimates that Macau borders register between 3.4 million and 3.5 million crossings during the next gold week - Labor Day holidays. The Public Security Police body anticipates a daily average of 680,000 to 700,000 entries and exits in the territory, and it is expected to peak from the transionic movement to take place this Saturday. Tourism services yesterday launched the new reserve popularity indicator of the visitors from the interior of China for sleeping macao.
 
 
Authorities yesterday advanced an estimate between 3.4 million and 3.5 million entries and exits at border posts on the golden week of May 1, a high time of travel, which has five days of holidays in the interior of China. In this case, Macao borders should record a daily average of 680,000 to 700,000 passenger trips.
According to the forecast of the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP), the peak of passenger flow is expected to take place next Saturday, May 3, with about 750,000 to 800,000 cross -border crossings. It is also expected that the peak of vehicles at the borders will take place on May 1st and 5th, and Thursday is the peak of departure and next Monday the peak return to Macao.
The body believes the terrestrial borders will continue to be more frequented by passengers, and the migration posts of the doors of the siege, hengqin and Qingmao will be the most used during the holidays.
The competent public services yesterday held a press conference to present the preparatory work to respond to the increase of tourists within the Golden Week.
Law Tak Fai, head of the CPSP Public Relations Division, was guaranteed that the body has already “coordinated in advance” with the border posts and made contingency plans. "During the period of the Golden Week, the entire team will be on service and we will open additional inspection channels before passenger flow peak, and deviation measures will be implemented to increase the efficiency of border passage when necessary," he said.
According to the official, CPSP and security forces services also concluded an equipment pressure test on the borders in order to ensure the stability and normal functioning of the system.
 
New indicator on the permanence of the tourists of the continent
 
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) has announced the launch, since yesterday, the “Influence Indicator of Influence of Visitors from Interior of China”, in cooperation with the online tourism reserve platform in the interior of China Ctrip. According to STD, the aim of the indicator is to “allow tourist operators and hoteliers to know the trend of the number of visitors in the interior of China who stay overnight in Macao, contributing to better preparation of companies”.
The stay popularity indicator is updated every Monday on the Macao Tourism Data Plus platform, with the following week's forecasts.
Liz Lam, head of STD Public Relations Division, also said at the conference that he has maintained contacts with the continent's tourism authorities to publicize visitors and tourist operators tourist information about Macau, namely during the golden week, and also performed interdepportional inspections on the reception of hotels and excursion programs, under the tourist market inspection.
The Macao Grand Prix Museum is open to the public during the Labor Day holidays, added the STD, and, from May 1st, the museum will include two new exhibitions: “Philatelic products related to the Macao Grand Prix” and “Drawings of João Simões Saldanha over the Macao Grand Prix”. In addition, between May 1 and 5, a temporary pedestrian zone will be created in the old neighborhood of Taipa.
The Directorate of Service for Traffic Affairs (DSAL) will add five additional bus careers in response to resident and tourist travel needs during worker day holidays. In this sense, operators will increase bus matches and operate seasonal careers 3bx, 17t, 21at, 26At and the special career of 101x (101xs) on May 1-5.
Macau's light meter will reinforce its services during the holidays, and the last match of all lines will be at 11:59 pm between 1 and 5 May. At the border stations there will also be an area for stopping "shuttle" of hotels and casinos, with temporarily wide space for queues.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 04:23:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Planet Toyota on the weekend Rovanperä mode</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/29/planeta-toyota-em-fim-de-semana-modo-rovanpera/</link><description>Pedro Maia
 
 
Japanese builder put four cars in the first four positions. Kalle Rovanperä dominated rally from the Canary Islands from beginning to end and added the first triumph of the time. Hyundai swallowed in the aridity of the Spanish archipelago asphalt.
 
If there was doubts, they are undone. After an atypical season start, Kalle Rovanperä (Toyota Gr Yaris Rally1) returned last weekend to WRC wins and showed that he is in a position to fight for the championship. The two-time world champion, navigated by co-pilot Jonne Halttunen, did not give the minimum margin of maneuver to competition on the asphalt of the Canary Islands. He got one of the most dominant triumphs of his career, having won 15 of the 18 Spanish rally specials. He also added the maximum points in dispute (35), after being the fastest on 'Super Sunday' and 'Wolf Power Stage'. Not even team companion Sébastien Ogier - eight times world champion and asphalt expert - had a progress for the Finn. The Frenchman was in second place to 55.5 seconds from Rovanperä.
"It was a fantastic weekend for us and the team. Getting a result 1-2-3-4 is amazing. The car was perfect and Jonne did a very good job. We had the goal of adding as much points and this was achieved. The difference for Elfyn is still big, but at least we are closer," Rovanperä said at the end of the rally.
The Finn's end of the Canary Islands more points than the one he had achieved in the total of the first three events of the World Cup. A performance that allowed him to take second place in the championship with 66 points. Elfyn Evans (Toyota) was third and returned to love precious points in the title race. There are now 109.
In addition to closing the podium, Toyota also put the Japanese Takamoto Katsuta in fourth place. The Japanese builder could even have humiliated Hyundai further, it wasn't for Sami Pajari road to Saturday.
 
Hyundai Cup in the Canary
 
Hyundai was caught by surprise. He soon realized that his cars would not fight on an equal to the Toyota. Explanation? No one knows for sure, it may have been the heat, tuning or engine settings. The Hyundai i20 n rally1 have always been very nervous and unstable on the road. The three pilots of the South Korean builder were perplexed in the quick interviews at the end of each special, with Adrien Fourmaux revealing early weekend ambitions: "I will compete for the Hyundai Cup. I will try to be the fastest among my teammates."
The goal was fulfilled with Fourmaux and Alexandre Coria to get the fifth place. Estons Ott Tänak and Martin Jarveoja (Hyundai) were sixth, and assumed that the team did not do proper homework for the cannaries asphalt.
The current world champion Thierry Neuville, navigated by Martijn Wydaeghe, fell to seventh place after a hole in the second to last classificative. “We have been trying a lot of things this weekend. Things that usually don't do in a rally. Sometimes the feeling was good at the beginning of the thing, but then it was more complicated. I did my best, sometimes the balance was better, but the speed was not right. He continued to fight despite all our problems, ”said the Belgian.
Who also revealed a lot of difficulties was the Ford M-Sport team. Irish Joshua Mcerlean went out on the morning on Saturday. Luxembourg Gégoire Munster never adapted with his Puma Rally1 to the winding roads and ended the rally in the eleventh position, behind several cars in the Rally2 category.
 
Yohan Rossel wins in WRC2
 
Yohan Rossel won in the WRC2 category. Citroen's Frenchman endured Toyota Gr Yaris Rally2's attacks from Spanish Alejandro Cachón. Nikolay Gryazin, behind the wheel of a Skoda, ended third.  The three WRC2 pilots closed the top-10 top-10.
The next race of the World Championship is the Rally of Portugal that goes to the road between May 15 and 18.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 04:28:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Portugal and Grande Bay use music as “Ponte” at the Luso-Chinese Festival of Music and Arts</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/29/portugal-e-grande-baia-usam-musica-como-ponte-no-festival-luso-chines-de-musica-e-artes/</link><description>The three -day event will present concerts, competitions and various interactive experiences, such as flash mobs or virtual reality, in which music is protagonist and link between Chinese and Portuguese cultures in Macao. The highlight goes to the concert of the band Tuna Macaense, which this year celebrates its 90th birthday.
 
The Galaxy Macau International Convention Center will host the Luso-Chinese Festival of Macau Music and Arts 2025 (Flcmam 2025) between May 30 and 1 June. The event, subordinate to the theme “Honor the past and create the future-using music and art as a bridge, building harmony and diversity”, branches into three axes: musical contests, concerts and presentations and experiences that aim to promote cultural and artistic exchange between the area of ​​the great bay and the Lusophone countries.
The first competition, the “Tuna Macaense singing Championship”, serves as a tribute to the anniversary of the homonymous band, established in 1935, which over 90 years has been stressing efforts to preserve Macaense culture. The contest will consist of the interpretation of topics of Tuna Macaense and will have a triling nature, encompassing the Chinese, Portuguese and English languages.
The “International Competition of Macao Chamber Orchestra and Music” and the “China-Chic Music Tournament in the Great Bay area” will take place on June 1, consisting of the participation of young musicians from different countries. According to a press release issued by the organization, it is thus intended to promote “the integration and innovation” of classic oriental and western musical cultures, which adds a modern element with the incorporation of 'pop' and other contemporary styles in the China-Chique music contest. This term refers to an aesthetic, musical and commercial trend in the last decade, combining the traditional Chinese identity with modern, futuristic or western influences.
As for concerts, the first will occur on the night of May 30, with Tuna Macaense playing its most famous themes and reviving “the precious cultural heritage and musical memories through unique macanese songs”. The following night, the Themed Concert “Sónica Alliance: Musical Battle - Culture Shock in Macao Melody Bay” will take place at the Galaxy International Convention Center and will feature “renowned musicians”, according to the same statement.
Finally, the closing concert and the awards ceremony of the three competitions are scheduled for the last day, June 1, predicting “the most exciting musical dialogues and the most exciting cultural integration of the three-day competition”.
In parallel to the main events, interactive activities such as 'Master Classes' of instruments, 'Master Classes', Macanese music workshops, flash mobs, rope instrument exhibitions and immersive experiences of virtual reality (VR in the English) will be shivered in which participants can “experience the inheritance of Chinese and Portuguese musical cultures in all in all the participants). the aspects ”.
Registration for contests and activities are already open, remembering the organization that Amadora music is welcome and that the winners will be entitled to cash prizes. Flcmam is co-organized by the China-Portuguese Cultural Exchange Friendship Association of Macao and the Macao Music and Art space, sponsored by Galaxy Entertainment Group and the support of the Cultural Institute and the Directorate of Macao Tourism Services. Among the various collaborators, include the Macao Intersectoral Arts Association, the International Association of Cultural and Artistic Exchange of Youth of Macao or the Asia-Pacific Educational and Cultural Exchange Association.
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item></channel></rss>