<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/05/sam-hou-fai-pede-que-macau-esteja-em-alerta-perante-as-incertezas-internacionais/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Cancer: Wong Kit Cheng defends better diagnostic, treatment and follow -up services</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/05/cancro-wong-kit-cheng-defende-melhores-servicos-de-diagnostico-tratamento-e-acompanhamento/</link><description>Yesterday was the World Cancer Day, a date established in 2000 by the Union for International Cancer Control that aims to increase awareness of the disease. Deputy Wong Kit Cheng took the opportunity to suggest universal screening and ask for better diagnostic and treatment services.
 
Yesterday was World Cancer Day, which began to be marked in 2000, instituted by the Union for International Cancer Control. The date aims to increase the conscientialization of the population in the face of the disease. Wong Kit Cheng, deputy to the Legislative Assembly and president of the Good Home Alliance Association, took the opportunity to request the universal screening of cancer.
According to the latest cancer registration report for 2022, in the last ten years the incidence rate of all types of cancer has increased by about 12%, while the mortality rate has dropped 6%. However, there was an increase in incidence rates of thyroid, lung and breast cancer for women; And for men, the prostate cancer incidence rate increased significantly by more than 60%.
In a statement cited by the newspaper or Mun, Wong Kit Cheng says he expects that when accelerating the implementation of the project for a “healthy macao” and with the awareness of various types of cancer, also increases the concern of residents with their own health , in view of the detection, diagnosis and treatment, growing the effectiveness of prevention and treatment work.
Wong Kit Cheng suggests that, based on cancer information, such as gender, age group, incidence rate and mortality rate, “more community tracking services can be developed through community organizations and non -organizations. health care government. The deputy also suggests the launch of “Health Promotion Activities promoting different groups of the population, in order to increase the proactivity of cancer prevention and treatment work and to increase awareness of prevention and treatment work of cancer ”.
In addition, the deputy stated that it was necessary to “continue to improve diagnosis and treatment, as well as follow -up services, including the introduction of advanced treatment technologies, palliative care and medical personnel training; Increase the number of palliative care beds and support relevant organizations in providing care services so that cancer patients and their families at different stages of the disease can receive proper care and support. ”
Wong Kit Cheng also proposes that the government, the community and the general public continue to cooperate in the prevention and treatment of various chronic and infectious diseases, “in order to achieve the objectives of the action plan for a healthy macao and to build in Set a healthy and beautiful house ”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05T00:52:59+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Timorese government hires 72 prison guards</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/05/governo-timorense-contrata-72-guardas-prisionais/</link><description>The Timor-Leste government hired 72 new prison guards to revitalize the staff and improve the human resources of public administration, Minister of Justice, Sérgio Hornai, said. “Today you are part of the Ministry of Justice and become civil servants of the State Administration Commission. From now on there are the statute of administrative agents of the Ministry of Justice, ”said Sérgio Hornai, at the signing ceremony of contracts, which took place in that ministry in Dili.
In addition to the 72 prison guards, two more drivers were also hired for that service.
According to the minister, with the integration of those new members began the “revitalization of the staff” and the consolidation of capabilities to improve human resources and ensure quality service in the public administration reform.
The new prison guards will be placed in the arrests of Dili, Suai, on the south coast of the country, and in Gleno, west of the Timorese capital.
Sérgio Hornai also stated that there are still 28 vacancies for prison guards to be filled. "I would like to reaffirm, on behalf of the Ministry of Justice, the commitment to strengthen human resources, ensuring their qualification and appreciation," added the Timorese Minister.
At the ceremony, the Ministry of Justice also delivered three vehicles to prison services.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05T00:54:57+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Almost 90% of the life tests were performed by electronics</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/05/quase-90-das-provas-de-vida-foram-efectuadas-por-via-electronica/</link><description>Until Sunday, about 162,000 life events were treated this year, of which 142,000 were made by electronic via, namely the Macao Single Account and the self-service kiosks, representing 87.8% of the total evidence Of life treated, the Directorate of Administration and Public Services (SAFP) said yesterday.
Authorities add that 98,000 people took their life test through the Macao Single Account, representing 69.1% of the total number of life tests performed by electronic via, with an increase of about 10,000 (10%) in relation to the same period last year. Thus, "online treatment of life proof has become widespread and the rate of use of electronic services has been increasing from year to year, the result of effective dissemination of the use of electronic services to the elderly."
According to the SAFP, more than 634,000 people joined the single account, which provides more than 440 public services.
“The Government of MGI, meeting the needs of the senior population and specific groups, makes available in the Macao Single Account of medical assistance, social security, recreation and welfare services, in addition to the proof of life. For example, through Macau's single account, users can make external queries, consult the individual clinical registration and health valleys' balance, require the subsidy for the elderly, the pension for the elderly, the disability pension and the insurance allowance Health residents of MSAR residents in the interior of China, and also to mark spaces, registration in activities and password lifting for the counter and use the 'my wallet', ”the authorities say.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05T00:49:42+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>651 processes instituted during post-election manifestations in Mozambique</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/05/instaurados-651-processos-durante-as-manifestacoes-pos-eleitorais-em-mocambique/</link><description>The Mozambican prosecutor (MP) announced yesterday that it opened a total of 651 cases, including criminal and civil, during the post-election crisis, promising that all situations that resulted in deaths will deserve the attention of justice.
 
“We want to ensure that all situations that have resulted in death, body offenses or destruction of heritage, resulting from violent manifestations, deserve and deserve proper treatment, with the triggering of competent procedures to identify the authors, determine the circumstances and other elements for accountability for accountability ”Said the Attorney General of Mozambique, Américo Julião Letela, during the opening of the judicial year, in Maputo.
Mozambique has lived since 21 October a climate of strong social agitation, protests, demonstrations and stoppages, convened by Venâncio Mondlane, former presidential candidate who rejects the electoral results of October 9, with violent confrontations between police and protesters, as well as looting e destruição de equipamentos públicos e privados.
In addition to the social agitation that country has watched in the last three months, more than 1,500 prisoners have fled prison establishments in various parts of the country, actions that, according to the police and the Mozambican authorities, are the responsibility of protesters. "Following the evasion of prisoners in some prison establishments that resulted in the death of some prisoners, eight investigation processes were established that still run their terms," ​​added Mozambican attorney general.
The most severe case of reclusive evasion occurred in Maputo on December 25, when 1,534 prisoners fled, after rebellions in the Special Penitentiary Establishments of Máximo and Provincial Maputo, located about 14 kilometers from the center of the Mozambican capital.
During the rebellion, 35 people died, the second national penitentiary service of Mozambique (Sernap), which also announced last month that 332 prisoners were recaptured.
At the time, then-Commander General of the Police of the Republic of Mozambique (PRM), Bernardino Rafael, considered that he was “a premeditated action” and the responsibility of post-election protesters who, since October, have been on the street protesting against those Results of the general elections.
On the same day, police said similar rebellions were registered in the northern chain of Maputo province, where protesters released the prisoners, and in the chain of Mabalane, which recorded an escape attempt.
On Monday, a total of 200 prisoners evaded the Gorongosa District Chain in downtown Mozambique, the local administrator told Lusa, who also blame a group of protesters protesting the cost of living.
According to the electoral platform decides, a non-governmental organization that accompanied the electoral process, in these protests of the post-election crisis in Mozambique there is at least 315 dead, including about two dozen minors, and at least 750 people shot . Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-05T00:54:57+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Increase in the number of visitors does not necessarily benefit hotels, warns the sector</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/05/aumento-do-numero-de-visitantes-nao-beneficia-necessariamente-os-hoteis-alerta-o-sector/</link><description>In recent days Macau have passed over one million visitors. According to the authorities, this year will pass through the region about 39 million tourists. But this considerable increase in the number of visitors may not directly benefit the hotels, alert Rutger Verschuren. The vice president of the Macau Hotel Association says, in statements to the end, that both the hotel occupancy rate and the prices practiced are still below the 2019 records.
 
Over the day of the Lunar New Year, Macau has received over one million visitors, however, local hotels may not have benefited significantly. Rutger Verschuren, vice president of the Macao Hotel Association, says to the end that, since the large majority of visitors do not stay overnight in the territory, the gain for hotels is limited.
“The arrival of visitors is a good indicator for Macao's economy, but this is not the only indicator for hotels. We look much more at visitors who stay overnight in Macao and the duration of their stay, ”he says. Rutger Verschuren stresses that "it is misleading to see the masses of people on the streets, since most do not spend the night in the region." "From an economic perspective, it is wonderful to see the number of visitors to grow, but we need to remember that hotels may not be directly benefiting from this," he says.
In recent days, according to the Macao Hotel Association, several hotel units have been with occupancy rates to brush the 100%, however, the prices per room are lower compared to last year. In addition, compared to the Lunar New Year period 2019, the occupancy rate and also the prices practiced were slightly lower this year.
The association's leader also says that there has been a growing trend in the sector in which people mark trips in advance, "which translates into longer periods of stay." “The hotel industry is looking for longer stay times and the direction of tourism services [STD] has also been working to increase the stay period,” he says.
For this year, the hotel sector expects “the occupancy rate to continue to improve” and should reach the levels of 2019. However, “bedroom prices will be lower”, foresees Rutger Verschuren, pointing to visitors' expenses, which have also been smaller than before. ” Visitors “are more cautious, there is a sense of instability at this time,” he says.
Authorities estimate that this year will pass by Macau more than 39 million visitors, which, if confirmed, would equal the best brand achieved in 2019. For the hotel association leader, the 39 million mark is attainable and even excessive. Rutger Verschuren points to the annual growth of 10% of the number of visitors before the pandemic and foresees that this increase scale can continue now.
The biggest increase in visitors, he says, will come from abroad. In 2023, the share of international visitors was 5%, which, according to the association's leader, "could increase 10%." "But it depends on the success of STD and resorts integrated into international markets," he says, suggesting the bet on Middle East markets, which are "a good connection to Europe and Africa countries." On the other hand, Hengqin will also cause the number of international visitors to increase: "The integration of tourist attractions in Hengqin will attract international visitors and make them increase their stays."
Finally, Rutger Verschuren warns of the Hong Kong competition and also from the interior of China. “The interior of China is opening and is doing everything to attract international tourists. Our biggest competitor is the Chinese continent, ”he says, also suggesting that" Macau can be a good starting or arrival point for a trip to China. "</description><pubDate>2025-02-05T00:54:03+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Tickets are already on sale for the Cristiano Ronaldo Museum of Life in Hong Kong</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/05/bilhetes-ja-estao-a-venda-para-o-museu-da-vida-de-cristiano-ronaldo-em-hong-kong/</link><description>Cristiano Ronaldo Life Museum, or Museum of Life of Cristiano Ronaldo, to be inaugurated in July 2025 at K11 Art &amp; Cultural Center, in Hong Kong, will celebrate the life and career of the Portuguese football icon. With VIP tickets for sale from today and others available from February 24, the date coincides with Ronaldo's 40th anniversary. In addition to honoring the player, the museum aims to boost tourism and the local economy. Ronaldo continues to shine in Saudi Arabia, consolidating his global impact on both sports and society.
 
The city of Hong Kong will soon host a new cultural attraction that promises to attract fans of football and visitors from around the world. It bears the official name of “Cristiano Ronaldo Life Museum”, or something like “Cristiano Ronaldo Museum of Life” in Portuguese, and will open its doors in July this year at K11 Art &amp; Cultural Center, located in the Tsim Sha Tsui neighborhood, in Hong Kong. This museum, the first of its gender in Asia, aims to present the career and life of the famous Portuguese footballer, who became a global icon, not only for his ability on lawn, but also for the impact that had outside of them, in your career of over two decades.
The sale of tickets to this immersion in the life of Cristiano Ronaldo starts today, February 5, a date that coincides with the 40th anniversary of the athlete. The organizers foresee a great interest, with marketing to include VIP and pre-sale tickets, before the opening of public sales, scheduled for February 24. Interested parties will be able to purchase tickets on Klook and CTRip online platforms, as well as the official K11 website. The price of general entry is set at 180 dollars from Hong Kong for adults and 150 dollars from Hong Kong for children and seniors, and anticipated buyers can enjoy a 10%discount. VIP and pre-sale tickets will be released today.
This museum with more than a thousand square meters of exhibition will be more than a simple demonstration of tropies, but will present a wide range of interactive experiences, rare objects and motivational stories, beyond the celebration of Ronaldo's career. Predictions point out that more than 12 million people visit the space during its operation, which will take place until July 2026, underlining the museum's potential to place Hong Kong once again on the priority tourist destinations map, according to the museum itself.
The museum also stated that the opening of this cultural space will create synergies between various areas of the local economy, promoting a movement called “Hong Kong United”, which aims to integrate and unite the local community and tourists. From product stores to partnerships in food, retail and tourism sectors, the museum is expected to function as a magnet, attracting both residents and international visitors.
In addition to the museum, two official product stores in Tsim Sha Tsui and Hong Kong Island until April this year, which will offer exclusive goods and objects autographed by Ronaldo himself. The event will be highlighted in a series of sports initiatives scheduled for the city, especially with the possible visit of Al-Nassar, the player's current club, and sporting events such as the Rugby Sevens tournament, which is returning to Hong Kong.
Recently, Cristiano Ronaldo has been prominent in both the field and outside of it. Desde que se juntou ao Al-Nassar, em 2023, o jogador tem demonstrado um desempenho de realce, contribuindo principalmente para a crescente popularidade do futebol saudita.
Additionally, Ronaldo remains a prominent figure in marketing and social responsibility campaigns, using his global platform to address issues such as health, education and support for young athletes. Through support to youth training academies, Ronaldo's long career already reaps fruits today. Icon -inspired soccer players, such as Georgia's star Khvicha Kvaratskhelia, and even Frenchman Kylian Mbappe, do not forget to honor the Portuguese, who now receives appreciations from the public of Hong Kong and surroundings. As for a visit from Ronaldo to Macau, there is no expected date yet.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Japanese court confirms a conviction of former Nissan Motor director</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/05/tribunal-japones-confirma-condenacao-de-ex-director-da-nissan-motor/</link><description>American Greg Kelly, former director of Nissan Motor, was yesterday again convicted in Japan for collaborating on the financial irregularities committed by former President Carlos Ghosn, run away from Japanese justice.
 
The Supreme Court of Tokyo upheld the decision made in March 2022 by another court in the capital, which was the subject of appeal by the defendant, after receiving a suspended sentence of six months in prison.
Kelly, once Ghosn's right arm, was considered guilty of conspiring with the former president of the company not to declare future compensation agreed between Nissan and the maximum leader of the automobile manufacturer.
The suspended imprisonment meant that Kelly had not to serve a prison sentence as long as she was not involved in any criminal activity over three years, and in practice allowed her to return to the United States.
Kelly alleged in the appeal the acquittal of all accusations that he was considered guilty. The prosecution requested up to two years in prison for the US executive, detained in Japan in November 2018, at the same time as Ghosn's detention.
The American jurist worked at Nissan as a representative director, one of the highest positions at the top of the company, and turned out to be the only Nissan executive to be tried after other Japanese officials have reached court agreements.
The sentence of 2022, confirmed yesterday, was the first in the 2018 process against Ghosn, which shook the automotive industry, because it is one of the most respected executives among the largest car manufacturers in the world.
After the Rocambolesque Escape from Ghosn to Beirut at the end of December 2019, the Japanese court decided to separate the lawsuits against the head of Nissan and Kelly, since the former president of the company could not be tried to default.
Ghosn managed to escape from Japan by hiding in a musical instrument box and was transported on a private plane to Lebanon with scale in Turkey, although he was prevented from leaving Japan as the bail.
Former President of the Nissan-Renault Alliance, with triple nationality (French, Brazilian and Lebanese), remains in Lebanon, a country that has no extradition treaty with Japan, and says he was the victim of a plot orchestrated by the Japanese manufacturer and for Japanese government. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-05T00:55:05+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China opens investigation against Google and imposes tariffs on US products</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/05/china-abre-investigacao-contra-google-e-impoe-tarifas-a-produtos-dos-eua/</link><description>China announced yesterday the opening of an investigation on Google and imposed new rates on a series of US products, hours after President Donald Trump has applied a 10% rate to Chinese products.
 
China will investigate the US technological giant for alleged violation of Chinese antitrust laws, according to a state administration statement to regulating the country's market.
Beijing also announced the application of 15% rates on coal and liquefied natural gas (LNG) and 10% over oil and agricultural equipment from the United States.
"The unilateral imposition of customs rights by the United States severely violates the rules of the World Trade Organization," the Chinese Ministry of Finance said in a statement announced the imposition of retaliatory tariffs. "Not only is it useless to solve their own problems, but also undermines normal economic and commercial economic cooperation between China and the United States," the Chinese government added.
China's measurements were taken almost immediately after the application of US tariffs.
Washington's decision against China contrasts with the situations of Mexico and Canada, in which both nations obtained a postponement from the imposition of 25% per month, after reaching separated deals with Donald Trump.
Last Saturday, Trump appealed through an executive order to the Communist Party of China to prevent criminal organizations from facilitating the flow of illicit drugs into the United States.
The reopening of the trade war between the United States and China reverberated in the performance of the Chinese currency in the offshore markets, where Yuan fell 0.3% to $ 7,3340 following the announcement of retaliation. Yuan negotiations in the 'ONShore' market are closed due to the Lunar New Year holiday.
If the US dollar has recovered from the Chinese currency, while Australian and New Zealand coins, which have strong commercial connections with China, fell almost 1%. Other Asian currencies, such as Thai Baht and Indonesia Rupia, reduced gains.
Google search and internet services for consumers have been unavailable in China since 2010, although the company has maintained operations in the country, especially around its advertising business.
The United States supplied about 6% of China's LNG imports last year, according to ships location data.
Over the weekend, the US Administration leader ordered the application of a general rate on Chinese imports, which came into force from midnight yesterday in the United States, due to what Trump justified as Beijing's failure. in preventing the flow of illegal drugs.
The executive orders of the new White House tenant included retaliation clauses that would increase customs rights if countries responded in the same way. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-05T00:55:01+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>OpenAi and South Korean messaging service Kakao announce a new partnership</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/05/openai-e-servico-de-mensagens-sul-coreano-kakao-anunciam-nova-parceria/</link><description>The American technology company OpenAi and the leading messaging service in South Korea, Kakao, announced yesterday a new collaboration project to incorporate Artificial Intelligence (AI) on this South Korean platform.
The purpose of the partnership is to incorporate the chatgpt language model in Kakao, announced the two companies after a seoul meeting between Kakao executive director, Chung Shin-A, and OpenAi official Sam Altman. "I am pleased to share our partnership with OpenAi as part of our ambition to reach new innovation and a leap in front through AI in 2025," Chung Shin-A told press.
According to explained, the two companies will work together to apply the technology of the US company to Kakao services and also develop AI joint products, while the South Korean company plans to launch the new AI Integrated brand, Kanana, until End of 2025. "ChatgPT technologies will be integrated into our services, including Kanana, and the partnership includes technology sharing and the joint development of AI products for Kakao's 50 million users," Chung added.
Kakao is South Korea's main information technology company and operates the largest application of mobile conversation, Kakaotalk, with more than 50 million users, a number that almost equals the country's population (about 51.7 million) .
The announcement of OpenAi and Kakao comes weeks after the launch of DeepSeek, the latest Chinese AI development alternative, which is at the top of the free transfers tables from the App Store mobile application store, both in China and the US, surpassing the chatgpt itself.
On Monday, Altman also visited Tokyo, where he announced Deep Research, a new chatgpt tool. Also announced a partnership with Japanese technological conglomerate Softbank, the SB OpenAi Japan, with an AI project called “Crystal” and intended for business use.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05T00:55:03+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China considers “unfortunate” removal from Panama from the Silk Road initiative</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/05/china-considera-lamentavel-retirada-do-panama-da-iniciativa-da-rota-da-seda/</link><description>China considered yesterday to remove Panama from the Seda Route initiative, which classified as an economic cooperation platform for “global south” countries, rejecting any “political agenda” in this initiative.
“I think it's a unfortunate decision, because, first of all, (…) it's an economic initiative. The goal is to build a platform for countries, especially from the global south, to have economic cooperation with each other. It is not related to any political agenda, ”said China's ambassador with the United Nations (UN), Fu Cong, at a press conference in New York.
According to the diplomat, the economic cooperation in question "is mutually beneficial," admitting to expect Panama to "see it rightly." "Any defamation campaign that is launched by the United States and some other Western countries" about the silk route initiative "is totally unfounded," he said.
At the same time, US Secretary of State Marco Rubio said yesterday that Panama took “a big step” by not renewing the commercial cooperation agreement with China about the Silk Route initiative. “The announcement made yesterday [Sunday] by President José Raúl Mulino that Panama will let his participation in the initiative of the waist and the Route of the CCP [Communist Party of China] is a big step forward to relations between the US and Panama and for a free Panama channel, ”Rubio said on social network X.
According to the head of US diplomacy, Washington's influence on the Panamian decision is an “example of leadership” US President Donald Trump in the protection of US national security.
The new Silk Route is a commercial and investment cooperation initiative started in 2013 by Chinese President Xi Jinping, designed to make China's connection to Europe in the Middle East, Africa and, more recently, to Latin America.
At the New York press conference, the Chinese ambassador also addressed the accusations of Donald Trump and his team that Beijing controls the Panama Canal, which he considered "totally false." “The accusation against China is totally false. It has no foundation. Let me emphasize that China did not participate in the management and operation of the Panama Canal and has never interfered with the channel's affairs, ”Fu Cong told journalists.
China added the diplomat, "respects Panama's sovereignty over the channel and recognizes the channel as a neutral international infrastructure."</description><pubDate>2025-02-05T00:54:59+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese Foreign Minister will preside over the UN Security Council meeting</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/05/ministro-das-relacoes-exteriores-chines-presidira-reuniao-do-conselho-de-seguranca-da-onu/</link><description>China, which presides over the United Nations Security Council this month, will organize a ministerial level meeting aimed at “reforming and improving global cooperation”, a meeting that will be attended by the Chinese Foreign Minister.
 
China's permanent representative with the United Nations (UN), Fu Cong, presented his agenda for February yesterday, and indicated that China Foreign Minister Wang Yi will preside over February 18 an open debate Under the theme "practice multilateralism, reform and improve global governance."
The invitation to participate in the debate was made to foreign ministers or high employees from other countries, including states that do not integrate the UN Security Council, Wang Yi said.
According to the Chinese diplomat, this will be a "good opportunity" for US Secretary of State Marco Rubio to meet the Chinese counterpart if he accepts the invitation to move to New York to attend the meeting of the Council Security.
“By noting this year the 80th anniversary of the UN foundation and as the world enters a very turbulent period, this open debate aims to encourage countries to revisit UN's original aspirations, reaffirm their commitment to multilateralism and Importance of the role of the United Nations, including the Security Council, and explore ways to reform and improve global governance, ”explained Beijing's representative. "The aim is to build a fairer and more equitable global governance system that addresses the global governance deficit and ensures that its benefits are shared by all," he added.
According to Fu Cong, solidarity and cooperation are being replaced by the division and confrontation, admitting that "the council often managed to do anything in the face of great security crises."
Asked whether the deterioration of relations between Beijing and Washington may affect the work of the Security Council -the organ of which the United States and China are permanent members -the Chinese diplomat said he hopes to be able to cooperate with his US counterpart, Elise Stefanik, despite the “wrong prejudices and ideas” that has expressed publicly about Beijing.
“Overall, I believe China and the US (…) have a lot in common and we can cooperate. For example, within the UN structure there are global issues that require joint efforts from the entire international community and, in particular, from countries such as China and the United States, such as the fight against terrorism, drugs, or non-village. And also, in my opinion, the issue of climate change must be an issue where the two countries can cooperate with each other, ”he said. "I hope that, despite all the rhetoric we hear from American politicians, we can adopt a constructive and underlined approach in our work here at the UN," he said.
During the Chinese presidency of the Security Council, the situation in the Middle East will continue to focus, being already scheduled 'briefings' about the Palestinian issue, but also on Syria and Yemen.
“Regarding Gaza, there is now a ceasefire, but the situation remains fragile. The board needs to closely monitor the events and take action, if necessary, to ensure that the ceasefire agreement is fully and effectively implemented, and that humanitarian access remains open and unimpeded, ”explained Fu Cong. “It is evident that the situation in West Bank also deserves our attention. Just yesterday [Sunday], we heard reports of military attacks from Israel's defense forces against residential blocks in the fields of Jenin and Tulkarem, ”he said.
In this sense, the Chinese ambassador met yesterday morning with the representative of the Palestinian mission with the UN, Riyad Mansour, who in turn asked the Security Council to adopt quick measures to end the situation and call a meeting to approach These attacks.
The situation in Africa will be another priority for the Chinese presidency, with several meetings on UN missions in South Sudan, Libya and the Central African Republic, as well as the situation in Sudan and the Democratic Republic of Congo (RDCONGO ), where the scenario has deteriorated in recent weeks.
About the situation at RDCongo, Fu Cong said, without providing details, that “a member of the Security Council” presented the idea for the writing of a project of resolution on this conflict, stressing that the situation on the ground “deserves a very fast response and robust by the Security Council. ”
In addition, this month the council will discuss the semester report of UN Secretary-General António Guterres about the threat represented by the Islamic State in Iraq and the uprising. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-05T00:55:01+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Recovered first parts of the plane involved in the deadly air collision in Washington</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/05/recuperadas-primeiras-partes-do-aviao-envolvido-na-colisao-aerea-mortal-em-washington/</link><description>Five days after the Washington air collision between a passenger plane and a military helicopter, which killed 67 people, the first pieces of the plane were recovered on Monday. The recovery operations of the two devices that fell into the Potomac River, near the Ronald Reagan airport in Washington, began on Monday, while searching for victims' bodies. At noon, a large crane, aided by a smaller second, used belts to lift part of the plane's fuselage out of the water and carefully placed it in a barge. “We started the operations at dawn. We recovered the first of the two (plane) engines around 10:00, the fuselage around 12:00 and, around 2:30 pm, we started working to remove a wing from the water, ”explained US authorities, During a new press conference at Ronald Reagan airport. “Our goal today was to recover the engine, the fuselage and the wing: we got it. Our goal tomorrow [Tuesday] is the cockpit, ”they added, although operations depend on tide and meteorological conditions, especially the wind. “During today's operations, new bodies were located. They are, as well as others withdrawn from the water previously, to be identified, ”said the local authorities. The number of 55 bodies identified communicated on Sunday was not changed at this time, they specified.
The President of the United States, Republican Donald Trump, was quick to blame-without proof-diversity policies implemented in the US government of Democrat Joe Biden to explain the air disaster. The level of personnel at the Ronald Reagan International Airport Control Tower in Washington "was not" in its normal at the time of the accident, according to US media. Investigators of the US Transport Security Council (NTSB), an independent agency, hope to disclose a preliminary report within 30 days. Full investigation may take a year.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05T00:54:59+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Manipulated images of nudity sent to deputies did not cause damage</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/05/imagens-manipuladas-de-nudez-enviadas-a-deputados-nao-causaram-prejuizos/</link><description>It has not been registered in Macao, so far, no case of sloping or extortion through videos synthesized with face exchange and voice simulation, which involve the 'Deepfake' technology. The warranty arose in response to an interpellation of the Secretary's Office for Security, where the extortion case with intimate images manipulated was addressed with the Macao deputies targeting. Authorities said the case did not cause any loss.
 
The case of extortion against the deputies of the Legislative Assembly using intimate images in which the faces are exchanged, which occurred last year, did not cause any loss of goods, said the secretary's office for security. Authorities assured that the Judiciary Police, following the case, took raising awareness measures and immediately issued an alert to remind the public in identifying and responding to related crimes.
"In the cases communicated to the police there was no loss, thanks to the fact that the victims had paid attention to police anti-fiprocal information in their daily life, keeping vigilantes and communicated in timely to the police," said Wong Sio Chak's office. In response to a written interpellation presented by Deputy Leong Sun Iok.
The blackmail with manipulated photographs arrived in the deputies in December last year. It is recalled that on the occasion of a plenary session, Deputy Leong Hong Said Wong Sio Chak who was the target of an attempted extortion, having received an email with falsified images of his face in a context of nudity. Several other deputies also received emails with similar content and said they were "afraid to open the email."
According to the report of the media to the media, the email also instructed the legislators to contact an individual through WhatsApp to “deal with the situation”, otherwise the image in question would be disclosed on social networks. Similar crime also happened in the neighboring city to blackmail several members of the Hong Kong Legislative Council.
During the Hemiciclo meeting, Wong Sio Chak admitted that it is difficult to detect online extortion crimes with pornographic images with face change, and that it is necessary to have more awareness actions so that the community knows that it is an extortion scheme .
In response to interpellation, Wong Sio Chak's office indicated that the manipulated images scheme is no longer a new type of crime, clarifying that the technique is different to face exchange and voice simulation that consists of talking by video in real time in real time , which uses 'Deepfake' technology. "To date, the police authorities have not detected or received any case of fraud or extortion by synthesized videos through face change and voice simulation," he said.
The executive stressed to be aware of the changes and evolution of crimes with resources to artificial intelligence, improving professional research capabilities and techniques and, at the same time, reinforcing information collection and online inspection work.
In addition, “we maintain close cooperation with the police of neighboring regions and the International Police, exchanging information on crimes and criminal investigation techniques, conducting the investigation and combating criminal groups under the transfronical police cooperation mechanism,” said the Judicial Police quoted by Wong Sio Chak's office.
The body reported having released a video awareness about crimes with resources to artificial intelligence aimed at alerting the audience about Deepfake technology, which had, by the end of last year, with 147,000 views.
According to the answer to the Secretary for Security, the Judicial Police last year organized about 700 advertising activities with the theme of combating online and telephone fraud, which welcomed 120,000 participants.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05T00:53:00+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai asks Macau to be on alert before international uncertainties</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/05/sam-hou-fai-pede-que-macau-esteja-em-alerta-perante-as-incertezas-internacionais/</link><description>Executive head, Sam Hou Fai, argues that Macau must be on alert and strive to “prevent various risks” due to international geopolitical uncertainties. In an article published in Bauhinia Magazine magazine, Sam Hou Fai appealed to an integral implementation of the Macau principle governed by patriots, expecting "Police" the Golden Card of Macao as "one of the safest cities in the world." The ruler also reiterated bets on the development of tourism, technology, investment and culture.
 
Macao must be vigilant and prepared, and strive to be careful against risks of all kinds, said Sam Hou Fai to maintain his prosperity and stability. The chief executive described the region as a highly abroad microeconomic, warning that the international environment is “complex”, thus asking for a “firm defense” to sovereignty, safety and the country's development interests.
"The world economy is not growing with enough impetus and, despite showing signs of recovery, the uncertainty of the game between the great powers is increasing and geopolitical externality continues to emerge," said Sam Hou Fai, in an exclusive article for the Bauhinia Magazine, a magazine published in Hong Kong by a Chinese state company.
Sam Hou Fai stressed that Macau is now in a “critical” phase of transition from repairing development to high quality development, so it is necessary, according to the ruler, fully implement the “Macao Macao governed by patriots” principle as well as Review in the legal system and execution of the National Security Law.
In this sense, the leader of the region promises commitment to governance work and “practical actions” to polish the Golden Card of Macao as one of the “safest cities in the world” and to ensure the continuity of the principle 'one country, two systems'.
Sam Hou Fai addressed in this article the executive bets for local development in the coming years. He said the diversification of the economy remains priority of the current government and considers it important to organize more tourist activities and events and expand the international visitors market, giving greater emphasis to the source of visitors to Northeast Asia, Southeast Asia, South Asia and South America.
As for the game industry, the chief executive reiterated a “healthy and ordained” development that “cannot undermine the fundamental interests of the state or the global interests of Macao”.
 
Technology, Business and Society
 
Sam Hou Fai, on the other hand, revealed that it plans a rational and effective allocation of tax resources to high -tech industries, which provides for an increase in the proportion of research and development financing in local GDP, as well as a grant for scientific projects that have good prospects for application and transformation.
“The new government will optimize the service of 'One Stop' for investors and further reduce business costs, improve the level of the convenience of operation and investment and create a freer, open and standardized business environment, welcoming global investors, ”he anticipated.
In addition, Sam Hou Fai indicated that the new executive will “innovate” the concepts of governance, promote the modernization of the legal system and reinforce public trust in the government through “cultivating national conscience, service, responsibility and work team ”of civil servants.
Sam's commitment also includes social support for creating a “more just society environment”. The official said he will promote more directed assistance to low -income groups and disadvantaged.
 
Greater Opening to the World
 
The chief executive has noted at the same time as Macau is an important bridge and window that connects the East and the West and plays the role of a special channel for the exchange between China and the rest of the world. "In the new historical age, the role of Macao as a special corridor will only be reinforced and not weakened," he said.
Sam Hou Fai once again highlighted the role of the Sino-Lusophone platform, and showed the desire to expand cooperation with Portuguese and Spanish countries, particularly emerging sectors such as modern finances, ecological environmental protection, transionic electronic trade and digital economy.
Sam aims to increase the global influence and attractiveness of Macao. He thus assured that he will raise his investment in the cultural sector and create local brands and cultural products, maintaining the characteristics of the intersection of Chinese and Western cultures.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05T00:55:59+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>