<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/associacao-de-policias-defende-aproximacao-urgente-entre-a-corporacao-e-as-comunidades/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Indian Rupi falls to historical minimals after Trump promises new tariffs</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/rupia-indiana-cai-para-minimos-historicos-apos-trump-prometer-novas-tarifas/</link><description>The currency of India, the Rupia, reached a minimum record of 87.95 per dollar at yesterday's opening after the US President promised new tariffs for business partners. "Rupia opened weak on Monday, following the losses in Asian currencies after US President Donald Trump said he will introduce more rates," increasing the risks of a possible trade war, the financial consultant Eforex said India, in your daily analysis.
The United States will impose 25% rates on aluminum and steel imports from yesterday, revealed on Sunday Trump, which also promised to announce reciprocal customs customs for business partners next week.
"Any steel in the United States will have a 25%rate," he told reporters on the presidential Air Force One plane, while flying from Florida to New Orleans to watch the Super Bowl final of football. "Aluminum too," he replied when asked about this matter, as he covers the neighbors Mexico and Canada.
Trump also said he will announce reciprocal tariffs-"probably Tuesday or Wednesday"-regarding products that are taxed in partner countries. "If they are charging ourselves 130% and we are not charging them anything, it won't continue like this," he told reporters. In this sense, the Republican politician said these tariffs will be put into practice "almost immediately" to "all countries."
During his first term (2017-2021), the US leader imposed 25% tariffs on steel and 10% on aluminum, but then granted tax-free quotas to various business partners, including Canada, Mexico and Brazil.
Although Indian steel and aluminum exports to the United States do not represent a large proportion of bilateral trade, other India articles may be affected by any new tariffs.
The drop in rupia occurs after the currency registered a minor recovery on Friday after the Indian reserve bank reduced the interest rate for the first time in five years. The Indian Central Bank reduced rates by 25 base points to 6.25%.
Since the dollar was worth 63.85 rupees, on January 1, 2018, the Indian currency has continued in a devaluation trend, although the speed of the fall has slowed since mid -2022.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:38:42+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Increased spending during a new year lunar removes China from deflation in January</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/aumento-dos-gastos-durante-ano-novo-lunar-afastam-china-da-deflacao-em-janeiro/</link><description>Inflation in China accelerated in January, for the first time since August, due to the strong increase in families' spending, at the time of Lunar New Year's holidays. The consumer price index rose 0.5%in January, compared to the same period in December, inflation set at 0.1%.
 
Inflation in China accelerated in January, for the first time since August, due to the strong increase in families' spending, at the time of Lunar New Year's holidays, contrary to persistent deflationist pressures.
The Consumer Price Index (IPC) rose 0.5%in January, compared to the same period, the National Statistics Office (NBS) of the Asian country reported on Sunday. In December, inflation settled at 0.1%.
The temporary increase in consumption during the eight -day break briefly checked the size of the world's second largest economy. The price of services increased by 0.9%, representing more than 50% of the total IPC increase, according to NBS.
The deflation in China factories extended for the 28th consecutive month, with a decline of 2.3%, remaining stable, compared to the contraction of the index in December.
The date of Lunar New Year's holidays - between January 28 and February 4 may have distorted the homologous comparison. This festive period, which follows the lunar calendar, pits in different periods every year. Last year was celebrated in full in February.
Domestic consumption is increasingly crucial to China, at a time when trade war with the US intensifies. Chinese families' spending could compensate for the effects of increased customs rates imposed by the new US President Donald Trump on assets from the Asian country.
The Chinese government has already advanced plans to increase public spending and reduce interest rates. With the wealth of families under pressure due to a prolonged crisis in the real estate sector, the increase in consumption was elevated to the main priority of this year's economic efforts.
The persistence of deflationist pressures in China is strongly contrasts with other major economies. Beijing's fear is that a rooted pricing cycle can restrain families 'expenses for longer and harm the companies' revenues in such a way tohabit the investment and lead to new salary cuts and disqualification. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:38:33+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Number of weddings in China fell in 2024 for lower value since 1980</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/numero-de-casamentos-na-china-caiu-em-2024-para-valor-mais-baixo-desde-1980/</link><description>China registered 6.1 million marriages in 2024, the lowest number since the records began in 1980, according to data released yesterday by the Ministry of Civil Affairs.
The number represents a new decline, after a recovery in 2023, after consecutive years of contraction, according to the statistical report of the fourth quarter of 2024, spread by the ministry.
By 2023, 7.68 million marriages were registered in the Asian country, compared to 6.83 million in 2022, a number that was already a historical minimum.
Chinese experts explained that the 2023 peak could be due to factors such as Covid-19 pandemic, which led to a reduction in personal interaction between men and women, resulting in a postponement effect of the wedding and after the pandemic period.
According to experts, the reasons for the decline in the number of marriage records since 2014 include a reduction in the young population, the gender imbalance in China, with more men than women among the young population, the postponement of the age of marriage , high costs to marry and a change of attitudes towards marriage.
At the 20th Congress of the Chinese Communist Party in 2022, the party in power stressed that the country needs a system that “increases birth rates and reduces the costs of pregnancy, childbirth, education and children's education”. .
China registered a decline of the population in 2022, 2023 and 2024, the first contractions since 1961, when the number of inhabitants decreased as a result of the failure of the policy of industrialization of the great leap in front and hunger that followed.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:38:01+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Wong Kit Cheng defends 90 days of paid maternity leave with government allowance</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/wong-kit-cheng-defende-90-dias-de-licenca-de-maternidade-remunerada-com-subsidio-do-governo/</link><description>Given the low birth in Macau, Deputy Wong Kit Cheng launched another appeal to the government to increase maternity leave from 70 days to 90 days for all resident workers. The deputy considers viable to realize the 90 -day maternity leave target by enlarging the complementary subsidy attributed to employers by the government. Regarding the new executive's government lines, Wong Kit Cheng said he expected more incentives for birth, including housing support and birth subsidy.
 
Deputy Wong Kit Cheng argues that the maternity leave will be 90 days for all local workers, suggesting that the measure is completed by enlarging the complementary allowance attributed to employers for the remuneration paid in the 14 -day maternity leave, 14 days. for the maximum limit of 34 days.
Macau resident workers currently enjoy 70 days of paid maternity leave and the extension of the period to 90 days, as in the civil service, has been requested by society for a long time, since politics is seen as one of the incentives for birth.
“Last year, the birth rate still remained low. In this situation, we hope that the government can launch relevant temporary measures, that is, the subsidy to employers for the remuneration paid in the maternity leave can become an administrative regulation, instead of a mere plan, to encourage companies while implementing policies Favorable to families, increasing maternity leave to 90 days, ”he said.
Wong Kit Cheng spoke to the media on the sidelines of the Legislative Assembly Spring Lunch and said that more incentives and support to companies are necessary to extend the maternity leave.
“The government can support through a subsidy. There is already a subsidy plan for employers corresponding to 14 days of the salary of workers. With the basis of this measure, if we want to continue with the subsidy and add 20 days of the salary of the workers, taking into account government expenses and the purpose of encouraging residents to have children, I think it is completely viable, ”he said.
It is recalled that, with the change to the Labor Relations Law in May 2020, the maternity leave in Macao went from 56 days to 70 days and, within three years of the transitional period, the government attributed to eligible employers a Subsidy equivalent to 14 days of the base remuneration of the workers, so that employers can gradually adapt to the increase in the number of maternity leave days.
After this period of three years, the government renewed the subsidy plan last year. The direction of services for labor matters, however, has not admitted that the plan will become a permanent measure.
Wong Kit Cheng said he did not receive any information about the government's position on maternity license to 90 days, but promised to continue “working for this objective, either through the review of the [labor relations] law, either through support measures ”. "The government should also play a more active role in promoting the increased maternity leave, both as the advice to women and children's affairs," the attention.
 
Birth in crisis
 
In terms of the new government's government lines, which is expected to be announced soon, Wong Kit Cheng requested more birth incentive policies that start from the aspects of economics, housing, employment and medical services, to “leave more guarantees ”To residents of making a family charge after having babies.
The deputy said she was aware of the pressure of child -rearing from couples who are both workers, appealing to the most friendly policies in the family. “Residents need more support, including maternity and paternity license, illness license to accompany any unwilling family member and license to accompany children. If the government does not support, companies will not be encouraged to do anything, ”he lamented.
The birth allowance has not been increased for several years, according to Wong. At the same time, housing is one of the main financial charges for families, asking for specific housing policies for families with newborns.
It is recalled that Macau now has the lowest fertility rate in the world, with only 0.68 children per woman according to the data last year, according to a report published by the United Nations.
 
More support in the area of ​​mental health
 
The deputy linked to the General Association of Women revealed that the number of requests for help at the association's psychological consultation center is increasing.
Wong Kit Cheng said that the center provides community health service, including early detection of people suffering from emotional problems. "We hope that the government reinforces the allocation of resources to prevent emotional disturbance in community services, as citizens are more willing to ask for help from community institutions compared to health centers," he said. The deputy also suggested that more resources are placed on community screening services and appointment vacancies on emotional disturbance, widening the coverage of the service.
The number of psychiatric doctors is "relatively stable," said Wong Kit Cheng, but indicated that "schools, service centers and youth associations are needing more psychologists and psychological counseling agents." The deputy also calls for legislation for a qualification and registration system for psychological counseling agents.
 
"I hope our team can continue in Hemiciclo"
 
The General Association of Macao Women should participate again in this year's legislative elections. Wong Kit Cheng, who led the Good Home Alliance list of the General Association of Women in the 2021 elections, said yesterday that he expects his team to "continue in the Legislative Assembly." “Our team has been promoting services to families. Our priority is women and children, but also the sustainable development of mashes, ”said the deputy, adding that“ I hope there are more deputies in the hemiciclo that defend the rights of women and children, to defend policies that give more support to families. ”He stressed. Without revealing whether he will be a list of list again, Wong Kit Cheng has confessed that he wants more women in the Assembly. "It is my hope that younger and women in society can participate in the discussion of policies," he said. Currently, two deputies - Wong Kit Cheng and Ma Io Fong, in the Legislative Assembly are linked to the General Association of Macao Women.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:37:38+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China says that visits the Prime Minister of the Cook Islands does not aim for third parties</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/china-diz-que-visita-do-primeiro-ministro-das-ilhas-cook-nao-visa-terceiros-paises/</link><description>China yesterday insisted that the visit of the COOK Prime Minister to Beijing this week is not intended to conspire against any country in the South Pacific, although the trip caused a diplomatic dispute with New Zealand. The visit seems to be part of China's campaign to court the small island nations of the South Pacific, where Beijing has been using their economic and diplomatic weight, as critics say it is an effort to reduce the influence of the United States and their own allies and grant itself access to mineral resources, fisheries and strategic navigation points. "The relationship between China and the Cook Islands is not for third parties and should not be subject or disturbed by third parties," said Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakun.
New Zealand Foreign Minister Winston Peters said he had repeated in a call with Cook Prime Minister Mark Brown, which he should discuss with New Zealand the content of the global strategic partnership and other agreements that Brown intends to sign with in China. "This absence of consultations is a matter of great concern for the government of New Zealand," said Peters's office in a widespread statement on Sunday.
The Cook Islands, a set of 15 small islands with a population of 15,000 inhabitants but with a large exclusive economic zone, have been self-government in free association with New Zealand, their largest source of help. The agreement, almost 60, allows the cook islands inhabitants to have citizenship and New Zealand passports and work and live in New Zealand. Brown said New Zealand was informed that the agreement with China does not concern security, but that Wellington has no right to review the exact writing of any documents.
The Prime Minister said that his visit of state to Beijing will focus on renewable energy and agriculture, but will also address the development of maritime transport and the exploration of minerals at sea bottom, areas that have particularly concerned with New Zealand, Australia or the United States.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:37:41+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Nippon Steel is reviewing US Steel's acquisition proposal, says Japan government</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/nippon-steel-esta-a-rever-proposta-de-aquisicao-da-us-steel-diz-governo-do-japao/</link><description>Japanese steelmaker Nippon Steel is reviewing the proposal to acquire US Steel and will adopt a different approach, Yoshimasa Hayashi, said yesterday.
 
“Nippon Steel believes this is not just a simple purchase, but a bold investment to produce excellent products that not only the United States, but the whole world demand, and is studying a bold proposal that can be mutually beneficial to Japan and the US, ”Hayashi said at a press conference.
Comments come after the new US President Donald Trump said on Friday during a press conference after a meeting in Washington with Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba, that Nippon Steel would withdraw the purchase offer from US Steel, instead, would invest in the company.
On Sunday, Trump went further by ensuring that Japanese steelmaker will not acquire a majority participation in the US company.
Ishiba said on Sunday, on the Sunday debate program of Japanese public broadcaster NHK, that US Steel would remain an American company without providing specific details. “U.S. Steel was once the number one company in the world. There is a strong resistance to which it is acquired and becomes a Japanese company, ”said Ishiba. He added: "It is very important for President Trump to be an investment and not just an acquisition, which remains a US company."
About a month ago, the United States extended until June 18 the deadline imposed on Nippon Steel to withdraw US Steel's acquisition proposal after companies filed a lawsuit.
On January 6, Nippon Steel and US Steel had announced a lawsuit against the administration of then-US president Joe Biden for “illegal interference” in the acquisition process.
On January 3, Biden announced the decision to block the operation for national security reasons and to ensure that "the United States has a national steel industry." "This acquisition would put one of the major American steel producers under foreign control and would have created risks for our national security and our essential supply chains," Biden said in a statement.
The decision was announced after the United States (CFIUS) committee in December (CFIUS), a federal agency chaired by the Treasury Department, referred the issue to Biden.
The US Metalworkers Union had expressed its firm opposition to the merger, an operation valued at almost $ 15 billion (14.6 billion euros), while Nippon Steel considered it a board of salvation for an industrial sector in difficulties. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:38:42+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ron Lam expects “concrete measures” to encourage the economy in LAG</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/ron-lam-espera-medidas-concretas-para-incentivar-a-economia-nas-lag/</link><description>They are “concrete measures and policies” to respond to the most pressing problems of the economy and employment that Deputy Ron Lam hopes to see in the next lines of governing action of the Sam Hou Fai team. The legislator suggested consumer valleys to support the local economy. Regarding the next legislative elections, Ron Lam is still undecided about the re -candidacy, noting that the team has limited resources and that there has not yet been an in -depth discussion with the team.
 
Deputy Ron Lam is aware of possible new government policies to solve the problems of the economy and employment that Macau is facing. For the government lines that will be presented by Sam Hou Fai, the new Chief Executive, Ron Lam considers that there is necessary urgent measures to relieve the financial difficulties of residents, such as stimulating measures to the economy, including consumer valleys and consumer program with discounts.
"We understand that, through stimuli to consumption, we can save our bad employment situation in Macau and the economic situation, and provide social support to low performance residents," said Ron Lam, on the sidelines of the Legislative Assembly Spring Lunch held. yesterday.
In this case, the deputy pointed out that many social assistance measures and benefits for the population “have been reduced or even interrupted” in recent years due to pandemic. "Company hopes, in fact, that the government can present concrete measures in the government lines of action, including measures that can achieve rapid results in terms of employment, economics and improvement of resident welfare," said the deputy, pointing out that Macau is undergoing a macroeconomic impact.
Ron Lam also calls for long -term policies about the economy, namely in the policy of introducing non -resident workers. For the deputy, the government must, in response to the opinion of the population, give greater defense to the priority to the use of residents.
On the other hand, Ron Lam pointed out that government communication to the population still remains in a “singular direction” and that the executive must be “more active, more open, more interactive and more communicative” with society. The deputy admitted that the previous government did not have a “normal practice” and the current executive must “resume the right path” to promote bidirectional communication with the media, rather than just issuing communications.
 
No decision on the elections
 
Ron Lam, who was first elected in 2021 to the Legislative Assembly, for direct suffrage, said yesterday that he has not yet decided whether to re -apply in the upcoming legislative elections scheduled for this year.
To journalists, the deputy linked to the Macao synergy association stated that the team has not yet begun electoral work, nor had an in -depth discussion, emphasizing, however, that the association is “small and limited resources”.  Ron Lam said he will actively ponder on the subject. “If we think seriously that we can help the community, speak for society and promote better policies of integration and sustainable development, we will continue,” said Ron Lam, indicating, however, that “there are too many tasks we have not yet dealt with and that I have to treat Before you can seriously think about the elections. ”</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:36:39+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Associations ask for inclusion of maids in the free vaccination program</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/associacoes-pedem-inclusao-de-empregadas-domesticas-no-programa-de-vacinacao-gratuita/</link><description>The recent confirmation of two influenza -related deaths in Macao, both unvaccinated cases, has driven associations to request the inclusion of maids in the free vaccination program against influenza. With the significant increase in cases of flu infection in neighboring regions and the approximation of the high season of the disease, the urgency of this demand becomes even more evident, according to the president of the “Macao Oversea Worker Employment Agency Association”, to Ieong Kuong Kao.
Thus, it highlights the importance of protecting non-resident workers (TNR), especially maids, who play a crucial role in family care and often face financial difficulties that make it difficult to access vaccination.
Ieong stressed that the proportion of elderly over 65 years old in Macao has continued to increase and, due to its weaker immune system, the risk of serious diseases after influenza infection is significantly higher than that of others age groups. Domestic maids are an important support in many families to take care of the elderly and young children, and their health directly affects the risk of family members' infection. However, foreign workers were not included in free vaccination objectives against influenza in Macao, and some maids may not take the initiative to be vaccinated due to financial considerations, creating a gap in preventing the disease.
In addition to the appeal for free vaccination, Ieong advocates the implementation of public awareness campaigns that inform maids about the importance of the vaccine and on influenza prevention measures. These campaigns could be carried out in multiple languages, considering Macao's cultural diversity, and can help ensure that all workers are aware of the available risks and preventive measures, the spokesman explained.
Health authorities are on alert to the growing spread of the virus and its potential severity. In this sense, Ieong also appeals to the public to reinforce its sensitization for prevention and vaccinate the flu as quickly as possible.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:36:37+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Kou Hoi in highlights improvements in the efficiency and effectiveness of the</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/kou-hoi-in-destaca-melhorias-na-eficiencia-e-eficacia-da-al/</link><description>In the speech given at the traditional Spring Lunch of the Legislative Assembly (AL), Kou Hoi In indicated that 2024 was the year when Hemiciclo had the most overwhelmed agenda. In addition, the president of the legislature foresees that work in the coming time will be "even more intense".
 
Yesterday the usual spring lunch of the Legislative Assembly (AL) was held. The president of the agency, Kou Hoi In, took stock of AL's work last year and drew attention to the improvements in efficiency and effectiveness in the works of the legislative body. For the future, the president of AL expects the work in the near future to be "even more intense."
"In this legislature, 2024 was the year when the Legislative Assembly had the most overwhelmed agenda," said Kou Hoi in in his speech, stressing that "all deputies, sharing an active and pragmatic attitude in the performance of their functions, have Given compliance with their attributions under the law, with a high sense of mission and responsibility, working together with the government, and promoting positive interaction and frank cooperation ”.
The president of AL pointed out that "the efficiency and effectiveness" of the hemiciclo have been improved, "ensuring that all works are developed and completed in a solid, ordained and stable manner."
Kou then pointed out to the theme of national security: "We have always taken the defense of national sovereignty, and the safety and interests of state development as guiding principles of legislative work developed by the Hemiciclo." The president of AL gave as an example the "effective implementation of the principle of" Macau governed by patriots "and the" improvement of the execution of the regulatory framework related to national security ".
On the other hand, Kou highlighted the revisions of the electoral law to the Chief Executive and Al and also the oath law at the time of the possession, diplomas that ensure that “the power of governance of Macao is firmly in the hands Of those who love the homeland and macau, ”he argued, stressing that“ the approval of these three legislative initiatives was essential to ensure, on the one hand, that the election of the sixth chief executive had been successfully completed under the law in 2024 , offering, on the other hand, the guarantees of a disciplinary framework applicable to the next elections of the 8th Legislative Assembly, to take place this year. ”
Alongside this, said the president of the AL, “it was necessary that legislative work to articulate with that of the Government of MSAR in deepening the reform of administrative management, raising the efficiency of governance, improving the electronic government, optimization of the environment of business and continuous elevation of the level of public services, materializing the objectives of making life easier for the population, benefiting it, and to safeguard its well-being. ”
AL also articulated with the government's work in the “deepening of administrative management reform, raising the efficiency of governance, improving the electronic government, optimizing the business environment and continuous elevation of the level of public services”, said Kou Hoi In, pointing out that this has made it possible to realize "the objectives of making life easier for the population, benefiting it and to guide its well-being."
"The results achieved by the Legislative Assembly are inseparable from the support of all parties," he said, taking the opportunity to thank the Central Popular Government, to the Hong Kong and Central Government's office to the central government's liaison office on the masters and to the Ministry of Foreign Ministry for “attention, support and help” AL over the years. The president also extended the thanks to the Chief Executive and the staff of the support services to AL.
This is, as Kou Hoi in yesterday recalled, the last legislative session of the current legislature and we are also at the beginning of the mandate of the new government of Sam Hou Fai. These factors precede that “work in the near future is even more intense,” he warned, promising that all work will be completed before the legislative session.
In the speech, Kou Hoi in assured that the legislative body “will continue to work for the welfare of the population, to vigorously promote the glorious tradition of the love of the homeland and Macau, and to accurately adhere to the new mission and the new tasks. attributed to Macao on the new journey of the new era of the country. ”
“We will perform the functions entrusted to us, working together in the improvement of diverse legislation, promoting the reform of public administration and optimizing the legislative production mechanism, in coordination with the government,” said the deputy, stressing: “We will persist, as Always, in the beginning of 'a country' and enhance the advantages of 'two systems', ensuring the stable and lasting implementation of the 'country', two systems in Macao, and raising the level and effectiveness of the special administrative region's governance of Macao through the exercise of supervisory competence ”.
In conclusion, Kou Hoi In said that Al will strive to “improve the construction of the institutional system and promote the development of high quality of the works of the Legislative Assembly, seeking to progress in a stable way”. “We are going to work towards a new mandate leap in the conquest of new development milestones in all its enterprises, thus contributing to the successful practice of the 'a country, two systems' with Macao characteristics to be projected to a new level, ”he said.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:39:08+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese mne moves to the United Kingdom and Germany before a UN meeting</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/mne-chines-desloca-se-ao-reino-unido-e-a-alemanha-antes-de-reuniao-na-onu/</link><description>Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi will move to the United Kingdom, Ireland, Germany and South Africa, between February 12 and 21, his ministry announced yesterday. Wang will also attend a United Nations Security Council meeting in New York on 18 February, the same source said in a statement.
During his stay in the United Kingdom, Chinese diplomacy chief will participate in the tenth round of the China - United Kingdom dialogue with his British homologist David Lammy. Then he will move to Ireland, where he will meet with the deputy minister and minister of foreign and trade, Simon Harris.
In Germany, Wang Yi will participate in the 61st Munich Security Conference, where he will intervene in a forum dedicated to China, to present Beijing's position on international issues.
China takes over the rotating presidency of the United Nations Security Council in February. In this context, on the 18th, Wang goes to New York to participate in an open debate of the organ.
The Asian country, as a rotary president of the Council, also invited US Diplomacy Chief Marco Rubio for the event, with whom Wang should keep a meeting in a context of commercial friction between the two powers.
The minister will also attend the meeting between the heads of diplomacy of the G20 countries, which will take place on February 20 and 21 in Johannesburg, at the invitation of his South African counterpart, Naledi Pandor.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:37:36+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Seak Chio Law takes office as a subdirector of DICJ</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/lei-seak-chio-toma-posse-como-subdirector-da-dicj/</link><description>Seak Chio Law took office yesterday as a subdirector of the Directorate of Inspection and Game Coordination (DICJ), a position it will perform for a period of one year, until February 10, 2026.
The ceremony took place at the body's headquarters and was chaired by the substitute director, Lio Chi Chong, and witnessed by the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP, and the chief of staff, Lo Chi Fai.
At the ceremony, Lio Chi Chong praised the vast professional experience of the new subdirector in the area of ​​Public Administration and Management and considered that the leadership capacity already demonstrated in previous positions will result in new ideas for DICJ, reinforcing the effectiveness of supervision and development healthy game sector. In turn, Seak Chio Law thanked the Government of MSA for their confidence deposited and guaranteed to focus all efforts on implementing the MSAR police and the work of inspection, coordination and management.
In a statement issued by the DICJ, it is detailed that the newly appointed subdirector is a master's degree in Public Administration from the National Institute of Administration of China and a degree in Engineering Management from the University of Huaqiao. He entered the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) in 2005 and exercised successively the positions of Assistant Technical and Technical-Sugerior; From 2016 to 2020, it was a functional leadership of the Occupational Safety and Health Inspectorate Group and serious work accident investigation from the DSSA Risk Inspection Division; From 2020 to 2023, he was head of the DSSA Risk Inspection Division; From 2023 to February 2025 he was head of the Department of Occupational Health and Occupational Health.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:38:34+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Timorese teachers dismissed in 2023 require agreement before testing</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/professores-timorenses-dispensados-em-2023-exigem-acordo-antes-de-teste/</link><description>The 1,499 Timorese teachers hired and dismissed in 2023 asked the Timor-Leste government to sign an agreement with the Ministry of Education before the special test, announced last week.
 
“We accept the special test, but if we are not approved, what solution will the Ministry of Education give teachers with a secondary education diploma to resolve this situation?” Contracting teachers from 2023, Agostinho Pinto.
According to Agostinho Pinto, the 1,499 former teacher hired teachers devoted themselves to the education sector for several years, some of which between 10 and 20 years, and for this reason, the former executive dignified his sacrifice by raising his status of volunteers to Public Administration agents, with their names published in the Jornal da República. “Now, the Ministry of Education intends to take a test for us, but with what intention? We don't know, ”he asked.
Agostinho Pinto acknowledged that the Statute of Teachers is that of public administration agents. However, he stressed that they have already fulfilled the three requirements required: a legal contract with the Ministry of Education, the possession of the minimum bachelor's degree and the performance evaluation with positive classification.
He also added that, despite the fulfillment of these requirements, the Ministry of Education refused to evaluate the performance of the teachers with the Public Function Commission so that they were registered in the Integrated Public Management and Audit System. “We think it is not necessary to perform a special test. But if the Ministry of Education forces us to do so, there has to be agreement between the dismissed teachers and the ministry, ”he suggested.
The official also explained that the public administration agents who have only secondary education diploma or who do not meet the necessary requirements to be teachers will have the opportunity, according to the Ministry of Education proposal, to make a contract to perform administrative functions or as a teacher assistant .
“We accept the special test as a way to contribute to the solution. However, we prefer that there is a debate before we advance to this special test, otherwise the problem will continue to generate discontent and dissatisfaction, ”he concluded.
The Timor-Leste Ministry of Education announced last week to perform a special test for teachers hired and dismissed in 2023 to give them the opportunity to enter the National Education System.
In 2024, the Ministry of Education also performed tests to former teachers dismissed from the education system to establish a scholarship. In total, 568 approvals were registered for a total of 2,400 vacancies available. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:37:36+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chongqing nullifies restrictions on the purchase and sale of houses</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/chongqing-anula-restricoes-a-compra-e-venda-de-casas/</link><description>Chinese Chongqing metropolis, one of the most populous in the country, announced on Sunday the end of the latest restrictions on the purchase of houses, aiming to counteract a prolonged crisis in the real estate sector.
In a statement, the city's Municipal Housing and Urban Development Commission announced the abolition of the last remaining exemption, following the elimination of a policy that required the property to be detained for at least two years before it could be sold.
According to local press, this means that there are no restrictions on the sale of houses in Chongqing, which has almost 32 million inhabitants, in an area similar to that of Austria, although it includes many rural areas divided into 12 villages.
At the end of 2022, the metropolis, located in downtown China, began to make the restrictions imposed in previous years flexible in the face of a overheated market. The city prohibited, for example, families from owning more than one house.
The financial situation of many Chinese real estate companies worsened after Beijing was announced in August 2020 restrictions on access to bank financing for promoters who had accumulated a high level of debt, including Evergrande, with a liability of almost 330 Mill million dollars (320 billion euros).
In recent months, the local government has announced several support measures, with state banks also opening multimillion credit lines to several promoters, aiming to finance the completion of projects sold in plant, an issue that worries Beijing for the implications for social stability, given that real estate is one of the main investment vehicles of Chinese families.
However, the market is not reacting: commercial sales measured per floor area fell 8.5%in 2023 and 12.9%in 2024.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:37:36+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Dsal and SJM launch “Employment + Training” plan for interested in mixology</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/dsal-e-sjm-lancam-plano-de-emprego-formacao-para-interessados-em-mixologia/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) announced, together with SJM Resorts, the launch of the “SJM Resorts Talent Mixologist Development Plan”. This project aims to support the full development of human resources in Macau, providing integrated vocational training in the tourism and leisure sector. Registration for the program starts today.
The plan offers 10 job openings in the function of commissioner in mixology, structured in the format “first hiring, then training”. Selected participants will have access to a comprehensive training and internship program for 24 months. In the first 9 months, participants will receive theoretical and practical formation, and then they will be able to choose from an additional 15-month training and specialize in the areas of scanning, mixology, tea art or coffee preparation, according to their interests.
The curriculum of the plan includes training in professional restoration techniques, with the supervision of Forbes Travel Guide, as well as internationally recognized courses, such as the “WSET Level 1 Award in Spirits”. Participants will also have the opportunity to participate in competitions, exhibitions and study visits.
The successful conclusion of the formations and the approval in licensing tests will allow trained participants to ascend to greater responsibility functions, such as a mixologist or barista commissioner, which may also be accompanied by a salary update. This initiative is not only intended to prepare residents for the job market, but also to promote their professional rise in the comprehensive Macao service sector.
Those interested in applying can find more information and make your online registration through the DSAL-themed page, from February 11 to 17. After this period, SJM will communicate to candidates who meet the requirements to participate in an informative lecture, to be held on 21 February, where the different plan formations and their available careers will be detailed. The interviews to the selected candidates will go to the lecture.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:38:33+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese New Year “Disappointing” reduces game revenue growth forecast by more than half</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/ano-novo-chines-desapontante-reduz-previsao-de-crescimento-das-receitas-de-jogo-em-mais-de-metade/</link><description>Citigroup predictions related to the growth of gross macao game revenues fell from 7% to 3% after a first -year first -year -old week than expected. The second half of 2025 is more positive, with several casinos to streamline events and shows throughout the summer.
 
The estimated growth of gross brace revenue from the MSAR gambling fell by more than half, after a new year's start of the serpent that the company Citigroup considered "disappointing". The first predictions pointed to an increase of 7%, which is now reduced to only 3%.
The Citigroup analysts, cited by the Gggrasia portal, justify this break with a number of visitors below expected during the first week of the Chinese New Year, a vacation season usually conducive to tourist visit and the largest flow of players in Macao casinos - including continental China players that Citigroup qualifies as "high value."
The same institution detailed that Macao will not have been able to reach the gross revenue of early game of 589 million daily patacas in January and about 900 million patacas in the first five days of February. As explanatory factors for this little dynamic New Year, tourist “last-minute cancellations” are pointed out and the imposition of additional rates on Chinese exports to the United States, implemented by US President Donald Trump on February 1.
According to Citigroup analysts, the end of the tariff exemption should continue to impact the Marem game recipes during the first half of 2025, tracing a dark prognosis for the region's economy, directly dependent on game recipes, and anticipating a Potential decline of 1% in homologous terms in the first six months of the year.
The recovery is expected to take place in the second half of 2025 in June, as the “impact of tariffs is digested” and casinos are preparing to host events and shows at the time -time time. In the fall, it is expected that the number of visitors during China National Day holidays boost the economy of MSAR and contribute to a second semester to reach 119.5 billion patacas and a growth of 6% in homologous terms .
The base budget prepared by the previous Government of MSAR for 2025 estimated that game revenues this year reach 240 billion patacas, which would mean an increase of about 7% compared to revenues of 2024. Citigroup prognosis, gross casino game recipes operating in Macao will not reach 234 billion patacas.
It is recalled that tax revenues from the game industry represent more than 80% of all of the MSAR tax revenues. In 2024, gross game revenues ascended to 226.7 billion patacas, according to DICJ data. This figure exceeds government projections, which pointed to 216 billion, and means an increase of about 24% compared to 183 billion 2023.
The 2024 revenues were the highest of the last four years. In pandemic restrictions, 2020, 2021 and 2022, the gross revenues of the casino industry were 60.4 billion, 86.8 billion and 42.2 billion patacas, respectively. Before the pandemic, in 2019, the game sector had revenues of 292.4 billion patacas and in 2018 of 302.8 billion, for example. The annual gross game revenue record was beaten in 2013, when operators received more than 360 billion patacas.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:36:35+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Wong Sio Chak greets security forces on the front line</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/wong-sio-chak-sauda-forcas-de-seguranca-na-linha-da-frente/</link><description>Security Secretary Wong Sio Chak yesterday visited some of the busiest zones in the city of Macao to greet the agents of security forces and services and recognize the commitment shown during the Chinese New Year festive court.
Accompanied by the Commander General of Unit Police Services, Leong Man Cheong, the Director-General of Customs Services, Adriano Marques Ho, and the Board of Directors and Managing Staff, Wong Sio Chak began by visiting the ruins From São Paulo and Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro, where it inspected the operation of the flow and vehicle flow control system. Then the secretary for security and his entourage moved to the area of ​​the border post of the Macao part of the Hengqin border post, in order to observe the customs inspection areas and ensure that the border passage runs “without starters” .
In a statement, the Secretary for Security's Office stressed the “excellence service” provided by front line agents to citizens and tourists during the Chinese New Year's Azafamada era, which this year “quiet and safely” thanks thanks to your effort. During the visit, and as it reinforces in the statement, Secretary Wong Sio Chak encouraged competent services to continue to show a “professional police image”, always under the motto “serving the citizen”.
On the New Year's Eve of the Serpent, several Macao Public Security Entities implemented the “Preventive Winter Operation 2025” - a series of security measures consisting of reinforcing policing and intensified collaboration between the Public Security Police body, The Judicial Police and Customs Services.
In a statement issued by this campaign, in mid -January, Wong Sio Chak appealed to the population so that during the festivities would redouble the surveillance of their assets, follow the guidelines of the police authorities and be careful with children and the elderly . He also stated that collective security is a shared responsibility, with the collaboration between the authorities and the fundamental citizens to build a “safe and quiet” festive environment.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:36:37+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New funding for scientific research with Lusophone countries launched</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/lancado-novo-financiamento-para-investigacao-cientifica-com-paises-lusofonos/</link><description>The Fund for the Development of Science and Technology launched this year a new program to fund scientific and technological investigation with the abroad, including Lusophone countries.
 
“Financing is available for cooperation investigation projects with any Portuguese -speaking country; It is not given preference to any particular country, ”the Fund explained for Science and Technology Development (FDCT) to Lusa.
Each of the projects approved under the Funding Program for External Cooperation in Science and Technology could receive up to five million Patacas, the fund added. "Given that this is the inaugural year of this program, the exact number of projects to be funded will be decided based on the quality and number of applications received," said the FDCT.
The fund organized a clarification session on this January 20 and other project financing programs, which had about 300 representatives of higher education institutions, scientific associations and technological companies in Macao.
However, according to the FDCT portal on the Internet, there is no date for opening the applications for the Funding Program for External Science and Technology Cooperation. Still, the fund said that applications for the new program will be open for a maximum of two months.
"To encourage more collaborations, there will be no specific priority areas in terms of technology," added the FDCT. "Any project that can help improve Macao's investigation capabilities and fulfill the eligibility criteria will have the chance to receive funding," the fund said.
In 2017, the FDCT and the Portuguese Science and Technology Foundation signed a memorandum of understanding to encourage cooperation between the research institutions of the two regions.
The latest data mention only joint funding in 2019 to joint research projects in areas such as marine pollution and marine biotechnology and FDCT confirmed that there have been no more projects funded since 2020. “During the pandemic was a bit stopped” , told Lusa, in April 2023, the Portuguese Rui Martins, vice-rector of the University of Macau.
The bilateral agreement signed in 2017 provides a maximum financing of one million patacas per project, on the side of Macao, and 100,000 euros on Portugal's side for three years.
“The values ​​are very low”, something that “does not allow to develop high scrutiny projects,” lamented Rui Martins, stressing that negotiations would take place for a new edition. "Negotiations are still ongoing," confirmed FDCT, who refused to reveal more details, adding that "the base established in previous collaborations offers a promising future for renewed efforts." Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:38:35+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong will ban electronic cigarettes in public places by mid -2026</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/hong-kong-vai-proibir-cigarros-electronicos-em-locais-publicos-ate-meados-de-2026/</link><description>Hong Kong will ban the possession and use of electronic cigarettes in public spaces by mid -2026 due to the health implications of young residents.
 
Hong Kong authorities will ban the possession and use of electronic cigarettes in public spaces by mid -2026 due to the health implications of young residents, authorities of the former British colony said.
"To protect our young people, we believe it is time to ban the use of electronic cigarette cartridges," the secretary for health, Lo Chung-Mau, said on Sunday.
"We will start by legislating against possession and use [of electronic cigarettes] outdoors," he added. "When everyone gets used to [the prohibition], we will implement it everywhere," he added
The announcement was made almost three years after the territory of southern China prohibited the importation, manufacture and sale of electronic cigarettes and heated tobacco products.
According to the Hong Kong law, anyone who imports electronic cigarettes can face up to seven years in prison and a two million dollars of Hong Kong. Manufacturers and sellers risk catching up to six months in prison.
Macao also banned, in 2022, the manufacture, distribution, import, export and transportation at the entrance and exit of the territory of electronic cigarettes.
The government justified the changes to the law with “the strong evidence that this type of tobacco product is not only harmful to health, but the use can endanger the safety of people”, noting that the consumption of electronic cigarettes increased, increased, increased, increased, increased, increasing electronic cigarettes, especially among young people.
Since 2015, the consumption of electronic cigarettes among young people aged 13 to 15 has increased “2.6% to 4%”, according to data revealed in May 2022 by the Macao Health Services Director. That is, underlined Alvis Lo, there are already young people to use electronic cigarettes than traditional (2.1%).
The law provides for penalties to four thousand patacas, and in the case of entities, a fine between 20 thousand patacas and 200 thousand patacas can be applied.
Although the proposal was unanimously approved, during the debate in the Legislative Assembly, several deputies maintained that Macau should go further and advance also with the total ban on the use of electronic cigarettes.
The then Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, Elsie to Ieong U, confirmed that the government consisted later forbid the use of electronic cigarettes after giving "some time" to smokers who could "have some in stock." Thirty -five countries banned the sale of electronic cigarettes, the World Health Organization said in 2024. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:38:33+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Coutinho or Rita Santos? ATFPM has not yet decided who will be the head of the elections</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/coutinho-ou-rita-santos-atfpm-ainda-nao-decidiu-quem-sera-o-cabeca-de-lista-nas-eleicoes/</link><description>The Association of Macao Public Function Workers (ATFPM) has not yet decided who will be the head-to -ist for the legislative elections that take place this year. The decision will be between Pereira Coutinho and Rita Santos. Yesterday, at the Legislative Assembly Spring Lunch (AL), Coutinho said it was unlikely that his list will get two places.
 
The Association of Macao Public Function Workers (ATFPM) has not yet decided whether the head-to-law for the legislative elections that take place this year will be José Pereira Coutinho or Rita Santos. Yesterday, at spring lunch, Coutinho was not optimistic in the face of the possibility of getting two seats in the Legislative Assembly (AL). "Keeping a place will be an excellent result for the next elections," he said.
It is recalled that the ATFPM announced in August last year that Rita Santos would be part of the lists, not indicating what position. In October, when Rita Santos suspended her mandate as a counselor of the Portuguese communities, Coutinho explained the decision by saying that the chairman of the ATFPM General Assembly was already preparing this year's legislative elections.
However, the uncertainty about who will be number one on the Nova Esperança list, linked to the association. “Let's see,” said Pereira Coutinho, adding that the direction of ATFPM will gather this Friday to analyze the theme. "I always put my place available to ATFPM and they will be the sovereign to decide," he said.
Stating that "it is important to have a voice that dominates the Portuguese and Chinese language in AL", the president of ATFPM recalled that it has been in AL for 20 years and "it is not easy to be a deputy elected by the way." "In the last five years I have fulfilled the role it should fulfill, serve the population and serve the Portuguese community," he said.
Pereira Coutinho indicated that Rita Santos is “a person with the ability to perform any public office, both in public administration and in the assembly and another side. It is committed and is a good valid picture. ”
The deputy took the opportunity to request the support of the population of Macau, “particularly from the Portuguese community”, noting that there are fewer directors of public services of Portuguese origin, as well as deputies in Hemiciclo.
Speaking to journalists, on the sidelines of the spring lunch, Coutinho left the government messages, stating that “the investments made in the area of ​​non -game have not resulted in the aspect of the creation of new jobs and increased revenue”, “there is a lot Unemployed people and inflation is shooting. ”
 
Coutinho Note “Remove” from the new government
 
José Pereira Coutinho also said that there is “a notorious difference” of this new government regarding the proximity to the population and the deputies. “It is increasingly difficult to have access to the new chief executive. In fact, since Sam Hou Fai has taken possession, "we have never had access [to the rulers] again so that we can express ourselves about the economy of Macao and other social problems." "There is a removal, but most importantly there is work and implementation of policies that can solve important problems in the area of ​​economics, creation of jobs and social policies," said Coutinho.
 
Marcelo in Macau “is essential support for the Portuguese community“
 
It was recently announced that Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, President of the Portuguese Republic, will be in Macao on the celebrations of June 10 - Portugal Day, Camões and the Portuguese Communities. This is “pleasant news”, commented yesterday José Pereira Coutinho, indicating that he liked to exchange impressions with the Portuguese head of state about the situation at the Portuguese School of Macau (EPM). “It is always essential support for the Portuguese community. There are people who understand that Portugal is broken or pay little attention to Macau. I do not understand why, from our contacts with the Portuguese authorities from different political areas, they always had great attention, ”said the deputy to AL, noting that, in his recent visit to Portugal, Portuguese Prime Minister Luís Montenegro, also to him He said he wanted to come to Macau soon.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:38:57+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Police Association advocates “urgent approach” between the corporation and the communities</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/11/associacao-de-policias-defende-aproximacao-urgente-entre-a-corporacao-e-as-comunidades/</link><description>The Mozambican Police Association defended the urgent approach between the corporation and the communities, considering that the authorities were placed by the demonstrations that marked the country in the last three months. “It is urgently necessary for the police to leave the office to the community. Make understanding to communities what policing is and what is its importance. Trying to rescue this confidence (…) within the police today there is a nervousness. This nervousness results from the fact that the police action is currently pinched, ”Lusa Nazário Muanambane, the president of the association, told Lusa.
At issue is a climate of strong social agitation that Mozambique has lived since October, with protests on the street that almost always culminate in violent clashes between police and protesters, who have already caused more than 300 dead and hundreds of shot wounded across the country , according to Mozambican civil society, as well as a trail of destruction.
For Nazario Muanambane, the way protests have occurred caused a “nervousness” in the corporation and the Mozambican police today face a test, with leaders in the corporation to demand a stance, sometimes opposite the interests of the communities, although it also admits that there is also excesses on the part of the population. “What society wants is respect for people's freedoms, but these freedoms end up exceeding the boundaries (…) for example, for example, a police officer was stoned to death. When the colleagues of this agent watch this, what reaction they will have, ”he asked.
According to Nazário Muanambane, in Mozambique, there is a tendency to look at the police as a “party instrument in power”, but agents face the same challenges as the community. “The problems that the ordinary citizen goes through are the same because the police pass, the cost of living, the problems of transport, are the same problems. The police live in the community, ”he said.
Nazario Muanambane defends the corporation's approach to communities, as well as criticizing an alleged lack of responsibility for Mozambican political interveners, who end up “encouraging violence”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11T07:37:34+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>