<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/12/potencial-do-portugues-no-mundo-contemporaneo-em-discussao-na-fundacao-rui-cunha/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Intercepted duo in case of alleged illegal immigration</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/12/interceptado-duo-em-caso-de-alegada-imigracao-ilegal/</link><description>Customs services intercepted two men on suspicion of illegal immigration activities, those detained from the interior of China, 20 and 30 years old, respectively. Authorities also seized a vessel that those involved used to move to Macau.
According to a press release, Customs carried out the detention operation on Saturday night. The body said it, through the intelligent maritime surveillance system and the nightly infrared vision chambers, a vessel that sailed near the beach of Há Sá "with an unusual trajectory" and "suspected of being involved in illegal immigration activities." Thus sent quick speedboats, customs staff and drones to intercept the vessel.
The target vessel driver was intercepted at the scene and an individual, alleged illegal immigrant, was caught in the area of ​​the barbecue of Hác Sá.
The man, who will have helped the entry to another individual, is suspected of having committed the crime of assisting illegal migration and was applied to pre-trial detention by the judicial bodies. The other detainee, who entered the territory when he was subject to an entry ban, was referred to the Department of Border Control of the Public Security Police, and may be accused of the practice of entry crime without subjection to migration control.
In the statement, customs guarantees reinforcement of maritime and coastal surveillance capacity, as well as the execution of the law, using technological equipment to perform a permanent surveillance of high risk zones for crimes, in order to intensify the efforts to combat illegal transionic activities.</description><pubDate>2025-03-12 03:03:34</pubDate></item><item><title>30 Macao restaurants featured on the list of the 100 best of RAE</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/12/30-restaurantes-de-macau-em-destaque-na-lista-dos-100-melhores-das-rae/</link><description>Macau got this year five more places on the South China Morning Post list compared to 2024, one of the distinguished restaurants is Portuguese: By José Avillez. The distinction of “best chef” was attributed to chef Tam Kwok-Fung, by chef Tam's Seasons.
 
This year's list of the 100 best tables in Macao and Hong Kong from South China Morning Post (SCMP) includes 30 Macao restaurants, five more than last year. Hong Kong-based newspaper selections are published annually, with the aim of promoting gastronomic offers of excellence in high-covered restaurants in both regions.
In this 13th edition of the “100 Top Tables”, restaurants distinguished by SCMP in Macau are mainly located at Cotai and are dedicated to different types of food: Cantonese, Italian, French, Japanese and Western. The only representation of Portuguese cuisine comes up with the restaurant Table by José Avillez, located at Grand Lisboa Palace Resort Macau, in Cotai.
The SJM chain restaurants were the ones that deserved the most prominence, with six restaurants to appear on the list: three located on Grand Lisbon and the other half on Grand Lisboa Palace. Here are the Galaxy, which has won five places on the list, and the Wynn and City of Dreams casinos, each equally represented by four restaurants. Studio City and MGM are also highlighted, each with two places in the SCMP ranking (ordered by alphabetical order and not for qualitative importance).
“We are deeply grateful to South China Morning Post for this recognition, which reaffirms our incessant pursuit of gastronomic excellence and reflects the passion and innovation of our culinary team, which continues to widen the boundaries and honor tradition. Each of our six award-winning restaurants offers a distinct experience, rooted in Macao's rich gastronomic heritage, ”SJM's executive director Daisy Ho said in a press release released after the publication of the results. "We are still committed to keeping the highest standards, further reinforcing Macao's reputation as a world -class gastronomic destination."
Also MGM's senior vice president of Hospitality, Iwan Dietschi, expressed gratitude for recognition: “We are immensely proud that our distinct Imperial Court and Five Road restaurants have been recognized again on SCMP 100 Top Tables 2025 'list. These MGM treasures, which are the epitome of our dedication to Chinese regional cuisine, continue to be celebrated by our customers by their exceptional and unique gastronomic experiences, showing the rich diversity of Chinese culinary culture. ”
The list of 2025 boosts the Macao Statute as a creative city of gastronomy, adding five more restaurants to 25 already highlighted in 2024. In total, six new restaurants entered the list: Don Alfonso, Greater Lisbon Hotel; Drunken Fish at Wynn Macau; L'Ttitude, in City of Dreams; and Sushi Kissho by Miyakawa, Teppanyaki Shou and Yamazato, in the Galaxy Macau. From the previous year list, the Golden Flower restaurant in Wynn Macau fell.
 
Best Chef of 2025 is from Macau
 
In parallel to the highlighted restaurant list, the South China Morning Post guide also assigns ten awards from different categories to various restaurants in Macau and Hong Kong: Best Chef, Best Service, Rise Star, Sustainability Hero, Best Bartender, Best New Interior Design, “Legend”, Chef Choice, Best New Restaurant and Best New Bar. The awards may or may not be attributed simultaneously to the same establishments.
This year's Best Chef Award was awarded to chef Tam Kwok-Fung, responsible for the Cantonesa food restaurant Chef Tam's Seasons, located at Wynn Palace. Last year, all ten prizes had been attributed to Hong Kong restaurants.
On the SCMP page dedicated to the 2025 awards, it is possible to read that Chef Tam Kwok-Fung to the Principles of Seasonality, reformulating tasting menus every fortnight, is “a remarkable feat” and “truly exceptional results”.
In a press release, the resort recognizes the distinction as "an honor" and "a will of culinary excellence and the continuous contribution of Wynn to the role of Macao as" creative city of gastronomy. "
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Arts Festival: A month to celebrate 35 years of art and growing performance</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/12/festival-de-artes-um-mes-para-celebrar-35-anos-de-arte-e-performance-em-crescimento/</link><description>Macao prepares to host the 35th Arts Festival, which will take place from April 25 to May 31st. With the theme “Growth”, the festival will feature a varied programming, including the long -awaited piece “PI life”, as well as workshops and outdoor exhibitions that invite reflection on transformation and evolution. The event is not limited to entertainment and brings with it a space for dialogues between artists and viewers. FAM promises to be a platform for cultural exchange and creativity in Macao, offering experiences that, according to organizers, thrill and inspire.
 
The 35th Macau Arts Festival (FAM), one of the main cultural initiatives of the region, will be held between April 25 and May 31. Organized by the Cultural Institute (IC), the festival will have as its central theme “growth”, which will be addressed through a multiplicity of artistic expressions, reflecting the different phases of life and the challenges associated with each of them. The festival aims to provide a comprehensive dialogue for the exchange of ideas and artistic experiences, promoting an approximation between the public and the artists present.
The opening ceremony will feature the presentation of the recognized theatrical production “The Life of PI”. Based on Yann Martel's namesake novel, this show mixes innovative cell techniques with the use of puppets to explore complex subjects such as courage, spirituality, and the meaning of life. “PI life” has had a warm reception in various parts of the world and marks its first performance in East Asia, having as a starting point Macao. In addition to the three performances marked during the festival, another play will also attract the audience with its originality. The “Bate Fado” has the coreography in charge of two Portuguese, Jonas and Lander, who transform the lost art of fado beaten into a contemporary version of dance and singing, where fado gets involved in the tap dancing. Another view of Portuguese musical traditions.
In addition to the robust program of shows, FAM will include 33 activities designated as “Extra Festival”, which aim to enrich the cultural experience of the public. Among these activities, we highlight the section “Meet the Artist”, where informal and deepened conversations will be held with artists of various disciplines. Stagnant Gabriella Bird will conduct a tertulia focused on adapting literary texts into the theatrical environment, addressing the creative strategies that involve the translation of narratives from one shape to another. Geoff Sobelle, known for his innovative style in theater, will present discussions about his play “Food”, a work that challenges traditional theater conventions by incorporating elements of interactivity and food -related sensory experiences. Additionally, the playwright He Jipping will share his experiences in the development of the play “Deling and Cixi”, which recreates elements of the history and culture of the Qing dynasty.
The original Japanese musical “Kiki, the Apprentice of Feitiçeira” will make his debut outside Japan, with an adaptation of the famous work by Eiko Kadono, winner of the Hans Christian Andersen Prize. This production has a new musical repertoire and a high -level production team that will promote the charm of Hayao Miyazaki's animation, inviting the audience to a “magic and transformative” journey. On the other hand, the South Korean group Tago will present “the shaman's beat”, a show that combines traditional percussion techniques with a contemporary aesthetics; A dive into the richness of Korean music through its traditional rhythms.
One of the most prominent sections of the festival is the “selected projections of international shows”. These presentations will include a selection of filmed theatrical productions that have received international acclaim. The show “A Cue and Reason”, directed by director Sam Mendes, and “Eva”, starring actress Gillian Anderson, from the “The X-Files” series, will be presented, offering an opportunity for Macao audience to have access to high-widen productions. In addition, there will be exhibitions of works such as “The Bamboo Cutting Tale”, presented by the Tokyo Ballet, and the musical “In the Company of the Gods: The Other World”, from the Seoul Performative Arts Company.
 
Workshops and Interactivity
 
The workshops that will take place during the festival aim, according to the IC organizers, to foster the development of artistic skills and the interactivity among participants. The “Physical Theater Workshop” will be led by the cast of “PI life”, teaching movement techniques that help actors express emotions and narratives through body movement. On the other hand, the “Exotic Beats” workshop will feature the participation of Tago members, who will demonstrate the use of several traditional Korean instruments, allowing participants to try the rich musical heritage of South Korea. Another relevant workshop is “What Complete Love?” Space for discussions about the experience of caregivers and recipients of care. Invited experts will also discuss the psychological implications of these roles, favoring a dialogue on emerging social issues.
The festival will also offer an outdoor shows show, which will take place in the Iao Hon market garden. For three consecutive nights, several artistic and international groups, to the stage to present a diverse range of performances ranging from puppet theater to contemporary dance performances and physical theater. This show aims to make art accessible to all segments of the population and promote cultural interactivity. In addition, the exhibition “New Perspectives: Modern and Contemporary Works of the Macao Art Museum” will take place at the Macao Art Museum, presenting about 100 works that highlight the diversity of contemporary artistic practices, covering various techniques such as watercolor, oil painting and digital art.
Tickets for international projections will be available for purchase from 10 am on March 22, selling at Enjoy Macao tickets and online purchase option. Registration for workshops and other activities of the Extra Festival may be held from 10 am on March 24, through the official website, where additional information will be available.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>MIECF2025 will have Gino Van Begin as the main speaker</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/12/miecf2025-tera-gino-van-begin-como-orador-principal/</link><description>The number of international participants who will be present at the Macao 2025 International Environmental Cooperation Forum and Exhibition (2025Miecf) will grow 15% compared to last year's edition, the organization said, adding that the main speaker of the event will be Gino Van Begin, Secretary-General of ICLEI-Local Governments for Sustainability, an organization that covers 2,500 cities in more than 120 countries and regions and regions and mission is to foster the mission and foster Development of low carbon, resilient and circular through international cooperation and technical support.
Gino Van Begin will talk about “The Way to Construction and Development of Green Cities under the theme 'Innovation and Green Development for the Construction of a Beautiful City'”.
During the 2025Miecf, which will be held between March 27 and 29, international experts and sector leaders will be invited to share, in more than 20 thematic activities, new trends and opportunities in areas such as the development of the global carbon credits, the urban transformation of low carbon and industrial cooperation, with the purpose of allowing participants to integrate from the current sector and exploit the sector and exploit the sector and exploit the sector and exploit the sector and exploit the sector and exploit the sector and exploit the sector and exploit the sector and exploit the sector and explore the sector and exploit the sector and exploit the sector and explore the sector and exploit the sector and explore. business opportunities.
This year's MIECF will host more than 60 foreign companies and their latest environmental protection projects, as well as more than 100 international companies in Asia-Pacific, Europe and Portuguese-speaking countries and regions.
During the exhibition period, several international exchange activities will be carried out, including the Round Table Seminar “Low Carbon Green Urban Transformation and Industrial Cooperation” will bring together representatives of Belgium, Brazil, Vietnam, Malaysia, Philippines, South Korea, Japan, Thailand, Uzbekistan, among other countries and regions, to encourage the exchange between cities and cooperation. business.
Five sessions of thematic contact scholarships will be organized for national and foreign buyers and professional visitors, with a view to creating meeting and cooperation opportunities to help all parties involved to explore a wide range of international green cooperation opportunities and stimulate MIECF's commodification process.</description><pubDate>2025-03-12 03:03:39</pubDate></item><item><title>China ends legislative agency session without clarifying how it will relaunch economy</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/12/china-encerra-sessao-de-orgao-legislativo-sem-esclarecer-como-vai-relancar-economia/</link><description>China's maximum legislative agency ended the plenary session, considered the largest annual political event in the country, without clarifying how far the authorities are willing to go to relaunch economic growth.
 
A recurring theme during a week meeting of the National Popular Assembly (APN), consisting of about 3,000 delegates, including political, business, technological, media and artistic leaders, was the need to boost investment and domestic consumption, at a time when the economy came into deflation.
China is suffering from a profound crisis in the real estate sector, the intensifying of trade war with the United States or excessive debt of local governments.
The legislative agency has stipulated the goal of economic growth for this year in “about 5%”, a level that analysts consider it to be difficult to achieve with the measures presented during the session.
These include the contraction of more loans for a number of initiatives, such as the concession of 300 billion Yuan in discounts for consumers to exchange their cars and antique appliances for new ones. But most loans will be intended to support the real estate and local administrations, which are overloaded with debt. "It is not clear what will be the impact of this budget on underlying internal demand and efforts to counteract deflation, despite the considerable increase in the deficit," wrote Jeremy Zook, an analyst at Fitch Ratings for China in a report.
The ambitious goal suggests that Beijing may adopt more stimuli. Last year, the government surprised markets with various measures, which started in September, to reach the 5%growth target.
Finance Minister Lan Fo'an said the government has sufficient instruments to cope with external or internal uncertainties.
Chinese President Xi Jinping seems to be committed to invigorating the private sector, which represents much of growth and job creation in an economy that continues to be dominated by the state. Years of a regulatory campaign, however, the confidence of entrepreneurs and investors shook.
APN analyzed comments on a law designed to improve the environment for private companies, regulating aspects of market access, financing, competition or protection of property rights.
Xi intends to send a “message to entrepreneurs, but also to local governments and regulatory entities that the private sector is important and necessary,” said Neil Thomas, a Chinese policy researcher in the Asia Society Policy Institute, quoted by Associated Press.
Companies will have access to a higher percentage of loans than previously and the financing obtained through the issuance of obligations will be extended, the Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang said.
Much depends on to what extent the US leader Donald Trump continues the trade war against China and other countries.
The Asian country has diversified export markets in recent years, but the US remains a vital commercial partner. The biggest fear is not customs rates, but the health of the US economy and the demand for Chinese products, wrote Alicia Garcia Herrero, chief economist for the Investment Bank Asia Pacific Natixis.
Trump has increased taxes on imports from China twice since he took office in January. "If the American side continues to follow this path, we will fight to the end," warned Minister of Commerce, Wang Wenta, during the plenary session.
Asked about Trump's “America First” policy, China's Foreign Minister Wang Yi said the Jungle Law would reign if all countries adopted the same approach. "A large country must honor its international obligations and fulfill its responsibilities," he said, on the sidelines of the APN session. "You should not put selfish interests ahead of the principles, let alone exercise their power to intimidate the weak," he said. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-12 03:03:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Former Filipino leader Rodrigo Duterte arrested by order of the International Criminal Court</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/12/ex-lider-filipino-rodrigo-duterte-detido-por-ordem-do-tribunal-penal-internacional/</link><description>Former Philippine President Rodrigo Duterte was arrested yesterday at Manila International Airport by order of the International Criminal Court, which accuses him of crimes against humanity during the bloody drug campaign, official source said. "This morning, the Manila Interpol received the official copy of a warrant of capture issued by the TPI [International Criminal Court]," said the presidential presidency in a statement. “It is currently in custody,” he said. Rodrigo Duterte (2016-2022) was arrested after arriving from Hong Kong and police took him in custody by order of the ICC, which has been investigating the mass murders that occurred during the former leader's repressive campaign against the drug, said President Ferdinand Marcos's office in a statement.
The ICC launched an investigation into murders related to the anti -drug campaign under the command of Duterte, between November 1, 2011, while still mayor of the city of Davao, in the south of the country, and March 16, 2019, as possible crimes against humanity. Duterte removed the Philippines in 2019 of the Rome Statute, as the human rights activists say aimed to escape accountability for murders. Duterte's government moved to suspend the investigation of this court in late 2021, arguing that the Philippine authorities were already investigating the same allegations and saying that the TPI - a court of last appeal - had no jurisdiction. TPI judges decided in July 2023 that the investigation could be resumed and rejected the Duterte government's objections.
Relatives of victims of the Rodrigo Duterte drug campaign, during which thousands of people died, they grew the detention of former Filipino President yesterday, by order of the International Criminal Court. "This measure of the ICC is proof of the validity of our appeal for Duterte and the accomplices to be held responsible for carrying out the war against the drug," Rise Up said in a statement, which brings together relatives of the victims of the brutal anti -drug campaign of the former leader. “I'm crying, I really wanted to see him in jail. They will pay for what they did, ”reacted Jane Lee, wife of one of the victims, quoted in the statement.</description><pubDate>2025-03-12 03:03:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Composition and video contests on security received 25,700 registrations</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/12/concursos-de-composicao-e-video-sobre-seguranca-receberam-25-700-inscricoes/</link><description>Composition and video contests of short films “My notion on the security of society”, which are organized by the Government of MSAR and the Central Government connection cabinet in the MSAR, had the participation of eight higher education institutions and 48 secondary schools, with more than 25,700 students enrolled, more than three thousand competitors compared to last year. 520 compositions and 85 short films were preliminarily selected.
In this year's competitions, subordinated to the theme “My notion on the security of society”, competitors could “show their understanding and attention by focusing on society's security and national security”, said the organization in a statement, stressing that “jurors understand that this competition allows students to better understand the importance of society's security, as encouraged by young people to greater consolidation of responsibility and mission in the defense of national security and to contribute to national security and security and to contribute to national security and security social development ”.
The awards will take place during the opening ceremony of the National Security Education Exhibition to be held on April 15 this year, and a part of the award-winning works will be shown during the exhibition.
Wong Sio Chak, Secretary for Security, recently met with members of the evaluation committees of both contests and said at the time that, “through schools and competing works, it is reflected that knowledge about national security is gradually increasing among young students from Macao”.
“During the process of creating the works in the contest, competitors understand and better considered the narrow relationships between national security with the security of society, or even with personal life, thus increasing their civic conscience and their sense of social responsibility, leading them to assume, by their initiative, the responsibility in defending national security and social stability. The contests reached expectations, ”said the secretary.</description><pubDate>2025-03-12 03:03:35</pubDate></item><item><title>What gifts can politicians in the territory accept?</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/12/que-prendas-e-que-os-politicos-do-territorio-podem-aceitar/</link><description>Can public office holders, including politicians, accept gifts? And do these gifts have value limits? The end point was to listen to analysts and realize what the territory legislation says.
 
The Macao Penal Code states that, in general, the acceptance of gifts from public office holders is illegal. Not defining a value, however, establishes some requirements. Executive Order No. 112/2010, which defines the rules of conduct of the main holders of public office, says it, but adds one exception: the lai-sis and those present on festive occasions, provided that the amount, the donor or the reason that leads to their attribution do not put the credibility of the ruler concerned.
In its provisions on passive corruption, the Macao Penal Code stipulates that the acceptance of gifts from holders of public office, including politicians, is subject to a prison sentence of one to eight years, in the case of unlawful acts (contrary to the duties of the position). On the other hand, when it comes to passive corruption for lawful acts (not contrary to the duties of the position), it is subject to being punished with prison up to two years or a fine up to 240 days.
For the professor at the University of Macao, Ieong Meng U, what is left here is that "acceptance of gifts is illegal, regardless of value." The former territory teacher, António Katchi, elucidates the requirements that are patent in the norm: “In its provisions regarding passive corruption crime, the Penal Code only prohibits public office holders, including political positions, the request or acceptance of advantage, without it (s) is due and as a counterpart of act or omission”. This means, in the context of the jurist, that, in order to be criminally responsible, this advantage, patrimonial or non -equity advantage, must be “improper” and, at the same time, a “counterpart of an act or omission by the holder - and this act or omission may be both lawful and illicit.”
 
And outside the domain of criminal law?
 
On the other hand, says the jurist, it is also necessary to verify the provisions of Executive Order No. 112/2010, which establishes the rules of conduct to the holders of the main positions of the MSAR, such as the Secretaries, the Commissioner against Corruption, the Audit Commissioner, the Commander General of Unit Police Services and the Custom Director General.
Not covering the Chief Executive or the deputies, as António Katchi warns, this diploma states that "the holders of the main positions cannot accept gifts, except for the gifts offered on festive occasions." And, even in these circumstances, the rulers should be careful: “In the event of the amount of gifts offered on festive occasions, the quality of the donor or the reason may cause in doubt about their credibility, or to harm the prestige of the government, the holders of the main positions must refuse the gifts, and the holders of the main positions to communicate the fact of the chief of the executive, and it is up to him to decide the chief of the executive. destination of these gifts. ”
This same diploma also states that, upon the authorization of the Chief Executive, holders of the main public positions "may accept sponsored visits at the invitation of foreign government or foreign private bodies."
However, warns António Katchi, these standards "have no criminal content, as they do not even have sanctioning content of another nature, nor are they completed by others that they have it."
Therefore, if any ruler violates this executive order what happens? "It will be up to the Chief Executive to file the severity of this fact and, if you understand it, propose to the Central Popular Government (Council of State) the dismissal of the holder in question, then competing to the Central Popular Government to decide whether or not to exonerate it," he says.
 
Lai-sis and other gifts, according to CCAC
 
Already the jurist of the territory, Carlos Veiga, reports what is located on the Commissioner's website against corruption (CCAC), warning of the need to ensure that "the way to offer and receive, the occasion and amount are comprehensive to local uses and customs."
In a 2000 CCAC press release, it was mentioned that, during festive periods such as Christmas, Universal Fraternity Day and Lunar New Year, “within the public administration, it is possible that someone will take advantage of these occasions to offer patrimonial or non-property advantages in exchange for some facilities” or, even if it does not have it, “who offers], yet, to question the duties of justice, impartiality, impartiality, impartiality, impartiality, impartiality, impartial services or employees and public agents, during the exercise of their duties. ”
Thus, it defined the CCAC in this press release, “the reception of illicit advantage is prohibited by any public official or public agent, because if he or or by interposed, to request or accept, for himself or to a third party, asset or non -equity advantage, regardless of his value, which is a counterpart of act or omission, contrary or not, to the duties of the position”, thus being committed to committing “a crime of corruption active that also implies your disciplinary responsibility ”.
If the advantages in question are gifts and lai-sis, “the way to offer and receive, the occasion and the amount should be compliant to local uses and customs (not constituting bad habit or addiction),” says the CCAC note, stressing that they should never be accepted “if they are offered by people who have business relations (or who may have) with the service or the public agent.”
On the other hand, in the case of hospitality and courtesy offerings, such as “the food and beverages provided and amusements that accompany them, they should be consumed” at the moment, but “the occasion, the recipient, the nature and the value in question should be reasonable and suitable for the event”, and should not be “luxurious or frequent”.
In addition, the CCAC press note continues, “Public Administration services should avoid receiving any sponsorship from abroad” to hold social parties, such as draw or workers' games.
If the holder of a public power has doubts “regarding the lawfulness about the patrimonial or non -property advantages to offer, by the presence at the festive occasion, commemorative or in similar activities”, he must report, in writing and in advance to his superior (or soon after the event), asking for a response to whether or not the advantages in question should accept or not.
 
Should there be defined value limits?
 
António Katchi has doubts. "There would be the advantage of certainty, but the disadvantage of stiffness," he replies, stressing that "the criteria set in the law seem enough to me."
In turn, Ieong Meng U states that it is important to have rules in these fields. "Promoting transparency is important and it is even more important to send a sign that corruption will receive a sanction," he says. To the question about whether there should be a defined limit, the teacher answers: "Government's liability has always been a question in Macao."</description><pubDate>2025-03-12 03:04:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Authorities advise measles vaccine to those who want to travel to the US</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/12/autoridades-aconselham-vacina-contra-sarampo-a-quem-queira-viajar-para-os-eua/</link><description>The Macao government advised yesterday residents who are not immune to measles to be vaccinated before traveling to the United States, where an outbreak has infected more than 200 people.
 
In a statement, the health services of Macau (SSM) appealed to all the inhabitants of the territory vaccinated “before they traveled to areas where measles is endemic”.
"Recently there have been many measles outbreaks in the United States and countries such as Philippines and Vietnam are also being affected by the low measles vaccination rate, resulting in cases," the SSM said.
Residents who were born from 1970 are pointed out as a priority group for vaccination, free through marking at public health centers. This is because, although the measles vaccine was introduced by the then Portuguese administration in Macau in the late 1960s, the vaccination rate remained low until the early 1980s.
Migrant workers are also entitled to receive the vaccine, but will have to pay 50 patacas for each dose. Only migrants who work in the health sector or primary to high school will be exempt from this payment.
In late January, Macau employed nearly 183,000 workers without resident status, which represented more than a quarter of the region's population, according to official data.
According to the latest report by the US Disease Control and Prevention Centers (CDC) in the United States, the country has already recorded almost 230 measles during the current outbreak.
The overwhelming majority of cases (94%) reached non-vaccinated people who did not complete vaccination and 80% of patients are children or adolescents, revealed the CDCs on Friday.
A school -age child died in late January in a region of the west of the state of Texas (southwest US) where 159 measles have already been identified.
On Friday, New Mexico's neighboring state health authorities announced that an adult who was infected with measles died, although the virus was not confirmed as the cause of death. The person who died was not vaccinated and did not seek medical attention, explained a spokesman for the State Department of Health in a statement.
The US CDCs announced, on the 4th, that they were going to send a team to Texas to help local public health authorities respond to the outbreak, which began in late January.
Measles is a respiratory virus that can survive in the air up to two hours. According to the CDC, up to nine out of ten people susceptible to the virus if exposed. The vaccine against measles, bread and rubella is safe and highly effective in preventing severe infections and cases. The first dose is recommended for children from 12 to 15 months, and the second for children from 4 to 6 years old. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-12 03:01:34</pubDate></item><item><title>United States and China discuss Trump-Xi Cimeira for June</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/12/estados-unidos-e-china-discutem-cimeira-trump-xi-para-junho/</link><description>The American diary Wall Street Journal (WSJ) reported that Washington and Beijing began discussions about a summit between the leaders of both countries in June. The Chinese press had already suggested the possibility of a meeting in April.
 
The discussions, which WSJ sources said they were in the early stages, are taking place at a time when the administration of US President Donald Trump imposed additional customs rates and other commercial measures against China.
Also the Hong Kong South China Morning Post newspaper has advanced that Trump could move to China in April to meet Chinese homologist Xi Jinping. Both the White House and the China embassy in the US declined to comment, the WSJ said.
Since the Republican's victory in US presidentials in November that Trump and Xi have expressed interest in holding a summit.
Regarding the possibility of Trump visiting China in April, Chinese diplomacy spokeswoman told no information.
Since Trump's inauguration in January, US administration has threatened, and then suspended customs rates about Mexico and Canada, while committing to punish Europe and other business partners as well. So far, China is the only country that has effectively faced widespread increases in Trump's rates decided.
The White House imposed additional 20% rates on all goods from China, citing the role of the Asian country in the US Fentanil crisis. Beijing retaliated quickly at his own rates, adapting the answer to avoid climbing the tensions.
Other actions that are being considered by the Trump business team include restricting Chinese investment in the US and US investment in China, aiming at China-dominated industries such as shipbuilding, and further limiting the sale of high-tech products to Chinese companies. Revisions on Bilateral Economic Relations, ordered by Trump on the first day of their term of office, should be made by early April.
For the WSJ, the leaders of both countries would like to be the other way to move, for the sake of diplomatic prestige. A trip to Washington causes Risks to Xi, when it appears to be subdued by Trump at a time when the pressure is increasing.
Chinese employees involved in the conversations to a summit are also cautious about a scene similar to the public rebuke of Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky in the Oval Room on February 28, "the same newspaper indicated.
Recent official data show that China's exports - one of the few positive points of the Chinese economy currently - increased 2.3%in January and February compared to the previous year, far below expectations. However, the country entered a deflation cycle, with consumer prices falling below zero last month, for the first time in over a year. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-12 03:03:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Current Currents of the Casinos more dependent</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/12/receitas-correntes-da-raem-mais-dependentes-dos-casinos/</link><description>MSAR public revenues are more dependent on the revenues generated by casinos, reveal the budget execution data for January this year. In the first month of the year, the total current management revenues of the administration was about 8.3 billion patacas, and more than 86% of these revenues came from the game sector. In January last year, the weight of casinos in mashed revenues was only 70%. Throughout 2024, the percentage was just over 80%.
 
In January of this year, the total current revenues of the administration was led by about 8.3 billion of patacas, of which 7.2 billion-86.7%-came from revenue from game concessions. According to budget execution data for January this year, available on the FINANCE SERVICE SERVICE (DSF) page, this is the highest percentage of recent years.
In January 2024, the total current revenues of the MSAR was 10.4 billion patacas, and revenues from taxes on the game were 7.3 billion, that is, just over 70%. In January, the casinos reached gross game revenues of 18.2 billion patacas.
In the previous year, still under the impact of the pandemic, January's tax revenues were only 2.5 billion patacas. In January 2023, the weight of the game industry was only 60%, as the revenues of fortune or unlucky games were 1.5 billion.
The months of January 2022 and 2021 were identical, with the weight of the game to stay in 71%. In both cases, the administration registered tax revenues of 4.5 billion patacas, of which 3.2 billion came from the casinos sector.
January 2020 surpassed this year with regard to the weight of the game sector in the total administration revenues. This month, current revenues were about 10 billion patacas, with 8.8 billion from casinos, representing 88%.
Last year's entirely, the game sector got gross recipes of 226.7 billion patacas. In 2024, the casinos operating in the region contributed 88.1 billion patacas for the total administration revenues, which were 109.5 billion. Thus, the weight of the game in MSAR revenues by 2024 was 80.4%.
It is recalled that the revision of the game law, which came into force in 2022, stipulates that the concessionaires of the game sector that operate casinos in the territory have to pay a direct tax of 35% of their revenues, plus an annual amount of 2% for a public fund and 3% more for urban development, tourism promotion and social security of RAEM.</description><pubDate>2025-03-12 03:03:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Musk entry into policy impairs Tesla's sales in China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/12/entrada-de-musk-na-politica-prejudica-vendas-da-tesla-na-china/</link><description>ASSOCIATION
 
Sales in China from the American Tesla electric car manufacturer fell to half in February, with the entry of the president, Elon Musk, in the policy to be “partially responsible,” according to an industry association. “A successful entrepreneur has to embrace the market 100%, treat everyone well and everyone will be good for himself in return. But if we approach the issue from an electoral perspective, half of the voters will like us and the other half, ”said the secretary general of the China Passenger Automobile Association (CPCA), Cui Dongshu, quoted by Bloomberg News Agency. "It is an inevitable risk after he sought his personal glory," he added Cui, who indicated that part of the population now sees Tesla as a political issue, given the proximity of Musk with the new president of the United States, Donald Trump, and the public notoriety of his initiative to reduce public spending.
Bloomberg recalled that China is not the only market in which Tesla is suffering: in Germany, where Musk was openly positioned in favor of the far right party, before the elections, Tesla sales fell 71%in the first two months of the year, while in France 44%fell.
In Asia, one of Tesla's biggest markets, sales fell 49%in February, in homologous terms, which also attributed to the traditional low time that follows the Lunar New Year - the country's main festive season - and buyers awaiting renewed Y model.
In addition to Musk's political stance, another factor that is weighing on Tesla's sales is the rapid rise of local competitors, such as BYD, who has already surpassed the US brand as the largest electric car manufacturer in the world and increased sales by 161%in homologous terms last month.
Tesla's drop occurred in a context where sales in the Chinese automotive market increased 26% after the renewal of the Beijing “renewal plan” subsidies, with those of electric and hybrid cars to rise 80%. Sales of the US company have been falling homologous for five months and in February they reached the lowest value since mid-2022, when economic activity in various zones of the country was practically stopped in the face of Zero Covid-19's 'zero cases' policy.
Musk enjoys a good relationship with China's authorities, a country he visited several times and where he has one of his main markets. In 2019, Tesla opened in Shanghai its first “gigable” outside the United States, which now produces about half of the vehicles it sells worldwide. Last month, it also started production at its new storage battery factory in the same city.</description><pubDate>2025-03-12 03:03:36</pubDate></item><item><title>APN received a proposal on center construction for sino-Portuguese agricultural products</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/12/apn-recebeu-proposta-sobre-construcao-de-centro-para-produtos-agricolas-sino-portugueses/</link><description>Kevin Ho and Dominic Sio suggested to the National Popular Assembly more measures to strengthen commercial ties between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, proposing to build a business center for Sino-Portuguese agricultural products in the Great Bay. Macao members in China's legislative agency want to create a barn of agriculture products in Brazil in the port of Nansha, in Canton.
 
A proposal submitted to the National Popular Assembly (APN) defends the creation of a business center for Sino-Portuguese agricultural products in the Great Bay, which will serve to increase the capacity of the zone's national food security protection, said Kevin Ho and Dominic Sio, representatives of Macao in China's national legislature.
According to APN members, the proposal aims to respond to this year's implementation of the 'continuous reinforcement of the ability to ensure the stable supply of food and other important agricultural products', a policy established in the government's work report.
Kevin Ho and Dominic Sio, noting that food security is an important component of national security and sustainable development, explained that the plan presented focuses on the trade of agricultural products between China and Brazil.
"Being one of the largest importers of agricultural products in the world, China depends strongly on Brazil and other countries for the importation of soybeans and other agriculture products," he said. Entrepreneurs noticed that agricultural production in Brazil has been constantly growing, but faces challenges in its insufficient storage capacity, which limits the competitiveness of its agricultural products.
Macao's two APN representatives have proposed to take advantage of the Macao Sino-Portuguese platform and the large bay's port resources to build an innovative commercial operations system.
Kevin Ho and Dominic Sio suggested building a barn from Brazil in the Porto de Nansha in Canton, and said it was possible to use Nansha and Macao Porto to develop a bulk product distribution center for Portuguese -speaking countries, performing a complete chain of services since production in Brazil, the transaction in Macau and the delivery in Nansha.
"It should also be incorporated the Sino-Portuguese Warehouse of Agricultural Products in the National Integrated Food Security Management System, in order to increase food supply resistance and reinforce interregional emergency intervention capacity," they asserted.
In the opinion of entrepreneurs, the measure can also contribute to the promotion of the policy of sino-Portuguese trade. In this case, they requested the improvement system of transfronting financial services to provide the provision of multilingual competition services and the transfronist payment.
Kevin Ho and Dominic Sio also recommended introducing quality assessment and inspection assessment bodies to the Chinese market, establishing a joint certification mechanism and promoting mutual recognition of standards.
On the other hand, Macao's 12 representatives in APN submitted a joint proposal on the integration of Macau and Hengqin into the national high-speed railway network, considering that there is an urgent need for relevant infrastructures.
The group has asked to accelerate the planning and construction of the high -speed hengqin station station, as well as the study on the possibility of extending the connection of the light metro of Macao, from the Hengqin border post, to the location of the future hengqin train station.
The delegation, which is made up of Lao Ngai Leong, Ng Siu Lai, Ho Sut Heng, Chan Hong, Si Ka Lon, Iong Weng Ian, Kou Hoi In, Kevin Ho, Vong Hin Fai, Dominic Sio, Jose Chui Sa Peng and Wan Nang Hon, hopes that a railroad channel that connects Macau, Canton, Shenzhen and Zhuhai.
The 14th APN ended its third session in Beijing (see page 11), whose ceremony on Tuesday afternoon was attended by Chinese President Xi Jinping and other central government leaders.</description><pubDate>2025-03-12 03:02:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Potential of Portuguese in the contemporary world in discussion at the Rui Cunha Foundation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/12/potencial-do-portugues-no-mundo-contemporaneo-em-discussao-na-fundacao-rui-cunha/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation will feature next Monday, March 17, at 6:30 pm, a Portuguese seminar entitled “The Potential of the Portuguese Language in the Contemporary World”, under the Route of Ideas Cycle. The entrance is free.
According to AEIMCP (Macao-China-China and Portuguese-speaking countries), the session will focus on the cultural and geostrategic importance of the Portuguese language in the contemporary global context. In this regard, it is recalled that Portuguese is the most spoken language of the southern hemisphere and the third most spoken Indo-European language in the world.
Quoted in a press release at the Rui Cunha Foundation, the association states that “the discussion will cover the historical factors that shaped the expansion of the Portuguese language, its economic and geostrategic influence” and “the challenges and opportunities related to the promotion and teaching of Portuguese on a global scale”. There will also be room for a reflection on “the possible future trajectories” of the Portuguese language and the Lusophone countries to the global school.
The event will be moderated by Marco Duarte Rizzolio, president of AEIMCP and co-founder of the 929 Challenge, an entrepreneurship program aimed at fostering cooperation between Chinese and Lusophone companies.
As invited speakers, the former Rector of ISCTE (University Institute of Lisbon), Professor Luís Reto, and the Associate Rector of the Faculty of Business of the University of Macao, Professor José Paulo Espera.
In 2016, university professors co-authoring the book “Novo Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, described on the National Press Electronic Page-House of Mint as “a contribution of excellence to the affirmation of the value and potential of a unique heritage, in a multidisciplinary and integrative approach, mirror of a multiform and dynamic reality, recreated to all space and time by all its speakers”.
The work proposes to analyze the Portuguese language about different prisms, from the geographical and demographic to the prominent personalities in Lusophone countries and the way language is used on the internet. The preface was signed by the then Minister of Foreign Affairs, Augusto Santos Silva.</description><pubDate /></item></channel></rss>