<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/chefe-do-executivo-projecta-macau-como-janela-importante-para-o-intercambio-com-o-ocidente/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>New case of collective infection by gastroenteritis in kindergarten</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/detectado-novo-caso-de-infeccao-colectiva-por-gastroenterite-em-jardim-de-infancia/</link><description>A case of collective gastroenteritis collective infection was detected in two kindergarten classes attached to the Lou Hau School, on the marginal avenue of Lam Mau. In total, 14 students were infected: six male and eight female.
The patients began to have symptoms such as fever, vomiting and diarrhea from February 15 and some even undergoing treatment at health institutions. There was no record of cases or serious complications.
Health services clarify that certain characteristics of the disease, such as symptoms and incubation period, exclude the possibility of food gastroenteritis and make the hypothesis more likely that the “pathogen agent is related to a viral infection”. Health authorities ensure that they are following the case and guide the school in question regarding control and infection measures, such as the correct way to treat vomiting and excrement and the maintenance of good ventilation.
Acute gastroenteritis has been rising in Macau, with alarming increase in cases of Norovirus infection since the end of last year. According to data from the health authorities, updated earlier this year, medical care for acute gastroenteritis has been growing sharply: the number of medical consultations went from 88 to 125 people per week at the end of December 2024, and the number of confirmed cases of Norovirus infection jumped from 24 to 92 weekly cases.
Norovirus and rotavirus are frequent diseases of viral gastroenteritis and spread easily, especially in collective equipment and at the time of autumn and winter. In a statement, health services warn that the transmission route includes the consumption of food or water eventually contaminated by this virus; contact with vomiting or waste of sick persons; contact with contaminated objects; or the transmission by saliva droplets.
Symptoms are generally slightly and last between one to five days without complications. Still, health services call for the population to pay attention to personal, environmental and food hygiene. Health and restoration professionals are especially advised not to attend workplaces when they have symptoms such as nausea or diarrhea, and should seek immediate medical care.</description><pubDate>2025-02-20T02:36:42+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Europe risks becoming a mounting line for Chinese battery manufacturers, says study</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/europa-arrisca-tornar-se-linha-de-montagem-para-fabricantes-chineses-de-baterias-diz-estudo/</link><description>The non-governmental organization Transport &amp; Environment has warned that Europe is in danger of becoming a “assembly line” for Chinese battery manufacturers unless they adopt regulation to ensure technology and skills transfer.
 
In a study released on Tuesday, Transport &amp; Environment (T&amp;E), which brings together non-governmental organizations that promote sustainable transportation in Europe, warned that current partnerships between Chinese battery manufacturers and European automotive companies are Too centered on short -term supply, without any regulatory framework for technology sharing.
This dependence, to keep up, can generate geopolitical and safety risks, warned.
“We can spend another 10 or 15 years to try and fail with companies like Northvolt,” wrote Julia Poliscanova, director of T&amp;E, in reference to the Swedish manufacturer who collapsed and was the main hope of the continent to counteract China's dominion in Battery matter. "Or we can [benefit] existing specialized knowledge and use them to recover quickly, as the Chinese have done in the last 20 years," he added, in reference to the policies created by China to attract European car manufacturers, in the condition of partnerships with local manufacturers, aiming at technology transfer and knowledge.
Companies like Chinese BYD and CATL invested, in the last ten years, in the development of this technology, anticipating the transition from the automotive sector to the electric segment.
The Asian country now has more than 80% of the global capacity for the manufacture of batteries for electric vehicles and the monopoly of the raw materials and key components needed for production, threatening to shake the 'status quo' of an industry dominated by western manufacturers for decades decades. and Japanese.
To collect this gap, the largest European car builders are establishing partnerships with Chinese battery manufacturers to ensure the launch of electric cars in order to comply with rigorous emissions rules.
In December, Stellantis announced that it will build a 4.1 billion euros lithium battery factory in Spain with CATL. According to the Spanish government, the project received almost 300 million euros on state supports. But no conditions were established for the transfer of technology or competencies.
Volkswagen is also collaborating with China's Gotion High-Tech in building a Salzgitter battery factory in eastern Germany.
The German manufacturer became Gotion's largest shareholder, after his subsidiary in China had invested more than 1,000 million euros in 2020 in the company, but without clauses that require transfer of intellectual or knowledge property, according to the T&amp;E study. “Without more European requirements, we will not learn. We will be just one assembly line, ”added Poliscanova.
Brussels now wants Chinese companies transfer intellectual property to European companies in exchange for EU subsidies and are reviewing their regulation. But the requirements that are being considered are a much smaller scale compared to those applied in China and the United States, the study pointed out. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-20T02:37:11+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Fighter convicted of negligence homicide after opponent died</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/lutador-condenado-por-homicidio-por-negligencia-apos-oponente-ter-morrido/</link><description>The Court of Second Instance (TSI) sentenced a Muay Thai fighter to a one -year and three -month prison sentence, suspended in execution for two years, for the practice of negligence homicide in material authorship and consummated form after his opponent have died.
The case dates back to October 2021, when the victim challenged a colleague to a friendly match, who would be arbitrated by a mutual friend of Muay Thai instructor. The fighters agreed that they would renounce the helmet during combat, using only oral protectors, gloves and shin to ensure safety.
The victim was eventually hit on his head with punches, who knocked him down on the carpet. He was then sitting on the floor. The referee soon declared the suspension of the match. Then the victim managed to get up, reached the ropes of the ring, drank water and took breath. Later, he went down from the ring voluntarily to rest, but a short time fainted and fell to the floor, bumping into the square chronometer with the right part of the head. The instructor immediately called the police for first aid, having been transported to the hospital, where he died.
The Base Judicial Court (TJB) acquitted the fighter of the crime of homicide for serious offenses to physical integrity and rejected the request for civil compensation made by the wife and daughter of the victim, who appealed the decision.
TSI then considered that "the rules of common experience teach us that the head is one of the vital parts of the human body" and "the non-use of helmet puts the brain at risk of serious irreversible injuries." The TSI then considered that the agreement to the non -use of helmet was invalid. This Court also says that the opponent should know that "in a confrontation without enough security measures, dangerousness intensifies significantly, which could cause physical injuries." Thus, “the risk increased is no longer within the measure allowed for a match whose safety is sufficiently guaranteed” and, therefore, the fighter “did not stop committing a negligent crime and must take on criminal liability for murder for negligence given the death caused. ”
The TSI then sentenced the fighter for a year and three months in prison, suspended in the execution for two years, for the practice of the crime of homicide for negligence in material authorship and in a consummate form. In addition, it is required to pay 378,260 patacas to the victim's wife and 371,400 more patacas to the daughter, as compensation.</description><pubDate>2025-02-20T02:36:41+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau received more than 7.1 million Hong Kong visitors in 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/macau-recebeu-mais-de-71-milhoes-de-visitantes-de-hong-kong-em-2024/</link><description>Raehk maintained the status of Macao's second largest visitors in 2024, with over 7.1 million tourists among a total of 35 million. STD, in cooperation with Hong Kong tourist agencies, aims to continue to consolidate the relationship between both regions and promote Macau's “gold business card”.
 
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) held its usual spring lunch in Hong Kong, about the Chinese New Year of the serpent, thus starting this year's promotions directed to the Raehk market - the second largest market of visitors in Macau .
STD director Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes said that among the 35 million visitors welcomed in Macao in 2024, 7.1 million from the neighboring region. In his speech at the event, the STD authority thanked the support of Hong Kong tour operators and expressed the expectation that this bilateral cooperation will continue to develop in 2025, further boosting the “sustainable development of the tourist industry” of both regions.
In addition to the participation of the STD director, who headed the delegation to Hong Kong, and the subdirector, Cheng Wai Tong, the event was attended by more than 100 representatives of the tourist industry in the neighboring special administrative region. These include the director of the Asia Tourism Center for the Ministry of Culture and Tourism of the Popular Republic of China, Zhang Dong, the commissioner for the Tourism of the Department of Culture, Sport and Tourism of the Government of the Special Administrative Region From Hong Kong, Angelina Cheung, Hong Kong Tourism Board, Dane Cheng, and the Board's vice president for the industry Hong Kong's tourist, ng Hi-On.
In a statement, STD clarifies that it will continue to explore the Hong Kong market “according to the promotional plan set through various channels and formats, both online and in person”, thus responding to the needs of different visitor groups. Also the representation of STD in Hong Kong will regularly carry out “product presentation sessions, thematic familiarization visits, joint and consumer promotions, among others”, in order to consolidate “even more” the visitors market and strengthen communication and cooperation between both tourist industries.
One of the most immediate projects goes through the “Experience Macao” Mega Sale campaign, a collaboration between STD and several Hong Kong travel agencies that, from February 20 to 23, will sell discounted tour packages at “Holiday &amp; Travel Expo 2025” . Other initiatives prepared for 2025, the press release continues, are training to tour operators, the inspection and promotion of quality tourism and the monitoring of the second phase of review and study of the General Plan for the Development of the Tourism Industry of Macau .
These efforts, as the body explains, "are led to deepen the intersectory integration of" Tourism +", consolidate the Greater China market and diversify the markets of international visitors." Also underlines the intention to promote Macao as “an international metropolis” and “a world center of leisure tourism”, namely through the development of its “creative city of gastronomy” status.
The festivals and events organized by STD in Macau can be consulted on the body's electronic page or in their official accounts on different social networks.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-02-20T02:32:14+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Nezha 2” surpasses “Inside Out 2” as an animated movie with the highest box office ever</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/nezha-2-ultrapassa-inside-out-2-como-filme-de-animacao-com-maior-bilheteira-de-sempre/</link><description>The Chinese animation movie “Nezha 2” exceeded the movie “Inside Out 2” (Pixar) and became the long-term animated feature film in history, local press said yesterday.
With a global revenue of 12.3 billion yuan (1.616 billion euros), the film is also the eighth cinematic work with the highest box office of all time, according to the Yicai news portal.
The success of “Nezha 2” is particularly remarkable for its origin, with over 99% of revenues to come exclusively from China, unlike Hollywood productions, which depend strongly on international distribution.
This sequel, which follows the story of “Nezha” (2019), is inspired by the sixteenth-century Chinese classic novel “The Investiture of the Gods”, which tells the adventures of a boy with magical powers that defends the Frequent City of Chentangguan.
Launched on January 29, during the Lunar New Year, “Nezha 2” led the daily box office in China for 21 consecutive days, contributing significantly to the increase of the national box office. The phenomenon of this feature film led to an extension of the debut in movie theaters until March 30.
Nezha's legacy as an iconic character of the Chinese animation will be honored at a special session on March 18 in Shanghai, where “Nezha conquers the Dragon King” (1979) and “Nezha 2” will be shown.
This event will bring together two generations of spectators and will offer a perspective on the evolution of Chinese animation in the last four decades, as well as the continuity of myth in popular culture.
Held by Yang Yu (known as Jiaozi), from Sichuan Province (Center of China), “Nezha 2” reflects the growing presence of Chinese animation films in the international film industry.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Vietname will build a railway connection of 8 million next to the China border</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/vietname-vai-construir-ligacao-ferroviaria-de-8-milhoes-junto-a-fronteira-com-a-china/</link><description>Vietnam approved yesterday the construction of a railway line connecting the Haiphong Port to Hanoi and the China border, with a cost of over eight billion dollars.
 
The railway between the northern coast of Vietnam and the region bordering Yunnan's Chinese province aims to reinforce links between the two border countries and facilitate trade.
The new connection will serve Vietname's main factories, where Samsung, Foxconn, Pegatron and other world electronics are located, many of which depend on regular charges for components from China.
About 390 kilometers long, the connection will start from the port city of Haiphong to Lao Cai, in the Vietname North mountainous north, on the Yunnan border via Hanoi. It replaces the old line in operation, built over a century during the period of French Indochina. China will finance part of the project through loans.
During the visit of Chinese President Xi Jinping, Hanoi, in December 2023, the two countries signed more than thirty agreements.
The new line will “boost economic, commercial, investment and tourist cooperation between the two countries,” said Vietnamese Foreign Ministry spokesman Pham Thu Hang last week.
The aging of Vietname transport infrastructures, which are of poor quality and are not sized to cope with the constant increase in demand, is considered one of the obstacles to the country's growth.
The new railway connection can help to mitigate the difficulties of international supply routes caused by the current dependence on slow and expensive trucks, which are “prone to strangles on the border,” explained Dan Martin, a consulting firm expert Dezan Shira &amp; Associates.
"China provides a large part of Vietname's industrial raw materials and it is essential to maintain this system stable," said the analyst, quoted by France-Presse. "A modern rail connection eliminates inefficiencies and ensures transport without problems of goods, whether sent to Vietnamese factories or world markets through Haiphong Port," he added.
The Vietnamese government stated that the Haiphong-Lao feasibility study should start in 2025, with expected delivery in 2030. But projects of this dimension often suffer delays in Vietnam.
The trains, designed to carry passengers and goods, will circulate at a speed of 160 kilometers per hour, against 50 kilometers per hour of the current line, according to the authorities.
Another line for China, which has not yet been approved by Parliament, will eventually connect Hanoi to the province of Lang Son, which borders the Chinese Guangxi region, through another vast area where foreign factories are found.
Vietnam also provides for the construction of a high -speed railway line to connect Hanoi to the city of Ho Chi Minh, the economic capital of the South, with an estimated cost of $ 67 billion (64 billion euros), with the objective to reduce travel time from 30 hours to about five hours. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-20T02:37:40+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UN Nuclear Agency Director in Fukushima to inspect soil decontamination</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/director-da-agencia-nuclear-da-onu-em-fukushima-para-inspeccionar-descontaminacao-do-solo/</link><description>The head of the Atomic International Energy Agency (AIEA) began a visit to Japan yesterday, which will take him to the damaged Fukushima Center to monitor soil decontamination, while the site is being dismantled.
 
Rafael Grossi, who visits Japan for the fifth time, is expected to visit temporary storage facilities (ISF) for first time contaminated soil on Wednesday.
"As Japan embarks on a gradual return of nuclear energy to its energy matrix, it is important that this be done with total safety and with the confidence of society," Grossi explained yesterday, quoted by France-Presse (AFP).
The UN agency leader met last night with Japanese Foreign Minister Takeshi Iwaya, who announced that Tokyo would make 14 million euros available for programs in Ukraine and other countries, including to improve cancer diagnosis.
Almost 13 million cubic meters of soil, the equivalent of about 4,300 Olympic pools, and 300,000 cubic meters of organic matter incineration were removed under the decontamination activities in the Fukushima province.
The Argentine's visit aims to ensure "the restoration of Fukushima, including the dismantling of the Fukushima Daiichi nuclear center and the control of the contaminated soil removed," explained a source from the Japan Ministry of Foreign Affairs.
Waste is being stored in a temporary installation that covers an area of ​​16 square kilometers (km²), extending to the neighboring cities of the Okuma and Futaba Nuclear Center.
Japanese authorities plan to recycle about 75% of contaminated soil-those with low radioactivity levels-using it, if confirmed as safe, for civil engineering structures, such as landfills and rails.
The soil that cannot be recycled is expected to be discarded by the 2045 deadline, and Tokyo plans to confirm the selection of the site and the process of destruction this year.
Soil decontamination work, decided after the disaster of March 11, 2011 and had not been carried out after the Chernobyl disaster in 1986, were performed at more than 9,000 km², or 40 municipalities.
The land removal method “was very effective in limiting (radioactive) transfers because the areas most related to watercourses were decontaminated,” explained Olivier Evrard.
In September, AIEA considered that “Japan's approach to the recycling and elimination of soils and radioactive waste from decontamination activities” was aligned with the organization's safety standards.
During Grossi's visit, experts from AIEA and various countries, including China and South Korea, will also collect seawater and fish water samples to increase transparency ”in the sea -treated water release process , guaranteed AFP another authority of the Japan energy agency.
TEPCO, operator of the Fukushima Daiichi Nuclear Center, has begun to dismantle treated water tanks to free space for nuclear waste storage.
After the huge tsunami, triggered by a 9.0 magnitude earthquake, Tepco maintained about 1.3 million tons of contaminated water - rain, groundwater and seawater - on site, as well as water needed to cool the reactors .
This water, treated by the Advanced Liquid Treatment System (ALPS) system to reduce its radioactivity, remains stored by more than 1,000 tanks that currently occupy most of the central terrain.
The dismantling of the reservoirs became possible with the beginning of the eviction of water in the Pacific Ocean in August 2023. Japan and the AIA ensure that this water does not harm the environment. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-20T02:37:41+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese New Year commemorative activities attracted more than 280,000 spectators</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/actividades-comemorativas-do-ano-novo-chines-atrairam-mais-de-280-mil-espectadores/</link><description>Golden dragon parade, firefight and floats: in 2025, the various STD-boosted shows attracted more than 280,000 residents and tourists. The organization says it has collected viewers' opinions, which it will use to improve future activities, and considers that the success of the festivities reflects “the capacity and attraction of Macao's' Tourism+ Events'”.
 
The spectacles integrated in the serpent New Year's celebrations, such as fireworks, floats of floats and interactive games, attracted more than 280,000 people. The figures were released by the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), which extols the importance of these festivities for the “diversified development of tourism” and the highlight of the “Golden Business Card” of Macao.
The fireworks show were the most visitors attracted, accounting for a total of 210,000 viewers over three different views. The exhibitions took place on the third and seventh day of the Chinese New Year and even on the day of the Lantern Festival, which annually ends the time of celebrations. Each exhibition presented synchronized pyrotechnic effects with festive music and lasted 15 minutes.
Also the parades of floats, held under the Celebration Parade of the Year of the Serpent, enlisted thousands of viewers: there were 78 thousand, in all, the people who moved to the two events that occurred in the third and tenth day of the fortnight of the fortnight celebratory of New Year. It is noteworthy that the floats that participated in the shows were then exhibited, free of charge, at the fishermen's dock and in Tap Seac Square, which attracted a new flow of visitors interested in seeing the cars closely and take photographs.
The “Happy Chinese New Year - Golden Stars” hobby, released by STD, has also proved popular among users, especially due to interactive games such as “Bricks of Fortune” or “Year of Snake”. During the promotion period, there were 108,438 people who participated in the games and 67,203 who entered the draws.
In a statement, STD informs that it has collected the opinions of residents and visitors through different means, both in person and electronic, in order to know their assessment of the activities performed and “thus improving the elements of activities in the future and the work Disclosure and Promotion, optimizing the content and format of the programs ”.
In addition to the celebration parade and the fire fire shows, the celebrated giant Dragon Dragon parade in the first two days of the Lunar New Year was also held. STD considers that the integration of these three activities in the “Cultural Exchange Brand Event with the abroad” - that is, the “Happy Chinese New Year” celebration framework of the Ministry of Culture and Tourism of the Popular Republic of China (RPC) - reflects “the capacity and attraction of 'Tourism + Events' of Macao”.
These three activities were not, however, the only ones: “different public services, industry operators and civil associations also carried out a variety of Chinese New Year's activities” and even led to the creation of a thematic electronic page with information on information These multiple initiatives.
In a final note, STD ensures that it will continue to “streamline the additional effect of 'Tourism + Events', leading visitors to walk and consume in different community neighborhoods, enriching their travel experience to Macao and promoting diverse development of the industry tourism".</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Prices of new houses in China fall for the twentieth consecutive month</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/precos-das-casas-novas-na-china-caem-pelo-vigesimo-mes-consecutivo/</link><description>The prices of new houses in China fell for the twentieth consecutive month in January, was announced yesterday, despite the measures adopted by the government to stimulate the sector, which is dipped in a prolonged crisis.
Prices in the 70 main cities in the country fell 0.07%, compared to the previous month, according to calculations made from the figures released by the Chinese National Statistics Office (GNE).
In December, the price of new houses registered a contraction of 0.08%.
Among the locations on the GNE list, 42 recorded reductions in house prices, compared to 43 in December, while 24 - including important cities such as Shanghai and Shenzhen - register increases, a number also slightly better than the previous month ( 23).
The calculations made based on GNE data also reflect a 0.34% reduction in the price of secondhand houses in January, after decreasing 0.31% in the last month of 2024.
In the case of this type of real estate, 60 of the 70 cities registered descents, three kept at the same level as in December and seven registered climbs.
In recent months, Chinese authorities have announced measures to wrap the real estate market, an issue that worries Beijing, due to the implications for social stability, as housing is one of the main investment vehicles of Chinese families.
One of the main causes of the recent softening of the Chinese economy is precisely the real estate crisis, whose weight in national GDP - adding the indirect factors - was estimated at about 30%, according to some analysts.</description><pubDate>2025-02-20T02:37:08+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysts highlight Huawei Victory against restrictions after release of a new model</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/analistas-destacam-vitoria-da-huawei-contra-restricoes-apos-lancamento-de-novo-modelo/</link><description>Analysts considered that the international release of the new three -screened Huawei mobile phone represents a symbolic victory for the Chinese technological giant, which has been the target of heavy restrictions from the United States.
At the release event in Kuala Lumpur, the group reported that Huawei Mate XT consists of three screen, doubled twice and is the thinnest folding phone, with a 25.4mm screen, similar to an iPad da American Apple.
“At this time, Huawei is the only innovative in triple screen design models,” said Bryan Ma, analyst at the International Data Corporation Market Research Company.
Huawei has achieved this position although it does not have access to advanced semiconductors or Google services, by imposition of the US government. "All these things have been basically big obstacles to Huawei," Ma said, adding that the "resurgence we are seeing is a victory."
Huawei, China's first global technology brand, is at the center of a US Battle - China for the domain of commerce and technology. In 2019, Washington cut Huawei access to US components and technology, including Google and other mobile phones, making Huawei models less attractive to users. It also prevented global suppliers from using US technology to produce components for the company.
US authorities have considered Huawei to pose a safety risk, which the company has denied. The Government of China has accused Washington of inappropriately using the concept of national security to contain a competitor on the rise of US technological companies.
Huawei announced Mate XT on September 20 last year, the same day Apple launched its iPhone 16 series in global markets.
At the Kuala Lumpur event, Huawei also introduced its Matepad Pro tablet and Free Arc, its first open auriculars, and other portable devices.
Although Huawei's state -of -the -art devices show their technological prowess, their long -term success remains uncertain, taking into account the current challenges related to global supply chain restrictions, semiconductor availability and limitations on access to 'software ’, said Ruby Lu, analyst of the research company Trendforce. "System limitations, particularly the lack of Google Mobile Services, mean that its potential in the international market is still limited," said Ruby Lu.
Huawei dominated the folding phone market in China, with 49% market share last year. In the global market, it had 23% of market share, behind Samsung's 33% quota in 2024. IDC predicted that total folding telephone shipments could increase to 45.7 million units by 2028 , more than 20 million last year.
Although most major brands have entered the folding segments, Lu said Apple has not yet launched a competing product. "When Apple enters the market, it is expected to significantly influence and stimulate greater growth in the folding mobile phones," Lu.</description><pubDate>2025-02-20T02:37:06+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Seoul will welcome North Korean soldiers captured in Ukraine who want to desert</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/seul-acolhera-soldados-norte-coreanos-capturados-na-ucrania-que-queiram-desertar/</link><description>South Korean authorities admitted yesterday to welcome the North Korean soldiers who are captured in Ukraine to fight along with the Russian troops and want to desert from North Korea.
The South Korea Foreign Ministry has advanced, in a statement, that "North Korean soldiers are South Korean citizens according to the Constitution" so "respecting the will of these people is to fulfill international law."
The South Korean government announcement was made following the latest reports that many North Korean soldiers were injured during the conflict after being sent to support Russia under the strategic defense agreement reached last year between the president Russian, Vladimir Putin, and North Korean leader Kim Jong Un.
The Ukrainian authorities announced the capture of two North Korean soldiers who fought alongside the Russian troops in the Russian province of Kursk, where Kiev launched a military operation last summer.
The Ukrainian government proposed to return them to North Korea if Pyongyang agrees to facilitate an exchange with Ukrainian soldiers currently detained in Russia.
Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky estimated that about 4,000 North Korean soldiers were killed or injured in Kursk, although the number was not verified.
The availability presented by the South Korean government appears after a soldier said in an interview with the Chosun Ilbo newspaper, which plans to ask for asylum in South Korea.
Seoul's ministry has reacted, arguing that these people "should not be sent back to a place where they face the threat of persecution."</description><pubDate>2025-02-20T02:37:40+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China rejects that Gaza is a "exchange coin" in political negotiations</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/china-rejeita-que-gaza-seja-moeda-de-troca-em-negociacoes-politicas/</link><description>Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi yesterday defended that Gaza is not transformed into a "exchange chip" into political negotiations, stressing that the enclave and the West Bank are "the homeland of the Palestinian people."
 
“The situation in the Middle East remains tense and fragile. Gaza and the West Bank are the homeland of the Palestinian people, not a currency of exchange in political negotiations. Palestinian governance by Palestinians is an important principle that should be followed in post-conflict governance, ”said Yi, in an intervention before the United Nations Security Council (UN) in New York.
"It is vital to defend the solution of two states, pressing on a comprehensive, fair and lasting solution to the Palestinian issue and bringing peace and lasting security to the Middle East," added the leader of China Diplomacy, which holds the rotating presidency this month this month holds of the Security Council.
Beijing's position comes a week after the new US President Donald Trump has reaffirmed his commitment to “buy and possess” the Gaza Strip, adding that the Palestinians would not be entitled to return to the territory.
Trump further ademed the controversy by proposing that the inhabitants of Gaza be reinstalled elsewhere, “permanently”, namely in the neighboring countries Jordan and Egypt.
However, these ambitions were harshly criticized by much of the international community and the UN, with the secretary general, António Guterres, warning that "any forced displacement of the population is equivalent to ethnic cleaning."
In the ministerial level debate of the Security Council, subordinate to the theme “Practicing multilateralism, reforming and improving global governance” and convened by Beijing, Wang Yi also addressed the war in Ukraine, stressing that “China supports all the efforts it conducts to peace conversations ”.
“The crisis in Ukraine has been going on for almost three years. Recently, the momentum of demand for dialogue and negotiation is increasing. Since the crisis broke out, China has defended a political solution and promoted peace negotiations. China supports all efforts that lead to peace talks, ”said the minister, at a time when the United States and Russia are in direct negotiations for this purpose, but without including Ukraine or the European Union.
According to Chinese diplomacy leader, Beijing will continue to work with all countries, especially the global southern countries, "to build a consensus to end conflict and to pave the way to peace."
The heads of US and Russia diplomacy-US Secretary of State, Marco Rubio, and Russian Foreign Minister Serguei Lavrov,-they gathered yesterday in Saudi Arabia to discuss the improvement of ties and negotiate the End of War in Ukraine-Conversations that represent a change in US foreign policy under Donald Trump's leadership.
This is the first Russian American meeting at this level and in this format since the beginning of the conflict.
The meeting was criticized by Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky, who condemned the fact that Kiev was not part of the discussions. “Negotiations are now running between Russian and American representatives. Once again, over Ukraine and without Ukraine, ”condemned the Ukrainian leader during a trip to Türkiye.
Zelensky said his country will not accept any results of this week's negotiations if Kiev does not participate. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-20T02:37:10+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>PR TIMORENSE receives credential letters from Ambassadors from 12 countries</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/pr-timorense-recebe-cartas-credenciais-de-embaixadores-de-12-paises/</link><description>The president of Timor-Leste, José Ramos-Horta, received yesterday the credential letters of non-resident ambassadors from 12 countries, in a ceremony that represents a “significant milestone” in the expansion of the country's “diplomatic partnerships”.
"By expanding our diplomatic partnerships by various continents, we are creating opportunities for cooperation," said the Timorese President, quoted in a press release after the presidency ceremony. "As a young democracy, we value international relations that help strengthen our position in the global community, while promoting our shared commitment to peace and prosperity," said José Ramos-Horta.
At the ceremony, the Nobel Peace Prize also highlighted the "importance of international cooperation to address global challenges and promote common goals of peace, security and sustainable development."
Yesterday delivered credential letters to Bosnia-Herzegovina, Guatemala, Venezuela, Turkey, Russia, Netherlands, Slovakia, Italy, Israel, Bulgaria, Namibia, Uruguay.
The presidency of Timor-Leste began yesterday with the ceremony of credential deliveries to annual diplomatic reception for resident and non-resident ambassadors dedicated to the theme “Build Bridges, Promote Partnerships”.
The reception, which will take place until Friday, includes a meeting with the Timorese President, cultural exhibitions, a presentation by the Government of the Development Plan, the main infrastructure and investment opportunities, as well as a visit to the Tibar Port . "The diplomatic reception highlights Timor-Leste's commitment to strengthen diplomatic relations, encourage dialogue and create opportunities for future cooperation with the international community," explained the Timorese presidency.</description><pubDate>2025-02-20T02:37:05+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Old problems and new challenges” can impact Macau's economy, warns Sam Hou Fai</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/velhos-problemas-e-novos-desafios-podem-impactar-economia-de-macau-alerta-sam-hou-fai/</link><description>The chief executive warned yesterday to the challenges that the economy of Macao will face in the future. Internationally, there are “turbulent changes” happening and Macau will not be immune to “unilateralism and protectionism” that is expanding; Internally, Macao's economy continues to live almost exclusively from the game sector - something “difficult to change substantially over a certain period of time,” lamented Sam Hou Fai.
 
Sam Hou Fai warned yesterday at the Council's plenary meeting for economic development, for the challenges - internal and external - that Macao's economy will face in the future. They are "old problems and new challenges" that "cannot be avoided."
The Chief Executive began his intervention by stating that the Government of MSAR “was able to ensure a good recovery of the economy of Macao, having maintained the main economic indicators and, in an orderly manner, the progress of the work adequate diversification of the economy ”.
However, “major changes are not seen in a century are accelerating their evolution and the world enters a new period of turbulent changes”, which makes Macao's internal and external environment will continue to “undergo profound changes and complex ”.
"From the point of view of the international environment, in recent years, unilateralism and protectionism have aggravated significantly," which causes "many unstable and uncertain factors," he said, adding that "Macao, as a highly open micro-economic abroad , cannot be immune. ” "At the same time, the international competition that the main sector of Macao is facing tends to get worse, so the inherent risks and challenges cannot be ignored," he said.
Note that the central government keeps unchanged the “basic trend for positive development” and, in the long run, “the economy ship of our country will certainly sail in the wind and break the waves for a brighter future,” Sam Hou Fai indicated That, in the short term, it must be aware that “as the US increases customs rates on imports this month, the international strategy of the new US government and the uncertainty of policies Regarding China bring us a new negative impact. ”
“The economic functioning of our country continues to face many difficulties and challenges, continuing to confront with certain respective pressures namely the insufficiency of domestic demand, the difficulties of producing and exploiting some companies, employment and increasing resident performance, among others Aspects, ”commented the executive leader, warning:“ These new situations require our extra attention and proper response, since Macao's economy has a pillar Integrated Tourism and Leisure Industry and is highly dependent on the market of visitors in the interior of China ”.
Internally, Macau also retains the “structural problem of exclusive development of the game sector as a single sector of the economy”, which is “difficult to change substantially over a certain period of time”. It also faces “the old problems”, such as “scarcity of resources, a unique structure of sources of tourists, imbalance of financial revenues and insufficient innovation ability, will be resolved to resolve more effectively,” said Sam.
On the other hand, "the new economic cycle and the changes verified around consumption model, conception of consumption and class of consumers also bring new challenges."
The chief executive also left some questions that Macau will have to answer in the future: “How can we properly deal with the problem of insufficient development and imbalance of Macao's internal economy during the economic recovery process? With conflicts derived from the development of industrial diversification not to meet the expectations of society, as well as with the common difficulties and pressing that Macao's small and medium -sized companies are facing? And how can we better develop hengqin exploration under the cooperation between Guangdong and Macau so that it can effectively contribute to the economic development of Macao? ”
These “old problems and new challenges” “cannot be avoided” and “concrete solutions” need to be found. “I hope that all present will come together to boost the various sectors of society to gather wisdom and gather forces to present more constructive opinions and jointly plan a substantial development, playing well, holding hands, the role of 'respondent' to Macao's economic development, ”he said.
Alongside challenges, there are also opportunities. “The current period and a near future constitute a crucial time marked by the full promotion of the country's construction, strengthening and modernization in the Chinese style, as well as the great cause of rejuvenation of the Chinese nation, having the practice of the principle, two systems, two systems 'entered a new phase of development, ”he said, reiterating that the country is a“ firm support ”for the region
Last year, when his passage in Macau, President XI Jinping addressed the Government of MSAR and the various sectors of society “four hopes”, “having instructed the placement in the first place the proactive promotion of diverse and adequate development of the economy of the economy of Macao, and indicated, for this purpose, valuable guidelines, with regard to subjects such as positioning, industries, projects and course, among others, which It fully demonstrates the great importance and strong support that the leader of our country has given to the economy of Macao. ”
"Having said that, we have to unite efforts and persist, with confidence and determination, in the reform, assuming all relevant responsibilities, so as not to defraud President XI Jinping and Central Government's expectations," he said.
Sam Hou Fai has assured that the Government of MSar will “unite and lead all sectors of society, effectively implementing President Xi Jinping's important guidelines regarding 'a country, two systems' and the tasks of Macao, especially as he says Respect for the promotion of the development of your economy; the concentration of forces to boost the economy, plan development and promote construction; stabilization of the economic base, and the stimulation of economic vitality, promoting a sustained and positive recovery of Macao's economy ”.
“We will maintain a precautionary and searching mindset for excellence, adopting new forms of reasoning, more effective methods and greater determination to achieve new advances in diversified and proper development of the economy and the construction of the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin, increasing the sense of participation and realization of sectors and residents, ”said the boss, adding:“ We will strive In the construction of a highly attractive territory for high -level international qualified frameworks, preparing and enabling Macau's economy for long -term development through internal and external connections. ”</description><pubDate>2025-02-20T02:36:53+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Child victim of the explosion in Taichung is in a stable situation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/crianca-de-macau-vitima-da-explosao-em-taichung-encontra-se-em-situacao-estavel/</link><description>The two-year-old child from Macao, a victim of the explosion in Taichung who continues to be treated at the intensive care unit, has stable vital signs and his brain pressure is gradually lowering. The hospital indicated that the minor has no longer needed controlled temperature treatment and subsequent medical care focuses on preventing infections and related complications. The airlines dismissed rumors about the alleged refusal to transport from the deceased residents of the Taiwan explosion to Macao.
 
A week after the gas explosion in the town of Taichung, Taiwan, the two -year -old Macao's child is still hospitalized in the intensive care unit, but the situation “is gradually improving” after a series of medical treatments, said the medical institution responsible on a press release.
According to the CMU Children's Hospital, the smallest has vital signs and brain injury is recovering with brain pressure relief. It is recalled that the girl was in a severe coma when she arrived at the hospital and the head trauma caused brain bleeding and cerebral edema, which led to an emergency craniotomy surgical operation to control brain pressure. It was also the target of a hypothermia treatment.
The hospital revealed that the girl's brain pressure has been gradually lowering in the last two days and that there was a gradual warm -up in the child, no longer needed treatment with controlled temperature. The smallest has passed the seven-day period at risk, however, "although brain pressure has lowered, it is not really out of danger, so the medical team will continue to treat it and watch it closely." assured the institution, indicating that it is now important to prevent infections and related complications.
The gas explosion took place last Thursday at Taichung's Shin Kong Mitsukoshi Shopping Center and caused four deaths and 39 injured. A four -generation family from Macao, who was traveling to Taiwan, was a victim in the incident, with two members losing his life and five were injured. Two residents have already been discharged from the hospital and three are hospitalized. The 85 -year -old great -grandmother and the 24 -year -old's uncle of the child remains hospitalized.
 
Corpses transportation
 
The corpses of the deceased residents in the accident are still maintained at Taichung's mortuary house. On Tuesday night, several reports on social networks indicated that airlines had rejected the transportation of the mortal victims residents of Macau, which allegedly forced family members to perform the funeral ceremony in Taiwan and take the ashes to Macao after the cremation in Formosa.
Starlux Airlines and Air Macau, airlines that operate routes between Taichung and Macau, have rejected that they refused the request of family members in question, saying they are willing to provide support and assistance.
Speaking to the Taiwan press, Starlux Airlines clarified that it received a request for information from the service, but had never received any formal request for the transport of corpses. In a response cited yesterday by the Chinese Channel of TDM, Starlux Airlines stressed that the company has established standard operating procedures for transporting corpse for many years, so there is no matter of refusal of service. "The airline will always help travelers with their orders, especially for unexpected incidents, which are really unfortunate, we will do the best to provide assistance," he said.
Air Macau, in turn, said it has taken the internal preparatory measures necessary for the matter and maintained contacts with all parties, being "willing and able to provide support and assistance at any time".
It is recalled that a group of tourism crises and the Macao Red Cross were in Taichung to assist the victim family in the case of explosion of gas, having accompanied family members of the deadly victims to meet with funeral agents and legal professionals in the area Local and, with relevant organizations and entities, deal with the processing of the remains and the compensations of the deceased.</description><pubDate>2025-02-20T02:34:43+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>3% increase in water supply this year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/previsto-aumento-de-3-no-abastecimento-de-agua-este-ano/</link><description>Macao Water estimated a 3% increase in water supply for this year, taking into account the entry into service of several housing projects in the new landfills and local economic development. The volume of water supply reached a record of 100 million cubic meters last year, said Nacky Kuan, the company's executive director.
 
Total water supply in Macau continues with a climbing trend and exceeded 100 million cubic meters last year, a historic record, the Macao Water Supply Society (Macao Water) has advanced. Compared to the 97 million cubic meters of water pumping from the previous year, there was a growth of 6%in 2024, a rise driven mainly by the overall recovery of the integrated tourism sector, according to the company.
Nacky Kuan Sio Peng, Macao Water's executive director, expects water supply in the territory to increase about 3% by 2025, taking into account the gradual conclusion of various construction projects and new buildings in the new urban area and development Economic of Macao.
“Several reasons were analyzed. Given the development of zone A of new landfills, we foresee that some public housing buildings are occupied successively, as well as the local economy to be developed, so it is expected that water consumption growth can reach 3% by 2025 ”Nacky Kuan explained to journalists on the sidelines of a spring lunch yesterday.
Macao Water launched in 2021 the “Financial Support Plan to repair the water supply facilities of low buildings”, which is scheduled to end next month. The official revealed yesterday that the plan will last for another three years and estimates that applications increase 20% to 30%, since “residents have greater awareness for water conservation and also for the maintenance and management of properties of the buildings themselves, and we believe the number of applications is higher than now, ”he said.
Nacky Kuan indicated that this plan invited the participation of about 700 buildings, representing 20% ​​to 30% of low -height buildings in Macao. It has promised that, in the future, Macao Water will analyze the way to widen the scope of the program through inspections and collection of opinion of residents.
According to the presentation, the Financial Support Plan to repair the water supply facilities of low buildings aims to encourage buildings of buildings to strive to maintain and repair the water supply facilities of the building. It covers financial support in the amount of 10 million patacas and it is expected to subsidize 400 to 500 residential buildings over three years and benefit about 5,000 residents.
Yesterday was also held the opening ceremony of the celebrations of the 90th anniversary of Macao Water. Nacky Kuan, in his speech, recalled that the company completed last year the installation of water equipment and conduct in the Ká Hó zone, aiming to support the expansion of the government's Hó Dam.
The project has increased the full effective capacity of local reservoirs to 2.64 million cubic meters, equivalent to 10 days of water consumption in Macao, “actually enhancing the guarantee capacity of the local water supply system,” he said.
The company's manager, in this sense, said she will continue to cooperate with the construction work of the water supply network and underground conduct shared in Zone A to contribute to the city's continuous development.
Macao Water is also advancing with two scientific research projects with the University of Tsinghua and the University of Sun Yat-Sen, as well as providing internship opportunities for students from various higher education institutions in Macao and in the interior of China, hoping to promote talent formation in the water supply sector.</description><pubDate>2025-02-20T02:33:50+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Loans not paid by the SMEs reached 4.9 billion of patacas</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/emprestimos-nao-pagos-pelas-pme-atingiu-49-mil-milhoes-de-patacas/</link><description>By the end of last year, the balance -related balance balance not paid by small and medium enterprises (SME) reached 4.9 billion patacas. The balance of the unpaid loans for loans granted to SMEs reached 6.2%.
According to a press release released yesterday by the monetary authority of Macau (AMCM), the new credit approved to the SMEs in the second half of 2024 registered a decrease. The amount used of the total loans granted to SMEs decreased while SME loans to major industries remained stable.
AMCM also says that in the second half of last year, the new Limit of Macao's SME credit decreased by 25.9% of the first half of 2024, reaching 3.3 billion patacas. The warranty ratio was 76.1%, corresponding to a rise of 29.3 percentage points compared to the latest data.
Until the end of 2024, given the one in this period, the reimbursement of several high loans, the balance used of the loans granted to SMEs reached 78.4 billion patacas and registered a decrease of 3.2%, when when compared to the end of June. When the analysis is done according to economic use and, comparing the situation in late 2024 and the one registered at the end of June, it was found that the loans granted to sectors in “education” and “transport, storage and communications”. increased 15.8% and 9.2%, respectively, while to sectors in “thick trade and retail” and “construction” registered decreases of 7.7% and 1.1%, respectively.
The use rate, defined as the proportion of the balanced balance sheet for the approved credit limit, grew 2.7 percentage points to 83.9%, when compared to the registered rate in the last six months.</description><pubDate>2025-02-20T02:37:12+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief Executive projects Macau as a "important window" for the exchange with the West</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/20/chefe-do-executivo-projecta-macau-como-janela-importante-para-o-intercambio-com-o-ocidente/</link><description>At the reception to the Permanent Secretariat of the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, Sam Hou Fai highlighted the importance of Macao's connection with the West, namely with Lusophony. "Macao will promote international exchange between people, present better Macau and China to the world, and become an important window for exchange and mutual learning between Chinese civilization and Western civilization," he said.
 
Yesterday the reception of the 2025 Spring Party of the Permanent Secretariat of the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and the Portuguese-speaking countries and Sam Hou Fai gave a speech underlining the importance of Macao's connection abroad was held yesterday. .
The chief executive began by recalling that the forum was created in Macao in October 2003, and in 2004 his permanent secretariat was officially installed at the MSAR. To date, six editions of the Macao Forum Ministerial Conference were held during which six action plans were approved for economic and commercial cooperation.
"As an important platform for cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, the Macao Forum plays a relevant role, among others, in the areas of economic, commercial, cultural and educational cooperation," he said, adding that last year last year , trade between China and Lusophony countries “progressed in their growth”, reaching US $ 225.179 billion. In addition, “fruit results were also registered in various areas of exchange and cooperation, such as humanistic, science and technology, teaching, health and tourism areas,” he said.
On the other hand, this organism “performed huge work, and played an important role in promoting trade and investment, human resources cooperation, cultural exchange between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, and the development of Macao as a platform of Services for commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries ”.
Sam Hou Fai also drew attention to Xi Jinping's recent visit to Macau, having presented “a series of important instructions for the development of Macau” and manifested “Macao's expectation to focus efforts to become a platform for opening abroad higher standard ”.
Remembering that the Chinese president asked Macau to “take advantage of his unique strengths and reinforce connectivity with both the continent and the rest of the world,” Sam Hou Fai ensured that the region will “take a more open and inclusive posture to intensify international ties and increase global projection and attractiveness; It will reinforce bilateral opening with Portuguese -speaking countries, promoting a comprehensive cooperation of mutual benefits. ”
It also goes, Sam assured, "actively participating in the high quality joint construction of the" a track, a route "initiative, making more friends around the world and acting as an important bridge for an opening of the high standard country."
“Since the place where Chinese and Western cultures meet, Macau will promote international exchange between people, present better Macau and China to the world, and become an important window for exchange and mutual learning between Chinese civilization and Western civilization, ”he said.
The boss also promised to “continue to fully support the works of the Macao Forum” and “support and collaborate with the permanent secretariat of the Macao Forum”. "In communion of efforts, we will continue to take full party from Macao's unique advantages to effectively enhance Macau as an interlocutor between China and Portuguese -speaking countries," he concluded.
 
China's economic growth is an opportunity for Lusophone countries, says Ji Xianzheng
 
The Secretary-General of the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries defended yesterday that Chinese economic growth will create opportunities for the Lusophone bloc. "China remains an important engine of world economic growth with good cooperation perspectives with Portuguese -speaking countries," said Ji Xianzheng, at a new year's new year reception, known as the Macao Forum. In a speech, Ji Xianzheng said that "Macao's efforts" at the opening abroad "will certainly bring new opportunities for China and Portuguese -speaking countries in the face of deepening cooperation in various domains." Despite optimism, Ji Xianzheng stressed that “the promotion of a comprehensive cooperation of mutual benefits with Portuguese -speaking countries is pending the set efforts of the ten countries” that are part of the Macao Forum.</description><pubDate>2025-02-20T02:35:04+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>