<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/13/china-espera-acordo-de-paz-duradouro-e-vinculativo/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Xia Baolong appeals to Macau's solidarity in the trade war with the United States</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/13/xia-baolong-apela-a-solidariedade-de-macau-na-guerra-comercial-com-os-estados-unidos/</link><description>The central government warned of the need for solidarity of Macao's industrial and commercial sector in the face of trade war with the United States. Xia Baolong, director of the Hong Kong and Macao affairs cabinet with the Council of State, said the local sector will have the courage to fight, but also appealed to confidence in the economic development of the territory.
 
Xia Baolong, director of the Hong Kong and Macao Work Office of the China Communist Party Central Committee and Director of the Hong Kong and Macau Staff's Office with the Council of State, appealed yesterday to the Macao Industrial and Commercial Sector to “join the homeland” before the trade war between China and the United States.
"With the rise of unilateralism and commercial protectionism in the United States, the industrial and commercial sector and the entrepreneurs of Macau and Hong Kong have to come together and position in the same front with the homeland," warned Xia Baolong, quoted by Tai Kin IP, secretary for economics and finance.
According to Tai Kin IP, Xia Baolong still encourages all local sectors to “dare to fight” in the face of international negotiations. "There is no way out if we make commitments and concessions, because only the fight can guarantee and gain development," said the head of RAE matters in the central government.
Xia Baolong yesterday held the fifth day of visit to Macau and had, in the morning, a meeting with more than twenty representatives of the industrial and commercial sector and local entrepreneurs, in the complex of the service platform for commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries. The meeting lasted more than two hours and, according to Tai Kin IP, Xia Baolong heard industry opinions about Macao's current economic development situation and the diversification of the economy.
On the sidelines of the meeting, to journalists, Tai Kin IP said that Xia Baolong recognized and praised the adhesion of the entrepreneurs of Macau and Hong Kong to the “tradition of patriotism and love Macau and Hong Kong”, as well as the will of the “take responsibility and to share the country's concerns” at important times in national development. In the opinion of Xia Baolong, the industrial and commercial sector, RAE entrepreneurs and companies are important for the country's development for “sharing the same fate”.
"The Xia Director, at the same time, expects the business sector and entrepreneurs from Macau and Hong Kong to be full of trust in economic development, and that we all keep firm in our confidence in investing in Hong Kong and Macao," he said. Tai Kin IP also stressed that Xia Baolong wants the local commercial sector to strive to develop the economy, expand the market and open abroad, taking advantage of the “own advantages” of Hong Kong and Macau.
According to the Secretary for Economics and Finance, in statements to the newspaper or Mun, the meeting yesterday was attended by representatives of traditional industries, commerce, small and medium enterprises, financial companies, national companies, tourism, digital technology and information, logistics and sector 'Big Health', which presented suggestions that cover the diversified development branches established by the government.
Xia Baolong, after listening to the opinions of the sector and entrepreneurs, gave instructions to the government of Macao, according to Tai Kin IP, for the protection of the economy to maintain contact with the industrial and commercial sector and to discuss it in order to follow the suggestions presented at the meeting.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 02:18:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines choose side in elections disputed by the two rival dynasties in power</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/13/filipinos-escolhem-lado-em-eleicoes-disputadas-pelas-duas-dinastias-rivais-no-poder/</link><description>The Philippines went yesterday to vote in the interchange elections, which place the two rival dynasties in power, headed by the president, Ferdinand Marcos, and his former ally, Vice President Sara Duterte, who faces an challenge.
 
Although municipalities and places are at stake in the Chamber of Representatives, Low Chamber of the Philippine Parliament, the main focus of the elections is in the Senate, due to any repercussions on the presidential election scheduled for 2028.
Together with 12 colleagues already in office in the High Chamber of the Filipino Parliament, the 12 senators to be chosen OJE will constitute the jury of the Sara Duterte dismissal judgment, scheduled for July, which may remove the 46-year-old vice-president from any public office.
In February, the House of Representatives already voted in favor of the dismissal of former President Rodrigo Duterte's eldest daughter on suspicion of crimes, including corruption and plans to murder Mark. Sara Duterte needs nine senators in her favor, from the 24th of the Alta Chamber, to be able to run for presidential 2028.
Sara Duterte was pointed out as her father's successor in the 2022 presidential, but gave up in favor of Ferdinand Marcos Jr., son of the autocrat with the same name (1965-1986), whom he allied before being elected vice president. The assumption of the agreement was to guarantee Duterte a privileged position to run for presidential 2028, as presidents are limited to a six -year term in the Philippines. The strategy resulted in a overwhelming majority of the duo Marcos-Duterte.
The union between the two rival dynasties was not long before imploding, giving way to public clashes in recent months.
In November 2024, during a press conference, Sara Duterte stated that she had given orders to kill the head of state if she was killed. He later denied having a death threat, describing his comments as an expression of "dismay" before the Filipino President's failures.
Of the 12 favorite candidates to earn a Senate place, seven are supported by President Marcos, four by Sara Duterte - including the sister of the head of state, EMEE Marcos.
At his latest campaign rally in Manila on Thursday, Sara Duterte accused the preparation of “massive” electoral fraud and again described her father's delivery as “abduction” to the International Criminal Court.
Rodrigo Duterte, head of state between 2016 and 2022, was arrested and transferred in March to the Hague Court in the Netherlands. It is accused of humanity crimes related to a deadly campaign against the drug while playing functions.
Despite the arrest, Rodrigo Duterte is a candidate in these elections in his family stronghold in the south of the country, where he intends to return to his former mayor, even being appointed as the favorite in a local poll.
Throughout the country, more than 18,000 terms are at stake in these elections, which started at 7:00 am.
About 68 million Philippines were called to choose 12 senators, 254 district representatives, 63 party representatives and 17,942 governors, members of provincial assemblies, mayors and counselors. The scrutiny will also cover the legislative seats of the Bangasamoro Muslim Autonomous Region, on the island of Mindanao, the second largest in the archipelago in the south.
The archipelago police are on maximum alert. About 163,000 agents were highlighted to ensure the safety of voting assemblies, escort the electoral employees and watch over the control posts. The military and firefighters were also mobilized to avoid any outbreak of violence.
A candidate for local elections, an electoral employee, a village chief, and 13 others lost their lives in attacks before the elections. Lusa
 
The Portuguese MEO Marta Temis (PS) will lead the EU electoral observation mission to these Philippine Legislatures.
 
It is the first mission of the EU to a Philippine elections that “marks a step towards reinforcing relations between the EU and the Philippines,” according to a statement from the European External Action Service.
 
Marta Temi, who led the PS list to the European Parliament in the June elections last year, was designated by the EU high representative for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, Kaja Kallas.
 
The mission in the 13th most populous country in the world will be “a huge challenge,” added the MEO.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 02:20:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao's role as a platform was under discussion at the University of Macau City</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/13/papel-de-macau-enquanto-plataforma-esteve-em-discussao-na-universidade-da-cidade-de-macau/</link><description>The University of Macao City organized yesterday a Forum of Academics from Portuguese -speaking countries about the role of MSAR as a strategic platform between China and Lusophony.
In the opening speech, IP Kuai Peng, vice-rector of the University of Macau and Director of the Institute for Research on Portuguese-Speaking Countries, highlighted the “strategic importance of the Institute to reinforce Macau as the Sino-Melusópone Platform”.
Quoted in the statement of the Higher Education Institution, Danilo Afonso-Henriques, Deputy Secretary-General of the Macao Forum, presented five practical strategies to reinforce the role of Macau as a connecting link in Sino-Lusophone commerce, highlighting the development of digital platforms for Sino-Busophone trade and the promotion of partnerships to drive a green economy.
Zhou Ping, a professor of that institution, stressed the ten years of work at the initiative "a track, a route" of Macao and referred advances in the development of partnerships with academic institutions from Portuguese -speaking countries, highlighting the opportunities for the materialization of academic projects in technological and scientific areas from Portuguese -speaking countries in mainland China. Zhou Long, also a professor at the University of Macau City, presented a pioneering project of sustainable aquaculture management in the region of Macau-Zhuhai, developed in partnership with Portuguese research institutions.
José Paulo Esperança, he also professor at Macau University, addressed financial innovation in Macau, highlighting the role of the region in the creation of international investment funds and promoting flexible financing mechanisms to stimulate economic growth in Lusophone countries. Professor Vera Borges reflected on the role of the Portuguese language and underlined the importance of teaching and research for the internationalization of Macao and the strengthening of interuniversitan relations.
Francisco Leandro, an associate professor at the University of Macau, analyzed the agents involved in cooperation between China and Lusophone countries, noting that these countries do not constitute a homogeneous bloc, but a diversity of cultural, economic and social realities. João Simões, professor at the University of Macao City, ended the Forum, highlighting the importance of multisectoral collaboration to position Macau as a strategic bridge between China and Lusophone countries.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 02:19:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Business Agreement between USA and China formally enters into force on Wednesday</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/13/acordo-negocial-entre-eua-e-a-china-entra-formalmente-em-vigor-na-quarta-feira/</link><description>Suspension for 90 days of much of customs rights between the United States and China come into force on Wednesday, marking a slowdown in the trade war that shook the world economy.
 
The 90-day suspension of most customs rights between the United States and China will formally come into force on Wednesday, representatives of the world's two largest economic powers in a joint statement published yesterday after two days of negotiations in Geneva, Switzerland.
According to the joint statement, the two countries also agreed to establish a mechanism to pursue discussions about trade and economic relations.
Yesterday, the US presidency welcomed himself with what he designated to be a new trade agreement with Beijing, without giving more details.
In concrete terms, the two parties agree to suspend overwhelms of 115 percentage points that had imposed on each other in recent weeks, as part of a war started in April by US President Donald Trump.
These decisions temporarily reduce US customs rights to the People's Republic of China to 30% and Chinese customs rights to the United States to 10%, while negotiations between the two countries continued, the US commercial representative, Jamieson Greer, said yesterday.
The announcement of this “truce” brought relief to the financial markets, with the Hong Kong Special Administrative Scholarship to rise more than 3% in the minutes following the publication of the joint statement.
The US dollar, which he had suffered from the trade war, recovered from yen and euro. "None sides want a dissociation" from their own economies, said US Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent adding that Washington intends a more balanced business relationship.
Bessent also said that customs barriers introduced in recent months have actually created an embargo on trade between the two countries.
The reduction of these customs rights is “of the world's common interest,” said the Chinese Ministry of Commerce, greeking what he considered "substantial progress" in commercial negotiations with Washington.
The truce announced yesterday was the result of two days of negotiations in Geneva between Bessent and Greer by the United States and the Chinese Minister Prime Minister He Lifeng by the People's Republic of China.
It was the first direct meeting between high employees of both countries since Trump imposed a 145% surcharge on products from China in early April, as well as pre-existing customs rights.
Beijing, who promised to fight the surcharges “to the end”, retaliated with 125% rates on US products.
Negotiations in Geneva took place with “great respect” and the result demonstrates that neither party intends to have an economic break, Bessent said in Geneva.
The official also added that the two countries are interested in a balanced trade by appealing to the Popular Republic of China to "open up to more American products." On Sunday, he Lifeng referred to significant progress in the conversations, which he described as "frank, deep and substantial."
The trade war between Beijing and Washington shook the world's financial markets and fueled the fears of inflation in the United States and an economic slowdown. "These conversations mark an important 'step forward' and, we hope, are a good omen for the future," the World Trade Organization (WTO) said on Sunday.
The conversations took place at the closed door, at the residence of the Swiss representative in the United Nations, a villa located on the left bank of Geneva Lake.
The meeting in Geneva took place two days after Donald Trump presented a trade agreement with the United Kingdom, the first as long as it imposed customs rights considered “prohibitive” worldwide.
 
Beijing addressed the Fentanil issue with US commercial negotiators
 
The high representative of the United States for the trade, Jamieson Greer, said yesterday that the Fentanil crisis was first addressed directly in commercial talks between the United States and China.  About Fentanil, Greer said the Popular Republic of China understood the severity of the issue. The issue of using fentanil, a synthetic drug, has become a public health problem in the United States in recent years. The issue has been one of the main points of the tariff confrontation between the two powers, with Washington asking Beijing to repress the illegal production and export of chemicals that allow the substance to manufacture. "There was a surprising commitment to deal with the Fentanil crisis. It was the first time China has understood the magnitude of what is going on in the United States," Greer said. Previously, the representatives of the Popular Republic of China congratulated themselves with what they considered to be substantial progress registered in commercial negotiations with the United States.
 
Gold falls more than 3% after agreement between Washington and Beijing
 
Gold, a secure refuge active in times of uncertainty, fell strongly yesterday, more than 3%, endangering the level of $ 3,200, after the United States and China announced a trade agreement. At 11:00 in Lisbon, the price of gold went down 3.23% to $ 3,217.58, although after the announcement of the agreement, a few minutes after 8:00 am, it fell even more markedly to 3,216.29 dollars. And this after the US and China announced a reduction in tariffs. Specifically, Chinese tariffs will rise from 125% to 10% of US products in the next 90 days. The US will do the same from 145% to 30% of Chinese products, as part of the terms agreed over the weekend to wage the new trade war this year. The agreement between the two main commercial powers drives the dollar, affecting the prices of metals in general. Gold also descends with the reduction of geopolitical tensions, following the ceasefire agreed between India and Pakistan, while Russia and Ukraine can meet Thursday in Istanbul to start a diplomatic way to resolve the conflict. With yesterday's fall, gold is moving away from the current historical maximum of $ 3,414.65, verified on April 21</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 02:20:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Manuel Basilio's Book on Baixo do Monte reissued in Chinese language</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/13/livro-de-manuel-basilio-sobre-baixa-do-monte-reeditado-em-lingua-chinesa/</link><description>The book “Stories and Memories - Baixo do Monte and surroundings”, by Manuel Viseu Basílio, which deals with the history of that specific geographical zone in the city center, will also have a Chinese language version. This reprint will be presented on May 19 at Apomac headquarters.
 
A Chinese language edition of the book “Stories and Memories - Baixo do Monte and around the surroundings” will be launched, by Manuel Viseu Basilio. The Chinese version of the book, whose Portuguese edition had been launched in October 2023, will be presented on May 19, at the headquarters of the Macao Retired, Reformed and Pensioners Association (Apomac). The book will be presented by Lok Po, director of the newspaper or Mun, who also writes the preface.
In a statement, Apomac says that after being launched in Portuguese, Manuel Basilio was also challenged to edit a Chinese language version, "given the interest that may be with the Chinese community in publicizing one of the most striking periods in the history of Macao."
The book deals with the “integration of the Chinese population in the so -called 'Christian city', thus beginning the effective miscegenation of western and eastern cultures, with the removal of the barrier created by the old wall and doors of the city, all living in harmony as neighbors”, describes the press note.
The Baixa do Monte, which the book refers to, is the South Zone of Colina do Monte, ranging from Fortaleza to Rua da Palha, São Domingos and Pedro Nolasco da Silva. This was an area where many Portuguese and Macanese families once lived.
The investigation for the book was based on data related to several families who lived in that area between the mid -nineteenth century and the second half of the twentieth century. In addition to references to macanese or Portuguese families, the book presents biographies of some individualities who lived in Baixa do Monte, namely Chinese traders.
With regard to toponymy, the author addresses some curious or enigmatic designations to various public roads in Baixa do Monte, such as Calçada das Verdados and Santa Filomena Street. Manuel Viseu Basilio also makes a brief description of the temple of Na Tcha, next to the sidewalk of truths, as well as the festivities in honor of that goddess. Finally, the researcher also makes a brief summary of the history of some buildings that existed and others that still exist in the borderfish zone of Baixa do Monte, such as the Capitol Theater.
The topics covered in this book are not restricted to the public or toponymics of that zone, including memories, experiences, uses and customs, as well as stories based on Macao's history, describes Apomac.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Former deposed president Yoon returns to court for insurrection</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/13/ex-presidente-deposto-yoon-volta-a-tribunal-por-insurreicao/</link><description>The former president of South Korea Yoon Suk-Yeol appeared yesterday at the third hearing of the criminal trial for insurrection and abuse of power, at the beginning of the campaign for presidential elections.
Yoon entered Seoul Central District Court around 10:00 am through the main door, and refused to answer the journalists' questions.
The hearing is the first since, on May 1, the South Korea Public Prosecution Service (MP) added the accusation of “abuse of power” in the context of the imposition of martial law on December 3.
The court provides to interrogate a senior head of operation of the Army Special War Command and an assistant commander of the capital's Defense Command as witnesses.
On the night from December 3 to 4, Yoon imposed the martial law unexpectedly, sending the army to block the parliament, dominated by the opposition. However, a few hours later, a high number of deputies managed to meet to vote on the survey of martial law in a crisis that caught the country by surprise.
Se for condenado, Yoon será o terceiro ex-presidente da Coreia do Sul a ser condenado por insurreição, depois de Chun Doo-hwan e Roh Tae-woo, em 1996, por um golpe de Estado efetuado em 1979.
Yoon denied having committed any act of insurrection - an accusation that may result in a conviction to life imprisonment or even the death penalty - in the context of his attempt to impose martial law in December. "To describe an event that lasted just a few hours, which was not violent, and immediately agree to describe the request for dissolution of the National Assembly as an insurrection ... It seems legally unfounded," Yoon said in late April.
The MP accuses Yoon of “wanting to provoke a revolt, with the aim of overthrowing the constitutional order”, noting that the martial law was prepared in advance and that orders were given to the army to cut electricity and depart the windows of Parliament.
The official election campaign for the presidential in the country began yesterday, with opposition leader Lee Jae-Myung, clearly leading the polls. Lee lost the previous election to Yoon for a narrow margin.
The early presidential elections will be held on June 3.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 02:20:17</pubDate></item><item><title>CTT announces new commemorative philatelic emissions and keeps orders for the US</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/13/ctt-anuncia-novas-emissoes-filatelicas-comemorativas-e-mantem-encomendas-para-os-eua/</link><description>The Directorate of Post and Telecommunications Services (CTT) has launched two new postcards to celebrate the “Science of Macau 1” Space Project and the 35th anniversary of the International Association of Portuguese Expression Communications (AICEP), to be held on World Telecommunications Day on 17 May. In addition, the entity took the opportunity to clarify issues related to the expansion of the 4G network and the situation of international orders at a press conference held yesterday.
 
Yesterday, at CTT headquarters, the entity's representatives launched a philatelic emission commemorating the Macau Science Satellite project, reinforcing Macao's commitment to scientific research and international cooperation with Portuguese -speaking countries. The emission will be officially available for purchase on May 17, and celebrates the success of the launch of the MSS-1 satellite held in May 2023.
Developed in partnership with China's National Space Administration, this satellite marks a worldwide advance by allowing the measurement of the low -inclined land magnetic field, equipped with antimagnetic sensors and high precision magnetimeters. The seals portray satellites A and B, while a philatelic block reproduces the moment of launch, made from the Jiuquan launch center.
Products, which include seals of various values, blocks, FDCs and Pagelas, were designed by designer Xiao Yong and have texts prepared by the University of Science and Technology of Macao. This initiative not only celebrates the technological development of the territory, but also reinforces its position as an innovation hub in spatial investigation, promoting its active partner image in international cooperation.
In addition to focusing on science and technology, CTT also decided to promote cooperation and cultural exchange actions in the area of ​​communications, through a joint emission of stamps with Portugal, Angola, Brazil and Cape Verde, to celebrate the 35th anniversary of the International Association of Portuguese Expression Communications (AICEP). This emission, launched during the XXXII Forum of Lusophone Communications, symbolizes the “union and strengthening of ties between Lusophone countries in the area of ​​telecommunications, promoting the exchange of knowledge, technological cooperation and the appreciation of common culture”. With this philatelic promotion, it is intended to promote intentional relations, enhance joint development and highlight the role of Macao as a link between several Portuguese language communities, according to the press release.
The official publication of “Macau Science 1 Satellite” will be launched on May 17. The collection includes 150,000 seals of 2.50 patacas, 150,000 of 6.00 patacas, 150,000 philatelic blocks of 14.00 Patacas, plus 3,000 FDCs of 6.00 Patacas, 3,000 FDCs/B and 2,000 Pagelas of 8.00 Patacas. Products will be available at Central Station and Communications Museum, with commemorative obliteration on launch day.
The release of the “AICEP - 35 years to converge” emission is scheduled for today. The new seal has a cost of 6.00 Patacas and includes 150,000 stamps, 2,000 FDCs and 1,000 page. In addition, there is the 1st day outstanding with seal for 12.00 Patacas and the seal pagela for 14.00 Patacas, available at Central Station, Communications Museum and Rua do Campo, also with commemorative stamp. This is the fourth emission of 2025, after topics such as the lunar year of Cobra and the Macao World Heritage.
At the same time, Macao has been reinforcing his presence in the area of ​​telecommunications through commemorative actions of World Telecommunications Day and the Information Society, instituted on May 17, by the International Telecommunications Union (UIT). These actions include the free distribution of commemorative envelopes, the emission of special stamps and the carrying out of a thematic ceremony entitled “Gender Equality in Digital Transformation”. The main objective is to sensitize the community to the importance of digital inclusion, promoting equal opportunities in access to information and communication technologies, a fundamental step for a more connected and equitable society. In addition, these initiatives aim to warn of the need for greater digital literacy, such as the inclusion of the population in the new 4G networks.
 
4G technology and shipping abroad
 
With regard to communication infrastructure, CTT has clarified that they are actively expanding the 4G internet network, dedicating themselves to raising the population about the need to update their devices to make use of the most powerful, more powerful networks. Many of the citizens are not yet connected to the refers to the highest range network due to the lack of more advanced technology of their personal devices. Most users of the most advanced network are machines or services, but you will still need to introduce the population more actively.
The entity has ensured that it has closely followed the situation of international orders and packages, with particular attention to the United States, which eliminated the exemption of customs rights on small orders from the interior of China and Hong Kong. On the subject, CTT director Derby Lau confirmed that, despite the regular operation of shipping by air, the maritime paths, traditionally made through Hong Kong, are temporarily suspended. This interruption can impact the flow of orders of higher volume or weight, although the service continues to operate normally by air.
In April, the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, even made criticisms on the “abusive imposition of customs taxes on all his business partners, including our country, under several pretexts, which severely devastated the multilateral trade system that has as its core the World Trade Organization, and impaired the stability of the world economic order” after the executive order of Donald Trump on May 2.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 02:17:09</pubDate></item><item><title>João Miguel Barros shows photographs of the performance “To add one meter to an anonymous mountain”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/13/joao-miguel-barros-mostra-fotografias-da-performance-to-add-one-meter-to-an-anonymous-mountain/</link><description>It is inaugurated today in the gallery in Lisbon of the curator and photographer João Miguel Barros, Ochre Space, an exhibition on the performance “to add one to anonymous Mountain”, in which the community artists who became known as “Beijing East Village participated”. The exhibition takes place 30 years after its realization.
 
By the time of the 30th anniversary of the performance of the performance “To Add One Meter to Anonymous Mountain”, João Miguel Barros takes the photographs of the initiative to Lisbon to show them in his gallery, Ochre Space. The exhibition, which also has 22 images of Chinese photographer Rongrong, opens today and is evident until June 21.
In the generation of performance was a group of Chinese artists who, between 1992 and 1995, settled on the outskirts of Beijing, in Dashanzhuang. A community that became known as Beijing East Village and contained artists from different areas - music, painting, photography, etc. Life in the community and artwork was documented precisely by Rongrong, he also resident artist of Beijing East Village.
On May 11, 1995 a dozen community artists - Cang Xin, Duan Yingmei, Gao Yang, Ma Zhongren, Wang Shihua, Zhang Huan, Zhu Ming and Zuoxiao Zuzhou - curated by Kong BU, performed “that stayed in Chinese contemporary art history. And in the history of international performance art, ”says Ochre Space on the room sheet of this exhibition.
The exhibition organized by Ochre Space “is a tribute to an event that is inscribed in all the manuals of Chinese contemporary art and international performative art” and, above all, is “a unique opportunity to see in a single space the sequence of photographs that constitute performance in its entirety”. Under the exhibition it will also be possible to see the performance video. Ochre Space points out that "there is no record that there has been such a complete show in any exposure previously held on this topic."
The curator of this show, João Miguel Barros, states, in the brochure of the exhibition, that "magnetism and the strength emanating from those ten naked bodies lying at the top of a apparently silent mountain will also attract many stakeholders over the years and will continue to resist the passage of time."
Open since 2022, Ochre Space, which is next to the Ajuda Palace in Lisbon, has been dedicated to contemporary photography and video art. The gallery aims to promote the great masters of Asian photography and present photographs and books difficult to find in Portugal. In this space by João Miguel Barros, which also has a library, workshops and lectures are also held, for example.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Timor-Leste expects a new Australian government to reinforce negotiations about Greater Sunrise</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/13/timor-leste-espera-novo-governo-australiano-para-reforcar-negociacoes-sobre-greater-sunrise/</link><description>Timorese Oil Minister and Natural Resources, Francisco Monteiro, said yesterday expects the negotiations about Greater Sunrise with Australia to intensify in the coming weeks after the new Australian government.
 
"The negotiations were very intense before the elections in Australia. In recent months, we can say that the process has been slower because Australia was in the electoral process, and only last week they completed everything," said the minister.
The ruler spoke to journalists on the fringes of a seminar at the University of Dili under World Geology Day.
Australian Prime Minister Anthony Albanese was reelected for a new term in the elections that took place last week. "We believe that within a week or two there will be more intense contacts to restore and intensify negotiations, so that we get results in the near future," said Francisco da Costa Monteiro.
Asked about a concrete date for the beginning of gas production in Timor-Leste, the minister explained that in negotiations there are never right dates. "I would like this year to finish the negotiating process according to our calendar, so that next year we can enter the engineering details, allowing the start of construction in 2027 and, eventually, the beginning of production in 2031 or 2032," he concluded.
Located 150 kilometers from Timor-Leste and 450 kilometers from Darwin, the Greater Sunrise project has been involved in an impasse, with Dili defending the construction of a southern pipeline and WoodSide, the second largest partner of the consortium, to lean to a connection to the unit already existing in Darwin.
Faced with the impasse, the consortium, consisting of the Timorense Timor Gap (56.56%), the operator WoodSide Energy (33.44%) and OSACA Gas (10%), decided to hire a company to do a feasibility study for the project.
The company studied four main options, namely the development of Greater Sunrise to Timor-Leste, for Darwin (Australia), in the Ichthys Gas field, also in Australia and operated by Japanese Inpex, and a new liquefied natural gas installation equally in Australia. "The liquefied Natural Gas of Timor-Leste (TLNG) stands out for predicting lower operating costs and, by allowing better rights and indirect returns for Timor-Leste, will create a major socioeconomic impact in the country," the Timorese government said in December. The study was not released to the press.
The Permanent Maritime Border Agreement between Timor-Leste and Australia states that Greater Sunrise, a shared resource, will have to be divided, with 70% of revenues for Timor-Leste in the event of a country pipeline, or 80% if processing is in Darwin. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 02:20:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong wants to allow national security cases to be tried in China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/13/hong-kong-quer-permitir-que-casos-de-seguranca-nacional-sejam-julgados-na-china/</link><description>The Hong Kong government has announced yesterday that it will propose a new law that allows continental court to judge the trial of national security -related crimes, including betrayal and sedition. The new law aims to create a mechanism that gives the courts of mainland China, at the request of Hong Kong, jurisdiction in crimes considered complex and "if the local government is not able to effectively implement the provisions of the law." This mechanism was already foreseen in the National Security Law promulgated in 2020 by Beijing to end Hong Kong's dissent after pro-democracy protests shaken the semi-autonomous region in 2019. The cases that can be covered by the new mechanism are those involving “third countries”, which may open up to the door to the defendants, including foreign citizens, to the news portal, according to the news portal, according to the news portal, according to the news portal, according to the news portal, according to the news portal, according to the news portal, according to the news portal, according to the news portal, according to the news portal Hong Kong Free Press.
In April 2024, the Hong Kong court sentenced the Portuguese Joseph John to five years in prison for the crime of incitement to subversion, within the 2020 National Security Act. Among other crimes, John was considered guilty of defending on the Internet from the neighboring city of Shenzhen, to free 12 Hong Kong activists who had tried to flee from boat to boat Taiwan, a group that included Kok Tsz-Lun, with double Portuguese and Chinese nationality. The National Security Protection Office, created by Beijing in Hong Kong, said in a statement that the new law is necessary in the light of “existing risks to national security, given the difficult geopolitical situation”. The proposal will include new crimes, including obstructing the performance of cabinet functions, which can be punished with fines up to $ 500,000 from Hong Kong and prison penalties up to seven years.
Hong Kong's secretary for court, Paul Lam Ting-Kwok, confirmed yesterday to journalists that the new law was related to the trade war between China and the United States. "Given the hostile actions taken by some foreign countries against China and also Hong Kong, there is clearly a need to ensure that our national security legal system is perfected," Lam said. The secretary spoke after a session of the Executive Board, where Mrs Doreen Kong Yuk-Foon asked if the proposal would not violate the Basic Law and international treaties. "Of course we are very concerned about human rights and freedoms," said Paul Lam. "In terms of law, there is absolutely no doubt. Human rights and freedom provisions will not be affected at all," said the leader.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 02:20:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Government guarantees security of personal data after the installation of cameras in day care centers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/13/governo-garante-seguranca-dos-dados-pessoais-apos-instalacao-de-camaras-nas-creches/</link><description>Authorities guarantee the protection of children's privacy after the future installation of video surveillance systems in more spaces in day care centers. The direction of personal data protection services said it will ensure the security of recording data. The system must be encrypted and cannot be connected to the internet. The contents of the day care chambers belongs to IAS, which is also responsible for overseeing access to recordings.
 
The extended installation of video surveillance systems in day care centers is “responding to the expectations of society” taking into account the “public interest”, defends the direction of personal data protection services (DSPDP), in a recent granting of the authorization to the program of installation of more chambers in the day care centers presented by the Institute of Social Action (IAS).
DSPDP has again ensured its commitment to protect the security of personal data collected in day care centers, stressing that it established a “reasonable balance” between the rights and legitimate interests of different parts. Speaking to the newspaper or Mun, DSPDP also pointed out that IAS will “adopt certain special security measures” to avoid data escapes.
It is recalled that the IAS program provides for the installation of the video surveillance system in more spaces for day care centers, especially in rest rooms and areas of activities, as the government will implement from the third quarter of the year. IAS had explained that interested day care centers must submit requests to the body to obtain the authorization and install the cameras according to the video recording agreements issued by IAS.
The proposal of this measure arose following a case of death of a four -month baby in 2023, in an establishment of child care in the mud, who died after a nap. The case raised the company's concern about the service of day care centers and the respective supervision.
In this context, DSPDP said it had authorized the installation of cameras in day care centers after analyzing the legal grounds and interests of children's development and security, as well as the fact that society has increasing expectations as to the quality of day care centers services.
 
Video content belongs to IAS
 
According to the document on the authorization released on the Electronic Portal of DSPDP, the body reiterated that day care centers who adhere to the program are subject to IAS supervision and must comply with the directions issued by IAS. "The kindergartens is a subcontractor and does not have the discretionary power regarding the purpose and method of processing the data recorded on video," he said. That is, the content of the videos recorded in the rest and activities in the day care centers belongs to IAS.
The DSPDP also stipulates that the program day care centers are required to notify parents or children in education of the children registered in the establishment of Video Vigilance.
The video surveillance system should avoid filming any kind of nudity of children, and cannot be associated with any wireless or remote control device and should not be connected to the internet.
The document, which is not yet available in Portuguese, also mentioned IAS by pointing out that data obtained from the video surveillance system “is stored in an encrypted electronic system or support”, whose access to information is subject to the use of passwords, being the firewall and regularly updated antivirus programs.
"The recording screen cannot be placed in a public place and the system can only be accessed by designated personnel when there are physical injuries to children or when there is evidence of suspicion that children are being mistreated in day care centers," he said.
In addition, day care centers should notify the IAS of all accesses within two business days, including the reasons for access, the scope of the access content, the date and the time and the person who has done the work. IAS, in this case, should assess whether access to information is in accordance with the mechanism and, if it is defaulting, express its objection to day care centers and communicate the incident to DSPDP for follow -up.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 02:20:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing wants Macau to optimize the relationship between the Executive and the Legislative Power</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/13/pequim-quer-que-macau-optimize-a-relacao-entre-o-poder-executivo-e-o-poder-legislativo/</link><description>Xia Baolong visited the Legislative Assembly (AL) on Sunday, where she met with the deputies. At the meeting, the director of Hong Kong's work office and Macau of the China Communist Party Central Committee and Cabinet Director for Hong Kong and Macao State Councils said Macau should “take another step in optimizing the relationship between Executive and Legislative Power, in the sense of respect and mutual support, to enhance the institutional advantages of the predominance of executive branch”.
Quoted on the AL press note, Beijing's guardian also said that the region should be prepared for adversity, "doing well the work of accelerating Hengqin-Macau integration and the proper diversification of Macao's economy."
Before the deputies, the Hong Kong and Macau's Office Director praised the work done by the AL, namely the timely elaboration of “important laws”, such as the defense of state security and the promotion of healthy and ordered development of the game.
During the meeting, Kou Hoi in mentioned that Xia Baolong's visit to Macau "fully aired the high attention, the strong support and the deep affection that President Xi Jinping and the Central Government attribute to Macao." The deputies also presented opinions and suggestions for matters such as Hengqin-Macau integration in the next phase, “for the promotion of the proper diversification of the economy of Macao”; the intensification of “virtuous interaction between the executive and legislative powers”, which creates “an effective mechanism of communication”; and the reinforcement “of Macau's advantages to serve the needs of the country”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 02:20:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing receives Lula and other Latin American leaders to reinforce ties against Trump</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/13/pequim-recebe-lula-e-outros-lideres-latino-americanos-para-reforcar-lacos-contra-trump/</link><description>Beijing yesterday received several Latin American leaders, starting with the President of Brazil, on the eve of a diplomatic forum aimed at reinforcing relations with the region, in the face of commercial tensions with Washington.
 
Some Latin American leaders are already in China, such as Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva, who arrived in the capital on Saturday for a five-day state visit. Since returning to power in early 2023, the 79 -year -old has been working to improve the country's relations with both Beijing and Washington.
Symbol of strong bilateral relations, Brazilian exports to China exceeded $ 94 billion in 2024, according to United Nations data.
As an agricultural power in South America, Brazil exports mainly soybeans and other raw materials to China. In the opposite direction, the Asian giant sells semiconductors, phones, vehicles and medicines.
Yesterday, Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi spoke in Beijing with Cuban counterpart Bruno Rodriguez Parrilla.
The Asian giant has intensified economic and political cooperation with Latin American countries in recent years and expects them to join forces in the face of the imposition of tariffs on imports by US President Donald Trump.
An approach that will be celebrated today with the opening in Beijing of the summit between China and the community of Latin American and Caribbean states (Celac), a regional intergovernmental organization.
The meeting is an opportunity to evaluate the relations between the two blocks in the context of the trade war launched by Trump and Washington's pressure to contain Beijing's influence on Latin America.
Two thirds of the Latin American countries have already adhered to a track, a route, China's main commercial infrastructure construction program (bridges, airports, ports, roads), carried out mainly in developing countries.
In a sign of the growing weight of the Asian giant, China has supplanted the United States as the main commercial partner of countries such as Brazil, Peru and Chile.
Other expected participants in the China-Celac Forum include Colombian President Gustavo Petro and Chilean President Gabriel Boric.
Last week, Gustavo Petro announced that he would sign, during the trip to China, a letter of intent for the country to join a track, a route.
Chinese leader Xi Jinping is also expected to speak at the opening of the China-Celac Forum, this Tuesday.
Chinese foreign assistant minister Miao Deyu said on Sunday that Beijing "has always addressed the development of Latin China-América Relations from a long-term strategic perspective." "The peoples of Latin America and Caribbean intend to build their own destination, not to serve as a backyard to any country," said Miao, in reference to the United States. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 02:20:15</pubDate></item><item><title>SMEs suffer from online commerce and shopping in mainland China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/13/pme-sofrem-com-comercio-online-e-compras-na-china-continental/</link><description>After the Covid-19 pandemic, with residents, often buying online or frequently traveling across the border, difficulties are higher for small and medium enterprises.
 
Official statistics account for a decline in billing, especially in the retail sector, with small and medium enterprises (SMEs) to suffer more and more. The situation is better for business that bets more on tourists, but remains far from the values ​​prior to 2019, the sector sources contacted by the end point say.
Terence (name by which he prefers to be identified) from the Vintage Market store says the times have not been so easy for the business. It opened in 2014 and sells secondhand clothing, chosen by itself and comes, above all, from the United States and Japan, despite also having for sale accessories from around the world. "We have been stable every year, but the main problem is that there are many residents who prefer to spend money in other places instead of Macao," he says.
In his opinion, everything changed during the pandemic. "We are only with a median business level in these last two years," he says. Overall, says the retailer, it is an issue that has affected Macau's small and medium businesses, especially those who are linked to the flap. “It has great impact when all residents choose to go outside the territory to spend,” he says.
 
What is happening?
 
For economist Henry Law, there are two important reasons that explain these results. On the one hand, there is a change in the consumption pattern. “People prefer to buy online, instead of doing it in person,” he says, explaining that this necessarily affects the SMEs. “People started gaining the habit of buying online and we were very familiar with the various online shopping channels,” says Henry Law.
Secondly, with the economy not yet in the same values ​​that was before the covid-19 pandemic, people "earn less, especially those who previously worked in the game sector." Therefore, with the loss of purchasing power and, in general, with the slightest confidence in consumption, people have become “more conservative in purchases”, harming the situation for small and medium enterprises. “We don't want to spend and if we do, we buy online,” summarizes the economist.
Then, as people found themselves confined to the territory during this time today, as they have an opportunity they try to go out and do something interesting. "That's why we return most often to mainland China," he says. In addition, however, some measures that facilitate travel to the other side of the border have emerged. “It was at this time that some policies related to the large bay emerged to improve the circulation and passage of borders,” he says. “We can now try to drive our own vehicle across the border,” he says as an example.
Overall, he concludes, this greater convenience in traveling to the rapid development of the retail sector in mainland China is not good for small and medium -sized companies in Macao.
 
More difficulties today than before the pandemic
 
In the opinion of economist José Luís de Sales Marques, the difficulties that small and medium businesses are facing Macau today are superior to those that existed during, or even before the pandemic.
On the one hand, the opening of a market around Macau has been one of the great responsible for the difficulties of local SMEs. “The cities of the Great Bay receive a flow of Macao residents who will consume there, purchase products, go to restaurants, resort to services,” he says, noting that prices are often more competitive across the border. In fact, in the territory, it is difficult to sell products at prices as low as in mainland China. "The high value of rent is an element of great lack of elasticity in prices and then we have the problem of labor, imported from abroad," he says, explaining: "Once we have difficulties in giving in this workforce, which is more affordable, and, on the other hand, we also know that the cost of investment in certain types of establishments, namely restaurants, is high, everything is expensive here, return of invested capital is complicated."
But there are also other factors. For example, “paradigm changes regarding game”, which resulted in a decrease in the weight of the VIP sector in the area. "There are many workers linked to this game sector that are in a very distinct economic situation from that they had in 2019 when the business went on stern," he says. Therefore, internally, there is now a “layer of the population whose income is not the same ones they had before”. And before, many SMEs, especially those linked to restoration and some products considered expensive, were very associated with this sector. "Some of these companies lived a lot at the expense of this clientele, which used to attend these sites and sometimes consumed thousands of patacas," he says.
 
Tourism does not pay
 
Diogo Vieira, manager of Portuguese Macau, a brewery that is part of the Portuguese group, does not complain about the business, given its location. "The brand holds two companies: Portuguese and butter, which opened in January this year," he says.
In the territory for 10 years, the starter of the brewery was not easy. “It was the positioning of the brand and adjustment to the local culture, we had to adapt,” he says. After this phase, it all started to go well to the Covid-19 pandemic. "We managed to stand the boat, but even at the end of the pandemic, there was a need to end the local partner, who was the landlord of the space, and we had to look for another place," he says.
By moving to a place closer to Rua do Cunha, in Taipa, at the end of April 2023, the business became better. “We are closer to a focus of tourism,” he says.
In fact, the manager considers that it is in residential areas that small and medium -sized companies suffer. “Where it feels the most difficulty is in areas where there is not so much tourism,” he says. “The 600,000 people from Macao are not at all enough for so much offer,” he says. Therefore, businesses with a more local market component will be passing “more difficulties”.
There are some advantages for small businesses more dedicated to tourism when compared to other SMEs. "These have reasonable operational profits, are located in tourist areas and helps compensate for the lack of demand for residents," says Sales Marques. Still, even in these cases, there are differences in relation to the pre-pandemic period. "There is a new trend in the tourism market, a certain layer of younger tourists, more linked to social networks, which do not come to Macau to consume much, is a relatively economic visit," he says. In addition, the “economic situation that is living in mainland China, with the resumption of consumer confidence not yet to reach the pre-pound levels and a certain retraction as to the volume of each tourist, on average”.
 
What can be done
 
There are some measures that have been adopted by the government over the last few years and there are new support plans on the way. For example, in April this year, in the context of the government lines, the Executive launched a Bank Credit Bottle Plan for Small and Medium Enterprises. Another of the measures of the business forum presented aims at the expansion of “SME 2025 digitization services”, with the increase of current 900 vacancies to 1500.
In Henry Law's opinion, some government initiatives, such as “the distribution of consumer vouchers to people, who can only be used on the weekend, can help,” but are only transitory. There are, however, other measures that may be more effective. “SMEs should be updated and seek to improve their services, introducing quality services to be more competitive,” he says.
One of the problems goes through the SMEs are selling the same one that can get online on certain platforms, but twice the value. “They need to change this, perhaps they can offer consumers better after-sales services, higher product quality to reinforce their competitiveness,” he says. Still, it admits, it is a process that takes time. "Local SMEs can also offer e-commerce services, so that they can also sell online," he says. “One of the great advantages of SMEs compared to online sales platforms is the ability to receive the fastest product,” he adds. And if so, consumers will most easily choose to buy online at places. Still, it admits, it is very difficult for SMEs to compete with certain online platforms that even provide “free delivery” services in Macau, regardless of sales volume. "The SMEs have to differentiate themselves, to ask for a better margin for the service they guarantee," he says.
Also economist Sales Marques believes that there is a change from the SMEs themselves. "They have to adapt to the new conditions of the market and, if they may, some will disappear, but others will be able to adapt," he says.
The analyst also argues that SMEs with “characteristics that differentiate them” have a greater hypothesis of survival. "Those that are very generic, that remain in the market just because they sell cheap, whose market are non-resident workers or others with small consumer power, which nowadays go, especially on the weekend, consume for Zhuhai and surroundings, these types of companies have no big hypotheses in the future and will have to find themselves," he argues.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 02:19:15</pubDate></item><item><title>China expects lasting and binding peace agreement</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/13/china-espera-acordo-de-paz-duradouro-e-vinculativo/</link><description>China said yesterday that it expects a lasting and binding peace agreement to end the war in Ukraine after Russian President Vladimir Putin's proposal to open direct negotiations between Kiev and Moscow. "We hope that the parties involved will continue to use dialogue and negotiations to reach a fair, lasting and binding peace agreement that is acceptable to all parties involved," said Lin Jian, spokesman for the China Ministry of Foreign Affairs.
Vladimir Putin proposed, on Saturday night, that Ukraine started direct negotiations between the parties on Thursday in Istanbul, a city that welcomed, in March 2022, the first and unique negotiations between the parts in more than three years of war.
Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky reacted to the proposal considering it "a first step" of Kremlin to end the war, but insisted that first there must be a ceasefire before Ukraine feels to negotiate.
Russia's proposal was presented a few hours after Ukraine and the European allies demanded from Moscow to agree with a total and unconditional ceasefire for at least 30 days, otherwise it will face new economic sanctions.
This requirement arose after a meeting held on Saturday in Kiev among the heads of state and government of Ukraine, France, Germany, the United Kingdom and Poland, the so -called “coalition of the disposed”.
The Russian proposal was also looked at with suspicion by the Ukraine European allies that required any conversations to be preceded by a lasting ceasefire.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 02:20:14</pubDate></item></channel></rss>