<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/30/caeal-acompanhou-18-queixas-sobre-propaganda-eleitoral-nenhuma-encaminhada-ao-mp/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Hotel occupancy rate was 89.1% in the first half</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/30/taxa-de-ocupacao-hoteleira-foi-de-891-no-primeiro-semestre/</link><description>Between January and June this year, the hotel occupancy rate in Macau increased 5.1% in annual terms and almost reached 90%. According to data revealed yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), the region's hotels received more than 7.2 million people in the period in question, stressing the growth of the number of international guests.

In the first half of this year, the average occupancy rate of the hotel rooms of Macao hotel establishments was 89.1%, an increase of 5.1 percentage points for the same period of the previous year. The data were revealed yesterday in a statement by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC).
At the end of June, there were 147 hotel establishments to provide public accommodation services (four more, in annual terms), providing a total of 45,000 guest rooms to tourists entering Macau (less 3.8%). The average occupancy rate was 89.1%, which represents a growth of 5.1% compared to last year's identical period. The occupancy rate of 5 -star hotels was the most significant (92.5%, more 6.6%in annual terms), followed by the rate of 3 -star hotels (85.4%, plus 4.4%) and 4 star (83.1%, plus 2.7%).
Between January and June, hotel establishments hosted 7,202,000 individuals, less than in the same period last year. As usual, most guests came from the interior of China (5,349,000 people, plus 0.8% in annual terms), although the number of international guests recorded an increase of 8.6% to 589,000.
Within this group, guests from South Korea (169,000), Japan (48,000), Malaysia (44,000) and India (41,000) are highlighted, with respective growth of 13.3%, 16.1%, 7.3%and 5.2%. In the opposite direction, guests from Hong Kong (879,000) fell 8.5% compared to the same period as 2024. As last year, the average permanence period remained at 1.7 nights.
The DSEC also calculated the entrances of excionalists in the territory, which reports a descent of 2.3%to 963,000, in annual terms. While the number of visitors in excursions from the interior of China (813,000) fell by 6%in homologous terms, international visitors in excursions (117,000) ascended 12.2%, with South Korea visitors (51,000 of the total) visitor with a significant increase of 19.7%.
Already the number of exits of residents of Macao who acquired services in agencies for travel abroad corresponded to 267,000 in the semester under analysis, rising 3.9% compared to the same period. 193,000 of these exits - that is, about 72.3% - were from residents who traveled on excursions in the interior of China.
Looking only at June, it is found that the average rate of occupation of guest rooms was 88.4%, plus 5.6%over the same month last year, and that hotel establishments hosted 1,197,000 individuals, plus 4.7%. The number of visitors from visitors who arrived on excursions to Macao was only 99,000 last June, a 27.5% decrease that DSEC justifies with the preference of tourists from the interior of China to enter the region with an individual visa.
Once again, international tour visitors register an 8.6% increase in homologous terms for 18,000. Unlike the first semester balance, June observes a 5.8% reduction in the number of exits abroad acquired by Macao residents in travel agencies.</description><pubDate>2025-07-30 00:00:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Fifth case of chikungunya fever requires authorities to reinforce prevention measures</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/30/quinto-caso-de-febre-de-chikungunya-obriga-autoridades-a-reforcarem-medidas-de-prevencao/</link><description>Health services count, for now, five cases of chikungunya fever, three of them in workers of the workshops in zone A of the new landfills, which led the authorities to reinforce disease control measures in that area. Macau and Zhuhai have also been coordinating efforts to control the disease.

Health services have so far diagnosed five imported cases of chikungunya fever. The increase in the risk of disease transmission is leading Macao authorities, together with neighboring regions, to reinforce disease prevention measures.
The fifth case of chikungunya fever detected by the authorities was diagnosed with a 70 -year -old woman, resident of Macao and retired, who, between 14 and 18 of this month, had been in Foshan. Last Friday, the elderly manifested joint pain in the right leg and took medicines on its own initiative, not resorting to medical appointment. On Sunday morning, rashes were detected in the right knee and arms, and the next day the woman went to the emergency room of the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center. After analysis of the blood sample, the presence of the chikungunya virus was confirmed. Currently, the patient is in a stable state and is admitted to the public hospital for medical treatment.
Of the five cases diagnosed in the region, three have to do with workers of workshops in zone A of new landfills, so the authorities say that "the possibility of spread within the works of works is not excluded."
Thus, between Monday and Tuesday, a series of preventive measures were established, including case research, sensitization and education, inspection of the mosquito proliferation source and mosquito elimination reinforcement, among others.
On Monday, health services sent personnel to the shipyards concerned to proceed with the face-to-face inquiry to workers and dissemination and education, through proactive research of suspicious cases and the harvest of blood at the site, with a view to undergoing analysis. After laboratory analysis of the three collected blood samples, chikungunya fever infection was excluded.
In addition, a comprehensive inspection was performed on the sources of mosquito proliferation, namely stagnant waters in the workshops, and some sources of mosquito proliferation were immediately removed. The Directorate of Public Works Services (DSOP) also exhorted those responsible for the establishments to reinforce, as soon as possible, the management of mosquito proliferation vectors and the elimination of mosquitoes.
Health services stress that a “narrow connection” has been established with the authorities in the interior of China, through a joint prevention and control mechanism, immediate communication of cases related to transfronist activities, definition of risk zones where cases are found and the time of permanence in Macao, developing prevention and response work, as well as following the epidemiological situation in Macao and regions closely in Macao and regions neighbors.
Due to the “increased risk of transmission” of chikungunya fever, Macao and Zhuhai authorities held a reunion for conferencing on the joint work of disease prevention and control. At this meeting, representatives on both parties evaluated the risks and also presented prevention and control strategies.
Given the frequent circulation between residents of the two regions, the way the border stations can collaborate with prevention and control work in general was discussed. In addition, profound exchanges and shares of experiences on mosquito and personnel vectors were carried out, mosquito elimination work, sensitization and education, among others. In a statement, health services say that the parts have reached consensus to develop the joint prevention and control mechanism, including information sharing and joint epidemics investigation, “continuously evaluating the development of chikungunya fever, admitting prevention and control measures to join the health and safety of residents of both regions”.</description><pubDate>2025-07-30 00:00:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Caeal accompanied 18 complaints about electoral propaganda, none sent to the MP</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/30/caeal-acompanhou-18-queixas-sobre-propaganda-eleitoral-nenhuma-encaminhada-ao-mp/</link><description>The Legislative Assembly Electoral Affairs Committee has so far received 18 cases of complaints relating to irregularities in the campaign and also defamation, some of which have been filed after appreciation. CAEAL confirmed that it has not received any appeal from the decision on the candidacies and rejected a possible high abstention. As for Chikungunya's outbreak, the commission said it believed the disease “won't affect the elections much”.

From the beginning of the period of the prohibition of election campaign at the end of last month to date, 18 cases of illegal propaganda complaints have been registered, the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) said yesterday.
Seng Ioi Man, president of Caeal, said the cases were referred by different entities and most complaints were related to the irregularity of the campaign or advertising about legislative elections, but also cases of defamation.
"Caeal analyzed the cases. After appreciation, some were not considered as an irregularity of the campaign […] and other cases, which have evidence, have already been referred to the authorities to continue the follow -up," said the official.
According to Caeal's information, some complaints were due to news coverage published on June 27, the day that the election campaign began, about the presentation of the lists the day before, that Caeal concluded that they were not part of the election campaign.
"As for the number recorded so far, yes, there have been some cases, but not many. The situation is optimistic," said Seng, ensuring that the authorities will continue to follow the cases to guarantee legality, impartiality and the justice of the election. He considers, however, that the awareness of the public integrity has been increasing.
Seng Ioi Man spoke yesterday to the sidwhwhere of another Caeal meeting, where he admitted that the illegal advertising complaints also involve the admitted lists for the elections scheduled for September 14, but refused to advance more details. "Since there are some cases we are still treating, it would not be appropriate to announce here," said the official. However, he said that the cases are under investigation and, therefore, have not yet reached the phase of referring to the prosecutor.
In this context, Caeal reiterated that it continues to oversee the acts related to public incitement to blank or null voting and also not to vote, indicating that “serious cases” have not been detected, but the work continues and there are mechanisms to combat these situations, even if they are practiced outside Macao. "Law enforcement entities have effective cooperation with abroad authorities to deal with cases," he said.

Vote to vote
 
Some comments have been circulating on social networks, namely in news publications, which warn of the lack of willingness to vote. However, Caeal has rejected that there may be high abstention in the elections.
"We have not yet noticed this situation, but we will continue to do the work […] to create better conditions, allowing the lists to have a better environment to publicize their political program […], ensuring that voters can have access to this information," he said.
In addition, Seng Ioi Man confirmed that the period of contestation to Caeal's decision has passed and the commission has not received any appeal or complaints about the acceptance or refusal of the candidates.

“Unjust” mosquitoes on elections
 
Seng Ioi Man was also asked about the possible impact of the recent outbreak of Chikungunya fever in neighboring regions. The judge also understands that the diseases transmitted by mosquitoes "will not bring big problem" to legislative elections because the transmission is not through people. "I think this disease will not greatly affect our work, and it will not affect the elections too," he said.
Seng Ioi Man said it gives great importance to public health and also the safety of voting assemblies, including facilities within spaces.
It is recalled that in the 2021 Legislative Assembly elections, a 57.62% abstention rate was recorded and Tong Hio Fong, then CAEAL President, argued that the main reason for abstention was pandemic, as well as the storms that "would have affected the will of voters." The official appointed at the time that the exclusion of candidates considered non -patriotic was not responsible for the low influx, but the epidemic measures.
The period of electoral propaganda will take place between August 30 and September 12. Caeal announced that it will hold an opening event on the day of the election campaign, which was not held in the past election due to the pandemic. Authorities will also install electoral propaganda panels in 25 places in Macau and make 18 places available for election campaign events.
CAEAL has defined the conception of the voting report for direct suffrage, increasing the space between the squares where voters stamp, in an A4 -size paper with the names and logos of the six candidate lists, the number of competitors to the lowest direct suffrage in history.</description><pubDate>2025-07-30 00:01:40</pubDate></item></channel></rss>