<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/07/taipa-village-cultural-association-apresenta-exposicao-de-pintura-chinesa-em-leques/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Beijing must prepare for any Washington financial offensive</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/07/pequim-deve-preparar-se-para-eventual-ofensiva-financeira-de-washington/</link><description>The prominent Chinese economist Lian Ping warned of the risks of an eventual US offensive against China in the financial domain, but considered that a total blockade of Chinese access to the global financial system would be difficult to realize.
In a rehearsal published this week, Lian, who chairs the Guangkai Industrial Research Institute and is also president of the China Economists Forum, stressed that the most feared scenario - the exclusion of China from the SWIFT system or the freezing of its currency reservations - would imply high costs and risks to Washington and the international financial system itself.
"The exclusion of China from Swift is not an easy task. The Chinese economy is too great to ignore," Lian wrote, pointing out that although the US does not directly control the consortium based in Belgium, the US domain over the Clearing House System (Clearing House) gives Washington a considerable influence.
The economist recalled that, contrary to what happened to Iran or Russia, there is no legal basis or international legitimacy at this time for a removal from Swift China.
Beijing and Washington, however, roam a prolonged trade and technological war, which has already involved the imposition of heavy customs rates by Washington on China goods and restrictions on high technology supply. Beijing retaliated with rates of equal value and restrictions on the supply of rare land minerals, but fears that the United States could impose financial sanctions, which would have a disastrous impact on Chinese foreign trade, mainly made in dollars.
In this case, the Asian country would have no equivalent response capacity, given the “marginal weight of the Chinese currency, Yuan, and the Chinese financial system at the international level”. Lian Ping recalled, however, that many of the countries that make up international payment systems have deep economic relations with China, which would bring them “serious damage” if such a measure was implemented.
The economist also stressed that forced exclusion from China could accelerate the development of alternative systems, such as the CIPS (Cross-Border Interbank Payment System) system in operation, and reinforces the “global trend” of reducing dollar dependence, which would weaken the position of the US currency in the medium term.
Regarding the hypothesis of freezing Chinese assets by the United States, the economist considered that this scenario would only be plausible in a context of military conflict declared between the two countries, as with Japan in 1941 or China during the Korea War.</description><pubDate>2025-07-07 02:25:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Companhia do Chapitô brings “Júlio César” and theater workshops to Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/07/companhia-do-chapito-traz-julio-cesar-e-oficinas-de-teatro-a-macau/</link><description>21
Between September 20 and 23, the Chapitô Theater Company comes to Macau to present more than a theatrical experience. In addition to the dramatization of the play “Júlio César”, the group will conduct physical and visual theater workshops where participants will be able to learn improvisation techniques, character creation and nonverbal communication, more centered on intuition than on the script.
 
The Portuguese theater group Companhia do Chapitô will present in Macau the play “Júlio César” on September 20, at 20:00, at the Macao Cultural Center. In the following days, from September 21 to 23, the same group will coordinate a series of physical and visual theater workshops at Casa Garden, intended for participants with or without experience in theater.
The initiative has the support of Somos! - Portuguese Language Communication Association (Somos - ACLP), which reaffirmed yesterday in a press release its “commitment” to “Portuguese language and culture promotion” in Macau, once again providing a stage for “intercultural dialogue and artistic development in the region”.
The show “Júlio César” is the first point in the programming of the artistic group, scheduled to debut on September 20, at 20:00, at Black Box I of the Macao Cultural Center. This is the 39th collective creation of the Portuguese Company, following the tight, satirical and socially conscious, in the limbo between fiction and reality, which characterizes the majority of previous pieces. On the Chapitô page, it can be read that the show is somewhat “between historical reconstitution, the documentary and parody”, taking as inspiration the life of Julius Caesar as narrated “by the great storytellers, from Plutarco to Shakespeare”.
"If he was a tyrant who deserved to die or a brutally murdered hero, come the devil and choose. Here there are no heroes or villains, there are circumstances and cunning people who do for life. There are also less cunning people who do what they send them. And virtuous people who do what has to be done." Somos - ACLP continues: "faithful to their physical theater style, actors use body, movement and gesture to create characters and convey emotions universally, allowing an affordable experience to different audiences."
The piece will be presented in Portuguese and subtitled in Chinese, lasting approximately 90 minutes. At the end of the experience, there will be “conversation and debate sessions” between the artists and the audience, in order to promote “direct cultural exchange” and the “exchange of ideas and reflections”. Tickets have 200 Patacas and are already available at the "Online" Macauticket Ticket.
In turn, the theater workshops will take place on September 21, 22 and 23, at the Casa Garden House of the Oriente Foundation, with the maximum capacity of 20 participants. The sessions will be conducted in English by the trainers Jorge Cruz, Pedro Diogo and Susana Nunes, and the translation to Chinese is also made available. Registrations can be made on the Somos - ACLP page, where you can enjoy a 10% discount by the end of July.
In these sessions, both actors and amateur will have the opportunity to “explore the possibilities of interaction and fusion between different forms of artistic expression”, learning how to build “physical and visual” narratives and characters that go beyond the “spoken text” that is in the scripts. It is intended, with these strategies, to reinforce the idea of ​​theater as something physical, improvised and cemented in “techniques of characterization, use of space and development of archetypes and psychological profiles”-concepts well based on methodologies and the artistic view of the Portuguese group.
The Chapitô Company was founded in 1996, with almost 40 original creations presented in Portugal and around the world and numerous awards and distinctions. The presentation of this most recent piece, “Júlio César”, is sponsored by the Fund for the Development of Culture of the Government of MSAR and the support of the Portuguese Institute of the East (IPOR) and the Oriente Foundation in Macao.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Beijing tries to end the price war that threatens the industry of electric vehicles</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/07/pequim-tenta-por-fim-a-guerra-de-precos-que-ameaca-industria-dos-veiculos-electricos/</link><description>Chinese authorities signaled this week that they intend to end the disordered competition in the electric vehicle sector, at a time when the price war between manufacturers threatens the sustainability of industry.
 
The alert comes at a time of strong sales growth, but also of increasing fears of over -supply and viability of many of the new manufacturers that emerged in the country. China is the largest car market in the world, the result of an industrial strategy driven by Beijing, which has driven the transition to electric vehicles.
BYD market leader announced that it sold 2.1 million vehicles in the first six months of the year, 31% more than in the same period of 2024. Almost half of these sales correspond to 100% electric vehicles, and the remaining hybrids, according to data released by the company.
The manufacturer has stopped producing cars with internal combustion engines in 2022, but has been criticized for the launch of successive price cuts, the latest in May, which took several competitors to follow the example. The president of manufacturer Great Wall Motors, Wei Jianjun, then warned that the current trajectory threatens the entire industry.
The Chinese government has committed, however, to combat what it designates “Involution”-a form of exhaustive and unproductive competition, which has become characteristic of various sectors in China, including teaching and technological sector.
Several entities have warned the risks of the price war, now in its fourth consecutive year. The Chinese Association of Automobile Manufacturers called on healthy competition, while the Ministry of Industry and Information Technologies said the current situation represents an obstacle to the sustainable development of the sector.
Abroad, Chinese builders try to compensate for export margins erosion. BYD more than doubled sales outside China in the first half to 464,000 units. However, it faces growing barriers: the United States and the European Union have imposed tariffs on electric vehicles manufactured in China, alleging unfair competition due to state subsidies.
The debate intensified after Wei Jianjun's statements, who compared the situation of the automotive industry to that of Evergrande-giant of the real estate sector whose bankruptcy shook the Chinese economy. "The" Evergrande "of the automobile sector already exists, just hasn't burst yet," he said.
BYD reacted with indignation. “I am confused, annoyed and this is ridiculous,” wrote Li Yunfei, the company's brand director on social networks, rejecting any resemblance to the collapse of the real estate sector.
The following month, 17 manufacturers, including BYD, signed a commitment to pay suppliers within 60 days - an unprecedented measure that could relieve financial pressure on the supply chain. So far, it was common practice to postpone payments for months, often with short -term debt instead of money, replicating mechanisms used by real estate promoters such as Evergrande. "The 60-day commitment is a direct government response against destructive competition," said Cui Dongshu, secretary general of the Chinese passenger cars association.
Analysts warn that the impact of these measures may be decisive to stabilize prices and avoid a systemic crisis similar to that of the real estate sector. "Let's see to what extent these initiatives are able to reverse the pricing trend and how it will affect demand in the next quarters," concluded Jing Yang, director of the Fitch Ratings Financial Notation Agency. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-07 02:25:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Government intends to legislate activities of influencers and online advertising</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/07/governo-pretende-legislar-actividades-de-influenciadores-e-publicidade-online/</link><description>The government will review the advertising activity law to introduce the regulation of new advertising models, especially online advertising. The public consultation document suggests that the presenters, often influencers, on online promotion and live marketing activities, are supervised under the law. It is also proposed that advertising ambassadors must promote goods or services “based on facts”.
 
Authorities have launched a public consultation on the review of the “Advertising Acting Law” and proposed to legislate the activities of advertising influencers and ambassadors, as well as online advertising, which include 'live marketing', ie live promotional actions on online platforms involving direct interaction with the target audience.
The public consultation document, presented by the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) last Friday, proposes to “clarify that participants in online promotion and live marketing activities, such as advertisers, advertising agencies, platform owners and presenters, are subject to the advertising activity law and must comply with their provisions when their acts constitute advertising”.
The government justifies the need to add standards for online advertising, as it has “become common” that traders use social networking platforms and applications to promote or market goods, using live marketing or ‘live commerce’. He also explained that the elaboration of the rules was based on online advertising regulations in the interior of China, whose 'digital marketing' is increasingly popular and used in the territory.
The public consultation of the Advertising Act, which has been in force for almost 36 years, has already started and will end on August 2. Yau Yun Wah, director of DSEDT, pointed out that, due to changes in the economic activities of the various sectors and technological evolution, the contents, forms of dissemination and means used in current advertising “are significantly different” from those of the past.
Thus, the executive intends to change the law to "better correspond to the needs of Macao's socioeconomic development." Authorities guarantee that they have heard opinions from the business sector to start the legislative review work, taking into account the legislative experience of other jurisdictions, including the interior of China and Portugal in the field of advertising regulation.
 
Protect consumer confidence
 
The consultation document also establishes provisions to clarify the responsibility of advertising, ie, hired persons to promote goods or services on their behalf or with their image, in order to "protect consumer confidence and prevent them from being errified."
“It is suggested to add advertising rules with ambassador, including the definition of 'advertising ambassador' as any entity other than the advertiser and who, in advertising, use their name, image, reputation or profession to recommend or witness on goods or services, or reflect their opinions, confidence or result of their personal experience on them,” may be read in the proposal.
In this case, advertising ambassadors, according to the document, should “be based on facts by promoting goods or services”, and should not recommend, witness or give their opinion on goods or services that have not used. The government also wants to ban the promotion of professional goods or services by people without relevant professional knowledge.
General principles will also be added to ensure that Internet users “have the right to not see advertising and use the network normally”, including the ability to easily close pop-up advertising.
 
RESTRICTIONS FOR MEDICAL ADVERTISING
It is proposed at the same time that health professionals cannot act as advertising ambassadors in advertising related to medical treatments, pharmaceutical products, medical equipment, health products or health. "Since they have an influence and persuasion power superior to those of the general public, and may lead citizens to believe that the products or services in question necessarily have the recommended effects or benefits," he said.
Regarding the advertising of medical services and medical devices, the document also suggests the ban on comparative advertising in the health sector, for example, comparisons from before and after treatment, or comparisons between different treatment methods, since each clinical case has individual differences, and effectiveness and safety cannot be simply evaluated based on isolated examples, according to DSEDT.
The document also suggests prohibiting all types of game activity advertising.</description><pubDate>2025-07-07 02:23:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal point 2025.07.07</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/07/ponto-fatal-2025-07-07/</link><description>The government will review the advertising activity law to introduce the regulation of new advertising models, especially online advertising. The public consultation document suggests that the presenters, often influencers, on online promotion and live marketing activities, are supervised under the law. It is also proposed that advertising ambassadors must promote goods or services “based on facts”.
 
Authorities have launched a public consultation on the review of the “Advertising Acting Law” and proposed to legislate the activities of advertising influencers and ambassadors, as well as online advertising, which include 'live marketing', ie live promotional actions on online platforms involving direct interaction with the target audience.
The public consultation document, presented by the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) last Friday, proposes to “clarify that participants in online promotion and live marketing activities, such as advertisers, advertising agencies, platform owners and presenters, are subject to the advertising activity law and must comply with their provisions when their acts constitute advertising”.
The government justifies the need to add standards for online advertising, as it has “become common” that traders use social networking platforms and applications to promote or market goods, using live marketing or ‘live commerce’. He also explained that the elaboration of the rules was based on online advertising regulations in the interior of China, whose 'digital marketing' is increasingly popular and used in the territory.
The public consultation of the Advertising Act, which has been in force for almost 36 years, has already started and will end on August 2. Yau Yun Wah, director of DSEDT, pointed out that, due to changes in the economic activities of the various sectors and technological evolution, the contents, forms of dissemination and means used in current advertising “are significantly different” from those of the past.
Thus, the executive intends to change the law to "better correspond to the needs of Macao's socioeconomic development." Authorities guarantee that they have heard opinions from the business sector to start the legislative review work, taking into account the legislative experience of other jurisdictions, including the interior of China and Portugal in the field of advertising regulation.
 
Protect consumer confidence
 
The consultation document also establishes provisions to clarify the responsibility of advertising, ie, hired persons to promote goods or services on their behalf or with their image, in order to "protect consumer confidence and prevent them from being errified."
“It is suggested to add advertising rules with ambassador, including the definition of 'advertising ambassador' as any entity other than the advertiser and who, in advertising, use their name, image, reputation or profession to recommend or witness on goods or services, or reflect their opinions, confidence or result of their personal experience on them,” may be read in the proposal.
In this case, advertising ambassadors, according to the document, should “be based on facts by promoting goods or services”, and should not recommend, witness or give their opinion on goods or services that have not used. The government also wants to ban the promotion of professional goods or services by people without relevant professional knowledge.
General principles will also be added to ensure that Internet users “have the right to not see advertising and use the network normally”, including the ability to easily close pop-up advertising.
 
RESTRICTIONS FOR MEDICAL ADVERTISING
It is proposed at the same time that health professionals cannot act as advertising ambassadors in advertising related to medical treatments, pharmaceutical products, medical equipment, health products or health. "Since they have an influence and persuasion power superior to those of the general public, and may lead citizens to believe that the products or services in question necessarily have the recommended effects or benefits," he said.
Regarding the advertising of medical services and medical devices, the document also suggests the ban on comparative advertising in the health sector, for example, comparisons from before and after treatment, or comparisons between different treatment methods, since each clinical case has individual differences, and effectiveness and safety cannot be simply evaluated based on isolated examples, according to DSEDT.
The document also suggests prohibiting all types of game activity advertising.</description><pubDate>2025-07-07 02:25:35</pubDate></item><item><title>MGM opens new intersectoral paths for artistic education</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/07/mgm-abre-novos-caminhos-intersectoriais-para-a-educacao-artistica/</link><description>This summer, the International Macao International Festival of Macao returns to the District of Barra with the exhibition “The Magic of Lines: The Wonderland of the Illustrated Books of Serge Bloch”, a collaboration between MGM and the Cultural Institute that presents the work of French illustrator Serge Bloch.
To expand the educational reach of the exhibition and promote community involvement, MGM organized the “Art Canvas．study Tour Palette” Symposium on Friday. The event brought together authors of children's books, editors, and study professionals from mainland China and Macau for an interdisciplinary dialogue on illustrated books, exploring how artistic education can be integrated into cultural and creative industries, as well as study travel programs, and how it can be marketed through innovative approaches, the company says in a statement.
Held at Naval Workshops in Barra, the Symposium had a panel of specialists from various sectors, including Wu Binrong, a veteran researcher and author of illustrated books; Solemn XIE, Consultant of the International Shanghai Children's Book Fair; Charles Tam, Director of the Macao Study Travel Development Association; and Catarina Lio, MGM's senior senior marketing marketing. The Symposium attracted more than 60 professionals from the areas of culture, gym, tourism and arts, generating insightful discussions about the multifaceted development of artistic education.
“Illustrated books are often the first contact of children with literature - they arouse love for reading and serve as a gateway to arts education. By bringing this exposure and symposium to the community, we are transforming imagination into shared experiences that seem familiar and welcoming, allowing families to discover the joy and inspiration of art,” Catarina Lio, cited by a statement by a statement by a statement MGM.
Wu Binrong, in turn, said that the books illustrated "are culturally rich and intrinsically interactive." "In addition to being educational tools, they can evolve into commercialized products. Illustrated books have the power to inspire exhibitions or bring intangible cultural heritage to life," he said. Solemn Xie also highlighted the collaboration between sectors as being “fundamental” for the commercialization of illustrated books. "By establishing partnerships with cultural and creative brands, educational institutions and tourist operators, we can create integrated offers that combine books illustrated with creative products and immersive study trips," he said.
The exhibition is open to the public for free. It covers three places: Naval Workshops 1 and 2 in Barra (until September 14) and “• Art Space” on the first floor terrace of the Macao Cultural Center (until October 7).</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Anger has already killed six people in Timor-Leste</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/07/raiva-ja-matou-seis-pessoas-em-timor-leste/</link><description>The anger has already killed six people in Timor-Leste, the Timorese government said, which said it was working to prevent and mitigate the outbreak of that disease, detected in May 2023 in the Indonesian part of Timor Island. "At this time, anger has become a concern for all of us because it threatens public health in our country. We would like to inform that anger illness has already killed 6 Timorese," says a joint circular of the authorities.
The circular, dated June 27, was released Thursday on the official government page. The deadly victims are from the enclave of Oecussi (3), Babonaro (2) and Ermera (1).
In the circular, the authorities ask people owners of dogs, cats and monkeys to keep them in prison or closed and to take them to vaccination posts installed by the Ministry of Agriculture, Livestock, Fisheries and Forests or Private Veterinary Clinics to be vaccinated against rabies.
The government also prohibited the transportation of those domestic animals between municipalities, including to Ariaro and Oedusi (enclave on the Indonesian side of Timor Island), and the entry of animals from abroad in the country, either by land, area or maritime. “In cases where the traffic stations or the joint team find them, the animals will be seized and eliminated,” says the circular.
Authorities will also shoot down dogs and cats without owner. "When the mentioned rules are not met and if someone is bitten by a dog, cat or monkey, the owners of these animals will be held responsible," the circular adds.
The anger was first recorded in the western part of Timor Island in May 2023 and reappeared in Timor-Leste in 2024. Between April 2024 and June, 1,445 dog bite cases were recorded in the country.
Data from the Ministry of Health indicate that the geographical distribution of cases shows that Dili is the municipality with the largest number of cases, 553, (41.2%), followed by the region of Oedusi, with 425 cases (31.6%) and Bobonaro with 294 cases (21.9%).
About 66% of dog -bit people received anti -rabies vaccine (VAR), but many did not complete the five recommended doses. Only 18% of patients received anti -rabies immunoglobulin (Rig), the Ministry of Health said.
The characteristic signs of rabies in dogs include aggressive behavior, uncontrolled races and random bite, excessive saliva production, looking for dark places, fear of water, difficulty eating and drinking, and limb paralysis.
The government of Australia supported 200,000 doses of rabies vaccine, allowing to vaccinate all dogs in national territory.</description><pubDate>2025-07-07 02:25:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Cape Verde thanks Macau's “valuable contribution” in the approach between China and Lusophony</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/07/cabo-verde-agradece-contributo-valioso-de-macau-na-aproximacao-entre-a-china-e-a-lusofonia/</link><description>The 50th anniversary of Cape Verde's Independence was also marked in Macau. Several rulers of the African country have moved to the region to participate in commemorative activities and meet with locations. Paulo Rocha, Minister of Cape Verde Internal Affairs, thanked her for the “valuable contribution she has given in the approach between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries”.
 
Several leaders of the Cape Verdean government have been in Macao to mark the 50th anniversary of the country's conquest of independence and also to meetings with local guardians. On Friday, there was a lecture at the Complex of the Commercial Cooperation Platform between China and the Portuguese-speaking countries, coorganized by the Cape Verde Embassy in China and the Macao Forum Permanent Secretariat. At the time, Paulo Rocha, Cape Verde's Minister of Internal Affairs, thanked the "for the" valuable contribution it has given in the approach between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries. "
In his speech, Paulo Rocha pointed out that Cape Verde "has a successful diaspora, which stands out in science, medicine, academy, technology, politics, business, sports, culture, and that contribute a lot to the country." The minister also recalled that the country is a “committed member of the China-Africa Cooperation Forum and the Macao Forum, and has been treading this path to the continuing narrowing of friendship and cooperation with the interior of China and Macau, in a mutually beneficial mutual understanding and strategic collaboration, bringing new contributions”.
In addition to the minister, also Ji Xianzheng, Secretary General of the Macau Forum, Arlindo do Rosario, Cape Verdean ambassador in China, and Helena de Senna Fernandes, director of MSAR Tourism Services (STD), also gave speeches in this lecture.
Ji Xianzheng has expressed “admiration for the great achievements of Cape Verde over the last 50 years”, noting that “the realization of the strategic partnership between China and Cape Verde has marked a new chapter in bilateral relations”. The Forum Secretary-General also stressed that Cape Verde and China have “converging wills on the full use of cooperation opportunities within the Macao Forum, striving to boost pragmatic cooperation between the two countries, raising their quality and effectiveness in printing greater dynamism in their own development”.
The official assured that the Macao Forum "will continue, in line with the action plan, to take better advantage of the role of Macao as a sino-illusophone platform, contributing to foster exchange and cooperation in different domains between China and Cape Verde."
Arlindo Nascimento do Rosario stated that "the present moment does not only mean a historical date" for the country, but also "an opportunity for Cape Verde to show the world the strength of a nation that, despite the difficulties, persevere, reinvents itself and thrives." The celebration event in Macao should then represent “a unique opportunity to reflect on the Cape Verde course since its independence, a remarkable trajectory marked by hope, resilience and growth”.
The ambassador also pointed out that "Cape Verde and China are two friendly countries and next year they will celebrate the 50th anniversary of the establishment of diplomatic relations." Arlindo Nascimento do Rosario stressed that "the Government of Cape Verde values ​​the relationship with China, especially with the mashes, and the diaspora." "Macao occupies a special place in the heart of the Cape Verdean people, the Cape Verdean diaspora in Macau and its associations not only strengthen friendships between peoples, but also promote the social and economic integration of the Cape Verdean community in the MSAR," said the ambassador.
Helena de Senna Fernandes, who was in the secretary's lecture to the Secretary for Economics and Finance, said that Macau and Cape Verde are “allied territories from historical ties, continuing united by the desire to join to work for the creation of more and several development opportunities for their people and economies”.
The director also pointed out that "the Macao Forum has been committed to the connection of governments, the private sector and the other institutions in favor of the implementation of the consensus achieved in the action plan for economic and commercial cooperation." In the context of the central government's purpose assigned to Macau as “a center, a platform, a base”, Helena de Senna Fernandes said he hoped Macau “continue to provide a high quality platform and opportunities for Cape Verde to his show in Macao, the Great Bay, in the interior of China, and at the international level”.
This lecture was also attended by Álvaro dos Santos Rodrigues and José Costa, who shared their perspectives on the role of diaspora in national development and his experiences, indicates the press release released by the Macau Forum.
 
Cape Verde wants “more and better” Chinese investment
 
On the sidelines of the lecture in Macau, the Cape Verde Internal Affairs Minister said Cape Verde wants to attract investment from China, who described as “one of the main partners” in the country's development since independence. "We, right now, already have a Chinese community in Cape Verde, essentially of small and medium entrepreneurs," said Paulo Rocha in an interview with Lusa. The minister said the next target is “attracting more and better investment [Chinese] in different sectors” to diversify the economy of Cape Verde, much dependent on tourism. The sea is a priority and the government “seeks partnerships” to implement the São Vicente Special Maritime Economic Zone, whose study was done with the support of China, Rocha recalled. Also in Macau, in March, the president of the Cape Verdean agency for foreign investment, José Almada Dias, challenged the Chinese state company Shaanxi Construction to take advantage of the 20,000 hectares that the country has put in the tourism service. Paulo Rocha said it would be "perfectly realistic" to Cape Verde want to attract tourists from China and other Asian countries, underlining the strong presence of Chinese visitors in Europe and "even further". "We continue to foster investments in this domain, grow the number of hotels under construction, the number of resorts, particularly in the two most touristy islands, Sal and Boavista," said the minister. Rocha argued that China is, "no doubt, a reliable partner" from Cape Verde and has been "essential in the development process in different sectors" over the 50 years of independence. Cape Verde has benefited from multiple debt perhaps from China - namely about 1.18 million euros in 2007 and another euros in 2016. In recent decades, China has consolidated its presence in Cape Verde through investments in public works, including the National Stadium and the new headquarters of the National Assembly. "In the coming months, we will inaugurate an important maternity hospital on the island of São Vicente, made with the support of the structuring government of China," for the entire Well region, "the minister defended. Cooperation extends to the area of ​​education, with more than a dozen scholarships attributed annually by the Chinese government.</description><pubDate>2025-07-07 02:25:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Japanese Prime Minister says that country is ready for all scenarios</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/07/primeiro-ministro-japones-diz-que-pais-esta-pronto-para-todos-os-cenarios/</link><description>Japanese Prime Minister Shigero Ishiba said on Sunday that the country is ready to “stay firm” and is prepared for all possible tariff scenarios that may result from commercial negotiations with the United States.
 
Speaking on the "Sunday News, The Prime" program of the Japanese television channel Fuji TV, the ruler stressed the determination of Tokyo in negotiating the application of null customs rights - Zero tariff - in the automotive industry sector.
Shigeru Ishiba also recalled that Japan is the largest direct foreign investor in the United States and the largest job creator in the world's largest economy.
Japan's main commercial negotiator, Ryosi Akazawa, announced this Saturday that he maintained two telephone meetings with United States Secretary of Commerce, Howard Lutnick, to discuss customs rights, at a time of July 9 to impose the increase in rates by Washington.
Akazawa and Lutnick spoke for 45 minutes on Thursday and for about an hour on Saturday, reaffirmed their positions on United States customs rights and "proceeded to an exchange of in-depth points of view," according to a statement from the Japanese government secretariat. The parties will continue to coordinate, it adds in the statement.
The phone calls took place at a time when a 10% general rate on Japan sales to the United States is expected to return to 24% on July 9, if the tariff agreement is not closed.
Akazawa has moved seven times Washington for conversations with his American counterparts, including Lutnick, but the previous conversations produced no great results.
US President Donald Trump announced on Friday that he signed 12 letters, which will be sent this Monday, to inform the commercial partners of the new US customs rates on their US exports, which will begin to be applied next August 1. Trump did not specify which countries will receive the letters.
In addition to the broader tariffs, as with other countries, Japan is also subject to a 25% rate on the importation of US automobile and automotive components and a 50% rate on steel and aluminum.
So far, Trump administration has announced agreements with the UK and Vietnam and has agreed with truce with China in specific sectors by reducing export controls.
Many of the top US business partners, such as Japan, South Korea and the European Union, are still working to complete their agreements.
Some automobile manufacturers and the leading European Union capitals are pressing towards the agreement with Washington focusing on public displeasure in exchange for an increase in investments in the United States, a strategy that is also implemented in the statements of the Japanese head of the Japanese. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-07 02:25:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Simulacrum set of fire and evacuation performed due to gas leakage</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/07/realizado-simulacro-conjunto-de-incendio-e-evacuacao-devido-a-fuga-de-gas/</link><description>The Fire Department (CB) and the Macao City Gas Company held, on Friday morning, a set of combating a fire of a natural gas escape, with the aim of intensifying contingency measures and communication and coordination mechanisms between both organisms.
The exercise took place at the gas company's gas pressure reduction post in the city of Macau, in Coloane, where a sudden escape of natural gas was simulated in adverse circumstances. The CB said that, by not being possible to remotely turn off the valve that controlled the rugged pipe “due to malfunction”, the worker who was on site had to immediately activate the internal emergency mechanism and act “in accordance with the emergency plan” provided for these situations, which included the evacuation of the site and the contact with the firefighters.
After the alarm, the corporation sent seven emergency vehicles and 27 firefighters to the site in order to perform the operational tasks of treatment of gas leakage, evacuation and relief. While the firefighters detected the place where the incident began and dismissed the overall switch of the gas pipe, rescuers counting people and simulated the transport of an injured employee that required hospital treatment.
The CB, the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP), the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) and the Gas Company of the city of Macao highlighted, in total, almost 60 people to participate in the simulacro. The experience lasted about an hour and concluded with the achievement of all “planned objectives and results”, according to the statement.
After the exercise, both parties held a review meeting, in order to improve the capacity for coordination in future emergencies and to reinforce the emergency and contingency plans of the site.</description><pubDate>2025-07-07 02:25:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Shanghai will ban delivery drivers work that commit traffic offenses</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/07/xangai-vai-proibir-trabalho-de-motoristas-de-entrega-que-cometam-infraccoes-de-transito/</link><description>Shanghai will prevent home delivery drivers from violating traffic rules from staying in the activity. The measure joins other previously taken by local governments and companies, after months of public debate in China on the pressure to which delivery drivers are subject to less than one dollar by delivery and have little time to rest, following several incidents.
 
Shanghai will prevent home delivery drivers, who violate traffic rules, stay in the activity, a new chapter in the debate on these increasingly present figures on Chinese streets, the press reported.
According to the Shanghai The Paper News Portal, city authorities have created a three -level system that includes expulsion from the workers industry that have been marked with a 'red code' and have not improved road behavior after several warnings.
These drivers will be placed on a black list and the companies that employ them cannot allow them to continue to accept orders on their platforms.
More than 400 drivers were suspended during the system pilot test, which began in April.
The measure joins other previously taken by local governments and companies, after months of public debate in China on the pressure to which delivery drivers are subject to less than one dollar for delivery and have little time to rest, following several news reports.
In one case, a relay threatened a client with a knife in Wuhan (center) and in another, the driver damaged a seal in Hangzhou (east) while rushing to deliver an order, having been forced to kneel as punishment by the security guards, which led to dozens of other colleagues to call a protest.
In several cities of the country it is common to see these drivers walking against, passing red signs or even accelerating on the rides, deviating from pawns.
In late November, Chinese authorities required digital platforms to review and correct the algorithms that could harm drivers - especially those that reduce delivery times and increase pressure on workers. The idea is to prevent drivers from committing traffic violations and causing accidents as they try to meet unrealistic delivery times. A few weeks later, the MEITUAN WAIMAI platform announced that it would force deliver drivers to rest when it turned out that they had worked too long.
Since the beginning of the year, road offenses committed by drivers of electric motorcycles have decreased by 14.8% in Shanghai and deadly accidents 42.9%, thanks to measures, read the Paper. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-07 02:25:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Influenza cases with an increase tendency</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/07/casos-de-gripe-com-tendencia-de-aumento/</link><description>Flu cases detected in Macao have recorded an increase tendency and authorities have warned that the region is now going through the sickness peak in summer. The weekly detection rate of positive cases of influenza virus has exceeded 13%.
 
Health services warn that Macau is crossing the spill of flu in summer. According to authorities data, the influenza virus in the region has shown a continuous growth trend, and the weekly detection rate of positive influenza virus cases has already exceeded 13.1%, representing the alert level.
According to data on hospital monitoring of influenza-like diseases, from the second half of May, there was an increase in the number of consultations with the influenza-like diseases in Macao, especially the number of cases of children who increased significantly.
The proportion of consultations in the adult emergency service for influenza diseases compared to the total number of consultations increased from 3.3 per 100 consultations in the same period last month to 4.1 in June 22 and 28, which means a 23%rise, and in the pediatric emergency service, the proportion of consultations increased from 19.4 to 24.5, which represented an increase of 26.6%.
According to laboratory results, the influenza virus positivity rate has increased significantly in recent times, from 7.2% in the same month to 20.9% last week, exceeding the alert level (13.1%), which shows that the influenza virus is active, approaching the peak registered in late January this year, which was 29.1%.
Health services recall that in Macao, winter flu peaks usually occur from January to March each year, and summer flu peaks from May to August. Anterior winter flu peaks were mainly caused by influenza A (H1) virus, while recently caused mainly by influenza B virus (representing 54.8%) and influenza virus A (H3) (representing 38.1%).
Authorities also advise the population to be vaccinated, noting that “vaccine administration can effectively reduce the risk of serious influenza and death cases”, noting that residents who were not vaccinated after last year may consider vaccination.
Regarding cases of collective flu infection, due to the approach of summer school holidays, a slight descent was recently recorded. The cases occurred mainly in day care centers, kindergartens and primary schools. Among them, three were caused by the influenza A virus, a case by influenza B virus and a case by an unidentified pathogenic agent.
Since the early 2025, there have been 10 serious influenza cases in Macao, requiring the use of fan, aged between 35 and 86 years.</description><pubDate>2025-07-07 02:24:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Al will have new rules: prohibition of signs with “political provocations” and more opaque commissions</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/07/al-tera-novas-regras-proibicao-de-placas-com-provocacoes-politicas-e-comissoes-mais-opacas/</link><description>The deputies who make up the Legislative Assembly (AL) Regiment and Mandates Commission presented a bill to amend the operation of the legislative body. When the document comes into force, the display of signs with “offensive content or political provocation” is prohibited. The deputies will also fail to reveal the content of the commissions meetings, with the exception of the president and secretary of the same commissions, and the president of the AL will be able to order the exit of the building to those who are disturbing the work.
 
The Legislative Assembly (AL) regiment shall be shifted soon. The deputies of the Regiment and Mandates Commission presented at the end of last week bill to change the operation of the legislative body, as well as the statutes of the legislators. The projects will be discussed and voted generally on Wednesday.
One of the changes to the hemiciclo regiment will prohibit that during the meetings, deputies wear clothes or signs, banners, signs or other objects with “offensive content or political provocation, or to undermine the dignity of the AL”.
In the justification written by the committee's deputies, it is read that “the prohibition of wearing clothes or using materials with offensive content or political provocation is normal in parliaments around the world, since parliaments are solemn bodies where the discussion of matters must be performed respectfully and solemnly”. The document also says that this change "in no way interferes with the rights of deputies, since they can express any opinions."
Another change provided for in this bill has to do with the “reserved character of commissions meetings”. It is thus added an apinose that says “the deputies cannot reveal, anyway, the content of the commission meetings that take place at the closed door”, except for the President and the Secretary of the Commission.
With the new regiment, the president of AL must “maintain order and discipline, as well as the security” of the hemiciclo through measures such as “warn and admonish who disturbs the work, order the cessation of the respective acts and the abandonment of the Plenary Room or the Al”.
In the chapter of the duties of the deputies, a paragraph is added that obliges parliamentarians to attend plenary meetings and the committees to which they belong and present “committed opinions and suggestions”. The deputies also have to present an activities report after the term of each legislative session.
The Commission of Regiment and Mandates took into account the difficulties felt during the pandemic period and in this revision to the regiment was added the possibility of, in exceptional cases and through the authorization of the president of AL, the meetings were held at a distance, and in this case the legislative body would have to provide the necessary technological means.
The bill provides that the new regiment will enter into force on October 16, when the next legislative session is to begin.
With regard to changes in the Statute of Deputies, highlighting the improvement of the regime of the effects of the suspension of the mandate. With the changes, the suspension also passes and has effects on the monthly compensation of the deputies, however, the allowance intended for the operating expenses of the population service and the hiring of support personnel remain intact.
The new statutes detail the new duties of deputies, who are “strictly observing and defending the basic law, being faithful to the Popular Republic of China and defending the constitutional order established in the Constitution of the People's Republic of China and the Basic Law”, “to realize the Macao principle ruled by patriots' and defend sovereignty, safety and the interest of the state” and to perform the functions in the functions in May they be invested, be honest and dedicated to the public and develop a narrow relationship with citizens, ”for example.</description><pubDate>2025-07-07 02:25:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Legend guaranteed to have an alternative for Hotel Casino in Cape Verde</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/07/macau-legend-garantiu-ter-alternativa-para-hotel-casino-em-cabo-verde/</link><description>The Cape Verde Internal Affairs Minister said the government will give Macau Legend a "last opportunity", which has promised "an alternative" to the unfinished beach hotel on the beach. In November, it should be recalled, the Cape Verde authorities began a reversal process of the Macau Legend's Hotel Casino and other unfinished works.
 
Paulo Rocha, Cape Verde's Internal Affairs Minister, told Lusa that the government will give the company Macau Legend a “last opportunity”, which promised “an alternative” to the beach-casino hotel on the beach. "The entrepreneur has had several opportunities and has this last opportunity. He says he will have an alternative and the government is awaiting the presentation of this alternative, while the reversal process takes place" of the project, said Paulo Rocha in an interview with Lusa.
In November, the Cape Verde authorities began a reversal process of the Hotel Casino and other unfinished works of Macau Legend, at Santa Maria Island and Gamboa Sea Marítimo, in Praia City.
Paulo Rocha said that the Cape Verdean executive gave the company founded by David Chow Kam Fai 60 days to present a new proposal to complete the project, but admitted not to know when this period "started to count". "If it does not present, within the period that was given, the reversal process will be concluded and then the government will look for others, likely, any investors," said the minister, during a visit to Macao.
There are currently only guards at the venue, an area of ​​about 160,000 square meters, which includes the partially sulved Santa Maria islet and, a paved bridge of a few meters that connects it to a building of about eight floors, empty and sealed with tails. "The works have been stopped for a long time, have been halfway through there is no movement in that construction shipyard and the government intends to see it resolved. In one way or another," said Rocha.
The executive said in November that he gave Macao Legend “all opportunities to resume the works or to negotiate the sale of shares or the assignment of his contractual position to a potential interested in continuing the project”, but no alternatives were presented. "The project remains important, remains strategic for the city of Praia, for Cape Verde, and the government is interested in finding a solution," said the minister.
In 2015, David Chow signed an agreement for an investment of 250 million euros. After revisions, about six years ago, the conclusion of the first phase was scheduled for 2021.
In late 2023, Macao Legend's president, Li Chu Kwan, said the group intended to end the projects in Cape Verde and Cambodia until 2025.
On March 28, Macau Legend announced losses of $ 45.9 million from Hong Kong in 2024, in part due to the reversal of the beach hotel on the beach.
The operator reiterated that she was “taking the necessary measures to safeguard the group's interests (…), including exploring all available options to contest the decision” regarding the reversal process of the Cape Verdean Hotel Casino.
On the other hand, Macao Legend admitted to "significant doubts about the group's ability to continue in activity" due to total dollar $ 2.51 billion debts. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-07 02:22:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Taipa Village Cultural Association presents Chinese painting exhibition in fans</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/07/taipa-village-cultural-association-apresenta-exposicao-de-pintura-chinesa-em-leques/</link><description>The new exhibition of Taipa Village Cultural Association shows the range as an aesthetic object, more than merely functional. Between July 16 and September 17, they will be on display at Taipa Village Art Space Leques Painted in Pinta-da-China by artist Chao Iok Leng, in honor of the “sublime” Chinese ancestral culture.
 
Hand fans and china ink are two of the most significant aesthetic and Chinese cultural legacies. From July 16 to September 17, Taipa Village Cultural Association presents to the public the exhibition “Chinese Foldable Fan Paintings by Chao Iok Leng”, in which the two artistic strands merge into a single aesthetic creation and recover the beauty of Chinese tradition for contemporary. The opening ceremony takes place on July 16, between 17:30 and 19:00, at the Village Art Space Taipa.
The works on display is by Chao Iok Leng, an artist based in Macau who is a frequent presence in individual and collective painting exhibitions in the territory. In a statement, Taipa Village says that "Chao Iok Leng's approach brings a refreshing approach to the tradition of Chinese folding fan paintings using China paint with an undeniably skilled technique."
The works on display at the headquarters of the Cultural Association represent “a rare intersection of function and beauty, in which the function of cooling of the fan is accentuated by the artistic print in its delicate role”. More than an object used to refresh those who wield it, the fan becomes “a work of portable art” in disuse “in contemporary urban life”. The purpose of the exposure is to "refuel everyday life with an exotic object rooted in ancient Chinese culture and the sublime appreciation."
Folding hand fans will have originated in Asia, initially fulfilling the initial ventilation function. Over the centuries, with the growing popularity of the accessory, other meanings and uses with the fans, which are seen as ornaments and symbols of status, have been associated.
Fan painting has been popularized in the Tang Dynasty, giving rise to a deeply Chinese artistic genre where the limited - and delicate - space of the fan semicircle becomes a screen for elegant designs, executed with precision and mastery. The use of china ink requires even more care to delineate the strokes, since this dye material-developed by the Chinese civilization there are more than two millennia-is rapidly absorbed by paper, making it difficult to retouch or remove already painted areas.
Chao Iok Leng was born in Nanhai, Guangdong Province, but lived and worked in Macao “for most of his life,” according to a biographical note published on the Taipa Village page. Between the 1970s and 90s, he devoted himself to the study and improvement of various artistic techniques, such as painting of landscapes, flowers and birds or Chinese handwriting.
His first solo exhibition in Macao took place in 1987, and has since participated in several individual and collective exhibitions at local and international level. In parallel to the artistic work, he founded the Ngai Chi Hin bookstore in the 1980s and the Nam Fan Lou Craft House, where he sells fans made with different types of materials.
Currently, he is vice president of the Association of Chinese Caligropos and Painters Yu Un, Academic Counselor of the Macao Chinese Cultures and Arts Association, Artistic Counselor of the Macao Association of Culture and Art, Honorary Counselor of the International Association of Macao Artists and Member of the Society of Artists of Macao.</description><pubDate /></item></channel></rss>