<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/03/musica-movimento-e-natureza-na-terceira-edicao-do-connections-em-coloane/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>DSEDJ plans more actions to increase the patriotic awareness of students and teachers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/03/dsedj-planeia-mais-accoes-para-aumentar-a-consciencia-patriotica-dos-alunos-e-docentes/</link><description>The government says it is committed to promoting national security education together by students and teachers, planning the organization of more visits to the basis of education of patriotism in Shandong and Beijing, in order to “deepen the patriotic sentiment and conscience of national security”.
The statement comes from the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ), in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Ho Ion Sang, where he states that the awareness work on patriotism, as well as national security, encompasses child school to higher education, to teaching staff.
According to DSEDJ, in addition to complementary teaching materials on national security education published by the body itself in the previous school year, children in Macau can also receive patriotic content through an illustrated children's book on National Security, launched by the Judicial Police (PJ).
The first illustrated children's book on national security, entitled “The Little Gate Bandeira”, was released in July this year. The PJ said that it has already given a theme to publicize this book that was attended by 70 elements of teaching and non -teaching staff of primary and children. "All this was done in the hope of promoting, through shared reading between parents, children, teachers and students, as well as collaboration between family members, school and police, education for love for the country, so that national security is taught to children from an early age," he assumed.
This children's book addresses the “unity of state sovereignty, territorial integrity and popular harmony”, according to the PJ presentation, guiding children “in recognizing the importance of respecting, valuing and protecting the symbols of the homeland, while fostering patriotism, love for Macau and national pride”.
DSEDJ also stressed that, in cooperation with Macao and Interior Higher Education Institutions, organized in the last three years of school, between 2022 and 2025, more than 100 sessions of teaching training courses related to education for national security defense.
In his opinion, the organization of systematic camp activities is equally important, and the DSEDJ has developed this type of activities for students since the 6th grade of primary education to complementary secondary education. The activities include visits to ecological study in Hengqin, National Defense Education Day and Military Summer Camp for young students from Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:00:22</pubDate></item><item><title>FMCC Annual Solidarity Dinner will help two organizations</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/03/jantar-solidario-anual-da-fmcc-vai-ajudar-duas-organiza-coes/</link><description>The France Macau Chamber of Commerce (FMCC, in the English acronym) will hold its usual solidarity gala dinner on September 19. Dinner, which has as its theme “Sena Travel”, will serve to raise funds for two associations: Zhuhai Autism Society and Macau Special Olympics.
The FRANCE MACAU CHAMBER (FMCC Chamber) Annual Solidarity Dinner takes place on September 19th. This is the 17th edition of this Gala dinner, which this time intends to support Zhuhai Autism Society and Macau Special Olympics. The Gala dinner, which takes place at the MGM Macau Grand Ballroom, has as its theme “Voyage in the Seine”, a river that crosses Paris and that symbolizes the “spirit of connection, innovation and commerce”, says the organization.
Macau Special Olympics was founded by a group of volunteers dedicated to supporting people with intellectual disabilities in 1987 and offers training and competitions throughout the year to improve health, trust and social inclusion, while social welfare programs collaborate with Macao authorities to provide lifetime care. Zhuhai Autism Society is a non-governmental non-profit organization founded in 2010 by parents of children with autism, legally registered by the Zhuhai Department of Civil Affairs, with the Supervisor of the Zhuhai Federation of Disabilities. With the mission of “creating a better life for people with special needs”, the association does research, training for parents, psychological support, public awareness campaigns and promotes the integration of autistic people and their families.
About 300 guests are expected and Rutger Verschuren, president of FMCC, indicated at yesterday's press conference that tickets are being sold at a good pace. It will be “a great night, a lot of fun, with fantastic music and food”, anticipated the official.
"The gala will start with a champagne cocktail, followed by an elegant gourmet dinner of five dishes harmonized with exquisite wines. The guests will enjoy captivating action, live music and an exciting draw," says the organization. The song will be carried out by the Hong Kong Onpoint band and there will also be room for a show of the local group Royalstar Creative. There will also be the usual draw of more than 20 gifts.
During dinner, will also take place the third edition of the delivery of ESG premiums, which distinguish best practices at the environmental, social and governance level. Distinctions of best project, best SME and best NGO will be attributed.
In addition to the gala dinner, FMCC will also make another activity that will involve Zhuhai Autism Society and Macau Special Olympics, entitled “FMCC Hengqin-Macau Including Fun Day”. This event will be held on November 22, in Hengqin, and will gather families of children with autism for a day of various activities, such as music therapy, adapted sports and games between parents and children. This is the first time FMCC organizes a transfronical event.
Last year, the FMCC Gala dinner brought more than 300 guests together, with about 60,000 patacas for a paper recycling initiative carried out by the Oxfam organization.
Rutger Vershuren stressed that "over 17 years, FMCC has been dedicated to strengthening ties between France and Macao." "Our mission is to create a platform where business, academics, entrepreneurs and communities can meet and share knowledge," he said, adding that "besides business and innovation, solidarity is also at the basis of FMCC's work," supporting the macao communities they need.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:04:36</pubDate></item><item><title>AI ensure that providing fresh and living foods is increasingly diverse</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/03/iam-garante-que-fornecimento-de-alimentos-frescos-e-vivos-esta-cada-vez-mais-diversificado/</link><description>The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) has revealed that the diversity of fresh and living food products in Macau has increased by 35% in the last five years. Currently, the main source of the importation of macau fresh foods is the interior of China, from which more than 260 types of vegetables and water, fruits and fresh meat and eggs that sell in the territory are coming from.

Fresh and living food products for sale in Macau are increasingly diverse, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) argues, stressing to have recorded a 35% increase in the types of food available on the market compared to the global amount of the previous five years.
AMI has stated that, in this sense, the population of Macau can nowadays access more fresh and living food options that are mostly coming from the interior of China.
In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Leong Sun IOK about the importation of fresh foods, the body revealed that, currently, in Macao there are more than 180 types of vegetables and aquatic products from 21 provinces and Chinese cities, as well as 60 types of fruits from 19 provinces and cities, and about 20 types of fresh meats and eggs of 10 provinces and cities.
"In recent years, AMI has actively helped the sector to introduce fresh foods from various areas of the country, including meats, eggs, vegetables, fruits and water products, among others, to supply supermarkets, restaurants, market sellers and for the purchase by the population," said Mak Kim Meng, substitute president of the board of directors for municipal affairs.
The person in response said he has been dedicated to widening fresh and live food and agricultural products in Macao through measures such as the celebration of the cooperation agreement with competent interior services, reduction and exemption from food inspection tariffs and the organization of the sector to participate in pairing and demand and product supply.
He also pointed out that the work, in addition to diversifying foods in food supply, safeguard food safety and stable food supply in Macau.
In questioning, the deputy complained about the restriction of importing fresh and alive food products to Macau, asking to diversify the source of products, including fresh ram meat, goose and black pig.
"There are few types of fresh meat for sale in municipal markets, and Macao, as" gastronomic city ", has long faced the problem of limiting fresh and living food products, so many residents prefer to go to China in search of food," said Leong Sun Iok.
It was not the first time that the deputy raised the issue about the variety of fresh and alive food products in Macao. In a plenary of the Legislative Assembly in April this year, the deputy questioned the government on the matter, and the advanced executive that the importation of fresh products for Macau has designated supply points to ensure the safety and quality of food.
At that time, the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, said that the fresh foods of Macau are mainly supplied by the continent, from a wide range of places across the country, and the best quality are "selected." As for fresh ram meat, André Cheong revealed that the slaughterhouse had already considered the need for such slaughter facilities, but did not advance with the proposal since the creation of a dedicated slaughter line would imply a substantial investment and high management costs.
AMI, in this scope of diversified supply of fresh and living foods, has ensured that it maintains close communication with the competent authorities in the interior of China to widen food sources from more provinces in the country, meeting the needs of the local market.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:08:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Zone A will have a soccer field of 11 and athletics track</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/03/zona-a-tera-campo-de-futebol-de-11-e-pista-de-atletismo/</link><description>Zone A of the new landfills will have a soccer field of 11 with athletics track and leisure facilities, revealed the direction of soil services and urban construction in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Ma Io Fong. In addition, the government also said that more Badminton and Basketball fields will be installed at Taipa and next to Lake Nam Van.

The government will make available the B13 lot of zone A of new landfills to build a 11 -football field of 11, equipped with an athletics track and leisure facilities, said the direction of soil services and urban construction (DSSCU), in response to a written interpellation presented by Deputy Ma Io Fong.
In addition, in the Nam Van Lake Zone and also in the Taipa, in a lot next to the Nations School, Badminton Campos, Basketball Fields and other recreational facilities will be installed, indicated that, since these land are close to residential areas, “after the completion of sports facilities, opening hours will be organized in a balanced way, giving priority to the needs of classes of classes Physical Education of Schools, with the remaining periods available to different groups of the community ”.
At the interpellation, Ma Io Fong suggested the introduction of inflatable sports. "There are successful examples of construction with inflatable enclosures. In addition, the size and cost of their facilities can be controlled, having advantages in the short term of construction, being more easily removed and reused," said the deputy linked to the General Association of Macao Women.
Authorities have closed the door to the idea: “Given that inflatable membrane construction technology is a relatively new model, these facilities must comply with the provisions of Macao laws and regulations on fire safety, construction and other requirements and should evaluate their viability broadly”.
MA IO Fong also asked the executive to “studies on the provisional use of the land reserve” and create a “uniformed and application management platform”, publicizing information about short, medium and long term plans, and temporary purposes.
DSSCU pointed out that, “as regards information on land integrated in the reserve whose definitive purpose has not yet been attributed, they have been disclosed by different means, allowing their knowledge by the competent and society services”.
In addition, the government stressed that, “to meet the needs of society, the Government of MSAR continuously proceeds to the revision of land in reserve that can be provided with provisional use, including the identification of suitable land to meet residents' needs, namely for use such as parking parks, community equipment or spaces intended for activities, among others”.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:07:39</pubDate></item><item><title>“Very satisfied” hotels with sector performance during the summer</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/03/hoteis-muito-satisfeitos-com-desempenho-do-sector-durante-o-verao/</link><description>It was a “very good” summer for the hotel sector, commented yesterday Rutger Verschuren, vice president of the Macao Hotel Association, noting that there was a drop in visitors' spending compared to previous years.

"It was a very good summer. July was excellent and August was even better," said Rutger Verschuren yesterday, stressing: "We are very pleased with the performance of different hotels and resorts." In September, the hotel occupancy rate is expected to fall compared to the previous two months, anticipated the vice president of the Macao Hotel Association, on the sidelines of the French Chamber of Commerce Gala Press Conference (FMCC).
According to data from the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), the average occupancy rate of guest rooms of hotel establishments set at 91% in July. That same month, nearly 3.5 million visitors arrived in Macau. The data related to August have not yet been released.
Verschuren stressed that "performance in summer months has reached hotel expectations," but visitors "spent less." "[Room] prices in August were not extraordinarily high. We also saw that the spending on hotel restoration were smaller than in 2023," he said.
September is a usual month calmer for hotels, but Rutger Verschuren believes it may also be good, as Macau will receive fewer young visitors, more elderly people will arrive. In the last quarter of the year, the good trend should be maintained, considered the representative of the sector.
Hotels are already looking forward to the golden week of National Day at the beginning of next month. Rutger Verschuren anticipated that hotels should perform well during this period, although there is still no increase in reserves for this week. According to the official, visitors now make the reservations later than in the past.
In November, Macau will receive some national games, such as Hong Kong and Guangdong Province. In the case of Macao, there are still no effects of the event in the reserve of hotel rooms, unlike Hong Kong, said the responsible for the Hotel Association: “Hong Kong is selling tickets and there is a lot of search for hotel rooms, but in Macao we still see no peak. When tickets enter the market, we will have more reservations, but not at the moment”. "Anyone who wants to watch the national games [in Macao] should now book because prices are still normal, in November they should increase," he warned.
Rutger Verschuren also commented on the advertised closing of the satellite casinos, stating that this will impact the hotels associated with these spaces. "We have to see what the strategy of these hotels will be to fill the rooms, one of the strategies may be to lower prices, but we hope not," he said, justifying that the sector needs revenues, as expenses are increasing.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:11:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Casa Garden receives series of lectures on collective housing until November</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/03/casa-garden-recebe-serie-de-palestras-sobre-habitacao-colectiva-ate-novembro/</link><description>Docomomo and the East Foundation will join the presentation of a series of five lectures in the Garden House auditorium, entitled "The Advent of Collective Housing in the 20th Century." The first session happens today, with a reflection on how architecture was able to respond to social changes in the 60s and 70s in Lisbon, Porto, Macau and Maputo. The lectures extend to November, with free admission.
 
Docomomo, an International Organization for the Defense of Modern Architectural Heritage, will join the East Foundation in the presentation of the project “The Advent of Collective Housing in the 20th Century”. The initiative will be open to architects, historians and the general public between September and November, in the auditorium of Casa Garden, with free admission.
The project consists of a series of five lectures where “the architectural, political and social dimensions of mass housing will be explored,” as described in a statement issued by the organization. The five invited experts-from different countries and regions, such as Portugal, the United Kingdom, Singapore and Macao-will focus on specific topics and invite the public to reflect "on the legacy and future of collective life." All sessions start at 6:45 pm.
The first lecture takes place today, conducted by Portuguese Jorge Figueira, professor at the University of Coimbra and researcher and vice president of the Scientific Council of the Center for Social Studies (CES-UC). The theme that begins the series of lectures is “Lisbon, Porto, Macau, Maputo: Heroic Collective Housing from the 60s &amp; 70s”: a study on “bold housing projects shaped by limited resources and change in change in Lusophone cities”, as described by the East Foundation. The session will be moderate by João Nuno Marques.
On September 5, Friday, the theme is specifically focused on the history of the macao with “Macao: Micro-Stories on Collective Housing Between the 50s and the 80s”. The speaker invited to deepen this theme is Ana Vaz Milheiro, associate professor at the Faculty of Architecture, University of Lisbon and researcher at Dynamia'Cet-Iul (ISCTE). Among the research projects signed by the Academic, there are studies on architecture and political dynamics in ancient African colonies, as well as a project on the construction of infrastructure in Macao during the Portuguese administration.
The third session will take place on October 30 and focuses on the topic “Un-Purposed Space: Rethinking Macau’s Urban Fabric Through Design”. Specialist in areas such as architecture, interior design and urban planning, Carlotta Bruni speaker is also the executive director of LBA Architecture &amp; Planning, an architecture and planning company based in Macao.
On November 6, the focus will be in Singapore with "From Sit to HDB: Singapore's Public Housing Morphology and Policy in the 20th Century." The session will be taught by Johannes Widodo, a professor at the Department of Architecture at the University of Singapore, where he teaches on urban history, the culture and morphology of Asian cities (with particular emphasis on Southeast Asia). Widodo is also one of the founding members of Docomomo Macau.
The lecture series ends on November 11 with a reflection on the situation of the neighboring region of Hong Kong, entitled “Mass Housing - The Global and Hong Kong History”. The special guest is Miles Glendinning, director of Scottish Center for Conservation Studies and professor of architectural conservation at the University of Edinburgh. He is the author of several works on the history of architecture and public housing in Hong Kong, Scotland and global.
Docomomo calls itself, on social networks, as a non-profit organization that promotes public interest and recognition of architecture in Macau, for example, the promotion of debates and lectures.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Music, Movement and Nature in the Third Edition of Connections in Coloane</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/09/03/musica-movimento-e-natureza-na-terceira-edicao-do-connections-em-coloane/</link><description>In the heart of the bucolic village of Colaane is born another outdoor experience. A call for the community to gather, not simply to watch, but to participate, feel and co-create. The “Connections-Music.Movement.nature” returns to its third edition, asserting itself as a recurring tradition in the Macao cultural calendar. On September 27 and 28, the Urban Farm in Coloane becomes a microcosm of well-being and artistic expression. This is the invitation: disconnect from the trivial and reconnect with the essentials.

It is no longer new, but a recurring meeting that renews and deepens. On September 27 and 28, the Urban Farm space, in the green heart of Coloane that tands the picturesque village of the same name, will be the space chosen this time for the “connections - music.movement.nature”. An event, described by the organizers as “a collective creation that combines a conscious way of life with unique experiences,” which promises total immersion in a positive, nature and connection environment. After two successful editions held in 2018 and 2019 at Ka-Ho Adventure Camp at K-O Dam, the non-profit community initiative returns for the third time in a larger place to celebrate union between people, art and well-being. His place in Macao's alternative cultural calendar is affirming himself in each new edition, in a collective effort by local organizers and artists.
The proposal is ambitious and meticulously organized in seven distinct zones, each with its own identity and offer. The heart of the activity will be in “Village”, an area inspired by traditional Chinese gardens and tea houses, composed of wooden houses that will houses 12 local artisans, from fashion and accessories to skin and crystals care, being Dreama, Neska, Zarja’s Selections, Ceragigi, Ododoodo, Dollfie, Wickd, White Lodge Dreamland, Wutoyeah, Gems Awakening, Lylon Skincare and Knotme. In addition, there will be a diverse food village with the offers of Larry’s Place, Concept H, Black Lotus, Cakes by Rose &amp; Muse, Juk and Happy Stand.
Bet on physical and mental well-being is a fundamental pillar of "connections". In the “Treetop”, a mezzanine built around a huge tree will take place from the mornings when dusk movement and meditation sessions. The program includes zumba, bachelor, conscious dance, yoga, pilates, gyrokinesis - a practice to relieve muscle tensions - and Sound Bath sessions. The premise is clear: that participants can absorb the sight of the sky and relax through the branches while rooting their feet in the natural world.
 
Space for families

Families have a dedicated space, Family Tent, with activities designed for all ages, from family meditation and mandala painting to interactive readings, as well as crochet and construction of masks. The organization emphasizes that children are welcome in any activity, as long as accompanied, and may also enjoy the permanent infrastructures of Urban Farm, such as fishing and agriculture. The guaranteed fun extends to a Yurte Mongol, which will serve as a scenario for an unprecedented Quiz night in English, and the “Concrete” zone, which will be occupied by urban art collectives such as the Outloud International Street Art Festival and Mid Age of Dawn Skateboards (M.A.O.D.), which will hold graffiti sessions.
For moments of relaxation and musical exploration, Gypsy Camp offers a shaded area with pillows and blankets, ideal for relaxing. Here, participants will be able to experience instruments such as Asalato, integrate in a circle of drums or be transported by the Duo Nàv Handpan and Didgreid Concert, at their regular meeting, usually held at the musicians' studio, entitled “Session For The Soul”. This zone will also be the epicenter of alternative practices, welcoming a fire ritual, lectures on spiritual principles and individual tarot sessions.
When the night falls, the stage moves to the Woods, a clearing in an adjacent grove that will become an outdoor music festival, with action by local DJs and the region, while Village will maintain a more “lounge” atmosphere with organic music and World Music.
Access to the event is held through a donation, with pre-sale prices from 150 patacas for a day or 250 patacas for access to the full event, being available for purchase and the promotion ending on September 5, Friday. This weekend, prices rise to 180 and 280 patacas for those who purchase the entries in advance, and the purchase value at the door is set at 200 and 300 patacas. With a vast and diverse program, “Connections” is not like a festival, but as an essential meeting point for the community that wants to value the precious nature of Macao, art and, above all, the connection between people. To expand access, the entry of children up to 12 years is free.</description><pubDate /></item></channel></rss>