<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/08/china-anula-pena-de-morte-de-um-canadiano-num-caso-de-droga/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Xi wants yuan with global status, but experts point to structural obstacles</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/08/xi-quer-yuan-com-estatuto-global-mas-especialistas-apontam-obstaculos-estruturais/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping last week defended the construction of a “strong currency” with global status, while experts warn that the yuan will only reach that level with profound structural reforms, incompatible with the current Chinese model.

Xi's appeal was published by Qiushi, the main theoretical magazine of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP). The leader outlined the attributes of a true financial power: solid economic base, top technological strength, competitive institutions, international financial centers and a widely used and credible currency.
Despite the size of Chinese banking assets and foreign exchange reserves, Xi acknowledged that the country's economy continues to be “large, but not strong”. Transforming the yuan into a global reserve currency will require a “prolonged effort”, according to the President. “We must improve the ability to regulate markets, prevent systemic risks and maintain global financial stability”, he highlighted. But experts warn of the limits of this ambition, given China's current governance model.
Michael Pettis, a researcher at Peking University, told Lusa news agency that making the yuan a real alternative to the US dollar would imply reforms “incompatible with the Chinese political system”, such as liberalizing capital markets, allowing free inflows and outflows of capital, and guaranteeing a legal system that is transparent, predictable and takes precedence over government authorities. “An economy that allows free capital flows cannot simultaneously maintain a fixed exchange rate and an independent monetary policy,” he warned, adding that the Chinese financial market remains closed to foreign capital and independent judicial scrutiny.
Wu Xiaoqiu, director of the National Academy of Financial Research at Renmin University, echoed these concerns during a forum in Beijing. The academic argued that the success of the yuan will depend on three pillars: market primacy, rule of law and institutional stability. "The path to making the yuan a reserve currency involves institutional transformation. Administrative strength or economic dimension are not enough," said Wu.
Currently, the yuan ranks third among international currencies, with an internationalization rate of 5.68%, according to Wu, and Beijing's ambition is to increase this value to 20% by 2035. However, the researcher stressed that the external circulation of the yuan remains limited, due to the lack of effective capital return mechanisms and persistent structural imbalances.
For the yuan to gain global status, it would need to allow access to diverse domestic assets, easy liquidity and an impartial regulatory framework – reforms considered difficult under the CCP's centralized control, according to experts.
The international use of the Chinese currency has, however, been growing, driven by trade relations with Russia, which intensified after Western sanctions, and by the signing of compensation agreements with countries such as Saudi Arabia, Brazil, Argentina or Mongolia.
Zambia recently began accepting taxes in yuan from Chinese companies, channeling the amounts to pay debt and finance imports. Brazil announced plans to issue yuan-denominated sovereign debt in the Chinese market.
Despite these advances, the renminbi represented, by the end of 2025, only 4.74% of international payments, remaining behind the dollar, the euro and the pound sterling, according to data from the Swift system. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-08 23:12:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Record number of border crossings recorded on the eve of Lunar New Year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/08/registado-recorde-de-passagens-nas-fronteiras-em-vesperas-do-ano-novo-lunar/</link><description>Macau recorded a new all-time high in border entries and exits, on the eve of the Lunar New Year. Around 867,000 people crossed the territory's borders on Saturday, the highest number since daily records began.
Macau recorded a new historic high of entries and exits at the region's borders, with just over a week to go until the Lunar New Year, the largest annual migration in the world, it was announced yesterday.
The Public Security Police (PSP) said that the territory's borders registered the passage of around 867 thousand people on Saturday, the highest number since daily records began. In a statement, the PSP said that the largest share of movements (39.1%) was due to tourists.
Macau received around 174 thousand visitors on Saturday, still far from the daily record, set on January 2nd: 188 thousand. On the other hand, Macau residents were responsible for 36.7% of entries and exits at the region's borders, while migrant workers represented 21.6%.
According to PSP data, the territory's largest border, Portas do Cerco, was also the busiest, with almost 463 thousand crossings, the highest daily value in the last five years, since the beginning of the covid-19 pandemic.
In the neighboring region of Hong Kong, Secretary for Culture, Sports and Tourism, Rosanna Law Shuk-pui, predicted on Saturday that 1.43 million visitors from mainland China will pass through the city during the Lunar New Year holidays.
Chinese authorities expect hundreds of millions of people to travel, in the world's largest annual migration, to celebrate the Lunar Year of the Horse, a holiday period that this year falls between February 15th and 23rd. But the travel season, the so-called 'chunyun', a period of 40 days before and after the start of the Lunar New Year, already started on February 2.
On January 29, Li Chunlin, deputy director of China's National Development and Reform Commission, the country's main economic planning body, predicted that Chinese people make up to 9.5 billion trips during 'chunyun'. If this forecast is correct, it would be a new historical record, far exceeding the maximum recorded in 2024: 9.02 billion trips.
According to official estimates, train trips could reach 540 million, while air trips are expected to be around 95 million, both potential historic maximums for this period. The authorities have promised that the capacity of the transport system will be reinforced on the busiest routes and in areas of greatest demand to cope with the expected increase in travel.
The 'chunyun' is often used as an indicator of economic activity and as a stress test for the country's transport infrastructure, in a context in which China seeks to boost consumption and services as drivers of domestic demand, which has not yet fully recovered since the pandemic. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-08 23:24:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Number of companies incorporated last year increased compared to 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/08/numero-de-sociedades-constituidas-no-ano-passado-aumentou-face-a-2024/</link><description>In 2025, 4,678 companies were formed, that is, 123 more than in 2024, informed the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). The majority of companies formed were in the wholesale and retail trade sector of economic activity (1,640) and in the sector of services provided to companies (1,352). Last year, 946 companies were dissolved, with the net increase in the number of companies being 3,732.
In the year under review, the share capital of the incorporated companies totaled 545 million patacas. Analyzing by share capital level, 3,430 incorporated companies (73.3% of the total) belonged to the share capital category of less than 50 thousand patacas and the share capital of these companies (88 million patacas) corresponded to 16.2% of the total. A further 52 companies were established with a share capital equal to or greater than one million patacas and the share capital of these companies (287 million patacas) represented 52.7% of the total.
Looking at data from the fourth quarter of last year, 1,401 companies were formed and 233 companies were dissolved, with the net increase in the number of companies being 1,168.
In terms of the origin of the share capital of companies incorporated in the fourth quarter of 2025, the share capital originating from the Macao SAR was 76 million patacas and that from the interior of China stood at 32 million patacas, representing 61.2% and 26% of the total, respectively. Share capital from inland Chinese cities located in the Greater Bay Area totaled 10 million patacas, of which 45.7% came from Zhuhai. Share capital from Hong Kong amounted to 9 million patacas.</description><pubDate>2026-02-08 23:13:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing price index recovers slightly, but it hasn't been this low for 13 years</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/08/indice-de-precos-da-habitacao-recupera-ligeiramente-mas-ha-13-anos-que-nao-estava-tao-baixo/</link><description>At the end of last year, Macau's global housing price index was 191.8. This index has been falling sharply over the last few years and is now at its lowest level since 2013. Even so, between October and December last year, the index recovered 0.1%.
House prices in Macau have been falling since 2021 and are now at the levels recorded in 2013. According to the most up-to-date data from the Statistics and Census Bureau (DSEC), the global housing price index was, in the period between October and December last year, at 191.8, that is, 0.1% more than in the previous quarter.
Data compiled on the DSEC website, consulted by PONTO FINAL, shows that, in 2011, the region's global housing price index was at 100 and in 2013 it was already at 188. House prices increased exponentially in the following years and, between 2019 and 2021, a peak of 266 was reached. Since then, however, the index has been gradually decreasing. From 2021 until now, the house price index in Macau has already fallen by 28%.
In the most recent statistics, DSEC details that, in the last quarter of 2025, the housing price index for Taipa and Coloane (200.1) increased by 1% and that the index for the Macau Peninsula (189.7) decreased by 0.3%.
The price index for built housing (204.6) rose 0.2% compared to the third quarter of last year. In terms of the year of construction of the buildings, the price index for houses built in the 6 to 10 years of construction category rose 3.6% compared to the previous period, however, the index for the category over 20 years old fell 1.9%. The price index for housing under construction (238.8) grew 0.7% compared to the previous period.
In terms of useful area of ​​autonomous units, the price index for housing in the range equal to or greater than 100 square meters of useful area increased by 1.6% in relation to the previous period, however, the index for the range from 75 to 99.9 square meters decreased by 2%. Analyzing by building height, the housing price index for buildings in the category with more than seven floors increased by 0.4%, while the index for buildings in the category less than or equal to seven floors decreased by 0.2%.
It is recalled that the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, had announced in December last year a measure to exempt stamp duty for residents who purchase their first apartment for a value equal to or less than 6 million patacas. Furthermore, the maximum mortgage loan percentage limit rose from 70% to a new ceiling of 80%. The two measures came into force in January 2026, aiming to reinforce the development of the real estate sector and provide extra support for residents looking for a home.</description><pubDate>2026-02-08 23:21:46</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korean music group took to the stage in Macau without a Japanese singer</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/08/grupo-de-musica-sul-coreano-subiu-ao-palco-em-macau-sem-cantor-japones/</link><description>South Korean boy group Riize performed in Macau this weekend without Japanese singer Shotaro, at a time of tension between Beijing and Tokyo. Riize, who currently have six members, took to the stage at the Galaxy Arena, at the Galaxy Macau hotel-casino, with just five artists, said the company IME Macau. In a statement published on social media, the company justified the decision with “unforeseeable circumstances”, without further details.
Asked on Tuesday about the cancellation of shows with Japanese artists, the director of the Tourism Services said she had “no concrete information about the situation”. Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes was speaking on the sidelines of the Lunar New Year parade, which celebrates the Year of the Horse. Unlike previous years, there will be no groups from Japan.
On January 28, South Korean broadcaster MBC, which was organizing the ‘Show! Music Core in Macau’, a music festival in South Korea, which included bands featuring Japanese artists, canceled the event. The festival was scheduled for this weekend, at the Outdoor Showgrounds, in the Cotai area. MBC did not provide any explanation for the decision, saying only that it was taken “after a thorough analysis of local circumstances and general logistical conditions”. Even before the official announcement by MBC, the South Korean press had already discussed the possible cancellation due to the alleged difficulty of Japanese artists in obtaining visas to perform in Macau.
On December 12, the president of the IC denied any interference in the cancellation of concerts with Japanese artists scheduled for the region and assured that these were solely commercial decisions by the organizers. “I think different parties have their own weighting factors,” said Leong Wai Man, at a press conference. "It is normal to have adjustments regarding concerts or different events. Situations of cancellation due to force majeure are common", he added. In December, shows with Japanese artists had already been canceled in at least three different hotel-casinos in Macau.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Macau recorded 850 fires last year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/08/macau-registou-850-incendios-no-ano-passado/</link><description>In Macau, 850 fires were recorded last year, a slight reduction of 3.36% compared to the previous year, with the main causes continuing to be “forgetting to turn off the stove” and “leaving unextinguished flames”. The Fire Department plans to send personnel to exchanges in mainland China this year, focusing on fire response strategies in high-rise buildings.

The Fire Department (CB) witnessed a decrease in operational actions in 2025, which registered a drop of 1.74% and totaled 53,190 incidents. Among these, 850 were fires, which represents a reduction of 32 cases (3.36%) compared to the previous year.
Wong Kin, commander of the CB, revealed that the main causes of fires were forgetting to turn off stoves, leaving flames not completely extinguished, burning incense and candles or votive papers, mechanical or equipment failures and electrical short circuits. These causes led to 534 cases, which corresponds to 62.82% of the total number registered in the year.
The majority of fires (705 cases) did not require the use of hoses. However, almost 80% of the cases that required the use of hoses were caused by factors such as left flames (50 cases), burning incense or votive papers (34 cases), electrical short circuit (19 cases) and mechanical failures (11 cases). In other words, the fires that required the use of hoses were, for the most part, related to residents' daily negligence or insufficient safety awareness, highlighted Wong Kin, in a CB talk with the media last Friday.
Regarding the ambulance service, the total number of ambulance departures last year was 45,370, corresponding to an increase of 134 cases (0.3%) compared to 2024. The main causes of requests for ambulance service were related to dizziness, abdominal pain, fever and bruises.
Wong Kin in this case highlighted that ambulance resources are limited and the CB will continue to promote information against the misuse of ambulances in the community to increase residents' awareness of the proper use of ambulance services.
Rescue operations totaled 1,700 cases, a decrease of 92 cases compared to 2024. The cases mainly involved assistance in opening doors and medical treatment of the injured. In addition, requests for special services from the CB resulted in the monitoring of 5,270 cases, in which firefighters mainly dealt with incidents such as removing fallen objects and cleaning surfaces or oil spills. The number is equivalent to a decrease of 953 cases (15.31%) compared to the previous year.
The organization stated that it carried out inspection and inspection of fire safety in buildings. Last year, a total of 11,760 inspections were carried out and administrative sanctioning procedures were completed in relation to 126 cases, including, above all, situations of placing objects and parking motorcycles on evacuation paths, among others. Ten more cases are also being subject to administrative sanctioning procedures.

FIRES IN HIGH-RISE BUILDINGS
 
On the occasion, the CB was asked about raising awareness against fires in the Macau community, as well as the safety of bamboo scaffolding and protective nets used in civil construction. The issue was raised following the mega-fire in Hong Kong at the end of November last year, which caused 168 deaths, including a firefighter.
Wong Kin assured that the CB, last year, already entered into communication with other competent authorities to carry out inspections of the safety networks of buildings under construction.
"In addition to checking the certificates of the bamboo scaffolding and nets, the on-site inspections also involved ignition testing. If suspicious materials were identified that did not comply with fire standards, immediate replacement orders were issued, with samples sent to the relevant departments for follow-up," he explained.
The spokesperson also emphasized that CB personnel follow international standards when carrying out fire prevention and firefighting operations, using helmets, protective suits and other personal protective equipment to protect themselves.
The CB, meanwhile, intends to launch more training programs for firefighters, with plans to send personnel on exchanges in the first half of this year in mainland China. The focus of the training will be on fire response strategies in tall buildings. The organization will also pay attention to updating protective equipment, assured Wong Kin.</description><pubDate>2026-02-08 23:21:03</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea's single party meets at congress at the end of February</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/08/partido-unico-da-coreia-do-norte-reune-se-em-congresso-no-final-de-fevereiro/</link><description>North Korea's single party announced that it will hold its first congress since 2021 at the end of February, where the leader promised to present “the next stage” of the nuclear deterrence plan.
“The Political Cabinet of the Central Committee of the Workers' Party unanimously adopted the decision to hold the ninth Congress of the Workers' Party in Pyongyang, the capital of the revolution, at the end of February 2026,” reported the official North Korean news agency KCNA.
The meeting had four items on the agenda, including the congress calendar and deliberations on the documents to be presented, KCNA added, without providing details on the content or an exact date for the congress.
The country's leader, Kim Jong-un, “praised the effectiveness of the congress preparatory committees, which boosted preparations for the congress in all aspects and clarified the principles and detailed tasks for its successful execution”, concluded the agency.
On January 27, Kim Jong-un declared that the congress “will clarify plans for the next step aimed at strengthening North Korea's nuclear deterrence.”
The leader was speaking during a ballistic missile launch. Before the congress took place, Kim Jong-un ordered the expansion and modernization of the country's missile production.
It was the second test in January for Pyongyang, following a volley of missiles fired just hours before the South Korean leader's departure for an official visit to China.
It also occurred the day after a trip to Seoul by the number three at the United States War Department, Elbridge Colby, who hailed South Korea as a “model ally”.
North Korea has stepped up missile testing in recent years. Analysts indicate that the campaign aims to improve precision strike capabilities, challenge the United States and South Korea and test weapons, before eventually exporting them to Russia.
The last single party congress, held in January 2021, named Kim general secretary, a title previously held by his father and predecessor, Kim Jong Il, something analysts saw as a maneuver to consolidate his authority.
The congress is the highest meeting point of the ruling party, which aims to strengthen the regime's authority and can serve as a platform to announce political decisions or changes in its leadership.</description><pubDate>2026-02-08 23:10:10</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM and University of Coimbra launch joint Digital Humanities program</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/08/upm-e-universidade-de-coimbra-lancam-programa-conjunto-de-humanidades-digitais/</link><description>The Macau Polytechnic University and the University of Coimbra have officially launched a Joint Research Program in Digital Humanities. The new program, presented during the celebrations of UPM's 45th anniversary, aims to build a multilingual research ecosystem, focusing on linguistic technology, digitalization of cultural heritage and artificial intelligence, highlighting Macau as a platform for academic exchange between China and Portuguese-speaking countries. 
The Macau Polytechnic University (UPM) and the University of Coimbra (UC) have taken a significant step in deepening their strategic collaboration with the official launch of a Joint Research Program in Digital Humanities. The ceremony, which was part of the celebrations of UPM's 45th anniversary, was presided over by the rector of the Macau institution, Marcus Im, and by the vice-rector of the Portuguese university, Nuno Mendonça, marking the expansion of the partnership of more than three decades to a new front of interdisciplinary research.
In his speech, Marcus Im highlighted the evolution of cooperation between the two institutions, which went from exchanging qualified staff to building joint laboratories in areas such as the smart city and digital health. “The recently launched Digital Humanities Program assumes a significant mission,” said Im, explaining that the project will focus on language technologies and the construction of databases of interlingual texts, promoting innovation in the humanities and social sciences. At the same time, through digital exhibitions and interactive experiences, the program aims to encourage the dissemination and sharing of multicultural resources.
In turn, Nuno Mendonça, vice-rector of UC, emphasized the transformative nature of digital humanities in the current context. “With artificial intelligence profoundly changing the way we research and teach, the rise of digital humanities is not just a technical challenge, but also a profound dialogue involving ethics and culture,” he said. Mendonça highlighted the historical role of the University of Coimbra as an academic bridge between East and West, expressing the intention to integrate linguistic technologies, creative industries and research into cultural heritage through the current program inaugurated last week.
The joint program will have as its main axes the promotion of Sino-Portuguese studies, which will include the digitization of historical archives, research and development in large-scale Portuguese language models and artificial intelligence, the digital revitalization of cultural heritage and contemporary digital communication. The project will aim to develop a multilingual digital humanities ecosystem centered on the territory, transcending geographical restrictions and characterized by openness, sharing and sustainable development.
The future of this cooperation is also linked to the development of the Macau International Education University City and Hengqin, where the two universities have already signed an agreement to establish a basis for cooperation in the field of higher education. In this space, they plan to create academic laboratories that are pioneers in technological innovation, which will merge traditional and modern aspects.
In a partnership that already has 30 years of history, the launch ceremony between UPM and UC was attended by several academic figures from both institutions, including the director of the UC General Library, Manuel Portela, the director of the Department of Computer Engineering, António Mendes, and, on the UPM side, the director of the Faculty of Languages ​​and Translation, Gaspar Zhang.</description><pubDate>2026-02-08 23:17:35</pubDate></item><item><title>More than ten thousand lifts passed last year's inspection</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/08/mais-de-dez-mil-ascensores-aprovados-na-inspeccao-do-ano-passado/</link><description>Last year, more than ten thousand elevators passed the annual inspection, reported the Directorate of Land and Urban Construction Services (DSSCU). Remember that, according to the legal safety regime for lifts, this equipment located in residential, commercial and public buildings must undergo at least one annual inspection.
According to DSSCU, those responsible for two lifts that were not inspected within the legal deadline were sanctioned due to the equipment being made available for use without approval.
With the beginning of the new year, the issued inspection approval declarations will begin to gradually expire and, therefore, the authorities remind those responsible for the lifts to carefully check the validity periods of the said declaration and hire, as soon as possible, inspection entities to carry out the inspections, completing in a timely manner the necessary formalities for the renewal of the declaration in order to ensure that the lifts continue to meet safe operating conditions.
If the inspection approval declaration expires without its renewal having been carried out, the use of the lift must be immediately suspended and can only be resumed after the inspection has been carried out and a new valid declaration has been issued. The provision of lifts for use without a declaration of valid inspection approval constitutes an offense, and those responsible may be punished in accordance with the law.
Since the implementation of the legal lift safety regime, “public awareness regarding the safety, inspection and maintenance of lifts has increased significantly”, say the authorities in the statement released yesterday.</description><pubDate>2026-02-08 23:14:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Authorities warn of cases of gastroenteritis after consumption of raw oysters</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/08/autoridades-alertam-para-casos-de-gastroenterite-apos-consumo-de-ostras-cruas/</link><description>Authorities are aware of the recent increase in collective cases of gastroenteritis, appealing to residents, especially those with compromised immune systems, the elderly, pregnant women and children, to avoid, whenever possible, the consumption of high-risk raw foods, such as oysters.
The appeal comes after Macau has registered, since the beginning of the year, 11 collective cases of gastroenteritis, compared to 4 in the same period last year. According to the Executive, preliminary investigations indicate that, of the total of 71 affected individuals, 97% (69 patients) are related to the consumption of raw oysters from France, Ireland and South Korea. Laboratory tests confirmed norovirus infection in some cases. All cases presented mild symptoms.
According to a note published by the Health Services and the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM), a collective case of gastroenteritis was detected on Thursday, in which 26 people were diagnosed with gastroenteritis, with preliminary investigation pointing to a possible link to the consumption of raw oysters and salmon in a restaurant in Macau Tower.
There were two more cases, which involved a private banquet held at MGM Cotai, with a buffet-style meal, and another buffet at Oceanus Macau, last week, involving 36 and 6 people, respectively. After meals, participants developed symptoms such as fever, abdominal pain, vomiting and diarrhea.
The IAM ensured the immediate reinforcement of inspection measures for the import of oysters. Authorities, after receiving the report of the cases, sent officials to the location in question to carry out an investigation, analyzing food handling procedures and collecting food and environmental samples for analysis.
The Health Services, in turn, state that gastroenteritis is normally caused by several pathogens, such as viruses or bacteria. Common pathogens include norovirus, rotavirus and Salmonella.
Transmission routes include consumption of contaminated food or water, contact with a patient's vomit or feces, contact with contaminated objects or transmission by droplets. Common symptoms include nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, abdominal pain and fever, and the illness is generally mild.</description><pubDate>2026-02-08 23:14:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Visitors spend less outside casinos</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/08/visitantes-gastam-menos-fora-dos-casinos-2/</link><description>In the last quarter of last year, each visitor spent, on average, 2,104 patacas in Macau, not counting expenses in the casinos. This means that the extra-game expenditure per capita of visitors in the Macao SAR decreased by 1% in annual terms. Looking at the whole of 2025, the 'per capita' expenditure of visitors outside the casinos was 2,000 patacas, registering a year-on-year decrease of 7.3%.
Visitors passing through Macau are spending less money in the region, not counting expenses in casinos. According to data from the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC), the average per capita expenditure of visitors during the last quarter of last year was 2,104 patacas, 1% less compared to the same period of the previous year. In quarterly terms, however, extra-game spending by visitors to the Macao SAR grew by 7.9%.
Total visitor spending in the fourth quarter amounted to MOP21.87 billion, registering an increase of 14.2%, as the global number of tourists also grew in this period in annual terms. Overall, day trippers spent 5.34 billion patacas in the Macao SAR, 85.9% more than the same period last year. Tourist spending rose 1.6% globally.
With regard to the type of ‘per capita’ expenditure, visitors spent mainly on purchases (45.4% of the total), followed by expenditure on accommodation (25%) and food (20.6%). Analyzing the main reason for visiting the Macao SAR, the 'per capita' expenditure of visitors who came to participate in conventions/exhibitions (4,821 patacas) was the highest in the fourth quarter of 2025, highlights DSEC.
The per capita expenditure of visitors not related to gambling throughout 2025 was 2,000 patacas, registering a year-on-year decrease of 7.3%.
Analyzing the per capita expenditure of visitors by main origins of visitors, it appears that that from mainland China (2,245 patacas), that from Hong Kong (988 patacas) and that of international visitors (2,064 patacas) decreased by 10.3%, 2.1%, and 3.5%, respectively, in relation to 2024. However, the 'per capita' expenditure of visitors from Taiwan (2,083 patacas) grew 6.7%.
 Analyzing the main reason for visiting the Macao SAR, the 'per capita' expenditure of visitors who came to participate in conventions/exhibitions (4,572 patacas) continued to be the highest in 2025, highlights DSEC.
In the entirety of 2025, total visitor expenditure not related to gambling was MOP80.12 billion, rising 6.3% year-on-year. It should be noted that the total expenditure of tourists (63.31 billion patacas) and that of day trippers (16.81 billion patacas) increased by 1.6% and 28.9%, respectively.</description><pubDate>2026-02-08 23:22:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Blood donations rose in 2025, but the number of young donors continues to fall</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/08/dadivas-de-sangue-subiram-em-2025-mas-numero-de-dadores-jovens-continua-em-queda/</link><description>Os Serviços de Saúde revelaram que as reservas de sangue em Macau se mantiveram estáveis em 2025, com quase 14.000 dadores registados e cerca de 19.000 unidades de sangue recolhidas. However, the proportion of donors under the age of 30 continues to decline significantly.

A total of 13,942 residents were registered as blood donors last year, representing a 1.47% increase from the previous year. The information was released by the Blood Transfusion Center, which adds that around 19,000 units of blood were donated to 3,669 patients throughout 2025 – an increase of 6.86% in annual terms.
Despite this growing trend overall, the percentage of young blood donors decreased again last year, to 19.1%. In 2016, remember, the proportion of donors under the age of 30 was 53.4%. This means that, in less than ten years, the number of young donors has fallen drastically by 34.3%.
The Health Services have sought to promote blood donation among the younger population through promotional activities such as, for example, the “Blood Donation Poster Design Competition”, which this year received 87 applications from secondary and higher education students.
On the sidelines of the awards ceremony, which took place last Saturday, the director of the Blood Transfusion Center, Hui Ping, acknowledged that the blood units collected in 2025 were “adequate” and that they even “exceeded hospital demand by 8%”. Quoted by Radio Macau in Chinese, the official warned, however, that “blood inventory levels fluctuate significantly” depending on the time of year, with a tendency to decrease during periods of “extreme” cold or heat or on long holidays – as is the case with the approaching Chinese New Year.
“Platelets have a storage period of just five days, while red blood cells last 42 days,” he explained. “If there are days with a low flow of donors, the inventory becomes unstable.” The answer to this problem involves “regular and long-term” blood donation, in order to guarantee a stable supply in hospitals in the region.
At the same event, the deputy director of Health Services, Cheng Seng Yip, also recalled that blood reserves do not have an artificial substitute, being completely dependent on donations from volunteers.
According to the website of the Blood Transfusion Center, a department under the Health Services, A and AB blood reserves are currently at “ideal” levels. The reserves of blood types O and B, on the other hand, are at a “safe” level – therefore classified between “ideal” and “critical”.
Blood donation requires a prior appointment on the official website and can be done at Alameda Dr. Carlos d’Assumpção, at NAPE, every day except public holidays. The department's blood donation vehicle is also parked in different locations every Tuesday, traveling from Coloane to Areia Preta.
According to authorities, the requirements for donating blood include being between 17 and 69 years of age and weighing 45 kilos or more. Men can donate blood every three months, while women must leave a gap of four months between each donation.</description><pubDate>2026-02-08 23:23:59</pubDate></item><item><title>BNU launches new 1,000 and 500 patacas notes</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/08/bnu-lanca-novas-notas-de-1-000-e-500-patacas/</link><description>Banco Nacional Ultramarino (BNU) announced that a new series of 1,000 and 500 patacas notes have been in circulation since February 6th. The issuance of banknotes with a higher monetary value completes the new series of BNU banknotes, which over the last two years had already put 10, 20, 50 and 100 patacas notes into circulation with a renewed design.
As explained by the bank in a statement, the series marks “a significant milestone in the modernization of Macau’s monetary system”, which thus becomes more “comprehensive and diversified”. In aesthetic terms, the design is inspired by the history and evolution of Macau, reproducing maps that attest to the way in which the territory has changed over the years – from an island to a peninsula expanded by landfills. From 20 to 1,000 patacas, “each note tells a story related to the transformation of the city, reflecting the unique cultural heritage and historical importance that Macau represents”, writes BNU.
In addition to the aesthetic value, new security features have been incorporated that include sparkling patterns that change color when tilting the note, metal security filaments and watermarks in the shape of a lotus flower. Features for the blind were also added, such as tactile marks and Braille marks, which allow these users to identify the note more easily. More than a “means of transaction”, BNU refers to the new series as “a reflection of Macau’s identity as a multicultural and prosperous community”.
It is recalled that BNU was the first bank issuing paper money in Macau, contributing to the creation and development of the local banking and monetary system. Currently, it continues to be one of the issuing banks for the Macao SAR Government.</description><pubDate>2026-02-08 23:13:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Government rejects calls to reinforce paternity leave</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/08/governo-rejeita-apelos-a-reforco-da-licenca-de-paternidade/</link><description>The Macau Government yesterday rejected calls to increase paternity leave, despite the region intending to reinforce maternity leave and annual leave, to reverse the lowest birth rate in the world.

In the first session of a public consultation, representatives of two of the most important traditional associations in the territory defended the extension of paternity leave, currently set at just five working days.
A leader from the General Union of Residents' Associations of Macau said that paternity leave should be extended up to 15 days or, alternatively, part of the leave could be taken by the father.
The representative, surnamed Sit, argued that the measure could help the father to take a more active role, particularly in the first months of the baby's life, especially if the mother is still recovering from a cesarean section.
A representative of the General Association of Women of Macau also called for the strengthening of paternity leave, to encourage fathers to take care of their children and “promote gender equality”. But Maria Chu Pui Man, director of the Directorate of Labor Affairs Services (DSAL), rejected the appeals and said only that the father could, as is currently the case, take days off to support the family after the birth.
The public consultation, running until March 16, is based on a proposal from DSAL to extend maternity leave in the private sector from 70 to 90 days – an amount already applied to public administration employees – with the costs to be shared between the Government and employers. The authorities also want to increase annual leave in the private sector, based on seniority. For 40 years, permanent residents of Macau have been entitled to just six paid days of rest annually. Civil servants are entitled to 22 working days.
The Executive proposes that workers have the right to one more working day of vacation for every two years they spend in the same company, up to a maximum of 12 working days per year.
One of the objectives of the changes, said DSAL director Chan Un Tong on January 30, is to allow the population of Macau to “obtain a better balance between work and family life”.
In 2025, the Government commissioned a study “from a third entity” – whose identity was not revealed – on the possible increase in maternity leave and annual leave, which was completed at the end of the year. The study included a survey, according to which workers consider both the current maternity leave and the annual leave period “insufficient to meet family needs”.
Asked by Lusa about the potential impact of changes in the birth rate in Macau, which in 2024 was the lowest in the world, Chan Un Tong replied that the objective is to “improve workers’ right to rest”.
In 2025, Macau registered 2,871 newborns, a drop of 20.4% and the lowest number of births in almost 50 years, said on January 1, the deputy director of Centro Hospitalar Conde de São Januário, Tai Wa Hou.
Macau recorded just 0.58 births per woman in 2024, far from the value needed to replace generations (2.1), the lowest fertility rate ever in the region and the lowest in the world, according to official data. This value is even lower than the estimate made in a report released in July by the United Nations Department of Economic and Social Affairs (UNDESA): 0.68 births per woman. Although more optimistic, the UNDESA estimate already indicated that Macau would have the lowest birth rate in the world in 2024, a long way from the second jurisdiction on the list, Singapore, with 0.95 births per woman. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-08 23:20:44</pubDate></item><item><title>NGO helps doctors from Timor-Leste to carry out internships in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/08/ong-ajuda-medicos-de-timor-leste-a-realizarem-internatos-em-macau/</link><description>The GX foundation has supported students from Timor-Leste to undertake medical internships in Hong Kong and Macau, said the president of the non-governmental organization (NGO). Leung Chun-ying explained that GX, based in Hong Kong, has provided financial support to allow medical students from the Timor Lorosa’e National University to travel to one of the two Chinese regions.
In an interview with Hong Kong public broadcaster RTHK, the former leader of the territory's government said that the foundation has expanded its work to ten countries on four continents, offering eight different types of assistance.
Leung said GX has signed agreements with three local higher education institutions: the University of Hong Kong, Chinese University and Polytechnic University. The objective, explained the former chief executive of the region, is to help students participate in humanitarian work, so that they can learn “benevolence” in Hong Kong and “compassion” abroad. Leung argued that, faced with major changes in the international panorama, China needs not only to consolidate existing friendships with other countries, but also to make new ones.
Hong Kong has many diplomatic opportunities to be explored, especially in the areas of culture, arts, sports and education, added the vice-chairman of the National Committee of the Chinese People's Political Consultative Conference.
In October 2024, the executive director of GX, Emily Chan Ying-yang, told Lusa that the foundation wanted to apply in other countries, starting with Honduras, a project that reversed the rapid growth of dengue fever in Timor-Leste.
Between January and July, GX installed more than 1,670 anti-mosquito lamps and distributed almost 30,000 adhesive tapes to catch insects, close to 18,000 rapid dengue detection tests and around 500 anti-mosquito nets, in the 14 Timorese municipalities.
Emily Chan said she was “very proud” of the success of the project in Timor-Leste, the first of its kind for a foundation, created in 2018, and which until 2024 was mainly dedicated to cataract surgeries. Emily Chan highlighted that, according to official data from the Timorese Ministry of Health, one of GX's partners, the number of dengue cases decreased by 10% in the first half of 2024, compared to the same period of the previous year. In comparison, the prevalence of this disease, transmitted by mosquitoes, has more than doubled in Southeast Asia, highlighted the leader.</description><pubDate>2026-02-08 23:14:23</pubDate></item><item><title>China revokes death sentence for Canadian in drug case</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/08/china-anula-pena-de-morte-de-um-canadiano-num-caso-de-droga/</link><description>China has canceled the death sentence of a Canadian accused of drug trafficking by Beijing, a Canadian government source said, marking a new sign of reduced diplomatic tension between the two countries. 

Arrested for drug trafficking, Robert Lloyd Schellenberg had been sentenced to death in January 2019, at a time when tensions were very strong between Beijing and Ottawa, following the arrest, in Vancouver (western Canada), of Meng Wanzhou, Huawei's financial director, at the request of the United States.   But relations have since calmed with the release of Meng Wanzhou and as US President Donald Trump's protectionist policies and sometimes erratic diplomacy have led Canada to move closer to China. But in recent months, American President Donald Trump's protectionist impulses and his sometimes erratic diplomacy have led Canada to move closer to China.
In mid-January, Chinese President Xi Jinping and Canadian Prime Minister Mark Carney discussed a new partnership in Beijing, after years of disagreements.
A spokeswoman for the Canadian Ministry of Foreign Affairs said that Ottawa had been informed of “the decision of the Supreme People's Court of the People's Republic of China in the case of Robert Schellenberg”.   “Canada advocated clemency in this case, as it does for all Canadians sentenced to the death penalty,” he added.
Arrested in 2014 for drug trafficking and sentenced in the first instance to 15 years in prison, Robert Lloyd Schellenberg was tried again and sentenced to death in 2019. At the time, the court had considered the initial sentence too “lenient”.
The court had accused him of having played a “key role” in drug trafficking aimed at sending around 222 kilograms of methamphetamine to Australia. Already convicted in the past in Canada for drug trafficking, Schellenberg claimed, in turn, that he was just a tourist who had been caught.
The confirmation of his sentence occurred at a time when Meng Wanzhou was before a Canadian court for hearings dedicated to his possible extradition to the United States.
The financial director of Huawei and daughter of the founder of the Chinese telecommunications giant was accused of having lied to circumvent American sanctions against Iran. At the same time, China had also put two Canadian citizens behind bars, Michael Kovrig and Michael Spavor, accused of espionage.
Although the three have since been released, tensions persisted, with Beijing blaming Ottawa for its alleged alignment with Washington's Chinese policy, until Donald Trump's return to power and his interference in the Canadian elections.
When visiting Beijing in mid-January, Prime Minister Mark Carney wanted to turn the page on years of friction between the two countries. This was the first visit by a Canadian head of government to Beijing since Justin Trudeau in December 2017.
Although Canada has, historically, economically and politically, much stronger ties with its American neighbor, Canada and China have in common suffered, directly or indirectly, in recent years, the effects of President Donald Trump's aggressive policies, both against his rivals and his allies.
Carney made a commitment to see Canada double its exports to countries beyond the United States by 2035. And he highlighted the weight of China: the second economic power representing a third of global growth and with which trade supports hundreds of thousands of Canadians.
China is Canada's second trading partner, behind the United States. The volume of exchange of goods between Canada and China reached 89.62 billion US dollars in 2025. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-08 23:12:46</pubDate></item></channel></rss>