<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/arquitectos-de-macau-em-destaque-na-corrida-aos-cada-2024-hkia-cross-strait-architectural-awards/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Debanda kills at least 18 at a railway station in the capital of India</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/debandada-mata-pelo-menos-18-numa-estacao-ferroviaria-da-capital-da-india/</link><description>At least 18 people died in a stampede at a railway station in the capital of India, Nova Deli, Press Trust of India reported news agency. Nova Deli's interim chief minister, Atishi, said many of the victims traveled to Prayagraj in northern India, where the Kumbh Mela festival is taking place, which originates annually the largest Hindu pilgrimage in the world.
The stampede took place on Saturday night, while thousands of people were gathered at Nova Deli's railway station waiting to catch a train.
The incident occurred after some passengers slipped and fallen over others as they descended from a passage that connects trains platforms, the authorities said.
Sheela Devi, who was at Hospital Lok Nayak Jai Prakash Narain in Nova Delhi, to collect her daughter -in -law, said an announcement about a change of train platform created confusion among passengers, which led to the stampede.
Indian Prime Minister Narendra Moda said he was "distressed by the stampede." “My thoughts are with all those who have lost their loved ones. I pray that the injured have a quick recovery. Authorities are assisting all those who have been affected by this stampede, ”Modi said on social network X.
Railway Minister Ashwini Vaishnaw said an investigation was ordered to find out what led to the stampede.
The incident happened a day after at least ten people died and another 19 was injured after a vehicle that was heading for Kumbh Mela collided with an bus.
Traffic accidents are common in India due to poor road conditions, the precarious conditions of some vehicles and the lack of attention to drivers' traffic rules. In recent days, Kumbh mela organizers have banned vehicle circulation in the festival area after thousands of people have been trapped in many traffic jams, with an extension of more than 200 kilometers and some drivers reporting that they needed 12 hours to Advance 50 kilometers.
Kumbh Mela has been taking place every 12 years in a different city (between Prayagraj, Ujjain, Nashik and Haridwar) and has a ritual bath that happens at the confluence of the Ganges, Yamuna and Saraswati rivers.
The Hindus, which represent almost 80% of the country's more than 1.4 billion more than 1.4 billion, believe that a dive in this considered sacred place can purify them from past sins and end the reincarnation process.
The train tickets sold out before Kumbh Mela began, while the cost of plane tickets fired, leading millions of people to opt for the car trip.
This year's edition of the festival, which lasts six weeks, was already marked by the death of at least 30 people in a stampede on January 29.</description><pubDate>2025-02-17T03:14:55+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cook Islands sign “Strategic Partnership” with China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/ilhas-cook-assinam-parceria-estrategica-com-a-china/</link><description>The Cook Islands announced the signing of a “strategic partnership” with China, but stated that it “does not replace” relations with the neighbors of the Pacific, where Beijing is expanding its influence.
 
The agreement covers “areas aligned with our national and long-term developmental interests,” said Prime Minister of the Little Archipelago of 17,000 in a statement on Saturday.
Mark Brown ended an official five-day visit to China on Friday, during which he met with Chinese counterparts, Li Qiang.
The head of the Government of the Cook islands said that the partnership with Beijing includes commerce, investment, oceanography, infrastructure and transport, adding that the details will be announced "in the coming days". "Our relationship and involvement with China complement, do not replace our longtime relationships with New Zealand and many other bilateral, regional and multilateral partners," Brown said.
On Friday, the Cook Islands, former New Zealand colony, had announced the beginning of conversations with China about the exploration of submarine mineral resources.
The small autonomous nation of the Pacific has granted a license to three companies to explore the marine background in search of metal rich nodules, such as nickel and cobalt, used in electric cars batteries. "These conversations have opened the door to new collaboration areas," Mark Brown said.
The ruler, who is also responsible for marine funds folder, stressed the fact that this sector is able to be worth several thousand millions of dollars.
Last year, Brown stressed that Cook Islands needed to protect themselves against climate change "with all the recipes we can get."
Deepwater extraction advocates state that potato -size nickel and cobalt tablets can be easily extracted from the bottom of the sea, helping to reduce the dependence of fossil fuels.
Last week, New Zealand expressed “profound concern” regarding a cooperation agreement negotiated with China, whose details were not published.
The Cook Islands, which have a vast exclusive economic zone in the heart of the South Pacific, have a “free association” agreement with New Zealand, which provides them with budgetary support and assistance in foreign affairs and defense. Its inhabitants enjoy New Zealand citizenship.
China is seeking to widen its diplomatic, economic and military influence in the strategic region of the Pacific, challenging the historical role of the United States, New Zealand and Australia.
In December, the Cook Islands received Chinese Foreign Minister Ma Zhaozu to discuss ties in areas such as economic development, health, education and response to climate change. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-17T03:11:05+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai strengthens ties with Hong Kong on an official visit</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/sam-hou-fai-fortalece-lacos-com-hong-kong-em-visita-oficial/</link><description>Macao and Hong Kong reinforced their collaboration on a official visit, led by Sam Hou Fai, focused on innovation, finance, tourism and other key sectors. The overall objective of boosting the great bay and aligning with national strategies for the development of the regions was discussed. The meeting highlighted the complementarity between the two governments and the commitment to cooperation.
 
In a demonstration of fraternal ties and shared objectives, the leaders of Macao and Hong Kong met to solidify relevant diplomacy for the future of the two regions. Executive head, Sam Hou Fai, traveled to Hong Kong last Friday, for a meeting with John Lee, his counterpart in Raehk, a clear sign of the priority that both administrations attribute to mutual collaboration. The meeting took place at the official residence of the local government leader, where strategies were outlined to boost a future of joint progress.
In focus there were areas considered crucial for the future development of Macau and Hong Kong, such as technological innovation, the financial sector, the promotion of traditional Chinese medicine, the increase in tourism, the cultural and sports exchange, and the joint organization of events relief, as conventions and exhibitions. The leaders have expressed a commitment to work together to raise the quality of building the Great Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau Bay, aligning efforts to contribute to national growth and improve citizens' lives. The information was advanced by the Social Communication Office (GCS).
Sam Hou Fai expressed gratitude for the support that Hong Kong has provided Macau, highlighting the unique advantages that result from the status of both regions under the principle of a country, two systems. Recognizing that each region has its own identity and specialization areas, it underlined the complementarity between Macau and Hong Kong, arguing that the narrowing of cooperation will bring mutual benefits and boost the progress of both territories.
Sam Hou Fai recalled once again the words and guidelines of President XI Jinping, namely with regard to the importance of economic diversification and the international projection of Macao. It argued that it is essential that both regions articulate their strategies with the National Development Plan and take advantage of the opportunities provided by the Great Bay, thus raising the level of bilateral collaboration, promoting the well-being of the populations.
During the meeting, the need to strengthen the mechanisms of legal aid between the two regions was also addressed, demonstrating the scope of the cooperation agenda.
Before the formal meeting, Sam Hou Fai and his entourage had the opportunity to visit Hong Kong Science Park and the Hong Kong Palace Museum, where they were able to get to know the technological advances and the results of cultural collaboration with the interior From China. The chief executive reaffirmed Macau's commitment to the diversification of his economy, in particular in the sectors of health and technology, and highlighted the importance of promoting multicultural coexistence. He expressed the desire that, in the context of integration in the Great Bay, Hong Kong and Macau continue to deepen cooperation in these areas, boosting joint development and a more prosperous future for both regions.
The delegation of Macao was attended by high government officials, including the secretary for the administration and justice of the MSAR, André Cheong, the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP, the secretary for transport and public works, also will Man, Chief Executive's Chief of Staff, Chan Kak, and the Director of Regional Policy Study Services, Cheong Chok Man. Finance Secretary Paul Mo-Po, Director of Services for Constitutional and Interior Affairs of China, Erick Tsang Kwok-Wai, the Director of Innovation, Technology and Industry Services, Sun Dong, the Director of Transportation Services and logistics, Mabel Chan MEI-PO, the director of culture, sports and tourism services, Rosanna Law Shuk-Pui, and the chief executive's office director Carol Yip Man-Kuen, among others.</description><pubDate>2025-02-17T03:13:47+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China and Brazil reaffirm in Munich commitment to peace</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/china-e-brasil-reafirmam-em-munique-compromisso-com-a-paz/</link><description>Chinese diplomacy chief Wang Yi reiterated in Munich in a meeting with Brazilian special counselor Celso Amorim, the commitment of the two countries to end the war in Ukraine, China said.
At a meeting on the sidelines of the Munich Security Conference, the Chinese and Amorim Foreign Minister, a special sent by Brazilian President Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva, reaffirmed the good health of bilateral relations.
In a statement, the China Ministry of Foreign Affairs said they both highlighted the work of the “Friends of Peace” platform, created by the two countries within the UN to explore alternative peaceful solutions for war in Ukraine, and pledged to play a role constructive in obtaining a political solution.
China and Brazil have pressured developing countries to support a six -point peace plan, which presented in 2024, which describes the Russian invasion of Ukraine as “a crisis”, asks “the end of climbing or provocation by either party ”and appeals to an international peace conference through a“ fair debate ”.
The initiative was received with skepticism by many Western countries and Ukraine itself, mainly due to the ambiguity demonstrated by Beijing since the beginning of the conflict and its tacit support to Moscow.
Wang stressed that China is willing to work with Brazil to continue cooperation, "practice true multilateralism, defend the fundamental role of the United Nations and safeguard the legitimate rights and interests of global southern countries."
Amorim told the Chinese diplomat that Brazil is open to continuing to work with the Asian giant to "defend international justice."
Wang and Amorim also agreed to deepen cooperation in Latin America and the BRICS Community of Emerging Economies, whose rotating presidency was assumed by Brazil this year.
The Brics of Brics Cimeira, formed by Brazil, Russia, India, China and South Africa, will take place in Rio de Janeiro on July 6 and 07. In addition to the founding countries, in recent years, Egypt, the United Arab Emirates, Ethiopia, Iran, Indonesia and Saudi Arabia joined the bloc as members of full right, and Bolivia, Cuba, Belarus, the Kazakhstan, Malaysia, Thailand, Uganda, Uzbekistan and Nigeria have recently joined as associated states.</description><pubDate>2025-02-17T03:11:03+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal point 2025.02.17</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/ponto-fatal-2025-02-17/</link><description>Chinese diplomacy chief Wang Yi reiterated in Munich in a meeting with Brazilian special counselor Celso Amorim, the commitment of the two countries to end the war in Ukraine, China said.
At a meeting on the sidelines of the Munich Security Conference, the Chinese and Amorim Foreign Minister, a special sent by Brazilian President Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva, reaffirmed the good health of bilateral relations.
In a statement, the China Ministry of Foreign Affairs said they both highlighted the work of the “Friends of Peace” platform, created by the two countries within the UN to explore alternative peaceful solutions for war in Ukraine, and pledged to play a role constructive in obtaining a political solution.
China and Brazil have pressured developing countries to support a six -point peace plan, which presented in 2024, which describes the Russian invasion of Ukraine as “a crisis”, asks “the end of climbing or provocation by either party ”and appeals to an international peace conference through a“ fair debate ”.
The initiative was received with skepticism by many Western countries and Ukraine itself, mainly due to the ambiguity demonstrated by Beijing since the beginning of the conflict and its tacit support to Moscow.
Wang stressed that China is willing to work with Brazil to continue cooperation, "practice true multilateralism, defend the fundamental role of the United Nations and safeguard the legitimate rights and interests of global southern countries."
Amorim told the Chinese diplomat that Brazil is open to continuing to work with the Asian giant to "defend international justice."
Wang and Amorim also agreed to deepen cooperation in Latin America and the BRICS Community of Emerging Economies, whose rotating presidency was assumed by Brazil this year.
The Brics of Brics Cimeira, formed by Brazil, Russia, India, China and South Africa, will take place in Rio de Janeiro on July 6 and 07. In addition to the founding countries, in recent years, Egypt, the United Arab Emirates, Ethiopia, Iran, Indonesia and Saudi Arabia joined the bloc as members of full right, and Bolivia, Cuba, Belarus, the Kazakhstan, Malaysia, Thailand, Uganda, Uzbekistan and Nigeria have recently joined as associated states.</description><pubDate>2025-02-17T03:10:05+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Young Timorese study English and Korean in search of work abroad</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/jovens-timorenses-estudam-ingles-e-coreano-em-busca-de-trabalho-no-estrangeiro/</link><description>Hundreds of young Timorese are studying English and Korean in various vocational training centers in the country to be selected for temporary work programs in Australia and South Korea.
 
“I am participating in the English course, because I want to work in Australia. We learned the language in packages: first the theoretical module, then the practice and the internship. The English course lasts only three months, which, for me, is sufficient. However, it all depends on individual effort, ”Lusa Nicolina Faria Freitas, 29, told.
Nicolina Faria Freitas stated that, after finishing the English language course at the Training Center, she may apply for vacancies that will be opened by the State Secretariat for Vocational Training and Employment (Sefope) to work in Australia, where her sister is already there for Four years. "This is my main goal and I am confident that I will be able to pass the exams that will come," said the young woman.
More than 70% of the population of Timor-Leste, with 1.3 million inhabitants, is less than 35 years old and, according to the United Nations data, more than 30% of young people are unemployed.
Nicolina Faria Freitas is one of hundreds of young people who attend the Grace of Development Training Center, which offers several courses, including languages, and recently received a visit from Sefope.
Martinho Nascimento Mali, 23, is another forming of that center, but chose to study Korean, inspired by the brothers and neighbors of the municipality of Aileu, where he currently lives. The course, lasting six months, has a monthly fee of $ 15. “I chose the Korean language course because I want to look for better living conditions abroad and thus improve my future,” said Martinho Mali, visibly pleased with his learning program.
With about 300 graduates, that educational establishment tries to inspire young people to be entrepreneurs and create their own job or to integrate work mobility programs. “Trainees who complete the course at the Center will be able to communicate with Sefope to facilitate the creation of small businesses” or receive information about work abroad, namely in Australia and South Korea, said the director of the Training Center, Hilario Gusmão Fraga.
In addition to languages, young people can also take entrepreneurship, computer science, administration, journalism, among others. "I hope that, upon completion of training, students will get a job or can work abroad and create their own businesses," said Hilario Gusmão Fraga.
Sefope's visit aimed to encourage young people and also share information about what they need to integrate the world of work.
Data from the World Bank, released in November 2023, indicate that about 20% of young Timorese, aged 15 and 24, do not study or work due to the lack of education, limitations on health and ineffectiveness of social protection. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-17T03:14:54+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>"Hard" season of "White Lotus" explores spirituality in Thailand</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/temporada-mais-dificil-de-white-lotus-explora-espiritualidade-na-tailandia/</link><description>The third season of the series "White Lotus", which opens on February 17 at the Max Portugal service, explores religion and spirituality in Thailand and was the "hardest of all," said creator Mike White.  "It was harder because it is longer, there are more characters, and Thailand is a beautiful place to film but presented many challenges," the creator said at a Los Angeles release conference.
The new season has eight episodes, one more than the previous and two more than the original. It brings back two characters that the audience met in the first and second seasons: Masseur Belinda (played by Natasha Rothwell) and the widower of Tanya Mcquoid, Greg Hunt (played by Jon Gries).  “We were sad because the character of Jennifer Coolidge [Tanya] died in the last episode and we wanted to bring her back, in a way, with Belinda,” explained Mike White. Belinda was the masseuse that Tanya said she was going to help in the first season and then did not.
White, interested in Buddhism for several years, wanted to turn to an exploitation of religion, God and spirituality this season. "Thailand seemed the perfect scenario because it is a Buddhist country and there is something in its culture where it seemed interesting to introduce the chaos of Western," he said.
Mike White also wanted to analyze how people seek to reach their ideal self but always seem to be supplanted "by a force that pushes them back to the land of the monkeys." The omnipresence of monkeys in the resort where the characters are installed reinforces this idea.
Although with a different theme and rhythm from the previous ones, the narrative style of “White Lotus” remains this third season. It starts with a crime, where it is not possible to see who the victim is, and walks back in time to explain how to the tragic outcome.
In this resort of Thailand, the audience is presented to a group of three friends in the forties - Jaclyn (Michelle Monaghan), Laurie (Carrie Coon) and Kate (Leslie Bible), whose relationship deteriorates over the episodes.  “Everyone is pretending to pretend,” Carrie Coon described at the Los Angeles conference. "And I believe that we can all identify with this to pretend that we live an extraordinary life, when we actually feel out," he added.
Leslie Bible pointed out that this is a problem exacerbated by social networks like Instagram, which make it difficult to resist comparison and judgment. "The lives of others look much more like a phone than in real life, which when they are really happening," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-02-17T03:14:54+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Pinto da Costa, the “President of the Presidents” died</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/morreu-pinto-da-costa-o-presidente-dos-presidentes/</link><description>At the age of 87, the man who was eternalized inside and outside the Football Club of Porto. Beloved and hated, controversial and acclaimed, he leaves an indelible legacy: he is the most titled sports leader in the world and also the one who has held the position longer. The president of the Macao Port Football Club Casa speaks of a “unrepeatable” figure that made an unavoidable - and eternal - mark in the sport world.
 
Jorge Nuno Pinto da Costa, former president of Futebol Clube do Porto, died on Saturday at the age of 87, a victim of prolonged illness. He had been diagnosed with prostate cancer in September 2021 and his health was worsened in recent weeks, which he preferred to pass among the family.
Still, the portist supporters welcomed the news with shock and unbelief. Not because it was inverse, not because it was unexpected. Because not only one man died, they say, An icon died.
Diana Massada, president of the Macao Port Football Club Casa, learned the news on social networks - it was Sunday dawn in Macau and early Saturday night in Portugal. Her reaction describes her using two constant words throughout the conversation with the end point: "Sadness" and "empty."
"It was not quite a surprise," he acknowledges, but the impact of the news has not been softened. “It was a punch. Although age and disease already guess that, in the near future, it could happen… there is always hope and an expectation that this future will be distant and not so present. ”
Controversial and acclaimed to an equal measure, Pinto da Costa reached the (hardly surplus) statute of the world's longer and award -winning sports leader: 2,591 the trophies that Porto gained under its leadership in 21 different modalities that are not only limited to soccer.  “It is 42 years of presidency that turned a club from a small town into a large world club,” says Diana Massada. “It was a great leader who got what no other, to this day, managed to achieve in worldwide terms. It is a phenomenon among all sports leaders in the world. ”
In parallel to victories, achievements and four -time championships achieved during the presidency, Pinto da Costa was coinning a way of thinking and communicating very its own, often scathing and sardile, which kept up to the last public interventions. In the last book he published in 2024, entitled “Blue to the End,” he is faithful to his essence and requires a personalized funeral, away from commonplaces and monotony-instead of black, blue ties; Instead of mourning, anecdotes and warm honors to FC Porto. Without curbing names, he also prepares a list of unwanted presences in the funeral ceremony, including the current president of the dragons, André Villas-Boas.
The scandals and controversies have followed over 15 terms, inside and outside their professional life. From alleged cases of corruption, trafficking in influence and coercion on tabloid headlines about his personal life, the reputation of Pinto de Costa suffered various shaking and remained irregular over the decades-though, in the eyes of justice, not justice, has been convicted of any of the criminal proceedings to which he was associated. In 2024, the reign at the club came to an end with blunt results and a polarized image between the partners: numa elections stories with more than 26,000 voters (more than double than the previous record of 1988), Pinto da Costa did not reach 20 % of the votes and passed the folder to André Villas-Boas.
“Personally, I'm sorry I left the club with such a heavy defeat,” admits Diana Massada, echoing the one who says she is a popular opinion among the fans. "A lot of people say they could probably and should have passed the presidency just before, without having to reach this defeat so vehemently." The president of the Macao Port Football Club House does not believe, however, that this bitter ending is significant in the global context of a career marked by the revitalization and internationalization of a club perhaps eternally associated with its figure. “It is not, surely, that it will be in the hearts of the Portuguese,” he reiterates.
What legacy leaves Pinto da Costa then? The nicks that have been receiving over the years by parts of the fans help to frame the true dimension of their figure: "Papa", "President of Presidents." Even the controversy helped cement a more personality than football itself, Diana Massada says. He was a “controversial man, with many jokes, always ready to find more at the fire between the north and the south,” but it was also this untimely and brutally honest temperament that worked as a “motor to bring the teams under his vitration” , both in football and other modalities. What will stay, believes the leader of the Porto Association, "is the person who turned this club into a major world club."
Findas over four decades of the presidency of Pinto da Costa, the year 2024 began a new era under the command of André Villas-Boas-“a great president,” praises Diana Massada. Nevertheless, it is hard to imagine a personality with impact and charisma similar to those of Jorge Nuno Pinto da Costa, inside and outside the pitch. The leader of the Porto Association believes in a prosperous future, with relief leaders, resounding victories and “great moments” eternalized in the club's history. But can the legacy of Pinto da Costa be overcome or even equal? Diana Massada does not hesitate to answer: “Very honestly, I doubt that we will have another leader who makes the transformation he has made. President Pinto da Costa, the president of the presidents, is unique and unrepeatable. ”
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>ASSOCIATION Alert for the fall of the purchasing power of tourists in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/associacao-alerta-para-queda-do-poder-de-compra-dos-turistas-em-macau/</link><description>The environment caused by the high interest rates and changes in international customs policies is threatening Renminbi and could affect the purchasing power of Chinese visitors in Macao, warned the Macao Economic Association. In its latest economic study, the association drew attention to increasing the global rally credit ratio and game revenues below expectations, stressing that the region faces uncertainties. However, the economy should remain stable.
 
The Macao Economic Association is concerned about the eventual decrease in purchasing power by tourists visiting Macau, especially those from the interior of China. According to the analysis, the global economic environment is “complicated” due to international interest rates and policies, and Renminbi “could continue to weaken”, which endangers the expense of visitors in the territory.
“The United States recently implemented additional products on products from many countries, including China, and friction in international trade are frequent. In January this year, the production rates of many of the main countries remained below the average purchasing managers' rate, ”said Joey Lao, president of the Macao Economic Association.
According to statistics and census services, the per capita expense of visitors, referring to last year, was 2,157 patacas, 14.6%, compared to 2023. The per capita spending of tourists staying over Macao, of 3,884 patacas, and that of the tour, 691 patacas, lowered 8.2% and 12.7%, respectively.
In a monthly report of economic forecasts, the economist also recalled that the last US consumer prices increase “exceeded market expectations” and Powell, president of the United States Federal Reserve System, reiterated that there is no hurry to adjust rates of interest. "Prudent policies could be maintained for a longer period of time, which further aggravated uncertainty," he warned.
Joey Lao pointed out that, as uncertainties and external complexities increase, visitors arrived slightly at 3.5% during recent Lunar New Year's holidays in Macao, while the game's recipes were “short of expectations” in the market . It is recalled that the daily average of the game's gross revenues, both in December last year and in January this year, went down below 600 million patacas, to 587 million patacas and 589 million patacas, respectively.
In this case, some analysis entities have adjusted their predictions for the growth of gross macao game revenues this year, which implies that the market is more cautious about perspectives, according to the economist.
The former deputy also recalled that the global loan ratio compared to local banks deposits continued to decrease, from 100% in June 2023 to 79.3% in December last year, ie there is a continuous demand decline for demand of loans. "Along with the fact that the Malparado global credit ratio has increased, the financial sector faces certain pressures," he warned.
However, the Macao Economic Association stressed that other employment-related indicators and unemployment rate “record good results” and, in general, economic perspectives for territory remain at a “stable” level in the next three months. Joey Lao said he hopes that monetary policies and incentives for consumption, now launched by the continent's authorities, could have a positive impact on Macau's economy.</description><pubDate>2025-02-17T03:15:25+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Deputy Minister of Education wants Macau to accelerate integration into national development</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/vice-ministro-da-educacao-quer-que-macau-acelere-integracao-no-desenvolvimento-nacional/</link><description>Wu Yan, Deputy Minister of Education of the Central Government, was in Macao, having found themselves with the authorities of the MSAR. At the time, the head of Beijing participated in a session of publicizing the “General Planning Lines for the Construction of a Strong Nation in Education (2024-2035)”, where Macao urged to accelerate integration into the national development strategy.
 
Wu Yan, Central Government Deputy Minister of Education, wants Macau to accelerate integration efforts into the national development strategy. The message was shared by Beijing's guardian on his recent visit to Macau.
In this visit, Wu Yan began to meet the head of the Executive of MSAR, where the education and the idea “Industry-Investigation” was discussed. In this meeting, Sam Hou Fai assured that the MSar is committed “in the development of the proper diversification of the economy, in the construction of a high quality education system in Macao, in reinforcing the promotion of the development of industry-university-investigation, and the realization of scientific and technological innovation and transformation of their results ”.
On the other hand, the chief executive told Wu Yan that the local executive is “studying long -term policies to fully take advantage of the singular role and special advantages of the territory and, based on the position of 'a center, a platform and A base ', promoting cooperation with more universities of excellence and exceptional national and abroad companies in the areas of innovation in high quality scientific research and industry-university-investment. ”
During the passage through Macao, Wu Yan also participated in a session of publicizing the “General Planning Lines for the Construction of a Strong Nation in Education (2024-2035)”, where 400 guests were present, including local rulers, responsible for the institutions of institutions Higher Education of Macao and representatives of educational associations, for example.
In this session, the deputy minister stated that Macau should be articulated with the national development strategy and “accelerate its integration into this development”, in particular, “must fully use the unique advantages of the deepened cooperation zone with Guangdong in Hengqin and integrate in the construction of an International Center for Scientific and Technological Innovation, an Integrated National Science Center and a place of aggregation of high-level qualified frames in the Great Bay area, and must advocate fundamental values, fostering inclusion and Harmony, transmitting full values ​​of love for the homeland and the region, stimulating exchange and multicultural fusion, uniting all positive forces, with the contribution of local forces to the construction of a great educational power. ”
LAM, secretary for social affairs and culture, also spoke at this session, stressing that "the Government of the MSAR will fully and firmly implement the spirit referred to in the important words given by President XI Jinping during his visit to Macao." The secretary highlighted the importance of creating a “fair and quality education system at various levels, coordinating and promoting the integrated development of education, science, technology and qualified staff, constantly increasing the influence and attractiveness of education. in Macao ”.
The secretary said he hopes that the “prosperous development of education will be promoted, with active integration in national development, and that Macao plays his role, making a strong contribution to the construction of a great educational power”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-17T03:12:07+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>About 260 foreigners rescued from online burla centers in Myanmar</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/cerca-de-260-estrangeiros-resgatados-de-centros-de-burla-online-em-myanmar/</link><description>About 260 foreigners, including Brazilians, who will have been trafficked and forced to work in online burla centers will be repatriated after being rescued from neighboring Myanmar, the Thailand army announced.
 
The army said on Thursday that the rescued in the latest operation came from 20 countries, especially China, Ethiopia, Kenya, Philippines, Malaysia and Pakistan. But the list also includes citizens of Taiwan, Brazil, Indonesia, Nepal, Uganda, Laos, Burundi, Tanzania, Bangladesh, Cambodia, Sri Lanka, Nigeria, Ghana and India.
Foreigners were sent through the MYAWADDY District border in Myanmar to the province of Tak, Thailand, on Wednesday.
The Thai press said that a Myanmar ethnic militia that controls the area where they were detained, the Democratic Benevolent Army Karen, was responsible for releasing workers and taking them to the border.
The army statement said that the rescued persons will be questioned and, if they are considered victims of human trafficking, will enter a protection process while waiting to be sent back to their countries.
Deputy Prime Minister Phumtham Wechayachai, who is also a defense minister, said on Wednesday that there may be many more workers retained in Myanmar. But it stressed that Thailand will only receive those who are ready to be taken back immediately to their home country. "I made it clear that Thailand will not set up another shelter," he told reporters during a visit to Sa Kaeo province, which borders Cambodia.
Thailand houses nine refugee camps along the border, welcoming over 100,000 people, most of Myanmar's ethnic minority.
On a visit to China, in early February, Thai Prime Minister Paetongtarn Shinawatra promised, along with Chinese leader Xi Jinping, repressing cyber burla nets that plague Southeast Asia.
On February 5, Thailand cut electricity at five points on the Myanmar border to combat cyber fraud centers in Burmese territory, which in recent years have created regional security problems with thousands of victims.
Cutting the supply of electricity also arises following an unusual request from the Myanmar Military Junta - in power after a coup in February 2021 - through an editorial published in the official media, in which it asks for help to countries neighbors in the fight against these groups.
According to the figures presented in the article, the Burmese regime deported more than 53,000 Chinese involved in online burla centers between October 2023 and late January 2024. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-17T03:14:56+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Wong Sio Chak alerts back to job proposals abroad</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/wong-sio-chak-volta-a-alertar-para-burlas-de-propostas-de-emprego-no-estrangeiro/</link><description>In the monthly message published on the Secretary's Office Portal for Security, Wong Sio Chak alerted to job proposals abroad again.
In the publication, the Secretary for Security recalls that, since September 2024, five citizens of Macao have been caught in this type of burles, four of which were arrested locally for criminal participation, while one managed to escape and return to Macao safely. In recent months, by the way, cases involving seduced Chinese citizens have been frequent to move abroad, where they are enticed and sometimes forced to engage in burlas using telecommunications and the internet.
"The scam -related workmanship abroad in danger, in a serious way, is the safety of people, being an extremely serious crime," says Wong Sio Chak.
The Secretary for Security warns that victims are seduced with false promises, deceived and taken abroad where they are later transferred to a circum -dedicated centers using telecommunications and the internet and where they are forced to perform criminal acts. According to the data, young people are the main target of the gangs. On the other hand, these criminal gangs take advantage of the victims' desire for high salaries and the urgency in searching for work. Victims are usually recruited over the internet, and when they arrive at their destination, their mobile phones and travel documents are confiscated, their personal and communication freedoms are restricted, becoming difficult for them to seek help.
So Wong Sio Chak leaves some advice: “Always be wary when you find online job offers abroad or have third party invitations for it. It is essential to carefully check whether the content of the work is legal and whether the contracting company or the employment intermediary operates legitimately. ” “Anyone involved in this type of activity, regardless of the role they play, can be the target of criminal action. Do not feed the illusion that you can escape justice and avoid putting yourself in an illegality, ”says the secretary.
In any suspicious case, the Judicial Police should be contacted through the open line for the prevention of the circumvents, 8800 7777, or through the open line 993.</description><pubDate>2025-02-17T03:10:05+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Poly MGM Museum receives half a million visitors in three months</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/museu-poly-mgm-recebe-meio-milhao-de-visitantes-em-tres-meses/</link><description>The exhibition “The Seda Maritime Route - discover the mystical seas and finds the treasures of the former commercial route” has provided a new breath to the Macao cultural and tourist industries, attracting more than half a million visitors since November 2024. Visitor, a tourist from Guangdong, was entitled to exclusive and personalized offers from the museum.
 
The Poly MGM Museum reached the milestone of 500,000 visitors in three months, with a number of daily visitors exceeding 10,000 during the Chinese New Year celebration period.
The feat was celebrated with the offer of a set of gifts to the 500,000th visitor, identified in a press release of MGM as “Mr. Chen of Foshan, Guangdong”, who was on vacation in Macao with his wife and children in moment of visiting the museum.
The statement details that the “precious commemorative gifts” included “an exquisite set of cups inspired by the ornate decorations of the Dougong columns [a very characteristic structural element of the Museum's traditional architecture], a catalog autographed by the MGM president and executive director, Pansy Ho, as well as “a series of exclusive MGM experiences”.
In a reaction to half a million visitors in a short time, Pansy Ho recognizes that the museum “has attracted visitors from around the world with great enthusiasm for cultural treasures and top -quality contemporary works”, a fact that “has been Very encouraging in our work of strengthening Macau as a window for cultural exchange between the East the West, strengthening its status as a crucial knot on the headquarters of headquarters, and for the promotion and preservation of Chinese culture. ”
It is recalled that the first exhibition of the Poly MGM Museum has as its theme “The Silk Maritime Route-discover the mystical seas and finds the treasures of the old commercial route” and besides the role of Macao on both the oceanic commercial route and Cultural exchange between China and the West.
In addition to various objects linked to the silk sea route, such as underwater discoveries, fabrics, spices and rare treasures, the exhibition also integrates contemporary works of art and interactive experiences using artificial intelligence. The highlight will probably be the exhibition of four of the 12 heads of the animals of the former Summer Palace of Beijing (Jardim Yuanming): the original sculptures of the monkey, the buffalo, the tiger and the pig.
Executive Chief Sam Hou Fai visited the exhibition at the beginning of February and said at the time that “the harmonious coexistence of Chinese and Western cultures over hundreds of years in Macao has accumulated a rich cultural connotation and deep, which gives a unique advantage by making Macau on a basis of exchange and cooperation with Chinese culture as the main and multicultural coexistence. ”
The chief executive stressed that tourism and leisure companies should “make the most of Macau's advantages with regard to the coexistence of cultures, making efforts to develop non-game elements projects such as subjects subordinate to cultural tourism”.
In a similar note, the president of MGM guarantees efforts to continue “developing the museum with innovation and creativity, bringing even more diverse experiences to our visitors and polishing the Macao's 'gold business card' as a cultural tourism metropolis” . Sandy Ho also announces that a second exhibition is expected to debut before the end of the year, without disclosing more details on the topic or specific dates.
The Poly MGM Museum, the first international standard museum within a resort integrated in Greater China, is born from a partnership with the Culture Culture Group Culture and Art Company and MGM game operator. Located on the second floor of MGM Macau, the space occupies almost 2,000 square meters and follows the Chinese national standards for the exposure of cultural relics.
The first and current exhibition of Poly MGM began on November 2 and will remain on display until September 2025, being available from Monday to Thursday from 11am to 7pm, Fridays from 11am to 9pm, and on the weekends and holidays from 10am to 8pm. The museum offers professional guided tours in Cantonese and Mandarin daily at 15:00 and 5:00 pm, respectively, and offers a digital guided tours system for visitors who prefer to explore at their own pace. Top of Formbottom of Form
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>China warns that Asia “is not a place for rivalries” after Trump-Modi meeting</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/china-adverte-que-asia-nao-e-lugar-para-rivalidades-apos-reuniao-trump-modi/</link><description>The Chinese government has warned that the Asia region - Pacific is not "an arena for geopolitical rivalry," after a summit between the United States and India, which aimed to counteract China's rise.
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakun made statements after a meeting the day before US President Donald Trump and Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi, in which the two praised each other mutually And they highlighted their friendship from decades, partly to wage China's advance in the world order. “Relationships between countries should not aim for third parties or seek to harm the interests of others. Asia Pacific follows the path of peaceful development and is not an arena of geopolitical rivalry, ”said the spokesman.
Not to mention at any time the United States or India, Guo has asked countries to have no purpose in their bilateral relations, creating “clashes between blocks” because this policy will not create security or maintain the region or the world stable and peaceful ”.
Trump reinforced his relationship with Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi, with the promise of a trade agreement to relieve US rates.
Among the pacts achieved are “a large energy agreement that will restore the United States as one of the leading oil and gas suppliers to India” and an increase in Washington military sales to the Asian country.
Relations between China and India, the two largest Asian powers, were severely deteriorated from 2020, when an illegal Chinese military detachment caused an Indian reaction that defined in a border confrontation in the Ladakh territory-a territory of Himalayas claimed by China - In which 20 Indian soldiers and 76 others were injured, and an official number of four dead Chinese soldiers. Since then, the powers have increased their military presence in the area, aggravating hostility.
Asian giants have a historical dispute for some regions of Himalayas, such as Aksai Chin, run by China and claimed by India, and various parts of Arunachal Pradesh's Indian state, where the situation is reverse.
However, in recent months, ties between the two countries have improved, and last January Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi defended “understanding” instead of “removal and suspicion” after gathering In Beijing with Indian foreign secretary, Vikram Misri.</description><pubDate>2025-02-17T03:11:04+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>ATFPM elections scheduled for October 26</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/eleicoes-na-atfpm-marcadas-para-dia-26-de-outubro/</link><description>The elections for the Board of Directors and Fiscal Council of the Macao Public Function Association (ATFPM) are scheduled for October 26 this year. The date was unanimously approved at the meeting of the General Assembly held last Thursday afternoon. It was also unanimously approved that the current structure of the Board and the Fiscal Council will remain until December 31, 2025.
In a statement, the association says that the members present expressed "the hope that ATFPM will continue to fight with the government to ensure the basic claims of the members." “Given that the members present are mostly civil service workers, they reported that, currently, the cost of living in Macau is extremely high, being forced to reside inside China to survive. Therefore, they expect the government to adjust the index value of the civil service from 94 to 97 patacas, ”the association reiterates.
According to the statement issued by the ATFPM, the members said at the meeting that "they hope the government truly understand the difficulties faced by the elderly of Macao in their daily lives." “With the constant increase in the prices of essential goods, the current amounts of the pension and the subsidy for the elderly are insufficient to cover daily expenses. Therefore, they suggest that these values ​​be increased to 4,500 patacas and 10,000 patacas, respectively, and that the payment of the pension is changed from quarterly to monthly ”.
The association whose president of the board is Deputy José Pereira Coutinho again asked for the distribution of “at least another round of electronic consumer cards worth 8,000 patacas, taking into account the current high cost of living environment”. Finally, the ATFPM says that “some partners also reported that the waiting time to join the elderly homes in Macau is too long, and the government must continue to increase the number of available households, so as to relieve current scarcity ”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-17T03:10:08+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lace of housing fractions grew by 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/rendas-das-fraccoes-habitacionais-cresceram-em-2024/</link><description>Last year, the square income of housing fractions was, on average, 137 patacas, which means an annual increase of 3.9%. According to data from the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), this was due to the “growth of the number of lease agreements of autonomous fractions of large housing buildings”.
 
Last year, the average income per square meter of housing autonomous fractions was 137 patacas, registering an annual rise of 3.9%, the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) said yesterday. This was due to the “growth in the number of lease agreements of autonomous fractions of large housing buildings”, explains the body.
The average rent of the Lamau's Doca (149 Patacas) housing fractures, the new black sand landfills (165 patacas) and the bass of the mud (136 patacas) rose 9.2%, 7.2% and 3.9% , respectively, in annual terms. However, the average income of the habitatal autonomous fractions of black sand and Iao Hon (122 patacas) lowered 1.5%.
By 2024 the average lace per square meter (service area) of autonomous fractions for stores was 479 patacas, less than 1.1%, compared to 2023. On the other hand, the average income of autonomous fractions for offices (293 patacas) and that of industrial autonomous fractions (123 patacas) decreased 2.8% and 0.1%, respectively.
The DSEC also says that, in terms of useful area, the largest declared lease agreements belonged to the 50 to 99.9 square meters of useful area and to the level of less than 50 square meters, with the average lace per square meter Of the housing autonomous fractions of these two echelons were 135 and 168 patacas, respectively, plus 4.1% and 4%, respectively, in annual terms.
Analysis by quarter, the average income per square meter of autonomous fractions for stores was 489 patacas in the fourth quarter of 2024, less 0.3%, compared to the previous quarter. The average income of autonomous fractions for offices (293 patacas) and that of industrial autonomous fractions (123 patacas) dropped 0.8% and 0.2%, respectively, in quarterly terms, while that of housing autonomous fractions (138 patacas) Ascended 0.7%.
According to DSEC, these data come from the statement of lease of the real estate over which the provision of the management of finance services falls. The purpose of the autonomous fraction is classified as mentioned in the building record. The statistical scope encompasses the leases of the entire autonomous fractions, which have non -expired contracts, and whose owners are not the government government or philanthropic associations, among other situations.</description><pubDate>2025-02-17T03:11:22+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Three residents of Macau remain hospitalized after explosion in Taiwan</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/tres-residentes-de-macau-continuam-internados-apos-explosao-em-taiwan/</link><description>Three residents of Macao who were injured in the gas explosion in Taiwan remain hospitalized, including a two -year -old child who remains intensive care. The hospital responsible for the treatment indicated that the minor has a “stable” vital signal, but it is not recommended to transfer it to Macau due to serious brain damage. The Tourism Services Crisis Group is in Taichung to assist family members of the deadly victims and the Macao wounded in the accident.
 
Among Macao's five wounded in an explosion in Taiwan, which also killed two residents of the territory, two have been discharged after medical treatments and three are still hospitalized. A two -year -old remains hospitalized for intensive care after being severely injured in the brain.
The smallest received a surgical operation of craniotomy and is currently “stable vital signs”, but the medical institution responsible for treatment, quoted by Radio Macau in Chinese language, said it is not recommended that the girl travel and be transferred to Macao to treatment doctor due to brain injury.
The hospital recalled that the child was “very serious” and “life -threatening” when he was taken to the hospital. “Brain bleeding is mainly due to its severe brain injury, so it had to undergo emergency surgery. Due to brain injury, it has to remain in the intensive care unit, ”said Cheng Yu-Kai, CMU Children's Pediatric Neurosurgery Director.
Thus, the doctor revealed that the most dangerous and most worrying part of the girl's state is the continuous swelling of the brain and lack of oxygen and blood in the brain.
The hospital stressed that this week will be a critical period for the child and the institution works in their neuroprotection, which involves future nerve healing. "It's like a stone beating a tofu, we can imagine the severity of the girl's injuries, which needs to use medical fan," said I-Ching, hospital spokesman, in statements quoted by Cheng Pou newspaper. Already the great -grandmother, 85, and the 24 -year -old uncle of the child are hospitalized and in stable health.
The explosion took place last Thursday at the SHIN Kong Mitsukoshi shopping center in the city of Taichung, and caused four deaths and 39 injured, two deaths and five injured are from a family from Macao. The explosion occurred in the feeding area of ​​the 12th floor of the shopping center and the family was hit by the rubble of the complex that fell after the explosion as it passed the immediate of the shopping center.
 
Macao Team in Taichung
 
In order to follow the situation of the family, the Macao Government's Tourism Crisis Coordination Group and the Macau Red Cross moved to Taichung on Thursday night and went to the hospital to visit the families of the family members Deadly and injured victims, transmitting the deep condolences of the Chief Executive, ”reads in a statement from the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD). The team will “determine a specific support plan and provide proper assistance,” he said.
Members of the Macao Group and Red Cross accompanied on Friday the family members of the two deceased to deal with the identification of the victims, and also communicated, through the delegation of the Red Cross of the site, with the competent entities the solving of related subjects related issues with the remains.
STD also advanced that the staff of the Macao insurer involved is also on site to provide support to family members in the monitoring of compensation related issues. The group of tourism crises and the staff of the Red Cross of Macao accompanied, this Saturday, relatives of the victims to meet with funeral agents and local legal professionals.
On Thursday night, the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, expressed “sincere and deep condolences” to the family members of the victims of the explosion. In a statement, the government leader said he “follows the case of the explosion of gas high” and “issued instructions to the competent services to provide all the necessary assistance” to those involved.
 
CPSP and Hotel Fortuna express condolences
 
The Public Security Police (CPSP) has confirmed that one of the two deceased residents is a retired police officer and an injured person is the special police unit. The information was advanced at a press conference on Friday, and CPSP said it was aware of the incident and expressed "its deepest condolences" to the injured and family members of the deceased. He also promised to coordinate with the STD crisis coordination group to provide assistance to the victims.
Another deceased in the explosion worked for over twenty years in the casino of Hotel Fortuna, the company said. The Fortuna Hotel issued a grade of condolence to the employee's death and said he sent staff to Taichung to accompany the needs of the victim's family members. The company added to have entered into communication with local hospitals through Yin Kui Hospital of Macau to provide assistance, both economic and medical, to the family.
 
Liability
 
The shopping center is still closed and Taiwan's authorities advanced with the investigation, considering that the cause of the incident is related to the renewal works of the space, which involved cutting gas conduct. The Taichung District Attorney's Office, quoted by the Taiwan press, called 18 people to interrogation as witnesses, and for now, no one was classified as a defendant.
The commercial center spokesman has assured that he will fully cooperate with the investigation and provide support to deadly victims and injured. Shin Kong Mitsukoshi has said it will pay compensation of 11 million Taiwanese dollars, corresponding to about 2.7 million patacas, to the families of each of the four deceased of the explosion, including “amount of condolences, insurance compensation and other compensations ”.
In this regard, the company stressed that it sent personnel to accompany family members of the family victim of Macau, since its arrival in Taiwan on Friday, and has to provide transportation, food, accommodation and assistance to address subsequent issues of the accident.
Taiwan's Continent Council of Affairs, in turn, also ensured that he has sent personnel to help the victims of Macau and notify, if necessary, the Macao government through the Taiwan-Macau communication channel. Liang Wen-Chieh, deputy director of the body, stressed that Macao currently has no office in Taiwan, so Taiwan communicates with the Macao government through the Taipé economic and cultural office in Macao. It is recalled that Macao's economic and cultural delegation in Taiwan suspended its operation in 2021, following the same act of suspension of delegation in Taiwan of the Hong Kong government.</description><pubDate>2025-02-17T03:14:05+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>XI receives leaders from the Chinese giants of technology in support sign</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/xi-recebe-lideres-dos-gigantes-chineses-da-tecnologia-em-sinal-de-apoio/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping will today receive the leaders of the country's technology giants, in a demonstration of support to the sector, according to sources cited by the Hong Kong South China Morning Post.
 
According to the Hong Kong South China Morning Post newspaper, between 20 and 30 founders or executive directors of start -up companies and already established companies, such as Huawei, Tencent, Alibaba and Xiaomi, they will participate in the unusual “Meeting of high level ”.
The meeting takes place weeks before the Chinese legislature holds its annual meeting, in which the government traces the economic script for next year, and in the midst of intensifying the trade war with the United States after the return to Donald Trump's power.
The newspaper said the legislature seeks to send a positive signal to the private sector to revive the country's economy, which does not face Trump's challenge at its best: China has achieved its 5% annual growth goal by 2024, but It still suffers from weak domestic consumption and a serious real estate crisis.
The meeting can also be interpreted as a Beijing turnaround, which in recent years has launched a harsh regulatory campaign against major technology companies.
In December 2020, the regulatory authorities announced the opening of an anti -monopoly investigation into Alibaba and suspended Ant, Fintech's branch, which would be the largest in history. This campaign included investigations to companies such as Tencent and “Uber Chinese”, Didi, for alleged risks to users' data security.
For years, the digital sector has flourished in China, not only thanks to the huge market in the country, but also to a rigorous regulation - or its application - to which Beijing wanted to end.
However, advances such as the Deepkseek artificial intelligence and intelligence, which will also be present at the meeting, were an important technological blow to Beijing, in the face of Trump's trade war.
Alibaba has also recently revealed its own AI model, Qwen, which will partner with Apple to allow iPhones to offer Apple Intelligence service in China, according to the Hong Kong newspaper.
Also present at the event will be representatives of Huawei, which in 2023 launched its icing smartphone Mate 60 Pro, the first to be made in China with a level of miniaturization that requires lithography equipment to which the Asian country theoretically has no access due to the restrictions imposed by the US.
Also present will be the so -called “six little dragons” of the Chinese “technology mastery”, which include, in addition to DeepSek, manufacturers of Uniquee and Deep Robotics robots, the Game Science video game studio, the 'design' software creator 'creator 3D Manycore interiors and brain, which develops products designed to train the brain. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-17T03:11:05+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao architects featured in the race every 2024 Hkia Cross-Strait Architectural Awards</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/17/arquitectos-de-macau-em-destaque-na-corrida-aos-cada-2024-hkia-cross-strait-architectural-awards/</link><description>The prestigious LBA architecture and planning, based on Macau, known for its innovative approach and commitment to sustainability, sees its work recognized with the appointment for every 2024 HKIA Cross-Strait Architectural Awards. Promoted by the influential Hong Kong Institute of Architects (HKIA), these prizes consecrate excellence in the domain of urban architecture and planning, with particular emphasis on projects realized in the dynamic region of the great bay.
The LBA is distinguished in this edition with two emblematic projects, such as the recent Metro Ligeiro da Barra and Fai Chi Kei's Social Housing Estate. Both works reflect the company's philosophy to create spaces that harmoniously combine functionality with aesthetics and environmental responsibility. “We received this appointment with great satisfaction,” says Rui Leão, from LBA Arquitetura and Planning. “Every 2024 hkia are a quality seal, representing a rigorous assessment independent of the best practices in the architecture sector. In the Great Bay, this is the most coveted recognition for design offices. ”
The appointment, according to Rui Leão, “is a tribute to our team's dedication to challenge the conventions of architectural design, seeking to respond to the constant evolution of communities and the planet. It is a privilege to be part of this prestigious platform, which celebrates global architectural excellence, focusing on the Great Bay region. ”
Founded from the Union of VLB Architecture and Limited Planning and Atelier of Architecture, LBA is a partnership led by architects Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni. The company is distinguished by a team dedicated to the conception of buildings that value the community, urban thinking and the conservation of heritage. Through original designs of adaptive reuse, renewals and interventions, LBA shapes environmentally and socially responsible public spaces, according to the description on its official page.
The announcement of the winners of each 2024 Hkia is scheduled for a gala ceremony in Hong Kong on March 1.</description><pubDate /></item></channel></rss>