<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/15/nova-palestra-da-universidade-de-macau-apresenta-o-belo-mundo-da-matematica/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>New commercial loans for real estate activities rise 301.8% in August</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/15/novos-emprestimos-comerciais-para-actividades-imobiliarias-sobem-3018-em-agosto/</link><description>Statistics released yesterday by the Macau Monetary Authority (AMCM) reveal that new mortgage loans for housing (EHHs) approved in August decreased compared to the previous month, while new commercial loans for real estate activities (ECAIs) approved grew exponentially. There was also a decrease in the gross balance of EHHs and ECAIs, compared to the previous month of July.
In August, new EHHs approved by Macau banks decreased by 22.2% compared to the previous month, to 820.82 million patacas. New EHHs approved for local residents, which represented 98.2% of the total, also fell by 22.5% to 806.05 million patacas, while the non-resident component fell by 3.1% to 14.77 million. From June to August, the average monthly number of new EHHs approved reached 977.79 million patacas, corresponding to a decrease of 4.1% compared to the previous period from May to July.
Statistics revealed by AMCM also indicate that new approved ECAIs grew 301.8% compared to the previous month, reaching 1.14 billion patacas. Of these, 54.1% were granted to local residents and decreased by 125.5%, to 617.70 million patacas, while the non-resident component grew to 1.10 billion patacas. Between June and August, the average monthly number of new EHHs approved reached 977.79 million patacas – that is, a decrease of 4.1% compared to the previous period.
New approved ECAIs rose 301.8% compared to the previous month, reaching 1.14 billion patacas. AMCM details that, of these loans, 51.4% were granted to local residents, with a growth of 125.5% to 617.70 million. The non-resident component also grew, reaching 524.48 million patacas.  From June to August, the average monthly number of new ECAIs approved reached 1.10 billion, meaning an increase of 20.8% compared to the previous period.
At the end of August, the gross balance of EHHs decreased by 0.6% compared to the previous month and 5.9% compared to the same period in 2024. The gross balance of ECAIs also decreased by 1.3% in monthly terms and 6.2% in annual terms.  As for the ratio of unpaid debts to EHHs, there was an increase of 0.1 percentage points compared to the previous month and a decrease of 0.5 percentage points compared to the same period in 2024.</description><pubDate>2025-10-15 23:22:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Consumer prices fall in September for the second consecutive month in China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/15/precos-no-consumidor-caem-em-setembro-pelo-segundo-mes-consecutivo-na-china/</link><description>Consumer prices (IPC) in China fell 0.3% in September, compared to the same period last year, registering the second consecutive month of decline, although smaller than the 0.4% drop felt in August, it was announced yesterday.

On the other hand, the drop in the consumer price index, the main inflation indicator released by the Chinese National Bureau of Statistics (NBS), was worse than market expectations, as analysts expect a drop of just 0.1%.
In six of the nine months this year, the CPI in China was negative, having recovered only in January (plus 0.5%) and June (plus 0.1%). The sharpest drop occurred in February (minus 0.7%).
The world's second largest economy has been facing deflationary pressures for more than two years, with weak domestic demand and excess industrial capacity penalizing prices, while uncertainty in international trade makes it difficult for suppliers to sell products.
Deflation consists of a fall in prices over time, as opposed to an increase (inflation). The phenomenon reflects weakness in domestic consumption and investment and is particularly dangerous, as a drop in the price of assets, usually contracted using credit, generates an imbalance between the value of loans and bank guarantees.
Another effect is to lead to the postponement of consumption and investment decisions as a result of expectations of lower prices in the future, which can create a downward spiral in prices and demand that is difficult to reverse, affecting the entire economy.
The fall in prices began in 2022, with the devaluation of the most important asset in China: residential real estate. The fall in property prices led to a drop in household confidence, resulting in a contraction in consumption. This, combined with the country's excess production capacity, fueled a price war between manufacturers and retailers, triggering a deflationary spiral.
Beijing has, however, taken steps to end the price war. The Chinese Communist Party also promised, in July, to combat “irrational competition” in several sectors.
Dong Lijuan, a statistician at NBS, preferred to highlight that underlying inflation – an indicator that excludes food and energy prices, as they are more volatile – marked the fifth consecutive month of increase in September, rising 1% compared to the previous year, the first time in 19 months that it reached this level.
The producer price index, which measures the evolution of ex-factory prices, fell 2.3% in August, marking the 36th consecutive month of contraction.
The value was in line with analysts' forecasts, but represented an improvement compared to the 2.9% drop recorded in August.
According to Dong, the slowdown in the fall is due not only to a lower comparative base, but also to the impact of macroeconomic policies promoted by Beijing, both in terms of creating a “unified national market” and in terms of “industrial restructuring and increasing consumption potential”. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-15 23:18:17</pubDate></item><item><title>GDP could grow 4.5% this year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/15/pib-podera-crescer-45-este-ano/</link><description>Macao SAR's GDP grew 7% in the third quarter of this year. The accounts are from the Macau Economic Association, which also says that, in the first three quarters of this year, the territory's economy grew 3.5% compared to the same period last year. GDP growth for the entire year could be around 4.5%, the association estimates.


The Macau Economic Association estimates that GDP stood at 112 billion patacas in the third quarter of this year, registering real growth of approximately 7%. This growth, according to the association, was driven by the tourism and leisure sectors.
As for the first three quarters, the accumulated GDP was 312 billion patacas, which represents a real year-on-year growth of around 3.5%, according to the association's accounts. At the end of the third quarter, experts point out, the territory's economy had recovered to approximately 90% of the size it had in the same period of 2019, before the pandemic. Based on this, the Macau Economic Association believes that GDP growth for the entire year will be around 4.5%.
The Economic Association report published on Tuesday also says that, during the National Day Golden Week, the tourism, leisure and entertainment sectors had “an exceptional performance, reaching several new highs”. “However, local consumption, credit and investment confidence remain relatively weak, with economic indicators expected to continue to show irregular performance”, highlights the association.
The association of now deputy Joey Lao predicts that the economic prosperity index will remain between 6.0 and 6.2 points in the fourth quarter of this year, with general economic conditions remaining stable until the end of the year.
The document also states that economic performance in August and September was “irregular”: “The peak season in September, combined with the impact of typhoons, resulted in a significant difference compared to August”.
In August, the average daily number of tourists arriving in the region reached 136,000, and the average daily occupancy of hotel rooms reached 42,000, with an occupancy rate of 92.9%. All three indicators reached the “very positive” level.
Gross gaming revenue also showed “a good performance”, reaching an average of 714 million patacas per day in August. In September, due to Typhoon Ragasa, which forced all casinos to suspend their operations for 33 hours, the daily average fell slightly to 610 million patacas. However, the group points out, the overall share price performance of gaming companies has recovered.
Furthermore, the job market “remained healthy”, with the general unemployment rate remaining at a low level of 2%. However, “domestic demand and investment confidence remained weak”. The report also notes that Macau's housing price index also fell to 192.4 points, reaching nearly decade lows.
Based on comprehensive analysis and projections, the prosperity index for August and September was 6.4 and 5.9, respectively, maintaining an overall “stable” rating.</description><pubDate>2025-10-15 23:30:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese airlines dispute US proposal to ban flights over Russia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/15/companhias-aereas-chinesas-contestam-proposta-dos-eua-para-proibir-voos-sobre-a-russia/</link><description>China's main state-owned airlines contested a United States proposal to ban flights that cross Russian airspace on routes between the two countries, citing an impact on passengers and a competitive imbalance.

Air China, China Eastern and China Southern are among six Chinese carriers that have filed complaints with the US Department of Transportation against the order, proposed last week, which seeks to ban flights over Russia by Chinese carriers.
In its response, China Eastern claimed that the measure “harms the public interest” and “creates inconvenience for travelers” from China and the US, stressing that increased flight times would translate into higher costs and more expensive fares.
China Southern warned that the ban would negatively affect thousands of passengers, while Air China estimated that at least 4,400 travelers would be affected if the restriction came into effect during the Thanksgiving (27 November) and Christmas season.
Russian airspace was closed to North American airlines and most European carriers in 2022 following the imposition of Western sanctions over Russia's invasion of Ukraine.
Chinese flights, however, continue to have access, giving them, according to Washington, an unfair advantage over their US competitors.
Chinese diplomacy spokesman Guo Jiakun had already reacted last week, considering that the proposal represents a “punishment” for passengers from all over the world.
According to David Yu, an aviation sector expert at New York University in Shanghai, the impossibility of flying over Russia has increased the duration of some US-China routes by two to three hours, putting pressure on the operational costs and profitability of North American companies. “Historically, the China-US route has been highly profitable for both sides,” Yu said. “If Chinese carriers can fly over Russia, their costs are lower,” he noted.
Still, Chinese companies have faced financial difficulties since the Covid-19 pandemic.
The US Department of Transportation argues that the ability of Chinese operators to use the most efficient route creates “competitive imbalances” by allowing them to offer faster flights and, therefore, more appealing to consumers.
North American carrier United Airlines also spoke out in the process, asking that Cathay Pacific – the flag carrier of Hong Kong, which is not on the list of Chinese companies covered – be excluded from the ban. European companies such as Air France-KLM have also filed complaints about the restriction of Russian airspace. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-15 23:17:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Operation uncovers cross-border prostitution ring in southern China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/15/operacao-descobre-rede-de-prostituicao-transfronteirica-no-sul-da-china/</link><description>An operation in southern China, including Macau, dismantled a criminal cross-border prostitution network operated through an online platform, with at least 100 arrests, the Judiciary Police announced.
The raid, which began on Monday, caught 18 identified as leaders, 58 women allegedly involved in prostitution and 44 alleged clients, said the PJ, cited by the local press.
The same source said that the network, active since January, circulated up to 40 advertisements per day for sexual services, generating 750,000 yuan (around 90,500 euros) in illicit profits through cryptocurrencies.
In Macau, eight individuals were detained, including seven local residents and a Vietnamese woman, and 10,000 condoms, lubricants, disposable sheets, vehicles and electronic equipment were seized in four hotels and a warehouse. In Guangzhou, seven suspects, including a Macau resident, were detained along with 24 women and 42 customers. Hong Kong recorded three arrests of recruiters and 25 women linked to them.
Leng Kam Lon, PJ spokesperson, described the action as “a decisive impact against cross-border organized crime”, launched in May. Investigations continue to clarify recruitment networks and money laundering.
The operation highlights enhanced collaboration in the Greater Bay Area, where tourism and connectivity are conducive to cross-border crime.</description><pubDate>2025-10-15 23:23:43</pubDate></item><item><title>AMCM went to Lisbon to participate in a meeting of the Central Banks of Portuguese-speaking countries</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/15/amcm-foi-a-lisboa-participar-em-encontro-dos-bancos-centrais-dos-paises-lusofonos/</link><description>The Macau Monetary Authority (AMCM) participated in the XXXV Lisbon Meeting between the Central Banks of Portuguese-Speaking Countries, which took place on Monday. The meeting promoted dialogues on financial cooperation between Portuguese-speaking countries and regions.

The XXXV Lisbon Meeting between the Central Banks of Portuguese-speaking Countries took place on Monday and the Macau Monetary Authority (AMCM) participated in the meeting on behalf of the Macao SAR. This meeting aimed to debate global economic and financial issues, promoting in-depth dialogues on financial cooperation between Portuguese-speaking countries and regions, says the press release released yesterday by AMCM.
Vong Sin Man, deputy chairman of the Board of Directors of AMCM, gave a speech on the occasion, highlighting that Macau has accelerated the construction of a bond market with the aim of “serving as a bridge to the interior of China and creating connections with the international market”. In this context, said the official, the Macao SAR is “promoting, in stages, the optimization and updating of the central infrastructure of the Macau bond market – the Macau Securities Deposit Center (CSD)”, which aims to “align itself with international practices and respond to the needs of external markets with regard to multi-currency settlement and multi-level custody models”.
On the other hand, Macau's Real-time Renminbi Immediate Settlement System (RMB RTGS) “can provide Portuguese-speaking countries with renminbi settlement services in a convenient and efficient manner”. In the future, Vong Sin Man promised, “AMCM will continue to improve financial infrastructures, optimize cross-border financial services and promote regional financial stability and inclusive development, giving a new dynamic impetus to the sustainable development of Macau and Portuguese-speaking countries”.
During the visit to Lisbon, the AMCM delegation also visited the Portuguese Insurance and Pension Funds Supervisory Authority, and the feasibility of creating an advanced training center for supervisors from the Portuguese-speaking Insurance Supervisors Association (ASEL) was discussed. This center aims to build a base for the training of financial talents between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, “further reinforcing Macau's role as a financial services platform between China and Portuguese-speaking countries”, according to AMCM.
AMCM currently has bilateral cooperation agreements in force with 12 financial supervisory authorities from eight Portuguese-speaking countries. “In the future, financial cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries will continue to be deepened, contributing to a better integration of Macau in the general context of national development”, assures the organization.</description><pubDate>2025-10-15 23:27:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Raymond Tam promises to increase the effectiveness of Transport and Public Works supervision</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/15/raymond-tam-promete-aumentar-eficacia-da-tutela-dos-transportes-e-obras-publicas/</link><description>To prepare the Government Action Lines (LAG) for next year, government officials have held meetings with some local associations. Raymond Tam, Secretary for Transport and Public Works, met with a number of local groups who made suggestions in the areas of land management, road works, leisure spaces and housing provision, for example. The secretary promised, at the meeting, that his supervision will “constantly increase the effectiveness of the work and the quality of the service”.

The Government is preparing the Governing Action Lines (LAG) for 2026 and, to this end, has been meeting with certain associations to listen to their suggestions. Raymond Tam met with representatives from various local groups, hearing opinions on road works, land management, traffic planning and housing, for example.
Without detailing the specific content of the opinions, a statement released by the Government says that Raymond Tam also heard suggestions on urban renewal, implementation of the Zone A plan for the new landfill and construction of school facilities, expansion of leisure spaces, deepening urban traffic planning, strengthening the effectiveness of weather forecasts, consolidating disaster prevention infrastructures, ensuring stability and security in the supply of water and electricity, promoting the maintenance of buildings, intensifying environmental protection, improving the procedure for requesting the entry and circulation of Macau cars within the country, improving the electronic payment system for the light rail, among other topics.
Raymond Tam stated at the meeting that “the work of government action in the supervision of transport and public works is intrinsically linked to the well-being of the population, and promised that the suggestions and opinions collected will be analyzed and discussed in a serious and orderly manner, serving as a reference in the elaboration of the lines of government action”.
The secretary said that the team under his supervision is committed to “improving the construction of infrastructure, increasing the efficiency of public transport, promoting the electronic payment system for public transport, responding in the best way to the population in terms of traffic, and successively advancing the construction of Macau into a livable city”.
Tam also highlighted that the Working Group for the Optimization of Road Works Coordination will “strengthen the anticipation of public works work, improve the coordinated procedure of road works, more strictly supervise the quality and control the construction deadline of the works”. The government official also guaranteed that “all services under his jurisdiction will work under the principle of prioritizing the population and constantly increasing the effectiveness of work and the quality of service”.
Those responsible for Transport and Public Works met this time with representatives from the Macau General Association of Fukien Countrymen, the Macau Institution People's Alliance, the Macau Education Association, the Macau Youth Federation, the Macau Commercial Association, the General Union of Residents' Associations of Macau, the General Association of Women of Macau, the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau, the General Association of Overseas Chinese from Macau.


BOX
 
Tai Kin Ip listens to opinions to prepare the LAG for the Economy and Finance department

Tai Kin Ip, Secretary for Economy and Finance, met with some associations to prepare the Governing Action Lines (LAG) under his supervision. The associations presented opinions on diversifying the economy, revitalizing the community economy, supporting the population and businesses and guaranteeing jobs for residents, for example. The secretary assured that the suggestions presented by the associations will be taken into account when drawing up next year's political guidelines. The governor also promised that the work of his authority will “focus on economic growth, promote diversification, benefit the lives of the population and seek development”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-15 23:29:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Asian Bank supports road improvements in Timor-Leste municipality with 3.4 million euros</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/15/banco-asiatico-apoia-com-34-milhoes-de-euros-melhoria-de-estradas-em-municipio-de-timor-leste/</link><description>The Asian Development Bank yesterday approved support of 3.4 million euros to improve roads in the municipality of Ermera, in central Timor-Leste, and connect rural communities to markets.

The support, given through the Asian Development Fund, aims to improve an “11-kilometer road corridor that connects rural communities to markets and essential services, while also protecting infrastructure against climate risks”, can be read in a statement released by the institution.
The project will rehabilitate the road infrastructure between Ermera and Fatubessi, in the central area of ​​the country, and will also strengthen the institutional capacity of the General Directorate of Roads, Bridges and Flood Control of the Ministry of Public Works. "This project empowers rural communities to stay connected to markets, essential services and livelihoods. By strengthening the Government's capacity to plan and maintain climate-resilient infrastructure, we are paving the way for a safer and more resilient Ermera", said ABD director in Timo-Leste, Stefania Dina.
According to the statement, the project supports “Timor-Leste's commitment to strengthening transport connectivity, with the aim of empowering communities, improving access to services and reducing climate risks and disasters”.

Timor-Leste negotiates a loan of 64.5 million euros to modernize roads

The Government of Timor-Leste yesterday authorized the negotiation of a loan with the Asian Development Bank of 64.5 million euros to modernize roads and bridges in the east of the country. According to a statement released after a meeting of the Council of Ministers, the project, with a budget of US$84.8 million, plans to modernize 42 kilometers of the national road between Lospalos and Iliomar and rehabilitate three bridges located between Baucau and Lautém.
The project also envisages strengthening climate resilience in six juices (a group of villages), located between Lospalos and Iliomar, vulnerable to floods and droughts. The project will be “mainly financed through a concessional loan of US$75 million and a grant of US$3 million from the Asian Development Bank”, the statement read.
O Governo salienta, com base numa análise macroeconómica e fiscal, que o financiamento não vai comprometer a estabilidade orçamental, nem a sustentabilidade da dívida pública timorense, que se “mantém em níveis prudentes e abaixo do limite de referência internacional”. “Além disso, o custo efetivo do total dos empréstimos existentes é inferior ao retorno estimado do Fundo Petrolífero de Timor-Leste, o que assegura que o recurso a este financiamento se mantém economicamente vantajoso e sustentável, contribuindo para a realização de investimentos estratégicos sem pôr em causa o equilíbrio das contas públicas”, acrescenta o Governo timorense. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-15 23:12:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Pedestrian space between ZAPE and NAPE will open on Friday</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/15/espaco-pedonal-entre-o-zape-e-o-nape-vai-entrar-em-funcionamento-na-sexta-feira/</link><description>The new pedestrian space at Jardim das Artes, located in ZAPE, should come into operation at 10am on Friday. From this day onwards, pedestrians will be able to move between ZAPE and NAPE in a direct pedestrian line, without having to go around the outside of the garden, as announced by the Government in a statement.
The reformulation works, which began in mid-September, are now “practically completed”, as the Chief Executive noted on a visit to the site. During this period, accesses without architectural barriers were also installed with the aim of providing a more inclusive, safe and comfortable experience for both citizens and tourists.
In parallel, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) guaranteed that it will continue to “optimize” the Jardim das Artes and replant the plants affected during the execution of the work, guaranteeing the “beautification of the landscape” and “a better pedestrian and leisure environment”.
The works carried out last month also resulted in the removal of existing water barriers on Avenida da Amizade, thus allowing the circulation of vehicles on the four lanes and optimizing the road environment in the area in question. In light of these changes, the authorities appeal to drivers to “pay attention to the adjustment of traffic ‘in loco’”.
At the same time, the pedestrian crossing on Avenida da Amizade was widened to 12 meters, while the pedestrian crossing next to Rua Cidade de Sintra was expanded to six meters, creating easier pedestrian access.
Part of the Jardim das Artes was closed to the public last month, while optimization measures were implemented. Before the works, pedestrians were forced to go around the garden along Avenida da Amizade, through a narrow temporary access delimited by water barriers.</description><pubDate>2025-10-15 23:24:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Criminal network that recruited residents for fraud in Taiwan dismantled</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/15/desmantelada-rede-criminosa-que-recrutava-residentes-para-fraudes-em-taiwan/</link><description>The Judiciary Police dismantled a network suspected of having lured citizens to Taiwan, with promises of high salaries, to engage in illegal activities. Six members of the group were arrested, all from Macau, who allegedly lured at least nine residents to Taiwan to participate in telecommunications fraud. The nine residents were convicted in Taiwan, including one minor.

Nine Macau residents, including a minor, have fallen victim to more fraudulent overseas job offer schemes. They were enticed to move to Taiwan, but ended up working in fraud networks using telecommunications and the internet.
The Judiciary Police (PJ) dismantled the criminal network responsible for the schemes and arrested, on Monday, six members of the group, all residents, aged between 17 and 43. Among the suspects, two were key members of a Taiwan-based fraud ring, including a 22-year-old man who posed as a night school student and a 37-year-old man who claimed to be a salesman.
According to newspaper Ou Mun, authorities revealed that they had received, since September last year, requests for help from several residents seeking police assistance in relation to missing family members.
Investigations later found that the nine missing residents were lured to work in Taiwan, where they were manipulated by local criminal fraud groups into participating in scams. The victims' main job was to help collect illicit funds from victims of local schemes.
According to the PJ, among the nine involved in the case were three middle-aged residents, five young people and one minor, who decided to go to work in Taiwan due to promises of high salaries.
The resident victims were detained by Taiwanese authorities and sentenced to prison terms ranging between three and eight months. Four were released and returned to Macau after serving their sentences between March and August this year, while the remaining five remain imprisoned in Taiwan.
"According to reports from some victims who returned to Macau, the network's activities in Taiwan mainly involved financial investments or the transport of precious metals. The group sent members to Macau to recruit staff, hiring two main members from Macau, continually expanding its ranks in the city", detailed the PJ, cited by the Chinese channel TDM Macau.
The PJ added that, upon their arrival in Taiwan, the nine victims were contacted to collect the money from the frauds and, later, they received instructions to transport the amount to locations designated by members of the criminal organization.
Authorities said that some victims, despite knowing that they could be involved in criminal activities, decided to take the risk of working abroad, while others had their documents seized immediately upon arrival in Taiwan, and were forced to participate in fraudulent schemes.
Victims said their daily wages ranged between 1,000 and 1,500 Macau patacas, and have yielded profits of several thousand to tens of thousands of patacas to date.
The two main members of the network received between 1% and 3% of the total amount defrauded as remuneration. However, the total illicit income received by these two main members, together with the illicit remuneration received by the remaining four suspects, remains under investigation.
The PJ guarantees that it will continue to investigate the case and find out if there are others involved in the network. Authorities remind the public to remain vigilant regarding recruitment advertisements that promise high remuneration for positions that do not require skills, qualifications or professional experience and that involve foreign travel.</description><pubDate>2025-10-15 23:30:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Hai does not want to support Portuguese-speaking products entering the Chinese market</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/15/hainao-quer-apoiar-produtos-lusofonos-a-entrar-no-mercado-chines/</link><description>The leader of the island of Hainan, in southern China, said he wants to help Portuguese-speaking products enter the Chinese market, defending synergies with Macau and Portuguese-speaking countries. Governor Liu Xiaoming pointed out as a goal “the construction of Hainan as a hub for the entry of products from Portuguese-speaking countries into the interior of China”. Liu was speaking during a visit to the facilities of the Forum for Economic and Trade Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries, known as the Macau Forum.
According to Forum Macau, the leader of Hainan asked the organization for support, also to help companies on the island “to deepen their knowledge of market rules and investment environments in Portuguese-speaking nations”.
According to a statement, Liu defended the bet on “synergistic development between Hainan, Macau and Portuguese-speaking countries” and recalled that the island will become a free port before the end of the year.
From December 18th, imported products that are processed in Hainan – with an added value of at least 30% – can enter mainland China without paying customs duties.
On Monday, Liu Xiaoming had met with the leader of the Macau Government, Sam Hou Fai. According to a statement from the Macau Government, Sam argued that there may be “complementarity of advantages” between the free port of Hainan and the Deep Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau. This special economic zone, jointly managed by Guangdong province and Macau, was launched by Beijing and 2021 and covers about 106 square kilometers in Hengqin.
Exports from Portuguese-speaking countries to China fell 11.3%, to US$86.6 billion in the first eight months of the year, according to official data.</description><pubDate>2025-10-15 23:22:39</pubDate></item><item><title>China forgives interest on loans granted to Mozambique until 2024 and donates 12 million</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/15/china-perdoa-juros-dos-emprestimos-concedidos-a-mocambique-ate-2024-e-doa-12-milhoes/</link><description>The Chinese Government forgave interest on loans granted to Mozambique until 2024 and announced a donation of 12 million euros to the African country, Mozambican Prime Minister Benvida Levi said yesterday.  “We had two positive news coming from [Chinese] President Xi Jinping, one of the news was the donation to our country of 100 million yuan [equivalent to 12 million euros] and the forgiveness of interest on loans granted to Mozambique until the year 2024,” said Levi, who was speaking to journalists after a two-day visit to China. The announcement was made by the Mozambican Prime Minister after an audience with the Chinese President, in a meeting that, according to the minister, also served to share Mozambique's main governance instruments, namely the Government's Five-Year Plan (PQG) and the State Economic and Social Plan and Budget (PESOE). "Together we identified some areas for follow-up. In our view, and also agreed with the Chinese side, we want to focus on investments in agriculture, and its entire value chain, in professional technical training and health", said Levi.
For the education sector, in which Chinese support allowed the construction of the Polytechnic Institute of Muanza, in central Mozambique, the Mozambique Government calls for more investment in the professional technical area, to allow the construction of more schools in other parts of the country.  More than 14% of Mozambique's external debt was held, in March this year, by China, the country's largest bilateral creditor, with a stock of US$1.383 million, according to data from the Mozambican government. The previous Chinese ambassador to Mozambique, Wang Hejun, estimated, last April, that Chinese investments in Mozambique already amount to 9.5 billion dollars (8.2 billion euros). Last year, the value of bilateral trade reached US$5.6 billion, the diplomat also said.
Chinese investments in Mozambique are based on the areas of infrastructure, energy and extraction of natural resources, in addition to the growing business presence in strategic sectors of the Mozambican economy.  A document, signed in 2016 between the two countries, established 14 principles that should guide bilateral relations, opening space, in addition to trade and investment, for strengthening contacts between the army, police and intelligence services. The agreement provides for China to provide technical assistance to the Armed Defense Forces of Mozambique (FADM), including staff training, supply of equipment and accessories, totaling around US$11.5 million.</description><pubDate>2025-10-15 23:11:11</pubDate></item><item><title>“Compatriots need more humanistic care and spiritual comfort”, says Chief Executive</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/15/compatriotas-necessitam-de-mais-cuidado-humanistico-e-conforto-espiritual-diz-chefe-do-executivo/</link><description>During the celebrations of the 105th anniversary of the founding of the Macau Red Cross, the Chief Executive praised the organization highly, also asking it to “consolidate itself in the new era to achieve new development”. In his speech, Sam Hou Fai pointed to the “period of turbulence and change” that the world is facing and stated that “compatriots need more humanistic care and spiritual comfort”.

The Macau Red Cross celebrates its 105th anniversary this year. The occasion was marked yesterday with a commemorative reception attended by the Chief Executive. On the occasion, Sam Hou Fai applauded the work carried out by the organization since its founding.
The Chief Executive began by recalling that the Red Cross has been rooted in Macau since 1920, the year of its foundation, and “persists in the fundamental principles of ‘humanity, impartiality, neutrality, independence, volunteerism, unity and universality'”.
“Its action translates into an effort to carry out a long series of practical actions, namely disaster prevention and relief, escort, rescue, community and people tracking services, which allow the prevention and alleviation of human suffering in the most extreme and most vulnerable situations in the belief of a better life for humanity”, highlighted the leader of the Macao SAR Government.
Since 1999, when he became a delegation with a high degree of autonomy from the Chinese Red Cross Society, he has contributed to “the successful application of the ‘one country, two systems’ principle with Macau characteristics”, said Sam, adding that, “whether courageously facing major disasters or discreetly dedicating himself in ordinary days, it is with his practical actions that he writes an exciting chapter on promoting the humanitarian spirit and developing the cause of Red Cross in Macao”.
Sam Hou Fai described the Macau Red Cross as an “essential partner” of the Macao SAR Government, “important in the humanitarian area”, collaborating with local authorities to “deepen and develop actions of human solidarity and promote cultural and interpersonal exchanges at national and international level, which raises the prospects for success to a more promising level”.
“The Macao SAR Government will fully support the Macau Red Cross in the planning and development of its activities, so that we can work together to ensure the readiness of, among others, emergency rescue actions, humanitarian assistance, protection of life, maintenance of dignity, continuing to promote new contributions to the development of the humanitarian cause”, promised the Chief.
Sam Hou Fai also stated that “the world is currently in a new period of turbulence and change, with new threats and challenges increasing”. Furthermore, “Macau has entered the new phase of applying the principle of ‘one country, two systems’, struggling with profound and complex changes in the internal and external environment”. The Chief then argued that “compatriots need more humanistic care and spiritual comfort”.
The Government leader said he hopes that the Macau Red Cross “will continue to pay attention and support to the development of the Macao SAR and the Government's actions, and, mindful of the government's plans and the demands of Macau's high-quality development in the new journey, will continue to promote love for the country and for Macau, improve the quality of its professional services, strengthen assistance work and safeguard social harmony and stability”.
Specifically, the Government expects the organization to “further strengthen cooperation with the Chinese Red Cross Society, make the most of Macau's unique status and advantages, promote internal and external interconnection, exchange and cooperation in the humanitarian cause, implement the idea of ​​building a community with a shared future for Humanity, for the joint promotion of peace and progress of humanity”. “Finally, I sincerely hope that the Macau Red Cross will consolidate itself in the new era to achieve new development”, concluded Sam.</description><pubDate>2025-10-15 23:28:30</pubDate></item><item><title>International organizations recognize media mogul convicted in Hong Kong</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/15/organizacoes-internacionais-distinguem-magnata-dos-media-condenado-em-hong-kong/</link><description>Hong Kong media mogul Jimmy Lai, serving time for organizing anti-government protests, has been recognized as a World Press Freedom Hero by the International Press Institute (IPI) and International Media Support (IMS).

“This year’s award recipients are an example of the threats journalists face around the world as authoritarianism advances and impunity continues,” said IPI Executive Director Scott Griffen. “With this award, we honor his courage, commitment and legacy, while reiterating the urgent call to protect press freedom as a pillar of any free society,” he added.
Born in 1947 in the Chinese province of Guangdong, at the height of the civil war, Lai fled at the age of 12 to Hong Kong, then a British colony, after the family lost its fortune with Mao Zedong's rise to power, wrote the Efe news agency, in a brief biography. He started as an apprentice in a textile factory and later founded the clothing brand Giordano, a commercial success throughout Asia. With the profits, he created the Next Digital group, responsible for the weekly magazine Next Magazine and the daily Apple Daily, launched in 1995. Since then, he has transformed the media into a pro-democracy point of reference and a critical voice in relation to Beijing, said Efe.
Later, the news agency continued, with the transfer of sovereignty to Hong Kong in 1997, the newspaper established itself as a defender of freedom of expression and a symbol of Lai's commitment to democratic values ​​in the face of control by the Chinese regime.
The businessman was detained in August 2020 on charges of “collusion with foreign forces” and “seditious publications” under a new national security law. The trial, concluded in August after almost two years of delays, could result in life imprisonment.
Lai, who is serving another sentence for “illegal assembly” and “organizing an unauthorized demonstration”, remains in isolation in a maximum security prison, while international organizations denounce the deterioration of his health and warn of violations of the businessman's fundamental rights. Apple Daily was closed in June 2021, following raids, confiscation of assets and arrest of managers.
The award will be presented on October 24th, in Vienna, at the IPI World Congress, and will be received by his son Sebastien Lai. “My father courageously sacrificed everything for principles essential to humanity,” said Sebastien Lai, hoping that “everything will be done to ensure his father’s immediate and unconditional release.”
The case generated a wave of international condemnation. In November 2024, a UN report deemed the detention illegal and demanded Lai's release. Governments and organizations from around the world expressed support, transforming it into a global symbol of the fight for freedom of expression. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-15 23:18:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Exhibition at the University of Macau celebrates the centenary of the birth of José Cardoso Pires</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/15/exposicao-da-universidade-de-macau-celebra-o-centenario-do-nascimento-de-jose-cardoso-pires/</link><description>The University of Macau (UM) will mark the centenary of the birth of José Cardoso Pires, one of the great names in Portuguese literature, with the thematic exhibition “Voices, Looks, Memories”. The exhibition will be open to the public until December 19th, in the hanging garden area of ​​the Wu Yee Sun Library.
The tribute is part of an initiative by UM's Chinese-Portuguese Bilingual Teaching and Training Center, which aims to present the author's “literary legacy and spiritual world” through a multifaceted approach to his works and the social comments they contain. The objective, according to the university's website, is to present “the life of the writer who reshaped the panorama of modern Portuguese literature through his incisive words and his profound reflections on human nature”.
José Cardoso Pires occupies a prominent role in Portuguese literary history of the 20th century, having produced 18 works that challenge literary genres or movements. His extensive literary career, which spans a period of almost fifty years, frequently addresses themes such as restlessness and wandering, as well as the inclusion of themes of a social nature. “O Delfim”, a 1968 novel set in the fictional village of Gafeira, is generally considered his masterpiece.
“Through his distinctive narrative style and insightful social observation, [the writer] deeply analyzed the complex interaction between power, identity and memory, offering an authentic chronicle of the social transformations and individual destinies of Portugal during the second half of the 20th century”, writes UM.
Since 2017, the Chinese-Portuguese Bilingual Teaching and Training Center of the University of Macau has been dedicated to promoting collaborations with mainland China and Portuguese-speaking countries, with particular emphasis on training Chinese-Portuguese bilingual teachers and talents and joint research in the field of teaching the Portuguese language.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>New lecture from the University of Macau presents the “beautiful world of mathematics”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/15/nova-palestra-da-universidade-de-macau-apresenta-o-belo-mundo-da-matematica/</link><description>The University of Macau (UM) is preparing to host a lecture given by two of the most prestigious mathematicians in the world, Efim Zelmanov and Zhang Jiping, in yet another effort to promote academic excellence and the internationalization of the institution. Also with these objectives, the university signed a new cooperation agreement this week with Ton Duc Thang University, in Vietnam, which praised UM's “growing influence” and “achievements”.
 
The University of Macau (UM) will host this Friday, at 3pm, a lecture on the role of mathematics in the modern world. The session features the participation of two world-renowned experts: Efim Zelmanov, full professor at the South China University of Science and Technology, and Zhang Jiping, professor at Peking University.
The lecture – free entry and open to the general public, subject to prior registration – will “focus on the unique charm and broad applications of mathematics”, as a UM statement describes. The two guest speakers will share their perspectives on the “unique nature” of the discipline and how it can be applied in different areas, from artificial intelligence to medium imaging. The way in which mathematics “inspired civilization” over the centuries will also be debated – namely, through promoting the “unification of sciences” and the “mechanization of problem-solving processes with digital technology”.
The presentation by Russian-American mathematician Efim Zelmanov will be titled “Welcome to the New Beautiful Mathematical World”. The specialist was awarded the Fields Medal in 1994 and, throughout his career, received honorary doctorates from more than ten top international universities. He is a member of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America and a foreign member of the Chinese Academy of Sciences and the Royal Academy of Exact, Physical and Natural Sciences of Spain.
In turn, Zhang Jiping will present a lecture dedicated to “Numbers and Algebra”. His research work on the theory of modular representation of finite groups earned him awards such as third place in the State Prize for Natural Sciences and the Shiing Shen Chern Mathematics Prize. His “exceptional vision for education”, in UM’s words, enabled him to train many renowned mathematicians and contribute to the “cultivation of mathematical talents” in China.

UM AND UNIVERSITY OF VIETNAM STRENGTHEN COOPERATION
 
In a parallel statement, UM also announced that it had signed a memorandum of understanding and a student exchange agreement with Ton Duc Thang University, in Vietnam, aiming for greater cooperation between the two institutions in areas such as education, research and talent development.
This agreement represents a new phase in the collaboration between UM and the Vietnamese university, which dates back a year. Em Outubro de 2024, recorde-se, uma delegação liderada pelo reitor da UM, Yonghua Song, deslocou-se ao Vietname com o objectivo de discutir o intercâmbio de professores e alunos. One year after this first meeting, it is the turn of a delegation from the Vietnamese university, led by rector Tran Trong Dao, to visit the higher education institution in Macau.
On this occasion, Rector Yonghua Song highlighted that UM “attaches great importance to internationalization” and that the two agreements concluded represent “a solid basis for academic and research exchanges between the two universities”. For his part, Tran Tron Dao praised UM's educational philosophy and academic offerings, considering the “growing influence on the international stage” that has occurred in recent years to be particularly notable.
The Vietnamese rector also said he hopes that Ton Duc Thang University can benefit from UM's “advanced teaching experience” and that it can, based on this acquired knowledge, “promote the exchange of teachers and students and further improve its own teaching quality and research capacity”.
During the visit to Macau, the group from Vietnam also visited the State Internet of Things Reference Laboratory for the Smart City, the Faculty of Health Sciences and the Wu Yee Sun Library, praising “UM's achievements” and the “development of the campus”.</description><pubDate /></item></channel></rss>