<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/producao-industrial-chinesa-aumenta-59-nos-dois-primeiros-meses-do-ano/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Cristiano Ronaldo opens unpublished store and Hong Kong Training Center</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/cristiano-ronaldo-abre-loja-inedita-e-centro-de-formacao-em-hong-kong/</link><description>Hong Kong inaugurated an emblematic store and an advanced Football Training Center, under the insignia of Cristiano Ronaldo and his brand “CR7”. Located in the iconic Times Square, the spaces occupy more than 2,500 squares between two widespread shopping center, signaling a new era in sports and trade in the city. The opening of these facilities comes in tune with the long -awaited inauguration of the “Cristiano Ronaldo Life Museum” in July.
 
Hong Kong has just welcomed a novelty of relief in his commercial and sports landscape with the recent inauguration of Cristiano Ronaldo's store, which is integrated into a new and modern soccer formation center. Located at the intermediate and higher levels of the famous Times Square, in Causeway Bay, these facilities, which also include products from other famous football players, occupy a space of more than 2,500 square meters, standing out as a reference point for fans of the region and admirers of the iconic Portuguese player.
According to information advanced by Futubull de Hong Kong, the 7th floor floor of the shopping center, corresponding to the special store that leads to Ronaldo's insignia, has an area of ​​about 930 square meters. This space has been carefully designed to provide a “unique shopping experience” with official “CR7” and merchandising products associated with the athlete. The design of the store includes interactive elements and the display of memories of Cristiano Ronaldo's life, as well as inspiring quotes from the athlete, such as "My Life Without Football Is Worth Nothing."
The training center, located on the 13th floor and covering approximately 1,580 square meters, was designed to be a space of excellence in sports training. With state -of -the -art equipment available for various ages and skill levels, the center will serve as a starting point for the new generation of Hong Kong soccer players, similar to other Ronaldo projects, such as the Dinamo Tbilisi Academy in Georgia and Cristiano Ronaldo Campus of the National CD in Madeira.
According to real estate experts, the market value of the Times Square shopping center has risen due to the popularity of the new store. The expected price for the lease of the space exceeds $ 1.650 of Hong Kong per square meter, while the training center is estimated at more than $ 500 of Hong Kong per square meter.
The interest in the facilities reflects the recent increase in the popularity of football in the region. In July, the “Cristiano Ronaldo Life Museum” will be inaugurated at K11 Art &amp; Cultural Center, located in Tsim Sha Tsui. The museum, which represents the first initiative of this kind in Asia, will have the aim of celebrating Ronaldo's life and career, covering more than two decades of sports achievements and impact of their solidarity initiatives.
The museum space will occupy more than 1,000 square meters and promise not only to display trophies and prizes won by the athlete, but also offer immersive experiences through interactive technology. Visitors will be able to find rare objects, such as autographed t-shirts, historic boots and other accessories that marked Ronaldo's career.
Tickets for the museum are available at affordable prices, with options ranging from 150 to 180 dollars of Hong Kong, and organizers predict that more than 12 million people visit the space during the operating period, which will extend until July 2026. In addition, the opening of this cultural space aims to provide new employment opportunities in the areas of commerce and services.
According to the museum organizers, the creation of “Cristiano Ronaldo Life Museum” is part of a larger initiative to integrate and unite the local community and tourists, called “Hong Kong United”, promoting synergies among various sectors. Customers will be able to purchase official products and exclusive goods from the player, further increasing the attractiveness of the place. With the combination of the store, the training center and the museum, Hong Kong intends to assert himself as a new epicenter for fans of Cristiano Ronaldo and the culture of football.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 02:40:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Cunha Foundation presents four more sessions of the Law Themes Cycle</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/fundacao-rui-cunha-apresenta-mais-quatro-sessoes-do-ciclo-temas-de-direito/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation presents in the next two Wednesdays and Thursdays, days 19 and 20 and 26 and 27, at 18:30, four sessions of the Cycle of Law, adjacent to the theme “Vicissitudes of the Process (I)”. The first two sessions, taking place this week, will be made in Portuguese, while the last two will be conducted in Chinese language. The entrance to the four sessions is free.
In a statement, the Rui Cunha Foundation said that the sets of sessions are intended to “identify possible incidents in judicial proceedings and address the respective regimes”, through an analysis of the circumstances in which incidents of varying degrees may cause inconvenience to ongoing proceedings or implications for the final decision. The first session will focus on the themes “Subjective Modification: Subjective Substitution vs. Subjective cumulation” and “third party intervention: main intervention”. The second session will further explore this last module, with “third party intervention: ancillary intervention and opposition”.
The lectures will have speaker Teresa Leong, judicial magistrate for more than 20 years in Macao. In the words of the responsible, “the judicial process begins with the dispute and ends with the decision to end this dispute. If the process follows its normal course, without major startles, justice is naturally served without disorder. However, incidents of the most varied order make this, sometimes difficult to achieve. These incidents, in addition to causing a certain disorder to the ongoing process, may even undermine the acts laboriously committed, including the final decision itself. ”
These sessions come to join the Conference Cycle organized by CRED-DM-Center for Reflection, Study and Dissemination of the Rui Cunha Foundation's Macao Law, already held in previous years with great interest and adherence. The objective of the lectures is, according to the Foundation, “to address, in a practical and explanatory way, relevant themes of the daily life of all the judicial operators of Macao”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 02:43:27</pubDate></item><item><title>The artisan soul</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/a-alma-do-artesao/</link><description>From scrap to art, Carlos Kuan Ka Peng gives new life and character to his beloved retro bikes. “I have to create art that resonates with others, expressing ideas that survive its Creator,” says Carlos.
 
Carlos Kuan Ka Peng is a fervent retro motorcycle enthusiast that stands out in unique retro -creations through meticulous manual work, preserving the original tones of vehicles. Its transformations allow vehicles to incorporate a true feeling of past decades, revealing textures with several layers in the sunlight.
At the height of his collection, Carlos had accumulated 60 second -hand motorcycles. These discarded machines, which others considered scrap, were miraculously “resurrected” by their hands.
“My first concern in personalization is balance,” he says. "The design of each motorcycle's body is adapted to the conductor's physique. The resulting machines are not only unique works of art, but also perfectly balanced for stable driving."
However, from the beginning I had doubts: “Do others appreciate these meticulous creations like me? Could they be considered art?
For over a decade, when he thought of opening his own personalized motorcycle store, a friend's incentive gave him confidence: “Why not? Never heard about mechanical art? Everything that is done with the heart becomes art. ”
Looking at his motorcycle collection from the 80s-90, Carlos decided to call his store "Retro Garage". Storing Retro Garage's entrance is a two -time sports motorcycle adorned with Pepsi decorations. "This 34 -year -old vehicle belonged to a late local pilot whose son sold me."
Carlos believes that these aged machines can recover their rebel charisma through improved engines, modern brakes, suspension systems, foot supports and tires.
This form of car personalization art, known as “Kustom Kulture”, has its roots in Post-World War II America, when the surplus military motorcycles of Harley-Davidson were disarmed by people and turned into all-terrain-style robust machines, which later became movable personifications of a lifestyle that mixed rock 'n' roll, the art of the art, the art of the art Tattoo and the culture of American barber shop.
Carlos's aesthetic sensitivity, perfected under the tutelage of the famous designer Aser But, is expressed in all aspects of his work - from the design of the body to the helmets painted by measure. Even everyday articles, such as coats, shoes and hand bags, have their creative marks.
Retro motorcycles always draw the attention of drivers on the streets. “The nostalgic architecture of the city forms a perfect setting for these retro bikes,” says Carlos.
His passion even influenced Macao's motorcyclist community, having founded several organizations, such as Macao's retro motorcycling society and the Macao's old vehicle culture association, where enthusiasts often plan mini-traffic around the city and enjoy cafes.
From an early age, Carlos was an adventurous and fearless child who loved to walk the mountains - he began to be obsessed with BMX (bicycle motocross) and trail cycling, later expanding his passion to various types of motorcycles. “I had numerous accidents, but I always survived,” he recalls. "This made me brave and began to walk faster and faster, even reaching speeds of 140 km/h."
It shows the scars in my arms and adds: "I broke my arms and legs, I lost several teeth and my elbows, heels and knees were always hurt or injured."
Proudly, Carlos shows his hands "to Motard" - the result of decades to grasp and cheer accelerators. The muscles at the base of their thumbs are so developed due to the years of driving that, when the fists, the size muscle is clearly visible.
For aspiring motorcyclists who do not have these “biker hands” or retro bikes, Carlos prescribes the following “uniform” of retro motorcyclist essential for those who want to feel this retro vibration: long hair or beard (for men), classic ganga pants, heavy work boots or vans vans and a bold color helmet.
“Wear a leather jacket, put on the boots and will be immediately channeling this wild and rebellious spirit,” he says.
In addition to mere transportation, Retro bikes represent a lifestyle - a style that makes us want to dust the leather jacket at home and relive the golden era of indomitable freedom. “Throughout the journey of life, I realized that conventional careers only make my soul hungry. I have to create art that resonates with others, expressing ideas that survive their Creator-while mortal lives eventually disappear, the art we create can be forever,” says Carlos.
 
Macau Closer</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Discarded, for now, application of there in psychological support</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/descartada-para-ja-aplicacao-de-ai-no-apoio-psicologico/</link><description>Health services studied the application of artificial to intelligence technology (AI) on the psychological support platform, but found problems in their viability and safety. In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Lam Lon Wai, the authorities say the subject should be studied "in depth."
 
Authorities will not, for now, include Artificial Intelligence Technology (AI) on the psychological support platform. According to a response from health services to Deputy Lam Lon Wai, the use of AI in psychological support was the subject of a study, but problems were found in viability and security.
Some of the problems have to do with the fact that the platform involves the location of linguistic systems, the treatment and protection of personal data, the accuracy of identifying the crisis, as well as the respective follow -up and support procedures. Therefore, "at this stage, it should still be studied in more depth."
On the other hand, health services say that “with the progress of computer technology, artificial intelligence technology demonstrates significant advantages in raising health efficiency, optimizing resource allocation and improving patient medical experience”. A language therapy system with artificial intelligence assistance, as an effective complement to childhood language therapy services, “increases children's linguistic capacity,” the authorities emphasize.
Authorities also recalled that an interdepartal collaboration mechanism was created for “joint four -level prevention, closely interconnected to tetracyclics”, more accessiblely providing mental and psychological health services, in order to progressively broaden the social support network.
Nine health centers were also created, an external mental health consultation, and two non -profit institutions continue to be subsidized to provide psychological counseling consultation services. On the other hand, among the Psychiatry Service of the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center (CHCSJ), health centers and non -profit institutions, the urgent contact mechanism for communication and referencing was established to accompany the cases referred.
In written interpellation, Lam Lon Wai said that voice assistants they use there can "effectively improve the symptoms of mild to moderate depression and anxiety, and improve problem solving capacity."  AI psychotherapy as a complement to traditional therapy “is especially suitable for providing immediate assistance when there is a lack of professionals,” said the deputy. Lam Lon Wai was then asked if the government had a plan to “introduce or develop a psychological support platform based on artificial intelligence, for example, the use of a technology similar to Deepseek, through a chatbot that provides immediate emotional support and preliminary psychological assessment for residents, as well as 24 -hour online psychological consultation services”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 02:42:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Coutinho calls for transparency in renewal and urban rehabilitation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/coutinho-pede-transparencia-na-renovacao-e-reabilitacao-urbana/</link><description>For Pereira Coutinho, the city's renewal and urban rehabilitation should be an “absolute priority” of the government. The deputy says that the "slowness and lack of transparency" of the processes has generated "a growing feeling of dissatisfaction between the population."
 
José Pereira Coutinho sent yesterday a written interpellation to the government in which he asks for greater transparency in the processes of rehabilitation and urban renewal. The deputy even says that he should be considered as "an absolute priority" of the executive.
The buildings that are in a state of severe degradation “have a high risk to public health, with extremely dirty, unhealthy and insecure common spaces for their residents”, points out Coutinho, adding that “the slowness and lack of transparency in this process of urban renewal and rehabilitation have generated a growing feeling of dissatisfaction between the population”.
The president of the Macao Public Function Association (ATFPM) is concerned due to the “high amounts of the funds raised for the repair and renewal of buildings in the territory”.
"Opacity for the details of the costs involved in the projects, which have never been disclosed, raises serious doubts about the reasonableness and destination of the funds raised," says Coutinho, adding that "in certain cases, property -managing companies require the additional expenses incurred with consulting companies to be shared by minority owners" which, in the deputy's opinion, "is absolutely unacceptable."
On the other hand, according to Coutinho, the adjustment of the expense ratio ratio has been questioned by the owners, however, the companies refuse to respond. "It is frustrating that the property management committee did not consider the points of view of minority owners by presenting the maintenance proposals," reads the interpellation.
The law in force is, according to the deputy, ambiguous and unclear, which “generates confusion and injustice in solving the problems faced by minority owners and the management authority in the execution of the works”. "This regulatory ambiguity has left the minority owners without knowing how to proceed," he lamented, requiring the government to clarify the situation to "prevent minority owners from being forced to bear high costs due to lack of clear guidance while preventing management authorities from arbitrarily in the classification of works."
“In addition to the need to clearly differentiate the definitions of 'renewal works' and' change works', the government must set a maximum limit to the capital amount to mobilize for maintenance works and stipulate the corresponding percentage of owners' consent due to the amount,” notes that “currently, the approval of 'conservation works' requires only 15% of consent, but when the amount is excessive, in some cases, in some cases, in some cases More than 100,000 patacas to divide by each household, this percentage is unrealistic and is out of reach of the ordinary citizen. ”
Coutinho also says that "if no measures are adopted to improve excessive maintenance rates, society will face a number of social problems, affecting harmony and social stability." The deputy elected by Via Direct says that he is aware of "worrying accounts of owners who have tried to commit suicide due to financial pressure," and "many young owners who feel desperate for not being able to balance maintenance costs with their financial obligations, such as the mortgage of a home."</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 02:41:27</pubDate></item><item><title>External consultations of specialty at the hospital of the extended islands to non-residents</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/consultas-externas-de-especialidade-no-hospital-das-ilhas-alargadas-a-nao-residentes/</link><description>The Islands Hospital has extended the size of the target audience of the external specialty consultation service, on the basis for non-residents. The new measure came into force yesterday, being accepted online markings made by non -resident workers, students abroad and bearers of the special permanence title.
 
Non-residents in Macao can now access to hospital service for external specialty consultations at Hospital das Ilhas. The service of widening the service, as a costly, was announced yesterday by the Islands Health Care Complex - Macao Medical Center of the Union Medical College Hospital, and the marking service has been available since 10 am yesterday.
In this sense, non-residents, including those with the title of non-resident worker identification, the holders of the student visa, the holders of the special permanence title, among other long-term individuals in Macao, were integrated into the target audience of external consultations specialized in this institution.
According to a statement from the hospital, the external consultation service available covers various specialties, such as gastroenterology, gynecology and orthopedics, among others. Service expansion aims to “benefit more users and provide convenient medical services”.
Macau Union Hospital indicates that medical service applicants can make their own markings for the following week's external consultations through the hospital's official electronic electronic page or online marking system. Given the limited number of vacancies for each week, the markings will end as soon as all vacancies are filled.
In addition, users can learn about targeting policies and common basic services rates, which include consultation rates, nursing care, laboratory and imaging tests through the official portal of Macau Union Hospital.
For the external specialty consultation service on costly, residents can enjoy a 30% discount on the tax collection, while for non-residents will be charged normal fees.
The medical institution thus ensures to optimize service procedures, gradually launch more external appointments specialized for markings and also expand the size of services.
It is recalled that the Macau Union Hospital officially launched, in October last year, the costly medical services for non-referred patients, for the holders of the MSAR resident identity ticket, within the 12 external specialty consultation services, which covers neurology, malnutrition and obesity, consultation of pathology, asthma, general internal medicine, pediatrics, diabetes and diseases. Thyroid, nephrology, gastroenterology, dermatology, chronic pain and varicose veins.
The hospital provides medical services with three rates of rates, and level I is free medical care for local residents who currently enjoy free health care. Level II is onerous health care that residents will have a 30% discount on the tariff, while level III is international health care, intended for residents and people abroad, and corresponding rates refer to the market price of private health care services.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 02:44:28</pubDate></item><item><title>China sends delegation to Panama after ports agreement and exit of the “track and route”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/china-envia-delegacao-ao-panama-apos-acordo-sobre-portos-e-saida-da-faixa-e-rota/</link><description>China sent a delegation to Panama, following the country's decision to abandon the Chinese track and route initiative and the sale of Blackrock strategic ports, the state press reported yesterday. The Chinese delegation, led by Communist Party's Deputy Minister MA HUI, has visited the Central American country in recent days, where he has kept talks with “leaders of major political parties” and reflection groups (‘Think Tank’), said the official Chinese news agency Xinhua. MA said - quoted by Xinhua - that China is "willing to strengthen exchanges with Panama's political parties and reflection groups, improve mutual understanding and confidence, and consolidate the public support base for friendly relationships between China and Panama." The visit was followed by a surprise ad made by CK Hutchison Holdings (CKH) of the Hong Kong Li Ka-Shing tycoon, which was going to sell port operations, including those that are located at the ends of the Panama Canal, to a group led by the American asset manager Blackrock.
The Panama Canal, a crucial for trade between Asia and ports on the east coast of the Americas, gained renewed importance in the face of increased transportation costs, partly due to the dried records in 2023 and early 2024, which restricted the number of ships that could transit through that road. Completed under the auspices of the United States in 1914, the Panama Channel, which crosses Central America, became one of the targets of US President Donald Trump, as soon as he returned to the White House on January 20. Trump accused China of mastering operations on the channel and promised to "take it back." The official portals of the Chinese administration in Macau and Hong Kong announced on Friday a comment from a publication near Beijing, underlining the discomfort caused by the sale of ports in Panama. “It's not a 'normal commercial practice',” said Ta Kung Pao's text, a Hong Kong publication, considered close to Beijing's Central Government's connection office in this special administrative region, which ends with a veiled threat to Hong Kong's richest man. Last month, the president of Panama, José Raul Mulino, said the government gave China the 90 -day notice of the decision not to renew the involvement in the track and route initiative, an international infrastructure program launched by the Asian country. The decision was described by Beijing as "not being in the vital interest of Panama."
Analysts considered that Chinese authorities should seek to clarify whether recent Panama measures constitute a “decisive change” in favor of the United States. Beijing should also look for more information about what the sale of ports can mean for China's commercial and sea routes, they added. The delegation led by MA belongs to the International Department of the Communist Party and not to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of China, which means that the visit was framed as a visit between parties. The director of the Institute of International Affairs at Renmin University in Beijing told the Hong Kong South China Morning Post newspaper that the visit occurs in a period of growing US concern with the increase in Chinese investments in Panama. For Wang Yiwei, Washington wants to "weaken China's position as the largest global commercial partner." "The US is trying to disturb things, forcing Panama to withdraw from agreements in a similar way to what happened to Italy," he said, referring to Italy in 2023 from the Chinese infrastructure program to align more closely with Western allies, including the US. According to Wang, the visit shows that, despite recent developments, China will continue to dialogue with Panama and seek to “avoid the negative impacts” of recent developments. "We need not only improve relationships between Panama and China, but also to avoid a domino effect that causes misunderstandings between China and other countries," he said. "We must continue to engage positively with these countries, encouraging them to resist US coercion, which violates their national interests," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 02:43:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Jockey Club also has 15 cats for capturing and sterilizing</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/jockey-club-tem-ainda-15-gatos-por-capturar-e-esterilizar/</link><description>In the Jockey Club space there are 15 cats that have not yet been captured, the animal's protective society, an association that is coordinating the work of re -delaying the cats living on the old horses in the mud in the mud.
According to an Animo social networking publication, the group said he hopes to complete the capture of all cats until 25 of this month, in order to advance with the later work of sterilization. The anima has updated the information that, in addition to the 22 cats that were adopted by the residents in the adoption campaign on Sunday, there are 61 cats that will be welcomed by animal protection organizations.
Among the 61 cats, three were diagnosed with feline panleukopenia and will be taken to a veterinary clinic by the Jockey Club for treatment, being the Jockey Club responsible for corresponding medical expenses. These three cats will be delivered to anima after their recovery. The remaining 58 cats will be subjected to Feline Panleukopen Tests during this week, and then sent to various animal protection organizations for progressively resettlement.
In the published note, Anima thanked the public for their participation in the adoption campaign, as well as the help provided by the nine volunteers of the event. The association stressed to be satisfied with the adoption and resettlement of cats in the Jockey Club, which did not have to be transported to Zhuhai. Anima also directed thanks to local animal protection organizations for offering the places for the friends to be resolved.
The Macau Jockey Club, which is about to return the land to the government after its closure, planned to send about 100 cats, who lived in its space, to the interior of China, without revealing details, such as the name and address, of the alleged shelter of cats in Zhuhai. The plan was revealed only on social networks by an animal care volunteer at the Jockey Club and received numerous criticism from the residents. The controversy led to the retreat of the Jockey Club's decision, which eventually collaborated with Anima to put the cats for adoption and resolving in Macao.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 02:43:27</pubDate></item><item><title>China reveals a plan to “vigorously boost” consumer spending</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/china-revela-plano-para-impulsionar-vigorosamente-gastos-dos-consumidores/</link><description>China announced yesterday a plan to revitalize domestic consumption, at a time when Beijing struggles to reverse the weak confidence of consumers and deflationist pressures in the second largest economy in the world.
 
The government will “propel vigorously consumption” and “expand internal demand in all directions,” said the official Xinhua news agency, echoing the appeal of Chinese President Xi Jinping at the end of last year for political decision makers to support demand, following a sustained boost to drive the industry.
The Council of State (Executive) will focus on increasing income, stabilization of real estate and the scholarship market and improving medical and pension services, although political officials have provided few details on tax expenses during a press conference in Beijing.
During the conference, the authorities largely repeated the figures published in the annual budget last week during the plenary session of the National Popular Assembly, where delegates reaffirmed consumption as a top priority.
Hang Seng Kong's Hang Seng Index rose 0.8%, while Brent oil futures, the international oil reference, rose 0.6% to $ 71 per barrel.
The CSI 300 index of mainland China, which brings together the largest companies quoted in Shanghai and Shenzhen, ended with a drop of 0.2%.
Consumer spending on China has been weak since the end of the Covid-19 pandemic for more than two years, as families have been cautious about expenses. Consumer prices registered deflation in February, although reading was affected by the Lunar New Year holiday.
The slowdown of China's vast real estate sector, partly driven by a government's disagreement initiative and that is already in its fourth year, also revived economists' appeals to reinforce internal demand.
Data from China's National Statistics Office showed that retail sales increased 4% in January and February compared to the previous year, surpassing the 3.7% increase in December. The average prices of the new houses fell over the previous month.
Last September, the political decision makers revealed a long-awaited package to support the economy, but the measures focused mainly on scholarship markets.
The new consumer plan includes promises to increase the minimum wage, reinforce support for education, and create a child custody subsidy system, a pressing issue, as China's population has been decreasing for three consecutive years.
Lynn Song, chief economist at Dutch Bank Ing to Greater China, wrote that the plan puts "a considerable emphasis on increasing families' ability and willingness" and could "help China's economic transition to a consumer-oriented growth model."
Data released on Monday also showed that industrial production grew 5.9% in homologous terms in the first two months of 2025, slowing over the 6.2% recorded in December, but exceeding analysts' expectations of an increase of 5.3%. The new measuring package will also promote “internal” consumption.
Beijing widened the exemption of visas to dozens of countries last year, in an effort to relaunch international tourism after pandemic. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 02:43:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Council of Portuguese Communities and Macao Forum come together in Timor-Leste</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/conselho-das-comunidades-portuguesas-e-forum-de-macau-reunem-se-em-timor-leste/</link><description>The Portuguese communities counselors in Asia and Oceania gathered yesterday, March 17, with members of the Permanent Secretariat of the Macao Forum. The meeting took place within the scope of an official visit to Dili, regarding the face-to-face meeting of the Asia Regional Council and Oceania of the Portuguese Communities Council (CCP), to be held on March 20 and 21, 2025.
The president of the CCP Regional Council of Asia and Oceania, Rui Marcelo, and the Portuguese communities counselors of the China Circle, Marília Coutinho and Luís Neves, maintained a “audience and presentation of greetings” of about an hour with the delegate of Timor-Leste with the Permanent Secretariat of the Macao Forum, António Ramos Silva, and the Deputy Secretary of the Permanent Secretariat of the Permanent Secretariat Macao Forum, Danilo Afonso Henriques.
According to a press release, the meeting “took place in a cordial and friendly environment” and addressed “issues of common interest, focusing on the promotion of Portuguese language and culture, through reinforcement and cooperation in the education sector, exchange in economic cooperation between Macao and Timor-Leste and in strengthening the relationship between Portuguese Communities of the Asia Regional Council and Oceania”.
In addition to the discussion of these topics, the “intense” program of activities to be done during the stay in the capital of Timor-Leste was also released, which includes a hearing with the President of the Republic of Timor-Leste, José Ramos-Horta, and the Portuguese Ambassador in Dili, Maria Manuela Freitas Barros.
In the CCP statement, it is read that António Ramos Silva and Danilo Afonso Henriques “thanked the visit of the Portuguese communities counselors of the China Circle and the sharing of information regarding their program”, making it available to “collaborate and support the activities of the CCP” and to promote “narrowing of relations between both regions”.
In addition to the Circle of China (Macao, Hong Kong, China, Tokyo, Bangkok, Seoul and Singapore), the Asia and Oceania Regional Council includes the circles of Timor-Leste and Australia.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 02:43:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Opposition announces refers to death penalty and martial law in Taiwan</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/oposicao-anuncia-referendos-sobre-pena-de-morte-e-lei-marcial-em-taiwan/</link><description>Taiwan's main opposition party announced yesterday the realization of referendums on the abolition of the death penalty and the law. In statements released by the Taiwanese news agency CNA, Kuomintang President Eric Chu explained that the goal of the two referendum is that the population “manifests and expresses their will”, opposing the “de facto abolition” of capital penalty and demanding that the government does not cause “risks of war or the imposition of marcial law”.
Although Taiwan's Constitutional Court confirmed the constitutionality of the death penalty for the most serious cases in September, Chu complained that the requirement that the courts issue “unanimous decisions” about these cases resulted in a “abolition of the death penalty, which prevents justice from being done”.
Regarding the second referendum, the opposition leader denounced that labeling China as "hostile foreign force" based on "pro-independence positions could lead both sides of Taiwan's narrow to a" quasi-war "situation.
On Thursday, the territory leader, William Lai, called China a “hostile foreign force” in one of his hardest speeches since taking office. “China already fulfills the definition of 'hostile foreign force' under the anti-infiltration law (…). The time has come to implement appropriate preventive measures, reinforce our democratic resilience and national security, and protect our estimated free and democratic way of life, ”Lai proclaimed.
Yesterday, during the same meeting with the press, a KMT deputy, Lo Chih-Chiang, argued that Lai's 17 proposals to mitigate China's influence and infiltration operations resemble an “almost martial state”, which raised fears of war among the island's population. "Promoting these two referendums is a collective effort to protect Taiwan and democracy, using broader democratic mechanisms to ensure the safety of all citizens," Chu concluded.
Following the announcement of these consultations, the leader of the Progressive Democratic Party Parliamentary Group (DPP, in power), Ker Chien-Min, classified as “a joke” the KMT proposal to make a referendum on marcial law, stating that the territory leader himself was speaking to such a measure and recalling that the Constitutional Court has already commented on the constitutionality of the death penalty.
According to the Taiwan referendum law, legislators have the power to summon popular consultations on relevant political issues. If approved, the proposal may be subjected to a review from April 21 in Parliament, where the KMT and Taiwan's popular party holds most seats, CNA said on Friday.
The announcement of these two referendums is part of a broader political struggle between the government and the Taiwanese opposition, which has used most to, among other things, reject the budget presented by the executive.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 02:43:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Temperatures rise with the arrival of spring</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/temperaturas-sobem-com-a-chegada-da-primavera/</link><description>Temperatures will rise again this week. According to data provided by Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG), the cold front and the Northeast Monsoon who have influenced the territory will give way to higher temperatures and higher moisture levels from tomorrow, Wednesday.
Today, temperatures should oscillate between 14 and 21 degrees Celsius, with very cloudy sky and moderate wind interspersed with occasional gusts. Temperatures will progressively rise to the weekend, settling at a minimum of 17 degrees and at a maximum of 25 degrees Celsius on Sunday.
Humidity will also gradually increase up to 40% to 85% scheduled for Sunday, contrasting with the drier time of the week. Next weekend of March 22 and 23, the wind should appease and stay between levels 2 to 3 of the Beaufort scale-that is, weak to good.
The first half of this month was marked by the alternation between cold and heat, as well as occasional sweepers and fog periods. SMG's weather forecast coincides with the arrival of spring, which will start this Thursday, March 20.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 02:43:26</pubDate></item><item><title>City of Dreams receives a tribute dinner for chef Alain Ducassase</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/city-of-dreams-recebe-jantar-de-homenagem-ao-chef-alain-ducasse/</link><description>The French chef, who supervises the Alain Ducassea at Morpheus restaurant, was received in Macao with a sensory and artistic experience of five French cuisine dishes, carefully selected wines and live musical shows. It was the chef himself who guided the restaurant team, while sharing his culinary philosophy with colleagues and guests.
 
The Alain Ducasse at Morpheus restaurant, located at City of Dreams, hosted a French French banquet of five dishes last Friday with live musical shows regarding the visit of chef Alain Ducasse to Macau.
In a statement released yesterday, Monday, Melco Resorts qualifies dinner as “a culinary and refined artistic experience”, which combined the flavors of French gastronomy with harp melodies, violins and saxophone, played live throughout the event. The curator of the dinner was chef Alain Ducasse himself, who interacted with the guests and shared “his unique culinary philosophy and their creative inspirations” while the main dishes were served.
The cuisine, led by Cedric Satabin, presented variations of five of chef Ducasse's most “iconic” signature dishes, starting with Alaska's real crab served with puree green peas and caviar specifically obtained for the restaurant.
The second and third dishes were referring to the spring season: the second presented Morchella mushrooms and earsome asparagos, “offering a fresh and earthy flavor” of the season, while the third combined the preached with “The Sweet Flavor of the Earth” provided by the carrot puree and the confit lemon.
The French cheese “Comé Fromagerie Vagne Special Reserve” was followed, whose 32-month process of rich rich cheese aroma, leaving an indulgent and persistent milk smell, ”according to Melco's description. The meal ended with the sweet notes of chocolate and coffee from Parisian chocolate les Manufactures Alain Ducasse.
The five dishes presented at the event will be gradually included in the restaurant menu and can be enjoyed by a more general audience.
Equally careful was the choice of wines that complemented the flavors of each dish, selected from a list of 1,200 copies present in the restaurant cellar. The goal, reiterates Melco, was "creating a truly unforgettable gastronomic experience for guests."
A legendary figure of French cuisine, chef Ducasse oversees almost 30 restaurants in nine countries. Many of these were awarded Michelin stars - as is the case of Alain Ducasse at Morpheus, who at this year's ceremony maintained the two -star rating. Among the others (and vast) recognitions received by the Macau Restaurant, there is also a diamond of the Black Pearl Restaurant Guide 2025, a guide that recognizes culinary excellence in China, and the inclusion in the list of excellence restaurants of the prestigious La Liste platform.
At the awards ceremonies this year, the critics praised Alain Ducasse at Morpheus for the contemporary view of French gastronomy and the use of products from small farmers, providing a respectful cooking experience of the stations.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Hong Kong appoints new cabinet leader in London after espionage case</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/hong-kong-nomeia-nova-lider-do-gabinete-em-londres-apos-caso-de-espionagem/</link><description>Hong Kong yesterday appointed Fiona Chau Suet-Mui as a new director general of the Commercial Office of the former British colony in London, ten months after a spy scandal that involved a manager of this cabinet.
 
In a statement, the Hong Kong government said Fiona Chau will immediately take office that has so far belonged to Gilford Law Sun-On, highlighted in the United Kingdom capital since 2021.
Chau will be responsible for promoting Hong Kong's bilateral relations with the United Kingdom, Denmark, Estonia, Finland, Latvia, Lithuania, Norway, Russia and Sweden.
Cited in the statement, the manager promised to work to promote Hong Kong's “international competitiveness” and “strengthen economic, commercial and cultural bonds” with nine countries.
Chau, who had already worked at Hong Kong's commercial offices in Whasington and Brussels, has so far been responsible for urban renewal policies in the Territory Government Development Department.
This appointment comes ten months after Bill Yuen Chung-Biu, 63, an office manager, was accused of helping Hong Kong information services and foreign interference.
Yuen and two other suspects, Peter Wai Chi-Leung, 38, and 37-year-old Matthew Trickett were arrested in early May and placed under coercion measures.
Trickett was found dead a week after going to court in a park in Maidenhing, west of London, and British police started an investigation into the case.
At the time of the detention, the representation of the Chinese Foreign Ministry in Hong Kong “vehemently condemned the British government for“ making accusations, arbitrarily arresting Chinese citizens and defaming ”the Hong Kong government.
Hong Kong has been a specific source of tensions between the United Kingdom and China due to its unique history as ancient British colony that was returned to Chinese control on July 1, 1997.
After the Hong Kong government approved by a comprehensive national security law that restricts the democratic rights previously guaranteed to territory residents, the United Kingdom flexed immigration rules for Hong Kong inhabitants born before the transfer of control.
About 5.4 million residents of Hong Kong are eligible for a visa that allows them to live and work in the UK and become citizens after five years of residence.
The repression of the pro-democracy movement has led many to seek asylum on British soil. More than 191,000 people have already received the visas and the government estimates that about 322,000 will be granted at the end.
In July 2023, London vehemently protested the capture warrants and promises of reward issued against pro-democracy activists who had fled from Hong Kong. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 02:43:31</pubDate></item><item><title>February recorded a significant drop in cases of communicable diseases</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/fevereiro-registou-queda-significativa-dos-casos-de-doencas-transmissiveis/</link><description>The data regarding February on the evolution of mandatory declaration diseases of health services revealed a total of 1,539 cases registered, especially influenza, norovirus and scarletin infection. Compared to the previous year, there was a clear tendency to reduce cases, signaling the positive impact of public health prevention measures and the continuous surveillance of the authorities.
 
Health services (SS) released February data on the evolution of mandatory statement diseases in the region, highlighting the importance of epidemiological monitoring for the implementation of effective prevention measures.
In total, 1,539 cases of transmissible diseases were reported during this month. The three diseases groups that most concern authorities are influenza, norovirus and scarletin infection, which together constitute a constant challenge to public health.
Influenza, or flu, was responsible for 1,252 cases in February, which represents a decrease of 28.2% compared to 1,744 cases of the same month of the previous year and a significant reduction of 42.8% over the previous month. This highly contagious acute respiratory disease is more prevalent during the winter and spring months. The most common types of flu in Macao are flu A (H1N1 and H3N2) and Flu B. Seasonal vaccination remains the most effective prevention method, especially for vulnerable groups such as elderly and children.
In the case of Norovirus infection, 62 cases were diagnosed, demonstrating a 40.4% drop from 104 cases recorded in the same month of the previous year and a decrease of 24.4% compared to the previous month. This disease, which affects the gastrointestinal tract, is transmitted mainly by consumption of contaminated food or water and contact with secretions of patients. Infection outbreaks usually occur in homes of elderly, schools and other collective establishments, and it is important to highlight that all age groups are susceptible, especially during winter, when the incidence is higher.
In turn, scarletin registered 60 cases in February, which indicates a significant decrease of 60.5% compared to the 152 cases of the previous year, as well as a decrease of 38.1% over the previous month. This respiratory infection, caused by group A hemolytic beta hemolytic streptococcus, has a period of incubation of 1 to 3 days and is transmitted through contact with oral and respiratory secretions of the sick. Although scarletin can occur at any time of the year, peaks usually happen in spring and winter, with children between the two and eight years the most affected. The absence of appropriate treatment can lead to serious complications, which shows the importance of early diagnosis and treatment.
Under current legislation, medical institutions, as well as health professionals, have the responsibility to notify cases of communicable diseases, thus contributing to more efficient and informed public health management, according to SS.
To further reduce the risk of influenza infections and other transmissible diseases, SS appeals to the population to be informed about individual protection measures. Periodic information provided by the authorities not only improves awareness of disease prevention, but also helps to foster a culture of care and health responsibility.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 02:43:29</pubDate></item><item><title>China condemns US sanctions against Thailand due to the deportation of Uigures</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/china-condena-sancoes-dos-eua-contra-a-tailandia-devido-a-deportacao-de-uigures/</link><description>China criticized the sanctions imposed by the United States on Thai employees involved in the deportation of 40 Chinese citizens. The Foreign Ministry spokeswoman rejected what she called “malicious defamation” and described Washington's restrictions on Thai officials as “illegal.
 
China yesterday criticized the sanctions imposed by the United States to Thai employees involved in the deportation of 40 Chinese citizens and accused Washington of politicizing cooperation between safety countries.
“Forced and indiscriminate deportation of illegal immigrants by the United States strongly contrasts with their attempts to attack, defame and impose sanctions against legitimate cooperation among other countries on law application. This is a typical act of harassment, ”said Foreign Ministry spokeswoman Mao Ning at a press conference.
Mao Ning rejected what he called “malicious defamation” and described Washington's restrictions on Thai officials as “illegal”, stating that cooperation between China and Thailand was performed “in the scope of Chinese and Thai laws, international law and global norms”.
Mao argued that the 40 repatient people "left China illegally" and were "retained in Thailand for 10 years." "The Chinese government has the responsibility to protect its citizens, help them meet with their families and facilitate their reintegration in society," he added.
The spokeswoman also criticized Washington's position, noting that, in the 2024 fiscal year, US authorities deported more than 270,000 illegal immigrants from 192 countries, the highest number since 2014. "The US use human rights to manipulate social issues, interfere with China's internal affairs and interrupt normal law cooperation," he said.
The US Secretary of State, Marco Rubio, recently announced sanctions against Thai employees and former employees for his role in the deportation of 40 members of the Chinese ethnic minority of Muslim origin Uiguur to China, arguing that Washington is “committed to fighting China's efforts to press the governments to force the Uigures and other groups” face abuse in the Asian giant.
Thailand's Ministry of Foreign Affairs defended the deportation on Saturday, stating that the process was performed “following humanitarian principles” and reiterated that Bangkok “clarified this subject on several occasions with the countries that expressed concern”, stressing that the relationship with the US should be based on “mutual respect”. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 02:43:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Cooperation between Macau and Jiangmen has achieved “fruit results over the years”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/cooperacao-entre-macau-e-jiangmen-alcancou-resultados-frutiferos-ao-longo-dos-anos/</link><description>The chief executive met yesterday with Chen Anming, secretary of the Jiangmen Municipal Committee of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP). At the meeting, Sam Hou Fai indicated that, given the geographical proximity and cultural affinity between Macau and Jiangmen, "bilateral cooperation projects have realized fruitful results over the years."
Sam reiterated that "the sons is committed to integrating the country's development conjuncture, continuing to reinforce cooperation with Jiangmen and other cities integrated in the Great Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau Bay, for a joint development with complementary advantages."
The chief executive also pointed out that "Macau will continue to fully play his unique role as a platform for services for economic and commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, supporting companies in the interior of China, especially from the areas of manufacturing, appliances and renewable energy from the great bay to enter Lusophone markets."
Finally, Sam Hou Fai also pointed out that Macau and Jiangmen “can further intensify cooperation in the area of ​​cultural tourism, promoting the connection and collaboration between the competent entities of the two regions, and establishing 'multi-deserted' tourist itineraries, in order to achieve mutual benefits”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 02:43:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese industrial production increases 5.9% in the first two months of the year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/18/producao-industrial-chinesa-aumenta-59-nos-dois-primeiros-meses-do-ano/</link><description>China's industrial production rose 5.9%, in homologous terms, in the first two months of the year, above the analyst forecast, according to official data released yesterday.
The pace of growth in the first two months of the year is, however, 0.3% lower than that reached in December.
Among the three main sectors in which the National Statistics Office (NBS) of the Asian country divides the indicator, which most contributed to production in January and February was the transforming industry (+6.9%), followed by the extractive industry (+4.3%) and the production and supply of electricity, heating, gas and water, which registered an advance of 1.1%.
The institution highlighted the resumption of production in some segments, such as the car manufacture industry (+12%), textiles (+7%) or the food processing industry (+8.3%).
NBS also released other statistical data, such as retail sales -consumer state key indicator -, which grew 4%in homologous terms, a percentage that is in line with analyst forecasts and exceeding December (+3.7%) and the overall value to 2024 (+3.5%).
The official unemployment rate in urban areas was 5.4% in late February, more 0.2% than at the end of the first month of the year.
Investment in fixed assets increased by 4.1%, in homologous terms, in the first two months of the year, also strongly exceeding the previous registration (+3.2%) and analyst predictions (+3.6%).
In the segments in which this last indicator is divided, the investment destined to the primary sector (agriculture, mining, fisheries, forestry) increased 12.2%, while intended for industry increased by 11.4%and the tertiary sector (services) 0.7%.
The investment in real estate promotion fell 9.8% in the first two months of the year, a lower value compared to the drop recorded in 2024 (-10.6%), in the context of a prolonged crisis in the sector, which has weighed on the economic recovery of the Asian country.
The NBS publishes the data for January and February together to avoid any distortion due to the Lunar New Year week, which pits every year on different days.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 02:43:30</pubDate></item></channel></rss>