<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/o-primeiro-discurso-politico-de-sam-hou-fai-e-a-politica-de-reforma-em-macau/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>India ends the main border with Pakistan after an attack in Caxemira</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/india-encerra-principal-fronteira-com-paquistao-depois-de-ataque-em-caxemira/</link><description>India announced yesterday the closure of the main border post with Pakistan, which will summon on Thursday the Pakistani National Security Committee.
 
These ads came up a day after the deadliest attack of recent years against Caxemira Indian, in which 28 people died.
The Attari-Wagah border between the two rival countries “will be closed with immediate effects,” said Vikram Misri, head of the Indian Foreign Ministry.
The same source added that people with valid travel documents can return before May 1st.
Nova Delhi also stated “Persona Non Grata” Pakistani defense counselors and decided to expel several diplomats after a meeting of the Security Office Committee, chaired by Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi.
The Committee has decided to apply a series of measures designed to manifest a firm position of India against what it considers to be Pakistan's support for transfronist terrorism.
India ordered the defense counselors, military, naval and air of the Pakistan High Commissioner (Embassy) in Nova Delhi to abandon the country within a week.
As a reciprocal measure, India will remove the counselors from Islamabade, thus abolishing the posts in the two diplomatic missions. The exemption regime of visas to Pakistani citizens was also suspended, revoking all previous visas issued under this program. A strategic treaty of water sharing with Pakistan was suspended.
For its part, Pakistan will call the National Security Committee on Thursday “to respond to the Indian government's statement,” said vice-minister and head of diplomacy, Ishaq to give.
Armed men attacked a group of tourists on Tuesday in the so-called “Little Switzerland”, near the tourist city of Pahalgam, in Caxemira administered by Nova Delhi.
Eye witnesses said the attackers left the dense forests of Pinheiros and apparently selectively aimed at people who thought they were not Muslim.
A hitherto unknown militant group who calls himself a resistance front (FRT) claimed the authorship of the attack in a statement issued by the Indian press.
Indian authorities consider FRT to be a branch of the Lashkar-e-Taiba (Let), a Pakistani militant group, responsible for violent India attacks in the past.
The FRT was formed after the revocation by India of the Cashmira Semi -automatonomy status in 2019, when the group stated that its motivation was to respond to the Indian government's policies in Caxemira, including the alleged installation of non -local population in the region.
The Cashmira region has historically been a point of conflict between India and Pakistan since independence in 1947. Both countries claim sovereignty over territory. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:09:39</pubDate></item><item><title>China prepares suspension of sanctions for MEPs with a view to investment agreement</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/china-prepara-suspensao-de-sancoes-a-eurodeputados-com-vista-a-acordo-de-investimento/</link><description>The European Parliament has announced that China is preparing to survey the sanctions imposed on MEPs due to disputes on human rights violations, at a time when it tries to revive an investment agreement with Europe.
A spokesman for Roberta Metsola confirmed on Wednesday the decision, initially reported by the German press, during a time when the trade war launched by US President Donald Trump is getting back to China and Europe.
Beijing imposed sanctions against various MEPs in 2021, after the European Union has imposed sanctions on some Chinese entities due to alleged human rights violations against the Chinese ethnic minority of Muslim origin Uiguur in Xinjiang in the far northwest of China.
The European Parliament then refused to ratify the Global Investment Agreement UE-China, which would have deepened commercial ties between the two parties.
However, Donald Trump's return to power seems to be overwhelming both sides, in the face of the antagonistic positions of the US leader in the face of the transatlantic alliance and the trade war against the rest of the world.
"The discussions with the Chinese authorities are still in the final phase," said Metsola spokesman. "The president will inform group leaders as soon as the Chinese authorities officially confirm the survey of sanctions. The European Parliament has always intended to raise sanctions and resume relations with China," he added.
Among those aimed at the sanctions is the German Reinhard Bütikofer (Green Group/European Free Alliance), former leader of the European Parliament delegation for relations with China, who however abandoned the position of MEP. Already Michael Gahler (Germany), Miriam Lexmann (Slovakia), Raphaël Glucksmann (France) and Ilhan Kyuchyuk (Bulgaria) continue in the European Parliament and were also targeted by the sanctions. EU sanctions against Chinese entities remain in force.
In addition to the MEPs, China sanctioned two EU committees, three national deputies, the Think Tank) Mercator Institute for China Studies, the Alliance of Democracies Foundation and two academics.
In another sign of rapprochement, the president of the European Commission, Ursula von der Leyen, and European Council President Antonio Costa are expected to visit Beijing in June for a summit with the leaders of the Asia.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:09:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong Court authorized Cardinal Joseph Zen to watch the funeral</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/tribunal-de-hong-kong-autorizou-cardeal-joseph-zen-a-assistir-ao-funeral/</link><description>Cardinal Joseph Zen, Bishop Emeritus of Hong Kong, was authorized the former British colony to watch Pope Francis' funeral in the Vatican City, the Associated Press agency said yesterday.
 
Joseph Zen, 93, left Hong Kong on Wednesday night after filing a court to recover his passport, his secretary told AP.
Authorities confiscated their passport to Zen after being temporarily detained under a national security law imposed by Beijing in the special administrative region in 2022.
Zen is among critics who in recent years have stated that the Vatican's agreement with the Chinese authorities about the appointment of bishops betrayed the Chinese Catholics who remained faithful to the Vatican. He also criticized the Secretary of State Pietro Parolin, the head of negotiations with Beijing, as a "man of little faith." Parolin is considered one of the main candidates to be the next Pope, given his prominence in the Catholic hierarchy.
On Tuesday, Zen issued a criticism of the Vatican, questioning why pre-competition meetings began on that day. His secretary said Zen would return to Hong Kong after the Pope's funeral, which is scheduled for Saturday. But he said he was not sure of the exact date of the return.
This is not the first time Zen has to ask for permission to leave Hong Kong, a neighboring city of Macao. In 2023, he underwent similar procedures to pay tribute to the late Pope Emeritus Benedict XVI. On this trip, he met Francisco at a private audience.
Zen was first arrested in 2022 on suspicion of collusion with foreign forces under the National Security Act. At the time, the detention caused a wave of shock in the Catholic community.
The religious was fined in 2022 after being considered guilty of not registering a now extinct fund that aimed to help protesters arrested following the pro-democracy protests, which in 2019 shook Hong Kong. The hearing of the appeal against the conviction is scheduled for December.
Beijing and the Vatican cut the diplomatic relations following the climb to the power of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) in 1949 and the expulsion of foreign priests from the Chinese continent. The great divergence that followed was focused on the appointment of the bishops, with Beijing and the Holy See to complain to itself this right. China has about 12 million Catholics, but Catholic manifestations in the country are only allowed under the Chinese Catholic Patriotic Association, the Church approved by the Vatican CCP and independent. However, many of the Chinese Catholics continued to celebrate their faith in clandestine churches who remained faithful to the Vatican exclusively.
In 2018, both signed the aforementioned agreement criticized by Joseph Zen and aimed at bringing together the divided Catholics between the official and clandestine churches. According to the document, the Chinese government retains the authority to propose the names of bishops candidates, but it is the Pope who has the final word, and may approve or refuse the appointment.
In a sign of increasingly cordial relations, China and Vatican announced last October that they had renewed the validity of the document for a period of four years.
The Chinese Constitution officially recognizes the “freedom of religious belief,” that is, the right to believe in a religion, but does not mention “religious freedom”, which has a wider scope. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:09:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Gifts that speak Chinese</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/presentes-que-falam-chines/</link><description>The experience of living in Macau is like diving in an ocean of traditions and superstitions, where each gesture and each gift carries a symbolic weight that can surprise even the most assertive and cautious. Na minha jornada por esta cultura rica rapidamente aprendi que presentear não é apenas uma questão de dar algo material; é um verdadeiro exercício de diplomacia social.
The flowers represent the usual situation. If in most cultures a branch of flowers is synonymous with affection and is almost always a right choice, in Chinese white flowers, instead of a smile can cause tears, being a symbol of mourning. It reigns the ban on the entry of flowers in hospitals and health services like this, when visiting the friend who had a plump baby, prefer to bring a basket of oranges or apples, sign of good luck, or a package of ginger crackers, health symbol and vitality, beyond their anti-inflammatory property.
Early on I was alerted to the prohibition of the act from giving clocks. In Western culture and, for me in particular, a timeless and striking gift. I remember, with love and nostalgia, the moment when my father passed me to the wrist one of the watches that best characterizes him. He had been presented to him by his best friend, my godfather of baptism, and my father wanted to inherit and honor him. In Chinese culture this gesture would be a direct invitation to bad luck, and the word "clock" phonetically resembles "death."
Gifts with sharp functions, such as knives or scissors, should be avoided because, in the eyes of Chinese culture, they reveal a fear of breaking relationship and bad intentions.
Thus, given the need to give a Chinese, give preference to well-being related items, such as a diffuser of essential oils or an inner plant, such as a lucky bamboo. Gift accessories or decoration elements are also a right choice; A small ceramic vase or a part of handwriting that represents happiness or prosperity. Offering a fruit basket, a typical cookie box or quality tea is an invitation to sharing, unity and mutual respect.
In Chinese culture, the gifting art goes far beyond the simple act of giving. This gesture, rooted in millennial traditions, teaches us that each gift carries a genuine intention and, especially, an invitation to the construction of ties. Who would say that offering a simple fruit piece could be more auspicious than a clock? And so, here, I still learn and respect. Always with an open heart, a smile on my lips, my father's clock on his wrist, and in his hand a very careful red package.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:08:59</pubDate></item><item><title>China announces detention of 920 suspects of fraud in cooperation with Myanmar</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/china-anuncia-detencao-de-920-suspeitos-de-fraude-em-cooperacao-com-myanmar/</link><description>China has received 920 suspects of involvement in fraudulent schemes through telephone calls and the Internet, operated from centers managed by criminal organizations at Myanmar, the Chinese Public Security Ministry of Public Security announced yesterday.
The suspects were delivered on Wednesday at the Daluo border post in Yunnan province, southern China, which borders Myanmar, the ministry said in a statement.
The operation “marks a new achievement in the continuous efforts of Chinese and Burmese police forces to combat fraud through telecommunications and the Internet in Myanmar, after the complete dismantling of large -scale fraud operations in the north,” the same source said.
China and Myanmar jointly detained a total of 55,000 suspects, after operations against fraud crimes themselves intensified in the Burmese Norte.
In recent months, although criminal organizations have been reduced, some suspects have escaped detention, moving, and hiding in the country's more remote areas, where they created new operations centers to continue the cross-border fraud, aimed mainly at Chinese citizens, according to Beijing.
China's security forces "intensified the analysis of information services and quickly provided data to Myanmar," the ministry said, adding that this collaboration resulted in "detention of more than 920 Chinese suspects and seizing large quantities of equipment used in crimes, including computers, mobile phones, bank cards and scripts on how to commit turns."
The large proportion of Myanmar suspects is explained by the proliferation of these centers in the border zones, following the February 2021 coup, which generated great instability in the country and encouraged the activity of several organized crime groups.
According to a UN report, at least 120,000 people are retained in these centers, where they are forced to practice fraud on the Internet, while in Cambodia - another epicenter of these crimes - the number is estimated at about 100,000.
In recent months, China has exerted pressure on the Burmese military junta and performed several operations to dismantle some of these networks.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:09:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Former South Korean President Moon Jae-in accused of corruption</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/antigo-presidente-sul-coreano-moon-jae-in-acusado-de-corrupcao/</link><description>Former South Korean President Moon Jae-in was charged with corruption, suspected of facilitating hiring the son-in-law in an airline, prosecutors announced yesterday. This is another episode to stain the South Korean political scene, shaken by several months of chaos after the state-of-the-art statement of martial law.
Moon Jae-in, former President of Center left (2017-2022), was “accused of corruption for receiving 217 million Won [132. 200 euros] after facilitating the signing of son-in-law from an airline,” said Jeonju district prosecutor.
According to the Public Prosecution Service, Moon's son-in-law was appointed director general of the Thai Eastar Jet airline, "despite having no relevant experience or qualifications in the aviation sector."
The company, controlled by a former Moon party deputy Jae-in, appointed son-in-law to get favors from the then president.
Any salary and other financial benefits paid by the airline to the Moon son -in -law between 2018 and 2020, "were confirmed as not being legitimate salary payments, but bribes to the president," the prosecutors added.
Moon Jae-in is known to have promoted the approach between Seoul and Pyongyang, in particular, for organizing conversations between North Korean leader Kim Jong-un and US President Donald Trump during the first term.
With the accusation of Moon Jae-in, two former South Korean presidents are being tried simultaneously.
Yoon Suk-Youol is currently being tried by insurrection, after on the night from December 3 to 4, 2024, imposed the martial law in the country, sending the army to block the opposition-dominated parliament. However, enough deputies managed to meet to raise the martial law hours later.
If considered guilty, Yoon may be sentenced to life imprisonment or even to death. However, the condemnation of death is highly unlikely, as South Korea has an unofficial moratorium on executions since 1997.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:09:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau International Airport moved 1.83 million passengers in the first quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/aeroporto-internacional-de-macau-movimentou-183-milhoes-de-passageiros-no-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>Macao International Airport released yesterday the statistical data for the first quarter of the year, accounting for 1.83 million passengers transported, ie 2.2% compared to the same period of 2024. About 14,000 aircraft movements were also registered, plus 1.6% annually. The volume of the cargo carried, for its part, fell 9.5%, “performing not as good as expected,” says the company that manages the airport in a statement.
According to the airport press release, "the geopolitical situation and world economic instability have placed challenges to the development of routes."
In terms of market segmentation, passengers from continental China air routes represent 46% of the total number of passengers and passengers from Taiwan air routes represent 18% of the total number. Passengers from Southeast Asia and Northeast Asia airlines represent 36% of the global volume of passenger flow.
The airport is accountable for the first two months, noting that the volume of international passengers reached 200,000, which represents a 13% growth compared to the previous year. Traffic in the Easter period reached 92,000 passengers, an increase of 3.5% over the same period last year, while the number of flights was 638, with a decrease of 3.4% compared to 2024. In addition, “the increase in airline operating costs further restricted its capacity, leading to visible changes in market structure and having a significant impact on passenger and load operations”, The company says, predicting that "the volume of passengers and load in 2025 is not aligned with the purpose of the year."
The airport also states that service centers will be established in Shenzhen Shekou, the port of Zhongshan and the port of Gongbei in Zhuhai in the second half of the year. “This initiative is intended to fully integrate maritime-air-living transportation resources to continually optimize route layouts and improve various facilities and services,” he reads in the statement, concluding that “Macao International Airport is constantly aligned with MSAR government policies, striving to provide more convenient travel services, attract more international visitors and support the development of the local civil aviation industry and Macao Tourist Sector ”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:09:34</pubDate></item><item><title>China launches three astronauts to replace crew of your space station</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/china-lanca-tres-astronautas-para-substituir-tripulacao-da-sua-estacao-espacial/</link><description>China yesterday sent three astronauts to replace the crew of the Chinese space station Tiangong, thus continuing the goal of sending astronauts to the moon and building a base in the coming years. Surrounded by flames and tobacco, the shenzhou 20, as planned, at the Jiuquan Launch Center in the Jiuquan Launch Center, on the Gobi Desert, in Northwest China, at 17:17 local hours to reach the space station about 6.5 hours later. The mission aims to contribute to China's ambitious goal of placing astronauts on the moon by 2030, followed by the construction of a lunar base.
The Mission Astronauts Shenzhou 20 are Chen Dong, Chen Zhongruui and Wang Jie. They will replace three astronauts who are currently at the Chinese space station. Chen Dong, who has participated in the Shenzhou 11 and Shenzhou 14 missions, is the group's leader, while his two crewmates will make the first trips to the space. Chen Zhongrui was a pilot of the Air Force and Wang Jie works as an engineer at China's Aerospace Science and Aerospace Technology Corporation. Chen Dong led the construction of the space station during the Shenzhou Mission 14. During the stay in space, astronauts will experiment with the field of medicine and space technology, will perform missions on the outside and introduce improvements to the space station.
China built the space station itself after being excluded from the International Space Station due to US national security concerns. China's space program has grown rapidly in recent years. The Chinese space agency has already landed an explorer robot on Mars and a space vehicle on the opposite side of the moon. The landing of astronauts returning from the space station is scheduled for April 29.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:09:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Sporting e Benfica fighting distance from the title against two 'afflicted'</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/sporting-e-benfica-em-luta-a-distancia-pelo-titulo-face-a-dois-aflitos/</link><description>The leader Sporting and the "deputy" Benfica, tied punctually, star in Sunday another distance battle in the race for victory in the 2024/25 edition of the I Portuguese League, facing opponents 'Afflicted' on matchday 31.
 
At a time when they are 'forbidden' to lose points, with four rounds for disputing, Rui Borges' formation moves to the worse team of the race at home, Boavista, while Benfica receives the least pointed out, AVS.
The two teams play on the same day, with the incarnates to enter the field first, back to Luz, where, between remarkable victories in the strongholds of FC Porto (4-1) and Vitória de Guimarães (3-0), lost two points, already in discounts, with Arouca (2-2).
Bruno Lage's 'eleven', without Florentino and Di María for 'strategic' punishments, will not expect, for sure, facilities, knowing that in the theoretically easier game until the end, will have to add the 11th triumph in the last 12 games.
Benfica has the inspiration of the Greek striker Vangelis Pavlidis - the author of seven goals in the last four games on the race and a total of 13 on the second lap, in contrast to the four of the first - and Trubin's security, decisive in Guimarães.
As for AVS, it follows since the 25th round in the 'pericliente' 16th position, access to the Maintenance Play-Off, counting only one point in the last six games and only nine out, in this regard, the worst record in the I Liga.
Two and a half hours after the light kick in the light, it begins, if the light does not fail, Sporting's clash, which, regardless of what Benfica does, can only think of winning, in his case for the third consecutive and seventh time in the last eight games.
In the penultimate game, before the light to the predictable 'title game', at 33rd round, Rui Borges' set goes to Bessa 'escorted' by the striker Viktor Gyökeres, author of 12 goals in the last eight rounds for a total of 34.
A great figure in I Liga's 2024/25 edition, after it was already the 'star' at the time of debut (2023/24), the Swedish has been the 'family allowance' and individually follows the fight for European 'golden boot', although its 34 goals only multiply for 1.5 points - those of the main leagues fold.
The 'Leões', in a series of 17 games without losing (11 wins and six draws), 15 with Rui Borges, face an opponent who won two of the last three clashes, both out, because at home, is the worst team of I Liga, with only six points added.
Under the command of the Scottish Stuart Baxter, the fifth technician of the time, counting the two Interinos, Boavista debuted with an important triumph in Faro (1-0), which was worth the 17th place, after 13 rounds last, just three points from AVS, 16th.
The 'axadrases' surpassed the Farense, which only won one of the last 15 games and fell, 16 rounds laid down to last place, needing to score in Barcelos, where Gil Vicente (14th, with 29 points), which has not punctuated at home for six games, will virtually maintenance with a triumph.
In the fight for the latter for the last place of the podium, Sporting de Braga, which won Cincos from the last six clashes, with one 1-1 in Alvalade in the middle, visits today the quiet Famalicão, at the opening meeting of the round.
For their part, FC Porto, a point below the 'Arsenalists', plays Saturday at the first team's home above the 'waterline', the Amadora star, at a time when he has been 'moved' to Rodrigo Mora (five goals in the last five rounds).
Below, in the battle for fifth place, which now has European 'seal' with the qualification of Benfica and Sporting for the Portuguese Cup final, Vitória de Guimarães hosts Rio Ave on Sunday, while Santa Clara, who adds less one point, is host of Arouca.
Ronda 31 also includes two games between four teams with the situation, in the middle of the almost defined table, the reception of Moreirense to Nacional, on Sunday, and Casa Pia to Estoril Praia, to close, on Monday. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:09:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing denies being in negotiations with the United States for an agreement</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/pequim-nega-estar-em-negociacoes-com-os-estados-unidos-por-um-acordo/</link><description>China has assured yesterday that “no negotiations or consultations have been started” with the United States to end the trade war, thus denying the information released in recent days by the press and official sources.
 
"These are false news," the spokesman for the Chinese Foreign Ministry, Guo Jiakun, reacted at a press conference. Guo stressed that this trade war "began by the US" and reiterated that Beijing's position "has always been consistent and clear."
"If it comes to fighting, we will fight to the end; if it is about dialogue, the door is open," added the spokesman, stressing that "any dialogue or negotiation must be based on equality, mutual respect and reciprocity."
The statements arise after US President Donald Trump has expressed optimism on Wednesday as to the possibility of reaching an agreement with China, and even advanced that tariffs on Chinese imports-currently 145%-"will be substantially reduced."
Asked about it, Guo insisted that if Washington wants to resolve the conflict, "he should abandon his maximum pressure approach, stop making threats and engage in a dialogue with China in the same terms."
The spokesman accused the US of "abusing tariffs" and "seriously undermine the rules of the World Trade Organization," to the detriment of the "common interests of peoples around the world."
The commercial conflict between the two powers, which intensified in early April, raised concerns about organisms such as WTO, which warned this week that antagonistic commercial blocks between the US and China were able to cause losses up to 7% of world GDP.
The Chinese Ministry of Commerce reported yesterday that it met with more than eighty foreign companies and representatives of commerce chambers in the country to address the effects of the tariffs imposed by US President Donald Trump.
The meeting, chaired by the Deputy Minister of Commerce, Ling Ji, served to “exchange opinions” on the impact that US tariffs may have on foreign companies' operations and investments in China, the folder said in a statement.
During the meeting, Lin urged foreign entrepreneurs to “listen to a rational voice, maintain confidence, overcome difficulties and turn crises into opportunities” in the face of US impositions that, according to him, “severely impair” the international trade system.
The Chinese official also insisted that Beijing will continue to expand his "high -level openness", to protect the "legitimate rights" of foreign companies, to "actively" resolve their operational difficulties and to ensure the "functioning of production and supply chains."
According to the statement, entrepreneurs said that the Chinese government "continues to attribute great importance to the resolution of the problems faced by foreign companies." And they expressed their desire to continue to invest in the country, since Chinese politics is "coherent, stable and predictable," the ministry said. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:09:34</pubDate></item><item><title>One and Must maintain positions in the ranking of the best universities in the world</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/um-e-must-mantem-posicoes-no-ranking-das-melhores-universidades-do-mundo/</link><description>The University of Macao (one) was able to keep 180th place in the latest Higher Education Ranking Times ranking, which this year evaluated 2,092 higher education institutions - 185 more than last year. The University of Science and Technology of Macao (Must) is also on the list, between places 251 and 300. The University of St. Joseph and the City of Macau were cited in the ranking, although they were not classified.
 
The University of Macao (one) and the Macao University of Science and Technology (Must) maintained their positions in the 2025 edition of the Times Higher Education ranking, which compares and evaluates the best universities in the world. To one emerge stable in 180th position among the more than two thousand higher education institutions considered this year, while Must is between places 251 and 300.
The results of both universities were equal to those of the 2024 ranking, where one reached its best ranking ever when reaching 180th and confirmed a growing trend that has been at all times. In 2016, for example, Times Higher Education placed one between positions 401 and 500, then rising to 193rd place in 2023. Must, in turn, continues between positions 251 and 300 since its debut in 2020, except 2023 in which it registered a slight climb to the category for positions 201 to 250.
The City of Macao University and the University of St. Joseph were mentioned again on the list, although they were not placed in any position. In reference to these two institutions, only statistical data such as the number of full -time students (7,183 and 1,391, respectively), international students (58% and 10%) or the ratio by gender, both institutions report to have more female students than male, appear (58% and 10%).
As for universities that ranked the ranking, statistics point to a presence of international students in one of the 46%, a percentage that at Must rises to a 93%overwriting. Also in these two institutions there is a greater female presence than male, composing a totality of 11,573 students in the first and 17,047 in the second.
In addition to human data, the compilation of Times Higher Education also evaluates performance indicators grouped in five domains: teaching (learning environment), research environment (volume, income and reputation); Quality of research (impact of citations and strength, excellence and influence of research); International Perspective (Personal, Students and Research); and industry (income and patents).
The highest classifications of UM and Must arise from the international perspective (96.6 and 90, respectively) and the quality of the investigation (90.7 and 79.6), approaching the maximum value of 100, while the points to be improved include the research environment (39 and 36.7) and teaching (37.7 and 33.9). The global classifications of each are, respectively, from 59.7 and from 53.7 to 55.7.
With regard to institutions in the neighboring region, five managed to position themselves in the first 100 places. The best were the University of Hong Kong, which maintained the 35th place of this ranking, and the Chinese University of Hong Kong, 44th. The interior of China is represented by 94 universities, seven of them above the top 100. The universities of Tsinghua and Beijing were the best classified on the continent and were in the 12th and 13th place, respectively, standing out as the first two Asian universities to appear on the list.
At points highlighted in this year's edition report, available for consultation on Times Higher Education's electronic page, it is read that "China is approaching the top 10, further increasing its influence on world investigation." On the contrary, Australia's five best -positioned universities have been “falling into rankings due to the decline of the reputation and world perspective” of these institutions. Also the reputation of British and American universities has been degrading, although the University of Oxford follows firmly in the first place in the ranking for a consecutive year.
Times Higher Education World University ranking evaluates intensive research universities in all their main missions: teaching, research, knowledge transfer and international reach. This year 2,092 higher education institutions from 115 countries and territories were evaluated.
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:08:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Macaenses and the Memories of the Revolution</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/macaenses-e-as-memorias-da-revolucao/</link><description>On April 25, 1974, Portugal shook the dictatorial regime that had been in force since 1933. The military coup, which became known as the Revolution of Cloves, was not only meaning by Portuguese, was also felt in Macao and in particular by the Maca community. At the end, Anabela Ritchie, Jorge Fão, José Luís Sales Marques and António José de Freitas recall how the regularity of the revolution was lived.
 
It was on April 25, 1974 - today precisely 51 years ago - that a group of young captains carried out a coup d'état that, in less than 24 hours, toppled the dictatorship that dominated Portugal for over four decades. The Revolution of Cloves stirred Portugal and the Portuguese, but not only: the Macaenses also lived the change of regime with joy and anxiety, as they now count on the end.
Jorge Fão witnessed the censorship exercised by the Estado Novo in Macau. At the Macao Council, the authorities received the jails of the newspapers in Portuguese, analyzed and cut what the regime did not want the population to know. Newspapers were not published without the endorsement of the Macao Council administrator, accounts, noting that the administrator would not have much to worry, since "journalists and directors were already self -prized."
"When we learned from April 25, we didn't even believe it," recalls the current chairman of the General Assembly of the Macao Retired, Reformed and Pensioners Association (Apomac). The news was received in Macau a few days later, through the Hong Kong press. "We all got very pleased, we were waiting for some democracy in Portugal to be, since there was only one party only in Portugal, the National Union," he recalls.
The Carnation Revolution brought press freedom to Portugal and Macau. From then on, the Portuguese newspapers in Macao also became more independent and free: "That joke is over, the newspapers published all and something."
Jorge Fão points out that, in Macao, the interest on April 25 was circumscribed to the Portuguese and Maca community, and “the overwhelming majority, naturally, accepted the revolution well”.
Anabela Ritchie was at the time in Portugal, she was a teacher at Cascais National High School in São João do Estoril. On the morning of April 25, 1974, he was still home when he began to hear people singing on the street. They sang the national anthem and songs of Zeca Afonso, recalls the former deputy and president of the Legislative Assembly of Macao.
Realizing that the dictatorship had fallen, the joy was contagious. "It was such a great explosion of joy, so big, so big," he comments, pointing out that "April 25 was intensely lived." For the next moment, all conversations revolved around it: “Many people I gave myself at school were extremely clarified and everyone wanted to argue, I wanted to discuss the future of Portugal, how in Portugal things could change for the better,” says Anabela Ritchie, stressing that “it was many years living in a closed regime” and “it wasn't what people wanted for the future”.
Quoting Sophia de Mello Breyner Andresen, it was the “initial and clean initial” day. “It was in fact one day that everyone kept as very special,” he says.
Anabela Ritchie's family was in Macao curious about what was going on in Portugal. "There were those who had been pleased and there were those who had been very apprehensive," but "it was a hard time to escape the wave of enthusiasm," recalls the former policy and teacher Macanese.
José Luís Sales Marques was also in Portugal, in the city of Porto, where he was a university student. “And the students joined with great joy on April 25,” he comments. The economist recalls that that day he was at his college residence when he heard the news that he had expected since at least March 16, when a military column from the Queen's Caldas Infantry Regiment advanced to Lisbon from the prospect of overthrowing Marcello Caetano's government, eventually failing.
"I was aware that the political situation in Portugal was not stable, although the information was not very easy to get. Maybe it wasn't expected that it would be so quickly. I knew things were in a certain course, but I didn't think it was so fast," he comments.
The economist remembers being at the residence and listening to the first password for the revolution, the song “And after Goodbye”, played by Paulo de Carvalho. He also heard the statement of the Armed Forces movement, which had just overthrown the dictatorial regime. Later, despite the appeals for the population to stay at home, Sales Marques accompanied the crowd and also went to the street. “We were all super excited,” he says.
António José de Freitas was in Macao in 1974, where he was an interpreter translator for the government. However, friends were studying in Portugal, many of them participated in the student movements of April, demanding freedom and democracy. The initial reaction was of uncertainty and concern: "It was a bit worried because at that time I had family members in Portugal and saw the images of the military on the streets." However, it turned out to be "all very peaceful, all positive scenes." In Macao, he recalls, "people generally were satisfied with what was going on," as "Freedom Day" was celebrated.
 
Dinner and exhibition celebrate April 25 in Macau
 
Macau will mark the 51 years of the Cloves Revolution with the usual dinner at the Military Club, which has the support of Casa de Portugal. The conviviality begins today at 18:30. Casa de Portugal also organizes an exhibition of photographs by Álvaro and José Tavares. The Portuguese School of Macao (EPM) will also celebrate the date this time with a digital visual arts exhibition that will be available from today in the inner atrium of the school until May 2nd. In yesterday's edition of “Quiz Nights” at Bookand, the theme of the questions was subordinate to April 25.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:08:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Sands China profit falls almost a third until March</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/lucro-da-sands-china-cai-quase-um-terco-ate-marco/</link><description>Sands China announced $ 202 million profits in the first quarter, a 32% drop over the same period of 2024. The company, it is recalled, ended 2024 with profits of $ 1.05 billion, an increase of 50.9%.
 
Casinos Sands Operator China yesterday announced $ 202 million profits in the first quarter, a 32% drop over the same period of 2024.
Sands China had ended 2024 with profits of $ 1.05 billion, an increase of 50.9%. The company was on positive land for the second year in a row, after three years of unprecedented losses due to Covid-19 pandemic.
Also the revenues of the five Sands casinos in Macau retreated, with a 5.6% drop in the first three months of 2025 to $ 1.71 billion. With the revenues falling, Sands China registered operational profits of $ 535 million in the first quarter of 2025, a decrease of 12.3% annually.
In a statement, Robert Goldstein, Sands China's mother's president, the American Las Vegas Sands (LVS), admitted that "in Macao, ... Market growth has slowed."
According to official data, the game industry in Macau registered total revenues of nearly 57.7 billion patacas between January and March, 0.6% more than in the same period as 2024. Still, Goldstein recalled that Sands China made a commitment of a decade of making investments that increase the Appeal of Macao Business and Leisure and support its development as a tourism center. ”
The company is one of six casino dealers who operate in the territory and whose concession contract, valid for ten years, came into force on January 1, 2023. At the time, the six operators pledged to invest “over 100 billion patacas” in unnataged elements. Sands announced “an iconic winter garden” with 50 thousand square meters. "We are still enthusiastic about our opportunities to achieve leading industry growth in both Macao and Singapore in the coming years," Goldstein noted.
Sands China made total investments of $ 379 million in the first three months of 2025, including $ 197 million in Macao. Most of the money served to reshape the integrated venture Hotel-Casino Londoner Macao, a partnership with former British footballer David Beckham.
Sands China President Grant Chum Kwan Lock said in a teleconference with investors, after the presentation of the results, that the remodeling was ready in mid -April. That is, in time of the so -called 'gold week' of May 1, a period of holidays in mainland China and a high time for tourism in Macao. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:10:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Ipim expects to increase companies quoted in Macau that create new jobs</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/ipim-espera-aumentar-empresas-cotadas-em-macau-que-criam-novos-postos-de-trabalho/</link><description>The Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM) is confident of a 20% increase in companies listed on a Macao -based stock market that can bring more than 1,000 jobs to the local market. Economics and technological development services have stated that community economy incentive events are having satisfactory results, increasing consumption in non -tourist areas.
 
The government intends to attract more listed foreign companies and quality companies to establish headquarters in Macao. The Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment (IPIM) has led to the work of promoting investment and said the number of these companies will increase 20% in the territory later this year.
Vincent U, chairman of the IPIM Administrative Board, said that it will provide “all support” to the implementation of large investment projects in Macau through the Investment Commission's interdepartal mechanism, with a sense that companies can provide more than 1,000 new jobs to Macao.
The official was yesterday at the Macao Forum, the morning program of the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, and, in relation to the development of conventions and exhibitions, said the body is working to increase the number of exhibitors and international visitors by 15% in 2025.
In addition, through IPIM, 490 people obtained professional certification in conventions and exhibitions, and seven training programs were launched this year, with over 330 registrations.
It is recalled that last year, IPIM's' One Stop Service 'Service' received a total of 362 new investment projects, and during the same period it completed the follow-up of 278 projects, which involved an investment amount of 3.45 billion.
Vincent U had also advanced on Wednesday at the Legislative Assembly that the authorities will accompany an investment project in Macao of a "large group" quoted in the scholarship of mainland China and Hong Kong, involving more than 100 workers.
In the radio program, the director of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), Yau Yun Wah, revealed that it plans to launch, in the second half of the year, discount plans for consumption to tourists watching concerts in Macao, in order to boost the community economy, as the number of sports concerts and events have been increasing in Macao in recent years.
"We are establishing contacts with the interior of China ticket sales platforms to discuss the way to encourage the travel of tourists from the continent. A consumer discount in Macao's community neighborhoods can be granted while buying concert tickets," explained Yau Yun Wah, hoping to generate an economic effect with non -tourist concerts.
DSEDT also stated that it had organized incentive activities for consumption and events in residential neighborhoods, namely the recent community activity “Flora Fête With Sanrio Characters” held in the North Zone.
Yau Yun Wah described that the event results were "satisfactory." The same responsible said that he had an inquiry, where 82% of respondents indicated that they had remained more time in the northern zone, and 75% said they spent more money on consumption in the north. "This demonstrates that it is feasible to use intellectual property economy to promote community development and that in the future we will do similar work in different neighborhood revitalization projects," he said.
After the debate on the governance lines of the economy portfolio in the Legislative Assembly, several managers of the sector spoke yesterday on the radio. The president of the Fund for the Development of Science and Technology, Che Weng Keong, has ensured that it will increase the financing of existing research platforms, especially national platforms in Macao, and improve the various types of scientific research instruments and equipment.
Che Weng Keong said that 90% of fund's expenses are used to support scientific research and human resources formation in universities, and that the amount of funding approved by the fund for technological companies increased more than 70% in annual terms last year.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:11:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Xi Jinping promises friendship with Africa regardless of international changes</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/xi-jinping-promete-amizade-a-africa-independentemente-das-mudancas-internacionais/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping told his Kenyan counterpart yesterday, William Ruto, that "regardless of international changes, China's sincerity, friendship and good faith policy in relation to Africa will not change."
 
At a time of global uncertainty due to the trade war triggered by US President Donald Trump, Xi told Ruto that “the original intention of China and Africa to share their wealth” will not change, according to a statement widespread by the Chinese state press. The Kenyan President is making an official visit to China.
Beijing "is willing to work with other countries to defend the rules of international trade and protect international equity and justice," said Xi Jinping, warning that "no one wins in a trade war."
"China doesn't cause problems, but it's not afraid of them either," said the Chinese leader, adding that "China's huge market is always open to the high quality products of Kenya." Xi encouraged more Kenyan companies to invest and do business in the Asian country.
The Kenyian President stated that “the trade war undermines existing international rules and order” and ensured that his country “values ​​the role of China as a stabilizer in the current turbulent situation and as a protector of the rights and legitimate interests of 'global south' countries,” a term that refers to developing nations.
Ruto also stated that China and Kenya “have a common view of cooperation, adhere to a people -centered approach and are strategic partners at all times,” according to Xinhua.
After the meeting, the two leaders presided over the signing of 20 cooperation documents in domains such as high technology, cultural exchanges, the economy and the press.
The Kenyan President is the first African leader to visit China since Trump has imposed “reciprocal tariffs” about the rest of the world, shaking the panorama of international trade.
Ruto, whose country has so far been an ally near the US in Africa has so far been to get economic support from Beijing during his visit to China. "The fact that Beijing receives ruth in a period of climbing geopolitical and commercial tensions with the United States is a victory for China in terms of imaging," said Adhere Cavince, a Nairobi -based international relations researcher, quoted by Hong Kong's South China Morning Post.
As the US “imposes fares and removes help” on their partners, “Ruto is looking for new markets, project financing and investors,” said Cavince, adding that “while China seeks to escape the growing commercial animosity with Washington, Nairobi is not only an option, but also a solid entry to the rest of Africa”, a continent where China has established its presence in the last two presence in the last two presence in the last two presence decades.
 
China will not stop climate action
 
The Chinese president assured yesterday that China "will not stop its climate action, regardless of the changes that occur in the world", during a summit made by video conferencing and summoned by Brazil and the United Nations.
In a speech given in the informal summit of leaders on climate and fair transition, convened by Brazilian President Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva, and UN Secretary-General António Guterres, Xi said Beijing “will not reduce his support for international cooperation”. "It will not give in to your efforts to build a community with a shared destination for humanity," he added, according to official news agency Xinhua.
In 2020, XI announced that China would reach the peak of carbon emissions by 2030 and that it would reach carbonic neutrality by 2060, given the growing global concern with climate change. In addition, 2030 is the date when Beijing wants non -fossil fuels to provide 25% of the energy produced in the country, and coal is currently responsible for 60% of it.
Wind and solar energy are the main engines of China's efforts to achieve carbon emissions reduction goals, while the country plans to expand nuclear energy capacity in the coming years.
In recent years, the Chinese leader has advocated the principle of “common but differentiated responsibilities”, calling for rich countries to take greater responsibility for attenuation of climate change. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:09:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Jinjin Xu returns to Macao with an investigation on displacement and language in Butter Room Space</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/jinjin-xu-retorna-a-macau-com-uma-investigacao-sobre-deslocamento-e-linguagem-no-butter-room-space/</link><description>"What could you say about your endangered language?" It is one of the reflections of the exhibition and performance series “What Would You Say IF You Could?”, By artist Jinjin Xu, which will take place at Butter Room, between April 30 and May 18. In this work, the artist explores the stories of women who often look out of voice and without space, bringing out the forgotten language of those who feel displaced. Through poetry, sound installations and live performances, Jinjin creates an engaging environment where we can hear and reflect on these singular experiences, in a rock on the emotions and rediscovered identities through the sensitivity of a poet.
 
Wash number 2 of the Calçada do Gaio will host, starting next week, the individual exhibition of Jinjin Xu, entitled "What Would You Say If You Could?". The show, which will be open to the public until May 18, will be installed at the Butter Room Cultural Space and proposes a reflection on the experience of displacement and the often silenced narratives of minorities in dilution. With a mixture of poetry, sound installations and performative arts, Jinjin seeks to explore the various dimensions of female voices in travel contexts.
Jinjin Xu is an interdisciplinary artist and poet to work between Macau, Shanghai and New York. Its artistic practice is characterized by a critical approach to the themes of memory, absence and representation. The work presented at the exhibition results from extensive research that brings together voices of women from nine countries, each to share their experiences of travel. In this way, the show is an invitation to viewers to consider realities often ignored, transforming the expository space into a place of listening and reflection on the condition of women in displacement situations.
The curatorship of the exhibition is in charge of Kathine Cheong Weng Lam and Tam Chi Chun, who intend to create an environment in which the sense of hearing is central to the experience of those visiting the gallery. Through the integration of different forms of expression and technologies, such as vibration and sound capture sensors, the exhibition questions the established rules of artistic narrative, promoting an interaction between visitors and works that favor empathy and dialogue, pertinent to the artist's continued research work. In doing so, Xu seeks not only to present his material art, but also to foster a broader discussion about the challenges faced by women in various parts of the world and small communities.
The event program will include a series of performances throughout the exhibition, starting with the opening performance, which will take place on April 30 at 6:45 pm, next Wednesday, the day before the holiday. Another significant element will be the collective recital scheduled for May 4, entitled "Chorus". In this event, the public will be invited to recite texts that emerge from the experiences shared by women in situations of travel collected by the artist. This joint reading format is not only an activity of involvement, but it also aims to democratize the voices represented, underlining the importance of each report in the collective context, as the curators describe.
 
Influence of Nüshu on Jinjin Xu's work
 
One relevant aspect of the exhibition is Jinjin Xu's new installation work, which is part of the context of years of research on Nüshu, an almost extinct language that was historically used by women in Hunan province, China. The Nüshu represented a form of secret communication among women who, in the face of the exclusion of access to formal education, found in the lyrics a means of exchange and expression. This "script", as the artist, past generation to generation, reveals an aspect of feminine resistance and the search for recognition.
“I wrote and recorded with displaced women around the world from refugees to migrant workers since 2017, and at first I was writing poems with them. I was doing a documentary, but then I questioned the House lens and how to the limits of empathy are permeated through listening, so I decided to make sound facilities with their voices directly,” Jinjin describes in conversation with the final point.
Jinjin Xu had the opportunity to interact with “grandmother he”, the last living heiress of Nüshu in Jiangyong. This meeting allowed the artist to capture the depth of emotions and memories associated with this language, incorporating these experiences into his work. The resulting installation combines resin and ashes collected from bonfires in the community, creating a tactile and auditory experience through transparencies obtained by materials such as ice and paper. A work that articulates the stories of women on displacement in various contexts. "I started to transcribe their stories to a kind of" women's script, "made of ashes (which are what they would write, without access to pen and ink), and created these facilities, each representing a different woman," added the artist to the description of her work.
Jinjin Xu's exhibition proposes a space for analysis, criticism and dialogue, as well as the beauty of the materials and the surrounding space. A piece that lives in contemporary times and where visitors are invited to consider as collective memories and individual experiences intertwine, highlighting sociocultural issues that permeate the lives of women and cultures in different parts of the world. With this approach, the artist seeks to involve the public in a reflection on the importance of listening and the recognition of frequently absent voices in the most dominant discourses. "Enter, close your eyes and hear." The exhibition “What Would You Say If You Could?” It is a platform for the discussion about displacement and identity, inviting the public to participate in a reflective process that seeks to highlight the realities of marginalized women.
Organized by Macau Experimental Theater (MEXP) in collaboration with the Bok Festival and the support of the Culture Development Fund, the event aims to promote a space for empathy and approach to other cultures of Greater China.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Cases of communicable diseases decrease in March</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/casos-de-doencas-transmissiveis-diminuem-em-marco/</link><description>According to data released yesterday by health services, in March there was a 60% reduction in cases of transmitted diseases of mandatory declaration compared to the previous month of February. Of the 608 cases accounted for, most were related to influenza, norovirus and scarletin infection.
 
Health services accounted for a total of 608 cases of mandatory declaration diseases in March, 60% less than the 1,539 registered in February. Among the 45 types of diseases with these characteristics, the three with the largest number of cases were influenza, norovirus and scarletin infection.
Influenza, or flu, was responsible for 320 cases in March, which represents a decrease of 77.9% compared to the 1,446 cases of the previous year's same year period and a substantial reduction of 74.4% compared to 1,252 verified in February. Reduction of values ​​can be justified with the characteristics of the influenza virus, more active during the winter and early spring months.
Although most symptoms are light and disappear without treatment, health authorities recall that flu is a highly contagious disease that can give rise to complications such as bronchitis or pneumonia. Seasonal vaccination remains the most effective method of prevention, especially for vulnerable groups such as elderly, chronic children or patients.
Norovirus infection arises in second place, with 74 cases diagnosed in March alone. Unlike the other diseases highlighted by health services, this was the only one in which cases were increased compared to the same month of 2024 (plus 1.4%) and the previous month of February (plus 19.4%).
This disease, which affects the gastrointestinal tract, is transmitted mainly by consumption of contaminated food or water or contact with secretions of patients. Regarding the first point, health services recommend reinforcement of food hygiene through, for example, the separation between raw and cooked foods and the total cooking of food, and should be stored at a proper temperature after making.
In turn, scarletin registered 54 cases in March - a decrease of 77.4% compared to the same month of 2024 and 10% compared to February. This respiratory infection, caused by group A hemolytic bacteria, is transmitted through contact with oral and respiratory secretions of infected patients.
Although the peak of the disease usually occurs in spring and winter, health services warn the population to remain attentive to symptoms such as fever, “tongue with a strawberry appearance” and rash in the body at any time of the year. As there is no scarletal vaccine yet, treatment goes through antibiotic administration.
Under current legislation, Macao health professionals and medical institutions are responsible for notifying cases of transmissible diseases within the legal deadline, thus contributing to more efficient and informed public health management, according to a statement of health services.
The implementation of individual protection measures is essential for the prevention of diseases covered by this definition. In addition to food hygiene measures already mentioned, sanitary authorities also advise the adoption of habits such as a balanced diet, regular sport, maintaining good hygiene, air ventilation inside the facilities and the use of mask if any symptoms appear.
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:08:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Dismantled network that used personal data from others in the record of mobile phone cards</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/desmantelada-rede-que-usava-dados-pessoais-de-outrem-no-registo-de-cartoes-de-telemovel/</link><description>Police authorities from Macau and Zhuhai dismantled, together, a network that allegedly operated fraudulent schemes made through telephone calls, namely the “guess who I am”, since October last year. 18 suspects were arrested, including the network leaders, of which 13 people were caught in Macao and five in the interior of China. According to the Judicial Police (PJ), the case caused losses of 1.11 million patacas to 26 residents.
Police investigation found that three network leaders explored a telephone store in the North Zone, having stolen personal data from others, taking photographs from their customers identification documents or buying personal information on the Internet to register telephone cards as an instrument for fraudulent purposes.
According to the Macau channel in Chinese language, the PJ indicated that the suspects were passed by family or friends of the targets on the pretext of committing driving crimes under the influence of alcohol or aggression on the continent to ask for money.
The network will have used more than 800 local prepaid telephone cards to commit the scam, of which 116 cards were registered with the identities of 28 residents of Macao and non-resident workers. The telephone cards were later delivered to the inland members of China to make the calls.
In addition, the PJ said the network has a “clear division of labor”, having established card registration, telephone, information and laundering of capital laundering groups. In this case, the group will have opened more than 150 accounts on Macao payment platforms to transfer money to the interior of China or to buy gold jewelry. To date, according to police, the amount of money laundering exceeded 400,000 patacas.
The PJ added that it first discovered that the criminal network collected the money from the mockery services on online requests online from the continent, requiring victims to put the money in a cookie box and take him to Zhuhai and deliver him to a driver.
In the police operation in Macao, more than 64,000 patacas in cash, 140 telephone cards, 24 mobile phones and three computers were seized. The 13 detainees in Macao, including residents and non-resident workers from the continent and a maid from Vietname, aged 33 to 61, were referred yesterday to the prosecutor.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:08:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Easter in Ukrainian life</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/a-pascoa-na-vida-ucraniana/</link><description>On Sunday, much of the world celebrated Easter, the most sacred day of the Christian calendar. For the first time since 2017, the East Orthodox Church celebrated the holiday the same day as Western Christians (Roman Catholics and Protestants). To mark the ephemeris, President Vladimir Putin announced a thirty-hour ceasefire, starting on Saturday night and term on Sunday night. Skeptical Ukrainian employees, including President Volodymyr Zelensky, agreed reluctantly. On Friday, the Trump administration indicated that if it could not make progress to end the war, it would abandon the ongoing talks. What it meant was not clear. Would the United States fail to lead peace negotiations but continue to provide vital military weapons and information to Ukraine?  Or would Washington completely wash his war hands and completely abandon Ukraine? On Easter Monday, Pope Francis suddenly passed away after a slow but positive recovery of two months of double pneumonia. What do these events mean to each other?
The Cessar-Fogo Crach, which began at 6 pm on Saturday, meant a calmer night than usual over the long front that crosses the eastern spine of Ukraine and in the two Russian border provinces where Ukraine still occupies some territory-Kursk and Belgorod. But both Ukraine and Russia said on Sunday that the attacks continued. Each of them accused the other of violating the ceasefire, which officially ended on Sunday at midnight. Zelensky stated that the Russian troops fired their artillery almost 2300 times between 6 pm on Saturday and midnight on Sunday. Ukraine also said Russia has launched 115 attacks of infantry and drones more than 1200 times. Russia vehemently denied having violated the respite. In turn, Russia accused Ukraine of violating the truce with more than 900 drone attacks and hundreds of artillery and mortar attacks. None of these allegations can be verified independently. Although not violent, the fighting continued throughout the front. Although they have not been specified by either part, the casualties over the past few months have been very heavy, as each part has fought bitterly by meters of land.
Russia claimed that the ceasefire was decreed as a humanitarian gesture on the occasion of Easter, to allow Ukrainians and Russians to make their cults in peace. Ukraine claimed that Putin declared the ceasefire to show the US president that Russia wanted peace so that bilateral conversations about the Saudi Arabia ceasefire organized by Americans could continue. Trump made the end of the war in Ukraine one of his objectives on foreign policy. In fact, he declared several times that he would end the war in 24 hours. On Sunday, he said that Ukraine and Russia would "make a deal this week."
However, the American “peace agreement” almost entirely favors Russia. Information escapes from the conversations include a “pause” along the 1000 km front line, the American recognition that Crimea officially belongs to Russia and an American veto to NATO's adhesion to the adhesion. The "pause" would give Russia the fact control of almost 20% of the territory of Ukraine, with its rich resources, large population, agricultural lands and industries. Even more importantly, the Russian possession of East Ukraine would remain for an indefinite period. On the other hand, Russia would be willing to renounce its claim of parts of Ukraine that does not currently occupy. This would be Russia's only concession. In turn, Russia and the US agree with the survey of sanctions and the normalization of relationships, which would allow business between the US and Russia in the field of energy and minerals.
The American recognition of Russia's Crime Control would violate the United Nations Letter, as well as several international treaties that prohibit the taking of another nation by the military force. It would also mark America's complicity in this violation of the territorial integrity of a sovereign state. A US veto for the adhesion of Ukraine would mean that Ukraine would face the future without serious security guarantees that would allow another Russian invasion within five to ten years, when its military forces were rebuilt. The only guarantee of future security for Ukraine would be provided by a “coalition of will” between the United Kingdom and France, composed of 30 countries, which would provide an indefinite “reassuring force” but would not include any terrestrial and American air support.
The Russians have insisted in stronger terms against Ukraine - control of all four provinces in eastern Ukraine (Luhansk, Donetsk, Zaporizehzia and Kherson), permanent Ukraine neutralization so that he cannot join the EU or born and new elections in Ukraine to replace Zelensky with a more flexible Ukrainian politician. Guardian reporter Luke Harding has stated that Russia is deliberately drawing peace talks, betting that continuous gain gains would reinforce their position, allowing him to demand even greater concessions from the besieged Ukrainians.
Currently, the most active part of the front line is near the city of Pokrovsk, a Ukrainian industrial and administrative transport center near Donetsk, which Russia has been trying to capture in the last six months, with a great cost in human lives on both sides. On Ramos Sunday, Russia launched an attack with ballistic missiles against the city of Sumy, in the northeast of the country, killing 35 people and injuring 129. Or would Washington completely wash his war hands and abandon Ukraine completely? On Easter Monday, Pope Francis suddenly passed away after a slow but positive recovery of two months of double pneumonia. What do these events mean to each other? The Cessar-Fogo Crach, which began at 6 pm on Saturday, meant a calmer night than usual over the long front that crosses the eastern spine of Ukraine and in the two Russian border provinces where Ukraine still occupies some territory-Kursk and Belgorod. But both Ukraine and Russia said on Sunday that the attacks continued.
Each of them accused the other of violating the ceasefire, which officially ended on Sunday at midnight. Zelensky stated that the Russian troops fired their artillery almost 2300 times between 6 pm on Saturday and midnight on Sunday. Ukraine also said Russia has launched 115 attacks of infantry and drones more than 1200 times. Russia vehemently denied having violated the respite. In turn, Russia accused Ukraine of violating the truce with more than 900 drone attacks and hundreds of artillery and mortar attacks. None of these allegations can be verified independently. Although not violent, the fighting continued throughout the front. Although they have not been specified by either part, the casualties over the past few months have been very heavy, as each part has fought bitterly by meters of land. Russia claimed that the ceasefire was decreed as a humanitarian gesture on the occasion of Easter, to allow Ukrainians and Russians to make their cults in peace. Ukraine claimed that Putin declared the ceasefire to show the US president that Russia wanted peace so that bilateral conversations about the Saudi Arabia ceasefire organized by Americans could continue. Trump made the end of the war in Ukraine one of his objectives on foreign policy.  In fact, he declared several times that he would end the war in 24 hours.
To solidify its support to Ukraine and allow more military and economic aid, the European Union may remove the right to vote under the European Union Treaty, which would be a “nuclear option” as this effective suspension of Hungary adhesion has never been decreed by any member country. Prime Minister Viktor Orban, an ally of Putin, has repeatedly sought to block the EU sanctions, as well as prevent the release of about 6 billion euros to reimburse nations for his military aid to Ukraine.
At this critical moment of world affairs, with two great wars to plague Ukraine and Gaza, a global trade war -instigated by the United States, a growing fear of global economic recession or even depression, the American transition to authoritarianism under Donald Trump's direction; On Easter Monday Pope Francis passed away.  People were happy when the 88 -year -old Pope emerged from a two -month stay in a Rome hospital, almost dying twice from double pneumonia. After his release, Francis seemed determined to resume his pastoral duties. On Easter Sunday, Francisco appeared before a huge crowd in St. Peter's Square, blessed her and even turned to the square in her “Paparmobile”. Therefore, we were all shocked when we received the news of their death. Francis devoted himself to the poor and marginalized, mixing with ordinary people much more than many other popes. I believe it was the most progressive Pope I have memory, opening the church to women, LGBTQ people, homeless and migrants. Francisco widened the College of Cardinals, making him a truly global organ. The world loses a very compassionate and dedicated spokesman, at a time when few leaders seem to demonstrate these characteristics. Francisco spoke with passion, appealing to the immediate end of the wars in Gaza and Ukraine. In this moment of death and destruction, a strong voice in favor of peace is now silenced by so many world leaders who only care about their own power and wealth. Pope Francis will be sorely missed, especially in today's world.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:08:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai's first political discourse and Macau's reform policy</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/25/o-primeiro-discurso-politico-de-sam-hou-fai-e-a-politica-de-reforma-em-macau/</link><description>Although the inaugural political discourse of the Macao Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, has fully demonstrated his political will and his comprehensive plan to deal with Macau's livelihood and economic diversification problems, ultimately as Macao's bureaucracy can and will implement all his political initiatives remains a political issue that remains observed.
Titled “Reform for development, diligent progress in opening a new chapter,” Sam Hou Fai's first political discourse has ten characteristics that define him.
Firstly, the organizational structure of your political discourse is parallel to that of its election campaign platform, in which both documents emphasized the protection of China's sovereignty, national security and development interests, stressed the primacy of addressing economic diversification and subsistence issues of Macao and mentioned the need for public sector reform and legal reforms. The section on national security on Sam's election campaign platform and its latest political discourse tend to be placed in the final part of the two documents, illustrating their pragmatic assessment that Macao's national security issues, although important, are not the main priority in the special administrative region of Macao, contrary to Hong Kong's case.
Secondly, Sam's political discourse stressed the importance of making Macau “internally linked to the continent and externally interactive” with other countries around the world - a theme mentioned by the Chinese government report during the March session of the National Congress of the People. In this respect, SAM's approach is to join the central government's political line - an approach that can be seen simultaneously in the recent observations of Hong Kong's chief executive John Lee.
Thirdly, Sam's approach to dealing with Macau's political discourse followed the structural perspective of the central government in Beijing, namely, outlining the external and macro level challenges to Macau in his political discourse and following the content of his political initiatives. Specifically, geopolitical changes, US impulse to protectionism, Chinese emphasis on multilateralism, and China's search for a continuous process of opening and deepening reforms constitute the context of Sam's political discourse. This approach reflects John Lee's political discourse in Hong Kong in 2024 - a phenomenon that shows that the two chiefs of the Macao and Hong Kong executive have been quickly learned and have adapted to the structural perspectives of the central government by writing their political speeches.
In fourth place, which distinguishes Sam Hou Fai's first political discourse from all the other political discourses given by his predecessors in Macau, from Edmund Ho to Fernando Chui and Ho Iat Seng, is that he addresses the lack of strong leadership and vigorous coordination in Macao bureaucracy. Unlike all its predecessors, Sam Ho Fai has openly criticized the bureaucratism and bureaucracy of Macao, pointing out the lack of intergovernmental coordination. For this purpose, it created six governing and coordination committees: (1) the public administration reform leading group, chaired by the Chief Executive; (2) the leading group of promoting the construction of the in -depth cooperation zone, chaired by himself; (3) the Public Administration Reform Coordination Group, chaired by the Secretary for Administration and Legal Affairs; (4) The Coordination Working Group of Legal Reform, chaired by the Secretary for Administration and Legal Affairs: (5) The Working Group on Imaging, Beautification and Urban Hygiene, chaired by the Secretary of Administration and Legal Affairs; and (6) the Coordination Working Group on the improvement of road work, chaired by the Secretary of Transport and Public Works.
The creation of these commissions is an unprecedented initiative of the Chief Executive of Macao to solve the problems of the lack of leadership and the persistence of a weak coordination between government departments. Leadership groups on the in -depth cooperation zone and public administration reform, which will be chaired by SAM itself, illustrate their willingness to formulate and implement not only a faster pace of economic diversification, but also reforms of public administration.
However, the success of these reforms depends on two critical questions: (1) If the bureaucracy of the average and lower strata will actually implement SAM reform plans and (2) what type of key performance indicators will be used to ensure “perfect” or smooth implementation. Often Macao bureaucracy is harmed by bureaucracy and lack of strong leadership at the middle and lower levels. For example, since December 199, the Macao government has often consulted public opinion at public opinion and other platforms, but it is not yet clear as categorizes, analyzes and uses these opinions. Some citizens have already required the government to consider using artificial intelligence to collect public opinion and respond to public opinions on a coherent platform, in line with 12345 public administrative affairs on the continent (Macau Daily News, April 19, 2025).
Sam Ho Fai's political will to reform Macau's bureaucracy is undoubtedly strong, but the challenge that puts themselves to their reform plans is whether the government's mid -level employees can and will lead their reform initiatives more effectively and efficiently.
Fifth, SAM's political discourse is characterized by considerable government expenses - details that may be revealed later in the financial budget. However, their economic and subsistence measures, which consist of granting more subsidies to small and medium enterprises, granting more disability subsidies and unemployment subsidies, supporting the elderly and children with more funds, providing more public health services, subsidizing some young people to work in the area of ​​the large bay and give them more career advice, and stimulate the rate of birth and more marriages through more Subsidies will imply, in the long run, considerable public expenses. It remains to be known to what extent all these measures will impact on public finances.
However, taking into account the context of the tariff war between the US and China and the gradual slowdown of the mainstream China economy and its concomitant effects on the number of mainland China tourists who will play and spend on Macao, the recipes from the Macau game industry will likely be fluctuated with caution.
Thus, Sam Hou Fai's first political discourse, a newly elected Chief Executive, is naturally marked by an increase in public expenses with social assistance, public health and social housing, but it remains to be known to what extent all these expense measures will have an impact on public finances. If the government will encourage more investments not only from the public sector but also from the private sector in the development of the in -depth cooperation zone, as Sam mentioned in his political discourse, the situation of public finances will eventually become less tight.
In short, the impact of Sam's political discourse on public finances remains unclear and lacks further observation.
In sixth place, unlike his predecessor Ho Iat Seng who, together with his subordinates, did not seem to know how to implement economic diversification, Sam Hou Fai demonstrated a deep sense of how to do it. He openly referred to the lack of human flows to the in -depth cooperation zone, the lack of use of the hengqin commercial space, the inadequacy of public services to the population of Macao resident in the area, the need for more strategic investments and the development of the center of securities and obligations in the area. Therefore, the leadership and coordination groups that created to boost reforms in the Macau-Hengqin in-depth cooperation zone are opportune and politically significant, filling the necessary gap in the integration process. Still, it remains to be seen how the investments of the public sector and the private sector will be mobilized and how the titles and obligations centers will be accelerated through the promulgation of the Securities Law, the Investment Fund Law and the legal and regulatory measures adopted by the zone. However, the contours and plans of economic diversification of Macao, through their integration with the Hengqin zone, are first presented in Sam's political discourse - a progressive step that naturally raised the immediate compliment and open appreciation of the mainstream China employees responsible for Macao issues on the day Sam gave his speech.
In seventh place, there are gaps to fill by the Macao government in the execution of Sam Hou Fai's global plan. These include the way the global talent scheme is and will be implemented (understandably more talents on the continent than “global” talents, although Sam mentioned the need to import global talents from Portuguese -speaking countries), the speed with which international university campuses will be developed in the in -depth cooperation zone, and the way the continent industries will be attracted to cooperate with cooperation. Macao universities in mutual research and joint cooperation for technological advances. The idea of ​​the University-Industry Partnership is a good idea raised by Sam, but for this it is necessary that the authorities and leaders of all Macao universities feel and discuss with the Government and the private sector companies not only from Macau but also from the continent, namely those of the Great Bay, how the scientific research will be conducted, as Chinese medicine will be “westernized” and advanced by investigation Innovative, and how new patents will be developed in the southern region of China. In addition, Sam Hou Fai has encouraged Macao Casinos dealers to invest in the in -depth cooperation zone, but details will have to be outlined to mobilize private sector companies to be effective in search of Macao's economic diversification.
In eighth place, given that most of Macau's recipes are still from the game industry, casinos capitalism will remain the pillar of the local economy. As such, it is wise that Sam Hou Fai's political discourse continues to underline the importance of maintaining the culture of Macao, its historical heritage, its unique food products and its vital role in Chinese initiatives “a track, a route”. Tourists from mainland China and other parts of the world will continue to be attracted by the Macao Casinos Center, although the official Chinese perspective is to dilute their characteristics, moving from casino capitalism to a more diverse economic development scenario.
In ninth place, an area that Sam's political discourse has not discussed in detail is the urgency of urban rehabilitation and the renewal of many old but historical neighborhoods - an issue that was accompanied by at least one member of the Legislative Council a day after his political speech. Urban renewal requires many funds and public investments. To maintain the historical uniqueness and architectural beauty of Macao, the authorities responsible for urban renewal will have to reflect more on the details of fundraising, oriented renewal processes, and the phased development, so that Macau remains attractive to tourists from the continent and other parts of the world.
In tenth place, Sam Hou Fai, former judge of law, in his first political discourse, emphasized legal reforms, including the need to update the administrative code and the Code of Civil Procedure, as well as the importance of synchronizing the rules and regulations of the deepened cooperation zone with those of Macao, in order to accelerate the process of human interaction and socioeconomic integration. From the perspective of integration, legal reforms are imperative and go through the mix of the rules and regulations of mainland China with those of Macao - a process of legal harmonization that takes time.
In conclusion, Sam Hou Fai's political discourse is quite comprehensive and bold in terms of its impulse to the economic diversification of Macao, driving its previous excessive dependence on casino capitalism. However, structurally, Macau will continue to be characterized by the main pillar of Casino's capitalism, but his social welfare, as can be seen in the large number of subsidies that Sam Hou Fai's discourse presents, remains another characteristic that defines the governance of Macao. Sam's political discourse is punctuated by his political will of reforming Macao, diversifying his economy and improving the means of subsistence of the population, but the main challenge continues to know if Macao's bureaucracy, at the middle and lower level, will really be able to implement its political initiatives smoothly and effectively. In addition, Sam Hou Fai has encouraged Macao Casinos dealers to invest in the in -depth cooperation zone, but details will have to be outlined to mobilize private sector companies to be effective in search of Macao's economic diversification.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 05:08:57</pubDate></item></channel></rss>