<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/09/hospital-das-ilhas-ja-atendeu-mais-de-mil-utentes-em-consultas-de-avaliacao-reprodutiva/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>India raises death toll to 25 in nightclub fire in Goa</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/09/india-eleva-para-25-numero-de-mortos-em-incendio-em-discoteca-de-goa/</link><description>The head of the Government of the Indian state of Goa, Pramod Sawant, raised to 25 the number of deaths in the fire that broke out this morning in a popular nightclub in the region and ordered a judicial investigation into the incident. "I am carefully analyzing the situation resulting from the tragic fire in Arpora, in which 25 people lost their lives and 06 were injured. The six injured are stable and receiving the best medical care. I have ordered a judicial investigation into the entire incident to determine the cause and responsibilities", Sawant said in a message published on the social network X.
Speaking to the Indian news agency ANI, Sawant said that the fire took half an hour to extinguish. "Some people managed to run away, but others didn't. As a result, some people died of asphyxiation. According to preliminary information, four were tourists and the rest were club employees," said the head of the Government of Goa, a former Portuguese colony, now a popular tourist enclave for Indian and foreign visitors on the Arabian Sea coast.
The Goa Police are still investigating the incident. The main hypothesis is that the flames were caused by the explosion of a gas cylinder inside the Birch By Romeo Lane nightclub. "There was a sudden commotion when the flames started to spread. We ran out of the club and saw that the entire structure was on fire," a tourist who was at the club at the time of the fire told Indian news agency PTI.
The Prime Minister of India, Narendra Modi, sent his condolences to the families of the victims and his office announced compensation for those closest to the fatal victims (200,000 rupees / 1,910 euros) and for those injured (50,000 rupees / approximately 477.5 euros).
Goa, a former Portuguese colony (1510-1961) located on the edge of the Arabian Sea, part of the Indian Ocean that separates the Indian subcontinent from the Arabian peninsula, is a world-famous seaside resort. It is frequented by Indian, Asian, Western and Russian tourists, attracted by the beaches, entertainment venues and rich colonial architectural heritage.
Goa welcomed more than ten million tourists in 2024, of which around 470,000 were foreigners, according to official statistics.
Fires in India are frequent, due to infrastructure that is sometimes in poor condition and safety and evacuation standards that are not always applied or respected.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:01:57</pubDate></item><item><title>International technology companies want to establish themselves in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/09/empresas-tecnologicas-internacionais-querem-estabelecer-se-em-macau/</link><description>The first edition of the Global Exhibition of Artificial Intelligence Machines and Electronic Products (AIE) promoted, for three days, strategic contacts between Macau and technology companies from around the world. According to a statement from the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM), at least 45 companies showed intentions to establish business in the region.

The Global Exhibition of Artificial Intelligence Machines and Electronic Products (AIE) had its first edition between the 4th and 6th of this month, in the cities of Macau and Zhuhai, with the presence of around a thousand technological companies and five thousand buyers from all over the world. The initiative is part of the strategy of the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM) of attracting investments through international conferences, following a model that combines participation in exhibitions, study and prospecting visits and networking sessions.
In this first event, IPIM says it has coordinated the participation of local companies and assigned employees to visit the main exhibitors, with a view to identifying concrete investment needs and promoting the commercial advantages of Macau and Hengqin. According to a statement released on Sunday, IPIM employees visited more than 350 technology companies in the interior of China, Portugal and Brazil, 45 of which – including companies listed on the stock exchange – “demonstrated intentions to establish business in Macau”.
To expand the cooperation network, the institute also promoted a business visit to Guangdong province, made up of representatives from the technology, 'big health', conventions and exhibitions and catering sectors. The Macau delegation visited several strategic points in Zhuhai, such as e-commerce industrial parks, large incubators and other facilities, allowing in-depth contact with local e-commerce and technology companies.
Macau's representatives were also welcomed at the AIE venue in Zhuhai, an exhibition area of 30,000 square meters divided into three main areas: the Smart Equipment Pavilion, the Smart Transport and Future Mobility Pavilion and the Smart Home Technology and Health Technologies Pavilion. In total, the space hosted 455 companies promoting innovative products such as industrial robots, drones, smart connected vehicles, vehicles autonomous vehicles, flying cars, smart home systems and health monitoring devices.
According to the various testimonies cited in the IPIM statement, the participating companies recognized the role of the event as a bridge to connect buyers from different origins – such as the Middle East, Russia and Thailand – and stated that they had established new business opportunities through study visits and contact scholarships promoted within the scope of the initiative.
Companies from the interior of China, in particular, said they were “optimistic” about the prospects for the development of the sector in Macau, citing the advantages of Macau as a platform for connecting abroad. On the other hand, a Portuguese-speaking company that participated in the AIE in Macau highlighted the convenience of administrative procedures in Macau and the business advantages offered by the territory as important factors for the expansion of its business within China.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:10:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Passengers at Macau Airport are expected to fall to 7.4 million</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/09/passageiros-no-aeroporto-de-macau-deverao-recuar-para-os-74-milhoes/</link><description>Macau International Airport may have been less busy this year, with forecasts pointing to 7.4 million passengers in 2025, lower than last year's number and also lower than the eight million projected at the beginning of this year. CAM admits that passenger flow was “less than ideal” in the first half of the year, due to the impact of the global environment.
Macau International Airport (MIA) lowered its 2025 movement forecast to 7.4 million passengers, contrary to the estimate made earlier this year, of more than eight million. The number now projected also represents a decrease compared to last year of 7.64 million passengers.
The forecast was put forward by Chan Weng Hong, administrator of the Board of Directors of CAM – Sociedade do Aeroporto Internacional de Macau, cited by Jornal Ou Mun. The official indicated that the number of passengers was not ideal during the first half of the year, which is due to “several factors”, including the general situation of the social, political and economic environment.
“However, from September to November, thanks to the joint efforts of the airport and airlines to develop new tourist destinations and improve promotion, passenger volumes increased by 4%, 11% and 4%, respectively, compared with the same period last year,” he pointed out. Chan Weng Hong added that passenger numbers are expected to peak during the Christmas festive season.
It is worth remembering that Macau International Airport handled more than 7.64 million passengers last year, an increase of 48% compared to the previous year, being the highest number in recent years since 2019. However, the 2024 level is still around 20.4% below 2019, before the pandemic.
In February this year, the airport infrastructure management company predicted an annual movement of more than eight million passengers, 8% more than the number recorded in 2024. CAM statistics show that, until September, 5.49 million passengers passed through Macau International Airport, less than the number registered at the same time last year, of 5.74 million.
Macau Airport, according to the Civil Aviation Authority (AACM), had until November 30th connections operated by 28 airlines to 42 destinations in mainland China, Taiwan, Southeast Asian countries, Japan and South Korea.
Information from travel booking platforms indicates that Macau will open a direct route to Vladivostok, Russia, operated by Cambodia Airways, with three round-trip flights per week. Tickets are on sale on platforms such as Trip.com, but are not yet on the list of flights approved by the AACM.
Speaking to the Chinese press, the director of CAM's Marketing Department, Eric Fong, stated that, since the beginning of this year, several new airlines have successively started their operations in Macau, with a series of new routes expected to be launched in the near future. Among them are the Macau – Jinan route, from Shandong province, which Air Macau begins operations this month, and the connection between Macau and Jeju Island, South Korea, operated by T’way Air and scheduled for January next year.
The Airport highlighted that it will align with the Government's strategy of attracting visitors by consolidating existing routes to mainland China and developing new connections to Southeast Asia and Northeast Asia. In addition, it will collaborate with travel agencies and airlines to promote long-haul connections from Macau to Europe, the Americas and the Middle East, through direct baggage check-in services, with the aim of achieving layover times of less than two hours.
On the other hand, seven intelligent inspection channels are in operation at the airport, which “significantly increased inspection efficiency”, stated CAM, revealing that the eighth channel will be opened soon.
The Airport is simultaneously moving forward with the installation of facial recognition systems, with completion scheduled for the end of the year. CAM expects the system to go into operation by the end of this year or early next year, so that passengers can perform facial verification during the check-in process, without presenting identification documents during subsequent security control and boarding procedures.
Another new Airport service will be launched in mid-January next year, which provides for the check-in service of hold luggage directly at hotels. According to CAM, the scheme will initially involve a partnership with three hotels in the Central and Northern zones, and will be gradually extended to more hotels.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:19:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Jazz, literature and conversations converge at the Macau Jazz Week 2025 festival</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/09/jazz-literatura-e-conversas-convergem-no-festival-macau-jazz-week-2025/</link><description>The connection between jazz and the written word is at the center of the 13th edition of Macau Jazz Week, which starts today and runs until December 12th. Under the theme “Culture, Literature and Music”, the festival brings to Macau two important names from the Asian scene: Malaysian pianist Tay Cher Siang, with his project dedicated to Haruki Murakami, and the acclaimed Taiwanese pianist and composer YuYing Hsu. With workshops, jam sessions and a night dedicated to local talent, the event will be an immersion in the universe of contemporary Asian jazz.
 
Macau Jazz Week opens its 13th edition with a program that expands the boundaries between sounds and letters. Organized by the Macau Jazz Promotion Association, the 2025 edition, which runs from the 9th to the 12th of December, has as its central theme “Culture, Literature and Music”, bringing to the city two outstanding figures whose work is fueled by an intimate conversation with literary narrative and cultural heritage.
The festival opens today with a free jazz workshop at 7pm, followed by a “Big Jazz Jam” from 8:30 pm, both at Associação Cultural e Musical Sifang, located on the 2nd floor of number 121A Avenida do Almirante Lacerda. The session will be led by Malaysian pianist Tay Cher Siang, leader of the prestigious band WVC, who will be accompanied by bassist AJ Popshuvit, drummer Adriel Wong and will feature a special appearance by vocalist Junji Delfino. The 'jam session' that follows hopes to bring together guest musicians and local talents in a moment of fun improvisation, to emphasize one of the fundamental pillars of the genre.
The literary highlight takes place tomorrow, Wednesday, December 10th, at the Bookand space, at Rua de Inácio Baptista, number 4B, ground floor. The evening begins with a free talk at 6:30 pm, where Tay Cher Siang will talk about her vision of jazz and literature. This will be followed, at 8pm, by the concert “Ouvir o Vento Cantar – Murakami e Jazz”, a conceptual project that the pianist has been developing. The show, costing 160 patacas, features fourteen themes. Seven are original compositions by Cher Siang inspired by the universe of Japanese writer Haruki Murakami, and the other seven are jazz standards mentioned in the author's works. The performance will be a multimodal experience, combining live music from the WVC trio with Mandarin readings of excerpts from Murakami, performed by vocalist Junji Delfino and Malaysian writer Li Zi Shu.
On Thursday, December 11th, it's YuYing Hsu's turn to take the Bookand stage. The Taiwanese pianist, composer and music producer, holder of multiple Golden Melody Awards, will first give a free talk about her creative process, at 6:30 pm. Their trio concert, scheduled for 8pm, also costing 160 patacas, will feature a repertoire of their critically acclaimed albums, such as “Happened, Happening”. For his performance in Macau, YuYing Hsu will form an elite trio with Japanese bassist Takashi Sugawa and German-French drummer Gabriel Hahn.
The festival closes on Friday, December 12th, with the “Macau Jazz New Forces” concert, a night entirely dedicated to showcasing the vigor of the new generation of local jazz musicians. Various formations from the Macau Youth Jazz Orchestra will take to the Bookand stage at 8pm, with tickets costing 160 patacas, for an overview of what is happening in the city, reinforcing the organizing association's mission of cultivating and promoting indigenous talent.
Founded in 2012, Macau Jazz Week is already considered a key event in the city's cultural calendar, a space for exchange between international artists and the local scene. Tickets for the concerts are on sale online, and all lectures are free. The full program and tickets are available on the Macau Jazz Promotion Association Facebook page.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>China promises “more proactive” fiscal policy and “flexible” monetary guidance in 2026</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/09/china-promete-politica-fiscal-mais-proactiva-e-orientacao-monetaria-flexivel-em-2026/</link><description>O Politburo do Partido Comunista Chinês (PCC) anunciou que vai manter em 2026 uma política fiscal “mais proactiva” e uma orientação monetária “moderadamente flexível”, num contexto de incerteza global e de persistentes desafios internos.

According to the official Xinhua news agency, the 24 members of the body met under the presidency of the general secretary of the CPC and head of state, Xi Jinping, highlighting that, despite the “difficulties”, China should achieve the “main economic and social goals” by 2025.
This year also marks the end of the 14th five-year plan (2021-2025), which the Party classified as a success. “We have responded to various disruptions and challenges, and both China’s ‘hard power’, in areas such as economy, science, technology and defense, and ‘soft power’, in culture, institutions and diplomacy, have registered significant improvements,” said the statement.
To ensure stability and progress in 2026, the PCC advocated “better coordination between domestic economic policies and international trade conflicts”, in an indirect reference to the trade war with the United States, currently suspended for a period of one year, following an agreement reached in October.
Among the priorities for next year, the Politburo highlighted the reinforcement of “countercyclical adjustments”, “improving the effectiveness of macroeconomic policies”, stimulating “new growth engines” and focusing on “development based on innovation”.
The communist leadership once again highlighted the importance of consolidating domestic demand, still weakened by consumer distrust, as the main driver of growth, and reaffirmed its commitment to economic openness to the outside world and the construction of a “strong internal market”.
The Politburo also defended greater coordination between development and security, and called for risk prevention in strategic sectors, with an emphasis on stabilizing employment and the expectations of companies and markets.
The year 2026 will mark the beginning of the 15th five-year plan, which will have technological self-sufficiency as its central axis. Economic goals should continue to follow the principle of “progress with stability”, according to the document.
In an allusion to the recent worsening of the crisis in the real estate sector and the increased pressure on family incomes, the Party also highlighted the need to promote “social harmony”, with measures to support the most vulnerable populations. The text specifically mentions resolving problems such as unpaid wages for migrant workers and outstanding payments to companies.
The Central Economic Work Conference is expected to be held later this month, an annual high-level meeting that defines China's macroeconomic guidelines for the following year.
However, the concrete objectives for 2026 – including GDP growth, deficit, inflation and unemployment – ​​will only be announced at the annual session of the National Popular Assembly, which traditionally takes place in early March. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:04:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal Point – 9 December 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/09/ponto-fatal-9-dezembro-2025/</link><description>O Politburo do Partido Comunista Chinês (PCC) anunciou que vai manter em 2026 uma política fiscal “mais proactiva” e uma orientação monetária “moderadamente flexível”, num contexto de incerteza global e de persistentes desafios internos.

According to the official Xinhua news agency, the 24 members of the body met under the presidency of the general secretary of the CPC and head of state, Xi Jinping, highlighting that, despite the “difficulties”, China should achieve the “main economic and social goals” by 2025.
This year also marks the end of the 14th five-year plan (2021-2025), which the Party classified as a success. “We have responded to various disruptions and challenges, and both China’s ‘hard power’, in areas such as economy, science, technology and defense, and ‘soft power’, in culture, institutions and diplomacy, have registered significant improvements,” said the statement.
To ensure stability and progress in 2026, the PCC advocated “better coordination between domestic economic policies and international trade conflicts”, in an indirect reference to the trade war with the United States, currently suspended for a period of one year, following an agreement reached in October.
Among the priorities for next year, the Politburo highlighted the reinforcement of “countercyclical adjustments”, “improving the effectiveness of macroeconomic policies”, stimulating “new growth engines” and focusing on “development based on innovation”.
The communist leadership once again highlighted the importance of consolidating domestic demand, still weakened by consumer distrust, as the main driver of growth, and reaffirmed its commitment to economic openness to the outside world and the construction of a “strong internal market”.
The Politburo also defended greater coordination between development and security, and called for risk prevention in strategic sectors, with an emphasis on stabilizing employment and the expectations of companies and markets.
The year 2026 will mark the beginning of the 15th five-year plan, which will have technological self-sufficiency as its central axis. Economic goals should continue to follow the principle of “progress with stability”, according to the document.
In an allusion to the recent worsening of the crisis in the real estate sector and the increased pressure on family incomes, the Party also highlighted the need to promote “social harmony”, with measures to support the most vulnerable populations. The text specifically mentions resolving problems such as unpaid wages for migrant workers and outstanding payments to companies.
The Central Economic Work Conference is expected to be held later this month, an annual high-level meeting that defines China's macroeconomic guidelines for the following year.
However, the concrete objectives for 2026 – including GDP growth, deficit, inflation and unemployment – ​​will only be announced at the annual session of the National Popular Assembly, which traditionally takes place in early March. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:00:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Marathon ends with new record</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/09/maratona-de-macau-termina-com-novo-recorde/</link><description>O queniano Victor Kipchirchir sagrou-se campeão da classificação geral no escalão masculino da Maratona Internacional de Macau, tendo quebrado o recorde do evento. The athlete from Ethiopia, Mastewal Birhanu Senay, became champion of the general classification in the women's category. Rosa Mota came second in the minimarathon.

Victor Kipchirchir, from Kenya, won the Macau International Marathon race with a time of 02:09:27, while John Hakizimana, from Rwanda, came in 2nd place and Barecha Tolosa Geleto, from Ethiopia, came in 3rd place. In the women's category, Ethiopian athletes won the first three places, which were Mastewal Birhanu Senay (02:31:37), Selam Fente Gebre and Kolole Mekashu Tefera, respectively.
The Portuguese Rosa Mota came second in the Macau mini-marathon, a 4.5-kilometer race that is part of the Macao SAR International Marathon. The 67-year-old former Olympic champion finished the race in 17 minutes and 10 seconds, 54 seconds more than the first, local athlete Kin I Chao.
In February, the Portuguese woman was discharged from hospital, following a planned surgical intervention, after overcoming a “serious problem”, a “dissecting aortic aneurysm”.
Rosa Mota, born in Porto, was Olympic marathon champion at the Seoul Olympic Games in 1988, after having won bronze in Los Angeles in 1984. Her achievements also include three European titles (1982, 1986 and 1990) and one world title (1987). She is still the national marathon record holder, clocking 02.23.29 hours, a mark achieved in Chicago in 1985.
In recent years, Rosa Mota had reappeared at the highest level and won several veteran events, having set the world half-marathon record in Barcelona in 2024 (1:24.27 hours), for the 65 to 69 age group. Also last year, the Portuguese woman won the Macau mini-marathon, repeating her triumphs in 2018, 2019 and 2023.
This year, the organization invited several athletes, nominated by the Association of Official Portuguese Language Olympic Committees (ACOLOP), from Portugal, Angola, Cape Verde, Guinea-Bissau, Mozambique, São Tomé and Príncipe, Sri Lanka and the state of Goa (India).
Lusophones were in the spotlight in the half-marathon, with Cape Verdean Samuel Freire, from Sporting Clube de Portugal, finishing third in the men's race, behind winner Martin Ndungu and David Kipkorir Rono, both Kenyans.
In fourth place came the Portuguese Fábio Oliveira, 30th in the marathon of the first edition of the European Road Championships, in April, and part of the Portugal team that finished in fourth place. Soon after came the young Mozambican Pinto Victor Jequecene, aged 22, while Angolan David Jundo Elias finished in seventh place.
In the women's race, Angolan Lúcia Kawele Capingala came in third place, behind the winner, Kenyan Lucy Ndambuki, and Chinese Na Zhao. Already off the podium, in fourth position, was the young Portuguese Joana Ferreira, who won the silver medal in the under-23 race of the national athletics championships over 10,000 meters, in May. Mozambican Domingas Ernesto Checane came in sixth place.
Around 12 thousand participants signed up for the three races of the Macau International Marathon, with the title of the premier race going to Kenyan Victor Kipchirchir and Ethiopian Senay Mastewal Birhanu.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:01:18</pubDate></item><item><title>291 slopes at risk registered in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/09/registados-291-taludes-em-risco-em-macau/</link><description>Until October, there were 291 slopes at risk throughout Macau – two of them considered high risk. The Public Works Services Directorate (DSOP) reported that it has reinforced maintenance and safety assessment work, registering 20 inspections of 135 slopes in the first ten months of the year alone.

From January to October, the Public Works Services Department (DSOP) counted 291 embankments at risk in Macau. Throughout this period, the authorities carried out a total of 20 inspections of 135 slopes spread across the territory, with seven more slopes being found to be at risk compared to the previous year.
The Macau Peninsula has the highest number of cases, with a total of 130 slopes at risk in this area. Among these, the majority (92) are low risk, with the remaining 38 being medium risk. In turn, the island of Taipa, despite accounting for only 73 cases (51 low-risk and 21 medium-risk), had a high-risk situation on Estrada da Ponta da Cabrita in October. The island of Coloane, with a total of 88 cases (67 low-risk and 20 medium-risk), also observed a more serious case near the Escola de São José de Ká Hó.
In a statement, DSOP confirms that these two most urgent cases “were monitored and treated by the competent authorities”, leaving a total of 79 medium-risk slopes and 210 low-risk slopes.
The same organization states that, between April 2022 and last October, 62 inspections were carried out on 337 slopes, nine of which were high risk. These data reveal that the number of inspections has been increasing in recent months. In 2025 alone, 135 slopes were inspected – that is, 40% of the total.
This year, DSOP completed several stabilization works: one on Estrada da Penha, another at the Macau Security Forces School and a third on Avenida Padre Tomás Pereira, in Taipa. For its part, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) completed two projects: the third phase of the “Slope Reorganization Work in Macau” and the first phase of the “Provisional Slope Protection Work in Municipal Parks and Cemeteries in 2024”.
On the other hand, the work to treat the slope of the Government facilities in Penha is still ongoing, while the reorganization work on Rua dos Pescadores de Macau, adjacent to the Tin Hau Temple, will begin soon.
The updated status of the works and safety assessment processes can be consulted on the official DSOP page, in a thematic section entitled “Information Network on Slope Safety”.
The data previously presented by the organization, dated July, showed 284 slopes at risk in the territory, although none were high risk. The numbers were released in response to a written question from deputy Ella Lei, in which she highlighted that “slope safety constitutes a crucial element in urban planning and disaster prevention management” and called for an increase in the frequency of inspections.
In its response, DSOP noted that the competent services have carried out maintenance work “in an orderly manner and according to the degree of urgency”, giving priority to the safety of the public and their property.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:15:32</pubDate></item><item><title>China achieves record trade surplus of more than a trillion dollars in 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/09/china-atinge-excedente-comercial-recorde-de-mais-de-um-biliao-de-dolares-em-2025/</link><description>China's exports grew 5.9% in November, exceeding forecasts and increasing the accumulated trade surplus in 2025 to more than one billion dollars, an annual record, reflecting dependence on external demand.
According to official data released, imports increased just 1.9% in the same period, resulting in a surplus of 112 billion dollars in the month. The average forecast of economists surveyed by the Bloomberg agency pointed to a 4% increase in exports.
The data comes in a context marked by a prolonged decline in prices in the real estate sector and an increase in job insecurity, which continues to limit domestic consumption. Even so, the increase in imports exceeds the 1% rate recorded in October.
The historic trade surplus also comes after a recent easing of trade tensions with the United States, and could intensify calls from several trading partners for a greater correction of China's external imbalances, namely the massive entry of goods at reduced prices, which has put pressure on local industries in other countries.
Among the points of the agreement with Washington, the two countries committed to reducing mutually applied tariffs, easing controls on the export of critical minerals and advanced technology, and cooperating in the fight against fentanyl trafficking. Beijing also committed to increasing purchases of North American soybeans.
Still, according to the think tank Peterson Institute for International Economics, the US maintains average tariffs of 47.5% on Chinese goods, while China applies tariffs of around 32% on US products.
The data also reveals Beijing's difficulty in rebalancing the economy, which remains heavily dependent on external demand. Net exports accounted for almost a third of Chinese economic growth in 2025.
Despite the trade war launched at the beginning of the year by US President Donald Trump, the world's second largest economy remained resilient, redirecting its sales to alternative markets to the United States.
Foreign demand has been the most constant driver of China's growth, offsetting weak domestic consumption and the prolonged crisis in the real estate sector.
O perfil comercial do país tornou-se cada vez mais assimétrico: a procura interna mantém-se anémica, enquanto empresas chinesas altamente competitivas continuam a reduzir a necessidade de importações.
This record surplus should have a positive impact on the acceleration of Gross Domestic Product (GDP), after several months of economic slowdown. Retail sales are emerging from the most prolonged cycle of slowdown since 2021 and investment has recorded a historic drop.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:05:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese conceptual photography at SCM Hostel to celebrate transfer of sovereignty</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/09/fotografia-conceptual-chinesa-no-albergue-scm-para-celebrar-transferencia-de-soberania/</link><description>To mark the 26th Anniversary of the Transfer of Sovereignty of Macau to China, the Circle of Friends of Culture opens tomorrow the solo exhibition “Above the Abyss”, by renowned Chinese conceptual photographer Zhang Lanpo. With 16 works that explore the limits of human existence and historical memory, the exhibition will be on view until February 15th in Gallery A2 of the SCM Hostel, with free entry. 

The Circle of Friends of Culture of Macau (CAC) joins the celebrations of the 26th Anniversary of the Transfer of Sovereignty with an artistic proposal of profound intellectual density. A exposição “Above the Abyss”, do fotógrafo conceptual chinês Zhang Lanpo, inaugura amanhã, às 18h30, na Galeria A2 do Albergue da SCM, marcando a primeira apresentação em Macau de um dos nomes mais representativos da fotografia conceptual contemporânea da China.
Born in Lanzhou and with a master's degree from the Guangzhou Academy of Fine Arts, Zhang Lanpo is recognized for appearing in the Top 20 new talents in contemporary Chinese photography. His practice is distinguished by an expansive investigation into the limits of human existence and consciousness, transcending pure aesthetics to place itself at the center of contemporary artistic debate. Its thematic focus remains on the exploration of death as a way to reconstruct a vision of life, a process that the artist himself describes as a confrontation with “a history of contradictions between function and excess, crime and punishment, humanity and divinity”.
The exhibition, made up of 16 works including photography and painting, functions as a visual journey across an abyss. Through a unique language, Zhang Lanpo does not seek to restore history, but to dismantle it. Sacred forms merge with weapons, nerves transform into crowns of thorns, ruins intertwine with organs. The result, as curator Iion Ho describes, are “traces, not allegories; wounds, not illusions,” which exert a “slow but powerful visual pressure” on the viewer.
Each work by Zhang Lanpo is an exercise in patience and meticulous craftsmanship, and may require up to eight months of work to complete. His large-format pieces are full of visual details and intricate layers of metaphor, having been part of the collections of institutions such as the Guangdong Museum of Art and the Zhejiang Museum of Art, and exhibited at prestigious events such as the 15th Havana Biennial and the Lianzhou International Photography Festival.
Once again, Iion Ho, leaves an accurate curation description. “Floating above the abyss is the position Zhang chooses – and perhaps the position we all share.” It is a threshold without ascension or escape, where “no truth is pronounced”, leaving the viewer to complete the images with their own gaze.
The exhibition, organized by CAC – an association founded in 1985 by figures such as Carlos Marreiros, Mio Pang Fei and Ung Vai Meng, and widely recognized as a pioneer in the local artistic scene – has the support of the Fund for the Development of Culture.
The exhibition “Acima do Abismo” will be on display from December 10th to February 15th, 2026, with free entry.  Galeria A2 is located at the SCM Hostel, at Calçada da Igreja de São Lázaro, number 8. The doors are open every day, from 12:00 pm to 7:00 pm, however, on Mondays, the opening hours are from 3:00 pm to 7:00 pm.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>APAVT delegation visited Hengqin</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/09/delegacao-da-apavt-visitou-hengqin/</link><description>Representatives of the Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies (APAVT) paid a visit to Hengqin on Friday, which aimed to explore the cultural and tourist resources of the Mountain Island.
According to the Hengqin Economic Development Services Bureau, the organization of the ‘post-tour’ within the scope of the 50th APAVT Congress in Macau offers collaboration opportunities for the Deep Cooperation Zone “to connect with European markets and attract international visitors”.
The program includes visits to reference spaces in the areas of hospitality, wellness, traditional Chinese medicine and entertainment, offering a comprehensive view of Hengqin's tourism potential. On this tour, the delegation visited the Hengqin Traditional Chinese Medicine Cultural Center, Hotel Serensia Woods and Hengqin Chimelong International Marine Resort.
Quoted by Hengqin Economic Development Services, APAVT representatives consider that Hengqin's leisure and resort resources complement Macau's historical and cultural heritage and, by designing inter-regional tourist itineraries, “the appeal to international visitors – particularly those from Portuguese-speaking countries – can be significantly increased”.
The note also highlights that the competent authorities of Macau and Hengqin will maintain in-depth communication with APAVT about possible collaborations. The parties will explore, in the future, the creation of a regularized cooperation mechanism that covers the development of tourism products, the promotion of markets and the training of professionals, aiming to “position ‘Macau + Hengqin’ as an emblematic tourist destination with influence on Portuguese-speaking markets”, he states.
According to APAVT, as part of the 50th APAVT Congress in Macau, and to take place after its closure, four post-tours promoted by Macau Tourism are planned, which include a tour to Fuzhou, Quanzhou and Xiamen; one each to Jiangmen and Shenzhen; one to Zhuhai and Guiyang; and one to Hengqin.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:09:32</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 850 candidates admitted to the qualified staff recruitment program</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/09/mais-de-850-candidatos-admitidos-no-programa-de-captacao-de-quadros-qualificados/</link><description>The Government admitted more than 850 candidates in the first two phases of the program to recruit qualified staff, who are already involved in work related to Macau's four emerging industries. The Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, announced that the third phase of the plan is underway, with the effort to attract international talent and professionals from Portuguese-speaking countries.
More than 850 candidates were included in the proposed list of Macau's qualified personnel recruitment program, including members of the Chinese Academy of Engineering, gold medal athletes and founders of publicly listed companies, announced the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai.
The Government leader, quoted by the Chinese channel TDM Macau, indicated that the talents admitted are already starting to work in the territory in the four emerging industries, with the program “achieving phased results”.
Sam Hou Fai's statement was given at the 2nd Ordinary Plenary Meeting of 2025 of the Qualified Staff Development Commission (CDQQ), which took place on Friday. During the meeting, Sam highlighted that the Government “has been actively monitoring” the assessment and approval procedures for the first two phases of the talent acquisition program, with the third phase of the program currently progressing steadily.
The third phase of the program to recruit qualified staff was launched on Tuesday last week, which will have an application period of almost one year, ending on December 1, 2026. “The program incorporates multiple elements aimed at attracting international talent and professionals from Portuguese-speaking countries, thus reinforcing Macau's competitiveness in recruiting global talent”, said Sam Hou Fai.
He pointed out that improvements were made to the mechanism through the creation of two interdepartmental working groups, which “adopt a more proactive approach in identifying, hiring and inviting international talents with potential or interest in developing their careers in Macau”, in addition to providing support to newly arrived professionals.
According to the presentation, the program, as in the previous two editions, is divided into three categories – Program for High Quality Qualified Staff; Program for Highly Qualified Staff; and Program for Advanced Level Professionals. The overall framework remains largely consistent with the previous two phases, with the addition of additional scoring criteria for those with qualifications from renowned Portuguese and Brazilian universities, diplomas in traditional Chinese medicine and international professional experience.
The two new working groups comprise the Qualified Staff Promotion and Development Group and the Qualified Staff Services Working Group, which are composed of representatives from the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment, the Economic and Technological Development Services, the Science and Technology Development Fund and other competent departments.
Sam Hou Fai added that, during the formulation of reform measures and supporting policies regarding talent work, he gave priority to coordinating policies related to the four major infrastructure projects planned by the Government.
The Executive also wants to reinforce exchanges in the scope of work on qualified staff with the Deep Cooperation Zone in Hengqin and the Greater Bay Area, with a view to “maximizing the advantages of resources and the synergy effects of the three regions of the Greater Bay Area, within the scope of the professional development of qualified staff, as well as creating more good conditions to attract qualified staff”, can be read in a note from CDQQ.
It should be remembered that the first phase of the talent acquisition program ended in the first quarter of last year, with the Government receiving 1,107 valid applications, while the second phase ended in November of the same year, with a total of 1,043 valid applications.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:16:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Study reveals that traditional values ​​continue to dominate sexuality in China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/09/estudo-revela-que-valores-tradicionais-continuam-a-dominar-sexualidade-na-china/</link><description>Traditional values ​​continue to dominate sexual relations in China, according to a study of three generations of families, pointing to pressures on women between conservative norms and modern expectations, such as premarital sex and virginity within marriage.

The investigation is presented in the book Embedded Generations: Family Life and Social Change in Contemporary China, by sociologist Liu Jieyu, professor at the School of Oriental and African Studies (SOAS), at the University of London. The work, published by Princeton University Press, is based on three years of fieldwork in urban and rural areas of China.
Despite the generation born in the 1980s and 1990s being more open to premarital sex – with 60% of women and 80% of men admitting premarital relationships – the expectation of marrying a virgin woman remains widespread, both among men and older generations.
“The conflict between these contradictory demands generates great anxiety among women,” said Liu, quoted by the Hong Kong newspaper South China Morning Post. “Virginity is used as a tool of control, while women feel they must compromise during courtship to prove their love,” Liu noted.
In many cases, men pressure their girlfriends to have sex, but want their future wives to arrive at marriage without prior experience. Liu called this phenomenon a “battle of virginity”, common especially among women of the only-child generation.
The study was based on interviews with members of 43 urban families and 37 rural families, in provinces such as Shandong, Fujian and Hunan, and cities such as Tianjin, Guangzhou and Xian. The interviews covered three generations: born between the 1930s and 1950s, between 1950 and 1970, and between 1980 and 2000.
According to Liu, premarital sex tends to occur with the aim of getting married. The majority of respondents ended up marrying the first person they had sex with. The average number of sexual partners remains low: between zero and one for younger women, and up to two for men.
The researcher also highlights a sharp increase in extramarital relationships. Data cited in the work indicate that, between 2006 and 2020, the infidelity rate among married men increased from 16.5% to 35%, while in the case of women it increased from 4.5% to 23%.
Although few admit to infidelity, 70% of men in the younger generation said they were open to the idea. Among women, the responses were more varied: some rejected, others admitted to separating “life” from “marriage”.
Liu pointed to factors such as the decline of state surveillance over private life, the influence of Western values, migration and the popularization of the culture of love and intimacy on television and social media as causes for these changes.
Another factor highlighted is the pressure to get married by the age of 30, despite restrictions on romantic life during youth. “Many people get married without being in love, which can contribute to the increase in extramarital affairs,” he noted.
The number of divorces has also increased, especially among young women. However, as people get older, the reluctance to ask for divorce grows, mainly due to fears about the difficulty of finding a new partner.
Sexual satisfaction in marriage is less linked to generation and more to the couple's stage of life, concludes Liu. Couples who reported greater intimate happiness are those with long-lasting relationships, based on “deep mutual knowledge and interdependence”. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:05:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Economia japonesa contraiu 0,6% no terceiro trimestre, menos do que o estimado</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/09/economia-japonesa-contraiu-06-no-terceiro-trimestre-menos-do-que-o-estimado/</link><description>The Japanese Government revised downwards the contraction of the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) in the third quarter, setting it at 0.6% compared to the previous quarter, two tenths less than previously estimated.

According to revised data published by the Cabinet Secretariat, gross public capital formation, which in November's preliminary estimates pointed to growth of 0.1%, ultimately registered a fall of 1.1% in quarterly terms. Public expenditure, in turn, rose just 0.2%, compared to the 0.5% initially indicated.
Private consumption, which represents around 60% of the Japanese economy, was revised slightly upwards, with growth of 0.2% between July and September, a tenth above what was indicated in preliminary estimates.
Despite the improvement, domestic demand was penalized by the 0.2% drop in companies' gross fixed capital formation, which contrasts with the 1% expansion projected in November.
Exports remained unchanged compared to previous data, with a drop of 1.2%, attributed to tariffs imposed by the United States and which constituted one of the main factors in the economic contraction.
Imports, however, were revised downwards, with a decline of 0.4%, compared to the 0.1% decline initially calculated.
In the second quarter of the year, Japanese GDP had grown by 0.5% quarter-on-quarter, according to revised data.
In year-on-year terms, GDP growth between July and September was also revised downwards, from 1.1% to 0.6%. The growth estimate for the first quarter, compared to the same period in 2024, was also corrected downwards, from 1.8% to 1.6%.

Surplus on the current account

Japan recorded a current account surplus of 2.83 billion yen (15.665 billion euros) in October, a record value for that month, the Japanese Government reported.
The value is 15.5% higher than that recorded in the same month of 2024 and 36.8% lower than that obtained in September, according to data published by the Japanese Ministry of Finance.
The Japanese trade balance had a surplus of 98.3 billion yen (543 million euros), in contrast to the deficit of 152.7 billion yen (844 million euros) recorded in the previous year, and a decrease of 58.3% in quarterly terms.
Exports increased by 2.8% year-on-year and 2.2% quarter-to-quarter, reaching 9.65 billion yen (53,387 million euros); while imports grew 0.1% year-on-year and 3.7% quarter-to-quarter, reaching 9.55 billion yen (52,840 million euros).
The services balance recorded a deficit of 294.6 billion yen (1.628 billion euros), 3.4 times more than last year and 37.3% more compared to September.
In the tenth month of the year, the income account recorded a positive balance of 3.46 billion yen (19.152 billion euros), an increase of 8.6% compared to the previous year, but 30% less than the previous month.
The transfers item recorded a deficit of 434.8 billion yen (2.403 billion euros), which represents an increase of 12.5% ​​compared to the previous year and a reduction of 10.9% compared to the previous quarter.
The balance of payments reflects payments and revenues from exchanges of goods, services, income and transfers abroad, and is considered one of the most comprehensive commercial indicators of a country. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:02:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Hospital das Ilhas has already served more than a thousand users in reproductive assessment consultations</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/09/hospital-das-ilhas-ja-atendeu-mais-de-mil-utentes-em-consultas-de-avaliacao-reprodutiva/</link><description>To date, more than a thousand users have been seen in external reproductive assessment consultations at Hospital das Ilhas. The service began operating at the end of February, in conjunction with the new law on medically assisted procreation techniques launched by the Government.
According to the Macau Union Hospital in a statement, in addition to providing artificial insemination services, some couples managed to achieve the goal of pregnancy after a series of “comprehensive treatments”, which included female endocrinological care, ovulation induction with medication and ovulation monitoring by ultrasound.
The month of July marked another stage in the development of the medical center's assisted procreation services, with the availability of the intrauterine insemination (IUI) service. This service already has 57 cases, including “some cases” that resulted in successful pregnancies.
Hospital das Ilhas also informs that, in recent days, a “new phase in the area of ​​assisted procreation techniques” has begun, as described in the same statement. Professor Sun Zhengyi, a gynecology specialist from Peking Union Medical College Hospital (PUMCH), was invited to provide clinical guidance and technical support in Macau, thus enabling advances such as in vitro fertilization (IVF) and intracytoplasmic sperm injection (ICSI) services, in addition to carrying out various essential procedures, such as oocyte retrieval surgeries, IVF, ICSI, embryo culture, embryo transfer (ET),
The institution reaffirms its commitment to “providing professional assisted procreation services”, as well as “improving work processes and equipment”, with a view to helping all couples facing fertility difficulties.
The “Medical Assisted Procreation Treatment Participation Program” was launched by the Government in December 2024, aimed at supporting infertile couples in Macau. The plan stipulates that couples who meet the requirements undergo a preliminary clinical assessment, and are then redirected to an external infertility consultation at Hospital das Ilhas.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 00:12:56</pubDate></item></channel></rss>