<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/china-testa-em-linha-real-comboio-de-alta-velocidade-que-pode-atingir-400-km-h/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Timor-Leste rectifies vote in the UN resolution to demand ceasefire in Gaza</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/timor-leste-retifica-voto-na-resolucao-da-onu-a-exigir-cessar-fogo-em-gaza/</link><description>Timor-Leste rectified the vote in the resolution of the UN General Assembly approved on Thursday, with the support of 149 countries, requiring an immediate ceasefire in Gaza and defending Israel's liability for non-compliance with humanitarian obligations. Initially, the country had chosen to refrain from voting for resolution.
In a letter, released by the Timorese Presidency and led to the president of the 79th session of the UN General Assembly, Philemon Yang, Timor-Leste requests rectification, stressing that "intended to vote in favor of the resolution." “After in-depth reflection, it became clear that our abstention of June 12, 2025 does not accurately reflect our position on the suffering of the Palestinian people, caused by violence and indiscriminate deaths,” read the letter. "Timor-Leste remains firm in his support for the Palestinian cause and defends the immediate termination of war, as well as the protection of civilians and respect for legal and humanitarian obligations. We also appeal to the end of conflict in Gaza and liberation, in security conditions, hostages in Gaza and their return to Israel," he adds.
Entitled "Israeli illegal actions in busy East Jerusalem and in the rest of the busy Palestinian territory", the resolution condemns the use of hunger against civilians "as a method of war" and the "illegal denial of humanitarian access."
He points out that Israel, as an occupant power, is obliged by international law to ensure that humanitarian aid reaches the entire needy population and requires full, fast, safe and unimpeded entry of large -scale help to the enclave.
The text goes further and appeals to all Member States so that individually and collectively take all the necessary measures to ensure compliance with Israelite obligations, stressing the need for Screen to be held responsible.
The document also reinforces the requirement of immediate, worthy and unconditional release of all hostages detained by the Hamas Extremist Group.
The resolution is not binding, but serves to evaluate the support that Israel has in the United Nations, in addition to its unconditional ally, the United States, which last week vetoed a resolution that required a ceasefire in Gaza again and the survey of all restrictions on the entry of humanitarian aid in the enclave.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:49:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Influencers of the interior of China invite followers to consume in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/influenciadores-do-interior-da-china-convidam-seguidores-a-consumirem-em-macau/</link><description>A hundred digital influencers from Douyin-China's interior social network-made a promotional action entitled “Enchanting Macao”, inviting their followers to travel to different areas of the city to explore tourist elements.
The travel program included the “Pop Mart Macao Citywalk” project, recently launched, the facilities of “Flora Fête With Sanrio Characters”, the Pedonal Rua da Fortaleza do Monte, the old Panchões IEC Lon factory, the Naval Lai Chi Vun shipyards, among others, and at night, a walk through the northern area, Areia Black and Fai Chi Chi Kei, looking for typical Macao delicacies. Some sights have also offered guided tours to further explain Macao's community culture so that celebrities and fans can have deeper knowledge and reinforce the promotion of Macao culture.
Influencers held tours, during which they filmed and released short promotional videos, combining the influence of celebrities and the secondary transmission force of fans, to attract visitors to visit Macao community neighborhoods and help promote community tourism and the night economy.
Several influencers have published short videos to share Macau's community tourism experience, publicize Macao's least known sights and gastronomy, among others, and, in conjunction with the influence of celebrities and the fan relay power, attracting visitors to visit the neighborhoods of Macao, contributing to the promotion of community tourism and the night economy.
The “Enchanting Macao” carnival was also organized, with an open line for stars, a trip of digital influencers with fans and a “Star Salon” sharing session. The event was jointly organized by the Tourism Services Directorate (STD) and the Influencing Marketing Operations Platform of the Douyin Group's Ocean Engine brand.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:56:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing will increase support to Mozambique in health and infrastructure</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/pequim-vai-aumentar-apoio-a-mocambique-na-saude-e-infraestruturas/</link><description>The Minister of Foreign Affairs and Cooperation of Mozambique said that the Chinese government will increase support to the country, especially in projects in health and infrastructure.
 
Maria Lucas, who spoke on the sidelines of a meeting with the Foreign Minister of the Popular Republic of China, Wen He, said the meeting exceeded her expectations, especially with the announcement of a reinforcement of Chinese support to Mozambique in several key areas.
"[Wen He] referred to the increase in the support they will make to Mozambique in several areas, but, above all, to galvanize the implementation of the project on the construction of the Surgical Center of Maputo Central Hospital [the largest unit in the country]," said the minister, who is visited to China.
According to Maria Lucas, the Chinese minister also highlighted the construction of a Health Training Center in Sofala, province of the center of the country. "It also referred to the two projects that we already submitted to the Government of China, one of them in relation to N1 [National Road 1], only to the sections of Maputo province to Gaza, and also referred to the project of interconnectivity in the digital area (…) that we had also submitted. He said they will also work in these projects and will soon give the answers," he said.
The minister stressed that the historical partnership between Mozambique and China goes beyond the last five decades, also extending to the period of the Mozambican national liberation struggle. "It was a very good meeting. It's always good to have an ally like China," he concluded.
The Minister of Foreign Affairs and Cooperation of Mozambique appealed, on Wednesday, to the flexibility of the mechanisms of preparation and presentation of business projects and the disbursement of Chinese funds in Africa.
Maria Lucas, who spoke during the Ministerial Coordination Conference for the implementation of the results of the IV China-Africa Cooperation Forum (FOCAC), in the Chinese city of Changsha, greeted and praised the “promising” initiative, but advanced some challenges to be overcome for their effective implementation in African countries. "To [the initiative] be viable and successful in our countries, and in Mozambique, in particular, there are challenges that must be properly addressed, including the flexibility of project preparation and presentation mechanisms, as well as disbursement of backgrounds," he said.
According to the minister, the partnership with China produced to Africa and Mozambique, particularly “significant results”, including the statement of the Africa-China forum and the advancement of the “belt and route” cooperation initiative, as well as the Macao Forum.
Maria Lucas assured that Mozambique is prepared to receive Chinese investments and bring trade between the two countries to higher levels.
China is the largest commercial partner on the African continent, with bilateral trade reaching $ 167.8 billion in the first half of the year, according to the Chinese official press. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:56:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Suspects of electoral corruption prohibited from leaving Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/suspeitos-de-corrupcao-eleitoral-proibidos-de-sair-de-macau/</link><description>The Commissioner Against Corruption (CCAC) has sent to the Public Prosecution Service (MP) the case of five individuals who will allegedly have offered pecuniary advantages to entice other citizens to sign a form of constitution of application to elections. The court applied to two of the suspects the measures of periodic presentation and prohibition of absence of MSAR. The authorities did not confirm the identity of the suspects.
 
The Public Prosecution Service (MP) announced yesterday that it received the case of five individuals suspected of the crime of electoral corruption. The court ordered measures to coercive periodic presentation, prohibition of absence and prohibition of contacts to two of the suspects, while the other three were subject only to the provision of security.
The case was referred to the MP by the Commissioner Against Corruption (CCAC), which, in a note published on Friday afternoon, indicated that there is suspicion of offering advantages, including pecuniary advantages, to entice the signing of the application for recognition of the application committee, having also identified individuals who accepted their respective brothers, in order to constitute an application committee for the next legislative elections.
The suspects “will have enlisted others to subscribe to filing forms with pecuniary advantages or other advantages or will have offered proposal forms already signed,” said CCAC, adding that one of the suspects confessed to the practice of their suspicious criminal act while another suspect confessed to falsifying voter signatures, signing proposition forms. The evidence is the practice of the crime of electoral corruption and falsification of document.
In the press release, the CCAC said that it was still looking for other potential individuals involved and warned that "those who offer, promise or grant any form of benefits, by themselves or through others, so that voters constitute candidacy commission or vote, is punished with prison penalty up to eight years, and the imprisonment applied cannot be suspended."
Thus, the Criminal Instruction Court, under the promotion of the MP, applied to the two mainly defendants measures to provide security, periodic presentation, prohibition of absence and prohibition of contacts and to the other three defendants measurement of security coercion.
The MP appealed, through a statement, that citizens “preserve jointly the justice, impartiality and integrity of the legislative elections, refraining from practicing any illegal act related to the elections to obtain immediate benefit, otherwise they incur criminal liability”.
According to All About Macau, the suspects of this case belong to the list of mutual grassroots, whose agent, Wong Wai Man, was also detained last week by the Judicial Police (PJ) for allegedly being responsible for an illegal Mahjong House. The publication writes that the list failed to submit the signatures to formalize the candidacy with the Electoral Affairs Commission of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) because the person responsible for this was at CCAC.
The final point tried to clarify, next to the PJ, if the case in fact involves Wong Wai Man, but the corporation refused to explain.
Before he allegedly being detained by PJ, Wong Wai Man was trying to finalize the formalization of his candidacy for the September 14 elections. The lists are required to present at least 300 signatures valid to officialize the recognition of the application committee constitution and mutual help Grassroots had achieved a total of 395. But initially Caeal validated just over 200 signatures. Thus, Wong Wai Man had until Friday to raise the other signatures, which did not happen.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:55:57</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 2,000 candidates participated in an integrated skills evaluation contest</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/mais-de-2-000-candidatos-participaram-em-concurso-de-avaliacao-de-competencias-integradas/</link><description>Yesterday was held the Contest of Integrated Competency Assessment regarding Academic Qualification of General Secondary Education for the purpose of competition for the exercise of respective functions in the civil service. The test was attended by 2,099 candidates from 3,539 candidates admitted, the Directorate of Administration and Public Function Services (SAFP) reported.
Now, the contest jury will do the evaluation work. The result of the integrated skills assessment is expressed only in the "fit" and "unaffered" mentions, considering "fit" the candidate with results equal to or greater than 50 values ​​and "not fit" less than 50 values, and the evaluation work will be completed within one month. The final classification list will be published on the Public Function Electronic Page in July (http://concurso-uni.safp.gov.mo/).
The period of validity of the classification of the contest is five years, that is, the candidates who obtain the "fit" mention and who fulfill the legal requirements provided, can later and for five years from the date of publication of the classification list, apply for professional or functional assessment contests that may be performed, for public services, technician and maritime staff, as well as to the contest Evaluation of professional or functional skills to other careers of academic levels lower than the level of general secondary education qualifications, namely, assistant, qualified worker, postal distributor, heavy driver and light driver.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:48:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal point 2025.06.16</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/ponto-fatal-2025-06-16/</link><description>Yesterday was held the Contest of Integrated Competency Assessment regarding Academic Qualification of General Secondary Education for the purpose of competition for the exercise of respective functions in the civil service. The test was attended by 2,099 candidates from 3,539 candidates admitted, the Directorate of Administration and Public Function Services (SAFP) reported.
Now, the contest jury will do the evaluation work. The result of the integrated skills assessment is expressed only in the "fit" and "unaffered" mentions, considering "fit" the candidate with results equal to or greater than 50 values ​​and "not fit" less than 50 values, and the evaluation work will be completed within one month. The final classification list will be published on the Public Function Electronic Page in July (http://concurso-uni.safp.gov.mo/).
The period of validity of the classification of the contest is five years, that is, the candidates who obtain the "fit" mention and who fulfill the legal requirements provided, can later and for five years from the date of publication of the classification list, apply for professional or functional assessment contests that may be performed, for public services, technician and maritime staff, as well as to the contest Evaluation of professional or functional skills to other careers of academic levels lower than the level of general secondary education qualifications, namely, assistant, qualified worker, postal distributor, heavy driver and light driver.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:48:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Agreements of more than 10 billion at IIICF reinforce Macao role in the global infrastructure market</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/acordos-de-mais-de-10-mil-milhoes-na-iiicf-reforcam-papel-de-macau-no-mercado-global-de-infraestruturas/</link><description>The 16th edition of the Forum and International Exhibition on Investment and Construction of Infrastructure (IIICF) has consolidated Macau as a prominent platform in the signing of cooperation protocols that totaled more than $ 10 billion. With the record participation of international professionals, the presence of companies in Macau and Hengqin grew more than 30%, in an event that promoted technological innovation, strategic alliances and the internationalization of the infrastructure sector.
 
The 16th International Forum and Investment Investment and Construction Exhibition (IIICF), completed on June 12, stood out for the tangible results and the impact on global cooperation on the area. Organized by the Association of China International Civil Builders (Chinca) and the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment (IPIM), the event reaffirmed its position as one of the main international meetings dedicated to the infrastructure sector.
During the three days of realization, cooperation protocols were signed that totaled about $ 10.1 billion US, referring to 31 agreements involving 22 countries and regions. Of these, approximately one third involved companies from Macao and Portuguese -speaking countries, consolidating the influence of the region in this context. Protocols cover areas such as transport, energy, water resources, construction and renewable energy. In addition to the signatures, the event promoted more than 200 commercial contact sessions, of which more than 70 had the participation of companies from Macau and Hengqin, noting a growth of more than 30% compared to the previous year.
The success of the IIICF also reflected in the diversity of promoted initiatives. The project “Premiere@Macau” proved to be one of the most prominent moments, with the presence of renowned companies, including 11 listed at Fortune Global 500. 30 new products and technologies were presented that reinforce Macao's position as an infrastructure innovation center, in a strategy that aims to enhance the influence of the city and promote opportunities in the international market.
The event program also included traditional contact scholarships between investment and infrastructure construction companies, which facilitated the approach between public and private entities, promoting business opportunities and strategic partnerships. In addition, guided tours were made to historic neighborhoods of Macau, in a strategy for promoting business tourism and economic diversification, reinforcing the integration of the event with the city's urban and cultural dynamics.
 
Enhanced connectivity
 
International participation was significant, with more than 3,500 professionals from more than 70 countries and regions, including high representatives of governments and sector entities. The presence of nearly 70 ministerial level leaders stressed the forum's relevance on the global infrastructure agenda. The theme of this edition, “improved connectivity for mutually beneficial cooperation” guided more than 250 thematic activities, which included forums, exhibitions and technical exchange sessions.
Following the event, those responsible highlighted four main results. Fang Qiuchen, president of Chinca, stressed the presentation of global trends and the reinforcement of international cooperation, as well as the dissemination of reports that guide the sector. Vincent U, president of IPIM, referred to the consolidation of four strategic chains: innovation, synergy, results transformation and industrial development. According to U, the event contributed to the generation of estimated revenues of about 20 million patacas for the convention and exhibition sector, as well as enhancing high -level business tourism in Macao.
According to IPIM, entrepreneurs from different regions expressed satisfaction with the results of participation in the event. Representatives from Lusophone countries, particularly, highlighted the role of Macau as a contact platform with Chinese companies, having been able to establish agreements in areas such as Information Technology and Electrical Engineering. Local companies, for their part, value the opportunity to expand international cooperation networks and internationalize their business.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:56:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Man detained by alleged homicide of the woman with a cleaver</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/homem-detido-por-alegado-homicidio-da-mulher-com-um-cutelo/</link><description>An elderly resident was arrested on suspicion of killing his wife, with whom he had been married for 50 years. The cause was the dissatisfaction with the dinner the woman had prepared. The man, according to the Judiciary Police, attacked the woman with a cleaver, causing at least 16 head and neck injuries, causing her death. The tragedy that took place on Friday was denounced by his daughter, who after returning the house in Nam Van, discovered the couple lying and bloody on the floor.
 
The Judicial Police (PJ) has detained a 74 -year -old man on suspicion of 71 -year -old woman's murder. The investigation points out that the suspect conflicted with his wife for being dissatisfied with dinner, and eventually attacked the woman with a cleaver. The victim died after suffering at least 16 injuries.
According to the authorities, the two had been married for about 50 years and had frequent discussions for little importance. The couple lived with their daughter in a housing located on Panoramic Avenue of Lake Nam Van.
The case happened last Friday afternoon, at 16h, when the two again had a discussion in the kitchen due to the meal that the woman prepared. During the discussion, according to the PJ, the man took a cleaver and struck several blows to his wife, hitting her mainly on his head and neck, making her fall to the floor.
The daughter returned home around 4:40 pm on the same day and found her parents lying and bloody in the living room near the kitchen, having immediately called the police. The couple was sent to the Conde de São Januário hospital center, and the medical staff confirmed that the woman had died even before being sent to the hospital.
The forensic exam found that the victim had injuries caused by at least 16 blows, especially in the head and neck, with fractures exposed in cervical vertebrae, skull and left shoulder. Preliminary analysis says that fatal injuries were on the back of the head and neck, but the exact cause of death is still awaiting confirmation by the forensic pathologist.
The PJ proceeded to an investigation at the home where a large amount of blood stains was found on the floor of the living room and the kitchen, and a timing and scissors stained with blood was found in the kitchen washbasin.
The suspect also had several superficial head lacerations, which did not need to be sutured. It received medical treatment for mild injuries and was taken to the police station for police investigation.
Asked if the detainee had admitted the commitment of the crime, the PJ only said that the individual "cooperated in the investigation", but added that there is "strong evidence" that show that the man "had assaulted his wife with a white weapon and caused his death."
The authorities also stressed that the suspect was in stable mental conditions, and that there was no previous record of the couple's complaints to the police due to discussions or aggressions. Police also refused to reveal whether the two had received psychiatric treatment or if they had medical history because they are a matter of privacy. The suspect was sent on Saturday to the prosecutor on suspicion of committing the crime of qualified homicide.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:53:52</pubDate></item><item><title>New Coordination Center for Burlas Fighting “Optimize” PJ's work, says Wong Sio Chak</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/novo-centro-de-coordenacao-de-combate-as-burlas-vem-optimizar-trabalho-da-pj-diz-wong-sio-chak/</link><description>In the secretary's monthly message for Security, released yesterday, Wong Sio Chak addresses the new facilities and technologies of the recently restructured Judicial Police Coordination Center, and admits the softening of burla crimes in the territory. Still, it appeals to the population: "Cooperation between police and citizens is the key to achieving a united community against circumvents."
 
Wong Sio Chak warned of the need to reinforce the strategies for preventing and combating circumventing crimes, in a note that highlights the work done by the modernized coordination center to combat the Judiciary Police (PJ), which is already in full operation.
In the monthly message published on the Secretary's Office Portal for Security, the ruler begins that the measures implemented by the authorities and the conscientialization of the public have contributed to the trend of increasing cyber burlas and using telecommunications since last year.
Nevertheless, Wong Sio Chak points out that “the public still needs to be aware of the constant change of fraudulent schemes”, which have been adopting new - and more “sophisticated” - ways of action. For example, the secretary states the case of a Burla use of artificial intelligence recorded in April (the first ever in the territory) and the “more than 100 people” victims of fraudulent telephone calls between early April and mid -May.
In order to improve its ability to respond to these cases, PJ inaugurated last May a modernized version of the Coordination Center to Combat Burks, which is already fully operational after an experimental period. The center's latest structure, originally conceived in the second half of 2022 and updated in April 2023, includes more advanced facilities and technologies designed to sensitize the public regarding the potentialities of artificial intelligence.
In the publication of the Secretary's Office for Security, it is read that the space has “four large functional zones”. The first corresponds to the “situation command zone”, in which real-time trends, statistical data and characteristics of the cases of burla are displayed, “thus materializing the concentration of management and data analysis”. The “specific dissemination and education zone” focuses on crimes that resort to modern technologies, providing 'malware' demonstrations and an interactive deepfake experience in which the face mutation process is simulated.
The Center also has a public call calls of the public, for reporting or consultation of information, which enables the immediate involvement of local banks in the payment block process. Finally, there is a multimedia room with filming and production equipment, where advertisements and anti-bubble information dissemination work are filmed.
The Secretary for Security says that PJ will “gradually organize” visits to the Center, intended in the first phase the “anti-bullshit ambassadors” of higher education institutions and various game companies, thus reconciling the functions of “visit” and “teaching”. Wong Sio Chak also points out that collaboration with counterparts from abroad-for example, through the interpol payment mechanism of “I-Grip”, in which 195 countries and regions participate-promotes “a narrower police cooperation” and therefore more effective in combating cross-border throws.
The "optimization" of the burla analysis models, which now combine "a large data visualization panel" with the information submitted through the open line, will have already had repercussions on the fraudulent so -called Macao. According to information presented by the official, "after two accurate repression operations, the cases of this genre have reduced almost zero since late May."
“The center is fully operational, providing more favorable conditions for PJ to advance deeply in the implementation of an integrated model prevention, recovery and combat against burla crimes”, reinforces Wong Sio Chak, adding that the maintenance and optimization of these results also depend on the awareness of citizens and the diffusion of anti-Burla messages between family and friends. "Cooperation between police and citizens is the key to achieving a united community against burlas."</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:54:53</pubDate></item><item><title>President of South Korea asks the north “recovery of lost time”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/presidente-da-coreia-do-sul-pede-ao-norte-recuperacao-do-tempo-perdido/</link><description>The president of South Korea yesterday proposed that the North "recover the lost time and peace" to build a common future, on the anniversary of the first intercorean statement since the division of the peninsula.
 
Lee Jae-Myung said the "June 15 declaration" in 2000, "was the starting point for overthrowing the confrontation and distrust walls that lasted more than half a century and inaugurating a new era of reconciliation and cooperation."
The document “Injected hope for peace in the peninsula and showed that the shared prosperity between the north and south was possible,” Lee wrote, in a message published on Facebook social network.
So-South Korean president Kim Dae-Jung and North Korean leader Kim Jong-il (father of current leader Kim Jong-un) signed the statement after a three-day summit.
A quarter of a century later, relations between the two Koreas have been at their worst moment since the end of the Korea War (1950-53).
Lee yesterday echoed the return "to a period of coldness similar to that of the past," with the interruption of dialogue and exchanges between the two neighboring countries, and appealed to the resume of the promise of peace emanating from that statement.
"We will turn the" risk to Korea "into" value for Korea "and together build a future in which both Korea can prosper," proposed the South Korean leader, who pledged to interrupt "unnecessary hostile acts" and resume dialogue and cooperation. "We will work quickly to restore suspended intercorean communication channels and rebuild the crisis management system to reduce military tension and promote a peaceful environment," Lee said. "We can overcome current challenges by joining forces and combining wisdom," he added.
The South Korean president added that he will work "to inaugurate a new era in which all the people of the peninsula can coexist peacefully and prosper."
A recent series of conciliatory gestures of the new Government of Lee and also the United States, after more than five years of frozen dialogue, increased expectations.
The most significant was the suspension, starting on Wednesday, of the advertising transmissions in altifalantes along the border, to which Pyongyang responded by turning off their own devices.
South Korea had resumed the transmissions in June 2024. North Korean altifalantes operated intermittently since July.
On Saturday, Lee Jae-Myung also expressed opposition to the sending of leaflets against the Kim Jong-un regime to the north, an act that he said he will penalize. "The government has already stated that the illegal distribution of anti-Pyongyang pamphlets should be interrupted as it can endanger the safety of border residents and aggravate military tension on the Korean peninsula," said presidential spokesman Kang Yu-Jung, cited by the South Korean public news agency Yonhap. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:56:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong and Beijing launch the first joint national security operation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/hong-kong-e-pequim-lancam-primeira-operacao-conjunta-de-seguranca-nacional/</link><description>China's authorities in Hong Kong and police from the former British colony carried out a joint operation, with searches in homes of six suspects of collusion with foreign forces to endanger national security.
 
China's authorities in Hong Kong, along with local police, launched the first joint operation, with searches in homes of six suspected collusion with foreign forces to endanger national security.
A statement from the Hong Kong police did not disclose the identity of the six people suspected of violating, between November 2020 and June 2024, the National Security Act imposed by Beijing in 2020.
The agents also searched an organization's office and seized documents, namely bank documentation, and electronic devices, for later investigation, according to the statement. The six people were required to deliver the travel documents to the police.
Beijing's national security arm in Hong Kong also requested assistance from the city's National Security Police, including to schedule interviews with the people involved in the case, police said. But the local police force did not reveal details about the accusations or the identity of the organization involved, stating that the investigation was still underway.
The operation took place hours after the release of an interview in which the Hong Kong Secretary of Justice defended the reinforcement of the legal framework through the new National Security safeguard law, passed in May by the local parliament. "We want citizens to face this protection as a natural responsibility, an integral part of our identity as Chinese citizens," said Paul Lam.
The new legislation allows the court of mainland to be given the judgment of national security -related crimes, including betrayal and sedition.
Infringements to the standard can be punished with fines up to $ 500,000 from Hong Kong and prison penalties of up to seven years.
Article 23 of the new law provides for crimes such as betrayal, insurrection or collusion with external forces to endanger national security, and may be punished with life imprisonment.
The reform was the subject of criticism from foreign governments and international organizations, which warned of the beginning of a “new era of authoritarianism” and the weakening of the principle of one country, two systems governing the two special administrative regions of Hong Kong and Macau.
Quoted by Chinese China Official Journal, Paul Lam argued that the National Security Act, imposed by Beijing in 2020 after a year of pro-democracy protests, was crucial to “restoring the stability” of the region.
The legislation “collected legal gaps without compromising the rule of law” and stated that several educational institutions “integrated national security in their curricula”, which classified as undeniable progress. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:56:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan considers China's “unacceptable” accusations of Air incident in the Pacific</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/japao-considera-inaceitaveis-acusacoes-da-china-sobre-incidente-aereo-no-pacifico/</link><description>The Japan Defense Minister has classified as unacceptable China's accusations that account for Tokyo for a dangerous approach between military aircraft from both countries, which took place over the weekend. "Chinese statements presenting Japan as responsible for the incident are unacceptable," said Gen Nakatani, adding that Tokyo has already communicated his position to Beijing.
On Thursday, Beijing accused a Japanese Air Force plane of having adopted dangerous behavior after a nipponic Defense Ministry spokesman declared that Chinese fighters approached “less than 45 meters and at the same altitude” from Japanese aircraft.
According to Tokyo, a Chinese fighter followed a Japanese patrol plane on Saturday for 40 minutes on high sea. The next day, two J-15 fighters repeated the maneuver for 80 minutes. "We do not consider that it has been dealt with a mistake," said Japan's self-defense forces, Yoshihide Yoshida. "Since it lasted 40 minutes and then 80 minutes, in two consecutive days, we understood that it was a deliberate act."
China Lin Jian Foreign Ministry spokesman rejected this version of events. "The source of these risks to maritime and air safety is in the nearby surveillance by Japanese ships and aircraft, directed against China's normal military activities. China urges Japan to end this dangerous behavior," Lin said.
In response, the Japanese Defense Minister stated that Japanese forces must, "through surveillance and alert operations, demonstrate Japan's will and ability to determine any attempt at unilateral" status quo "by force."
On Tuesday, Tokyo revealed that, for the first time, he observed two Chinese aircraft carrier to navigate simultaneously in the Pacific, including in Japan's exclusive economic zones (ZEE).
According to the Japanese Ministry of Defense, these naval and air operations, described by Beijing as “routine exercises”, illustrate the expansion of Chinese maritime military activities.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:56:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Association concerned with economic impact due to the end of the satellite casinos</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/associacao-preocupada-com-impacto-economico-devido-ao-fim-dos-casinos-satelite/</link><description>The Macao Economic Association warns of the negative impact on society due to the closure of satellite casinos by the end of the year, which mainly affects employment and commercial activities in community neighborhoods. The institution maintains a forecast of “stability” in the economy over the next three months, but admits that Macau faces pressure on internal demand as the high cost of living and the slow growth of wages retains the desire for consumption of the population.
 
Macau Economic Association maintains “stable” economic perspectives for the territory in the coming months, but draws society's attention to some “latent structural concerns”, namely the lack of internal demand and the impacts brought by the closure of satellite casinos in the short future.
According to the Prosperity Index report released monthly by the Association, Macau is still in a “critical period of transition and uncertainty”, although economic indicators remain stable.
"With the end of several satellite casinos by the end of this year, there may be greater pressure on the commercial viability of some community neighborhoods. According to recent unemployment rates and the number of people employed, pressure on employment has increased slightly and there may be signs of subtle changes in the job market," he noted.
The analysis elaborated by the economist and former deputy to the Legislative Assembly Joey Lau also pointed out that the “persistence of a high cost of living, the slow growth of wages and the shortage of housing supply” reduced the will of consumption of residents and exerted pressure on internal demand, which negatively affects local economic evolution.
“Residents are looking for savings much more about credit, reflecting the lack of incentives for consumption and market investment, as well as the difficulty in actually converting capital to real economic power,” can be read in the document, justifying the fact that the resident loan/deposits ratio has fallen to 50.9%, the lowest level in the last ten years.
He also added that the Macao real estate market continues to weaken, with the residential real estate price index to go down to 203.6 points in April this year, being close to the minimum value of the last three years, which highlights “the weak desire to acquire home and the lack of confidence in investment”.
The expired credit ratio, which reached 5.7% in January this year, and the total amount involved, recorded a decrease for three consecutive months. However, the economic association has stressed that the two indicators are still oscillating at a high level and do not show any significant signs of slowdown.
The Macao Economic Association has pointed out that economic performance reveals a relatively pessimistic trend globally, noting that international oil prices rose rapidly after the Israeli attack on Iran last Friday.
"The world markets of gross oil and gold recorded a dramatic fluctuation as a result of tensions. Sudden conflict not only increased tensions in the Middle East region, but also triggered a widespread concern on the international community regarding the impact on regional security and the world economy," he emphasized.
Thus, the analysis recalled that the world economy is currently under a downward pressure and international organizations have been successively lowering their predictions of economic growth.
It is recalled that the International Monetary Fund (IMF) lowered its expected world economic growth from 3.3% to 2.8% by 2025 and to 3.0% in 2026, the two lower levels from the epidemic.
According to the document, the World Bank also indicated that, due to the impact of commercial barriers and tariff conflicts, the expected global economic growth to 2025 was again reviewed at 2.7% at the beginning of the year to 2.3%. "Almost 70% of economies have seen their low growth predictions, implying the weak dynamics of the world economy and the increase in uncertainties in the internal and external environments," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:52:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Inaugurated Cuppa Coffee at Studio City</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/inaugurado-cuppa-coffee-no-studio-city/</link><description>The new Cuppa Coffee space was inaugurated on Saturday at Studio City. This is “a new paradise for coffee and pastry lovers,” says the group. In addition to this new store at Studio City, there is currently one at Macau Square, is also open this year.
Cuppa Coffee has opened its first store in Macao in 2008 and, in the last 17 years, has become a “popular brand between expatriates, locations and tourists, being considered one of the most traditional and authentic Portuguese and pastry experiences in Macau,” adds that this new store now takes Cuppa Coffee Products and Services to Cotai, “The Heart of Entertainment and Style Central Macao's life ”.
In a statement, the company points out that “Cuppa Coffee presents a mix of quality, creativity and community, providing an inviting and unforgettable experience of coffee and pastry”.
Quoted in the press release, Nicole Massa Helm, director and shareholder of Cupa Coffee, said: "We are excited to continue to be part of the vibrant culture of Café de Macao and share our passion for exceptional coffee with the community." João Encarnação, director and shareholder, stressed that the team "worked tirelessly to create a space where people can enjoy an excellent Portuguese coffee and pastry shop in a welcoming environment."</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:44:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Gansu intangible cultural heritage exhibition inaugurated at the Macau Museum</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/exposicao-sobre-patrimonio-cultural-intangivel-de-gansu-inaugurada-no-museu-de-macau/</link><description>The exhibition “Genesis and Spirit - Gansu 2025 intangible cultural heritage show was inaugurated on Saturday at the Macao Museum. The show is evident until July 13, featuring Qingyang fragrance sachets, linxia brick sculptures, Dunhuang colored sculptures, sculpted bright cups and other works.
In the press release, the Cultural Institute (IC) says that the purpose of the exhibition is to “deepen the exchange and cooperation between China and Macau in the field of intangible cultural heritage and actively play the role of 'a base' in promoting excellent traditional Chinese culture”.
Located in the Yellow River, the province of Gansu is an important stretch of the old silk route, where several cultures converged and mixed, giving rise to a “rich variety of intangible cultural heritage, with strong regional characteristics and ethnic diversity”, reads in the IC statement.
This heritage, which has been continually accumulated, transmitted and developed, has become a "treasure for the Chinese nation." The series of genesis and spirit activities is held until July 13, and has thematic exhibitions, performances, demonstrations of artisanal techniques and experimental workshops, displaying residents and tourists the rich and diverse intangible cultural heritage of the Gansu province.
Today, like what happened on Saturday and Sunday, there is also a demonstration of handcrafted techniques and sales of intangible cultural heritage products at the Macau Museum, where Gansu transmitters will present the essence of the techniques incorporated into the intangible cultural heritage of their province, allowing the public to experience the inheritance and creativity of this intangible cultural heritage.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Chief asks Chinese Academy of Social Sciences to support Macau's “Stability and Development”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/chefe-pede-que-academia-chinesa-de-ciencias-sociais-apoie-estabilidade-e-desenvolvimento-de-macau/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai met last Friday with Gao Xiang, president and secretary of the Chinese Academy Party Leadership Group of Social Sciences and director and secretary of the Chinese Academy Party Committee of History. During the meeting, the Chief Executive said the Chinese Academy of Social Sciences will continue to “offer more valuable suggestions on the diversified development of local industries and other important topics, in order to jointly promote the stability and development of the city”.
The boss also recalled that, "being a superior institution in the country in the area of ​​social science study and research," the Chinese Academy of Social Sciences has been conducting exchange and cooperation with Macao Higher Education Institutions in the areas of Social, Cultural and Human Sciences Studies and Research, "constantly contributing to the development of MSAR."
Quoted in a government statement, Sam Hou Fai said that the Executive and all social sectors of Macao are dedicated to the “preservation and continuity of the diverse characteristics of Macao culture, taking advantage of the advantages that meet Chinese and Western cultures, with a view to promoting greater cultural and human exchange at the international level”.
Thus, “the Chinese Academy of Social Sciences and the Higher Education Institutions of MSAR can jointly take advantage of the Macao platform, to promote opportunities and spread the excellence of traditional Chinese culture and thus tell the stories of Macao and China well,” said the chief executive.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:48:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Consulate (re) remembers fifth centenary of Camões with book and exhibition by Sara Augusto</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/consulado-relembra-quinto-centenario-de-camoes-com-livro-e-exposicao-de-sara-augusto/</link><description>Luís de Camões becomes the central figure of June with the launch of “The Vast Empire of the Heart”, anthology and photographic exhibition of Sara Augusto about the poet's presence in Macao's literature. The inauguration will take place at 6:30 pm on June 18, Wednesday, at the Consulate General of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong.
 
The book “The Vast Empire of the Heart”, by Sara Augusto, will be presented this Wednesday at 18:30 at the Dr. Stanley Ho auditorium of the Portuguese Consulate-General in Macau and Hong Kong. The photographic exhibition that accompanies the work will be inaugurated on the same day and will remain patent to the public by the end of the month, in the chancelaria of diplomatic representation, between 9:30 and 18:00 of business days.
Still inserted in the celebrations of the 500th anniversary of the birth of Luís de Camões, celebrated in 2024, the work brings together records of literary texts of Portuguese writers who passed, lived or live in the territory where the poet himself will have resided, for two years, in the mid -16th century. Through poetic clippings signed by authors who leaned over Camões - such as António Couto Viana, whose poem “Camões painfully” lent one of her verses to the title of anthology - the author creates a mosaic of tribute to the maximum exponent of Lusophone letters in Asian territory.
The parallel photographic exhibition continues this exploration, focusing on the great physical monument to the writer in Macao: the Camões Cave, described in a statement from the Portuguese Institute of the East (IPOR) as an “emblematic place where a small bust of the poet became a point of literary pilgrimage”. It was in this cave that Luís de Camões will have finished his most distinct epic, "The Lusíadas", although there are no concluding proofs of his stay in Macao - the image of the lonely poet in the cave was therefore imagined by Almeida Garrett in the poem "Camões", 1825.
The photographs, also by Sara Augusto, thus capture “the essence of a space that is, at the same time, mythical and deeply human”, where the poet's bust materializes as a milestone of tribute and tourist interest between the nebula history and the romantic legend.
The one notes that Sara Augusto's project "celebrates not only the power of the Word, but also that of imagination and time, which transform poetic and not poetic places into eternal symbols." At the same time, a legacy is solidified that “remains alive in the collective memory of the region” and “continues to inspire generations, transcending borders and eras” with its literary excellence, rich in “universal themes, innovative poetic forms and a decisive contribution to the Portuguese language”.
The initiative is supported by the Portuguese Consulate-General in Macao and Hong Kong and the mission structure of the celebrations of the birth of Luís de Camões, inserting this year's program for “June, Portugal's month at MSA”.
Sara Augusto is a photographer and Portuguese professor at the City of Macau. As a researcher, she has developed projects under Portuguese literature and presented works at conferences, congresses and meetings, both in Portugal and abroad.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Cambodia appeals to the International Court in border dispute with Thailand</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/camboja-recorre-a-tribunal-internacional-em-disputa-fronteirica-com-tailandia/</link><description>Cambodian Prime Minister Hun Manet announced yesterday that he asked the International Court of Justice (TIJ) to resolve a different border with Thailand, a day after a meeting between leaders from both countries.
 
Hun Manet wrote on the social network Facebook that “Cambodia presented an official letter to the International Court of Justice to find a solution to the border dispute” about four areas in dispute with Thailand. "Cambodia only needs justice, impartiality and clarity in the demarcation and delimitation of borders with our neighboring countries, so that our future generations do not continue to have problems with each other," he added.
On June 2, Hun Manet had already indicated that the Kingdom would file a complaint to the Tij about a border conflict that he described as "fed by small extremist groups in both countries."
On Friday, the prime minister stated that his government was waiting to find out if Thailand would join Cambodia in this appeal to the TIJ.
On Saturday, negotiations between Thailand and Cambodia, in Cambodian capital, Phnom Penh, resulted in progress, according to the Thai Foreign Ministry, and are expected to continue in the coming days.
A Cambodian soldier was killed on May 28 during a shooting in a place known as “Emerald Triangle”, a common border zone between Cambodia, Thailand and Laos.
Thai and Cambodian armies agreed to soothe the tensions the next day, but Phnom Penh decided to keep their troops in the area despite bangacoque removal requests.
The Thai royal army has taken control of the "opening and closing" of all border passages with Cambodia, invoking a "threat to Thailand's sovereignty and security."
On June 7, the authorities of the Thai province of Chanthaburi (east) explained that they had “temporarily suspended” the passage of tourists at two permanent border posts.
However, they specified that trade was not affected and that Cambodian workers were still allowed to enter Thailand.
Deputy Prime Minister and Minister of Defense, Phumtham Wechayachai, considered it “deeply unfortunate” that Cambodia rejected the proposal to remove their armed forces.
Cambodia and Thailand have long been in conflict on the stroke of their border of more than 800 kilometers, largely defined by agreements celebrated during the French occupation of then Indochina.
In 2011, clashes around the Preah Vihear Temple, classified as a world heritage by UNESCO and claimed by both countries, caused at least 28 dead and tens of thousands of displaced people.
Although the TIJ has attributed to Cambodia the contested zone below the temple in 2013, the layout of other areas continues to oppose Bangkok and Phnom Penh. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:56:13</pubDate></item><item><title>China condemns and calls for an end to Israel's attacks against Iran</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/china-condena-e-pede-fim-dos-ataques-de-israel-contra-o-irao/</link><description>China condemned Israeli attacks against Iran and appealed to Israel to stop military activity against the Islamic Republic. China's permanent representative in the United Nations said Israel "caused massacres in Iran and damaged nuclear facilities in the country."
 
Chinese authorities were against Israeli attacks against Iran and appealed to Israel to stop military activity against the Islamic Republic during an emergency meeting of the UN Security Council.
"Increasing tensions in the region will not benefit anyone and we appeal to Israel to stop the attacks on Iran," said China Ambassador to the Security Council, Fu Kong, quoted by Iranian IRNA official news agency.
China's permanent representative in the United Nations said Israel "caused massacres in Iran and damaged nuclear facilities in the country." Fu referred to the attacks launched by Israel at dawn against military and nuclear facilities in Iran that caused at least 78 dead and 320 injured, according to Tehran authorities.
In the attacks, according to IRNA, the Chief of Staff of the Armed Forces, Major-General Mohammad Bagheri, the commander of the central headquarters of Khatam-AL ANBIYA, Major-General Gholam Ali Rashid, and the commander of the guards of the Revolution, Major General Hossein Salami.
Physicist Mohammad Tehranchi and nuclear scientist Fereydoon Abbasi, as well as civilians were also killed. "According to the Israelite authorities, these attacks will continue. China condemns these actions that violate Iran's safety and territorial integrity," said the Chinese diplomat.
Fu warned that the attacks “will have serious consequences”, which did not specify, and that the aggravation of tensions in the region “will not benefit anyone”. "We appeal to Israel to end the attacks and that all parties respect international law," he insisted.
Fu Kong said China was “very concerned” about the direct effects of the attacks on the diplomatic process of Iran. “China has always supported diplomacy and opposed unilateral actions,” he said.
Fu also defended respect for the right of Iran, as a signatory to the non -nuclear non -proliferation treaty, to use nuclear technology for peaceful purposes. "There have been conflicts for a long time in the Middle East and the situation remains critical. The international community should seek to obtain a ceasefire in Gaza, a crumbling in the region and the prevention of tensions and conflict climbing," he said.
Fu Kong appealed to "countries with influence on Israel," an allusion to the United States, to play "a constructive role." "The UN Security Council must play the role of Guardian of Peace," he added, according to the Iraqi agency.
Following Israelite attacks, Iran launched hundreds of missiles and drones against Israel that caused at least 22 injured, two of which are in serious condition, according to Telavive authorities. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:56:03</pubDate></item><item><title>China tests in real high speed train that can reach 400 km/h</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/16/china-testa-em-linha-real-comboio-de-alta-velocidade-que-pode-atingir-400-km-h/</link><description>China began last week the first real line tests of the new CR450 high speed train, fully developed in the country and designed to reach an operational speed of 400 kilometers per hour, local press reported.
The tests, with a scheduled duration of about 15 days, take place in the Wuhan-Yichang section of the newly settled Wuhan-Chongqing-Chongdu line in Hubei's central province, considered adequate to validate technical performance without interfering with regular rail traffic.
The train left on Thursday of Yichang Norte station, having traveled the route to several speeds to collect data on acceleration, braking, stability and energy consumption, within the scope of what is designated as a “type test”.
Although the maximum speed in commercial operation is 400 km/h, the CR450 is designed to reach up to 450 km/h in test conditions, in an attempt to exceed the current technical limits of the Chinese high speed network, set at 350 km/h.
The CR450 represents an evolution of the fuxing model, the first high -speed train fully developed in China without resorting to foreign technology. It is part of an innovation program started in 2018, supported by the current five -year development plan of the Chinese government, which defines the country's strategic and economic priorities to five years.
Project technical objectives include maintenance of energy consumption levels and noise similar to those of the models currently in operation, despite the increase in speed.
If the tests are successfully completed, the new train will be able to go into commercial service from 2026, according to experts from the China Institute of Rail Sciences.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 04:56:03</pubDate></item></channel></rss>