<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/09/ruben-amorim-e-manchester-united-em-digressao-de-final-da-epoca-na-asia/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Shanghai and Shenzhen bags rise 1.58% and 0.64% despite Trump's ultimatum</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/09/bolsas-de-xangai-e-shenzhen-sobem-158-e-064-apesar-de-ultimato-de-trump/</link><description>The reference rates of the Shanghai and Shenzhen scholarships yesterday advanced 1.58% and 0.64%, respectively, after US President Donald Trump threatened to apply additional 50% rates on China products.
 
The Shanghai bag earned 48.97 points to 3,145.55, while the Shenzhen bag rose 60.18 points to 9,424.68, after falling 7.34% and 9.66%, respectively, on Monday, with the intensification of commercial tensions between the two largest economies in the world.
On Monday, these markets had evaporate accumulated gains since last September, when the economic stimulation ads of the Chinese authorities have led the index to maximums not seen since 2023.
Chinese state investment platforms have announced an increase in their participation in scholarship funds (ETF) and state -owned companies, as part of their efforts to stabilize Chinese financial squares.
China Chengtong Holdings Group, under the purpose of the Council of State Assets Supervision and Administration, said yesterday that their financial branches expanded their positions in these active. China Reform Holdings, another state investment company, has issued a message to express confidence in market prospects and its intention to act as strategic capital with “a long -term approach”.
These shares joined an initiative announced on Monday by the Central State Investment Fund Huijin, which said he recently increased his participation in ETF and would continue to do so.
The Chinese authorities expressed yesterday "firm condemnation" of the "black belief" of the United States and ensured, in a statement, that the contracted announced last Friday by Beijing are "completely legitimate" and "aim to protect their sovereignty, safety and development interests, and maintain a normal international commercial order." "If the United States remains stubborn to go this way, China will fight to the end," the Chinese Ministry of Commerce warned.
The president of the European Commission, Ursula von der Leyen, asked yesterday to "avoid climbing" following the customs imposed by the United States during a telephone conversation with Chinese prime minister, I read Qiang. According to a community executive statement, during the call, “the president appealed to a negotiated solution to the current situation, underlining the need to avoid a new climb. Von der Leyen also pointed out the vital importance of stability and predictability for the world economy.
In response to the widespread disturbance caused by United States customs rights, the leader of the community executive stressed the responsibility of Europe and China, “while two of the world's largest markets” of supporting a solid and retired commercial system, fair and based on equitable competition conditions.
He also recalled the urgency of structural solutions to rebalance bilateral trade and ensure better access to European companies, products and services to the Chinese market.
Finally, Ursula von der Leyen reaffirmed with the Chinese prime minister the Firm support of the EU to just and lasting peace in Ukraine, noting that peace conditions must be determined by Ukraine. He invited China to intensify his efforts to contribute significantly to the peace process.
 
Beijing criticizes remarks from the US Vice President on “Chinese peasants”
 
China called the comments of the vice president of the United States, JD Vance, who stated in an interview that Washington was asking money to borrow from the “Chinese peasants” and then buy them the fruits of their work.
In an interview with Fox News, Vance defended President Donald Trump's commercial offensive, who shook the world economy by introducing customs rates, in particular against China, despite fears of global repercussions and criticism within his own party. "We borrow money from Chinese peasants to buy what Chinese peasants produce," Vance said.
A spokesman for the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs said yesterday that "China's position on Sino-American economic and commercial relations was clearly expressed." "It is surprising and sad to hear such ignorant and unkind words from this vice president," Lin Jian said at a press conference.
The vice president of the United States said he saw this measure as an antidote to the "globalist economy," which, in his opinion, is not working for the benefit of the American people. "This is not a method for economic prosperity. It is not a method for low prices, and is not a method for good jobs in the United States of America," added Donald Trump's right -hand man.
Since its inauguration in January, Donald Trump has applied an additional 20% surcharge to Chinese products entering the United States. This surcharge is expected to increase to 54% on Wednesday. In response, Beijing has announced that it will impose 34% rates on US products from Thursday. The president of the United States threatened to increase rates by another 50% if Beijing maintains his decision. Lusa
 
BOX
 
White House says products from China can reach 104%
 
North American tariffs on Chinese products are expected to make a total of 104%if Beijing maintains the response to President Donald Trump's measures, the White House said. If Trump materializes the latest threat, imposing an additional 50% tariff, Chinese products will face an additional 104% tariff when entering the United States, taking into account the cumulative taxes announced by the US head of state since returning to power in January. Donald Trump threatened to impose an additional 50% tariff on China if Beijing does not withdraw until Tuesday the rates he imposed on US products in retaliation of the Washington tariff plan. For the Associated Press news agency, Trump's threat raises new concerns that the alleged effort to rebalance the global economy could lead to a trade war. The words of the US President, released on social networks, emerged after China indicated that he will retaliate against US tariffs announced last week. The new taxes will be added to 20% rates, such as punishment for fentanyl trafficking, and the additional 34% rates announced last week. This can not only increase prices for US consumers, but you can also give China an incentive to flood other countries with cheaper products and look for deeper partnerships with other business partners, according to multiple market analysts.</description><pubDate>2025-04-09 04:08:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Cunha Foundation receives a conference on the International Financial Action Group</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/09/fundacao-rui-cunha-recebe-conferencia-sobre-o-grupo-de-accao-financeira-internacional/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation will host today a conference entitled “Gafi Legal Statute in the International Order” at 6:30 pm on the book “The Legal Status of the Financial Action Task Force in the International Legal System”.
The event, organized under the “Reflections on Afternoon” cycle and spoken in Portuguese, will be attended by author Ilda Cristina Ferreira and moderator Paulo Cardinal, both jurists and teachers at the University of Macao Law School.
In a statement, the Rui Cunha Foundation clarifies that the seminar intends to streamline a discussion about the International Financial Action Group (Gafi, or FATF in the original English acronym), an organization “responsible for setting international policies and standards in combating capital laundering, financing terrorism and proliferation of weapons of massive destruction, and the occurrence of other threats to the integrity of the world financial system”.
The professional path of the invited speaker Ilda Cristina Ferreira, centered on international law, allowed him to witness the “gradual metamorphosis” of the “complex and multifaceted organization, whose legitimacy is impaired by the lack of clarity as to its legal position”.
Thus, the Conference proposes to analyze the “evolution of the legal status” of this intergovernmental organization, reflecting on “the long -reaching impact of its policies and measures” and its ability to respond “to global trends and threats that pose a risk to the international financial system”.
It will also be analyzed "the way members, not members, international organizations and other interveners accepted them and implemented, without a thorough examination (weights and balances) and without questioning their legal status."
According to the foundation's note, the seminar “has special relevance” for an audience of political, academic decision makers, professionals in the areas of law, lawyers, regulators and students. The seminar, with free admission, will also have a live online broadcast.</description><pubDate>2025-04-09 04:08:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Caeal warns that schools should maintain a neutral position</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/09/caeal-avisa-que-escolas-devem-manter-posicao-neutra/</link><description>The Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) held a clarification session on the elections from September 14 to the educational sector, which was attended by 200 people. In this session, Seng Ioi Man, president of Caeal stressed that public schools should maintain a neutral position, such as their employees while performing their tasks, and cannot proceed to electoral advertising during the time or in the work space.
The president of the body also explained that the electoral law does not specifically regulate private schools in the field of electoral propaganda, so these subjects must be decided and applied by the private educational institutions themselves, "but always in accordance with the law and carried out within the period of electoral propaganda."
Kong Chi Meng, director of the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ), was also present at this session and said that “teaching is an important part in the implementation of mission and social responsibility, so the sector must strictly comply with the regulations of the electoral law and their instructions, to safeguard that elections take place in a fair, impartial and full environment”.
The official said that the DSEDJ "will continue to improve civic education" and said that teaching materials will elaborate for schools to use, "in order to deepen their knowledge of elections for the Legislative Assembly, as well as their rights and duties as voter, and promote equity in elections." CAEAL will install a vote meeting replica, before election day, so that educational institutions organize study visits to the site, "allowing students to better know the voting procedures, which is a civic duty."</description><pubDate>2025-04-09 04:08:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Fire Department registers falling occurrences in the first quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/09/corpo-de-bombeiros-regista-queda-de-ocorrencias-no-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>O número total de acções operacionais dos bombeiros decresceu 6,32% em comparação com o mesmo período do ano passado. Tanto as saídas de incêndio e de primeiros socorros como as operações de salvamento e os serviços especiais registaram diminuições homólogas significativas. Tal como nos anos anteriores, os curtos-circuitos, falhas mecânicas e o esquecimento de fogões acesos continuam a ser os motivos mais frequentes para a ocorrência de incêndios.
 
The Macao Fire Department (CB) revealed yesterday, in a press release, which fell to a total of 13,207 cases in the first quarter of the year, representing a 6.32% drop compared to the same period of 2024.
Between January and March this year, the homologous variation rate decreased in all operational services carried out by firefighters. The total of fire exits fell 15.35% over the first three months of last year from 254 to 215 cases. Within this number, 155 cases - ie 72.09% of the total - corresponded to occurrences that dispensed with the use of hoses (compared to 204 cases in 2024), while 35 were related to burnt food (almost half of the 61 cases recorded last year).
The CB statement clarifies that, in the first quarter, the fires were due mainly to the forgetfulness of lit stingers, the flames not fully extinguished and the burning of incense, candles or votive papers. The short circuits of electrical installations and mechanical or equipment failures were the most frequent reasons, representing 63.72% of fire exits.
Regarding first aid exits, using ambulance, there was a decrease of 365 cases (or 3.1%) compared to last year, and 11,409 occurrences were recorded in the first three months of this year. Firefighters attribute this year's numbers to a “reduction in cases of slight indisposition, fever and difficulty breathing”. As for output data, the figures released by CB show a 3.3% decrease in rescue operations from 454 to 439 cases, and from 39.21% of special services, from 1,616 to 1,144 occurrences.
In the same statement, the CB reserves a word for security work that has boosted in community buildings, referring to 1,601 inspections in the period in mind. Regarding the control of hazardous substances, 1,582 security inspection actions were performed in industrial buildings, gas stations and food establishments, among others, in order to ensure the safety of storage and the surrounding environment.
In parallel, firefighters have often been organizing actions of dissemination and awareness to the general public, "in order to strengthen citizens' ability to respond in case of emergency." In addition to the “Fire Safety Training Course”, which has already trained 11,522 individuals until March, the CB also organized 155 disclosure activities; 38 lectures on fire protection, disaster prevention, emergency medical knowledge and fuel safety; 15 Evacuation and incident simulacros and seven stages of fire fighting.
The Fire Department states that it also continues to develop civil protection work in preparation for the typhoons, which this year is expected to start around June and extend by October. As the low areas of the region are the most affected, the authorities, under the coordination of unit police services, have remembered residents and owners of commercial establishments in these areas to prevent disasters and define evacuation plans.
In a note directed to the general population, the CB calls for citizens to maintain “good habits” to use electrical or gas equipment, “always paying attention to safety awareness, eliminating the risks and preventing accidents.” Schedule of gas equipment inspections at home can already be done since March 4, through numbers 89891373 and 89891374 or the electronic mail address *protected email *. In case of fire, the CB should be informed “as soon as possible” by the aid lines 119, 120 or 28572222.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-04-09 04:09:03</pubDate></item><item><title>DSEDJ wants to reinforce the “sense of identity” of young people before the country</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/09/dsedj-quer-reforcar-o-sentido-de-identidade-dos-jovens-perante-o-pais/</link><description>The Board of Education and Youth Services (DSEDJ) has announced that it will launch a series of activities within the 80th anniversary of China's victory in the war against Japan in 1945. The objective is to reinforce the “sense of identity” of young people before the country.
 
This year are the 80th anniversary of China's victory in the 1945 Sino-Japanese war. This is the pretext for the direction of Education and Youth Services (DSEDJ) to organize activities such as visits and exchanges, whose aim is to “deepen the knowledge of young people and students about the history of war against Japan and reinforce their sense of identity before the country and nation”.
The information left the ordinary meeting of the Education Council that took place on Monday afternoon. At the time, the representatives of the DSEDJ also indicated that the organization of the participation of teachers and students of higher education institutions and teaching staff and non -higher education schools will be organized in the volunteer work in the National Games. In this edition, it is recalled, some tests will take place in Macau.
DSEDJ also plans to launch the “Dynamic School Program”, with a view to “supporting schools in creating better conditions to increase the participation of Macau students in sports, cultivating good regular sports habits in them”.
At the meeting, the authorities also said that the general staff of the teaching staff of private schools of non -higher education and the statute of private schools of non -higher education for the creation and functioning of schools for the students of the HEGQin cooperation in Hengqin.
On the other hand, the DSEDJ said that the work related to the interim assessment of the general and long-term development of development of Macao (2021-2030) and the medium and long term planning of non-higher education (2021-2030) will be started and will be developed in the next phase, “with reference to the implementation of national policies and educational policies of neighboring regions, so that the planning of higher education and not higher education can correspond the development needs of Macao and the guidance of national policies ”.
On this occasion, LAM highlighted the implementation of the government by the “spirit of the important speeches given by President XI Jinping” and the commitment to establishing a “high quality development standard”.
The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture explained that the objective is to “encourage higher education institutions to optimize disciplinary planning in articulation with economic development, improve faculty development and reinforce cooperation with international higher education institutions at international level”.
In the future, he stressed Lam, “will be continued to optimize the education system and increase pedagogical quality” to “promote interdisciplinary collaboration and curriculum integration, closely monitor the needs of the current era and form excellent qualified frames, who love the country and macau and are equipped with an international view and innovative capabilities”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-09 04:07:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Government follows suicide cases to increase psychological support for residents</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/09/governo-acompanha-casos-de-suicidio-para-aumentar-apoio-psicologico-aos-residentes/</link><description>Health services ensure that they are accompanying and monitoring the situation of suicide cases in the territory and analyzing them based on the data collected related to gender, age, profession of victims and causes of suicide. In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Ho Ion Sang, the executive said that a three -level suicide prevention system was created and especially dedicated to young people, high -risk groups and individuals who tried suicide.
According to the government, the system includes the realization of educational dissemination actions on mental health with residents, especially to young people, also providing a tracking mechanism for high -risk groups and the improvement of the process of referring high -risk cases and the intensification of early intervention of mental disorders such as depression.
First psychological aid and social action intervention will also be provided to individuals who have tried to commit suicide. Authorities underlined that there is a case monitoring management mechanism, as well as mourning counseling services and other support services to suicide cases.
Last year in Macao, 91 people died as a suicide victim, the largest number of the last ten years, and, according to the secretary's statistics for security, a total of 249 people tried suicide. Among the suicide victims, 26 were under 34 years old, while more than half of the people who tried to commit suicide were young. It should be noted that the age group aged 15 to 24 stood out among suicide attempts, with 83 people last year. "The Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services will launch even more measures to support students and youth, so that they create positive values ​​and proactive attitude, as well as improve their ability to face adversities, which include increasing the dimension of the students' advice to the needs and reinforcing the team's functions in the identification, support and follow -up of students with needs," he said.
In the response, health services also revealed that the government will restructure the Commission for the healthy city and reinforce interdepartmental cooperation to decentralize resources to community neighborhoods to strengthen services and psychological support in schools and the community.</description><pubDate>2025-04-09 04:07:40</pubDate></item><item><title>"The position of neutrality [in Ukraine] has favored the image of China in relation to western ones"</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/09/a-posicao-de-neutralidade-na-ucrania-veio-favorecer-a-imagem-da-china-relativamente-aos-ocidentais/</link><description>The Macao Scientific and Cultural Center in Lisbon seeks to set a bridge between Europe and Asia and its educational service has the specific mission to connect to the Portuguese, organizing courses, workshops and conferences. Coordinating this area, researcher Ana Cristina Alves, who has been highlighted, over the years, in the study of Chinese culture and literature themes, says, in an interview with the final point, that nowadays, there is already a greater knowledge in Portugal in mainland, Macao and the rest of Asia. And it states that the neutrality assumed by the Asian giant, before the war in Ukraine, came to guarantee a better image.

 
What are the major objectives of the Educational Service of the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center?
I am currently in three areas: in educational service, museology and research. The CCCM has as its purpose and mission to establish the bridge between Europe and Asia. As we are very few, we work immensely, but work goes well. Run well with the spring conferences, for example - we are already in the fifth edition, with a first online, which was still during the pandemic (2021/2022). We are betting a lot on transforming the Macao Cultural Scientific Center into an aggregating hub of Asian Studies in Portugal. We have partnered with the Foundation for Science and Technology (FCT) and every year we opened a doctoral scholarships in the area of ​​Asian Study and will now open in May a new contest and, who is very interested in developing Asian studies, can compete for these scholarships. With this FCT partnership, the scholarships always have hours to give to the center and collaborate in all conferences, seminars and workshops. We currently have 40 scholarships.
 
These are the objectives of CCCM as an institution. But where is it specifically focusing on the area it coordinates, the educational service?
The educational service is concerned with establishing a bridge with the local community-with Portugal, with the Portuguese and the Portuguese-speaking countries. This does not mean that we will not seek Asian themes. We seek to organize workshops or courses. This year are some courses on the gutter. We have a translation of Chinese to Portuguese, in which I will be coordinator and trainer, in partnership with António Graça de Abreu, the distinct synologist from our square that has translated immense poets and ancient Chinese literature. We also have a Patuá course to take the bridge here with the Portuguese -speaking communities - if we can open it, we will already for the third edition. This Patuá course has among the trainers the researcher Raúl Gaião, who is very close to Patuá and will now launch a wide dictionary of Patuá (he had already released one and now the dictionary will have 2,500 pages, with cultural framing). We will also have a third course aimed at Japan and Japanese anthropology - I hope it is later this year, but if not this year, it will be in 2026. The concern is to serve the local community, but bringing outside. In addition, we do the wise conversations and in these we try to invite local local researchers or investigators who are working abroad, but come here and seek to publicize Asia's topics to the general public. We have a program with Radio Parish of Belém for the Community of Belém, the trip through the Macao Museum, where we visit the Museum [Macao Scientific and Cultural Center], but we also talk about themes related to Chinese culture and Macanese culture. Another program on radio is the wings of the language, which is Trilingual - I'm me, in partnership with Professor Álvaro Rosa, from ISCTE, who speaks Cantonense, and with Joaquim Pereira, who speaks Patuá. I present, in Mandarin, Chinese concepts and themes. Professor Álvaro Rosa introduces them in Cantonense and Joaquim Pereira does the same for Patuá. With this concern of serving the community of Alcântara, I teach at Senior Alcântara University, and I go to the fourth year of classes with them. In the first year it was Chinese culture and history of Macao, in the second year was Macao at Espaço Asia, in the third year was myths and legends of China and in the fourth year I give literature in Macao and China.
 
In this work of disseminating Chinese culture and Macao culture to the local community, over these years in which it has been involved, have you noticed a greater knowledge in Portugal?
I think the community is approaching the themes of Macao, China and Asia and this is not only seen by adherence to workshops, the courses of the educational service, but also by adherence to spring conferences. The first edition was online and we had a lot of people. But then, on Monday, it was in person, there were very few people and, in the third, the auditorium was also perfectly empty, but on Wednesday we had many more people and on Thursday, this year, we had a lot more people. It is noted that, in fact, the center is able to reach the community.
 
In Portugal, Chinese culture, in particular, and Asian, is still a slightly distant reality. What consider being the main challenges for greater interest?
Sometimes these distant cultures, both Macao and China's, and those of the various Asian cultures, appear as a distant reality where people like to inform themselves here and there, but do not like to study in -depth. It is necessary to move from this first phase of superficial knowledge to an increasingly profound knowledge. This is well done with the distribution of scholarships, with the creation of more courses, workshops, wise conversations and conferences. Note that this center is increasingly a research center. At this point, we already have two center researchers, one main, which is Dr. Isabel Pina, and another assistant, which is me, and besides, we have 40 pockets in partnership with FCT. It is to make people really interested, but they are in -depth interest in the themes of Asia. People have to bring people closer to serious research, such as giving people the opportunity to contact people and we can give this opportunity for a more academic point of view, but we can also open spaces for cultural dialogue with more movie shows or even the creation of a theater group - I know this is being done, for example, through Joaquim Pereira in connection with the Casa de Macao Foundation.
 
There have always been many preconceived ideas in Portugal regarding China. Do you feel that in recent years this has been changing?
There was strong prejudice regarding China and Asian countries - not for Japan, because Japan profits our western values, especially from the end of World War II, not regarding India, which is considered the largest democracy in the world, with more or less quotes. But in relation to China, where it does not prevail, in the western eyes, a democratic system, but a meritocratic system, is different. Of course, the Macau scientific and cultural center has helped precisely because, when we know, we approach and, if we do not know, we move away. There were problems, much of them for ignorance of Chinese reality and Chinese cultural reality. Today, the image is better and not only due to the scientific and cultural center of Macau. It is also because, in the War of Ukraine, China has maintained a position of neutrality. The neutral position has favored China's image regarding Western. There was a lot of idea that the Chinese were very opaque, they did not know each other, but now, with these positions of neutrality, it is seen that the Chinese are not in the world to assault. At most, they are here to expand economically, but not politically, nor trying to impose their political values ​​- that is, practicing a policy of non -interference in the other states and, therefore, the image has improved. Of course, then, with cultural knowledge, which we promote through the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center, is another aid for the construction of a positive image of the Chinese in the West.
 
Over the course of more than three decades, it has been dedicated to the field of research, especially Chinese culture. What projects do you have at this time in hand?
For over 35 years I have been investigating, above all, Chinese culture, but I have expanded and expanded the study to Macau and also to Japan, which is a culture that I like particularly. What I have developed is an research project that began in early 2025 with the University of Macao: the translation of a great classic from Chinese to Portuguese literature, the work “Pilgrimage to the West”.
 
Author of “The Woman in China”, has long dedicated to this theme. Is the role of the woman from Continental China and in Macao changed?
Regarding gender studies, I think that, whether in China or in the West, there is always a great way to go. In fact, there was a great improvement from the nineteenth and twentieth century of the Women's Statute. The woman has a very active social role and now it is not just a social role, but a very active political role, especially in the West, but there are still discrepancies, namely in salary terms. Discrepancies are not at the level of public institutes, but in the private sector there are still many discrepancies between wages for men and wages for women. As for China, women in China went a long way and succeeded in the nineteenth century and then in the twentieth century, a good social parity. From the political point of view, it is enough to look at television and, when he sees the political consultative conferences of the Chinese people and the Chinese governments, are mostly consisting of men. From a social point of view, the woman is well and getting better. It possibly has the same problems as Western women, in terms of salary parity, but, from a political point of view, there is still a great way to get top and top places. In Portugal, we have more and more women in prominent places, but it is not yet totally level. In Asia, and namely in China, the woman already has a beautiful social prominence, already holds relief positions. In the business world, there are women who are examples of obvious success in professional careers, but then, in the political area, do not yet have that weight in China that is already starting to have in other western and European countries.
 
When it comes to women, is the reality of Macau different from the reality of mainland China?
It should be, because Macau is a special case of culture meeting. And, being a case of culture meeting, the fruit of this meeting of cultures will benefit from the Western Women's Statute, which will in principle a greater mobility in the statute of society. In principle, it should be different, but with the change to the Chinese administration, I do not know to what extent will not be a more Chinese model of social organization.
 
Do you already see evidence in this regard?
I am an optimistic. My great hope is that Macao, a special administrative region of China, until 2049, does not become completely Chinese in every parameters, but remains a culture meeting and, being a culture meeting, this will be reflected in the Women's Statute.
 
Looking at the research area, what would be the big themes that matter to China, in particular, and to Asian studies in general?
Who is as a main researcher at CCCM is Dr. Isabel Pina. She is of history and has always privileged the religious history of the Jesuits. The history of the Jesuits in the East is fundamental and Dr. Isabel Pina has played a key role. However, it would be excellent if this strong historical component of CCCM could be complemented, opening the area of ​​research also to contemporary studies. Note that the translation project I have has to do with classic studies and it is even good, because it does not contrast with the center's historical studies. It is time to begin to open the investigation into the contemporary world and our pockets have been precious to this. They have been dedicated to contemporary Asia, contemporary China, the new Silk Route, and have done immense work in this regard-good work on international relations and history, but more dedicated to the present. Take advantage of this impetus of new researchers to develop studies in the contemporary area. So that we approach today's China without fear. It is a very different cultural model from ours, which has given signs that it deserves respect, even for the policy of neutrality it has followed. If China had not followed a policy of neutrality, it had been a disgrace that had happened to us. There was a third world war.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>South Korean army fires warning shots to repel North Korean soldiers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/09/exercito-sul-coreano-dispara-tiros-de-aviso-para-repelir-soldados-norte-coreanos/</link><description>North Korean soldiers briefly crossed the Demilitarized Zone (DMZ) yesterday that separates the two Koreas on the eastern side, the South Korean army said, which responded to the incident firing shots into the air. The incident occurred at 17:00 local, when "about 10 North Korean soldiers crossed the military demarcation line in the demilitarized zone in the eastern front," said South Korean joint staff in a statement. The South Korean army issued a warning message and “fired warning shots”, which led the North Korean soldiers to return to the north, the command said by the Spanish news agency EFE. The Staff added that the South Korean Armed Forces were closely monitoring the North Korean Army movements "and taking the necessary measures in accordance with operational procedures." Military sources cited by the South Korean news agency Yonhap admitted that North Korean soldiers crossed the error demarcation zone.
It is the first incident of this type since several forays of North Korean soldiers in South Korean territory in June 2024. At the time, there are three identical episodes, with the North Korean soldiers crossing the demilitarized zone and retreating after warning shots were fired by the South Korean army. Incidents of 2024 were attributed to increased tensions between neighboring countries due to the presence of North Korean troops in areas near DMZ to put Minas, build anti-barriers and reinforce roads. South Korea has been in political crisis since former President Yoon Suk-Youol ordered the martial law on December 3, 2024, a decision that was annulled by Parliament. Yoon was arrested on January 15 on charges of leading an insurrection and was deprived of office in April. The Korea Peninsula, in the northeast of Asia, is divided between North Korea and South Korea, which crashed a war between 1950 and 1953. Pyongyang and Seoul remain technically at war, as they never signed a peace agreement, although an Armistitus allowed the fighting to cease.</description><pubDate>2025-04-09 04:08:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Representatives of Hong Kong's tourist industry visit Macau at the invitation of STD</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/09/representantes-da-industria-turistica-de-hong-kong-visitam-macau-a-convite-da-dst/</link><description>A group of 27 members of the Hong Kong Tourist Council for the day before yesterday, on April 7, a familiar visit to Macau, at the invitation of the Tourism Services (STD). The meeting aimed to deepen the cooperation between both regions in the area of ​​tourism, with special focus on regional tourism or with multiple destinations.
The Hong Kong delegation was received by representatives of the Macao tourist industry and the Substitute Director of STD Cheng Wai Tong. The meeting began with a working meeting, in which tourist operators in the neighboring region, headed by the chairman of the Hong Kong tourist industry, Tommy Tam, discussed Raehk Statute as an international attraction point for the entry of visitors in the Great Bay. According to a statement released yesterday by STD, topics were also addressed such as the joint promotion of “multi-desert” tourism, the use of tourist resources from the two neighboring regions and the potential for study travel development.
There was a lunch between 52 leaders from the Hong Kong and Macau tourist industry, which STD described as an opportunity for active cooperation between both parties. This joint action could happen, for example, “launching more tourist products and promotional plans, promoting mutual flow flows between Hong Kong and Macau” and “raising the characteristics of Hong Kong and Macao connection tourism”. After lunch, the Hong Kong entourage visited the Barra zone-where attractive points are located such as the A-MA temple or the Fortress of São Tiago da Barra-to “get to know the rich and diverse tourist resources of Macau.”
Hong Kong is the second largest visitors market in Macao, surpassed only in the interior of China. In February of this year, STD director Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes said that among the 35 million visitors hosted in Macao in 2024, 7.1 million came from the neighboring region. In a speech made at the time, it expressed the expectation that the bilateral cooperation of the two regions would continue to develop in 2025, further boosting the “sustainable development of the tourist industry” in the Great Bay area.</description><pubDate>2025-04-09 04:07:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Inequalities contribute to the exclusion of women in Timor-Leste, says report</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/09/desigualdades-contribuem-para-exclusao-das-mulheres-em-timor-leste-diz-relatorio/</link><description>Inequalities continue to affect women in Timor-Leste which contributes to poverty and gender-based exclusion, according to a gender analysis report yesterday presented in Dili.
 
The report was made from the data of the 2022 population census and housing of the Timorese National Institute of Statistics with the support of various United Nations System Agencies.
The document states that early marriage remains a concern with 12% of women, aged 20 to 24, to have married before the age of 15 and 4.9% before 18.
According to the report, family aggregates headed by women, representing about 17.8% of the total, are poorer and the double care responsibility diminishes their economic opportunities. "The intersection between poverty, the exclusion of the labor market and the gender vulnerabilities underlines the continuous marginalization of women, especially those of the most disadvantaged groups," the document points out.
Although life expectancy at birth for women to be higher, 69.2 years, the maternal mortality rate remains high with 413 deaths per 100,000 births.
Only 59.2% of rural women received qualified childbirth assistance compared to 91.8% in urban areas, the report says. “These disparities are still shaped by variations in the level of maternal education and the richness of household aggregates,” can be read in the document.
Regarding education, the report release advances with more girls than boys attending primary, secondary and university education. But even with the increase in access to education, disparities persist in literacy with 33% of women to never have attended school, which reinforces generational cycles of poverty and marginalization.
The report points out that one of the “most critical factors that drives gender poverty is the weak participation of women in the workforce”.
The rate of participation in the workforce for women is only 29.7%, which means that for every 100 men working for only 70.9 women. "Women are disproportionately involved in vulnerable employment (50.1%), compared to men (39.2%), which may often be associated with lack of social benefits, lower wages and unsafe working conditions," the document stresses.
That disparity is even more aggravated by the traditional responsibility of care, which continues to be assumed by women and limits them in access to formal employment and economic opportunities.
For Timor-Leste Equality Secretary Elvina de Sousa Carvalho, the report is not just a statistical data set, but a “mirror that reflects reality”. "It shows us that despite important progress, there is still much to ensure that all women and girls can achieve their full potential in all dimensions of life," said the government official. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-09 04:08:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan and the United States will continue talks about tariffs</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/09/japao-e-estados-unidos-vao-continuar-conversacoes-sobre-tarifas/</link><description>Japan and the United States decided yesterday to continue talks about the fares imposed by President Donald Trump, Japanese Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba announced. The decision was made after a telephone conversation between Ishiba and Trump.
 
Ishiba told journalists in Tokyo that Trump "presented a honest view of the current US situation in the international economy," according to France-Presse (AFP) news agency. "Based on today's exchange of opinions. (…) The two parties decided to appoint members of the cabinet to take charge of the continuation of the discussions," he said.
Japanese companies are among the largest foreign investors in the United States and Ishiba has asked Washington to revise measures within the two parties.
The call was the first direct contact between the two leaders since Trump signed on Wednesday an executive order that imposed at least 10% rates on all imports for the United States.
Customs 10%tariffs came into force on Saturday, but will be increased from Wednesday to several dozens of US business partners, such as the European Union (20%) and China (34%). Japan was one of the most affected countries, with a rate of 24%.
The United States has been applying 27.5% tariffs on Imports of Japanese vehicles since the beginning of the month, 25% more than previously, according to the Spanish news agency EFE.
The Japanese automotive sector is one of the main pillars of the fourth largest economy in the world, directly or indirectly employing about 5.6 million people.
The vehicles represented about 28% of the $ 142 billion of exports from Japan to the United States in 2024.
Prior to contact with the US leader, Ishiba said in Parliament that Japan would present Trump a package of measures to obtain tariff relief. "We believe we have to present a package of measurements and we cannot do it in a fragmented way," he said, quoted by AFP. Ishiba admitted that the package could include Japan's participation in a pipeline project in Alaska.
In February, after talks with Ishiba in Washington, Trump assured that Japan would be a partner in the project. Ishiba also told deputies that it will be necessary to adopt identical measures to those of the Covid-19 pandemic, as loans practically without interest and without guarantees for small and medium-sized businesses (SMEs).
Sources linked to the subject in Tokyo told Japanese news agency Kyodo that the government is considering a supplementary budget for the current fiscal year with measures to mitigate the impact of tariffs.
Japan approved the general budget for the 2025 fiscal year, which began on April 1, just a week ago.
The main index of the Japanese bag, the Nikkei 225, fell almost 8%yesterday, similar to what has happened in the general markets. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-09 04:08:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Local consumers remain confident in the face of economic situation in general</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/09/consumidores-locais-mantem-se-confiantes-perante-situacao-economica-em-geral/</link><description>The University of Science and Technology of Macau has carried out an inquiry about the population's perspective for the economy and found that resident consumption confidence is still reinforced. The consumer confidence index recorded a slight growth in the first quarter of the year and is, for four consecutive quarters, on the scale of "confident". However, the inquiry left an alert about economic risks.
 
Macau's consumer confidence level recorded a slight increase in the first three months of this year of 0.85% and obtained 103.82 points, on a scale from zero to 200, revealed a quarterly inquiry developed by the Macao University of Science and Technology (Must). The indicator also represents an increase of 9.3% compared to the first quarter of last year of 94.97 points.
"The index of consumer confidence remained in the interval of 'confident', that is, above 100 points, for four consecutive quarters, which means that the basis of global consumer confidence was stabilized," the institution said.
Must interviewed 818 residents of Macao over 18 years old and analyzed in its study six detail parameters that make up the global index, of which two registered climbs and four had descents. Despite the growth tendency of the general index of consumer confidence, the inquiry stressed the concern that the sub -index related to the local economy is in a descending trajectory there are three consecutive quarters, “a change that suggests the need to maintain caution regarding risk factors inherent to the current economic conjuncture and future challenges”.
In this case, respondents attributed to the “local economy 'subsidiary 100.61 points, which represents a 3.14% decrease over the previous quarter of 103.87 points, while the' price level 'subscribe obtained 98.02 points, a reduction in quarterly terms of 2.32%.
The results of the survey also indicate that the 'investment in actions' subndice registered a 16.68% rise from 96.31 to 112.37 points, and the 'purchase of houses' was 100.22, an increase of 2.41% over the previous quarter. Already the classification of subsidies relating to 'standard of living' and 'employment conditions' verified a quarterly decrease of 0.21% and 0.76%, respectively, fixed at 108.3 and 103.39 points.
According to Must's presentation, the consumer confidence rate is an indicator that quantifies consumers' subjective perception of the economic situation, serving as a reference to predict economic and consumer trends in the short future.
"As we entered the first trimester of 2025, the complexity of the global external environment intensified and the severity of the situation became more evident. The dynamics of world economic growth continued to weaken, with significant differences in economic performance between major economies and greater uncertainty about infacting trends and monetary policy adjustments," he said.
The inquiry also pointed out that the economy of mainland China maintained a “globally stable” operating tendency and continued to advance on the road of “high quality”, trying to progress in the midst of stability. "However, it is still necessary to recognize the challenges of the current economic functioning, which include the need to reinforce the momentum of interconnected and overlapping interconnection and overlapping challenges of various types of risk and hidden dangers," read the inquiry report.</description><pubDate>2025-04-09 04:08:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Sánchez visits China for the third time in two years and in the middle of trade war</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/09/sanchez-visita-china-pela-terceira-vez-em-dois-anos-e-em-plena-guerra-comercial/</link><description>Spain Prime Minister Pedro Sánchez visits two of the countries most affected by new commercial rates announced by the United States, Vietnam and China to promote bilateral trade and investments.
 
In the case of China, it is the third time in just two years that Sánchez visits Beijing and will meet again with the country's president, Xi Jinping, as happened in March 2023 and September 2024.
This trip to Asia occurs a few days after US President Donald Trump has announced the intention of imposing and aggravating rates on products imported across the country, with China and Vietnam to be the most percentage: 34% and 46%, respectively.
The Spanish government has highlighted in recent days that Sánchez's visits to Vietname and China have been coordinated with the European Union (EU) and were already planned before Trump's announcements.
Sánchez's trip to Vietname and China is thus not response to the US trade war or "against anyone," the same sources said, who recognized, however, that the trip has acquired new relevance in the context of the last days.
Spain's aim is to diversify markets for export, as well as destination and origin of investments, but not replace the commercial relationship with the US, the Spanish government said. Spain has with Vietname and China a huge commercial imbalance, which aims to reduce.
According to official data, in 2024, Spain imported from Vietname 5.200 million euros and exported 530 million. In the case of China, imports rose to 45 billion euros and exports to 7,400 million.
Last week, the day after the announcement of the new US commercial fees, Sánchez accused Trump of starting an unjust and unjustified trade war against everything and against everyone ”and with a" unilateral attack. "
The Spanish Prime Minister has appealed to an EU response to negotiate with the US and the imposition of reciprocal rates, but also for the diversification of business partners, in line with the principle of “strategic autonomy of Europe” in which European leaders have insisted in recent years, especially after the Ukraine war started by Russia.
China “has to be a strategic partner in the future” and “regardless of the current situation compared to the United States,” Spanish Economy Minister Carlos Cuerpo, Luxembourg, said on Monday, arriving at a meeting of EU ministers with the Commerce Folder.
Cuerpo stressed that Spain has been "for several years to insist on the reinforcement of this relationship" with China. "Among other things because it helps us open a very important market and, moreover, it is a potential source of investments in our continent, in our countries," added the minister, who said Spain wants to "establish a strategic relationship with China."
Sánchez begins on Wednesday the first visit of a Spanish Prime Minister to Vietnam, which includes meetings with political leaders in the country and businessmen.
It arrives in China on Friday and has on the agenda meetings in Beijing, with Chinese president, Xi Jinping, Prime Minister, Li Qiang, and with Chinese businessmen.
The previous visit, in September 2024, coincided with a moment of tension between the European Union and China, because of Brussels' decision to advance with new rates on the importation of Chinese electric cars and the threat of retaliation in relation to European pig meat that Spain is one of the largest producers within the community bloc.
In addition to trade, Spain has attracted significant Chinese investments in recent years. According to official data from Spain authorities, Chinese companies have invested more than 10 billion euros in the country for the production of electric cars, along with other projects in the area of ​​batteries or electrolyzers (used in the production of the so -called Green Hydrogen). Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-09 04:08:07</pubDate></item><item><title>China has nothing to lose if rates increases another 50%</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/09/china-passa-a-ter-nada-a-perder-se-taxas-aumentarem-mais-50/</link><description>Beijing is approaching a point where there is nothing to be losing in the trade war with Washington, economists said after US President Donald Trump threatened to increase rates by another 50% over Chinese products.
“The profit margin of the Chinese export sector is between 30% and 40%,” wrote Dan Wang, director for China of the Think Tank) Eurasia Group. "If the United States imposes customs rates over 35%, most of its profits will be eliminated. The fact that the rates are 70% or even 1000% makes no big difference, as it prevents China from negotiating directly with the United States," he argued.
Since his inauguration in January, Trump has applied an additional 20% overflow on Chinese products entering the United States. This surcharge is expected to increase to 54% on Wednesday.
Wang explained that although Chinese exporters are now facing the new reality of a permanent increase in export costs, this does not mean that exports will stop. On the contrary, it forces exporters to find new markets and reduce the sending of goods directly to the US.
Alicia Garcia-Herrero, chief economist for the Asia Pacific region of the French investment bank Natixis, also minimized Trump's last threat. "The US market is already closed for Chinese products, at least directly from China to the US, so [an additional 50% of tariff increase] is not a [effective] threat," he said.
The decision reflects the fact that the US is aimed at China more than any other country, which "already happened before China retaliated," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-04-09 04:08:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Iim launches a new edition of the photography contest that explores the relationship between Macau and Hengqin</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/09/iim-lanca-nova-edicao-do-concurso-de-fotografia-que-explora-a-relacao-entre-macau-e-hengqin/</link><description>Macao and Hengqin will be the scene of a new edition of the “discovery of Macao and Hengqin” photography contest, a collaboration between public entities and local associations aimed at celebrating shared cultural richness between borders. In order to “reinforce the feeling of belonging” and explore the traditions that unite the two places, this contest invites photographers of all levels to capture the essence of the community. Open to residents and beyond, registration is open until September 26.
 
The photography contest “In the discovery of Macau and Hengqin 2025” stands out as a unique initiative of the International Institute of Macau (IIM), in order to celebrate and promote the cultural traditions of the region. Sponsored by the Macau Foundation, this initiative aims not only to give visibility to the various cultural manifestations that characterize Macau and Hengqin, but also reinforce the “feeling of belonging” and local identity, especially with young photographers.
The contest, which has been consolidated as a milestone in the region's cultural programming, expands its scope this year by including the attractions of the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin, such as Sumlodol Camping Park or the Novotown Complex. Contest organizers expect participants to use their artistic sensitivity and their view to portray Macau's essence, capturing not only their landscapes and historical monuments, but also festivities, daily habits and traditions that make up the rich cultural mosaic of the region. This invitation to visual exploration is also a way of encouraging a dialogue about the interconnection between past and present, and between the cultures that intertwine in Macao and in the surrounding regions.
The contest is divided into two categories. One for residents from Macao and one for participants outside Macao, which seeks to ensure wide participation of the community. Photographers are encouraged to present works that reflect significant aspects of their cultural identification and experience in the city, from a personal perspective, exploring topics ranging from historical architecture and immaterial traditions to new developments that emerge in the hengqin zone, built or to come. All works must be original and created between September 2024 and September 2025, and participants may use a variety of techniques, including digital photography and digital creativity, in order to expand the artistic possibilities.
Awards to be assigned include 5,000, 3,000 and 2,000 patacas monetary values ​​for the top three. In addition, honorable mentions will be granted in the amount of 500 patacas to some highlighted works. The organizers also foresee a special prize of 1,000 patacas for the best work presented by an AFDM partner, thus encouraging the active involvement of the members of this association. Following the careful evaluation by a jury composed of representatives of the various organizations involved, an exhibition will be organized that will highlight the award -winning works, providing a platform to share the different cultural narratives that emerge from this interaction between Macau and Hengqin.
Photographers interested in participating have until September 26 to submit their works.
The event is co-organized by the Macao Digital Photography Association (AFDM), Macau Heritage Ambassadors Association (MHAA), Halftone-Macao Photography Association and Macau Cable TV, with the collaboration of the Language and Culture Central Club and Cultuure Promotion Association (AJM), Language Exchange and Culture Promotion (Lecpa) (MACC).
The close collaboration between the institutions involved not only reflects a joint desire to promote local culture, but also to integrate Macau in the broader context of the region's visual culture, creating opportunities for new visual narrators to offer their perspective on this constantly evolving urban space.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Ruben Amorim and Manchester United in the end of the time in Asia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/09/ruben-amorim-e-manchester-united-em-digressao-de-final-da-epoca-na-asia/</link><description>Manchester United, by Portuguese coach Ruben Amorim, will tour Asia after the last game of the English soccer league, in the face of the need for “additional revenue”. The tour, the first one that the team will perform after a period end, predicts games immediately following the last matchday, at home play with Aston Villa, with the Red Devils playing in Kuala Lumpur on May 28 and Hong Kong on 30. The first clash will be with a team of 'stars' from Asia and the second against Hong Kong. According to the club, which counts on the team with Portuguese internationals Bruno Fernandes and Diogo Dalot, this “is a unique opportunity for games and technical team to be in contact with fans in Asia and the club to activate commercial value with the region's partners”. “Importantly, tour games bring significant additional revenue that will make the club stronger and allow us to continue to invest in success in the lawn,” said United CEO Omar Berrada. Ruben Amorim's team, who is 13th in the English League, is still on the Europa League test in the quarterfinals against Lyon and if he reaches the final of the competition on May 21 and winning, will have direct entrance to the Champions League.</description><pubDate>2025-04-09 04:08:40</pubDate></item></channel></rss>