<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/08/nba-invade-macau-com-cidade-do-basquetebol-de-14-000m%c2%b2-no-venetian/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>House prices fell to 2013 levels</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/08/preco-das-casas-caiu-para-niveis-de-2013/</link><description>The global housing price index in Macau is now at 194. This index has been falling since 2021 and only going back to 2013 has it reached such a low level. Economist Henry Lei believes that Macau's real estate market should stabilize by the end of this year.

House prices in Macau have been falling since 2021 and are currently at 2013 levels. According to data recently released by the Statistics and Census Bureau (DSEC), the global housing price index was, in the period between May and July this year, at 194.
Data published on the DSEC website, consulted by PONTO FINAL, shows that, in 2011, the index was at 100. Two years later, it was at 188. The price of houses continued to increase in the following years and between 2019 and 2021 it reached a peak of 266. From then on, the index has been gradually decreasing. The 2024 average was 215.5 and is now at 194.
These data show that “the real estate market is still in the process of adjustment and, together with the increase in the number of residential unit transactions in July 2025, this reflects that real estate developers are becoming realistic in setting the price of their units”, explains economist Henry Lei to PONTO FINAL.
DSEC figures also show that, in the second quarter of the year, 801 autonomous housing units were transacted, almost half of the 1,555 transacted in the first quarter. Consequently, the overall value of transactions fell from 7.3 billion patacas to 3.7 billion patacas. In the second quarter of 2013, 4,059 autonomous units had been transacted.
Henry Lei also says that the drop in house prices may reflect “the strong desire of some sellers, who accept lower prices compared to the market value and sell their apartments to obtain a greater financial flow”.
The economist also notes that the Macau real estate market hopes that the cut in interest rates by the United States Federal Reserve could be a “positive factor for property prices” in the territory. The American Federal Reserve (Fed) recently decided to cut interest rates by 25 basis points, to a range between 4.00% and 4.25%, for the first time since December 2024.
Another factor that could increase the overall housing price index in Macau has to do with the increase in gross gaming revenue. If the growth trend until the end of the year is between 6% and 10%, as several investment companies expect, “this will help support the stabilization of the Macau real estate market”, estimates the economist. Henry Lei believes that the Macau real estate market should stabilize by the end of this year.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 23:15:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Hospital das Ilhas performs 200 cataract surgeries per month</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/08/hospital-das-ilhas-realiza-200-cirurgias-de-catarata-por-mes/</link><description>Hospital das Ilhas began offering cataract ophthalmological surgery services in July this year and currently performs around 200 cataract surgeries per month. The institution revealed that it is planning to invite specialists from Beijing to Macau, at least once a quarter, to guide the most complex cataract surgical interventions.

Every month, around 200 patients with cataracts have surgeries at the Islands Health Care Complex, the medical institution revealed yesterday, which began offering ophthalmological cataract surgeries in mid-July this year.
The hospital, commonly known as Hospital das Ilhas, said it plans to invite experts from Peking Union Medical College Hospital in mainland China to Macau at least once a quarter to provide guidance on the treatment of a small number of the most complex and difficult cataract cases.
Despite being an institution that operates under a public-private partnership model, Hospital das Ilhas guaranteed that the medical service will give priority to Macau residents.
"Taking advantage of the century-old experience of Peking Union Medical College Hospital, the Macau Medical Center's ophthalmology team, in the next phase, will expand its services. Surgical capacity will be increased and the waiting time for cataract surgeries in Macau will be progressively reduced, thus improving the well-being of Macau residents", he assured.
In a press release, Hospital das Ilhas said it had recently invited a doctor specializing in cataracts from Beijing to perform cataract ophthalmological surgeries in Macau. According to the information, doctor Zhang Shunhua, from Peking Union Medical College Hospital, performed surgeries on 14 local patients with “highly complex cases of cataract”, all of which were completed successfully.
The institution stated that the cases included not only patients from the Macau Medical Center, but also those referred from the Centro Hospitalar Conde de São Januário (CHCSJ) due to the high surgical complexity. He highlighted that each surgery took an average of less than 30 minutes, “with 100% patient satisfaction reported in the first post-operative follow-up”, he pointed out.
In this regard, the hospital stated that it had been established, with Peking Union Medical College Hospital, a long-term mechanism that combines real-time remote consultations with regular on-site guidance.
It is recalled that Hospital das Ilhas announced the start of providing cataract treatment, with the collaboration of three main surgeons from the hospital itself and CHCSJ, to “respond to the needs of the population”. "The aging trend of the population in Macau is becoming increasingly evident. Many people over the age of 60 begin to experience a decrease in visual acuity, seeing everything 'blurry'. After ophthalmological consultations, they are diagnosed with 'senile cataract', a condition that requires surgical treatment", he explained.
According to the medical institution, for surgical treatment, on the day of surgery, patients, who meet the criteria for day surgery, can normally complete all procedures in less than three hours, which include handling formalities for hospital admission during the day, pre-operative preparation, surgery and completion of hospital discharge processes.
Hospital das Ilhas said it believes that the number of cataract patients treated will increase steadily in the future, with the advancement of the cataract surgery service and the optimization of treatment procedures.
Cataract is an eye disease characterized by the opacity of the crystalline lens, the natural lens of the eye that helps to focus images on the retina, causing reduction or loss of vision. According to medical research, the opacification or gradual sclerosis of the lens occurs naturally with aging, but the disease can also be caused by other reasons, including eye trauma, diabetes, inflammation and intraocular infections, among others. Currently, there are no specific statistics on the number of cataract patients in Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 23:18:50</pubDate></item><item><title>DSC employee obtained salary with fraudulent medical certificates, says CCAC</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/08/funcionario-da-dsc-obteve-vencimento-com-atestados-medicos-fraudulentos-diz-ccac/</link><description>The Commissioner against Corruption reported a case in which a doctor from the Correctional Services allegedly used fraudulent medical certificates to obtain medical leave, with which he earned, between 2018 and 2024, a salary of 150 thousand patacas. According to the investigation, this employee's practice was carried out in collusion with several doctor friends who work in public or private medical institutions.

The Commissioner against Corruption (CCAC) yesterday revealed a suspected case of fraud and document forgery carried out by a doctor who works at the Directorate of Correctional Services (DSC).
The investigation indicates that the employee, in collusion with doctors who worked in public or private medical institutions, obtained several fraudulent medical certificates for himself or his parents, between 2018 and 2024.
The CCAC explained that, through practice, the Civil Service doctor “managed, fraudulently, to obtain medical leaves from his service and to earn, for several years, a salary of around 150 thousand patacas”.
According to the results of the investigation, the doctor in question, despite the fact that neither he nor his parents were sick, previously contacted doctors, who were his friends and who work in public or private medical institutions in the city, for them to help with issuing medical certificates or proof of absences due to family supervision. Obtaining these medical certificates allowed the suspect to then deal with his private matters, on the days of medical leave.
The doctors who issued the certificates collaborated with the suspect so that he could obtain, through fraudulent means, authorization for absences due to illness from the service where he worked, even though they knew that the people in question were not sick, according to the CCAC.
Furthermore, it was found that the doctor in question worked part-time on a paid basis without the knowledge and consent of the service where he worked.
The case has already been forwarded to the Public Ministry and communicated to the respective services. According to the CCAC, in this case, the public service worker in question, the suspect's respective family members and the private entity doctors involved will have committed the crimes of fraud and document forgery provided for in the Penal Code. The DSC doctor and the public entity doctors involved will also face charges of the crime of forgery committed by an employee.
In a statement released yesterday, the CCAC recalled that several cases of abuse of the sickness absence regime by public sector workers have been detected in recent years. “The CCAC warns, once again, public service workers and health professionals to know and comply with the law, always keeping professional ethics in mind and not to abuse the absence regime due to illness”, he warned.
Last year, the CCAC detected three suspected cases of undue and prolonged absences due to illness, with the connivance of doctors, three former customs inspectors and one active customs inspector.
Since 2016, the suspects have resorted to medical consultations based on back problems or leg pain, thus obtaining medical certificates to justify their absences due to illness. They frequently entered and left Macau and went abroad to have fun on sick days, according to a CCAC investigation last year.

DSC REVIEWS MANAGEMENT MECHANISM
 
In response to the case, DSC assured that it immediately initiated disciplinary proceedings against the employee involved, collaborating with the CCAC investigation and cooperating with judicial bodies in monitoring the case.
DSC, in a statement, said it attaches “high importance” to the case and has already carried out a comprehensive review of the mechanism for managing absences from work due to illness, as well as reinforcing internal supervision.
According to the organization, the improvement of the management mechanism involves visits to workers' homes and checking their illness status together with Health Services professionals, with suspected cases of fraud being forwarded to the Health Services Health Board, in order to prevent the abuse of sick leave to obtain public funds.
DSC reiterates zero tolerance towards the practice of illegal acts or disciplinary violations by workers, stating that it ordered the heads of subunits under its supervision to reinforce supervision and required workers to strictly comply with the obligations inherent to the exercise of public functions.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 23:17:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macanese identity under debate at the Rui Cunha Foundation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/08/identidade-macaense-em-debate-na-fundacao-rui-cunha/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation will present today, at 6:30 pm, another session of the new cycle of conferences under the theme Being Macanese in the 21st Century – Culture, Tradition, Identity, Challenges, with the second round table entitled “The Art of Batê-Skirt”.
The session will be led by José Luís de Sales Marques, president of the Council of Macanese Communities, with guest speakers Maria Magalhães de Sousa and Marina Senna Fernandes, “two distinguished local representatives of the arts of confection, cake decorating and traditional cuisine”, says a statement from the Rui Cunha Foundation.
"Bâte Saia? Cuza São? What is that? Beating the skirt? What nonsense! Is it a mainato's work? They are all predictable expressions of astonishment for those who, not knowing what it is about, come across this advertisement! Well, 'bâte skirt' is a traditional Macanese decorative art, the dissemination of which will be the subject of this talk", adds the organizers' proposal.
Those present will learn, among other things, about “bate skirt”, an ancient local tradition of cutting out tissue paper or lace paper, initially to decorate baskets and cake trays, but which evolved into decorating dolls that decorated festive cakes on special occasions such as baptisms, communions, confirmations, weddings, birthdays, and other important events.
The event also aims to address “the way of life of the Macanese, the community or communities, in Macau and in the diaspora, and their daily challenges to maintain the being and feeling of the Macanese reality”, historically between two cultures: Portuguese and Chinese.
The purpose of the conference, and the next ones in this cycle, is a “constructive discussion looking at the present and the future, without forgetting the tradition and the different identity landmarks, especially Gastronomy and Theater in Patuá, both Intangible Heritage of the Macao SAR and the PRC”, according to the organizers.
The event will be held in Portuguese and has free entry.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>“Fado is music that has no borders and goes beyond language”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/08/o-fado-e-uma-musica-que-nao-tem-fronteiras-e-que-vai-para-alem-da-lingua/</link><description>Cuca Roseta has toured the world with his fado, with packed rooms in places as diverse as Spain, Brazil or even China. On October 11th, at 8pm, it is time to perform for the first time to the Macau public, together with the Macau Chinese Orchestra (OCM). In conversation with PONTO FINAL, the artist promises a night of dialogue between different cultures and sounds, without losing the essence of what makes fado the Portuguese genre par excellence.
 
Although some translators continue to argue that the word “saudade” is untranslatable, its definition goes beyond linguistic constraints. Even without subtitles or interpreters, any audience from anywhere in the world can understand what the fado singer's moving voice expresses, what the moans of the Portuguese guitar that accompany her convey. Words are unnecessary: ​​perhaps fado is the best translation of a concept that, after all, is universal.
Cuca Roseta, one of the most important contemporary fado singers, recognizes this transcendent power of the music she performs. He even calls it “medicine”; a balm in the form of a melody that purifies both artist and listener. Portuguese roots shaped this musical genre and made it an intangible symbol of a small country, but they do not define it, he says. More and more artists are writing, composing and giving a more current flavor to the content of their songs – and Amália Rodrigues was already incorporating different instruments and languages ​​into her music.
It is this nostalgic and contemporary fado, traditional and with open arms to the world, that Cuca Roseta presents in Macau this Saturday. The first concert in the territory took place in 2019 in video format, due to pandemic restrictions, and only heightened the desire to get to know an audience up close who, even on the other side of the globe, still shows “a great connection to Portugal”. The Macau Chinese Orchestra gives an oriental touch to poetry sung in Portuguese, deepening the ties between one part of the world and another. And, perhaps, there will even be space to leave a special “treat” to the Macau public, confides the artist.
Tickets for the show, taking place in the large auditorium of the Macau Cultural Center (CCM), are available for sale with prices ranging between 150 and 400 patacas.
This is the first time he has performed in Macau, after a video concert in the middle of the pandemic. What memories do you have of that show?
It was a very good concert... but, of course, it was in 2019. We always wanted to return to Macau and be able to perform in person. We received fantastic feedback from this concert, but we are very, very, very happy to finally be able to go to Macau. The Macau Chinese Orchestra also made our mouths water more.
What can we expect from this first live show?
As the previous one left a lot of desire to return in person, this one will certainly be much more special. We are preparing for that too. Last year we celebrated the 15th anniversary of our career in December and we did a special show for that moment, at Meo Arena [the largest event space in Lisbon, located in Parque das Nações], and therefore we took this concert around the world, which involves tradition, fado, but not only that. There are traditional songs from other parts of the country – for example, folklore and popular marches – and also, of course, the songs that have become more successful over the years. So we are very, very excited, especially with this fantastic orchestra [OCM].
 
The concert is described by the Macau Cultural Institute as “a fusion between East and West”. Does the alignment planned for October 11th reflect this idea? Were any of the songs chosen specifically for Macau?
I think this encounter between West and East has more to do with the fact that music from the West – the Portuguese tradition, in this case – is played by a Chinese orchestra, by musicians from the East, with typical instruments. Automatically, there is this fusion. We're still trying, but we'd like to try singing a traditional song so that this fusion would be even more beautiful. It would also be like a little treat that is left to the Macau public.
In September, I had already participated in the “Sentir Macau” tourist campaign in Lisbon. Do you think of fado as a bridge between the two cultures?
It’s true, I was part of “Sentir Macau”. I was invited to sing and it's really interesting to realize that there are no coincidences, isn't it? There is a bridge, yes; there is still a large connection from Macau to Portugal. I think there is still interest on both sides for culture, for tradition. I think there is a lot of curiosity among the Portuguese towards Macau and the Macanese towards the Portuguese.

He had already performed in several cities in China, such as Beijing or Shanghai. How do you think fado is understood on the other side of the world, far from its Portuguese-speaking origins? Is the melancholy of fado universal, capable of transcending linguistic barriers?
Fado is very well received in China. In fact, when we sang for the last time in Shanghai, it was a street concert, which had 2,500 seats, and sold out in 20 minutes. Therefore, not only is it a fantastic audience, which is extremely attentive and curious, but there is also an interest in different cultures. In this case, because of Portuguese culture. One of the phrases I say most often is that there are no borders for fado – which is why it has become an intangible heritage of humanity, right? Fado comes from a very small country, but it is a song that is valued and listened to all over the world, mostly by foreigners and not by communities. There is a bit of an idea that fado singers travel a lot around the world, but they sing for their communities. No, it's not the truth. Last year, we did a count of the different countries we sang for, and only two of them were for communities – Switzerland and France, and even then we also sang for the Swiss and the French – and the other 54 countries were for foreigners who understand absolutely nothing of the language. In China it was exactly the same: there were many people reacting to fado in a very emotional way. It is music that has no borders and goes beyond language. It's a feeling, a vibration, an energy... it comes from this nostalgic and Sebastianist culture, but it really goes from soul to soul, which touches a deeper place, not so mental or superficial. Although words and poetry are extremely important for fado and for those who sing it – and it is important that the fado singer or the performer is really moved by the truth of what he sings – on the other hand, that is enough. Just feel this truth that goes straight to your heart.
Cuca stands out in the contemporary fado scene for its modern vision, which often integrates other musical genres. Would you be interested in combining fado with traditional Chinese instruments?
I am very interested in combining fado with traditional Chinese instruments. I think this is beautiful. I really like fusions, always keeping to fado and roots. And I think these doors were already opened by Amália: we heard Amália sing in Italian, in Spanish, in English. She didn't just sing fado. Wherever she went, she also sang in other languages ​​and other musical genres, but her skin, her essence, was fado. I think the same thing is happening to me too. I went to Cape Verde to do a tour and I wanted to sing in Creole, for example, the mornas on each island. Then I went to Goa and wanted to learn some Konkani songs. I think it is always very interesting to maintain, obviously, fado, but to be able to sing one song or another in the places where we go, where people are open-hearted to receive our tradition... I think it is even a beautiful gesture, of gratitude, to create this fusion between the cultures that are interested in welcoming Portugal, in receiving the Portuguese tradition, and the fado singer who pays homage and thanks to this audience by singing or inviting musicians who bring a little of that country's tradition. This is something that I really enjoy doing and that I do often. I've sung in Russian, Hindi, Spanish, Italian, English. In Georgian, in Tbilisi. It's really nice to be able to always do this fusion.
Fado, despite being closely linked to tradition, has evolved a lot in recent years. Is it difficult to maintain this balance between the essence of fado and its modernization, with more experimental touches?
I think it's not difficult, it's not difficult to maintain the roots of fado. When it stops being fado, you immediately notice that it is no longer fado. Fado is something specific: it has that cadence, it uses many minor tones; it is this recitation of sung poetry, a story that is told about something that is true, that the performer must have lived. It's this closing of the eyes to look at the heart, this introspection, this depth... It's not superficial, it's not to show the dress and the clothes and the pretty face. It really is a song for someone who looks inside, at their heart, and shares all these emotions from a deep place to a deep place. Regarding the modernization of fado, I think that fado only adapts to the times it is in. Basically, it adapts through… not musically, musically it remains the same, but it adapts through new, more current lyrics, because nowadays many people compose and write. In the past, perhaps, there was talk of a more nostalgic, sadder, more melancholic Lisbon... about husbands leaving on boats and wives not knowing when they would return. Nowadays we sing about saudade and we sing about love, we sing about Lisbon, we sing about typical neighborhoods and traditional festivals, equally, but in a more modern way. Regarding the instruments, I think there is nothing very new. All instruments have already been used in fado. We saw Amália singing with an orchestra, and everything that happens will always enrich her. It's also very beautiful to go to the fountain, sing with just the Portuguese guitar and the viola. Maybe add a bass, some percussion… I think that just adds. It modernizes, in a certain way, but it takes absolutely nothing away from the essence of fado.
As one of the most important voices of the genre, how do you see the future of fado? Do you believe that concerts across borders – like this one in Macau – contribute to fado becoming a global musical language?
I see a great future for fado. By chance, I see it as very stable compared to the era we find ourselves in, because there are always many songs that come and go and fado remains the same. It is a tradition that is always alive. It's great to continue taking fado across borders, as Amália started to do. Fado continues to be a world music, which reaches more and more people, and for me it continues to be a bit of a music that is somewhere between devotional singing and performance. It is neither one thing nor the other. There is a cure; There is always a catharsis for those who sing fado and for those who listen to fado, even if they don't understand anything. I think there will always be a space for this music to travel the world. There will always be space for it to reach those who appreciate music and those who want to travel through this art that transforms, which becomes the sadness of a people, these sadness that become beauty and art and that inspire the world. They inspire and heal. Because this song, when people sing it… It's always a formula for opening lids that are closed. Emotional caps. It's always a cure, a moment of relief, of leaving behind something that no longer belonged to us. So I think there will always be a place for this medicine – I can call it medicine. There will always be open doors in the world and more places to take this song.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Floods caused by Matmo have already caused 10 deaths in Vietnam</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/08/cheias-provocadas-pelo-matmo-ja-causaram-10-mortos-no-vietname/</link><description>At least ten people have died and several are still missing in northern Vietnam as a result of the floods caused by Typhoon Matmo, which hit southern China on Monday before weakening, the Vietnamese Government declared yesterday.
Vietnamese Prime Minister Pham Minh Chinh yesterday visited the city of Thai Nguyen, capital of the province with the same name and the region with the highest number of deaths, with four fatalities and around 200,000 homes affected.
Knee-deep in water, the Vietnamese politician inspected the area and helped distribute humanitarian aid, according to information published on the government portal.
Authorities have mobilized more than 7,600 soldiers and volunteers for emergency relief efforts after the country was hit by seven severe storms since late August.
According to the provisional report, three people also died in Bac Ninh province — 30 kilometers northwest of Hanoi —, another two in Thanh Hoa province and one in Cao Bang province, on the border with China. Emergency teams are looking for at least two people in Thai Nguyen and another in Thanh Hoa.
The floods also caused significant losses to agriculture and considerable damage to infrastructure, while authorities warn the population of the possibility of landslides and river overflows in regions affected by the rains.
In Thailand, the rains caused by Matmo caused at least 22 deaths, and floods were recorded in around twenty provinces in the center, north and northeast of the country on Tuesday, affecting almost 370 thousand people, authorities reported.
Typhoons are recurring phenomena in Southeast Asia, when the warm waters of the Pacific Ocean favor the formation of cyclones.
At the end of September, Typhoon Bualoi left at least 58 people dead or missing in Vietnam and, at the end of August, Typhoon Kajiki killed seven people. In September 2024, the country was hit hard by Typhoon Yagi, which killed more than 300 people due to heavy rains and landslides.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 23:10:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Monetary circulation increased, but current deposits fell</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/08/circulacao-monetaria-aumentou-mas-depositos-a-ordem-tiveram-uma-quebra/</link><description>The money supply fell in August, says a statement from the Macau Monetary Authority published yesterday. Furthermore, it was also found that deposits and loans from residents decreased compared to the previous month.
Monetary circulation grew by 0.3%, but current deposits decreased by 6%, says the Macau Monetary Authority, adding that M1 decreased by 4.3%, compared to the previous month. On the other hand, quasi-monetary responsibilities remained unchanged, says the organization. The sum of these two elements, that is, M2, fell by 0.4%, reaching 835.2 billion patacas. The proportion of pataca (MOP), Hong Kong dollars (HKD), renminbi (RMB) and United States dollars (USD) registered “weights” of 32%, 44.8%, 6.5% and 14.3%, respectively, in M2.
Statistics from the Monetary Authority also indicate that resident deposits decreased by 0.4% compared to the previous month, reaching 813.8 billion patacas. Non-resident deposits, in turn, decreased by 7.1%, reaching 338.1 billion. On the other hand, public sector deposits in banking activity grew to 220.9 billion, representing a growth of 5.2%. In this way, total deposits in banking activity registered a decrease of 1.3%, reaching 1,372.8 billion. The proportion of MOP, HKD, RMB and USD in deposits was 19.4%, 45.2%, 8.5% and 24.9%, respectively.
Regarding internal loans to the private sector, the Monetary Authority states that they decreased by 1.1% compared to the previous month, reaching 501.9 billion. For now, loans abroad decreased by 9.1%, reaching 511.8 billion. As a result, the total volume of banking loans decreased by 5.3%, reaching 1,013.7 billion, while in MOP, HKD, RMB and USD, the “weights” were reached 21.9%, 44.2%, 10.4% and 20.2%, respectively.
At the end of August, the resident loans/deposits ratio decreased from the level of 49.4% recorded at the end of July to the level of 48.5%. For now, the volume that included the non-resident loans/deposits ratio decreased from the level of 76.9% to the level of 73.8%. Current assets to be calculated based on periods of one month and three months against liabilities stood at 61.2% and 55.9%, respectively. Furthermore, the overdue credit ratio increased to 5.4%, due to the decrease in total loans compared to the previous month, concludes the statement from the Macau Monetary Authority.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 23:13:58</pubDate></item><item><title>China and Singapore exchange congratulations on 35th anniversary of diplomatic ties</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/08/china-e-singapura-trocam-felicitacoes-pelo-35-o-aniversario-dos-lacos-diplomaticos/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping and Singaporean President Tharman Shanmugaratnam exchanged congratulations on celebrating the 35th anniversary of diplomatic ties between the two countries.
 
Stressing that China and Singapore are friendly neighbors and important cooperation partners, Xi Jinping said that in the past 35 years since the establishment of diplomatic ties, the two countries have adhered to mutual respect, mutual trust and mutually beneficial cooperation.
“The bilateral relationship has continuously improved and updated, with cooperation in various fields producing fruitful results,” said the Chinese leader, adding that both sides “have also advanced hand in hand in their respective modernization processes, bringing tangible benefits to the people of both countries.”
China is willing to take the 35th anniversary of diplomatic relations as an opportunity to further deepen political mutual trust, promote high-level cooperation, strengthen people-to-people exchanges and jointly safeguard the multilateral trading system and basic norms governing international relations, so as to promote the future-oriented high-quality comprehensive partnership between China and Singapore, further contributing to peace and regional and global prosperity, considers the Chinese ruler.
For his part, Shanmugaratnam indicated that, in 2023, Singapore-China relations "have been elevated to a high-quality, future-oriented comprehensive partnership, and cooperation between the two governments has continued to advance, constantly integrating new features and demonstrating foresight."
Responding to the challenges of the times, both sides have actively expanded cooperation into new areas, while the people of the two countries have strengthened cultural ties, Shanmugaratnam said, expressing a "firm belief" that the two countries will continue to work together, taking their bilateral relationship "to new heights."
On the same day, Chinese Premier Li Qiang and Singapore Prime Minister Lawrence Wong exchanged congratulatory messages. Li said China stands ready to further strengthen the alignment of development strategies with Singapore, deepen high-level cooperation in various fields and work together to uphold the multilateral trading system, so as to contribute to the development of both countries and the prosperity and stability of the region. For his part, Wong said that Singapore-China relations have continued to deepen over the years, with strong mutual trust built.
“Singapore is willing to continue expanding cooperation with China in various fields and jointly safeguard free trade and the multilateral system,” added the official, in statements published by Xinhua.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 23:11:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Coimbra and Macau academies create joint laboratory for aging</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/08/academias-de-coimbra-e-macau-criam-laboratorio-conjunto-para-o-envelhecimento/</link><description>The University of Coimbra (UC) and the Macau Polytechnic University (MPU) signed a cooperation agreement to create a laboratory dedicated to the study and development of solutions for aging.
The partnership establishes the “Joint Artificial Intelligence Laboratory for Healthy Longevity”, with a research center in Coimbra and another in Hengqin, revealed the UC, in a statement sent to the Lusa agency.
According to the Portuguese higher education institution, the central mission of the structure is “the development of innovative solutions that can slow down aging and improve the quality of life of the population, combining biomedical research with the potential of artificial intelligence”.
The laboratory reinforces the collaboration between UC and MPU, a partnership that has brought together several research teams in scientific projects, such as the Joint Laboratory in Advanced Technologies for Smart Cities, created in 2022.
During the ceremony that marked the launch of the new scientific structure, protocols were also signed to promote cooperation in teaching and mobility of students, teachers and researchers from the two academies.
For the rector of the UC, Amílcar Falcão, mentioned in the statement, the laboratory “means the internationalization of the knowledge of the University of Coimbra in the area of ​​aging”, with a global projection of the work developed by the UC in this area, through the Multidisciplinary Institute of Aging (MIA Portugal). In turn, the rector of the Macau Polytechnic University, Im Sio Kei, highlighted the objective of working together in health, with a special focus on healthy longevity, “since the University of Coimbra is very strong in this area” and the MPU “is very strong in the area of ​​artificial intelligence”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 23:18:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Cancer mortality rate has been decreasing in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/08/taxa-de-mortalidade-de-cancro-tem-vindo-a-diminuir-em-macau/</link><description>The Health Services held a press conference yesterday on the evolution of cancer in Macau. According to data from 2023, the number of fatal cases has been decreasing over the last decade, which authorities justify with greater awareness and population adherence to screening programs.

The results of the Health Services' annual report on cancer in Macau, for 2023, were analyzed yesterday at a Health Services press conference. In this presentation, those responsible welcomed the gradual decrease in the global mortality rate and the increase in the survival rate from cancerous diseases, calling on the population to continue participating in screening programs.
The Director of Health Services, Alvis Lo, began by recalling that cancer is the “main killer” in Macau, which is why the Macao SAR Government has attached “great importance” to the prevention and treatment of the disease. There are three action strategies outlined by the Executive: optimizing the medical services system, mobilizing community participation and promoting healthy behaviors.
The effects of improving this mechanism are reflected in statistics collected throughout 2023, which point to a decrease in the global mortality rate and an increase in the five-year survival rate, which rose from 59% to 62% in a decade. Alvis Lo stressed that one third of cancer cases are preventable and, as such, require increased public awareness. In this regard, he cited initiatives such as the Healthy Community program or the more than one hundred promotional activities promoted by the authorities, which reached more than 80 thousand people.
Still focusing on the topic of prevention, the director of Health Services said that the vaccination rate of the third dose against hepatitis B for children aged one year old was greater than 97%. At the same time, the administration rate of the second dose of the cervical cancer vaccine to girls up to the age of 15 exceeded 90% and therefore reached the global target set by the World Health Organization (WHO) for 2030.
Looking at the data on cervical cancer, it appears that incidence and mortality rates have fallen to 30% in the last ten years. Alvis Lo indicated that around 66% of women living in Macau were screened before the age of 35, although he draws attention to the need to undergo periodic screenings.

MORTALITY IN MACAU IS BELOW THE WORLD AVERAGE

At the same conference, Leong Iek Hou, head of the Center for Disease Prevention and Control, reiterated that cancer causes “almost 10 million deaths per year around the world”, mainly related to factors such as the aging of the population and changes in lifestyle.
According to the data presented by the person responsible, the incidence rate in Macau has seen growth similar to the international trend. However, this comparison with the general panorama brings good news for Macau: the mortality rate fell by 18% compared to the previous decade, placing it below the average for developed countries.
Breast cancer is the one in which there has been a most significant increase in the incidence rate, with an increase of 30% in the last five years. At the same time, vaccination against human papillomavirus (HPV) and the promotion of screening programs ensured that the incidence rate of cervical cancer fell by 34% in ten years.
The conference's third speaker was Lei Sao Kuan, an assistant family medicine physician in the Community Health Care Area, who focused specifically on colorectal and lung cancer. Regarding the first, the doctor warned that this disease tends to progress slowly, without significant clinical symptoms at an early stage, which makes early detection, diagnosis and treatment essential.
The colorectal cancer screening program, opened in 2016, has already mobilized around 35 thousand participants and enabled the detection of 230 malignant polyps and 175 cases of malignant tumors. The specialist highlighted that the majority of cases detected during this period were still in the initial phase. Appointments for screening can be made in person or electronically, in the “My Health” tab of the Macau Single Account.
When it comes to lung cancer, the most common in Macau, both smoking and exposure to secondhand smoke are the main risk factors. The doctor called on at-risk individuals – residents aged between 50 and 70 or those who smoke more than 30 packs of cigarettes per year – to participate in the lung cancer screening pilot project, implemented in 2019.
Oncologist Peng Xiang Hong concluded the conference with an overview of the current situation in the treatment of cancerous diseases and tumors in Macau. The specialist assured that the Macau region is “located at the top of Asia” in terms of the introduction of new anti-cancer medicines, allowing patients to obtain the most advanced medicines in the world “in a timely manner”.
The day hospital for cancer patients at Centro Hospitalar Conde de São Januário currently receives around one hundred patients per day, who can return home after medical care. Peng Xiang Hong highlighted that the fact that Macau is a small region – and, therefore, with a relatively concentrated distribution of health services – allows the follow-up rate for cancer patients to be greater than 95%. "Our objective is to restore the health of patients. If this is not possible, the second objective is to prolong life and improve the quality of life of patients", he stated. In addition to the various forms of treatment associated with cancer, such as chemotherapy or radiotherapy, the oncology doctor also highlighted the importance of psychotherapy for the well-being of cancer patients.

MACAU SINGLE ACCOUNT HAS NEW TRACKING PLATFORM

Chou Mei Fong, director of the Areia Preta Health Center, also announced that the Health Services will launch today a screening platform for various types of cancer through the Macau Single Account, in order to serve the population with increasingly comprehensive and efficient prevention mechanisms.
The platform will automatically adapt to the user's characteristics, indicating eligibility for certain screenings based on age and gender (cervical and breast screenings will not be presented to men, for example).
The official also said that, starting tomorrow, instructional videos will be made available on the Macau Single Account, in order to provide detailed guidance on how this new service operates.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 23:17:38</pubDate></item><item><title>European Union supports Timorese civil society with more than two million euros</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/08/uniao-europeia-apoia-sociedade-civil-timorense-com-mais-de-dois-milhoes-de-euros/</link><description>The European Union (EU), in partnership with several Timorese non-governmental organizations, yesterday launched three projects to strengthen the capacity of civil society to support vulnerable communities and monitor the implementation of public policies. "The EU and Timor-Leste share a commitment to ensuring a free civic space, because monitoring and advocacy by civil society organizations is essential for a free society like ours. We are pleased to partner with this coalition to improve development performance and accountability," said European Union Ambassador to Timor-Leste, Thorsten Bargfrede.
European Union partner civil society organizations include CARE, Oxfam, PLAN International, A-HAK, Caucus, Timor-Leste Women's Communications Forum (FOKUPERS), Timor-Leste Non-Governmental Organizations Forum (FONGTIL), Kdadalak Sulimutu Institute (KSI) and Mata Dalan Institute (MDI). European Union support, worth 2.2 million euros, will be distributed across three projects.
The first project, called “Strengthening Local Civil Society Organizations for Responsive and Accountable Governance in Human Rights and Gender Equality in Timor-Leste”, aims to improve the leadership, sustainability and advocacy capacity of civil society organizations.
The second project, entitled “Strengthening Civil Society to Promote Good Governance in Timor-Leste”, aims to achieve good governance of land and property by supporting women, young people and people with disabilities in matters of land rights. “Strengthening Civil Society for Diversity: Strengthening Civil Society Leadership to Improve Governance and Sustainable Development in Timor-Leste” is the third project, which focuses on working together with women, youth and vulnerable groups, including LGBTIQ+ people and people with disabilities, to support their work in promoting inclusive development, among others.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 23:10:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Fireworks competition ends on Saturday with displays from the UK and Brazil</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/08/concurso-de-fogo-de-artificio-termina-no-sabado-com-exibicoes-do-reino-unido-e-do-brasil/</link><description>The 33rd Macau International Fireworks Competition (CIFAM) will return on Saturday night with pyrotechnic companies from the United Kingdom and Brazil, who will light up the skies of Macau at 9:00 pm and 9:40 pm, respectively, in front of the Macau Tower.
Pyrotex Fireworx, from the United Kingdom, makes its debut at the event with a fireworks show scheduled for 9pm. The first show of the night will focus on the quality of design techniques, using a large amount of fireworks effects and high-quality products, organizers say. Under the theme “Luzes Câmara Acção – Cinema Night”, the exhibition will revolve around a series of soundtracks from famous films, with the integration of well-known dialogues from the films, taking the audience to the past and bringing them back to the present.
The Brazilian pyrotechnic company will also make its debut in Macau. The Vision Show presents at 9:40 pm a fireworks show entitled “Emotions in Every Look”, which combines different generations of music to remember the past and create emotions in the night sky, say the organizers. The company, which invests in progress, creativity and development of its team and technology, has achieved rapid growth in its reputation through participation in major events in Brazil and abroad.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 23:16:04</pubDate></item><item><title>NBA invades Macau with 14,000m² “basketball city” at the Venetian</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/08/nba-invade-macau-com-cidade-do-basquetebol-de-14-000m%c2%b2-no-venetian/</link><description>Macau becomes the Asian capital of basketball with the opening of the first NBA House in the region. The renowned project now arrives at Cotai Expo at the Venetian Macau and occupies an immersive space of 14,000 m², and brings five days of immersion in one of today's most popular sports. From October 8th to 12th, the mega-event also welcomes the arrival of six NBA giants, including Shaquille O’Neal and Stephon Marbury, in a series of free activities that combine basketball, technology and high-level games. 

The NBA (National Basketball Association of the United States of America) arrived in Macau in force, installing in the Venetian what appears to be a “basketball city”, a new concept of sporting experiences in the territory. The NBA House, which occupies 14,000 square meters at Cotai Expo, represents the largest initiative of its kind ever undertaken in Asia, offering free entry during five days of intense programming between October 8th and 12th.
The NBA House space stands out for its pioneering technological installations, according to the organizers, which includes a unique LED basketball fountain in the world where NBA elements are mixed with patterns inspired by the classic art of Chinese marble and the urban landscape of Macau. Visitors can also experience the NBA “Tunnel Walk”, which simulates players entering games, capturing instant videos to share on social media. For those more competitive, the NBA Replay Center allows fans to take on the role of professional referees, replaying classic moments from the games. The Brooklyn Nets and Phoenix Suns themed areas include endless rooms for photos and a sneaker vault specially set up for brand collectors.
One of the highlights of the event is the arrival of six living basketball legends in Macau, namely Shaquille O’Neal, Stephon Marbury, Tim Hardaway, Shawn Marion, Mitch Richmond and Deron Williams. These classic and current American basketball stars will be available for fan interactions, autograph sessions and opportunities to photograph them playing throughout the five-day event. The days on which they will be present at NBA House have not been indicated, which suggests extra attention should be paid to fans who want to meet them.
The parallel schedule includes the highly anticipated NBA China Games 2025, with two preseason meetings between the Brooklyn Nets and Phoenix Suns at the Venetian Arena. The first game takes place on October 10th, at 7:30 pm, followed by the second match on October 12th, at 6:30 pm. The Nets have a roster that includes 2023 NBA champion Michael Porter Jr. and pivot Nic Claxton, while the Suns have four-time All-Star Game selection Devin Booker and Jalen Green.
On October 11th, at 3:30 pm, the Venetian Arena hosts NBA Fan Day, an interactive event that promises to excite basketball fans. Four-time NBA champion Shaquille O’Neal joins singer Keung To and rapper MC Jin for a moment of sharing on stage. The program for this extra event includes skills competitions with Nets and Suns players, namely a triples contest, a midfield shooting challenge and a slam dunk contest with professional dunkers.

NEW LEVELS

NBA House in Macau follows the success of previous editions in Brazil, Canada, France, India, Mexico, the United States and the United Kingdom, but takes the concept to new heights, according to the organizers, through the integration of local cultural elements and the unprecedented scale of the event, once again in an attempt to position the territory as a premium destination for international sporting events.
Fans can register in advance for NBA House via the event's official website, guaranteeing priority entry at the three available daily times, between 11am and 2pm, 2pm and 6pm, 6pm and 10pm.
Tickets for the NBA China Games come with a range of options, from budget seats at 488 patacas to VVIP experiences on the floor at a surprising 24,888 patacas. The complete price list includes VIP Floor at 16,888 patacas, VIP at 5,888 patacas, A Reserve Floor (restricted view) at 3,888 patacas, A Reserve at 2,488 patacas, B Reserve at 1,688 patacas, C Reserve at 1,288 patacas and D Reserve at 888 patacas. VIP ticket holders and above have access to the exclusive “Hospitality Lounge” inside the arena and receive a commemorative game t-shirt at the Londoner's NBA Flagship Store.
For NBA Fan Day, prices vary between MOP388 and MOP4,988. Different types of tickets are sold through the official channels of Cotai Ticketing, Taobao 88VIP, Trip.com and MPay, with collection available from September 22nd at the Venetian Macau ticket offices. Children up to 3 years old are exempt from tickets, as long as they do not occupy seats.
NBA House takes place at Cotai Expo (Hall A) at the Venetian Macau. The space is open from 11am to 10pm, with the exception of the 9th, which closes at 3pm.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 23:08:45</pubDate></item></channel></rss>