<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/30/terceira-fase-de-captacao-de-talentos-facilitara-candidatos-com-experiencia-de-trabalho-em-portugal/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Air Macau updates A320 aircraft software after notification from Airbus</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/30/air-macau-actualiza-software-de-avioes-a320-apos-notificacao-de-airbus/</link><description>The Macau Civil Aviation Authority announced that Air Macau updated the flight control software for A320 aircraft, after Airbus asked customers to replace this software vulnerable to solar radiation.

“Following the notification from Airbus on November 28, 2025, which requested preventive software updates for A320 family aircraft, the Civil Aviation Authority (AACM) immediately instructed Air Macau to evaluate and resolve the problem”, reads a statement from the authority.
Following this request, the note continues, the flag airline of the Chinese semi-autonomous region “acted promptly, updating the necessary software on the affected aircraft” and “making the necessary adjustments in the rescheduling of affected flights, minimizing inconvenience to passengers”.
AACM will “continue to monitor the situation to ensure the operational safety of air services”, it concludes. According to the Chinese radio channel Macau Television, 12 Air Macau aircraft were affected, with “minor flight delays” expected.
Airbus announced on Friday the recall of approximately 6,000 A320 aircraft for the urgent replacement of flight control software, vulnerable to solar radiation, following an incident at the end of October in the United States.
In a statement, the aeronautical manufacturer said it had asked all airline customers that use this software to “immediately suspend their flights” after analyzing the technical incident.
The company acknowledged that “these recommendations will cause operational disruptions for passengers and customers.” “We apologize for the inconvenience caused and will work closely with operators, keeping safety as our absolute and paramount priority,” he added.
The European Aviation Safety Agency (EASA) indicated in a statement that it was informed of the situation by Airbus. "These measures may cause short-term interruptions to flight schedules and, consequently, inconvenience for passengers. However, as always in aviation, safety is paramount", said EASA.
The incident occurred on October 30, on a JetBlue flight between Cancún, Mexico, and Newark, near New York, when an aircraft had to make an emergency landing in Tampa, Florida.
Analysis of the incident “revealed that intense solar radiation can corrupt data essential for the operation of flight controls”, informed the European company.
For most aircraft, updating the software from the previous version will take “a few hours”. But, for around a thousand aircraft, it will involve changing the computer hardware, “which will take weeks”, a source linked to the process revealed to France-Presse (AFP).
The incident involves a device – ELAC – Elevator Aileron Computer – manufactured by Thales. This Airbus supplier clarified to AFP that it was not responsible for the problem: “The functionality in question is supported by software that is not the responsibility of Thales”, he assured. Airbus did not specify which company designed and updates this software.
Iberia, part of the IAG group, confirmed today that it is working to make the “necessary changes” to its A320 aircraft safely and guaranteed that Saturday's operations will not be affected by this situation, reported the Efe agency.
Colombian airline Avianca estimated that 70% of its fleet will be affected and foresees “significant interruptions in the next ten days”, having explained in a statement that ticket sales are suspended until December 8th.
The Airbus A320, which entered service in 1988, is the best-selling aircraft in the world. In September, Airbus dethroned the Boeing 737, from the North American manufacturer Boeing, whose first unit was delivered in 1968.
At the end of September, Airbus had delivered 12,257 A320 planes (including business class versions), compared to 12,254 Boeing 737s. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-30 23:30:06</pubDate></item><item><title>China asks miners to leave area between Afghanistan and Tajikistan after deaths</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/30/china-pede-a-mineiros-que-abandonem-area-entre-afeganistao-e-tajiquistao-apos-mortes/</link><description>The Chinese embassy in Afghanistan has asked Chinese companies and officials involved in mining activities on the border with Tajikistan to quickly leave the area. At issue is a violent episode in the border area between Afghanistan and Tajikistan that caused casualties among Chinese citizens.

The Chinese embassy in Afghanistan has asked Chinese companies and officials involved in mining activities on the border with Tajikistan to quickly leave the area following a new security incident with fatalities.
In a statement released on the social platform WeChat, the diplomatic delegation stated that, in recent days, there had been “another” violent episode in the border area between Afghanistan and Tajikistan, which caused casualties among Chinese citizens. The note does not specify the number of deaths or explain the circumstances of the attack.
The embassy urged all companies and workers involved in gold mining projects in northeastern Afghanistan to immediately withdraw from the region and avoid any unnecessary travel.
The message also recommends that, in the event of an emergency, they immediately contact the local police and the diplomatic mission itself.
Media outlets close to the Chinese government, such as the English-language newspaper Global Times, reported that three Chinese workers were killed in an attack from Afghan territory on Thursday, citing Tajik officials.
According to this version, an attack with drones and firearms that day hit employees of a Chinese company in southern Tajikistan, close to the Afghan border.
Northeastern Afghanistan and the mountainous areas connecting the country to Tajikistan are considered high-risk areas due to the presence of armed groups and cross-border trafficking networks, an environment that has raised recurring concerns among Chinese and Central Asian authorities.
Since 2021, China has maintained a pragmatic relationship with the Taliban regime, focused almost exclusively on border security and investment protection.
In recent months, Beijing has sought assurances directly from the Islamist movement's toughest wing, including the powerful Interior Minister Sirajuddin Haqqani, with whom it discussed anti-terrorism cooperation and border control.
At the same time, in Kabul, China promoted a cooperation axis with Afghanistan and Pakistan and intends to start mining projects and integrate the country into the “Belt and Road” initiative.
Beijing is also financing security infrastructure in Tajikistan, such as the base it is building near the Afghan border, in an attempt to protect the region from possible cross-border attacks or the presence of Uyghur groups on Afghan territory. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-30 23:22:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Healthy eating and exercise earn points and rewards for Macau residents</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/30/alimentacao-saudavel-e-exercicio-valem-pontos-e-recompensas-a-residentes-de-macau/</link><description>Macau will launch a program in 2026 that will reward residents who adopt healthy lifestyle behaviors, because “prevention is better than cure”.

During the debate on the Lines of Government Action (LAG) for next year, the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, said that the region will focus on disease prevention.
The LAG report foresees the launch, in the second quarter of 2026, of an incentive program for health management, through the electronic platform ‘Minha Saúde 2.0’. “Residents who adopt behaviors such as healthy eating, regular physical exercise, disease screening and vaccination will be able to accumulate points and exchange them for rewards”, states the document.
The objective is to “encourage the adoption of good lifestyle habits and implement proactive health self-management”, explains the report. “We are going to do this work to assess health and prevent chronic diseases”, explained O Lam to deputies in the Legislative Assembly, in reference to the Macau Health Survey.
The initiative will also be launched in the second quarter of 2026 and will, by the end of the year, collect and analyze health data from a sample of the city's almost 690 thousand inhabitants.
The goal is “to determine the epidemiological situation and the evolution trends of the main chronic diseases, some communicable diseases and (…) risk factors, establishing scientific bases for defining health policies”, states the LAG report.
On Wednesday, authorities had already launched a campaign that offers rewards to overweight residents who manage, in the first five months of 2026, to lose at least 3% of their body mass.
The campaign is part of the Chinese national initiative 'Year of Weight Management' and O Lam has now highlighted that preventive health is part of the Chinese 15th Five-Year Plan, which comes into force in 2026.
Investing “in a health assessment and screening our diseases”, defended the secretary, “will be very important for an aging society” like Macau.
In April, when presenting the LAG for 2025, Lam had already warned that the region will “enter a phase of super-low birth rate” by the end of the decade.
In 2024, elderly people (aged 65 and over) represented 14.6% of Macau's total population. By 2029 there should be 21.4% and by 2041 almost a quarter of the population (24.8%), predicted the leader.
Lam said that the Government will create, in a pilot project, a service center for the elderly in Seac Pai Van, the largest social housing neighborhood in the territory, in Coloane. In the future, the objective is to ensure that all elderly people in Macau have “access to at least one culture, health, sports or social support service within a 15-minute walk”.

Facilitate access for local students to universities in Brazil

Macau's Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, promised to work to facilitate access for local students to universities in Brazil and Spanish-speaking countries. During the debate on the Lines of Government Action for 2026 in the area of ​​Social Affairs and Culture, deputy Kevin Ho defended the extension of mutual recognition of secondary school final exams to “other jurisdictions, for example Spanish-speaking countries”.
The leader of the Macau Government, Sam Hou Fai, who took office in December 2024, highlighted the development of economic and commercial relations with Spanish-speaking markets as a priority.
Kevin Ho recalled in the Legislative Assembly that Macau has already signed protocols with the Council of Rectors of Portuguese Universities and with the Coordinating Council of the Higher Polytechnic Institutes of Portugal. “Students can use these results obtained in exams here in Macau to access university courses in Portugal”, highlighted Ho, shareholder of the group that owns Diário de Notícias, Jornal de Notícias and TSF. Lam responded positively to Kevin Ho, but asked for patience: “We will follow this path to reinforce this work, for example in Brazil and Hispanic countries, but this is not easy”.
Mutual recognition of secondary school final exam results could also facilitate access to Macau universities for students from Portuguese-speaking countries.
The LAG report highlights the creation of the ‘Study in Macau’ brand platform as a priority for 2026, including the launch of a scholarship program for students from abroad who want to continue their studies in the region.
The objective is to “strengthen the attractiveness for students from Portuguese-speaking countries and countries and regions covered by the ‘One Belt, One Route’ initiative”, states the document.
The initiative, announced by Chinese leader Xi Jinping in 2013, involves more than 80 countries – including Angola, Cape Verde, Equatorial Guinea, Guinea-Bissau, Mozambique, São Tomé and Príncipe and Timor-Leste – to develop maritime, road and rail links.
On the other hand, O Lam said that in 2026 the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) will open another three thousand places in an exchange program that brings students from mainland China to Macau.
DSEDJ launched, in cooperation with the Science Center and local higher education institutions, short-term training and professional certification programs, explained the secretary.
The Cultural Institute will, in the future, develop research itineraries and study visits to attract more groups of students from the interior of China, added O Lam.
On the other hand, the director of DSEDJ, Kong Chi Meng, promised to study suggestions to open primary and secondary education to students from mainland China, in response to the reduction in the school population.
However, Kong stressed that it is first necessary to ensure that students from across the border can take advantage of the facilities provided to local students in accessing universities in Macau and mainland China.
The birth rate in Macau will have been the lowest in the world in 2024, according to a report by the United Nations Department of Economic and Social Affairs. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-30 23:28:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Timor-Leste highlights air agreement with Macau to start direct flights to Greater Bay Area</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/30/timor-leste-destaca-acordo-aereo-com-macau-para-inicio-de-voos-directos-para-a-grande-baia/</link><description>The Timorese Government highlighted the importance of the Air Services Agreement, being prepared to be signed between Macau and Timor-Leste, due to the possibility it opens up to direct air flights from the country to the Chinese region of the Greater Bay Area.

In a speech at the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-Speaking Countries (Macao Forum), which opened a session to promote investment in Timor-Leste, the Timorese Minister for Strategic Planning and Investment (MPAE), Gastão Francisco de Sousa, highlighted the importance of the agreement, due to “the possibility of establishing direct air links between Timor-Leste, Macau and the Greater Bay Area”.
The weekly flight between Dili and Xiamen, in the Chinese province of Fujian, “continues to strengthen connections” between Timor-Leste and China, highlighted the director, referring to the only direct air route between the two countries, opened in February.
Referring also to Forum Macau's three-year action plan, the Timorese minister highlighted the measures planned in the financial sector by including the “use of the Chinese currency, the renminbi (RMB), in bilateral trade”, and welcomed “the opening of Chinese financial markets to foreign investment”.
“For Timor-Leste, this cooperation would support the Chinese business community in Dili, reinforce investment flows and deepen regional integration, especially in the context of ASEAN [Association of Southeast Asian Nations]”, an organization to which Timor-Leste formally joined in October.
The leader of the Macau Government, Sam Hou Fai, highlighted last week the priority given to “promoting the renminbi” in trade with Portuguese-speaking markets. The Chief Executive recalled that, in May, the central banks of China and Brazil signed a memorandum of strategic financial cooperation and renewed a bilateral agreement on exchange lines in local currencies.
Beijing, one of the main capitals promoting Brics Pay – the BRICS payment system, an alternative to the Society for Worldwide Interbank Financial Telecommunication (SWIFT, dominated by the dollar, and an instrument frequently used by the West to impose sanctions), has sought to internationalize the renminbi, a currency that is not entirely convertible into other currencies. Beijing imposes strict controls on the flow of capital, especially out of the country.
Gastão Sousa, who is in Macau when Timor-Leste celebrates the 50th anniversary of the unilateral proclamation of independence on November 28, 1975, also welcomed the deepening of “practical cooperation with China in several priority sectors”. “In fisheries, we work with the Directorate-General of Fisheries to ensure that cooperation within the scope of the Macau Forum is aligned with our Blue Economy Policy, welcoming large-scale investments, such as the Guangxi Yanxi Fishery Development project, through Timor Sea Fishery Development, in a value equivalent to 685 million dollars [591.2 million euros]”, pointed out the minister.
In the agriculture sector, the Timorese official highlighted the importance of cooperation between seven municipalities in Timor-Leste and the province of Hunan, in China, especially in rice production and agricultural tourism development. “We also welcome the Caizi China Group’s multi-phase investment, worth one billion dollars, which has already started with the construction of the manufacturing factory in Ulmera and the integrated ‘resort’ in Tíbar, Liquiçá”, he concluded.
The governor left an invitation to Macau's official entities and businesspeople present at the session to explore “opportunities in the sectors of tourism, agriculture, renewable energy, blue economy, digital services, transport and logistics” and also to build partnerships in the knowledge and technology sectors. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-30 23:26:06</pubDate></item><item><title>China launches campaign against fire risks in skyscrapers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/30/china-lanca-campanha-contra-riscos-de-incendio-em-arranha-ceus/</link><description>China has launched an “inspection and rectification” campaign against fire risks in high-rise buildings, public television broadcaster CCTV announced, following the fire that caused at least 146 deaths in Hong Kong.

According to the state channel, this campaign will focus, in particular, on the exterior or interior renovation works of buildings that are still occupied and the use of flammable materials in the works and bamboo for scaffolding.
Flammable materials and bamboo are believed to have accelerated the spread of flames in the Hong Kong fire that occurred on Wednesday.
The campaign will target “the use of prohibited materials and processes and equipment such as bamboo scaffolding or protective nets without flame retardant effect,” according to CCTV. It will also target unauthorized works or works carried out without following procedures, the channel said.
Hong Kong began three days of mourning after the fire that consumed the Wang Fuk Court residential complex, in Tai Po, in the north of the city, and which left at least 146 dead and around 200 missing. The Chief Executive, John Lee, presided over a session in which there were three minutes of silence outside the Government headquarters.
The flags of China and Hong Kong (HKSAR) are at half-mast in all public buildings until this Monday.
The fire broke out at around 3pm on Wednesday in the Wang Cheong House block and affected seven of the eight buildings. Preliminary investigations indicate that the fire originated in the scaffolding protection net on the lower floors and spread quickly vertically. Highly flammable expanded polystyrene sheets, used to seal the openings and frames near the elevators, as well as the exterior tarpaulins that violated fire safety standards, made it easier for the flames to enter the apartments through the corridors.
Since Wednesday night, thousands of citizens, neighborhood groups, unions, churches and volunteers have mobilized spontaneously, raising millions of Hong Kong dollars and distributing water, food, clothing and temporary shelter.
The Government announced an initial fund of 300 million Hong Kong dollars to help victims and affected people, which has now reached 800 million Hong Kong dollars.

Hong Kong anti-corruption agency detains 8 people

Hong Kong's anti-corruption agency announced the arrest of eight people linked to the renovation work on the residential complex that was destroyed by the fire. In a statement, the agency said it was investigating the circumstances of the fire, and indicated that it had detained seven men and one woman, aged between 40 and 63, on suspicion of corruption.
The detainees are two heads of the study office responsible for the renovation work, two construction managers, three scaffolding subcontractors and an intermediary.
The government of the former British colony concluded that the large fire, which occurred on Wednesday, was worsened by bamboo scaffolding and flammable foam insulation panels.
According to the preliminary expert report, the materials used in the ongoing works contributed to the progression of the flames and to the higher temperatures recorded at the site. “Based on the initial information we have, we believe that the fire started in the protective screen [foam material to protect against the spread of dust and falling objects] located on the outside of the lower floors (…), and quickly rose due to the panels” that protected the windows, said Hong Kong Secretary for Security, Chris Tang. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-30 23:31:15</pubDate></item><item><title>International banking sector activity remained stable in the third quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/30/actividade-internacional-do-sector-bancario-manteve-se-estavel-no-terceiro-trimestre/</link><description>The proportion of international activity in Macau's banking sector remained stable in the third quarter of 2025, revealed the Macau Monetary Authority (AMCM). At the end of September, the share of financial investments in international markets in the total assets of the banking system was 84.5%, while international liabilities in the total liabilities of the banking system stood at 81.3% – values ​​in line with those released at the end of June.
Foreign currencies were the most used in international banking transactions. In the third quarter, the pataca represented just 0.8% of international financial assets and 0.6% of liabilities. On the other hand, the United States dollar, the Hong Kong dollar and the renminbi totaled 43%, 28.3%, 21.8% and 6.1% of international assets and 37.6%, 38.3%, 18% and 5.5% of total international liabilities.
In the period under review, the total volume of international assets in the banking sector grew 3.2% compared to the previous quarter, reaching 2,153.6 billion patacas. Of this amount, it is worth highlighting a 1.9% growth in foreign assets and a 7.7% growth in local assets in foreign currencies. Interbank loans granted to banks abroad constituted the majority of international assets, with growth of 4% to 584.7 billion.
The total international liabilities of the Macau banking sector also rose 3.2% in quarterly terms, reaching 2,073.7 billion patacas at the end of September. Liabilities abroad reached 1,042.8 billion patacas, which corresponds to a decrease of 0.5%, while domestic liabilities in foreign currencies rose 7.3% to 1,030.9 billion. Deposits in foreign currencies of the Macao SAR government and Macau residents in local banks, which represented the main component of total international liabilities, rose 1.9%, reaching 780.5 billion patacas.
According to AMCM, Macau's international banking activity was mainly distributed across Asia. In this quarter under consideration, the Macau banking system's claims on Mainland China and Hong Kong were 35.8% and 23.9%, respectively, of total foreign assets. Portuguese-speaking countries and countries included in the “One Belt, One Route” initiative occupied 0.6% and 14.8% of this amount.
As for liabilities abroad, shares of 47.2% were recorded for Hong Kong and 35.7% for the interior of China. Regarding Portuguese-speaking countries and countries included in the “One Belt, One Route” initiative, the shares were 0.4% and 6.9%, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-11-30 23:23:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Unemployment falls to 1.7% in Macau despite the closure of 'satellite casinos'</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/30/desemprego-cai-para-17-em-macau-apesar-do-fecho-de-casinos-satelite/</link><description>The unemployment rate in Macau fell to 1.7% between August and October, the lowest figure since January, despite the closure of 'satellite casinos'.

According to the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC), the indicator decreased by 0.1 percentage points compared to the period between July and September, with the number of unemployed people falling by around 200, to 6,700.
The rate represents less than half of that recorded in the third quarter of 2022 (4%), the highest value since 2006, at a time when Macau was in the midst of an economic crisis caused by the covid-19 pandemic. But the recovery motivated by the end of the 'zero covid' policy, which was in force in Macau and mainland China for almost more than three years, led unemployment to fall to 1.6% between November 2024 and last January, a historic low since DSEC began collecting data on unemployment in Macau, in 1992, even before the transition of administration of the territory, from Portugal to China.
Hotels hired around 700 more people, compared to the period between July and September, while the workforce at casinos – the largest private employer in the region – increased by around 300. On the contrary, restaurants laid off around 1,200 people and the number of workers in wholesale and retail trade decreased by around 400.
On June 9, the Government of Macau announced that gaming concessionaires had announced the end of operation of the 11 'satellite casinos', where around 5,600 residents work. However, one of the 'satellite casinos', the Royal Arc, must remain open, as the concessionaire SJM acquired the hotel where the gaming space is located and asked the authorities to take over direct management.
The 'satellite casinos', under the responsibility of the concessionaires, are managed by other companies, being a legacy of the Portuguese administration and which already existed before the liberalization of gambling in the territory, in 2002.
When the legislation regulating casinos was changed, in 2022, the end of 2025 was established as the deadline for ending the activity of these gaming spaces.
The first casino to close was Grandview, at the end of July, followed by Grand Dragon, on September 22nd. Emperor Palace and Waldo closed at the end of October, while Legend Palace closed on November 12 and Casal Real six days later.
Ponte 16, with 1,025 employees, closed on Saturday and Fortuna closes on December 10, according to an internal note from the property's owner, the company Kou Seng Holdings, cited by gaming news portal GGRAsia.
On Monday, the Secretary for Economy and Finance confirmed that 1,300 workers from six 'satellite casinos' had been reinstated as part of the gambling concessionaires' staff. “There are still four ‘satellite casinos’ that will close, with around three thousand workers involved,” said Anton Tai Kin Ip.

Casino Ponte 16 closed on Saturday “in accordance with the planned procedures”

The Ponte 16 satellite casino closed on Saturday morning under the supervision of the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ), which guarantees that the process took place “in accordance with the expected procedures”. After ceasing operations at 11:59 pm on Friday, the organization suspended the operation of tables and gaming machines and monitored, throughout Saturday morning, the removal of the respective equipment. The process was carried out in collaboration with other departments, namely the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), which was on site to provide clarification to affected workers, and the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) and the Judiciary Police (PJ), which were responsible for maintaining public order at the site and in its surroundings. “The DICJ will continue to optimize the inspection mechanism, promoting the regularization of the gaming sector and its healthy and orderly development, together with the respective sectors”, reads the statement.</description><pubDate>2025-11-30 23:26:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese industrial activity falls for the eighth consecutive month in November</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/30/actividade-industrial-chinesa-cai-pelo-oitavo-mes-consecutivo-em-novembro/</link><description>China's industrial activity fell in November for the eighth consecutive month, although at a slightly more moderate pace, according to official data released by the Asian country's National Statistics Office (GNE).
The official purchasing managers index (PMI, the sector's benchmark indicator) stood at 49.2 points in November, 0.2 points above the 49 recorded in the previous month, in line with analysts' forecasts.
In this indicator, a value above the 50-point threshold represents growth in the sector's activity, in relation to the previous month, while a value below represents a contraction.
Among the five sub-indices that make up the PMI, only the one relating to delivery times escaped contraction, rising to 50.1 points. The one relating to production remained at 50 points and the rest – new orders, inventories of raw materials and employment – ​​were below that threshold, with 49.2, 47.3 and 48.4 points, respectively.
By company size, large manufacturers registered 49.3 points, below the previous month, while medium and small manufacturers registered 48.9 and 49.1 points, both still in contraction territory.
GNE statistician Huo Lihui attributed the slight improvement in the industry indicator to the fact that “production and new orders showed a simultaneous improvement”, advancing 0.3 and 0.4 points, respectively, which reveals, in the expert’s words, “a partial recovery in both supply and demand” in the sector.
Huo noted that “small businesses saw a particularly notable recovery,” with the PMI reaching its highest level in six months, while the high-tech industry “continued to expand for the tenth consecutive month.”
The GNE also released the activity index in the services and construction sectors, which fell from 50.1 points in October to 49.5 in November.</description><pubDate>2025-11-30 23:22:14</pubDate></item><item><title>DST reinforces “defense barrier” against fires</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/30/dst-reforca-barreira-de-defesa-contra-incendios/</link><description>The Tourism Services Directorate (DST) put into practice, last week, a plan aimed at strengthening the tourism sector's capacity to prevent and respond to emergencies. The initiative aims to build a collective “defense barrier”, by carrying out surveys and inspections of establishments and strengthening the communication mechanism with the industry.
The measures began to be implemented last Thursday, the day on which DST sent letters to all hotels, restaurants, bars, food establishments and other establishments related to the tourist industry in Macau. As detailed in a statement, authorities urged operators to “raise fire safety awareness” and “rigorously carry out prevention and response work and reinforce the management of the daily use of fire and electricity”.
In parallel, DST inspection teams also intensified their on-site inspection of fire safety measures, paying special attention to establishments with ongoing works. The aim was, in this way, to alert workers to “strict compliance with safety standards” and the prevention of fire outbreaks, namely through the inspection of equipment and the removal of flammable materials.
The following day, Friday, DST coordinated efforts with the six gaming concessionaires and associations linked to the hotel industry. The meeting served to learn in depth about its fire safety plans and establish a communication channel for emergencies, in order to increase the capacity and speed of response in the event of accidents and continue to guarantee the safety of visitors and the industry itself.
DST's measures extend to the facilities under its authority – as is the case of the Macau Grand Prix Museum, where inspections were organized with the support of maintenance companies. DST adds that entities organizing activities financed by them were also made aware of the need to reinforce security measures. “DST will continue to maintain close communication with tour operators and carry out periodic inspections, in order to encourage those responsible for establishments to assume responsibility for security management, jointly safeguarding a safe environment with favorable conditions for tourism in Macau”, concludes the organization.</description><pubDate>2025-11-30 23:23:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal Point – 1 December 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/30/ponto-fatal-1-dezembro-2025/</link><description>The Tourism Services Directorate (DST) put into practice, last week, a plan aimed at strengthening the tourism sector's capacity to prevent and respond to emergencies. The initiative aims to build a collective “defense barrier”, by carrying out surveys and inspections of establishments and strengthening the communication mechanism with the industry.
The measures began to be implemented last Thursday, the day on which DST sent letters to all hotels, restaurants, bars, food establishments and other establishments related to the tourist industry in Macau. As detailed in a statement, authorities urged operators to “raise fire safety awareness” and “rigorously carry out prevention and response work and reinforce the management of the daily use of fire and electricity”.
In parallel, DST inspection teams also intensified their on-site inspection of fire safety measures, paying special attention to establishments with ongoing works. The aim was, in this way, to alert workers to “strict compliance with safety standards” and the prevention of fire outbreaks, namely through the inspection of equipment and the removal of flammable materials.
The following day, Friday, DST coordinated efforts with the six gaming concessionaires and associations linked to the hotel industry. The meeting served to learn in depth about its fire safety plans and establish a communication channel for emergencies, in order to increase the capacity and speed of response in the event of accidents and continue to guarantee the safety of visitors and the industry itself.
DST's measures extend to the facilities under its authority – as is the case of the Macau Grand Prix Museum, where inspections were organized with the support of maintenance companies. DST adds that entities organizing activities financed by them were also made aware of the need to reinforce security measures. “DST will continue to maintain close communication with tour operators and carry out periodic inspections, in order to encourage those responsible for establishments to assume responsibility for security management, jointly safeguarding a safe environment with favorable conditions for tourism in Macau”, concludes the organization.</description><pubDate>2025-11-30 23:17:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Floods cause around 465 deaths in Southeast Asia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/30/inundacoes-causam-cerca-de-465-mortes-no-sudeste-asiatico/</link><description>Floods caused by torrential rains in Indonesia, Thailand and Malaysia have already caused around 465 deaths, according to the most recent assessment made by local authorities.

In the three countries, images of flooded cities, populations surrounded by water and landslides caused by torrential rain that has been falling for several days are repeated.
Indonesia's disaster agency recorded more than 303 deaths, while the Thai government reported that 145 people died in the south of the country and Malaysian authorities recorded two victims.
In Indonesia, the province of North Sumatra is the most affected, with 166 deaths. In West Sumatra, the number of victims almost tripled, from 23 to 90, with “85 people still missing”, according to the spokesperson for the regional disaster management agency, Ilham Wahab. In Aceh province, at least 47 people died.
In Thailand, flooding in eight southern provinces caused 162 deaths, while in Indonesia the provinces of North Sumatra, Aceh and West Sumatra recorded a total of 303 deaths.
The most affected Thai province is Songkhla, with 126 victims, local authorities reported. The other provinces with recorded deaths are Nakhon Si Thammarat (nine), Pattani (seven), Satun (five), Yala (five), Phatthalung (four), Narathiwat (four) and Trang (two).
The waters rose up to three meters in this region, which suffered one of the worst floods of the decade. Meanwhile, several refrigerated trucks were mobilized to store the bodies of the victims.
On Friday, Thai Prime Minister Anutin Charnvirakul visited a shelter in the hard-hit Hat Yai district. “I really have to apologize for letting this happen while I'm in Government,” he told the AmarinTV channel, adding that “the next step is to prevent the situation from deteriorating” and adding that cleaning the district would take two weeks.
The Government announced compensation of up to US$62,000 for families who lost members in these disasters. Public dissatisfaction is increasing in Thailand regarding the management of the situation, with two local officials being suspended for alleged failures.
In neighboring Malaysia, two people died due to flooding in the state of Perlis (north). The monsoon season, which generally runs from June to September, is often synonymous with heavy rainfall in the region, with risks of landslides and flash floods.
In Indonesia and Thailand, the number of fatalities is among the worst in recent years due to floods.
Furthermore, in South Asia, Sri Lanka also suffered torrential rains this week, brought by cyclone Ditwah, which is moving towards India.
The island's Disaster Management Center (DMC) yesterday reported at least 123 deaths in floods and landslides, with around 44,000 displaced. The Government requested international assistance and appealed to its citizens abroad to make donations to support the approximately 500,000 people affected. The worst floods of the century in Sri Lanka, in 2003, caused 254 deaths.
According to scientists, global warming caused by human activity makes extreme weather events more frequent, deadlier and more destructive. For each additional degree, the atmosphere can contain 7% more humidity, with more intense precipitation, experts warn. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-30 23:21:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Local artists display 180 works of art in the biggest exhibition of the year at the Parisian</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/30/aristas-locais-expoem-180-obras-de-arte-na-maior-exposicao-do-ano-no-parisian/</link><description>The region's art scene reaches a new level with the opening of the Macau Artists Association's annual exhibition, bringing together 180 works at the Parisian. The event, which runs until March 2026, celebrates the territory's double international recognition as East Asian City of Culture 2025 and the Historic Center's 20 years as a World Heritage Site. 

In a dialogue between tradition and contemporary times, Sands China reveals the creative soul of Macau through the most comprehensive art exhibition of the year. From December 1st, the Parisian Macao Shoppes will transform into a cultural epicenter, hosting the exhibition that consolidates the territory as an emerging platform for visual arts in Asia. The exhibition occupies five commercial spaces on the third floor of the resort, creating an unusual exhibition path that challenges traditional conventions of artistic presentation.
Curated by Lok Hei and coordinated by Ng Wai Kin and Lao Chon Hong, the exhibition presents 180 works that function as a collective portrait of the artistic maturity of the territory's artists. Each piece tells a story, from Lao Fu Ip's technical mastery of the traditional Chinese painting “Goddess of the Rhythmic Waves” to the conceptual boldness of Eric Fok, whose felt-tip “Dialogue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems” defies convention. The selection demonstrates how local artists master with equal excellence media as diverse as Lio Man Cheong's watercolor, capturing the drunken dragon dance, or Chan In Tong's contemporary engraving in “The Last Repair”.
The diversity of techniques and supports is the central point, ranging from Zha Rui's traditional oils in “Exterminating Evil” to Kou Iun Fong's mixed media experiments in “The Beauty of the Gathering”. Ng Si Meng's classic calligraphy coexists with Lok Hei's contemporary acrylic painting in “Hei! What brings U here”, creating a temporal dialogue that mirrors Macau's own cultural identity. The selected works represent different generations of artists, from established masters to emerging talents, offering a panoramic view of the local artistic ecosystem.
The opening moment of this exhibition could not be more symbolic. By simultaneously celebrating the 20th anniversary of the Historic Center's classification as a World Heritage Site and Macau's designation as East Asian City of Culture 2025, the exhibition can establish a bridge between cultural legacy and contemporary creation. This convergence of events highlights the evolution of the territory from a heritage conservator to an active promoter of contemporary cultural production, contributing to positioning Macau in the regional artistic panorama.
The Macau Artists Association, founded in 1956 and holder of the Cultural Merit Medal since 2016, demonstrates through this exhibition its role in structuring the local artistic environment. With more than 400 members, the institution has cultivated successive generations of creators, promoting exchanges ranging from “Rainbow Road” educational programs in mainland China to regular collaborations with Portugal, South Korea, Italy, Myanmar and Egypt. Furthermore, the creation of the Macau Young Artists Association in 2019 reflects the commitment to generational renewal and artistic innovation.
The choice of the Parisian as a setting also represents another curatorial strategy. By placing local artistic production in a context of luxury and internationality, the exhibition appears to blur conventional boundaries between cultural and entertainment spaces, once again reflecting the unique nature of the territory as a meeting point for global art. The organizers highlight in the curatorial statement that “the Parisian’s exquisite works and elegant, luxurious ambiance resonate with each other, creating a renewed brilliance through their harmonious interaction.”
The “Exhibition of Works by Members of the Macau Artists Association 2025” remains at the Parisian Macao from December 1, 2025 to March 27, 2026. Admission is free, daily from 10am to 11pm.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Macau hotels register highest occupancy in October since before the pandemic</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/30/hoteis-de-macau-registam-maior-ocupacao-em-outubro-desde-antes-da-pandemia/</link><description>Hotel establishments had 89.3% of rooms occupied last month, the highest figure for October since before the pandemic. In October, Macau had 147 hotels and guesthouses, one more than last year and the highest number since these data began to be compiled

Hotel establishments in Macau had 89.3% of rooms occupied last month, the highest figure for October since before the covid-19 pandemic.
According to official data from the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC), the average occupancy of hotels and guesthouses increased by 0.9 percentage points, compared to the same month in 2024, and is the highest since 2018.
In October, the territory had 147 hotels and guesthouses, one more than last year and the highest number since DSEC began compiling this data, in 1997, even before the transition of administration from Portugal to China.
The approximately 45,200 rooms were busier as the number of guests increased by 3% year on year last month, surpassing 1.21 million.
Regarding the period between January and October, the territory also registered an increase in annual terms of 0.4%, to 12.1 million guests.
In the first 10 months of 2025, Macau received 33.1 million visitors, 14.1 percent more than in the same period of 2024 and the second highest figure ever for the start of a year. However, 58.5% of visitors (19.4 million) arrived on organized tours and spent less than a day in the city.
The number of guests continued to rise in October, the month in which hotels lowered average room prices to 1,413 patacas, 0.5% less than in the same month of 2024, according to data from the Macau Hotel Association, which brings together 48 local establishments.
According to the report, released by the Tourism Services Department, the decline was mainly due to five-star hotels, whose average price fell by 1.8%, to 1,572 patacas.
Macau's hotel establishments welcomed more than 14.4 million guests in 2024, setting a new historical record. The previous record, 14.1 million guests, had been set in 2019, before the covid-19 pandemic, in a year in which Macau ended with just 38,300 rooms in 122 hotel establishments. “We have more and more tourists, but the level of consumption is falling”, warned, on May 13, the leader of the Macau Government, Sam Hou Fai.
The average consumption of each visitor in Macau, excluding casinos, fell 9.5% in the first nine months of the year, compared to the same period in 2024.
DSEC had already pointed out the “change in visitors' consumption patterns” as one of the main reasons for the 1.3% drop in Macau's economy between January and March.
It was the first time that the territory's Gross Domestic Product shrank, in year-on-year terms, since the end of 2022, when the region began to lift restrictions due to the covid-19 pandemic. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-30 23:28:17</pubDate></item><item><title>A third of stalls in public markets are unoccupied</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/30/um-terco-de-bancas-nos-mercados-publicos-estao-desocupadas/</link><description>The number of unoccupied stalls in Macau's eight public markets reached 329 by the end of September this year, which represents around 30.95% of the total stalls, revealed the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM), in response to a written question from deputy Ngan Iek Hang. The unoccupied stalls are mainly distributed across the Mercado do Bairro Iao Hon, Mercado de S. Lourenço and Mercado de S. Domingos.
In relation to vendors, to date there were 100 empty stalls in 14 vendors' areas, corresponding to around 17.3% of the total, distributed mainly in the Vendors' Zone surrounding the Mercado de S. Domingos, in the Fai Chi Kei Vendors' Zone and in the Vendors' Zone on Rua de Fernão Mendes Pinto.
Reiterating its dedication to the revitalization of public markets, the IAM said that it had been carrying out, in recent years, optimization works “designed according to the characteristics of municipal markets”. According to the organization, public tenders were successively launched for the distribution of a total of 35 unoccupied stalls in the Horta da Mitra Market, the Patane Food Center and the Taipa Market, “which were well received”, he said.
The IAM indicated that it will draw on experiences from the aforementioned optimization projects and will introduce stalls in the public markets “of new types of activities, more diversified and attractive”, depending on the characteristics of the markets and the consumption demand of Macau residents or tourists. Through the measure, the authorities intend to attract more young and middle-aged residents to participate in competitions for the operation of the stalls.</description><pubDate>2025-11-30 23:24:54</pubDate></item><item><title>APAVT reinforces strategy to attract tourists from China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/30/apavt-reforca-estrategia-de-captacao-de-turistas-da-china/</link><description>The Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies says that the strategy of approaching the main tourist source market, China, was one of the reasons for choosing Macau for its 50th Congress. “There has been work for years and years with Macau, which, when it goes well and becomes more intense from year to year, ends up naturally ‘asking’ for a congress to take place, as happened this year”, begins by saying the president of the Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies (APAVT) to Lusa when asked about the choice of location.
In addition to the reason mentioned, Pedro Costa Ferreira reinforces that “there is an obvious strategy to approach the largest tourism source market in the world, China, a strategy that is absolutely adopted by both private operators and Turismo de Portugal”.
The 50th National Congress of APAVT, which takes place from the 2nd to the 4th of December in Macau, has the theme “75 years looking to the future” and marks the culmination of the celebrations of the association's 75th anniversary. “From the 2nd, we will all be together, public and private, in Macau”, he states.
Asked about the number of professionals registered this year, Pedro Costa Ferreira said that, until Friday morning, the event had passed “one thousand accreditations, which is the highest number” of APAVT congresses since there has been registration. "It's an extraordinary number, even though we had very high expectations. The fact that it was in Macau, a city we hadn't been to since 2017, that it was our 75th anniversary, that it was our 50th congress, or even the fact that we incorporated the 'roadshow' [presentation] of Portugal's Tourism for Asia, in one of our panels, would have been fundamental reasons for this very positive result", he explains to Lusa. Thus, regarding expectations, the person responsible states: “With sincerity, we hope for a memorable congress”.
Regarding the main challenges, Pedro Costa Ferreira says that they began when there was a congress organized on the other side of the world.
Then with "the support it had, due to the themes presented, the speakers involved, the connection with the Chinese issuing market, the challenge, from this moment on, is to manage a congress with a few hundred more people than usual. Maintain proximity to members, maintain the normal flow of work, transport people, etc", he explains.
Regarding the choice of theme, he guarantees that it “reveals ambition and follows a strategic development model”. "In fact, we are going to look to the future, 'on top' of the best numbers in the sector, occurring in 2024, and to be consolidated throughout this year. On the other hand, we feel that, throughout 75 years of history, this is how we live each year, preparing the future, planning the future, thinking about the future. We will finally celebrate the 75th anniversary, in the same way we live each year of our lives, looking to the future", concludes the president of APAVT.</description><pubDate>2025-11-30 23:23:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Third phase of talent acquisition will facilitate candidates with work experience in Portugal</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/30/terceira-fase-de-captacao-de-talentos-facilitara-candidatos-com-experiencia-de-trabalho-em-portugal/</link><description>The Government is about to launch the third phase of the program to recruit qualified staff, providing more facilities for candidates with international professional experience, especially in Portugal and Brazil. In the two previous phases of attracting talent, 800 talent applications have already been preliminarily admitted, which “respond to Macau's needs”, guaranteed the Executive.

The third phase of the program to recruit qualified staff will be launched “soon”, announced Kong Chi Meng, director of Education and Youth Development Services, in the debate on the Governing Action Lines (LAG) of the Social Affairs and Culture portfolio.
Kong Chi Meng, who is also secretary-general of the Qualified Staff Development Commission, said that the new phase of the program will be “highly ambitious” and will introduce “several improvements”, such as the attribution of additional points in the evaluation of applications based on professional experience in Portugal and Brazil.
In addition to the commitment to bringing professionals who work in Portuguese-speaking countries, the authorities will also give extra points to those with international professional experience and those with specialized experience in traditional Chinese medicine prescriptions.
The issue was raised in the plenary session of the Legislative Assembly on Friday, where deputy Vong Hou Piu pointed out that Macau's work to attract talent “remains insufficient” and asked to expand the admission of professionals from abroad.
In response, Kong Chi Meng revealed that more than 800 applications have already been included in the list of qualified professionals proposed for recruitment over the two previous editions of the program, which are “talent in short supply in Macau”, he reiterated.
The official, however, highlighted that the program to recruit qualified staff does not aim to attract the largest number of talents possible, but rather to introduce professionals who are urgently sought after for the development of Macau. “When there are locally trained professionals available for Macau’s ‘1+4’ industries, priority will be given to local young people and locally trained talents,” he said.
Kong Chi Meng added that two additional working groups will be created to support the new edition of the program, one of which will be the talent development group, which will proactively collaborate with the investment and economic promotion departments. “A green channel will be opened in which we will offer integrated investment and talent recruitment packages to help companies find necessary professionals,” he explained.
The Government, in addition, will establish cooperation agreements with a scientific research association and two chambers of commerce, with the aim of taking advantage of commercial networks to identify and capture international talents, said the director.
According to the Executive's presentation, attracting qualified staff can help increase the Macao SAR's innovative capacity, competitiveness and international prestige, as well as promote the diversification of the economy. The qualified professionals admitted and the members of their household enjoy the same rights and system of social benefits as Macau residents, such as “a low tax regime, 15 years of free schooling, medical assistance and social security”, he described.
The first phase of the Qualificados program ended in the first quarter of last year, with the Government receiving 1,107 valid applications, while the second phase ended in November of the same year, with a total of 1,043 valid applications.
The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, assured that the Government is monitoring and evaluating the implementation of the two phases of the program. The minister also indicated that she was aware of the need for qualified staff to move forward with the four major infrastructure projects proposed by the Government. “Relevant departments will assess their needs and we will collect relevant information to update the talent shortage list and formulate a comprehensive talent strategy,” he stressed.</description><pubDate>2025-11-30 23:29:58</pubDate></item></channel></rss>