<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/14/salao-de-outono-volta-a-trazer-a-arte-contemporanea-de-macau-a-casa-garden/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Authorities combat chikungunya with a week of home visits</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/14/autoridades-combatem-chikungunya-com-uma-semana-de-visitas-domiciliarias/</link><description>The Health Services and several associations in Macau came together this Monday to carry out a joint action to prevent chikungunya, in which they disseminated useful information and helped residents remove stagnant water inside their homes. The project will continue until Sunday, with more awareness-raising actions planned for community neighborhoods such as Ilha Verde or Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro.

The growing number of chikungunya cases in Macau, both of imported and local origin, led the Health Services to initiate a seven-day program aimed at preventing and controlling the epidemic in community neighborhoods. According to the most recent data, eight local cases and 24 imported cases were detected throughout 2025.
The authorities explain that the climatic factors that have characterized this month of October, marked by hot and rainy weather, contributed to the proliferation of mosquitoes that transmit the virus – and, consequently, to a significant increase in the number of infections. The 32 cases registered so far “should not be underestimated”, emphasize the Health Services, remembering that it is “necessary to constantly reinforce prevention and control measures”.
It was with this aim that the “Healthy Community – Elimination of stagnant water for all residents” program was created, the result of cooperation between the Health Services, the Macau Workers' Women's Federation, the General Union of Macau Residents' Associations and the Macau General Women's Association. Over the course of a week, from the 13th to the 19th of October (that is, until Sunday), around 130 workers from the aforementioned associations meet daily in groups and carry out “door-to-door” awareness raising activities, providing useful guidance so that residents know how to dispose of stagnant water and prevent the emergence of mosquitoes.
On the first day of this project, Monday, 24 teams were mobilized for awareness raising activities that took place, mostly, in the Portas do Cerco area. With the residents' consent, the teams entered residents' homes and provided support in checking and removing stagnant water, recalling the fundamental measures for preventing mosquitoes and the most frequent routes of transmission of the “two fevers” – that is, chikungunya and dengue infections.
The Health Services inform that, in the coming days, the publicity teams will increase their reach with visits to several community neighborhoods, which include Ilha Verde, Fai Chi Kei, Rua Central (up to Rua da Alfândega), Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro and also the Tap Seac area. During the period of operation, health authority personnel will be duly identified with the Health Services logo, while workers from other associations will wear their own uniform. In case of doubt, residents can also demand an identification document from workers.
In a statement, the authorities clarify that this joint action to disseminate information aims to “continuously promote community education on mosquito prevention” and increase “residents’ awareness and practical capacity for self-protection”.
Chikungunya is transmitted through the bite of Aedes mosquitoes carrying the virus, which complete their life cycle in approximately seven days in an aquatic environment. By eliminating accumulated water or replacing water in jugs at least once a week, residents help eradicate mosquitoes in their early stages of life and interrupt the chain of transmission. If it is not possible to remove stagnant water, authorities advise the appropriate use of larvicides to treat the affected area.
The clinical manifestations of chikungunya are similar to those of dengue, characterized by symptoms such as muscle pain, headache, nausea, fatigue, fever or skin rashes. If in doubt, citizens can consult the Health Services website or contact the communicable diseases line directly on 2870 0800.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 23:06:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Lotus Art Space hosts drawing exhibition about time and memory</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/14/lotus-art-space-recebe-exposicao-de-desenho-sobre-o-tempo-e-a-memoria/</link><description>The cultural association of As Entranhas Macau will present the drawing exhibition “Common Vision” at the Lotus Art Space gallery, between October 25th and November 19th. The inauguration takes place on the 25th, with the presence of artist Pedro Pascoinho.
“Common Vision” brings together 20 charcoal works on ‘artistic Fabriano’ paper, in which the author presents “intimate, sober and refined compositions”, as described by the organization. The elements portrayed in the drawings – such as fragments of bodies or objects – paint “enigmatic” and “almost ghostly” spaces, which combine an introspective reflection with a universal message about the passage of time.
“The works now presented are the result of pieces designed individually, but born from the desire to create a space of common memory”, summarizes the association of As Entranhas, in a note sent to the newsrooms. This is Pedro Pascoinho's second solo exhibition in Macau, who had already presented the “Establishment” collection at Casa Garden in 2019. Based in Portugal, the artist has exhibited regularly since 1992 in his country of origin, in multiple European countries and in the United States.
The latest exhibition will be open to the public from Tuesday to Sunday, between 1pm and 7pm, with free entry. The project is organized by the cultural association d’As Entranhas and co-organized by the Lotus International Arts Exchange Associação Cultural and the Lotus Art Space gallery, with the support of Macau Fisherman’s Wharf.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Governor of Hainan wants to reinforce economic cooperation with the Portuguese-speaking world</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/14/governador-de-hainao-quer-reforcar-a-cooperacao-economica-com-o-mundo-lusofono/</link><description>A delegation from the province of Hainan paid a visit this Tuesday to the Permanent Secretariat of the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries, in a meeting in which both parties expressed their intention to strengthen bilateral communication and exchange mechanisms.
Liu Xiaoming, the governor of Hainan, began by presenting the preparations for the launch of the Free Trade Port, which will make the island the largest free trade port destination in the world in terms of size and boost its status as China's gateway to the outside world. The Free Trade Port of Hainan, remember, will officially begin its customs operations on December 18, 2025.
Addressing the secretary-general of the permanent secretariat of Forum Macau, Ji Xianzheng, the governor said he hoped to reinforce support for “synergistic development” between Hainan, Macau and Portuguese-speaking countries – namely, through help in deepening knowledge regarding “market rules and investment environments” in Portuguese-speaking countries.
In turn, Ji Xianzheng presented the general situation of Forum Macau and its Permanent Secretariat and confirmed the intention to jointly develop actions to boost cooperation and exchange between the three parties mentioned above: Hainan, Macau and the Portuguese-speaking world. Also present on the Macau delegation were deputy secretaries-general Xie Ying and António Lei, the coordinator of the Administration Office Li Xiaohui and the advisor to the Administration Office Liu Yimei.
After the meeting, Governor Liu Xiaoming and his delegation went on a visit to the Exhibition Pavilion of the Service Platform for Trade Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries. Opened in 2022, the pavilion acts as a driver for the construction of the Sino-Lusophone cooperation platform in Macau, with more than 2,600 articles representing the nine Portuguese-speaking countries.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 23:01:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Health Services call for flu vaccination before December</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/14/servicos-de-saude-apelam-a-vacinacao-contra-a-gripe-antes-de-dezembro/</link><description>The incidence rate of flu-like illness is rising. With Macau expected to be at the peak of seasonal flu again in December, the Health Services are launching an appeal for vaccination before then. The administration of flu vaccines is already underway among high-risk individuals and, as of last Friday, more than 19 thousand people had received the vaccine, the majority of whom were elderly.

The Health Services warn of the increasing risks of flu infection in the coming months, with the peak expected in mid-December. At the end of last month, the organization began seasonal anti-flu vaccination, free of charge, for high-risk individuals. According to statistics, as of 5pm on Friday, more than 19,000 people have already been administered the flu vaccine, representing a significant increase of almost 60% compared to the 12,000 doses administered during the same period last year.
Chou Mei Fong, director of the Areia Preta Health Center, revealed that among those vaccinated, the majority were elderly. The official advises the population to receive the flu vaccine before December, while high-risk individuals should be vaccinated before the second half of November.
Speaking to Jornal Ou Mun, the doctor cited surveillance data on illnesses with flu-like symptoms, released weekly by the Health Services, to state that there has recently been a slight increase in influenza in Macau, with the incidence rate of flu syndrome rising from 12% to 12.96%.
“The virus situation remains relatively active, justifying continued surveillance, especially as the winter flu peak is expected from mid-December to mid-February next year”, he highlighted.
Chou Mei Fong also warned that to establish immunity in the community, residents should aim to complete vaccination before December, as it takes two to three weeks after vaccination to develop sufficient antibodies.
According to Health Services surveillance, in the first week of this month, there was an increase in the number of residents who sought medical assistance at Centro Hospitalar Conde de São Januário (CHCSJ) and Kiang Wu Hospital, with an increase in the number of illnesses with flu-like symptoms. In this case, the detection rate of infection caused by the influenza virus increased, with cases detected mainly of Influenza A (H3).
Influenza virus tests performed at the Public Health Laboratory had a positivity rate of 12.9%, while CHCSJ and Kiang Wu had a laboratory detection rate of the flu virus at 14.6%.
Regarding the supply of vaccines, according to Chou Mei Fong, Macau currently has around 213 thousand doses of flu vaccine, “vaccines from foreign brands recognized by the World Health Organization”, highlighted the spokesperson. According to the information, the organization now offers inactivated flu vaccines produced by the companies Sanofi and Abbott.
He added that the current volume is considered sufficient to meet the needs of residents, the Health Services, and will adjust vaccine procurement based on vaccination progress.
The Health Services therefore recall that the antigen composition of the flu vaccine for 2025-2026 has been updated, and is expected to be more consistent with the types of flu viruses that will circulate this winter. Therefore, vaccination of eligible people is recommended, regardless of whether they have been vaccinated against the flu.
It is recalled that the free administration of the seasonal flu vaccine for 2025-2026 to high-risk groups of people already began on September 30, giving priority to the elderly, children, pregnant women, individuals with chronic illnesses, as well as healthcare professionals, users and workers in nursing homes.
Chou Mei Fong highlighted that the organization is encouraging vaccination among Macau residents aged 50 and over during external consultations. As for children, the Health Services indicated that they are moving forward with mass vaccination programs in schools, aimed at students and teachers.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 23:07:45</pubDate></item><item><title>DSPA provides 32 food waste collection points</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/14/dspa-disponibiliza-32-pontos-de-recolha-de-residuos-alimentares/</link><description>The number of food waste collection points increased this year to 32, and more Alegria Environmental Centers were also made available, “with a view to further expanding the community collection network”, indicated the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) in response to a written inquiry from Ho Ion Sang. In the interpellation, the deputy said that measures to reduce waste and collection facilities should be reinforced.
DSPA also responded that, in collaboration with two housing complexes that met the necessary conditions, intelligent beverage container collection machines were installed to promote the Domestic Food Waste Collection Pilot Project.
The organization stressed that it “continues to promote, at various levels, the collection of food waste and the culture of food recovery”, including promoting the participation of the hotel sector in the collection of food waste through the “Hotel Verde Macau Award”.
According to DSPA, currently, more than 60% of the awarded hotels have already started collecting food waste, with some of them having installed food waste treatment machines. At the same time, hotel restaurants are encouraged to disseminate the concept of valuing food through menu design and promotion among customers, among other aspects.
In its response, DSPA also points out that it has promoted initiatives that aim to reinforce environmental education and raise public awareness of environmental protection, namely ecological conservation and waste reduction and recycling, such as organizing visits to environmental facilities and infrastructures or Alegria Environmental Centers, for example.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 22:59:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple launches iPhone Air in China after eSIM system approval</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/14/apple-lanca-iphone-air-na-china-apos-aprovacao-do-sistema-esim/</link><description>Apple announced the launch of the new iPhone Air in mainland China on October 22nd. The iPhone Air will be the brand's first model in China that works exclusively with eSIM, a technology that replaces physical cards with digital modules integrated into the device.

Apple announced the launch of the new iPhone Air in mainland China on October 22, coinciding with the entry into force of eSIM services from the country's main operators, local press reported yesterday.
With a starting price of 7,999 yuan, the iPhone Air will be the brand's first model in China that works exclusively with eSIM, a technology that replaces physical cards with digital modules integrated into the device.
The launch comes after China Mobile, China Unicom and China Telecom – the three main Chinese telecommunications operators – received authorization from the Ministry of Industry and Information Technology to begin national registration of users with eSIM.
The announcement was made during a live broadcast on the Douyin platform – the Chinese version of TikTok – marking Cook's first public appearance since the opening of the Apple store on the Douyin Mall platform in August.
The executive also participated in an event at the toy company Pop Mart, in Shanghai, where he received a commemorative figure of the character Labubu and highlighted Apple's connection to local creativity and design.
Presented in September, along with the iPhone 17 series, the iPhone Air is the thinnest model ever launched by Apple, with a 6.5-inch screen, polished titanium structure and a single 48-megapixel rear camera.
The ultra-thin design and the absence of a physical SIM card slot led to the postponement of the device's launch in China, while Apple awaited official authorization to operate with eSIM, approved this month.
The new model also includes an 18-megapixel front camera with a square sensor, capable of automatically switching between vertical and horizontal orientations, and dual video features that allow recording with the front and rear cameras simultaneously.
China, Apple's third-largest market in the world, is also a key pillar in the company's global supply chain.
Despite growing local competition from brands like Huawei and Xiaomi, Cook has reiterated his commitment to increasing Apple's investment and technological development in China.
The launch of the iPhone Air coincides with a new boost in the sector in China and occurs in a context of growing trade tensions between Beijing and Washington. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 22:56:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Cloves join shrimp with radioactivity detected in Indonesian production</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/14/cravinho-junta-se-a-camaroes-com-radioactividade-detectada-em-producoes-indonesias/</link><description>Indonesian authorities have detected traces of radioactivity in a clove plantation on the island of Sumatra. Remember that the same had already happened with shrimp exported to the United States.

Indonesian authorities detected traces of radioactivity in a clove plantation on the island of Sumatra, after the same happened with shrimp exported to the United States, the Jakarta Government announced yesterday.
In August, the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) announced that it had found traces of the radioactive isotope cesium-137 in frozen shrimp imported from Indonesia. More recently, the FDA detected cesium-137 in a sample of cloves imported from the Southeast Asian archipelago.
Following the complaints, the Indonesian Government appointed a commission that began investigations and inspections of a processing factory and a farm on the island of Java, as well as an exploration in Lampung (Samatra).
Traces of radioactivity were discovered at the clove-producing farm in Lampung, according to commission spokesman Bara Hasibuan.
The company was forced to suspend the sale of production of the spice originating from the Indonesian islands of the Moluccas. “Until a conclusion is reached, we ask that the cloves from the farm not be sold,” he said, quoted by the news agency France-Presse (AFP).
Bara Hasibuan said the Indonesian Nuclear Energy Regulatory Agency (Bapeten) was carrying out tests on samples collected from the exploration.
The announcement came after traces of contamination were detected in at least 22 frozen shrimp production facilities in the Cikande industrial zone, 60 kilometers west of Jakarta.
Indonesian health authorities carried out medical examinations of workers in the industrial area and nearby residents, identifying nine people positive for cesium-137.
People were able to return home after hospital examinations, but some were relocated to carry out decontamination.
Indonesian authorities have also imposed restrictions on imports of scrap metal, suspected of being the source of pollution. According to the FDA, prolonged exposure to cesium-137, even in low doses, may increase the risk of cancer. Cesium-137 is used in various medical and industrial applications. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 22:55:30</pubDate></item><item><title>China sanctions five branches of South Korean Hanwha in the US following US investigation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/14/china-sanciona-cinco-filiais-da-sul-coreana-hanwha-nos-eua-por-inquerito-norte-americano/</link><description>The Chinese Government announced yesterday a ban on transactions between Chinese companies and five subsidiaries of South Korean shipbuilder Hanwha Ocean, in a new response to US President Donald Trump's policy of relaunching the shipping industry in the United States.

In a statement released yesterday, the Chinese Ministry of Commerce also indicated that it will investigate Washington's decision to open an inquiry into China's growing dominance in global shipbuilding, warning that it may apply new retaliatory measures.
Chinese authorities stated that the investigation “puts the national security” of China and its maritime industry at risk, pointing to Hanwha’s involvement in the process as one of the reasons for the sanctions.
The US investigation, under Section 301 of US trade law, was launched in April 2024 and concluded that China's dominant position in the sector harms US companies. “Beijing has just transformed shipbuilding into a weapon,” said Kun Cao, executive vice-president of the consultancy Reddal, quoted by the international press. “It is a clear sign that it will affect companies from third countries that collaborate with the US in its effort to contain China’s maritime dominance”, he pointed out.
The Chinese 'blacklist' includes the entities Hanwha Shipping LLC, Hanwha Philly Shipyard Inc., Hanwha Ocean USA International LLC, Hanwha Shipping Holdings LLC and HS USA Holdings Corp.
Hanwha Ocean shares fell by more than 8% on the South Korean stock exchange yesterday. In response, the company stated that it was “analyzing the situation”.
The announcement comes at a time of escalating trade and maritime tensions between the world's two largest economies. Both countries introduced new port taxes on each other's ships yesterday. Chinese fees cover vessels owned or operated by US companies or individuals, with a shareholding equal to or greater than 25%, US-flagged vessels or vessels built in the US, largely replicating the criteria defined by US authorities.
The truce in the trade war appears to have broken down after Trump threatened to impose 100% tariffs on all imports from China, in protest against recent Chinese controls on the export of rare earths.
Beijing assured yesterday that the two parties remain in contact, having held a round of technical talks on Monday.
The rapprochement between Washington and Seoul in shipbuilding has intensified as a response to Chinese dominance – China is currently the largest shipbuilder in the world.
At the end of 2024, Hanwha acquired the Philly Shipyard, in Pennsylvania, for 100 million dollars (86 million euros), and announced in August an investment plan of 5 billion dollars (4.3 billion euros) to expand port infrastructure in the USA.
The company also signed contracts with the US Navy for maintenance and repair services for military vessels.
In May this year, Hanwha revealed that it would exit a 'joint venture' it maintained in China.

Beijing threatens to “fight to the end” if the United States maintains tariffs

China yesterday warned the United States that it is willing to “fight to the end” if Washington insists on imposing new tariffs and trade restrictions, although it reiterated its openness to dialogue. “If you want to fight, we will fight to the end; if you want to talk, the door is open,” declared the Chinese Ministry of Commerce, in a statement, in response to the White House’s announcement of the application of 100% additional tariffs on Chinese products and other restrictive measures.
Beijing defended that the recent limitations imposed on the export of rare earths and associated products are “legitimate actions” under national legislation and stressed that they are not a total ban, as applications that meet the requirements “will continue to be approved as before”.
According to the ministry, China previously notified the United States about these measures through the bilateral export control dialogue mechanism.
Chinese authorities accuse Washington of “abusing the concept of national security” and of having introduced “a series of discriminatory restrictions” since the last round of trade negotiations, held in September in Madrid.
The spokesperson urged the United States to “correct its mistakes”, demonstrate “genuine sincerity” and work “in the same direction” as China to return to the path of economic dialogue.
Even so, Beijing recalled that “both countries share broad common interests and a large space for cooperation” and that the confrontation “harms both parties”.
The statement indicates that the two countries maintain contacts within the scope of the economic and trade consultation mechanism and that they even held a “technical meeting” on Monday.
However, he criticized the fact that the US is trying to dialogue “while threatening new sanctions”, considering that “it is not the appropriate way to deal with China”.
The exchange of statements comes at a time of renewed trade tensions, after China announced, last week, new restrictions on the export of rare earths and Washington responded with the threat of doubling tariffs on Chinese products.
On Friday, North American President Donald Trump declared that he no longer sees any reason to meet with his Chinese counterpart, Xi Jinping, at the APEC summit scheduled for the end of the month in South Korea, although both countries guarantee that diplomatic contact “remains open”. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 22:56:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau and Hainan promise greater cultural and economic-commercial cooperation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/14/macau-e-hainao-prometem-maior-cooperacao-cultural-e-economico-comercial/</link><description>A delegation from Hainan, led by the governor of that province, is visiting Macau. The visit served as a way for Liu Xiaoming to meet with Sam Hou Fai in a meeting where both parties promised to promote cultural and economic-commercial cooperation. Macau and Hainão also intend to reinforce the promotion of tourist activities and exhibitions and conventions.

The Chief Executive had, on Monday, a meeting with Liu Xiaoming, governor of Hainan, who is leading a delegation from that province on a visit to Macau. According to a note released yesterday by the Macao SAR Government, at the meeting, the two parties exchanged views on promoting cultural and economic-commercial cooperation between the two regions, as well as strengthening coordination in the promotion of tourist activities and exhibitions and conventions.
At the meeting, Sam Hou Fai recalled that the Macao SAR and the province of Hainan are located in the Greater Pearl River Delta region, “having access to the vast market in the interior of the country”, while at the same time being “linked to the Southeast Asian market”. The Chief added that, “since always, both parties have maintained frequent and in-depth exchanges and a solid basis of cooperation in areas such as tourism, culture, exhibitions and conventions, achieving notable results”.
The Macao SAR Chief Executive also said that, with the joint promotion of the model of “a multi-destination trip”, the two parties are “deepening the space for cooperation in their respective areas, creating mutual gains”. Sam indicated that, “by encouraging the reciprocity of tourist flows, the dynamic development of the tourist industry in both regions will be promoted, achieving reciprocal benefits”.
Sam Hou Fai also highlighted that “Macau has the specific advantage of the ‘one country, two systems’ principle”, as well as the “strategic positioning attributed by the country of ‘one center, one platform and one base'”. The Government leader pointed out that, together with the Guangdong-Macao Deep Cooperation Zone in Hengqin and the Free Port of Hainan, “these policies generate an accumulated effect, achieving complementarity of advantages and creating favorable conditions for regional cooperation”.
The Chief also indicated that the Macao SAR Government is “accelerating the development of adequate diversification of the economy, promoting high-quality socio-economic development with full commitment”. Finally, he said he will continue to count on “great support from Hainan”, and through pragmatic cooperation between the two parties, “fully take advantage of the advantages of each party, explore more collaboration models to create broader development opportunities”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 23:06:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Golden Week was not very bright for casinos</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/14/semana-dourada-foi-pouco-brilhante-para-os-casinos/</link><description>During Golden Week, casino revenues were not brilliant, with a 5% drop compared to the same period last year, indicates JP Morgan. The broker is not optimistic about gross gaming revenues until November.

JP Morgan says gross gaming revenues in the Golden Week period fell short of expectations. In a report released yesterday and cited by the GGRAsia portal, the broker says that the results were not very golden, with a decrease of 5% compared to the same period last year.
These Golden Week results are seen as a “temporary setback”, possibly caused by the typhoons that have passed through the region in recent times and the weaker mass market due to the Mooncake Festival gathering season. There was also, says JP Morgan, a possible loss of high-level players to Singapore due to the Grand Prix that took place in that country between the 3rd and 5th of October.
It is worth remembering that Macau welcomed 1.14 million tourists over the eight days of October's Golden Week, an increase of 16.5% compared to last year's numbers. Even so, the total number of visitors was slightly below the expectations of the Tourism Services Directorate (DST), which at the end of September anticipated the arrival of 1.2 million tourists.
Analysts added that results until November are expected to be “uninspiring”. “However, we still see significant value even with the reduction in estimates,” says the JP Morgan report. Analysts predict that revenues will improve from December onwards and that this will continue until the first quarter of 2026.
A week ago, JP Morgan did the calculations for the first days of Golden Week and said that casinos had reached the best mark in the last five years during this period. However, the broker warned that revenues could fall by 30% in the following period.
According to the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ), in the month of September, gaming revenues were 18.3 billion patacas, 17.5% less compared to the previous month of August, when casinos earned 22.15 billion patacas and broke the post-pandemic record.
In terms of accumulated revenue, between January and September this year the casinos raised around 181.34 billion patacas, that is, 7.1% more compared to what they had raised in the same period last year.
The basic budget prepared by the previous Macao SAR Government for 2025 estimated that gaming revenue this year would reach 240 billion patacas. After a start to the year that fell short of expectations, the current Government presented a revised budget with a forecast of 228 billion patacas, a figure that casinos should reach before the end of the year if they maintain their current pace.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 23:08:33</pubDate></item><item><title>IC invites the submission of proposals for the provision of restaurant services</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/14/ic-convida-a-apresentacao-de-propostas-para-prestacao-de-servicos-de-restauracao/</link><description>As several concerts will soon be held at the Outdoor Performance Venue – on the 8th, 9th and 21st of October – the Cultural Institute (IC) has launched a call for proposals to provide catering services during these events. Applications are open until October 20th.
Remember that the Macau Open Air Performance Venue is located at the intersection of Avenida do Aeroporto and Rua de Ténis, in Taipa. Six containers are installed there, intended for providing light meal services during concerts.
The IC will then select six proposals for each concert. Each selected company will operate a container, assuming exclusive responsibility for its own profits and losses and for applying for licenses, if any. Applicant entities can register for the Submission of Proposals for the Provision of Catering Services program for one, two or three concerts. If applying for more than one concert, you must submit separate documentation for each concert.
According to the IC, the selection will be made according to evaluation criteria, including, “the viability and integrity of the operation plan, harmony with the atmosphere of open-air shows, the diversity and reasonableness of the price of light meals and the compatibility of the menu with the event, the aesthetics and functionality of the venue's decoration and the CV of the team members regarding the experience of operating and managing food establishments. restoration.”</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 22:58:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Thomas Arasi succeeds Ted Chan as Galaxy's chief financial officer</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/14/thomas-arasi-sucede-a-ted-chan-no-cargo-de-director-financeiro-da-galaxy/</link><description>Galaxy Entertainment Group (GEG) announced yesterday that Ted Chan will step down as chief financial officer and Thomas Arasi will assume this role from October 27th. According to the group, Ted Chan “decided to pursue personal interests.”
Ted joined Galaxy in 2018 as Director of Operations – Japan Development and led the Japan development project until 2022. Ted was named the company's Chief Financial Officer in March 2023.
In a statement sent to the newsrooms, Francis Lui, president of Galaxy, leaves a word of thanks to Ted Chan for his “efforts and contributions to the group over the last seven years”. During this period, “Ted made valuable contributions to the group in his important leadership role, leading financial operations, corporate finance and investor relations”, reads the Galaxy statement.
Quoted in the statement, Ted Chan thanks “the president's support and guidance over the years” and highlights that it was a “privilege to serve this company and work alongside so many talented and dedicated colleagues”. "I am grateful for the opportunities, challenges and experiences at GEG over the last seven years. The journey has been professionally rewarding and personally enriching. I would like to express my deep gratitude to everyone who was part of it", says the person in charge.
Francis Lui says that Thomas Arasi will bring “a wealth of experience to the group, with more than 35 years of corporate experience in various sectors, including financial services, hospitality and, most importantly, 16 years in integrated resorts”. “In addition, Tom also has multicultural sensitivity, having managed several businesses in North America, Japan, Singapore and the Philippines”, notes Galaxy. The GEG chairman says he is “confident” that, under Tom’s leadership, the group will continue “to have an exceptionally strong financial function to support the group’s commercial performance and strategic growth”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 22:57:45</pubDate></item><item><title>PJ warns that “factors of uncertainty and instability in cybersecurity continue to emerge”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/14/pj-avisa-que-factores-de-incerteza-e-instabilidade-na-ciberseguranca-continuam-a-emergir/</link><description>The Cybersecurity Incident Alert and Response Center (CARIC) carried out, on the 10th of this month, a cybersecurity incident test, at the headquarters of the Judiciary Police (PJ). On the occasion, Sit Chong Meng, director of the corporation, stated that, “in recent years, cybersecurity threats and risks have become increasingly high, infiltrating various security domains, both traditional and non-traditional, constituting one of the most complex, real and serious security challenges today”.
The official warned that “cyber warfare and technological warfare continue to intensify, new types of cyber crimes are constantly emerging and factors of uncertainty and instability in cybersecurity continue to emerge”.
According to a statement released yesterday by the authorities, this test included the participation of the main organizing entities of those games, representatives of the 17 operators including entities providing telecommunications services, electricity supply, water supply, Macau International Airport Society, as well as cybersecurity supervision entities.
The trial simulated a cyber attack and defense. The simulation system specially created for this purpose allowed participants to “deepen their knowledge of the modi operandi and process of cyber attacks launched by hackers, as well as implement, based on this, the corresponding prevention, supervision, incident response and evidence collection measures to improve the ability to resist and respond to cyber attacks”, says the press release, adding that, “during the trial, through proactive interaction between CARIC and the participants, promoted the exchange of technical knowledge, establishing a solid basis for future in-depth cooperation”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 22:59:14</pubDate></item><item><title>IPIM bets on attracting Portuguese and Spanish brands to open stores in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/14/ipim-aposta-na-atraccao-de-marcas-portuguesas-e-espanholas-para-abrirem-lojas-em-macau/</link><description>Portugal and Spain were recently the scene of Macau's trade promotion activities. A delegation from the Trade and Investment Promotion Institute was in Lisbon, Porto, Madrid and Barcelona, ​​to attract eligible brands to establish their first stores in Macau. The organization states that the initiative received “positive responses”.

The Trade and Investment Promotion Institute (IPIM) will launch a new financial support plan to attract foreign brands to set up shop in Macau. Focused on this new project, an IPIM delegation traveled to Europe and held a roadshow in Lisbon and Porto, Portugal, as well as in Madrid and Barcelona, ​​Spain, between the 4th and 11th of October, which was attended by around 100 representatives from business associations and local companies.
According to IPIM, this was the first promotional event abroad for this new plan, which aims to “attract eligible Portuguese and Spanish brands” to establish their first stores in Macau.
“By reinforcing Macau’s role as an interlocutor between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries, the program aims to transform Macau into a first destination for Portuguese and Spanish products to be launched in the city and, subsequently, enter the market in the interior of China”, highlighted the organization in a press release.
IPIM said that participants representing local business associations and companies are involved in sectors such as catering, household items, high-quality works of art, jewelry, food, hotel supplies, among others.
Highlighting that the initiative was “well received”, IPIM added that, during the visit, the delegation also visited several renowned local companies, international chains and chambers of commerce, in order to present Macau's business environment and policies, including the China-PLP Commerce Conduit Services and the One Stop Investor Service, “further expanding the investment promotion network in Europe”.

INTERESTED COMPANIES
 
IPIM said that, on this trip, it visited several Portuguese and Spanish companies to present the First Stores Plan, including international food groups, restaurant chains, jewelry brands, traditional crafts brands, furniture and housewares companies and aromatherapy brands.
“Portuguese and Spanish companies believe that, by relying on Macau's vast tourist market, they will be able to make their brands known to visitors from more countries”, indicated IPIM, pointing out that companies are confident in Macau's role for their future entry into the markets of Hengqin, the Greater Bay Area and even other cities in the interior of China.
Among the interested brands, IPIM says that a Spanish jewelry brand, headquartered in Spain and with more than 200 stores in 30 countries, has already preliminarily confirmed a visit to Macau at the end of this month to learn about the business environment and the local store market.
According to the organization, there are interested Portuguese companies that have shown their intention to include Macau in their international expansion plan. “They are considering operating in Macau through local partners, to introduce their brands in the city and promote Portuguese products in collaboration with the Macau business sector”, he said.
It is recalled that the Economic Development Plan to Support the Establishment of the First Store in Macau, launched by IPIM in cooperation with the Industrial Development and Commercialization Fund, will open for applications on November 1st. Brands from abroad, including those from Portuguese or Spanish-speaking countries, that enter Macau and open their first store, will be able to obtain financial support of up to one million patacas to cover expenses related to starting up and operating the store.
During the visit to the Iberian Peninsula, IPIM took the opportunity to promote, among local business associations, business sectors and industry experts, the latest commercial opportunities in Macau.
IPIM presented the second edition of the China–Portuguese Speaking Countries (Macau) Economic and Trade Exhibition (2nd C-PLPEX), which will take place in Macau from the 22nd to the 25th of this month. The organization invited Portuguese and Spanish companies to visit Macau to participate in the event and gain a comprehensive understanding of the city's business panorama through an inspection visit to the territory.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 23:05:06</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Startups’ from PALOP and Timor-Leste in Sino-Lusophone competition in Macau rise 73%</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/14/startups-de-palop-e-timor-leste-em-competicao-sino-lusofona-de-macau-sobem-73/</link><description>The Sino-Lusophone 929 Challenge competition in Macau attracted 170 startups from Portuguese-speaking African Countries (PALOP) and Timor-Leste, 73% more than in 2024, one of the organizers told Lusa yesterday.

Marco Duarte Rizzolio, co-founder of the 929 Challenge, chose the increased participation of less developed Portuguese-speaking countries as the highlight of the fifth edition of the 929 Challenge.
The professor at the City University of Macau justified the rise with the competition's new partners: “we signed strategic agreements with Cabo Verde Digital and Eduardo Mondlane University [Mozambique]”.
Since the end of the last edition, in November 2024, Rizzolio has already been to Angola twice to promote the 929 Challenge, while the other co-founder, José Alves, visited São Tomé and Príncipe and Timor-Leste. “They are very small countries, with a very small population and a very undeveloped ecosystem, but we are even able to have projects there”, highlighted the organizer, thanks to “a particularity of developing countries”.
In countries with a relatively low average age, “also due to the lack of jobs, young people are full of energy, they are very open to developing businesses”, explained Rizzolio.
The fifth edition of the 929 Challenge in Macau includes for the first time the ‘Future Builders’ award, for the best startup in the PALOP and Timor-Leste.
The only time that a team from PALOP and Timor-Leste reached the finalists was in the first edition, launched in 2021, in the middle of the covid-19 pandemic, then only aimed at university students.
A project by the Lusófona University of Guinea-Bissau to install solar panels in the Gabu region, in the east of the country, came in second place.
Rizzolio also highlighted that, for the first time, startups from Portuguese-speaking countries – including Portugal and Brazil – are in the majority in the 929 Challenge, representing around 65% of the 402 participants. “We had many more projects coming here from [mainland] China”, said the organizer.
The 929 Challenge “has already acquired a certain notoriety”, defended Rizzolio, namely through the promotion carried out at the SIM Conference, in May, in Porto, and at the Web Summit, in June, in Rio de Janeiro.
The 929 Challenge's online bootcamp began on Monday, attracting more than 400 teams and startups, an increase of more than 25% compared to 2024.
The last edition of the competition had recorded a maximum, with more than 1,600 participants in more than 320 teams.
Until October 11th, teams will have a series of lectures, mentoring sessions and workshops every day “designed to help teams shape, validate and strengthen sustainable business models”.
The best 16 plans – eight from companies and eight from university students – will have 10 minutes to convince the 929 Challenge jury and potential investors in the final, on November 30th. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 23:02:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Autumn Salon brings contemporary art from Macau to Casa Garden once again</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/14/salao-de-outono-volta-a-trazer-a-arte-contemporanea-de-macau-a-casa-garden/</link><description>The Autumn Salon is returning to Casa Garden, after a last edition in the Parisian galleries. This year, in addition to the main exhibition, there will also be space for a parallel ceramics exhibition and the exhibition of the project “Surrealist Chinoiserie: Golden City of Seres – A Cultural and Artistic Exchange Exhibition and Performance between Macao and Antwerp”, opened this summer in Europe.

The 16th edition of the All For All Society (AFA) Autumn Salon, one of the most relevant events in Macau's artistic scene, opens its doors to the public on October 24th, at 6:30 pm, at Casa Garden. This year's initiative, under the theme “Homecoming: A Reunion Amidst the Light and Shadow of History”, once again presents the best of Macau's contemporary art in its multiple aspects, crossing different styles and artistic areas.
In total, around a hundred works signed by more than 50 local artists will be on display, demonstrating how the talents of Macau's contemporary art scene are evident in media as diverse as Chinese painting, oil painting, sculpture, photography, ceramics or digital art. In the words of AFA, the latest edition of the event “showcases the diversity and vitality of Macau’s contemporary art scene, while highlighting emerging talents and demonstrating the heritage and energy of Macau’s artistic ecosystem”.
This 16th anniversary also celebrates the return of the Autumn Salon to its original home, Casa Garden, after a brief stint at the Shoppes at Parisian. It is worth remembering that the historic Fundação Oriente building was closed for five months for restoration work, in the first half of the year, and is now returning to host the exhibition with a renewed appearance.
In addition to the main exhibition, there will also be a ceramic exhibition “The Whims of Creation”, designed by the winner of last year's Fundação Oriente Art Prize, Lio Pou I, and curated by Julia Lam Tsz Kwan and Leong Kit Man. According to the AFA, the award-winning artist's work stands out for the “characteristic shapes of clouds and bodies” that “explore the deep meaning of life and existence”.
Casa Garden will also house the project “Surrealist Chinoiserie: Golden City of Seres – A Cultural and Artistic Exchange Exhibition and Performance between Macao and Antwerp”, exhibited this summer in Antwerp. Organized by Art For All Society (AFA Macau) and curated by artist Alice Kok, the exhibition is inspired by the 'chinoiserie' aesthetic and combines multiple artistic branches – dance, music or visual arts – in a single immersive journey about “desire, technology and cultural symbolism”, according to a statement released at the time.
The intercultural show brings together a series of names already common in AFA exhibitions. Visual artist Leong Chi Mou uses steel and brass mesh to reimagine a new type of silk, while juxtaposing traditional landscape motifs with seemingly out-of-contextual elements like drones and surveillance cameras. Choreographers Jay Zhang and Tina Kan are responsible for the dance aspect, integrating elements of contemporary ballet with artistic expressions from the sandy city of Dunhuang.
Stylist and body painting artist Mandy Cheuk complements the futuristic component with tiaras inspired by “crystalline structures and cyborg forms, imagining the interaction between body and technology”, as detailed by AFA. In turn, the music is written by composer Faye Choi, one of the three elements that make up the Macau electronic band EVADE, and performed by Iris Lo. Through the sounds of the flute, the aim is to guide the viewer through an immersive sensory experience that combines the “ethereal” tones of the East with the “texture” of Western electronic music.
The Macau public can witness this performance at 6:30 pm on December 6th, the closing day of the Autumn Salon.</description><pubDate /></item></channel></rss>