<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/27/maioria-dos-gatos-adoptados-no-jockey-club-tem-problemas-de-saude/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Thai Prime Minister survives the motion of distrust</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/27/primeira-ministra-tailandesa-sobrevive-a-mocao-de-desconfianca/</link><description>The Prime Minister of Thailand resisted a motion of distrust in Parliament, which questioned the management of the economy and calls to former leader and father, Thaksin Shinawatra, convicted of corruption. Paetongtarn was supported by 319 deputies, against 161, who voted against her, in a total of 500 members of the Chamber of Representatives.
 
The Prime Minister of Thailand, Paetongtarn Shinawatra, survived yesterday to a motion of distrust in Parliament, which questioned the management of the economy and the links to the former leader and father, Thaksin Shinawatra, convicted of corruption.
Paetongtarn, 38, who took office in August, was supported by 319 deputies, against 161, who voted against it, totaling 500 members of the Chamber of Representatives, the Baixa do Parliament
As planned, the leader was supported by the 11 parties of the government coalition, led by Puea Thai (Thai people), a platform linked to the Shinawatra clan.
The motion was presented Monday by the Popular Party, in opposition, heir to the Avanzar party, dissolved last August by a controversial court decision.
During the two sessions preceding the vote, the debate turned around the poor performance of the Thai economy and the alleged influence of Thaksin, who ruled the country between 2021 and 2006, the year that was removed from power by a military coup.
Paetongtarn, a first-minister candidate for PUEA Thai in the May 2023 elections, reached the power in August 2024, after the then leader Srettha Thavisin, also from PEA Thai, was deprived by order of the Constitutional Court after appointing minister a corruption-convicted leader.
Thaksin, Thailand's most influential and polarizing politician in the last 20 years, has returned to the country after spending almost 15 years in exile the same day Srettha has taken office.
The former leader was arrested on arrival at Bangkok, accused of corruption, but did not pass a night in prison, having been transferred on the same day to a hospital, where he was six months old, and then placed in house arrest until his release, days after his daughter had risen to power.
Thaksin, 75, claims to be taken from politics, but occasionally admitted advice to the current leader and was seen to preside over meetings with other prominent Thai political leaders.
The Reform Party Advance won the May 2023 elections, but failed to rule due to a Senate veto (upper -tune of Parliament), then composed of representatives linked to the extinct Military Junta.
The party was eventually dissolved by the Constitutional Court, following an electoral promise to alter the laws that protect the Thai Royal House of criticism.
PEA Thai, which initially allied with Advance, eventually agreed with a coalition government in which parties are associated with the military, once enemies of the Shinawatras. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:51:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Rangel highlights in Beijing the importance of Chinese investment for the Portuguese economy</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/27/rangel-destaca-em-pequim-importancia-do-investimento-chines-para-a-economia-portuguesa/</link><description>Paulo Rangel highlighted yesterday the “important role” of Chinese investment in the Portuguese economy, during a meeting with Chinese counterparts, Wang Yi. The Portuguese Foreign Minister has invited “more Chinese companies to invest and thrive in Portugal” and indicated that Lisbon “is willing to reinforce cooperation with China” in several fields.
 
Portuguese Foreign Minister Paulo Rangel highlighted yesterday the “important role” of Chinese investment in the Portuguese economy, during a meeting with Chinese counterparts Wang Yi, according to a statement issued by the Chinese authorities.
The head of Portuguese diplomacy has invited “more Chinese companies to invest and prosper in Portugal” and indicated that Lisbon “is willing to reinforce cooperation with China in the domains of economics and commerce, energy, health, finance, infrastructure and ecological transformation”.
Rangel stated that Portugal and China "have a long history of interaction" and that relations between the two countries "have been developing well," reads the note spread by the Chinese Foreign Ministry.
Beijing and Lisbon “gave an example to the world” by solving the issue of Macao peacefully, he added.
Quoted in the same statement, Wang Yi highlighted the “good tradition of respect and mutual support” between the two countries. "Portugal is one of the countries of the European Union that receives the most Chinese investment" per capita "," said the chief of Chinese diplomacy, who appealed to "widening cooperation in the domains of investment in projects, ecological transformation, digital economy, innovation and research, information and communication."
Wang highlighted the role that Macau can play "like a bridge to promote the relationship between the two countries to achieve greater development."
The Chinese diplomat expressed his "support for Europe in maintaining his strategic autonomy" and the hope "that Portugal play an active role in" healthy development of relations between China and Europe. "
The two ministers “discussed issues of common interest, such as the 'crisis' in Ukraine,” according to the Chinese Foreign Ministry's statement, which no longer gave details.
China has become, in the last decade, the fourth largest foreign direct investor in Portugal. Chinese, state and private companies have a global position valued at 11.2 billion euros in the Portuguese economy, according to Banco de Portugal (BDP). Investments cover the areas of energy, bank, safe or health.
In 2018, the two countries signed a memorandum of understanding of the “Track and Route” initiative, a mega project of infrastructures launched by Beijing that aims to expand its global influence through the construction of ports, railways or self -established. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:50:24</pubDate></item><item><title>China is “important partner” in the industrial training of Portugal in new energies, says AICEP</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/27/china-e-importante-parceiro-na-capacitacao-industrial-de-portugal-em-novas-energias-diz-aicep/</link><description>China is an “important partner” in the industrial training of Portugal in the sector of new energies, said yesterday the president of AICEP, Ricardo Arroja, highlighting the technological advances of the Asian country. The leader of the Portugal Agency for Investment and Foreign Trade (AICEP) pointed to the Lusa Agency in Beijing, the “conciliation of interests” between the human resources of Portuguese “great value”, Portugal's ability to serve as China's global platform and capabilities. The Asian country represents three quarters of global investment in the production of all clean technologies (photovoltaic, wind, green hydrogen or heat pumps), according to data from the International Energy Agency (AIE). Photovoltaic solar energy and electrical batteries manufacture are the technologies in which the geographical concentration of production is more pronounced, with 80% of the total global capacity in China, the same source indicated.
Calb (China Aviation Lithium Battery), one of the largest Chinese batteries manufacturers, confirmed last February an investment of two billion euros in Portugal to build a Lithium-Lithium Battery Factory in Sines, inserting itself into its European expansion strategy. "It is a large investment that will really allow Portugal to have a fundamental axis to develop the electric vehicle industry," said the president of AICEP. The investment also opens a new chapter in China's participation in the Portuguese economy, which has grown at a two -digit pace per year over the past decade, but has been the acquisition of assets in the areas of energy, bank, insurance or health. Chinese, state and private companies, already have a global position evaluated at 11.2 billion euros in the Portuguese economy, according to Banco de Portugal (BDP). "The big challenge is a little extend the presence of foreign direct investment [Chinese] in Portugal in the industrial domain. It is very important to have greater industrial traction in China, because there are many of these sectors where innovation is increasingly from here," said Arroja. The official also revealed that Portugal wants to attract Chinese investment to build wind parks 'offshore', after visiting Goldwind headquarters in Beijing, the world leader in the manufacture of wind turbines. "Obviously, China has important companies that may be interested in addressing the investment opportunities that will be formed in Portugal in this area," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:50:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Airbus bets on sustainability with “total electrification” of helicopters by 2030</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/27/airbus-aposta-na-sustentabilidade-com-electrificacao-total-de-helicopteros-ate-2030/</link><description>The low -altitude economy is one of the major bets for the economic diversification of MSAR, although it leads to risks and environmental concerns. In the scope of the Breakfast Talks of the France Chamber of Commerce Macau, speaker Joseph Baptiste, a high leader of Airbus Helicopters, reveals the sustainability strategies and measures being taken by the sector to reconcile innovation safely, in a sky increasingly disputed by airplanes, helicopters and drones.
 
Imagine a trip between Malta and the island of jouissance, separated by the Mediterranean Sea and about 22 kilometers away. Conventional means of transport - car and a boat crossing - would require approximately two hours and forty minutes to complete the route and reach the center of the island. What if this route could be shortened for only 50 minutes, without transhipment, with a single helicopter trip?
This was one of the reflection points explored yesterday morning, during the March session of lectures and breakfasts organized monthly by the France Macao Chamber of Commerce (FMCC), at the Sofitel Hotel. The panel, entitled “climbing new heights: the view of the Helicopters Airbus for the low -altitude economy,” was speaker Joseph Baptiste, pilot and high leader of Airbus Helicopters three years ago in China, where he took the direction of the first helicopter simulator in the country.
Macao currently offers round trip helicopter trips to Hong Kong with hourly matches except Tuesdays and Wednesdays. Macau's “Sky Shuttle” also provides trips from and to Shenzhen, though less frequently. The speaker of the lecture explained that Macau and Hong Kong will probably be the “easiest” areas to take off in the Great Bay, in general, a “geographical embarrassment” in the region's air traffic. The fact of four international airports - Macao, Hong Kong, Zhuhai and Guangzhou - are concentrated within 150 kilometers hinders low -altitude air traffic due to the high circulation of commercial aircraft and branch and landing movements in this area.
How is it possible to ensure flight safety in a “congested environment” by helicopters, airplanes and drones? The speaker clarified that Airbus has invested in new technologies for this purpose, citing, for example, the possibility of obtaining a safe flight trajectory, detecting obstacles and communicating with air vehicles nearby through interaction with a tactile tablet. "We can see others while others can see us, which helps to ensure a safe flight even when it comes to autonomous aircraft such as drones," said Joseph Baptiste.
A word has also been dedicated to the efforts that Airbus has implemented to make low altitude flights more sustainable, such as the preference for biological -based materials, known to experts in the area such as SAF (“Sustainable Aviation Fuel”, an acronym translated as “sustainable aviation fuel”). Currently, all Airbus helicopters are able to operate with up to 50% SAF, and the goal for the end of the decade is to reach 100%. "For those who are not familiar with the concept of sustainable fuels, it is basically recycled oil of chips," he joked, pulling laughter to the audience.
Joseph Baptiste warns that the objectives of fuel decarbonization and efficiency are not instantaneous, to implement gradual strategies, “step by step”, aligned with the Chinese concept of “Yi” (义) - to act in agreement with solid moral and ethical principles. Prototypes already under discussion at Airbus headquarters includes a “micro-hybrid” helicopter that offers the “possibility of turning off a engine during the flight, reducing 15% of fuel consumption” of bimotor vehicles. Another proposal from Airbus goes through the "total hybridization", in which the helicopter can work with both rechargeable electric batteries and traditional fuel methods, something that already happens in cars such as "Lexus, Toyota Prius and BMW". The aim is to reach “total electrification” by 2030, with the creation of a “fully autonomous electric vehicle”.
In response to an intervention by an audience member, who questioned the possibility of existing hydrogen -powered helicopters, the speaker said that this idea is "definitely on the table for airplanes." According to Joseph Baptiste, Airbus has developed a “carbonic emissions” plan using hydrogen, initially scheduled for 2035, but indefinitely postponed for “political reasons”. As for helicopters, the question is more complex: the volume of this gas takes up much more space than traditional fuel, even in liquid or compressed form. The only way to reconsider this issue would be with the creation of “a technology capable of decreasing the volume of hydrogen, so far nonexistent.
Another public issue was related to the safety problems of the so-called VTOL, an acronym for the expression “vertical Take-off and Landing” (translated into Portuguese such as “vertical drop and landing”) that refers to air vehicles that do not require traditional landing lanes. Having mainly over the drones, Joseph Baptiste acknowledged that “one of the great concerns of industry is related to the fact that the VTOL are not subject to the same rigid rules of helicopters or airplanes”-even “endangering” the operations of these means of transport. The speaker argued that the solution to the problem goes through two hypotheses: either the VTOL began to guide the same guidelines as the remaining air vehicles, or the control towers will be forced to stop dropping outputs to ensure the flight of drones in total autonomy-which, he concluded, is “impossible”.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:50:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism sector expects 10% increase in the number of visitors during Easter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/27/sector-do-turismo-espera-aumento-de-10-do-numero-de-visitantes-durante-a-pascoa/</link><description>At Easter height, the number of visitors coming to Macau could increase 10% compared to the same period last year. On the contrary, Macao residents who will take advantage of the holidays to travel no longer prefer South Korea or Japan, exchanging these destinations in the interior of China, says the Macao Tourist Industry Association.
 
The Macau Tourist Industry Association believes that, during the Easter period, the number of visitors who arrive in the region will increase 10% compared to last year's same -year period. This year, the Easter holidays are joined by a weekend, bunching between April 18 and 21.
According to Andy Wu, president of the association, this increase should be driven by international and Hong Kong visitors, since in the interior of China Easter days are not a holiday. The representative of the sector points out that the government has continued to promote Macau with abroad. "This year, the trend of international arrivals has been encouraging, with 240,000 international arrivals in January, an increase of 2% over the previous year, and more than 200,000 international arrivals in February, an increase of 18% over the previous year, and it is estimated that arrival for this year's Easter holiday increase 10% over previous years," said Andy Wu.
Last year, at the time of Easter, Macau received more than one million visitors. In 2024, the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) accounted for 1,051,826 visitors for a total of 11 days from the Easter period.
On the contrary, Macao residents who will take advantage of Easter's holidays to travel are changing the most attractive traditions, such as South Korea or Japan, in the interior of China, the association points out.
This new trend, explains the president of the association, has to do with the price of travel to Japan, which "increased markedly during the holidays, with the charges and airplane tickets at another 1,000 to 2,000 patacas than on weekdays." Therefore, "many residents have chosen to travel in a staggered calendar, and the number of residents traveling to Japan is expected to be 20% to 30% lower than the same period last year."
As for South Korea, “due to uncertainties such as air accidents and influenza epidemics”, the number of residents traveling to that destination is expected to decrease 50% over the previous year.
Continental China thus becomes a popular destination for Macao residents during the Easter period. Since in China there are no Easter holidays, travel prices remain relatively stable and the price/performance ratio "is excellent," says Andy Wu, adding that "the rich tourist resources of mainland China are extremely attractive."</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:50:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese teaching at EPM should be approached with MNE, says Apim</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/27/ensino-do-chines-na-epm-deve-ser-abordado-com-mne-diz-apim/</link><description>The president of the Macanese Instruction Promotion Association (Apim) suggests that Chinese teaching at the Portuguese school, where Mandarin and Non -Cantonese is, locally dominant language, is approached on Paulo Rangel's visit to Macau.
 
"I have always advocated that Cantonese must have status. Because students, when they leave school, are in a Cantonese world. This with all the merit that can have teaching in Mandarin," he told Lusa Miguel de Senna Fernandes, who directs Apim, Portuguese Cultural and Educational Association.
"It should always be approached," he replied, when asked if the issue should be taken to the Foreign Minister, who has the tutelage of the Portuguese School of Macau (EPM) and will be in Macau this Friday. "It is an issue that should be posed. It is a delicate question, because we are talking about an official language," he added, referring to Mandarin, an official language in China.
The official, also vice president of the Portuguese School of Macau Foundation (EPM), admits that this is not a question that generates consensus -"many parents do not agree with this vision" -but stresses that the learning of Cantonese "is a vehicle of integration" as it is the dominant language in the territory.
Basic law establishes Chinese and Portuguese as official languages, and it is not defined which Chinese is. Mandarin is the Chinese official language, but Cantonese, spoken in southern China, remains the dominant language in the two special administrative regions of Macau and Hong Kong.
In recent years, however, Mandarin has been a growing option in teaching in Macao, with experts warning that the future of Cantonese and local culture is concerned.
The president of the Macao Yue Dialect Association, Tong Choi Lan, told Lusa in December that education authorities encourage local schools to use Mandarin in teaching Chinese discipline since about 2011. Some, noticed, even chose to adopt the mandarin as a teaching language. In the case of EPM, a private institution that is part of the public school network of Macao, the option also falls on the Chinese official language.
Despite defending the teaching of Cantonese, Senna Fernandes recognizes the importance of Mandarin learning - "It's a desiderate, therefore noble, absolutely valid, I have no doubt."
Doubts raise, however, regarding the results of the bet, since in the “contact with some students”, they reveal difficulties, he added. "Those who are not aware of Chinese arrives here and learn Mandarin. ... There are students who are exceptional for languages, I am not in question, but in most cases it does not happen. Why? Because the environment does not speak mandarin, although now it is started to listen more," he said.
 
Portugal's positioning in relation to China
 
The president of the House of Portugal in Macao (CPM) defended the importance of Paulo Rangel to clarify the Portuguese community about the government's position in relation to China. "We are here, we suffer the consequences of these relationships [between Portugal and China], good or bad. We had very close relationships for a long time, which changed with Covid. I have not seen things again, and I think it was important that the minister explains what the position is," he told Lusa Maria Amelia António, saying that Portugal does not have to "align faithfully with all that is said in Europe and above all states. United, ”he said.
Before the pandemic, he recalled the official, there was “permanent communication” and “much exchange” between the Portuguese and Chinese authorities.
Today is noticeable a “hardening regarding the Portuguese” in macao immigration, Maria Amelia António declared, but not being able to affirm categorically whether the position is related to “this removal” between China and the West.
Macao authorities have not accepted new requests for residence in the territory for Portuguese for the “exercise of specialized technical functions”, allowing for justification of family reunion or previous connection to the territory. The guidelines eliminate a practice signed after the transition from Macao in 1999. The alternative to a Portuguese national guarantee the resident identity ticket (BIR) undergo an application to recent qualified frame capture programs. Another hypothesis is the issuance of a BlueCard, a limited authorization to the labor bond, without the benefits of residents, namely at health or education level.
These limitations have affected CPM in hiring professionals to integrate the School of Art and Crafts. Mentioning the strategic relationship between China and the Portuguese -language universe and Beijing's interest in the Portuguese language, the associative leader mourned the “slightly contradictory” stance. "We can not make omelets without eggs, we who are here and who work with the Portuguese culture and the Portuguese language, we have a hard time having people who replace those that went out. Many Portuguese from Macao, and working in these areas with these qualifications] is very complicated," he said.
The head of Portuguese diplomacy visits Macau this Friday, after passing by Beijing and Haikou, in the province of Haião. In Macau, Paulo Rangel has scheduled meetings with Sam Hou Fai, as well as with the counselors of the Portuguese communities, associative representatives, educational institutions and Portuguese entrepreneurs. Visit the EPM and the Consulate General of Portugal in the territory. At the end of Friday, MNE goes to Hong Kong to visit “Lush Stories”, an exhibition dedicated to the Portuguese community at the Hong Kong History Museum. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:47:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese government accuses Taiwan of “delivering the TSMC tray” to the United States</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/27/governo-chines-acusa-taiwan-de-entregar-a-tsmc-de-bandeja-aos-estados-unidos/</link><description>China yesterday accused Taiwan authorities of “delivering tray” to Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing Company (TSMC), the largest semiconductor manufacturer in the world, to the United States, where the company announced major investment and expansion plans.
The Council of State's Office spokesman for the Taiwan affairs, Chen Binhua, lamented that "TSMC has become a piece of juicy meat on the cutting board, ready to be undone in pieces," according to state television CCTV.
According to Chen, TSMC is becoming "an American company," which, according to him, is a sign that the Progressive Democratic Party (DPP) in Taiwan power, "only has in mind party selfishness and is not concerned with the well-being of the Taiwan compatriots or the interests of the industrial sector."
The spokesman warned that the DPP "will move forward" on the road of the "sale and destruction of Taiwan" and that the industrial sector and the people of the territory "will not only lose jobs, but also opportunities for future development."
TSMC controls about 90% of the worldwide manufacturing market of advanced semiconductors, essential for US companies such as Nvidia and Apple, and for technologies such as Artificial Intelligence.
TSMC CEO C.C. Wei announced earlier this month, from the White House, an investment of $ 100 billion in the US, which some analysts played as a gesture of goodwill to US President Donald Trump.
The investment is intended to build three new factories, two advanced chips packaging facilities and a research and development center.
These $ 100 billion join the investment of TSMC's $ 65 billion (60 billion) from Phoenix, Arizona, where there is a factory that started operating in late 2024 and plans to open two more factories in the coming years.
Although TSMC defended these investments from a purely commercial perspective, the Taiwan government is looking for an approximation with Trump, which threatened to impose rates up to 100% on Taiwanese chips and repeatedly accused the island of the United States semiconductor industry.
According to Taiwan's leader, TSMC's global expansion reinforces its leadership and the competitiveness of the Taiwan semiconductor industry.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:50:22</pubDate></item><item><title>9% of public bus passengers traveled in express careers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/27/9-dos-passageiros-de-autocarros-publicos-viajaram-nas-carreiras-expresso/</link><description>DSAT, TCM and Transmac officials participated in the Macao Forum program, where they took stock of the results of 2024, the year in which a passenger fee similar to the same period of 2019 was achieved. The three leaders recognized the need to adjust and optimize bus routes, in order to satisfy the growing number of passengers and to promote greater operational transportation efficiency in Macao.
 
Last year, Macao's public buses carried about 227 million passengers, a number similar to the record of 229 million observed in 2019 and an increase of 6.4% compared to the previous year of 2023. Passengers who traveled in express careers, with the indication “X”, represented about 9% of the total of travelers of 2024.
The figures were released by the head of the Transport Management Division of the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT), Lau NGA Hong, on the Macao Forum Program of the TDM Radio Channel in Chinese language. The Deputy Director-General of the Macao Collective Transport Society (TCM), Chan IAT, and Transmac Operations Director, Un Kuan Ngai, were also present in the emission, where they recognized the need to gradually increase the number of drivers and buses-including electric-in order to respond to the growing flow of passengers.
In this regard, the DSAT leader also assured that the government will continue to monitor bus routes and make the necessary adjustments and improvements, as well as to provide express or special buses for the largest passenger flow. By way of example, it mentioned the change from Route 10a to Route 60, which facilitated coordination between buses on the bar and the light meter.
Transmac's director of operations also took advantage of the TDM program to respond to listeners' concern about banks facing the opposite direction, arguing that the position of banks is inevitable because they are behind the bus wheels, and that their removal would lead to the reduction of bus capacity - and therefore make the discussion over new bus stops obsolete. It is recalled that by the end of last year, 75 new stops were completed.
According to data presented in the Macau Forum Program, TCM currently has 544 vehicles in operation, making 5,900 trips per day; Transmac, in turn, has 410 electric vehicles that make more than 4,200 trips a day.  The two public bus companies have a total of 929 buses powered by environmental energies, which corresponds to more than 92% of all buses in Macao.
According to information previously released by the operators, the total carbon emissions of their operational vehicles have decreased significantly over the past three years. Total carbon emissions by 2023 decreased 18.2% to 30% compared to 2019 and, in the first three quarters of last year, emissions reduced another 3.1% to 6.2% over the same period last year.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:49:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Hospital das Islands will have centers of assisted procreation and hemodialysis this year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/27/hospital-das-ilhas-tera-centros-de-procriacao-assistida-e-de-hemodialise-este-ano/</link><description>The territory will have another assisted procreation center later this year, which will be inaugurated at the Ilhas Hospital. According to the medical institution, this center has already opened the procreation assessment services and external prior admission consultations, at the same time the acquisition, installation, testing of relevant facilities and equipment and the formation of personnel, predicting that the center will start as soon as possible, in the second half of this year.
The Macau Union Hospital stated that the opening of the center is in articulation with the introduction of the new medically assisted procreation techniques law. The hospital points out that the new service aims to provide users “a complete range of assisted playback options”, thus improving the global quality of life of residents.
In a statement, the institution added that this year will also open a center of hemodialysis, due to increased demand for service. In addition, a health management center and the international medical hospitalization service will begin their operations.
The island hospital began operating in September last year and is gradually widening its services. Until last month, the number of external consultation services specialized increased to 52, and the number of consultations in specialties rose 50% compared to the registration at the start of the hospital's opening.
The institution's computed tomography (CT) capacity has already reached a quarter of the total public services of Macao. Regarding tumor treatment services, whose patients are most often sent for treatment outside Macao, two state -of -the -art linear accelerators were placed in operation at the hospital's radiotherapy center, having already performed 277 radiotherapy services for cancer patients.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:49:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing wants to create electromagnetic space launch platform by 2028</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/27/pequim-quer-criar-plataforma-de-lancamento-espacial-electromagnetica-ate-2028/</link><description>China plans to develop the world's first electromagnetic rocket launch platform by 2028, in a project that seeks to reduce costs and increase the frequency of access to space.
 
The system, developed by the private company Galactic Energy in collaboration with state research institutes, the Ziyang Municipal Government (in Sichuan Central Province) and China Aerospace Science and Industry Corporation (Casic), will use superconducting imm to accelerate rockets at supersonic speeds before ignition, in a structure similar to a Maglev, but Miglev train, but vertically oriented.
According to its creators, this technology would double the load capacity, significantly reduce operating costs and facilitate more frequent releases with less maintenance, the Hong Kong South China Morning Post post on Tuesday.
The long-term objective is to make rocket launches as frequent, predictable and efficient as daily high-speed train trips, integrating them into a regularly used technological infrastructure. However, experts warned that there are still technical obstacles, such as flight accuracy and thermal resistance during the initial climb.
The verification platform is being built by Casic and the Ziyang government. In September 2023, a magnetic levitation test using high temperature superconductors reached a speed of 234 kilometers per hour on a 380 meter track, as part of the project's initial technical checks.
Founded in 2018, Galactic Energy conducted 18 successful releases of its Ceres-1 rocket, with a total of 77 satellites placed in orbit.
The most recent, on March 21, placed six meteorological satellites in a heliosyncron orbit.
The company is also working on the development of CERES-2, with a payload capacity up to 3.5 tons compared to the 400 kilograms of the previous model.
In September 2023, however, one of its releases failed due to “abnormal flight performance”, according to the company. A few days earlier, Galactic Energy had become the first Chinese private company to make a successful sea release.
Chinese scientists have already begun to investigate similar systems to the lunar environment, with the objective of transporting materials such as the helium-3 of the terrestrial satellite surface using electromagnetic catapults, thus eliminating the need for large amounts of fuel.
Although the plan is still in a preliminary phase, the initiative is part of the Chinese government strategy to consolidate its commercial aerospace industry.
China has invested strongly in its space program in recent years, reaching Marcos such as the landing of the Chang'e 4 probe on the hidden side of the moon, the arrival in Mars and the construction of the Tiangong space station, which will operate for about ten years. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:50:23</pubDate></item><item><title>China accuses USA of violating international law by restricting access to technology</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/27/china-acusa-eua-de-violarem-direito-internacional-ao-restringir-acesso-a-tecnologia/</link><description>China said yesterday that the United States “are seriously violating the basic rules of law and international relations” by adding 70 Chinese companies to a list of prohibited entities to access US technology.
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakun said at a press conference that Washington "seriously undermines companies' legitimate rights and interests the safety and stability of global production and supply chains."
"We urge the United States to cease to generalize the concept of national security and stop politicizing, instrumentalize and militarize economic, commercial and scientific and technological issues," the spokesman said, adding that China "firmly opposes" to this measure.
Beijing "will take the necessary measures to firmly safeguard the legitimate rights and interests of Chinese companies," the spokesman added, installing the US to "stop unjustifiably repressing Chinese companies."
The US Department of Commerce Industry and Security Office reported in a statement on Monday that it added 80 Companies from China, United Arab Emirates, South Africa, Iran and Taiwan to the list for their "national security and foreign policy activities."
Among the companies, about 70 are Chinese, including 11 in advanced artificial intelligence and semiconductor development, among other domains, and 27 highlighted for “acquiring or trying to acquire” components from the United States to support the modernization of Chinese armed forces. The names of the companies were not disclosed.
The statement stressed that the expansion of the list aims to "restrict China's Communist Party's ability to acquire and develop exascale computing capabilities, as well as quantum technologies for military application," and "prevent the development of China's hypersonic weapon program." "Under the strong leadership of President Donald Trump, the Trade Department is taking decisive measures to protect America," United States Secretary Howard Lutnick said in a statement.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:50:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Forest Fires in South Korea have already caused death of 24 people</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/27/fogos-florestais-na-coreia-do-sul-ja-causaram-morte-de-24-pessoas/</link><description>The wind fires caused by the wind, which are among the worst in the history of South Korea, caused the death of 24 people, destroyed more than 200 structures and forced the evacuation of 27,000 people, according to the last balance.
The death toll included a pilot who died after a helicopter dropped during efforts to contain forest fires in the city of Uiseong in the Southeast, one of the hardest areas, according to the authorities. The aircraft had no other crew.
According to the National Fire Agency, at least 26 other people suffered varying degrees of injuries.
An old Buddhist temple, houses, factories and vehicles are among the structures destroyed in forest fires.
South Korea's acting president Han Duck-Soo said the forest fires that started on Friday are causing worse damage than many other previous forest fires. "The damage is increasing. We fear having forest fires damage we have never had before, so we have to concentrate all our capabilities to erase the fires by the end of this week," said Han.
According to the official, about 4,650 firefighters, soldiers and other employees are on the ground, with the help of about 130 helicopters.
The biggest fires occurred in Andong, in the counties of neighbors of Uiseong and Sancheong and in the city of Ulsan, according to the South Korean Ministry of Interior.
The Uiseong fire destroyed almost half of more than 30 structures in Gounsa, a temple that was originally built in the seventh century.
Korea Forest Service has raised forest fire alert to the highest level across the country on Tuesday, requiring local governments to designate more workers to respond to emergencies, increase the entrance restrictions to forest and parks and recommend that military units suspend royal exercises.
Government authorities suspect that human error caused several fires.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:50:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Exports grow and imports shrink</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/27/exportacoes-crescem-e-importacoes-encolhem/</link><description>In the first two months of the year, the value of the exported goods was 2.38 billion patacas, ie 13.8% compared to the same period of 2024. In the same period, the imported value of goods for the MSAR was 19.8 billion, less 5% compared to the early months of last year.
Thus, the commercial balance deficit in January and February this year was encifted at 17.51 ​​billion patacas, less 1.33 billion compared to the same year's same year period, which was 18.84 billion patacas. The information was released yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC).
Observing only the month of February, it appears that the value of re-export (1.15 billion patacas) grew 31.8%, compared to February 2024. It is emphasized that the value of perfume re-export and the jewelery without diamonds ascended 310.1%and 113.3%, respectively. However, the value of beauty products, make -up and skin care and casino articles decreased by 31.4% and 20.8%, respectively.
The value of imports of goods increased by 5.5%, in annual terms. DSEC emphasizes that the imported value of optical instruments and casino articles rose 113.3% and 66.2%, respectively. However, the amount imported from construction materials and mobile phones fell 27.4% and 24.2%, respectively.
Analyzing exports by countries or destination territories, exported goods for Hong Kong (1.84 billion patacas) and to the European Union (40 million patacas) from January to February of this year increased 24.2% and 2.3%, respectively, compared to the same period last year. However, the exported amounts of goods to the interior of China (117 million patacas) decreased 3.8%.
As for the countries or territories of origin, the amounts imported from goods produced in the European Union (6.26 billion of patacas), in the interior of China (5.87 billion patacas) in the first two months of 2025 dropped 8.4% and 1.1%, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:50:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Financial Reserve starts 2025 to gain 5.3 billion of Patacas</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/27/reserva-financeira-arranca-2025-a-ganhar-53-mil-milhoes-de-patacas/</link><description>Macau's financial reserve began 2025 on the rise, with the value of assets increasing 5.3 billion patacas in January, was announced yesterday.
The value of the reserve was 621.5 billion patacas in late January, according to data published in an official bulletin. Still, the value remains away from the record of 663.6 billion patacas reached in February 2021, in the middle of the pandemic.
According to data from the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM), the reserve had recorded by 2024 the best year since the COVID-19 pandemic after earning 35.7 billion patacas. This was the highest annual increase since 2019, when the value of the reserve increased by 70.6 billion patacas.
The value of the extraordinary reserve at the end of January was 452 billion Patacas and the basic reserve, equivalent to 150% of Macao's public budget, was 164.2 billion patacas. The territory budget for 2025 foresees a 7% increase in total expenses to 109.4 billion patacas.
The Macao Financial Reserve is mostly consisting of deposits and current accounts worth 248.1 billion, credit securities of 119.3 billion patacas and up to 247.6 billion in subcontractors.
In 2024, investments yielded to the financial reserve nearly 31 billion patacas, corresponding to a profitability rate of 5.3%, AMCM said in late February.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:50:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Author of attack with knife at Travessa dos Anjos hospitalized for psychiatric treatment</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/27/autor-de-ataque-com-faca-na-travessa-dos-anjos-internado-para-tratamento-psiquiatrico/</link><description>On Tuesday afternoon, a man entered a telecommunications store in Travessa dos Anjos and stabbed two employees who had to be hospitalized, not in danger of life. The Judicial Police (PJ) said yesterday that the perpetrator of the attack has no history of mental problems, but was hospitalized for psychiatric treatment. Authorities consider that there is evidence that it is an attempted murder and an offense crime to aggravated physical integrity.
 
The author of the attack with a knife that took place on Tuesday afternoon, in Travessa dos Anjos, next to Rua do Campo, was admitted to the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center for psychiatric treatment, despite not having a history of mental problems, the Judiciary Police (PJ) said.
At a press conference, the authorities explained that the suspect was in that area on the day of the attack since 4 pm, after bought the knife in a nearby supermarket. The man then walked to the rod of the rua do Campo, having given a slap on the back of a passerby for no apparent reason.
Around 5:30 pm, he suddenly advanced with a knife to hurt employees from a telecommunications store, stabbing two of them. The employees then managed to retreat to an office inside the store and, when closing the office door, the suspect's knife was trapped, disarming it. Even after being unarmed, the man remained abroad of the store until he was dominated by police officers who arrived at the scene.
Shortly after stabbing, information circulated on the internet that, before the attack, the suspect was involved in verbal clashes with the staff of that store, but, according to the latest police information, the theory is not confirmed. The PJ says that, according to the information provided by the telecommunications company, there is no registration of any dispute or complaint between the company and the suspect, and that several employees of the store, including the two people injured, said they did not know the suspect and had no grudge from anyone.
The PJ considers that there is evidence that it is an attempted murder and an offense crime to aggravated physical integrity. The case is now being investigated by the crime investigation section against the person.
One of the injured, a 26 -year -old resident, was injured in the neck area and lost consciousness, having been sent to the Conde de São Januário hospital center. The neck wound is over 18 centimeters and the man had to be sutured with more than 100 points. The other, also a 29 -year -old resident, suffered only one cut on his left arm and was sent to Kiang Wu Hospital to receive medical treatment. The victims are not in danger of life.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:48:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Most cats adopted at Jockey Club have health problems</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/27/maioria-dos-gatos-adoptados-no-jockey-club-tem-problemas-de-saude/</link><description>Most of the Jockey Club cats who have been adopted present disease manifestations, unlike the company's previous guarantee of animal health before claiming to send them to the continent. According to anima, among the 22 cats adopted, eight were diagnosed with feline panleucopenia, of which two have died. Several cats have respiratory infections at different levels. Macau's Jockey Club reacted yesterday and promised a 5,000 -pataca subsidy to medical expenses.
 
Anima, the Animal Protective Society, denounced the worrying state of health of several cats that were adopted by the public at Macau Jockey Club, in a recent adoption campaign after the controversial plan of the company sending almost 100 cats to Zhuhai. Of the total, more than 60 were welcomed by animal protection associations and 22 were placed in an open adoption process.
In a social media publication, anima revealed that most adopted cats have different infections. It is recalled that Macau Jockey Club had secured, either before the extinct shipping plan and before adoption, that all cats were in good health.
Among the 22 adopted, it was found that eight were diagnosed with feline panleucopenia, highly contagious viral disease between cats and possibly fatal, and two cats have already died for this reason.
The anima indicated that six cats, which are “in serious condition”, require hospitalization in veterinary clinics for observation. In addition, several cats showed signs of respiratory infections. Only four adopters reported that their cats have not expressed any clinical symptoms so far, so they were not taken to the veterinary clinic for examination.
The Animal Protection Association also highlighted some cases of cat health problems, including a serious case of bronchitis, which remained in the vet since adoption day. There is also a case of a cat with an open wound due to sterilization surgery that needs debridement every day. The organization also received the report of an adopter noting that all the cat's teeth were removed and that the animal was only one year old.
Of the more than 60 cats that were welcomed by the various local animal protection associations, two died due to feline panleukopenia and two lost their lives because of respiratory diseases. More than ten have disease demonstrations, whose medical expenses will be the Macau Jockey Club.
Tuesday's animal note stressed that, as for the adopted cats, it has been trying in the last two days to communicate with the Jockey Club to take the medical expenses and are waiting for the company's response. "The anima deeply regrets the unexpected financial position that fell on the adopters and the pain of the loss of cats due to feline panleucopenia," he said.
 
Jockey Club reacted
 
Macau Jockey Club reacted yesterday and left the guarantee of paying 5,000 patacas to each adopter. "The Jockey Club would like to express their condolences to adopters for the two cats that unfortunately died due to the disease, and will grant a 5,000 patacas allowance per cat to 22 March 16 adoption session," the horse race company said.
Quoted by Anima, the Jockey Club will assign the subsidy to the adopters through check, by animal. The association's note revealed that the Institute for Municipal Affairs participated in the coordination during the negotiation process with the Jockey Club.
It was thus concluded, for now, a new Macau Jockey Club controversy after its plan to send the cats that were in their space to the interior of China.
The Jockey Club held its latest horse racing at the end of March last year and, with the end of the space, the government will recover the ground in question at the beginning of next month. The cats were initially at the Hippodrome to catch mice and the Jockey Club insisted that they found “accommodation and permanent care” in Zhuhai, but unable to give details of the shelter. The situation provoked society's dissatisfaction with the issue of animal security and protection, and the Jockey Club ended up retreating in the decision.
 
Animates, with debts exceeding 822 thousand patacas, asks for donations to the Society
 
Anima, the Macao Animal Protective Society, continues to face serious financial difficulties and has again launched an appeal for the public to make donations to support their operations. In a publication, the group revealed that it currently has a debt of over 822,000 Patacas referring to December 31 last year, with unpaid accounts for veterinary clinics corresponding to 445,254 patacas and 376,829 patacas to animal food suppliers. Founded in 2003, anima now has 400 dogs and 300 cats in its shelter. "This number has been constant for a long time because, after each animal was successfully adopted, we welcome another animal that needs to be saved, and even welcomed cats and dogs that were captured by the Institute for municipal affairs or abandoned by their owners in the kennel," he said. The animal protection group added that more than 500 dogs and cats living on the streets or in places outside the anima receive sterilization, food and medication under the Anima Special Protection Program. In this sense, the anima also guarantees that it has been committed to rescuing stray animals in order to relieve the suffering of these animals, and promote adoption, thus asking for funds and also food from society.
 
Zhuhai received 177 horses from the Jockey Club of Macau
 
A total of 177 horsepower from the Macau Jockey Club has already been sent to Zhuhai, the gongbei customs revealed yesterday. The shipping process began in April last year after the end of horse racing in the territory, and the horses were taken in five lots to the other side of the border. Quoted by the newspaper or Mun, the gongbei customs indicated that the latest group of 41 horsepower introduced in mainland China concluded, last Thursday, the 30-day quarantine period in Zhuhai. The concession contract for the exploration of horsepower in Macao do Jockey Club was terminated on April 1 last year, and the horses had to be transferred out of Macao until March 31 this year. According to authorities, horses will begin a systematic training program, "contributing to the development of the equestrian industry in the Great Bay." The information had mentioned that horses will be dedicated to different areas, including competition, exhibition and artistic performances. Customs has stressed that it will continue to follow the relocation of retired running horses and, at the same time, will work to reinforce cooperation between mainland and Macao China, ensuring animal welfare and promoting sustainable development of the equestrian industry.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:46:20</pubDate></item></channel></rss>