<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/23/ponto-fatal-24-novembro-2025/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>China takes dispute with Japan to the UN and promises to defend itself against possible aggression</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/23/china-leva-disputa-com-japao-a-onu-e-promete-defender-se-perante-eventual-agressao/</link><description>The Chinese government took the diplomatic dispute with Japan to the UN, accusing Tokyo of “launching a threat to use force” against Beijing and warning that it will defend itself against any “act of aggression” in the Taiwan Strait.

In a letter sent Friday to UN Secretary-General António Guterres, China's ambassador to the organization, Fu Cong, stated that Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi "made provocative comments about Taiwan in a flagrant manner."
China and Japan are immersed in an escalation of diplomatic tension after Takaichi, who has held the position for a month, declared in the Japanese Parliament that a Chinese attack against Taiwan could justify the intervention of the Japanese Self-Defense Forces.
According to Fu, these words are “gravely wrong and extremely dangerous, with a deeply malicious nature and impact”. “Despite China’s repeated steps and protests, the Japanese side refuses to repent or retract its erroneous statements”, highlighted the diplomat, recalling that this is “the first time that Japan has launched a threat to use force against China”, something that “openly” challenges “Chinese fundamental interests”.
The ambassador warned that if Japan dares to intervene militarily in the Taiwan Strait, this will be considered by Beijing as an “act of aggression”. "China will resolutely exercise its right to self-defense under the UN Charter and international law and firmly defend its sovereignty and territorial integrity," Fu said. “As a country defeated in World War II, Japan must deeply reflect on its historical crimes, strictly fulfill its political commitment on the Taiwan issue, immediately cease provocations and crossing red lines, and retract its erroneous statements,” concluded the Chinese diplomat.
Following Takaichi's statements, China advised its citizens to avoid traveling to Japan, which led to the suspension of hundreds of thousands of flights, and also banned the import of Japanese seafood, among other measures.
The Japanese Prime Minister, for her part, refused on Friday to withdraw her statements on Taiwan, considering that they represent the “consistent position” of the Japanese Government, and reiterated her desire to maintain beneficial relations with China, in a new call for dialogue.
Japan, which broke diplomatic relations with Taipei in 1972 to establish them with Beijing, maintains close unofficial contacts with the island – which close parliamentarians frequently visit – as well as a security commitment with the United States, which gives strategic weight to its position in the Indo-Pacific. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-23 23:27:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai presents five guidelines for “a bright new chapter” in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/23/sam-hou-fai-apresenta-cinco-directrizes-para-um-novo-capitulo-brilhante-em-macau/</link><description>Sessions to publicize the spirit of the fourth plenary session of the 20th Central Committee of the Communist Party of China (CCPCC) were held last Saturday. The Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, summarized the central guidelines in five points related to promoting the patriotic spirit, strengthening links with the outside world and reinforcing government efficiency, calling on those present to join forces in building Macau's “bright new chapter”.

Last Saturday, two sessions were held to publicize the spirit of the fourth plenary session of the 20th Central Committee of the Communist Party of China (CCPCC), with the presence of 600 leaders and representatives from various sectors. The Chief Executive summarized the central guidelines and presented five guidelines for their application in Macau, which range from promoting the patriotic spirit to strengthening links with the outside of the country.
In his opening speech, Sam Hou Fai began by highlighting that the fourth plenary session of the PCC, concluded on October 23, “was a very important meeting”, in which proposals were approved “for the economic and social development of the country over the next five years” and, at the same time, “a strategic and important plan was designed for the Macao SAR to better implement the tasks assigned to it during this period”.
Addressing those present, the government official called on them to “seriously” study the strategies defined by the 15th Five-Year Plan and to determine “the sense of responsibility and urgency”, by aligning “thoughts and actions with the guidelines and scientific conclusions of the Central Government”.
Sam Hou Fai then went on to present the five main reflections on learning and implementing the spirit of the plenary session. Firstly, he called for “firmly defending the sovereignty, security and development interests of the country” and of Macau, “in all aspects”, and for this it was necessary to “correctly identify, manage appropriately and actively seek changes”.
The second orientation relates to the promotion of the “patriotic spirit”, through the strengthening of collaboration mechanisms between the Government and “the associations that love the country and Macau”. The success of these objectives also depends on associations, which must “strengthen their own development” and “better play their role as a bridge of communication and guidance at the service of society”, he added.
Thirdly, the Chief Executive mentioned the adequate diversification of the economy and the achievement of new results in the integration of Macau and Hengqin. “We must consider the population as our highest priority, ensure their basic living conditions and promote social justice, so that all residents enjoy the fruits of development”, he instructed.
The fourth objective relates to enhancing Macau's “unique advantages”, both in strengthening its context in the Greater Bay Area and, equally, in its connection with the outside world and the expansion of the “circle of international friends”. The role of the territory as “a precise interlocutor between China and Portuguese and Spanish-speaking countries” stands out here.
Finally, the fifth reflection stipulates the articulation between the 15th national Five-Year Plan and the 3rd Five-Year Plan of Macau, thus aiming to enable “a more favorable development for Macau within the scope of integration into the context of national development and the provision of services to the country”.
All of these guidelines have the common purpose of implementing “a brilliant new chapter” for Macau, explained Sam Hou Fai, so as to “not frustrate the Central Government’s affection and expectations” in relation to the region.
Zheng Xincong, director do Gabinete de Ligação do Governo Central na RAEM, consolidou esta ideia afirmando que a nova equipa governativa da RAEM é “crucial” na implementação das estratégias de desenvolvimento e no impulsionamento as prosperidade e estabilidade de Macau a longo prazo. Por outro lado, salienta-se que também os “participantes de todos os sectores da sociedade são forças importantes no princípio de amar Macau e amar a pátria, bem como na construção da cidade”.
In a subsequent intervention, Zhu Weidong, member of the Central Publicity Delegation, highlighted that the country's economic base is currently “stable, with numerous advantages, strong resilience and great potential”, creating favorable conditions for Macau's economic and social development.
In turn, Hou Jianguo, president of the Chinese Academy of Sciences, highlighted that the suggestions of the 15th Five-Year Plan should “further” strengthen cooperation between Macau and other cities in the Greater Bay Area, accelerate the transformation of scientific and technological results and “form new productive forces”. Furthermore, the relationship between Macau and Portuguese-speaking countries could also help companies from the interior of China to expand abroad, by building “a relevant high-level connection in trade opening”.
On the part of the Macao SAR Government, the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, assured that the Economics and Finance team will implement these provisions and promote “the development of adequate and high-quality diversification of the Macau economy, including the construction of a modern industrial system” and “industrial synergy between Macau and Hengqin”.
The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, also promised to deepen the design and construction of the Macau International Integrated Tourism and Culture Zone, highlighting the role of the university city in the Deep Cooperation Zone as a “strategic pillar”.
The director of Economic and Technological Development Services, Yau Yun Wah, revealed that the concept of construction work on the Macau Science and Technology Research and Development Industrial Park is “fully aligned with the strategic objectives” of the five-year plan, based on strengthening scientific and technological innovation in the territory.
Finally, the president of the Cultural Institute, Leong Wai Man, guaranteed that she will continue to support “the training of cultural and artistic talents”, in order to safeguard and enhance cultural heritage.</description><pubDate>2025-11-23 23:34:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippine police with warrants for 18 corruption suspects in flood relief</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/23/policia-filipina-com-mandados-para-18-suspeitos-de-corrupcao-no-combate-as-cheias/</link><description>The Philippine Police has arrest warrants for 18 corruption suspects in a scandal linked to flood containment projects. The arrest warrants, about which Marcos jr. commented that they were just the beginning, they were decreed by the “Sandiganbayan”, a special court to combat corruption.

The Philippine Police has arrest warrants for 18 corruption suspects in a scandal linked to flood containment projects, which has already provoked protests and resignations of congressmen, announced the president, Ferdinand Marcos jr.
The Philippine head of state has been struggling with public and even international outrage over the phenomenon of corruption in an archipelago country with a lot of poverty and geographical target of atmospheric phenomena such as typhoons and consequent floods, in the tropical zone of Southeast Asia.
The arrest warrants, about which Marcos jr. commented that they were just the beginning, they were decreed by the “Sandiganbayan”, a special court to combat corruption, targeting former member of the House of Representatives Zaldy Co, who resigned and is in an uncertain whereabouts, and 17 other suspects, including government technicians and executives from the construction company Sunwest Corporation.
The Public Prosecutor's Office requested that a bail amount not be established because the amount of funds for the dike project in question amounts to 289 million pesos (Philippines), around 43 million euros. “They will be arrested and answer in court, as the law dictates. There will be no special treatment and no one will be spared”, said the Philippine president in a video message in which he thanked the population for their patience.
Marcos prometera há uma semana que, pelo menos, 37 senadores e membros do Congresso filipino, bem como vários construtores civis estavam ligados ao escândalo e que passariam o Natal na prisão.
One of the prosecutors in charge of the case, Jesus Crispin Remulla, told the American agency Associated Press that at least five former or current senators are under investigation for allegedly accepting bribes in construction projects to combat flooding.
Among the suspects are allies and opponents of Marcos, such as Martin Romualdez, cousin of the Philippine president, or senator Bong Go, close to former Philippine president Rodrigo Duterte, both of whom have denied their respective accusations in the scandal.
At stake are 9,855 drainage control projects, valued at more than 545 billion Philippine pesos (eight billion euros), which should be under construction after Marcos takes power, in mid-2022.
In September, Philippine Finance Minister Ralph Recto admitted that, since 2023, 118.5 billion Philippine pesos (1.75 billion euros) may have been embezzled due to corruption linked to these flood containment projects. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-23 23:26:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau achieves the best results ever at the National Games</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/23/macau-alcanca-os-melhores-resultados-de-sempre-nos-jogos-nacionais/</link><description>The 15th edition of the National Games came to an end with historic results for Macau. Sam Hou Fai applauded the “hard work” of the athletes, which culminated in a total of five medals in karate, and assured that he will continue to support athletes in “achieving more honors for Macau”. The National Games also had a positive impact on the tourism sector, with the arrival of more than two million visitors to the region.

The closing ceremony of the 15th edition of the National Games took place last Friday, the 21st, in Shenzhen. The 13 days of games in various disciplines resulted in three gold medals and two bronze medals for Macau – the region's best performance ever in the sporting competition.
Hours before the ceremony, the Organizing Committee of the 15th edition of the National Games held a press conference, also in Shenzhen, to publicize an overview of the work carried out. According to data provided by the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, the Macau Competition Zone received more than 1,800 coaches, athletes and technicians, as well as 3,500 volunteers who provided support in various areas and ensured that the logistics and venue and protocol services operated in a “stable manner”.
Focusing specifically on the competitions, O Lam indicates that 479 games were organized in Macau and 74 medals were awarded – among these, 22 gold. The 295 athletes sent by the Macau sports delegation managed to achieve the best result ever in the territory's history, winning three gold medals and two bronze medals in karate. “Macau’s athletes achieved good results in various sports, demonstrating the spirit of tenacity, fighting and being ever better, as well as the essence of Macau sport”, praised the official, on the occasion.
Lam also highlights that the recently concluded edition of the National Games, hosted for the first time in Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau, contributed to promoting the city as a “world center for tourism and leisure”. According to “a preliminary assessment”, more than two million tourists came to Macau to watch the events organized across the entire territory, from the Cotai casino arenas to the Tap Seac sports hall.

SAM HOU FAI APPLAUDS MACAU ATHLETES

The chairman of the Chinese People's Political Consultative Conference (CPPCC), Wang Huning, declared the event closed at the ceremony following the press conference. The event was marked by cultural and sporting presentations under the theme “The Stars and the Sea”, which served as a love letter to the fusion of Shenzhen's city, technological and natural elements. With the sea, the sky and the urban landscape as a backdrop, the venue hosted shows meticulously prepared over months and staged by hundreds of swimmers, dancers and artists.
At the athletes' parade, the Macau delegation was led by table tennis player Zhu Yuling. Athlete Kuok Kin Hang, winner of a gold medal in the men's karate category, was selected to start the countdown to the end of the competition, together with Guangdong tennis player Wang Xinyu and Hong Kong cyclist Ceci Lee Sze-wing.
The ceremony was also attended by the Chief Executive of the Macao SAR, Sam Hou Fai. Accompanied by his counterparts from Hong Kong and Guangdong, the Government leader passed the National Games flag to the head of Hunan province, Mao Weiming, thus beginning preparations for the 2029 edition of the National Games.
Speaking on the occasion, Sam Hou Fai began by “expressing his most sincere thanks to President Xi Jinping and the Central Government for the guidance and support provided” to this edition of the National Games, the first to take place in Macau. From the “exciting opening” to the “magnificent closing moment” to the “fierce competition on the field”, the event served to start a new chapter in the history of sport in China, as well as strengthening cooperation between the host regions.
The city of Macau, in particular, “has accumulated invaluable experience in organizing sporting events and achieved its best results since joining the National Games”, representing a source of “honor” and “pride” for the territory. In a message sent directly to the Macao SAR sports delegation – and later released by the Social Communication Office (GCS) – the Chief Executive reiterates “the most sincere and warm congratulations to all members of the delegation” for the results obtained, which allowed “the population to [be] filled with pride and enthusiasm”.
“The MSAR sports delegation achieved excellent results, which were obtained through hard work, personal resilience and the rigorous and continuous training of the athletes”, praised Sam Hou Fai, guaranteeing that the Government “will continue to support Macau athletes in participating in various large-scale competitions” and in achieving “even more success in achieving more honors for Macau”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-23 23:34:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau government restricted use of Western devices due to “hostile stance”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/23/governo-de-macau-restringiu-uso-de-aparelhos-ocidentais-face-a-postura-hostil/</link><description>The Macau Government revealed that the public administration is giving priority to Chinese electronic devices, because those coming from Western countries “with a hostile stance towards China” represent “a risk”.
“Instructions have already been issued by the Directorate of Administration and Public Service Services (SAFP), especially for critical infrastructures”, said the secretary for Administration and Justice. “We considered, as a priority, the use of devices from our country” in the Macao SAR government services and departments, highlighted Wong Sio Chak.
O dirigente, que tomou posse em 16 de Outubro, admitiu que “existe um risco” no fornecimento de dispositivos electrónicos de telecomunicações. “É uma questão muito sensível e em que também se verifica uma fragilidade”, referiu Wong, apontando o dedo aos “países do Ocidente, sobretudo alguns com uma postura hostil em relação à China”.
However, the secretary highlighted, during the presentation of the Lines of Government Action for 2026 in the area of ​​Administration and Justice, that the limitations only apply to the public administration of Macau. "We have an open market and we will not restrict the private sector to use foreign devices. Entities and the private sector have the freedom to choose these devices", explained Wong.
On October 19, the Central Government of China accused the United States of carrying out a cyber attack against the National Time Service Center (NTSC), responsible for maintaining the accuracy of the country's official time.
The Chinese Ministry of State Security said the “systematic and long-planned” attack began in 2022, through a vulnerability in the SMS (short message) service of a “foreign brand” of mobile phones.
The vulnerability made it possible to “covertly attack and gain control of the cell phones of several NTSC employees and steal confidential data stored on them”, said the ministry.</description><pubDate>2025-11-23 23:28:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Camilo Pessanha and his affinities with Chinese culture</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/23/camilo-pessanha-e-as-afinidades-com-a-cultura-chinesa/</link><description>Na sua apresentação intitulada “Poéticas do conhecimento analógico: a literatura portuguesa de/em Macau”, o investigador e autor do livro “O Delta Literário de Macau”, José Carlos Seabra Pereira, destacou Camilo Pessanha, um “dos poucos poetas ocidentais que, à época, se familiariza com a língua chinesa e com a cultura ancestral que nessa língua se constrói e se exprime”. 

Focusing on the literary representation of Camilo Pessanha's work, the professor at the Faculty of Arts of the University of Porto, José Carlos Seabra, states that he wants to understand “the affinities” of the symbolist author with Chinese culture and language, when it comes to calligraphy, but also “to move towards another type of values ​​that perhaps help us read his work in a more intense and fruitful way”.
The academic cites the rondel “In the distance as boats of flowers”, considering it to be a “summer poem” as it “reflects the decadence of the end of the [19th] century, but which goes beyond this crisis”, containing elements that go beyond it.
More generally, the academic understands that Pessanha's work “is not limited to the dynamics of perceptions, the bitterness of the monadic fun of beings and, through the splitting of the self, breaks the solipsistic enclosure, identifies itself as the stigma of an ontic exile (…) and alludes, time and time again, to eschatological reintegration and mediation”.

Chinese elements

In “In the distance the flower boats”, as in “Chinese guitar”, references to Chinese elements appear. In this last poem, says the academic, “an endless and invisible meaning of life prevails, but a question that, contrary to apparent reason and, in the form of suffering, all of this gains new strength”.
On the other hand, Pessanha also reveals himself to be familiar with the Chinese language, not only because he uses Chinese characters, but also uses Sinic themes, thus “coming into contact with some fundamental elements of the esoteric system of Chinese tradition disseminated in language and art, analogical intuition and occult belief, but with correspondence at different levels of reality, from immanence to transcendence, and the value of oracular instruments attributed to the linguistic characters in the vectors magicians of Chinese translation and culture”, he says.
Analyzing Pessanha's work, he states that “metaphysical restlessness appears touched by mystery and the sacred, but still contained in spiritual tolerance”. And, in this sense, if we see it as close to the Chinese cultural tradition and Buddhist wisdom modeled by Taoist principles, Camilo Pessanha's poetry seems to require an equivalent reading in the poem “In prison”, experienced by the foreign subject in a world to the point of vertigo, in which “all that remains is to live calmly in anguish in the face of the problem of origin and end.”</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Government intends to impose greater supervision on local associations</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/23/governo-pretende-impor-maior-fiscalizacao-a-associacoes-locais/</link><description>The Government will present a law that introduces greater supervision and control over local associations, which also includes standards related to national security. The Secretary for Administration and Justice, Wong Sio Chak, said he was aware of the number of associations in the territory, which has been growing, and possible irregularities, noting that it was necessary to define a supervisory body for the associations.

The number of associations founded in Macau increased exponentially by more than seven times during the creation of the Macao SAR. Wong Sio Chak, Secretary for Administration and Justice, said that associations have a very varied quality and admitted the need for a regulatory legal framework for them.
As revealed by Wong Sio Chak in the debate session on the Lines of Government Action (LAG) for 2026, last Friday, Macau only had around 1,700 associations at the time of the transfer of sovereignty, while the most recent number is set at 12,315 associations. Wong acknowledged that Macau hosts a substantial number of associations with “very varied quality standards” and many of them have “irregularities”.
The secretary understands, in this case, that the Government needs to review the association system, given that the current regulations on the right to association came into force in 1999, and “many things have changed in more than twenty years”. "We must clarify the supervisory authority of associations, reinforcing supervision before, during and after their creation. Currently, there is no body explicitly responsible for supervision", he highlighted.
Wong Sio Chak, who began leading the administration and justice department on October 16 of this year, pointed out that the lack of a regulatory entity is the reason why the “irregularities” practiced by associations emerged, noting that the Executive does not have the necessary regulatory tools.
Furthermore, a significant part of the current regulations governing associations are stipulated in the Civil Code, which, according to the secretary, has caused considerable confusion in the application of the law, resulting in “ambiguity and uncertainty” and requiring improvements.
Wong Sio Chak explained that the legislative change also serves the purpose of dealing with associations that have ceased to function or have been dissolved. "Among the more than 12 thousand associations now registered, a significant proportion could be inactive associations. They continue to exist even if they have remained inactive for years, for example, ten years or twenty years. However, they only reappear in the public eye and make their voices heard when something happens. These issues must be monitored", he noted.
The Government will, in this case, present next year the proposal for the Legal Regime for associations, the preparation of which has already been completed with the introduction of standards related to national security and supervision. The diploma will later be submitted to a public consultation.
It is recalled that the authorities had announced in March this year that they will review the legislation that regulates local associations, so that they are in line with “the requirements inherent to the general perspective of national security” and with “the real needs for social development” of the territory.
The Executive assumed that associations have an important participating role in community governance, and said that it will “expeditiously ensure the important guiding spirit of President Xi Jinping, attaching special importance to communication and cooperation with associations that love the country and Macau”. Therefore, it intends to create communication mechanisms between these “associations that love the country and Macau” and the Executive, “in order to reinforce the cohesion of common aspirations of the population, the collection of the population's opinions and the union of the population's wisdom”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-23 23:33:18</pubDate></item><item><title>All Macau civil servants swear loyalty to China by the end of the year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/23/todos-os-funcionarios-publicos-de-macau-juram-lealdade-a-china-ate-final-do-ano/</link><description>Wong Sio Chak, Secretary for Administration and Justice, said that all Public Service workers will complete the oath by the end of the year, due to the entry into force of the new Public Administration Workers Statute.
 
The Macau Government predicted on Friday that all public servants, including those of Portuguese nationality, will take an oath of loyalty to China and the territory by the end of 2025.
The oath is part of a review of the statutes of management and leadership staff and public administration workers, which came into force on 1 November.
The two revised laws provide that workers already in office have 90 days to take the oath, with refusal automatically implying the annulment of the appointment to the position or dismissal. But the Secretary for Administration and Justice said he believes the process will be completed sooner and that “all public service workers will take the oath by the end of this year”.
Wong Sio Chak defended, during the presentation of the Lines of Government Action for 2026, that the review “improved the management and accountability regime of management and leadership personnel”.
On November 1st, 264 directors of public entities and services took an oath in a ceremony, declaring that “they will dedicate themselves with all loyalty to the Macau Special Administrative Region [SAR] of the People's Republic of China”.
In a speech given during the ceremony, the leader of the region's government, Sam Hou Fai, asked civil service leaders to “firmly safeguard the full governance power of the Chinese Central Government”.
In December 2024, the assembly approved, unanimously and without any debate, the law that provides that public servants in Macau can be dismissed if they carry out “acts contrary” to their oath.
A month earlier, when presenting the proposal, the then Executive Council spokesman, André Cheong, warned that public servants could be fired due to private conversations or comments published on social media.
The oath will be mandatory for all public officials, including Portuguese ones, but it can be taken in Portuguese, one of Macau's two official languages, along with Chinese.
According to the most recent Public Administration Human Resources Report, in 2023 the region had 34,311 employees. The document does not mention how many have Portuguese nationality, only mentioning that 257 were born in Portugal.
The two proposals also oblige public servants to take the oath in a “sincere and solemn” manner. The sincerity of the oath will be assessed by the hierarchical superior and any dismissal may be appealed to the courts.
On September 1, Sam Hou Fai sent a circular asking all civil servants to vote in the elections for the local parliament as “a relevant demonstration of the defense of the Basic Law and loyalty to the Macao SAR”.
But the president of the Macau electoral commission, Seng Ioi Man, guaranteed, five days later, that “the question of disciplinary responsibility” will not arise for public officials who did not vote in the September 14 elections. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-23 23:31:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Abelha da China: um espaço para debate</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/23/abelha-da-china-um-espaco-para-debate/</link><description>Written in Macau, between 1822 and 1823, Bee of China assumes the role of “privileged vehicle for debate”, imbued with the liberal doctrines of the time, said researcher Cátia Miriam Costa.

Being the first Portuguese-language newspaper in Asia, Abelha da China ended up being widely studied by local academics. “It was fundamental to its historical process, both from a political and philosophical point of view, as well as from an identity perspective”, stated Cátia Miriam Costa, from the ISCTE Center for International Studies, who also said: “It is the first great testimony of the arrival of liberal ideas in Asia.”
It was a short-lived newspaper, as it only existed between 1822 and 1823, but was widely studied for its impact. “It represents the political ambition of a colony, which is not separated from the colonial model and which only requested greater autonomy, and is the first attempt to create a public sphere and a public debate in which the participation of at least the Chinese elite is included”, explained the author of the study “The Bee of China: the Macanese appropriation of political discourse”.
Reflecting liberal ideals, it promotes the exchange of ideas. In fact, the researcher says, despite being created as a space for liberals to assert themselves, it ends up being a territory for “political confrontation and debate”.
Modern in the forms it uses for debate, but also in language, the newspaper Abelha da China begins to publish opinion articles, memories and debates among the Macau public. "From issue 4 onwards, they publish translated articles, first translated from Cantonese into Portuguese. It is a way for those who have access to disseminate these texts and these perspectives, in a period in which we have the demonstration of an empire that is already a little decadent", he says. But it is only in number 10 that he assumes himself as the Government's spokesperson, but whose objective is common happiness. “There is a political and philosophical bias, which only in this issue is the newspaper openly assumed, which is still interesting”, he continues.
The “ambivalence in Portugal’s relations with China” was also evident in the China Bee. “It is the first testimony that those elites know perfectly well that both countries have a role and that China’s role is no less than that of Portugal”, he highlights.
In response to sinologist António Graça Abreu, who was in the audience, and who questioned the term “colony” to refer to the status of the territory, the researcher responded that the Bee of China was part of the colonial-type press, in the sense of “territory administered by another exogenous power and which is not contiguous”, but, she admits, the territory “never became a colony like the others, because, in fact, this connection to China was fundamental”.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Revenues from cultural industries increased 12.7% last year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/23/receitas-das-industrias-culturais-aumentaram-127-no-ano-passado/</link><description>Last year, revenues from services in cultural industries, made up of four areas: digital media; creative design; cultural exhibitions and shows and collection of artistic works, amounted to 9.73 billion patacas, an increase of 12.7%, in annual terms, indicated the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC).
The gross value added, which reflects the economic contribution of these industries, stood at 3.01 billion patacas, an increase of 4.7% compared to 2023.
The organization explains this increase in revenue with the fact that the Government has “continuously promoted the development of the industries under analysis and the constant recovery of the Macao SAR economy”.
In the reference year, revenues from services in the digital media area were 4.12 billion patacas, an increase of 9% in annual terms, representing the largest weight (42.3% of the total) in relation to revenues from services in the cultural industries and the added value stood at 1.32 billion patacas.
DSEC highlights that revenue from film production and distribution services stood at 157.3 million patacas, having grown by 47.5% compared to 2023, “due to the Macao SAR Government having reinforced the promotion of local film production and increased the production of activities related to the ‘double celebration'”. The added value of these services (44.6 million patacas) recorded strong growth of almost 3.9 times.
In turn, revenue from services in the area of ​​exhibitions and cultural shows amounted to 2.89 billion patacas (29.7% of the total), 22.6% more than in 2023. Gross value added was 766.8 million patacas. Revenue from services in the creative design area stood at 2.65 billion patacas (27.3% of the total) in the year under review. Revenue from services in the collection of artistic works area was 76.8 million patacas (0.8% of the total).</description><pubDate>2025-11-23 23:27:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau sets new maximum visitor record in second consecutive month</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/23/macau-fixa-novo-recorde-maximo-de-visitantes-em-segundo-mes-consecutivo/</link><description>Macau received 3.47 million visitors in October, 10.8% more than in the same period in 2024 and the highest figure ever for this month.

The number of tourists passing through the territory was the highest for any month of October since the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) began compiling monthly data, in 1998, still during the Portuguese administration. The region had also recorded an all-time high for September the previous month: almost 3.8 million visitors, 9.8% more than in the same period in 2024.
However, in October almost 61% of visitors (2.1 million) arrived on organized tours and spent less than a day in Macau.
In 2024, the Central Government announced a series of measures to support the territory, such as increasing the tax exemption limit for goods for personal use purchased by visitors from China. At the same time, the Chinese authorities expanded the list of places with “individual visas” to visit Hong Kong and Macau to 10 more cities in China. Additionally, since January 1, residents of the neighboring city of Zhuhai can visit Macau once a week and stay for up to seven days.
As a result, the overwhelming majority (89.8%) of tourists who arrived in Macau in September came from mainland China or Hong Kong, while just over 353 thousand were international visitors.
The city received a total of around 33.1 million visitors in the first ten months, 14.1% more than in the same period in 2024 and the second highest figure ever for the start of a new year.
According to official data, the number of tourists passing through Macau was only surpassed between January and October 2019 – before the Covid-19 pandemic -, a period in which it registered more than 33.4 million visitors.
On January 17, the director of Macau Tourism Services said she expected between 38 and 39 million visitors this year.

In August, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes set a goal of more than three million international visitors by 2025.
In the first ten months of the year, Macau received almost 2.97 million tourists from abroad, 14.9% more than in the same period in 2024. Citizens of Saudi Arabia, Qatar, Kuwait, Bahrain and Oman began to be exempt from visas to enter the city from July 16th.
Despite the increase in the number of tourists, the average consumption of each visitor in Macau, excluding casinos, fell by 9.5% in the first nine months of the year, compared to the same period in 2024.
At the beginning of May, DSEC pointed to the “change in visitors' consumption patterns” as one of the main reasons for the 1.3% drop in Macau's economy between January and March.
It was the first time that the territory's Gross Domestic Product shrank, in year-on-year terms, since the end of 2022, when the region began to lift restrictions due to the covid-19 pandemic.
Macau received 34.9 million visitors last year, 23.8% more than the previous year, but still far from the record, 39.4 million, set in 2019, before the pandemic. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-23 23:33:12</pubDate></item><item><title>“Why didn’t we create a sinological school in Portugal?”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/23/porque-e-que-nao-criamos-uma-escola-sinologica-em-portugal/</link><description>Researcher Rui Lopo chose Inácio de Andrade and Manuel da Silva Mendes to address the representation of Chinese thought in philosophy in Portugal, while professor José Carlos Seabra Pereira highlighted Camilo Pessanha. At the conference “Between Portugal and Macau: cultural bridges, bridges to the future”, on November 19th, at the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center, in Lisbon, academics, philosophers and historians gathered to analyze Chinese thought in Portuguese literature or philosophy.

“Porque é que não criámos, nestes 500 anos, uma escola sinológica em Portugal?” The question comes from Rui Lopo, from the Institute of Philosophy at the University of Porto, at the beginning of his presentation on “Reception and representation of Chinese thought in philosophy in Portugal: the place of Macau”, assuming the gap. Also highlighting that “there is a lack of a systematic study of the history of reception of China and its philosophies in the history of philosophies in Portugal”, the researcher referred to Inácio de Andrade and Manuel da Silva Mendes, as two important names to reflect on this topic.
In the missionary period, there are “very interesting and pioneering” references of “instrumental knowledge of the cultures of the Far East, Asia and China”, such as Tomás Pereira or Fernão Magalhães. “There are a series of authors who were pioneers in making known to the Western world, the European world and Christianity, what they found there”, he says.
Then, a more or less new period began, with the founding of the newspaper Abelha da China, in Macau, in the 19th century. “New intellectuals emerge, they are not missionaries, they are not employees of the Portuguese State, some may have even been diplomats, but I was specifically interested in authors and scholars, who put themselves in an eccentric perspective, which is neither that of a missionary nor that of an employee of the Portuguese State”, he says. This is the case of Inácio de Andrade and the compilation of letters he sent to his wife in the 19th century, as they seemed “a very important document”, to provide an overview of the vision of a Portuguese man, who is neither a missionary nor an agent of the Portuguese State, but a merchant.

The non-supremacy of European philosophy
 
In the study of the representations of Chinese thought in philosophy in Portugal, Rui Lopo also refers to Lopes Praça, a historiographer of Portuguese philosophy, who warns “against the temptation to consider European primacy, in this case Hellenic, regarding questions of philosophy, calling into question the very originality, the pioneering spirit of Aristotle”.
This is the spirit that will govern the work of Inácio de Andrade and, later, of Manuel da Silva Mendes, a professor at the Lyceum of Macau who wrote extensively about the territory, but with a “secular approach to the subject of Chinese thought”.
For the academic, both Inácio de Andrade and Manuel da Silva Mendes, due to their experience in Macau, “are deeply interested in Chinese subjects, in completely different ways, and present very different aspects of China to Portuguese culture”. In the case of Inácio de Andrade, the researcher states that he distinguishes himself from other orientalist authors, due to the sources he uses: his personal experience, local sages and his travels through China and India. “He learned Chinese and was constantly accompanied by capable translators and interpreters, who allowed him to communicate with wise men, teachers and representatives of the cultural and religious traditions he encountered”, he says. He also refers to “European works of Chinese material and calls for them to be assessed through the sieve of experience, despite valuing authors who focus on China, without having ever been there”. Overall, Andrade condemns the “ignorance and misrepresentation of sinic matter in Europe”.
In Rui Lopo’s opinion, “it is necessary to recognize a Sinic and Sinological dimension in the history of Portuguese philosophical thought”, stating that “there are a series of reflective texts that seem to have been ignored.” And, in his opinion, in the conception of Chinese philosophical thought, Taoism must be taken into account. “It is the popular religion, and, in the tradition of scholars and officials of the empire, it is pure of superstitions”, he explains. In fact, these same employees even mention that “Buddhism is less worthy because it is a foreign religion”, also describing Taoism based on what they see as popular superstitions and divination. Therefore, continues the academic, Inácio de Andrade, who “is a critic of the epistemic cheats of others, also commits these cheats, saying that certain traditions are erudite, such as Confucian, but others he considers only popular or less Chinese”, he says.
Trying to think about the specificity of philosophical reflection, Rui Lopo once again highlights the “peculiarity” of Inácio de Andrade. “Because of his social origin, because of the novelty of someone writing from an experience that is neither ecclesiastical nor diplomatic and because he dialogues with Chinese scholars”, he states.
Por seu turno, Manuel da Silva Mendes “apresenta uma ideia de sinicidade complementar e oposta àquela que, 60 anos antes, Inácio tinha apresentado”, referindo que, “na China, coexistem, de forma intrincada, a confuciana, a taoista e a budista, e que não há uma mais chinesa do que a outra”.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Fatal Point – 24 November 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/23/ponto-fatal-24-novembro-2025/</link><description>Researcher Rui Lopo chose Inácio de Andrade and Manuel da Silva Mendes to address the representation of Chinese thought in philosophy in Portugal, while professor José Carlos Seabra Pereira highlighted Camilo Pessanha. At the conference “Between Portugal and Macau: cultural bridges, bridges to the future”, on November 19th, at the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center, in Lisbon, academics, philosophers and historians gathered to analyze Chinese thought in Portuguese literature or philosophy.

“Porque é que não criámos, nestes 500 anos, uma escola sinológica em Portugal?” The question comes from Rui Lopo, from the Institute of Philosophy at the University of Porto, at the beginning of his presentation on “Reception and representation of Chinese thought in philosophy in Portugal: the place of Macau”, assuming the gap. Also highlighting that “there is a lack of a systematic study of the history of reception of China and its philosophies in the history of philosophies in Portugal”, the researcher referred to Inácio de Andrade and Manuel da Silva Mendes, as two important names to reflect on this topic.
In the missionary period, there are “very interesting and pioneering” references of “instrumental knowledge of the cultures of the Far East, Asia and China”, such as Tomás Pereira or Fernão Magalhães. “There are a series of authors who were pioneers in making known to the Western world, the European world and Christianity, what they found there”, he says.
Then, a more or less new period began, with the founding of the newspaper Abelha da China, in Macau, in the 19th century. “New intellectuals emerge, they are not missionaries, they are not employees of the Portuguese State, some may have even been diplomats, but I was specifically interested in authors and scholars, who put themselves in an eccentric perspective, which is neither that of a missionary nor that of an employee of the Portuguese State”, he says. This is the case of Inácio de Andrade and the compilation of letters he sent to his wife in the 19th century, as they seemed “a very important document”, to provide an overview of the vision of a Portuguese man, who is neither a missionary nor an agent of the Portuguese State, but a merchant.

The non-supremacy of European philosophy
 
In the study of the representations of Chinese thought in philosophy in Portugal, Rui Lopo also refers to Lopes Praça, a historiographer of Portuguese philosophy, who warns “against the temptation to consider European primacy, in this case Hellenic, regarding questions of philosophy, calling into question the very originality, the pioneering spirit of Aristotle”.
This is the spirit that will govern the work of Inácio de Andrade and, later, of Manuel da Silva Mendes, a professor at the Lyceum of Macau who wrote extensively about the territory, but with a “secular approach to the subject of Chinese thought”.
For the academic, both Inácio de Andrade and Manuel da Silva Mendes, due to their experience in Macau, “are deeply interested in Chinese subjects, in completely different ways, and present very different aspects of China to Portuguese culture”. In the case of Inácio de Andrade, the researcher states that he distinguishes himself from other orientalist authors, due to the sources he uses: his personal experience, local sages and his travels through China and India. “He learned Chinese and was constantly accompanied by capable translators and interpreters, who allowed him to communicate with wise men, teachers and representatives of the cultural and religious traditions he encountered”, he says. He also refers to “European works of Chinese material and calls for them to be assessed through the sieve of experience, despite valuing authors who focus on China, without having ever been there”. Overall, Andrade condemns the “ignorance and misrepresentation of sinic matter in Europe”.
In Rui Lopo’s opinion, “it is necessary to recognize a Sinic and Sinological dimension in the history of Portuguese philosophical thought”, stating that “there are a series of reflective texts that seem to have been ignored.” And, in his opinion, in the conception of Chinese philosophical thought, Taoism must be taken into account. “It is the popular religion, and, in the tradition of scholars and officials of the empire, it is pure of superstitions”, he explains. In fact, these same employees even mention that “Buddhism is less worthy because it is a foreign religion”, also describing Taoism based on what they see as popular superstitions and divination. Therefore, continues the academic, Inácio de Andrade, who “is a critic of the epistemic cheats of others, also commits these cheats, saying that certain traditions are erudite, such as Confucian, but others he considers only popular or less Chinese”, he says.
Trying to think about the specificity of philosophical reflection, Rui Lopo once again highlights the “peculiarity” of Inácio de Andrade. “Because of his social origin, because of the novelty of someone writing from an experience that is neither ecclesiastical nor diplomatic and because he dialogues with Chinese scholars”, he states.
Por seu turno, Manuel da Silva Mendes “apresenta uma ideia de sinicidade complementar e oposta àquela que, 60 anos antes, Inácio tinha apresentado”, referindo que, “na China, coexistem, de forma intrincada, a confuciana, a taoista e a budista, e que não há uma mais chinesa do que a outra”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-23 23:26:25</pubDate></item></channel></rss>