<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/26/concluida-obra-de-habitacao-para-troca-no-lote-p-na-areia-preta/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Apomac goes to votes: Mannão and Fão should continue to lead association</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/26/apomac-vai-a-votos-manhao-e-fao-deverao-continuar-a-liderar-associacao/</link><description>The duo Mannão/Fão should continue to lead the destinations of the Macao's retirees, retired and pensioners association (Apomac). The elections of the association's managing bodies take place this Friday. Without competition, Francisco Mannhão and Jorge Fão should remain in the positions of chairman of the board and chairman of the General Assembly, respectively.
 
The Association of Retirees, Reformed and Pensioners of Macao (Apomac) will go this Friday, March 28, votes to elect the managers to the triennium from 2025 to 2028. Francisco Mannhão and Jorge Fão should remain in the positions of chairman of the Board and Chairman of the General Assembly, respectively, as they are not competition. “We are elderly but energetic” is the motto of the list of the duo/fão.
Speaking to the end, Mannão regrets no longer interested in assuming the destinies of the Association. Apomac was founded about 24 years ago and has since been led by Jorge Fão and Francisco Mannhão, who admits that there is still “a lot of work to do”.
For the next term, Mannão promises that the association will "seek to accompany the policy of the Government and the Macau Foundation, with a view to adjusting the needs to our action program throughout this three -year term."
In concrete, Mannão says that the association will continue to support associates regarding the bureaucratic process of requests for reimbursement of discounts made improperly in Portugal, "which takes some time." In fact, Francisco Mannhão says he will take advantage of PAULO RANGEL MACAU, Portuguese Minister of Foreign Affairs, this Friday, to ask you to facilitate the process to “overcome the delay in solving the problems of pensioners of the Caixa Geral de Retirement”.
In addition, the chairman of the Board ensures that the association will continue to provide support to members to address formalities with the Institute of Social Action, the Pensions Fund and the Social Security Fund. Annually, Apomac, which has about 1,000 associates, supports the completion of life test, for example. The association also wants to organize more excursions to bring the elderly to the interior of China, for example, and organize more lectures on health and well-being-in this context, the association will organize a dementia lecture on April 3.
The statutes of the Association, founded in 2001 by Jorge Fão, say that the group's objectives go through the representation and defense of the interests of the retired and retirees of Macao, as well as the study of the issues that interest the associates. Apomac also aims to promote and organization actions and initiatives of a social and cultural nature, for example.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 05:53:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Photographer Jessie Rao Yongxia has her debut in Macao, at the SCM hostel</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/26/fotografa-jessie-rao-yongxia-tem-a-sua-estreia-em-macau-no-albergue-scm/</link><description>The exhibition “Time Nomada, an Introduction”, with the work of Chinese photographer Jessie Rao Yongxia, was inaugurated at the SCM Hostel, under the 14th Macao Literary Festival. This is Jessie Rao's first photographic presentation in Macau.
 
The photographic exhibition “Time Nomada, an Introduction” was recently inaugurated at SCM hostel and features a selection of photographers from Chinese photographer Jessie Rao Yongxia. This exhibition is integrated in the 14th edition of the Macao Literary Festival and marks the first time that Jessie Rao's work has been exposed on the peninsula.
Curated by João Miguel Barros, the exhibition focuses on the Mongolia Interior, with the aim of presenting the landscapes of the region, the cultural practices and the lives of its nomadic peoples. The curator expressed the impact of his initial meeting with the photographer in Shenzhen, where he first saw Jessie's portfolio. "When she showed me her portfolio, I was amazed at the kind of photographs she takes from Mongolia," he recalled. João Miguel Barros also indicated that while the exhibition represents the quality of Jessie's work, it does not cover the complete scope of his photograph, which is significantly wider than what is currently exposed.
Jessie Rao is recognized as a distinct disciple of Wang Zhengping, from whom she quickly assimilated techniques and concepts. Under his influence, he developed his own independent photographic style, allowing him to document real life experiences in the inner Mongolia. His work focuses mainly on capturing the routines of the nomadic communities, highlighting the way their lives change with the seasons. The strong contrasts of the inner Mongolia landscape serve as a backdrop for their photographs, reflecting the challenges and beauty of this environment.
Jessie's repeated visits to the inner Mongolia gave her a deep knowledge of culture. This immersion allowed him to interact closely with local communities, where he developed the calls that inform his art. Through these relationships, Jessie captures the emotions and stories of the people who photographs, presenting both moments of joy and those of difficulties. “This night will be unforgettable in my memory,” the photographer confessed during the opening night of the exhibition.
“Nomada time, an introduction” not only shows Jessie Rao Yongxia's art but also works as a cultural bridge, linking Macau to the Mongolian heritage. The exhibition highlights the meaning of telling stories through photography, illustrating how visual art can promote understanding and appreciation of different ways of life.
The exhibition will be evident at the SCM hostel until April 10, providing locals and visitors the opportunity to interact with these images.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Game recipes reach 14.6 billion Patacas in March</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/26/receitas-de-jogo-atingem-146-mil-milhoes-de-patacas-em-marco/</link><description>The game sector was able to generate 14.6 billion patacas in the first three weeks of March, and the daily rate of March 17 to 23 grew 3% compared to the previous week. Still, the results continue to be lower than those observed in February and guess a first trimester short of government objectives.
 
Macao casinos have generated 14.6 billion patacas in the first 23 days of March. In the third week of the month, between 17 and 23, gross game revenues were on a daily average of 643 million patacas-a 3% higher than daily revenues from the previous week, 621 million patacas.
The data were presented in a note from Citigroup Analysts George Choi and Timothy Chau, quoted by the Inside Asian Gaming (IAG) portal. Experts stressed that, despite last week's promising results, daily game recipes continue to be inferior to February. According to the same source, the gross revenues of the Macao casinos VIP segment fell from 8% to 10% over the previous month, while the mass market had a similar decline between 7% to 9%.
To date, March has registered a daily revenue rate of around 635 million Patacas, which analysts describe as a “practically stable” position compared to the same month of 2024. “We maintain our forecast of gross revenues for March 2025 unchanged at 19.5 billion patacas, which implies conservatively that revenues will be an average of 613 million Patacas Day until the end of the month, ”conclude Citigroup analysts. According to this forecast, March will be able to raise about 75% of the same month of 2019.
Consultant Macquarie Equity Research, quoted by Macau Business, also anticipates that revenues obtained in March are between 18.8 and 19.7 billion patacas, reflecting a 1% decrease compared to 2024 and a 2% decrease compared to February.
The sector analysts have been lowering the growth forecasts of game revenues in Macau since the beginning of the year, after a first week of Chinese New Year less busy than expected. Correct Citigroup's prognosis for the second half of 2025 was more positive, with various events and shows planned for the summer season and the hope that the holidays of China's National Day boost tourism and the economy of MSAR.
As for the first quarter of the year, the Macao Economic Association has already assumed that gross game revenues will fall short of the 60 million patacas that the government foresaw for each quarter, totaling 240 billion patacas at the end of the year. In a report released last week, the Association stated that Macao's economic conjuncture will face “many uncertainties” this year, due to the customs imposed by the United States, the slowdown in China's economic growth and the fall of Renminbi.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 05:52:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Elfyn Evans packs an epic safari rally</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/26/elfyn-evans-embala-num-rali-safari-epico/</link><description>Pedro Maia
 
Toyota's Welsh driver cmented the World Cup lead after the Safari Rally. Relentless conditions in Savana do Kenya made many victims in a race that was also marked by a protest of the pilots.
 
Patience, reliability and some dose of luck. They are fundamental ingredients for surviving the hardest rally of the season. Elfyn Evans and co-pilot Scott Martin packed in the race for the title by adding in Kenya the second consecutive victory in the Ralis World Championship. And yes… they had patience, they had the reliability of Toyota Gr Yaris Rally1 and benefited from a lucky dose. Or rather the unlucky of competition.
Evans was the one who best survived the harsh conditions in the Kenyan savannah, in a rally marked by a lot of mud, sand, dust, stones and vegetation among the specials. There were also food intoxications and intense heat. And wild animals with plenty. The torrential rainfall that fell before and during the rally turned some of the special swamps.
"It's special to win the Safari rally. Thanks to the team for having a fantastic car. It was a very demanding weekend, perhaps the most extreme safari I participated in. There was a temptation to try to get more points on Sunday, but the most important thing was to reach the goal first," said the Toyota pilot.
Evans is making an impeccable World Cup beginning. The Welsh now has 88 points, 36 more than the current world champion Thierry Neuville. The Hyundai driver faced many problems during the rally, including food poisoning and several penalties due to the extra time the team needed to repair the i20 n rally1 over the four days of race.
Despite the difficulties, the Belgian, who is pair with compatriot Martijn Wydaeghe, ended third (more than three and a half minutes of Evans), having benefited from the displeasure of Japanese Takamoto Katsuta (Toyota) in the special rally.
Hyundai performed in Kenya with the i20 version of last season, justifying greater reliability. Ott Tänak even led but ended a second over a minute of Evans. Estonium had the same problems that affected Neuville's car: transmission. Without the penalties, Tänak and Neuville showed that they had a progress to discuss the victory. But the truth is that to beat the Safari Rally is not enough to be fast. Tänak is third in the World Cup accounts at 39 Evans points.
Adrien Fourmaux (Hyundai) compromised the race early on Friday after being stopped with electrical problems. The Frenchman, navigated by Alexandre Coria, redeemed himself in 'Super Sunday' by easement of the 10 points in dispute, including 5 of the Wolf Power Stage victory.
Who again disappointed was Kalle Rovanperä. Toyota's Finn (who won in Kenya last year) suffered from several holes, a starting suspension and an electric problem that forced him to abandon. At the end of three races, Rovanperä is tied with Adrien Fourmaux in the fifth place of the championship (31 points). Very little for the two-time champion who returned to the WRC full time.
In the rally1 highlight to Sami Pajari (Toyota). The Finnish young man fulfilled the goal of taking the car to the goal and benefited from the misfortune of others with a promising fourth place. Katsuta (Toyota) was fifth. The luxembourg Greegoire Munster was the best among the M-Sport Fords, when finished sixth.
In the accounts of the World Cup, highlight the double podium of Hyundai. The South Korean builder added 22 more points than Toyota. But the Japanese maintain a 26 points advantage in the overall classification.
 
Gus Greensmith wins in 'home'
 
Gus Greensmith and Jonas Andersson were seventh overall and won the WRC2 category. It is the third triumph in Kenya for the British duo behind the wheel of a Skoda Fabia RS Rally2. The leader of the category, the Swedish Oliver Solberg (Toyota Gr Yaris Rally2), was not beyond fifth place after having been running on one of the specials.
 
Pilots against FIA rules
 
O Rali Safari ficou também marcado por mais um episódio no braço de ferro que envolve os pilotos e os dirigentes da FIA. Virtually all pilots sympathized with Adrien Fourmaux, fined 30,000 dollars (20,000 with suspended penalty) for saying a bad word during a quick interview in the previous stage, the Sweden Rally. The fines and threats of FIA President Mohamed Bin Suulayem had a concerted strategy of boycott of statements at the end of the sections.
“Hello Adrien. A very important rally for you, you got a podium here in Kenya last year. What is the goal for this year?” Asked the WRC reporter at the end of the super-special opening of the rally. The answer of Hyundai's young talent was as follows: “Hakuna Matata!”
Takamoto Katsuta was followed by talking about Japanese. Elfyn Evans answered in Welsh. A pair of pilots, including World Champion Thierry Neuville, responded with little words in French.
"We all agree to maintain the rudeness to the microphone at least. At the same time, it is necessary to maintain a certain freedom of expression and keep emotions alive. Pilots do not need to be afraid of being punished at all," warned the Ralis pilots association. The ball is now on the FIA ​​side, which had also imposed tight F1 rules.
The next round of the WRC is the rally of the Canary Islands that runs from April 24 to 27.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 05:54:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Kyoto multiplies for 10 spending rate to tourists from 2026</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/26/quioto-multiplica-por-10-taxa-de-pernoita-aos-turistas-a-partir-de-2026/</link><description>Kyoto, one of Japan's most visited cities, approved yesterday a drastic increase in the spending tax on hotels to 10 times the current maximum rate, a decision motivated by the tourism volume in the city.
 
The city's Municipal Assembly introduced a various level tax system in 2018 with a maximum limit of 1,000 yen (6.15 euros) per night, but from March 1, 2026 will increase the maximum rate to 10,000 yen (61.52 euros), with the aim of increasing local funds to implement measures against excessive tourism and other purposes.
Visitors currently pay between 200 yen (1.23 euros) for stays of less than 20,000 yen (123 euros) per person and a night, and a maximum of 1,000 yen (6.15 euros) for 50,000 yen (307.65 euros) per night.
The new fiscal system will divide fees to pay into five levels: the minimum will continue to be 200 yen, but now for over 6,000 yen (36.78 euros), and other amounts will be introduced, up to a maximum of 10,000 yen when the cost per night is exceeding 100,000 yen (615.35 euros).
After tax increases, local tax revenues should increase to about 12.6 billion yen (77.55 million euros) per year, compared to 5.2 billion yen (32 million euros) by 2023, according to the latest data from the Japan National Tourism Office (JTO).
The tax will be the highest among the 11 Japanese municipalities that have adopted such measures in recent times to meet the country's tourist boom, which received a record of 36.87 million foreign tourists in 2024.
Kyoto is the third most visited city hall in the Asian country, behind only Tokyo and Osaca, and is a popular destination for both international and national visitors.
 
Tokyo bag closes to win 0.46% with disagreement compared to tariffs
 
Tokyo Stock Exchange, Nikkei, yesterday closed to earn 0.46%, after US President Donald Trump, signaling that some countries may not be covered by imposing rates. Nikkei, which includes the 225 most representative actions on the market, finished the day with a 172.05 points to 37,780.54.
However, Topix, which includes the highest capitalization companies in the main section, rose 0.24%, or 6.64 points, to 2,797.52 points. The reference Nikkei briefly surpassed the 38,000 points line, after major gains at night on Wall Street, after Trump signaled that there will be exemptions from reciprocal tariffs.
Investors in the Tokyo Exchange also sought export -oriented car emissions due to a weaker yen that benefits exports. At noon, the local currency was being negotiated within 150 per US dollar.
Technological actions attracted much of their purchases during the day, with some of the most negotiated shares to be companies in the semiconductor sector. Disc and Tokyo Electron rose 3.59% and 0.65%, respectively, while Advantest and Lasertec lost 3.36% and 0.6% respectively.
Electrical equipment manufacturer Fujikura won 1.52% and Mitsubishi Heavy Industries' machinery manufacturer lost 1.76%.
In the main section, 1,009 companies climbed, 562 descended and 66 remained unchanged. The turnover rose to 3.93 billion of yen (about 24.207 billion euros). Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 05:54:50</pubDate></item><item><title>70 infractions of the alcohol control law until February</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/26/registadas-70-infraccoes-da-lei-do-controlo-de-alcool-ate-fevereiro/</link><description>The sanitary authorities made 26,358 inspections in the first two months of the year alone, making a daily average of 1,578. According to health services, 15 of the registered offenses are related to the sale of alcohol to minors.
 
Health services detected 70 suspected cases of violation of the alcohol consumption control law between November 2023 and February 2025, with 15 of these infringements related to the sale or availability of alcohol to minors.
According to a statement of health services, among the remaining cases accounted for inspection included “several” establishments that did not afford the prohibition on the sale of alcohol to minors; Establishments with self-service boxes (self-service) where the areas of alcoholic and non-alcoholic beverages were not properly marked and differentiated; and also advertising advertising of alcohol content that contained no warnings in Chinese, Portuguese and English languages.
In total, 339,571 inspections were carried out since November 5, 2023, the date on which the law related to the regime for preventing and controlling alcohol consumption by minors came into force. In the first two months of this year alone, 26,258 inspections have been held, which makes an average of 536 inspections per day.
In the same statement, it is read that the Office for prevention and control of smoking and alcoholism (GPTCA) has reinforced the strategies of prevention and control of alcohol and tobacco consumption, namely through periodic inspections “to all types of establishments regulated by law, together with the services responsible for [their] execution”, in order to ensure the provisions of the 2023 regime are respected.
The availability of alcoholic beverages to minors, both commercial and non -commercial purposes, is illegal and can be punished with fines that rise at 20 thousand patacas. If compulsory destics are not affixed by commercial establishments, the amount can go to 200,000 patacas.
In the year 2024, the authorities reported 47 suspected cases of infringement, 11 of which involving the sale or availability of alcohol to minors. In the context of smoking control and prevention of alcohol consumption by minors, the authorities last year, a total of 259,081 inspections to establishments, resulting in an average of 708 inspections per day.
One of the first cases of the law's infringement - and also, probably, the most famous - occurred when the 16 -year -old pilot Arvin Lindblad drank champagne on the Macao Grand Prix podium after winning the Formula 4 test. The infrastant was the Grand Prix organizing committee, which eventually paid 1,500 Patacas de Fim.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 05:54:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Sector wants to increase sentence for illegal tour guides</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/26/sector-quer-aumentar-pena-para-guias-turisticos-ilegais/</link><description>The Macau Tour Guide Association wants to impose a more serious sanctioning regime to combat illegal tour guides. It was then suggested the increase of fines for infringements, as well as the introduction of a point deduction system and punishment against travel agencies using illegal tour guides. The association also highlights the low case detection rate due to the difficulty of obtaining evidence.
 
The proposal for the activity of travel agencies and the tourist guide profession is being analyzed at the Legislative Assembly and the industry has defended the increase of the penalty for illegal tourist guides.
The Macau Tour Guide Association proposes to increase fines for illegal tour guides and introduce a mechanism for deducting points for travel agencies to punish the use of illegal tour guides, increasing the deterioration effect on irregularities. On the other hand, the entity expects to have an incentive system to praise tourist guides, encouraging the industry to provide high quality services.
Speaking to the Citizen Journal, Wu Wai Fong, president of the Association, is concerned about the emergence of more illegal tour guides in Macao with the arrival of more visitors to the territory, but also the low case detection rate and their difficulties in the investigation.
"The authorities have placed human resources in the inspection of illegal tour guides, but little has been done due to the difficulty of obtaining evidence. Therefore, it should review the law to change the sanctioning regime, better and more clearly define illegal acts to more effectively fight violations," he said.
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) revealed last week that in 2024, a total of 1,615 inspections at border stations and sights, along with random inspections to excursions and inspections on the work of tour operators. He also made, together with the Public Security Police, inspections to combat the illegal activities of the tour guides.
In this case, news records were raised against 17 individuals suspected of illegally exercising the tourist guide profession. Already between January and mid -March this year, STD made 314 inspections at the main points of tourist attraction and border posts and established sanctioning procedures against an individual suspected of the illegal exercise of the tourist guide profession.
Wu Wai Fong claimed to have difficulty obtaining evidence, which led most of the illegal excursions not to be processed. "Some illegal excursions claimed to be a family, and some even gathered their members in Zhuhai and give them instructions to cross the border alone and take a transportation to reach the ruins of Sao Paulo to escape inspections," he said.
He also added that some illegal tour guides from the interior of China take advantage of new visa policies to keep the use of local guides. According to explained, in the past, for the residents' excursions on the continent, there should always be local guides to work as escorts, since the tour guides from the interior of China could not follow the return of customers to Macau. However, with the facilitation of Macao's entry and exit, the continent's guides can come to Macau and bring the tourist group to enter and leave the territory.
The association received reports from professionals about the suspension of cooperation with travel agencies on residents' excursions. Wu Wai Fong said that the survival of local tour guides is being affected by the mentioned situations, expecting the government to pay attention to such incidents and take effective measures to suppress illegal acts.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 05:55:47</pubDate></item><item><title>“Love and fingers standing back to Macau after 33 years</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/26/amor-e-dedinhos-de-pe-regressa-a-macau-apos-33-anos/</link><description>Luís Filipe Rocha's movie “Love and Tingers” was screened yesterday at the Capitol Theater, marking his return to Macau after 33 years. This special projection was held under the 14th Macao Literary Festival.
Originally debuted on March 20, 1992, “Love and Foot Fingers” is a romantic drama based on the homonymous novel of Macanese writer Henrique de Senna Fernandes. The film has the participation of actors such as Joaquim de Almeida, Ana Torrent and Jean-Pierre Cassel, and focuses on the lives of Portuguese settlers in Macao in the late nineteenth century. “Love and fingers” portrays the tensions faced by the Portuguese settlers, who are trapped between their European identities and the realities of their colonial existence.
Speaking after projection, Luís Filipe Rocha shared his thoughts about the return of the movie Macao, calling him "the heaviest movie of my life." The director referred to the challenges of filming in a territory that is simultaneously familiar and enigmatic, stressing that, despite its extensive research, it considered the theme deeply intricate. “As much as I knew, as much as I scrutinized, as much as I had read and studied the story of Macau, the story of the Portuguese presence in Macau and the history of China, that was not enough. I was in a very complex and very delicate territory. Macau is it.
When asked about book adaptation for film, the director discussed his perspective on film loyalty. "Faithfulness is not measured by the illustration of the books, I am not illustrator, I am cinematic author." Luís Filipe Rocha also pointed out that the authenticity of his own expression as a filmmaker is essential to honor the literary work he adapted.
The projection of “Love and Foot Fingers” provided an opportunity for nostalgic viewers, familiar with the past, and for a new audience to get involved with a critical portrait of the colonial history of Macao. The film addresses universal themes such as love, identity and complexities of cultural heritage, making it relevant even decades after its initial release. The return of this film not only honors its legacy, but also promotes the dialogue about the continuous impact of history today.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai goes to Haião today to participate in the Boao Forum</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/26/sam-hou-fai-vai-hoje-a-hainao-para-participar-no-forum-boao/</link><description>The chief executive moves today to the province of Haião to participate in the opening ceremony of the Boao Forum Annual Conference.
Sam Hou Fai will be in Haião today and tomorrow and, in his absence, will be André Cheong, secretary for administration and justice, to exercise the position of Chief Executive. The mashed delegation that will participate in the forum will also count on Tai Kin IP, secretary for the economy and finance. Liu Xianfa, commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Popular Republic of China at MSAR, also is part of the Macao delegation as a guest advisor.
In this year's edition, the BOAO FORUM annual conference for Asia 2025, which runs until Friday, has as its theme “Asia in the world in transformation: Towards a shared future” (Asia in the Changing World: Towards a Shared Future), and will focus on four areas: rebuild confidence and promoting cooperation in a rapid transformation world; Encourage growth and rebalance globalization for inclusive development; Modeling the future and rapidly implementing the objectives of sustainable development to respond more effectively to global challenges; and explore potentialities and intensify the application and governance of Artificial Intelligence (AI) for development motivated by innovation.
The Boao Forum is a non -profit organization that annually performs high -level forums for government, business, and academic leaders from Asia and other continents to share their view on the most pressing issues in this region and in the world in general.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 05:54:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Net profit from Chinese car manufacturer BYD increased 34% by 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/26/lucro-liquido-da-fabricante-automovel-chinesa-byd-aumentou-34-em-2024/</link><description>Chinese electrical vehicle manufacturer BYD reported yesterday that it had a net profit of 40.254 billion yuan in 2024, 34% more than the previous year.
 
In the results sent to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange, where it is quoted, the company also reported an annual increase of 29% in turnover, to 777 billion Yuan.
Net profit of 2024 is the highest in the company's history and exceeds the expectations of analysts, who did not expect it to be beyond 40 billion Yuan.
The company said that revenues from cars and related products rose to about 617.382 billion Yuan, which represents a homologous increase of 27.70%.
BYD, which maintained its leader status in the Chinese electricity sector last year, said that in 2024 it became the world's first car brand to reach 10 million new energy vehicles. New energy vehicles encompass electric and hybrids.
In the last quarter of last year, BYD destroyed the American Tesla as the world's largest saleswoman of electric cars.
In recent weeks, the company based in southern China has shook the market by revealing an ultra -rarefall system of vehicles that can provide a full charge to its latest electric vehicles within a period of five to eight minutes, similar to the time required to fill a fuel deposit.
The founder and president of the car manufacturer Wang Chuanfu stated in the presentation of the results that the Chinese auto industry demonstrated in 2024 its "vitality", despite the "uncertainties", and local brands are "taking advantage of the strong growth of new energies, gaining quota of the market thanks to the double impetus of technology and artificial intelligence."
In this regard, the company said it has invested approximately 54.2 billion yuan (6.8 billion euros) in research and development in 2024, representing a 35.68%homologous increase. "BYD has become industry leader in all sectors, from batteries and electronics to new energy vehicles, breaking the dominance of foreign brands and turning the global market overview," he said.
Looking at 2025, Wang says BYD will take advantage of the “historical opportunity” to continue to develop and reinforce its independence, further increasing the competitiveness of its products. "We will accelerate the international expansion of our business to help the Chinese car industry lead the global transformation of new energy vehicles," he said.
In addition to its presence in China, BYD has been investing heavily in Latin America for years, where it has recently started building a manufacturing complex in Brazil, and is also present in markets from over 50 countries, including Portugal. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 05:54:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Rangel underlines “very positive” state in the relationship with China despite the absence of visits</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/26/rangel-sublinha-estado-muito-positivo-na-relacao-com-china-apesar-de-ausencia-de-visitas/</link><description>Portuguese Foreign Minister Paulo Rangel stressed yesterday to Lusa, in Beijing, the “very positive” state of the relationship with China, devaluing the absence of visits in the last five years. "There is a very positive state in relationships. The fact that there was this hiatus did not slow the interest that both countries have in their bilateral relationship," he said after meeting with Chinese counterparts Wang Yi.
The Portuguese minister yesterday began a four -day visit to the Asian country, which ends up more than five years without Portuguese high -level visits to Beijing, at a time of reconfiguration of the international order. Visits from high Portuguese government officials were almost monthly frequently, by the end of 2019, but were interrupted by the COVID-19 pandemic, which led to the closing of China's borders. However, the absence of travel was extended even after the reopening of the borders of the People's Republic in January 2023 and the visit to Portugal by Chinese Vice President Han Zheng in May of this year.
Paulo Rangel justified the absence of visits with “some government instability in Portugal”, refusing any discomfort in relationships, despite the approach of Beijing to Moscow, in the context of Ukraine's Russian invasion, and Lisbon's decision to exclude Chinese suppliers from 5G networks, namely the Huawei technological giant. "Our relationship with China is bilateral. It is not dependent on the geopolitical circumstances of each moment, even if they may be relevant, in terms of orientation changes, which we think they may have medium or long term impact, not just short -term," he said.
Regarding the possibility of the antagonistic position of US President Donald Trump, in relation to the transatlantic alliance to be able to revitalize the dialogue between Portugal and China, the Portuguese minister was clear: "The dialogue with China does not depend on the situation in the United States." "The relationship with China is 500 years old. In the last 45 years he had great development, deepening and enrichment. Macao's transition model was an exemplary model. After that, this strategic relationship was created," he said.
This year marks the 20th anniversary of the Comprehensive China Strategic Partnership - Portugal. China has become, in the last decade, the fourth largest foreign direct investor in Portugal. Chinese, state and private companies have a global position valued at 11.2 billion euros in the Portuguese economy, according to Banco de Portugal (BDP). Investments cover the areas of energy, bank, safe or health. In 2018, the two countries signed a memorandum of understanding of the “Track and Route” initiative, a mega project of infrastructures launched by Beijing that aims to expand its global influence through the construction of ports, railways or self -established.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 05:54:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Health services recommend measles vaccine for those under 55</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/26/servicos-de-saude-recomendam-vacina-contra-o-sarampo-a-quem-tenha-menos-de-55-anos/</link><description>Health services appeal to residents wishing to travel to measles -affected regions to adopt preventive measures and complete vaccination - the most effective method of prevention and reduction of disease transmission - at least two weeks in advance. Priority groups include children, health professionals and individuals born from 1970, including.
Although the Macao region is not, currently affected by measles outbreaks, its statute as a tourist city makes it vulnerable to the importation and propagation of the virus. The risk intensifies with the approximation of qingming and Easter holidays, both occurring in April, resulting in a higher flow of inputs and exits in the region. It is recalled that on these occasions many residents travel abroad for the veneration of ancestors in cemeteries, to visit the family or simply by leisure.
The measles epidemic has been aggravated in recent years, all over the world, due to the low rate of child vaccination. In 2024, more than 127,000 measles in Europe and Central Asia-the highest number since 1997-40% of which involving children under five years old were reported. Until the beginning of March, the World Health Organization (WHO) was notified of 38 disease -related deaths in these locations. The number of cases has also increased in the United States of America and Canada and in geographically close countries to Macao, such as Vietname and Philippines.
In a statement, health services indicate that residents born in or after 1970 should be inoculated “as soon as possible” before moving to the affected regions. This is because, although the measles vaccine was introduced by the then Portuguese administration in Macau in the late 1960s, the vaccination rate remained low until the early 1980s. In turn, residents under the age of 18 are advised to take two doses of the vaccine to obtain complete immunity.
In addition to residents, for whom inoculation is free, also non -residents authorized to remain in Macau for a long period can schedule vaccination in centers or health posts through prior marking. For this slice of the population, the vaccine costs 50 patacas per dose.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 05:54:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines receive rescued citizens at online crime centers at Myanmar</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/26/filipinas-recebem-cidadaos-resgatados-em-centros-de-crime-online-no-myanmar/</link><description>Thirty people landed yesterday in Manila, the first of the 206 Philippines who will be repatriated after being rescued from centers led by online crime gangs at Myanmar, where they were forced to work.
The first group arrived yesterday morning on a commercial flight to Ninoy Aquino International Airport, in the Filippine capital, said the Undersecretary of the Filipine Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Eduardo de Vega, in statements to ABS-CBN television. This Wednesday, another 176 Philippines will return home in a chartered flight from Thailand.
Undersecretary of the Department of Migrant Workers (DMW), Bernard Olalia, said repatriads will receive financial aid of 60,000 pesos (about 1,046 euros) upon arrival.
The Asian country authorities stated that the rescued were attracted to Thailand with fictional employment promises, but upon arrival in the country were trafficked to neighbor Myanmar to be forced to commit 'online' fraud from computers installed in these centers. "Our program includes doing justice, so DMN will collect testimonies so that we can find out who brought them illegally and how they came to Myanmar," said Olalia, quoted by the Philippines media.
In recent weeks, thousands of people have been repatriated after being released from online burla centers in Myanmar, as part of a mega Beijing -led operation.
Thailand hopes to receive about 7,000 people from the neighboring country.
The existence of these complexes, which in practice act as arrests or slave fields in Southeast Asia, allegedly managed by Chinese mafias, where victims of human beings are forced to commit online fraud, is not new.
Many of these complexes have begun as casinos linked to the laundering of capital. The size of rescue operations highlighted the abuses committed against forced workers.
One of the Philippines who returned to his country yesterday told ABS-CBN the long hours of work of almost 17 hours a day, during which he tried to gain the victims' confidence to invest in fraudulent platforms.
Those who did not reach the quotas established by the captors for the amount of fraud, he explained, could be left for hours in the sun.
The Indonesian government, which repaired 400 citizens rescued from Burmese centers, denounced torture with electrocussions and others, as well as threats of removal of the organs of trafficking victims.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 05:54:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Lusofonia companies look for in Macau business in renewable energy</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/26/empresas-da-lusofonia-procuram-em-macau-negocios-nas-energias-renovaveis/</link><description>A set of 26 companies from Portugal, Brazil and Timor-Leste will be present in Macao at the Forum and International Exhibition of Environmental Cooperation (MIECF), which runs from March 27 to 29, the organizers said yesterday.
Lusophony exhibitors “will expose products related to new energies, waste management, wastewater treatment and environmental hygiene,” said the president of the Institute for the promotion of commerce and investment, Vincent U SENG.
The event, which has been organized since 2008, aims to address topics such as carbonic neutrality, green and ecological mobility, and has activities such as “Green Forum”, Green Exhibition, Contact Bags and a “Green Public Day”. “Innovation and Green Development - Solutions for Construction of Beautiful Cities”, is this year's theme, which will be exposed in an area of ​​12,000 square meters, according to the organizers.
This year, “we will also organize business visits to Hengqin and Zhuhai for representatives of Portuguese -speaking countries, and thus expand the influence of our platform to new international green business opportunities,” said U.
José Carlos Pimenta Machado, president of the Portuguese Environment Agency, will participate in the event with a lecture dedicated to the theme “Green Transformation and Development”, scheduled for the third day of the event.
According to the organizers, more than 60 international exhibitors participate in this year's Miece, 17% more than last year, and will be visited by a number of foreign professional buyers also higher than last year, around 23%.
The event is organized by the Executive of the Macao Special Administrative Region, with the support of a dozen neighboring Chinese provinces and the Beijing Government.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 05:54:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Tsang Tseng Tseng presents a lecture on Chinese landscape painting in Hong Kong</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/26/tsang-tseng-tseng-apresenta-palestra-sobre-pintura-de-paisagens-chinesas-em-hong-kong/</link><description>Artist Tsang Tseng Tseng will give a talk titled “The Authentic Way of Panting Chinese Landscapes” on March 30, between 13:30 and 14:15, at the Hong Kong Convention and Exhibition Center, in the field of Art Basel Hong Kong. According to a note sent to the press, the event - conducted in English, mandarin and additional information in Cantonese - aims to “provide the public lover of the arts a shared reflection on the mastery, techniques and artistic conception of Chinese landscape painting, as well as the unique meaning of landscape contemplation and its aesthetics in the contemporary life context”.
The lecture will be attended by Shuo Sue Hua, an associate curator of the Museum and Art Gallery at the University of Hong Kong (UMG), which will start in the cultural afternoon with a brief contextualizing introduction of the artist. The Tsang Tseng Tseng event is part of the same program as the exhibition “Wondrous Rivers: Exploing Chinese Landscape Paintings”, promoted by UMG, where the public is invited to know the world of Chinese landscape painting through a selection of works that extends from the beginning of the Qing dynasty to contemporary.
Tsang Tseng Tseng (also known by the stage name San Zhan) is an emerging artist from Macao who stands out for mixing Chinese traditions with contemporary practices, standing out his mastery in the painting of Chinese landscapes. With a promising start in 2008, she was the winner of the New Talent Award at the 24th Collective Exhibition of Macao Artists, awarded by the Institute for Macao Municipal Affairs. Recently, he represented the masket in Goa at the 30th anniversary celebrations of the East Foundation delegation in India.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Completed housing work for exchange in lot p in the black sand</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/26/concluida-obra-de-habitacao-para-troca-no-lote-p-na-areia-preta/</link><description>All works of the Housing Project for exchange in Lot P in the Black Sand, which is intended for sale to the eligible buyers of the previous project “Pearl Horizon”, were completed. The current “Pearl Metropolitan” project consists of six blocks and offers 2,064 fractions, all equipped with balconies and cooking electrodomes. According to Macau Urban Renewal, the complex is currently in the final phase of quality inspection and reception.
 
The housing project for exchange in Lot P in Areia Preta, in the old Pearl Horizon ground, already has all the works completed, yesterday revealed Macau Urban Renewal S.A. The venture, which does not occupy the entire lot P, consists of six blocks with 50 floors, providing 2,064 apartments, being currently in the final inspection phase on quality guarantee.
Called “Pearl Metropolitan”, that housing for exchange may be acquired by the eligible buyers for the pre-sale of the former “Pearl Horizon” project, which was never built within 25 years of land concession.
Macau Urban Renewal ensures that it is advancing with the work of visits to the site so that eligible buyers can know the situation of the units they have selected. The information known on the company's portal indicates that 1,932 eligible housing applications were received and, by the end of 2023, 1,880 proceeded to the selection of apartments, 47 were absent in the choice of unit and five cases were suspended.
The works, which followed the rules of construction of the private sector, were completed in December 2023 and then began the phase of inner works of the houses. According to the company's presentation, referred to in a press release, "Pearl Metropolitan" has a "Clubhouse", an outdoor pool, recreational facilities and green zones, which "will increase the vitality of the community." As for the fractions, they were built with porch, cooking electrodomers and windows with triple glasses energy saving for thermal and acoustic insulation.
Macao Urban Renewal also pointed out that in the venture were installed anti-cable cables, the first used in a property in Macau, for safety of residents. The complex parking park offers 1,873 car parking places and 490 parking places for motorcycles, all equipped with electricity supply stations.
Lot P, according to the statement, also includes a commercial space, a bus terminal, a pedestrian zone and an emergency route for fire vehicles. Two new 24 meters wide public roads were also added, with four two -way lanes and pedestrian paths, “to facilitate the displacement of owners and to their homes and to create a habitable and affordable community environment,” he said.
It is recalled that Lot P, located in the new landfills of Areia Preta, occupies an area of ​​approximately 68,000 square meters, whose land concession was declared lame in January 2016 for terminating the provisional concession period without the construction established in the concession agreement with the government. The concessionaire, Polytec Group, filed a judicial appeal to the last court, but was dismissed in 2018. The government reversed the land in 2019.
In this installment, the residence has already been inaugurated for the elderly and the remaining spaces are used by the housing projects for temporary accommodation (lot and c) and housing for exchange (lot A). Housing for temporary accommodation, which has eight residential towers with about 2,000 fraction units, aims to help people whose houses will be subject to urban renewal, such as temporary accommodation when their properties are being refurbished.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 05:54:21</pubDate></item></channel></rss>