<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/07/melco-investe-no-turismo-de-saude-com-primeiro-hospital-dentro-de-um-casino/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Casinos made 5.5 billion patacas in the first five days of October</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/07/casinos-facturaram-55-mil-milhoes-de-patacas-nos-primeiros-cinco-dias-de-outubro/</link><description>The first five days of the golden week of October translated into gross revenues of 5.5 billion patacas-the best result in more than five years, despite the temporary interference of Typhoon Matmo. Revenue should fall 30% in the week following this period of holidays, although analysts maintain an optimistic perspective for October.
 
Macau's casinos achieved gross gaming revenue worth 5.5 billion patacas in the first five days of October alone, totaling a daily average of 1.10 billion patacas. Despite the interference of Typhoon Matmo, which led to the temporary closure of casinos while signal no. 8 remained erected, October's Golden Week has already managed to achieve the best result in more than five years.
The data was revealed by broker JP Morgan and cited by the GGRAsia portal, in an assessment of the period between last Wednesday and Sunday. It is important to remember that this year's Golden Week continues until today, the 8th, covering China's National Day and the Mooncake Festival, unlike the usual seven days of holidays in the interior of China.
Analysts note that this month's growth seems “relatively moderate” in annual terms and “below market expectations”, with only 3% increase over the same period last year. Still, cited by the same portal, they guarantee “not being worried” and remember that newly released data do not include all the second half of the golden week.
“This year’s longer holidays – eight days, instead of seven – suggest more sustained demand in the second half of Golden Week, resulting in stronger and longer-lasting demand after the peak”, indicates the report from the analyst team. Although Typhoon Matmo affected visitor arrivals and limited the gaming industry for eleven hours – that is, almost half a day –, this temporary interruption could even lead to an “amplification” in the flow of players from the Mainland, attracted to the territory after the passage of the tropical storm.
Regarding the second week of October, after the golden week, analysts expect gross game revenues to continue to increase in annual terms, with 15% and 20% climbs from the same month last year. This means, therefore, that casinos should make about 750 million patacas per day during this period. On the other hand, comparing this data with the first week of October, there should be a drop of about 30%.
JP Morgan experts say "the projection for the whole month remains unchanged for now, with gross game revenues to reach the highest value in six years with 23 billion patacas, growing between 11% and 13% over the previous year." In an even longer prediction, analysts also believe that game recipes should continue to grow “with a stronger flow” by at least the first trimester of 2026.
According to data released by the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP), between 1 and 5 October, 790,016 visitors entered Macau. Saturday, October 4th, was the busiest day at the border posts, with 191,176 visitors entering. This number dropped precipitously to just 113,051 entries on Sunday – the day with the fewest visitors in the entire Golden Week, due to bad weather and restrictions lifted by Typhoon Matma. The day before yesterday, the 6th, there was a slight recovery with the arrival of 128,890 visitors.
Last year, Golden Week lasted from the 1st to the 6th of October. During this period, casinos generated revenue of 6.5 billion patacas and reached a daily average of 1.16 billion patacas per day, thus breaking the post-pandemic record.</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:38:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau has received more than a million visitors since the beginning of the month</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/07/macau-recebeu-mais-de-um-milhao-de-visitantes-desde-o-inicio-do-mes/</link><description>Macau received 1,032,752 visitors between October 1st and 5pm yesterday, according to data released by the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP). In total, 4,643,415 border movements were recorded during this period.
The day with the greatest flow of visitors was Saturday, the 4th, with the arrival of 191,176 tourists. The day immediately following, Sunday, saw fewer entries at the border crossings to Macau, with just 113,051 visitors. This decrease of approximately 41% was due to the passage of Typhoon Matma, which led to the temporary closure of borders.
The following day, with the cancellation of all tropical storm warning signs and the return to normality, the flow of tourists increased again in Macau, albeit somewhat modestly: until midnight on Monday, the border posts counted a total of 128,890 visitor arrivals, the second lowest number of October's Golden Week.
Visitors registered until 5 pm yesterday indicated that the region continues to recover from Sunday's exponential fall, with 113,846 visitors input in this partial period. From a global perspective, 407,350 transionic movements were added only in the morning and yesterday afternoon.
It is recalled that the day before yesterday, the lunar cake festival was celebrated, an occasion that usually motivates family meetings and is less conducive to travel. The day following the “Chong Chao”, October 7, is a holiday in Macao and the interior of China, which could justify the highest influx of tourists in the interior of China.
As usual, the busiest borders during the golden week were the doors of the siege, the Hengqin border post and the sea bridge that crosses between Hong Kong, Zhuhai and Macao. Holiday Week in the interior of China ends today, on October 8th.</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:22:45</pubDate></item><item><title>European companies say that Mozambique privileges Chinese companies despite “lower quality”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/07/empresas-europeias-dizem-que-mocambique-privilegia-empresas-chinesas-apesar-de-menor-qualidade/</link><description>The Association of European Businessmen in Mozambique (EuroCan) says that the State prefers to contract services from Chinese companies, to the detriment of European ones, as they have low prices but “lower quality”.
"There is a growing institutional preference for products of Chinese origin, often of lower quality, due to their lower prices and ease of supply. This trend compromises the competitiveness of European products, generally more durable and technologically advanced", reads the report on Examples of Barriers and Constraints to European Investment in Mozambique.
In the recently launched document, European entrepreneurs add that Mozambican state preference for Chinese services also harms Mozambican companies, in a practice that "contradicts the principles of equal treatment and promotion of local content", as well as demotivating investors wishing to establish "roots in the country".
The most affected sector, according to the EuroCan study, is the construction and supply of equipment, which has been awarded to foreign companies with minimal local representation, resulting in limited access for European products to the Mozambican market.
According to European entrepreneurs, the delay in payments by state entities-which has accumulated for more than seven years-is also a barrier to investment in Mozambique, in a process that “seriously compromises” the financial sustainability of companies, especially small and medium-sized (SME) that operate in sectors such as health, education and construction.
Eurocan also points to the lack of transparency in public tenders, namely the lack of response to public tenders, even after companies submit to complete proposals, as well as the performance of the Mozambican Tax Authority (TA) which he considers “aggressive”. "Some competitions launched by the Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Development did not have results, even after the end of the previous term," explains the document, adding that, regarding the AT performance, especially at the provincial level, "is seen as centered on immediate collection, with misaligned collection goals with the financial reality of companies."
Import of panels from China helps Africa break record in solar energy
Consultant Oxford Economics said the increase in the purchase of African countries solar panels to China has helped solar capacity by July to hit the record with 9,516 Megawatts (MW). “Africa, with its vast solar potential, is undergoing an increase in imports of solar panels from China; this influx is boosting the continent's generation capacity, with this year's imports by July to reach a record of 9,516 MW,” reads an analysis by the African department of this British consultant.
In a commentary on the evolution of solar energy production on the African continent, sent to customers and what Lusa had access to, analysts write that the reduction in solar facilities costs has made Africa solar capacity increase. “The cost of the life of solar energy has dropped dramatically over the past decade, and is now considered the cheapest form of electricity in history. These lower costs are boosting the increase in investments and generation worldwide, with the global solar capacity more than doubles in the last three years.
For Africa, this means an important benefit, analysts point out: “Sub-Saharan Africa has the lowest access to electricity in the world, with only 53.3% of the population electrified in 2023, well below the global average of 91.6%, and many African countries also face an unreliable supply and high electricity costs, which hinders economic development”.
The amount of solar panel imports by capacity reached a record value of 1,702 MW in July 2025, but looking at the first seven months of the year, solar imports by capacity increased to 9,516 MW, compared to 6,625 MW last year, which represents a 43%increase. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:06:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan considers that attack on the island would also threaten USA</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/07/taiwan-considera-que-ataque-a-ilha-tambem-ameacaria-eua/</link><description>The Taiwan government leader said that if China assumes the island's control by force "it will gain even more power to compete with the United States in the international arena," which would impair US "fundamental interests". William Lai also said that "as long as there is equality and respect," Taiwan is willing to negotiate with China and "achieve the purpose of peace and shared prosperity."
In an interview with the American radio show “The Clay Travis and Buck Sexon Show”, William Lai said that if he had the opportunity to meet US President Donald Trump, he would tell him that Beijing is not only performing “increasing” military exercises around Taiwan, but “is also expanding his military power” in the seas of East China and South China.
"Chinese military maneuvers already cover the entire Indo-Pacific region: its aircraft carriers have crossed the first and second island chains, the northern fleet surrounded Japan during its exercises and even fired real ammunition within the exclusive economic zone of Australia," Lai pointed out, according to a transcription of the interview released by the local government office. "What is at stake is not just Taiwan's 'annexation': if China seized the island, it would gain even more power to compete with the United States in the international arena, disturbing the world order based on rules and impairing the fundamental interests of the United States themselves," he added.
During the interview, Lai reiterated that Taiwan is open to dialogue and negotiate with Beijing. "As long as there is equality and respect, Taiwan is willing to negotiate with China and, through dialogue and cooperation, achieve the purpose of peace and shared prosperity," he said. Lai also expressed confidence that the island will “continue to have the support” of Donald Trump, who publicly stated that in a telephone conversation, Chinese leader Xi Jinping promised him not to send troops to attack Taiwan while he is president of the US. "If President Trump gets Xi Jinping to waive forever to use the force against Taiwan, he will certainly be worthy of the Nobel Peace Prize," he said.
More than 20 Chinese military aircraft flew over Taiwan
More than 20 Chinese military aircraft flew over yesterday the outskirts of Taiwan, a few days before the celebration of the National Day of the Republic of China, the island's official name, local authorities said.
Local authorities said in a statement that as of 9:20 a.m., they had detected a total of 23 incursions by Chinese warplanes, including J-16 fighters, JH-7 fighter-bombers, KJ-500 early warning planes and drones.
Of the total aircraft, 17 crossed the median line of Taiwan Strait and its extension, entering the North, Center and southwest of the self -proclaimed Taiwan Air Defense Identification Zone to perform a joint patrol of readiness for combat. ” "The Armed Forces maintained a strict surveillance through joint surveillance, information and recognition means, and mobilized aircraft, ships and terrestrial missile systems to respond adequately to the situation," said the military statement.
These overflows occur only three days before the celebration of National Day, on October 10, when local authorities celebrate the fall of the last imperial dynasty in 1911 and the establishment of the Republic of China (Taiwan).
The weeks leading up to this year's National Day were also marked by an escalation of disputes between Taipei and Beijing over United Nations Resolution 2758, which in October 1971 recognized the People's Republic of China as China's sole legitimate representative at the UN.
Beijing maintains that the resolution also supports his sovereignty on Taiwan, an interpretation that Taipe contests for considering an "distortion" of the original text. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:10:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Fu Hong plans opening a community canteen</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/07/fu-hong-planeia-abertura-de-uma-cantina-comunitaria/</link><description>The Fu Hong Rehabilitation Association of Macau is planning to open a “community canteen”, a project that could create jobs for people with disabilities. The plan was announced by Jennifer Chao, executive director of Fu Hong, on Monday.
According to the association, cited by the newspaper Chengpou, the cafeteria will provide meals at affordable prices for vulnerable groups, being also open to the general public, in order to promote community interaction.
Jennifer Chao highlighted that the project will work with a model “market-oriented and combined with social services”. "We hope to convey affection through food. We intend to seek to create more employment opportunities for people with disabilities, in order to improve their quality of life. On the other hand, we will encourage groups in need, such as elderly people living alone, people recovering from mental illnesses and single-parent families, to get involved with the community, to connect them to other social services, as necessary", he explained.
However, Jennifer Chao confessed that the project still faces difficulties, with the biggest obstacle being obtaining adequate facilities for its operation. The official hopes that the Government will provide support through policies, making unused public stores available, namely units on the ground floor of social neighborhoods, for use by social enterprises at affordable prices, contributing to the sustainable development of social services.
The director recalled that the Association has accumulated years of experience in operating social enterprises, having carried out several projects such as a laundry, a second-hand products store and an art studio. Therefore, he is confident that the canteen project can further help the social integration of people with disabilities.
The Fu Hong Rehabilitation Association will carry out, on this weekend, a product charity sales made by disabled artists, as well as a 'flag Selling Day', hoping to raise 500,000 patacas, a value dedicated to the development of services for people with disabilities.</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:28:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong seizes anesthetic linked to synthetic drug that killed three people</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/07/hong-kong-apreende-anestesico-ligado-a-droga-sintetica-que-matou-tres-pessoas/</link><description>Hong Kong authorities have seized 850 grams of an anesthetic used to produce a new synthetic drug known as 'space oil'. The substance, in powder form, was found hidden inside two cans of children's milk powder, inside a private vehicle that had crossed the bridge to enter Hong Kong.

Hong Kong police have announced the seizure of 850 grams of an anesthetic used to produce a new synthetic drug, known as 'Space Oil', which will have caused at least three deaths in the territory.
In a statement released on Sunday, Hong Kong Customs said the anesthetic etomidate was seized on the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macao Bridge. The substance, in powder form, was found hidden inside two cans of children's milk powder, inside a private vehicle that had crossed the bridge to enter Hong Kong, on Saturday.
The 41 -year -old driver and the 49 -year -old passenger were both detained. Police later found, among the passenger's belongings, an ethomidate capsule, which can consumed on electronic cigarette devices.
The quantity of etomidate seized had a street value of 2.3 million Hong Kong dollars.
Etomidate, a short-acting anesthetic administered intravenously, is mainly used in emergency departments, anesthesia units, operating rooms and intensive care units.
According to Hong Kong media, police said at a press conference that the seized substance had originally been sent from Malaysia to Macau.
In February, Hong Kong security forces announced the seizure of three kilograms of etomidate at the airport, inside unclaimed luggage from Malaysia.
In early November, Hong Kong authorities confirmed suspicions that at least three deaths are related to 'space oil'.
In February, the territory implemented new protocols involving more rigorous control not only about drug storage, but also on documentation and handling requirements in local hospitals.
Ethomidate was included in a list of hazardous products targeted by restrictions, raising the maximum penalty for possession of "space oil" to seven years in prison and a fine of one million dollars from Hong Kong. The trafficking or illegal importation of this substance has been subject to a maximum penalty of five million dollars of Hong Kong.
Macao also revealed in December that police have already detected four cases linked to this narcotic since the first case of 'space oil' found in a local school in October 2023. This drug is known in Hong Kong as 'Zombie drug' because it can cause serious physical and mental damage, including dependence, memory loss, seizures, loss of consciousness and even death. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:21:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Registration of toxicode dependents fell 11.5% in the first half</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/07/registo-de-toxicodependentes-caiu-115-no-primeiro-semestre/</link><description>The number of registered toxicode dependents decreased by 11.5%, in annual terms, to a total of 85, in the first half of this year, the Institute of Social Action revealed. It was not registered, in fact, no case of toxicodependence among adolescents under the age of 21, the first time since this has been registered. The analysis points out that methamphetamine remains the most consumed drug.

The Institute of Social Action (IAS) revealed that it had identified 85 people with drug-related problems during the first six months of this year. The number represented a drop of 11.5% compared to the same period last year.
The statistics of the central registration system, which was released at a plenary session of the drug struggle committee, also pointed out that there were no cases of young people with young people under 21 years. This was the first time there were no cases of drug addiction from young people throughout the IAS registration, which began in 2009.
The most used drug was methamphetamine (ICE), which corresponded to 22.7%of toxicodependents, followed by heroin (9.1%), cannabis (4.5%), midazolam (sleepy) and cocaine, both accounted for 2.3%.
The press release about the meeting did not set out the entire analysis of the central registration system for drug addicts, however, a report published on the Government's anti-drug electronic portal provided more details about people affected by drug addiction.
According to the document, registered between January and June of this year, the minimum age of drug addicts is 22 years old, while the maximum age is 78 years old. The proportion of female drug addicts stood at 27.1%, which represents a slight increase of 7.1 percentage points compared to the same period last year. Both non-residents in Macau (20%) and non-Chinese (17.6%) showed a decrease in annual terms.
Toxicode dependents continue to reside mostly in the North Zone, representing 42.4% of cases. The number of unemployed among registered toxicode dependents rose to 40% of the total. 29.4% had criminal records, with an increase of 7.9 percentage points for the first half of 2024.
The IAS report also indicates that the toxicode dependents spent more drugs, and the average monthly expense for narcotics settled at 2,359.4 patacas, a higher value compared to the 2,172.7 patacas from the same period last year.
In relation to places of consumption, 58.4% occurred at home and 14.2% at a friend's house, while 8% chose to consume the drug in hotels, and 7.1% in less hidden places such as parks, streets and public toilets.
As for the reasons for drug use, 43.4% said they resorted to the drug to “reduce stress/anguish/frustration/melancholy,” a percentage similar to the same period last year. The data also reveal that 18.9% of toxicode dependents mentioned the "influence of friends."
There are currently 28 government departments and associations that help register data for the Central Drug Addicts Registration System, in order to be able to “define anti-drug policies and create the respective services” in an improved way, highlighted the IAS.

MORE DRUGS ON THE CHECKLIST
 
In addition to the toxicodependent statistics, work on drug control was also a theme for the plenary session of the drug struggle committee, which took place on Monday.
LAM, secretary for social affairs and culture, who presided over the meeting, said that after the revision of the “prohibition of production, trafficking and illicit consumption of narcotic and psychotropic substances” in June, the government is now advancing with six substances recently included in the list by the 68th session of the United Nations Commission for the skeptic.
"The drug struggle committee closely follows the evolution of regulation and the trends of abuse related to emerging drugs in neighboring regions. It will continue to collect, evaluate and analyze the opinions of members and relevant organizations, to ensure that Macao remains in accordance with international and regional rules, thus reinforcing the effectiveness of preventing and combating drugs," said the ruler.
According to a statement from IAS, the meeting was proposed at the launch of “more diverse” anti -drug activities, encouraging young people to assume an “active role” in drug fighting initiatives.
The difficulties and restrictions faced by rehabilitated young people when reintegrating into society were also addressed. In this case, the Commission hopes to strengthen collaboration between medical and social services units, create mechanisms to promote the participation of individuals in drug rehabilitation in professional training.</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:38:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Health Services provide treatment to 3,830 people diagnosed with dementia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/07/servicos-de-saude-prestam-tratamento-a-3-830-pessoas-diagnosticadas-com-demencia/</link><description>There is currently in Macao a total of 3,830 people who have been diagnosed with dementia and who are receiving medical treatment in health services. According to the body, from the beginning of the year to August, a mental state examination has been performed at more than 2,270 people to evaluate their cognitive functions.

Faced with the worsening of population aging in Macau, the authorities guarantee a “continuous concern” with medical services related to dementia, revealing that, to date, the number of people diagnosed and treated with dementia in Health Services exceeds 3,830.
Health services proceeded to perform a small mental state examination (MMS) to more than 2,270 people, with the purpose of evaluating cognitive functions in the period between January and August this year.
The numbers were advanced in a response from the Institute of Social Action (IAS) to Deputy Leong Hong Sai, who warned, in written interpellation, to the need for measures to reduce the risk of dementia among the elderly in Macao.
Remember that the Government had announced last month that the Health Services' dementia consultation receives an average of around 600 new cases per year. The number showed an increasing trend, as the average number of new cases in recent years was around 500. Furthermore, the Macau Alzheimer's Disease Association stated that there are currently around 6,000 dementia patients in Macau, including the almost four thousand patients treated in the Health Services.
In this context, IAS has ensured in the response that various initiatives related to prevention and dementia services are available in the territory. According to Hon Wai, president of IAS, the Dementia Evaluation and Treatment Center and the Dementia Support Center were established, where they provide one -stop diagnostic and treatment services, cognitive groups, and dementia educational training courses, as well as providing more comprehensive support services for light to moderate dementia and their families.
The IAS said it launched, in 2017, in collaboration with the Alzheimer's Disease Association of Macau, the project “Charter of the friendly community for people with dementia in Macau”, which currently has the membership of 209 professional associations in the health sector, primary, secondary and higher education establishments, institutions that support the elderly and young people. “Institutions that support the elderly also act proactively to flag suspected cases of elderly people with dementia and then contact their family members and provide support in submitting these elderly people to the assessment of cognitive functions in health centers”, he continued.

HEARING PROTECTION TO PREVENT DEMENTIA
 
Deputy Leong Hong also questioned the government about complementary measures for dementia prevention, including the generalization of periodic auditory and memory examination for the elderly, as well as the promotion of the allowance for the use of hearing aids and cochlear implants.
The legislator cited the World Health Organization to indicate that, among elderly people over 60 years of age, one in four of them suffers from disabling hearing loss that “increases the risk of dementia, falls and depression”. Leong added that several studies show that hearing interacts with the brain, and when you don't hear well, the brain has to guess, which puts a strain on the brain.
“Early intervention, such as the use of hearing aids and cochlear implants, not only improves hearing, but also delays memory loss”, argued the deputy.
In the replica, IAS said that, in recent years, it has resorted to a pilot plan held in two rounds, through which it attributes financial support to eligible persons, holders of the disability assessment card, to acquire auxiliary equipment that include hearing aids and related instruments.
He revealed that the Government is taking stock of the implementation of this pilot plan, with the aim of making the said plan a permanent measure later this year.
The executive also stated that he will conduct the “Health Inquiry of Macau 2026” next year, where hear exams will be included in order to evaluate the global state of hearing in society.</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:36:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Advertising and conventions and exhibitions grow in 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/07/publicidade-e-convencoes-e-exposicoes-crescem-em-2024/</link><description>The Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) released the results of a survey of the branches of advertising and the organization of conventions and exhibitions, referring to last year.
According to the body, the gross surpluses of these two branches recorded homologous growths due to the “increased demand for promotional services on the market” and the number of conventions and exhibitions that took place in Macao over 2024.
In the year in question, the revenues of the 686 establishments dedicated to the advertising sector amounted to 697 million patacas – 16.8% more, compared to 2023. Expenses totaled 648 million patacas, an increase of 12%, and were mainly made in purchases of goods, contracted services and commissions (17.2% more) and personnel expenses (10.6% more). The sector's gross surplus was 48 million patacas, an increase of 199.7% year-on-year.
Shifting the focus to the field of organizing conventions and exhibitions, there were 102 establishments that generated total revenue of 678 million patacas – a growth of 9.7% compared to 2023. Expenses stood at 600 million patacas, an increase of 5.3%, with 68.5% of the total amount related to purchases of goods, contracted services and commissions (an increase of 4% in annual terms) and 21.7% with expenses spent on personnel (plus 15.6%). Here, the gross surplus was 78 million patacas, an increase of 61.7% compared to 2023.
As DSEC details in a statement, the main economic activity of establishments in the advertising sector includes advertising, design and production of advertising and dissemination in social media. The branch of organizing conventions and exhibitions covers the planning and organization of this type of event, excluding establishments that provide specialized services to organizers, such as production, installation, decoration, advertising, promotion, public relations and transport. Establishments that provide services for the organization of cultural and recreational activities are also excluded from this definition.</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:25:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Six more public car parks with half-hour charging model</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/07/mais-seis-parques-de-estacionamento-publico-com-modelo-de-cobranca-por-meia-hora/</link><description>Six more public parking parks in Macau will implement the collection model for half an hour from October 15. With the extended measure, the city will have a total of 15 public parking parks to charge for every half hour, where users need to pay at least one hour, regardless of the parking time is shorter.
According to the Directorate of Service for Traffic Affairs (DSAT), the measure will be adopted in the Public Car Park at Rotunda da Concórdia, Public Car Park at Estrada Flor de Lótus, Public Car Park at Edifício Lok Kuan, Public Car Park at Edifício Ip Heng, Public Car Park at Edifício Koi Nga and Public Car Park at Alameda da Harmonia.
With the entry into force of the new tariff model, the daytime and night parking for light cars will be 3 patacas and 1.5 patacas, respectively, for each half -hour period or fraction. For motorcycles and mopeds, the fare will be 1 level during the day and 0.5 patacas at night.
DSAT said it had extended the half-hour pricing model to more public car parks “taking into account the views of society” and “to further encourage drivers to use public parking facilities”.
There are a total of 71 public parking lots in Macau, of which those at the Mong Son Building, the Qingmao Border Post, the Macau Union Hospital, the Public Health Specialty Building, the Northeast Avenue Residence for the Elderly, the Tong Seng Building, the Tong Kai Building, the Tong Chong Building and the Governor Albano de Oliveira Road Public Parking Lot are already operating under the new tariff model.
DSAT said it will continue to monitor the operation of these parks and study the gradual expansion of this charging model to more suitable public car parks.</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:26:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong breaks record with the largest number of tropical storms in 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/07/hong-kong-bate-recorde-com-maior-numero-de-tempestades-tropicais-em-2025/</link><description>Hong Kong has already been affected by 12 tropical storms and typhoons this year, the highest annual figure since records began in 1917, according to the meteorological agency of the former British colony. The new record was set with the passage of Matmo, the fourth typhoon to affect southern China in five weeks, which led Hong Kong to issue tropical storm signal 3, the second lowest level during the weekend.
Matmo “breaks the record (…) since numbered tropical cyclone warning signs were introduced in 1917,” a spokesperson for the meteorological agency told the Hong Kong Free Press news portal on Sunday.
Both in Hong Kong and in the neighboring region of Macau, the tropical storm warning scale consists of signals 1, 3, 8, 9 and 10 (the highest), with the issue depending on the proximity of the storm and the intensity of the wind.
Tuffons are recurring phenomena in Southeast Asia, when the hot waters of the Pacific Ocean favor the formation of cyclones, and southern China is hit by dozens of these tropical storms, especially at the rainy season, which usually begins in June and ends in November or December.
According to a study published in July 2024, typhoons in the region are forming closer to the coast than in the past, intensifying more quickly and remaining over land for longer, as a result of climate change.
According to scientists, climate change is causing more frequent and intense extreme weather events around the world.</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:19:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Portugal starts preparing games with Ireland and Hungary</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/07/portugal-comeca-a-preparar-jogos-com-irlanda-e-hungria/</link><description>The Portuguese team began yesterday preparing the games with Ireland and Hungary, both at the José Alvalade stadium in Lisbon, which can guarantee in October the Field F for the World Cup2026 football. The coach Roberto Martínez called 25 players for the meetings of the third and fourth Days of Group F, in a list where the defender João Cancelo is low due to injury. The midfielder João Neves was in the initial call, but was dismissed even before the start of the internship also due to physical problems. To his place, Martínez called the left back Nuno Tavares, as had happened in September, at the time replacing Diogo Dalot. After another year of absence, Matheus Nunes is returning to the national team, as well as Nelson Semedo and Rafael Leão, who failed the September Games by injury.
Portugal receives the Republic of Ireland on Saturday and Hungary, three days later, on the 14th, in two meetings scheduled for the José Alvalade Stadium in Lisbon. In the start of qualification, Portugal went to Erevan to win Armenia 5-0, followed by a new triumph in Budapest before Hungary (3-2). The Lusa team leads the group with six points, three more than Armenia, while Hungarian and Irish add up to one, resulting from the draw between them. Portugal can already guarantee the determination and ensure the ninth presence in worlds, the seventh in a row, if the two meetings won and if Armenia does not triumph in any of their matches (Hungary, Budapest, and Ireland, Dublin).
The group winner automatically secures a place in the tournament that will be played next year in the United States, Canada and Mexico, and which for the first time will have 48 teams. The second-placed team will have to compete in the qualifying play-offs.</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:09:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing prices fall again between June and August</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/07/precos-da-habitacao-voltam-a-cair-entre-junho-e-agosto/</link><description>The housing price index registered a new 0.8% drop between June and August. The data were released by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), confirming a decreasing trend that has been observed since 2022.
 
The global housing price index was 192.4 in the period between June and August, which represents a decrease of 0.8% compared to the previous period from May to July. According to data released on Monday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), the price index for constructed housing fell by 1.1%, to 206.7, while the index for housing under construction increased by 0.3%, to 233.6.
The decline in the price index for built housing was common to the Macau peninsula and the islands of Taipa and Coloane, with respective drops of 1.3% and 0.2% compared to the previous period. Considering the year in which the buildings were constructed, it can be seen that the price index for housing in the category over 20 years old decreased by 1.4%, although the index for the age group from 11 to 20 years old registered a slight increase of 0.1%. On the other hand, the indices for the bracket less than or equal to five years and the bracket for six to ten years recorded the same drop: 1.2%.
Looking at the useful area of ​​the autonomous units, it is possible to see that the index for the range from 50 to 74.9 square meters and the index for the range from 75 to 99.9 square meters had respective drops of 1.5% and 0.8%. In turn, the index for the category of less than 50 square meters rose 0.2% in the same time window.
Considering the height of buildings, there is a decrease of 0.2% and 0.9%, respectively, in the index for buildings with a level of less than or equal to seven floors and in the index for buildings with more than seven floors.
In annual terms, DSEC data show that the global housing price index between June and August fell 10.3% when compared to the same period in 2024. The index for the Macau peninsula stood at 189.6, down 10.3%, while the islands of Taipa and Coloane would both reach an index of 204.6, representing a drop of 10.4%.

ESTABLISHMENT REVENUES AND EXPENSES INCREASE
 
In a parallel statement, DSEC also released the results of the inquiry into the branches of building administration, security and cleaning for the year 2024.
In the year under review, there were 234 establishments dedicated to the property administration branch of economic activity. Both revenue and expenses for the year increased by 3.5% and 2.2%, respectively, compared to 2023, amounting to 1.95 billion patacas and 1.82 billion patacas.
Analyzing only the expenses, it appears that the money spent on personnel (1.11 billion patacas) and on business operation (509 billion patacas) grew the most compared to the previous year, with respective increases of 5.1% and 2.5%. In the opposite direction, expenses incurred in purchasing goods, contracted services and commissions fell by 11.9% to 200 million patacas. During the period under review, the sector's gross surplus was 138 million patacas.
The DSEC report also shows that in 2024 there were 64 establishments dedicated to the branch of security. In this parameter, revenues increased by 9.8% over the previous year due to a “greater demand” of safety services in the territory, as the body details in a statement. Expenses also grew by 10.1%, ciphering by 2.17 billion patacas. More than 90% of total expenses concerned personnel expenses, which registered a 9% homologous growth. In this sector, the gross surplus stood in 166 million patacas.
Finally, regarding the cleaning sector, DSEC counted 375 establishments with total revenue of 1.54 billion patacas, 6.8% more compared to the previous year. The expenses recorded by this sector were 1.44 billion patacas, 9.7% more compared to 2023. This growth is mainly attributed to personnel expenses (10.4% more), operating expenses (0.4%) and expenses incurred in purchasing goods, contracted services and commissions (19.5%). Last year, this sector achieved a gross surplus of 103 million patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:33:05</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korean leader inspects a new five thousand tons</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/07/lider-norte-coreano-inspecciona-novo-contratorpedeiro-de-cinco-mil-toneladas/</link><description>Kim Jong-un inspected the latest five-thousand-ton warship intended to “punish enemy provocations”. The launch of Choe Hyon “is a clear demonstration of the development of armed forces guided by the Juche doctrine [North Korea's self-sufficiency ideology],” said the North Korean leader.

North Kore leader Kim Jong-un inspected the latest five-ton war ship on Sunday to “punish enemy provocations,” the official KCNA news agency said yesterday.
Presented in April by Pyongyang, the Choe Hyon is the country's first five-thousand-ton destroyer to be equipped with nuclear missiles.
The launch of Choe Hyon “is a clear demonstration of the development of armed forces guided by the Juche doctrine [North Korea's self-sufficiency ideology],” the leader said, according to KCNA. “The formidable capabilities of our navy must be exercised in the vast ocean in order to deter or counter and punish the enemy’s provocations to the sovereignty of the State,” he added.
The destroyer Choe Hyon is one of two 5,000-ton warships that North Korea has, both of which were completed this year. Kim Jong-un has committed to building another destroyer of the same type by October 2026 in order to reinforce naval capabilities.
According to the South Korean army, this ship may have been developed with help from Russia, possibly in exchange for sending thousands of soldiers to help Moscow fight in Ukraine.
Photos from the KCNA agency show the North Korean leader supervising what appears to be a control room inside the ship. Another photograph shows the leader pointing to a blurred map in front of generals.
This visit comes after Kim Jong-un announced the mobilization of "special means" against the southern neighbor, without specifying nature, according to statements released on Sunday by KCNA.
Around 28,500 US troops are stationed in South Korea to counter Pyongyang's military threats. In September, they carried out a joint military exercise with their South Korean and Japanese allies.
North Korea regularly denounces these exercises, which considers essays for an invasion, while allies insist on the defensive character of maneuvers. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:07:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Wong Sio Chak says extreme climate phenomena are increasingly frequent</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/07/wong-sio-chak-diz-que-fenomenos-climaticos-extremos-sao-cada-vez-mais-frequentes/</link><description>Secretary Wong Sio Chak warned of the increasingly frequent occurrence of extreme climate phenomena in Macao, calling for members of the civil protection structure to “lower the guard” and strive to minimize the impact of possible natural disasters on the territory.
Taking stock of the work to respond to Typhoon Matmo, the Secretary for Security and Joint Action Commander (CAC) said that “the safety of the lives and property of residents and tourists was well safeguarded”, thanks to the efforts made by the Civil Protection Operations Center (COPC) and the other services involved.
In a year in which the city of Macau has already been affected by twelve tropical storms, the official highlighted that members of the civil protection structure have acted “persistently”, based on “advance planning for extreme and adverse situations, issuing alerts in a timely manner and promptly adopting the corresponding measures”.
Matmo, remember, was the twelfth tropical storm recorded in Macau this year, a number that had been seen since 1974. The 2025 typhoon season also goes down in history as one of the four in which there was a need to issue four signals no. maximum signal alert: typhoon Wipah, in June, and super typhoon Ragasa, last September.
Given the data in recent years, Wong Sio Chak has acknowledged that it is “increasingly frequent the occurrence of extreme weather conditions” in the region and stressed the importance of building “a solid security line line” in order to minimize “the impact of eventual natural disasters” in Macau. In this sense, the secretary urged members of the civil protection structure to remain “always alerts”, to constantly improve the various specific contingency plans ”and to promote“ disaster prevention work ”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:29:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Melco invests in health tourism with the first hospital inside a casino</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/07/melco-investe-no-turismo-de-saude-com-primeiro-hospital-dentro-de-um-casino/</link><description>Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, in partnership with the iRad group from Hong Kong, opened in Studio City the first hospital in the world located within an integrated resort, equipped with magnetic resonance imaging and computerized tomography. The pioneering project aims to position Macau as a regional medical tourism hub, in line with the Government's “1+4” economic diversification strategy. 

The territory has taken another step in its economic diversification strategy with the inauguration of Irad Hospital in Studio City, which operator Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment says it is the first hospital establishment in the world integrated into an entertainment resort and the only one in Macao with magnetic resonance imaging and computed tomography. The opening ceremony, held last Monday, was attended by the Director of Health Services, Alvis Lo, the Director of Tourism Services, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, and other individuals of the government and the connection office.
The new hospital, the result of a partnership between Melco and IRAD, the largest supplier of Hong Kong magnetic resonance imaging services, represents a strategic investment in the Big Health sector, aiming to capitalize on the forecast of 38 to 39 million annual visitors in Macao. Located in an area of ​​1,400 square meters at Studio City, Irad Hospital offers health tracking services, image diagnosis, aesthetic medicine, longevity treatments and medical concierge services.
Lawrence Ho, President and CEO of Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, highlighted during the inauguration that “the project is aligned with the Economic Diversification strategy‘ 1+4 ’of the Government of Masters”, adding that “Studio City is now prepared to become a leading destination for health and well-being, establishing Macao as the main regional hub of medical and well-being”.
The hospital team is mostly made up of local professionals, with specialized reinforcements from South Korea, for aesthetic medicine, and from Hong Kong for imaging. Dennis Tam, honorary president of iRad, explained that “tourists will be our main audience, but we also rely on the local population, as many people today prefer preventive care rather than waiting to have health problems.”
Irad Hospital positions itself as a premium but affordable health option, with also comparing the concept to "a high-end restaurant but does not star Michelin." The hospital is already operational for medical examinations and non -invasive aesthetic treatments, being equipped with an operative block that is not yet in operation.
The project comes at a time when Macau intends to invest in the possibility of becoming a regional health tourism hub. The director of Tourism Services, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, has been actively promoting this aspect, recognizing the territory's potential to attract visitors looking to combine entertainment with quality healthcare, including traditional Chinese medicine.
iRad's investment in Macau reflects growth in the health tourism sector in the region, with the group bringing to the territory the experience accumulated since 2006 in Hong Kong, where it is the largest provider of magnetic resonance diagnostic services, including serving the Hong Kong Government and other leading medical groups. The investment follows the purchase of a majority stake in iRad Medical Holding, by Black Spade Capital, a company that manages Lawrence Ho's private investments, for an undisclosed amount in 2021, of which Dennis Lam is the president and CEO.</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:34:12</pubDate></item></channel></rss>