<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/25/visita-guiada-revela-historias-dos-bairros-por-ocasiao-dos-20-anos-do-patrimonio-mundial/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Trump announces visit to Beijing in April after phone call with Xi Jinping</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/25/trump-anuncia-visita-a-pequim-em-abril-apos-telefonema-com-xi-jinping/</link><description>North American President Donald Trump announced a visit to Beijing in April, which will be reciprocated with a trip by his counterpart to the United States at the end of next year.

Donald Trump made the announcement just hours after speaking with Xi by phone on Monday morning, when, as he indicated, both discussed issues such as the conflict in Ukraine, the fight against the opioid fentanyl and the soy trade. The phone call took place almost a month after the two met in the South Korean city of Busan.
Chinese officials confirmed the phone call, without mentioning the two leaders' state visits, reporting that topics discussed included Ukraine, trade and Taiwan.
After the conversation, the White House leader considered, in a message on his Truth Social network, the relationship with Beijing as “extremely strong”, but made no reference to the sensitive issue of Taiwan.
According to a statement from the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Xi told Trump that Taiwan's return to mainland China is “an integral part of the post-war international order” and expressed hope for a “fair, lasting and binding peace agreement” on Ukraine.
The conversation came after Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi recently stated that Japan's military could become involved if China takes action against Taiwan.
Over the weekend, Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi said Japan had “crossed a red line that should not have been crossed.”
During the telephone call, Xi Jinping argued that China and the United States, which fought together against fascism and militarism, should “jointly safeguard the victory of the Second World War”.
The United States has not taken sides on the issue of Taiwan's sovereignty, but opposes the use of force to seize the territory. By domestic law, Washington authorities are required to supply weapons to the island to deter any armed attack.
Earlier this month, the head of Taiwan's Foreign Affairs said he had received official notification that the Trump administration approved an arms sale worth $330 million, including parts for fighter jets. Beijing immediately protested this deal, saying it “grossly violated” the “One China” principle.
The two leaders also discussed the crisis in Ukraine, which began with the Russian invasion in February 2022, with Xi saying, according to Beijing's diplomacy, that the crisis must be resolved “at its root”, a formulation usually used by Moscow.
The Chinese President highlighted his support for “all efforts that contribute to peace”, according to the statement, despite Western governments accusing Beijing of enabling the Russian war effort through its industrial support for Moscow.
In the call, Xi also said that the bilateral relationship “has maintained a stable and positive trajectory” since the Busan summit, and stated that both sides should strive to achieve “even more positive progress”. Beijing's diplomacy has not revealed any concrete agreement on issues such as the purchase of American soybeans. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 23:53:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Inspired by the National Games, deputies want greater promotion of sport</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/25/inspirados-pelos-jogos-nacionais-deputados-querem-maior-promocao-do-desporto/</link><description>After the 15th edition of the National Games, in which some of the events took place in Macau, several deputies to the Legislative Assembly (AL) asked the Government to better promote sport in the region.

The 15th edition of the National Games ended a few days ago, which were hosted for the first time in Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau. This sporting event inspired several interventions before the agenda of yesterday's plenary meeting of the Legislative Assembly. Many deputies called for measures to promote sport in the region.
The 13 days of games in various disciplines resulted in three gold medals and two bronze medals for Macau – the region's best performance ever in the sporting competition.
Ella Lei was the first to congratulate the Macau athletes for their achievements at the National Games, also taking the opportunity to thank the Macau workers and volunteers who demonstrated “a spirit of unity, collaboration and professionalism”.
In her intervention, the deputy said she hopes that the Macao SAR Executive will provide “more support for the training and development of local athletes, and continuously improve, and through various measures, the conditions for the preparation of young people with potential and the training of athletes, and reinforce the financial support plan for the training of athletes and for retired athletes, thus ensuring global support and protection for athletes”.
One of the new features of the Governing Action Lines (LAG) for next year is the merger of the Sports Institute with the Cultural Institute. Ella Lei said she hopes that this merger will create “new development opportunities” and promote “the decentralization of resources, sport for all, and the creation of a sports environment for the entire population”.
Ella Lei suggests that the Government study the “articulation of part of the space of the former Jockey Club with the Olympic Sports Center and other adjacent sports facilities, to carry out updating and long-term planning, as well as to improve the sports facilities and the coordination with the tourist industry and Cotai facilities, through appropriate spaces and supports”.
Lam Lon Wai also used his speech before the agenda to applaud the fact that Macau was the venue for this edition of the National Games. According to the deputy, the event demonstrated Macau's “institutional advantages and its ability to manage major events”, increased “Macau's international visibility” and showed the “spirit of hospitality of Macau residents”.
The deputy linked to the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau (FAOM) said he hopes that “the Government will make a good assessment of the National Games, accumulating and transforming their experiences, and continue to promote Macau as a stage for high-level events”.
In a joint intervention, Angela Leong and Ma Chi Seng also asked the Government to continue promoting the development of “performance sport and sport for all”. “In the future, I hope that the Government will continue to increase the investment of resources, strengthen the systematic training and selection of young sporting talents, and comprehensively raise the competitive levels of Macau’s athletes,” said Ma Chi Seng. The nominated deputies also suggested opening sports facilities used in the National Games to the public.
Angela Leong and Ma Chi Seng also indicated that the Executive can better explore the “sport+culture+tourism” dynamic and take advantage of the “synergetic cooperation between Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau”, increasing the “cohesive force for regional development”.
The 15th edition of the National Games “not only revealed the top competitive level, but also stimulated public enthusiasm for sport, promoting the diversified development of ‘sport+’, deepening regional cooperation and injecting new dynamism into Macau’s ‘event economy’”, said Ngan Iek Hang. The deputy linked to the Residents presented several suggestions to the authorities, including the focus on “sports tourism”, the improvement of sports venues and facilities and the deepening of regional cooperation.
Deputy Lee Koi Ian suggested that the Government improve the “talent cultivation system for performance sports” and draw up specific plans for the development of the sports industry. Finally, Chan Hao Weng highlighted that “the National Games were not just a stage for competitions, but a crucial step towards Macau’s integration into national development”. “We will transform this enthusiasm into a long-term driving force and jointly build a dynamic Macau city, with a view to making a greater contribution to the integration and development of the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area”, he highlighted.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 23:57:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Tai Kin Ip cautious about the future</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/25/tai-kin-ip-cauteloso-face-ao-futuro/</link><description>The Legislative Assembly (AL) approved, in general, the budget proposal for 2026 yesterday. A proposal that, according to the Secretary for Economy and Finance, is prudent, given the geopolitical tensions surrounding Macau. Tai Kin Ip did not want to offer an estimate for next year's GDP, due to the various “uncertainties” that remain.

The budget proposal for 2026 was generally approved yesterday, with all deputies voting in favor. This budget foresees that gross gaming revenue – the main driver of the region's economy – will be 236 billion patacas next year. Furthermore, it estimates that there is a budget balance of 5.3 billion patacas.
The proposed budget law for 2026 puts the Macao SAR's revenue at 118.8 billion patacas, 2% more compared to what was stipulated in the budget for this year. Expenses will suffer an annual reduction of 2.4% to 113.4 billion patacas, according to the Government's estimate.
During the discussion in the Legislative Assembly (AL), deputies asked Tai Kin Ip, secretary for Economy and Finance, what data the Government was based on to prepare this budget proposal for next year and the government official replied that last year was taken into account. The first budget for 2025, remember, estimated gross gaming revenues of around 240 billion patacas, but the first months were below expectations and the Executive reduced the estimates to 228 billion.
Questioned by deputy Joey Lao about GDP forecasts for next year, Tai Kin Ip was cautious regarding the future development of the Macao SAR economy. “Honestly, it is difficult to make an accurate and correct forecast”, he began by saying, adding that Macau’s economy is conditioned by the “geopolitical tension that we see around us”. “We can, on the one hand, count on the development of our country, but, on the other hand, we have to be careful against any slip-up”, he highlighted, remembering that Macau has an “economy exposed to the outside world”.
Even so, the secretary left a message of optimism for potential investors, saying that gaming revenues tend to increase, as does the number of visitors.
The budget for next year also foresees that the value related to the implementation of measures to promote the well-being of the population will be 26.7 billion patacas, which means an increase of around 1 billion compared to the 2025 budget. According to Tai Kin Ip, the amount that the Administration saves with the restrictions imposed in the financial contribution plan is used to be applied to well-being measures for the population.
Next year, three tax benefit measures will be applied: exemption from property transfer tax on the acquisition of housing units in the first 6 million; tax benefit rate of 5% relating to Supplementary Income Tax for companies that carry out corporate treasury center activities; and tax benefit of 5% relating to Supplementary Income Tax and various tax benefits for investment fund management companies.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 23:58:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Special Olympics torch travels across Greater Bay Area with stop in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/25/tocha-dos-jogos-olimpicos-especiais-percorre-grande-baia-com-parada-em-macau/</link><description>The flame of the National Games for People with Disabilities and National Special Olympics Games will begin its journey through the Greater Bay Area on November 29th. Macau, which will host the badminton competitions, will host the torch on a 2.6 km route between the Government headquarters and Largo do Senado, involving 1,500 local volunteers. 

The Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area will witness a historic moment of inclusion and sporting unity with the replacement of the torch for the Special Olympics Games for the Disabled, which will simultaneously travel through the four cities, Shenzhen, Guangzhou, Hong Kong and Macau, next Saturday, November 29th. The announcement was made this Monday during a joint press conference at the Guangzhou Main Press Center, which was attended by coordinators from the three regions.
The “Union of the two flames” model, shared with the 15th edition of the National Games, will symbolize the theme “Together in the Greater Bay Area, Inclusion of people with and without disabilities”. The ceremonies will begin at 9:00 am at the Shenzhen Talent Park, followed by parallel events in Guangzhou, Hong Kong and Macau at 9:30 am. In total, 200 torchbearers, 50 per city, will participate in this symbolic moment that precedes the Games, scheduled for December 8th to 15th.
Pun Weng Kun, Coordinator of the Preparatory Office for the Organization of the Macau Competition Zone, explained that the territory will host the badminton events of both the National Games for People with Disabilities and the National Special Olympics Games. The relay route in Macau, measuring approximately 2.6 kilometers, was “carefully planned to guarantee total accessibility, allowing all torch relays to participate on an equal footing”.
The route in Macau will begin at the Government headquarters, ending at Largo do Senado, including the concept of “cultural integration” through passing through areas classified as World Heritage. The composition of the torchbearers is intended to reflect the diversity of the community, including local athletes from the Special Olympics Games for the Disabled, representatives from institutions serving people with disabilities, socially renowned personalities, local sports figures and event sponsors.
The operation in Macau will have the support of 1,500 volunteers who have completed systematic and specific training according to the needs of the different modalities. Pun Weng Kun highlighted the commitment to preparing these volunteers, who developed specialized skills “together with the respective entities, in order to reinforce the general quality and service capacity”.
In other regions of the Greater Bay Area, the routes take on different characteristics: Hong Kong will organize a nine-kilometer relay between the Central Government Office Tamar and Kai Tak Sports Park, passing through several emblematic locations, while Shenzhen and Guangzhou have developed thematic routes centered on the concepts of innovation and regional integration.
During the press conference, the Mandarin version of the song “Gong Fu Shanhai” (Towards the Sea and Mountains), performed by Jackson Yee and the choir from the three regions, was also presented, conveying the spirit of “Equality, Participation, Sharing and Inclusion” that characterizes the event, according to the Preparatory Office for the Organization of the Macau Competition Zone.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 23:51:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan considers stable relationship between US and China “extremely important”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/25/japao-considera-extremamente-importante-relacao-estavel-entre-eua-e-china/</link><description>Japan declared yesterday that it considers a stable relationship between the United States and China to be “extremely important”, at a time of Sino-Japanese tensions and after the North American President spoke with his Chinese counterpart.
Ties between Washington and Beijing are “extremely important”, said Japanese Government spokesman Minoru Kihara, before stressing that the archipelago will continue to rely on the alliance with the United States to urge China to “fulfill responsibilities compatible with its role” on the international stage.
Relations between China and Japan are going through a difficult time, after Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi recently stated that a Chinese military attack on Taiwan could justify intervention by the Japanese army. Beijing responded with harsh reprimands, economic retaliation and demanded that Takaichi withdraw the statement.
China also advised against non-essential travel to Japan – which led to the suspension of hundreds of thousands of air travel – and again banned the import of Japanese seafood, among other measures.
Takaichi refused on Friday – exactly one month after becoming the first woman to lead Japan – to backtrack on statements about Taiwan and stated that they reflect the “consistent position” of the Japanese Government.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 23:51:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Timor-Leste and Australian company Woodside sign agreement for studies for gas production</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/25/timor-leste-e-a-australiana-woodside-assinam-acordo-para-estudos-para-producao-de-gas/</link><description>The Timorese Ministry of Petroleum and Mineral Resources signed yesterday with the Australian Woodside Energy a cooperation agreement to carry out studies and activities to develop the production of Liquefied Natural Gas in the country.

At the agreement signing ceremony, the Minister of Petroleum, Francisco Monteiro, highlighted that the signing “sends a clear message that the Government and Woodside are united in the ambition to get Greater Sunrise producing in a way that benefits all interested parties”.
“The Timor-Leste Liquefied Natural Gas project presents the best economic, social and strategic advantages for the people of Timor-Leste, and we are committed to working constructively with Woodside, the Greater Sunrise joint venture and other parties to advance the project and make our vision for Greater Sunrise a reality,” the minister added.
Woodside Executive Chairman Meg O’Neill said the agreement represents the next step in the relationship and a shared commitment to the development of the Greater Sunrise fields. “This work is an extension of the concept study carried out last year and will address the remaining considerations required to arrive at concept selection, such as agreeing on the most appropriate downstream commercial structure to attract financing and identifying the preferred route for the gas export pipeline”, highlighted Meg O’Neill.
The signing ceremony was witnessed by the Timorese Prime Minister, Xanana Gusmão, and the Australian Ambassador to Timor-Leste, Caitilin Wilson, and took place during the 5th Timor-Leste Energy, Mining and Business Forum, which ends this Wednesday.
In a joint statement released to the press, both parties emphasize that the agreement “represents a significant milestone in the long-standing efforts between Timor-Leste and Woodside to unlock the value of the Greater Sunrise gas fields.
Under the agreement, studies will be carried out for the Liquefied Natural Gas project in Timor-Leste with capacity to produce around five million tons per year, including gas supply for domestic use and a unit to extract helium. “These activities will take place in parallel with ongoing negotiations on the fiscal, regulatory and legal framework necessary to support the ‘upstream’ development of the Greater Sunrise fields between the Sunrise Joint Venture and the governments of Timor-Leste and Australia”, highlights the statement.
The agreement includes a high-level plan that defines the key activities required to develop and advance this opportunity, under which the first production of Liquefied Natural Gas could occur between 2032 and 2035, subject to concept selection and investment decisions.
Located 150 kilometers from Timor-Leste and 450 kilometers from Darwin, the Greater Sunrise project has been mired in an impasse, with Dili defending the construction of a gas pipeline to the south of the country and Woodside, the consortium's second largest partner, leaning towards a connection to the existing unit in Darwin.
The consortium is made up of the Timorese company Timor Gap (56.56%), the operator Woodside Energy (33.44%) and Osaca Gás (10%).
The impasse led the joint venture to request a conceptual study prepared by the British company Wood, which confirmed the feasibility of developing Greater Sunrise in Timor-Leste. “The Timor-Leste Liquefied Natural Gas (TLNG) option stands out for providing lower operating costs and, by allowing better general direct and indirect returns for Timor-Leste, will create a great socioeconomic impact in the country”, says the Timorese Government.
The permanent maritime boundary agreement between Timor-Leste and Australia states that Greater Sunrise, a shared resource, will have to be shared, with 70% of revenues going to Timor-Leste in the case of a gas pipeline to the country, or 80% if processing is in Darwin. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 23:52:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Indonesian capital bans sale of dogs and cats for human consumption</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/25/capital-indonesia-proibe-venda-de-caes-e-gatos-para-consumo-humano/</link><description>Authorities in the Indonesian capital, Jakarta, yesterday banned the slaughter and sale of dog, cat and other animal meat for human consumption because they transmit rabies, although this consumption is a minority in that country. “We hope that this will contribute to the maintenance and improvement of the [public] health of the inhabitants of Jakarta,” said the city governor, Pramono Anung Wibowo, after signing the new legislation, which also illegalizes the trade for that purpose in bats, monkeys and civets (similar to ferrets).
In that Southeast Asian archipelago with around 17,500 islands – the largest Muslim country in the world, practically in terms of population – it is considered unclean to eat pork and dog meat, but the meat of these latter companion animals to the West is consumed in non-Muslim areas of Indonesia. This is the case of Celebes - between Borneo and the Moluccas -, whose Tomohon market is known for the sale of exotic animals for human food, but banned the slaughter and trade in dog meat in July 2023. “This measure by the Government of Jakarta sets an important precedent and should serve as an example for other regional leaders”, reads a statement from the confederation of animal rights organizations Dog Meat Free in its account on the social network "Cat meat is much less common, with a consumption rate of around 1%. However, thousands of cats are sold every year, especially in markets in northern Celebes," according to the website of the non-governmental organization Humane Society International.
In January 2024, the South Korean parliament decided to outlaw the breeding and sale of dogs for human consumption from 2027 onwards, a common practice in other Asian countries, such as China, India, Vietnam, the Philippines and Cambodia, for example.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 23:55:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Health Services consider banning smoking in more areas near schools and daycare centers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/25/servicos-de-saude-ponderam-proibir-de-fumar-em-mais-zonas-junto-a-escolas-e-creches/</link><description>Macau may have more non-smoking areas in the future, especially at the entrances to schools and daycare centers. The Health Services will assess the situation of four pilot smoking ban points near non-higher education establishments to expand smoking control.

Four areas next to three schools and a daycare center in Macau have become pilot smoking ban points since Monday. The Health Services say they will evaluate the effectiveness of the initiative so that the measure can be progressively extended to other local schools and daycare centers, with the aim of “better protecting the health of minors” and promoting a healthy, smoke-free living environment.
The new non-smoking areas are located at the entrance of three schools and a daycare center, including the Luso-Chinese School of Taipa, the Technical-Vocational Secondary School of the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau, the Estrela do Mar School (Primary Section) and the Helen Liang Diocese Nursery – Diocesan Center for the Helen Liang Family. In other words, smoking is now prohibited in areas within 10 meters on each side of the entrance to these educational institutions.
The authorities indicate that the selection of locations was a joint decision by the Health Services and the Institute for Municipal Affairs, with both sides of this entrance being delimited by a white line on the floor, with no-smoking signs, which can delimit the no-smoking areas. The signs are also displayed in visible places at the entrance to schools and daycare centers, to alert people who enter this area where smoking is prohibited.
This delimitation coincides with the current no-smoking areas indicated at bus stops, where illegal smokers can be punished with a fine of 1,500 patacas.
In a statement published on the first day of implementation of the new measure, the Health Services reveal that the Office for the Prevention and Control of Smoking and Alcoholism sent employees to carry out inspections and raise awareness about tobacco control in these four pilot locations, particularly during morning and afternoon school hours.
According to the organization, until 5pm last Monday, no violations of the Smoking Prevention and Control Regime were detected in the aforementioned areas.
The Health Services add that if the public has any queries or complaints about smoking bans, they can contact the Office for the Prevention and Control of Smoking and Alcoholism via hotline no. 28556789 or send an email to *protected email*.
On the same note, the organization once again appeals to smokers that “they must immediately refrain from smoking” to protect their health and that of their family members. Please note that smokers who wish to stop smoking can make an appointment for a “smoking cessation assessment consultation” on the Conta Única application or by calling 2848 1238.
Furthermore, the authorities reiterate that they have been implementing tobacco control policies, such as legislation, law enforcement, educational outreach and encouraging smoking cessation, with the rate of tobacco consumption in Macau having decreased, say the Health Services.
Data from the Health Services indicate that the rate of consumption of tobacco and related products among the population aged 15 years and over decreased to 11.6% in 2023, while the rate was 16.9% before the Smoking Prevention and Control Regime came into force, which represents a drop of 31.4% and “achieved in advance the objective of reducing by 30% by 2025, promoted by the World Health Organization”, he points out. the organism.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 23:56:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong wants to ban two exile organizations it accuses of separatism</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/25/hong-kong-quer-banir-duas-organizacoes-de-exilados-que-acusa-de-separatismo/</link><description>Hong Kong Security Secretary Chris Tang Ping-keung said yesterday that he wants to ban two organizations created abroad by exiles from the semi-autonomous Chinese region, which he accused of separatism.
On Monday, the territory's government announced that it was considering banning the organization Hong Kong Parliament (Hong Kong Parliament), created in Canada, and the Hong Kong Democratic Independence Union (HKDIU), established in Taiwan.
In a statement, the Hong Kong executive said it had sent written notices to the two organizations, allowing them to present allegations before a possible ban.
Yesterday, at a press conference, Chris Tang confirmed that the two groups have a week to respond to the allegations, but hinted that the decision has already been made. “I analyzed the relevant evidence and believe that the ban is a necessary measure to safeguard national security”, highlighted the leader. "The objective of these two organizations is to divide the country and subvert the power of the State. They promote the so-called autonomy, that is, the independence of Hong Kong, and what they describe as the constitution of Hong Kong", said the secretary. “In fact, this undermines the basic system of our national Constitution and also harms the power of Hong Kong and our country,” assured Tang, quoted by the local press.
The leader advised Hong Kong residents not to participate in the activities of the two organizations and recalled that, according to the national security law approved in March 2024, they risk a prison sentence of up to 14 years.
Tang recalled that the city's courts have already issued arrest warrants for 19 members of the Hong Kong Parliament organization and that a collaborator of the group was sentenced to 12 months in prison.
On November 13, a court found 19-year-old Lan Fei guilty of the crime of sedition for appearing in two videos, published in April and May, that promoted the election for the Hong Kong Parliament organization.
Four members of the Democratic Union for the Independence of Hong Kong have already been detained – including a 16-year-old – and are awaiting trial, while another member is wanted for calling for a boycott of the elections for the local parliament on December 7.
In 2018, the Hong Kong government banned the Hong Kong National Party, a pro-independence movement, in an unprecedented decision since the transfer of sovereignty from the former British colony in 1997. John Lee, the then Secretary for Security and current leader of the Government, justified the ban at the time with the protection of national security, public safety, public order and the freedom and rights of citizens.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 23:52:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Mocha Hotel Royal closes its doors on December 28th</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/25/mocha-hotel-royal-fecha-portas-a-28-de-dezembro/</link><description>After Kuong Fat and Grand Dragon, Mocha Hotel Royal becomes the last of the three Melco-operated Mocha clubs to cease operations. The remaining three Mocha clubs, Golden Dragon, Porto Interior and Sintra, will continue to operate through the hiring of a management company.

The Mocha Hotel Royal will close permanently at 11:59 pm on December 28th, Melco Resorts announced yesterday. With the closure of Royal, three Mocha spaces remain in operation – Golden Dragon, Porto Interior and Sintra – which will continue to be operated by Melco through the hiring of a management company.
Remember that, in June, the operator had already announced that three of the six Mocha clubs it operates – Kuong Fat, Grand Dragon and Royal – would cease operations by the end of the year. Kuong Fat was the first to close its doors, on September 24th, followed by Grand Dragon two months later – that is, this Monday.
In a statement released yesterday, Melco Resorts informs that all electronic gaming machines will be relocated to other casinos in the group. “Customer rights will also be safeguarded after the closure of operations”, guarantees the concessionaire, and Mocha Hotel Royal customers can continue to use their gaming tickets in spaces such as the Altira Casino, the Mocha Inner Harbor, the Mocha Golden Dragon and the Mocha Sintra Hotel.
As for the 64 employees who currently work in the space, Melco reveals that it is planning “a smooth transition” to other casinos and gaming areas of the group, where they will continue to perform similar functions. The press release highlights the operator's concern for “the protection of local employment”, in addition to contributing to the “sustainable and healthy development of the gaming industry in Macau”.
In a statement also released yesterday, the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ) informs that it will appoint employees to “strictly supervise the closure procedures” and ensure that the process takes place in accordance with the proposal defined by Melco and presented to the Government.
It also adds that it will “maintain initial communication” with the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), in order to ensure compliance with the relocation of more than six dozen workers and guarantees regarding remuneration, benefits and working conditions.
“The DICJ will continue to ensure the coordination established with the concessionaires operating games of chance and the competent services, jointly promoting the healthy and orderly development of the gaming sector in Macau”, it reads.
 
MOCHA HOTEL GRAND DRAGON CLOSED YESTERDAY “IN AN ORDERLY WAY”

In the same statement, the DICJ reveals that it supervised the closure of the Mocha Hotel Grand Dragon, which it says took place “in an orderly manner” and “in accordance with the established procedures”. After ceasing operations at 11:59 pm on Monday, the organization suspended the operation of gaming machines and monitored, throughout yesterday morning, the process of removal from the respective premises.
Coordinating this process required “close interdepartmental collaboration” with various services, such as the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) and the Judiciary Police (PJ), which were responsible for “preserving public order in the location and its surroundings”. DSAL also sent staff to the site to provide clarifications to the 64 affected workers and provide information “on an open line for further consultation”.
In June, SJM, Melco and Galaxy announced that they would stop operating the satellite casinos and gaming machine rooms that had been operating until then. The gaming operators' decisions are based on the review of the gaming law, carried out in 2022, which stipulated the end of 2025 as the deadline for the cessation of satellite casino activity. If the concessionaires intended to continue exploring these spaces, this exploration could only be done through the hiring of a management company.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 23:56:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Guided tour reveals stories of neighborhoods on the occasion of 20 Years of World Heritage</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/25/visita-guiada-revela-historias-dos-bairros-por-ocasiao-dos-20-anos-do-patrimonio-mundial/</link><description>As part of the celebrations of the twentieth anniversary of the inscription of the Historic Center of Macau on the World Heritage List, the International Institute of Macau (IIM) is promoting a guided community tour on December 6th that invites participants to discover the city's multicultural roots. The initiative, which has the support of the Macau Foundation and the partnership of the Association of Macau Heritage Ambassadors (MHAA), aims to make the public, particularly younger people, aware of the experiences and stories of the neighborhoods that shaped the cultural identity of the territory.
The route, entitled “Macaense Neighborhoods: Roots of a Multicultural City”, will begin in the iconic Largo do Lilau, continuing along Rua Central, Largo de Santo Agostinho and Rua da Felicidade, before ending at the Dimensões M activity center, where a gathering with drinks is planned for all participants. Along the route, MHAA Heritage Ambassadors will provide detailed explanations about the historical and cultural importance of each location, revealing the marks left by the different communities that have inhabited these spaces over the centuries.
The visit will take place in two sessions, one at 2:30 pm and the other at 4:30 pm, with a limit of 25 participants per session, totaling 50 places available. Registration is now open through the IIM and MHAA social networks, requiring online registration by filling out a digital form accessible through the event's promotional poster.
In addition to the educational and cultural component, the IIM will distribute publications of its own authorship related to the theme of Macau's historic neighborhoods during the visit, simultaneously seeking to promote the habit of reading among participants. This initiative represents one of several projects that IMM intends to develop in the future, with the aim of awakening young people's interest in learning about Macau's cultural identity and preserving the city's historical heritage.</description><pubDate /></item></channel></rss>