<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/nao-se-deve-meter-china-e-russia-no-mesmo-saco-quando-se-fala-de-africa-diz-gomes-cravinho/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Feng Shui: How much is a number worth in Chinese culture?</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/feng-shui-quanto-vale-um-numero-na-cultura-chinesa/</link><description>In Chinese culture, numbers have a meaning that exceeds their quantitative value; They carry meanings based on their phonetics, having direct impact and influencing areas from the real estate market, vehicle acquisition, choice of telephone numbers and even prices.
The phonetic similarity of number 8 with the word “prosperity” led to its association with wealth and good luck. On the other hand, number 4 is feared, for its phonetic resembles "death," as well as 14, interpreted as "guaranteed death." Aversion to number 4 is evident in the structures and project of buildings. Many buildings simply do not have 4th floor and, lease or buying apartment on this floor, when it exists, it can be substantially cheaper than on lower floors.
I remember my green years of Macao, when I drank daily litred from Chinese culture, enjoy in a sip of fascination and surprise the episode in which a great friend Macaense was presented by the father with a purchase enrollment, when the acquisition of his first car: XX -54-54. The dreaded 4 when combined with 5, suggests “does not die”, being 5 phonetically interpreted as negation.
Auspicious are also 2, 6 and 9: associated with harmony, fluidity and longevity. Combinations such as 12 (“positive”), 13 (“life”), 18, 28, 66 and 99 are highly coveted. Considered favorable in the face of Chinese culture, ascending sequences such as 1238 symbolize growth and success.
On the other hand, when we look at Western cultures, the approach is different; Prices often end in 9, a practice that strategically aims to make the consumer believe they are paying less.
In an increasingly globalized world, understanding these cultural nuances becomes a premise for companies that want to thrive in foreign markets. The ability to respect and integrate these differences can be the key to success, showing that numbers, more than mere quantities, are symbols loaded with meaning and value.

Francisca Beja
Interior design and architecture project manager</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:35:56+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Helena de Senna Fernandes estimates hotel occupation in the 95%</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/helena-de-senna-fernandes-estima-ocupacao-hoteleira-nos-95/</link><description>Helena de Senna Fernandes states that the hotel occupancy rate will stay up during the New Year Lunar and estimates that it will reach 95%. The director of tourism services also indicated that the rate in some days could reach 99%. No irregularities were detected about the increase in hotel prices, and Helena de Senna Fernandes ensures that the body has been supervising prices and also to combat illegal housing.
 
The director of tourism services revealed that the reserve rate of hotel in Macao has reached 90% last week and provides that the hotel occupancy rate remains high and may reach 95% or even more during the next few days of holidays.
Helena de Senna Fernandes, in statements to the newspaper or Mun, admitted that the prices of the hotel room for the Lunar New Year "are slightly higher" than those of last year's same year, but authorities remain optimistic about the performance of tourist activities during this time. According to Radio Macau in Chinese language, the official also made an estimate of the hotel occupation rate, considering that it will reach 99% on some days of the Lunar New Year.
It is recalled that the ruler had already revealed that Macau registered an average of more than 100,000 daily visitors arrives last week, and reiterated his expectation that the daily average visitors throughout the Lunar New Year could reach 185,000 .
On the sidelines of the Blessing Ceremony of the Lunar New Year's Celebration Parade that took place yesterday, Helena de Senna Fernandes stressed that so far, any irregular situation of increase in accommodation prices has not been recorded. He said he noticed significant hotel price fluctuations in certain travel reserves platforms, and the Tourism Services (STD) directed with the hotels concerned to follow the situation.
"It is part of a free market to change the prices of the hotel rooms, which will be adjusted according to supply and demand," said the director, ensuring that the body, however, has mechanisms for inspection. “STD requires Macao hotels to communicate bedroom prices and notify their increases in advance. We are always monitoring the relevant data. If there is any exaggerated increase, STD will follow the case and apply sanctions, ”he said. It also launched an appeal to the sector to pay attention to the situation.
STD detected last year a total of 186 suspicious fractions of illegal accommodation of accommodation, number close to what was recorded in 2019. Helena de Senna Fernandes said that illegal accommodation increased again and is probably due to reopening the tourist market after The pandemic, and the fractions are mainly in the vicinity of the casinos.
Helena de Senna Fernandes has appealed to the owners to pay attention to whether their apartments are being used for illegal accommodation, especially those who are casinos's fantasy, ensuring while authorities will reinforce the inspections in the future.
 
Macau received 273,000 tourists on the weekend
 
Last weekend, 273,407 visitors entered the territory, with a daily average of 136,000 arrivals during the two days of 25 and 26. According to the statistical data of the Police and Public Security body, the number of entries and exits in Macau border posts was 706,726 and 645,414, respectively, last Saturday and Sunday, totaling 1.35 million border passages. Until 5 pm yesterday, the number of tourists arrived 93,397 people.
 
Game Legalization in Thailand
 
Thailand stepped forward at the opening of casinos, and the Thai government approved a bill that provides for the legalization of the game, which will also be analyzed by Parliament. Asked about how Macau will deal with the situation, Helena de Senna Fernandes said she believed Macau is still attractive to different profile tourists. On the occasion of an event held on Sunday, Helena de Senna Fernandes argued that Macau will continue to develop the tourism and leisure industry and also make progress to diversify its development and the offer of services. The director said authorities have already started several tourist promotion work and this year plan to continue to explore the European market.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:32:07+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao exports to the European Union grew almost 43% by 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/exportacoes-de-macau-para-a-uniao-europeia-cresceram-quase-43-em-2024/</link><description>In 2024, the total amount of foreign trade in goods was 142.15 billion patacas, being 8.2% behind what was registered in the previous year, 154.78 billion patacas.
The data were released yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), which also indicated that, last year, the exported value of goods was 13.49 billion patacas, plus 1.1%compared to the year of 2023. Reexport (12.00 billion patacas) rose 1.8%, however, domestic export (1.49 billion patacas) decreased 4%. The imported value of goods was 128.67 billion patacas, minus 9%, in annual terms.
Thus, the 2024 trade balance deficit was 115.18 billion patacas, less 12.93 billion patacas, compared to 2023 (128.11 billion patacas).
Analyzing exports by countries or destination territories, exported goods for Hong Kong (9.6 billion patacas) and to the European Union (216 million patacas) by 2024 grew 0.7% and 42.9 , respectively, compared to 2023. However, the exported amounts of goods to the interior of China (748 million patacas), to the countries of the initiative “one track, a route” (667 million patacas) and the states United in America (302 million patacas) fell 23.3%, 13.7%and 31.1%, respectively.
As for the countries or territories of origin, the amounts imported from goods produced in the interior of China (39.47 billion of patacas), in the European Union (37.61 billion patacas) and in the countries of “one track, a route ”(29.52 billion patacas) by 2024 lowered 2.6%, 15.7%and 4.5%, respectively, compared to 2023. However, the imported value of goods produced in Japan (9.12 billion patacas) increased by 6.2%. Analyzing by countries or territories of origin, the amount imported from the interior of China (20.96 billion of patacas) grew 0.3%, in annual terms, while Raehk (100.60 billion patacas) descended 11.7%.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:36:04+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Coutinho denounces “alarming increase in the proliferation of cockroaches, flies and mice”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/coutinho-denuncia-aumento-alarmante-na-proliferacao-de-baratas-moscas-e-ratos/</link><description>After, at the beginning of the month, he circulated a video showing a rat in a supermarket, Coutinho now presents a written interpellation on the subject in which he asks the authorities asking measures. According to the deputy, several residents have reported an “alarming increase” of cockroaches, flies and rats.
 
Earlier this month, a video circulated on social networks that showed a rat eating fresh foods in a refrigerator of a local supermarket. After the Institute's inspection for municipal affairs (AMI), three supermarkets were forced to temporarily end their activity. Pereira Coutinho now asks, through a written interpellation sent to the government, measures for the elimination of rats and cockroaches.
The deputy says he annually receives in his office complaints from citizens regarding the "alarming increase in the proliferation of cockroaches, flies and rats." This situation "not only generates discomfort, but also represents a risk to public health, as these vectors can transmit diseases such as leptospirosis, dengue and zika, and cause various types of allergies." Thus, says the deputy, "it is essential that more effective and sustainable measures are adopted to combat this plague and protect the health of the population."
Coutinho points out that a year and a half after alerting the authorities through a first written interpellation, the problem continues, which raises “serious concerns about food safety and public health in the MSAR, which highlights the urgency of intervention in this situation , through continuous inspection and more robust preventive actions, which involve not only trap placement, but also awareness campaigns on the correct waste management and the maintenance of hygiene in commercial establishments, emphasizing the need for a stricter approach It is effective to ensure a safe and healthy environment for consumers, and the ineffectiveness of measures already implemented for the management and eradication of rodents in the MSAR ”.
The deputy then asks the government to take stock of the deractization actions since October 2023: “What effective measures to control the population of rodents and cockroaches were implemented during this period, especially in sanitation networks? What were the results of control actions, particularly as regards public sewage networks? ”.
On the other hand, Pereira Coutinho suggests conducting deratization campaigns with the community and local merchants and ends the interpellation asking the reasons for increasing rodents complaints in public spaces.
It is recalled that after the controversial Mouse video in the supermarket, AMI had already indicated that the number of traps for mice placed on the streets increased from 200 to 1,400, noting that technological means will be used to resolve infestations.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:31:53+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lusófona Group Evaluate Create Vocational Education in Angola and Cape Verde</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/grupo-lusofona-avalia-criar-ensino-profissional-em-angola-e-cabo-verde/</link><description>The Lusófona Group should soon create in Angola and Cape Verde Vocational Establishments, corresponding to the interest of the authorities of both countries, the founder, Teresa Damásio told Lusa.
 
Administrator of the Ensinus Group, which is part of the Lusófona Group, Teresa Damásio points out that those two countries need skilled labor for industry and services.
Angolan and Cape Verdean authorities have effectively demonstrated a lot of interest in this type of education. There is beginning to be a business fabric and even different industrial needs in the various regions ”of Angola and Cape Verde so“ obviously that vocational education begins to be very necessary ”, insofar as“ good vocational teaching is essential for good economy ”.
The creation of vocational training establishments in Angola and Cape Verde replicates what the Lusophone group already has in Mozambique and Guinea-Bissau.
Author of the book “The State of Things - Visions on Equality, Teaching and the State of the Country In general”, Teresa Damásio presents in his work his reflections on topics such as Management and Leadership, Politics, Education, Gender Equality and Cooperation with Africa.
With about 27,000 students currently attending different degrees of education, in higher education establishments in Portuguese-speaking countries, except for Sao Tome and Principe and Timor-Leste, the Lusophone group has already formed about 30 thousand being The “group that has the largest professional schools in Portugal,” he said.
Teresa Damásio recognizes that brain escape is a problem, namely in Cape Verde. “We work so that it doesn't happen, right? And therefore, we qualify people so that this does not happen. I would say that in Cape Verde this is a problem, in fact, completely mirrored in scientific studies and statistics, ”he says. "Cape Verde has a very serious problem, assumed by the Cape Verdean authorities, that the young people all leave Cape Verde to come to study out," he adds.
Teresa Damásio announces that the Mindelo City Council, the second city of the country, has already given land to the Lusophone group to build a university residency. "What we understand is that Cape Verde has the geopolitical, geostrategic situation, perfect for welcoming West African students," he says.
Unlike Cape Verde, in Guinea-Bissau the brain escape is not verified. “It's very curious. The paintings always want to return to Guinea, that is, that question of 'guineanity', ”says Teresa Damásio, referring to the concept of national identity, the sociocultural experience of the Guinean or the Creole language. “Therefore, that very strong feeling of belonging that the Guineans have, effectively feels. And that's why I understand, I and our group, understand that when you look at Guinea-Bissau, you have to realize that Guinea has been and should continue to be a partner of excellence within the CPLP [community of Portuguese -speaking countries] ”, he stresses.
Teresa Damásio considers that this is due to the geographical location of the country, filled in a crushed region. “Guinea is a country of Cedeao [Economic Community of the States of West Africa], it is a Uemoa country [monetary and economic union of West Africa]. That is, the Francophone pressure in Guinea-Bissau leads to the state, the authorities and all economic agents should have a huge concern to consolidate the ties ”with Portugal. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:35:56+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hamas admits to give gaza control after withdrawal from the troops of Israel</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/hamas-admite-ceder-controlo-de-gaza-apos-retirada-das-tropas-de-israel/</link><description>Hamas yesterday admitted to give control of the Gaza range once the removal of Israeli troops followed by the ceasefire agreement, which has been in force since 19 this month. The intention comes at a time when there are several appeals of Palestinian Authority (AP) to put the enclave under its administration. Mussa Abou Marzouk, a high Islamite group, told Al-Arabiya television that Hamas does not intend to maintain enclave control and said that "any Gaza administration should be based on a regional consensus." Abou Marzouk recalled that the group gave its support to the agreed commission with Fatah, which leads the government in the West Bank to create a joint committee to manage matters in the Gaza Strip. According to that Hamas leader, the Gaza Strip would be under the authority of a Palestinian government, headed by Mohamed Mustafa, who is also the Palestinian Minister of AP. Abou Marzouk stressed, however, that it is FATAH that “rejects” this committee and added that “Israel could not find an alternative to the management of the hamma track”, stressing that the Islamite group “is open to all proposals on the future of the Administration ”of the Enclave.
On the other hand, the Hamas leader reinforced the movement of the movement to the idea advanced by the president of the United States, Donald Trump, who said he will address Egypt and Jordan the possibility of both countries receive 1.5 million displaced from Gaza for "accommodation" in the medium or long term. “No Palestinian or Arabic will accept the idea of ​​travel,” at least as long as the enclave reconstruction lasts, a scenario that the two countries have already rejected, he recalled. "This idea of ​​travel is an ethnic cleaning of the population of Gaza," he said, alluding to the identical position of the Arab League, while stated that the group "is open to dialogue with the United States" and stressed that the cease agreement stressed -Fogo “would not have taken place” without the efforts of Trump's envoy. "The position of Hamas leadership is of opening to dialogue with all parties except Israel," said Abou Marzouk, who reiterated the group's support for the creation of a unified Palestinian state in the West Bank, Gaza and East Jerusalem, in line with the Solution of two states supported internationally. The Hamas leader also mentioned that the attacks of October 7, 2023, who killed about 1,200 people and allowed the kidnapping of 250, which led Israel to launch the offensive against Gaza, reached "some of the goals", although "" others have not been reached. ” "The goal of obtaining a Palestinian state was not achieved, nor the purpose of stopping colonates," he lamented, without specifying which ones were achieved and after recognizing that the Palestinians suffered "huge losses" due to the offensive.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:35:59+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Serpent Year: Year of Change and Opportunities</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/ano-da-serpente-ano-de-mudanca-e-de-oportunidades/</link><description>With the farewell to the dragon, the year of the serpent, the sixth animal of the Chinese horoscope, which symbolizes wisdom, prudence and flexibility. Feng Shui master Mickey Hung said to the end that the year of the serpent will bring change and transformation, which means the emergence of new opportunities as well as challenges in our lives. Be thoughtful in making decisions and finding your own way in the midst of change, they are the master's suggestions for the new lunar year. Mickey Hung predicts that economic recovery continues, but at a modest pace, and the sector of electronic trade and health care will have potential for hopeful development.
 
The year of the serpent is coming. According to the traditional interpretation of Feng Shui's study, is a year of the serpent auspicious?
In traditional Chinese culture, the year of the serpent is considered an average year, neither good nor bad. The serpent is one of the 12 signs of the Chinese zodiac. In Feng Shui's analysis, the serpent has the character of wisdom, prudence and flexibility. The year of the serpent means change and transformation, which implies that this year will emerge new opportunities and challenges in both personal life and luck of society in general.
For a year of the serpent to be auspicious or not, I say it has the potential to bring auspices. However, it may be accompanied by a certain risk. Serpent's characteristics make this year suitable for more thoughtful planning and action. Since the serpent is linked to wisdom, the year 2025 can lead people to provide more importance to internal growth and learning. For those who want to increase personal competence further, therefore comes a great time.
The year of the serpent, however, can bring challenges. For example, due to the characteristic of the serpent, people will become more cautious and defensive, which will cause tensions in interpersonal relationships. In terms of professional career, excessive caution may lead to miss some good opportunities. Therefore, this year, people are suggested to maintain flexibility when they make decisions and be braver in grasping opportunities.
In my opinion, this year will be a potential year, but the key to success lies in one's attitude and behavior. If they can take advantage of wisdom and occasions of change brought this year, positive results in professional career, academic studies and interpersonal relationships can be achieved.
 
Will this year of the serpent be very different from last year of the dragon?
The symbolism of the serpent and the dragon is very different in traditional Chinese culture, the dragon year represents the energy and symbolizes the peak of luck since the dragon is considered as a more powerful and most majestic animal. In contrast, the serpent belongs to the Yin concept (陰) in the theory of the five elements (五行) of Chinese philosophy, (which is contrary to Yang (陽) and represents the moon, night, autumn and winter, etc.), highlights -Inner scholarship, caution and change, making them both significantly different in terms of Feng Shui's divination and interpretation.
First, the dragon year is characterized by dynamism and vigor, and has emerged in 2024 a spirit in a hurry to recover delay. People were easier to achieve success last year, and they were confident in both their careers and their own lives. The dragon year emphasized the behaviors and positive actions, making it easier for people to stand out from the competition.
On the other hand, the year of the serpent tends to be more introspective and thoughtful. This year we need to pay more attention to our inner world and think about how to find our way in the midst of change. So this year may not be as full of energy as the dragon year, but it can lead to deeper learning and growth.
As for interpersonal relationships, the dragon year is usually an easier time to establish contacts, and people are generally more open and sociable, which helps to establish good relationships. The year of the serpent, on the other hand, can make interactions more cautiously interpersonal due to their prudence characteristics, which can lead to some misunderstandings or tensions. It is therefore extremely important to maintain good communication and understanding.
In this sense, it is believed that the main difference between the year of the serpent and the dragon year is the issue of motivation and flexibility. The dragon year emphasizes external performance and success, while the year of the serpent focuses more on inner wisdom and change. Each of these two years has its own unique characteristics of luck, we can adjust our behavior and strategy according to different characteristics of the year to adapt to changes in the environment.
 
What are the forecasts for Macau throughout this year?
 
Macao General Economy
In 2025, Macao's global economic situation is expected to recover gradually, but at a modest pace. Due to the impact of the epidemic in recent years, Macau's economy has faced significant challenges. Especially the economic model based on tourism and game industry, which had been particularly affected. However, with the relief of the epidemic and the gradual recovery of the tourism industry, Macao's economy is expected to be between a new growth period.
According to the study by Feng Shui, the height of the terrain and the flow of “Qi” (“氣”, cosmic and vital force) have an important impact on economic development. Macao's favorable geographical location, in the heart of the Rio das Pérolas Delta and in the area of ​​the large bay, makes it an important place to attract foreign capitals and business investments. With the support of government policies and the improvement of infrastructure, Macao's economic development will be more stable.
In addition, the government intends to reduce its dependence on the game industry by promoting diverse sectors, which will help improve the resilience of the general economy. Next year, local economic performance will have constant progress and provide residents of more employment opportunities and the ability to improve their lives.
 
Tourism sector and game industry
Tourism and the game are the pillars of Macao's economy and it is expected to record new growth as the global travel market recovers. In the interpretation of Feng Shui, the flow of water symbolizes the entry of wealth, and the tourism industry is a direct manifestation of this “IQ”.
In 2025, Macau will host a series of international events and exhibitions and attract more tourists from the continent and abroad. This will not only increase the vitality of the tourism sector, but will also further boost the growth of related sectors, such as restoration, retail and entertainment. The game industry is expected to recover gradually and can reach a new peak.
However, in the face of growing competition, the Macao game industry needs to innovate and become adapting to changes in the market. This may include the introduction of new game methods, improving customer service experience and developing emerging areas such as online game.
 
Culture industry
The cultural industry will also become an important component of Macao's economic development next year. Macao is rich in historical and cultural resources, which not only attract tourists, but also promote a sense of cultural identity among local residents. In Feng Shui, the prosperity of culture is closely related to the harmony of society, which will give an intrinsic impetus to the economic growth of Macao.
In 2025, Macau could increase investment in the cultural industry, promoting the development of local arts, traditional handicrafts and cultural and creative products, while Feng Shui trips and cultural travels will become the new culture of Macao. This will not only promote employment, but will also improve cultural literacy and quality of life in general.
 
What industries will be most blessed?
This year, with the recovery of the economy, online platforms and food delivery will look good. Secondly, traditional Chinese medicine, beauty, cellular genetic therapy, tourism and the restoration industry will open new opportunities. With the increase of tourists, the demand for the retailer and service sector will increase. In fact, the technology and digitization sector will also have a strong growth potential.
The health and well-being sector, on the other hand, will continue to grow in popularity. As people's sensitization increases, the search for related products and services will rise. This provides good market opportunities for investors and entrepreneurs.
In short, 2025 will be a year full of hope and potential for Macao. With the recovery and development of various industries, living standards and residents' economic conditions will also improve.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:35:55+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>1.77 billion hours of internet in 2024, 4% more than 2023</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/utilizadas-177-mil-milhoes-de-horas-de-internet-em-2024-mais-4-do-que-em-2023/</link><description>At the end of 2024 there were 774,678 subscribers registered with internet services, plus 7.4%, compared to the end of 2023. Last year, 1.77 billion hours of these services were used, plus 4%, in annual terms. In December 2024 alone, 146 million hours of internet services were used, plus 3.1%, in relation to the identical month of 2023.
The data were released yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) in the Annual Bulletin on Transport and Communications, which also shows that, at the end of last year, there were 81,696 telephone users of the fixed network, less 6.7%, compared to the end of 2023. The number of mobile phone users was 1,448,713, corresponding to a homologous increase of 5.4%.
Under transportation, DSEC accounted for 12,900 vehicles with new enrollment (4,045 were electric), plus 7.7%, compared to 2023. In 2024, the automobile movement in border posts totaled 9,194,986 plus 25.8%, in annual terms. The light passenger car movement at border stations equivalent to 8,597,552 (26%, compared to 2023), of which 1.58 million inputs and exits were from Macao's single enrollment that circulated between Macao and Hengqin and Hengqin and 1,488 million inputs and exits were from cars under the “circulation of Macao vehicles in Guangdong province”, registering homologous additions of 20% and 33.6%, respectively.
In the year 2024 the passenger vessel movement totaled 79,599, plus 17.5%, in relation to 2023. On the other hand, 56,595 commercial flights at Macao International Airport, plus 44.4%, in annual terms were performed.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:35:52+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sébastien Ogier King and Lord of Monte-Carlo</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/sebastien-ogier-rei-e-senhor-de-monte-carlo/</link><description>Gaul pilot added the tenth triumph in the iconic rally of the French Alps and dedicated victory to the late uncle. Toyota was blameless in the inaugural race of the WRC. World Champion Thierry Neuville had unlucky proof.
 
Sébastien Ogier expanded last weekend the legend in Monte-Carlo and scored another record in the motorized sports history books. Toyota's French pilot won the race for the tenth time after mastering the event practically from beginning to end.
Navigated by compatriot Vincent Landais, Ogier, the wheel of a Toyota Gr Yaris Rally1 secured the victory with a margin of 18.5 seconds for teammate Elfyn Evans.
“I think I had a lucky star accompanying me this weekend. It must have been my uncle, who passed away a year ago. I'm sure it gave me everything. This is for him. I don't know if it was my last (Monte-Carlo). But it's a good time to stop, ”he revealed, thrilled, at the end of the race. Sébastien Ogier referred to the deceased uncle last year, just before Monte-Carlo's rality. A family member who helped him discover his passion for rally.
The triumph on the winding roads of the French Alps is historical because it becomes the event where it added the largest number of victories. There are nine in the rally of Germany and Catalonia.
The Gaul, eight-time world champion, entered the right foot in the World Cup, added 33 points-including the 5 Wolf Power Stage-although the plan remains a season in 'part-time', with the participation in about half of the events of the time. The strategy was the same last year, but after fighting a ninth world title, Ogier took the effort to the end. Errors in the last stages have set the goal for land. The future will say it this time.
The last test day on Sunday was a real show. The rain that fell at night added a surprise factor. The low temperatures have turned part of the asphalt roads into ice traps. Let Takamoto Katsuta (Toyota) and Sami Pajari (Toyota) go off road in 17 and had to leave. The same happened with Greegoire Munster (Ford) on the next section.
In the decisive phase of the rally, Sébastien Ogier had Elfyn Evans and Adrien Fourmaux to the leg. He won the first special of the day, but in the second lost 23.4 seconds to Adrien Fourmaux, Hyundai's new 'bonito'. Part of the difference was on the tires, there was a lottery in the choices that varied between the soft and those that had the peaks to the ice. Decisions were kept for Wolf Power Stage in the mythical Col de Turini, with Ogier overcoming Evans for just 0.3 seconds.
Elfyn Evans secured second place and double to Toyota. The Welsh, navigated by Scott Martin, added 26 points. It ended with an advantage of 7.5 seconds for the duo Adrien Fourmaux / Alexandre Coria (20 points), which debuted the steering wheel of the Hyundai i20 n rally1. A podium that demonstrates the potential of the one that is considered a new WRC talent, after last year, in view of the commands of a M-Sport Ford Puma.
Finnish Kalle Rovanperä (Toyota) ended fourth, having surpassed the Ott Tänak (Hyundai) stoned in the last classificative. More than both expected, because they are former champions of the world.
 
Thierry Neuville Azarado
 
Who had a very unlucky test was the current holder of the title, Thierry Neuville. The Belgian, next to co-pilot Martijn Wydaeghe, left the road early on the second day while leading the rally. He had a very poorly treated rear wheel and from there were several episodes that made him waste a lot of time. It only minimized the damage after recovering until sixth place in the overall classification, benefiting from the accidents of Takamoto Katsuta and Sami Pajari. I knew little by those who arrived in Monte-Carlo to defend the triumph reached last year.
Also noteworthy is the test of Joshua Mcerlean. The Irish pilot, who made his debut on Rally1 with a Ford Puma, showed progress in some specials, fulfilled the goal of getting intact to the goal and ended behind Thierry Neuville.
 
Yohan Rossel wins in WRC2
 
Yohan Rossel, behind the wheel of a Citroën C3 Rally2, gave no major hypothesis to the competition in the WRC2 category. The Frenchman led from beginning to end and ended with an advantage of more than two minutes for the Hyundai i20 of compatriot Eric Camilli. It was as much as a memorable event for the Rossel family with Yohan's brother Leo Rossel to finish in third place.
 
Macau company continues in the WRC
 
It should also be noted that the Hyundai n rally1 of the South Korean builder maintains a sponsorship connected to Macau.  A partnership with Ixo Modelcars, manufacturer of automotive miniatures, highlighting WRC models. According to the final point the contract remains for season 2025 with the Hyundai showing off the company logo on car rearview mirrors.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:36:09+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Health services warn of hypothermia risk</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/servicos-de-saude-alertam-para-risco-de-hipotermia/</link><description>The cold weather that has been registered in Macao should extend until tomorrow, with the minimum temperatures go down to 10 degrees Celsius. Health services warn of the risk of hypothermia.
Authorities appeal to residents, especially elderly and people with chronic diseases, to prevent themselves against hypothermia, paying particular attention to the use of appropriate clothing against cold, as well as appealing to individuals or institutions responsible for the care of the elderly and Patients with chronic diseases to apply adequate prevention and care measures to protect the health of these groups.
For the prevention of hypothermia, health services appeal to the elderly and those with chronic diseases and the professionals and institutions responsible for their care to adopt prevention and care measures.
The first advice is the use of proper clothing: “Wear enough clothes to protect yourself from the cold, and it is advisable to wear smooth, light, comfortable, permeable and hot fabric clothes; Do not wear too thick and tight clothing to prevent blood circulation from being prevented and the movement is affected. ”
It is also suggested to keep the house hot and with good ventilation and to drink and eat hot, highly digestible and highly digestible foods and drinks, such as milk, soup, soup, pasta and rice, for example. Authorities also advise that physical exercise is performed on body heat production, which and take medical prescription drugs at the right time and that citizens remain alert to weather changes.
Finally, health services advise to “give the elderly more affection”: “Family and friends should take care and help the elderly, encouraging and reminding them to take adequate measures to prevent themselves against hypothermia; Neighbors are asked to call and always visit the elderly isolated or with disease, in order to reduce the risk of accidents. ”</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:35:52+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Timor-Leste government pays part of the debt to hospitals abroad</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/governo-de-timor-leste-paga-parte-da-divida-a-hospitais-no-estrangeiro/</link><description>Timor-Leste vice-master-minister Mariano Assanami Sabino said yesterday that the Timorese government has already paid part of the debts to Malaysian, Indonesia and Singapore hospitals, which receive sick Timorese. "Earlier this year, we paid debts to hospitals from Singapore, Malaysia and Indonesia, in a total amount of over $ 12 million [11.4 million euros]," the vice-minister vice-president told Lusa.
Asked about the information that the Timorese government debt to hospitals in the three countries totals $ 30 million (28.6 million euros), Mariano Sabino clarified that, at this time, the debt does not exceed $ 20 million (19 , 1 million euros). “We have already paid almost half of the debts we had. Now we are waiting for the Ministry of Health to perform appropriate audits and correctly check the evidence and receipts so that we can continue to pay, ”he explained. Mariano Assanami spoke in Parliament, on the fringes of the discussion of the 2023 State General Account.
The vice-minister also assured that the government is studying mechanisms to improve the conditions of Lahane Hospital in Dili, in order to enable the treatment of patients with less serious cases in Timor-Leste. But, he stressed, serious cases will continue to be sent for treatment abroad. "We are looking at the future and we want to reduce costs, but we have to guarantee the necessary conditions to save lives and manage these cases well," he added.
Many Timorese citizens receive annually treatment abroad due to the inability of the country's health system to perform certain procedures and treatments.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:35:57+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macanese in the diaspora have a strong cultural identity, concludes a study by the US</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/os-macaenses-na-diaspora-tem-uma-identidade-cultural-forte-conclui-estudo-dos-eua/</link><description>To evaluate the cultural identity of the community in the diaspora, the project of Macanese and Portuguese Studies of the University of California analyzed the responses to an inquiry from 327 Macanese, spread throughout 10 countries and 200 cities.
 
 
Although in different parts of the world, the Macanese in the diaspora maintain family links, especially through the internet, and have a strong cultural identity. These are the main conclusions of a study by the University of California Macanese and Portuguese Studies project, which has evaluated, from June 30 to now, 327 people in 10 countries. The results will be published early next month, but the end point spoke before with the director of this department, Roy Xavier.
In order to determine how many descendants of Diaspora Macanese maintain their family connections and cultural identity, an inquiry with 11 questions to the diaspora was distributed, with the help of the Macaean Communities Council and the 13 Macao Houses around the world. “I also found many macanese through the internet, social networks and my personal correspondence,” adds Roy Xavier.
 
A strong identity using technology
 
The main conclusion that the researcher removes is that the “cultural identity of the Macanese community is very strong”, despite the 500 years of history and migration. After all, about 70 percent of respondents soon identified as "Macaense and Luso-Asian."
Secondly, he also concludes that they were quite aware of where their families came from history. “Many of the people who I perened look at their history through ancestors, history and often my work,” he says, adding: “They are very aware of where their families come from, from Portugal, Goa, Macao, Hong Kong, Shanghai or other sites. ”
Another interesting point of this study concerns the size of families, important to estimate the “dimension of the Luso-Asian population” in the world. "We realized that the average was 30 or 35 living members, immediate or extended family, while 20 percent have more than 100 living members, many around the world," he says. But how do you keep the contact? "We realize that they use social networks especially-they do it, above all, for fun, but also to maintain contact," he says, explaining that "this is particularly relevant to a diaspora, which is spread in different countries." This is how they can “maintain their cultural identity”, using technology to achieve “the conscience history” of their place of origin. “And often this is translated or communicated to your children,” he adds.
The main differences referred to the population type, whether it is active or if it is already renovated. "In this case, we had a participation of more than 50 percent reformed," he says, explaining that this is "understandable," as it is the group "with more interest in learning about history and giving the message to the next generation" .
As the population seems to be older, the use of the average seems more prominent. And if the first inquiry, carried out in 2012, was made mainly by email and distributed on paper, “now everything was done through the internet and social networks”, allowing more people to participate. The number of people who responded, although it doesn't look too big, "it's quite good."
About where they are, most seem to be concentrated in the United States, Australia, Brazil and Europe, while a lower percentage is in Asia. "We were surprised to realize that 10 percent of the community is still somehow in Southeast Asia," he says, adding: "Less are in Macao, but more in Hong Kong and around Southeast Asia."
Regarding the reasons that lead him to coordinate this study, Roy Xavier emphasizes that this is an effort to “investigate identity and how it can keep over the years”, but also, considering the last political developments in Macau and Hong Kong, the perception that exists in the two special administrative regions is particularly important. “Many people in the diaspora, especially the younger generation, those who are between 20 and 55 years old, work on technology -related sectors and I think it is one of the keys of their interest in China,” he says, explaining that the Asian giant, especially In the Great Bay, there is a great focus in this area. "Therefore, part of the study is to realize whether the cultural identity of the macanese can translate into a way to connect the West and the East," he concludes.
 
What was sought to evaluate
 
To the inquiry responded to Macanese (or Portuguese-symatic), defined in the study as “descendants of Portuguese mestizos from Asia with family connections in China, Southeast Asia and India, and specifically from Goa, Macau, Hong Kong, Shangoi, Canton, Japan, Malaysian , Singapore or Timor ”. His ancestors did not need to be from Macau, but there must be a cultural connection in his family with the Portuguese in Asia for the last 500 years.
The inquiry contains 11 questions in Portuguese and in English, prepared by the Portuguese and Macanese Studies Project of the University of California, and by the School of Public Health of the State University of Georgia, both in the United States.
The first eight questions sought to collect demographic information and determine cultural identities within the macanese (or Portuguese-Asian) communities around the world. The last questions intended to gauge the physical and mental conditions of all respondents.
Seeking to understand whether identity and memory, through the family, was maintained or, as Roy Xavier says, if they identified with cultural identity, sought to realize in what categories respondents fit-euro-seatic, luso-symatic, European, Chinese, Chinese , Americans. "We were trying to understand if they retained the cultural identity of Macao, as Luso-Asian, in general, and Macaenses, in particular, and we wanted to see where they fit and get an idea of ​​the size of the population," he says. In the inquiry, they asked them, on a scale, where they were, beyond the age group and gender. “We have been inquiry about the identity, where they are located, where families come from - Portugal, Goa, Macau, Shanghai, Hong Kong, to Southeast Asia, including Timor,” he adds.
This study, which had already been conducted three or four times previously, this time included two health questions. “One about health in general, because it is an active but also reformed population,” he says, adding that the other concerns mental health. “They feel anxious and gender things, how many days a month do not feel well,” he says.
 
The reasons for the study
 
In the introduction of the study's preliminary results, released in August on the MacStudies.net website, researcher Roy Xavier, also he explains the motives, personal and professional, who lead him to want to study this community. "To realize the roles that the Macanese (Luso-Asian) had in the development of Macau, Hong Kong, Shanghai and other regions of Southeast Asia, and their migration to other countries after World War II," he says. Another reason is “to document the stories of past and present community members, whose biographies and writings witness colonial development, the expansion of China's trade and the origins of the current global economy,” he says, adding one last item: “ Use the project of Portuguese and Macanese studies and social networks to involve anyone interested in perceiving, contributing and preserving the cultural history of the macanese of Portuguese origin. ”
It is the fourth time it conducts a gender study, Roy Xavier, says that "it has been refined over the years."</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:34:55+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>A Portuguese Odyssey in the "Sea of ​​People" in the lunar year of China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/uma-odisseia-de-portugueses-no-mar-de-gente-no-ano-lunar-da-china/</link><description>João Simões is concerned, on the eve of train traveling to the woman's homeland in Chenzhou, because he has not yet bought the tickets, and the traffic of hundreds of millions of Chinese in the new lunar year does not expect.
 
“This year I still haven't been able to buy tickets. Every year it is difficult. But usually a week before I have tickets. Perhaps there are more people traveling, ”the Portuguese risked in Macao.
From Tuesday and during a 'golden week', hundreds of millions of people will travel in the interior of China, in the largest annual migration in the world, to receive from family members the lunar year of the serpent, which this year is popping between 28 January and February 4th. In this odyssey, once again, three Portuguese, who described Lusa, as it is to travel at this time of year.
Since January 14, when Chunyun began, a period of 40 days before and after the beginning of the lunar year of the serpent, and until Friday, the Chinese state railway company China State Railway Group had sold more than 297 online Millions of tickets. "For me, Chinese New Year has always been synonymous with many people and starts just passing the border" to mainland China, says João Simões, a professor at the Institute for the investigation into Portuguese -speaking countries at the City of Macau University.
In the Semiautomanoma region, police decided to highlight more personal for border posts, facing the forecast of entrances and exits of almost 5.4 million people during the 'gold week', 3% more than in the same period of 2024. Sea of ​​people. That arrival at the Canton South Train Station. This is the first idea I have from the Chinese New Year, since the early years I started passing them in mainland China, ”says Simões.
According to the state press, nearly 20.2 million passengers are expected to go through Canton South, one of China's busy railway stations in the capital of Guangdong province, which borders Macao.
The station recruited 1,575 volunteers to help travelers during this period, including some who speak English and Cantonese, the official language of the two semi -autonomous regions, Macao and Hong Kong.
João Coimbra Sampayo, a Portuguese married six years ago with a Chinese, also says that “traveling in China alone is not easy”, but in the Chinese New Year, “is much more boring because of the queues”.
John describes them: “There are all the Phillets for [the control of] security. There is the line to go buy I don't know what, some cookies, for example. There is the line to enter the train… ”. Despite the scale of the human movement, “there is no confusion. Things seem to work, they are orderly. This is curious. How in a country with so many people things work so well, ”says the academic.
The Council of State, the Chinese executive, said this year expects nine billion internal travels during Chunyun, which will be a record for a country with a population of 1.4 billion. “I think China has this magic,” he says with a smile Charlotte Yuan Tian, ​​married 11 years ago with a Portuguese. “It sounds like chaotic, but then things work. Even on the streets, it seems very confusing, but then things are walking. ”
Charlotte plans to her homeland, Chengdu, the capital of Sichuan Province, in southwest China, but still has memories of train travel during the Lunar New Year at night to visit grandparents in a rural area. “The carriage was full, full, full, we couldn't even set foot, we had no place to sit, but I don't know how, my mother got a place and had to go to her lap, already big, nine years old ”Recalls the teacher, today based in Macau.
More than 30 years later, China has the fastest trains in the world, but certain things have not changed.
“The crowded trains of people, standing, bags and children everywhere. Those unfoldable stools. Children to eat instant pasta. This is one of the images I have from the Chinese New Year, ”says João Simões. Still, since in 2014, the teacher has been practically every year to spend this period to the woman's homeland. “It's not even anything else, it's like going to Christmas to Viseu,” he explains.
The Lunar New Year is usually compared to Christmas in Western countries, but João Coimbra Sampayo says the importance of the main party of Chinese families "is amplified to the fullest." “In Portugal it is very easy for a person to go home anytime of the year. In many cases, in China this is impossible. It is impossible for the family to gather, the man with his wife, children and parents, other than in the Chinese New Year, ”says Sampayo. “Therefore, they are very strong feelings. There are a lot of rice brandy, talk a lot ”, because many of those who travel“ were their land to work for cities and do not have the hukou of these cities. Therefore, they cannot take the family, ”he adds.
Hukou is the Chinese residence system that, in practice, prevents migrant workers from rural areas from having access to health and their children from attending schools in large cities.
Return to homeland is also taken advantage of to offer the so -called 'Hong Bao' ('Lai Si' in Cantonese, used in Macau and Hong Kong), red cash envelopes, which are usually given by older to the younger ones. But in rural areas, it is sometimes the children who work in the cities that give Hong Bao to their parents, says Charlotte Yuan.
The rapid aging of China's population has placed greater pressure on the already fragile social security system, with a growing number of Chinese to refuse to pay for the pension system, which has long been sub-financed. “If parents don't have a large renovation, they depend a little on this money that their children will send,” explains Charlotte.
This is the case of John Simões's in -laws: "They are in their 70s, they have no reform, they have nothing." "At the time of the Chinese New Year, children take the opportunity to deliver a larger amount of money, which is to give them to live for a while," adds the teacher. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:33:54+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump's Americanism and its implications for US-China relations</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/o-americanismo-de-trump-e-as-suas-implicacoes-para-as-relacoes-eua-china/</link><description>The inauguration speech of US President Donald Trump not only emphasized America's sovereignty and national security interests as the main concern of his administration, but also pointed out the US determination to recover the so -called Chinese "control" From the Panama Canal - Signs that point to the ideology of Americanism that will most likely be shocked by the ideology of China anti -Americanism in the coming months and years.
Trump's Americanism can be seen as a mark of his position on foreign policy, which includes perception of the so -called Tik Tok's so -called "national security" for Americans, the need to use tariffs for Chinese products to resolve Commercial imbalance between the US and China, criticism of Panama regarding the Panama Canal, the statement that increasing economic sanctions would exert pressure on Russia in the impasse of the Ukrainian war, and a contradictory duality of praising the president Chinese Xi Jinping as a good friend of Trump, on the one hand, but considering the Popular Republic of China (RPC) as a threat to national security in economic and military terms for the US.
On the night of January 17, Chinese President Xi Jinping received a telephone call from President -elect Donald Trump. Xi began to congratulate Trump for his reelection as president of the US and said that both attributed enormous importance to Sino-American interactions, expecting a good beginning of Sino-American relations. President XI added that he would like to ensure greater progress in Sino-American relations from a new starting point, as both countries are committed to providing a better life to their peoples. Given the common interests and the historical cooperation of the two countries, Xi expects the two parties to continue to contribute to mutual success and prosperity.
President XI also stressed that China and the US must respect each other's fundamental interests and concerns and seek appropriate solutions. He added that Taiwan's issue concerns the sovereignty and territorial integrity of China. As such, according to XI, the American part should address the issue with prudence. Although bilateral relations are mutually beneficial, President XI expects confrontation and conflict to be an alternative to both countries, which must follow the principles of mutual respect, peaceful coexistence, and advantageous cooperation for all.
Trump revealed to the media that he and President Xi discussed trade, Fentanil, Tik Tok and many other issues, such as the Ukraine crisis and the Israelo-Palestinian conflict. Trump also stressed that he and Xi would do "anything possible to make the world more peaceful and safer."
When Trump was a candidate for presidential elections, he said he would impose 60% rates on all goods from China, but later softened by saying that once elected president, an additional 10% rate would be applied to Chinese goods until China stopped sending illegal drugs to the US.
Trump's lieutenants are the most aggressive politicians compared to China, including Secretary of State Marco Rubio and Secretary of Defense Pete Hegseth. While Rubio was constantly a critic of China before becoming secretary of state, Pete Hegseth warned that China would militarily represent a serious threat to the US and that China would reach "global domain."
An attenuating factor that could relieve tense relationships between the US and China is the role of Elon Musk, the founder of the Tesla electric vehicle giant, which produces at least half of his cars in mainland China. Musk was invited to meet Chinese employees and has been considered a friend of China. The weight of Mush compared to other hawks in China, such as Rubio and Hegseth, will continue to be observed.
As a former businessman, Trump's approach to external relations adopts a strictly American ideology, combined with economic pragmatism. During the presidential election campaign, Trump stated that autonomous democracies, such as Taiwan and South Korea, should pay more to the US for military protection and that Taiwan “stole” the American semiconductor business. His comments raised the eyebrows of some politicians in Taiwan and South Korea.
On January 22, two days after Trump's inauguration, President XI and his Russian counterpart Vladimir Putin had a VideoChamada during which Putin referred to Xi as a "dear friend." Both parties promised to build their relationships based on friendship, mutual trust and support. President XI appealed to Putin to deepen strategic coordination, consolidate mutual support and safeguard the legitimate interests of both countries. President XI told Putin that 2025 marks the 80th anniversary of the victory of the Chinese people's resistance war against the Japanese invasion, the Great Patriotic War of the Soviet Union and the World Antifascist War. He added that both countries must defend and continue multilateralism, working together to advance BRICS cooperation and reinforce the global south.
Interestingly, Putin has diplomatically observed that Russia and China often rely on each other and that Russia firmly supports Taiwan as an inalienable part of China's territory and which opposes Taiwan's “independence” in any form.
Clearly, while President XI seemed to tell Putin that China appreciates Russia as a strategic partner after he and Trump had a call, Putin stressed that Russia supports one China's policy and Russian President seemed to indirectly criticize the US for adopting a problematic policy regarding Taiwan.
On January 24, Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi spoke to the new US Secretary of State Marco Rubio. Wang hoped that Rubio play a constructive role in the development of US-China relationships. However, Rubio told Wang that Trump administration would seek to establish a relationship with China to "promote US interests and place the American people first." In addition, Rubio expressed the US commitment to his allies in the Asia Pacific region and serious concerns about China's "coercive actions against Taiwan and the Southern Sea of ​​China." During the confirmation of his Senate appointment, Rubio referred to China as the “most serious threat” that the US faces. Your comments Wang Yi can also be seen as a reiteration of the US political position in relation to China.
Wang Yi said that both China and the US should implement their common understandings, maintain communication, manage differences, and expand cooperation - a topic that echoes President XI said to Trump on the phone. Wang also reiterated Xi's position on Taiwan, namely the US should manage Taiwan with prudence, as Taiwan has been part of China's territory since ancient times. Wang added that China will never allow Taiwan to separate from China. In addition, the United States committed themselves to the policy of one China, so they should not deny this political position.
In response, Rubio said the US does not support Taiwan's “independence” and hopes that Taiwan's issue can be peacefully resolved in an acceptable way on both sides of Taiwan's Strait.
Judging by interactions between Trump and Xi, Xi and Putin, and Wang and Rubio, the first American policy adopted by the new Trump administration is designed to find Chinese resistance and opposition. It is likely that the development of relationships between the US and China is unstable, floating and full of uncertainty.
Firstly, while Trump sees his policy on Tik Tok as a potential bargaining china, Chinese leadership is relatively silent and tends to see it as a private sector company with which the Chinese government distances your relationships. As such, it is another American perception and perhaps biased from the backstage support of Chinese authorities to Tik Tok. If Trump and his tentn places understand that Washington has his influence on Tik Tok as a bargaining china, they may have already misunderstood the Chinese official perspective.
Secondly, Trump's statement that Panama's channel has already been controlled by China found immediate criticism in the media, which point to the fact that the channel's operation by a Hong Kong company does not necessarily mean control of the Chinese government. Trump's rhetorical, perception and anti-china prejudice can and will generate deeper misunderstandings and distrust with Chinese leadership.
Thirdly, although Trump claims that he and President Xi are good friends, the fact that Xi had a call with Putin shortly after the discussion of the Chinese president with the US president -elect means that China was and is interested in avoiding avoiding a position that is seen as too close to the US. China is interested in designing an image of balance between the interests of Russia and those of the US. As such, if Trump wants to guarantee Chinese support to “remove” so -called logistical supplies to Russian military equipment in the Ukraine War, this policy is intended to go out by Culatra. First, China denied the supply of logistical material to the Russian military in the Ukraine War. More importantly, the export of civil goods that can be used in military weapons belongs to a gray area where it is quite difficult to check, the more an appeal for China to apply economic sanctions to Russia. After all, economic sanctions have limited functions and impacts on US international policy compared to Russia.
Fourthly, Trump using tariffs as a bargaining china has its limitations in the relationship with China. Although tariffs seem to be an effective weapon to force China to accept more imports from the United States, the RPC can delay these imports. Most importantly, if customs rights are widely applied to Chinese products, they will be the American consumers themselves to suffer from the need to pay the products at a much higher price. The use of customs rights to force China to buy more American products also means that customs rights cannot easily be used as a bargaining chip in other non -economic issues.
Fifth, Trump's Americanism is transforming the US into self -protectionism and isolatism, without globalism, and with an American soft power in continuous decline. US self -protectionism is evident in Trump's desire to withdraw from the Paris and the World Health Organization agreement. Unlike the US, whose Soft Power reached its peak shortly after World War II, when it led the allies in the defeat of the defeat Axis of evil and maintenance of world peace, Trump administration has been increasingly seen as US hegemony, American arrogance and American negligence in relation to the different cultures and values ​​of many other countries. Contrary to the late Jimmy Carter, whose foreign human rights policy has gained respect for many countries of the world, Trump's Americanism represents US parochialism without internationalism and without strong moral rhetoric and a principle of human rights defense.
However, the ideology of anti -Americanism is prominent in the foreign policies of China and Russia. In a new era of emerging new powers, such as the BRICS central countries, US soft power has been slowing down so quickly that its moral legitimacy and its global leadership have been seriously posed and questioned. In particular, Israelo-Palestinian conflicts dragged the US to a degree of unpopularity unprecedented in the eyes of many peoples of the world. As such, Americanism is now facing not only a strong opposition in the world, but also a crisis of legitimacy of US global leadership.
In sixth place, Taiwan remains a thorny problem in US-China relations. Both Xi and Wang warned the US from any reckless behavior. By implications, China has seen US policy about Taiwan to gradually or silently move away from one China's policy to a policy that implicitly or explicitly supports the "Taiwan independence." As such, the Chinese side will probably negotiate with the US the continuous supply of weapons to Washington Taipe. While the American side appeals to the Chinese side for a peaceful resolution about Taiwan's future, the core of the problem is that Washington has changed apparently and slightly his policy regarding Taiwan, in fact recognizing his regime, how to organize and tolerate that politicians And even current and retired employees visit Taiwan and meet with Taiwan leaders. Unless Washington adjusts its policy compared to Taiwan, China will probably continue to criticize the apparent change of US policy compared to Taiwan. Above all, the US does not have any constructive solution for China to deal with Taiwan and continue to insist on the same theme of appealing to both parties to a peaceful solution.
 
In seventh place, although Rubio criticized China for his “coercive” actions in relation to Taiwan and the Southern China Sea, US relations with China on the islands and reefs claimed by Beijing and Manila will be increasingly difficult . On the one hand, the Armed Forces and the Philippine Defense sector are nationalist in relation to the reefs that Manila considers to be under their sovereignty. On the other hand, China has argued that the sovereignty of these reefs belongs to Beijing. Currently, the maritime forces on both parties have shown a stalemate about controversial reefs - a phenomenon that remains fragile and vulnerable to sudden conflicts. A more aggressive American administration that lies with the Philippines regarding the controversial reefs of the southern China Sea will not be a good omen for peace in relations between the US and China. It is likely that both China and the Philippines see their relationships seriously put to the test in the coming months and years, unless the US control the nationalist feelings of all stakeholders.
In conclusion, relations between the US and China are intended to be tense and floating during the new Trump administration, whose Chinese hawks will likely antagonize China in their observations and approaches. Above all, Americanism is an ideology that conflicts with anti -Americanism. Americanism aims to penalize China for commercial imbalance in US and China relations, blaming China for the loss of US jobs, seeing Tik Tok as a "threat" to US national security and considering China as having "coercive acts ”In Taiwan and the Southern Sea of ​​China. All of these perceptions are by no means favorable to US-china relationships. In particular, Taiwan's issue will be increasingly controversial and difficult in US-China relations. It remains to know who are the Chinese experts who play a crucial role in the moderation of Chinese hawks and the transformation of US-china relationships into a more constructive, fruitful and friendly relationship, with advances in various thorny issues. Otherwise, relationships between the US and China will be tense and uncertain in the coming months and years.
 
SONNY LO
Author and Teacher of Political Science
This article was originally published in English at Macau Newsagency/MNA</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:35:55+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese IA application leads discharges on USA devices in the USA</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/aplicacao-chinesa-de-ia-lidera-descargas-em-dispositivos-apple-nos-eua/</link><description>The Chinese application of Generative Artificial Intelligence Models (IA) DeepSeek R-1 led the discharge table in the App Store, both in China and the United States, beating the popular chatgPT.
 
The Deepseek-R1 model, launched on January 20, is, according to the creator, comparable to OpenAi model O1, the ChatgPT creator, in solving mathematical problems, programming and natural language inference.
The model is a creation of Deepseek, the Chinese artificial intelligence modeling company supported by the quantitative investment company Huanfang Quant.
The open source tool has recently had a significant impact on the international program of programmers and the technological sector due to its efficiency and low cost.
According to the company, the model was trained over 55 days, with a budget of $ 5.57 million (5.33 million euros), using a set of 2,048 units of H800 graphic processors from the American semiconductor manufacturer Nvidia, a low capacity version designed for the Chinese market, given the restrictions imposed by the United States about high -tech exports to China.
This cost represents less than one tenth of OpenAi's 4th model formation expense, according to Chinese press.
According to DeepSek, the R1 used advanced automatic learning techniques in the post-workout phase, which significantly improved its ability to perform complex tasks with few previously classified data.
The company has made public the technical details of the training process, allowing other users to use them as the basis for the development of other tools.
Price comparisons are based on the tokens calculation, in which 1,000 chips are equivalent to approximately 750 English words. Deepseek offers application programming interface services (API) at a cost of 1 yuan per million chips and 16 yuan per million chips produced.
By comparison, OpenAi's O1 model is priced at $ 15 (about 14.4 euros) per million chips introduced and 60 dollars (about 57 euros) per million chips produced.
The launch of Deepseek-R1 took place the same week that US President Donald Trump announced the 'Stargate' project, which aims to invest up to $ 500 billion (478 billion euros) over the next four years to Build 20 new data centers to support AI projects. “Deepseek's technological approach challenges US dominion in AI, demonstrating that its restrictions on semiconductor sales to China have been ineffective,” said Li Baiyang, professor of artificial intelligence studies at Nanjing University, cited by the Chinese official newspaper Global Times.
Expert Tian Feng told the same communication body that the results of DeepSeek, with lower training costs, along with his open source approach, "will redefine AI development rules."
More than 200 major linguistic models were launched in the Chinese market, some developed by the country's technological giants, such as the “Doubao” by Bytedance (proposing Tiktok video platform), the “Jiutian” of the telecommunications operator China Mobile, “Wenxin” Baidu's Yiyan ”(holder of the most popular Chinese search engine), the“ Tongyi Qianwen ”by the Huawei Cloud“ Pangu ”e -commerce giant and Lanxin. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:36:00+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Agility of the serpent can benefit China in a year of recovery and disputes</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/agilidade-da-serpente-pode-beneficiar-china-em-ano-de-recuperacao-e-disputas/</link><description>The agility and wisdom symbolized by the serpent, the sign of the Chinese zodiac for the year -old, can benefit Beijing, pointed out a master of the millennial feng shui system, in a period of economic resum and geopolitical competition.
 
"The serpent represents, in Chinese culture, wisdom and agility," Wang Haohua noted to Lusa, while preparing a tea teapot under the aroma of incense in his studio, located in southern Beijing. "These are characteristics that can be useful to China in the times that have been prevented," he noted.
Wang, 52, began "since childhood" studying the feng shui, the millennial system from China. In addition to being an investigator, he is one of the most sought after astrologers by the Chinese state press.
According to the Chinese calendar, which is based on moon cycles, the New Year begins on January 29, under the sign of the serpent, one of the 12 animals in the Zodiac of China.
It is the main party of Chinese families, equivalent to Christmas in Western countries, and for many workers the breaks and holidays granted on this court constitute the only vacation of the year. But Wang has been busy predicting what will bring the new year in business, love or politics. “The next New Year Lunar stands out for coinciding with two starting spring. It's a very auspicious sign, ”he said, predicting“ positive winds ”to the Chinese economy, but warning the need to negotiate with caution.
The first early spring, called 'Lichun', on the Chinese lunar calendar, takes place on February 3, on the sixth day of the Lunar New Year, and the second occurs on February 4, 2026, more than a week before the end of the year of the serpent, on February 16.
In Chinese tradition, shaped by agricultural activity, spring represents a new beginning. With the arrival of the season, the time of daylight and temperatures begin to increase. In northern China, arid and monochrome landscapes quickly give way to exuberant green as spring gains traction. "As an old Chinese saying says:‘ Do your plan for all year in spring, as your day plan in the morning, "said Wang Haohua.
The second largest economy in the world has been shaken in recent years by a profound crisis in the real estate sector, which resulted in the bankruptcy of dozens of builders. The most emblematic case is that of the giant Evergrande, whose liabilities ascends to almost $ 330 billion (316 billion euros).
The contraction in the sector, which is the main investment vehicle of Chinese families, has affected consumer confidence, generating deflationary pressures. But Wang foresees a “gold year” for entrepreneurs, with an increase in internal demand and increases on profit margins.
The Chinese Communist Party launched a series of stimulus measures in the last quarter of last year, including the reduction of mandatory bank reserve ratios and interest rates. Beijing promised to pursue “more proactive” budgetary policies and a “moderate flexibility” of monetary policy, aiming at “boosting domestic consumption vigorously.
Donald Trump's rise to power in the United States can, however, disrupt Chinese plans. The Republican promised to tax the goods from China up to 60%, at a time when exports constitute the main economic growth engine of the Asian country. “Trump thinks like a businessman. He is making threats, but will have to negotiate with China. China will have to be agile and wise in negotiations, ”he said.
With roots in Taoist philosophy, feng shui (literally “wind and water” in Portuguese) seeks to attract positive energy through harmony with the elements of nature.
During the Cultural Revolution (1966-76), launched by the Founder of the Popular Republic of China, Mao Zedong, that practice was prohibited and its persecuted practitioners. Wang was then criticized at school for his 'superstition'. One of the greatest sages of ancient China, Confucius (551-478 BC), was then labeled a "decaying and reactionary thinker." Today, in the Master's studio, two small statues of Mao and Confucius are inplay side by side.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:35:59+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China considers it extremely unlikely that virus has leaked from laboratory</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/china-considera-extremamente-improvavel-que-virus-tem-vazado-de-laboratorio/</link><description>China said yesterday it was “extremely unlikely” that COVID-19 leaked from a Chinese laboratory following an accusation in this regard by the US espionage agency.
"The authorized scientific conclusion to which the China and World Health Organization (WHO) sets up, based on ground visits to relevant Wuhan laboratories, is that it is extremely unlikely to have an escape from the laboratory." said Mao Ning, spokesman for the Chinese Foreign Ministry. "This was widely recognized by the international community and the scientific community," said the spokesman at a press conference.
This weekend, the CIA considered that the “most likely” is that the virus escaped from a Chinese laboratory rather than being transmitted by animals.
This position arises following the confirmation on Thursday of John Ratcliffe as director of CIA, after the beginning of the second term of US President Donald Trump. "The CIA believes, with a low degree of confidence and based on all available reports, that an origin related to COVID-19 research work is more likely than a natural origin," a spokesman said on Saturday agency.
To date, the agency had not reached any conclusion about whether Covid-19 resulted from a laboratory accident or was transmitted by animals. "The United States must stop politicizing and explore this issue and stop defaming and blaming other countries," said Mao Ning.
US authorities should "respond as soon as possible to legitimate concerns of the international community" and "share the data on the first suspicious cases proactively," he added.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:35:58+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>"You shouldn't get China and Russia in the same bag" when talking about Africa, says Gomes Cravinho</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/01/28/nao-se-deve-meter-china-e-russia-no-mesmo-saco-quando-se-fala-de-africa-diz-gomes-cravinho/</link><description>The special representative of the European Union for Sahel, João Gomes Cravinho, said in an interview with Lusa that “one should not put China and Russia in the same bag” when talking about relations with Africa.
 
“While Russia is interested in creating a zone of instability in what it considers to be the southern flank of the European Union and, above all, the southern flank of NATO, because that is how Russia thinks, China is interested in the extraction of natural resources ”Said Gomes Cravinho, who since December 1 has been the special representative of the European Union for Sahel.
Gomes Cravinho gives as an example of Chinese interest in Africa the investment of $ 5 billion (about 4.7 billion euros) in a pipeline between Niger and Benim, the largest of the genre in Africa, with almost 2,000 kilometers of extension.
Beijing was “very concerned” because, following the coup d'état of July 26, 2023 in the Niger, the relations of this country with neighboring Benin deteriorated to the point that the common border was ended. “Well, China has strived with a long time and much energy in mediation to create conditions, finally, to improve the relationship between Benin and Niger, to be able to extract their oil, which had deserved the investment of 5 billion 5 billion [dollars]. What they got. They were successful, in a way, because they managed to convince the two parties to allow the pipeline to work, ”he said.
Relations between Niger and Benin “remain terrible, with their borders closed, except for the pipeline,” but, according to Gomes Cravinho, this is irrelevant to Beijing. “What they want is that the oil can be transported from the oil fields to the coast. If the borders are closed, if there is no passage of people or goods, it is already something that matters little. Therefore, their posture is a very opportunistic stance, very turned to what is their immediate interest, which is the extraction of resources, ”he said.
“With the Chinese, we know what we can expect, which is a great, finally, no scruples regarding the nature of the regime, because they had a great relationship with the previous Niger regime, and when the regime was overthrown with the regime Coup of state, they just tried to establish a great relationship with the new power. Therefore, they are agnostic, say, in matters of quality of governance, ”he reiterated.
In the case of Russia, and starting from the decision announced, on 29th of this month a year, by Mali, Niger and Burkina Faso to leave the economic community of the states of West Africa (CEDEAO), Gomes Cravinho interprets what follows as being the “Increased Russian influence”. "I think everyone is weakened by this exit and the countries themselves do not benefit either, although they are giving signs of some integration dynamics to compensate," he said.
For the former Portuguese Foreign Minister, “this represents an increase in Russian influence. The Russians entered Mali about four years ago (…) and Burkina Faso and Niger more recently. But in this period of time, it became clear that the Russians are not able to correspond to what is the great purpose of military regimes in Mali, Burkina Faso and Niger, which is the reconquest of the territory. “We see that in Mali, which is where the Russian presence is stronger, the Russians suffered very significant casualties and their military posture changed from a territory reconquesting attempt to a regime protection posture ”He added.
And therefore, there are partners within the region. I think it's bad for the region, and therefore, I think you reduce everyone's ability to play a role, also to the United Nations, which have an important office there for West Africa.
Regarding the performance of other international actors, Gomes Cravinho says that, in the last year, two years, “a much larger internationalization has been seen, due to a certain emptiness of power that exists in the region, with Turkey with a commercial posture , also related to the sale of military products, but also the Gulf countries: Saudi Arabia, but especially the United Arab Emirates and Qatar. ”
“And even Iran, looking for uranium, so far to no avail. As is well known, Niger is an uranium producer. And Iran has been committed to this, but with difficulties in establishing a convincing relationship, because due to financial sanctions can not pay and therefore is not an interesting customer for Niger or any country, ”he said.
As for the United States, the special representative of the European Union considers that they are "unknown." “Because we do not yet know what the attitude of the new administration will be. But I believe that the new administration look at the Sahel region as a problematic region in terms of proliferation of some terrorist movements and therefore that is the concern. And secondly, as a concern that will have to be managed by others, namely Europeans, ”he said. “I believe they will look at the region as a region that Europeans have to know how to work, because they themselves do not believe they work particularly. At least that was the attitude of the first Trump administration, ”he said. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-01-28T04:35:59+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>