<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/25/governo-esta-a-negociar-acordo-bilateral-de-transporte-aereo-com-a-arabia-saudita/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Government is negotiating bilateral air transport agreement with Saudi Arabia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/25/governo-esta-a-negociar-acordo-bilateral-de-transporte-aereo-com-a-arabia-saudita/</link><description>The civil aviation authority is negotiating with Saudi Arabia authorities the establishment of a bilateral agreement for air transport. Later this year formal meetings will be held that will aim to establish a legal framework for the opening of regular flights between the two parties.

The government, through the civil aviation authority, is currently negotiating with the Saudi Arabia authorities the conclusion of a bilateral air transport agreement. Later this year will be held formal meetings to establish, “brevity”, a legal framework to open regular flights between the two parties.
The information was shared by the civil aviation authority in response to a written interpellation presented by Deputy Lam Lon Wai, who asked for the use of air traffic rights and the expansion of the Macao air network to emerging markets.
Currently, Macao has established air agreements with 50 countries, including five of the main markets of the Middle East: United Arab Emirates, Oman, Türkiye, Israel and Qatar. The civil aviation authority explains that although there are no direct passenger flights between Macau and these destinations, air load operators, such as Turkish Airlines and Qatar Airways, have appealed to the Fifth Freedom Traffic Rights, that is, the right or privilege, in relation to regular international air services, attributed by one state to another state, to embark and disembark passengers and load from or intended for a third state.
Macao authorities also say that to attract more foreign airlines to settle in the territory, the Macao International Airport Society (CAM) “continues to launch incentive plans, actively negotiating with target airlines for the exploration of routes to Macau and supporting the existing airlines in increasing frequency and destinations for their flights”.
In response to Lam Lon Wai, it is also read that Cam has taken advantage of its Express Link service and the various existing direct flights that connect the main tourist cities of the Southeast and Northeast Asia, "in order to provide passengers with a convenient connection service."
Authorities point out that passengers can resort to local or foreign airlines operating in Macao, starting from Macau and scale in cities such as Beijing, Kuala Lumpur, Bangkok, Singapore, Tokyo and Taipei, bound for various parts of the world, "benefiting from the luggage convenience to the final destination with a single ticket." For example, airlines based in Macau can, by sharing codes with the mother company on the Beijing route, facilitate the connection of passengers between Macau and Frankfurt, and vice versa, says the civil aviation authority, stressing that “the number of users on this route has been gradually increasing, becoming gradually in one of the viable options for the connection between Macau and Europe”.
In turn, the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) has been collaborating with local, regional and international airlines in offering discountplane offering and other preferred tourist products, as well as promoting Hong Kong's maritime and terrestrial offer to Macau for international tourists through Hong Kong International Airport, “thus encouraging more international tourists to extend their own. Visits to Macau ”.</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 00:00:22</pubDate></item></channel></rss>