<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/macau-pode-ser-afectado-por-5-a-8-tempestades-tropicais-este-ano/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Piostri wins in China in a test dominated by McLaren</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/piastri-vence-na-china-em-prova-dominada-pela-mclaren/</link><description>Australian pilot Oscar Pistri (McLaren) won yesterday the Grand Prix of Formula 1 China, the World Cup, entirely dominated by the British team, which got the 'double'. Piostri, who departed from the pole position, concluded the 56 laps to the Shanghai layout on 01: 30.55.026 hours, leaving in second position the teammate and leader of the championship, Lando Norris (McLaren), 9.748 seconds, with also British George Russell (Mercedes) to 11,097.
British Lewis Hamilton (Ferrari), Monegasco Charles Leclerc (Ferrari) and Frenchman Pierre Gasly (Alpine) were disqualified from the China Grand Prix, the second round of the Formula 1 World Cup by the commissioner panel. Lewis Hamilton's Ferrari had excessive rear protection panel wear, which should have a minimum thickness of nine millimeters at the end of the race, which was sixth. Leclerc's monoligles, which was finished fifth, and Gasly, 11th, ended with the weight below the minimum regulatory. In the case of Ferrari, it was a difference from a kilogram dictating disqualification, dictated by the commission panel, of which the former Portuguese pilot Pedro Lamy includes. With this outcome, Norris held the command of the championship, with 44 points, with Verstappen in second position with 36, followed by Russel, with 35, and Pistri, with 34. McLaren leads at the 78 points, more than 25 than Mercedes. The next round will be the big prize in Japan, within two weeks.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 05:22:03</pubDate></item><item><title>14th Macau Literary Festival officially opens the doors</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/14-o-festival-literario-de-macau-abre-oficialmente-as-portas/</link><description>The 14th Macao Literary Festival opened its doors in the old municipal slaughterhouse with a ceremony that highlighted the multifaceted nature of literature and the arts. The events of the first day of the festival explored the impact of independence on the world and artificial intelligence on literary creation.
 
The 14th Macau Literary Festival began last Friday, at 17h, in the former Municipal Slaughterhouse, marking the beginning of a celebration of literature and the arts. The festival aims to connect the various forms of artistic expression by creating a platform for dialogue and understanding within the community. The festival's director, Ricardo Pinto, gave the motto for the opening ceremony, stating that “poetry, music, photography and cinema, history and fiction, join us once again in this 14th edition of Rota das Letras”. His speech underlined the festival's commitment to show the multifaceted nature of literature and the arts.
Yao Jingming, deputy director of the festival, also underlined the role of literature in the formation of human experience. "Literature is a lighthouse of the human spirit that guides us in our pursuit of the meaning of life." Yao also added: "Regardless of the development of science and technology, humanistic concern and the spiritual value of literature never change." His comments reflected on how literature goes beyond geographical, racial and cultural divisions, promoting empathy between people and reinforcing the continuous relevance of literature among technological advances.
Carlos Morais José, also deputy director of the festival, concluded the speeches by pointing to the importance of language. His ideas have positioned language as a “vital tool” to human expression and understanding. "It is in words and through words that humanity still finds one of its specificities, the ability to relate to its own world and with ourselves," he said.
 
After the opening ceremony, the festival continued with the inauguration of a photography exhibition entitled “New Independence”, with the work of photojournalist Alfredo Cunha. The exhibition celebrates the 50 years of independence from Portuguese -speaking African countries, presenting images of countries such as Angola and Mozambique. Curated by João Miguel Barros, the exhibition is organized in five themes that explore the independence path of these nations. The 52 selected images represent almost five decades of photographic documentation and contribute to a broader dialogue on cultural identity and historical memory.
The festival culminated in a discussion panel entitled “Poetic Writing in the Age of Artificial Intelligence: Challenges and Opportunities,” where poets Xu Jinjin, Zang Di, Chan Ka Long and Shanshan Wang participated in a discussion about the impact of artificial intelligence on creativity.
Xu Jinjin offered an optimistic perspective on this emerging technology by stating that "artificial intelligence will never know what resilience is, what persistence is, human instinct to continue." Their opinions throughout the panel reflected a belief in the lasting power of human creativity in the midst of the advancement of technologies. Similarly, Shanshan Wang argued that “human creativity is wild. It is our way of affirming our existence,” underlining the unique aspects of human artistic expression throughout the conversation.
However, not all opinions were optimistic. The Zang Di poet expressed a more cautious perspective. "Perhaps one day artificial intelligence destroys humans so that it does not have to continue to compare their work with ours," he said. This feeling of concern was shared by the audience, including MEI MEI, a university student who confessed to his "strong anxiety" on the implications of artificial intelligence in the creative areas.
On the other hand, the poet Chan Ka Long took a balanced approach. "It is a gradual process… imitation. The irreplaceable characteristics of humans are the fact that we understand how and because we write poems. This is something that artificial intelligence cannot, cannot imitate," he said. His comments during the panel illustrated the varied perspectives of participants and the audience, returning optimism and caution regarding the influence of artificial intelligence on literary creation.
The 14th Macao Literary Festival promotes an environment that encourages involvement and introspection through a variety of artistic expressions. The events of the day emphasized the importance of literature and art in understanding individual and collective identities.
The festival will be patent until March 30 and offers a unique opportunity to reflect on the past, while contemplating the challenges and future opportunities in the literary world.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Tai Kin IP went to Europe to reinforce international connections from Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/tai-kin-ip-foi-a-europa-reforcar-ligacoes-internacionais-de-macau/</link><description>Tai Kin IP, Secretary for Economics and Finance, led a delegation from the Government of Masters on a visit to Europe, namely Portugal, Spain, Belgium and Monaco. The purpose of the initiative was to extend the international links of Macao and explore opportunities for cooperation.
 
A delegation from the Government of MSAR, led by the secretary to the economy and finance, was visiting Europe. Earlier this month, Tai Kin IP passed through Spain, Portugal, Belgium and Monaco and intended “even more, international links and explore opportunities for cooperation,” the authorities point out in a statement released on Friday.
The visit program began on March 3, when the delegation was present at Mobile World Congress 2025 (MWC25), an annual science and technology event that took place in Barcelona, ​​Spain. In this edition of the event, where Huawei took over the rotary presidency, technologies and products focused on 5G themes and artificial intelligence were exhibited. During the event, the delegation met with Groupe Specialle Mobile Association (GSMA), the event organizer, to discuss eventual future cooperation. The delegation also had a meeting with China's consul general in Barcelona, ​​Meng Yuhong.
The delegation of Macao was in Lisbon between March 4 and 6 and visited Banco de Portugal, the Ministry of Economy and the Ministry of Education, Science and Innovation of Portugal, among others, with, respectively, with the administrator of Banco de Portugal, Luís Morais Sarmento, the Secretary of State for the Ministry of Economy, João Rui Ferreira, and the Secretary of State for Education, Science and Innovation. The occasion served to “negotiate the consolidation and deepening of cooperation between Macao and Portugal in the areas of science, technology, economy and commerce, with a view to better developing the role of Macao as a platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries,” says the government.
Still in Portugal, the delegation also had a meeting with the Ambassador of the Popular Republic of China in Portugal, Zhao Bentang, and participated in the unveiling ceremony of the Sino-Portuguese Laboratory plaque of Artificial Intelligence and Public Health Technologies, constituted jointly by Higher Education Institutions of Macao, Canton and Portugal. In addition, the delegation also visited several higher education and scientific research institutions, namely the Portuguese Catholic University, the New University of Lisbon and the Institute of Nanostructures, Nanomodeling and Nanofabrication (I3N), to learn about the latest development of scientific research in Portugal.
During the visits, the Memorandum of Understanding between the University of Science and Technology of Macao (Must) and the New University of Lisbon in stories of reinforcing cooperation in scientific research and personnel exchange, as well as the signing of a cooperation agreement between the two universities for the creation of a joint research center.
On March 7, in Brussels, Belgium, the delegation had a meeting with the China Mission Head of the European Union, Ambassador Cai Run, having exchanged impressions on the reinforcement of cooperation between Macao and I. The delegation also made a courtesy visit to the European service for external action (SEAE), meeting with the Assistant Director-General for Asia and the Pacific at SEAE, Paola Pampaloni, and both parties and a preliminary discussion about the 24th meeting of the Macao Joint Commission, as well as impressions on the deepening of relations and cooperation. bilateral economic and commercial.
Throughout the meeting, Tai Kin IP said that "Macau will better take advantage of the institutional advantages of the" one country, two systems "principle, proactively establishing a platform for international exchange and cooperation within the new opening round abroad in the country." The secretary also added that "the European Union is one of Macao's main business partners, and the mechanism of the Macao mixed commission provides an effective platform for Macao and the EU discussing economic and commercial affairs of common interest, playing a positive role in promoting close cooperation between the two parts and the reinforcement of mutual connection."
During the visit to Monaco, on March 8 and 9, Skål International Monaco made a welcome reception to the MSAR Government delegation, which brought together leaders from tourism, finance and technology, among others, to promote exchange and contacts and explore opportunities for cooperation. Tai Kin IP pointed out that “Monaco and Macao are famous tourist destinations, with a similar history, culture, and similar tourist characteristics”, and with their privileged geographical location, both territories can promote cooperation relations between Monaco (all over Europe) and Macau (to all of China), especially the large Guangdong-Macau Bay, in the field of tourism, conventions, conventions, conventions, conventions, conventions exhibitions and events ”.
In addition, Monaco's ambassador in the People's Republic of China, Marie-Ppasscale Boisson, offered a welcome dinner to the delegation. Marie-Passcale Boisson recalled that this year marks the 30th anniversary of the establishment of diplomatic relations between China and Monaco, and that this visit played “a positive role in promoting sino-monegasque relations”.
In a statement, the Secretary's Office for the Economics and Finance says that, on the visit, “the delegation reinforced communication with the sector of Polast Technology of Europe, expanding the macao international cooperation spaces in Europe, which is of great importance for the proper diversification of the Macao economy and the deepening of international cooperation and exchange”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 05:23:25</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korean leader reaffirms full support to Russia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/lider-da-coreia-do-norte-reafirma-apoio-total-a-russia/</link><description>North Korean leader Kim Jong-un reaffirmed the availability to support the Russian war against Ukraine during a meeting with a high security official responsible for security, the North Korean state press said.
Kim maintained “important and useful” conversations with Russian Security Council Secretary Serguei Shoigu in Pyongyang on Friday, according to North Korean news agency KCNA.
The two parts exchanged opinions on issues related to the defense of security interests of both countries, and on regional and global issues, said the same source, according to the Spanish agency Efe. "The firm choice and firm will of the North Korean government is invariably to support Russia in the struggle for the defense of national sovereignty, territorial integrity and security interests in the future," Kim said, according to KCNA.
Shoigu delivered Kim a “important signed letter” by Russian President Vladimir Putin, the North Korean agency, monitored in Seoul, said without revealing details.
The Secretary of the Russian Security Council arrived in North Korea on Friday for meetings with Kim and other high officials of the regime, according to Russian state agency Tass, in another chapter of the growing approach between Moscow and Pyongyang.
The visit of former Russian Defense Minister follows a recent series of high level contacts between the two governments.
In mid-March, Russian Foreign Deputy Minister Andrei Rudenko also visited Pyongyang, where he discussed with North Korean counterpart, Choe Son-hui, the possibility of “higher level political meetings.
The bonds between Moscow and Pyongyang have intensified since the beginning of the war in Ukraine in February 2022.
North Korea provided soldiers and weaponry to support the Russian forces, according to South Korea and Western allies.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 05:22:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Revitalization of the mud market scheduled to end in the fourth quarter of the year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/revitalizacao-do-mercado-da-taipa-prevista-para-terminar-no-quarto-trimestre-do-ano/</link><description>The Institute for Municipal Affairs will start the Revitalization Project of the Taipa Market, on Rua do Regrador. The conclusion of the works and the reentry in operation of the enclosure are scheduled for the fourth quarter of this year. According to the authorities, the number of stalls on the mud market will be reduced from 66 to 52, of which 20 will be light food and cultural and creative industries, including a terrace terrace of the complex. O organismo vai proceder ainda à remodelação da fachada do mercado.
 
The mud market will have revitalization and optimization works, which will start next month and should be completed in the fourth quarter of this year. The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) revealed that the project aims to introduce elements of “gastronomy + cultural creativity” into traditional markets.
A public tender of 20 lights of light food and cultural and creative industries will be launched, including a terrace terrace. Authorities hope that the experimental entry into operation of these new newsstands is also in the fourth quarter of the year.
AMI announced the revitalization plan last Friday and indicated that the mud market currently has 66 newsstands, half of which is unoccupied and the rest in business exploration. At a press conference, according to the Cheng Pou newspaper, the body revealed that the number of newsstands will be reduced to 52, which is due to the increase in the size of some newsstands and the addition of four restoration zones on the first floor of the market, and current stalls can continue the operation on site.
In this sense, after the works, on the ground floor of the venue will be held the sale of fresh and living food products and traditional goods with 28 stalls. On the first floor there will be 23 newsstands, of which 19 stalls of light food and cultural and creative products will be set to contest, with a minimum area of ​​8.1 square meters and a maximum of 30.9 square meters. In addition, a terrace terrace will be installed to “provide a leisure and comfort environment” to residents.
The AMI explained that the mud market has a history of operation and cannot be used on site liquefied oil gas or natural gas to cook, depending only on electricity, so it will only be provided mild meals, which "can also meet the needs of consumers."
AMI expects, under the assumption of the good use of public resources, to create a platform for citizens interested in dedicating themselves to the sector of cultural and creative industries or gastronomy with their own characteristics, in order to provide “a friendly environment for young people and entrepreneurs” and promote the transformation of traditional markets.
The body did not advance the revitalization budget, justifying that the public tender process is underway and that the budget cost could not be disclosed for a matter of equity.
It is recalled that the Taipa Market, located at Rua do Regrador, was inaugurated in 1983, occupying an area of ​​506 square meters, being the only municipal market in Taipa. The government proceeded a few years ago to expand this market, introducing conditioned air and facilities without architectural barriers, with a view to responding to the needs of social development.
The AMI has stated that the area where the mud market is located is a zone of large concentration of residents and tourists, and is surrounded by popular sights and a large flow of people, so it has been collecting opinions to improve the spatial disposition of the installation. Ensuring that it will “beautify” the market facade, AMI said that large signs and screens will be placed on the outer walls of the construction, adding Chinese and Portuguese elements.
For the newsstands put to the public tender, the AMI said that the evaluation committee will evaluate the proposals according to the competitor's exploration, experience and qualification strategy, banking daily opening hours, diversity and uniqueness of product types, convenience of the means of payment, among other criteria, and the term of the contract is three years.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 05:20:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing, Seoul and Tokyo seek to overcome differences against the US commercial offensive</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/pequim-seul-e-toquio-procuram-ultrapassar-diferencas-face-a-ofensiva-comercial-dos-eua/</link><description>The heads of Japan, China and South Korea diplomacy began, in Tokyo, a meeting designed to strengthen cooperation, at a time when the US -launched trade war threatens the region.
 
"The international situation has become increasingly difficult and it is no exaggeration to say that we are at a point of turning into history," Japanese Foreign Minister Takeshi Iwayaa said, before Chinese and South Korean counterparts, Wang Yi and Cho Tae-Yul, respectively.
This trilateral meeting, the 11th in this format, occurs at a time when East Asia has been particularly affected by the imposition of the customs launched by the United States.
In this context, "it is more necessary than ever to redouble our efforts to overcome divisions and confrontations through dialogue and cooperation," Iwaya added before the meeting.
Remembering that this year is the 80th anniversary of the end of World War II, Wang Yi said that "it is sincerely reflecting on the story" that can "better build the future."
The Chinese official added that the reinforcement of cooperation will allow “resisting the risks, together” and promote “mutual understanding” among peoples. "Cooperation between the three countries can send to the world a message of hope for the future," Cho Tae-Yul said, adding to expect "open and frank discussions (…) on the North Korean nuclear issue."
The heads of state of the three countries met in Seoul in May 2024 for the first tripartite summit in five years, where they agreed to deepen commercial ties and reaffirmed the goal of denuclearizing the Korean peninsula-in reference to the nuclear weapons developed by North Korea.
Seoul and Tokyo usually adopt a firmer position compared to Pyongyang than Beijing, which remains one of North Korea's leading economic allies and supporters.
Ministers discussed issues such as economic cooperation, dialogue between peoples, and measures to counteract the fall in the birth rate -a critical problem for the three countries -according to NHK Japanese public television.
NHK also reported that ministers will try to agree on organizing a potential new trilateral summit by the end of the year.
This new meeting “should give priority to economic issues” compared to the rates imposed by the Trump administration, alerted Lim Eul-Chul, a professor at the Far East Studies Institute of Seoul.
The US implemented additional 20% rates on Chinese imports and 25% tariffs on steel and aluminum -a decision that has hardly hit Japan and South Korea -before a series of reciprocal tariffs directed to all countries, scheduled for early April.
The leaders of the three Asian nations “are increasingly forced to diversify the options” in the face of this US pressure analyzed Brookings Institution researcher in Washington, Patrica Kim. "It is not surprising that the three largest economies in East Asia are becoming one to each other in search of new economic opportunities," Kim told France-Presse agency. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 05:22:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Paulo Rangel visits China this week and goes through Macau on Friday</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/paulo-rangel-visita-china-esta-semana-e-passa-por-macau-na-sexta-feira/</link><description>Paulo Rangel, Minister of State and Foreign Affairs of Portugal, will be visiting China throughout this week. On Friday, Rangel will go through Macau and Hong Kong.
 
The Minister of State and Foreign Affairs, Paulo Rangel, visits China this week, a four -day trip that includes contacts with high representatives of the Chinese government and a passage through Macao.
The agenda of the head of Portuguese diplomacy starts tomorrow in Beijing, at 10am, with a meeting with the Director General of the International Department of the Communist Party of China, Minister Liu Jinchao, indicates a note issued by the Ministry protected by Rangel.
There is a meeting with Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi and a meeting with Beijing Foreign Studies University, Jia Wenjian. Still in the Chinese capital, Paulo Rangel will give a lecture at Beijing Foreign Studies University (BFSU) subordinate to the theme “Portuguese Language and Culture”.
The next day, already in Haikou, the Portuguese minister intervenes in the Boa Forum For ASIA 2025, an annual conference held in the Chinese province of Haião that aims to promote and deepen exchange, coordination and economic cooperation between Asia and other parts of the world. Also on Wednesday, Paulo Rangel has foreseen a bilateral meeting with Chinese vice-prime minister, Ding Xuexiang.
The Minister of State and Foreign Affairs also participates on Thursday at the plenary session of the Boa Forum for Asia 2025 and has scheduled bilateral meetings.
The last day of the trip to China, Friday, is dedicated to Macao and Hong Kong, with a scheduled schedule, among other moments, with meetings with representatives of associations, educational institutions and entrepreneurs and a visit to the Portuguese school of Macau.
Paulo Rangel will meet equally with the head of the Executive of the MSAR, Sam Hou Fai, and the advisers of the Portuguese communities elected by the Circle of China (China, Korea, Japan, Singapore and Thailand).
The official program of Paulo Rangel's visit ends with a visit to the exhibition “Stories Lusas”, an initiative dedicated to the Portuguese community, at the Hong Kong History Museum.
 
Retoma of Strategic Dialogue with Beijing
 
The trip to Paulo Rangel's China breaks a hiatus of more than five years without Portuguese high -level visits to Beijing, at a time of reconfiguration of the international order.
Rangel's visit happens in a context where Donald Trump's return to the power of Donald Trump can reshape geopolitical alignments and economic partnerships between Europe and China, according to analysts.
Visits from high Portuguese government officials were almost monthly frequently, by the end of 2019, but were interrupted by the COVID-19 pandemic, which led to the closing of China's borders.
However, the absence of travel was extended even after the end of the country's reopening in January 2023 and the visit to Portugal by Chinese Vice President Han Zheng in May of this year.
In an interview with Lusa, Michael Sheridan, a journalist and author of an article on the relations between Lisbon and Beijing for the Think Tank group) Center for European Policy Analysis, admitted a distance between the two countries, in line with a change in European Union (EU) foreign policy.
"Portugal's posture aligned with a general change [in politics] of the EU," he argued. "I don't see anything antagonistic between the two countries. The political base [in Europe] was to reduce risks. This became the new paradigm. There are differences in the way each European country interpreted, but the direction was clear," he noticed.
China has become, in the last decade, the fourth largest foreign direct investor in Portugal. Chinese, state and private companies have a global position valued at 11.2 billion euros in the Portuguese economy, according to Banco de Portugal (BDP). Investments cover the areas of energy, bank, safe or health.
In 2018, the two countries signed a memorandum of understanding of the “Track and Route” initiative, a mega project of infrastructure launched by Beijing that aims to expand its global influence through the construction of ports, railways or self -established.
Michael Sheridan pointed to a change of attitude in Europe in the face of China due to the pressure of the United States, the COVID-19 pandemic, which deteriorated the perceptions of the country, and the approach of Beijing to Moscow, in the context of the Russian invasion of Ukraine. "All of this led to a reduction in confidence and political sympathy for Beijing," he said.
In 2023, a Portuguese government advisory body deliberated on the de facto exclusion of Chinese companies from the development of fifth generation networks (5G). The decision was “the most extreme” among all European countries, they then told Lusa Huawei's officials.
Paulo Rangel's visit to Beijing runs after the return to power in the United States of Donald Trump. The antagonistic positions of the American leader in the face of the transatlantic alliance are seen by analysts as susceptible to recontecting Europe and China.
"Many European leaders will see an opportunity to mark the narrowing of ties to China as a lever to ensure continuous US commitments," he wrote in a report the London -based "Think Tank" Chatham House. "This strategy may be successful. Despite the confidence crisis, Europe has very important letters in the US - China - European triangle," he added.
Last month, Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi, with whom Rangel is due to meet in Beijing, proposed at the Munich Security Conference on Europe's participation in Ukraine peace negotiations and a wider reformulation of bell-europeias relations.
"China has always seen Europe as an important part in the multipolar world," said Wang. "The two parts are partner and not rivals. China is willing to work with the European part to deepen strategic communication and mutually beneficial cooperation," he said.
 
Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 04:38:24</pubDate></item><item><title>China simplifies wedding records to encourage birth</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/china-simplifica-registos-de-casamento-para-incentivar-a-natalidade/</link><description>China yesterday announced measures to simplify wedding registration and try to reduce financial pressure on bride and groom, as another measure to foster birth rates.
Marriage is almost a prerequisite for having a child in China, as out-of-marriage births are poorly seen and do not offer the same level of recognition and protection.
However, the number of weddings decreased by 20.5% last year and, by 2024, China will record the third consecutive year of decrease in the population, which is a challenge for economic growth and pension financing.
Authorities have already launched various measures, such as subsidies for those who marry and have children, and the construction of more children's reception centers was promised.
The last initiative states that couples can now register marriages anywhere in the country, according to information released by state broadcaster CCTV, citing a government document.
So far, couples had to move to the place where the bride or groom were registered. For example, a couple living in Beijing (north) for professional reasons, but whose wife was from Guangzhou (south) and the husband of Shanghai (east) had to move to one of these two cities to fulfill the necessary formalities.
According to the channel, the Ministry of Civil Affairs also promises to "fight certain harmful habits such as excessive skills and excessively expensive marriage ceremonies."
One dowry is the sum of money that the groom's family usually gives the bride and is often seen as a sign of respect for in -laws and a contribution to the beginning of the young couple's life. But in some cases the amounts became very high, creating financial pressure for the groom's family and feeding social inequalities.
Many young Chinese are reluctant to marry and have children. Among the main reasons for this, there are financial disability to buy an apartment, which is often a previous condition for marriage, and the high cost of education, from child care to private classes, considered almost indispensable for a child's school success.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 04:38:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal point 2025.03.24</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/ponto-fatal-2025-03-24/</link><description>China yesterday announced measures to simplify wedding registration and try to reduce financial pressure on bride and groom, as another measure to foster birth rates.
Marriage is almost a prerequisite for having a child in China, as out-of-marriage births are poorly seen and do not offer the same level of recognition and protection.
However, the number of weddings decreased by 20.5% last year and, by 2024, China will record the third consecutive year of decrease in the population, which is a challenge for economic growth and pension financing.
Authorities have already launched various measures, such as subsidies for those who marry and have children, and the construction of more children's reception centers was promised.
The last initiative states that couples can now register marriages anywhere in the country, according to information released by state broadcaster CCTV, citing a government document.
So far, couples had to move to the place where the bride or groom were registered. For example, a couple living in Beijing (north) for professional reasons, but whose wife was from Guangzhou (south) and the husband of Shanghai (east) had to move to one of these two cities to fulfill the necessary formalities.
According to the channel, the Ministry of Civil Affairs also promises to "fight certain harmful habits such as excessive skills and excessively expensive marriage ceremonies."
One dowry is the sum of money that the groom's family usually gives the bride and is often seen as a sign of respect for in -laws and a contribution to the beginning of the young couple's life. But in some cases the amounts became very high, creating financial pressure for the groom's family and feeding social inequalities.
Many young Chinese are reluctant to marry and have children. Among the main reasons for this, there are financial disability to buy an apartment, which is often a previous condition for marriage, and the high cost of education, from child care to private classes, considered almost indispensable for a child's school success.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 04:38:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai anticipates further cooperation with Guangdong</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/sam-hou-fai-antecipa-cooperacao-mais-aprofundada-com-guangdong/</link><description>The Chief Executive shows a desire to further advance in cooperation between MSAR and Guangdong province to accelerate mutual development. Sam Hou Fai indicates that Macau has an “important mission” in national integration, stating that the reinforcement of cooperation with Guangdong is thus the “first and strategic priority” of the government. Guangdong's head reiterates the importance of the development of Hengiqn.
 
The government intends to further reinforce communication and collaboration with Guangdong Province in the future and boost the in-depth development of cooperation between the two places, the executive head, Sam Hou Fai, said at a Guangdong Province Spring reception, which took place in the territory last Friday.
Sam Hou Fai, in his speech, argued that the MSAR is willing to work with the province and revealed the hope of enhancing the parties' advantages and characteristics of the parties, as well as to open a “new chapter of most pronounced and deepened level” between Macau and Guangdong.
"Guangdong and Macau communes from the same roots and are joined by fraternal ties. The first and strategic priority of the Government of MSAR is always, therefore, reinforcing cooperation with Guangdong Province," he said.
Valuing bilateral cooperation, the chief executive pointed out that Guangdong “has guaranteed strong support” Macau in various areas over the years, namely the supply of materials, facilities of border passage and the promotion of economic development, which will provide, according to SAM, facilities and conditions for Macau residents to study, work and live in Guangdong.
The government leader added that the integration and service of Macao at the conjuncture of national development is “an important mission”, and the key to maintaining prosperity and long -term stability ”of the region. It therefore guaranteed that the government actively participates in the development of the Great Bay and also placed the Hengqin cooperation zone as the first priority of cooperation with Guangdong.
According to Sam Hou Fai, the present government will follow the instructions of Chinese President Xi Jinping to accelerate the work of the second phase of the Hengiqn project with a thought of reform and innovation. “Swept out a highly connected economy system and a deep articulation of rules between Macao and the cooperation zone, thus contributing more significantly to sustain the development of the proper diversification of the economy and to leverage the construction of the large bay,” he said.
 
Trade with guangdong
 
In turn, Guangdong Province Governor Wang Weizhong marked the “vitality” of the great bay and the “fruit results” for Guangdong-Macau cooperation. In his speech, the official said that last year the import and export of goods between Guangdong and Macau reached 19.34 billion Renminbis, an increase of 22%; There were also 2,449 new companies that were established in Guangdong by Macao, an increase of 13.3%, while the circulation of Macao vehicles in Guangdong province reached an average of 126 thousand per month, an increase of 34%.
Wang Weizhong remembered Xi Jinping's visit to Macau and Hengqin in December last year where he emphasized the need to promote the development of Mountain Island. He recalled that in 2024 Hengqin began to function as an autonomous customs zone, and that more and more residents, capital and companies in Macao seek to live and develop in Hengqin with the tendency of the “four new” industries.
Thus, the governor of Guangdong province said he will support Macao in a “better integration in national development” and maintaining long -term prosperity and stability, stressing that “he always has the original intention of hengqin's development for the proper diversification of Macao's economy”. Wang Weizhong, thus hopes to create a new perspective on Hengqin's work to make the country greater contribution.
 
C.c.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 04:38:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Macanese and Luso-Asian population resident in San Francisco surpasses Macau, says study</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/populacao-de-macaenses-e-luso-asiaticos-residente-em-sao-francisco-supera-a-de-macau-diz-estudo/</link><description>A study released by a Chinese researcher concludes that, currently, the population of Macanese and Luso-Asia that resides in the area of ​​São Francisco Bay, in the United States, is larger than that of Macao.
 
“Há cerca de 70 mil macaenses e luso-asiáticos a residir em São Francisco, o que é mais do que o número em Macau”, afirmou em declarações à Lusa a investigadora Leong Wong Un Na, que apresentou esta quinta-feira na Universidade de Macau, o livro Macanese and Luso-Asian in the San Francisco Bay Area, de 1940 a 1950, um título que resulta da sua tese de doutoramento.
According to the latest censuses held in Macao in 2021, only 13,021 residents in Macau had Portuguese ancestry, representing 1.9% of the total population.
The data also reveal that even less, 6,668, 1% of the total population, had Chinese and Portuguese descent, characteristics normally used to define the Macanese community
According to Leong, the Macanese, some of which had departed to various regions of Asia in the nineteenth century, Luso-Asian and the Portuguese in Asia, emigrated to the United States from Macao in the twentieth century, due to political and economic reasons, choosing as the main destination of the São Francisco Bay in California.
Leong Wong Un NA, a Chinese who grew up in Macao and says maintaining a close relationship with the Macanese community, has many family members resident in San Francisco, including parents and siblings.
The immigrated macanese and Luso-Asiatic-symatics in San Francisco, concluded Leong, were not soon recognized as Portuguese when they arrived in the United States and were even discriminated against for decades by the Portuguese community itself.
At the same time the Communist Party was taking power in China, “the macanese and the Luso-Asiatics, when they immigrated there [San Francisco], could not participate in the organizations created by the Portuguese of Portugal,” said Leong Wong Un na. "Some of the descendants of Portuguese who came from Asia did not speak fluent Portuguese, so the Portuguese from Portugal said that if they did not know Portuguese, they were not Portuguese," he explained.
Leong describes in his book not only how is the community of Macanese and Luso-Asia that currently lives in the area of ​​São Francisco Bay, such as the origins and cultural traits of the Portuguese community and even the architectural characteristics they have imprinted on the urban surroundings.
The researcher concluded that the Macaenses and Luso-Asia of San Francisco "maintain habits still very alive in Macau, such as the Macaense cuisine and the Catholic religion."
According to the Directorate of Macao Statistics and Census Services, in 2021, 13,021 residents in Macau had Portuguese ancestry, representing 1.9% of the total population. The Portuguese Leadership Council of the United States has a total population of 1,454,262 with Portuguese ancestry. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 05:22:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Prices in Macau retreat 0.16% in February</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/precos-em-macau-recuam-016-em-fevereiro/</link><description>The Consumer Price Index (IPC) in Macao descended in February 0.16%, in annual terms, announced the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC).
The descent is due to “mainly to the high comparison base, as the occurrence of the Lunar New Year in February 2024 led to the prices of some goods/services to be at a relatively high level,” read in a DSEC statement.
This year, the so -called Lunar New Year's 'Golden Week', a period of holidays in mainland China, which changes depending on the lunar calendar, also caught a few days of January. In 2024, this high time for tourism in Macau took place fully in February.
In monthly terms, the IPC dropped 0.19% in February, while "the average general IPC of the 12 -month ending in the reference month, compared to the immediately preceding 12 months (March 2023 to February 2024), ascended 0.57%," added that board.
In February, the price indices of the leisure, recreation, sport and culture (-5.03%), transport (-4%), information and communication (-2.83%) and clothing and footwear (-1.98%) registered the largest falls compared to last year's homologous month.
The price indices of the sections of various products and services, alcohol and tobacco and education and education increased 2.05%, 2.03%and 1.17%, respectively, in annual terms.
The price index of food products and non -alcoholic beverages (+0.69%) and housing and fuels (+0.31%) also ascended in annual terms. In the first two months of this year, the average General IPC grew 0.2%, compared to the same period of 2024.
Inflation in the neighboring region of Hong Kong again slowed in February, a month when mainland China fell into deflation for the first time in over a year.
The Consumer Price Index (IPC) rose 1.4% in February, compared to the same period, said the Census and Statistics Department (CSD) of Hong Kong. In January, inflation settled at 2%.
In a statement, the CSD justified the slowdown with the impact of Lunar New Year's variation, "particularly food prices and tour package costs." “To neutralize the effect of the Chinese New Year,” the CSD stressed that homologous inflation for the first two months of 2025 was 1.7%, higher than in December (1.4%).</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 05:19:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Cape Verde challenges Chinese company to seize tourism opportunities</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/cabo-verde-desafia-empresa-chinesa-para-aproveitar-oportunidades-na-area-do-turismo/</link><description>The president of the Cape Verdean agency for foreign investment, José Almada Dias, challenged in Macao the Chinese company Shaanxi Construction to take advantage of the opportunities offered by the 20,000 hectares that the country has put in the service of tourism.
 
CV Tradeinvest, chaired by Almada Dias, and Shaanxi Construction Engineering Group Corporation (SCEGC, one of the 500 largest sector companies worldwide), through one of their vice-presidents, Xiong Bangye, signed a memorandum of understanding (MO) that formalizes the parties' interest in taking advantage of “technical capacity technological capacity in MO). and financial ”of the Chinese company in the development of projects in Cape Verde.
Shaanxi Construction has been present in Cape Verde since 2009, but Almada Dias has underlined new reasons that can capture the renewed interest of the Chinese construction giant in the country, starting with the recent bet of the beach city in the infrastructure of Integral Development Zones (ZDTI), to which it allocated 20,000 hectares in the nine inhabited islands of the archipelago.
"At this time, we have over 20,000 hectares of special areas for tourism development," said the manager. "Since now, I challenge Shannxi Construction, along with the state of Cape Verde, to look at the infrastructuring of these special zones, which are great opportunities for construction companies," he added, explaining that Cape Verdean law allows the infrastructure of the zones to be assumed in full by private companies or in public-private partnerships (PPP), the Cape Verde State or the municipalities.
Speaking to journalists at the end of the event, Almada Dias stressed that the Cape Verdean government has “a lot of interest in attracting companies of this type, not only for the technical quality they bring, know-how, but above all for the capacity to mobilize significant” that Cape Verde “cannot mobilize internally”.
Xiong Bangye characterized Cape Verde as “a well -developed political economy”, and underlined Shannxi Construction multifaceted nature, as “full company, with businesses in different areas, including housing, real estate, transport, energy, desalination”. "We have tourism concentrated on two islands -Sal and Boa Vista -we want to spread across the country more organized and planned, and to bring the benefits to the populations of the nine inhabited islands and beyond," CV TRADEINVEST President explained to Lusa.
Shannxi Construction offers, from the Cape Verdean foreign investment agency perspective “technical capacity in various sectors: social housing, real estate, construction”. "These are sectors that interest us, the development of tourism itself in certain islands is creating a huge need for huge social housing. We have a fantastic deficit in this sector, which is normal in countries that are developing. There is a lot of internal migration between the islands, there are people who come out to come to work."
The ceremony completed the visit to Macao of the Cape Verdean ambassador in Beijing, Arlindo do Rosario, who attended this Wednesday at the 20th Ordinary Meeting of the Permanent Secretariat of the Macau Forum and was present in the signature of Mou.
The diplomat stressed that “there is a lot of market in Cape Verde for Chinese companies and companies from other countries”, distinguishing the priorities established by the country's government in the energy sector, from renewable energy, electric mobility, among others, namely in the São Vicente Special Economic Zone project. "We have already worked with China in the elaboration of the first phase of the project and there is room for companies around the world, including Chinese, being able to enter and invest in this area," said Arlindo do Rosario. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 04:38:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Consumption stimulation plan in community zones starts today</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/plano-de-estimulo-ao-consumo-nas-zonas-comunitarias-comeca-hoje/</link><description>Today the consumer incentive initiative “major consumption prize in community zones 2025” is started. The initiative takes place until June 1st.
When the electronic portfolio user of any of the collaborating entities make a mobile payment at any of Macau online or physical stores in the amount of not less than 50 patacas for each transaction, from Monday to Friday during the course of the activity, it can get three opportunities to gain electronic discount coupons (maximum limit of three opportunities per week for each real name) that expires at midnight immediately follows the midnight. of your obtaining.
The obtained electronic discount coupons should be used on Saturday and Sunday immediately after obtaining more than 20,000 Macao physical stores that accept them, and can automatically be used only one coupon in each value transaction actually paid equal to or higher than triple of the nominal value of the coupon. If you have several electronic discount coupons at the single electronic portfolio, when the consumption value meets the conditions of “triple the value of the coupon”, the discount coupons will be used automatically on a single transaction. All discount coupons will be expired at midnight on Monday immediately after their obtaining.
During the activity, on Saturdays and Sundays, consumers can automatically participate in weekly raffles and the big final draw with award -winning awards, provided they actually pay 50 patacas with the electronic portfolio of any of the collaborating entities in any of the Macao stores that can discount electronic discount coupons.
In addition, from today, the elderly with the new version of the Macau Pass card for the elderly can get immediate discounts worth 300 patacas by loading the card, with more than 120 services indicated in Macau, and simultaneously gaining electronic discount coupons after consumption through mobile payment, enjoying two types of benefits.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 05:19:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Word celebration: the main events of the first weekend of Rota das Letras</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/celebracao-da-palavra-os-principais-eventos-do-primeiro-fim-de-semana-do-rota-das-letras/</link><description>The first weekend of the 14th Macao Literary Festival had four panels, four book releases and debates and two film projections. The two days of the event aimed to promote dialogue and show the diversity of the cultural fabric of the region and the world.
 
The second day of the 14th Macao Literary Festival last Saturday began with the panel "Drawing Words, Writing Images", with André Letria, who also performed the illustration workshop "If I were a book." The day followed with the release of the book “The Dreamed Girl” and a creative writing masterclass, both directed by author Sonia Leung.
In the afternoon was the panel “The Literature of Hong Kong and Macau, in the context of the New Age”, which was attended by the authors Zang Di, Zhou Jieru and Tan Jianqiao and a full audience. Each speakers presented their own perspectives on the Hong Kong and Macao literary landscape, underlining the complexities inherent in their narratives.
"Wherever there is life, there is literature. Literature is just a reflection of life," said Tan Jianqiao, giving the motto to a debate that had both reflective and provocative. Interaction of contrasting values ​​in Macau was a recurring theme. Tan Jianqiao explained that "Macau is a city of contrasts and a city that constantly challenges our values. Macau exposes humanity of all." This feeling resonated throughout the panel, intertwining personal experiences with broader social observations.
Zhou Jieru stressed the challenges faced by local authors, noting that "very few publishers are willing to publish novels in Macau. Life is too comfortable here. Most Chinese novels are about misery. A comfortable life is not conducive to great literature." In response to this statement, Zang Di challenged the narrative around the perception of the stagnation of literary production, insisting that portraying literature only through the discomfort lens is a reduction. "I do not agree. It is a bad service provided to the Chinese people and all they do is propagate a stereotype. Why are we always so unhappy? Well, we are not," he noted, defending a more varied representation of experiences in literature.
At night, the festival showed “Your Face will be the last”, a film based on the work of João Ricardo Pedro. In a panel held hours before it was attended by the author and filmmaker Luís Filipe Rocha, discussions arose about the adaptation. "A book, when you are lucky in your life, can have several lives," said John, while Luís shared a more intimate connection with the work, confessing: "I even wondered if the book would have been written for me to film it."
Yesterday, the festival continued with the launch of Halftone #11 magazine, which featured contributions from photographers Gao Hongru, Eloi Scarva, David Lopo, José das Neves and João Palla. João Miguel Barros, discussing the impact of the magazine, said that "Halftone was a chance, but all that happened after it was not a chance." He stressed the inclusive character of the magazine, affirming his role in accepting diversity within the photographic community: "Halftone is an inclusive association, it is an association that accepts diversity ... without excluding styles, without excluding ways of looking."
Shortly thereafter, Valério Romão and Carlos Morais José presented their new book, "another disappointment." “We were promised a modernity for which we set forth in their feet and we have not yet reached,” said Romão, discussing the anticipation of modernity and the consequent disappointment felt by many, while Carlos Morais José concluded that “only those who believe”, numbing the feelings of juxtaposed hope with the reality that permeate the literary community.
The day ended with the projection of the film “The Saal Operations”, followed by a debate on the origin of the expansion of social housing with architects Maria José de Freitas and Carlotta Bruni, and the poetry recital “flying beyond new forms of ignorance”, with poets Chan Kalong, Jia Wei, Song Ying, Wang Shanshan, Yuan Xuefang and Zang Di.
The first weekend of the festival not only served as a platform for the launch of new works, but also promoted deep discussions about the current state and the future of literature. With the presence of a mixture of established and emerging voices, the event has been promoting an environment rich in dialogue, showing the dynamic cultural fabric of the region.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Tobacco consumption rate in Macau exceeds WHO reduction goal</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/taxa-de-consumo-de-tabaco-em-macau-ultrapassa-meta-de-reducao-da-oms/</link><description>Macao tobacco consumption has been decreasing since the implementation of the Smoking Prevention and Control Law in 2011, although in 2023 a slight climb has been verified in homologous terms. Organizations and anti-tabagist associations now reflect on other measures to implement in the future, such as the ban on water pipes and electronic cigarettes.
 
The tobacco consumption rate has registered a relative decrease of 31.4% since the introduction of the smoking control law in 2011, and has already exceeded the 30% reduction target proposed by the World Health Organization (WHO). The data were presented in the follow-up and evaluation report of the “Smoking Prevention and Control Regime”, referring to the years 2021 to 2023, and released last Friday by health services.
According to the results of the inquiry, consumers of tobacco and related products over 15 years old represent 11.6% of this population slice, a relative reduction of 31.4% compared to 16.9% verified in 2011. This means that, among the 559,900 people over 15 years resident in Macau, 64,700 are smokers. The vast majority smoke daily (55,800 people, or about 86% of the total) and opts for conventional cigarettes (96.8%), with poor adhesion to electronic cigarettes and warm tobaccos in the territory (0.6% and 0.2%, respectively). The report also points out that tobacco consumption is predominantly male: 21.6% of men over 15 are smokers, against only 3.3% of women.
The tobacco consumption rate has been decreasing since the entry into force of Law No. 5/2011, referring to the “Smoking Prevention and Control Scheme”. As the health services report describes, the law has been implementing, in phases, “measures to prohibit public enclosures and some outdoor public establishments”, as well as promoting “dissemination and education on tobacco harms, encouraging them to move away from tobacco” and stop smoking “as soon as possible”. Awareness work also warns of the impact this habit has on the health of the smokers in the second or third hand, especially in vulnerable groups such as children or the elderly.
Consciousness measures were well received by the population of Macau, according to the data published by health services. Throughout the year 2023, 16.2% of smokers sought to cease the habit, especially those who identified themselves as “occasional smokers”. Regarding exposure to passive smoke, the report applauds “the increase in awareness of compliance with the law by the local population” and reveals annual decreases constant in the multiple aspects analyzed. Exposure to second hand smoke in closed restoration establishments was the one that registered a more pronounced decrease, from 93% in 2011 to 7.5% in 2023. In closed workplaces, the percentage went from 53.5% to 6.1% in the same period of twelve years. Passive exposure to smoke at home also decreased, although with less expression (from 30.3% to 13.8%).
 
Consumption rate increased among non -residents
 
Health services emphasize that current percentages are aligned with “the proposed objective of the reduction in the tobacco consumption rate from each country to 30% in 2025, compared to 2010, which demonstrates the effectiveness of implementing MPOWER measures [a set of six smoking control measures]”.
Still, the year 2023 was marked by the first increase in the consumption rate since the implementation of the smoking control law, from 11.1% last year of 2022 to those already mentioned 11.6%. Proceeding to an analysis for sexes, it is found that the increase was more significant in females (from 2.2% to 3.3%) than in male (from 21.5% to 21.6%).
This climb is mainly due to the smoking habits of workers and non-resident students living in Macao, as explained by a graph of health services in which the population is divided between the resident and the non-resident. With regard to the resident population of the territory, only female increased by 2.3% to 2.7%, and tobacco consumption in men dropped from 21.8% by 2022 to 19% by 2023.
 
Macau plans prohibition of electronic cigarette
 
The results of the report - available for consultation on the Electronic Health Services page - were presented and discussed in a seminar with the participation of representatives of various civic associations and smoking control. According to a statement from the Macao Health Authorities, participants in this meeting greeted the effectiveness of the measures already implemented and "presented many constructive opinions on future smoking control work."
In addition to the reinforcement of awareness campaigns already in force, the following suggestions were also proposed: “A study on the act of smoking authorized only in certain areas of some streets and squares, the prohibition of consumption of new tobacco products or other non -fashionable products (water pipes, herbal cigarettes), simple packaging for tobacco products, reinforcing the regulation of the regulation of the regulation of the regulation of the regulations. electronic cigarettes, among others ”.  The chief of in the prevention and control of alcohol and tobacco beverages, Lam Chong, also pointed out that one of the measures to be implemented in the future could even be the prohibition of possession of electronic cigarettes, although without establishing a deadline for their realization.
It is recalled that, last week, the director of the region for the Pacific-Width of WHO, Skirt Ma'u Piukala, visited Macau and praised the efforts of the territory to alleviate the problems caused by smoking. At the time, he left the suggestion of "adopting as soon as possible, the total prohibition of the electronic cigarette."
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 05:24:24</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 80% of the elderly use the internet</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/mais-de-80-dos-idosos-utilizam-a-internet/</link><description>The number of internet users in Macau has been growing over the years and at all age levels, but the most significant increase has been in the senior layer. According to the Board of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) last year, 81.3% of citizens over 65 years of age used internet services, and the percentage rose 3.5 percentage points compared to the previous year.
Overall, the Internet penetration rate in Macau is 94%, increasing 1.2 percentage points compared to 2023. The number of internet users in the region by 2024 was 610,300, plus 2.2%compared to year 2023. It is emphasized that 91.4%of users accessed the internet daily.
The DSEC further details that last year there were 200,200 household aggregates in Macau, representing 97.7% of total household aggregates (205,000), plus 0.4 percentage points, in annual terms. It is noteworthy that 99.4% (198,900) of household aggregates that accessed the internet used the mobile network, increasing 0.6 percentage points, compared to 2023.
Most users continued to access the Internet for communication or access to social networks (578,600), plus 1.6%, compared to 2023. Then came the users who accessed the Internet for entertainment purposes (547,300) and for online banking services (457,400), plus 20.3%and 1.8%, respectively. The number of internet users who used online government services (338,200) grew significantly (+21%, compared to 2023).
The number of internet users who made 'online' purchases (245,500) increased 3.3% compared to 2023. DSEC points out that online purchases of 'Take-Away' services and drinks (151,900 people) and clothes, shoes, suitcases, accessories, etc. (140,200 people) were made by more users. In terms of expense, the median online shopping expense was in 1,800 patacas in the fourth quarter of 2024, plus 20%, in annual terms. It is noteworthy that the median of online purchases of tourist services (5,000 patacas) remained the highest and similar to the year 2023.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 04:38:22</pubDate></item><item><title>At least 900 children displaced in northern Mozambique reintegrated in teaching</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/pelo-menos-900-criancas-deslocadas-no-norte-de-mocambique-reintegradas-no-ensino/</link><description>At least 900 children displaced in Cabo Delgado province, northern Mozambique, are being reinstated in the National Education System, under the accelerated education program for minors who have abandoned teaching due to terrorist attacks.
"These programs allow children to recover the time lost and the competences not developed at the right time, thus reaching colleagues of the same age and school level," said the director of education in Cabo Delgado, Afonso Sacume, during the Provincial Advisory Board.
Since October 2017, Cabo Delgado, rich in gas, faces an armed rebellion that has caused thousands of dead and a humanitarian crisis, with more than one million people displaced.
According to the Director of Education in Cabo Delgado Province, the Government Accelerated Education Program in 2024 is being implemented in the districts of Mueda, Ancuabe and Chiúre and aims to “improve the learning of displaced children”.
The official said the program aims to "recover the displaced children and outside the school and return them to the teaching of the National Education System and to satisfactorily integrate the displaced children through the recovery of time and lost skills."
In 2024 alone, at least 349 people died in attacks by Islamic extremist groups in the province, an increase of 36% over the previous year, according to data recently released by the Center for Strategic Studies of Africa, an academic institution of the US government department of the government that analyzes conflicts in Africa.
The last major attack took place on May 10 and 11, 2024, to the district headquarters of Macomia, with about a hundred rebels to plunder the village, causing several dead and strong combat with the Mozambican and military defense forces and Military Military, who support Mozambique to combat armed attacks.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 04:38:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Li Qiang promises to open more sectors from China's economy to foreign investment</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/li-qiang-promete-abrir-mais-sectores-da-economia-da-china-ao-investimento-estrangeiro/</link><description>Chinese prime minister has promised that China will open more sectors of the economy to foreign investment and "protect the legitimate rights and interests of all companies." The message was given in a speech given at the opening of the China Annual Development Forum in Beijing.
 
Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang has promised yesterday that China will open more sectors of the economy to foreign investment and "protect legitimate rights and interests from all companies."
The guarantee was given in a speech given at the opening of the China Annual Development Forum in Beijing, which was attended by important business leaders. Li emphasized the commitment of the Chinese regime to “economic opening” and also asked international companies to resist protectionism. "We hope entrepreneurs will bear more active measures to maintain globalization," said Beijing government number two.
Li also stated that he expects business leaders to “work together, cooperate and achieve greater development of (…) companies for mutual benefit”. "The Chinese government will strive to protect the legitimate rights and interests of all companies," regardless of the nationality of the owners, promised the prime minister.
The Forum is attended by executives from multinational companies such as Mercedes-Benz and Samsung, including US Technology CEO Apple, Tim Cook.
Beijing for months has been trying to restore consumer and business confidence, which has been weakened by a persistent crisis in the real estate sector and new commercial tensions with the United States.
I read Qiang said Beijing is prepared for “unexpected external impacts,” referring to the trade war triggered by US President Donald Trump. “Estamos preparados para choques inesperados, que, claro, vêm sobretudo do estrangeiro. O Governo chinês terá políticas em vigor para garantir o bom funcionamento da sua economia”, disse Li.
The leader has promised that China will continue in the “right direction of globalization” in the face of the growing fragmentation of the world economy as the trade war with the US intensifies. "As a large responsible country, China will remain firmly on the right side of history (…) [practicing] true multilateralism," Li said at a meeting with leaders of multinational companies in Beijing.
China "will follow the correct direction of economic globalization, will practice true multilateralism and strive to be a force of stability and certainty," Li said, adding that "the fragmentation of the global economy is intensifying," while "instability and uncertainty are increasing."
Beijing retaliated with additional customs of up to 15% on US agricultural products, including wheat, soy and cow meat, in response to additional 20% rates that the US began to apply on Chinese imports. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 05:19:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau can be affected by 5 to 8 tropical storms this year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/24/macau-pode-ser-afectado-por-5-a-8-tempestades-tropicais-este-ano/</link><description>The territory of Macao may be affected by about five to eight tropical storms throughout this year, especially during the typhoons that will begin around June and end in October. According to an informative note published on the Electronic page of the Meteorological and Geophysical Services Directorate (SMG), it is possible that "some" of the tropical storms planned for this year reach the "tuffal level of severe or higher", known as "Super Typhoon".
The most recent maritime observations and predictions indicate that the climate phenomenon “La Niña” is “slowly slowing”, and it is foreseen that it stabilizes and returns to the “normal state” in the end of spring. The average temperature of the rainy season, between April and September, will be “normal to relatively high”, with “normal” accumulated precipitation levels. Also the number of tropical storms planned for this year is between the "normal to high" indicators.
The SMG point out that the year 2024 has been the hottest since 1952, along with 2019. In addition to increasing average temperatures, global warming has resulted in more frequent and intense meteorological phenomena in recent years. It is recalled, for example, that in November last year four storms occurred simultaneously in the northwest of the Pacific Ocean, three of which entered the Southern Sea of ​​China and fustomed Macao at the same time, “establishing a record” in the region.
SMG Signal Signs Hsating Statistics, covering a large period between 1968 and 2023, allow you to conclude that the frequency and intensity of the tuffles in the territory have been intensified from 2008, the year in which four signal tropical storms have been accounted for - the maximum number so far registered with 1993 and 2022.
In 2017, with Typhoon Hato, records related to speed and wind gusts (132 km/h and 217km/h, respectively). The following year of 2018 broke a new record, when signal 8 remained raised for an unprecedented period of 138 hours. In parallel, the dates of the first and last signs of tuft signals have been widening, starting soon and ending later. In 2008, the first sign of tropical storm was released on April 17, and by 2022 the alert period was extended until almost the end of the year on December 20.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 04:38:23</pubDate></item></channel></rss>