<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/pelo-menos-22-mortos-apos-queda-de-guindaste-sobre-comboio-na-tailandia/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Jimmy O. Yang responds to demand with extra show for Chinese New Year in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/jimmy-o-yang-responde-a-procura-com-espectaculo-extra-para-o-ano-novo-chines-em-macau/</link><description>High demand for tickets has led to a change of plans for the Chinese New Year celebrations at Galaxy Arena. Jimmy O. Yang, the Chinese-American comedian and actor, announced the addition of a second session to his special show, which will now take place not only on the 21st, but also on the 22nd of February. The decision comes after the success of his last tour of the territory.

The calendar of events for the Year of the Horse received a last-minute boost. Jimmy O. Yang, the international comedy star, will perform not one, but two shows at the Galaxy Arena during the Chinese New Year celebrations. The announcement of an extra session for February 22nd comes as a direct response to the rapid demand for tickets for the original date, scheduled for February 21st.
This is not the first time that the comedian has captivated Macau audiences. In July 2025, its six screenings at the Broadway Theater sold out completely in a short space of time, attracting more than 13,000 people. Now, the move to the grander Galaxy Arena, with capacity for 16,000 spectators, and the addition of a second date extends his rise as one of the most sought-after comedy voices in the region.
Jimmy O. Yang's story is one of cultural resilience and perseverance. Born Au Yeung Man-sing in Hong Kong, to Shanghainese parents, his move to Los Angeles at the age of 13 was a remarkable experience that, according to him, almost made him lose his childhood memories. Today, he masters four languages, English, Cantonese, Mandarin and Shanghainese, a skill that has become a pillar of his global appeal. Although he pursued an economics course to satisfy his parents' expectations, his path changed after hearing an inspiring speech about “following your dreams”. He abandoned an internship in finance to enter the precarious world of comedy, working as a used car salesman and a DJ at a strip club.
His moment came with the role of Jian-Yang in the HBO series Silicon Valley in 2014. However, early success did not come with financial stability; During the break between the first and second seasons, Yang worked as an Uber driver in Los Angeles, driving a used Toyota Prius purchased with his first salary from the actors' union. A key turning point in his career and his perception of the industry was the film “Crazy Rich Asians” in 2018, which he described as “the first production where I wasn’t the only Asian face on set.” His career continued to evolve, culminating in starring roles and an influence that saw him stage a triumphant return tour to Hong Kong in 2025, including five sold-out events at the Hong Kong Coliseum and Macau.
The new show, titled “Galaxy Macau Presents: Jimmy O. Yang's Chinese New Year Show”, appears in a festive tone that goes beyond the traditional 'stand-up'. The production will include live musical performances and will feature special guests, namely singer and rapper Jackson Wang and Hong Kong comedian Wan Kwong, ensuring a varied and dynamic evening.
Tickets for the new session on February 22nd, which falls on a Sunday, starting at 6pm, will go on public sale on December 29th, 2025. Prices remain between 380 and 880 patacas, with a limit of four tickets per transaction. The original session on February 21st, on Saturday, at 8pm, tickets for which went on sale on December 19th, is already sold out, with now only one opportunity to attend one of the most anticipated events of the festive season.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Trade between Brazil and China grows to record value in 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/comercio-entre-brasil-e-china-cresce-para-valor-recorde-em-2025/</link><description>Trade between Brazil and China grew 8.2% year-on-year in 2025, to a record value of 171 billion dollars, according to data released yesterday by the Brazil-China Business Council (CEBC). China remained Brazil's main trading partner, far surpassing the United States, with which bilateral trade totaled US$83 billion in the same period. According to the CEBC, the Brazilian trade surplus with China was 29.1 billion dollars, equivalent to 43% of the country's entire positive balance with the world.
The growth of Brazilian exports was mainly driven by the agricultural and extractive sector. The sale of crude oil to China alone reached a value of 20 billion dollars, with a record volume of 44 million tons – representing 45% of all oil exported by Brazil.
Soy exports totaled US$34.5 billion, while beef exports grew by almost 48%, reaching US$8.8 billion, also a record. In contrast, chicken and pork sales fell 53% and 36%, respectively.
On the import side, the acquisition of a platform for oil exploration worth US$2.66 billion stood out. Purchases of hybrid cars also increased by 25%, totaling US$1.87 billion. On the other hand, 100% electric vehicles suffered a 37% drop in imports.
China was also the main supplier of manufacturing goods to Brazil, with emphasis on fertilizers, chemical and pharmaceutical products, the latter with a 39% growth in purchases, driven especially by insulin-based medicines.
Among Brazilian states, Rio de Janeiro led exports to China for the third consecutive year, with 18.1 billion dollars, 94% of which came from oil sales.
With the new data, the Brazil – China trade chain represented 27.2% of all Brazilian foreign trade in 2025, consolidating the importance of China in the South American country's trade balance.</description><pubDate>2026-01-15 00:14:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Free daycare scheme received 22 applications in two days</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/regime-de-gratuitidade-de-creches-recebeu-22-inscricoes-em-dois-dias/</link><description>The “Free Daycare Scheme for Children from Families in Vulnerable Situations”, launched by the Institute of Social Action (IAS) on January 12th, received 22 applications in just two days. Families that meet the requirements can submit their application until January 23rd.

The Institute of Social Action (IAS)'s free daycare program for disadvantaged families has already received 22 applications since its launch last Monday. Applications remain open until January 23rd.
The registration process for the “Free Daycare Scheme for Children from Families in Vulnerable Situations”, promoted by IAS in cooperation with more than 30 subsidized daycare centers in Macau, began on 12 January. The Chinese channel Radio Macau reports that, in just two days, 22 applications for registration were received – with seven applications already formalized by the IAS.
Cited by the same source, the director of Creche Fai Chi Kei, Ng Fei Lei, informed that the three daycare centers affiliated with Cáritas Macau – including Creche Vamos a Brincar and Creche Cáritas – had a total of 555 places for the current academic year 2025/2026. Within the occupancy rate of approximately 65%, only 3% of places were occupied by children from disadvantaged families.
According to the official, the Government program should result in an increase in the number of registrations and “relieve the pressure on families” in Macau, especially those in vulnerable situations. However, he makes a suggestion: the program's registration period, scheduled to end on January 23rd, should be extended to the entire year. Some guardians interviewed by Rádio Macau also proposed extending the opening hours of daycare centers covered by the initiative, in order to reinforce support for families in which both parents work.
At the beginning of the year, the Government announced the launch of a free daycare scheme aimed at children from families experiencing economic difficulties. Applicant children must be residents of the Macao SAR, under the age of three and come from single-parent families, consisting only of grandparents and grandchildren, beneficiaries of the regular IAS subsidy or in which one of the members suffers from a chronic illness or disability.
In a statement, the IAS clarifies that the household's total monthly income cannot exceed a certain maximum limit, calculated depending on the number of household members. For families with two members, the maximum limit is 19,975 patacas; for three members, 27,550 patacas; for four, 33,475 patacas; for five, 37,800 patacas; for six, 42,125 patacas; for seven, 46,450 patacas; for eight or more elements, 50,675 patacas.
Eligible families can access the IAS website until 6pm on January 22nd to complete and print the request form, which must then be delivered, together with the required documents, to the organization's headquarters or one of the subordinate Social Action Centers by 6pm on January 23rd.
In total, there are 38 daycare centers that participate in the IAS program: 14 located in the parish of Nossa Senhora de Fátima, six in the parish of Sé, five in the parish of Santo António, four in the parish of São Lourenço, one in the parish of São Lázaro and eight on the islands (seven in Taipa and one in Coloane).</description><pubDate>2026-01-15 00:21:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau teachers warn about the weakness of AI in correcting students’ work</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/professores-de-macau-alertam-para-fragilidade-de-ia-na-correccao-de-trabalhos-dos-alunos/</link><description>Macau teachers believe that artificial intelligence can help reduce the workload, but warn of the weaknesses of this technology. The local authorities, remember, recently announced the launch, in the next academic year, of “a localized service platform, within the scope of artificial intelligence teaching”.

Macau teachers recognize that artificial intelligence (AI) can help reduce the workload, but warn of the weaknesses of this technology, particularly when used to correct students' work. Authorities in the region recently announced the launch, in the next academic year, of “a localized service platform, within the scope of artificial intelligence teaching”.
This tool will include functions such as “intelligent composition of statements, intelligent correction and other functions, with a view to reducing the workload of teachers, from class preparation to assessment”.
Although they are in favor of the platform, teachers highlighted the current limitations of the technology. “Using AI to classify work may result in errors that require manual correction,” said Ruan Zhanpeng, information technology teacher at Pui Va Secondary School.
Ruan acknowledged that AI can reduce the workload in “correcting simple multiple-choice questions, but for open-ended questions, manual adjustments are still required.”
Chinese teacher Nora Lam, from Escola dos Moradores de Macau, has the same opinion regarding the limitations of AI when it comes to issues that require development. “A review is necessary after correcting a composition made by AI, because it cannot understand texts based on feelings”, he said.
Pedro Lobo, a teacher with more than 30 years of experience in information technologies in the territory, revealed that he has used AI as a “starting point in preparing classes and materials for students”. The Portuguese agrees that it can be a good tool for teachers, but emphasizes the need for training. “For teachers who don’t speak Chinese, I have hardly seen any training,” he told Lusa.
The Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) stated that, for the current academic year, it will provide at least 10 hours of training for information technology teachers and at least six hours for teachers of other subjects. “In the 2025/2026 academic year, around three thousand training places and more than 51,800 teaching hours were made available to teachers in the information technology discipline and around nine thousand training places and more than 355 thousand teaching hours were made available to teachers in other subjects”, said DSEDJ in a written response to a question from deputy Ella Lei on strategies to reduce teachers' workload. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-15 00:19:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippine leader wants to negotiate with Portugal for repatriation of former deputy accused of corruption</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/lider-filipino-quer-negociar-com-portugal-repatriacao-de-ex-deputado-acusado-de-corrupcao/</link><description>The Philippine President has ordered the country's government to explore all options for Elizaldy Salcedo Co to be repatriated from Portugal, where the former congressman is believed to be living, according to the Philippine press.

Better known as Zaldy Co, former party deputy Ako Bicol is the target of an arrest warrant for alleged involvement in the scandal of “ghost projects” of infrastructure for flood control.
Dozens of construction company owners, government officials and elected representatives across the archipelago are accused of embezzling funds or executing substandard projects.
In addition to facing three criminal cases arising from the corruption scandal, Zaldy Co also made explosive allegations in a series of videos accusing Marcos Jr. and his cousin, former speaker of the Philippine House of Representatives Martin Romualdez, of receiving billions of pesos in bribes, according to the Philippine newspaper Inquirer.
Interior Secretary Jonvic Remulla said on Tuesday that President Ferdinand Marcos Jr.'s directive orders it to be verified whether Zaldy Co can be extradited from Portugal, where he is believed to be located. "We are still studying the case because the situation is complicated. We don't have an extradition treaty [with Portugal], but there are other routes that we can follow and that he wants to investigate," Remulla said, according to the English-language Philippine newspaper.
The Government, continued the official, is considering other options, including coordination with the International Criminal Police Organization (Interpol), the UN and other international agencies, he added. "An [extradition] treaty would take too long. A treaty takes years and years to conclude. Therefore, the other possible routes, as instructed by the President, are about how we can carry out his extradition without going through a treaty", he said on Tuesday.
Through repatriation, the Inquirer also states, a person can be returned to their country of origin by choice or by force. In the case of extradition, “it is a legal process in which a country delivers a person accused or convicted of a crime to another country to face trial or punishment”.
The newspaper also recalls that the Department of Foreign Affairs (DFA) canceled Co's Philippine passport on December 10 last year, on the order of an anti-corruption court. Remulla, however, stressed that Co may also be using a Portuguese passport obtained many years ago.
According to the DFA, the Philippine Embassy in Lisbon has not yet received information about Co's whereabouts or any confirmation from the Portuguese Government that it actually granted the former deputy a passport.
Leila de Lima, a deputy from the Mamamayang Liberal party, also said on Tuesday that the Marcos government should negotiate with Portugal on the deportation of Co to the Philippines, instead of working on an extradition treaty “which requires much more effort and more time”. “Deportation can be negotiated diplomatically immediately, even without the formality of concluding an extradition treaty”, said Leila de Lima, noting that “an extradition treaty is not indispensable for the return of a fugitive to the country”.
Among the suspects are allies and opponents of Marcos Jr. At stake are 9,855 drainage control projects, valued at more than 545 billion Philippine pesos (eight billion euros), which should have been built since Marcos took power, in mid-2022.
In September, Philippine Finance Minister Ralph Recto admitted that, since 2023, 118.5 billion pesos (around 1.75 billion euros) may have been embezzled. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-15 00:13:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Curatorial course brings Delfim Sardo to the Art Museum</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/curso-de-curadoria-traz-delfim-sardo-ao-museu-de-arte/</link><description>The universe behind the exhibition. As a major retrospective of Portuguese artist Helena Almeida opens in Macau, the Art Museum offers a rare glimpse into the intellectual process that shapes a contemporary art exhibition. In an intensive workshop, the exhibition's chief curator, professor and theorist Delfim Sardo, will share his reflections on the art of creating visual narratives, in an event that goes beyond technique and discusses the social role of curation itself.

The Macau Museum of Art (MAM) is the new meeting point for a deep dive into the mind of one of the most influential thinkers of Portuguese contemporary art. On January 18th, the MAM auditorium hosts a “Contemporary Art Curation Workshop” led by Delfim Sardo, the curator of the exhibition “Helena Almeida: I'm Here – Presença and Resonance”, on view at MAM from January 23rd. The session, free and with limited places, invites curators, artists, students and enthusiasts to a six-hour dialogue about the principles and challenges of designing exhibitions in the 21st century.
Delfim Sardo is a curator and pivotal figure in the world of art, with a career that spans academia, writing, criticism and cultural management. Professor at the Faculty of Fine Arts of the University of Lisbon, where he coordinates a master's degree in Curatorial Studies, Sardo brings a unique background to Macau. He was administrator of the Centro Cultural de Belém, visual arts programmer at Culturgest and, most notably, the curator of the Portuguese Representation at the 1999 Venice Biennale. His approach to curating is often described as an exercise in writing “deep essays in space”, where the arrangement of works challenges viewers to rethink the public role of art.
The workshop comes at a particularly fertile moment for cultural dialogue in Macau. It functions as an academic and practical extension of Helena Almeida's own exhibition, which opens on January 23rd. The retrospective, the first large-scale one in Asia dedicated to the Portuguese artist (1934-2018), will serve as a living case study. Sardo promises to go beyond the simple presentation of concepts, delving into practical analyzes of curatorial strategies, case studies and the concrete challenges of materializing an artistic vision in the same space in which Almeida's exhibition lives.
This is an opportunity for the local artistic community to experience up close the currents of thought of the European avant-garde. The event, to be conducted in English, was designed to encourage dialogue and the exchange of ideas, with space for questions and discussions. Registration, open since January 6, is done through the Macau Single Account system, with admission to be decided today by draw.
Sardo's presence in Macau extends beyond the workshop. The day after the opening of the exhibition, on January 24th, the curator will return to the MAM auditorium for a special conference entitled “Helena Almeida and Dialogue on Contemporary Art”, followed by an open conversation with the public and co-curators of the exhibition. This series of events is part of MAM's programming that aims to enrich the exhibition experience with educational programs that deepen the context and critical thinking behind the works presented, among other events of a similar nature.
The exhibition “Helena Almeida: I’m Here – Presence and Resonance” will be on display until April 26th. At the same time, the exhibition “Resonância – Corpo. Objecto. Reflexão” will present works by six artists from China and Macau invited to dialogue with Almeida's legacy. Together with the “Contemporary Art Curation Workshop”, these exhibitions and activities introduce the life of a fundamental artist, the experience of an essential curator and make Macau a center for the expansion of Art in the Portuguese-speaking world. The transnational curatorial reflection meeting takes place between 10:00 am and 5:30 pm, in the auditorium of the Macau Museum of Art.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>New law may affect bus services in housing complexes</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/nova-lei-pode-afectar-servicos-de-autocarros-de-ligacao-nos-complexos-habitacionais/</link><description>Bus services connecting housing complexes in Macau may be impacted due to the law on the activity of travel agencies and the tourist guide profession, which will come into force next month.
Some housing complexes in the territory of Taipa and Coloane, such as Jardins do Oceano and One Oasis, offer transport services to residents, with the operation of some of these services being awarded to travel agencies.
However, the new law clarifies that services provided by travel agencies can only be for tourism purposes, in addition to carrying out religious, charitable, sporting, cultural or academic activities when they are acquired by religious associations and other legal entities or non-profit institutions, as well as by schools and higher education institutions. The other exception is when they are acquired by public services or entities in the pursuit of their responsibilities.
The Macau Property Management Association, speaking to Radio Macau in Chinese, revealed that, according to information received, “several” large housing complexes in Taipa have already suspended connecting bus services because of the new law.
"Property management companies are communicating with their respective condominium owners to find legal alternatives to provide similar services to residents. They are also communicating with the Directorate of Tourism Services (DST) and other competent authorities to find viable plans so that transport services can continue", he highlighted. The Association also hopes that the Government will provide more support to the property management sector to study and help provide transport services in housing complexes in order to meet the needs of residents.</description><pubDate>2026-01-15 00:17:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Young man from Macau selected for UN gastronomic program</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/jovem-de-macau-seleccionado-para-programa-gastronomico-da-onu/</link><description>Daniel Chio, a young aspiring chef from the Galaxy Macau team, was selected for the “Young Chefs Program” (YCP), coordinated by the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO) and the World Food Forum (WFF).
In a statement released yesterday, the resort highlights that this is “a notable achievement for Galaxy and for Chio”, who thus becomes “the first and only young chef representing Macau to receive this honor”.
The United Nations initiative involves the selection of ten young chefs from around the world, aged between 18 and 35, who come together to “transform agri-food systems through sustainable culinary practices”. The basic purpose is to “train the next generation of culinary leaders and promote sustainable consumption and production patterns around the world”.
Daniel Chio will join the 2026 team of the program, which runs from this January until the same month of next year. Galaxy adds that the young man will receive guidance from the World Association of Chefs Societies, will participate in 16 to 20 hours of online activities per month and will represent Macau in high-level international food forums, in order to further improve his skills and knowledge regarding sustainable gastronomy.
According to the statement, the young man has more than ten years of experience in haute cuisine and is currently 'sous chef' at Galaxy, guided by a philosophy of zero waste and prioritizing organic food. “The company has been providing Chio and the entire culinary team with various training opportunities and professional development guidance to improve their specialized knowledge in sustainable gastronomy”, emphasizes the resort.
Quoted in the statement, Daniel Chio expressed gratitude for the “continuous support and development of the company” and confessed that being selected for this international program is “a great incentive” for his career. “I will apply what I learned to show the world Macau’s creative and responsible gastronomic culture, contributing to a healthier and more sustainable future in the restaurant sector”, he guaranteed.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Government will use 30 plots of land for parking, leisure areas and sports facilities</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/governo-vai-aproveitar-30-terrenos-para-estacionamento-zonas-de-lazer-e-instalacoes-desportivas/</link><description>Currently, the Government has a total of 39 unused plots of land at its disposal and yesterday it was announced that 30 of them already have a defined destination. Thirteen will be for the creation of leisure areas and 12 for car parks, for example. The information was shared by the Executive during a meeting with the Monitoring Committee for Land Affairs and Public Concessions of the Legislative Assembly (AL).

The Government indicated yesterday, during a meeting with the Monitoring Committee for Land Affairs and Public Concessions of the Legislative Assembly (AL), that 30 of the 39 unused lands already have a defined destination.
After the meeting, deputies Ella Lei and Joey Lao informed that the Government informed them that it will soon release these 30 plots of land for temporary use. Thirteen of them for temporary leisure areas, 12 for outdoor parking for light and heavy vehicles, one for sports facilities, one for an environmental protection and leisure center, and three for other mixed-use developments.
When the plans are implemented, it is expected that more than 1,000 parking spaces for light private vehicles will be added in Macau, said AL representatives cited by Jornal Ou Mun.
These unused land are located in several areas, including the creation of temporary parking lots in the parish of Santo António, where the demand for parking is high, implementing the principle of “developing new areas without forgetting the old ones” and satisfying the needs of citizens.
Some of these 30 plots of land are already ready for their design plan and then construction to be drawn up. Others will still need to be cleaned. Three of the plots of land being prepared are located in the Nam Van Lake area and the Transport and Public Works authority had already indicated that they would be used for a “padding embankment, in order to eliminate the emerging risk of stagnant water in the long term”, and a “city view” for use by citizens. The reuse of these three recovered plots of land in the city center will alleviate the pressure of the flow of people in the surrounding areas and also raise the image of the tourist city of Macau, “realizing the rational use of soil resources”.
The Executive guaranteed that it will proceed with the projects “in an orderly manner, seeking to make them available to the public as quickly as possible”.
Last year, the Government began the design and construction of three open-air parking lots on unused land, two ecological leisure areas, three temporary sports facilities and a fast charging station, said Ella Lei.</description><pubDate>2026-01-15 00:21:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Zika virus case diagnosed</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/diagnosticado-caso-do-virus-zika/</link><description>The Health Services registered, on Tuesday, an imported case of Zika virus infection, this being the first imported case registered this year in Macau.
The patient is a 53-year-old man, resident of Macau who traveled with his family to Malaysia between December 20th and January 6th. On January 9th, he developed symptoms of fever, muscle pain and rash, and last Monday he went to Centro Hospitalar Conde de São Januário due to the persistence of his symptoms. On Tuesday, Zika virus infection was confirmed in the blood sample for laboratory analysis. Currently, the patient is in a stable clinical condition and his cohabitants and travel companions are not showing any discomfort, informed the Health Services.
This disease is transmitted mainly by the bite of certain mosquitoes, although there are other forms of transmission, including sexual contact, blood transfusion and from mother to fetus. Authorities explain that most people infected with the Zika virus are asymptomatic, but the most common symptoms include fever, rash, conjunctivitis, muscle and joint pain and headaches, among others, with symptoms generally being mild. Zika virus disease has received attention in the past because of microcephaly in newborns.
Zika virus disease is transmitted mainly by the Aedes Aegypti mosquito. To date, no Aedes Aegypti mosquitoes have been found in Macau. The most common Aedes mosquito in Macau is the Aedes Albopictus mosquito, which can transmit dengue fever and chikungunya fever. Therefore, the risk of continued transmission of the respective case in Macau is considered low.
The Health Services point out that Zika virus disease can be transmitted through sexual contact or from mother to fetus. Therefore, “pregnant women or those planning to become pregnant should practice safe sex or avoid sexual intercourse when traveling to affected areas, taking precautions against mosquito bites to reduce the risk of infection”, warn the authorities.</description><pubDate>2026-01-15 00:17:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau has the 32nd strongest passport in the world</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/macau-tem-o-32-o-passaporte-mais-forte-do-mundo/</link><description>The most recent Henley Passport Index (HPI) report placed Macau in 32nd place in the ranking of the most powerful passports in the world in 2026, directly above Taiwan, with visa-free access to 141 destinations. As last year, the list continues to be topped by Singapore, while Afghanistan remains in last place. In turn, the Portuguese passport was evaluated as the fifth strongest in the world.

Macau ranked 32nd in the Henley Passport Index (HPI), which every year evaluates each passport based on the number of countries and territories to which it is possible to travel without a visa. The Macau passport allows visa-free entry to 141 destinations – four fewer than last year, when it ranked 31st on the list.
Despite the slight drop compared to 2025, this year's position is the second highest since 2014 – when Macau reached 30th place – and the third highest since the HPI began compiling data in 2006. The worst position occurred in 2010, when the passport weakened to 44th place, with a significant recovery from 2013 onwards.
Macau passport holders can travel to 141 destinations without needing a visa in 2026, four fewer than in 2025 and three fewer than in 2024. Among the list of territories that require the presentation of a visa are names such as Angola, Canada, São Tomé and Príncipe or the United States of America.
Macau appears in the global ranking of 199 passports between Peru, in 31st position with 142 destinations without visa requirements, and the province of Taiwan, in 33rd position with 139 destinations. China appears further down the list, in 59th place, with visa-free access to 81 destinations. It should be noted that this is China's best position ever in two decades: the previous record was set last year, when it reached number 60.
The Hong Kong region appears in 15th place, the third best position ever in the ranking after 2013 (14th place) and 2006 (13th place). Currently, Hong Kong passport holders have access to 171 countries and territories without needing to apply for a visa.
Looking outside China, it can be seen that the Portuguese passport is one of the strongest in the world. It is positioned in 5th place, the same position as other countries such as Hungary, Slovakia, Slovenia and the United Arab Emirates, with visa-free entry guaranteed in 184 destinations.
First place continues to belong to Singapore, which has maintained leadership since 2024 and which since 2018 has alternated between 1st and 2nd place. The number of 'visa-free' destinations is the largest among all passports in the ranking: 192. Next on the podium are Japan and South Korea, both in 2nd place with access to 188 destinations, and Denmark, Luxembourg, Spain, Sweden and Switzerland, tied in 3rd place with 186 destinations.
On the opposite side of the table, Afghanistan remains in last place (101st) with only 24 countries and territories that it can access without the need for a visa. Other of the world's weakest passports include Syria (in 100th place), Iraq (99th) and Yemen and Pakistan (equal in 98th place).
On the official HPI page, it is said that this is “the original and most reliable classification of all passports in the world, according to the number of destinations that their holders can visit without a prior visa”. The index includes 199 passports and 227 travel destinations, organized according to “exclusive data” from the International Air Transport Authority (IATA).
“With historical data spanning 20 years and regularly updated expert analysis on the latest changes in passport power, the index is an invaluable resource for global citizens and the standard reference tool for government policy in this field,” highlights Henley &amp; Partners, the company responsible for the index.</description><pubDate>2026-01-15 00:22:15</pubDate></item><item><title>SJM presents gastronomic offerings for the Chinese Year of the Horse</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/sjm-apresenta-ofertas-gastronomicas-do-ano-chines-do-cavalo/</link><description>SJM Resorts released its Chinese Year of the Horse gastronomic collections yesterday, curated by the culinary teams at Palace Garden, The Eight and Chalou restaurants. The delicacies consist of traditional New Year's dishes, packaged in gift boxes with themed illustrations.
A primeira colecção é composta por três bolos festivos centrados na cozinha cantonesa, cada um deles personalizado com os sabores característicos dos três restaurantes que aderiram à iniciativa.
The next collection, “SJM Collection – “Majestic Celebration", features festive tones and a galloping horse on its packaging, alluding to the vitality of the Fire Horse. The available flavors suit all tastes and diets: there is an aged tangerine peel cake and rice pudding with Pu'er tea, a traditional turnip cake with Cantonese-style preserved meat and a vegetarian cake with chestnut, sweet potato and taro. The menu also features a “Double Delight” for the most indecisive, which combines the tangerine peel cake and the vegetarian cake.
The “Blossoming Delights” collection is based on the decor of the Palace Garden restaurant to present gift boxes adorned with floral motifs and a menu inspired by imperial cuisine. The offerings consist of a ‘premium’ bird’s nest pudding with almond essence and a turnip cake with matsutake mushroom and preserved meat.
This is followed by the “Golden Treasures” collection, based on symbols of prosperity and success (such as, for example, the image of the iconic “8”) and the culinary principles of The Eight restaurant. The menu consists of a bird's nest pudding with coconut cream and a turnip cake with conpoy and preserved meat, cooked in fish broth.
Specially designed with family gatherings in mind, SJM also prepared two selections of 'poon choi': one made with South African abalone, goose foot, fish fin, sun-dried oysters and prawns and another consisting of braised abalone, dried Japanese conpoy, dried Japanese oysters and free-range chicken.
As Chinese New Year is a time of togetherness and sharing, SJM restaurants have designed two “Majestic Celebration” gift baskets to offer to family or close friends. Each of the baskets includes delicacies such as mushrooms, tea, bottles of wine and themed soft toys and red envelopes. All of these offers are available for pre-order until February 16th.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Hong Kong leader promises to “get to the bottom” of social housing fire</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/lider-de-hong-kong-promete-ir-ao-fundo-de-incendio-em-habitacao-social/</link><description>Hong Kong's Chief Executive yesterday promised to "get to the bottom" of the deadly fire in Tai Po, hold those responsible accountable and find long-term solutions to house those affected, the public broadcaster reported.

According to RTHK, John Lee indicated to the Legislative Council (LegCo) that post-disaster recovery work is an “urgent task”, with the Executive presenting a motion of support at the first meeting of parliament.
The Government, the person responsible told deputies, “will finalize the long-term accommodation plan for the affected families as quickly as possible, so that they can settle in their new homes soon”. Lee assured that those responsible for the November 26 tragedy will be held accountable. “The police authorities and the independent committee will leave no stone unturned,” he said, promising to “get to the bottom of this issue.” “Those who must be held accountable, whether they are public servants or not and regardless of their level, will be held accountable according to the facts,” he added.
The fire in the Wang Fuk Court residential complex, which is undergoing repair work, started when the net covering the bamboo structures between the ground floor and the first floor of the Wang Cheong House block caught fire. The fire spread with unusual speed to the rest of the complex, hitting six other towers and killing a total of 161 people.
Also yesterday, the Chief Executive revealed the expectations he has in relation to the LegCo deputies, elected on December 7th, shortly after the fire. “I will be happy to hear your opinions, whether you agree with the Government or not,” he said.
These were the second elections since the electoral reform introduced in 2021 at the behest of Beijing, which reduced the seats elected by universal suffrage from 35 to 20, increased the weight of non-direct mechanisms and transformed the ballot into a vote in which “only patriotic (candidates)” can compete.
The vote took place without the two main pro-democracy parties: the Civic Party, dissolved in 2023, and the Democratic Party, in decline.
Although the Executive initially considered the possibility of postponing the elections after the fire and the three days of mourning and suspension of campaign activities that followed, it ended up deciding to keep them on the scheduled date.
Authorities argued that carrying out suffrage demonstrates institutional maturity and that the process can coexist with respect for victims and emergency management.
In total, 161 candidates competed for 90 seats: 51 in territorial constituencies, 60 in functional constituencies and 50 designated by the Electoral Commission, dominated by profiles close to the Chinese central government.
Functional constituencies represent professional groups, commercial sectors or specific special interests and only voters registered in these sectors can vote for them, which has raised criticism for the limited representation in favor of corporate interests and elites. "When you disagree with government policies, please point out the problems and make recommendations and suggestions. We will consider your suggestions seriously. When we are doing the right thing, please be fair to us," said Lee, as quoted by RTHK.
The Chief Executive also indicated that legislators must speak based on facts and filter out misinformation when addressing the public. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-15 00:15:11</pubDate></item><item><title>IAS received eight family conciliation requests in two weeks</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/ias-recebeu-oito-pedidos-de-conciliacao-familiar-em-duas-semanas/</link><description>The Social Action Institute received eight requests for family conciliation in two weeks since the new conciliation regime for family matters came into force in Macau. The authorities have appointed 48 family conciliators to monitor a possible increase in cases, and intend to recruit more social workers qualified as conciliators through training.

The conciliation regime for family cases came into force on January 1st of this year and, in two weeks, the Social Action Institute (IAS) has already received eight requests for mediation services.
The information was shared yesterday by Lei Lai Peng, head of the Family and Community Services Department of the IAS, on the “Fórum Macau” program on the Chinese channel Rádio Macau. The official also indicated that they received more than 30 requests for information about the new regime, most of which were forwarded by other departments.
The eight formal family conciliation requests concerned contested divorce, exercise of parental authority, provision of maintenance and matters relating to the family's home. The applicants were between 30 and 59 years old, with 75% of the applicants in the cases being women. "After the service request is approved, the IAS will appoint a conciliator within six days, and the conciliator will convene the first conciliation conference within 20 days. The entire conciliation process generally requires 60 days to complete," explained Lei Lai Peng.
The IAS, therefore, must issue the applicant a certificate of conciliation, within five working days, after having received the conciliation report or the reconciliation agreement drawn up by the family conciliator.
Under the conciliation regime for family matters, the IAS is also the competent entity responsible for appointing a family conciliator. According to Lei Lai Peng, the current IAS list already has 48 family conciliators, of which 25 are IAS conciliators and 23 come from community organizations, including the General Women's Association of Macau, the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau and the Marital and Family Relations Support Center of the Catholic Family Support Movement of Macau.
The authorities have so far organized eight professional training sessions for these family conciliators, which covered legal knowledge and practices, aiming to expand the number of qualified social workers who become family conciliators through training programs.
The IAS recalled that conciliation for family matters does not cover the distribution of assets, but conciliators would help the parties analyze subsistence, education, health and other expenses to clarify the provision of maintenance. “However, the final decision is determined by the agreement reached between the parties”, he highlighted.
With regard to cases involving domestic violence, the IAS pointed out that conciliators have the duty to communicate the situation to the authorities, and must immediately monitor the situation of the family in question and take emergency measures in critical cases.
If domestic violence is identified before the start of conciliation, according to Lei Lai Peng, conciliators must carry out a professional assessment and, if the circumstances meet the legal criteria, the conciliation process can be terminated and the process would proceed directly to the contested divorce.
The IAS, in this case, understands that, regarding family causes, family conflicts involve family morals and can be resolved, harmoniously, through family mediation, while the new conciliation regime offers a “more harmonious way to resolve disputes”. “Before divorce, it is recommended to have frank communication with your spouse, seek psychological support and evaluate post-divorce issues, such as parental authority over minors, payment of maintenance and family housing arrangements”, states the IAS.</description><pubDate>2026-01-15 00:20:26</pubDate></item><item><title>New matching sessions will make 309 more job offers available</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/novas-sessoes-de-emparelhamento-vao-disponibilizar-mais-309-ofertas-de-emprego/</link><description>The Labor Affairs Bureau (DSAL) and the Federation of Macau Workers' Association (FAOM) will organize four more job matching sessions until the end of January, providing a total of 309 offers. Registration opens today and closes on January 20th.
The first of these sessions, for Broadway Information System Limited, will take place on the afternoon of January 21st and will offer 12 job vacancies for project manager in the systems research and development department, systems analyst, IT technician, electronic security technician, among others. This session will be at DSAL headquarters.
On the morning of January 22nd, a matching session for the hotel sector will be held, with participating companies being “Companhia de Hotel Cidade Viva (Macau) Limitada” and “Companhia de Gestão do Centro Católico”, with a total of 51 job openings for customer service manager, room service supervisor, security supervisor, engineering technician and room counter employee, among others. This session is in the FAOM building, in Patane.
On the afternoon of January 22nd, also in the FAOM building, the pairing session for the cleaning sector will be held, with participating companies being “Pro Administração e Limpeza, Lda.”, “Companhia de Gestão de Serviços de Segurança Kun Lun, Lda.”, “Ou Kei Serviços de Limpeza, Limitada”, “MH Serviços de Limpeza Limitada” and “Sociedade de Prestação de Serviços de Gestão de Serviços de Instalações Macau Enxin, Limitada”, with a total of 185 job vacancies for cleaning staff, security guards, doormen, residential building security guards, administrative staff, tree planting agents, among others.
The pairing session for the telecommunications and e-commerce sector will be held on the afternoon of January 23rd, with “Hong Kong Technology Venture Company Limited” and “Companhia de Telecomunicações de Macau, S.A.” as participating companies, with a total of 61 job vacancies for direct line agent, customer support center logistics support staff, customer service director (sales store) and telecommunications service technician.</description><pubDate>2026-01-15 00:16:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Melco also announces raises for its workers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/melco-tambem-anuncia-aumentos-para-os-seus-trabalhadores/</link><description>Like Sands, Wynn and Galaxy, Melco announced salary increases for its workers ranging from 2% to 6.3%, according to the gaming operator.
In a statement, the group said that eligible full-time workers who do not hold management positions and receive a monthly base salary of up to 16,000 patacas will receive a salary increase of 500 patacas per month, representing an increase of 3.1% to 6.3%. For eligible full-time employees who do not hold management positions and receive a monthly base salary of more than MOP16,000, the increase will be 2%.
Lawrence Ho, president and CEO of Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, said: "Our team is critical to the service we provide at Melco. We are pleased to implement this salary increase as a way to recognize their commitment, dedication and hard work." Quoted in the group's statement, Lawrence Ho says that, "looking to the opportunities that the coming year holds for us, we are committed to moving forward as a united and stable workforce."
In recent days, Wynn, Galaxy and Sands also announced salary increases for their workers in the same proportion as those at Melco. Of the six gaming concessionaires operating in Macau, only SJM and MGM have not yet announced raises for their workers.
Remember that the results of a recently released survey indicate that local companies plan to increase salaries by 2.23% on average throughout 2026.</description><pubDate>2026-01-15 00:16:55</pubDate></item><item><title>At least 22 dead after crane falls on train in Thailand</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/15/pelo-menos-22-mortos-apos-queda-de-guindaste-sobre-comboio-na-tailandia/</link><description>More than 20 people died when a construction crane fell onto a passenger train in northeastern Thailand. Rescue operations were temporarily suspended due to a “chemical leak”.

At least 22 people died yesterday when a construction crane fell onto a passenger train in northeastern Thailand, authorities said. The crane fell as the train was traveling from the capital Bangkok to Ubon Ratchathani province, causing the derailment and a fire, according to the Public Relations Department of Nakhon Ratchasima province.
The accident occurred at around 09:00, involving a crane that was being used in the construction of a high-speed elevated railway.
The department said in a social media post that the fire was under control and that rescue teams were now searching for people inside the train, many of whom were trapped in overturned train cars.
Rescue operations had been temporarily suspended due to a “chemical leak”, local police reported, without specifying the origin. “More than 80” people were injured, Thatchapon Chinnawong, head of a police station in Nakhon Ratchasima, northeast of Bangkok, told France-Presse news agency.
Transport Minister Piphat Ratchakitprakan said there were 195 people on board the train and said he had ordered an investigation into the accident, which occurred in Ban Thanon Kho, 32 kilometers from Bangkok.
Thai media outlets and internet users published numerous images of the disaster on social media, showing part of the fire and dozens of rescuers at the scene. “I heard a loud noise (…) followed by two explosions,” said Mitr Intrpanya, 54, a resident who was at the scene. "When I went to see what had happened, I found the crane resting on a three-car passenger train. The metal from the crane appeared to have split the second car in half," he added.
The crane was part of a vast high-speed train construction project in Thailand that began in 2017, a decade late.
The US$5.4 billion project aims to connect Bangkok to Kunming, in southern China, via Laos. The first section is scheduled to open in 2028 and the second in 2032. The line is supported by China as part of the One Belt, One Road initiative, launched to boost trade in the region.
Industrial, construction and transport accidents are relatively frequent in Thailand due to sometimes lax enforcement of safety standards. In 2020, 18 people died in Thailand when a freight train collided with a bus carrying passengers to a religious ceremony. Eight people also died in 2023, in a collision between a freight train and a van that was crossing a railway in the east of the country. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-15 00:14:16</pubDate></item></channel></rss>