<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/china-orienta-empresas-a-evitar-negocios-com-li-ka-shing-apos-venda-dos-portos/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Chronic</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/cronica-13/</link><description>Paul French
 
Vanishing Games, by Roger Hobbs (2015)
 
 
The pocket -edition thriller is the contemporary heir to the stories that were published in American and European Pulp Fiction magazines, omnipresent between the 1920s and the 60s of the past éculum (many of which were later printed and reprinted as novels in cheap editions). Action, rhythm, and page turn had priority over the literary refinement. The stories featured robust heroes, in danger, exotic places, and explosive outskirts. However, while older pulp fictions had a special drop in Macao, later thrillers writers (with some remarkable exceptions such as Jake Needham, Ian Hamilton, and some others) scandalously ignored the territory. This is not the case of the author of American thrillers Roger Hobbs.
The hobb figure was that of a young promise, a prodigy of the world of highly quoted police writing and pointed out as one of the best in the late 1980s. Having grown on the east coast of the United States, he ended up settling in the city of Portland, Oregon, which was in fashion. His debut novel, Ghostman (2013), won a series of literary awards, reached the top of the US bestsellers tables, was praised by authors such as Lee Child and was eventually bought by Warner Bros Films. Vanishing Games (2015) was the book that followed, considered by critics a very well -obtained police novel - Hobbs had just turned 27. It was expected much, much more of him, but unfortunately he died of overdose in 2016, less than a year after the publication of Vanishing Games.
The romance is about an unnamed man, professional thief and a master of robberies, but is invisible to the world in general, especially for police forces, secret services and even for other organized crime groups. There is only one friend in the world - Angela, the woman who has taught you everything she knows about stealing, living in anonymity and changing to always keep one step ahead of the law or whoever has stolen. However, Angela is in trouble after stolen a bag of smuggled burmented sapphires and millions of dollars in "Superbills" (the most perfect false notes that the counterfections can produce, often deceiving the federal reserve). Now Angela is hidden in a Casino hotel in Macao, a step ahead of her stalkers, and asks for help.
           Vanishing games always keeps an accelerated pace throughout the text. Oscillating between the first and third person, to increase tension, confirms that young hobbs was a successful style cultivor. It's an elegant but difficult trick, the focus of the focus of tension in the middle of the route and repeatedly, something that only masters like Raymond Chandler managed to do.
In addition to Angela, there is a very interesting secondary character cast - Bautista, a Filipino drug dealer who can get anything in Macao, without asking questions, from a new face to a machine gun; Johnnie, the bodyguard and driver of Angela, who knows all the alley and blocks of degraded apartments in the old town; Elisheva, a Ukrainian precious trader in the mud, who is known to have achieved a stolen diamond, or, in fact, a sapphire; and Laurence, a psychopath killer who cannot be detained. The scenarios range from Cotai to north of the mud, passing through the light sources of the Road of Isthmus and the maze of narrow streets on the rear of the former Hotel Lisboa.
Some time after Ghostman's success, Hobbs lived in China for a period and at that time visited Macau and wrote Vanishing Games. The author writes: "Macao is a city of contradictions. It is a classic Portuguese colonial city with a chinese game frantic game on top ... If it wasn't for the casinos, Macau would be really picturesque." Vanishing Games is mainly passed in the upper part of the city-luxury hotels, casinos that work all night. For Vanishing Games inhabitants “this city is no more than champagne, sports cars and fiduciary funds”.
Of course, Macau is a great scenario for a jewelry theft story. As Hobbs says, "jewelery is all in Macau ... Seattle has coffees, New York, Pizzerias, Paris, Bakeries. Macao has jewelery." It is also a great scenario for a pair of criminals outside their natural environment and invading the territory of others. At one point, the head of a local gang tells Angela, "Now you're in Macau ... You must be prepared to play according to my rules."
           Vanishing Games offers many persecutions, fights and shootings. It remembers the already classic 90's movie, Heat, transplanted from Los Angeles to Macao. The environment evokes Robert de Niro's classic phrase: "Do not let you arrest you to anything that you are not willing to leave in 30 seconds if you feel pressure when turning around the corner."
This is Vanishing Games, a brilliant 370 -page book, uninterrupted action, criminal details and the hot and sticky streets of contemporary macao. Unfortunately, Hobbs died too young and too early in his career to become known outside the circle of US writers and readers specializing in crime. But it left us one of the great Thrillers not appreciated from the 21st century, passed in Macau, which deserves to be more read.
 
Roger Hobbs Vanishing Games has an American edition with a Knopf seal and English edition by Corgi.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:57:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Editorial #93</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/editorial-93/</link><description>Add authors from different languages, call those who want to talk to them and them, show books, movies, images, music, leave clues for new ideas, concerns, discoveries. All this is a literary festival, beyond the conviviality and the stories that are telling and living - and perhaps give rise to new books, movies, shows. The 14th edition of the Macau Literary Festival - Rota das Letras is coming to an end, but there is still a weekend full of programming to accompany, concentrated in the space of the old slaughterhouse, there in Barra, but spread across other sites of the city. It was in this context that André Letria, illustrator with more than three decades of career, visited Macau, and talked to the paragraph about his work, the many ways of creating images and telling them stories, the possible (and still unknown) modes of making books. We have also taken advantage of the presence of Jason Wordie, the local historian who has lived in Hong Kong for over thirty years and has been a regular visit of Macau, to accompany one of his tours around the city, to the ride of reissue this essential book titled Macao - People and Places, Past and Present, now with a seal of Praiagrand Editions. Anyone who wants to join Wordie on this walk through the streets around Barra and São Lourenço can still do it next Sunday morning. Taking the book is bad idea, because the weight is considerable, but it is worth following the author and then passes to the pages where it speaks in detail this area of ​​the city and others, in a record that illuminates a series of stories, less known episodes and details of the territory where we do not always notice in everyday race.
As always, we have room for other readings, some designed for younger readers (from which the rest are not excluded), new books to discover and the usual chronic that, in different shades, mark the identity of these pages. We came back in May with more books and with some of the many worlds, not always on printed pages, which they open us.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 04:00:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai aims to reinforce cooperation with Haião, who sees Macau as “reference”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/sam-hou-fai-pretende-reforcar-cooperacao-com-hainao-que-ve-macau-como-referencia/</link><description>As part of a two -day visit south of the country, the head of the Executive of the MSAR and the Haião head of Haião stressed the similarities of the territories and expressed their intention to reinforce the exchange and cooperation between them, with a view to obtaining “mutual benefits”. Feng FEI also revealed that the “successful experiences” in the cooperation zone in Hengqin are seen as a “reference” for Haião's free trade port.
 
The chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, was in Haião this Wednesday, on the occasion of the annual conference of the Boao Forum for Asia 2025, where he met with the Secretary of the Provincial Committee of Haião of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP), Feng FEI. At the meeting, the main subject of discussion was the deepening of cooperation between the two regions in various areas, highlighting the sectors of tourism, health and education.
According to a statement issued by the Government's Social Communication Office, Sam Hou Fai began to emphasize the importance of this year for both regions: besides being the first year of the VI Government of MSAR and the beginning of the second phase of the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin, also the Haião Free Commerce Port will enter into 2025 as an autonomous customs zone.
Greeting the “deep and longtime relations” between Macao and the province southern China and “the good base of cooperation between the two parts in the sectors of tourism, health and education”, Sam Hou Fai assumed “expectant” regarding new opportunities for development and cooperation. The Chief Executive said that the Hungqin cooperation zone and Haião's free trade port reveal “identical aspects in political terms”, so the investment in the communication of both projects could “enhance their unique advantages” and bring “mutual benefits”.
Specifically referring to the Macao region, the chief executive assured that the government is implementing “the spirit consecrated in President XI Jinping's speeches” and “accelerating the impulse to the proper and diversified development of the economy, fully promoting the high quality growth of society and the economy”.
 
Macau's “Successful Experiences” are a reference
 
In his speech, the Secretary of the HaiNão CCP Committee began to thank the visit of the politician of the latter to the island province, taking advantage of the occasion to make a brief sharing of the economic context of recent years. In this parameter, the opening of the Haião Free Commerce Port, which aims to assume itself as a new platform for liberalization of trade and facilitating investment in the Chinese market.
Feng Fei said he used as a reference for this project “the various successful experiences in the hengqin cooperation zone”, adding that Haião will remain “attentive to the latest information” regarding the work done in this area. Macao and Haião are, moreover, regions with various “common aspects” - such as a “proportion of the tourist sector” quite high compared to other Chinese regions. Thus, the leader expects these points of convergence to bring the two territories “even more” and reinforce “the union for a new chapter of cooperation in several areas”.
Sam Hou Fai was in Haião between Wednesday and Thursday to participate in the opening ceremony of the Boao Forum Annual Conference, a non-profit organization that annually performs high level forums for government, business and academic leaders. In his absence, it was André Cheong, secretary for Administration and Justice, to act interimly as head of the Executive.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:17:48</pubDate></item><item><title>INTERVIEW</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/entrevista-5/</link><description>Books that create worlds
For more than three decades André Letria creates books, images that tell stories, sometimes arm given with words of others, sometimes solo. In 1999, he won the National Illustration Award with verses to do him, with text by José Jorge Letria, and has had his work published in Portugal and abroad, in different supports. 15 years ago, she created the Pato Logic Publisher to be able to make the books she wanted and how she wanted, starting to build a catalog that is among the most coherent of this new place of Portuguese publishers who work, in various ways, books with image. He has now returned to Macau more than thirty years after the first time to participate in the 14th edition of the Literary Rota das Letras festival, and that's when we talked about an already long career, a way of thinking books, a way to create stories and universes that do not want to be dependent on railroad laws or an idea about what should read children - and adults who are not afraid of diving in books where there are more than letters.
 
 
You have worked in the area of ​​illustration for over three decades. How do you relate to this work longevity?
I think about it the same way I think of the things of life, it's not… Time goes by. And I think in many ways, because sometimes I'm confronted with things I did in this past, things I prefer not to see, that were done at times very different from the functioning of the market, this editorial ecosystem.
 
Things that renegade?
These are things I did in a hurry, there were years when I think I made twelve books! In some cases because it was those collections from zero to eight, and that was made in jail, right away. But then, over it, maybe it did even more. Probably there were years when I fourteen or sixteen books, it's crazy! Returning to the beginning, I walked in the beautiful arts and began to be illustrator by chance.
 
Were the Jornal de Letras paginator, right?
It is still in front of college, yes, because I had a year of forced stop, with a delayed physicochemistry exam. Therefore, this year, while studying for the exam, I joined JL. And although I already have some contact experience with the newspapers, because of my father [José Jorge Letria], because sometimes I went with him to the diary when I was little, that was extraordinary.
 
Why?
Only later did I realize, but that had been a training since I remember, when I had no classes, or in the late afternoon. I remember the telex room, the noise of writing machines, the conviviality of journalists, which at that time was fascinating. And there was one thing that only later did I value it, although at the time I fascinated me, which was the graphic, even under the newspaper. And there were the machines and the typographs, the printers, who were another fauna, a class apart, with whom I learned things unknowingly. I still saw things to be printed with movable types, although there is already rotating. When I went to JL, unknowingly, I already took this memory, and I felt it was luck because it was a place of cultural life. For example, Eduardo Lourenço passed by to deliver the texts and talked to who was. And other writers, artists, painters, people who were going to be interviewed. And then, as JL was a bit prehistoric, although there were already computers to pagine the other newspapers in the group, we still did that with some large model leaves, we used a calculator to make the relationship between the number of characters and the space, we aligned out there. And then I learned a lot, from Miguel Eduardo Serrano, and it was extraordinary. It was a school.
 
Did this influence your relationship with the graphic arts, the illustration?
I didn't know at that time because that was a job, but. Then I joined college and did the two parallel paths, which led me not to finish the course. I was lazy in many things and couldn't find a sense for college. I figured I was going to be a painter, artist, but I couldn't see, I had nothing to say. In the newspaper, José Carlos Vasconcelos, director of JL, has always created a section at one time on the last page where there were tales of Portuguese authors. And as I was in college, he thought I could do some illustrations to accompany the tales. And I started doing illustrations for Mario de Carvalho and Urban [Tavares Rodrigues], the first two and I remember well.
 
Is this that begins this work that starts from the relationship between text and image in a conscious way?
Yes. In fact, that was all very empirical, because there were no schools of illustration. We only talked about this in a trimester of the drawing discipline, with Pedro Saraiva, who thought the drawing could also serve for that. Then, in JL and the publishers I went to work with, I did not know what I was doing; I was learning as I was making mistakes. And however, the connection with my father is inevitable and the most regular work of illustration begins with him. Then it became a regular activity, so that I thought the college was no longer sense, because I was no longer there. And I became illustrator.
 
This was at a very different time in terms of market and even perception of what illustration is.
Yes, it was a very different way than it is today. It was not paid in the same way, there was payment to the head, that is, it received a unique amount, even if the books came to have I do not know how many editions, and the idea of ​​contract was a mirage. On the other hand, I still painted everything on paper, of course, by the way, these illustrations for JL were in Aguarela, something I never used again. And things were walking, I still worked at JL for a few years and had to make a lot of books to be a livelihood, and yet it was not enough. Later, I started to realize that it was necessary to do other things, participate in events, accept invitations to design things I couldn't even do, but were a source of performance. And there was always the notion that all this was a discovery and that I was always trying to realize what I could do in a different way. I remember an invitation from Amber publisher to do more copyright things, where I conceived everything, or could suggest. It was like this with fantastic animals and verses for parents to read their children on moonlight nights, which are large books, with a little standard format, that perhaps other publishers would not accept at that time. The amber had an advantage, beyond the desire to experiment, which was to have its own graphics.
 
Then you were aware that this inheritance you have received from the graphics, from conversations with the typographs, the pagination of JL, had influence on what you did and even the way you wanted to do it?
With some things, I think so, because I used the machines in a certain way because I knew how they worked and what they could do. On the other hand, I always had a lack of great confidence when I had to take the step towards the graphic conception itself. But it eventually emerged the certainty that to be illustrator is not enough to think of the image that will be drawn, create, you need to perceive the whole process. But, finally, when I reached the part of deciding design questions, the choice of source, I had no confidence. And when I come to the verses of doing, I realize that I feel like doing it all as it should be.
 
And this is even a award -winning book.
Yes, it received the National Illustration Award. But it is a milestone for me because I already knew Jorge Silva, thanks to João Paulo Cotrim, as he had made a book with text by Luísa Ducla Soares, about the libraries, which was late because I didn't know what to do about design. At that time, it took a kind of emergency plan and Cotrim said we were going to talk to Jorge Silva and that I had to know him. From there, we never stopped talking about almost all the things I was doing. And he helped me there to solve it, and we made a little book in the form of a house, which on top of the cover, unthinkable, and I was always learning a lot from Jorge, simplifying things, realizing relationships with space on the page, and when I want to do the verses to do it, I ask you help.
 
It is relevant to note how Jorge Silva marks several generations of illustrators and the very way of making books with images in Portugal.
There is no doubt! At that time I had no confidence to decide, but I was not ashamed to knock on his door and ask for help. And from him I learned that we need to think about in other things beyond the images. The guards, the way you change page, all. And with the verses of doing it, it was like that. In addition, I think there was also an important thing, which was the discovery of the French bookstore in Lisbon, where extraordinary books arrived, very different from those we knew. I remember seeing the books of the Oeds Du Rouergue and thinking that it was possible to do other things anyway.
 
The verses of doing Ó-O are published at a time when various background changes are happening in the Portuguese publishing market, in this chapter of the books designed for childhood.
Yes. For example, in 1998, a year before this book, there is the Lisbon hall, once again, associated with Jorge Silva and João Paulo Cotrim, and this is an essential milestone to perceive how to the panorama of today's illustration. It is the meeting point of people who worked in newspapers and publishers, or in advertising, where they talk and begin to realize that there are people without contracts, who can receive rights, out there. By the time I was already a partner of the Spa [Portuguese Society of Authors] and had a lot of conscience and was one of those who told others to not do things without contract, without receiving rights. In addition, in the Lisbon salon we started to see each other's work, because everything was there, João Fazenda, André Carrilho, Gonçalo Pena, whose work fascinated me. And then there is a crossing of languages ​​that I realize today: I was painting, in the beautiful arts, and unlike most illustrators used acrylic on paper, there were some more surrealistic references and there was a transposition of this universe that was more in editorial, newspapers and magazines, to children's books.
 
When you started publishing in book your works had this distinctive trait of the very dense, textured, sometimes almost bassy colors…
Yes, that was it, it was all these influences, of painting, some illustrators, from college experiences. And it was not only the issue of technique, but also the symbolic issue.
 
Like this?
I started to do in these books for the kids something that didn't see much, which was a more metaphorical language in illustration and that was something that began to interest me a lot and that I increasingly like to explore, even today, and that has everything to do with this relationship between text and image. For me it failed to make sense to be representing the things the text already describes. In addition, I also started doing a lot of illustration for poetry and then the use of this symbolic and metaphorical language is almost a brand image. The images with this kind of characteristic and the relationship with the text create something else, another type of publication. And that's what I wanted to explore more and more. Then, at one point, I begin to realize that if it continued to be a freelance illustrator, you might not be able to take things further.
 
And that's where the publisher comes in, the logical duck?
Yes. The idea had been sedimenting for some time…
 
Does your initial idea be to create a publisher for power to publish your books, doing whatever you wanted, or was it also to create a catalog with other authors?
It begins as a desire for personal creative freedom, never losing sight of the hypothesis of being able to work with other people, but it was very the idea of ​​“I want to do this and I do not feel like giving satisfaction” and escape the fear of what will not sell, or that it is very expensive to do so, or that it is too dark to be for children, or has many pages. I felt this limitation and began to want, but there was the problem of no money. However, there was a mishaps that solved this.
 
Do you want to tell?
Yes, deep down were two things that went wrong. One of them was that I had made a set of illustrations for a publisher, all painted in acrylic, and the book was published, but time has passed and I didn't receive the originals back, but I didn't remember that for a while. There is a time when telephone there to ask for the originals and they did not know, they had lost us, it had been printed on a graph that I close in the meantime. And that's a request for compensation and I received more money than I had ever won for a book.
 
This is very ironic.
Yeah, but this is the origin of the logical duck. And this is associated with another case, which is the republication of a collection of Portuguese classic book in pocket version, made by a weekly from our square, using the same covers and the same illustrations I had made, but without asking me to be aware, without even warning. I saw that because I read an ad to the collection. And then, ready, the spa came in with a precautionary action and so on. And that's it, more money came to use for the publisher. I was already thinking about doing something, but so, instead of making a unfoldable, or another very cheap edition, I thought of making a book and starting.
 
And that's where we come to light.
Yes, because I thought that making a book about Benfica was going to be a success, that it was going to sell to the thousands, but it was a total misfortune… It's been 15 years and still today I have a part of the edition for selling.
 
Given the size of Benfica and the passion of fans, what may have been bad?
I think there is an editorial and market ecosystem that does not allow this to work like this. First, I thought that a certain type of distribution was sufficient and had FNAC, which had centralized distribution, and then count on Benfica's store and Benfica's houses. The first presentation of the book was to put it for sale in the presentation game of the time that was going to start, was Benfica-Monaco, with 55,000 people in the stadium, with a friend of mine who offered to stay in the store that afternoon with the books, because I was not in Lisbon, and at the end of the day there had been four books! Therefore, it was a disastrous beginning. On top of that, I did four thousand and five hundred copies for the first edition… If we think there are 6 million and such supporters in Portugal, it was enough that 1% had bought to be an editorial success, but it didn't happen.
 
Leaving aside this commercial failure of the beginning, the truth is that the logical duck has built a very coherent catalog and that the books circulate, not only by Portugal, and sell themselves.
Yes, it's true, it wasn't all bad, it was just the beginning. By the way, even if the publisher ended now, and I have no plans for it, there would always be a victory to celebrate that it was living 15 with this to work, without debt, treating the authors well, out there. That is great. And it is also an illusory, because the publisher would not survive if they did only these books.
 
There are a number of partnerships and other things you do.
Yes, if it wasn't for that, we might make a book a year, but it was around. The publisher survives because of these many other things, from clients such as the National Press - Casa da Mint, with whom we have a partnership, and others. Sometimes books made with the exclusive investment of the Logic Duck, it can only be one in a year, it has happened, but as we do several with INCM, and the effort and dedication are the same, it seems to be six or seven in one year.
 
After 15 years of publisher, this process of conceiving all the root books and thinking about them in the tiny details changed your artistic work, your way of thinking and creating images?
Yes, no doubt. And I think it changed soon from the beginning, as if I had found a solid foundation to be comfortable, especially in relation to the issue of time. I think this is the big difference between the two work models, being illustrator or being also the person who does and edits the books, taking some time to conceive things. And then there is this idea… I think more and more I prefer the word author instead of illustrator.
 
Why?
It is not because being illustrator diminishes something, but with the publisher I can put into practice a form of work that is not only that of visual creation and is not only to conceive the object, sometimes is also influenced and defining the rules for those who write. I have an idea for the book that is not very clear early on, and this can also be a shape, because it is not the question of wanting to control everything, but there is a project that, to fit the widest editorial project, must have certain characteristics, that I want to be so. And this can do with the books we are creating from root.
 
This influence on, for example, who writes, has happened to many books? Because this is the opposite of what usually thinks it happens, which is, in the case of a book with writer and illustrator, to always be the writer to define things.
Yes, it happens because it is a work together. For example, at work with my father, when we made the war, it happened. And this is a book that I know I would hardly do in another place, in another context.
 
How was this process?
The book took four years to be done. My father had written that for some time and I asked him to keep the text to me. When I took the text to start taking notes and defining something, I gave myself to feel the need to tell a story, although the text is a series of verses without fixed order. And when I entered this path, I realized that I could no longer get out of there, but also that that text no longer served. It came to this point! I spoke to my father, took her a storyboard with the sequence of the images and suggested that we did it in another way.
 
And did he react well?
Yes, and immediately adhered to that challenge, doing something that most writers are not used to doing that is revealing the process, that is, having a visual base and has to write from there. And it was a very educational process for me and him. You always need to find out, in each project, what are the ways to get where you want. For example, with Ricardo [Henriques], when we made Jean, John and John, about the French invasions, it was that ping-pong process from side to side after visiting the sites and defining some ideas. With the latter, how to create a library, with Inês [Fonseca Santos], I had a thoughtful story and had been thinking for a long time to make a book about a library, which was even a more fantastic story at first, but then I liked that simple thing. And then I told Inês that the base was that and that it was necessary something that worked in another layer, but that left that free space for the reader, because it is almost like a triangle: we have who writes and who illustrates, but the reader is just like at the same level, because that only joins by the hand of those who read. And the publisher seems to me the only possible way to do this.
 
You are in Macao for the second time, the first one was about 30 years ago. How do you see the city, what memories brings you this return?
Yes, it was there in 1991 or 1992. The possibility of coming here was something that I had a lot of hope that I could realize, because this other trip was my first plane trip, and soon to come to the other side of the world and dropped into a totally different reality. The idea I have is that it was a huge shock and it left me a fascination that I still keep in the East, although even coming with some regularity, not to Macao, but to other sites. It is a return to the past in many ways, because it reminds me of that period when I was 18 and I came with my father, having been received in a totally different city from this. And then, as I like history, it is a return to the past in this sense, also to the colonial past and the Portuguese presence around the world, which is something that raises many questions about the difficult history it has generated. I feel very well here, I have to say, and very well welcomed.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:55:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Report</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/reportagem/</link><description>On the streets of Barra, with open and closed eyes
 
Macao-People and Places, Past and Present, by Jason Wordie, returned to bookstores in a second edition, with a seal of Prail editions, and the author came to the Macao Literary Festival to introduce him and guide two tours through Barra and São Lourenço. We accompanied one of them and listened to Jason Wordie revealed a series of stories and small details about the streets, houses and the people who have passed here.
 
 
«My interest in Macau began 35 years ago. The first night I spent here at Hotel Belavista, I remember being on the porch and ahead was the water. There was nothing, because it was dark, but you could hear a fish jumping from time to time. And I can't explain why I was so clinging to Macau, because I remember opening the tap and the water out brown… It wasn't the most comfortable thing in the world, but I loved it. And I continued to come back, always. » This is how Jason Wordie answered when we asked him, even before joining the group that participated in this first guided tour, which attracted him in Macao. Throughout the walk, which began in the old slaughterhouse, climbed Penha and returned to Barra, passing to St. Lourenço, this attraction to the territory was visible in the enthusiasm with which Wordie, a historian fixed in Hong Kong for over three decades, told historical episodes and less known stories of the city's life.
We started the tour next to the Lake Water Line Sai Van, on Avenida da República. "I want to focus on less known aspects, those details in which we do not always notice and that go through architecture, but also geography, history, people," says the guide author, defining the tone of this tour. The floor we stepped had not existed for a decades ago and it is still possible to see some points, next to the wall that delimits the new lands, where the fishermen settled with their nets supported by Bambus, hoping that the fish would fall into the trap. Further on, the Fortress of St. Tiago da Barra, with its stories of haunted Santos statues, the houses that belonged to Fu Tak Iam, legendary macao game of Macao, and the statue of Henri Dunant, founder of the Red Cross, which was to be another, says the initial plan was to make a memorial of Portuguese expansion, but this will have created some discomfort in Beijing and ended up the authorities and ended up at the authorities of Beijing and ended up as authorities ended up Choose a Dunant bust, which was never in Macau, assuming that the Red Cross was innocuous enough for anyone to be displeased… »
On the way up to the Church of Our Lady of Penha, under a little recommended sun, we stopped to see some points where it is hardly noticed in an occasional passage. Here, a traditional Chinese house, which was already in ruins when Wordie made the first edition of the book later, the Skyline building, a residence of F. J. Gellion, a British engineer who directed the Macao Electricity Company, whose modernist lines are quite visible.
In Penha, as usual on weekends, there are a couple of grooms to be photographed with the church facade in the background. We give them some time, but Jason Wordie wants us to see the plate that records the year of church construction, and we ended up invading the scenario. «Built in 1934-35 replacing the primitive chapel built in 1622 and reissued in 1837,” we read, while Wordie draws attention to the architectural lines of the Estado Novo, creating a strong contrast with the surrounding area.
We went down, passing near the Belavista Hotel and the Fortress of Good Birth, below. And Wordie underlines the strategic position of this fortress and what we saw earlier, both forming an angle that allowed to monitor these waters and ensure that no one arrived without being seen. The author says that “it is curious that these fortresses, built by the Portuguese, were intended to keep other European peoples away. It could be thought that they would serve to stop the Chinese, separating the waters, but it was nothing like that. And it was so with the Dutch, as the story records.
 
Closed -eyed
In front of São Lourenço Church, a longer stop for Jason Wordie tell the story of architect George Vitalievich Smirnoff, a “white Russian” who fled the 1917 revolution, settling in Harbin, where he studied architecture before moving to Qingdao. Then the Japanese occupation forced him to the new escape and the family takes refuge in Hong Kong, where he draws several buildings, but where he has to leave as a refugee, following US bombing against Japanese occupation. Refugee in Macao with his family, settles in the courtyard of the six houses. This is where it paints a series of macao watercolors, commissioned by José Pedro Lobo, who thus helps the architect's family survive.
The route between the Church of St. Lourenço and the old Smirnoff House is made with Jason Wordie, who met the two daughters of Smirnoff (Irene and Nina), remembering the joke they both did: one of them closed his eyes and, holding hands with other children, made the way to home recognizing the streets for the sounds and smells, namely the small altar of tou today. Tei next to the Tigre Mata Travessa. We did not walk with our eyes closed, but it was easy to realize that attention to the details that come to us by other senses that would not look for the look to redo this route, yes.
We went down to Barra, moving to the Moorish barracks and ending the visit in front of the A-MA temple, implanted by the waters even before the Portuguese navigators landed here. Jason Wordie tells the story of one of the oldest photographs of Macao, made by Frenchman Jules Itier in the 1840s. Technology allows us to see this photograph quickly, on the phone of one of the members of this tour, and the contrast of the time facade, in black and white, with the buzz that the tourist excursions produce at the time we are, is revealing of the so much that has changed so much. in Macao over the decades.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:50:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing rejects Trump's offer to reduce rates in exchange for agreement on Tiktok</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/pequim-rejeita-oferta-de-trump-de-reduzir-taxas-em-troca-de-acordo-sobre-tiktok/</link><description>China yesterday refused the offer of US President Donald Trump to grant customs relief in exchange for an agreement on the sale of Tiktok video sharing application.
 
"On the Tiktok issue, China has expressed its position on several occasions. China's position against the imposition of additional customs rates is also consistent and clear," said Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakun.
Donald Trump said on Wednesday that he is prepared to reduce some of the rates on imports from China if the owner of Tiktok, Chinese Bytedance, agreeing to alienate her US operations. "China will have to play a role in selling the application, it will possibly have to approve it and, if you do, you may grant you a small reduction in customs rates," the US president said from the White House.
This happened shortly after Trump announced 25% of additional rates for the automotive sector, thus joining the long list of rates used by the head of state in his commercial and political negotiations with other countries.
In the case of Chinese electric cars, which have been taxed 100% since August 2024, the rates will be 125%. “We'll have some form according to Tiktok in the United States, Donald Trump said.
On January 20, as soon as he took office, Trump gave Bytedance 75 days to sell his operations in the US, ie until April 5.
At the end of this period, if not, the platform is expected to be prohibited in the United States, where it has 170 million users, pursuant to a law approved last year in the name of protection of national security. “We will have some kind of agreement,” repeated Trump. "But if it is not completed, it is nothing special. We will simply prolong [the term]. I have the right to extend it if you want it," he added.
In 2020, at the end of his first term, he himself tried unsuccessfully to ban this platform in the United States, also in the name of national security.
Last year, Democratic and Republican deputies again insisted and were able to pass a law to ban the social network while it belonged to Bytedance. But Donald Trump changed ideas during his campaign, coming in defense of the application.
Several suitors are queuing to purchase it, although Bytedance has not declared its intention to sell. “We are negotiating with four different groups and there are a lot of people interested,” said Donald Trump earlier this month.
The Perplexity Artificial Intelligence company made an offer, such as the Project Liberty, created by the promoter and owner of the Olympique de Marseille, Frank McCourt, and to which the co -founder of Reddit social network was joined by Alexis Ohanian.
Other personalities who expressed interest include influencer MRBEAST and Steven Mnuchin, Treasury Secretary during Donald Trump's first term. The White House mentioned other potential buyers, such as Microsoft and Oracle. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:17:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Navigating</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/navegar-e-preciso-25/</link><description>www.tnsj.pt
 
 
In 2020, when many people were confined at home to avoid the propagation of the Covid-19 virus, the São João National Theater (TNSJ) in Porto invited a group of actors and actresses to use the stage and behind the scenes of that room, then uninhabited, and create the first entries of what would be an untimely glossary about the stage arts. Baptized with the name Bambolina!, Term that designates one of the many fundamental pieces that are part of the view of viewers, a theatrical stage, this glossary grew and extended a lot beyond the pandemic, continuing to collect new entries. At this time, more than 80 entrances are available, by different staging professionals, representation, translation, sonoplasty and other technical areas, but also signed by writers, essayists, playwrights and other authors who somehow relate to theater.
 
How do you read on the TNSJ website: «What is a“ stage? And a “busy rehearsal”? How to define “sonoplasty”? Where is the “web”? Who is Ubu? What does the LGP interpreter? Say it and do it. » Of all these doubts, and another series of them that may never have crossed the minds of viewers, this theatrical glossary made of Voice was born, to know the cleaning places and the least publicized meanders of the great art made of many arts and crafts that is the theater videos. They deserve our time in front of the screen, before and after we sit in that or any other room in the world, always with eyes on stage.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:50:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Caeal attentive to the advertising material distributed by the applications of the legislative elections</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/caeal-atenta-ao-material-de-propaganda-distribuido-pelas-candidaturas-das-eleicoes-legislativas/</link><description>The electoral propaganda material of applications to legislatures that will be distributed to the population “should avoid benefits”, argues the Electoral Affairs Committee of the Legislative Assembly. In this case, applications must present the list of advertising material to be distributed, as well as the respective quantity, which will be supervised by the authorities. The commission also assured it to have mechanisms to oversee any irregularities practiced outside Macao.
 
The Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) will require applications for legislative elections that present the list and the amount of advertising material to be distributed, as well as the activities they intend to perform during the election campaign period, ie, between August 30 and September 12.
Already the electoral propaganda material, which the population can receive, "should avoid benefits," said Seng Ioi Man, president of Caeal, giving the example of tea or 'powerbanks', which "is not related to advertising." He stressed that if the distributed articles are related to benefits, there is a possibility of constituting an act of electoral corruption.
The next elections for the Legislative Assembly are scheduled for September 14 this year. CAEAL and CCAC held on Wednesday a clarification session on electoral procedures, which had 220 participants, of which six citizens asked questions about the inspection of electoral activities.
Seng Ioi Man mentioned at the time that the request for election campaign information to applications is intended to help CAEAL Supervision and Commissioner against Corruption (CCAC), following the execution of the expense limit that each application can spend on the elections.
Quoted by the Cheng Pou newspaper, Seng Ioi Man pointed out that it is recommended that electoral propaganda materials be presented in the form of paper copies such as leaflets or bulletins with number printing, photos and electoral program, as “the campaign should focus on the political platform and candidacy ideas” for the elections. Hand flags, paper tissues, fans and water are articles that can be distributed, according to Caeal, but “there is no need in the campaign” to distribute portable electric fans, wine or expensive drinks.
The spokesman also revealed that Caeal is studying the issue of advertising materials and will talk to future candidates about the guidelines. It is recalled that candidates are punished with a prison sentence up to six months or a fine up to one million patacas, if their effective expenses with the election campaign exceed the limit of expenses set. "It is expected that all sectors of society will continue to support and participate together and diligently in electoral activities, contributing to the elections for the Legislative Assembly to take place fairly, impartially, full, according to the law and successfully," he said.
 
Out of macau
 
CAEAL, on the other hand, has ensured that it has mechanisms, such as judicial or police cooperation, to combat and deal with illicit acts related to electoral activities that occur outside Macao. The issue was raised by a participant in the session that was concerned about the election campaign directed at Macao residents living outside the territory, such as Hengqin.
Seng Ioi Man, quoted by Radio Macau's Chinese channel, said the electoral law already provides for punishment of violations committed outside Macau and is confident that the current mechanism is effective ”to treat possible cases of irregularities.
The judge of the second instance court said he no longer received complaints about the elections. Regarding the previous cases of pressure or coercion of voters regarding the signing of the candidacy proposal bulletin, Caeal said it was unable to collect more updated information, including the name of the association in question, to advance with the investigation. Seng Ioi Man appealed to the population to submit complaints and complaints to Caeal and CCAC if they come across suspicions of electoral corruption or other irregularities.
In addition, he said that by Wednesday a total of nine people requested the request for recognition of the constitution of the candidacy committee.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:18:28</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea accuses Japan of preparing for war for 80 years</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/coreia-do-norte-acusa-japao-de-se-preparar-para-a-guerra-ha-80-anos/</link><description>North Korea yesterday criticized the new Unified Military Command of Japan and accused Tokyo of preparing for war 80 years ago after the defeat in World War II (1939-1945).
 
"Japan, the criminal nation of war, is going into a large -scale battle formation to open the door to reinvasion," the official agency KCNA wrote to open a comment on Tokyo's decision.
The Japanese government has announced the formation of a new command, with about 240 staff, to achieve “greater coordination” within the Army.
It also aims to improve coordination with US forces, especially in the case of any contingencies compared to Taiwan, according to the Spanish Europa Press agency.
Pyongyang said the new command will be used to “test long -distance missiles” as part of the preparations for a possible conflict.
Japan “has created an environment and conditions that could lead you to get into war at any time,” said the North Korean official agency in his comment.
According to KCNA, Tokyo continues “actively the US hegemonic invasion strategy.
He referred to the creation of "An Asian Version of Nato centered on a tripartite military alliance between the United States, Japan and South Korea in Northeast Asia."
For the Kim Jong-un regime, the creation of the new command shows that Japan is entering the final phase of becoming a "state of war." "Reality shows that the overseas invasion of Japanese militarists is no longer a fantasy or speculation, but an established fact, and of course as the day that the first target of their attack is our republic," he said.
For Pyongyang, it will just be a matter of time until Japan "firing the first shot that marks the beginning of a new invasion" from North Korea and China. "The Japanese militarists, millennial enemies of the Korean people, should know this clearly: the line to which Japan dared to approach will become a cruel grave from which it will never come out," he added.
North Korea last week condemned Japan's military actions on the island of Kyushu, where he is thinking of installing long -range missiles.
Japan dominated Korea between 1910 and 1945, when it capitulated before the Allied forces after the United States launched atomic bombs in Hiroshima and Nagasaki.
Japanese imperial troops also invaded and occupied Manchuria in northeastern China in 1931 with the two countries involving in an armed conflict between 1937 and 1945.
 
North Korea sends another 3,000 soldiers to Russia
 
North Korea sent about 3,000 military personnel to Russia between January and February to join the troops that confront the Ukrainians, yesterday said South Korean military.
South Korea's joint staff said North Koreans have also sent more missiles, artillery equipment and ammunition to help Russia in the war in Ukraine, stressing that North Korea could increase its support with the sending of weapons, depending on the situation of the war.
Russia and Ukraine recently agreed with a limited ceasefire, although both sides have been mutually accused of the truce violations.
North Korea's military equipment sent to Russia includes a “considerable amount of short -range ballistic missiles, 170 millimeters self -propelled obuses, and about 220 multiple units of 240 mm rocket launchers.
North Korea had already sent approximately 11,000 military personnel to combat in the war against Ukraine, in its first involvement in a large-scale conflict since the 1950-53 Korean War.
According to the South Korean joint staff about 4,000 North Korean military personnel were killed or injured. The South Korea National Information Service earlier the North Korean lows the probable difficulties of troops to adapt to the drones and other elements of the modern war.
North Korean troops are even more harmed by the tactics of their Russian commanders, who sent them to attack campaigns without rear support, the South Korean information service to legislators said in January. Military officers and Ukrainian information services consider that North Koreans are gaining a crucial experience on the battlefield, sending a large number of soldiers to fighting in the Kursk Russian region.
The South Korean military report came after North Korean leader Kim Jong-un expressed his unshakable support to the Russian War in Ukraine during a meeting with Russian Security Council Secretary Sergei Shoigu last week in Pyongyang.
The war in Ukraine began in 2014 with the annexation of the Ukrainian Peninsula of Crimea by Russia and, in 2022, the Russian military again invaded the Russian territory. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:18:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing asks Asian countries to oppose protectionism</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/pequim-pede-aos-paises-asiaticos-que-se-oponham-ao-proteccionismo/</link><description>Chinese vice-master-master, Ding Xuexiang, yesterday asked “resolute opposition to protectionism,” in a forum dedicated to economic cooperation in the Asia-Pacific region. "Asia has become the world's most dynamic region in terms of development and growth potential," said Ding Xuexiang, a member of the Chinese Communist Party Permanent Committee, the power summit in China, in his intervention at the event, featuring Portuguese Foreign Minister Paulo Rangel.
"Asia has actively opened its doors and took the initiative to integrate into the world," the Chinese-minister vice-prime minister recalled in a period of growing commercial frictions the United States and the rest of the world.
Ding Xuexiang stated that the region should “work together to protect free trade, adhere to open regionalism and resolutely oppose commercial and investment protectionism”.
He appealed to the “resolution of differences and differences through dialogue and consultation” and defended “opening, cooperation and economic globalization” as “inevitable choices” for the region.
The deputy minister said China's economic performance “remains stable” and that “industry growth rates, consumption, investment and other indicators in the first two months of this year were higher than those last year”.
Ding said authorities “will implement more proactive macroeconomic policies” and “expand internal demand on all fronts” at a time when weak domestic consumption raises deflationary pressures in the world's second largest economy.
He added that the Chinese government will "promote the healthy development of real estate and scholarship more vigorously."
The forum, which runs until Friday under the theme “Asia in a change world: towards a shared future”, stressed the resilience of the region in a global environment marked by geopolitical tensions, moderate inflation and unequal recovery, with a report on Tuesday to predict real 4.5%GDP growth in 2025, compared to 4.4%in 2024.
Known as “Asian Davos”, the Boao for Asia Forum, created in 2000 by agreement from 29 countries in the region, was first held in February 2001, with the aim of promoting Asian economic integration, which later extended to a global scale.
Trump's return to the White House and the imposed or announced customs rates that particularly affected the largest US business partners, such as China, Canada, Mexico and the European Union, were the focus of this edition.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:17:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Ias cuts financial support from Smart Nursry and Creche calls for justifications</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/ias-corta-apoio-financeiro-da-smart-nursery-e-creche-pede-justificacoes/</link><description>The Institute of Social Action announced the end of financial support and equipment to Smart Nursry, a daycare managed by the Macao Zonta Club and currently hosts more than 80 children. Authorities report that the decision is not related to children's care problems, but lack of consensus with the day care center for “some basic principles and important provisions” for cooperation without revealing further details. At the end, Smart Nursry requested the government's justification of the decision, criticizing the approach of Hon Wai, president of the body, which could occur in illegalities.
 
The government will no longer provide financial support to the Smart Nursery day care center, and will recover their subsidized facilities as well as the equipment in their space, a decision advanced yesterday by the Institute of Social Action (IAS), after several reports on concerns with the sudden change of creches of their children.
IAS stated that the reason for the end of the subsidy “was not due to any problem with the care provided to children in the day care”, but because there was no agreement on some aspects of cooperation. "The two parts, after a long time communication, failed to reach a consensus on some basic principles and important provisions for cooperation," the body said in statements to Radio Macao in Chinese language.
However, the authorities did not reveal more information for their decision, namely what were the disparities in cooperation between IAS and the Zonta Club of Macao, the management entity of the day care center. They only stress that they will stop supporting the day care center from August 26 this year and that IAS “is not in a position to disclose details at this time” as Zonta Club may contest the decision.
Several parents of children who are in the day care center complained about the confusion caused by the decision, as IAS notified parents about the closure of the daycare centers while the day care centers ensured the continuation of operations, since the day care center may contest and resort to the decision of the authority and did not end the administrative process.
Smart Nursry, however, pointed out that IAS never explained the situation. "The day care center has been very cooperative with the authorities and now we also want to know what the concrete reason [for the end of support] is, and what we did badly," said Christiana Ieong, president of the Macao Zonta Club and director of the nursery.
Speaking to the end point, the official criticized the approach of Hon Wai, president of IAS, for lack of legality in this process. He said that the case is still in the contestation phase, with a period of 15 days, but IAS has already announced the end of the day care center, which “caused panic to parents and society”, questioning the reputation of the day care center and the management association, also impairing the well-being of children.
Christiana Ieong, also ancient Subdirector of Finance Services, revealed that IAS had asked, last Friday, a list of contacts from parents in the scope of “updating information”, but took advantage of the list to inform parents that the day care center would close, not to mention the institution. "As president of IAS, it does not work in accordance with the administrative procedure," he criticized.
The day care center went into operation in 2019 and “has had a quiet operation” with multilingual activities, according to the spokesman, with very positive financial balance and without accidents in child care.
In this sense, the nursery urges the president of IAS to deal with the situation with rationality, justice and impartiality, as well as to give justification of the decision. He also requested the secretary's intervention for social and culture affairs and the chief executive.
According to IAS, there are currently more than 80 children in the day care center and about half of them will enter the kindergarten in September this year.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:19:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Chronic</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/cronica-14/</link><description>Dora Gago
 
Artificial Paradise
 
"Can you solve everything in New York? Can we now be together in the coming months?" Quincy is expressed in fluent English, although sometimes mixed a few words from Thai, as if this linguistic cocktail made her more seductive and mysterious. Sometimes it tries to guess by gestures what words will not say… In fact, their greatest talent is not exactly the gift for tongues, but the art of seduction, with which it has always dropped the most diverse cultural barriers, thanks to a boundless imagination and remarkable power, regardless of circumstances.
"No, you know, it's not easy to solve everything, there are too many things, immense work and always new problems arising. This time, I'll stay here a week. It's not bad, right?"
He has more twenty years than her. They met there in Bangkok four years ago. He came to a company meeting and she was a receptionist at the hotel where she was housed. A problem with channeling in his room and all the necessary steps to resolve the incident approached us.
In the other life, on the other side of the world, he is married, has a son. In order not to be disadvantaged, Quincy pregnant too. John (he insisted on giving him an American name, although he had another Thai, to reaffirm his western strand) was now two years old and was handed over to his grandmother's care that week. He thought that a child would be another factor to weigh on the scale and tilt him to that side of the planet. However, he had deceived. His life has not changed that much. Of course he started to pay him a generous pension. Would you suspect his wife from those encounters? Of the existence of the child? Of that double life? From her husband's ecstasy when landing in Bangkok and run to the five -star hotel closest to the airport, where she was waiting for him to love themselves, as if they ride the fire of the days and nights, in the red and boundless pace of clandestine passions?  Maybe I didn't know or wanted to know. He was rich, could support both families without a problem. And deep down, although he liked to play the role of hopeful, naive and disappointed lover, he did so as long as the monthly fee did not fail the bank account. The rest were fairy tales and love stories for people who didn't have to start making a living at eleven, like her. Therefore, the old American who comes when the woman's idiot or the obsession with her business allows. She will assure her the moments of pleasure, with which he has never even dreamed and it will be enough.
“Dear, I miss you so much” and really stages a stubborn tear to the corner of the eye. He, as it is already part of the routine, hugs her, whispers sweet words and leads her to dinner or lunch in one of the best restaurants. The choice is always hers. And after dinner or lunch, stone in the hotel bed, he finds it difficult to believe in his artificial paradise - so far from New York and the jealousy of the woman, whom he will call a few hours, when the time difference allows him - to simulate longing and an even more false desire to return to the United States. "Without you, time doesn't pass, honey! This week here in Thailand seems to me a year, I can't wait to return." This as a search on the internet, in order to find the house you want to buy at Phuket - your paradise will be even more complete on those beaches. She awaits the purchase to settle with her son. That western are volatile, unfaithful men by nature and given to the most basic instincts, it is known. From one moment to the next, another more attractive and younger woman can start to dwell her bed. And what will hers and the mestizo son when it happens? You have to guarantee the future.
And in a wet hug, the bodies, in a symphony of movement, of pleasure, bury the masks, for the life is made, in this unusual bridge between appearance and essence, to cross the artificial paradises.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:57:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Sporting defends leadership in the Reboleira before rival Benfica</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/sporting-defende-lideranca-na-reboleira-perante-ameaca-do-rival-benfica/</link><description>Sporting seeks to defend the leadership of the First Football League in the Star of Amadora stronghold, in a matchday 27 in which the most direct stalker, Benfica, receives the 'distressed' Farense and FC Porto plays at Estoril.
 
The national champion leads the race with 62 points and goes through a good moment, compared to the three straight wins before the pause for the selections, all 3-1 and with goals from Swedish Viktor Gyökeres, returning to the best way.
However, rival Benfica follows close behind, with three points, and the 'lions' can take the field on the reboleira already on timely equality with the 'eagles', if they surpass Gil Vicente, this Friday, in Barcelos, in a delayed 24th round.
For the confrontation that will take place at José Gomes Stadium, in front of the Amadorense emblem, which has not triumphed for fourth games, coach ‘Leonino’ Rui Borges is still deprived of the injured Nuno Santos, St.just, João Simões, Pedro Gonçalves and Daniel Bragança and, by punishment, does not have Maxi Araújo.
The incarnates will close the 27th day on Wednesday at Estádio da Luz when they receive Farense and, in the image of the lions, also want to keep the triumph sequence in the race-they add six in a row in the I Liga.
By the end of the championship, the Algarvians are probably the most accessible opponent for the team led by Bruno Lage, for what to win is mandatory not to let Sporting escape in the lead.
Absent from the reception to the previous last place are Alexander Bah, Manu Silva and Tiago Gouveia, all due to injury, while Di María and Amdouni can recover in time of the challenge.
In the last place on the podium, with 53 points, the same as Sporting Braga (fourth), is FC Porto, which has been inconsistent in exhibition and results. Still, it remains the lurking of Sporting and Benfica 'slippery' on the eve of receiving the 'eagles' in the 28th round classic on April 6.
The latest travel to the António Coimbra da Mota Stadium were almost always complicated for the 'dragons'-last time they lost to the league and league cup-and on Sunday should be no different, although the host set, eighth, has not won for three games. Argentine coach Martín Anselmi can not count on Marko Grujic and Vasco Sousa, who recover from injury.
Sporting de Braga wants to keep the fight for the last place of the podium at the reception to Arouca on Saturday, with a possible triumph put pressure on FC Porto, and an equality also leaves the worms, provisionally, ahead of the dragons.
On the same day, the Casa Pia-Rio Ave game will open the 27th round, a duel between two teams seeking to return to victories in the competition and will be arbitrated by Catarina Campos, who will be the first woman to arbitrate a clash of the I Liga.
On Sunday, Famalicão will be the host of AVS, while Santa Clara receives Nacional, with the Guimarães derby between Moreirense and Vitória to end the day in Moreira de Conegos. After measuring forces with Benfica for the delayed journey, Gil Vicente moves to Bessa on Tuesday to face red lantern Boavista. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:17:48</pubDate></item><item><title>China asks France to choose multilateralism rather than unilateralism</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/china-pede-a-franca-que-escolha-o-multilateralismo-em-vez-do-unilateralismo/</link><description>Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi yesterday appealed to the French homologist Jean-NOël Barrot, who "chooses multilateralism rather than unilateralism," during a meeting in Beijing.
 
China and France should “look for mutual benefits and advantageous results for both parties, instead of dissociation and isolation,” said Wang, during the meeting with Jean-Noël Barrot, who began a two-day visit to China on Thursday.
The visit of the French minister coincides with the trip to China of the head of Portuguese diplomacy, Paulo Rangel, illustrating the reproach between Europe and the Asian country, in a period when the antagonism of US President Donald Trump shakes transatlantic relations.
Wang Yi's appeal reflects the language often used by China to criticize the US foreign policy and the Western -led political order.
France has firmly supported Ukraine in its fight against Russian invasion, while Beijing has supported Russia at the diplomatic level and provided an economic line of economic life through the purchase of Russian natural resources. Barrot's visit is an opportunity to evaluate China's attitude towards Ukraine before a major meeting organized by France about a possible peacekeeping force in the country.
Conversations arise at a time when fissures are evidenced between the US and Europe regarding support for Ukraine.
French Foreign Minister Jean-Noël Barrot yesterday appealed to a “powerful frank-chinese partnership”, given worldwide crises, but warned that Europe will defend its interests and values. “More than ever, the current context requires a powerful frank-chinese partnership in the service of geopolitical stability, prosperity and the future of our planet,” Barrot defended, visiting Beijing, before meeting his Chinese counterpart, Wang Yi.
The two ministers squeezed their hands on Diaoyutai's state -owned residence in front of the flags of both countries before keeping conversations on the door closed.
Paris said the conversations would focus on the resolution of the Russian conflicts - Ukraine and the Middle East, and in commercial tensions between China and the European Union. "The rhythm of the crises is accelerating," said the French minister, alongside Wang Yi. "Our two countries should therefore promote a stability dialogue that leads to solutions," he said.
France and China have sought to reinforce their ties in recent years. But Paris also approached Beijing's bonds with Moscow, who have narrowed since the war in Ukraine, although China never condemned the Russian invasion. "Given the political, economic and security challenges, a new Europe is emerging rapidly. Its only compass is strategic autonomy," said Jacques Barrot. "Europe will be particularly vigilant in defending its interests and values," he added.
The minister also stressed that Paris and Beijing "must coordinate to promote just and lasting peace in Ukraine." "China also has a role to play to convince Russia to sit at the negotiation table with serious proposals and in good faith," the French minister told the Chinese counterpart. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:17:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Readers under construction</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/leitores-em-construcao-12/</link><description>Make sense in time
Ricardo Fonseca Mota and Rachel Caiano
Save the weather
Horizonte Books
Already there is the time when the books designed for younger readers set aside a series of more, say, existential themes. In this saving time, there was, fortunately, this moral censorship that believes that children are not insightful and unable to realize what surrounds them. With text by Ricardo Fonseca Mota, whose meanings expand through the images of Rachel Caiano - who so often add numerous dimensions to the text, without falling in the temptation to replicate it - this book is openly over time and passage, without being fatalistic.
Approaching a possible definition of “time”, what is shown here is a poetic drift that declies the possible senses to this category that defines us life, even though quantum physics say that objectively does not exist. Here more land crosses the earth, with the criticism of the attempt to tame time between watches, times and hurry (a domestication that is actually ourselves, and not exactly time), and more general reflections on this idea of ​​change, aging, transformation. In the background, what echoes always is the most important, gestures, shares, memories, therefore, everything that allows us, as far as possible, resist the relentless hourglass and feel that, despite everything, cross the time that is in luck is really worthwhile.
The world fits in a dog
Joana Estrela
They
Tangerine Planet
This is a beautiful book to start the very small in the comic, allowing them to accompany them and point to the ellipses, the scene changes, the onomatopoeias, the visual elements that make sense to a story and allow their construction. Anyone who already knew Miau!, A book that can somehow double with this one, will recognize the familiarity with which Joana Estrela summons the animals to characters, not through her humanization, but placing them in a frank dialogue with the human characters, in a proximity that is also discovered and that the younger ones, less given to this habit of tidying in drawers (species included), may read differently from adults.
Without text beyond the onomatopoeias, they will be accompanied by a girl and her parents on the way to a farm, where they will spend some time. In the luggage are the two cats of the family and on Thursday will find a dog, responsible for the title of the book, as well as other animals. Adventures aside, and age limitations in the distance, in this little book that the youngest can read in mode of discovery is a copy of excellence of how the comic band, even without words, can be used to tell a story and fill it with multiple senses and narrative layers.
Ricardo Henriques and André Letria
Foxy &amp; Meg find a mas-but
Logical duck
Klara Persoon
MOLLY &amp; SU
Black orphew
Ana Diniz's translation
Lily Murray and Jenny Løvlie
A dress with pockets
Susana Cardoso Ferreira Translation
Fable
Rui Correia, António F. Nabais and Hélio Falcão
On the contrary
Cloud of letters</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:53:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Criticism</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/critica-13/</link><description>Margarida Ferra
Know how to lose
Companhia das Letras
More sisifo than Penelope
Sucking for two poetry books, intensive gardening course and lucky luck (both with edition of &amp; etc), the first prose book of Margarida Ferool composes six texts, the last one that gives title to the volume. If the texts read autonomously, each maintaining its integrity, reading this knowledge loses another body when the six moments are assumed as chapters of the same text. It will look like structuralist preciousism, but the crossing of these pages deserves to be complete, and even if it is bridged in a benefit in an uncompromising way, giving in one or another text without planning, it is on the full route that is the power line that makes this book a complex mosaic and not just a collage of fragments.
The first chapter, "Games Field", begins with the record of the moment the narrator teaches her son to mileage. It is old the metaphor of the act of weaving related to the narrative, but it is not necessary to reach Penelope, as read on page 23: «Penelope is too spent an image. There are many centuries of misuse of the nights. » It is not the wait (from Ulysses or whoever) or the need to entertain it that guides these writings, but rather the gesture itself, this doing that leads a thread on itself until it becomes a fabric: the writing as a process that is wondered as it is built.
From that beginning, much of what is going through this book is precisely writing, not in its technical aspect or workshop, but in a question about motives, abandonment, dropout, impulses. In this question, a considerable space is occupied by the constant postponement of writing, its material realization: “He refused invitations to go under the pretext that he was writing. ... This modest lie made me feel powerful. A little power over myself: I control my life, to have a few hours for me without saying what I did, without obligations. » (pg.16) While recording loose conversations with Karim, the Pakistani who works at coffee near home, family memories or objects that have remained time, or who have disappeared by action, longer travels or small displacements in space, the narrator reflects on the role that writing can play in a life in her life. These records cross the whole book, but it is at the end of this first chapter (or this first text), which reads: “Alibi has become a defense: writing again, writing about reality, writing so as not to be dominated by what happens to me. Write to name. Write about my life to have some control over it - to be a little more than a witness. ' (pg.27) It is not a closed response, an epiphany that explains and leaves it either, nor would it be expected, but it is an open door to the rest of the text, a way of pointing the light to this web that will confirm, with the pages, huge philigan.
In this confirmation, other wires intersect with this, without imposing a need to identify the dominant wire, which one supports the text. The themes that are being registered and frayed seem to obey the chance of everyday life, without another planning beyond that of the days that happen, or sometimes to a recurring interest and that causes the narrator to turn to the world's interpretation. Knowing how to lose, this interest is linked with museology and museography, expensive areas to the author, whose professional path passes by. But it is not so much biographical drift that calls these areas of knowledge and practice for the text, it is rather a need to give some order to the chaos of the world. Organizing, understanding functions, cataloging, arranging in the right place, all are tools that allow museums to present their collections in a legibly way, and this knowing that the same tools will produce different results over time, another reflection that will punctuate this text, namely from objects that were always presented as naturally belonging to the place where they are exposed, but today, not to be subtracted from another place. Knowing how to lose will be a set of fragmentary texts that collect past stories, daily episodes, separate information about their own biography and some other people, but in a way it may be mainly about this constant tidying that dominates time and the impossibility of ever giving the completed tidying up.
Near the end of the book, in the last of the texts/chapters, the story of a maternal grandfather who hid some current coins on the wall of the house he built, leaving traces, traces for a future, perhaps anticipating ruin, but also anticipating the possibility of communicating something to those who witnessed, or even provoked, this ruin. This gesture is likely to anticipate ruin, but it also anticipated the possibility of communicating something to those who witnessed, or even provoked, this ruin, giving coins this status of talking things, objects that come from a more or less distant past, and to whom we continue to ask questions, or to whom we attribute some kind of sortilégio. More than the metaphors that call texts and tissues in long gestures of urgent, perhaps Sisyphus and their stone are more precious resource for this knowing how to lose, confirming that repeating gestures and paths is not necessarily punishment.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:58:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/breves-24/</link><description>Book exchange
On April 23rd, World Book Day is celebrated and the Cultural Institute marks the date with a book exchange. The collection process has begun, and will continue until April 13, a date until which can be delivered to the Macao libraries the books they want to change. In addition to the exchange of books, during the next month, the city will have a series of reading points created to mark this ephemeris, in an initiative that aims to promote community reading. For this, any entity, association, school or company can present a proposal to create one of these reading points and streamline the idea of ​​sharing what is read with those who want to join.
 

Macao in Photography and Drawing
In the Creative Macao space, at the Cultural Center, you can see until April 17 an exhibition that brings together photographs by Nelson Silva and drawings by João Nuno Marques. Curated by Sara Neves, the exhibition Framing a Future Past | Macau 2018-2024 puts these two languages ​​in dialogue, showing Macao in a record where harmonies and contrasts predominate and where the territory shows in its various layers, calling different times and reflecting on this passage of days, months and years and its effects on urbanism and public space. It deserved a book, so that the exposure deadline would not exhaust the so many dialogues that these images and their disposal provide.

Bologna Fair
It starts on the 31st of this month and extends until April 3 the most important editorial rights fair of the children's and youth sector. In Bologna, publishers and authors from around the world will be present, with the Portuguese delegation including a contingent of several publishers and also the official representation of the Book General Directorate, Archives and Libraries. On April 1, the winner of the Alma - Astrid Lindgren Memorial Award will be announced, for which authors, publishers and projects around the world are appointed, including the Portuguese Adélia Carvalho, André Letria, Catarina Sobral, Bernardo P. Carvalho, Madalena Matoso and Mariana Rio, beyond the Bairro dos Books project.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:59:45</pubDate></item><item><title>COMMA</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/virgula-7/</link><description>The Mexican Dream
Eduardo Antonio's tales Parra make a way in front of those who, reading, advance by the strength of words and, at the same time, by the rural and urban landscapes of northern Mexico. If we kept walking north, we would find the border with the United States. With each step, with each paragraph, we realize that we could pass it and never go back or, as easily, we could die while trying to pass it. In this line, there is a huge distance. We are able to imagine what exists on the other side, but we do not pass, we never pass, we can not pass. On our side of the border, on the edge of this limit remain the limits of misery, suffering and desolation.
In this earth, borders are not only scratched on the floor. An equally defined trace is one that separates sanity from madness. Almost always, sanity is to have power, to send, to break down, to force. Madness is to cross the line of inhuman suffering and fear. This is also the border that separates the center and margin, justifiable and unjustifiable. Then, in the division that, when read, always separates two countries, the one who belongs to the text itself and the one who belongs to the reader, the justifiable becomes unjustifiable and vice versa.
Eduardo Antonio Parra is one of the most notable Mexican short story writer of the last thirty years. His work contributes to news of a collective memory that, although so immense and present, is not the most widespread and dominant. I refer to the perspective of all people who, south of the border that divides Mexico and the United States, dream of the side there, are subject to terrible sacrifices in an attempt to fulfill this dream.
Often this life project is suspended in a limbo, with no possibility of leaving or returning. We, by reading Parra, are taken by inclementary deserts, dreamed villages, real cities, streets and garbage alleys, neighborhoods where life has little value and where cruelty decides who has the right to hope. With us, the last among the last of the Mexican society: migrants, peasants, crazy, vagabonds, prostitutes, wizards, orphans, widows. In the words that describe their faces, we watch the tragedy, but also the tenderness. This is, by the way, one of the strong marks of Parra's writing: his humanity. After a few pages, we know that these characters live and that their suffering is real. In the tragedy that is imposed on them, there is no room for good intentions or socks. The violence that condemns them is absolute and could be reported on the pages of sensational newspapers. However, Eduardo Antonio Parra's approach could no longer move away from voyeurism and the exploitation of violence by crime tabloids. The fundamental difference is the compassion of words that describe their faces, their illusions of happiness, the reality of their lives.
All human beings, even the last, even the most forgotten, are made of contradictions and multiple perspectives that paradoxically reinforce their unity: heterogenea homogeneity. Perhaps for this reason, the tales of Parra are like a kaleidoscope of writing and ways to narrate the world, always including people: from mythological account to realism, from delirium to denunciation, the apparent complexity of poetry to the apparent simplicity of information.
Heir to the Great Mexican Culturers of the tale, Eduardo Antonio Parra opens a way to a world that happens today in northern Mexico, a few distance from the United States border; And that, in other ways, happens much closer, right here.
Their own migrations, whatever they go from, as well as the enormous price in lives and injustice that they cause, and that it is so much feel in the world in which we live, are masterfully theorized by Parra's humanism.
The apparent inevitability of violence, the eternal confrontation of the human being with himself, faith as an invisible and indestructible space of salvation are some of the various aspects that give Parra's work a universal perspective. Northern Mexico is perhaps much closer than imagined.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:42:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Books Montra</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/montra-livros-7/</link><description>Paul French
Destination Macau
Blacksmith Books
After Shanghai and Beijing, Paul French revisit Macao, crossing stories of so many people here or who has passed here, from painter George Chinnery to writer Deolinda da Conceição, and calling episodes, some historical, others perhaps fictional, but eventually helped establish the image of the territory.
 
Sónia Vespeira de Almeida
Build the Revolution - April 25 and the Cultural Dynamization of the MFA
China's ink
This book reports the role that the cultural dynamization campaigns of the Armed Forces Movement had on April 25. Military and people of many formations, men and women linked to culture, science and so many knowledge, walked around the country, taught to read and write, helped build infrastructure, involved in assemblies that decided what was missing in this or that land.
 
Marie Bardiaux-Vaïente and Carole Maurel
Coil 1972
Wing editions
In 1972, at a time when abortion was criminalized in France, Marie-Claire Chevalier, pregnant following a violation, was denounced by clandestine abortion by her own aggressor. Your case will be one of those that will contribute to an intense claim movement that will end the criminalization and this is the story of this process told in comics.
 
Machado de Assis
Quincas Borba
China's ink
In the collection the best of them all, who have been publishing books by Brazilian authors chosen by Clara Rowland and Abel Barros Baptista, China's ink now brings to bookstores one of the most extravagant novels of Machado de Assis and one of the great literary monuments of the Portuguese language.
 
Bruno Vieira Amaral
Everyone has a plan
Quetzal
Bruno Vieira Amaral's new novel is a story about lost possibilities, a tour of the life of Calita, tragic contours character who has an unavoidable obstacle to the realization of his dreams in the past and memories.
 
Ana França
Lampedusa - Go and not arrive
China's ink
Journalist Ana França's long report on the wreck of October 3, 2013 in the Mediterranean, one of the many who has made this sea an authentic marine cemetery. There were 366 people killed off this island of Sicily where every year they try to reach thousands of people escape from war, misery, hunger, oppressive regimes, violence or catastrophic effects of climate change.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:52:05</pubDate></item><item><title>China guides companies to avoid business with Li Ka-Shing after selling ports</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/28/china-orienta-empresas-a-evitar-negocios-com-li-ka-shing-apos-venda-dos-portos/</link><description>Chinese authorities have ordered state-owned companies to stop doing business with Li Ka-Shing, owner of CK Hutchison, who prepares to sell the two ports he controls on the Panama channel, Bloomberg reported yesterday.
According to anonymous sources cited by the news agency, the instruction to veto the Hong Kong entrepreneur was given last week by high employees and only affects new business, without impact on existing collaborations.
Beijing's Directive follows the CK Hutchison agreement this month to sell most of its global port business, including assets on the Panama channel, to a consortium led by US active manager Blackrock.
The sale would leave about $ 19 billion in net revenues for the Hong Kong conglomerate and include not only Balboa and Cristobal ports, but also 41 others controlled by the group in more than 20 countries.
The deal was described by analysts as a lucrative Li play - the richest man in the former British colony and the richest eighth in Asia - in the face of pressure from the new US President Donald Trump.
However, with Trump to boast of the agreement as a US victory over alleged Chinese interference on the channel, Beijing questioned what was also seen as an attempt by CK Hutchison to appease the president of the United States.
Chinese authorities did not directly intervene, but have been pronounced through Hong Kong's pro-peimquin newspapers, warning that companies that collaborate with the US "will not have a future, regardless of the volume of business and money they get", and demanding the cancellation of sales by "impairing national security".
However, Beijing would have difficulty preventing such a business, since Hong Kong's legal system is very different from that of mainland China, although it is doubtful that the security law imposed on the former British colony to block it.
CK Hutchinson is owned by Li, who, at age 96, is the 38th richest person in the world, with a fortune valued at about $ 38.3 billion.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 03:17:05</pubDate></item></channel></rss>