<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/um-realizou-iniciativa-para-integrar-estudantes-internacionais/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Judge rejects accusing members of The 1975 by gay kiss at Malaysian music festival</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/juiz-rejeita-acusar-membros-dos-the-1975-por-beijo-gay-em-festival-de-musica-da-malasia/</link><description>Members of the British band The 1975 cannot be held responsible for the losses of a Malaysian music festival, closed by the authorities after vocalist Matty Health kissed a bandmate on stage.
Good Vibes Festival organizer is asking for £ 1.9 million (2.3 million euros) in losses after Healy criticized the country's anti-human laws and kissed bassist Ross Macdonald at the concert in Kuala Lumpur, in July 2023.
Future Sound Asia sued the 1975 Productions LLP at the Higher Court in London for contractual non -compliance and said that its four members had a duty of care. But the band's lawyer argued that the process should target only the company - not the musicians.
The images of the kiss caused a negative reaction in the predominantly Muslim country, where homosexuality is a crime punishable with up to 20 years in prison and punishment with rods.
Some LGBTQ+ groups also criticized the band for putting their community at risk and disrupting the work of activists who fight for change, the Associated Press (AP) agency (AP) reported.
Judge William Hansen said the charges against the band members were "bad from a legal point of view and that there was no good reason for the matter to go to trial." It allowed the case to continue the company, but ordered the FSA to pay £ 100,000 (120,000 euros) in court costs.
The band's lawyer, Edmund Cullen, argued that the claim was an “illegitimate, artificial and incoherent” attempt to “attribute responsibility to individuals” because the FSA only had a contract with the band's company.
FSA lawyer Andrew Burns said authorities initially refused to let the band act because of reports on healthy drug addiction and their subsequent recovery. They gave in after the band promised that it would follow the guidelines and regulations, he said.
When the band played at the same festival in 2016, they agreed not to say bad words, smoke, drink, take off or talk about religion and politics on stage, Burns added.
Burns said the band deliberately provoked the Malaysian authorities in 2023 by smuggling a bottle of wine to the stage and through the “obscene speech” of Health and the Kiss. He said the band also played a “second -category set of songs” to irritate the crowd.
The band should receive 332 thousand euros (276 thousand pounds) for a one -hour concert, Burns said.
This concert was not the first time Healy made a political statement on behalf of LGBTQ+rights: he kissed a fan at a 2019 concert in the United Arab Emirates, which prohibits same -sex sexual activities.
After the concert in the capital of Malaysia, The 1975 canceled their concerts in Taiwan and Jakarta, Indonesia. The Malaysian government put the band on the Black List.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:33:49+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China defends “equity and justice” of human rights in the UN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/china-defende-equidade-e-justica-dos-direitos-humanos-na-onu/</link><description>Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi underlined the importance of “equity and justice” in human rights, in a UN speech, reaffirming China's position on this issue. "We must insist on equity and justice, and consider the right to subsistence and development as fundamental human rights," Wang said on Monday during a high level meeting of the 58th UN Human Rights Council session. The official rejected the existence of “double or multiple patterns” in this matter.
Chinese diplomacy chief stressed that human rights should not be used as an “instrument of pressure or imposition of foreign models” and appealed to dialogue and mutual learning between nations. "We must firmly reject any action or rhetoric that seeks to impose our own models on other countries or politicize human rights," he added.
Beijing argues for what he says is human rights “centered on people”, based on stability and economic development. The Asian country rejects criticism of its history of human rights as attempts to interfere with its internal affairs.
Human rights organizations such as Amnesty International and the Human Rights Observatory denounce what they consider to be a “systematic repression” of ethnic minorities in Xinjiang and Tibet, regions of northwest China, as well as restrictions on freedom of expression and persecution of activists across the country.
The western powers, led by the United States, criticize China for what they describe how genocide and mass detention in members of the Chinese ethnic minority of Muslim ethnic minority Uigur in Xinjiang, the rigorous surveillance of dissidents and the repression of the demonstrations in Hong Kong after the imposition of the National Security Law in 2019.
Beijing says these accusations aim to harm his image, claiming that the measures contributed to the stability and security of the country.
During the 2024 periodic periodic review of human rights, which has not been held in China since 2018, sources said the Asian country has pressured several countries, especially developing nations, to praise their human rights registration or to make sufficiently vacant recommendations so that Beijing would accept them easily.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:33:23+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China wants to reduce marriage age and eliminate restrictions on the number of children</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/china-quer-reduzir-idade-de-casamento-e-eliminar-restricoes-ao-numero-de-filhos/</link><description>A member of the Chinese government's leading advisory body has proposed to reduce the legal age of marriage to the age of 18 and the elimination of restrictions on the number of children, aiming to increase the birth rate.
The initiative was presented by Chen Songxi, a member of the Chinese Academy of Sciences, as part of the issues to be discussed in this year's “two sessions”, the annual meetings of the National Popular Assembly and the Chinese people's political advisory conference (the main advisory body from the country), which start next week.
The minimum age for marriage in China is 22 years old for men and 20 years for women, while the law allows couples to have up to three children.
Chen stressed that the measure aims to expand the fertile population base and explore China's reproductive potential, in a context of growing concern with the aging of the population and the low birth rate, according to the Global Times, the Chinese Communist Party's official newspaper.
Although the proposal is not intended to force young people to marry an early age, but to offer more options, it is in accordance with international trends on the minimum age for marriage, Chen argued.
According to official statistics, the number of marriages in China was 6.1 million in 2024, the lowest since 1980. In addition to changing legal age, Chen suggested a broader reform of population and birth legislation.
The academic proposed to change the name of the current “Family Planning and Population Law” of 2021, to “law of population and birth”, eliminating any restrictions on the number of children and promoting incentive policies, such as monthly subsidies and medical support for each child up to a certain age.
For several years China has been struggling to increase the number of births, although policies implemented to date have not been able to significantly reverse the low birth rate in urban areas.
The window of opportunity to implement these measures is between 2025 and 2035, a key period when the number of women of childbearing age will stabilize between 290 million and 310 million, he said.
During these years, the authorities expect to conduct surveys on the intentions of having children and adjust the programs to different population groups.
The projected aging of the Chinese population is also alarming for China authorities, where in 2024 more than 15% of the population was 65 years or older and it is estimated that by 2031 more than 20% of the population will have more than 65 years .
By 2050, this percentage is expected to increase to 29.5%, with the consequent negative impact on the country's labor and economy.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:33:47+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau team received gold and silver in a high value patent training contest</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/equipa-de-macau-recebeu-ouro-e-prata-em-concurso-de-formacao-de-patentes-de-alto-valor/</link><description>A team from Macao received a gold and silver prize in the contest for the formation of high value patent formation of the Great Guangdong-Hong Bay Kong-Macau 2024, whose ceremony took place yesterday in Jiangmen.
This contest was subordinate to the theme “Implementing the concept of new development and establishing the high value patent standard” and was organized by the Guangdong Province Market Regulation Administration, by the popular government of the Municipality of Jiangmen, by the Intellectual Property Department of the Raehk government and the DSEDT of the Government of MSAR.
The contest attracted the participation of “innovative subjects” from the interior of China, Hong Kong and Macau, and a record number of 1,660 projects was received. After selection and evaluation in the preliminary and semifinal phases, three Macao projects were selected in the list of the 200 best projects for the contest semifinal. The Macao team eventually received the gold and silver prizes.
Chan Tze Wai, a subdiator of the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), said the contest “effectively introduced innovative subjects in the creation of high value patents, high level of innovation and strong competitiveness in the market, In strategic industrial areas, as well as promoted the transformation, application and industrialization of patents ”.
In a statement, the government says that “it will continue to promote the development of the proper diversification of the economy '1 + 4', in order to foster industry-university-investment cooperation and the transformation of scientific and technological results, reinforce support role and Guidance on scientific and technological innovation in economic development and more actively participate in the construction of the large Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau Bay, in order to serve the national development of high quality ”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:33:16+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing establishes as a goal to eliminate severe pollution in the country by 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/pequim-estabelece-como-meta-eliminar-poluicao-severa-no-pais-ate-2025/</link><description>China announced a significant improvement in air quality in 2024 and set new goals to consolidate these achievements this year, aiming to eliminate severe pollution in the country.
 
Chinese authorities yesterday announced a significant improvement in air quality in 2024 and set new goals to consolidate these achievements this year to eliminate severe pollution in the country. "We must accelerate the elimination of severe pollution days and protect our beautiful blue sky," Li Tianwei, director of the atmospheric Environment Department of the China Ministry of Ecology and Environment at a press conference.
According to the official data provided by the state agency, the average concentration of PM2.5 particles -the finest and most likely to infiltrate the lungs -in 2024, fell to 29.3 micrograms per cubic meter, a homologous reduction of 2 , 7%.
In addition, 87.2% of the days of the year registered good air quality, an increase of 1.7% compared to 2023, while days with severe or worse pollution fell to 0.9% of the total, an improvement 0.7%.
At the regional level, Beijing complied with the National Grade II Air Quality Standard of no more than 35 PM density micrograms 2.5 per cubic meter for the fourth consecutive year, as key areas, such as the Plain of Fenwei (Center ) and the Chengdu-Chongqing (Center) region recorded decreases of 4.8% and 10.8%, respectively, at PM concentration 2.5.
The World Health Organization (WHO) considers PM concentrations 2.5 over 50 micrograms per cubic meter as “severe” atmospheric pollution.
Until 2025, China intends to “essentially eliminate episodes of severe pollution” in priority regions such as Beijing-Tianjin-Hebei and the Plain of Fenwei, added the department representative.
For this purpose, emission control will be intensified in major industries, clean heating will be promoted and regulation of volatile organic compounds (CoV) and mobile pollution sources will be enhanced, the official said.  “We can't expect it for the blue sky, we have to fight for it,” Li insisted, who stressed that the transition to an energy, energy -efficient, energetic, energetic model, will be critical in the future.
In recent years, China, the world's largest emitter of greenhouse gases, has redoubled its efforts to improve carbon dioxide levels, clean the air and maintain biodiversity.
It also established goals such as reaching the peak of carbon dioxide emissions by 2030 and carbonic neutrality by 2060, as well as to make non -fossil fuels represent 25% of the energy produced in the country, where coal still performs a important role. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:33:48+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Deputy suggests creation of psychological support service with artificial intelligence</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/deputado-sugere-criacao-de-servico-de-apoio-psicologico-com-inteligencia-artificial/</link><description>Lam Lon Wai defends the development of psychological support services with artificial intelligence, especially the creation of a platform that provides conversation with robots and initial psychological evaluation. The deputy proposes to the government to use the technology of Deepseek and Migados to provide emotional support to residents.
 
Local mental health services are worrying about Deputy Lam Lon Wai, who has asked the government to develop a psychological support service based on artificial intelligence. The deputy's proposal is for the authorities to launch interdepartmental cooperation and collaboration with technological companies and academic institutions to create an integrated psychological support platform.
According to the deputy, the deputy approached in written interpeação, artificial intelligence technology is developing rapidly, in particular the advanced technology of natural language processing, which has opened new possibilities for providing “efficient and convenient” online psychological support services online .
Lam Lon Wai, in this sense, pointed out that it is possible to introduce or develop a psychological counseling platform with resources to a technology similar to DeepSeek, a large -language artificial intelligence model developed by a Chinese company that has recently become viral.
“Such platforms can provide instant emotional support and preliminary psychological assessment to residents through the conversation with robots while offering 24 hours a day online psychological counseling,” he proposed.
The deputy stressed that artificial intelligence technology has been increasingly popular since the launch of chatbots, such as the GPT chat in 2022. “Studies have shown that artificial intelligence voice assistants can effectively improve symptoms of light depression and anxiety. A moderate, reinforcing problem solving capacity, ”he said.
In addition, Lam Lon Wai stressed that artificial intelligence psychotherapy, as a complement to traditional therapy, is particularly suitable for immediate assistance when there is a lack of professionals.
Also vice-director of Lou Hau Secondary School recalled that in Hong Kong was also developed an application of free mobile phone of “Mental Health Company”, created by a team of students from the University of Hong Kong Innovation and Entrepreneurship Center, provide psychological support to young people.
According to the legislator, the Hong Kong application uses played analysis and artificial intelligence technology to monitor sleep quality, cardiac rhythm, stress index and the use of social platforms by application users, To analyze your mental health, detect emotion and provide suggestions to ask for help. Users can bind to a 24-hour direct line to get professional support of social workers through application help. In addition, the application conceived daily registration and meditation activities as games to encourage users to participate in therapy. "The sector considers that this application can help therapists understand their patients' emotion changes and provide more accurate diagnostics and treatments, and they are also conducive to the popularity and application of applications in the field of mental health," said Lam Lon Wai, Hoping that Macau also develops a similar service.
Lam Lon Wai urges, at the same time, to the government to consider how to integrate technological innovations to deal with and analyze community needs more efficiently and directly, given the acceleration of the development of 'Bighealth' by the executive and the continuous increase looking for psychosocial support from residents in recent years.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:33:17+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>The Roadhouse Macau brings the revelry of the Brazilian Carnival to the streets of Cotai</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/the-roadhouse-macau-traz-a-folia-do-carnaval-brasileiro-as-ruas-do-cotai/</link><description>Macau receives this weekend the most traditional and colorful Brazilian Carnival, with performances by Jandira Silva and DJ Brincher. An event organized by Broadway Hotel on March 1, Saturday, is scheduled to take place at Broadway Macau Food Street and the outside of The Roadhouse Macao. From 17h00, the typical revelry will feature samba parades, dance wheels, performances and activities for children, promising a vibrant and special experience.
 
On March 1st, Saturday, the city will be the scene of a show with a lot of color and music: the traditional Brazilian Carnival. Marked to start at 5 pm, the event will take place at Broadway Macau Food Street and the outside of The Roadhouse Macau, located near the Galaxy-Casino Hotel. The party promises to be a celebration of traditions, music and flavors, highlighting the rich culture of Brazil.
With a diverse program and support from the Brazilian Consulate General in Hong Kong, Broadway's “Brazilian Carnival In Macao” will be a real party for all ages. The festivities will begin with “CarnaKids”, a special moment dedicated to children, providing a lively and familiar atmosphere. The central event, the great parade of samba, will be followed at 6.30 pm, which will be attended by the Macao Samba School and Axé Capoeira Macau, two institutions that promise to bring the contagious joy of Brazil's so traditional musical style and energy of capoeira, presenting the traditions that are synonymous with the recognized Brazilian Carnival.
At 19h00, the rhythms of Brazil will continue to resonate with a samba wheel, a more intimate and participatory moment, allowing the guests to dance and surrender to the authenticity and vibration of the party. In addition to the various options of Brazilian food and drink that will be available, one of the most anticipated moments will occur at 8:30 pm, when the fantasy parade will take over the space, rewarding the most original and inspiring creations, once again encouraging the participation of those present .
The singer Jandira Silva will take the stage at 21h00, offering a performance full of animation and contagious music with well -known classics. The night will continue with DJ Brincher, which will ensure the best beats and maintain the energy high from 10 pm.
After another presentation of Jandira Silva at 11:00 pm, DJ Brincher will end the celebration at dawn, leading everyone to dance until the early hours of the next day.
The manager of The Roadhouse Macau, Florendo Amabilis, expressed his enthusiasm about the event, stating that the realization of the Brazilian Carnival in Macau is a great opportunity to promote Brazilian culture and the union of communities.  “[The event] promises to be a highlight for our community, offering a wonderful opportunity to show and share the rich culture of Brazil,” said Amabilis.
The Brazilian Carnival has deep roots in the cultural history of the country, combining influences of African, indigenous and European traditions. It originated at the festivities that preceded Lent, with the “Burning” in Portugal, where people had fun with water and food play. The word carnival has its origin in Latin, specifically in the expression "carnis leadle", which means "to take the flesh." This meaning is associated with the fasting that should be practiced during Lent, as well as containing the pleasures of earthly life. This reveals an attempt by the Catholic Church to moderate the desires of his faithful.
With the arrival of the colonizers on the American continent, this tradition has evolved and mixed with African rhythms and local dances, especially in cities such as Rio de Janeiro and Salvador. Over the centuries, Carnival has become a large event, famous for samba school parades, street blocks and parties, celebrating Brazil's cultural diversity and attracting millions of visitors every year.
According to the organizers, this Brazilian Carnival in Macau is an excellent opportunity for the community to gather and celebrate the cultural diversity of a centenary tradition. The party invites all participants to wear their most exuberant carnival costumes, enriching the festive and colorful atmosphere.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Average price per room of five -star hotel drops 2.3% in annual terms</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/preco-medio-por-quarto-de-hotel-de-cinco-estrelas-cai-23-em-termos-anuais/</link><description>In early 2025, a 2.3% decrease in prices of higher-rated hotel rooms in Macao was observed, a counterbalanced by an increase of 4.5% in the occupancy rate. On the other hand, four -star hotel rates have increased, as well as the occupancy rate of the globality of hotels. All major masters' main markets have grown in homologous terms except Thailand. STD has already announced efforts to continue to promote Macau and expand the market of visitors from Southeast Asia.
 
In January, the average price per night of the five -star hotel rooms in Macau decreased by 2.3% over the same period of 2024.
According to data provided by the Macao Hotel Association to Macau Tourism Data Plus, a platform of the Tourism Services Directorate (STD), the average rate of the rooms in this category recorded a decrease of 1,587.2 patacas in 2024 for 1,550.2 Patacas, in the first month of the year 2025.
January thus becomes the seventh consecutive month to mark a homologous decrease in the average price of five-star hotel rooms. The latest homologous growth took place in July 2024, with an increase of 3.6% over the same period of 2023. Since then, consecutive decreases have been registered between 0.1% and 10.2%.
Nevertheless, the global average of hotel rates under the purview of this association - including those with lower four and three -star classifications - grew 1.5%from 1,387.2 patacas to 1,408.2 calculated in January. Four -star hotels were those where there was a more pronounced climb, around 13.2%, followed by three -star hotels, with a growth of 12.1%.
As for occupancy rates, the global average of hotels rose from 91% to 94.7%, which translates into a 3.7% increase compared to 2024. The occupancy rate of five star hotels was the one that most grew (+4.5%), rising from 90.7% from last year to 95.2% in January 2025. Four star hotels are followed, with a 2.6% rise, and those of Three stars, with 2.2%.
The statistics mentioned concern hotels and resorts members of the Macao Hotel Association, which brings together a total of 46 establishments: 26 with the five -star classification, 13 with four stars and seven with three stars.
 
STD wants to expand Southeast Asia tourist market
 
Data provided by STATISTICS and STD census services have no changes to the podium of the main visitor markets of MSAR since at least 2008 - the year that dates back to the first data provided by the “Macao Tourism Data Plus” platform. The interior of China invariably comes first, this time with a homologous growth of 27.4%. Raehk follows, with a less significant increase of 5.8%, and the Taiwan region rising 29.8%. Only these three regions of the podium represent 91.1% of the total tourists welcomed by MSAR in January.
Here are South Korea, Philippines and Indonesia, with homologous increases of 29.9%, 42.2%and 54.6%, respectively. The news comes from the seventh place, with the United States climbing the table, due to a 13.2%homologous increase, and Japan ascending from tenth to eighth place, with a growth of 13%. Completing the list of the top ten tourist markets are Malaysia (with a 9%climb) and Thailand. This last country stands out as the only one to go down in homologous terms, suffering a decrease of 26.6% compared to January 2024.
The list also includes data related to visitors from other unspecified countries, representing 1.6% of the total visitors and also mark a growing trend (plus 8.3% compared to January 2024). The total homologous visitors rose 27.4%, and the entry of 3,646,561 tourists in Macao was accounted for in the first month of the year.
In a press release, STD announces its intention to “continue to move efforts to expand the Southeast Asia visitors market”, where most countries in the last half of the table come from. One of the initiatives already developed consisted of the participation of the Indonesian International Tourism Fair, “one of the greatest indoles of consumers' indonese tourism”, for the third consecutive year.
In the 2025 edition, STD installed a macao pavilion decorated with the mascot of Marem Tourism, Mak Mak, and some of the characteristic features of the merger of sino-Portuguese crops, such as tiles and floors on Portuguese sidewalk. In the four tourist promotion sessions for interaction with the public, dancing from the lion and Portuguese folk dances were also displayed.
Tourism services also announce have invited 21 tour operators from Jakarta and Surubaia for a “familiar visit” to Macau, between January 1 this year, considering that this initiative “helped boost cooperation between both sides”.
For this year, informs the STD, are planned tourist promotions in Korea, Japan, Singapore, Indonesia, Thailand and Malaysia, with the aim of continuing to encourage a “greater diversity of visitor markets and boosting tourism and the economy of Macao” .
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:33:48+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai highlights the importance of SMEs and promises measures to revitalize old neighborhoods</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/sam-hou-fai-destaca-importancia-das-pme-e-promete-medidas-para-revitalizar-bairros-antigos/</link><description>To prepare the lines of governing action (LAG), the chief executive has held meetings to hear some sectors of society. He has recently met with Macao members in the National Committee of the Chinese Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC) and representatives of the Macao Small and Medium Enterprises Association (PME). During the meetings, Sam Hou Fai promised measures to revitalize the old neighborhoods, highlighting the importance of SMEs.
 
Sam Hou Fai has met, in recent days, with members of Macao in the National Committee of the Chinese People's Political Conference (CCPPC), representatives of the Macao Small and Medium Enterprises Association (PME) and also with the Association for the promotion of China-Asean industrial development cooperation. The meetings served to prepare this year's Governing Action Lines (LAG).
At the meeting with the Chief Executive, Stanley Au, president of the SME association, said the new government will “establish a fair, rational and incentive investment environment, and encourage SMEs to resort to computer technology and artificial intelligence to increase productivity ”.
Stanley au, who was a candidate for the position of head of the Executive of MSAR in 1999, asked Sam Hou Fai to efficiently use human resources, in order to revitalize the economy of old neighborhoods and improve the level of science and technology and the technology Professional Education of Higher Education Establishments. The SME representative also suggested to the government to launch measures to create good employment opportunities for Macao residents.
Other issues under discussion at this meeting had to do with the opportunities of the low altitude economy, the construction of the qualified framework incubation base necessary for the different industries, the promotion of the 'Big Health' industry, the encouragement of return to Macao of small and medium -sized transforming industries, the economic vitality of residential neighborhoods, and the promotion of cultural tourism for the construction of Macau as a “city of concerts”.
Sam Hou Fai assured that the opinions of the association will be taken into account in the elaboration of LAG and indicated that “SMEs are an important force for the socioeconomic development of Macao”, contributing “significantly to the sustainable and healthy development of the local economy and employment market ”.
The chief executive pointed out the “valuable historical and cultural context” of the old neighborhoods and promised that the government will “proceed, globally and integrated, to the work of revitalizing neighborhoods, giving constant impetus to the cultural and tourist economy”. The aim is to “ensure the business environment for SMEs and employment opportunities for the population of Macao,” said Sam Hou Fai, cited in the government's press release.
 
Aging of the population, education and diversification
 
At the meeting with Macao members at CCPPC, topics such as population aging, education and the diversification of the economy were focused.
Ho Ion Sang, a permanent member of the CCPPC National Committee, has asked the government to revise demographic policy in the face of changes in the Macao society in the last decade. Also deputy to the Legislative Assembly of the MSAR suggested the extension of the paid maternity leave and the paternity license, the increase in birth allowance, the introduction of policies favorable to the family and housing.
Zhang Zongzhen suggested the formation of qualified staff for the in -depth cooperation zone, in order to “provide strength for the economic diversification of Macao”. Lao NGA Wong has requested the improvement of the “Patriotic Political Training System” and the creation of a team of civil service workers “with a political, competent and high quality morals”.
Sam Hou Fai answered promising "adding different projects of leisure, culture and tourism in the old neighborhoods to divert the flow of tourists and increase the tourist attraction of Macao." The Chief Executive also said that “the unique advantages of Macau and the integrated development of education, science and technology and qualified paintings as foundations, forming and supporting the development of all kinds of highly highly highly highly founded, forming and supporting the development of the development of the development of the development of the development of the development of the development of the development. Qualified, attract and bring together high quality qualified pictures and promote the development of Macau as a place of aggregation of prominent international qualified frames. ”
 
Cooperation with Southeast Asia
 
At the meeting with the Association for the Promotion of China-Asean Industrial Development Cooperation, Sam Hou Fai indicated that the Government “has been committed to deepening exchange and cooperation between Macao and ASEAN countries, with the purpose of expanding the Cooperation space, ”he said he was“ very pleased with the association's visit to promote China-Asean industrial development cooperation to Macau to increase exchange with all sectors places ”.
The chief executive also said that the government will actively "perform the strength and advantages of the overseas Chinese and their family members who returned to Macau." Finally, the leader of the Government of MSAR has made votes to be driven “the exchange and cooperation between Macao and the countries of ASEAN”, and that there is a “joint and quality promotion of 'a track, a route', with The aim of contributing to building Macau as a higher level opening platform. ”</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:31:23+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Filming team that caused a road accident “not fulfilled” CPSP guidelines</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/equipa-de-filmagem-que-causou-acidente-de-viacao-nao-cumpriu-orientacoes-do-cpsp/</link><description>The Public Security Police body said it had disagreed with the filming of high-speed driving on the seminary street, where a road accident occurred on Monday. The filming team "did not fulfill" the guidelines presented by the police authorities and the police said that "there is no conditions" for a fine process. Already the Cultural Institute ensured that it is also investigating the situation.
 
The 12 injured, victims of a run over during a filming on Monday, were discharged from Kiang Wu Hospital after medical treatment. Authorities continue to investigate the case, and the Public Security Police (CPSP) confirmed that the shooting team did not respect the authorities' directions on the conduction on site.
“Police expressed explicitly deconcidation about the filming method proposed by the filming team. But the group did not meet the relevant requirements during the shoot, so the police have already reported the situation of non-compliance with the Cultural Institute, ”said Wong Wai Chon, CPSP spokesman at a press conference held yesterday.
The authorities, according to the Chinese channel of Rádio Macau, held an interdepartal coordination meeting about this filming in Macau. At that time, the opinions presented by CPSP included the ban on dangerous driving behaviors in the area concerned. "Once the street there is narrow and has tight curves, the place is not suitable for high speed driving," the agent explained, ensuring that he asked the filming team to film safely.
Asked about the sanctioning process, as a fine, to the filming team following the failure of the guidelines, the CPSP, however, indicated that there are no conditions for a judicial action at this time.
“There is no information on measuring. But the team had obtained a filming authorization from the Cultural Institute and the filming activities of the entire team were not considered illegal work, so the conditions were not gathered to process the case, ”he said.
The accident occurred on Monday afternoon during the production of a film, where a driver lost control of the car and ran over 12 colleagues from the filming team. Two residents of Macao, nine residents of the continent, and a person from Singapore recorded slight injuries.
The preliminary investigation of the authorities says that the car involved was walking in a closed circulation zone and authorized to the shoot. The driver will have lost control of the vehicle causing the car to stuff in a seal before rushing to a alley, which was not an area predicted to circulation of car and where the 12 actors were resting and waiting for filming.
The driver concerned comes from the interior of China and entered Macao on the same day of filming, having passed the alcohol research exam after the accident.
The Geographic Information Network for Traffic of Cartography and Registration Services also shows that the area was conditional on traffic due to the filming work of the “Communication Communication Company Grande Time Bay. Lda ”.
In turn, the Cultural Institute (IC) said the investigation of the accident is still pending and is collecting information about the case before further details to the public. Regarding filming requests, according to Leong Wai Man, president of the IC, entities may request the license through the license and filming platform. "The IC, thus, in its quality of service responsible, will send relevant filming plans for the competent services, to provide an opinion on the viability of the proposals," he explained.
Leong Wai Man added that for some of the filming projects with more advanced technical requirements, the authorities call a group meeting for approval, although meetings may not be necessary "if they are not special circumstances," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:32:18+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong Ethnic Minority Defense Association ponders closing doors</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/associacao-de-defesa-das-minorias-etnicas-de-hong-kong-pondera-fechar-portas/</link><description>Hong Kong Unison, an association created 24 years ago to defend the rights of ethnic minorities in the former British colony, will consult members about closing doors, local press said. According to the newspaper Ming Pao, the organization's management will meet on Friday to discuss a special resolution that, if approved, will lead to the voluntary dismissal of members. "The plan has nothing to do with political pressures or financial reasons," said the Pro-Pequim newspaper.
Hong Kong Unison was founded in 2001 and constituted as a non -profit organization in 2005. According to the Internet portal, the Association aims to promote racial equality and opportunities in social participation, “especially in education, for minorities Hong Kong ethnics, through the influence of policies and the change of practices. ” According to the latest official data, in 2021 they lived in Hong Kong almost 620,000 people of ethnic minorities, representing about 8.4% of the population.
Hong Kong Unison was involved in the implementation of legislation against racial discrimination, which was promulgated in July 2008 and came into force a year later. After Beijing imposed the first national security legislation in 2020, many of the city's main pro-democracy activists were arrested and others fled abroad. Dozens of civil society groups have been dissolved and media such as Apple Daily and Stand News closed. On Thursday, the Hong Kong Democratic Party, the largest opposition party and one of the last to function, announced that it would consult members about the possibility of dissolution, which would end more than 30 years of political activity. Party President Lo Kin -i stated that a working group will organize a general assembly for the 400 members to make a final decision on the party's future and deal with legal issues related to dissolution.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:33:47+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“In Macau, there are more and more women who exceed the limitations imposed by tradition”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/em-macau-ha-cada-vez-mais-mulheres-que-ultrapassam-as-limitacoes-impostas-pela-tradicao/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai was present at the commemorative reception of International Women's Day, organized by the General Association of Women of Macao. At the time, the Chief Executive reiterated the commitment to defend the rights of women and equal opportunities for both sexes.
 
The chief executive was present at the commemorative reception of International Women's Day, organized by the General Association of Macao Women, which also served to take office and the organization's fiscal council. At the time, Sam Hou Fai spoke, stating that "it is inspiring that, in Macao, there are more and more women who exceed the limitations imposed by tradition."
At the meeting, women join “actively in different sectors and branches of activities, with tuning and incessant commitment”, having the “ambition to be extraordinary women in their position, demonstrate talents and splendid skills, becoming an indispensable force for development Economics and Society of Macao, ”said Sam.
However, “we are also well aware that many women still face various challenges and difficulties,” said the government leader, reiterating the “commitment of the mashely government in defending women's rights and equal opportunities for both sexes” .
"We will continue to unite all sectors of the community to safeguard women's rights and well-being in Macao," he said, "We will continue to promote faster and better development of women's affairs, we will support compatriots in building their own Professional careers, encouraging them to perform their life aspirations that develop their talents. ”
Sam Hou Fai said he hopes that Macao women “will continue to demonstrate their unique charisma, to gather strength and be brave, to contribute to their wisdom and ability in their professions, and to continue to use their advantages and use full use and unique roles in the construction of family civility ”.
On the other hand, the boss expects women to “give a new boost in the practice of 'a country, two systems' with Macao characteristics and continue to gain new merits in the opening of a new conjuncture of Macao's high quality development in Macao, great cause of the strengthening of the country and the rejuvenation of the Chinese nation ”.
In the speech, Sam Hou Fai pointed to the changes over the last 100 years: "Women have gone from home work to work in society, no longer confined behind the scenes to take the stage, gain visibility." “With their perseverance and a spirit of hard work, they shone in various domains and gained equal rights and respect. With entrepreneurship, wisdom and courage, women from all countries wrote their own glorious chapters, ”he said, highlighting“ the pioneers of female emancipation ”.
About the General Association of Macao Women, Sam Hou Fai indicated that, since it was created 75 years ago, the organization “has always led to the beautiful tradition of patriotism, love to Macau and care for women and children” , also making "major contributions to the development and progress of Macao's women and children, with remarkable achievements."</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:33:21+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao is present at the 57th Session of the Tufões Committee</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/macau-marca-presenca-na-57a-sessao-do-comite-dos-tufoes/</link><description>The 57th session of the Tuphin Committee took place in Manila, in the Philippines, from 17 to 20 February. The MSAR was represented at the event by the Directorate of Meteorological and Geophysical Services (DSMG).
According to a press release, the delegation of Macao and “about 100 experts in meteorology, hydrology and prevention and reduction of disasters from Asia-Pacific” made the appreciation and balance of works developed in 2024, and project the work plan to project the work plan for 2025.
DSMG reports that “it actively participated at various points in the agenda, sharing its experiences on tropical storm forecast techniques and disaster prevention and reduction work, as well as the way of reinforcing regional cooperation in order to better communicate the challenges brought by tropical storms. ”
DSMG's head of the delegation and director, Leong Weng Kun, said he will strive “in promoting exchange and meteorological cooperation at the international and regional level”, together with the other members of the committee, while promoting the development of techniques of meteorological surveillance in Macau.
Leong Weng Kun also announced that the 20th Seminar on the Integration of the Tuphin Committee will take place in the fourth quarter of this year, assuming “honored” for contributing to “an important platform for exchange and cooperation in meteorological technology” in Asia Pacific.
The Tuphin Committee was set together by the United Nations Economic and Social Commission for Asia and the Pacific (Escap) and the World Meteorological Organization (WMO) in 1968, currently with 14 national and regional members. Its objective is to reinforce regional cooperation in order to reduce the damage caused by vapors and natural calamities in the Asia-Pacific region.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:32:41+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Central Bank of South Korea reduces interest rates due to poor growth</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/banco-central-da-coreia-do-sul-reduz-taxas-de-juro-devido-ao-fraco-crescimento/</link><description>South Korea Central Bank reduced interest rates by 0.25 percentage points to 2.75%. The cut takes place after the Korea bank had kept the reference rates unchanged in December and was the third reduction since October.
 
South Korea Central Bank yesterday reduced interest rates by 0.25 percentage points to 2.75%a month after reviewing the forecast for economic growth.
The cut takes place after the Korea Bank (Bok) had kept the reference rates unchanged in December and was the third reduction since October. This after the Central Bank had kept the interest rate on the rise for four years and five months, for fear of the high levels of inflation left by the Covid-19 pandemic.
In the monetary policy report for 2025, the South Korean Central Bank said new rate cuts aim to "maintain the moderate pace of inflation growth," as well as "mitigating risks to the economy."
In the document, Bok promised to be more attentive to avoid any volatility in the financial markets, in the midst of the uncertainty caused by the return to power in the United States of Donald Trump.
The prospects for South Korea exports are more modest after Trump's reelection, which promised to impose tariffs on imports, including the automotive industry, one of the key sectors for the South Korean economy.
Yesterday's decision stressed the focus of Bok's policy in economic growth, since on January 20, the institution had reviewed the forecast for growth in 2025 of the fourth largest economy in Asia, from 1.9% to 1.5%. "The unexpected statement of martial law in early December, along with the continuous political instability and disaster of the Jeju Air passenger plane, significantly affected economic sentiment," the Central Bank underlined.
A Boeing 737-800 of the South Korean airline Jeju Air drew on December 29 at Muan Airport (Sudoeste), killing 179 people, the worst air disaster ever occurred on South Korean soil.
The accident and the political crisis "led to contractions in domestic consumption and investment in construction, which probably pushed the fourth quarter growth rate well below the November projection," said the Central Bank.
Therefore, the institution estimated that growth in the fourth quarter of 2024 was “far below the initial projection of 0.5%, possibly reaching 0.2% or a little less”.
The Central Bank of South Korea has also reviewed the growth estimate to 2024, which goes from 2.2% to “an interval between 2% and 2.1%”. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:33:49+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Tesla announces implementation of advanced autonomous conduction functions in China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/tesla-anuncia-implementacao-de-funcoes-avancadas-de-conducao-autonoma-na-china/</link><description>The American electric vehicle manufacturer Tesla announced yesterday the launch of advanced autonomous driving functions for its cars in China, including Autopilot, on the streets of major cities.
 
The announcement comes after several years of attempts by the US company to overcome regulatory obstacles that prevented this update in the Chinese automobile market.
Tesla explained that it will gradually launch a 'software' update that includes 'autopilot -assisted automatic driving on the streets of cities' and a role in the rearview mirror that detects whether or not drivers are paying attention. These features are similar to those of the FSD (Full Self-Driving '(FSD) system that the manufacturer offers in the United States.
Cars equipped with this software are not, in fact, fully autonomous, and are intended to be used under the control of a driver.
The update “has been launched for certain automobile models and will be gradually extended to other appropriate models,” the company said in a statement published on the Chinese Wechat social network.
According to the Bloomberg Financial News Agency, the plan allows users who paid the equivalent of $ 8,800 through the FSD package to use it on urban roads.
According to sources cited by Bloomberg, Tesla will have offered its employees in China the ability to participate in a pilot test of these systems before they are launched to the public.
Musk moved to Beijing in April, where he met with government leaders, including Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang, to discuss FSD's viability in China.
Tesla has signed a cartography and navigation agreement with Chinese Baidu technology and met local data security and privacy requirements.
However, in January, during a call with analysts after the release of the results, Musk acknowledged that Tesla still faced challenges to launch FSD in China, blaming the limitations that both Beijing and Washington imposed the way the company trains its system to recognize the local roads.
According to Musk, Tesla engineers were solving the problem using internet videos showing streets in China to instructions to the system.
Driver assistance technologies are becoming increasingly common in the Asian country, where the local BYD company, the world's largest electric car manufacturer, recently announced a system known as “God's Eye” that will be incorporated into vehicles with Prices from equivalent to $ 9,630.
China is an important market for Tesla, which has two factories in the country and is trying to compete with local rapidly growing electric vehicle manufacturers. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:33:49+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea Delegation arrives in Moscow for an official visit</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/delegacao-da-coreia-do-norte-chega-a-moscovo-para-visita-oficial/</link><description>A high-level delegation from the North Korean single party arrived in Moscow for an official visit to the party's party invitation in Russia, the North Korean state press said yesterday.
 
The delegation of the North Korean Workers Party, led by Ri Hi-Yong, a member of the North Central Committee Politburo, landed in the Russian capital on Monday after an invitation from the United Russian Party, the official news agency said North Korean KCNA.
Andrey Klimov, a member of the United Russian Party Supreme Committee and deputy chief of the party's foreign activities committee, received the North Korean delegation to his arrival at the airport, KCNA said without further details.
The visit occurs at a time when the United States began negotiations to end Russia's Ukraine invasion, which has been supported by thousands of North Korea troops on the ground.
New US President Donald Trump said on Monday that the priority was to reach an agreement to end the war in Ukraine, although he was open to a ceasefire as a preliminary step for deeper negotiations.
Since signed a mutual defense treaty last year, Pyongyang and Moscow have reinforced bilateral cooperation in defense, economy, sports and various other fields.
Relations between North Korea and Russia, which share only 20 kilometers of border, intensified in mid-2024, with Russian President Vladimir Putin's first visit to Pyongyang since 2000.
According to South Korean, Ukrainian and Western sources, Pyongyang provided Moscow large amounts of ammunition in exchange for the transfer of civil, spatial and military technology.
In addition, both countries have signed a strategic treaty that provides for mutual military assistance in case of aggression and more than 10,000 North Korean soldiers will have been sent to Russian territory to combat Ukrainian troops in the Russian border regions.
 
New British sanctions aim at Chinese and Officers from North Korea
 
The British government has announced yesterday the “largest package of sanctions against Russia since 2022”, which aims to provide companies from military components from China, Turkey and India, and North Korean military officers.
Announced to coincide with the third anniversary of the Ukraine invasion of Russia on February 24, 2022, the package of 107 sanctions to people and entities “targets Russian military supply networks, revenues that feed Putin's illegal war war And the cleptocrats who generate profits for Kremlin, ”says a statement from the United Kingdom Ministry of Foreign Affairs.
Sanctions are aimed at not only Russian companies and organizations that are contributing to the defense sector, but also entities in third countries - such as China, Thailand, India or Turkey - goods such as machines and electronic products used in weapons systems.
North Korean Defense Minister at Kwang Chol and other generals and senior North Korean officials are others targeted by sanctions due to the sending of more than 11,000 soldiers to combat Russian forces.
For the first time, a foreign financial institution was included, the OJSC Keremet Bank, based in Kirguizistan, which will be used by Russia.
This new package adds 40 more ships of the 'shadow fleet' that carries Russian oil to reduce Moscow's recipes and 14 “new cleptocrats” that drive large Russian companies such as Roman Trotsenko, one of Russia's richest men.
British Foreign Minister David Lammy said these measures intend to increase pressure on Russia to make concessions during peace negotiations.  “Each interrupted military supply line, each blocked ruble and every facilitator of Putin's exposed aggression is one step towards just and lasting peace and safety and prosperity in the UK,” he said.  “Lasting peace will only be achieved through strength. This is why we are committed to putting Ukraine as strong as possible, ”he added.
In total, the United Kingdom sanctioned more than 2,100 people and entities, of which 1,900 since 2022. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:33:50+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Health services recorded 2,529 cases of transmissible diseases in January</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/servicos-de-saude-registaram-2-529-casos-de-doencas-transmissiveis-em-janeiro/</link><description>Health services (SS) accounted for a total of 2,529 cases of compulsory declaration diseases. The data refer to the month of January this year. Among the most common diseases are influenza, scarletin and norovirus infection.
Influenza cases totaled 2,190, indicating a 30.9% reduction compared to the same month of the previous year. However, there was a remarkable increase compared to the previous month. Such variation reinforces the seasonal nature of the disease, which tends to get worse during the colder months. Experts emphasize the importance of vaccination, especially for high-risk groups, such as elderly and patients with pre-existing conditions.
Scarletin showed 97 cases, showing a 55.7% drop from last year. Despite the decrease, the disease remains a concern, especially among the child population, and its early identification is crucial to start treatments with effective antibiotics.
Norovirus infection, although with 82 recorded cases, demonstrated a substantial increase over the same month of the previous year, highlighting the need for rigor in food hygiene practices. Norovirus is known for its high contagion, often transmitted by contaminated foods or surfaces.
Influenza is a highly contagious acute respiratory disease, common in winter and spring. In Macao viruses a (H1N1 and H3N2) and B) predominate mainly mainly by saliva droplets and contact with secretions, has symptoms such as fever, muscle pain and cough.
Scarletin, caused by hemolytic beta streptococcus, above all affects children between 2 and 8, manifesting with fever, sore throat and rash. Antibiotic treatment is effective, but the lack of it can lead to serious complications.
Norovirus infection causes gastroenteritis, transmitted by contaminated food or water and contact with excrement, with higher incidence also in winter.
SS reinforce the need for population awareness of preventive measures and the importance of adherence to public health recommendations and personal hygiene, which are essential for the prevention of outbreaks of this type of diseases.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:32:45+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DSAT will launch a new taxi contest to caution licenses about to expire</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/dsat-vai-lancar-novo-concurso-para-taxis-para-acautelar-licencas-prestes-a-caducar/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) is preparing a new public tender to replace licenses that will expire this year. Authorities also indicated that they are studying ways to increase taxi response rate to requests.
 
The government is accelerating the preparatory work to carry out a new public tender for taxis, in order to prepare the replacement of licenses that will expire this year, indicated the direction of services for traffic issues (DSAT), in response to A written interpellation of Deputy Leong Sun Iok. The details of the contest have not yet been released by the authorities.
At this moment they operate in Macau about 1,750 taxis. Of these, 300 are special. According to DSAT previously revealed, in the first nine months of last year more than 30 million special taxis calls were received, and the response rate has been low. In fact, from the data provided by DSAT last year, it appears that each special taxi receives an average of 370 requests per day.
At the question, Leong Sun Iok wondered if the government had plans to promote the call of taxis over the internet, as Hong Kong is studying the implementation of diplomas on the subject. In the answer, DSAT stated that "it will remain attentive to legislative update and the complementary work related to the provision of passenger transport services by online marking in neighboring regions", indicating that it will proceed to the "necessary studies in timely time".
The body also added that it is studying "the number of special taxis and ways to increase its response rate to the call, continuing to alert the opinions of society and to present suggestions, in order to respond to the needs of residents and tourists."
In the last public tender for the taxi operation, licenses were assigned to ten companies to the operation of a total of 500 vehicles. The public contest caused controversy and was the subject of complaints by some of the candidates who claimed lack of transparency of the process. In the contest, almost half of the 40 proposals submitted were not allowed, and some were accepted and then rejected. DSAT admitted, at that time, that it received contestation from some excluded companies, but reiterated that the procedures of the public opening of the proposals were conducted according to the law. Macao Nova Era Taxi, S.A., subsidiary of state companies China Travel Service (Macau) Limited, was first place on the list, with the highest license price, corresponding to 3.8 million patacas.
Recently it was also known that in January this year, the irregularities practiced by taxi drivers tripled, compared to last year's same month.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:34:20+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>One held an initiative to integrate international students</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/26/um-realizou-iniciativa-para-integrar-estudantes-internacionais/</link><description>The University of Macao (one) organized an initiative to integrate its international students. This first edition of the “Empowering Your Future: Cultural Immersion and Opportunity Experience in Macao” was attended by 30 students from abroad and ten more ambassadors of the institution.
The program aimed to improve the understanding of Macao and the one by its international students. Cultural activities were organized and visits to explore the advantages and development opportunities in Macao and one.
According to the press note, the international students who participated "agreed that the program provided them with unforgettable experiences and reinforced their calls with local students."
The program included "a wide range of activities organized by students and teachers from residential colleges, such as lectures on various topics, local visits and workshops." "These activities gave international students a vision of the history of Macao, their urban development, their special characteristics and their unique political status."
The students visited the integrated resorts and the Macao entertainment complexes and obtained information about their development and the industry; They experienced Chinese tea culture and learned preparation techniques with tea specialists; They learned basics of Nanquan martial art from Wong Sam In, a student of UM and Nanquan champion of the world university games; And they acquired knowledge about the principles of conception of ancient Chinese architecture, construction techniques and their cultural meaning by building a miniature bridge with Chinese characteristics.
Guided by college scholarships and professional tourist guides, international students explored the historic places of Macao, walked through their streets and alleys, enjoyed the typical macanese dishes and got to know the culture of Macao.</description><pubDate>2025-02-26T03:32:40+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>