<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/raymond-tam-pede-reducao-do-prazo-de-execucao-de-obras-viarias-e-aplicacao-de-novas-tecnologias/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Rui Cunha Foundation exposes calligraphy works</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/fundacao-rui-cunha-expoe-obras-de-caligrafia/</link><description>It is inaugurated today, at 6.30 pm, the collective exhibition of handwriting entitled “Feelings Exprsed in Ink” at the Rui Cunha Foundation. The show will display about 60 works of calligraphy the pen and brush by 40 amateur artists between 45 and 88 years old, senior students of the artist and teacher to WAN U, from the I Chon Center of the General Union of Macao Residents Associations, an event co-organized in partnership with the Jardim da Flora Friends Poetry Association. The entrance is free and the works will be exposed until this Saturday.
“Calligraphy, an essential aspect of Chinese culture, transports wisdom and aesthetic traditions developed over thousands of years. It is not only a form of art, but also a way for spiritual growth,” says the teacher and curator of the exhibition, adding that “besides arousing the participants' mental potential”, “the practice of calligraphy serves to enrich their understanding and appreciation of this form of art through learning through learning through learning collaborative and exchange ”.
Quoted in the Rui Cunha Foundation statement, Wan U says that "participants convey their stories with paint, expressing their emotions through works of art" and "this effort perfectly reflects the principle of" lifelong learning ".
The mentor of the project has a master's degree in education and over 20 years of experience in teaching calligraphy. He also received several awards in Macau calligraphy contests for basic and secondary school teachers.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>China prepared to lock business war with the United States, says CCP</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/china-preparada-para-travar-guerra-comercial-com-estados-unidos-diz-pcc/</link><description>The Chinese Communist Party's official newspaper (CCP) yesterday admitted that the rates imposed by Washington will impact the Chinese economy, but pointed out that the leadership in Beijing was already preparing for this moment.
 
"Although international markets generally consider that US tariff abuse exceeded expectations, the [Communist] Central Committee had already foreseen this new round of economic and commercial containment and repression against China, fully estimated its potential impact and prepared response plans with sufficient time and reserves," the People's Diary said.
Recognizing that the application of additional customs of 34% on imports from China, in addition to the 20% rates previously imposed, will result in a “reduction in bilateral trade with the US” and a “short -term negative impact on exports”, the newspaper recalled that “many US products have high dependence on China”.
“The US depend on China not only for many consumer goods, but also for investment and intermediate products, with a dependence of more than 50% in various categories, making it difficult to find alternatives in the international international market,” reads in the editorial.
The percentage of exports from China to the United States, compared to the total of its external sales, fell from 19.2%in 2018 to 14.7%in 2024. Part of this fall is due to 'triangular trade', in which products are exported almost completed from China to other countries, including Vietname, Thailand or Cambodia, where a component or finishing is added to change the change Place of manufacture, aiming to circumvent the rates. The newspaper does not refer to this phenomenon.
The People's Diary recalled that, in recent years, “despite internal and external pressures,” Beijing “has been persisted in doing difficult but correct things,” including release the real estate sector and reducing the indebtedness of local administrations and small and medium and medium financial institutions. "These three major risks have been effectively controlled and contained and are decreasing," he said.
Pointing out the “large dimension” of the Chinese economy, the newspaper recalled that China has monetary policy instruments, such as reducing mandatory reserve ratio and interest rates, to stimulate domestic consumption with “extraordinary strength”, which would allow the Asian to reduce its dependence on exports.
"The domestic market has a wide margin of maneuver," said the Chinese Communist Party's official newspaper. He also stressed the country's ability to transform the adverse effect of US measurements into an "impulse" to accelerate economic transformation and "industrial innovation." "Strangular, repressing and restricting only forces China to accelerate fundamental technological advances in key areas," he said.
Beijing launched several contracted on Friday to the rates announced by US President Donald Trump.
Beijing measures include 34% rates on US products, sanctions against US companies, restrictions on exporting certain rare lands, or opening anti-monopoly and anti-dumping investigations against US companies and products. "Given the extreme and extreme pressure of the United States, we did not closed the door to negotiations," said the People's Diary. "But we also do not feed hopes, having made several preparations to respond to impacts," he said.
 
BOX
 
Customs rates ruined agreement with China on Tiktok
 
US President Donald Trump explained on Sunday that the decision to impose customs global rates annulled an initial agreement with China on Tiktok application operations in the United States. "We had an agreement with Tiktok, not exactly an agreement, but quite close, and then China changed it because of the rates," Trump told journalists aboard the Air Force One. "If I had slightly reduced the rates, they would have approved the agreement in 15 minutes, which shows the power of rates," he added. Trump launched on Wednesday a trade war against the rest of the world, imposing a minimum rate of 10% on all imports. In the case of China, the rates are 34%. Beijing retaliated with rates at the same value on American products. A law passed during the term of Joe Biden (2021-2025) obliges the Chinese company bytedance, owner of Tiktok, to disassociate the social network in the US market so that the platform can operate in the country. Due to the absence of an agreement, the application ceased to work for a few hours in the United States, until Trump, on its first day in the White House, signed an executive order to grant a 75 -day extension, which expired this Saturday and has just been extended. Trump said he is willing to grant China a relief in the fees, as long as Beijing takes this pact, which has the right to veto.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 01:19:19</pubDate></item><item><title>"Spicy" massage between three men gives rise to false denunciation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/massagem-picante-entre-tres-homens-origina-falsa-denuncia/</link><description>A man from the interior of China was accused of making a false complaint to the police authorities after having asked for sexual services from two men, allegedly thinking they were two women.
According to the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP), the suspect was approached, on Avenida Dom João IV, by two Southeast Asian men who were dressed as women for sexual services, having combined the price of 1,000 patacas for services. The man in the interior of China, allegedly to think they were two women, took them to his hotel room for a massage and sexual services. After the acts, the men clarified that the price was 1,000 patacas for each, that is, a total of 2,000 patacas, which led to a verbal dispute because the suspect thought the total price was only 1,000 patacas.
The man eventually paid 2,000, but later, as he returned to the hotel, he contacted the police and denounced that he had been the victim of a theft. The man confessed that he was a sexual transaction and eventually told the authorities that he did not know that they were two men.
The police investigation found that it was not theft and, therefore, accused the man of the slanderous denunciation. The case was delivered to the prosecutor that is investigating.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 01:19:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Two million crossings at the border stations during Cheng Ming holidays</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/dois-milhoes-de-travessias-nos-postos-fronteiricos-durante-os-feriados-do-cheng-ming/</link><description>Macao border posts recorded 2.014 million entries and exits in the three days of Cheng Ming holidays. With a daily average of 671,000 crossings, the number represents an increase of 0.8% compared to the 1.817 million registered during the same period last year, the Public Security Police (CPSP) said.
The body released yesterday the balance of the weekend passage of the weekend and stressed that the various immigration posts "welcomed the peak of the passenger movement", as there were three days of mandatory holidays of Cheng Ming inside China and a prolonged weekend in Macao and Hong Kong.
Statistics show that, among the various border posts, the siege gates dealt 1.011 million passenger trips, corresponding to 50.2% of the total; The Qingmao Border Post registered 311 thousand entries and exits (15.5%); The Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge Border Post was used by 273,000 passengers (13.6%); and the Hengqin Border Post registered 260,000 passenger trips, which was 12.9% of the total movements.
In addition, visitors' entrances to Macau reached 409,000, causing the daily average to reach 136,000 people, which reflects an increase of 14.7% over the same time last year. Residents of Continental China led among visitors who arrived in Macau, representing 73.7% of the total, followed by Hong Kong visitors, with 17.6% (72,000 people), and visitors from Taiwan and tourists from other regions and countries, with 2% (0.8 million), and 6.7% (27,000) of the total, respectively.
CPSP ensured that police measures have been dealing with to deal with the increase in passenger flow at border posts during this period.
In addition to highlighting more police officers to maintain order in the most busy places, in order to ensure the safe and ordained passage of pawns and vehicles, CPSP said it has resorted to technological measures to predict and monitor border pedestrian flow, also adopting multitudes control measures in tourist areas.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 01:19:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Arsenal challenges Real Madrid and Bayern receives Inter in the start of the 'rooms' from Champions</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/arsenal-desafia-real-madrid-e-bayern-recebe-inter-no-arranque-dos-quartos-da-champions/</link><description>Real Madrid, holder of the successful trophy and record holder (15), visits Arsenal today, at the opening of the Champions League's final rooms, which also cross Bayern Munich and Inter Milan, finalists in 2009/10.
 
Having overcome the four-time English champion Manchester City in the play-off (6-3 in both hands) and rival Citadino Atletico Madrid in the ‘octaves', with some controversy to the mixture in their penalties tie (4-2, after a 2-2 draw), the Spanish league will challenge the vice-leader of the English championship, which was never a European champion.
The best provision of the 'gunners' dates back to 2005/06, when they were defeated in the final by the Spaniards of FC Barcelona, ​​after removing in the 'octaves' Real Madrid (0-1 in Madrid and 0-0 in London) in the only games of history between the two emblems.
With 11 provisional points of delay for leader Liverpool in the Premier League and the national cups, Arsenal has the best opportunity to celebrate a trophy at this time, from which the Brazilian central defender Gabriel Magalhães was recently removed, while the extreme Bukayo Saka, leader in influence, with 10 goals and 26 duels, has returned to 26 duels. pitch more than three months later.
The ‘Gunners’ thrashed the Dutch champion PSV Eindhoven in the previous round (9-3 in the aggregate of both hands) and appear by the second edition followed between the eight finalists, putting Real Madrid, present in the 40th time, and fifth.
Present on several fronts, at a time when they have already snatched the European Super Cup and the Intercontinental Cup, but have faltered in the Spanish Super Cup, the "Merengues" are four points from FC Barcelona in the fight for the revalidation of the domestic championship and will discuss the King's Cup in front of Catalans, among the goal of the 16th continental "crown".
Arsenal or Real Madrid will find in the semi-finals the winner of the elimination between Paris Saint-Germain, a newly tetractic French champion to six unbeaten and unbeaten games in major European championships, and Aston Villa, sixth to the condition in the Premier League.
On Saturday, a success at the reception to Angers (1-0) of the 28th round, allowed the Portuguese international club Nuno Mendes, Vitinha, João Neves and Gonçalo Ramos to dilate the record of 13 Ligue 1 titles, equaling the 'tetra' achieved between 2012/13 and 2015/16.
Winner of the Super Cup and finalist of the France Cup, the PSG aims to combine the second full inward with an unprecedented 'Champions', whose candidacy was reinforced in 'octaves', aside from Liverpool, winner of the league phase and six times European champion (4-1, after 1-1), after beating Brest compatriots on the play-off (10-0).
The Gauls hosted Aston Villa, winner of the then-so-called European Champions Cup in 1981/82, which has not been in the "rooms" for 42 years and has been trained by Spanish Unai Emery, winner of seven trophies in Paris, from 2016 to 2018.
Birmingham's team has removed Belgian champion Club Bruggge in the previous round (6-1) and is exceeding expectations in their current competitive format, whose second hand of the 'rooms' will take place on April 15 and 16, having two paths previously traced to the decisive game of the 70th edition, May 31, in Munich, Germany.
On the other side of the painting, Bayern Munich will try to take advantage of the Casa Factor against Inter Milan, in a duel between isolated leaders of the Germanic and Italian championships, respectively, who measured forces in the 2009/10 decision, won by the ‘Nerazzurri’, then commanded by Portuguese coach José Mourinho in Madrid (2-0).
The Bavarians, by Raphaël Guerreiro and João Palhinha, have already surpassed the three-time Scottish champion Celtic (3-2) and the German champion Bayer Leverkusen (5-0), who are about to dethrone the Bundesliga conquest for the 12th occasion at the last 13 times, while the Transalpino champion left behind the dwarfs of Feyenoord (4-1) In the eighth.
On Friday, Jamal Musiala contracted a muscle injury and joined Manuel Neuer, Dayot Upamecano, Alphonso Davies and Kingsley Coman in the extensive Bayern Munich clinical bulletin, which has 35 presence at this stage-six consecutive-and six of those of Inter Milan, and the winner will find FC Barcelona, ​​five times champion, or O FC, or Borussia Dortmund, victorious in 1996/97 and finalist won in 2023/24.
'Carrasco' by Portuguese champion Sporting (3-0) and Lille French (3-2) in previous rounds, the eighth Bundesliga classified again in the Champions League the way of escape from the time, but needs to reverse a history of two draws and three defeats before the Catalans, with whom they lost at home on the sixth round of the League phase (2-3).
The knockout on Wednesday in Barcelona, ​​where Portugal said goodbye to the race, in the face of Benfica's defeat in the ‘Eighths’ (4-1), with Brazilian Raphinha, former striker of Vitória de Guimarães and Sporting, isolating as the best scorer, the result of 11 goals. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 01:19:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Imperial couple from Japan visits Iwo Jima for the 80th birthday of the end of World War II</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/casal-imperial-do-japao-visita-iwo-jima-pelo-80-o-aniversario-do-fim-da-ii-guerra-mundial/</link><description>The emperors of Japan, Naruhito, and Masako are already on the island of Iwo Jima, the scene of one of the bloodiest battles of World War II, within the 80th anniversary of the global conflict. This is the first time that the imperial couple visits the remote island, now officially designated Ioto.
 
The emperors of Japan, Naruhito and Masako, yesterday arrived on the island of Iwo Jima, scenario of one of the most bloody battles of World War II, under the 80th anniversary celebrations of the end of the global conflict.
This is the first time that the imperial couple has visited the remote island, now officially designated Ioto, located about 1,250 kilometers south of Tokyo, where they will pay tribute to the war memorials highlighted there.
The Battle of Iwo Jima is considered one of the bloodiest battles of the Pacific World War Pacific campaign. During the five weeks that lasted, about 7,000 US soldiers and almost 22,000 Japanese soldiers were killed, among 80,000 soldiers who fought on this island of only 21 square kilometers.
The island take, remote and strongly fortified, on March 26, 1945, was considered a fundamental step in advancing allied forces in the Pacific, in order to invade the main territory of the Japanese archipelago, although the strategic importance of the battle is still debated by the experts.
The island was returned to Japanese sovereignty in 1968 and officially renamed Ioto in 2007, at the request of the area inhabitants, a name actually used by the former inhabitants. The island was wrongly designated by Iwo Jima when the inhabitants were removed shortly before the battle.
After the occupation, the inhabitants were not allowed to return and, during the US occupation, the island maintained that name, which contributed to popularize the caption of Joe Roshental's historical photography, in which US marines are raising the US flag, an adapted image for clint Eastwood.
In 1994, emperors Akihito and Michiko visited the island to pay tribute, within the 50th anniversary of the end of World War II, marked a year later.
The presence of Naruhito and Masako follows a previous tribute on March 29, starring Japanese Prime Minister Shigero Ishiba, and the Ministers of Defense of Japan and the United States, Gen Nakatani and Pete Hegseth.
The digression of the emperors this year continues in June with a stint in Okinawa, the southernmost island city hall of Japan, where another of the most emblematic battles of this war took place, the battle of Okinawa.
In the coming months, the imperial couple will also visit Hiroshima and Nagasaki, on the first trip to the cities devastated by US nuclear bombing since they ascended to the throne. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 01:19:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Social Security Fund advises payment of electronic contributions</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/fundo-de-seguranca-social-aconselha-pagamento-de-contribuicoes-por-via-electronica/</link><description>The Social Security Fund (FSS) remembered yesterday, in a statement, that payments from the social security regime for the first quarter of the year can be made by the end of April through the “FSS payments” service, available on the Platform for Companies and Associations and the Macao's single account.
Through these two platforms, employers can afford the contributions of the mandatory regime to “without movement” of workers' employment, the contributions of the compulsory regime that were declared by electronic means and the hiring rate of non -resident workers. For this purpose, it is sufficient to access any of the mentioned electronic platforms, introduce or verify the registration number of the employer or BIR (resident identity ticket) and confirm the amount of the amounts to be paid.
"Employers who do not have the movement of employment of workers in the current quarter and are subject to payment of the hiring fee of non-resident workers, if they use the payment service at the designated online banks, can make payment after consultation of the quarter-in-quarter map number and the amount due to the FSS online platform," added the entity.
The FSS recalls that, throughout April, the beneficiaries of the optional regime can also pay the Macao Single Account or "through the electronic means, counters and automatic jetco boxes of designated banks, as well as in self-service kiosks."
The use of online platforms aims to offer an “easy and convenient” alternative to the need to travel to service or banks. The FSS warns residents who choose face -to -face media to make a prior marking or collect passwords through the Macao Single Account, in order to streamline the process and reduce waiting time.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 01:19:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Asian bags fall after collapse of Wall Street</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/bolsas-asiaticas-caem-a-pique-apos-colapso-de-wall-street/</link><description>Asian actions opened yesterday in a heavy fall, following Friday's collapse on Wall Street due to the imposition of tariffs by US President Donald Trump and Beijing's reaction. The main index of the Hong Kong Stock Exchange fell by 13.2%yesterday, the largest drop since the 2008 crisis, compared to the aggravation of the trade war between Beijing and Washington. Hang SENG dropped 3,021.5 points to 19,828.30, while the index that measures the performance of the hong Kong mainstream China, the Hang Seng China Enterprisses, fell 13.75%. This is the biggest drop in one day since October 2008, when the index lost more than 2,000 points in the middle of this year's global financial crisis. The Taipé Stock Exchange reference index, Taiex, a few minutes after opening, fell 9.8%, losing 2,054 points to 19,243, with the Hon Hai technology company (Foxconn), the world's largest manufacturer of electronic products, and the Giant Taiwanesa TSMC, which dominates the world chip foundry market, also registering close losses of 10%.
Likewise, oil prices remained on a descendant plan, with the US oil reference price falling 4%, or $ 2.50, to $ 59.49 per barrel. Brent oil, the international standard, gave $ 2.25 to $ 63.33 per barrel. Future markets in the US also closed in red, with S&amp;P 500 it lost 4.2%, while Dow Jones Industrial Averag fell 3.5%. The Nasdaq index lost 5.3%. Tokyo negotiations opened in significant fall, with Nikkei, the main index of the Japanese scholarship, losing almost 8%, shortly after the opening of the market. One hour later, 7.1%was dropped to 31 375.71. The second Japanese index, Topix, also opened to lose 8.64% at the beginning of the session. South Korea Kospi opened to lose 5.5% to 2,328.52, while Australia's ASX 200 ASX 200 began negotiations to fall 6.3% to 7,184.70.
The monetary market also registered major movements, with the US dollar to fall to 145.98 Japanese yen from 146.94 yen, and Iene is often seen as a safe port in times of turbulence. The euro rose from $ 1.0962 to $ 1.0967. On Friday, in the worst record since Covid-19, Wall Street closed with S&amp;P 500 to fall 6% and the Dow 5.5%. The compound nasdaq fell 5.8%. The losses accelerated after China equaled the large increased customs rights announced by Trump last week, climbing the stop in a trade war that could end with a recession of the world economy. Even a better report than expected about the US labor market, released on Friday, which usually assumes itself as the economic highlight of each month, was not enough to sustain the fall of markets. All shares of the 500 S&amp;P 500 index companies, except 14, fell on Friday.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 01:19:38</pubDate></item><item><title>China accuses United States of unilateralism, protectionism and economic intimidation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/china-acusa-estados-unidos-de-unilateralismo-protecionismo-e-intimidacao-economica/</link><description>China has accused the United States of unilateralism, protectionism and economic intimidation, given the intensifying of the trade war between Beijing and Washington.
 
Beijing accused the United States of unilateralism yesterday, protectionism and economic intimidation, in view of the intensifying of trade war between Beijing and Washington. "Putting" America first ", above international rules, is a typical act of unilateralism, protectionism, and economic bullying," said Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian at a press conference.
Last week, Trump imposed an additional 34% rate on products from China, as part of the “Liberation Day”, which added to two rounds of 10% already declared in February and March. China quickly retaliated with its own 34% rate on US products.
Beijing also suspended imports of sorghum, capoeira birds and bone flour from some US companies. China's latest retaliation measures include more export controls on rare land minerals, essential for various technologies, and a judicial action in the World Trade Organization.
Lin stated that Trump's rates impair the stability of global production and supply chains and seriously affect world economic recovery. "Pressure and threats are not the best way to deal with China," said Lin. "China will firmly safeguard its legitimate rights and interests," he added.
Beijing tried to convey confidence, with the People's Diary, the official newspaper of the Communist Party, to ensure that "the sky will not fall." "Given the indiscriminate blows of US rates, we know what we are doing and we have instruments at our disposal," he added.
It is not known if China's leader Xi Jinping will meet Trump to reach an agreement. Lin addressed questions about a possible meeting to other departments.
On Sunday, Chinese government officials met with representatives from US companies, including Tesla and GE Healthcare. "The root of the problem of customs rates is in the US," said Ling Ji, Deputy Minister of Commerce, at the meeting with 20 US companies, according to a statement. "We hope that US companies can solve the problem by the root, issue reasonable statements, make concrete measures and work together to safeguard the stability of global supply chains," he said.
Ling, who is also China's adjunct commercial negotiator, has ensured that the Asian country will protect “legitimate rights and interests from foreign companies according to the law” and “actively promote the resolution of their problems and demands”. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 01:19:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Urban Renewal generated profits of 1.8 billion PATACA</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/macau-renovacao-urbana-gerou-lucros-de-18-mil-milhoes-de-patacas/</link><description>Macau Urban Renewal, S.A. closed last year with profits of nearly 1.8 billion patacas, reversing the situation of loss recorded in the previous year of 559 million patacas. The sale of real estate was the main source of the company's revenues. According to the Macau Urban Renewal annual report, in 2024 1,388 fractions of the new Macau neighborhood of Hengqin were sold.
 
Macau Urban Renewal, S.A. again generated profits last year and registered a net result of the positive exercise of 1.792 billion, and the company's annual business volume, by the end of 2024, was 3.694 billion.
The financial statement was released in an annual group of group activities, updated on the public information publicity platform by public capital companies from the supervision services and management of public assets.
According to the document, among the profits, 1.599 billion patacas were attributed to gains of changes in the fair value of properties for investment. Thus, excluding the yield obtained with the variation of the fair value, the profit was 193 million patacas.
The report also revealed that real estate commercialization revenues represent 99% of the company's total business volume, with an amount of 3.69 billion patacas, while 4 million revenue patacas came from the lease of real estate.
It is recalled that Macau Urban Renewal is currently responsible for the projects of the new Macao neighborhood in Hengqin, the housing for temporary accommodation and housing for exchange in the Plado Place, as well as the reconstruction of the seven housing blocks in the Iao Hon neighborhood.
Already the new neighborhood of Macao in Hengqin is now the company's only project put for sale, ie the main source of revenues generated by the company last year. According to the statistics known in the report, until December 31, 2024, 1,388 units of this project were sold, occupied by more than 2,500 residents, and 462 parking places were sold.
"The number of apartments and parking spaces sold reached 1,700, with a constant increase in the number of residents. Complementary facilities are fully operational and most stores have already opened. The area became more vibrant in terms of people and businesses in 2024," he said.
The acquisition of the new Macao neighborhood in Hengqin is exclusive to Macao residents, in the context of creating a life environment similar to Macau on the other side of the border. With the availability of 4,000 residential units, with an average price of the sale of 30,000 per square meter of gross area, the sale of houses began in November 2023. After more than a year, the sale did not reach half the number of fractions, although Macau urban renewal announced last year the survey of some restrictions on houses.
For the project is also underway the construction of a secondary school, whose conclusion is scheduled for next year. The school will occupy an area of ​​20,000 square meters, with a five -story complex for the initial opening of 36 classes.
Macao Urban Renewal, on the other hand, said it is advancing the reconstruction of the seven blocks in the IAO Hon neighborhood. It recalled that it has already helped create 63 management committees of 46 buildings of the seven housing blocks, “after the team continues to travel to the neighborhood to negotiate with the owners in question and promote the arrival of consensus,” he said.
The company has ensured that it has presented the renewal plan to the owners of the seven Hong Tai blocks, Kat Cheong, Son Lei, Heng Long, Mau Tan, Man Sau and SENG YEE, and are also contacting some owners living outside the territory.
Macau Urban Renewal was created in April 2019, with a capital of 100 million patacas, as part of coordinating and promoting urban renewal, promoting the prevention of aging and the degradation of health, aesthetics and safety conditions of existing buildings and promoting the development of innovative urban functions in recovered spaces. The company is led by Peter Lam Kam Seng, whose annual remuneration is set at 540,000 patacas for this position.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 01:12:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Tension between USA and China may pose a risk to US casinos in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/tensao-entre-eua-e-china-pode-representar-um-risco-para-casinos-norte-americanos-em-macau/</link><description>The “tariff war” between the United States and China is a threat to the three US casinos in Macau: Wynn, Sands and MGM. With the increase in political and economic instability between the two countries, consultant analysts of Morningstar have dropped the fair value estimates of two of the three operators and warn of a high “uncertainty” classification.
 
Consultant Morningstar considers that the tariffs imposed by the United States of America on China can negatively impact US operators with a presence in Macao, reducing Wynn's fair value estimates, Las Vegas Sands and MGM Resorts.
In a press release published on Thursday, Morningstar analysts stated that "the geopolitical actions of the United States" come to destabilize the game market in Macao and "increase the risk award" required by investors, defined as the supplementary performance that is intended to compensate for the risk rate.
Given the current context of economic tension between the United States and China, the investment analysis company has lowered fair value estimates of two of the three US casino operators: Las Vegas Sands descended from 56 to $ 53 per action, while MGM Resorts registered a slightly sharper decline from 49 to 46 dollars per action. Wynn Resorts, on the other hand, remains stable worth $ 111 per action.
On the Morningstar page, it is possible to read that the “uncertainty classification” of the three operators is “tall”, positioning half the list of possible classifications (“low”, “mean”, “high”, “very tall” and “extreme”). It is also estimated that, by the end of the decade, about 60% of operational profits (profit before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization-or EBITDA in the English acronym) will come from Macau. Following are the 50%Wynn Resorts and MGM Resorts, with 20%.
Although, so far, the year 2025 has recorded revenues below expected, the profits of playing operators in Macao and the large tourist flow ensure the continuity of the three American casinos in Macao. “Although we continue to monitor the macroeconomic environment of our [MSAR] coverage, we maintain the opinion that all six game dealers will be renewed and prolonged beyond the 2032 period,” wrote Dan Wasiolek, senior analyst of Morningstar Actions in the same note. It is recalled that the last public tender for the gambling of casino games took place in 2022, with the celebration of a a decade contract that will end on December 31, 2032. “Our position is based on China's desire that Macau is a worldwide tourist destination, which, in our opinion, requires the experience of Las Vegas Sands, MGM Resorts and Wynn Resorts” specialist.
After US President Donald Trump announced the imposition of a 34% tariff on Chinese imports, China reciprocated with an equal rate on imports of all products manufactured in the United States starting next Thursday, April 10. In February of this year, the MSAR had already been classified as an “external opponent” of the United States, as well as Hong Kong, because both regions belong to the Popular Republic of China.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 01:14:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Halftone exhibition shows “The Spirit of China” of the 21st century</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/exposicao-da-halftone-mostra-o-espirito-da-china-do-seculo-xxi/</link><description>The Halftone Photographic Association will inaugurate this Friday a collective exhibition on the fluidity of Chinese identity and the way history and tradition and technology and futurism coexist in contemporary China. The show brings together works of 17 associates, all based in Macau.
 
The evolution of Chinese identity throughout space and time, captured by the optics of seventeen photographers based in Macau. This is the motto of the photographic exhibition “The Spirit of China”, organized by the Halftone Association, whose inauguration will take place this Friday, the 11th, at 18:30, at Parisian Macau. The show will be available to the public for a month, until May 11th.
It is a collective exhibition that brings together works from different photographers based in Macao, all focusing on the “Multifaceted Soul of Contemporary China”, as described in the Halftone presentation text. Participating artists, organized by alphabetical order, are António Mil-Homens, Carmen Serejo, Cássia Schutt, Elói Scarva, Flávio Andrade, Francisco Ricarte, João M. Rato, João Palla Martins, Jorge Veiga Alves, Jose Sales Marques, Marta Pereira, Sara Augusto, Sofia Mota and Stefan.
Through “strong visual narratives” - supported by photographic genres such as documentary, contemporary and conceptual - artists “travel through the past, present and imagined future” to explore the meaning of “being Chinese” in a 21st century that is positioned in a limb between tradition and innovation, history and technology, past and future. The historic neighborhoods, much present in Macau, coexist with futuristic “megacities”; “Religious rituals and old festivities” are now interpreted by the digital culture of hands -on mobile phones and social networks at a distance of a click.
Halftone emphasizes that China's “accelerated modernization”, especially in recent decades, has been reconfigured “not only its urban horizons and architectural landscapes, but also the very essence of its cultural identity”. “More than a representation of Chinese legacy, 'The Spirit of China' reveals identity as a living force-constantly shaped by social, dynamic diaspora and digital interconnectivity. The public is invited to reflect on the coexistence between the old and the new and to engage with the spirit of a nation in transformation,” explains the photographic association.
The Halftone Association, currently with more than 50 members, aims to promote and disseminate photographic art and visual narrative in Macau and worldwide. Several members of the group attended the 14th Macao Literary Festival - Rota das Letras, at the end of March, where they presented the 11th edition of the Journal of Homony Photography. The first edition was launched in November 2021, with the objective assumed to become “a symbol of the quality and diversity of Macao's photography and the great bay”, as mentioned at the time by the president of the Francisco Ricarte Association.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Government will review laws that regulate associations to adjust to national security requirements</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/governo-vai-rever-leis-que-regulam-associacoes-para-que-se-ajustem-as-exigencias-de-seguranca-nacional/</link><description>The executive will “review and optimize” the legal diplomas that regulate Macao associations to be in line with “the requirements inherent to the general perspective of national security” and “the real needs for social development” of the territory.
 
The government has said that it will review “in time” the legislation that regulates local associations, so that they are adjusted to the “requirements inherent to the general perspective of national security” and the “real needs for the social development of Macao”. The information was advanced by the Administration and Public Function Services (SAFP) in response to a written interpellation presented by Deputy Lei Chan U.
It is recalled that, according to the most current data, there are more than 12,000 associations in Macau. In question, the deputy linked to the Federation of Macao Workers' Associations (Faom) asked how the executive would optimize the role of “communication bridge in participation in social affairs and service to society” of associations. On the other hand, law Chan U pointed out that "the improvement of the grassroots governance system is an important component to promote the government's governance system and the modernization of governance capacity."
In response, SAFPs say that "Macau associations have a long history of development and have played, over time, an important role of participants in community governance and the provision of public services."
The government ensures that it will “experately ensure the important leading spirit of President XI Jinping, attributing special importance to communication and cooperation with associations that love the homeland and Macau”, establishing mechanisms of communication between these “associations that love the homeland and macao” and the executive, “in the sense of reinforcing the cohesion of common aspirations of the population, the collection of the population's opinions and the union of the population”.
SAFP also guarantee that the authorities will “support the growing development of associations that love the homeland and Macau in grassroots governance”, as well as “improve the community work network, consolidate and expand resident adhesion; study and elaborate social service plans, discuss the establishment of criteria for the quality of social services and the creation of an examination and evaluation system, as well as promoting intelligent and professional development of social services provided by associations ”.
Other Government objectives are the expansion of public services provided to the base social layer and enhance the contributions of associations “that love the homeland and Macau” in the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 01:13:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing prices fall again. Nine years ago the index was not so low</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/precos-da-habitacao-voltam-a-cair-ha-nove-anos-que-o-indice-nao-era-tao-baixo/</link><description>The global housing pricing index was 202.3 in the period between December last year and February this year, yesterday indicated the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). The data provided by the body show that this brand has been the lowest since early 2016.
 
Between December 2024 and February this year, the global housing price index was 202.3, less 0.9%, compared to the period between November last year and January this year, the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) said yesterday.
The body details that the Macau Peninsula Housing Price Index (200.3) and the Taipa and Coloane Index (210.2) fell 0.9% and 1.2%, respectively. The price rate of built housing was 222.8, which reflects a decrease of 0.4% compared to the previous period. The index related to housing under construction (213.8) had a more significant drop of 3.8%.
The DSEC specifies by geographical zone: The housing price index built on the peninsula fell 0.8% to 208.7, while the housing index built in the mud and coloane rose 0.9% to 278.8. In terms of the year of building construction, the price rate of built housing belonging to the level from 6 to 10 years of construction and the rate of the level of less than or equal to 5 years decreased by 1.9%and 1.4%, respectively, even though the level of the 11th to the age of 20 has grown 1.6%.
Looking at the useful area of ​​autonomous fractions, it appears that the level of dwelling prices of the level of 50 square meters of useful area and the level of the level from 50 to 74.9 square meters descended 4%and 2%, respectively, compared to the previous period, however, the level of 75 to 99.9 square meters rose 3.2%.
Compared to the same last year, the global index shrunk 11.8%. Compared to December 2023 to February 2024, this year the Macao Peninsula Housing Index fell by 12.6%, while the Taipa and Coloane decreased 8.7%.
 
Minimum of the last nine years
 
According to the data available on the DSEC website and analyzed by the end, the current housing price index has been the lowest since the first quarter of 2016, when the index was at 203. From there, housing prices rose and reached peak between May and June 2018, when the index was 270.7. Housing prices remained relatively stable between 2018 and 2021. From 2022, the global rate of housing prices in Macao began to go down and last year the fall was abrupt: descended from 231.4 registered in January to 202.3 of the latter update.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 01:15:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Urban Practice awarded in London with sustainable innovation project for Hac Sá Beach</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/urban-practice-premiada-em-londres-com-projecto-de-inovacao-sustentavel-para-a-praia-de-hac-sa/</link><description>Urban Practice's “Park of Tides” project received the Silver Prize in the Landscape - Public Londos Design Awards 2024 Category. Located on Hac Sá beach, the project aims to create an affordable pedestrian path that unites the ends of the beach, with leisure zones that promote interaction with nature. With a strong focus on sustainability and inclusion, “Park of Tides” stands out as an example of how public spaces can be designed to respect and preserve the local ecosystem.
 
The “Park of Tides” project, developed by Urban Practice, has just been distinguished with the Silver Prize in the Landscape Design - Public Landscape category during the London Design Awards 2024. The proposal led by architect Nuno Soares aims to transform the area of ​​Hac Sá beach, creating an affordable pedestrian path that connects the two ends of the beach, while incorporate Innovative and sustainable leisure spaces, including a tower that will serve as a viewpoint and access to the main road.
The public tender for the creation of this project was launched by the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) in early 2024, reflecting the demand for solutions that promote sustainability and inclusion in public spaces. With a comprehensive area of ​​12,000 m², the “Park of Tides” is inspired by the natural tidal rhythm, transposing the fluid movement of the sea to the design of the route. This path has been reconfigured in waveform, allowing a more dynamic interaction between visitors and the coastal environment.
Nuno Soares stressed the relevance of the sustainable approach of the project, stating that “adopts a minimal impact approach, where permeable structures and natural materials are involved with the terrain. It represents our commitment to sustainable and inclusive architectural practices, ensuring ecological preservation while increasing the well-being of the community. If we give priority to environmental responsibility, we can create spaces that not only protect nature, but also contain nature, but also non-protection. para uma economia local mais resiliente e para uma esfera pública mais saudável e vibrante”.
The project is divided into three distinct zones, each with specific characteristics that contribute to improving the experience of visitors. Zone A, called leisure area, is designed to welcome families, offering interactive playful spaces and a green landscape that promotes a welcoming environment. In zone B, or area of ​​exploration, visitors have the opportunity to interact with the surrounding natural environment, through organic materials and spaces programmed for outdoor activities, encouraging a deeper connection with nature. Finally, zone C, or area of ​​nature, stands out for landscape appreciation, using a contemporary design to create a space for reflection and connection with the natural environment, incorporating more green areas than the remaining zones.
The integration of sustainable practices goes beyond aesthetics and highlights the commitment to preserve the local ecosystem of both the responsible team and the institutions involved. The project incorporates ecological lighting systems that automatically fit into color intensity and temperature, minimizing the impact on local fauna and flora, and ensuring that the natural beauty of Hac Sá beach remains intact for next generations.
London Design Awards is an international platform created to recognize projects that stand out for innovation and creative influence. This competition promotes the work of various designers, from architects to product designers.
Urban Practice, based in Macao, as a team of architects, engineers and designers, aims to create a positive and sustainable impact on each project. With a focus on solutions facing complex challenges, Urban Practice also promotes human interaction in built environments, exploring the potential of places to actually involve the community, always with the purpose of improving the landscape and experience in Macao and surroundings.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>G7 expresses “deep concern” with Chinese military maneuvers with Taiwan</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/g7-manifesta-profunda-preocupacao-com-manobras-militares-chinesas-junto-a-taiwan/</link><description>G7 foreign ministers expressed yesterday “deep concern” in a statement about the frequent military maneuvers of China around Taiwan, and appealed to a “constructive dialogue” to resolve differences between Beijing and Taipe.
"These increasingly frequent and destabilizing activities are increasing tensions between the two sides of the Strait and endangering global security and prosperity," said the ministers of Germany, Canada, the United Kingdom, the United States of America, France, Italy and Japan, as well as the high representative of the European Union (EU).
The group of the most industrialized countries expressed their "interest in preserving peace and stability in the Taiwan Strait" and their opposition to "any unilateral action that threatens such peace and stability, including through strength or coercion." "G7 members continue to encourage peaceful resolution of problems through constructive dialogue between the two sides of the narrow," they said.
This week, the Chinese military performed military exercises near Taiwan, including long -range royal shooting exercises in the East China.
The maneuvers, nicknamed “Strait-Thunder 2025a”, included naval blockages, important facilities accuracy attacks and missile launches in a closed area of ​​the East China Sea, about 400 kilometers from the island, the Taiwan Ministry of Defense said.
The exercises occurred weeks after the Taiwan government leader, William Lai, defined China as a hostile external force and announced initiatives to contain Beijing's “infiltration” operations against the island.</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 01:19:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Raymond also asks for a reduction in the execution period of road works and application of new technologies</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/08/raymond-tam-pede-reducao-do-prazo-de-execucao-de-obras-viarias-e-aplicacao-de-novas-tecnologias/</link><description>Raymond Tam, Secretary for Transport and Public Works, yesterday chaired the meeting of the Working Group to optimize the Coordination of Road Works, taking advantage of the occasion to ask the entities to reduce the deadline for execution of the works and apply new technologies, “in order to avoid repeated excavations and minimize the impact caused by works on citizens' lives”.
At the meeting, the secretary reiterated that "one of the main guidelines of the working group is to reinforce coordination and communication", so the government will require promoters of the prior reserve of spaces for the installation of channeling during the execution of the work, "in order to reduce the possibility of repeated excavations on public roads."
At the same time, he gave instructions to members of the working group and channeling companies to, “in the assumption of ensuring safety in the execution of works”, reduce the deadline for execution of works and introduce the application of new technologies in order to minimize the impact of road works for residents and retailers.
Channeling companies said they would “actively collaborate with the work guidelines given by the Working Group”, as well as “strive to coordinate and properly prepare measures related to the reserve of spaces for the installation of pipes and the execution of works”.
Meetings were also held to review all aspects related to the process of works, from the request and coordination to approval, preparing a series of optimization measures, involving the simplification of documents and the reduction of administrative procedures, among others, refers to the press release of the Service Directorate for Traffic Affairs (DSAT).</description><pubDate>2025-04-08 01:19:14</pubDate></item></channel></rss>