<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/05/groenlandia-e-mineapolis-precursores-do-futuro/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Hiroshima survivors express concern about end of NEW START treaty</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/05/sobreviventes-de-hiroshima-demonstram-preocupacao-sobre-fim-do-tratado-new-start/</link><description>Japanese survivors of the 1945 atomic bombings said yesterday they fear the world is heading towards nuclear war with the end of the last arms control treaty between the United States and Russia.

The validity of the NEW START treaty ended yesterday, after the North American President, Donald Trump, rejected the proposal of his Russian counterpart, Vladimir Putin, to extend the limits on nuclear warheads for another year.
Terumi Tanaka, leader of Nihon Hidankyo, an organization of survivors of the North American atomic bombings against the cities of Hiroshima and Nagasaki in August 1945, said that “the world has not yet understood the gravity of the situation”. This pacifist group was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 2024.
The last nuclear weapons pact between Russia and the United States expired yesterday, removing limits on the world's two largest atomic arsenals. The end of the NEW START Treaty could pave the way for the nuclear arms race.
Russian President Vladimir Putin declared last year that he was ready to respect the limits of the treaty for another year, if Washington also complies with the same terms. US President Donald Trump has not committed to an extension.
Putin discussed the end of the pact with Chinese leader Xi Jinping on Wednesday, said Russian presidential advisor Yuri Ushakov, noting that Washington did not respond to the extension proposal. Russia will act in a balanced and responsible manner, based on a thorough analysis of the security situation, Ushakov added.
The Russian Ministry of Foreign Affairs stated, in a statement released last night, that “under the current circumstances”, it presumes that the parties to the treaty are no longer bound by symmetric obligations or declarations, including the main provisions.
The NEW START Treaty, signed in 2010 by then US President Barack Obama and his Russian counterpart, Dmitri Medvedev, restricted both parties to a maximum of 1,550 nuclear warheads on a maximum of 700 ready-to-use missiles and bombers. Originally, the treaty was supposed to expire in 2021, but it was extended for another five years. The pact provided for inspections to verify compliance with the provisions. Inspections were interrupted in 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic and were never resumed.
In February 2023, Putin suspended Moscow's participation in inspections, claiming that Russia could not allow US visits to Russian nuclear facilities at a time when Washington and the Atlantic Alliance allies were openly declaring Moscow's defeat in Ukraine. At the same time, Russia stressed that it was not completely withdrawing from the pact, promising to respect established limits on the possession of nuclear weapons.
By offering, in September 2025, compliance with the NEW START limits for a year, to give both parties time to negotiate a new agreement, Putin stated that the end of the pact would be destabilizing and could lead to nuclear proliferation. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 23:57:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Night of jazz classics at The Ritz-Carlton with the international voice of Ines Trickovic</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/05/noite-de-classicos-do-jazz-no-the-ritz-carlton-com-a-voz-internacional-de-ines-trickovic/</link><description>The city's jazz scene gains a special touch this week. Tonight, The Ritz-Carlton Macau welcomes Croatian singer Ines Trickovic in a free concert. The internationally acclaimed artist and Croatian Grammy winner will share the great jazz standards with Malaysian pianist Sarah Soosay, promising a night of musical expression in a genre known for its improvisation and sophistication.
A prestigious ambassador for European jazz returns to the stage. Croatian singer Ines Trickovic will perform a free concert tonight at The Ritz-Carlton Macau, promising a journey through the history of jazz. The singer takes the stage at 9:30 pm where she will revisit the great classics of this musical genre, in an interpretation marked by the emotional depth that characterizes her, while accompanied on the piano by Priscilla Sarah Dominica Soosay.
With a career that spans more than a quarter of a century and includes more than three thousand concerts across the four corners of the world, Trickovic has a CV that speaks for itself. Among his most notable achievements is a performance at the emblematic Carnegie Hall, in New York, and winning the Porin Prize, Croatia's most prestigious musical distinction, equivalent to a Grammy, in the category of Best Jazz Performance.
His career is marked by an unusual and deeply self-taught training. Born in Dubrovnik in 1982, her passion for jazz awakened and grew in a context where she was nurtured by intensive listening to recordings by icons such as Billie Holiday, Ella Fitzgerald, Chet Baker, Miles Davis and John Coltrane. This different origin forged a vocalist with an expressive timbre and an independent interpretative sensitivity, which catapulted her into the elite of contemporary jazz without any formal academic training.
Throughout his career, Trickovic has collaborated with some of the most influential and respected instrumentalists on the international jazz scene, names such as pianist Aaron Goldberg, guitarist Gilad Hekselman and drummer Marcus Gilmore. These partnerships attest not only to his recognition among his peers, but also to the depth and authenticity of his artistic work.
Ines Trickovic's connection to the territory, where she lived for several years and even prepared a cabaret-varieté project that aimed to unite artists from the Portuguese and Chinese communities, gives this return a special meaning.
Trickovic, who sings in seven languages, including Portuguese, which he learned to speak through Tom Jobim's bossa nova, promises a selection of the most recognized sounds from the jazz repertoire, which dialogue with his vast life experience, from memories of the war in his native Dubrovnik to the multicultural energy he absorbed in Macau and New York.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>China's direct investment abroad reaches maximum since 2018</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/05/investimento-directo-da-china-no-estrangeiro-atinge-maximo-desde-2018/</link><description>China invested around US$124 billion abroad in 2025, the highest amount in new agreements since 2018, North American consultancy Rhodium Group said yesterday.

Although it remains far from the historic record of US$287 billion recorded in 2016, the total value was driven by new generation projects in the mining, data center and energy sectors, which together represented around US$100 billion last year.
The report also highlights that the operations actually completed amounted to US$73 billion – the highest value since 2019 –, reflecting the usual delay between the announcement and completion of investments, as well as the cancellation of some projects.
According to Rhodium, although China continues to invest heavily in overseas factories, the trend is declining. On the contrary, exports continue to be the main driver of Chinese economic globalization. “Chinese companies may be localizing part of their production through foreign direct investment, but China’s globalization strategy continues to focus on exports,” states the report, which adds that “domestic production capacity has grown much faster than outside China since the pandemic.”
North Africa was the only region in the world to record an increase in Chinese investment in new manufacturing units during 2025, which could represent “a disappointment” for countries that hoped to revitalize the industry with capital from China.
In 2025, Asia remained the main destination for Chinese foreign investment, followed by markets such as Latin America, driven by mining and infrastructure projects. In contrast, the share of investments in North America, Europe and Oceania fell from around 70% of the total in 2016 to less than 20%.
The decline was particularly pronounced in Central and Eastern Europe, highlights the consultant, who associates the decline with Beijing's reluctance to allow advanced Chinese technologies to be transferred abroad.
The automotive sector represented 13% of investment, the lowest share since 2020, due to the slowdown in electric vehicle production chains. Conversely, investments in iron, lithium and gold exploration projects, as well as in fossil and renewable energy, increased.
The report also highlights the growth of digital services, the second largest in the historical series, with emphasis on the “boom” of data centers in Southeast Asia, and the consumer goods sector, driven by the acquisition of historic European brands and retail networks.
Rhodium Group's estimate differs from official data released by Beijing, which points to US$174.4 billion invested abroad in 2025, 7.1% more than in the previous year.
The difference, according to the consultant, is due to Chinese companies that maintain revenues in dollars in their branches abroad, avoiding repatriating profits and converting them into assets denominated in renminbi. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 23:59:05</pubDate></item><item><title>China out of discussions on nuclear weapons “at this stage”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/05/china-fora-de-discussoes-sobre-armamento-nuclear-nesta-fase/</link><description>China yesterday excluded the possibility of participating “at this stage” in discussions on nuclear disarmament, as the United States once again defended, with the end of the last nuclear disarmament treaty linking Washington and Moscow.

“China’s nuclear capabilities are on a completely different scale from those of the United States and Russia, and [China] will not participate in nuclear disarmament negotiations at this stage,” said Lin Jian, spokesperson for the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs, at a press conference.
New Start, the last nuclear disarmament treaty in force between the United States and Russia, expired yesterday, increasing fears of nuclear proliferation.
Russia announced on Wednesday that it was no longer bound by the treaty. The United States reacted cautiously, but the head of North American diplomacy, Marco Rubio, reaffirmed that, for President Donald Trump, true control requires China's participation, “due to its considerable and rapidly growing arsenal”. "China regrets that the New Start treaty between the United States and Russia has expired. This treaty is of vital importance for preserving global strategic stability," said Lin Jian.
However, “China has always maintained its nuclear capabilities at the minimum level necessary to guarantee its national security and is not involved in any arms race with any country”, assured the spokesperson.
According to the Stockholm International Peace Research Institute (SIPRI), at the beginning of 2025, China possessed at least 600 nuclear warheads – still significantly behind Russia and the United States –, but “Chinese nuclear arsenal is growing faster than that of any other country, with around 100 new warheads per year since 2023”, pointed out the June 2025 report. “China has always followed a nuclear strategy of self-defense, a policy of no first use of nuclear weapons and an unconditional commitment not to use or threaten to use nuclear weapons against non-nuclear states or nuclear-weapon-free zones,” Lin Jian reiterated.
The spokesperson also expressed China's support for the proposal made in September 2025 by Russian President Vladimir Putin to extend the limits set out in the New Start treaty for one year. “China urged the United States to respond positively” and “quickly resume dialogue with Russia on strategic stability,” he said. “This is also what the international community generally expects.”
Chinese President Xi Jinping held separate talks on Wednesday with his Russian and American counterparts.

“Small circles” rejected in mineral trade

China has rejected the creation of exclusive “small circles” in international trade in critical minerals and advocated an “open, inclusive and universally beneficial” trading environment in response to US-led initiatives.
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesperson Lin Jian said at a press conference that “maintaining an open, inclusive and universally beneficial international trade environment serves the common interests of all countries”. Lin further stressed that “all parties have a responsibility to play a constructive role” to safeguard the stability and security of global production and supply chains for critical minerals.
The spokesperson added that China “opposes any country harming the international economic and commercial order through exclusive ‘small circles’ rules”, in an indirect reference to the cooperation mechanisms promoted by Washington with partners and allies to reduce China's dependence in this sector.
The statements come after the United States announced the creation of a commercial alliance for critical minerals and Washington and the European Union agreed on a first joint action plan to coordinate supply policies for these raw materials, considered essential for industries such as semiconductors, advanced batteries and defense.
Beijing reiterated in recent days that its position on the stability of global supply chains “has not changed” and defended the strengthening of communication and dialogue between countries, to the detriment of formulas that “fragment international trade”. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 23:58:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Helena Almeida's work-presence lives in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/05/a-obra-presenca-de-helena-almeida-habita-macau/</link><description>The Macau Museum of Art materialized a unique artistic dialogue with the first major Asian retrospective of Helena Almeida (1934-2018). Entitled “Helena Almeida: I’m Here – Presence and Resonance”, the exhibition was structured around two curatorial axes. “Presença”, which presented, in chronological order, around 200 works by the Portuguese artist in which her body is simultaneously subject and medium, and “Resonância”, where works by six contemporary artists from China and Macau, specially invited, responded to her legacy.
The body, as a painting space, and photography, as the ground on which everything was built. The conceptual, radical and deeply personal material that made up the work of Helena Almeida, born in 1934 and who left us in 2018. Last January, this dense and profound body of work came into existence as a retrospective in the rooms of the Macau Museum of Art (MAM) in the exhibition “Helena Almeida: I'm Here – Presença and Resonance”. Which not only appears as the first large-scale Asian retrospective of the Portuguese artist; it is the materialization of a legacy that transformed the solitude of the creative act into a universal and continuous dialogue.
The exhibition is organized around two complementary forces: the artist's physical, obsessive and performative Presence, and the Resonance that this intimate gesture unleashed beyond. If the Presence is the breath, the singular and unrepeatable act, the Resonance is the echo it causes, the wave that spreads through space. In Macau, this duality gained a special dimension. Almeida's historical Presence, his body painted blue, his face deliberately omitted, his shadow projected, was not confined in the past. Instead, she found a living, unforeseen Resonance in the present, at a crossroads of cultures where her defiance of borders was reenacted and reimagined by a shared feminine spirit. The exhibition proves that the most personal of Presences can generate the broadest of Resonances, transforming a studio in Lisbon into an agora in Macau.
This structural vision was intentional by the curators. As Margarida Saraiva, curator of the Museum, explained, the “Presence – Resonance” structure was designed precisely to “expand Helena Almeida’s intimate practice in a transnational dialogue”. The selection of artists was not based on direct influence, but on a principle of resonance:
"resonance was privileged over direct influence. These artists were selected because their practices interrogate presence, absence and self-representation in ways that echo and extend their legacy." In this logic, Almeida’s solitary gesture became a “shared language of visibility”.
The main curator, Delfim Sardo, in his introduction to the exhibition, highlighted the uniqueness of Almeida’s career, defining her as “one of the most relevant Portuguese and European artists of her generation”. Sardo highlighted the conceptual core of the exhibition when describing the purpose of the retrospective: “to address the main moments and dimensions of Helena Almeida’s long career with the aim of offering a comprehensive reading of the unique relationship between the performativity of the body and the practice of self-representation that characterizes her work”. It was this unique relationship that the curators wanted to highlight in the chronological path, which begins with his first critical paintings and culminates in the last pieces of 2018, which curiously revisit previous themes, closing a poetic circle in his career.
This exhibition space brings together around 200 original works. He has covered half a century of a meticulous, obsessive career, dedicated to dismantling and merging the boundaries between painting, photography, performance and drawing. But the curators went further, creating an active conversation chamber, which includes works by six contemporary artists from the interior of China and Macau, who responded to Almeida's work. The curators thus affirm Macau not as a mere exhibition stage, but as an international laboratory, where a Portuguese artistic language was reinterpreted and revived in Asia.
From intimate ritual to universal dialogue
The exhibition journey begins with a founding act: in 1969, Helena Almeida, a painter by training, wore a “Pink Canvas to wear” and photographed herself. It was an initial, almost timid affirmation of what would become a mantra of his life: “My work is my body, my body is my work”. In the 1976 series “Tela Habitada”, the gesture was already fluid, confident, a ritual. His body, often dyed an ultramarine blue or wrapped in ropes, was not an object to be represented, but the painting's own malleable support, a living extension of the line. The “Presence” section reveals Almeida’s almost choreographic rigor, a controlled process where, however, the importance of the accident resided. "Even so, there are many mistakes. A mistake is everything I don't want [laughs]", he confessed in an interview with Expresso in 2016 at the age of 82. It was these unexpected sparks that injected humanity and tension into his compositions, inviting the viewer to visually grope the image.
The great challenge of this undertaking, reveals Margarida Saraiva, was precisely starting from an absence: "The biggest challenge was confronting the absence of Almeida's work in the Macau Museum of Art's collection. This absence required restitution, and the retrospective became a symbolic act of reinscribing his legacy into the museum's narrative." However, this absence proved to be a creative opportunity. The greatest discovery, continues the curator, was “the immediacy with which Almeida’s practice resonated when placed in dialogue with contemporary artists from Macau and China”. This active dialogue transformed the museum into a “site of experimentation and negotiation, transforming absence into a generative condition”.
If “Presença” consolidated the artist’s intimate universe, the “Resonance” section demonstrated its expansive power. The complementary exhibition “Resonance – Body.Object．Reflection”, open since December 2025, functions as a dialogical prelude, bringing together a pantheon of female artists, namely Min Han, Gao Fuyan, Sun Xiaoyu, Pang Yun, Wong Weng Io and Angel Chan On Kei. His works, which explored the body, the object and the reflection, created a transcultural and timeless bridge, proving that Almeida's quest to “overcome the limits of the body” continues to generate new artistic languages ​​today. This curatorship transformed the retrospective into a living organism, where its European avant-garde spirit was reinterpreted through a contemporary sensitivity, materializing what the artist herself wanted: for her work to be “very much my thing”, but where “everyone can see themselves again”.
In addition to the chronology and transnational dialogue, the exhibition in Macau allows us to glimpse the deeper and more circular motivation of Helena Almeida's work. Daughter of the sculptor Leopoldo de Almeida, she was educated in the studio space, in the materiality of form. His work was not an escape from that legacy, but a radical internalization of it. "I go in a circle; the cycles return. The work is never complete, it has to be done again", he said. This cyclical movement – ​​which took her from painting to photography, from three-dimensional drawing to the painted body, and always back to the beginning – reveals itself less as an exploration of media and more as an archaeological excavation of creative consciousness itself. The same themes, the space, the floor, the corner, the ceiling of his house-studio in Sintra, were revisited incessantly, not as a setting, but as extensions of his self. His practice was a way of inhabiting the world, of “dealing with emotions”, transforming physical space into psychological space. Each photograph, each blue gesture, is a map of this intimate geography, an attempt to draw the contours of an interior house that was, simultaneously, body, canvas and universe. This was his “act of love” for his father’s studio, his sacred ground.
His physical presence, captured in the analogue era, spoke of a perennial need: to use the body to map the limits of the self and the space that contains us. In Macau, a crossroads city par excellence, this dialogue found a particularly powerful echo. “Helena Almeida: Eu Está Aqui – Presença e Resonância” invites us to look with our whole body and, perhaps, to begin to inhabit our own borders in a more conscious way. The artist is here. And his presence continues to generate responses, proving the simple truth with which he faced life and art: “I live my life as if it were eternal”.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Military-backed party declared winner of Myanmar elections</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/05/partido-apoiado-por-militares-dado-como-vencedor-das-eleicoes-no-myanmar/</link><description>The military-backed party was declared the winner of the elections in Myanmar, authorities announced yesterday. At the same time, the head of the army sanctioned a law that allows him to remain in power without formally leading the new Government.
The victory of the Union, Solidarity and Development party (USDP), led by former generals, was widely expected, given that the vote excluded the main opposition parties and drastically restricted dissent.
The Constitution guarantees 25% of parliamentary seats to the military, ensuring, in practice, control of the armed forces and allied parties. General Min Aung Hlaing, head of the military government, is also expected to assume leadership of the government when the new parliament convenes.
The Constitution prevents, however, a head of Government from simultaneously occupying the position of commander-in-chief of the army — the most powerful position in the country —, but Min Aung Hlaing has meanwhile signed a law that authorizes the creation of a new Union Consultative Council, a body that will allow him to exercise leadership of the country without formally occupying the position.
The law, published in the state newspaper Myanma Alinn, allows the new head of government to form the council with at least five members, including the leader, and determines that the new body advises and coordinates matters of national security, international relations, peace processes and legislation, without affecting the executive or judicial powers.
The measure reflects the use of parallel bodies by the military since the army took power in Myanmar, in 2021, from the elected Government, led de facto by the opposition and Nobel Peace Prize winner Aung San Suu Kyi, plunging the country into a wave of unrest and armed resistance that evolved into a civil war.</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 23:56:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai says he prevented infiltration by external forces</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/05/sam-hou-fai-diz-ter-prevenido-infiltracao-de-forcas-externas/</link><description>The Chief Executive stressed that he had taken decisive measures to safeguard national security and handled cases in accordance with the law, thus preventing and preventing infiltration and interference by external forces. “This ensured the effective maintenance of stability and harmony in Macau”, he highlighted.
In a review made by Sam Hou Fai over the past year, the Government leader said that the legislative elections “were carried out successfully” and in accordance with the law, which guaranteed that governance remains firmly in the hands of patriots.
The statement came from the speech given yesterday at the Spring reception hosted by the Central Government Liaison Office in the Macao SAR, where Sam Hou Fai said that this year will be crucial for the Government to align with national strategies and deepen reforms.
In his speech, Sam pointed out, as on all occasions, that he will continue to implement the principle of 'one country, two systems', as well as “firmly safeguarding sovereignty, security and national development interests” and “defending with determination the insurmountable line that 'there can be no chaos in Macau'”.
When talking about the main missions for this year, Sam Hou Fai said that he will dedicate himself even more to integrating national development and serving the country. Specifically, it argues that it promotes the predominance of executive power, and will deepen public administration reforms.
He also committed to improving the effectiveness of governance and strengthening constructive interaction and efficient collaboration between the executive, legislative and judicial powers. The Government leader considers that the approach will help create a “robust synergy” for local development.
Furthermore, the Chief Executive assured that he will “listen carefully” to the voices of citizens, with a view to maintaining focus on their concerns and solving the problems that affect their lives, to improve the well-being of the population and build “a smarter Macau, with ideal conditions for living, safer and more inclusive”, can be read in his speech.</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 23:59:41</pubDate></item><item><title>MGM China profits rise 10.7% in 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/05/lucros-da-mgm-china-aumentam-107-em-2025/</link><description>Macau gaming operator MGM China announced record profits of US$1.2 billion in 2025, an annual increase of 10.7%. This is the third consecutive year with a new maximum, after, in 2023, MGM China registered a historic record of earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation, amortization (EBITDA) of 786 million euros and, in 2024, of 984 million euros.
These data, according to a statement sent to the New York Stock Exchange on Wednesday, were published “inadvertently”, as the publication date was scheduled for February 11th.
Also according to the document, in the last quarter of last year, MGM China achieved profits of US$332.3 million, an increase of 30.5% compared to the same period last year (US$254.7 million).
The company ended the year with an annual increase of 10.9% in revenue, with earnings of 4.5 billion dollars in 2025 compared to the 4.02 billion dollars obtained in the previous year.
In quarterly terms, MGM China achieved net revenues of US$1.24 billion in the last three months of the year, which represents an increase of 21.4% compared to the same period in 2024 (US$1.02 billion).
Casinos in the region closed 2024 with revenue of 226.8 billion patacas, 23.9% more than in 2023 (183.1 billion patacas).
Macau casino revenues reached 247.4 billion patacas (25.94 billion euros) last year, an increase of 9.1% compared to the previous year.</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 23:58:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Pragmatic move in UK relations with China and its implications</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/05/movimento-pragmatico-nas-relacoes-do-reino-unido-com-a-china-e-suas-implicacoes/</link><description>British Prime Minister Keir Starmer's three-day visit to China marked not only a pragmatic return of British foreign policy towards China after eight years of frosty relations, but also the UK's attempt to adopt a measured approach to handling its trade and business relations with China amid an increasingly hegemonic US foreign policy. As the US's closest partner, the UK's shift in policy towards China has important geopolitical implications.
Starmer brought with him a 60-member delegation, achieving billions of pounds in exports and investment deals for the UK. Specifically, China agreed to reduce tariffs on whiskey from 10% to 5% — an estimated £250 million in profits for the UK economy over the next five years. China is the tenth largest market for Scotch whiskey and as such the tariff adjustment will hugely help Scottish distillers compete in the international market.
Meanwhile, Chinese entertainment brand Pop Mart, which produces the popular Labubu toy, has agreed to establish London as its European hub and will open 27 stores next year — a move that will create at least 150 jobs in the UK. Chinese Chery Commercial Vehicles confirms its decision to open a headquarters in Liverpool. The Chinese company's chief executive, Yin Tongyue, said it is committed to supporting job creation in the UK and the revival of the country's green supply chain.
The rapprochement of Sino-British relations can also be seen in the energy sector, where HiTHIUM agrees to invest in energy storage in the UK. The company also aims to bring around two hundred million pounds of investment to the UK and create almost three hundred jobs, strengthening its sovereign capacity and strengthening the local economy and energy sector.
Currently, China remains the UK's third largest trading partner, supporting 370,000 British jobs. As such, deepening relations between the two countries creates a win-win situation for both countries, especially for the UK, whose economy has not performed well since Brexit in 2016. No wonder Starmer said: “We are bringing stability, clarity and a long-term strategy to how we engage with China, so we can bring benefits to businesses and workers.” Engagement with China is necessary to boost the UK economy. As he openly admitted: “Engagement with China is how we ensure British businesses grow, support good jobs at home and protect our national security” (UK government press release, 30 January 2026).
Peter Kyle, Business and Trade Secretary, also said that the UK delegation “will leave China having strengthened our relationship with one of the world's largest economies, generating billions for the UK and setting the course for new trading partnerships”.
Bicycle manufacturer Brompton will export its products to China, worth £111.5 million over the next three years, following a visit by its chief executive to Beijing. The World Snooker Tour, which has a global audience of 1.8 billion people, has a new event in two Chinese cities that will be worth £15 million over the next five years. Given the large Chinese market for the British sports sector, the potential for further bilateral development and business in sport is enormous.
In healthcare, Cultech – a Welsh manufacturer – will cooperate with China Resources to generate more exports and create new jobs in Port Talbot, while Birmingham Biotech hopes to reach twenty million in sales of its innovative, drug-free healthcare products in the large Chinese market.
In 2025, Glasgow Prestwick Airport opened three direct freight routes to China, achieving £76 million of new business and creating 250 jobs by 2026. This expansion will also support Scottish salmon and seafood exports. At the same time, Asymchem has expanded its life sciences research operation, while pharmaceutical giant AstraZeneca invests its research program in China with a commitment of fifteen billion pounds and the creation of 10,000 jobs in Cambridge, Macclesfield, Speke, Luton and London.
When President Xi Jinping met with Starmer on the 29th, he said that the United Kingdom and China are permanent members of the UN and as such, both countries must safeguard peace and security and strengthen dialogue and cooperation. He also said that trust is the basis of relations between states, adding that China is committed to pursuing peaceful development. According to President Xi, China has never started a war and has never conquered an inch of foreign territory. President Xi's message to Starmer was and is clear: the so-called “Chinese threat” was and is a myth.
President Xi also told Starmer that China is committed to pursuing multilateralism and economic globalization – a strong message that implies that the UK's close partner, the US, was and is pursuing isolationism and economic protectionism.
During the visit to Shanghai, a Memorandum of Understanding was signed between the China-UK Business Council and Suzhou, in Jiangsu province, expanding the establishment of start-ups in China. Deals have also been signed between the UK and China across a range of sectors, from luxury fashion brand Burberry to food and drink exporter Diageo, and from health food company Holland and Barrett to Jaguar Land Rover. Many other British business representatives went to China with Starmer, including the chief executives of HSBC, Standard Chartered, Schroders, Octopus Energy and Pearson. The role of the UK-China Joint Economic and Trade Commission will be strengthened, with ministerial-level meetings being held for both sides to boost their bilateral trade in the coming years.
Chinese Premier Li Qiang said China is willing to work with the British government to create a good business environment for closer cooperation and people-to-people exchanges. He called on businesspeople and people from all walks of life to contribute more to the development of Sino-British bilateral relations.
In fact, the London Stock Exchange and the Industrial and Commercial Bank of China signed an agreement to consolidate their operations in global financial markets, data analysis, cross-border yuan transactions and the development of sustainable finance and financial innovation.
Ashley Alder, chairman of the UK Financial Conduct Authority, met with officials from the China Securities Regulatory Commission and the National Administration for Financial Regulation to discuss measures to strengthen cross-border trading and stock connections between the UK on the one hand and Shanghai and Shenzhen on the other. The Chinese side is exploring the possibility of creating a framework, similar to the Greater Bay Area Wealth Management Connection Scheme in 2021, to allow mainland Chinese investors to access UK-based asset management and retirement products. If this plan is realized, cross-border wealth management products and investments will achieve significant advancement, especially as China's aging population may be interested in exploring retirement provisions in the United Kingdom.
Discussions were also held on how to improve the London-Shanghai and London-Shenzhen equity link framework introduced in 2019 to enable and support cross-border listings through depositary receipt mechanisms (South China Morning Post, January 31, 2026). Currently, six Chinese companies are listed on the London Stock Exchange and both the UK and China are exploring whether the number of shares will be expanded and what measures should be taken to attract more trading. Cross-border data sharing was also discussed with the aim of increasing government capacity to oversee the emerging cross-border stock market more effectively.
The recent rapprochement in relations between the UK and China is geopolitically significant.
Firstly, although relations between the UK and China were at their peak in 2015 when President Xi Jinping visited London, relations between the two parties were subsequently affected by the 2019 turmoil in Hong Kong and, more importantly, the perception of the so-called Chinese threat in the UK. The deterioration of relations between the United Kingdom and China was regrettable at a time when political ideologies predominated over pragmatic considerations. Although Starmer, on his three-day visit to China, raised the issue of human rights with the Chinese side, the emphasis on the UK's engagement with China has already sent a positive message and provided a favorable environment for the British side to raise this politically and ideologically sensitive issue with the Chinese hosts at the negotiating table.
Secondly, at a time when the US, under the Trump presidency, has demonstrated its military might around the world and its ability to use tariffs as punitive trade weapons, the British delegation led by Starmer showed its tendency to lean towards economic pragmatism to the detriment of ideological struggles and to highlight the importance of cordial diplomacy rather than megaphone diplomacy. Thus, the agreements and agreements reached by the United Kingdom and China appear to be very productive, marking the return of a more harmonious and cordial relationship between London and Beijing eight years after 2018.
Third, Starmer's approach to China appears to have been influenced by Canadian Prime Minister Mark Carney's determination to reduce Canada's economic dependence on the US, on the one hand, and to re-engage China assertively, on the other. Geographically, the UK is located in neither the front nor the back yard of the USA. As such, the UK could be bolder in its approach to China. However, Starmer and his subordinates and advisors are aware of the perception of the “Chinese threat” in some sectors of British politics, especially those on the far right and conservatives. Therefore, Starmer's approach to dealing with China is to reach pragmatic trade agreements without creating an overt impression that his government is opening the door to the so-called "China threat". In fact, the UK government had already demonstrated its goodwill towards China by supporting the construction of the Chinese super embassy in London just days before Starmer's visit. The UK leadership has also demonstrated its sensitivity to the Taiwan issue by repeating its one-China policy rather than risk alienating the mainland Chinese leadership.
Fourth, Starmer has adopted a delicate foreign policy in balancing rapprochement with China and a remarkably close partnership with the US. Shortly after Starmer's trip to China, Donald Trump stated that the UK's foreign policy drift is "very dangerous". However, unlike Canada, which is located in the US's 'front yard' and is more vulnerable militarily to the US's tendency to adopt its gunboat diplomacy, the UK does not have to face such Canadian geopolitical risks. Therefore, Starmer's immediate visit to Japan with the aim of reaffirming the UK's defense relations with Japan was a shrewd move that could allay Washington's fears. After all, the UK belongs to one of the Five Eyes members, with close defense and intelligence agreements with the US, Australia, New Zealand and Canada.
Fifthly, Starmer's attempt to attract Chinese investment to the UK could help him secure the support of more big business people in the UK; however, this cannot stop the Labor Party's decline in popularity. The Labor Party's unpopularity can be easily seen in opinion polls in the United Kingdom, where many people are dissatisfied with the Labor government's economic policies. The Reform Party in the UK is gaining popularity — a reflection of the rise in popularity of the far right in many countries around the world, especially in Europe and the US. Therefore, although Starmer has done his best to engage China in productive economic arrangements that benefit the UK, his policy of engagement with China has failed to halt the internal decline of the Labor Party.
Sixth, although not a member of the European Union, the United Kingdom, as a central country on the European continent, has adopted a more economically pragmatic policy towards China, with the implication that other European countries may follow suit. France, under Macron, already maintains much friendlier relations with China than many other European countries. In the coming months, German Chancellor Frederich Mertz's visit to China in February will likely adopt a more pragmatic approach to dealing with China, like the United Kingdom and Canada. If this analysis is correct, then Starmer's visit to China was politically significant, as it served as a rude awakening for Germany, which viewed China as being too close to Russia in the Russian-Ukrainian war.
Seventh, Starmer has received clear messages from Chinese leaders, including President Xi Jinping and Premier Li Qiang, that China is committed to pursuing peace, multilateralism and economic globalization. As such, it is necessary to maintain economic globalization in the world and, in this context, it is in the interests of both the United Kingdom and China to reach pragmatic trade and business agreements, achieving a win-win situation for both parties in the world of international trade. The pragmatic business orientation of both the UK and China is the right one, rather than following the paths of hegemonism, isolationism, economic protectionism and megaphone diplomacy, using tariffs as threats from time to time.
In conclusion, Starmer's visit to China signaled a notable shift in the UK's foreign policy towards China, abandoning the previously hostile rhetoric of viewing China as a «threat» and drifting towards a more economically pragmatic and ideologically diluted approach to dealing with China. Like Canada, which sees China as an emerging power that deserves closer engagement rather than ideological discrimination, the UK's foreign policy towards China has become much more economically pragmatic and less ideologically rigid than ever before. In the era of major geopolitical transformations, in which the unipolar world previously dominated by the US after the collapse of the former Soviet Union has been constantly challenged by other emerging powers, including China, the United Kingdom has demonstrated its realistic adaptation to the emerging multipolar world in a relatively slow but inevitable way. However, Starmer and his business delegation's most recent visit to China became a testament to the need for pro-US European states to rethink how they should treat China in a more economically pragmatic, less ideological and more diplomatically productive way than before.</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 23:52:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Greenland and Minneapolis: harbingers of the future?</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/05/groenlandia-e-mineapolis-precursores-do-futuro/</link><description>Every year in mid-January, after the New Year celebrations end, world political and economic leaders gather in the small, wealthy Swiss ski resort of Davos to discuss global and international economic issues.  Typically, these annual gatherings are uneventful affairs. However, this year's Davos World Economic Forum proved important, as several issues concerned participants and speakers: tensions between the United States and other NATO members, specifically Donald Trump's demands for US control over the Danish territory of Greenland; the American attack on Venezuela and the kidnapping of its leader, Nicolas Maduro; and the ongoing war in Ukraine.
Two speeches electrified attendees at Davos, but in very different ways. On January 20, Canadian Prime Minister Mark Carney argued that the post-Cold War, rules-based order is no longer working. He said powerful states are increasingly using economic ties and integration as weapons and advantages rather than mutual benefits. He said we are in a new world order, reiterating the ancient Greek historian Thucydides: “The strong do what they can and the weak suffer as they must.” Consequently, middle powers must work together to combat the demands of great powers. He urged middle powers to build new coalitions based on common values ​​and interests. The speech received a rare standing ovation in Davos and sparked widespread discussion about its geopolitical implications. His speech was widely interpreted as a rebuke of US foreign policy under Donald Trump and the changing landscape of global power.
The following night, US President Donald Trump responded to Mark Carney with a robust, nationalistic, fact-free and confusing speech. He vigorously defended his tariff and trade policies, positioning them as a central part of his leadership strategy. Second, Trump demanded OWNERSHIP of Greenland, arguing that its physical possession is essential to the security of the United States. Although he declared that the United States will take control of Greenland one way or another, he stated that the US will not take Danish territory by force, a declaration that relieved the United States' former NATO partners, who had imagined the impossible scenario of NATO troops facing off against troops from NATO's largest and most powerful member. Trump's speech mixed the triumphalism of “America First” with the imperial expansion of the 19th century.
About 4,000 kilometers from Arctic Greenland lies the city of Minneapolis, which has become the focal point of dissent against Donald Trump's increasingly tyrannical government and immigration policies. In late December, Donald Trump sent around 3,000 members of his paramilitary force, ICE, to Minnesota's frigid capital, Minneapolis, outnumbering local police by about five times.  For the past four weeks, this heavily armed, uniformed and masked force has paralyzed this city of 400,000 inhabitants, sowing fear and terror among its population.  Acting with impunity, ICE agents have beaten, arrested, humiliated, and detained hundreds of U.S. citizens, and disappeared tens of thousands of legal and illegal migrants into distant, dirty, and unsanitary internment camps. In reaction to this reign of terror and military occupation imposed on a US city by its own federal government, tens of thousands of people in Minneapolis and hundreds of thousands across the country have demonstrated daily.
A broad grassroots movement has emerged in Minneapolis, organizing solidarity patrols, mutual aid and strikes in opposition to the federal campaign of fear and intimidation aimed at crushing all dissent to Trump's policies. On January 7, an ICE agent, Jonathan Ross, shot a bystander, Renee Good, a mother of three, three times in the face, killing her in her own car as she tried to flee paramilitaries. On January 23, two ICE agents murdered another bystander, Alex Pretti, an intensive care nurse at a veterans hospital, by shooting him ten times in the back, execution-style. In reaction, hundreds of thousands of ordinary US citizens marched in thousands of demonstrations across the country demanding that ICE agents leave Minneapolis and other occupied US cities, including Portland, New Orleans, Chicago, Los Angeles and New York.
What do Greenland and Minneapolis have in common besides dark, snowy and extremely cold January? Both were threatened with military occupation and seizure of power. Both are victims of attacks by Donald Trump. These attacks radically changed their daily lives.  Both are also victims of Trump's personal wrath for defying his demands.
However, last week, in reaction to these two distant events, resistance grew, forcing the Trump regime to retreat. Strongly and broadly, European leaders rejected Trump’s demand that the US “must have Greenland.” They emphasized that the territory belongs to Denmark and Greenland, not the United States. Denmark's Prime Minister Mette Frederiksen met smartly, quickly and discreetly with key European leaders to secure their support. Several countries, including Britain, France, Germany and the Scandinavian countries, sent small numbers of troops to act as a "trigger" — that is, a small military force sent to a vulnerable area to warn an aggressor that an attack on the territory would trigger a much larger deployment of troops and a full-scale war by the defending countries. Top European leaders called Trump and said clearly that an attack on Greenland would be considered an attack on everyone.
Faced with unexpected and solid European opposition, Trump withdrew his threats to impose tariffs on European countries that support Denmark and to invade and militarily occupy Greenland. However, Trump's demands awakened Europe, which called American imperial demands a «wake-up call» for Europe to strengthen cooperation. On Monday, February 3, former European Central Bank President Mario Draghi went further, declaring that the rules-based liberal world order is “dead” and that the European Union must change and move towards a closer federal structure so that it can face aggressive challenges from the United States to the west and Russia to the east. Otherwise, Draghi warned that Europe would face a future in which it risked “becoming subordinated, divided and deindustrialized” — in other words, marginalized in the new world. Europe is finally speaking out against the aggressive stances of the new United States. Will your future actions live up to your words?
In reaction to the paramilitary murders of Americans on the icy streets of Minneapolis, reversing US policy, Trump recalled his director and enforcer, Gregory Bovino, and brought in the apparently more moderate Tom Homan to lead ICE operations. To try to calm tempers, last night Homan said he would immediately withdraw 700 of his ICE paramilitaries, but declared that any further withdrawal would depend on the local population abandoning the protests and returning home. Furthermore, despite widespread demands, there is still no independent and impartial investigation into the two murders of Renee Good and Alex Pretti. ICE agents continue to arrest people on the streets, removing them from schools, hospitals, places of worship and work, stores and offices.  On February 2, in a small town south of Minneapolis, ICE paramilitaries forcibly removed a bystander from her car at gunpoint, mistreated her, and attempted to arrest her. For the first time, local police intervened and stopped these ICE thugs from disappearing and perhaps killing another American citizen. Significantly, although the rhetoric has changed in Washington, its actions have not.
Two weeks ago, during the Davos Forum, things looked very bleak for democratic forces in Europe and the United States. Last week, Europe and the brave people of Minneapolis fought back, forcing the Trump regime to back down. The question we don't know the answer to is: how long-lasting and deep will its retreats be? Will the United States descend into total autocracy by the end of the year? There are already serious doubts as to whether the November elections will be fair and free. Yesterday, Trump demanded that the Republican Party take control of the 2026 elections, a completely illegal and unconstitutional action. On Tuesday, the FBI, controlled by him, raided the Election Center in Atlanta, Georgia, seizing ballots from the 2020 election, further muddying the waters regarding the US elections.
Will Donald Trump return to his obsession with annexing Greenland to the United States, destroying NATO and perhaps forcing a world war? The United States entered a period of instability, decline and chaos. The world community will see how lasting and deep Trump's current withdrawals are. This year will determine the shape and scope of the new world order and the United States' place in that world order.</description><pubDate>2026-02-05 23:53:05</pubDate></item></channel></rss>