<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/governo-pondera-alterar-forma-de-atribuicao-dos-cheques-pecuniarios/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>STD launches programming of cultural and gastronomic events for March</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/dst-lanca-programacao-de-eventos-culturais-e-gastronomicos-para-marco/</link><description>Tourism on March. The Directorate of Tourism Services presented another “Tourism +” program, which includes historical coloane tours, a gastronomic experience with chef Michelin Justin Paul and “Happy Macao Tour 7” for families. In addition, “Spring Cultural &amp; Creative Market” and “Macanese Cooking Experience”, with chef Antonieta Marnhão, also highlight local culture and cuisine, offering unique experiences for visitors and residents.
 
March brings to the city a variety of activities that promise to enrich tourist experience in the region and encourage the economy of local communities. The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) is promoting a new program, following the initiative “Tourism +”, which combines culture, gastronomy and history, providing unique experiences for both residents and visitors.
Among the main attractions are the “historical and nostalgic walk in coloane” tours, or “historical and nostalgic ride in Coloane”, in Portuguese, which will take place on Saturdays and Sundays between March 8 and 16. During these walks, participants will explore the shipyards of Lai Chi Vun and may appreciate the history of naval construction in Macao, accompanied by a documentary and a documentary and a documentary and a documentary and a documentary and a documentary and a documentary and a documentary Tasting of traditional teas. Visits, available in Cantonese, Mandarin and English, offer a unique opportunity to connect with Coloane's historical past.
In the gastronomic field, STD offers the program "Boarding a gastronomic trip with the master chef: explore flavors in local markets." Every Saturday, between March 1 and April 19, renowned chef Michelin Justin Paul will lead participants to local markets to buy fresh ingredients. In addition to preparing typical dishes of macanese cuisine, participants will be able to taste the famous red bean cake and enjoy teas in a centenary store, plunging into the traditional gastronomic culture of Macao.
“So Yummy! Macao Loca Cuisine Experience ”invites participants to learn how to make and customize NATA and Sanbayaki pastries, between 9 and 22 March. This activity, carried out in collaboration with local establishments, offers the possibility not only to cook but also to take home a delicious memory of Macanese delicacies.
Among the initiatives aimed at fun, we highlight the “Happy Macao Tour 7”, which will take place on March 22, 23, 29 and 30. With animated mascots, participants will experience walks through cultural spaces, such as the Lin Zexu Memorial Museum and the Lin Fong temple. The event will present interactive activities, games and performances, an enriching and fun experience for everyone, the organizers say.
Given the Spring Scenario, the “Spring Cultural &amp; Creative Market”, which will operate from March 7 to 30, will turn the Bazaar Pagoda Largo into a surface of handicrafts and cultural experiences. Visitors will be able to participate in free swolk workshops of cream pastel candles, enjoy animation shows and explore a variety of handcrafted products, all within a festive atmosphere.
To end these cultural experiences, the “Macanese Cooking Experience” will be conducted by award -winning chef Antonieta Marnhão during weekends from March 22 to April 20. In this activity, participants will learn to prepare traditional dishes while listening to stories about the fusion of culinary influences from Portugal and China in Macao.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>GDP grew 8.8% last year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/pib-cresceu-88-no-ano-passado/</link><description>Macao's economy grew 8.8% in 2024. GDP was 403.3 billion patacas, equivalent to 86.4% of the economic volume recorded before the pandemic. The data released by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) also show that the per capita GDP rose 7.6%.
 
Last year, Macau's Gross Domestic Product (GDP) ascended at 403.3 billion patacas, plus 8.8% annually. This amount is equivalent to 86.4% of the economic volume of 2019, indicate data released on Friday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC).
In last year's GDP statistics, DSEC stresses that service exports and internal demand (including private consumer expense, government's final consumer consumption expense grew by 9.2% and 2.3%, respectively, in annual terms.
In addition, GDP per capita, which measures the average value of goods and services produced per person, was 587,922 patacas, rising 7.6% compared to year 2023. The implicit deflator of GDP (105.0), which measures the global price variation, also rose 0.4%.
According to DSEC accounts, service exports registered a 9.2%homologous increase, driven by the annual growth of 23.8%of the number of visitors' entries in 2024. It is noteworthy that game service exports increased by 21.8%. Exports of other tourist services descended 6.1% in annual terms, “due to the basis of relatively high comparison of the year 2023”, however, 13% grew, compared to the year 2019. Regarding foreign trade in goods, exports fell 14.5% and imports of goods decreased by 7.6% in homologous terms.
On the one hand, private consumer expense in the year under analysis increased 4.9% in annual terms. This was due to “the continuous recovery of economic activities and the uninterrupted stability of the labor market”, justifies DSEC. The final consumer expense of families in the local market and the final consumer expense of families abroad had 3.8% and 11.1% increase, respectively. On the other hand, the government's final consumer consumer expense dropped 5.1% in the year of reference, “due to the term of life subsidy measures,” says DSEC, indicating that net purchases of goods and services descended 11.2% and employee remuneration rose slightly 0.2%.
For its turn, gross fixed capital formation of 2024 increased 4.6% compared to 2023, "because companies continually increased their investments in Macao during the year." DSEC emphasizes that, in the private sector, investment in construction and investment in equipment increased 5.1% and 31.1%, respectively. Regarding the public sector, the investment in equipment also increased by 1.2%, in annual terms, while the investment in construction fell 10%due to the completion of part of the large public works.
Looking only at the fourth quarter of last year, GDP annually increased 3.4% in real terms, with the recovery equivalent to 88% of the economic volume of the same quarter of 2019. It is noteworthy that internal demand and exports of services had homologous additions of 2.8% and 2.1%, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:14:07+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China says that deportation of Thailand's Uigures is an internal subject</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/china-diz-que-deportacao-dos-uigures-da-tailandia-e-assunto-interno/</link><description>China expressed “firm opposition” to the interference of other countries in its internal affairs “in the name of human rights” following criticism of the deportation of Thailand of 40 members of the Chinese ethnic minority Muslim Uigur.
"China is a rule of law," said Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian at a press conference arguing that Beijing acts in accordance with international practices and laws in the fight against illegal migration and smuggling.
US Secretary of State Marco Rubio said he was alarmed by the deportation of Uigures to China, "where they have no rights and face persecution, forced labor and torture." "This is the lies of the century," Lin said in response to the accusations that the Chinese government is committing genocide and imposing forced labor in Xinjiang, the Chinese autonomous region where most of the Uigures and other ethnic groups of Muslims are concentrated.
The diplomat urged politicians from other countries who criticized China because of Xinjiang to “stop making lies,” defended the region's development and prosperity and said Beijing will intensify cooperation with other countries to reinforce the struggle against transnational crime.
Thailand deported the 40 Uigures to China on Thursday, following an agreement with Beijing and despite the appeals of the United Nations and the human rights organizations.
Thai Prime Minister Paethongtarn Shinawatra said the deportation was made “respecting international principles” and Beijing's confirmation that legal measures would be taken against the Uigures, according to a statement from the Thai government.
In late January, the UN asked Thailand to immediately suspend the deportation of 48 Uigures to China due to the risk of reprisals against minority members. The 48 Uigures are part of a group of about 350 people who were detained in 2014 when they entered irregularly in Thailand.
In 2015, Bangkok deported more than 100 Uigures men to China, causing a wave of international indignation, and, in parallel, sent 170 women and children to Turkey.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:10:55+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Delegation from the University of Macau visits top universities in Ireland</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/delegacao-da-universidade-de-macau-visita-universidades-de-topo-na-irlanda/</link><description>The vice-rector of the University of Macau (one), Rui Martins, led a delegation to several higher education institutions in Ireland. The visit aimed to expand the international cooperation network of UM and the reinforcement of academic partnerships with the universities of English -speaking countries.
In a note published on the university's electronic page, the Global Affairs Office details that the institutions visited were Trinity College, Griffith College, University College Dublin and Dublin City University. Regarding the first university, the delegation reports that it has reached consensus to reinforce cooperation in areas such as Energy Engineering and the application of the Internet of Things (IoT) in smart cities.
At the second university, in turn, the mutual interest in exploring cooperation in degree programs in domains such as international and electronics, as well as promotion in material science, microelectronics and electrical engineering to develop innovative and competitive talents worldwide.
The delegation of UM was then received at the University College Dublin, where both parties agreed to promote exchanges of students and teachers, joint research projects and academic seminars.
Dublin City University also revealed interest in the exchanges of students and teachers, and also in cooperation in engineering, microelectronics, computer sciences and smart cities. The two parts also came to a consensus on the creation of double graduation programs.
Balanced the visit, Vice Rector Rui Martins states that the relations of the one with the universities of Irish top not only have been reinforced, but still open prospects for future cooperation in the fields of teaching, investigation and talent cultivation with the Anglophone world, contributing to the efforts to internationalize one.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:08:52+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Photography and Drawing come together in a reflection on the urban transformation of Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/fotografia-e-desenho-unem-se-numa-reflexao-sobre-a-transformacao-urbana-de-macau/</link><description>Images drawn with light and ink. Works of photography and drawing of architects Nelson Silva and João Nuno Marques invite the public to reflect on the ephemerality and constant metamorphosis of the urban space. The exhibition “Framing a Future Past”, curated by Sara Neves, will be inaugurated at Creative Macau on March 20, at 6.30 pm, extending until April 17.
 
In the intersection between memory and innovation, the core of the exhibition “Framing a Future Past”, which will be presented at Creative Macau between March 20 and April 17. With a sensitive curator to cultural advances by Sara Neves, this show exposes the artistic interpretations of two local architects, Nelson Silva and João Nuno Marques, whose work invites a reflective dive into the incessant evolution of the city.
Macao, a territory characterized by its cultural and historical richness, is, at the same time, a place in permanent transformation, according to the description of this team of artists. “Framing A Future Past” proposes a close look at this phenomenon. Through the lens of Silva and the trace of Marques, the exposed works come to life, becoming visual chronicles that capture not only the aesthetics of urban space, but also the historical narrative that underlies every corner, building and street.
Nelson Silva, architect and photographer, brings to the show an intimate and poetic perspective. His formation in architecture from the University of Minho, associated with a transformative experience in Norway, enriched their ability to observe and record the daily life of Macao and the nuances of habitable space. His photographs are not mere records, but interpretations that reveal the co-existence of nature and urbanity. Second place in Macao's architectural photography contest in 2024 was a recognition of his talent, but, more than anything, his visual narratives that talk about the transformations of the city from a single perspective.
Already João Nuno Marques stands out for his focus on illustration and drawing as tools of registration of reality. Graduated at the University of Porto Faculty of Architecture, he brings with him a cultural background acquired in several countries. Their designs, which document the urban landscape and the city's Cultural Pulsar, go beyond the technique. Reflections that capture the lightness of the ephemeral moments, and the essence of the city in constant change. Through the trace, Marques transform what could be fleeting into eternity, allowing visitors to the exhibition to experience a new way of seeing and feeling.
Curator Sara Neves has an approach that combines aesthetic sensitivity with a critical reading of the city. By organizing “Framing a Future Past”, Neves proposes a space of dialogue where urban transitions are discussed through art. Your intention is for visitors not only to see, but feel the multiplicity of Macao, reflecting on what it is, what it is and what may be.
By visiting this exhibition, participants are invited to introspect on the ephemerality of things, an increasingly pertinent theme in a constantly evolving world. The works of Silva and Marques, although distinct, create an intrinsic interpersonal dialogue, reflecting the way art can be a powerful means of reflections beyond visible.
With the inauguration in sight, “Framing A Future Past” promises to be an enriching experience that will contribute to the valorization of Macao's urban heritage, while encouraging a dialogue about its continuous transformations.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Worst fires since 1992 in Japan have for the removal of two thousand people</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/piores-incendios-desde-1992-no-japao-obrigam-a-retirada-de-duas-mil-pessoas/</link><description>About two thousand people had to abandon their dwellings in northern Japan, where forest fires have already burned the largest area since 1992 and did a dead, the Japanese authorities said.
The Japanese disasters and fires response agency (FDMA) said the areas around the city of Ounato were evacuated in the Iwate Forest Region.
Many took refuge with friends or family, and more than 1,200 were taken to shelters, added FDMA.
At least one person died in the flames, which triggered on Wednesday, and also damaged over 80 buildings. "We are still trying to determine the affected area, but it is the largest since 1992," a FDMA spokesman said to the France-Presse news agency. "We are still trying to determine the affected area, but it is the largest since 1992," said FDMA spokesman for the AFP news agency on Saturday.
In 1992, a fire destroyed 1,030 hectares in Kushiro, Hokkaido, in the north of the country.
According to the Japanese press, the fire has already spread to 1,800 hectares. Aerial images of the Japanese public broadcaster NHK showed military helicopters to fly over white tobacco clouds, four days after the beginning of the fire.
About 1,700 firefighters were mobilized across the country to try to extinguish the flames.
The cause of the fire is not yet known, but it is believed to have started in a work shed and spread from there to a wooded zone, where dry meteorological conditions favored its propagation.
This is the third fire in a week affecting the southern coastal areas of Iwate, which have been on alert for dry weather since February 18.
The last fire in the Iwate region was fueled by “strong winds,” the mayor of the Chamber of Ounato, Kiyoshi Fuchigami, said on Wednesday.
According to government data, the number of forest fires decreased from peak in the 1970s, but by 2023 Japan suffered about 1,300 forest fires, concentrated from February to April, when air becomes dry and winds increase.
The year 2024 was also the hottest ever recorded in Japan, according to the National Meteorological Agency, following the increase of extreme events worldwide due to climate change.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:13:12+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cut on American support makes room for Chinese influence in Africa, says analyst</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/corte-no-apoio-norte-americano-abre-espaco-a-influencia-chinesa-em-africa-diz-analista/</link><description>Washington's decision to cut into external support offers China an opportunity to increase the influence in Africa, an analyst told Lusa, setting a parallel with donations made during the pandemic.
 
The government led by Donald Trump confirmed this week that it will eliminate more than 90% of US Agency for International Development Agency (USAID) and $ 60 billion (58 billion euros) foreign assistance contracts around the world.
In Africa, the cuts should have a particularly serious impact on health, which occupies the largest share of US support to the continent. Similar to what happened during the COVID-19 pandemic, experts expect China to fill the void left by Washington again.
“Among African leaders, China has already built significant influence. Now it has the opportunity to seduce public opinion, ”explained Paul Natulya, a researcher at the African Center for Strategic Studies, a US Department of Defense Institute and funded by the US Congress.
The US provides more than a quarter of all development aid on the African continent. An analysis performed by Denver's International Futures concluded that cuts can shoot another 5.7 million Africans under the extreme poverty threshold of $ 2.15 a day next year.
During Trump's first term, which coincided with the Covid-19 pandemic, Africa became the region that most benefited from Chinese vaccine donations, testing, masks or fans, while Washington diminished his contributions and withdrew from the World Health Organization.
"When the West retained donations of vaccines and medical equipment, China quickly filled the void," Natulya recalled. "In return, they received a lot of publicity and prestige, for a relatively small investment," he noted.
Beijing's decision has marked a paradigm shift in a dominated cooperation in recent decades by relations between states: Chinese state banks have granted loans worth thousands of millions of dollars for the construction of infrastructure, in charge of Chinese state companies, and with the natural resources of their countries to serve as collateral.
The Chinese industries were thus supplied on the continent, obtaining oil in Angola, Madeira in Mozambique or Copper in Zambia, while flooding the markets in Luanda, Maputo or Lusaca with cheap products, generating animosity among local traders. But different polls now show that China has surpassed the United States in the popularity rate among African public opinion.
According to an international poll from the Gallup Association, Beijing's approval among Africans went from 52%in 2022 to 58%in 2023, while Washington's popularity fell from 59%to 56%in the same period. Inquiries conducted by other institutes, such as Afrobarometer and Ichikowitz Family Foundation, demonstrate the same trend. "China is using all the tools at its disposal to gain this competitive advantage in the face of the United States," the researcher described. "At this time, I bet that, in Beijing, employees are studying the next step and when and how to increase China's contribution," he said. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:10:58+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Unemployment rate drops to 1.6% historical minimum</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/taxa-de-desemprego-cai-para-minimo-historico-de-16/</link><description>The unemployment rate in Macao fell to 1.6% between November and January, a historical minimum, according to official data released. According to the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), after seven months in a row to round 1.7%, the indicator fell 0.1 percentage points compared to the previous period, between October and December. The 1.6% value is the lowest since DSEC began collecting data on unemployment in Macao in 1992.
In a statement, the DSEC explained that the rate reduction is due to “mainly the Chinese New Year originating the reduction in the number of individuals looking for employment, which led to a decrease in the number of unemployed”.
The casinos sector hired 900 more people between November and January, reaching a labor of 72,500, while the Grosso and Retail trade also hired 200 more people.
Macau received in January almost 3.65 million visitors, 27.4% more than in the same month of 2024 and the second highest value ever, while the game's revenues fell 5.6% in annual terms.
In the last three months the unemployment rate has dropped to a historical minimum, despite the labor coming from abroad, including from mainland China, increasing by almost 5,900 during the year 2024.
According to data from the Public Security Police Corps, released by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs on February 5, Macau employed more than 182,500 migrant workers at the end of December. A number still far from the maximum peak of 196,538, reached in late 2019, before the beginning of the Covid - 19 pandemic.
In fact, the unemployment rate among the inhabitants with resident status fell further, 0.2 percentage points compared to the previous period, between October and December, to 2.1%, a value that is also a historical minimum.
Between November and January, the number of unemployed residents cried by about 500 to 6,200, the lowest value from 27 years ago. Since 1998, however, the population of Macau has increased by 61.5%to 686,600 at the end of September, according to the latest DSEC estimate.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:12:01+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan announces law to prevent use of AI in misinformation and 'deepfakes'</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/japao-anuncia-lei-para-prevenir-uso-da-ia-em-desinformacao-e-deepfakes/</link><description>The government of Japan presented a bill to reduce risks in the development and use of artificial intelligence (AI), such as the dissemination of false information or hyperrealist videos 'Deepfakes'. “Artificial intelligence has advantages and is innovative as it can improve productivity and solve problems such as labor scarcity. However, there is a risk that it can be used to commit crimes, so we will address both aspects, ”said the Japanese executive spokesman.
The legislation was developed based on existing international regulations on AI, "to avoid damage such as violation of public rights and interests," added Yoshimasa Hayashi during a press conference.
The bill states that although AI is one of the engines of future socioeconomic development, it can also be used to commit crimes or disseminate personal data, and therefore establishes a number of measures to ensure their safe use.
The legislation states that the government may open an investigation in the event of a serious AI and, based on results, provide guidance and counseling to companies, as well as information to the public.
The proposal also expressly states that companies must cooperate with government investigations, according to details, mentioned by the Japanese public broadcaster NHK.
The new law also determines that it will be a government organism to establish basic guidance to promote the research, development and proper use of AI, as well as to improve the international competitiveness of Japanese companies. "We are not imposing comprehensive AI regulations, but the idea is to share information with private companies and ask them to inform us about areas where there may be high risks," said Japan's Minister of Digital Transformation. "I hope the bill will be approved quickly to reinforce the government's role as a command center," Masaaki Taira added.
The proposal should be discussed and voted during the current regular session of the diet, the Japanese Low Chamber, which runs until June 22.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:13:12+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal point 2025.03.03</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/ponto-fatal-2025-03-03/</link><description>The government of Japan presented a bill to reduce risks in the development and use of artificial intelligence (AI), such as the dissemination of false information or hyperrealist videos 'Deepfakes'. “Artificial intelligence has advantages and is innovative as it can improve productivity and solve problems such as labor scarcity. However, there is a risk that it can be used to commit crimes, so we will address both aspects, ”said the Japanese executive spokesman.
The legislation was developed based on existing international regulations on AI, "to avoid damage such as violation of public rights and interests," added Yoshimasa Hayashi during a press conference.
The bill states that although AI is one of the engines of future socioeconomic development, it can also be used to commit crimes or disseminate personal data, and therefore establishes a number of measures to ensure their safe use.
The legislation states that the government may open an investigation in the event of a serious AI and, based on results, provide guidance and counseling to companies, as well as information to the public.
The proposal also expressly states that companies must cooperate with government investigations, according to details, mentioned by the Japanese public broadcaster NHK.
The new law also determines that it will be a government organism to establish basic guidance to promote the research, development and proper use of AI, as well as to improve the international competitiveness of Japanese companies. "We are not imposing comprehensive AI regulations, but the idea is to share information with private companies and ask them to inform us about areas where there may be high risks," said Japan's Minister of Digital Transformation. "I hope the bill will be approved quickly to reinforce the government's role as a command center," Masaaki Taira added.
The proposal should be discussed and voted during the current regular session of the diet, the Japanese Low Chamber, which runs until June 22.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:09:03+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese president recognizes that the country's economy faces many difficulties</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/presidente-chines-reconhece-que-economia-do-pais-enfrenta-muitas-dificuldades/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping acknowledged that China's economy continues to face “many difficulties” in an article widespread by an official body on the eve of the Chinese Parliament annual session next week.
 
"Currently, the adverse impact of external changes has worsened and the Chinese economy faces many difficulties and challenges," Xi Jinping wrote in an article published in Chinese Communist Party (CCP), Qiushi magazine. "But we must also recognize that China's economic foundations remain solid, with many advantages, strong resilience and real potential," said the Chinese leader. "The favorable conditions for long -term growth and the positive global trajectory have not changed," he added.
The Chinese Communist Party's Board (CCP) stated that by 2025 it will give priority to the stabilization of the economy and the “risk prevention” measures, to ensure the recovery of the world's second largest economy.
According to the Xinhua official news agency, the 24 CCP Politburo members reaffirmed, during a working meeting, their intention to redouble their efforts to stabilize the real estate sector and financial squares.
The leadership of the Chinese regime has also promised to take more measures to improve people's living and continue to promote a “high -level opening” with “more proactive and effective macroeconomic policies”, citing the expansion of internal demand as one of its priorities. "We will anticipate and resolve risks in key areas, as well as shocks that may come from abroad, with the aim of achieving continuous economic recovery," the agency added, according to the state agency.
The Gross Domestic Product Growth Goal (GDP) is the 'strong dish' of the Plenary Session of APN every year, which also serves to approve legislation or state budget.
The CCP arrives at the meeting in a context of softening the economy, appeals to the promotion of the private sector and intensifying the trade war with the United States.
China has achieved its annual growth objective of 5% in 2024, but is still trying to replace the dynamism of its economy in a context of weak domestic consumption and a profound real estate crisis, which have raised risk of deflation.
The threat of a climb of trade war with the United States following Donald Trump's return to the White House has aggravated the perspectives of the world's second largest economy. In addition to the stimulus packages of recent months, with support measures to the financial sector, real estate and scholarships, the authorities revealed a plan to stabilize foreign investment after a year of 2024 that registered a record negative flow, and plan to approve the country's first specific law to support the private sector in the annual session of the legislature. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:11:00+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China warns US that coercion is not the best way to deal with problems</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/china-avisa-eua-que-coercao-nao-e-a-melhor-forma-de-lidar-com-problemas/</link><description>The Chinese government has warned that pressing and coercing “not the best way to deal with China,” after Washington has announced that it will double the additional customs quotes placed on Chinese products to 20%. "China regrets and opposes this decision and will do everything it deems necessary to defend its legitimate interests," the Ministry of Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian told a press conference. Lin said unilateral rates impair both the World Trade Organization and international trade relations and insisted that "there are no winners in commercial wars."
Considering the fentanil “an internal problem of the United States,” Chinese diplomacy spokesman said Washington is using his opioid crisis to “press and coerce” China, although the Asian country is “one of the hardest” in the fight against the drug.
The diplomat also stressed that Beijing has supported the US in his response to the Fentanil problem, transnational cooperation with results he described as "very remarkable."
The diplomat urged Washington to address the problems "through dialogue and on an equality" and reiterated that China is willing to continue to cooperate with the US to achieve a "solid, stable and healthy" relationship.
The conviction of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs follows to that of the Ministry of Commerce, which stated hours before China will take "all necessary countermeasures" to "defend its rights and legitimate interests."
United States President Donald Trump promised on Thursday that his country would impose an additional 10% rate on China, joining another rate at the same amount previously announced, with the argument that the Asian country made enough efforts to fight fentanil entry in the US.
Trump made the rates of "progress" depend on the fight against fentanyl trafficking, also announcing 25% rates on goods from Mexico and Canada. “Drugs are coming from Mexico and many of them are coming from China; Not all, but many of them are coming from China, ”he said.
Beijing responded last month to the first round of Trump rates at a rate of 10-15% over certain US products, as well as new essential mineral export controls and an anti-monopoly investigation into the Google US technological giant.
China has also protested 25% US import rates applied by steel and aluminum as it exports these materials to other countries, such as Canada and Mexico, which in turn sell them to the US. In his first presidency (2017-2021), Trump had a tense relationship with Beijing by imposing several rounds of rates on hundreds of millions of dollars of imports from China.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:09:30+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao and General Administration of China Customs Sign cooperation agreements</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/macau-e-administracao-geral-das-alfandegas-da-china-assinam-acordos-de-cooperacao/</link><description>André Cheong, Secretary for Administration and Justice, met on Friday with Wang Lingjun, Deputy Director of the General Administration of China Customs. At the meeting, agreements were signed to reinforce cooperation in animal health and food safety.
The “Cooperation Work Plan for Electronic Certification of Animal Animals and Animal Products” aims to promote the facilitation of border and trade passage under the assumption of safeguarding national biological security. At the same time, gongbei customs services and the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) signed cooperation agreements on aquatic animals for consumption and exotic invasive species.
The “Cooperation Work Plan for Electronic Certification of Animal Animals and Products”, based on the “Cooperation Agreement for Electronic Certification of Plant Products” signed in 2019, extends the scope of cooperation in electronic certification, from plant health and food safety products. “Through the exchange of information on electronic animal and animal certificates, the initiative will not only deepen cooperation in electronic certification, but also raise the efficiency of inspection and confirmation and the level of trade facilitation,” explains the statement issued by the Government of MSAR.
Foi ainda assinado o “acordo de cooperação sobre o desenvolvimento conjunto da monitorização da qualidade, segurança, saúde e riscos dos animais aquáticos para consumo” e o “acordo de cooperação sobre o desenvolvimento conjunto (de investigação de base de espécies invasivas exóticas) em Macau”. O primeiro visa elaborar um plano de monitorização e realizar inspecções, em conjunto. O segundo consiste na cooperação entre as duas partes na efectuação de uma nova investigação de base sobre espécies invasoras exóticas.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:08:34+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Casinos revenues grew to 19.7 billion patacas in February</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/receitas-dos-casinos-cresceram-para-197-mil-milhoes-de-patacas-em-fevereiro/</link><description>In February, gross casino game revenues operating in Macao rose to 19.7 billion. Compared to February 2024, the jump was 6.8%. Between January and February this year, the game industry has accumulated close to 38 billion patacas, slightly above the amount recorded in the first two months of last year.
 
The casinos operating in Macao in February fought a total of 19.7 billion patacas, which means a growth of 6.8% compared to the 18.4 billion reached in February last year. The data were released yesterday on the Electronic Page of the Games Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ). Compared to January this year, there was also an improvement, in this case of 8.2%.
Cumulatively, between January and February this year, the casinos got gross revenues of 38 billion patacas, which is in line with what happened last year, when in the first two months of the year the game industry had pocketed 37.8 billion patacas. Growth this year was only 0.5%.
For all this year, the government expects the game industry to reach 240 billion patacas in revenues, which makes the expected monthly average of 20 billion, and this goal has not been reached in the first two months of the year. The base budget for this year was prepared on the basis of this forecast of 240 billion of gross game revenues.
It is recalled that tax revenues from the game industry represent more than 80% of all of the MSAR tax revenues. The review of the Game Law, which came into force in 2022, stipulates that the concessionaires of the sector have to pay a direct tax of 35% of their revenues, plus an annual amount of 2% for a public fund and 3% more for urban development, tourism promotion and social security of MSc.
In 2024, gross game revenues ascended to 226.7 billion patacas, according to DICJ data. This figure exceeded government projections, which pointed to 216 billion, also meaning an increase of about 24% compared to the 183 billion of 2023.
The 2024 revenues were the highest of the last four years. In pandemic restrictions, 2020, 2021 and 2022, the gross revenues of the casino industry were 60.4 billion, 86.8 billion and 42.2 billion patacas, respectively. Before the pandemic, in 2019, the game sector had revenues of 292.4 billion patacas and in 2018 of 302.8 billion, for example. The annual gross game revenue record was beaten in 2013, when operators received more than 360 billion patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:13:03+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SMG predicts normal to relatively high temperatures in spring</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/smg-preveem-temperaturas-normais-a-relativamente-altas-na-primavera/</link><description>During the period between March and May, the average air temperature in Macao should be normal to relatively high, predict meteorological and geophysical services (SMG). The accumulated precipitation throughout the quarter will be normal to relatively low. Despite the milder temperatures of the last days, it is expected that, between tonight and tomorrow morning, a cold front arrives on the coast of Guangdong, which, besides the cold, can also cause water and thunderstorms.
 
Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) released climate forecasts for approaching spring, pointing out that the average air temperature of Macao in spring of 2025 - between March and May - is from normal to relatively high. The accumulated precipitation throughout the quarter will be from normal to relatively low, anticipate SMG.
It is considered that the normal climate value is between 21.9 and 22.6 degrees Celsius. The climate value considered normal for precipitation is between 380 and 640 millimeters.
Spring in Macao is a transitional station between winter and summer monsoons, they point out the SMG, adding that in early spring, the climate in Macau is mainly influenced by an east quadrant air stream after high -pressure cold air output to the sea.
Time will be mostly damp with rainy periods. Subsequently, the high cold pressure that affects mainland China will weaken and the temperature will gradually rise again. The climate in the southern region of China will be affected by a depressive valley. Consequently, it will increase the rainfall activity and the thunder phenomenon at the end of the season, from May.
The most up to date data show that the temperature to the surface of the sea in the Ecuador, from the east to the center of the Pacific Ocean continues to go down and is in a state of “La Niña”. Based on the forecast of the integrated model, it is expected that the phenomenon “La Niña” gradually slows and can change to the “neutral state” in the end of spring.
 
Cold front will hit Macau from this night
 
Despite the milder temperatures of recent days, SMG predicts that, between tonight and tomorrow morning, a cold front reaches the coast of Guangdong. During this period, waterproofs and possible thunderstorms may occur.
The cold weather will stay during the week. Today, temperatures will reach 26 degrees Celsius and tomorrow will oscillate between 17 and 21.
Between Wednesday and Friday, temperatures will remain low, with the maxims reaching 18 degrees and minimum of 13. In addition, throughout the week, dispersed rainfall should be recorded, according to the authorities.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:12:54+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Improvement of the business environment among government priorities</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/melhoria-do-ambiente-de-negocios-entre-as-prioridades-do-governo/</link><description>The government will include in the government lines of governing policies aimed at improving the business environment for local companies, as well as measures to reinforce the connection between Macao and Mountain Island. The Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, met with the Macao Commercial Association and the Macao members in the National People's Assembly to hear their opinions. The representatives asked the government more commercial and tourist promotion.
 
The executive will define specific policies and measures in the scope of the diversification of the economy with the aim of creating a better business environment for Macao companies. The statement came from the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, in a meeting with the Macao Commercial Association where the elaboration of the Governing Action Lines (LAG) was addressed for this year.
According to a government press release, Sam Hou Fai also said he expects the Macao Commercial Association to “take advantage of its influence” to encourage the industrial and commercial sector to participate in the development of the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin and the Great Bay. The ruler also requested support and collaboration of the association in the implementation of various policies and measures, contributing to the sustainable development of the territory.
Chui Sai Cheong, president of the Macao Commercial Association, stressed at the time that the government gives importance to the commercial sector and the Association gathered opinions of the members on restoration and beverage, tourism, retail trade and macao finances, which have already been submitted to the authorities.
The deputy also assured that the entity will continue to play the role of platform to focus on Macao's economic development and social stability and boost communication and cooperation with various sectors.
In addition, MA IAO LAI, permanent president of the Association, appealed to accelerate the integration of Macau and Hengqin, while the other representatives, Liu Chak Wan, Jia Tianbing, Pansy Ho, Chui Sai Peng, Lam Kam Seng and Chui Yuk Lum, asked for the promotion of Macao brand products, the full performance of role as a platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, environmental improvement, environment business, tax incentives, among others.
The chief executive also met last Thursday, with the representatives of Macau to the National Popular Assembly (APN), highlighting the government's effort in integrating hengqin, as well as the work of revitalization of neighborhoods, with historical and cultural context, in order to create tourist attractions with local characteristics.
Sam Hou Fai has assured that he will formulate measures and policies in a pragmatic way that will be favorable to the stable development of Macao and the well-being of the population, and encouraged Macao deputies to APN to give their opinion on national sovereignty, security and development interests.
Quoted by the statement at the meeting, Kou Hoi In, a member of the APN Permanent Committee, suggested the creation of a new tourist framework and the total coverage of the WiFi -free network connection throughout the city. Lao Ngai Leong has made votes that the government will perfect the infrastructure of border posts and study with the competent services of the interior of China the adoption of an even more convenient border passing model.
 
Sam Hou Fai highlights bets on science and innovative technology
 
The Chief Executive received, on Friday, the Rector of the United University and UNDER-Secretary-General of the United Nations, Tshilidzi Marwala, and guaranteed at the meeting that he gives high importance to the development and application of innovative science and technology as well as boosting its industrialization. According to Sam Hou Fai, Macau can enhance his function of linking universities and foreign companies to start cooperation and create bases for scientific research in Macao and Hengqin. In addition, the government leader also had meetings with the managing director of the General Administration of Customs, Wang Lingjun, and Zhong Nanshan, chairman of the Guidance Commission of the Macao Institute of Translational Medicine and Innovation, respectively, to discuss the evolution of Hengqin and the 'Big Health' and traditional Chinese medicine industry.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:09:23+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau promoted in the Middle East</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/macau-promovido-no-medio-oriente/</link><description>Macao, as a tourist destination, was promoted in the Middle East at the end of February. The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), accompanied by representatives of the region's tourist industry, was in Riyadh, Saudi Arabia, and Dubai, in the United Arab Emirates, to hold a promotion seminar on the latest products of “Tourism + Conventions” and Macao exhibitions.
During the events, a total of more than 200 representatives of the Macao tourist industry and both places participated in contact scholarships to discuss opportunities for cooperation in the areas of tourism, marketing, conventions and exhibitions and business environment, among others.
“This visit to Riyadh and Dubai for seminaries is an important measure of STD to reinforce Macau's promotion in the Middle East, allowing more tourist operators and visitors from the Middle East to know the Macao Unique Charm, promoting the diversified development of visitors' markets,” reads STD statement.
STD also announced that in May, Macau will participate in the largest tourism fair in the Middle East, Arabian Travel Market (ATM), “with the aim of attracting high level and business visitors”.
On the other hand, to attract visitors from the Middle East, STD launched, during the seminaries, a Macao tour guide to Muslims, and was distributed to local tourist operators of the English and Arabic version. The guide presents the aspects to take into account during the stay in Macau, gastronomic culture, itinerary recommendations, among other useful information for Muslim visitors. STD will soon translate the guide to Chinese, Malay and Indonesian, for distribution in other promotional activities to be done abroad in order to show that Macau continues to improve the Halal Offer facilities.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:11:27+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>At least 41 people are missing after avalanche in northern India</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/pelo-menos-41-pessoas-estao-desaparecidas-apos-avalanche-no-norte-da-india/</link><description>At least 41 people were missing after an avalanche hit the shipyards of a building in a mountainous area in northern India, the authorities said, adding that 16 people have already been rescued. “A total of 57 workers from the India Border Roads Department was buried after an avalanche. However, 16 of these have already been rescued, ”said Uttarakhand State Chief Minister Pushkar Singh Dhami in a statement to the media.
The regional government leader said the Indo-Tibetan Border Police (ITBP) is helping with rescue efforts in the area of ​​Mana village in Chamoli district in Uttarkhand province.
The mountainous area in western Himalaias, 20 kilometers from China's border, has been hit by rainfall in recent hours and remains orange, according to the latest Indian Meteorological Department report (IMD).
According to the head of the India Border Roads Department, C.R. Meena, at least three ambulances were sent to the area, but the rescue team is having difficulty reaching the place where the incident occurred.
Snow storms and avalanches are the two largest dangers in Indian Himalayas, located in the north of the country. Avalanches often affect visitors who come to the region to admire their landscapes and walk their mountains.
At least nine walkers died in Indian Himalayas on June 6 last year after being arrested for almost 48 hours in a snowstorm.
Accidents during infrastructure construction are common in India, where conditions are not always the safest or fulfill safety standards.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:13:11+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Secretary for Hong Kong Innovation seeks business in Portugal</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/secretario-para-a-inovacao-de-hong-kong-procura-negocios-em-portugal/</link><description>Hong Kong's secretary for innovation, technology and industry will be on Thursday in Portugal to “explore business opportunities” to the innovation and technology industry.
 
Sun Dong, Hong Kong Innovation, Technology and Industry Secretary, will be on Thursday in Portugal to “explore business opportunities” to the innovation and technology sector. In a statement, the Hong Kong government said Sun Dong left a delegation of innovation and technology representatives, which will be in Lisbon on March 6.
The visit program includes “meetings and exchanges with leaders of the political, business and innovation and technology sectors”, as well as infrastructure visits, technological parks, research institutes and companies.
The aim is to “reinforce ties and cooperation” with Portugal in this sector, “promoting the advantages of Hong Kong innovation and technology and exploring business opportunities abroad,” according to the statement.
The delegation includes leaders from three public institutions: HKSTP, a company created in 2001 to promote innovation and technological development in the region, the Institute of Research in Science and Technology Applied and the Institute of Research and Development of Microelectronics.
In addition, they will be in Lisbon leaders of the Cyberport Technology Park, as well as representatives of 24 companies or Hong Kong innovation and technology institutions.
Before passing through Lisbon, the Hong Kong delegation will be in Barcelona, ​​in northeastern Spain, to participate in Mobile World Congress, considered one of the most influential technological events worldwide.
This will be the second visit to Portugal of a member of the Hong Kong government within a year, after the secretary for the region's financial and treasure services had passed through Lisbon in June.
At the time, Christopher Hui Ching-Yu asked Portugal to remove Hong Kong from the list of tax havens and argued that it already fulfills European Union (EU) standards to combat fiscal dropout.
The request was filed at a meeting with the Secretary of State for Tax Affairs, Claudia Reis Duarte, "in the light of Hong Kong's continuous efforts in supporting international cooperation."
Christopher Hui “expressed concern” for Hong Kong being considered a fiscal paradise since Portugal created the list in 2004.
Something that would “subject Hong Kong companies to a tax increase and special measures” in Portugal, stressed the ruler, who also recalled that the two parties signed an agreement to avoid double taxation, which came into force in 2012.
The list includes 80 countries, territories and regions that Portugal classifies as having privileged, clearly more favorable tax regimes, and in relation to which are applied to various financial taxes on aggravated tax rates. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:10:56+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Government considers altering a form of attribution of pecuniary checks</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/03/governo-pondera-alterar-forma-de-atribuicao-dos-cheques-pecuniarios/</link><description>The chief executive guaranteed the continuity of the pecuniary reimbursement plan, but will still consider the value and form of attribution of the checks. Sam Hou Fai said he wanted to hear even more opinions for a more “just and accurate” implementation of the measure. Speaking for the first time in an interview with journalists, Sam also reiterated the need for policies to encourage young generation to “assume social responsibility” of having children.
 
The government is still awaiting more opinions from the company to determine whether to impose adjustments in the form of attribution and the value of pecuniary checks, especially changes to “improve the principles of justice and accuracy” of the pecuniary reimbursement plan, said the chief executive.
Sam Hou Fai spoke last Thursday night for the first time in an interview with journalists and confirmed that the checks will continue this year that the plan is a "measure that benefits people" and a "expectation of society", noting that 90 billion patacas were awarded to the population in the last 16 years of implementation of the program.
“The measure has to be implemented this year. In terms of the space for improvement, how much should be attributed, everyone may make suggestions. If money is assigned and as it will be attributed, we have to take into account the global economic environment. The public can give their opinion on these details, ”he said.
The pecuniary reimbursement plan for this year foresees a budget of 7.48 billion patacas. The chief executive indicated that the budget was made based on the revenue of a monthly game of 20 billion patacas, a calculation that implies that there will be a "small surplus" of revenues. "However, considering the current economic situation, including the fact that the revenues of the game in December [last year] were only about 18 billion Patacas, the government has to think about it, in particular auscultation of sectors about the attribution of checks," he said.
It is recalled that the monetary reimbursement was implemented in 2008, and at the time a temporary beneficial measure being in response to economic recession and high inflation, whose objective “went to share with the population the result of economic development, if there were conditions in the government's safe,” explained the executive in a statement. Some deputies, economists and association representatives have appealed to the government to review the way of attributing checks, suggesting that only those who live in Macau can receive the amount.
 
“Social Responsibility” to have children
 
Sam Hou Fai, on the sidelines of a Spring Dinner of the Macao Chinese Business Association, also reiterated the need for a solution to the aging of the population and the low birth rate.
“Let's think about how to encourage birth. At least, as a government, send a sign to society [with incentive policies] when finances allow it, supporting the younger generation to have more children, which I think is a social responsibility, ”he said.
The government leader said that he will study the possibility of a subsidy for babies care, as Macau currently assigns only a birth allowance to his parents. Underlining his “high attention” to the elderly and children related issues, Sam added that he is also considering increasing the pension to the elderly.
"The improvement of the welfare of the population and support to the vulnerable group are the focus of government government actions," and the executive expects, "under the assumption of safeguarding the basic needs of the population's welfare and if the financial situation allows, fully ponders the various factors and studying the policy of adjusting various benefits," he said.
 
Casinos-satellites in exit
On the other hand, regarding the arrival at the end of the period of three years of transition from the satellite casinos, scheduled for the end of this year, the chief executive did not express concerns and said he believed that game operators and managers of casinos-satellites will coordinate according to the contract entered into and proceed effectively transition work.
"Casinos-satellite employees are recruited by game operators, so they have the responsibility to take appropriate action on their workers, and if necessary, the government will support," Sam has taken on the importance of "stable, healthy, phase" development of the game sector in Macao.
Sam Hou Fai, at the time, also spoke about the controversy of the viaduct of Zones A and B of new landfills and said he knows the different opinions of society about the project. Without novelty, the ruler pointed out that Zone A will become an important area of ​​education and housing in Macao, indicating that it is necessary to have a good planning of the complementary road facilities and that the competent services will still analyze opinions to “improve” the project.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03T06:15:23+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>