<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/rita-santos-diz-que-investigacao-foi-caso-tipico-de-instrumentalizacao-da-justica/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Casinos earned more than 24 billion patacas in October, a record for the last six years</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/casinos-facturaram-mais-de-24-mil-milhoes-de-patacas-em-outubro-recorde-dos-ultimos-seis-anos/</link><description>In October, the gross revenues of the Macau gaming industry were slightly above 24 billion patacas. Only going back to October 2019 does one find a value higher than this. Between January and October this year, casinos operating in the territory have already accumulated 205.4 billion patacas in gross revenue, 8% more compared to the same period last year.

In October, gross revenues from the gaming sector in Macau broke the record of the last six years. Last month, according to data released by the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Department (DICJ), casinos earned 24.08 billion patacas. In October 2019, before the pandemic restrictions applied by the Macao SAR Government were felt, casinos had raised 26.4 billion, but since then they have not exceeded 22 billion.
Comparing last month's gross revenues with those of October 2024, the jump is 15.9%. Compared to September this year, revenue growth is even more significant: 31.8%. It is worth remembering that Macau received 1.14 million tourists over the eight days of Golden Week in October, an increase of 16.5% compared to last year's numbers.
Between January and October this year, casinos operating in Macau have already accumulated 205.4 billion patacas in gross revenue, 8% more compared to the same period last year.
The basic budget prepared by the previous Macao SAR Government for 2025 estimated that gaming revenue this year would reach 240 billion patacas. After a start to the year that fell short of expectations, the current Government presented a revised budget with a forecast of 228 billion patacas, a figure that casinos should reach before the end of the year, if they maintain their current pace.
A report released last month by consultancy Seaport Research Partners said that this year's gross gaming revenues are expected to exceed MOP245 billion.
Last year, gross gaming revenues amounted to 226.7 billion patacas, an increase of around 24% compared to 183 billion in 2023. These figures, although significant, remain below revenues before the pandemic: in 2018, for example, the gaming sector obtained gross revenues of 302.8 billion patacas.
Tax revenue from the gaming industry represents more than 80% of the Macao SAR's total tax revenue. The revision to the gaming law, which came into force in 2022, stipulates that concessionaires in the sector have to pay a direct tax of 35% of their revenue, plus an annual amount of 2% to a public fund and another 3% for urban development, tourist promotion and social security in the Macao SAR.</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:14:29</pubDate></item><item><title>AL's proposed budget reaches new record of 224 million patacas</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/orcamento-proposto-da-al-atinge-novo-recorde-de-224-milhoes-de-patacas/</link><description>The Legislative Assembly foresees more spending next year. The hemicycle's private budget for 2026 is set at 224 million patacas, representing an increase of 2.81% compared to the current year. The budgeted amount is also the highest in the history of this legislative body, which recently passed to a new legislature with almost half of new deputies, including its president.

The Legislative Assembly (AL), which recently started the new legislature, has already established its private budget for activities next year, with an expected increase in expenses to 224 million patacas, the highest value recorded in history.
This budgeted amount represents an increase of 6.13 million patacas, that is, an increase of 2.81% in annual terms, compared to the budget for the 2025 financial year, of 217.87 million patacas. Before this date, with the exception of the budget for 2023, the budgeted expenditure for AL never exceeded 200 million patacas.
According to the proposal submitted by the AL Administrative Council for consideration and deliberation by the Hemicycle in today's plenary, the budget is made up of five categories, among which personnel expenses should continue to be the largest source of expenditure for the legislative body, accounting for more than 80% of the total amount.
Personnel expenses are projected at more than 184.69 million patacas for next year, a decrease of almost 2 million patacas compared to the current year. The AL attributes the reduction to “retirement and dismissal of workers”.
Meanwhile, there are two items with greater positive variations in the amounts of budgeted expenses, including operating expenses and facilities and equipment.
Operating expenses will increase from 24.28 million patacas, budgeted for this year, to more than 31.92 million patacas, which corresponds to an increase of 31.5%. The increase is “mainly due to the replacement of the air conditioning and conference and interpretation systems in the Plenary Room, which have been in use for several years, and the optimization of the AL website and IT system”.
Expenses for installations and equipment amount to more than 1.36 million patacas, representing an increase of 46.22% in relation to the current year's budget, which the diploma justifies with the need to purchase computer equipment and pay expenses related to software copyrights.
The AL, on the other hand, will maintain the budgeted expenses under the headings “transfers, support and allowances” and “other current expenses” at the same value as in 2025, setting them, respectively, at 10 thousand patacas and six million patacas.
As clarified in the proposal, the 2026 budget, worth 224 million patacas, results mainly from estimates on “Transfers from the Macao SAR's central budget”, with more than 223 million patacas, as well as estimates on “Press and publications”, at 10 thousand patacas, “Replacements of payments made in previous years”, at 5 thousand patacas, and “Mobilization of budget execution balances” in 500 thousand patacas.
It is worth remembering that the expenses paid by AL in the previous year amounted to more than 202 million patacas, which corresponds to an execution rate of 96% of the initial budget.</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:17:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Unemployment falls in the third quarter despite the closure of two casinos</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/desemprego-cai-no-terceiro-trimestre-apesar-do-fecho-de-dois-casinos/</link><description>The unemployment rate in Macau fell to 1.8% between July and September, the lowest figure since February, despite the closure of two 'satellite casinos'.

According to the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC), the indicator decreased by 0.2 percentage points compared to the period between June and August, with the number of unemployed people falling by around 700, to 6,900.
The rate represents less than half of that recorded in the third quarter of 2022 (4%), the highest value since 2006, at a time when Macau was in the midst of an economic crisis caused by the covid-19 pandemic. But the recovery motivated by the end of the 'zero covid' policy, which was in force in Macau and mainland China for almost more than three years, led unemployment to fall to 1.6% between November 2024 and last January, a historic low since DSEC began collecting data on unemployment in Macau in 1992.
According to official data, construction hired 8,300 more people, compared to the period between June and August, while the workforce in restaurants increased by around 2,500. On the contrary, the casinos laid off around 200 people.
On June 9, the Government of Macau announced that gaming concessionaires had announced the end of operation of the 11 'satellite casinos', where around 5,600 residents work. However, only nine 'satellite casinos' are expected to close their doors, as the concessionaire SJM wants to acquire the hotels where two are located – Ponte 16 and Casino Royal Arc – and ask the authorities to take over direct management of the spaces.
The 'satellite casinos', under the responsibility of the concessionaires, are managed by other companies, being a legacy of the Portuguese administration and which already existed before the liberalization of gambling in the territory, in 2002. When the legislation regulating casinos was changed, in 2022, the end of 2025 was established as the deadline for ending the activity of these gambling spaces.
The first casino to close was the Grandview, at the end of July, followed by the Grand Dragon, on September 23, and the Mocha Kuong Fat gaming machine room, two days later. The Emperor Palace casino closed on Thursday, after the period included in the most recent unemployment data, followed by Waldo. At the beginning of June, the then Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, assured that the authorities would require operators to guarantee the employment of affected workers and “closely” monitor the relocation.
According to data released by DSEC, 18.3% of unemployed people were looking for their first job between July and September, 3.8 percentage points more than between June and August, precisely due to the entry into the job market of university graduates. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:13:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese manufacturing industry slowed growth in October</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/industria-transformadora-chinesa-abrandou-crescimento-em-outubro/</link><description>Activity in China's manufacturing industry grew in October for the third consecutive month, at a slower pace than in September, according to the purchasing managers' index (PMI, the sector's benchmark indicator) released by consultancy RatingDog.
This indicator, prepared by the risk analysis agency Standard &amp; Poor’s (S&amp;P) and which many international investors take as a reference to analyze the Chinese manufacturing sector, slowed from 51.2 points in September to 50.6 in the month that just ended.
When measuring the PMI, a mark above 50 points represents an expansion of activity in the sector compared to the previous month, while below this means a contraction.
The data is also below what was expected by analysts, who expected a slowdown in growth, but less pronounced, to around 50.9 units.
The S&amp;P reading is more positive than the official one, released last Friday by the Chinese National Statistics Institute (INE), which pointed to a seventh consecutive month of contraction in industrial activity, placing the PMI at 49 points.
RatingDog founder Yao Yu explained that both demand and supply slowed in October, and that, in both cases, the trade war with the United States was among the main culprits. "On the demand side, greater commercial uncertainty in October caused new export orders to fall sharply (…). Market fears regarding the weakening of exports remained. On the supply side, uncertainty in the external environment also harmed production growth", he stated.
Yao clarified that all sub-indices that measure productive activity continue to show positive results, as does the employment index, which follows the evolution of the labor market in the Chinese manufacturing sector, which recorded the highest level since August 2023 in March.
Given the current situation, the Chinese Executive believes that the new five-year plan (2026-2030) recently approved by the Chinese Communist Party “can offer some support in the future” to the PMI, thanks to the promised measures in terms of economic stabilization and boosting domestic demand.</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:06:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing makes entry into Macau and Hong Kong more flexible for Mainland residents with talent visas</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/pequim-flexibiliza-entrada-em-macau-e-hong-kong-dos-residentes-do-continente-com-visto-de-talentos/</link><description>China's National Immigration Administration announced a set of ten new border control measures, including more flexible multiple entry policies for Mainland residents traveling to Hong Kong and Macau on talent visas. It is also planned to expand the border inspection measure with facial recognition to more border posts, such as Hengqin and the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge.

The Central Government announced the extension of entry permits to Hong Kong and Macau for professionals from mainland China who have official talent certification.
Starting tomorrow, qualified personnel from more locations in mainland China will be able to apply for multiple entry into the SAR, with permits valid for one to five years, and the policy, previously applied in Beijing, Shanghai and the Greater Bay Area, will be extended to cover the entire Yangtze River Delta and the Jing-Jin-Ji (Beijing-Tianjin-Hebei) metropolitan region, as well as all pilot national free trade zones across the country.
The initiative is part of a set of ten measures announced yesterday by the Chinese National Immigration Administration in relation to immigration control at borders. Chinese officials say the measures are dedicated to “supporting high-level opening-up and high-quality development.”
According to the organization, eligible professionals from mainland China, including distinguished talents and experts in research, culture, education, health and law, will be able to apply for multiple entry permits in Macau and Hong Kong, with stays of up to 30 days per visit.
The new measures also provide for ease of extension of stay in Macau and Hong Kong for visitors holding family visit permits. According to the document, Mainland residents traveling to the SAR with family visit authorizations can request visa renewal through the local China Travel Service, at least seven working days before the end of their authorized stay.

BORDER CROSSING WITH FACE RECOGNITION
 
The announcement by the National Immigration Administration of China also advanced the promotion of the application of the “intelligent system”, through facial recognition, at border crossings at several migration posts, including the Hengqin checkpoints and the Zhuhai checkpoint on the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge.
According to the Macau police authorities, this border crossing without showing documents will be adopted from tomorrow, with service available to people who have reached the age of 14.
Recipients of the service include Macau and Hong Kong residents holding valid “Hong Kong and Macau Residents Round-Trip Safe-Conduct for Mainland China”, including non-Chinese nationals. The measure also covers residents of the interior of China who hold Safe Conduct with Authorization to travel to the SAR, multiple times in the categories of Stay (D), Family Visit (T), Business (S), Qualified Personnel (R) or Other (Q), as well as residents of Taiwan who hold Safe Conduct valid for five years. Those interested in using the service must consent to the collection and verification of facial and fingerprint information for immigration border control verification.
In a statement issued by the Public Security Police Corps, the authorities of Macau and the Mainland state that they have already carried out work to update the software and hardware of the automatic full inspection channels at the Hengqin Border Post, of which 48 are in the inspection rooms and 16 in the vehicle passenger inspection rooms.
At the Hengqin post, next year, 46 automatic full inspection channels will be installed with border crossing functionality with facial recognition, “with which it is expected that at least 65% of inspection capacity can be increased, improving border crossing efficiency”, stated the organization.
In addition, Hengqin and Delta Bridge posts will become designated ports for the 240-hour transit visa-free policy. This policy allows visitors from 55 designated countries, with valid international travel documents, to enter mainland China through any of 65 ports and stay in the country for up to 240 hours (10 days) without a visa, before continuing on to a third destination.</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:16:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Seoul Launches Last Space Military Espionage Network Satellite</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/seul-lanca-ultimo-satelite-de-rede-de-espionagem-militar-espacial/</link><description>South Korea launched on Sunday the fifth and final satellite of a military espionage network aimed at strengthening independent surveillance capabilities over North Korean activities, the South Korean Ministry of Defense confirmed.
The spy satellite, equipped with a synthetic aperture radar (SAR), was launched aboard a Falcon 9 rocket from the company SpaceX at 01:09 hours in Florida, United States, as part of the Bandwagon-4 mission, from the Cape Canaveral Space Station, in that North American state.
The successful placement of the satellite into orbit was announced about 20 minutes later by South Korean authorities. “The joint operation of five reconnaissance satellites will allow for faster and more accurate detection of North Korea's provocations,” the South Korean ministry said in a statement.
Seoul thus completed the implementation of the first network of spy satellites, around two years after the launch, on December 2, 2023, of the first of the devices, a week after Pyongyang announced that it had placed its own spy satellite into orbit, in a context of escalating bilateral tension.
Once the five satellites are in orbit, it is expected that the country will be able to monitor North Korea every two hours, reducing dependence on US satellite images.
South Korea hopes that the five reconnaissance satellites will serve as “eyes” intended to support the Kill Chain preemptive strike system, by allowing rapid detection or early warning signals of a possible nuclear or missile attack by North Korea.
Kill Chain is a platform for detecting possible enemy attacks and activating preventive attacks with surface-to-surface and sea-to-land missiles from Seoul, presented in 2022.
As part of this space surveillance campaign, Pyongyang launched its first military spy satellite, Malligyong-1, on November 21, 2023, and guaranteed that it would launch three more spy satellites in 2024, but has not launched any more since a rocket carrying a satellite exploded after takeoff in May last year.</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:05:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Association concerned about Portugal's silence on the closure of All About Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/associacao-preocupada-com-silencio-de-portugal-sobre-fecho-do-all-about-macau/</link><description>An association of media professionals expressed concern about Portugal's silence following the announcement of the closure of the online newspaper and monthly printed publication All About Macau.
The Society of European Journalists and Communication Professionals in Asia (JOCPA) expressed “deep concern about the silence of authorities and international institutions — including Portugal and the European Union” (EU).
Lisbon and Brussels “have a moral and historical responsibility to defend the rule of law and fundamental rights, including freedom of the press and expression”, defended the president of JOCPA, Josep Solano, cited in a statement. “Press freedom in Macau is also a European concern: defending it means keeping alive the spirit of cooperation, pluralism and respect for fundamental rights that the EU claims to represent,” added JOCPA.
All About Macau announced on Thursday that it will close due to “increasing pressures”, lack of resources and legal proceedings in the territory against three of its journalists. “Faced with increasingly scarce resources, increasing external pressure and journalists involved in legal proceedings, the team is finding it increasingly difficult to maintain its standards”, he explained, indicating that this month the last monthly printed publication will be published and from December 20th the website and activity on social networks will be put to an end.
In a post on the social network Facebook, All About Macau recalled that “since October last year” that “certain official events have restricted the participation of journalists in their coverage”.
In April this year, the “publication was again prevented from covering the Legislative Assembly”, with three of its journalists “facing charges of crimes related to this incident”, and could “be subject to criminal proceedings”, added the media.
The Committee to Protect Journalists (CPJ) argued that the region's authorities “should stop persecuting” All About Macau and restore the registration of the online newspaper and monthly printed publication. "The closure of All About Macau is a blow to press freedom and seriously undermines the public's right to independent information. It is an indication of the rapid deterioration of the media environment in Macau", lamented CPJ's Asia coordinator, Beh Lih Yi.</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:09:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Hotels set new guest record until September</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/hoteis-fixam-novo-recorde-de-hospedes-ate-setembro/</link><description>Macau's hotel establishments welcomed more than 10.9 million guests until September, a new record for the first nine months of a year. According to official data from the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC), this value represents an increase of 0.1% compared to the same period in 2024.
Furthermore, it is the highest number since DSEC began compiling this data in 1998, even before the transition of administration of Macau from Portugal to China.
With more guests, hotel establishments in the territory had 89.3% of rooms occupied between January and September, 3.9 percentage points more than in the same period in 2024 and the highest rate since the beginning of the covid-19 pandemic.
At the end of September, Macau had 147 hotels and guesthouses, three more than last year and a historic maximum, providing around 45 thousand rooms, said DSEC. Also last month, three hotels were being built, with a total of 204 rooms, and nine more are in the design phase, which could provide a thousand rooms, announced the Directorate of Land and Urban Construction Services.
The region received 29.7 million visitors in the first nine months, 14.5 percent more than in the same period in 2024 and the second highest figure ever for the start of a year. However, 58.2% of visitors (17.3 million) arrived on organized tours and spent less than a day in the city.
In September alone, the average occupancy rate of hotel establishments fell 0.1 percentage points, to 84.6%, while the number of guests remained similar to the same month last year: 1.12 million. This is despite hotels having lowered average room prices to 1,270 patacas, 1.1% less than in the same month of 2024, according to data from the Macau Hotel Association, which brings together 48 local establishments.
According to the report, released by the Tourism Services Directorate, the decline was felt mainly in three-star hotels, whose average price fell by 5.4%, to 850 patacas.
Macau's hotel establishments welcomed more than 14.4 million guests in 2024, setting a new historical record. The previous record, 14.1 million guests, had been set in 2019, before the covid-19 pandemic, in a year in which Macau ended with just 38,300 rooms in 122 hotel establishments. “We have more and more tourists, but the level of consumption is falling”, warned, on May 13, the Government leader, Sam Hou Fai.
The average consumption of each visitor in Macau, excluding casinos, fell 12.8% in the first half, compared to the same period in 2024.</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:07:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese group Wingtech guarantees supply of 'chips' to customers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/grupo-chines-wingtech-garante-fornecimento-de-chips-aos-clientes/</link><description>The Chinese group Wingtech Semiconductor has guaranteed that it will be able to maintain the supply of 'chips' to customers, despite the interruption of shipments from the Dutch subsidiary Nexperia, the center of a trade dispute between China and the Netherlands.

In a letter sent to customers, Wingtech informed that Nexperia Netherlands stopped sending, on October 26, the silicon wafers used to manufacture 'chips' to the assembly and testing factory in the Chinese city of Dongguan, alleging alleged late payments by the local administration.
The Chinese parent company classified the accusations as “false” and stated that, on the contrary, it is Nexperia that maintains debts with the Dongguan factory worth around 1 billion yuan.
Wingtech guarantees that it has accumulated sufficient inventories of finished and in-process components “to satisfy orders until the end of the year and beyond”.
The company added that it has implemented contingency plans to reinforce production and avoid future disruptions, at a time when European car manufacturers are warning of possible stoppages of assembly lines due to a lack of components.
The conflict began at the end of September, when the Dutch government intervened in Nexperia, citing reasons of national security and the need to prevent the transfer of technology to China. In response, Beijing banned the export of 'chips' manufactured by the company from the Chinese factory, a measure that affected global supplies.
This Saturday, the Chinese Ministry of Commerce announced that it will grant exemptions to the exports of companies that meet certain requirements to alleviate the crisis, while the European Commission confirmed that the Chinese suspension of controls on the export of strategic materials also applies to the European Union.
The Chinese Ministry of Commerce stated in a statement that “the Dutch Government's inappropriate interference in the company's internal affairs caused the current chaos in global production and supply chains” and stressed that China, as a “responsible country”, is considering measures to ensure the stability of industrial chains. "We invite companies facing real difficulties to contact the Ministry or the competent local authorities. We will consider the circumstances and grant export exemptions to those that meet the requirements", said the statement.
Nexperia, founded in the Dutch city of Nimega and acquired by Wingtech in 2019, produces semiconductors commonly used in automobiles and electronic devices. The factory in Dongguan, southern China, has maintained limited operations since the imposition of export bans. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:06:06</pubDate></item><item><title>“Friends Fest” launches festival dedicated to animals and their owners in Coloane</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/friends-fest-lanca-festival-dedicado-a-animais-e-respectivos-donos-em-coloane/</link><description>On the 8th and 9th of November, Grand Coloane Resort hosts Macau's first “Friends Fest”, a free event dedicated to pet lovers. The festival includes workshops, competitions, educational talks and a local market, with part of the proceeds going to Anima Macau and MASDAW for veterinary care and sterilization of animals. 
Coloane is preparing to host the first, and unprecedented, edition of “Friends Fest”, a two-day festival entirely dedicated to pets and their owners, which will take place at the Grand Coloane Resort on the 8th and 9th of November. With free entry, the event focuses on the theme “Love and Care” and aims to become a meeting point for the local community of animal lovers, offering a program that runs from 10am to 8pm on both days.
The solidarity component constitutes one of the fundamental pillars of the event, with all proceeds raised being fully donated to Anima Macau and MASDAW. The two local organizations are dedicated to sterilization, medical care and promoting animal welfare, allowing participants to actively contribute to a worthy cause while enjoying a variety of activities designed to strengthen the bonds between humans and their four-legged companions.
As part of the practical workshops, visitors will be able to create personalized accessories, including neckerchiefs made without the need for prior sewing experience, leashes created using traditional knotting techniques adapted to the size and personality of each dog, and healthy “macaron” treats that the animals themselves can enjoy. The dog training workshops, namely “Table Etiquette” and “Stress-Free Walks”, were specially developed to improve animal behavior in public spaces and restaurants.
The festival also includes a street market that brings together local Macau brands, from handicraft products and creative designs to nutritionally balanced foods and animal fashion accessories. For moments of relaxation, a picnic area has been meticulously prepared to offer unique photographic experiences, complemented with snacks safe for canine consumption, designed by the specialized team at Grand Coloane Resort.
The “Canine Talent” and “Best Dressed Dog” competitions stand out as central attractions, providing a stage for the demonstration of special skills and creativity in canine attire, with prizes awarded to the most outstanding participants. In addition, there will be free educational lectures led by professional veterinarians, covering topics such as disease prevention, daily care and sharing adoption stories that inspire responsible animal ownership.
The “Friends Fest” team hopes that the event will be positioned as a “platform for promoting a more animal-friendly city”, combining fun, education and solidarity in the same space, with the aim of more respectful care for the region’s animal community.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai challenges Chinese businesspeople to invest in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/sam-hou-fai-desafia-empresarios-chineses-a-investirem-em-macau/</link><description>The opening ceremony of the 18th world convention of Chinese businesspeople took place yesterday in Macau. The Macao SAR Chief Executive was present and took the opportunity to invite Chinese businesspeople to invest in the territory.
"I cordially invite all friends, Chinese businesspeople, to invest in Macau and Hengqin, the Greater Bay Area, China and our future. Let's, together, seize new development opportunities and create a new era of cooperation", said Sam Hou Fai.
The Chief Executive described Chinese businesspeople as “an important force in promoting world peace and development”. "In every corner of the world, they create, one after another, commercial miracles, achieve success and gain respect. Chinese businesspeople, in addition to having boosted the economic development of the countries and regions where they are located, have become promoters of excellent Chinese culture, contributors to causes of public interest and philanthropic, they are links and bridges between China and the world", highlighted Sam.
In his speech, Sam Hou Fai pointed out that “economic globalization is an irreversible historical trend”, and multilateralism is “decidedly the choice to resolve the difficulties and challenges facing the world”. "Only through strengthening the concept of 'community' and concerted collaboration will it be possible to find certainty in the midst of uncertainty and open a new situation in the midst of change. Chinese businesspeople from all over the world, naturally united by ties of blood and solidarity, form a community with a shared future", he stressed, adding that they are "an important force that connects China and the world and contributes to exchanges between East and West".
Highlighting Macau's commitment to developing economic diversification and the inauguration, in 2021, of the Deep Cooperation Zone, the Chief Executive also took the opportunity to suggest that businesspeople present at the convention deepen their knowledge of the region, strengthen “friendship with each other”, increase “pragmatic cooperation”, work together to “build a community with a shared future for Chinese businesspeople”, inject “greater stability and positive energy into the global economy” and raise a “new example for building a community with a shared future for humanity”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:08:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Travel agents from Tokyo and Osaka visited Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/agentes-de-viagem-de-toquio-e-osaka-visitaram-macau/</link><description>Between October 29th and November 1st, a group of around 30 representatives of Japanese travel agencies from Tokyo and Osaka visited Macau to familiarize themselves with Macau's “tourism +” offers and to carry out exchanges of contacts with local partners.
According to a press release from the Tourism Services Bureau (DST), one of the highlights of the visit's agenda was a Contact Exchange for Tour Operators from Macau and Japan (Tokyo and Osaka). The business pairing session brought together the Japanese delegation with representatives from more than 40 travel agencies, hotels and integrated tourism and leisure companies, exhibition and convention venues, air and sea carriers, among others. “Both sides explored partnership opportunities to serve the market of different traveler profiles in Japan,” says DST in a statement.
During their stay in Macau, “the group had the opportunity to experience first-hand the destination's traditional and new offerings to help inspire the creation of new tourism products tailored to different segments of Japanese visitors, including women's tourism and study trips”.
The itinerary included walking tours through the Historic Center of Macau, the towns of Taipa and Coloane, inspections of hotels and integrated resorts, entertainment offerings such as resident shows and a night tour on a panoramic bus, along with experiencing the variety of gastronomic offerings. The group also learned about new tourism developments to transform NAPE and ZAPE, and participated in a workshop to create souvenirs of Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:08:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese Communist Party expels two senior officials accused of corruption</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/partido-comunista-chines-expulsa-dois-altos-funcionarios-acusados-de-corrupcao/</link><description>The Chinese Communist Party (CCP) announced yesterday the expulsion of two senior representatives from the political formation for “serious violations of Party discipline and the law”.

According to statements from the Central Commission for Discipline Inspection (CCDI), the main internal anti-corruption body of the CCP, and the National Supervision Commission, its state counterpart, Xu Xianping, former vice minister of the National Development and Reform Commission (CNDR), and Wang Jianjun, former vice president of the Securities Market Regulatory Commission (CSRC), transformed public power into a “tool for personal benefit” through networks of exchange of favors and money.
Xu Xianping, 70, a former vice minister of the country's main economic planning body, was accused of accepting bribes, offering promotions and job adjustments in exchange for favors, as well as receiving gifts, decoration services and trips paid for by entities under his supervision.
The CCDI pointed out that Xu “lost his ideals” and “violated the principles of political and administrative integrity”. Wang Jianjun, former vice-president of the stock market regulator, was accused of accepting “large sums of money and valuables”, and of having unduly interfered in company listing and financing processes, using his influence to favor family members.
Wang Jianjun was further accused of attending banquets that could affect impartiality and resisting internal investigations.
Wang, 57, has been vice-president of the regulatory body since 2021 and previously headed the Shenzhen Stock Exchange, where in 2020 he promoted the reform of the ChiNext technological index, considered one of the most relevant in the sector. The dismissal occurred in May, a month after the disciplinary investigation began.
Both officials were stripped of all public positions, expelled from the party and their ill-gotten gains will be confiscated. The cases were referred to the Public Ministry for possible criminal prosecution.
The anti-corruption campaign in the financial system comes after the Chinese President and general secretary of the Communist Party, Xi Jinping, stated that the country must become a “financial superpower” in a context of “decoupling” with the United States.
In the last year alone, Chinese authorities have investigated dozens of senior officials, including Yi Huiman, president of the stock exchange regulator between 2019 and 2024, also accused of disciplinary infractions.
After coming to power in 2012, Xi Jinping began an anti-corruption campaign in which several senior Chinese officials, both institutional and state-owned companies, were convicted of accepting million-dollar bribes. In recent months, this campaign has extended to sectors such as finance, tobacco, energy, sports and pharmaceuticals. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:07:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal Point – 4 November 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/ponto-fatal-4-novembro-2025/</link><description>The Chinese Communist Party (CCP) announced yesterday the expulsion of two senior representatives from the political formation for “serious violations of Party discipline and the law”.

According to statements from the Central Commission for Discipline Inspection (CCDI), the main internal anti-corruption body of the CCP, and the National Supervision Commission, its state counterpart, Xu Xianping, former vice minister of the National Development and Reform Commission (CNDR), and Wang Jianjun, former vice president of the Securities Market Regulatory Commission (CSRC), transformed public power into a “tool for personal benefit” through networks of exchange of favors and money.
Xu Xianping, 70, a former vice minister of the country's main economic planning body, was accused of accepting bribes, offering promotions and job adjustments in exchange for favors, as well as receiving gifts, decoration services and trips paid for by entities under his supervision.
The CCDI pointed out that Xu “lost his ideals” and “violated the principles of political and administrative integrity”. Wang Jianjun, former vice-president of the stock market regulator, was accused of accepting “large sums of money and valuables”, and of having unduly interfered in company listing and financing processes, using his influence to favor family members.
Wang Jianjun was further accused of attending banquets that could affect impartiality and resisting internal investigations.
Wang, 57, has been vice-president of the regulatory body since 2021 and previously headed the Shenzhen Stock Exchange, where in 2020 he promoted the reform of the ChiNext technological index, considered one of the most relevant in the sector. The dismissal occurred in May, a month after the disciplinary investigation began.
Both officials were stripped of all public positions, expelled from the party and their ill-gotten gains will be confiscated. The cases were referred to the Public Ministry for possible criminal prosecution.
The anti-corruption campaign in the financial system comes after the Chinese President and general secretary of the Communist Party, Xi Jinping, stated that the country must become a “financial superpower” in a context of “decoupling” with the United States.
In the last year alone, Chinese authorities have investigated dozens of senior officials, including Yi Huiman, president of the stock exchange regulator between 2019 and 2024, also accused of disciplinary infractions.
After coming to power in 2012, Xi Jinping began an anti-corruption campaign in which several senior Chinese officials, both institutional and state-owned companies, were convicted of accepting million-dollar bribes. In recent months, this campaign has extended to sectors such as finance, tobacco, energy, sports and pharmaceuticals. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:04:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Economic growth accelerates to 8% in the third quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/crescimento-da-economia-acelera-para-8-no-terceiro-trimestre/</link><description>Macau's economy grew 8% year-on-year in the third quarter, 2.9 percentage points more than in the previous period. In relation to GDP, according to local authorities, the value reached 103.86 billion patacas between July and September.

The local economy grew 8% year-on-year in the third quarter, 2.9 percentage points more than in the previous period, after the first drop in two years.
Between July and September, Macau's Gross Domestic Product (GDP) reached 103.86 billion patacas, said the Statistics and Census Bureau (DSEC).
In a statement, DSEC highlighted the “continuous increase in service exports, driven by the notable increase in the number of visitors who benefited from both the high tourism season (summer holidays) and the sustainable development of the tourism branch of economic activity”.
The economic benefit of services – the majority of which come from tourism, the sector that dominates Macau's economy – rose 10.5%, with DSEC pointing to a 13.6% increase, to almost 10.5 million, in the number of visitors in the third quarter.
DSEC also mentioned the “maintenance of stability in private consumption expenditure in the local market”, which increased by 0.8% year-on-year. Government expenses in the region rose 2.7%. On the contrary, investment in infrastructure and equipment fell by 26.1%, “due to the decrease in the number of private and public construction works”, said DSEC.
In the third quarter, Macau's economy already represented 92.6% of the economic volume in the same period in 2019, before the start of the covid-19 pandemic.
Macau's economy had grown 5.1% in the second quarter, after shrinking 1.3% between January and March, the first drop in the territory's GDP since the end of 2022.
Mainland China – by far the main source of visitors to Macau – gradually began to lift all restrictions due to the Covid-19 pandemic precisely in mid-December 2022. Macau's economy ended last year rising 8.8%.
On April 10, the University of Macau (UM) revised downwards the forecast for the region's economic growth, in part due to the potential impact of tariffs imposed by the United States on the confidence of Chinese tourists.
The Macau Study Center and the UM Department of Economics predict that the territory's GDP will rise by 6.8% in 2025, 1.1 percentage points less than the previous forecast, made in January.
In early March, financial rating agency Fitch predicted that Macau's economic growth will slow to 6.9% this year, due to a “slower” recovery in tourism and gaming. “However, a sharp slowdown in the Chinese economy, such as substantial increases in US tariffs, and a strong devaluation of the yuan represent downside risks to Macau's prospects,” said Fitch. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:15:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Law providing for dismissal of civil servants disloyal to China comes into force</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/lei-que-preve-demissao-de-funcionarios-publicos-desleais-a-china-entra-em-vigor/</link><description>A law has now come into force that provides that public servants in Macau, including those of Portuguese nationality, can be dismissed if they carry out “acts contrary” to an oath of loyalty to China and the territory.
In a ceremony held on Saturday, 264 leaders of local public entities and services took an oath, declaring that “they will dedicate themselves with all loyalty to the Macau Special Administrative Region [SAR] of the People's Republic of China”.
In a speech given during the ceremony, the leader of the Government, Sam Hou Fai, asked civil service leaders to “firmly safeguard the full governance power of the Chinese Central Government”.
In December 2024, the assembly approved, unanimously and without any debate, the law that obliges both management and leadership staff as well as public administration workers to take an oath of defense of the Basic Law and loyalty to China upon taking office. A month earlier, when presenting the proposal, the then Executive Council spokesman, André Cheong, warned that public servants could be fired due to private conversations or comments published on social media.
The oath will be mandatory for all public servants, including Portuguese ones, but he added that they will be able to take it in Portuguese, one of Macau's two official languages, along with Chinese.
De acordo com o mais recente Relatório de Recursos Humanos da Administração Pública, em 2023 a região tinha 34.311 funcionários. O documento não refere quantos têm nacionalidade portuguesa, mencionando apenas que 257 nasceram em Portugal. Workers already in office will have 90 days to take the oath, and refusal automatically implies the annulment of the appointment to the position.
The two proposals also oblige public servants to take the oath in a “sincere and solemn” manner. The sincerity of the oath will be assessed by the hierarchical superior and any dismissal may be appealed to the courts.
On September 1, Sam Hou Fai sent a circular asking all civil servants to vote in the parliamentary elections as “a relevant demonstration of the defense of the Basic Law and loyalty to the Macao SAR”. But the president of the Macau electoral commission, Seng Ioi Man, guaranteed, five days later, that “the question of disciplinary responsibility” will not arise for public officials who did not vote in the September 14 elections.</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:11:33</pubDate></item><item><title>National Games torch passed through Macau on Sunday</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/tocha-dos-jogos-nacionais-passou-por-macau-no-domingo/</link><description>The 15th edition of the National Games will take place from the 9th to the 21st of November in Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau. Macau will host five sports in this edition of the National Games, namely table tennis (all groups), 3-a-side basketball (all groups), 5-a-side basketball (men's under-18s), volleyball (women's adults) and karate (all groups). To mark the start of the competition, the torch was transported in Macau on Sunday.
The route was about 2.6 kilometers. The match took place at the Government Headquarters at 9:30 am and was presided over by the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, the director of the Liaison Office of the Central People's Government in the Macao SAR, Zheng Xincong, the commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs in the Macao SAR, Liu Xianfa and the deputy commander of the Macau Garrison of the Chinese People's Liberation Army, Dai Jinsong. At the beginning of the ceremony, the flame protection guard entered the place with the lamp, then lit the ignition stick to light the flame stick and the pyre. The guard handed over the torch to the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, and then the torch was passed to the first relay, Li Yi, the wushu athlete and gold medalist at the Hangzhou 2023 Asian Games. The last of the 50 relays, Kuok Kin Hang, the karateka who won two silver medals at the 2023 Asian Games in Hangzhou, and the historic first medal for Macau at the 14th edition of the National Games in 2021, ran to the destination – Ruins of S. Paulo and lit the pyre.
Then, the flame protection guard escorted the flame back to the lantern at the closing ceremony, preparing for the flame joining ceremony, which took place in Guangdong at the Guangdong Olympic Sports Center. At the time, the flames from the four cities joined together into a single flame, which will be used to transport the torch and ignite the main pyre inside the venue during the opening ceremony of the 15th edition of the National Games.</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:10:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Well-being, employment and transport are the topics that most concern the population</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/bem-estar-emprego-e-transportes-sao-os-temas-que-mais-preocupam-a-populacao/</link><description>The Executive has been preparing the Governing Action Lines (LAG) for next year and, to this end, asked the population for opinions. Between September 17th and October 17th, authorities received more than 3,500 suggestions from the population. The majority, according to the Government, have to do with topics such as the well-being of the population, employment and labor issues and also transport.

The Executive is about to present the Lines of Government Action (LAG) for 2026. To this end, as is usual before preparing the report, the Government collected opinions from various sectors and the population from different social classes. This year, 3,548 opinions were collected, according to the Government, which guarantees that these suggestions will be analyzed when preparing the report.
This year's collection of opinions, which took place between September 17th and October 17th, was carried out through various channels, “in order to facilitate the active participation of the population”. The authorities detail that there were opinions presented in Chinese, Portuguese and English, “which reflects a broad participation of different communities”.
In a statement released on Friday night, the authorities reported that “the opinions and suggestions cover a diversity of areas, including the well-being of the population, the diversification of the economy, the reform of public administration and regional development”.
The first three areas with the most opinions presented are “well-being and services to the population”, with 28.1% of the total, then “employment and labor rights”, with 15.1%, and in third place transport, with 8.1%. There were also those who made suggestions on topics such as public administration, culture, education and sport. In the statement, the Government does not detail what type of opinions were presented.
The authorities specify that the three topics that most interest the population are “cash contributions”, “employment” and “transport issues other than public transport”, representing 7.1%, 6.94% and 5.46%, respectively.
Among the opinions, there were those who asked for support for the maintenance of financial contributions and the improvement of the allocation application process, an increase in the amount of the pension for the elderly and disability pension. In the field of employment, requests were made to adjust the number of non-local workers, guarantee employment for local residents and increase the minimum wage. In the area of ​​transport, it is suggested to promote electric vehicles, increase the number of park units and reinforce traffic control.
Furthermore, according to authorities, many opinions focused on issues such as the reform of public administration and the diversification of the economy, including increasing the efficiency of public administration, improving the organization and organic structure of public services and entities; and promoting the development of emerging industries and the implementation of industrial development plans, among other topics.
“This collection of opinions represents an interaction between the Government and the population, an important practice when working together to increase the efficiency of governance”, reads the Executive's statement, which adds that “the Government of the Macao SAR is analyzing in a comprehensive and global way the opinions and suggestions collected”, and “those that are viable and constructive will be integrated into the lines of government action for the financial year 2026, in order to effectively respond to the demands of the population and promote the continuous and healthy development of the Macao SAR in all aspects”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:17:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Rita Santos says the investigation was “a typical case of instrumentalization of justice”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/11/03/rita-santos-diz-que-investigacao-foi-caso-tipico-de-instrumentalizacao-da-justica/</link><description>Rita Santos was being investigated in Portugal after being the target of a complaint lodged by Socialist Party activists about alleged electoral irregularities carried out in the 2024 Portuguese legislative elections. In a statement sent to the newsroom on Friday, Rita Santos indicated that the Portuguese Public Prosecutor's Office had closed the criminal case filed against her. PONTO FINAL attempted to confirm the information with the Portuguese Public Prosecutor's Office, but received no response by press time.
The former counselor for the Portuguese communities states: “Throughout the entire process, I have always actively collaborated with the Portuguese authorities in discovering the material truth and, with that, in protecting my good name, honesty and unblemished character, supported by the trust that the Macanese community places in me, which I will never defraud”.
According to Rita Santos, the case was “based solely on speculation, defamation and character attacks”. A “typical case of instrumentalization of justice with political-partisan objectives, but which were not achieved”. “As expected, with the Public Prosecutor's Office carrying out a thorough investigation, finding that no illegality had been committed and concluded by the absence of criminal evidence, archiving is the logical corollary and would always be the only and fair solution to this 'non-prosecution'”, highlights Rita Santos in this press release.
Rita Santos ends by stating: “Values ​​such as respect for the law and the individual freedom of each citizen are non-negotiable for me and I will never give up on them, which is why I will never stop, as I have always done, being an active voice in defending democratic and humanist principles, and having an active civic participation in defending the interests of the Portuguese community in Macau”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-03 23:10:31</pubDate></item></channel></rss>