<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/governo-timorense-lanca-campanha-para-informar-populacao-sobre-nutricao/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Game with strong demand in early May</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/jogo-com-forte-procura-no-inicio-de-maio/</link><description>The game sector recorded a strong demand from the visitors who entered Macao last weekend, which included the Labor Day holiday. According to a Citigroup report, the performance of the casinos during this period was "chin to fall".
 
"The chin falls." This is how Citigroup described the search for Macao Casinos in the early days of May, which included the Labor Day holiday. A report by the banking institution, and quoted by the Portal Inside Asian Gaming, says players “remain in love with the game” and that “the current trade conflict between China and the United States seems to be discouraging players to enjoy game offers and not Macao players so far.
During this period of Labor Day, 170 thousand visitors per day entered Macao. In total, between May 1 and 5, more than 850 thousand visitors entered the territory.
Citigroup says that during this period, the premium mass segment bet a total of $ 27.2 million from Hong Kong, which is a record in this segment, drawing with last year's Golden Day of National Day. The bank institution also says that the average bet of "whales" - players who bet more than $ 100,000 at a time - was $ 281,000 from Hong Kong, plus 79% compared to the same period last year.
The number of premium mass players registered ascended to 949, an increase of 22% compared to May 2024. On the other hand, the average bet per player increased 26% compared to the same period to $ 28,654. Citigroup analysts explained that 63% of premium mass bets observed during this period of early May occurred in the premium mass rooms of US operators-MGM, Sands and Wynn-which, for the institution, shows that the current Sino-American trade conflict is not so far affecting players' preferences.
It is recalled that in April the casinos operating in Macao made a total of 18.8 billion patacas, ie 1.7% more than 18.5 billion April last year. According to data released by the Directorate of Inspection and Game Coordination (DICJ), in April there was a 4% break compared to March this year. Cumulatively, in the first four months of this year, casinos got gross revenues of about 76.5 billion patacas, more 0.8% than the 75.8 billion from the same period last year. Despite the annual growth, these amounts are still short of the government expected. In the budget for 2025, the authorities put the goal for all this year in the 240 billion Patacas, which would imply that, per month, casinos were an average of 20 billion patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:16:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Ipim and UTM collaborate in the sale of “Macao Quality Products” until May 8</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/ipim-e-utm-colaboram-na-venda-de-produtos-de-qualidade-de-macau-ate-8-de-maio/</link><description>The Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM) and the University of Tourism of Macau (UTM) inaugurated yesterday an exclusive session of exposure and sale of “Macao Ideas - Macao Quality Products”. The event runs from 11:00 to 19:00 until tomorrow, May 8, at the atrium of the Forward building of UTM.
For three consecutive days, IPIM and UTM propose to present 16 brands of Macau-manufactured and/or designed in the territory-to the university public, in an attempt to expand the Z Generation Z consumer market. Several students in Digital Marketing Sciences will be present at the event to facilitate the promotion of products with younger consumers, and gain experience with exhibitors. In all, there are patents more than 150 products from various companies from Macao Ideas, ranging from food and drinks to everyday articles.
According to a statement released yesterday by IPIM, several exhibitors stated that the first day of the session allowed a deeper understanding of generation Z public preferences, considering it “effective” in promoting Macau products with new customer segments. For their part, Digital Marketing Sciences Masters have recognized that the initiative “deepened their practical marketing management skills” and pledged to consider “priority” to Macao brands in future research projects.
Macao Ideas was established by IPIM for the purpose of promoting the designed and/or manufactured products in Macao. The joint IPIM and UTM session - the first collaboration between these institutions - succeeds a first exhibition and sale session already organized in February at the Grand Mart Department Store headquarters in Taipa. On this occasion, the event took place for eight consecutive days and made more than a hundred products of various categories available.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:19:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao construction company suspected Hong Kong fraud with counterfeit accounting</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/empresa-de-construcao-de-macau-suspeita-de-fraude-em-hong-kong-com-contabilidade-falsificada/</link><description>Catarina Chan
The Commissioner Against Corruption (CCAC) assisted Hong Kong authorities in resolving a case in which Macao construction company “Huarchi Global” will have paid $ 1.5 million from Hong Kong to four auditors and consultants from Hong Kong to falsify accounting reports, defrauding Hong Kong Exchange and Clearing Limited (HKEX) Admission to quote on the stock exchange.
 
A Macao building company will have filed a Hong Kong accounting group to falsify accounting reports in order to deceive the Hong Kong Exchanges and Clearing Limited (HKEX) to approve your request for quote on the stock exchange.
The situation was revealed yesterday by the Commissioner Against Corruption (CCAC), which advanced to have supported Hong Kong's Independent Corruption Commission (ICAC) in the case resolution.
According to the RAE authorities, the official, also resident of Macao, from the construction company “Huarchi Global Group Holdings Limited”, requested four auditors and consultants of “Wellink CPA”, the neighboring city's accounting company, the counterfeiting of accounts to fool HKEX. The local company falsely claimed that its accounting reports accurately reflected the financial situation of the construction company by showing the growth of its activity, causing HKEX to approve its request for quote to the Hong Kong's Main Board.
Macao's company later offered Hong Kong's $ 1.5 million to reward to the people involved so that they could subscribe to their actions in the first public offer of the construction company, according to CCAC.
CCAC indicated that in 2021 it made a joint action with the Hong Kong ICAC in the context of the construction company and the accounting company in Macao involved, as well as inquiring several people involved in the case.
Hong Kong's ICAC filed last Friday, a lawsuit promoting accusations against the auditors and consultants of the accounting company involved, among others, and the case continues to be investigated in Macau and Hong Kong.
Hong Kong authorities also indicated yesterday that the seven defendants, aged 36 to 50, including auditors and consultants and their families, were released under ICAC's security while awaiting their parties today at Eastern Magistrates' Courts.
According to ICAC, Huarchi Global hired Wellink CPA in October 2016 to be the accountant responsible for the preparation of the accounting report and, in October 2019, the request for admission to Huuchi Global quote was approved by HKEX.
In November of the same year, an opi and AFG Securities Limited was launched was one of the placement agents responsible for subscription to the actions. In this case, in addition to the accusation of falsification of accounting report, those involved also face the accusation of defrauding AFG Securities to attribute actions to place Global Huarchi to family members of auditors and consultants concerned. Later, in September 2023, Huarchi Global was withdrawn from the list.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:17:15</pubDate></item><item><title>AI ARE SHAKED 101 ANIMALS IN THE FIRST LARGE, LESS 42% than 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/iam-abateu-101-animais-no-primeiro-trimestre-menos-42-do-que-em-2024/</link><description>The number of animals slaughtered by the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) in the first quarter went from 175 from 2024 to 101. Although the trend of cats has been growing in recent years, the same does not happen to dogs: only 29 adoptions from January to March 2025, the lowest quarterly number of the last two years, at least.
 
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) slaughtered a total of 101 animals - 32 cats and 69 dogs - in the first quarter of 2025. These numbers represent a decrease of about 42% over the same period last year, in which 175 occasions were recorded. The data were released by AMI on its electronic page, which contains various statistical data from the DICV (Veterinary Inspection and Control Division) divided quarterly until 2023. Previously, the data retreated by 2015.
At the same time that the occasions diminished, the cases of adoption and animal complaints in the Coloane municipal kennel rose. Among the 131 animals adopted, there is a growing trend of felid adoption, with 102 cats adopted or claimed in the first three months of this year. In the same period of 2023, the number of cats adopted did not exceed 70, rising to 97 in 2024. In the opposite direction, the number of dogs adopted is constantly lower than that of cats and has even decreased in the last two years. Between January and March 2025, only 29 dogs were adopted or claimed - a number that had never been so low in any quarter of 2024 and 2023, according to the data provided by AMI.
The most optimistic numbers in the table refer to cases of animal returns, where owners return cats or dogs to care for the impossibility of breeding. In the first quarter of this year, the body only pointed out the return of a cat and a dog-numbers that contrast significantly with the 40 animals delivered in the same period as 2024 and the 26 of 2023. In relation to captured animals, there was a new decrease in relation to last year with a total of 268 animals collected from the streets, and four of these had microchip. In the homologous months of 2024 and 2023, the AMI captured 632 and 197 animals, respectively.
As for the accusations for infringement of the animal protection law, all three strands considered decreased in relation to the same quarter of last year. The first parameter refers to the abandonment of the animal (article 5 of the law), having registered a single offense. Regarding the animal ride in public spaces without the necessary documentation or means of transport, there were only two cases-half of those registered in the first quarter of 2024 and 28 than in 2023. The law also requires the acquisition of a license for dogs more than three months, which has been transgressed 14 times in the latest quarter. In total, 13,106 dog licenses were recorded until March.
According to the data released by the body, it is also possible to verify that there was a slight homologous reduction in cases of animals involved in aggressions, from 34 to 31. In 2023, however, the number was only 26. The most pronounced decrease concerns the introduction of microchips, with only 388 cases recorded in 2025. In addition to representing a dizzying decrease in relation to the homologous periods of 2024 and 2023 (667 and 554 cases, respectively), the number of microchips placed had never been so low in any of the quarters presented in the AI ​​data.
Sterilization surgeries were set at 289-number of 226 surgeries in the first quarter of 2024, albeit slightly less than 294 of 2023. There were also 1,704 anger vaccinations in the first three months of this year, a descent against 1,811 vaccines administered in the same period as 2024 and 2,934 in 2023.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:19:19</pubDate></item><item><title>China very concerned about Israel's plan to widen offensive in Gaza</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/china-muito-preocupada-com-plano-de-israel-de-alargar-ofensiva-em-gaza/</link><description>China expressed profound concern yesterday with the situation in the Gaza Strip and expressed its opposition to the plans announced by the Israeli government to expand military operation at the Palestinian enclave.
"China is deeply concerned about the current situation in Gaza and opposes the continuation of Israel's military operations in that region," Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian said yesterday during a press conference in Beijing.
Lin appealed to all parties to effectively implement the ceasefire agreements and resume “the right way” towards a political solution to the conflict.
Israel's Security Office approved in the early hours of Monday a new document that foresees, among other points, the permanent occupation of territories in the track, the forced displacement of the population to the south and a new system of humanitarian aid distribution, rejected by the UN and all humanitarian organizations present on the ground.
As part of its broader position, China defended last week before the International Court, that Israel "has no sovereignty" about the occupied territories and, therefore, cannot veto the work of organisms such as the United Nations Palestinian Refugee Assistance Agency (Unrwa), which he called the "spine column" of humanitarian aid in Gaza.
Beijing has insisted that the solution is due to the respect of international law, the end of collective punishment to the civilian population and the defense of the principle of the two states.
The Israeli attacks on Gaza have caused more than 52,200 dead in the year and a half of conflict triggered by Hamas attacks to Israel in October 2023.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:19:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Betis and Fiorentina fight for the final, Chelsea with open path</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/betis-e-fiorentina-lutam-pela-final-chelsea-com-caminho-aberto/</link><description>Betis and Fiorentina fight tomorrow in Florence for a place in the final of the Football Conference League, where is practically Chelsea, which should confirm the qualification in London.
Betis, who again featured William Carvalho in this final phase of season, travels to Italy with a 2-1 luggage, reached in the first leg in Seville, while Chelsea left Sweden with a Daredevil 4-1 before Djurgardens, who has already made history in Swedish football.
With everything apparently resolved between English and Scandinavians, the attention of the second hand of the semi-finals were mainly to Florence, with Fiorentina trying to recover from the disadvantage of a goal to reach the third final followed by the conference league and thus try to 'avenge' the defeats suffered in 2023 and 2024.
In addition to continuing to dream of a European title, which would be the second in its history, after the 1960/61 Cup Cup, the Italian emblem also in the Conference League the possibility of jumping to the Europa League next season, and continuing to have international evidence, as this scenario is very complicated (eighth classified).
In 2023, Fiorentina was defeated in the final by West Ham (2-1) and, in 2024, new discouragement before Olympiacos (1-0).
With William Carvalho back, who recently became the foreigner with more games for the club, Betis dreams of his first European title ever and, for that, seems to have the precious help of Brazilian international Antony at the end of the season.
The extreme, loaned by Manchester United in the second part of the season, and badly loved by Ruben Amorim in Red Devils, has been decisive in the first leg and has three goals in the last four games for the Andalusian emblem.
The Florence game promises to warm the conference league socks, while in London, Chelsea has a treadmill extended to the final and to make history in Wroclaw, Poland.
If you get the title on May 28, Chelsea, which has Portuguese international Pedro Neto, becomes the only club with Champions League, Europa League and conference on UEFA history.
This should really be the big goal of the blues at this stage of the race, besides, of course, a new trophy for the museum, as in the Premier League, they are in full struggle to return to the Champions League in 2025/26.
After becoming the first Swedish team to reach the semi-finals of a European race, Djurgarden will have nothing to prove in Stamford Bridge, just trying to reduce the difference in the final sum of the round.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:19:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau population increases in the first quarter due to non-resident workers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/populacao-de-macau-aumenta-no-primeiro-trimestre-devido-a-trabalhadores-nao-residentes/</link><description>According to information provided by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services, the population of Macao recorded an increase of 1,500 people in the first three months of the year, mainly due to the increase in the importation of non-resident labor. The number of births again came down in homologous terms, after a year of 2024 with the lower birth rate ever in the region.
 
Macau's total population increased to 687,900 people in the first quarter of 2025, plus 1,500 compared to the same month of 2024. The data were revealed yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), which justified the population increase with the number of non-resident workers domiciled in Macao.
The number of individuals from the interior of China who arrived in Macao with a unique safe conduct descended 41 in this first quarter, in annual terms, to the current 685. This decrease was, however, contained by 267 new residence authorizations in Macao, which now settled in 539. Compared to the previous quarter, compared to October, November and December 2024, the number of workers, the number of workers, the number of workers, the number of workers, the number of workers, the number of workers residentes estabelecidos na região subiu 826 e alcançou um total de 183.368 pessoas.
Analyzing the demographic data corresponding to the resident population of Macao, DSEC calculates a positive natural balance with 750-swimming and 637 deaths in the semester of reference. Still, the number of births is lower in annual and quarterly terms, with respective 106 and 237-nads reductions. Regarding the number of deaths, there were four less deaths than in the homologous quarter and 26 over the four trimester of 2024. Stratifying these numbers for the reason for the death, the three main causes of death in Macau are tumors (225 deaths in this quarter alone, representing 35.3% of the total); Circulatory device diseases (181 new cases, or 28.4%); and diseases of the respiratory tract (76 deaths, or 11.9% of the total).
According to DSEC data, 717 marriages were recorded in Macao in the first quarter, showing a decrease in both quarterly terms (less 156 marriages) and annual (minus 220). As for the distribution of the population by gender, statistics indicate that there are 369,600 women and 318,300 men in Macao. Translating these numbers into percentages, it appears that women represent 53.7% of the total population and men only 46.3%.
Statistical information released yesterday by the body allows you to conclude that labor imports is one of the main factors responsible for the population increase. In a broader data analysis, comprising the last decades, it is found that the birth rate in Macao has reached the peak in 2021, with 12.9%, and has been continually decreasing since 2014. In 2022, the lowest record of the last years reached the first time-which was again exceeded in 2024, with the registration of the lower birth rate in the region.
The early 1920s brought another milestone in the demographic analysis of Macau. In 2023, the slice for the elderly population exceeded the young population for the first time, after a gradual increase in the proportion of the elderly over the previous ten years. If, in 2014, only 8.4% of the territory population was considered elderly - that is, aged 65 or over - by the end of 2024 this percentage already corresponded to 14.6%. In the same period, the proportion of young people from zero at 14 was only 12.5%.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:18:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Manchester United and Tottenham on the way to a Made in England final</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/manchester-united-e-tottenham-a-caminho-de-uma-final-made-in-england/</link><description>Manchester United, trained by Portuguese Ruben Amorim, and Tottenham are preparing to ensure a 100% English European Football League final when they face Athletic Bilbau and Bodo/Glimt, respectively, in the second leg of the semi-finals.
 
The second European Club race is a real board of salvation for both clubs, sunk in subordinate positions in the English League, and the results of the first confrontation open excellent perspectives to both: Red Devils beat in Spain 3-0 and the Spurs imposed at home to Norwegian 3-1.
Portuguese international Bruno Fernandes was primarily responsible for the unexpected triumph in Bilbau -for the dimension he hit -scoring two goals, in the 37th minute, and at 45, after the Brazilian Casemiro opened the marker at 30.
The midfielder is one of the best markers of the race, with seven goals, equal to Danish Kasper Hogh (Bodo/Glimt) and Moroccan Ayoub Kaabi (Olympiacos), and it is in it that fans deposit the highest expectations for United to repeat the only title in the Europa League, reached in 2016/17, under the technical command of Portuguese José Mourinho.
For Athletic, the dream of erecting the first European title at home at San Mamés stadium on May 21 will have been smoky at 35 minutes from the first leg of the socks, when Dani Vivian was expelled to commit a penalty about Dane Rasmus Hojlund, paving the way to a seemingly irrecoverable defeat.
The conquest of the Europa League brings with it a valuable bonus, the presence in the next edition of Champions, and if for Athletic Bilbau this does not even seem relevant, since it occupies fourth place in the Spanish Championship, for Ruben Amorim's team is invaluable.
Manchester United has been experiencing the worst season since the creation of the Premier League, in which it occupies the 15th place, and the best one can aspire is to finish the championship in the 12th, far from the places of access to European competition and even more than the Champions League.
Tottenham is in an identical situation, plunged into the 16th position of the English League, only two above the release zone (but, like the 'Red Devils', with no possibility of falling there), and will only save the time with a third title in the race, reissue the successor in 1971/72 and 1983/84.
The first -hand triumph, with goals from Brennan Johnson, in the first minute, James Maddison, at 34, and Dominic Solanke, at 61, in a great penalty, leave the Spurs in a good position for the second clash with Bodo/Glimt, which he surrendered in the fight for the goal of Ulrik Saltnes at 83.
Tottenham will also be alerted to the opponent's performance, the first Norwegian team to reach this phase in a European race that defeated FC Porto (3-2) and Sporting Braga (2-1) in the new phase of Liga and eliminated Lazio, first classified in this mini-championship, in the quarterfinals.
If Manchester United and Tottenham meet in Bilbau, this is the third time that the title will be discussed between English teams (the first happened in the inaugural edition, in 1971/72, with the victory of the Spurs on Wolverhampton) and the 11th among clubs in the same country, one of which was exclusively Portuguese, in 2010/11, with triumph of FC Porto over Sporting Braga, by 1-0. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:19:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Leão and Carlotta dissertations Bruni intersect in Venice</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/dissertacoes-de-rui-leao-e-carlotta-bruni-cruzam-se-em-veneza/</link><description>Layering the City, a book that brings together the dissertations of doctoral dissertations by architects Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni, will be presented on Friday in Venice, under the Biennial. They are “two theses about the city and how architecture can work, intervene and qualify the city,” describes Rui Leão to the end.
 
Macao's architecture will be focused on the Venice Biennial, with the presentation of “Layering the City”, a book that dialogue the theses of doctorate of architects Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni. The work, edited by actar Books, will be presented at the Faculty of Architecture of the University of Venice on Friday at 9:30 am.
The book then contains two theses “about the city and how architecture can work, intervene and qualify the city”, crossing “two understandings of an expanded view of the architect as an urban agent”, describes Rui Leão to the end. The work is born of a reflection on the built work and the contribution of LBA Arquitetura and Planning, atelier founded by the authors, to the city, says the architect, adding: "It is a kind of dialogue between the two dissertations."
The theses were produced under the architects' doctorate by the Royal Melbourne Institute of Technology. Rui Leão's dissertation is titled “Designing by Increments: Opportunistic Planning as Urban Strategy for Macau”. The focus is on the use of projects for creating a directing plan for the “a little abandoned in terms of strategic vision” zone of Nam Van.
"There is this thing I call 'Design by Increments', which has to do with taking each project and inserting it into a plan logic that is in our head," he explains, stressing: "This was a huge contribution that our studio made to Macau that was creating a very important public space to a very important scale, clinging the landscape." Also, he says, that zone "was a road system and could be an abandonment zone." With the LBA project, it was created, in the South Zone of the Peninsula, “a public space on the large scale of the lake, with immense solutions to mediate the road system and pedestrian system”.
Carlotta Bruni calls on “Shaping Macau’s Unpurposed Space: Design in Context”. "It is about how the city lives a lot overdensified," and "spaces for people are very disregarded," Rui Leão begins, adding that "in fact, there is a lack of systematic space and planning policies are greatly sacrificed people's quality of life." “There is an institutional void to create quality of life through public space,” reiterates the architect. "We want to respond to a gap in terms of urban policies in Macao" and "use these projects as a vehicle to solve these situations," qualifying the projects and creating "precedents to try to influence policies in the future," he concludes.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>AFA presents SINO-FRANCES ARTISTIC DIALOGUE ON TIME AND MEMORY IN PARISIAN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/afa-apresenta-dialogo-artistico-sino-frances-sobre-tempo-e-memoria-no-parisian/</link><description>Art for All Society, in partnership with “Avant-Garde” Innovative Multimedia Art Association, presents “Déjà Vu”, the first exhibition of a series entitled “Mirroring, Looping, Generatting”. Integrated in the official program of the French May Art Festival, the show plunges into the phenomenon of “Déjà Vu” and its relationship with time, memory and perception in the digital age. Through the work of artists from Macao and France, the exhibition proposes an artistic dialogue that explores how technology shapes our understanding of reality and memory, questioning the nature of experience and the persistence of the past in the present. It has opening scheduled for May 14.
 
The renewal of art through new technologies brings sensations from an already lived past. In a imagined déjà-vu, this new show, the first of a series entitled “Mirroring, Looping, Generatting”, explores the complex relations between time, memory and perception through the prism of contemporary art. Organized by Art for All Society (AFA) in collaboration with “Avant-Garde” Innovative Multimedia Art Association, and with the support of the Macau Cultural Development Fund, the exhibition “Déjà Vu” brings together three artists, Alice Kok and Catherine Cheong, both from Macau, and the French Robert Cahen, for a Sino-Frank artistic dialogue that transcends borders transcend geographical and disciplinary.
The exhibition, which is part of the official program of the French May Arts Festival, opens on May 14, at 6.30 pm, at The Shopppes Parisian Macao, and proposes an immersion in video art installations, images generated by artificial intelligence and other multimedia creations, urging a deep reflection on the philosophical concept of “Déjà-Vu” and the impact of technology on contemporary reality. An extension of the event, the MasterClass "Video Postcars", with Robert Cahen and Alice Kok, will offer an opportunity to the public to explore the poetics of the moving image and its connection to the territory of Macao.
The exhibition, whose title evokes the theory of French philosopher Henri Bergson about the simultaneous perception of the present "real" and its "virtual" mirror in memory, is positioned as a meeting point between philosophy, art and technology. The three participating artists address this phenomenon through distinct visual and sound languages, but converging in their exploitation of the nature of reality and memory.
Robert Cahen, a prominent figure in the French video art, known for his temporal and spatial manipulation of the image, contributes works that challenge the linearity of perception, inviting the viewer to confront the fugality of the moment and his persistence as a mynic track. His approach, often described as a "poetics of ephemeral images", resonates with the essence of the "déjà vu", where the present moment seems to carry the weight of a previous experience.
Alice Kok, artist and curator of Macao, dialogues with Cahen's work and the central concept of the exhibition through her own artistic investigations, which often incorporate new technologies and address topics related to identity, collective memory and the urban and natural landscape of Macau. His artistic work, which extends from video art to installation and photography, demonstrates a particular sensitivity to the way personal and historical narratives intertwine with the lived space. The inclusion of Alice Kok in the exhibition reinforces the size of this Sino-Frante cultural exchange, offering a local perspective on the universal themes covered.
Catherine Cheong, another artist from Macao, completes the trio with an approach that integrates artificial intelligence in his artistic production. The use of algorithms to generate images and installations adds a contemporary and provocative layer to exhibition, questioning the role of technology in the creation and perception of reality. The concept of “generation” in the title of the exhibition series (“mirroring, looping, generating”) acquires literal meaning here, referring to the capacity of machines to produce new forms and contents, but also a figurative meaning, alluding to how memory and perception are constantly “generated” and reconstructed by the human mind and technological tools.
 
Words like conceptual axes
 
The keywords “mirror”, “circular” and “generate” function as conceptual axes that cross the exposure. "Mirror" suggests the idea of ​​reflection, both literal (the image reflected in a mirror or screen) as a metaphorical (memory as a mirror of the past, the present as a mirror of the future). “Circular” evokes repetition, the cycle, the return - intrinsic characteristics to the phenomenon of the “déjà vu”, where the present experience seems to be “in loop” ”with a previous memory. In the context of video art and digital technologies, “loop” is also a formal technique, a way to build narratives and visual rhythms. “Generating”, as mentioned, refers to creation, whether human or artificial, and to the way reality and memory are continuous processes of “generation”.
Extra activity, the MasterClass "Video Postcars", conducted by Robert Cahen and Alice Kok, offers a learning and creation opportunity. In inviting participants to explore Coloane's landscape and transform it into “memory postcards” through video techniques, Masterclass establishes a direct connection between theory and practice, between philosophical reflection and sensory experience. Coloane's choice, with its mix of nature and history, is particularly significant, as it invites meditation on time and space, how places carry memories and how art can capture and reinterpret these memories.
The inclusion of the exhibition in the official program of the French May Arts Festival underlines its importance in the context of cultural exchange between China and France. Visual arts function here as a vehicle for dialogue and mutual understanding, exploring universal themes that resonate in different cultures. The continuation of the series of exhibitions in Paris in August 2025 reinforces this exchange dynamics and allows a wider audience to have access to artistic reflection on time, memory and technology.
“Déjà vu” propose as an immersive experience that addresses the perception of reality, reflected in the constant passage of time and the cyclic memory of the human being. Artists Robert Cahen, Alice Kok, and Catherine Cheong invite the public to explore a universe where the present and the past are confused, where reality and virtuality interconnect, and where technology acts as a possible tool to investigate the depths of human consciousness, leaving open a perspective on current issues in the digital age and their connection with the human experience, the way of an inevitable future.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>China confirms survey of sanctions against MEPs</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/china-confirma-levantamento-de-sancoes-contra-eurodeputados/</link><description>Beijing confirmed yesterday that he agreed with the European Parliament for the total and simultaneous survey of sanctions imposed due to disputes on human rights violations, at a time of rapprochement, given Washington's aggressiveness.
 
"After consultations, China and the European Parliament decided to raise simultaneously and complete the restrictions on mutual exchanges," Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian said.
Confirmation comes days after the European Parliament announced that China raised the sanctions imposed four years ago to five MEPs and parliamentary committees - a measure that has since blocked official contact between the legislative agencies.
Lin noted that exchanges have been conditioned in recent years for "known reasons" and stressed that, in the current context, both parties consider that reinforcing cooperation between China and the European Union "is of great importance." "We trust that, with the full resuming of legislative exchanges, both parties deepen communication and mutual understanding," said the spokesman.
The European Parliament had already considered, last week, the survey of sanctions as a step towards the normalization of parliamentary dialogue, although it has warned that it will continue to be aware of the persistent challenges in the bilateral relationship.
As the institution then explained, China began to express interest in restoring contact in September 2024 and, after several meetings held during the fall, decided this year to remove the restrictions that affected MEPS and commissions.
Beijing imposed sanctions after the European Union adopted measures against some Chinese entities due to alleged human rights violations of the Chinese ethnic minority of Muslim origin Uigur in Xinjiang, in the far northwest of China. The European Parliament then refused to ratify the Global Investment Agreement UE-China, which would have deepened commercial ties between the two parties.
However, Donald Trump's return to the power in the United States seems to be both sides reconing the antagonistic positions of the American leader in the face of the transatlantic alliance and the trade war against the rest of the world.
Among those aimed at the sanctions is the German Reinhard Bütikofer (Green Group/European Free Alliance), former leader of the European Parliament delegation for relations with China, who however abandoned the position of MEP. Already Michael Gahler (Germany), Miriam Lexmann (Slovakia), Raphaël Glucksmann (France) and Ilhan Kyuchyuk (Bulgaria) continue in the European Parliament and were also targeted by the sanctions.
In addition to the MEPs, China sanctioned two EU committees, three national deputies, the Think Tank) Mercator Institute for China Studies, the Alliance of Democracies Foundation and two academics.
 
China ready to receive Ursula von der Leyen and António Costa
 
China is ready to receive the president of the European Commission and the president of the European Council, before a summit between Beijing and the European Union (EU), a source of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs said yesterday. "European Council President António Costa and European Commission Chairman Von Der Leyen are welcome to China for a new series of Sino-European meetings," Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian said at a press conference.
China and EU will maintain “high-level dialogues in strategic, economic, ecological and digital domains,” the spokesman added. Lin Jian did not specify when European leaders will be able to visit China.
In April, a European Council spokesman announced that the next summit between Brussels and Beijing would be held in China in July. The summit arises at a time when Beijing seeks to strengthen relations with the European bloc, in the context of a commercial conflict with Washington.
Last week, China described its ties with the EU as a "precious stability" for the world economy. Despite profound differences with Beijing on commercial issues and human rights, the European bloc seeks to diversify its business partners over the growing US unpredictability. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:19:20</pubDate></item><item><title>IC launches 3,000 copies of the new edition of its periodic publication “The Books and the City”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/ic-lanca-3-000-exemplares-da-nova-edicao-da-sua-publicacao-periodica-os-livros-e-a-cidade/</link><description>The Public Library of the Cultural Institute (IC) was launched the 39th edition of its periodic publication, “The Books and the City”. This edition, accessible to the public for free, has as its central theme the convergence between “reading and sport”, a meeting point explored by guest specialists. These professionals analyzed how reading and sport complement each other and presented practical suggestions with the aim of promoting healthy habits with the resident population.
For this edition, 3,000 copies were made available for distribution. Interested parties can raise their copy at various points of Macao, namely in all libraries under IC, higher education institutions, TAP Seac Gallery, in various bookstores and different cultural and artistic spaces. Additionally, the digital version of the publication is accessible for consultation on the Electronic Site of the Public Library of the IC.
The content of the 39th edition of “The Books and the City” is diverse, offering a panoply of perspectives on the main theme and other relevant subjects. The “Library Manual” section offers clarification on the legal deposit regime in Macao, contributing to a greater understanding of local cultural conservation mechanisms. The “reading landscape” shares joint reading experiences within the “Baby and Children Reading Program”, inspiring the promotion of family reading. The chapter “Speaks The Author” invites to discover the creative process behind Macau's illustrated book of Cognitive Psychology, “The Butterfly That Wasn´t Painted Gold”, allowing readers to access the author's view of the conception of the work. Finally, the "New Launches" section features a selection of recent publications, complemented by ten reviews of concise and insightful books, written in Chinese, Portuguese and English, aimed at guiding and inspiring readers into their literary choices.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>XI asks the Union to “unilateral intimidation” and reinforcement of partnership</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/xi-pede-a-ue-uniao-contra-intimidacao-unilateral-e-reforco-de-parceria/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping said yesterday that China and the European Union should “oppose unilateral harassment” on the occasion of the 50th anniversary of the establishment of diplomatic relations, which coincides with commercial tensions with the United States. Xi stressed that the relationship between China and the EU is “one of the most influential bilateral relations in the world” and framed this bond in a global scenario marked by uncertainty. "Humanity is again in a historic crossroads," said the Chinese leader, who highlighted the role of bilateral cooperation as an international reference model. "A healthy and stable relationship between China and the EU not only benefits both parties, but enlightens the path of the world," he said. XI said it attributed great importance to the development of Brussels relations and expressed his desire to work with the president of the European Council, António Costa, and the president of the European Commission, Ursula Von de Leyen, to “deepen strategic communication, expand mutual opening and properly manage friction and disagreement”.
The message, released yesterday, also included a response from European leaders, who highlighted the evolution of the bilateral relationship and expressed their willingness to “face shared challenges together and promote peace, safety and sustainable development,” said Chinese diplomacy. XI's appeal comes at a time when Beijing seeks to reinforce cooperation with Brussels to the growing pressure that is being targeted by Washington. China has repeatedly criticized the economic measures imposed by the United States - such as customs tariffs or technological restrictions - and has appealed to the EU to maintain an independent policy based on multilateralism and mutual benefit. Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang also exchanged messages with Costa and Von der Leyen, reaffirming Beijing's commitment to a "stable, constructive and mutual benefit" relationship. The celebration of the anniversary also coincided with the announcement of the full resuming of the legislative dialogue between Beijing and the European Parliament, after the mutual survey of the restrictions imposed in 2021. The Chinese Foreign Ministry reaffirmed yesterday that cooperation with the EU “weighs more than competition”, at a time when both parties seek to preserve a common agenda with the United States.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:19:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Almost crowded hotels in the golden week</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/hoteis-quase-lotados-na-semana-dourada/</link><description>During the Golden Week of May, the first five days of the month, the hotel occupancy rate reached almost 100%, Helena de Senna Fernandes, director of tourism services (STD) yesterday. At the opening ceremony of Global Gaming Expo Asia (G2E Asia) and Asian Ir Expo, the official also said that the occupancy rate of the first quarter of this year was about 90%, representing a return to 2019 levels.
In a statement released yesterday afternoon, STD details that the average occupancy rate of hotel establishments reached 94.1%, but the maximum occupancy rate reached 98.1% on May 2.
At the inauguration of events at Venetian, Helena de Senna Fernandes also mentioned, cited by Macau radio in Chinese language, that there were about 47,000 hotel rooms in the first quarter of this year, with some resorts reducing the number of rooms, renewing them in larger rooms, while some new hotels are under construction and should make more rooms available in the future. The STD director also indicated that the industry has reflected the need for more hotels that do not cover high prices, and authorities are flexible regulations in this regard in the hope that licensing can be compatible with, for example, youth inns, small inns, etc.
The ruler also added that the Macao Tourism Industry is recovering healthily, with 9.86 million arrivals from visitors registered in the first quarter. South Korean visitors climbed to fourth place in the table of tourists' source, recovering to 65% of the same period of 2019, while the Philippines and Indonesia registered more visitors than in the same period of 2019.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:19:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Credit limit approved by banks to SMEs shrunk 39%</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/limite-de-credito-aprovado-pelos-bancos-as-pme-encolheu-39/</link><description>Last year, the limit of credit approved to small and medium -sized companies by local banks continued to retreat due to “poor demand for credit,” said the monetary authority of Macao. The amount approved limit decreased 39%, in annual terms, to 7.7 billion patacas, which was also the lowest value since 2009. According to the body's report, the balance of unpaid loans reached the highest level in history with 6.2%.
 
In 2024, there was a marked decrease of 39% in the amount of new and medium-sized Small Business Credit by Macao Banks to 7.7 billion Patacas, the lowest annual amount since the monetary authority of Macau (AMCM), started in 2009. The body justified that the continued breach of the approved credit limit is due to the “fragile demand. credit ”in the market.
According to a report on SME credit statistics, released in the Macao da AMCM Monetary Study Bulletin, in the first half of 2024, the approved credit limit fell 28.8% in semester terms to 4.4 billion patacas, while the respective calculation was 3.3 billion of patacas, 25.9% than six months ago.
AMCM also analyzed the use of SME loans, and the “business expansion” represented the highest purpose for credit, with its weight rising from 36.1% in 2023 to 64.1% in 2024, with 4.9 billion of approved value-value patacas.
Already the percentage of the "Operation Fund" fell 24.9 percentage points to 16.2%. In addition, the use of loan for “new projects” and “newly created companies” accounted for 15.9% and 0.8% respectively.
Regarding the sectoral distribution of the loans granted to the SMEs, the report said that, by the end of 2024, loans to the “construction” sector reached 32.1 billion patacas, which corresponds to the largest serving of 40.9%of the total loans. The sector “Trade by Grosso and the Retail” and that of “Restoration, Hospitality and Similar Activities”, which represent 13.9% and 6.9%, respectively, of the total value of loans granted by banks.
The analysis also pointed out that the balance of loans to the “Transport, Storage and Communications” sector and “restaurants, hotels and similar activities” increased by 39.6% and 4.4%, respectively, compared to the previous year. Already the balance of loans to “Grosso Trade and Retail”, “Transforming Industry” and “Construction” decreased 15.9%, 10.6%and 7.3%, respectively.
 
“Weak credibility” of SMEs was the biggest reason for rejection of loans
 
AMCM, in this document, also conducted an inquiry to know what are the reasons for not accepting SME credit claims by local banks, so as to “evaluate the difficulty of SMEs in gaining access to financial support from banks”.
Among the various reasons for the rejection of credit requests, the “weak credibility” of the SMEs dominated the list, given that 38.2% of banks inquired prioritize credibility assessment and consider the element “very important” in the decision to grant loan. The “unsatisfactory” business performance took second place and 26.5% of banks evaluated this factor as “very important”. On the contrary, more than half of banks inquired have denied taking into account the “high operating cost in granting SME loans” during credit assessment and approval.
"On the other hand, the quality of SME loans recorded a deterioration, as the unpaid debt ratio increased during the year," AMCM said.
The body indicated that the amount of unpaid loans, that is, loans to SME won more than three months ago, raised 4.9 billion patacas by the end of 2024, more 67% of a year. Thus, the unpaid debt ratio rose to 6.2% at the end of last year, beating the historic record.
It should be noted that SME loans with delay of 3 to 6 months, 6 to 12 months and more than 12 months ascended to 582.4 million patacas, 1.2 billion patacas and 3.1 billion patacas, respectively. These three diminals and expired credit represented, respectively, 12.0%, 25.0% and 63.1% of the total expired SME credit in Macao.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:19:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Travel in China increases 6.4% during May holidays</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/viagens-na-china-aumentam-64-durante-feriados-de-maio/</link><description>China recorded about 314 million domestic trips during the extended weekend of International Workers Day (May 1), a homologous growth of 6.4%, according to data released yesterday.
Tourist expenses also increased this year, the Ministry of Culture and Tourism said, reaching 180.3 billion Yuan, an increase of 8%compared to the previous year.
Authorities had already foreseen an increase in tourist activity during vacation from May 1-5, with reservations pointing to a preference for long -range travel within the country.
The Asian country registered about 10.89 million entry and exit trips during the holiday, an increase of 28.7% over the same period of 2024, according to the National Immigration Administration.
The Tourism sector, one of the most affected by Covid-19 pandemic and covid zero policy, which has closed the Asian country's borders for three years, is one of the great hopes of the Chinese government to boost consumption and strengthen sectors such as restoration, transport and retail trade.
In March, the government released an action plan with guidance to ensure a favorable environment for consumption, for which it designed proposals such as the protection of labor rights in terms of rest and vacation, the improvement of commercial infrastructures and the reduction of consumer restrictions.
According to official data, the world's second largest economy has completed the 5% growth goal in 2024, but analysts continue to point out problems such as weak internal and international demand, trade war, insufficient stimuli, a prolonged real estate crisis and lack of confidence from consumers and private sector.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:19:15</pubDate></item><item><title>China sends guard of honor to participate in the Victory Day parades in Moscow</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/china-envia-guarda-de-honra-para-participar-nos-desfiles-do-dia-da-vitoria-em-moscovo/</link><description>The China army will send a guard of honor to the Victory Day parades in Moscow, where Chinese President Xi Jinping should attend the Russian homologist Vladimir Putin in Red Square.
 
The China Ministry of Defense announced on Monday that it will send a guard of honor to participate in the military parades in the capitals of Russia and Belarus, to mark the 80th anniversary of the defeat of Germany Nazi, which is celebrated this Friday.
Beijing sent Moscow Honor Guards to a Victory Day commemorative parade in 2015, but this will be the first time a Chinese guard of honor will participate in a similar event in Minsk.
According to Chinese analysts, the gesture aims to demonstrate support for the International Order of Post World War, which Beijing considers to be under threat.
Videos released on Chinese social networks showed the rehearsals of Chinese soldiers in Minsk and Moscow last week.
As part of the preparations for the Moscow Parade, Chinese soldiers rehearsed the “Guerrilla Song” in Red Square on Sunday, described the Global Times, the Chinese Communist Party's official newspaper. The patriotic song describes the difficulties faced by Chinese soldiers during the Japanese invasion.
Official News Agency Xinhua said this year is important to China and Russia, as well as “all those who love peace around the world,” as it also marks the 80th anniversary of the end of the invasion of Japan in China.
Xinhua added that China and Russia will "defend written history with blood and lives, and oppose any attempt or behavior that seeks to deny, distort or falsify the history of World War II."
Beijing had already announced that Xi will visit Russia between Wednesday and Saturday, and will maintain a “strategic dialogue” with Putin.
The visit occurs at a time when the trade war began by then -US President Donald Trump pressures the international commercial system and weakens the transatlantic partnership - an alliance that Beijing and Moscow has long considered a dominant force to be counterbalanced in the international system.
Cited by the local press, Zhao Long, deputy director of the Institute for Strategic Studies and International Security of the Institute of International Shanghai Studies, said that one of the main reasons for this year's celebration is that “some countries are trying to distort the history and postwar order” through unilateral sanctions and tariff wars.
The celebration also reflects the growing political confidence between Beijing and Minsk, as the two countries have reinforced cooperation in areas such as trade and security in recent years.
China sent a guard of honor to participate in the Annual Independence Day Parade of Belarus in 2018, but did not for the country's victory day parade in 2015.
China also sent a guard of honor to the city of Ho Chi Minh, for the first time last week to mark the 50th anniversary of the end of the Vietname War (1955–1975).
Zhao stated that China's participation in military parades abroad is probably aimed at supporting a "correct view of postwar history and international equity and justice." Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:19:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Timorese government launches campaign to inform population about nutrition</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/07/governo-timorense-lanca-campanha-para-informar-populacao-sobre-nutricao/</link><description>The government of Timor-Leste launched a campaign yesterday to raise awareness of the Timorese to the importance of consuming nutritious, varied and safe foods and having healthy eating practices.
 
The campaign will be held in the first week of each month until the end of the term of the current government, which ends in 2028. "Nutrition is an essential part of human development, starting from conception, through pregnancy, childhood, adolescence, adulthood to old age, being all target moments for effective nutritional interventions," said the minister of health, Élia dos Reis Amaral.
The minister was speaking during the official launch of the National Nutrition Campaign in Dili, at a ceremony that was also attended by Deputy Prime Minister, Mariano Assanami Sabino, and Deputy Minister of State Administration, Jacinto Rigoberto Gomes.
According to data released by the government, 47% of children under the age of five suffers from chronic bad nutrition, 8.6% acute malnutrition, 32% have a weight below and deficiencies of vitamin A, iron and iodine.
The Timorese authorities presented, in March, a multiserial nutrition action plan, which aims to reduce the delay in child growth to 25% by 2030 focusing on newborns and children up to 23 months and women of reproductive age.
The minister said that Timor-Leste faces malnutrition problems, such as weight deficit, extreme thinness and short stature caused by nutritional deficiencies, but also warned of the growth of obesity cases and associated diseases such as hypertension, diabetes, cardiovascular disease and cancer. "Nutrition is the basis of a healthy nation. Nutrition is not just about eating - it is also the knowledge to choose nutritious foods to ensure the proper amount and quality necessary for good health and a promising future," Élia dos Amaral explained. "Without good nutrition, our children can't grow, our students can't learn, our workers can't be productive and our elderly people can't live with vitality," she added.
The National Nutrition Week aims to inform fathers and mothers, teachers, students, community and religious leaders on the importance of consuming nutritious, varied and safe foods, promoting breastfeeding and healthy food practices, avoiding processed foods, excessive sugar and salt. "I hope the National Nutrition Week, celebrated monthly, bring key messages to the whole country, to schools and families, through the distribution of printed and video communication materials," said the minister.
Deputy Prime Minister Mariano Assanami Sabino recognized the importance of this monthly campaign as a way of raising awareness and promotion of healthy nutritional practices for children, young people and the entire population. "We have a strong commitment to nutrition. Investing in our children is investing in the future. We reap what we sow and eat what we produce. It is the local foods that will give us healthier bodies," said Assanami. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:19:47</pubDate></item></channel></rss>