<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/espera-se-assembleia-com-muitos-mais-leais-apos-desqualificacao-de-candidatos/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>China warns “Risks for National Security” arising from the use of AI</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/china-alerta-para-riscos-para-a-seguranca-nacional-decorrentes-da-utilizacao-da-ia/</link><description>The Chinese State Ministry of Security warned yesterday with the risks associated with the misuse of Artificial Intelligence (AI), warning that technology can threaten social stability, sensitive data protection and national security.
In a statement issued on the Wechat social network, the ministry recognized AI benefits for economic and social development, but stressed that its inappropriate use can facilitate disinformation and other harmful activities.
Chinese authorities have mentioned that AI systems capable of generating manipulated content - combining deep learning algorithms with counterfeit images, sounds or videos - can be used by foreign entities to “instigate agitation” between the Chinese population.
Although ultra -realistic content generation techniques have legitimate applications in the film, advertising or video game industries, the ministry has warned that its unlawful use can violate individual rights and be used to "confuse public opinion."
The statement also points out that AI Generative Systems are able to collect, store and even disseminate sensitive personal data, which could be used by foreign intelligence services to perform “subversion, infiltration and sabotage activities” in China. Another point of concern is the ideological bias algorithms, which can serve to spread “biased ideologies”.
The Ministry of Security urged the population to reinforce their ability to “distinguish the truth” from information and reiterated the need to ensure that AI use respects the principles established by the authorities.
Since 2023, China imposes regulations on artificial intelligence services, forcing these platforms to respect the “fundamental socialist values” and prohibiting the generation of content that undermines national security, territorial unit and social stability.
Despite the rapid growth of the AI industry in the country, with chatbots developed by companies such as Alibaba, Deepseek, Tencent or Bytedance, doubts about the application and effectiveness of these technologies in an environment strongly controlled by state censorship.
The State Ministry of Security often uses the official account on the Wechat platform to disclose espionage cases and appeal to citizens' surveillance, encouraging them to be suspicious of suspicious job offers, especially from abroad, and avoid sharing confidential information 'online'.
In 2023, the ministry appealed to the mobilization of the whole society to “prevent and combat espionage” and announced measures to “reinforce national defense” against “foreign intelligence activities”. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 00:22:50</pubDate></item><item><title>China against possible scale of the Taiwanese leader in the US “under any pretext”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/china-contra-possivel-escala-do-lider-taiwanes-nos-eua-sob-qualquer-pretexto/</link><description>Beijing manifested “firm opposition” to a possible scale of Taiwanese leader William Lai in the United States during his visit to Paraguay in August. According to the Chinese authorities, such a gesture may aggravate the tensions with Beijing.

China manifested yesterday “firm opposition” to a possible scale of Taiwanese leader William Lai in the United States during his visit to Paraguay in August, warning that such a gesture could aggravate the tensions with Beijing.
"We are firmly opposed to any official exchange between the United States and the Chinese region of Taiwan, as well as William Lai's passage through the US, under any pretext," said Chinese Chinese Cabinet spokesman for Chinese Council of State (Executive), Chen Binhua at a press conference.
Chen appealed to Washington to "manage the issue of Taiwan with extreme caution" and to avoid "sending wrong signs to the separatist forces seeking independence of the island." "Trusting in the United States to achieve independence is useless and condemned to failure," added the spokesman, referring to the Taiwanese head of state, labeled by the Chinese authorities as "independentist" and "provocative."
On Monday, the president of Paraguay, Santiago Peña, announced that William Lai will visit the country within 30 days, in which it will be its first trip to South America since taking office in January 2024.
Lai visited Paraguay in August 2023, when he was the number two of the Taiwan government, scales in New York and San Francisco. At the time, China responded with military maneuvers around the island.
Taiwan government spokeswoman Karen Kuo said on Tuesday that "there is still no information" about a possible LAI scale in US territory. "As on previous occasions, any confirmed plan will be announced timely," he said in response to the local press.
According to the Taiwanese press, William Lai's itinerary could include stops in New York and Dallas (Texas), as well as visits to Guatemala and Belize, Taipei's diplomatic allies in Central America and Caribbean. Lai has already made scales in the US Territories of Guam and Hawaii at the end of last year, during a southern Pacific tour. After this trip, China performed one of the biggest naval exercises in recent decades.
The United States, the leading arms supplier to Taiwan, maintain a policy of strategic ambiguity: they do not have formal diplomatic relations with Taipé, but may intervene in their defense in case of conflict with China.

Taiwan admits mutual concessions in dialogue with Washington

The head of the Taiwanese foreign folder said yesterday that negotiations between Taiwan and the United States to reach a trade agreement before 1 August remain underway and involve a process of “mutual concessions”. According to statements quoted by CNA news agency, Chen Ming-Chi warned that "no conjectures can be made" on the fares that will be applied to Taiwan after the completion of the conversations, adding that details about purchases to US companies "are still being discussed between both parties."
The ruler pointed out that acquisition proposals "include delicate processing processes", stressing that the "sincerity of Taiwan is fully present." Yen Huai-Shing, deputy chief of the Taipe negotiating team, indicated that “the goal is to achieve consensus before 1 August,” a date set by US President Donald Trump as a deadline for closing new commercial agreements. Yen also assured that Taiwan's "red line" is the defense "of national interests, food safety and public health." Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 00:18:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Air India will resume part of the international routes after flight accident AI171</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/air-india-vai-retomar-parte-das-rotas-internacionais-apos-acidente-do-voo-ai171/</link><description>The airline Air India announced the partial resuming of the suspended international routes after the AI171 flight accident, which left 260 dead. The company foresees restarting part of the international calls from 1 August, with the aim of completely restoring its network until October 1.

Air India airline announced the partial resuming of the international routes suspended after the AI171 flight accident, which left 260 dead in June, falling seconds after taking off from Ahmedabad's Indian city.
Air India has announced "the partial replacement of the reduced times under its 'security break', adopted after the tragic AI171 accident on June 12, 2025," the carrier said in a statement released on Tuesday night.
The company foresees restarting part of the international calls from 1 August, with the aim of completely restoring its network until October 1.
The changes include the operation of three weekly flights between Ahmedabad and London-Heathrow airport, between August 1 and September 30, replacing the previous five connections to Gatwick-the route where the accident occurred.
During this break, the company carried out additional inspections to its 787 Boeing Airplanes and adjusted operations compared to the closing of airspace over Pakistan and the Middle East.
The accident involved a Boeing 787 Dreamliner to London, which lost power shortly after offspring in Ahmedabad and drew it, causing the death of 241 out of 242 people on board, plus 19 victims on land. Following the disaster, Air India has reduced several international routes, including frequencies for Europe, the United States and Pacific Asia.
In an internal note addressed to employees on Monday, the company's executive president, Campbell Wilson, called on to caution and rejection of “premature conclusions”, ensuring that the initial investigation “confirms that there were no problems with fuel, maintenance or technical or mechanical failures”.
The message helped calm strategic markets and partners such as Boeing, whose actions rose after the preliminary report, which did not point to conception defects.
According to the Air Accident Investigation Authority (AAIB), all mandatory maintenance were up to date, although it was identified that Air India did not perform recommended inspections in 2018 by the US Aviation Agency (FAA) to the fuel cutting mechanism - a system that will have failed after decay.
The company's mother company, the Tata Conglomerate, is trying to contain reputational damage while the official investigation is due, whose final report is expected within one year. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 00:15:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Detainee owner of a restaurant that burned 26 Filipino countrymen with false employment</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/detida-proprietaria-de-restaurante-que-burlou-26-conterraneos-filipinos-com-emprego-falso/</link><description>The Judicial Police stopped a woman, of Filipine nationality, on suspicion of a burla against 26 countrymen, having ease 500,000 from the injured person under the pretext of recruitment at his Japanese restaurant in Macao. According to the investigation, the suspicion charged each between 14,000 and 22,000 patacas for expenses for 'BlueCard' requests, but then ceased to be contactable by the workers.
 
After having 26 Philippine countrymen, a total of 500,000 patacas, through a false employment scheme, the owner of a Japanese restaurant was arrested by the police authorities.
The details of the case were released yesterday by the Judicial Police (PJ). According to the newspaper or Mun, according to the police investigation, the suspect, a 50 -year -old Filippine resident of nationality operating a Japanese restaurant in the area of Avenida de Horta and Costa, began in October last year to publish social networking platforms ads of employee "recruitment" for food establishment.
In the announcements, he claimed while he could assist in the procedure for requesting a non -resident worker identification.
After contacting those interested, the businesswoman required each person to pay her, from an advance, between 14,000 and 22,000 patacas, who served as "process expenses" for 'BlueCard'. The woman also made a commitment to complete all formalities for the importation of non-resident workers within two months.
PJ reported that the victims trusted the proposal and paid the cash expenses, as requested by the suspect, and the suspect passed them in paper.
However, after receiving the money, the woman failed to update the process of 'BlueCard' requests, using “several excuses to delay the process,” the PJ found and when the victims asked for a refund, the restaurant owner refused and ended up completely contactable, the authorities said.

Denunciated Exploration at Work
 
The 26 injured were Philippine, young and middle-aged citizens, corresponding to 11 men and 15 women. Some of the victims filed a complaint with the Public Security Police Corps, in the direction of services for labor affairs, in the prosecutor and even in the consulate of the Philippines. The PJ also admitted to having received complaints about this case since mid -month.
The case of a false employment scheme was also reported to TDM Canal Macao by some of the victims, and the All About Macau press, by the progressive union of domestic workers in Macao.
According to reports, the victims spent months without receiving salary and worked many times for more than 12 hours a day. In addition to being forced to pay to secure the job, they failed to recover the amount after leaving office. Some said they had started working at the restaurant in March this year, while some had not even started work even after paying the "expenses" required by the owner.
During a press conference held yesterday, the PJ confirmed that the restaurant in question did not have any quota of foreign employees beyond those being used, and that there is no record that the suspicion has helped to request the victims 'Bluecard' in this case.
After the detention, the PJ seized in possession of the suspicion a receipt notebook. The detainee admitted the practice of burla and confessed that the money had been used for the restaurant's daily expenses, refusing to reveal more details.</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 00:57:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Fourth Tropical Storm of the Year will arrive this weekend Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/quarta-tempestade-tropical-do-ano-podera-chegar-este-fim-de-semana-a-macau/</link><description>The Pacific Ocean is watching the formation of a tropical storm that is expected to affect the Southern Sea of China during the weekend, although Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) warn of difficulties in the forecast of the trajectory. Until Saturday, at least, the region remains on orange alert due to high temperatures that may exceed 36 degrees Celsius.
 
The Directorate of Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) warned of the “high” probability of formation of a tropical storm in northwestern Pacific Ocean, which is expected to enter the southern sea during the weekend.
According to information published yesterday on the SMG page, a “tropical disturbance” is currently developing in northwestern Pacific that, “over the next two or three days”, should approach the island of Luzon, in the Philippines, and acquire the Statute of Tropical Storm. According to official forecasts, the phenomenon is expected to enter the northern part of the Southern Sea of China during the weekend.
The trajectory of the potential cyclone is still uncertain, according to the SMG. The most recent forecasts indicate that the storm is expected to follow "a trajectory of 'Xi Deng', playing land on the west coast of Guangdong, with the possibility of passing closer to the south of the river of the Pearls between Sunday and Monday." According to this forecast, rain and wind will intensify “significantly” in Macau early next week, while the risk of flooding in low zones increases.
Still, SMG denounce the existence of “uncertain factors” that make it difficult for an exact forecast of the trajectory, such as a possible “change in the real location of storm formation” and the possibility that “its development in intensity” is affected after reaching the island of Luzon.
The body ensures that it will continue to “closely follow the evolution of the state of time”, appealing to the population to “pay attention to the latest weather information” and adopt “contingency measures as soon as possible”.
If it is realized, this will be the fourth tropical storm to affect Macau since the beginning of the typhoons in June. The first, called Wutip, forced Macau authorities to maintain the warning signs for 105 and a half hours - the fourth largest period ever - in mid -June. In the same month, Macao was affected by a tropical storm “that had no name”, as confirmed by SMG spokeswoman Vera Varela, in statements to the end. The Danas Cyclone emerged more recently, in the second week of July, accompanied by sweeteners and thunderstorms.

Orange alert due to intense heat

The territory of Macao has been on orange alert since yesterday, due to the “intense heat” that will be felt in the region until at least Saturday.
The SMG explain that “due to the continuous influence of an anticyclone at high altitude and the gradual influence of peripheral subsidence of a tropical cyclone,” the wind in Macao will be “weak”. On the other hand, thermometers may reach or even exceed 36 degrees Celsius. During this period, “grade periods” and “thunderstorms” are expected.
While the orange warning is in force, SMG advises the population to drink more water and avoid staying outdoors for long periods, paying special attention to obese, elderly or fragile health. On Monday, while the region was still on a yellow alert, health services had already advised the population to adopt preventive measures against hyperthermia.</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 00:59:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Convicted of Old Chinese Old Corruption of Tibet</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/condenado-por-corrupcao-antigo-responsavel-chines-do-tibete/</link><description>The former head of the Tibet Autonomous Region in southwest China was sentenced yesterday to the death penalty suspended for accepting 343 million Yuans in bribes, a court said. A suspended death penalty is generally switched in life imprisonment if the convict does not commit a new crime during the suspension period of two years in this case. The condemned politician, Wu Yingjie, held from 2016 to 2021 the position of Secretary of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP, in power) to the autonomous region of Tibet, of which he was the main political responsible. Wu accepted bribes in the total amount of more than 343 million Yuans, said the People's Intermediate Court of Beijing, in a statement published on the Chinese Wechat social network. These crimes were “extreme gravity”, of “particularly harmful” social impact and “severely harmed” the interests of the state and the people, considered the court.
Since taking power just over 10 years ago, Chinese President Xi Jinping has made the fight against corruption a priority at all levels of the state and the CCP. Defenders of this campaign claim that it promotes healthy governance. Opponents consider that it also allows XI to move political rivals. The court indicated that Wu Yingjie has used several official functions since 2006 to favor companies and individuals, offering help in obtaining contracts or facilitating economic activities. The former official benefited from a two -year suspension of the execution of the death penalty, after being guilty, actively cooperated with the authorities and returned much of the illegally acquired money, the court needed.
The Chinese army assumed the control of the territory in the Himalayas in 1951, independent for four decades, following the end of the Chinese imperial regime. The Tibetan government and the spiritual leader of the Tibetans, the 14th Dalai-Lama, fled in 1959 and exiled in India. Since then, China has said it has invested greatly to modernize the region, increase the lifestyle and ensure religious freedom.</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 00:21:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Access to Higher Education in Timor-Leste will be controlled by the government by 2035</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/acesso-ao-ensino-superior-em-timor-leste-vai-ser-controlado-pelo-governo-ate-2035/</link><description>The government of Timor-Leste approved yesterday, to the Council of Ministers, the rules of access and entry into higher education in the country, which will be controlled by the authorities until 2035, then being managed by university establishments.
According to the statement of the Council of Ministers, the diploma defines the legal regime with the “establishment of common rules for the procedures of application, selection and placement of students”. "The measure applies to all students who have completed secondary education and who want to enter public or private higher education institutions, with uniform criteria for the admission of new students," read the statement.
In addition to the general access regime, the diploma also creates special regimes directed to specific groups, namely people with special needs, families in vulnerable situations, over 23 years old and Timorese citizens who have completed secondary education abroad.
The diploma also provides for the possibility of courses to require specific prerequisites and defines tiebreaker criteria, appeal mechanism for candidates and the creation of a higher education coordinating commission, which will organize the entire process, “during a transitional period of 10 years [2025-2035] the management of the public higher education process will be ensured by the government. They will be able to organize their own entry processes, ”adds the statement. More than 40,000 students attend Timor-Leste 18 public and private higher education institutions.
In April, the Timorese Government decided to suspend the opening of new higher education courses in areas where there is a lot of offer and end unauthorized doctoral courses, with the objective of preventing the saturation of the labor market and to promote a better suitability between the educational offer and the needs of the country.
The areas affected by the suspension included the law or science courses of law, management, accounting, financial management, public management, civil engineering, computer engineering, civil construction, public health, nursing, midwife, public administration, political science and international relations.</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 00:12:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Health services seize 1,008 illegal cigarette packaging in Zape</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/servicos-de-saude-apreendem-1-008-embalagens-de-cigarros-ilegais-no-zape/</link><description>Authorities registered a suspected case of illegal sale of tobacco products in a convenience store in Zape, which resulted in the seizure of 1,008 cigarette packaging.
After receiving a complaint, the Office for prevention and control of smoking and alcoholism of health services and customs services performed an inspection at the store in question on July 14. Inside, more than a thousand cigarette packaging (totaling 20,160 units) whose labels were not in accordance with the Macao law were detected.
According to the health services, in addition to the seized packaging do not comply with “the labeling required by Law No. 5/2011 (Smoking Prevention and Control Regime) and approved by administrative regulation”, the owners of the convenience store were unable to present their respective import documents. If the illegality situation is confirmed, the objects will be “destroyed” and the establishment may be fined in a amount up to 200 thousand patacas.
In a statement, authorities stress that "the Macao Law rigorously regulates the circulation of tobacco products" appeals to traders to "not risk luck or challenge the law, otherwise they are severely punished."</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 00:46:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Government provides “significant increase in the recycling rate” of organic waste</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/governo-preve-aumento-significativo-da-taxa-de-reciclagem-de-residuos-organicos/</link><description>The Organic Waste Recovery Center that will be built by Airport Avenue in Cotai will allow “a significant increase in the recycling rate of this type of waste,” said the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA), in response to a written interplies of SI Ka Lon.
Authorities say that, “with the gradual resuming of socio-economic activities after the pandemic, the amount of macao urban solid waste has returned to pre-pandemic levels” and, according to data from recent years, a “slight variation in the proportion of various waste types”, with organic compounds to represent about 30% to 40% of the total.
DSPA also said it has already been in charge of a professional institution to start a study on solid waste management measures to “review and analyze the respective sources and the current situation of management measures”. "Based on the experiences of the interior of China with regard to the construction of 'cities without waste', solid waste management measures appropriate to the reality of Macau will be prepared," said the body.
According to the Macao State Report of 2024, this year there was an increase in the amount of urban solid waste, building materials, flying ash and abandoned vehicles. Last year, the amount of urban solid waste produced in Macao reached 526,000 tons, representing a 5.1% increase over 2023, and the amount of per capita solid waste also increased by 4% and reached 2.1 kg per day, both of which is similar to those of 2019. Solids included organic waste, 32.3%, paper/card, 24.3%, and plastic waste, 24%.</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 00:48:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese Foreign Minister praises increasingly multipolar world</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/ministro-dos-negocios-estrangeiros-chines-enaltece-mundo-cada-vez-mais-multipolar/</link><description>China's Foreign Minister Wang Yi greeted the advance of a "multipolar world" and the "deepening of globalization" at a time of international "turbulence". During the head meeting of the member countries of the Shanghai Cooperation Organization (OCX), held in the Chinese city of Tianjin, Wang appealed to “greater consensus” among OCX Member States in the face of “advancement of protectionism” and the intensification of “regional conflicts”, according to a statement issued by Chinese diplomacy. Chinese minister warned of a “complex and severe” international security context, marked by the “constant emergence of new threats and challenges”. Wang also condemned the recent Israeli attacks against Iran - a member country of OCX - which he classified as a “violation of sovereignty” Iranian.
In an appeal to the “good neighborhood” among members of the organization, Wang Yi recalled that OCX includes countries with tense relations such as India and Pakistan, which in May exchanged air attacks, causing dozens of dead.
 China's Foreign Minister Wang Yi yesterday assured his Iranian counterpart, Araqchi Abás, that Beijing will continue to support Tehran in defense of his "national sovereignty and dignity." The meeting took place yesterday in the Chinese town of Tianjin, on the sidelines of the meeting of Foreign Ministers of the Shanghai Cooperation Organization (OCX), according to a statement issued by Chinese diplomacy. "China and they will have diplomatic relations for over half a century, having resisted international vicissitudes with stable and healthy development," said Wang Yi, adding that, as an integral strategic partner, China "will continue to support Iran in defense of their rights and interests through dialogue."
Chinese diplomacy head has also expressed availability to “deepen mutual trust, reinforce cooperation, expand exchanges, and promote stable and long -term development” of bilateral relations. Araqchí thanked Beijing's “valuable support”, stressing that “Iran's willingness to develop relations with China is even firmer”. "The integral strategic partnership between Iran and China has great potential and wide perspectives," added the Iranian Minister. On the nuclear issue, Araqchí reiterated that Iran "does not develop nuclear weapons," but also "does not resign its legitimate right to peaceful use of nuclear energy." "We are willing to resume negotiations and consultations with all parties as soon as possible, provided there is mutual respect, with a view to a political solution," he said. Wang Yi reiterated that China "opposes the use of strength or threat of use of force" and argued that "differences must be resolved through dialogue and consultation."</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 00:16:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Number of international visitors rose 15% in the first half</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/numero-de-visitantes-internacionais-subiu-15-no-primeiro-semestre/</link><description>The first six months of the year were marked by the growth of the slice of international visitors, according to data released by the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD). Considering the total number of entrances to Macau in the first half, it is found that the sector has already been able to recover 95% of visitors from the same period of 2019.
 
In the first half of the year, 1.34 million international visitors entered Macao, an increase of about 15% over the same period of the past. The three main markets of international tourists were South Korea, the Philippines and Indonesia.
According to information provided in the day before yesterday by the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), between January and June this year, Macau was able to recover about 95% of the visitors market prior to the pandemic. In total, there were 19,223 million tourists-national and international-who arrived in Macau in the first half of 2025. In the same period of 2019, it is recalled, the number was 20.28 million.
The survey of the most recent data took place under the first 2025 plenary meeting of the Council for Tourism Development, chaired by the Secretary for Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP. According to a STD statement, the meeting was intended to present the work developed throughout the first half and those to be implemented in the second half of the year, as well as to streamline an exchange of opinions and suggestions among sector experts.
Speaking at the time, Tai Kin IP has ensured that the government will “increase the investment of resources and vigorously optimize the industrial structure, (…) actively launching policies and measures” aimed at promoting the development of the sector and the economic diversification of the region. The investment in the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin is essential for the fulfillment of these objectives, says the ruler, as is the role of “infallible link” that Macao plays between China and Portuguese -speaking countries.
At the same meeting, STD presented the latest data in the Macao tourist industry and recalled the promotional efforts it is preparing to attract more international visitors. Among the tourist campaigns scheduled for the second half of this year are initiatives to take place in Portugal, Indonesia and Malaysia and an international event with popular digital influencers on the Asian continent.
Concomitantly, the city of Macao will host theme events centered on different areas, in order to attract a varied audience. In addition to the International Gastronomy Cities Festival, since the 11th, there are also activities such as the 33rd Macao International Fire Competition, the Macao International Light Festival and the 50th National Congress of the Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies.
Another of the topics under discussion at the meeting was the development of the second phase of review and study of the General Plan for the Development of the Macao Tourism Industry, whose implementation will take place in the second half. STD has presented proposals for review and action lines on “six important topics”: the promotion of diversified development of tourism and leisure sectors, the exploitation of diverse tourist markets, the deepening of regional tourism integration, “healthy, orderly and resilient” growth of tourist industry, the conception and planning of tourist products and the innovation of tourism with the use of artificial intelligence.
STD also reveals that the elements present at the meeting presented opinions and suggestions on various topics, such as the appreciation of the outer port area, the night economy and the holding of more international events. This department says that government representatives "seriously listened" to interventions, "drinking from collective wisdom to jointly promote the diversification and sustainable development of the Macao tourist industry."</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 01:02:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Health services advise extra care during summer trips</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/servicos-de-saude-aconselham-cuidados-redobrados-durante-viagens-de-verao/</link><description>Health services appeal to residents planning to travel on summer holidays to adopt measures against communicable diseases, recommending consultation with the epidemiological situation of the destination site and extra attention to personal and food hygiene.
Authorities draw particular attention to the measles epidemic, which has been increasing all over the world - including geographically close countries to Macao, such as Vietname and Philippines. Vaccination, the most effective method of prevention and reduction of disease transmission, should be completed at least two weeks in advance and are particularly recommended to minors and adults born after 1970.
The peak risk of dengue fever transionic propagation happens during the summer, so travelers should also minimize the risk of mosquito bites when wearing long -sleeved clothes and applying insect repellents to exposed parts of the body. It is recalled that this year's first dengue fever case in Macao was registered on the first Saturday of the month, on July 5, and the authorities have highlighted that the risk of local propagation through imported cases is “very high”.
Maintaining good personal hygiene habits is another of the suggestions for health services, which remember the importance of often washing hands with soap and water and covering your mouth and nose in case of cough or sneezing. Care is also recommended to choose restaurants in order to reduce the risk of diarrhea or gastrointestinal diseases.
Authorities also appeal to a safe distance from birds or wild animals. In case of bites or scratches, wounds should be treated as speed as possible to reduce the risk of infection.
Any suspicious symptoms that emerge during or after travel, such as fever, chills, rash, cough, diarrhea or vomiting, should be immediately reported to a doctor.</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 00:43:05</pubDate></item><item><title>MGM clarifies that it is solved legal case involving Jacky Heung</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/mgm-esclarece-que-esta-resolvido-caso-legal-que-envolvia-jacky-heung/</link><description>After news that MGM China had filed a judicial action against the Hong Kong Jacky Heung actor due to a $ 1.4 million debt that had not been paid allegedly, the game operator issued a statement to clarify that the situation is resolved. MGM says the loan was a credit guarantee Heung provided to third parties, noting that all payments have already been made and legal proceedings have been closed.

MGM China clarified yesterday that the legal case involving Hong Kong Jacky Heung actor was resolved. Macau's game operator said that what was concerned was a credit guarantee Heung provided to third parties.
"Due to the non-payment of delay debts, MGM China later started common legal procedures to resolve the issues related," reads the press release released by the operator, in which he adds that "recently, all payments were fully settled and the corresponding legal proceedings were closed."
The concessionaire pointed out that, although not its usual practice, this time decided to respond to the rumors circulating due to the "inconvenient and inconvenience that this incident caused Jacky Heung Cho."
According to the news circulating in the neighboring region, the public figure faced a judicial action by MGM China Holdings after allegedly did not comply with the payment of a substantial loan contracted in one of the group's casinos in Macao. Hong Kong news said MGM China presented the action at the Hong Kong District Court, requiring a $ 1.4 million reimbursement from Hong Kong.
Hong Kong's press said Heung would have contracted a two million dollar loan from Hong Kong on December 1, 2024, trading the amount for play cards with a commitment to reimburse the loan on the same day. According to the news, MGM China claimed that, despite partial reimbursements, the balance continued largely for paying and, after accounted for partial reimbursements, Heung was still $ 1.4 million from Hong Kong and the applicant asked for the reimbursement of the debt capital, along with interest rates at an annual rate of 18%, from the time the loan was granted to payment to payment until payment full.
In addition to actor, Jacky Heung is also a martial arts enthusiast with over 30 years of career. Heung is also the eldest son of Charles Heung, president of China Star Entertainment, an important film producer and real estate investment company quoted on the Hong Kong stock exchange.</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 00:50:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Seac Van Seac Reservoir will have capacity up to 780 thousand cubic meters</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/reservatorio-de-seac-pai-van-tera-capacidade-ate-780-mil-metros-cubicos/</link><description>The government launched a public tender for the SEAC Pai Van reservoir expansion contract in Coloane, which aims to increase the total capacity of the 300,000 cubic meter to about 780,000 cubic meters.
According to the Directorate of Public Works Services (DSOP), the project aims to “reinforce the safety of water supply in Macau, raise the storage capacity of freshwater resources and the response capacity of the water supply system in emergency situations”.
The body said that the work is also one of the important projects provided for in the Decenate Disasters Prevention and Reduction Plan in Macao (2019-2028).
The project includes the construction of vertical walls on the west and southern reservoir sides and the reservoir bottom. In order to increase reservoir impermeability and reduce its water losses, a waterproof barrier will also be built inside the reservoir.
DSOP added that a pumping station will be built to transport water from the reservoir to the Pai Van Seac Van Water Treatment Plant. This pumping station will be equipped with three pumps, including two current use and one reserve, and its joint water extraction capacity is about 1,170 liters/second when both pumps are working simultaneously.
In addition to the expansion of the reservoir, the scope of the contract also covers the construction of the leisure zone south and west of the reservoir, the extension of the green zone, the bike path and the jogging track on the east and north sides of the reservoir.
As expected, after the respective extension, the bike path around the reservoir will have a total length of about 1,415 meters, while the play track will have a total length of about 1,160 meters.
In response to the government's policy of promoting the use of clean energy, a photovoltaic solar energy system will be installed on the reservoir surface, which will occupy approximately 10% of the reservoir area, DSOP said. Already the electricity produced of this system will be provided to the Seac Pai Van Water Treatment Station, which is adjacent to it, in order to “achieve the objective of environmental protection and energy savings,” he said.
The maximum period of the execution of the work posted to the competition is 655 working days, according to DSOP, and the deadline for presentation of a proposal for the public tender, which does not provide base price, will be on the 18th of next month.</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 00:45:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Society according to the creation of a new type of hospitals in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/sociedade-de-acordo-com-a-criacao-de-novo-tipo-de-hospitais-em-macau/</link><description>The final report of the public consultation of the new law on the activity of private institutions providing health care was released. The results indicate that society “agrees, in general,” with the creation of a new type of day hospital license, hoping to increase resident medical treatment options, relieving the pressure of existing hospitals and helping the development of the sector.

Health services reveal that all sectors of society “have generally agreed with the legislative review that provides for the creation of the Hospital de Day, a new category of the private institution providing health care classified between hospitals and medical clinics.
The final report of the public consultation was released last Tuesday. According to the document, “most opinions are in favor” of creating a new type of license for the day hospital, in addition to hospitals and clinics in Macao.
It is considered that the measure "contributes to increasing the development space of the private health market and increasing the options of medical treatment of residents and tourists", while some opinions consider that "the creation of hospitals can alleviate the pressure of waiting time in the hospital and reasonably guide the health care needs of residents," according to the document.
According to health services, public consultation on the “legal regime for the exercise of activity of private health care institutions” was held between April and May. For a period of 30 days, 892 opinions or suggestions were received, of which 33.8% were submitted by associations and medical institutions; 31.6% of civic associations, commercial sector, integrated tourism and leisure companies; 21% of residents and academic institutions; and 13.6% came from health professionals.
The report points out that, according to the opinions received, the creation of the Hospital de Day will contribute to the promotion of the development of the 'Big Health' industry.
In addition, some opinions have considered that Macau should take advantage of their geographical position and focus on the development of medical services such as aesthetic medicine, health management, stem cell therapy, “in order to attract more international tourists and raise Macao's essential skills as a regional health tourism destination”.
It is recalled that the government, by creating a new type of day hospital license, plans to expand some differentiated health care services, which are currently merely being performed in hospitals. Authorities had explained that the future creation of the Day Hospital enables treatments with a shorter duration and without hospitalization in its facilities, including state -of -the -art aesthetic medicine services, medically assisted procreation, among others.

Concerns
 
In the report, there are also some concerns about the emergence of a new type of medical institution. "Currently, clinics are facing many restrictions on the development of medical specialties, and the creation of day hospitals will further affect the survival space of clinics, leading to health professionals, affecting the balanced development of the health system," read the opinions of some clinics.
In this case, the clinics propose that the government clarifies that day hospitals should have as its main recipients tourists, avoiding unfair competition with clinics.
In contrast, the government ensures the healthy development of medical institutions, indicating that the regime will clarify the position of hospitals, hospitals and clinics. It reiterated that the contents and recipients of the services provided by these three parts are “different”.
"The Hospital de Day develops part of the specialty services that should be provided in hospitals, which not only does not affect the existing primary health care market, but, on the contrary, can provide opportunities for professional updating and the transformation of clinic services, further broadening the development space of the private health market," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 01:00:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Alberto Wong's list requires explanations about disqualification and asks for reversal of the decision</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/lista-de-alberto-wong-exige-explicacoes-sobre-a-desqualificacao-e-pede-reversao-da-decisao/</link><description>The Popular Liveliod Force list in Macao, which authorities considered to be insufficiently patriotic to participate in the elections of September 14, sent a letter to the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) to ask the decision to be reversed. The head-by-head, Alberto Wong, reaffirmed that the elements of his group defend the basic law and are faithful to masters.

Those responsible for the Liveliod Popular Strength list in Macao, which was disqualified on Tuesday of the September 14 elections, yesterday were to the Legislative Assembly Electoral Affairs Commission (Caeal) to deliver a letter asking the authorities to go back to the decision and also to return the 25,000 patacas of security they had to pay.
It is recalled that CAEAL, at the appointment of the State Security Defense Commission, has decided to rule out the six elements from the list of elections because they are not sufficiently patriotic, according to the authorities' standards. The same happened with the power of the synergy, whose leader is Deputy Ron Lam. In total, 12 candidates were prevented from going to votes. Caeal did not explain what facts led to the disqualification of these two lists.
In the missive that was delivered yesterday to Caeal, the group says that, despite the evaluation made by the State Security Defense Commission, always defended the basic law of the MSAR and “faithfully” fulfilled the obligation to be loyal to MSAR. "There was no circumstances in which we have not defended or we have not been loyal," the letter stresses.
Stressing that the elements that make up the list have never violated any of the seven criteria imposed by the authorities so that the candidates can enter the race, such as the defense of the constitutional order and the respect for sovereignty, security and national development, the group led by Alberto Wong points out that it has actively participated in social affairs ”, disclosed“ positive comments ”and demonstrated“ love to Macau and the country through practical actions ”.
The electoral law that came into force last year stipulates that disqualified candidates cannot appeal the decision. However, the force of popular Liveliod in Macau recalls the principle of the “right of the parties to be informed of the reasons”, provided for in the Administrative Procedure Code, and asks for explanations to the State Security Defense Commission on which “specific factual and logical factual basis” of the decision.
"This is not only our basic right to understand the reasons for our disqualification, but it also helps us better understand the correspondence between our actions and legal requirements, allowing us to better serve Macao society in the future," says the list, "even if the committee's opinion is binding, he should not deprive us of the right to expose the facts and express our position." "This is a basic requirement for the legitimacy of administrative procedures and an important manifestation of the protection of citizens' legal rights and interests," he says.
To refute the accusation that they are not patriotic, the group points out that it has participated in government initiatives, promoted trade with the interior of China and Myanmar and also participated in the annually national security exhibition, “seriously studying the importance of national security, understanding that the safeguard of national security is the cornerstone of stability and long -term development of Macao”.
"We sincerely ask the commission to fully consider our appeal, make a prudent study and give a reasonable response to our determination of eligibility in conjunction with the above evidence, and to protect our legal rights and the basic rights of citizens," he says.</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 01:04:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Assembly is expected with “many more loyal” after disqualification of candidates</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/17/espera-se-assembleia-com-muitos-mais-leais-apos-desqualificacao-de-candidatos/</link><description>Political commentator Sonny Lo said yesterday that with the disqualification of 12 candidates for deputies in Macao, for lack of patriotism, an assembly with “many more loyal than opponents” is foreseen in the future.

The disqualification of 12 deputies, announced on Tuesday by the Macao Electoral Commission, "means deputies have to be more politically correct and there are many more loyal than opponents," said Sonny Lo Shiu-Hing. "Changes to deputies' rules and regulations seem to point out in this direction," he added.
Sonny Lo refers to the approval, a week ago, in the Legislative Assembly (al) of amendments to the laws of the Deputies Statute and the normative of the parliamentary regiment, which, in fundamental, reinforce the powers of the President of the Assembly and plasmam in the two articulated the fundamental principle of the “Macau ruled by patriots” and the State Security Defense Law.
The Macao Electoral Commission said on Tuesday that the State Security Defense Commission (CDSE) excluded, for lack of patriotism, two lists candidates for the elections for AL. The chairman of the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) explained that 12 candidates from both lists "do not defend the Basic Law and are faithful to the Special Administrative Region of Macao of the Popular Republic of China." Exclusion covers six candidates from the Liveliod Popular Strength list in Macao, led by social worker Alberto Wong, who first competed in AL. The other list is the power of the synergy, led by the current deputy Ron Lam, who, in the last elections, in 2021, had been the seventh most voted, with 8,764 votes.
Seng Ioi Man has ensured that the binding opinions of the CDSE, of which it is not possible to appeal, "have a clear and sufficient legal foundation" and have been elaborated "taking into account the facts." However, the judge refused to reveal the facts that led to exclusion, arguing that "the works and documents of the State Security Defense Commission are confidential."
Its dissemination "may represent certain risks to national security, and should not even be published its content," he added. "We don't really know the reasons, because the electoral law and the National Security Act include a number of possible reasons," Sonny Lo told Lusa.
Former pro-democracy deputy NG Kuok Cheong said the disqualification "is a national secret" and that, "according to CDSE, to comment on a national secret is to publicize a national secret." "A new system was created in Macau, that is, CDSE has made the decision and its statute is to be respected at all ... They want to disclose information so that everyone knows that the decision does not depend on anyone else, just the subjective decision of the CDSE," said NG, one of the candidates disqualified in the 2021 legislatives.

Portuguese “saved” Coutinho

The former deputy of Macau Au Kam San said, also yesterday, that disqualifying moderate candidates shows intention to bet on pro-peak deputies and that Deputy José Pereira Coutinho was spared due to a possible political impact. Au Kam San, also disqualified in 2021, said that this year, deputies were left out that "could be considered dissidents in the political spectrum" and "often criticized the government in a forceful way." However, according to Au, those who have been disqualified now "are basically" outsider "from the pro-seystem field and can not even be described as dissidents."
About the acceptance of the candidacy of the list of Portuguese deputy José Pereira Coutinho, usually critical voice in AL, Au Kam San indicated that it earned his identity. "According to the current rules, Coutinho would also be disqualified, but he represents the Portuguese community and the political impact would not be good, so they did not move him away," he said.
Shortly after the announcement of the Electoral Commission, CDSE stressed in a statement that when a candidate is excluded for lack of patriotism, all other candidates from the same line are also removed. At the same time, the government demonstrated, in another statement, "strong support" to the decision of the CDSE, which described as "a correct measure for the full implementation of the fundamental principle" Macau ruled by patriots ".
In 2021 it was the Electoral Commission to exclude five lists and 21 candidates-15 of which pro-democracy. With the decision released on Tuesday, they will run for elections, scheduled for September 14, six lists by direct suffrage, eight less than four years ago.
 
Newspaper or world reiterates that Caeal's decision is “legal and grounded”

The newspaper or Mun has published an opinion article reiterating that Caeal's decision is “legal and grounded”, and that the opinion of the CDSe “is undeniable”. The article states that the Government and the Central Government's connection office in the MSAR “expressed their unanimous support to the decisions made, according to the Law, by the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly, fully implementing the principle of Macao ruled by patriots”, also showing “zero tolerance” in relation to those who do not defend the Macao Basic Law or are not faithful to the field. "The deputies of the Legislative Assembly, while important members of the Government team of MSAR, must be convinced patriots," may be read in the article. The publication also recalls that the version of the electoral law for the AL was revised in 2024, "creating unpublished institutional provisions to establish a security valve for the mashed regime", which "allow the entry of genuinely firm patriots and prevent" false patriots "access to al who can have" subversive intentions against China and Macao destabilizers. " Regarding the opinion of the CDSe, the article states that the decisions made by Caeal "have absolute authority and cannot be contested." The article concludes by stressing that, in the current world, “marked by turmoil and intensifying competition between great powers, it is imperative to face the uncertainties of the internal and external environment with the stability of national development and macao”, showing their support to both Caeal decisions and CDSE opinions.</description><pubDate>2025-07-17 00:56:20</pubDate></item></channel></rss>