<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/ponto-fatal-2025-03-31/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Portuguese government replaced financial support to EPM after 11 years, says Rangel</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/governo-portugues-repos-apoio-financeiro-a-epm-apos-11-anos-diz-rangel/</link><description>Foreign Minister Paulo Rangel announced that the government has increased financial support to the Portuguese School of Macau (EPM), returning to the legally expected level after 11 years of cuts.
 
“We just replaced the Portuguese contribution to the Portuguese School of Macao, which (…) had suffered a huge cut,” Rangel said on his visit to Macau.
The Portuguese State has the majority (51%) of the capital of the Foundation of the EPM, but since 2014 that Lisbon only contributed to 10% of the school's expenses, a decision taken under the Portuguese Financial Rescue Program.
EPM financing “is now at legal levels again and is the first time after 11 years,” Rangel announced, at a reception to the Portuguese community in Macao, and after a visit to school. Shortly thereafter, the chief of Portuguese diplomacy told reporters that "there was no reason, honestly, to have this cut and he remained." "We have increased five times this value [of EPM financing], so this is something that is highly significant of the commitment we have," said Rangel. "There are governments that really give importance to Macau and China and there are others who do not give, this is something that has to be said," lamented the minister, pointing his finger at the previous PS executive.
The replacement of financing “is undoubtedly an important help” for EPM, which Rangel described as having a key role for Portugal in Macau. "We also have pleased (…) that there have never been so much Portuguese students - and now I speak of students from the Chinese community - as there are today in multiple schools," added the leader. "It means that also the special administrative region [of Macau] has encouraged Portuguese teaching and knowledge of Portuguese, and this is something that can only bring good relations between the two sides," added Rangel.
Foreign Minister also assured that authorities want to solve the problems that caused the strike in Portuguese schools abroad, but admitted to being limited to being a management government.
Teachers in the Portuguese schools of Timor-Leste, Mozambique, Angola and Sao Tome and Principe end in recent days a two-day strike for the “equity of work conditions between teachers”. "I honestly can only say that our desire to solve the problems is total, so let's work for it," said the head of Portuguese diplomacy, after a visit to the Portuguese Macao school.
However, Rangel admitted that the government is limited to having only management powers, given the dissolution of the Assembly of the Republic, on March 20: "This is obviously also an embarrassment we have at this stage."
The minister confirmed that "there are really questions to resolve" in Portuguese schools abroad, but stressed that some of the problems "are structural and come from far behind." Rangel argued that the government was able to "anticipate ... The resolution of some problems in several schools", but added that "it is not solved all at once".
On the other hand, on the sidelines of a reception to the Portuguese community in Macau, the diplomat stressed that “not all the same” the problems faced by Portuguese schools abroad. "Each school has a different context, it also has to do with the fact that they are in countries with very different regimes [and] the agreements to found are different," he added.
The stoppage in the Portuguese schools of Timor-Leste, Mozambique, Angola and Sao Tome and Principe was convened by the Union of All Education Professionals (S.to.P). The director of the Portuguese School of Mozambique, Luísa Antunes, admitted to Lusa that Maputo's establishment did not work normally on Thursday due to the strike and recognized difficulties and damage to the students.
 
Reinforcement of Chinese language in Portugal
 
Paulo Rangel also promised to strengthen Chinese language teaching in Portugal, which described as decisive for the country's future. “With the Chinese authorities I made a point of saying that we are very committed to teaching Chinese in Portugal,” said the chief of Portuguese diplomacy after a three -day visit to mainland China.
In the capital, Beijing, Rangel met with Chinese counterpart, Wang Yi, before meeting with Chinese vice-minister, Ding Xuexiang, on Haião Island, where the Boa Boao Forum Annual Conference took place. "The situation today is much better than it was 20 years ago ... We have, in fact, a formation that we did not have at all," said Paulo Rangel, in a reception to the Portuguese community in Macau.
In addition to Chinese Language and Culture Degrees, the Confucius Institute, under the protection of a government agency, guarantees free mandarin courses in five Portuguese universities: Porto, Aveiro, Coimbra, Lisbon and Minho.
At the end of February, the dean of the University of the Azores, Susana Mira Leal, announced her intention to open a delegation from the Confucius Institute at the institution. The formation of fluent people in Mandarin “is also decisive for our future”, but “it is not enough for the challenges we have ahead,” warned Paulo Rangel.
On Tuesday, the minister had asked Beijing's authorities to promote the teaching of Chinese more borders, particularly in the community of Portuguese-speaking countries (CPLP).
Faced with a group of Chinese students during a lecture at a university in northern Beijing, Rangel also argued that "Portugal is an old country, but Portuguese is the language of the future." "It is the most spoken language in the southern hemisphere and, until 2100, there will be more than 600 million Portuguese speakers," predicted the head of Portuguese diplomacy, in an auditorium with more than 100 students from the University of Foreign Studies of Beijing ('Beiwai').
Rangel also stressed the economic weight of countries and regions of Portuguese official language, which estimated to have a gross domestic product of three billion euros. "The community of Portuguese -speaking countries would be the sixth largest economic bloc in the world," he explained.
The oldest Portuguese Language Degree in China was created in 1961, precisely at Beiwai, and was the only one of the genre in the country until the late 1990s. However, the teaching of Portuguese on the Chinese continent has registered accelerated growth in the last 25 years, fueled by the evolution of trade between China and Lusophony.
 
Sam hu fai visits Portugal this year
 
The Minister of Foreign Affairs has announced that the Macao Government leader will visit Portugal this year and that restrictions on the Portuguese residence are on the bilateral agenda. Sam Hou Fai is expected to visit Portugal “immediately before August or in September,” said the chief of Portuguese diplomacy to journalists after a meeting with the chief executive of Macao. Rangel stressed that he is the Foreign Minister to visit Macau since his inauguration, on December 20, from Sam Hou Fai, whose visit to Portugal will be the first trip abroad. "There is clearly here also an alignment of the priorities that is highly symbolic," said the diplomat, on the fringes of a meeting with the Portuguese community in Macau. Asked about restrictions on the Portuguese residence, Rangel said he spoke with Sam Hou Fai “on all the issues that are relevant to the relationship between Portugal and the Special Administrative Region of Macao” (MSAR). "But, as it is a dialogue that is underway, I have a duty to give the opportunity we can, with the questions that have been raised from one part and the other, now we have space and time to build solutions," he added.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 08:36:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Travel alerts to Myanmar and Thailand are still in force due to earthquake</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/alertas-de-viagem-para-myanmar-e-tailandia-continuam-em-vigor-devido-a-sismo/</link><description>The Macao government issued a travel alert to Thailand and maintains the same warning to Myanmar following the 7.7 magnitude earthquake on the Richter scale that shook the two countries on Friday. The Directorate of Tourism Services received a request for assistance, whose applicant returned yesterday in Thailand to Macau. The chief executive addressed a message of condolences to Myanmar and three charity organizations in Macao began a collection of donations for the disaster victims.
 
Travel alerts to Myanmar and Thailand are in force due to safety issues after the earthquake in both places on Friday afternoon and caused thousands of injuries and deaths. The Macao Tourism Services Directorate (STD) issued a travel alert to Thailand at level 1, the lowest of a total of three echelons, which was already in force for Myanmar, but due to the country's civil war.
Ensuring continuing to accompany the incident, the authorities have so far received a request for assistance and seven requests for information from residents of the situation in Thailand, and no request for help or information related to Myanmar has been registered.
This request for assistance was submitted by an individual who lost his flight to Macau due to the closure of the roads, which caused the impediment of access to the airport. According to the body, the STD representative in Thailand has already provided proper assistance and necessary information. Helena de Senna Fernandes, director of STD, revealed that the care applicant has already managed to take a flight and returned to Macau on Saturday morning.
Although there are no organized excursions from Macau either in Thailand or Myanmar, STD has sent messages to 1,475 mobile phones registered in the territory that are currently accessing roaming services in both countries or neighboring Laos.
Helena de Senna Fernandes, quoted by Macau radio in Chinese language, said there are no immediate plans to raise the travel alert level or to send charter flights to transport residents to the territory. "The situation in Thailand has not reached an extreme danger level and is gradually returning to normal, without interruption in transportation. And Macao residents in the country are generally in relatively safe places," he said.
"The situation will be continuously evaluated," said the official, noting that the warning emission is still in mind of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of China and neighboring regions, such as Hong Kong. STD appeals to Macao residents who are traveling to pay attention to their personal security.
 
Sam Hou Fai condolence message
 
The chief executive of Macau sent a message of condolences to Myanmar leader Min Aung Hlaing following the earthquake of strong intensity to express “senses condolences, condolences and solidarity” to the victims' wounded and relatives in the incident.
Sam Hou Fai began to say that it was "with great dismay" that became aware of the earthquake in Myanmar, noting that Macau and Myanmar have strong traditional friendship ties and narrow contacts between the two peoples, so "Macao residents have empathy and joint, worrying about the situation caused by this catastrophe and the affected population."
In a statement, the government leader also expressed respect for relief and rescue teams, who are dedicated to rescue operations and other assistance work. "We are available to arrange, within our abilities, all the necessary support for rescue work and later reconstruction," said Sam Hou Fai.
 
Donations for affected
 
Three charity organizations in Macau have launched a donation action to raise funds to help people affected by the earthquake.
The Macao Vermelha Cruz has already made available $ 50,000 through its international headquarters to support relief work and created a specific donation account, with the aim of receiving support from the Macao society to help with Myanmar rescue operations.
Caritas de Macao said citizens can donate through the online portal or bank accounts of the organization, and the collected funds will be used to purchase the materials needed to send to Myanmar.
The World Vision Macau has indicated that the organization's office at Myanmar has already started emergency operation plans and appealed to the citizens of Macao to join the funds donation.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 08:37:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Tokyo, Seoul and Beijing respond to Trump with acceleration from the free trade agreement</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/toquio-seul-e-pequim-respondem-a-trump-com-aceleracao-de-acordo-de-comercio-livre/</link><description>Japan, South Korea and China have announced that they intend to reinforce cooperation and provide a “predictable environment” to companies and “accelerate” negotiations on a free trade agreement that responds to US uncertainties.
 
The Ministers of Industry and Commerce of the three countries held an emergency meeting in Seoul, designed to settle policies to respond to the acceleration of tariff increases imposed by Washington - a tripartite emergency meeting and the first in this format since 2020.
South Korean Industry Minister Ahn Duk-Geun, his Japanese counterpart, Yoji Muto, and Chinese trade minister Wang Wenta agreed to “pursue discussions to accelerate negotiations for a comprehensive trilateral trade agreement” and “fair” according to a joint statement.
Discussions about this agreement began in 2013 and continued until 2019, when they stagnated. They were relaunched in 2024, in a special tripartite summit, which brought together the leaders of the three countries in Seoul.
For now, “we will continue to work to ensure equitable competition conditions at the world, in order to promote a predictable, free, fair, non -discriminatory, transparent and inclusive commercial, free, non -discrimination environment,” adds the joint statement.
For the three countries, the goal is to “gradually intensify their cooperation” in order to “create a predictable commercial environment, stabilize supply chains and improve communication on export controls,” Seoul insisted on a separate statement.
More generally, Seoul, Beijing and Tokyo have agreed to “work in close collaboration” to promote the Reform of the World Trade Organization (WTO) and encourage new members to join the vast Economic Economic Partnership (RCEP), which brings together China and 14 Asian countries. Among them, China, Japan and South Korea represent about 20% of the world's population, a quarter of the world economy and 20% of global trade.
The tripartite meeting arises after the US Administration of Donald Trump, in mid-March, 25% customs rights on steel and aluminum, a few days before the imposition, from April 2, of customs of customs of 25% on imported cars for the United States.
Japan and South Korea respectively represent 16% and 15% of total US car imports, an important sector for their national economies. China, for its part, faces a total customs surcharge of 20% over all its exports to the United States. There is also the spectrum of “reciprocal” customs rights, which Washington also threatens to impose from next week. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 08:39:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Rewrite the rules, the female presence in literature according to Kwok Yim Mei</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/reescrever-as-regras-a-presenca-feminina-na-literatura-segundo-kwok-yim-mei/</link><description>The last weekend of the 14th Macao Literary Festival featured a panel led by author Kwok Yim Mei, who highlighted the advances that women have made in the literary world. The discussion focused on the growing number of female voices that contribute to the literature and the importance of rewriting the prejudice narratives already dated. Kwok addressed the challenges faced by women writers and the progress achieved thanks to their resilience.
 
The literary panorama of the current is watching a palpable change as women's voices become higher and more influential. This was the transformation that was at the center of the discussion of the “intertwined borders, me and us in the writing of female fiction”, integrated in the last weekend of the 14th Macao Literary Festival. Hong Kong writer Kwok Yim Mei shared her ideas about the evolution of women's role in writing.
Kwok's perspective on social norms underlines a wider dialogue about creativity and individuality. "We all attribute definitions to everything around us. A bottle of water is just a bottle of water, a chair is no more than a chair, a secretary is just that. But we can create our own definitions; we don't have to follow the definitions of others. You can be you," he said. For the author, this philosophy encourages young writers to break free from traditional restrictions, I defend the authenticity of expression.
Historically, women writers have faced obstacles that suffocate their voices and narratives. "Women's literature has been mistreated in every way possible. We will not continue to be silenced," Kwok said, articulating the frustration and resilience of women in the literary community.
The panel presented a series of topics, from historical barriers to contemporary achievements. Kwok stressed the fact that the greatest recognition and greater opportunities for writers to have created an increasingly inclusive literary atmosphere in recent years. "We are at a time when we finally see progress of society in the literary world, especially with regard to women in creative spaces," he said. This progress is evidenced by the growing emergence of authors and their decoration, shaping narratives that resonate with more diverse audiences.
The dialogue started by Kwok Yim Mei at the Festival encapsulates a crucial moment in the literary world. With a progressive number of female voices to emerge and defend its place in writing spaces, the literary landscape is becoming and paving the way to comprehensive and border narratives. The festival is a testimony of this progress, celebrating the different contributions of women in the pursuit of creative expression over ten days.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>In the abyss of change</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/no-abismo-da-mudanca/</link><description>Is a new geopolitical era now, where the law of the strongest prevails? Does ultranationalism and authoritarian drift from some countries, in particular in the United States of America, shake the order of the world? In panel “2025: the year of all changes”, included in the program of the 14th edition of the Macao Literary Festival, Sonny Lo, António Costa Silva and Michael Share tried to give answers to questions, but were pessimistic.
 
Geopolitics was also under discussion yesterday, on the last day of the Macau Literary Festival - Rota das Letras. Michael Share, Sonny Lo and António Costa Silva made up a panel titled “2025: The Year of All Changes”, which tried to decode the agitations that are taking place in the world and foresee the possible future effects.
Sonny Lo, Professor of Political Science in Hong Kong, began by stating that before 2025 changes were seen, namely with the rise of ultranationalist movements in several countries and with the invasion of Russia's Ukrainian territory. The "turbulence" looked at Donald Trump's return to the White House.
António Costa Silva agrees: "Trump's emergence in the White House for the second time is very dangerous." The former Minister of the Portuguese Economy points out that with Trump, nationalism and the “demonization of the other” grow. Pointing to the fall of Constantinople in the fifteenth century, Costa Silva stated: "We are at the end of one era and at the beginning of another."
Michael Share went further and said we have definitely entered a new era. An era without multilateralism or international organizations. "This new age has no rules, only the law of the strongest prevails," lamented the sino-Russian relations professor in the Hong Kong Baptist University, which argues that the beginning of the new age has happened in three distinct moments: Covid-19 pandemic, Russian Ukraine invasion and Trump's election in the United States.
In this new era, Michael Share anticipated great changes to Macau as well. The university professor said he believed that "if Ukraine falls, China will attack Taiwan, because he will see that no one will react." In this case, he argued, Japan and South Korea would possibly seek to defend themselves by obtaining nuclear weapons, which could affect the international trade in Macau and Hong Kong. "If the exchanges fall as happened in the late 1930s [early World War II], there will be nothing in Hong Kong and Macau except for buildings," he warned.
António Costa Silva drew attention to the relationship that will develop from here between the United States and China: "A key question for the future is how the US and China will interact. Today I have more confidence in China's leadership because it has a long -term strategy and the US does not."
The American Michael Share has described what is going on in his country as a "counterrevolution" of nationalist and authoritarian. "I fear for the future of the US," he said. Share even said that last year's elections may have been the last free elections in the country, as Trump will want to centralize power in themselves, ignoring the decisions of the courts and extending in power, even though the US constitution does not allow it.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Chinese mne moves this week to Russia for strategic dialogue with Lavrov</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/mne-chines-desloca-se-esta-semana-a-russia-para-dialogo-estrategico-com-lavrov/</link><description>Chinese diplomacy chief Wang Yi will visit Russia between Monday and Wednesday at the invitation of Russian homologist Serguei Lavrov, his ministry announced.
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakun said at a press conference that “the China-Russia relationship maintains a healthy, stable and high level development under the strategic guidance of the two heads of state,” Xi Jinping and Vladimir Putin, and considered that bilateral exchanges have been constantly deepened on several domains.
During the visit, Wang will maintain talks with Lavrov to exchange views on bilateral agenda, regional cooperation and international issues of common interest, added the spokesman.
China refused to condemn Russia for the invasion of Ukraine and criticized the imposition of sanctions against Moscow. The Asian country has provided important political, diplomatic and economic support to the neighboring country. Bilateral trade registered, in 2023, a homologous growth from 26.3%to $ 240 billion. Xi Jinping has stressed several times that maintaining robust relations with Russia is a "strategic choice" of Beijing.
Wang's trip takes place at a key point in the conflict in Ukraine after the United States approaches Moscow to the detriment of Kiev's support and the possibility of Europe sending troops to support the Ukrainian forces.
Last week a new summit was held in Paris to discuss the sending of a peace force to Ukraine, as part of the goal of about thirty European countries, Canada and Australia of reinforcing Kiev's business position with Russia.
The meeting also agreed to maintain economic sanctions against Russia until peace is achieved, as well as to continue to support Ukraine military and politically so that it is in a better negotiating position against Moscow.
The trip of Chinese diplomacy chief may also be a prelude to Xi Jinping's official visit to Moscow in the coming months. Xi will participate in the celebrations, on May 9, the 80th anniversary of the victory over Germany Nazi.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 08:39:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Public revenues fall 14% until February</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/receitas-publicas-caem-14-ate-fevereiro/</link><description>Macao current revenue fell by 14% in the first two months of 2025, in annual terms, mainly due to a drop in financial revenues and a slowdown in the game's revenues.
Current revenue between January and February was 15.9 billion patacas, according to published "online" data by finance services. The main reason for the decrease was financial revenues, which went from billion in the first two months of 2024 to just two thousand patacas this year.
This heading corresponds to the results of the monetary authority of Macao, including investment and interest and dividends revenues.
On the other hand, the data also reveal a drop of 3.8%, to 14.2 billion patacas in tax revenues, which still represented 89.3% of the total.
The six city game operators pay a 35% direct tax on game revenues, 2.4% for the Social Security Fund and urban and tourist development and 1.6% to the Macau Foundation for cultural, educational, scientific, academics and philanthropic purposes.
Os impostos sobre o jogo caíram apesar dos casinos de Macau terem registado receitas totais de quase 38 mil milhões de patacas nos primeiros dois meses do ano, mais 0,5% do que no mesmo período de 2024.
In January and February, Macau collected 14.2% of the projected current revenue for 2025 in the region's budget, which is 112.6 billion patacas.
In early December, the Macao Study Center and the University of Macao Economics Department foresaw that revenues should be smaller than the government's estimated: 111.8 billion patacas.
With falling revenues, Macao ended February with a surplus in public accounts of six billion patacas, 24.8% lower than in the same period as 2024.
Macao closed last year with a surplus of 15.8 billion patacas, more than twice the record in 2023. In addition, it was the first year since 2020, at the beginning of the pandemic, that the territory was able to keep the accounts on positive ground, something required by the basic law, without making transfers from the financial reserve.
The surplus of the territory shrunk despite the public expense designed 6.1% in January and February, to 9.99 billion patacas, mainly due to the lower investment in infrastructure.
The Macao government spent 2.48 billion patacas under the administration's investment and expenses plan, less 24.9% compared to the first two months of 2024. On the contrary, current expense increased by 3.1% to 7.51 billion patacas, mainly due to a 5.7% rise in social support and subsidies given to the population.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 08:39:04</pubDate></item><item><title>China asked Portugal reciprocity in the exemption of visas</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/china-pediu-a-portugal-reciprocidade-na-isencao-de-vistos/</link><description>China has asked Portugal to facilitate the entry of its citizens, as there is an exemption from visas since October 2024 to Portuguese who moves to the Asian country, said Chinese ambassador Zhao Bentang.
 
"China has already asked Europe, Portugal, which facilitates the entry to Chinese citizens. If the Portuguese can go very easily to China to do business, their partners in China want to come and they can't or it's very difficult," he said.
In an interview with Lusa agency, the Chinese diplomat in Portugal said that the "Chinese government expects the Portuguese government, European governments to also facilitate [entries] to tourists, traders and Chinese entrepreneurs on the subject of visas."
"We always talked to the Portuguese Government. I spoke many times. I believe that during the visit of the Minister [Portuguese Foreign Affairs, Paulo Rangel] also the Chinese part spoke of this theme," added the ambassador, referring to the trip of the head of Portuguese diplomacy to the Asia.
Zhao Bentang recalled that since October 2024 the Portuguese can travel to China without the need for seen, under certain conditions, following a “unilateral policy” and whose final is scheduled for December.
"But [the continuity of the exemption] depends on the appreciation, the demand. I believe that when it comes to height, if necessary, the Chinese part may consider some extension, some renewal. But it has not yet come to evaluate," he said.
At the end of September 2024, China announced the extension of the visa exemption policy to Portuguese citizens, in stay up to 15 days, thus inserting Portugal into a list that covered another 16 European countries.
The enlargement, which was confirmed in a statement by the Chinese Foreign Ministry, appears after Beijing included Norway, Slovenia, Greece, Denmark and Cyprus on the list of countries whose citizens can remain in the Asian country for tourism, business or traffic for 15 days, exempt from visa. The measure came into force on October 15, 2024 and in force until December 31, 2025.
Beijing tries to stimulate international tourism and foreign investment, paralyzed by the Covid-19 pandemic, during which China imposed an almost total closure of the borders.
In November 2023, the Asian country announced that the nationals of France, Germany, Italy, the Netherlands and Spain would benefit from a unilateral visa exemption. In March 2024, he extended policy for stay of up to 15 days to six other European countries - Switzerland, Ireland, Hungary, Austria, Belgium and Luxembourg.
When the 20th anniversary of the global strategic partnership between Lisbon and Beijing marks, since Tuesday, the visit of the china's china diplomacy has been visited since Tuesday and that “gives a very important sign” because we talk about “good cooperation in all areas”, from politics to technology, Zhao Bentang said. “The return of Macao [China] is an example of how to solve problems through peaceful negotiations between countries” and in the Portuguese support “one country, two systems, supports Macao to develop and maintain in stability and adapt to new realities”, as well as foster the quality of bilateral relations.
Zhao Bentang also noticed the “importance” of Paulo Rangel's visit as it was the “first” of a European diplomacy leader after the recent annual session of the National Popular Assembly. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 08:39:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Children and adults built a story on the Route of Letters with live illustration</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/criancas-e-adultos-construiram-uma-historia-na-rota-das-letras-com-ilustracao-ao-vivo/</link><description>"Once upon a time there was a cup where they mingled ..." From a simple phrase, the public of the 14th Macao Literary Festival, consisting of kids and large, was invited to contribute to descriptions and adjectives and to create an authentically his story, while a cartoonist was giving life to the narrative with real -time illustrations. Organizers Catarina Mesquita and Rodrigo de Matos, who had already streamlined similar sessions in the two previous editions, recognize that this year a “record” number of spectators was reached, in what was the last day of Rota das Letras.
 
The author of children's books Catarina Mesquita and the cartoonist Rodrigo de Matos streamline yesterday, on the last day of the 14th Macao Literary Festival, an interactive activity in which the audience helped build and illustrate a story. Although “theoretically” directed to a children's audience, both children and parents participated in the event and contributed to the assembly the pieces of what, gradually, became a finished story.
"Basically, the idea is to tell a live story. We don't have a story in mind, just a skeleton, and we need the public participation to complete it. They will give us adjectives, descriptions of what they want to happen in the story, and Rodrigo [de Matos] draws what is said in real time," said Catarina Mesquita, in statements to the end before the event. "The story is not told, but discovered. It is a challenge for both the public and for us, since neither party knows what will happen."
Unlike previous editions, where “improvisation was total”, this time the duo chose to start from an “existing story” to start the creativity session - which, Catarina points out, should not be exclusive to the younger ones. "Last year we notice that children sat down and parents behind. But our goal is for the whole audience to participate, regardless of age." At yesterday's session, on the closing day of the Rota das Letras, both kids and big ones occupied all available banks; Those who did not get place, were standing to follow the construction of the story.
As a starting point, a single sentence: "Once upon a time there was a man and a woman who had a cup where they mixed ... Mixed what?" Given the issue of Catarina Mesquita, dozens of children raised their hands and exclaimed the first ideas that came to their heads, from chocolate mousse to paint. In front of the audience, Rodrigo de Matos's pen was materializing these images in a huge panel.
Starting with the image of a simple cup, “fat”, “beautiful”, “smelly” or “pork tail” people, according to the adjectives and unusual details that children-and some adults-were suggesting to the story. The end result was a surrealist work of art, as Rodrigo de Matos granted in statements after the end point: "It was not much sense to include a pig tail, but the audience is what it decides." And how did the artist himself play the work he had just created? "The only interpretation is that children have a boundless, indomitable imagination."
The work of the cartoonist is precisely to adapt to the interventions of a hyper-creative audience, always paying attention to the size of the panel. "In the first meter of drawing, I still had no idea where the story would stop. You have to realize when the story is in the middle or coming to an end, to be able to fill everything and not leave space blank," he explained. In the end, the children were invited to color the design finished with multicolors distributed stickers for this purpose.
Rodrigo de Matos acknowledged that the activity exceeded all expectations of adhesion, probably becoming that “with the most presence ever”. "I think we broke a record, here. We have done this two or three times and I think this time were as many people as in the other two sessions together." Part of the justification may be related to the availability of the space, much broader than in previous events: “It was well the event to take place here,” said the illustrator, referring to the former Municipal Slaughterhouse, in Barra.
The 14th Macao Literary Festival began last Friday, at 17h, in the former Municipal Slaughterhouse, and ended yesterday, around 7 pm, with a dinner under the motto “A Storytelling: Seven Douts, Seven Traditions”.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Humanity in the crossroads, the reflections of António Costa Silva on contemporary challenges</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/humanidade-na-encruzilhada-as-reflexoes-de-antonio-costa-silva-sobre-os-desafios-contemporaneos/</link><description>Under the 14th Macao Literary Festival, António Costa Silva led a panel in the auditorium of the Consulate General of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong, centered on the crossroads of humanity and priorities for the 21st century. Throughout the panel, the former Minister of Economy and Sea expressed his views on the complexities of contemporary governance.
“We entered the age of 'Desração',” said Costa Silva, highlighting a “worrying” trend in global decision making, since rational speech seems to be in his view to disappear. Also discussing the challenges of leadership in this environment, Costa Silva stressed that “connectivity is the paradigm of this century”, indicating the importance of connectivity in the approach of modern issues and also warning the dangers posed by armed conflicts. "We live a complete erosion of the democratic and liberal international order and its replacement for anarchy, which is what results when the great powers decide to violate all principles, invade countries, not respect the territorial directs of each country and each nation," he said.
António Costa Silva also addressed environmental issues and expressed alarm about climate change. "We made a fatal mistake, our divorce of nature. It went to think that alone, in our arrogance, we were able to do everything," he said. Looking to the future, the former minister expressed concern about the possible upcoming crises of humanity. "I am convinced that one of the next great crises we will face is an food crisis," he said, underlining the potential for widespread food insecurity as global disturbances continue.
António Costa Silva summarized the urgency of international cooperation in solving these problems: “The crossroads in which we are is a supposedly rational species that has a whole story that developed, that created an international order that was working and was minimizing risks and conflicts, and suddenly forgets all that learned, involved in blind protectionism, in a geopolitical fragmentation that tries to form Antagonistic blocks, in a logistical use of technologies for the great powers if gladed with each other. It is always more war, more destruction, more suffering. For him, the need for a renewed commitment to collaboration between nations to face shared challenges is unavoidable and immediate.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Portugal leads European delegation to the Macau International Tourism Fair</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/portugal-lidera-delegacao-europeia-a-feira-internacional-de-turismo-de-macau/</link><description>Tourist sector professionals and Portuguese journalists will lead a European delegation to the Macao International Tourism Fair, from April 25 to 27.
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) has revealed that a European delegation will participate in the 13th International Tourism Expo (Industry) of Macao (Mite).
In a written response, STD added that the delegation is being organized by the Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies (APAVT).
Macao will host in June the semi -sectional meeting of the European Confederation of Travel Agency Associations and Tour Operators (ECTAA). “I think it's a good start,” said STD director Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes. "Although it will have less than 100 people, they represent 80,000 travel agencies from all over Europe in all," said the leader. "This is also a result of good collaboration between us and APAVT, because it was through APAVT that we were introduced to Ectaa," said Senna Fernandes.
Senna Fernandes added that Portugal can help the region attract more visitors from the rest of Europe. “Portugal is not just about reaching Portugal. Portugal also serves to help us reach the European market,” said Senna Fernandes.
In April 2024, Ectaa Vice President Heli Mäki-Fränti told Lusa during the 12th Mite that the meeting in the territory happens “at initiative” of APAVT. It will be the second time that Ectaa has gathered outside Europe after Kuala Lumpur in Malaysia. The Confederation also chose Macau as a favorite destination for 2025.
The territory wants to attract more international visitors and this year alone, participated in the Madrid International Tourism Fair in January and at ITB Berlin, the largest travel fair in the world, between March 4, as well as seminars in the United Arab Emirates and Saudi Arabia.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 08:37:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau deputy wants cooperation with Portugal to attract football friendly</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/deputado-de-macau-quer-cooperacao-com-portugal-para-atrair-amigaveis-de-futebol/</link><description>Deputy Eddie Wu Chou Kit defended cooperation with the Portuguese Professional Football League to organize friendly games with “European top teams” in Macao.
 
In an intervention at the last session of the Legislative Assembly, which took place on Friday, Eddie Wu Chou proposed “Establish [one] Deep Cooperation” with the Portuguese Professional Football League (LPFP) for creation, “together, a permanent training base”.
The deputy explained that the objective would be to “attract top teams in Europe to train and perform itinerant games, promoting sports and cultural exchange at the international level”.
Extending the scope to Portuguese -speaking countries, Eddie Wu appealed to reinforce the “commercial collaboration (…) in the area of ​​football [and] introduce its famous high -level brands and competitions”. Wu argued that cooperation with the Lusófono block would allow "creating a platform of international events [and] attracting fans from East Asia to Macau to watch the games."
The deputy, appointed by the previous leader of the local government, pointed out as a goal "to transform Macau into an important bridge for the exchange and cooperation between Portuguese -speaking countries and China at football."
China leader Xi Jinping, an assumed football fan, launched an ambitious plan for the sport, with the aim of organizing and earning the World Championship one day. The Chinese men's team continues, however, absent from large international events and is currently classified in 90th place in the FIFA world ranking, just above the Caribbean island of Curaçao.
In December, the Chinese Football Association (CFA) stated that 2025 will mark a “new start” in Asian country, after years of exuberant spending and corruption results in the bankruptcy of dozens of clubs.
On the other hand, Wu, also president of the Macao Engineers Association, linked international cooperation to the need to “train local football talents (including players, coaches and managers)”.
Macao's men's national team, made up of amateur players, is currently classified in 193rd position in the FIFA world ranking, consisting of 210 teams.
Luso-Angolan soccer coach Lázaro Oliveira left the Macao selection in September, after the selection was eliminated from the qualification to the 2027 Asian Cup by Brunei. In late August, FIFA confirmed the exclusion of five Portuguese players for not having a passport. Only Chinese citizens with permanent resident status in Macau can get a territory passport. The decision prevented the captain, the Luso-Sul African Nicholas Torrão, Filipe Duarte, graduated from Benfica and former young international for Portugal, Central Vítor Almeida and the striker Iuri Capelo to play against Brunei. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 08:39:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Government will review the implementation of non-game investment plans of concessionaires</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/governo-vai-rever-a-implementacao-dos-planos-de-investimento-nao-jogo-das-concessionarias/</link><description>The government “is very attentive” to the investment plans of non-game elements by the concessionaires and will review its implementation, the secretary said to the economy and finance. Tai Kin IP spoke at the plenary meeting of the Legislative Assembly on Friday, where the report on the execution of the budget of 2023 was approved.
At the time, Deputy Ron Lam expressed concern about the lack of transparency of these investment plans, whose period is ten years, asking to become public the real amount of non-game investments and the effectiveness of execution.
"There is an established mechanism for the supervision of investment plans, and a third institution has also been invited to monitor its implementation," said Tai Kin IP, in response. "The concession [gaming license] provides for an intermediate review mechanism, and concessionaires must undergo an assessment of the execution of their commitments every three years," added the secretary, reiterating that the six dealers "have an obligation to fulfill the plans presented to the government during the concession process."
It is recalled that new concession contracts for game exploration stipulate that the six dealers should invest 108.8 billion patacas in game-related elements over ten years. And, according to the law, given that the gross revenue of the game by 2023 exceeded 180 billion patacas, the amount of that investment was increased by 20%, reaching approximately 130.4 billion patacas.
On the other hand, the Hemiciclo also questioned the low budget execution rates of various government funds, such as 45.6% for the industrial and marketing fund and 55.4% for the Forum Permanent Secretariat Support Office for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries.
Tai Kin IP explained that this was due to postpandey effects and excess budget appropriations, but ensured that the situation on the execution rate "has already improved" last year.
The Legislative Assembly also approved, in general, the proposal to change two laws on the general staff of teaching staff and the statute of private schools of non -higher education. The proposal provides that students and teachers residing in schools in Hengqin enjoy the same rights and benefits as those in private schools in Macao.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 08:38:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Deputies concerned with the survival of satellite casinos</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/deputados-preocupados-com-a-sobrevivencia-dos-casinos-satelite/</link><description>Deputies to the Legislative Assembly reported being aware of the eventual wave of satellite casinos closing at the end of this year with the change in the exploitation model required by law. Ella Lei and Nick Lei ask the government to communicate with these casinos on their exploitation, evaluate the impact on the economy caused by the possible end of various satellite casinos and have contingency plans to ensure the use of their workers.
 
The various satellite casinos may choose to close the doors later this year with the end of the three-year transition period to their activity, provided for in the current game of the game, a question that is concerned with the sector as well as the deputies.
The theme was approached in the plenary of the Legislative Assembly last Friday, where the law enforcers Lei and Nick Lei asked measures to ensure employment of casinos-satellite employees.
Casinos-satellite are casinos operated by management societies outside the premises of the concessionaires. The current law provides for the alteration of the exploration model of these casinos, preventing the sharing of casinos revenues with management companies, or the payment of commissions to them.
In this way, companies that generate satellite casinos can only receive a remuneration for management, which has caused some local satellite casinos already “been successively closed,” warned Nick Law.
In his intervention before the agenda, Nick Lei cited estimates of the real estate to mention that there are currently 11 satellite casinos with 4,000 workers from the game and hotel sector, and the associated stores in their vicinity have about 5,500 workers, making a total of 13,500 workers, representing 4.6 percent of the total macao labor force.
"The government should evaluate the unemployment situation caused by the eventual closure of a large number of satellite casinos and their impact on the community economy," noted Nick Law.
In turn, Ella Lei stated that the continuity of satellite casinos involves the right to employ many local workers, including supervisors and croupiers directly hired by the concessionaire and other workers hired by the satellite casinos or who ensure awarded services, "which are concerned with maintaining their employment and whether salaries and perks will be affected."
The deputy expects the government to take the initiative to communicate with the satellite casinos to know its intention regarding the continuity of the operation. Authorities must, according to Ella Law, subsequently prepare contingency plans to ensure workers' employment and prevent their rights from being harmed.
In the hemiciclo, the deputy also reported the problem of the “black list of employment” in the game sector, and some workers will have been the target of verification of antecedents when they tried to find employment in the sector. He stressed that it is a situation that “lacks legal foundation and lack of evidence and objective criteria” and requested solutions from the government.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 08:38:17</pubDate></item><item><title>One hundred days of Sam: reinforcement of governance, tune with the continent and communication management</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/cem-dias-de-sam-reforco-da-governacao-sintonia-com-o-continente-e-gestao-da-comunicacao/</link><description>Yesterday 100 days since Sam Hou Fai took office as head of the Executive of the MSAR. Balanced the first hundred days ahead of the region's government, analysts heard by the end point highlight the great proximity to the interior authorities of the country.
 
Yesterday was the day when the government led by Sam Hou Fai reached 100 days. One hundred days when, according to the analysts heard by the end, Sam tried to reinforce the capacity for governance and bet on all the relationship with the continent.
In this first hundred days, Sam Hou Fai has gone to China four times - Great Bay, Beijing, Haião and Harbin. On the other hand, it has been multiplied in sessions for the “transmission of the spirit of the two sessions” and the “spirit of President Xi Jinping's important speeches” when his visit to Macau, precisely for the possession of the new government.
“Sam Hou Fai has been hard to visit the cities of the Great Bay to improve regional cooperation-an effort that had never been seen in the previous chiefs of the executive,” begins by stating Meng U Ieong, assistant professor at the Department of Government and Public Administration at the University of Macao (one). The academic points out that even before the election it was already guessed that Sam would be much more focused on the interior authorities: "The himself expressed it very clearly when he applied for the elections."
Sonny Lo says there are “remarkable differences” between Sam Hou Fai and Ho Iat Seng. One has to do precisely with this desire to establish more ties not only with the continent, but also with Portugal and the Portuguese -speaking countries. For the author and professor of political science in Hong Kong, Sam Hou Fai has been "in tune with central government wishes."
NG Kuok Cheong, former deputy to the Legislative Assembly for three decades and whose candidacy was disqualified by the authorities in the 2021 elections, agrees and says that Sam Hou Fai has been dedicated to "demonstrating that he understands and actively fulfills and fulfills central government political expectations."
Another aspect highlighted by Sonny Lo has to do with the creation of the leadership groups of the Public Administration and leadership reform to promote the construction of the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin. For the university professor, "the chief executive has done a good job by satisfying the desire of the central government to reinforce his governance capacity and 'internal communication and external connections'."
There is also the idea that this government of Sam Hou Fai is more opaque than that of Ho Iat Seng. The Macao Synergy Association, for example, criticized the “unidirectional” form of government communication, usually only through press release. In the first 100 days, Sam Hou Fai only for one occasion agreed to answer questions on the fringes of an official event.
However, Meng U Ieong says that Ho Iat Seng was no better to communicate. Still, Sam's style "is very similar to that of mainland China, and this is how the relationship between government and the media is processed."
NG Kuok Cheong describes this government's communication strategy as a "successful management of information for good governance." The boss has issued a press release "indicating that he is constantly meeting with trust groups to hear opinions while abstaining from revealing his political decisions in advance to prevent this as a pretext for controversy," says the former deputy. According to NG, "this is probably the most appropriate and safe way to deal with cases: not take a position, just collect the points of view and information, and make your opinion only when you are legally obliged to do so."
Sonny Lo comments that "it's too early for critics to evaluate Sam; at least two years, it takes time to evaluate their performance in a comprehensive and fair way." “An early assessment can be unfair and immature,” he says.
Sam Hou Fai should present the Governing Action Lines (LAG) soon. What will be the tonic? Meng U Ieong believes Sam will be “consistent with his political platform last year,” leading to social welfare policies, such as the pecuniary reimbursement plan, even though these measures can be adjusted later.
Sonny Lo Aventa that the Chief Executive will focus on issues related to the subsistence means of the population and the “faster and deepest integration” with Hengqin. On the other hand, it should also promote measures to stimulate the economy of small and medium enterprises, says the Hong Kong Academic.
In turn, Ng Kuok Cheong says they hope that these lag will focus on housing and employment policy. “The difficulty in finding a job has become an important pressure that undermines the professional aspirations of the youth of Macao,” he laments.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 08:38:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Loss of Macao Legend triggers after loss of unfinished casino hotel in Cape Verde</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/prejuizo-da-macau-legend-dispara-apos-perda-de-hotel-casino-inacabado-em-cabo-verde/</link><description>Macao Legend Development announced that the game operator's losses fired by 2024. According to a report sent to Hong Kong's Stock Exchange, the company lost $ 667.2 million from Hong Kong last year.
 
Macao Legend Development (MLD) announced that the damage of the game operator fired in 2024, in part due to the decision of the Government of Cape Verde to recover an unfinished casino hotel in the capital. According to a report sent to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange, MLD lost $ 667.2 million from Hong Kong last year.
By 2023 the company had registered a loss of less than three million dollars from Hong Kong.
MLD estimated a loss of Hong Kong's $ 45.9 million after the Cape Verdean government on November 18, formalizing the reversal of the company's Hotel and other unfinished works of the company, at Santa Maria's Ilhéu and Gamboa Sea Sea, in Praia.
The operator reiterated that she is "taking the necessary measures to safeguard the interests of the group (..), including exploring all available options to contest the decision." On the other hand, MLD admitted to “significant doubts about the group's ability to continue active” due to total $ 2.51 billion debts from Hong Kong.
In 2015, the then MLD leader, David Chow I, signed an agreement for an investment of 250 million euros. After revisions, five and a half years ago, the conclusion of the first phase was scheduled for 2021.
In recent years, there are only guards at the gates of the enclosure, an area of ​​about 160,000 square meters, which includes the partially sulved Santa Maria islet and, a paved bridge of a few meters that connects it to a building of about eight floors, empty and sealed with tails.
The government said it gave Macao Legend "all opportunities to resume works or to negotiate the sale of shares or the assignment of its contractual position to potential interest in continuing the project," but no alternatives were presented. “Given that the MLD has violated, flagrant and repeatedly, the obligations (…) there is no other way out of the State of Cape Verde, other than to resolve” the contracts, reads a decision of the Council of Ministers.
According to the executive, the company "also violated" the legal regime of exploitation of games, "by transferring, without authorization from the Government of Cape Verde, the property of more than 20% of the capital capital."
The government also cites "convictions, by the courts of the Special Administrative Region of Macao, shareholders, administrators and other elements with rights and responsibilities in MLD", as well as "the economic and financial situation of the Mother Society."
In late 2023, in an interview with Hong Kong TVB television, Macau Legend's president and executive director, Li Chu Kwan, said the group intended to end projects in Cape Verde and Cambodia until 2025. Lusa.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 08:39:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan advances with construction of the first high latitude patrol boat</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/taiwan-avanca-com-construcao-do-primeiro-barco-patrulha-de-alta-latitude/</link><description>Taiwan leader William Lai led the release ceremony of the head of the island's first high latitude ocean patrol ship, designed to reinforce the control of maritime borders, compared to the growing pressure of China.
Lai guaranteed an event held in the city of Kaohsiung in the south of the territory that the Taiwan Maritime Patrol capabilities will reach “a new level” with the entry into service of this ship, scheduled for 2026.
He explained that the ship uses a hybrid propulsion system that allows it to circumvent the Taiwan perimeter 30 times by travel, “significantly improving its autonomy and widening the scope of its high -sea missions,” according to statements from the presidential office.
The ship will also be able to adapt to different missions, transport large amounts of rescue supplies, multifunctional vessels, special assault boats or unmanned air vehicles ("drones"), Lai said. "This not only allows ocean patrols, but also the supply of remote islands, greatly reinforcing the capacity of the law of maritime fishing and humanitarian missions," said the Taiwanese leader, who stressed the importance of building an "autonomous national defense, with local production and independent manufacture."
By 2022, Taiwan awarded a budget of $ 12.9 billion Taiwanese (360 million euros) to build six ocean patrol ships over ten years to combat illegal fishing around the island.
However, the construction of these ships, about 124 meters long and 16.5 meters wide, is also intended to send a message to China and, more specifically, to its coastal guard, which increased its activities around Taiwan in the last year.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 08:39:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong beats record with a golden bars in case</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/hong-kong-volta-a-bater-recorde-com-caso-de-contrabando-de-barras-de-ouro/</link><description>Hong Kong has announced that he had seized gold bars worth $ 110 million from Hong Kong, in the largest case of gold smuggling ever registered in the region. The bars were found at Hong Kong International Airport, in charge to Japan, which was declared as containing plastic bags.
 
The Hong Kong government has announced that it has seized gold bars worth $ 110 million from Hong Kong, in the largest case of gold smuggling in the Chinese semi -autonomous region.
In a statement, the city's customs said that on Tuesday, he seized about 145 pounds of gold bars, with an estimated market value of about 110 million dollars from Hong Kong. "This is the largest case of smuggling of gold bars ever recorded in terms of seizure and market value," the police force stressed.
The bars were found at Hong Kong International Airport, in charge to Japan, which was declared as containing plastic bags, said the customs.
The police force said that an investigation is underway and that the possibility of making arrests "is not discarded."
Customs stressed that smuggling is subject to a maximum fine of two million dollars from Hong Kong and a prison sentence that can go up to seven years.
On March 11, the Hong Kong government had announced the seizure of gold bars worth 5.4 million euros, at the time the largest case of smuggling in the history of the territory.
In a statement, the city's customs said that, on March 5, seized about 64 pounds of gold bars, with an estimated market value of about $ 46 million from Hong Kong.
The bars were found at Hong Kong International Airport, in charge to Japan, which was declared as containing toys, lamps and hats, said the customs.
The price of gold rose more than 17% this year. Analysts cited by the Efe news agency believe that in the face of the recent instability of the US dollar, investors have decided to invest in gold. This after US President Donald Trump announced a new 25% tariff to all cars and components exported to the US, starting April 2.
In a report, Ned Naylor-Leyland, Gold and Silver Investment Manager of the Jupiter AM consulting firm, said the rising price of gold is related to the traditional role of metal as a refuge asset.
The price of gold is rising due to concerns about economic growth and Trump's trade policies, expectations of interest rates and demand from central banks, he said.
The Jupiter AM manager said that the central banks, in particular China, have bought more gold in recent years and predicted that demand should accelerate further. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 08:39:02</pubDate></item><item><title>A world of artists, adventurers and pirates: Paul French presents ancient macao</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/um-mundo-de-artistas-aventureiros-e-piratas-paul-french-apresenta-macau-antiga/</link><description>Writer Paul French presented his two new books, “Destination Macau” and “Her Lotus Year”, before a full audience on the last day of the 14th Macao Literary Festival - Rota das Letras. The first, released in 2025, is the third entrance to the “Destination” collection, centered on previous editions of Shanghai and Beijing, and traces a vivid portrait of the social, cultural and political plans of the Macao region of the nineteenth and twentieth centuries.
 
British author Paul French presented yesterday on the last day of the 14th Macao Literary Festival, his latest book, “Destination Macau”, the third entrance to the relevant western world's book series that visited China. At the launch event, which featured an crowded audience, the writer and historian also took the opportunity to expand the themes of the work “Her Lotus Years”, edited last year.
After the big metropolises of Beijing and Shanghai, Paul French had several options on the table as to the region to explore in the third volume of the “Destination” collection. With the restrictions of the covid-19 pandemic in 2020, the author was forced to interrupt the “usual trips to China” and to proceed to a lonely introspection about what he knew from the Asia. It was Macao - a region that, recognizes, does not occupy a place of such prominence in world bookstores as the destinations previously chosen - continually flowing into their reflections, perhaps because it is a destination that always faced as a "refuge" conducive to daydreams and inspiration.
"Macau has always been a place where I liked to sit down, look out the window and dream. In addition, I had already written some stories about Macau for South China Morning Post and I thought it could expand some topics of interest," he recalled, confessing that another factors that weighed on the choice was something stereotyped and pejorative of the British about the old Portuguese colonia. "English sensational journalism has created an image of Macau as Mediterranean representation in Asia - and when the English describe something like 'Mediterranean', they never understand it as a compliment," he confessed.
The nineteenth-century English writers-and later the Americans-described Macao as a “troprarian and retrograde” region, where the “successful and stirring” personalities of Hong Kong or the interior of China came to “release tension”. According to the author, this negative representation of the Portuguese presence intended to establish a comparison with British domain in Hong Kong, which the English authors of the time self-proclaimed as “the upper and most successful version” of European occupation in Asia.
“Destination Macau” comes to demystify this idea by painting ancient macao as a dynamic stage shared by artists, writers, combatants, war refugees… and even pirates. In all, the book brings together 18 essays on “fascinating” people - using the adjective used in the official description of the work - who lived or passed by Macao in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, when the territory was still under Portuguese administration.
 
China from the 1920s, seen by Wallis Simpson
 
One of the famous figures that lived temporarily in China was Wallis Simpson, an American socialite whose marriage to Eduardo VIII made her one of the most commented (and controversial) women in the history of British royalty. His passage through Shanghai and Beijing at age 28, when his first marriage, later led to myths about the propagated “Chinese Dossier”, a supposed compilation of the alleged sex and criminal scandals that he would have committed in China “chaotic, impending explosion” from the 1920s.
The book “Her Lotus Year”, released by Paul French last year and also presented at yesterday's Rota das Letras session, helps to lighten some of the preconceived ideas that, stressed, remain perpetuated by British tabloids. Through the lens of Wallis Simpson and his infamous trips across the East, the author describes a still “very boring” Hong Kong region; a vibrant Shanghai city, the boil of jazz bars and nightlife; And an ancient bease, with temples and ancestral stories in each stone, whereby Windson's future duchess "fell in love aesthetically."
At the presentation event, the author revealed that the starting point for the creation of this work was not Wallis Simpson, but his own fascination with the “crazy years” of China - more specifically, about the Full Years of 1924 and 1925. “In 1911, we have the end of the Qing dynasty and the beginning of the first republic. Chaotic, ”he pointed out, citing the clashes between warlords, Hong Kong strikes, and internal conflicts between Sun Yat Sen's revolutionary forces." That's when China could have exploded and it seems to the central Asia we know today. "
The name of the Windsor Duchess was essential to boosting a book that, at its heart, is a deep investigation into the fragmented China of the second decade of the twentieth century. “Let's imagine this book:‘ Paul French, China 1924 ’. No one would buy it, no? But Wallis Simpson is well known to the public; everyone has heard of his story,” he admitted. If they interpret it as "the greatest love story ever told" or "the account of how a woman almost destroyed the British royal family," it depends on the perspectives. Still, the time space in which the socialite remained in China-precisely between September 1924 and September 2025-puts it “at the center of the hurricane” of the country and definitely impacts its reputation in Europe.
"The fact that he was American and divorced twice was not enough: they had to invent something more. It is the 1930s, where stories are told about Fu Manchu and the" yellow danger ". It is said that no white woman must go to China, which is in danger of losing their moral measure. It is in this context that they call" Chinese dossier, "which in reality never existed," the author explains. Instead, a “whisper campaign” was orchestrated that suggested a series of criminal activities allegedly carried out in their passages by Shanghai and Beijing: from opium to a session of pornographic photographs with Victor Sassoon, leaving a series of shrewd heart weddings and hearts. None of these rumors had a solid foundation, nor was it able to fulfill the goal of stabilizing the monarchy: Eduardo VIII abdicated the throne, married the woman they wanted and the couple was exiled in France. Wallis Simpson's reputation, yes, "was stained for a century."
The books “Destination Macau” and “Her Lotus Year” by Paul French are already available in Macau and can be purchased at the Portuguese Bookstore. Among some of the author's most celebrated works, currently based in Shanghai, include the 'bestseller' “midnight in Beijing”, “City of Devils” and “Carl Crow”.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Fatal point 2025.03.31</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/31/ponto-fatal-2025-03-31/</link><description>Writer Paul French presented his two new books, “Destination Macau” and “Her Lotus Year”, before a full audience on the last day of the 14th Macao Literary Festival - Rota das Letras. The first, released in 2025, is the third entrance to the “Destination” collection, centered on previous editions of Shanghai and Beijing, and traces a vivid portrait of the social, cultural and political plans of the Macao region of the nineteenth and twentieth centuries.
 
British author Paul French presented yesterday on the last day of the 14th Macao Literary Festival, his latest book, “Destination Macau”, the third entrance to the relevant western world's book series that visited China. At the launch event, which featured an crowded audience, the writer and historian also took the opportunity to expand the themes of the work “Her Lotus Years”, edited last year.
After the big metropolises of Beijing and Shanghai, Paul French had several options on the table as to the region to explore in the third volume of the “Destination” collection. With the restrictions of the covid-19 pandemic in 2020, the author was forced to interrupt the “usual trips to China” and to proceed to a lonely introspection about what he knew from the Asia. It was Macao - a region that, recognizes, does not occupy a place of such prominence in world bookstores as the destinations previously chosen - continually flowing into their reflections, perhaps because it is a destination that always faced as a "refuge" conducive to daydreams and inspiration.
"Macau has always been a place where I liked to sit down, look out the window and dream. In addition, I had already written some stories about Macau for South China Morning Post and I thought it could expand some topics of interest," he recalled, confessing that another factors that weighed on the choice was something stereotyped and pejorative of the British about the old Portuguese colonia. "English sensational journalism has created an image of Macau as Mediterranean representation in Asia - and when the English describe something like 'Mediterranean', they never understand it as a compliment," he confessed.
The nineteenth-century English writers-and later the Americans-described Macao as a “troprarian and retrograde” region, where the “successful and stirring” personalities of Hong Kong or the interior of China came to “release tension”. According to the author, this negative representation of the Portuguese presence intended to establish a comparison with British domain in Hong Kong, which the English authors of the time self-proclaimed as “the upper and most successful version” of European occupation in Asia.
“Destination Macau” comes to demystify this idea by painting ancient macao as a dynamic stage shared by artists, writers, combatants, war refugees… and even pirates. In all, the book brings together 18 essays on “fascinating” people - using the adjective used in the official description of the work - who lived or passed by Macao in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, when the territory was still under Portuguese administration.
 
China from the 1920s, seen by Wallis Simpson
 
One of the famous figures that lived temporarily in China was Wallis Simpson, an American socialite whose marriage to Eduardo VIII made her one of the most commented (and controversial) women in the history of British royalty. His passage through Shanghai and Beijing at age 28, when his first marriage, later led to myths about the propagated “Chinese Dossier”, a supposed compilation of the alleged sex and criminal scandals that he would have committed in China “chaotic, impending explosion” from the 1920s.
The book “Her Lotus Year”, released by Paul French last year and also presented at yesterday's Rota das Letras session, helps to lighten some of the preconceived ideas that, stressed, remain perpetuated by British tabloids. Through the lens of Wallis Simpson and his infamous trips across the East, the author describes a still “very boring” Hong Kong region; a vibrant Shanghai city, the boil of jazz bars and nightlife; And an ancient bease, with temples and ancestral stories in each stone, whereby Windson's future duchess "fell in love aesthetically."
At the presentation event, the author revealed that the starting point for the creation of this work was not Wallis Simpson, but his own fascination with the “crazy years” of China - more specifically, about the Full Years of 1924 and 1925. “In 1911, we have the end of the Qing dynasty and the beginning of the first republic. Chaotic, ”he pointed out, citing the clashes between warlords, Hong Kong strikes, and internal conflicts between Sun Yat Sen's revolutionary forces." That's when China could have exploded and it seems to the central Asia we know today. "
The name of the Windsor Duchess was essential to boosting a book that, at its heart, is a deep investigation into the fragmented China of the second decade of the twentieth century. “Let's imagine this book:‘ Paul French, China 1924 ’. No one would buy it, no? But Wallis Simpson is well known to the public; everyone has heard of his story,” he admitted. If they interpret it as "the greatest love story ever told" or "the account of how a woman almost destroyed the British royal family," it depends on the perspectives. Still, the time space in which the socialite remained in China-precisely between September 1924 and September 2025-puts it “at the center of the hurricane” of the country and definitely impacts its reputation in Europe.
"The fact that he was American and divorced twice was not enough: they had to invent something more. It is the 1930s, where stories are told about Fu Manchu and the" yellow danger ". It is said that no white woman must go to China, which is in danger of losing their moral measure. It is in this context that they call" Chinese dossier, "which in reality never existed," the author explains. Instead, a “whisper campaign” was orchestrated that suggested a series of criminal activities allegedly carried out in their passages by Shanghai and Beijing: from opium to a session of pornographic photographs with Victor Sassoon, leaving a series of shrewd heart weddings and hearts. None of these rumors had a solid foundation, nor was it able to fulfill the goal of stabilizing the monarchy: Eduardo VIII abdicated the throne, married the woman they wanted and the couple was exiled in France. Wallis Simpson's reputation, yes, "was stained for a century."
The books “Destination Macau” and “Her Lotus Year” by Paul French are already available in Macau and can be purchased at the Portuguese Bookstore. Among some of the author's most celebrated works, currently based in Shanghai, include the 'bestseller' “midnight in Beijing”, “City of Devils” and “Carl Crow”.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 08:38:15</pubDate></item></channel></rss>