<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/pc-chines-afasta-antigo-presidente-de-empresa-aeroespacial/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>China says he was always on the side of peace on the 3rd anniversary of the war in Ukraine</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/china-diz-que-sempre-esteve-do-lado-da-paz-no-3-o-aniversario-da-guerra-na-ucrania/</link><description>China said yesterday that it has always been “on the side of peace” and will continue to work to “build a consensus” that end the war in Ukraine, which has been going on for three years.
 
"Since the beginning of this crisis, we have been working and maintaining communication with the parties involved, with the aim of building a consensus on peace," said Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian, in conference of the press.
The spokesman added that China has always been "on the side of peace" and maintained a "just and objective" position, which has been "clear and consistent from the beginning."
China greeted conversations between US President Donald Trump and Russian President Vladimir Putin to negotiate a way out of the war in Ukraine, a process in which Beijing wants to continue to play "a constructive role."
According to Chinese spokesmen, the Asian country hopes to “maintain communication with all parties involved” and will continue to “effort” to play “a constructive role” in resolving the conflict.
In recent weeks, Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi has said China's position on conflict has been “rational” and that Beijing wants to “establish a balanced, effective and sustainable security framework for Europe, aiming at a peace lasting ”. "China wants to work with all parties, including Europe," said Wang.
Since the beginning of the war in Ukraine, China has maintained an ambiguous position on conflict, appealing to respect for the “territorial integrity of all countries”, including Ukraine, and attention by “legitimate concerns of all countries” reference to Russia.
Beijing was opposed to "unilateral" sanctions against Moscow and called on "decancing and a political solution." However, the West accused China of supporting Russia's military campaign, something the Asian country has always denied.
China has sent diplomatic representatives to the region and presented peace initiatives, such as the plan it elaborated with Brazil last year, which did not include the removal of Russian troops and was rejected by Kiev.
 
Taiwan reaffirms humanitarian commitment
 
Taiwan said yesterday that he will continue to cooperate with the international community to provide humanitarian assistance to Ukraine, in the context of the third anniversary of the Russian invasion. In a statement, local authorities stressed that the Taiwanese government remains “very attentive” to the development of the conflict between Russia and Ukraine and that “follows” the positions of the United States, Russia and Europe, in relation to possible negotiations of peace.
Taiwan's diplomacy also instructed his diplomatic missions abroad to collect “relevant political information”, aiming to “respond in time” to changes in the international geopolitical situation, read in the official statement. "As a democratic nation and responsible member of the region, Taiwan maintains a firm determination to defend himself and continues to reinforce his defensive abilities to resolutely safeguard his national sovereignty and the freedom of his people," the Ministry of Foreign Affairs said. "Taiwan will continue to work closely with all countries that share the same ideas to jointly face interference and threats from authoritarian regimes," the same note added.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25T07:08:57+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau and Angola will sign agreement to combat money laundering</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/macau-e-angola-vao-assinar-acordo-para-combater-lavagem-de-dinheiro/</link><description>Macau and Angola will sign an agreement to exchange information from forming money laundering and terrorism financing, the government announced
 
According to an order published yesterday in an official bulletin, the memorandum of understanding for the exchange of information regarding the combat of capital laundering, associated preceding crimes, terrorism financing and financing the proliferation of weapons of massive destruction will be signed with the unit of Financial Information of the Republic of Angola.
According to the order, signed by the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, on February 14, the Secretary for Security, Wong Sio Chak, can delegate this mission to the Commander General of Unit Police Services (SPU), Leong Man Cheong.
The Macao Information Office (GIF), responsible for combating capital bleaching, financing to terrorism and proliferation of weapons of massive destruction, is under the protection of SPU.
In March 2022, an annual US State Department report designated Macao as one of the main points of worldwide capital bleaching.
According to the annual GIF report, Macao became in 2019 the only member of the Asia Pacific group against the laundering of capital (Gafi) that fulfilled “all 40 international standards” on the prevention of money laundering, terrorism financing and the proliferation of weapons of mass destruction.
Angola was added to the Gafafi 'gray list' in 2024, after falling short of his legal and financial regulation regimes.
Gafi, an intergovernmental organization, establishes international standards in the field of struggle of capital laundering, the financing of terrorism and the proliferation of weapons of massive destruction.
The 'gray list' identifies the countries that are actively working with Gafafi to resolve strategic deficiencies in these areas.
The GIF signed agreements for the exchange of information with 33 countries and territories, including the Portuguese Judicial Police Financial Information Unit, in 2008, the Central Bank of Timor-Leste Financial Information Unit in 2018 and in 2019 , the Brazilian financial activity control board and the Cape Verde Financial Information Unit.
The number of suspicious transactions recorded in Macao casinos reached a new record by 2024 due to the recovery of the economy and tourism, GIF told Lusa in early February.
According to data released on January 15 by the GIF, the six casino operators in Macau submitted, totaling 3,837 suspected capital bleaching or terrorism financing transactions in 2024, 11.8% more than in the year previous. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-25T07:09:05+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China performs real fire exercises in the Gulf of Tonkin after Hanoi marks border</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/china-realiza-exercicios-de-fogo-real-no-golfo-de-tonkin-apos-hanoi-assinalar-fronteira/</link><description>China said yesterday she started royal -fire naval exercises near Tonkin's Gulf, a few days after Vietnam announced a new line that separates the territory between the two countries in that maritime space.
China's sea security administration said the exercises would focus on the Beibu Gulf area, closer to the Chinese side of the Tonkin Gulf, and would take place until Thursday night.
The administration no longer gave details, but the exercises follow an announcement made last week by Vietnam, which established a base line used to calculate the width of its territorial waters in the Gulf of Tonkin.
The state newspaper Vietnam News reported that the line is in accordance with the United Nations Convention on Sea Law and provides “a solid legal basis to safeguard and exercise sovereignty, sovereign rights and the jurisdiction of Vietnam”. Vietnam did not publicly respond to the Chinese exercises.
China and Vietnam have long been maritime agreement that governs the Gulf of Tonkin, but have a difference in the neighboring Southern Sea of ​​China on the Spratly and Paracel islands and the adjacent marine zones.
China has been becoming increasingly assertive in its claims and in October assaulted 10 Vietnamese fishermen near the Paracel Islands, three of which suffered members in the members.
In addition to Vietnam, China's claims also shock with those of the Philippines, Malaysia, Brunei and Taiwan, while Indonesia has also participated in violent clashes with the Chinese coast guard and fishing fleets in the waters around the Natuna islands.
Tensions have been particularly high with the Philippines, with regular clashes between the two countries. Recently, a Chinese navy helicopter flew less than three meters from a Philippine Patrol plane over the Southern China Sea, near the disputed Scarborough Atol, off the northwest of the Philippines.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25T07:08:53+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Woman transferred to intensive care due to flu</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/mulher-transferida-para-os-cuidados-intensivos-devido-a-gripe/</link><description>Health services reported yesterday that a 48 -year -old resident of Macao had to be taken to the Conde de São Januário Hospital Intensive Care Unit due to a flu infection. The woman is considered serious.
The woman, with several chronic diseases, resorted last week to a medical institution for having a fever and cough, having been diagnosed with influenza A and treated with Tamiflu. Days later, the symptoms got worse and shortered, and headed for the public hospital, where he was diagnosed with flu and pneumonia complications. The patient was not vaccinated against seasonal flu.
Health services say that after the holidays of the Lunar New Year, there was a descent of the number of influenza cases in Macao. However, it is expected that the flu activity will remain at a certain level of prevalence during February, so they appeal to residents to remain vigilant.
“Residents who have not yet been vaccinated against influenza, especially pregnant women, children, the elderly and those with chronic diseases, which are more likely to suffer serious complications or death after influenza virus infection, should be vaccinated with As soon as possible against the flu, ”says the press release for health services.
Sanitary authorities also appeal that citizens are vaccinated against seasonal flu and COVID-19, which maintain good personal hygiene, cover their mouths and nose when they sneeze or cough, which maintain good air ventilation in closed spaces and who wear a mask when they have symptoms, for example.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25T07:07:07+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines and France perform combat exercise in the Southern Sea of ​​China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/filipinas-e-franca-efectuam-exercicio-de-combate-conjunto-no-mar-do-sul-da-china/</link><description>The French nuclear propulsion aircraft carrier and the accompanying war ships performed this weekend combat exercises with the Philippine forces in the Southern Sea of ​​China.
 
Charles de Gaulle docked on Friday in Subic Bay, a former US naval base northwest of Manila, after more than two months of Detachment in Indo-Pacific.
Over the weekend, the aircraft carrier performed anti-submarine war exercises and air combat training in the Southern Sea of ​​China, the Philippine and French authorities said. "We intend to deepen our cooperation with the regional partners with whom we share common values, such as respect for international law and the guarantee of freedom of navigation in shared maritime spaces," said the French ambassador in Manila, Marie Fontanel, in a conference of Press held on Sunday on the Charles de Gaulle flight deck.
Fontanel spoke close to several Rafale supersonic fighters, a robbery helicopter and a surveillance plane. The flags of France and the Philippines emerged side by side. "Our presence is a constant reminder of the importance of promoting and protecting what joins us all - international law and cooperation," Fontanel said.
In 2024, the French Navy first highlighted a frigate to participate in a joint navigation with homologous forces from the United States and the Philippines in the waters disputed with China and nearby.
The operation was part of the largest annual combat exercises performed in several years by the American and Philippines Allied forces in the Philippines. The exercises, known as Balikatan (“shoulder to shoulder”), involved more than 16,000 military personnel.
At the time, China strongly criticized the exercises, stating that the Philippines were joining countries outside Asia, in reference to the US and security allies, and warned that the exercises could instigate confrontations and undermine regional stability.
Recent and ongoing military detachments in France in the Philippines underline their “commitment to regional security and the common goal of reinforcing maritime cooperation in Indo-Pacific,” said the Filipine Armed Forces spokesman, Colonel Xerxes Trinidad .
Charles de Gaulle, the world's only nuclear propulsion aircraft carrier, beyond those of the US Navy, led a attack group that included three destructive war ships and an oil replenishment ship, French authorities said.
France has been reinforcing military commitments to the Philippines and other Southeast Asian nations that are in dispute with China due to Southern China Sea sovereignty, a fundamental route for world trade and security.
China is against the presence of foreign forces, especially the US army and its allies in the Southern Sea of ​​China, which Beijing claims almost in its entirety.
Beijing's claims overlap with those of the Philippines, Vietnam, Malaysia, Brunei and Taiwan. Indonesia has also participated in violent clashes with the Chinese Coast Guard and fishing fleets in the Natuna waters.
In late 2023, French Defense Minister Sébastien Leconnu and Filipino Defense Secretary Gilberto Teodoro signed an agreement to reinforce military cooperation and joint commitments.
France and Philippines began conversations in 2024 about a defense pact that would allow each country's troops to exercise the other's territory. French negotiators delivered a project according to the Philippine counterparts to start negotiations. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-25T07:09:34+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Construction works of the entrances and exits of two east line stations begin soon</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/obras-de-construcao-das-entradas-e-saidas-de-duas-estacoes-da-linha-leste-comecam-em-breve/</link><description>The construction of the entrances and exits of the ES1 and ES2 segment of the northern segment of the east of the Light Metro, which will be located along the northern avenue of the Hippadrom and Avenida da Ponte da Friendship, in the zone of 'Avenue are Mudflat '.
According to the Directorate of Public Works (DSOP), it will be necessary to occupy a part of the tour and to seal the sports facilities zone to ensure the safe passage of pedestrians. Given the travel of residents and the business of traders in the area, the construction of the entrances and exits of the stations will be performed phased.
Recently, DSOP has provided clarification on the information related to the work, the execution plan and the main management measures, with the representatives of the General Union of the Macao residents' associations and the area's commercial establishments, among others. According to the body, "representatives of associations and commercial establishments reported that they understand the need for execution of the work and agree with the prohibition and execution of the work phased to reduce impact." In addition, the representatives of the associations suggested to the authorities to, during the execution of the work, to take into account the needs of travel and parking of vehicles of residents and reserve the space sufficient, to ensure that the displacement of residents is not affected. DSOP says it will continue to optimize various measures for the execution of the work.
The construction work of the northern segment of the east line of the Light Metro began in August 2023, the planning of 'Mudflat' and the peripheral geotechnical prospecting, and entered the construction phase and outputs and exits of the stations.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25T07:07:04+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan leader considers Trump's return is the opportunity for the island</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/lider-de-taiwan-considera-que-regresso-de-trump-e-oportunidade-para-a-ilha/</link><description>Taiwan's leader argued that Donald Trump's return to the White House should be seen as "an opportunity" to reinforce the island's position, in the face of growing tensions between Taipei and Beijing.
William Lai made the statements during a meeting with Parliamentarians of the Progressive Democratic Party (DPP) in power, said the secretary general of the Legislative Group of DPP, Rosalia Wu Szu-Yao, in statements released by the news agency Taiwanese state -owned CNA.
According to Wu, Lai appealed to party legislators to face possible political changes under the Trump administration as "an opportunity" and not as "a challenge," despite the uncertainties arising from the Magnata's return to the oval room. The Taiwanese leader also stressed that Taiwan's economic and national security teams are “fully prepared” to respond to “any changes” in US politics.
These statements arise in a context of uncertainty about Trump's commitment to Taiwan's defense. The Republican leader, who intensified military aid to Taipé during his first term (2017-2021), has been very critical of the island in recent months, stating that Taiwan has usurped the American semiconductor industry and should Pay Washington for your defense.
In this context, Lai said on February 14 that he would seek a “mutually beneficial” solution with the United States following Trump threats to impose rates on Taiwanese semiconductors, which are fundamental to US companies such as Nvidia , Apple and AMD.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25T07:07:23+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>PR TIMORENSE IN VIETNAME to participate in the Southeast Asia Nations Forum</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/pr-timorense-no-vietname-para-participar-em-forum-das-nacoes-do-sudeste-asiatico/</link><description>The president of Timor-Leste, José Ramos-Horta, traveled yesterday to Vietnam to participate in the Future Forum of the Association of Southeast Asia Nations (Asean) and to strengthen regional cooperation relations.
"The ASEAN Future Forum represents a crucial platform for dialogue and collaboration as we work to build a more integrated and resilient Asian Southwest," said the Timorese President, quoted in a press release.
According to José Ramos-Horta, Timor-Leste's participation in that forum demonstrates the country's commitment to “regional cooperation” and the availability to “contribute significantly to the shared view of the Asean for sustainable development and prosperity”.
"As we advance in our adhesion process, we are committed to working closely with our neighbors to face common challenges and take advantage of opportunities for collective growth," added the head of state.
During the visit to Vietnam, which ends Wednesday, the Nobel Peace Prize will hold bilateral meetings with Vietnamese President Luong Cuong and the Secretary-General of the Vietname Communist Party, to Lam, to “reinforce the ties diplomatic and “deepen regional cooperation and development”.
At Asean's future forum, José Ramos-Horta, who traveled accompanied by a delegation from the Timorese Foreign Ministry, will give a speech at the opening ceremony and participate in a question and answers session.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25T07:07:21+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Registered more than 4,000 infringements to the tobacco control law in 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/registadas-mais-de-4-000-infraccoes-a-lei-do-controlo-do-tabaco-em-2024/</link><description>Over the past year, authorities have detected more than 4,000 cases of violation of the provisions of the smoking control law. There were also 47 violations of the alcohol control regime by minors. In 2024, 259,081 inspections were carried out to various establishments in the context of smoking prevention and alcohol availability to minors. The restoration establishments were the ones that recorded the most infringements.
 
Last year, the authorities registered more than 4,000 violations of the smoking prevention and control regime and 47 infringements to the prevention and control of alcohol consumption by minors, health services indicated yesterday.
Regarding smoking, health services and the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP), the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI), the Directorate of Inspection and Coordination of Games (DICJ), Customs Services (SA ) Accounting 3,941 cases of illegal smoke, 138 cases of electronic cigarette transport for macao entry and exit, 126 suspected cases of violation of other provisions, Namely, the non -posting of the tummy prohibitionbans, in the places provided for by the law and the non -posting the notice of prohibition of sale of tobacco products, to children under 18 in the places of sale.
The restoration establishments were the ones that recorded the most infringements, in total, 604 cases (15.3%), followed by casinos, 531 cases (13.5%), parks, gardens and leisure zones, 361 cases ( 9.2%) and, among others. DICJ, in collaboration with health services, made 709 inspections to casinos, having detected 531 cases of people to smoke in forbidden places.
Regarding the control of alcohol consumption in 2024, there were then 47 suspected cases of infringement, 11 of which involved the sale or availability of alcoholic beverages to minors, and other cases related to various sales establishments or availability of drinks Alcoholics who did not affix the for sale or availability of alcoholic beverages to minors.
It is recalled that, according to the prevention and control of alcohol consumption by minors, the availability of alcohol to minors, both commercial and non-commercial purposes, is illegal and can be punished with a fine up to 20,000 patacas. If the destics are not affixed by commercial establishments, fines may be applied up to 200,000 patacas.
In the context of smoking control and prevention of alcohol consumption by minors, the authorities last year, a total of 259,081 inspections to establishments, which makes an average of 708 inspections per day.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25T07:07:12+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Falling the demand for offices in China should get worse in 2025, analysts say</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/queda-da-procura-por-escritorios-na-china-deve-agravar-se-em-2025-dizem-analistas/</link><description>The reduction of demand in the office market in China should persist this year, compared to the exodus of foreign companies, in a period of slowdown in the second largest economy world, analysts said.
 
US law firm Cleary Gottlieb Steen &amp; Hamilton became one of the latest companies to leave China last week. The company said it will end the office in Fortune Financial Center in July, a busy Business Zone of Beijing.
Also last week, a Blackrock background, the world's largest active manager, said he could not find a buyer for two office towers at the Waterfront Place in Lujiazui's financial district in Shanghai, even after having offered a discount 30%.
“For multinationals in general, [the retreat] is the result of multiple factors, [and] the main one is their profitability,” said Guo Shan, partner at Hutong Research, an independent consulting firm for multinational companies in China, quoted by the Hong Kong South China Morning Post (SCMP).
Guo said the persistent decline of profits led to cost reduction measures by foreign companies.
Foreign industrial companies' profits fell 1.7%last year after a drop of 6.7%and 9.5%, respectively, in 2023 and 2022, he added, citing data from the National Chinese Statistics Office. "For law firms, geopolitical risk may have been a bigger problem," said Guo.
According to the Dealogic Research Unit, the activity of mergers and acquisitions in China has been registering a decreasing trend in the last five years, since the COVID-19 pandemic. Last year, the total value of mergers and acquisition businesses was less than half of the $ 533 billion generated by 2020.
"The office market is a barometer for the service industry and is closely linked to the flow and reflux of the macroeconomic environment," said Vincent Li, a research team of Savills, a real estate consultant, quoted by SCMP.
“Regardless of being a state-owned company, an Internet giant or a foreign company, due to external uncertainty, cost reduction and improving efficiency become a prerequisite and the income of office is, without Doubt, one of the largest and most obvious expenses to cut, ”he said.
In Beijing's central business area, where there are reference points such as China World Trade Center, China Central Place and Beijing Kerry Center, headquarters such as Deutsche Bank and McKinsey, the vacancy rate rose to about 16 % at the end of last year, compared to 10% in 2019, according to Li. Income, in turn, fell to less than 300 yuan per Square meter per month, compared to 365 yuan before the pandemic, Li said.
In Shanghai, where the presence of international companies is even stronger, 22.1% of the office space was vacant, according to a report by real estate consultant CBRE.
Although a 5% and 10% vacancy rate indicates a “relatively healthy market”, the rate in the office segment in 10 large mains in mainland China reached a “dangerous” 20% level, since demand failed to follow The offer, said Savills, in a report widespread this month. The consultant stated that, at national level, the unemployment rate should increase 3.2% this year.
The eviction rate could reach 25.2% in major cities and 34.8% in secondary cities, by the end of the year, said Savills, adding that the average income in the 10 main cities should fall up to 6%, in a market where Tenants are increasingly negotiating power. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-25T07:08:57+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Irregularities practiced by taxi drivers tripled in January</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/irregularidades-praticadas-por-taxistas-triplicaram-em-janeiro/</link><description>In the first month of the year, there were 187 infractions committed by taxi drivers: an exponential increase of 206.56% compared to the January 2024 data. 105 cases in 2022 for 870 in 2024. Last year's monthly average of 72.5 cases per month, it has been exceeded by January numbers 2025.
 
The irregularities practiced by taxi drivers tripled earlier this year. According to statistical traffic data released by the Public Security Police (CPSP) body, in January 187 taxi drivers were registered, which reveals an increase of 206.56% compared to the 61 irregularities recorded in the same month of 2024.
Of the 187 cases accounted for by CPSP, most of them (126) relate to instances in which taxi drivers did not wait in order of arrival in the taxi squares. Thus, a 3050% aggravation of last year's same year's same month, in which only 4 cases of the genre were worsened. Police authorities also verified 6 cases of abusive collection and 32 of refusal of transport, representing a 200% and 6.67% increase compared to January last year.
In all 2024, 870 irregularities practiced by taxi drivers were detected, which translates into a monthly average of 72.5. Comparing this number with the one registered in January 2025, there is an increase in the order of 158%. The trend of recent years has been, moreover, frankly growing: since 2019 that so many taxi drivers have not been accounted for, a number that decreased dramatically from 2020 with pandemic restrictions and constraints in urban mobility.
According to the same report as CPSP, the number of road accidents involving almost double pawns in January, with an increase of 91.67% compared to the same period. On the other hand, the number of deaths and injuries resulting from these accidents has reduced: no deaths have not yet been accounted for in this context, and the number of injuries (almost all without hospitalization) descended 3.44%.
There is also a growth of 51.54% in reported cases of illegal parking lots in places of tariff parking or parking meters and 74.81% in their blocking.
Despite the increases already mentioned, the generality of irregularities in traffic and the offenses committed by drivers decreased by January last year in different categories, from the use of mobile phones during driving (less 41.29%) to the disrespect of pawns by the rules by the rules of traffic when crossing the treadmills (less 67.68%).
The data released by the authorities also show that, in January this year, the infractions related to the road traffic law and the Road Code regulation generated a value of 16.1 million patacas in fines - ie a reduction of 6, 68% compared to the amount of 17.3 million patacas collected with fines from last year's same temporal window. In all 2024, the fines were 189.8 million patacas.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25T07:09:18+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Alibaba will invest 380 billion in AI and cloud computing over the next three years</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/alibaba-vai-investir-380-mil-milhoes-em-ia-e-computacao-em-nuvem-nos-proximos-tres-anos/</link><description>The Chinese giant of electronic trade Alibaba has announced that it will invest 380 billion Yuan in Artificial Intelligence (AI) and cloud computing infrastructures.
 
According to a statement widespread by the company through its News Portal Alizila, the announced amount exceeds the combined investment of the last decade in these two fields, identified by the group as strategic, along with the traditional e -commerce business.
When presenting the results of the third fiscal quarter, on Friday, the group's CEO Eddie Wu revealed that the company intended to make “greater investment” in areas such as AI and cloud data services, although not had specified amounts.
According to Alibaba, the measure "reinforces its commitment to long -term technological innovation" and "underlines the company's bet on AI -driven growth and its role as a leading [data services in] cloud."
At the conference with analysts who followed the presentation of the results, Wu stated that AI is a “unique opportunity in a generation” and noted that achieving artificial general intelligence (AGI, a type of AI that would equal human intelligence) will be the main objective in the long run of the company.
In his opinion, AI's ability to replicate human labor, both intellectual and physical, “could remodel” industries worldwide, leading “significant transformations” in economy and technology.
The CEO recalled that a growing part of the AI ​​-generated data will be processed and distributed through cloud networks, positioning Alibaba AI subsidiary, Alibaba Cloud, as "a key infrastructure supplier."
During the third fiscal quarter (between October and December), the adjusted revenue of the cloud intelligence subsidiary increased by 11% over the previous year, while the IMA revenue related to AI experienced its sixth consecutive three -digit growth quarter .
In recent weeks, Alibaba has announced a pact to incorporate its QWEN model into Apple's iPhones in China, and there has been speculation that it may be interested in becoming investor at Deepseek, the AI ​​Chinese platform that shook the sector. "Looking to the future, the growth of revenues in the cloud intelligence division will continue to accelerate, driven by AI," Wu explained on Friday in a message that accompanied the dissemination of the company's results, sent to the Stock Exchange Values From Hong Kong, who exceeded the expectations of analysts.
In the last quarter, Alibaba increased the turnover of 8% and profits in 239%, in homologous terms.
Following yesterday's announcement, the actions of the technology company quoted in Hong Kong rose 0.14%during the morning session, placing the appreciation since the beginning of the year by 70%, although they are still less than half (-53 , 5%) of peak reached in October 2020. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-25T07:08:55+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Leadership groups serve to implement Xi Jinping's “important speeches”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/grupos-de-lideranca-servem-para-implementar-os-importantes-discursos-de-xi-jinping/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai presided yesterday to the first work meetings of the newly created Leadership Groups of the Public Administration Reform and the Leadership Group to promote the construction of the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin. The chief executive indicated that these groups serve to “implement the spirits consecrated in the important speeches of President XI Jinping, given during the visit to Macau at the end of last year, raise the capacity and level of public management of Mashere and reinforce high level orientation and intersectory coordination ”.
At the meeting of the Public Administration Reform Leadership Group, the continuity of raising the capacity for governance and the level of services to the public was discussed, namely the optimization of rights, responsibilities, functions, structure and personnel regime of public services, the Improvement of management and leadership personnel, deepening the construction of the electronic government and the expansion of electronic services to facilitate the population and companies.
At the Leadership Group's working meeting to promote the construction of the in -depth cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin, Sam Hou Fai asked the secretaries to strive to reinforce coordination in different areas of the Government of MSAR, to focus on Main tasks in various areas, to boost a convenient circulation of qualified paintings, capital and goods in Hengqin, join the new positioning Strategic “Macau + Hengqin” and promote high quality the completion of the second phase goals and tasks of the in -depth cooperation zone.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25T07:07:21+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Xi tells Putin that he is "happy to see efforts" to end the war</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/xi-diz-a-putin-que-esta-feliz-por-ver-esforcos-para-por-fim-a-guerra/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping told Russian homologist Vladimir Putin yesterday, who is happy to see that Russia and other countries are making "positive efforts" to end the war in Ukraine. "China is pleased to see that Russia and relevant parts are making positive efforts to end this crisis," Xi said in a telephone conversation, which takes place on the third anniversary of the Ukraine war. Quoted by the Official News Agency Xinhua, Xi also said that the ties between China and Russia have a “strong internal driving force” and a “unique strategic value”, and that the two countries are “two good neighbors” and “true friends ”, Which support each other in search of a“ common development ”.
The Chinese leader added that the bilateral relationship “is not directed against third parties, nor will it be influenced by anyone”, stressing that ties will continue to develop “easily” and “will help mutual development, injecting stability and positive energy into international relations ”. According to Xinhua, Putin said he is committed to "eliminating the deep causes of conflict" between Russia and Ukraine in order to "achieve a sustainable and lasting peace solution."
China greeted conversations between Putin and US President Donald Trump to negotiate a way out of war, a process in which Beijing wants to play “a constructive role,” according to his spokesmen, keeping communication “with all parts ”. In recent weeks, Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi has ensured that China's position on conflict has been "rational" and that Beijing wants to "establish a security staff for Europe."</description><pubDate>2025-02-25T07:08:55+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Fire in the lake building forces the removal of 20 people and takes two to the hospital</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/incendio-no-edificio-do-lago-obriga-a-retirada-de-20-pessoas-e-leva-duas-ao-hospital/</link><description>A fire launched in block 5 of the Lake Building and forced yesterday morning the withdrawal of 20 people. Two residents, 79 and 51 years old, who were semiconscient, were sent to hospital. The fire was shown by a short circuit in a television. The Fire Department sent 54 firefighters and 12 rescue vehicles to the site, admitting that elevators' malfunction, water supply and wind added difficulty to rescue. The Institute of Social Action promises support to the residents involved.
 
The lake building was the target of a fire yesterday morning, which forced the withdrawal of 20 residents and hospital assistance to two residents, aged 79 years of 51, who live in the fraction where the fire broke out. According to the Fire Department, women will have suffered tobacco inhalation and were found semiconscients, having been transferred to the Conde de São Januário hospital center to receive emergency medical services.
The fire launched on the 7th floor of Block 5 of the Lake Building and the preliminary investigation of the authorities indicates that the accident was caused by a short circuit in a television set in the living room of the fraction concerned.
The Fire Department was notified of the fire at 7:40 am and the fire was fully extinguished at 8:55 am. The apartment that gave rise to the fire was about 400 square meters and was "completely destroyed." Two other neighboring apartments were also involved, one of which has a burntwood door and the floor corridor was darkened due to smoke.
Speaking to Radio Macau in Chinese language, Lam Chon Sang, the 2nd commander of the Fire Department, stressed that the floor temperature was high when firefighters arrived at the scene, admitting that the rescue work was hampered by the damage in the elevators, for the water supply problem in the place and the force of the wind.
“Initially it was reported that the fire had triggered on the 10th floor and it really was in the 7th, it took some time to locate the correct position of the incident and, as the elevator was damaged, the team had to transport their equipment through Stairs, ”said the fire brigade spokesman. He added that the fraction door concerned was open and, due to the wind, the floor temperature “was quite high,” which made rescue operations difficult.
"It took some time to treat the water supply on site and it took about 15 minutes to open the fire hose and the fire was extinguished at 8:55 am," he said. The body confirmed that 54 firefighters and 12 relief vehicles were sent to the scene.
According to the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, some residents of the building indicated that the alarm bell did not sound and eventually came out after smelling the smoke and seen the emergency light of the corridor.
The Fire Department, however, said the alarm bell sounded when the team arrived at the scene, but residents of some units "may not have heard it due to their location."
The Lake Building, inaugurated in 2012 at Taipa, is one of the government's economic housing projects. The Institute of Social Action (IAS) guarantees that it is “very attentive” to the fire and were immediately sent to the social workers accompanied by workers from various social service institutions in the mud, with the aim of providing emotional support, advice and other necessary supports , according to the needs of residents. So far, no request for temporary accommodation services from residents involved has been received.
IAS calls for residents with needs to call 2826 1126 in order to obtain adequate services and supports. According to the body, workers from the Community Centers of the General Union of Macao residents, the Federation of Macao Workers' Associations and the General Association of Macao, to provide support.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25T07:06:10+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>T Theater organizes artists exchange between Portugal and Macau, in June, in the territory</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/t-theatre-organiza-intercambio-de-artistas-entre-portugal-e-macau-em-junho-no-territorio/</link><description>After a first phase in Lisbon, the “Next Step”, a performance residence program in performative arts, starts in mainland China and Macao, between June 18 and 27. Launched by T theater, in the territory, it is a project organized in partnership with the Parasite Association in Portugal.
 
At the beginning of February, at an initiative promoted by T theatre in Macao, two China Continental dancers, Wu Hui, Cantão, and Lin Yixing, from Beijing, were at Parasite Space in Lisbon, for a week of residence, which included studio sharing with other guest artists, a workshop and a public presentation. Integrated in “Next Step”, an exchange program in collaboration with the Parasite Association in Portugal, the second phase of this project will take place in mainland China, between 18 and 22 June, and in the territory, between 24 and 27 June.
João dos Santos Martins, from the parasite and co-cure association of “Next Step”, met artist Guo Rui, in 2018, when he participated in another project, also organized by T Theater in Macao. “They were trying to create an exchange platform in the region, a collaboration with people from Taiwan, Mongolia, Hong Kong, Continental China and there were some European guest artists,” says João dos Santos Martins to the end.
Guo Rui, a Canton-based artist who has been trying to establish calls in the Great Bay, again contacted him last year, proposing the creation of a dynamic of homes and exchange, which could be articulated in Portugal. Thus was born the “Next Step”, with the curation of these two artists. “The idea is to open axes of experimental thoughts and practices within contemporary dance, related to the very context of dance in China, which is traditionally closer to classic dance, traditional Chinese dance, more folkloric things and modern dance itself” , says the Portuguese choreographer.
 
The first phase of “Next Step”
 
In a first phase, following a call open to artists from mainland China, Macao and Hong Kong, five artists were chosen to go to Portugal, participate in an artistic exchange residence. They were: Lao Pui Lon (Macau), Lou Hio Mei (Macau), Zhu Rong (Shenzhen), Wu Hui (Canton) and Lin Yixing (Beijing). In the end, by a series of people people, only these last two artists were able to move to Lisbon.
In Lisbon, the residence was conceived “not only as a space to think about work, but to be in relation to others”, and it was, therefore, that the organizers invited three distinct Portuguese artistic projects to “spend two hours In a more theoretical sharing, which then unfolded in a more practical sharing, fostering the knowledge of the other, ”explains the Portuguese co-cure.
In addition to this session, the exchange also included a workshop, taught by these dancers in residence and attended by local artists, ending with a public presentation of the projects on February 1, and a living with people from the community. “A Yixing trabalha muito com memória de trauma, também pensando muito na relação que estabelecemos com o lugar”, explica. A sua performance começou no exterior, com o público dentro do estúdio a observar da janela, passando depois para o interior. “She climbed and had a dress, one of the dresses was full of stones, and these stones begin to compose a monument on the floor and are reactivated through a drawing on the floor and vocalization that create connections between the bodies of the past and the bodies of presente”, descreve.
On the other hand, Wu Hui's presentation “comes from a relationship or how to think of dance”, conceiving the choreography through “a relationship with the movement of plants and how to tension the ideas between the human and not human ”. In fact, explains João dos Santos Martins, the artist's work has been guided in this direction, also questioning the ideas of femininity.
After the residence of mainland China artists in Portugal, the Parasite Association has now launched a call, seeking to select the four residents in Portugal whose practice identifies in the field of contemporary dance or expanded choreography. "At this time, we are in the public call phase for artists living in Portugal to participate and, by the end of March, we will conclude this process," he says.
 
An idea of ​​Guo Rui
 
For dancer and curator Freelance, Guo Rui, invited by T Theater to organize this project, “Next Step” comes to support young and emerging artists. And, unlike a normal residence project that focuses a lot on the end result, is concerned about the creation process. “The center of this project is to promote a cultural exchange, helping young artists, showing different forms of conception,” he explains to the end point.
Highlighting the lack of “this kind of dance story in mainland China, as well as in Macao”, since here the “import of different techniques” occurs, sought to launch these young people in the search for new sources of creation. And here will try to promote a “self-organized practice” through online meetings.
With the residence in China to take place in two places in June - on the one hand, in Shenzhen or Canton (still deciding the final destination), as well as Macao - there will also be two public presentations. Still, it guarantees, the focus will be the process and interaction of artists with the inhabitants or students, rather than the final stage of sharing with the public. “As Macau has little audience, we also added a place in mainland China to have more public,” he explains.
There are, however, says Guo Rui, several hypotheses still open: the definitive place in mainland China and the possible collaboration with universities.
T theater is a space for non -profit performance in Macao, with the aim of promoting various forms of choreographing, exploring a wide range of body practices in different contexts, and encouraging local/regional artists to interact with international artists. In recent years, the T theater has been defending the diffusion of contemporary dance and experienced different forms of exchange between China and other countries.
In turn, the parasite is a non -profit association, whose occupation translates into the production and realization of artistic objects and cultural events where experimentation and critical discourse is privileged through research proposals where processes and products interact without distinction. To operate as a cooperative, it integrates four resident artists and each develops their work autonomously, although there is a sharing of production resources, working space and accounting, as well as mutual support. “We have made applications together and, since last year, we have a space in Lisbon called Parasite Space,” explains João dos Santos Martins.
Funded by the Culture Development Fund, the “Next Step” program focuses on encouraging and supporting marginalized and exploratory body practices, while providing a platform for exchange and sustainable development opportunities for the investigation and creation of experimental dance contemporary. Based on self-organized practices, during a week of residence, there are practice shares, individual investigations, workshops, lectures and sharing sessions with artists, as well as research presentations, in order to foster the development of individual practice of artists and promote dialogue and intercultural exchange.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Road accident during a shoot caused 12 injured</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/acidente-de-viacao-durante-uma-filmagem-provocou-12-feridos/</link><description>A driver lost control of the car during a shoot and ran over 12 people, also team members, all with slight injuries. Among the victims were four children aged between five and six. The road accident occurred yesterday afternoon on the sidewalk of Francisco António. The Public Security Police body ensures that the driver from the interior of China, who was not injured, legally led in Macao and will investigate the case and inspect the vehicle.
 
Twelve people from a film team were injured following a running over, caused by a member of the team driving a car on the seminary street and will have lost control of the vehicle's management.
The victims suffered mild injuries and, according to the Fire Department, were mainly bruises and abrasions. All were aware and in a stable situation when they were referred to Kiang Wu Hospital for treatment.
Among the 12 people are three men's and nine female victims, aged between five and 61. Four are children who are five to six years old. Regarding the place of origin, a five -year -old and a 42 -year -old woman are residents, nine come from the interior of China and one is a Singapore passport holder. Authorities said the case was also reported to the Directorate of Tourism Services.
Already the driver, 62 and from the continent, was not injured and passed the alcohol research exam. The man entered Macao yesterday and has a driving letter from the interior of the valid China. “Legally conducts in Macao,” said the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP).
At a press conference yesterday at the incident site, the police authorities revealed that the running over occurred at 2:23 pm, when an image -producing team was recording a movie.
“The car involved walked inside a closed area to the circulation of other cars, on the seminary street towards Aquino's Largo. The driver will have lost control of the vehicle and the car crashed in a seal before rushing to the sidewalk of Francisco António, ”explained Ma Chio Hong, head of the CPSP Traffic Department.
The official said that the sidewalk of Francisco António was not an area foreseen for car circulation and, at that time, the 12 wounded actors were resting in this alley and waiting for the filming.
Ma Chio Hong assured that after the accident, CPSP immediately sent the scene immediately to help maintain order and help the injured. The Fire Department said it had highlighted a fire service vehicle and five ambulances in response to the accident.
In this case, the CPSP Traffic Department will carry out an investigation based on the images of the surveillance system on site, the film's recording images and the driver's physical state. Authorities have already removed the vehicle in question of the site and will send the vehicle to the Inspection Center of the Services Directorate for traffic issues to perform an examination of its status of operation, “in order to determine if the vehicle specifications meet Legal requirements or whether there are other mechanical problems, ”he said.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25T07:08:16+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese PC departs former president of aerospace company</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/25/pc-chines-afasta-antigo-presidente-de-empresa-aeroespacial/</link><description>The Chinese Communist Party (CCP) expelled Tan Ruisong, former president of state -owned Aviation Industry Corporation of China (AVIC), following the expansion of the ongoing anti -corruption campaign in the country to aerospace and military sectors.
The Central Inspection and Disciplinary Commission (CCDI), the maximum anti -corruption body of the CCP, said Tan “took sides with the military sector for his personal benefit” and transformed his position into an illicit enrichment instrument.
The agency accused the former employee of accepting bribes and using his position to influence business restructuring and project contracts.
The investigation revealed that the former president “lost his ideals and convictions, betrayed his original aspirations” and violated the CCP's internal regulations by “accepting inappropriate banquets”, “involving power exchanges for sex” and when using their position to “seek benefits for third parties in the restructuring of companies and hiring engineering projects”.
Tan, who was secretary of the Communist Party at AVIC, is also accused of covering information on official investigations, giving illegally present and diverting large sums of public funds.
Following its expulsion of the CCP, the case was sent to the judicial authorities, which may lead to a criminal proceedings.
The announcement is part of the vast anti -corruption campaign launched by Chinese President Xi Jinping after ascending to power in 2012.
The campaign has intensified in recent years, with almost 900,000 employees punished in 2024.
The military sector became one of the investigators' leading focuses: CCP's leadership announced in December that it would “redouble their efforts” in a fight that resulted in the fall of army ministers and officers over the past year.
XI stressed the need to reinforce discipline and fight corruption within the Popular Liberation Army (ELP), to ensure that the Armed Forces are "absolutely loyal, absolutely pure and absolutely reliable."
The current campaign aims to civil servants, but also as many sectors as finances, tobacco and pharmacist products, among others, and follows to the launched in 2012, which was accompanied by greater repression, censorship and suspicions that the accusations make part of a maneuver to silence critics.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25T07:08:53+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>