<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/largo-da-se-sera-alvo-de-renovacao/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Macau will facilitate automatic border passage to foreign visitors</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/macau-vai-facilitar-passagem-fronteirica-automatica-para-visitantes-estrangeiros/</link><description>The Secretary for Security has announced plans to accelerate the border control of foreign visitors through the use of automatic electronic channels.
 
During the presentation of the Governing Action Lines (LAG) to 2025 from the security area, Wong Sio Chak stated that the territory will extend the use of automatic passage points to foreign citizens without resident or work authorization.
To facilitate “exterior exchanges”, authorities will expand self-service equipment to the biometric data collection system, which will apply to all foreign visitors, the secretary explained for security.
To the deputies at the Legislative Assembly (AL), the ruler added that the executive will continue to optimize iris recognition technology in border controls and to study their extension to non -residents by 2025.
"We are also studying ways to widen the number of users eligible for automatic passage channels, allowing more foreign tourists to benefit from faster immigration processes and more fluid circulation in the large bay," Wong said.
According to official data, Macau received, in 2024, 34.9 million visitors, 23.8% more than the previous year, but only 2.42 million were international tourists.
In October, the Chinese Foreign Ministry extended the Portuguese visa exemption policy, thus inserting Portugal into a list that already encompassed 16 other European countries. In the same month, Continental China had announced the expansion, from 90 to 180 days, from the permanence period for foreign residents of Macao on multiple entries in the country. The measure includes permanent and non -permanent foreign residents of Macao that move “to the interior of China for short -term tourism, trade, visit to family members, visits and other activities”.
From July, the Chinese National Immigration Administration (NIA) had already allowed foreign permanent residents from Macao and Hong Kong to request authorization to enter the interior of China, valid for a maximum of five years.
The measure covers members of the Portuguese community who are permanent residents in Macao and, until then, were required to ask for a visa to travel to the other side of the border.
 
“Space oil” with tighter control
 
At the same session, Wong Sio Chak also announced that he will implement more strict controls for an anesthetic used in a new synthetic drug, known as 'Space Oil', linked to three deaths in Hong Kong.
In AL, the Secretary for Security revealed that the bill has already been sent to the Executive Board and will be discussed in this advisory body on May 2.
Wong said the new protocols could reach the Hemiciclo to be voted on urgent character in mid -May.
The secretary argued that the review will be "very complete" as it will include in a list of hazardous products targeted by restrictions not only the Ethomidate anesthetic, but also 20 other substances linked to 'spatial oil'.
Ethomidate, an intravenous short action anesthetic, is mainly used in emergency services, anesthesia units, operating rooms and intensive care units.
In February, Hong Kong implemented new protocols involving more rigorous control not only about drug storage but also on documentation and handling requirements in local hospitals.
Ethomidate was classified in the city as a controlled substance, so the sale or illegal possession could lead to a two -year prison sentence and a $ 100,000 fine of Hong Kong.
But the drug was included in a list of hazardous products targeted by restrictions, raising the maximum penalty for possession of "space oil" to seven years in prison and a fine of one million dollars from Hong Kong.
The trafficking or illegal importation of this substance has become a maximum period of life imprisonment and a fine of five million dollars from Hong Kong.
Wong Sio Chak stressed that, both in mainland China and Hong Kong, it is "relatively simple" to restrict ethomidate use and punish possession or trafficking in space oil as it is enough to publish the equivalent of an administrative regulation. In Macao, these measures require the approval of legislation by AL, said the secretary.
In early November, Hong Kong authorities confirmed that at least three deaths were related to 'space oil'.
It was also revealed in December that police have already detected four cases linked to this narcotic since the first case of 'space oil' found in a local school in October 2023.
This drug is known in Hong Kong as 'Zombie drug' because it can cause serious physical and mental damage, including dependence, memory loss, seizures, loss of consciousness and even death. Lusa
 
BOX
 
First case of attempted burla at the use of AI
 
Wong Sio Chak advanced at the Friday's plenary meeting that police authorities recently registered the first case of attempted Burla with Artificial Intelligence (AI) in the territory. According to the Secretary for Security, it was a fake investment scam. Wong indicated that this attempted slogan would not have made victims. In Hemiciclo, the Secretary for Security said that "it is very difficult" to precarious this type of crime, noting that the authorities will still reinforce combat work and dialogue with the services of the interior of China.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:53:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal point 2025.04.28</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/ponto-fatal-2025-04-28/</link><description>The Secretary for Security has announced plans to accelerate the border control of foreign visitors through the use of automatic electronic channels.
 
During the presentation of the Governing Action Lines (LAG) to 2025 from the security area, Wong Sio Chak stated that the territory will extend the use of automatic passage points to foreign citizens without resident or work authorization.
To facilitate “exterior exchanges”, authorities will expand self-service equipment to the biometric data collection system, which will apply to all foreign visitors, the secretary explained for security.
To the deputies at the Legislative Assembly (AL), the ruler added that the executive will continue to optimize iris recognition technology in border controls and to study their extension to non -residents by 2025.
"We are also studying ways to widen the number of users eligible for automatic passage channels, allowing more foreign tourists to benefit from faster immigration processes and more fluid circulation in the large bay," Wong said.
According to official data, Macau received, in 2024, 34.9 million visitors, 23.8% more than the previous year, but only 2.42 million were international tourists.
In October, the Chinese Foreign Ministry extended the Portuguese visa exemption policy, thus inserting Portugal into a list that already encompassed 16 other European countries. In the same month, Continental China had announced the expansion, from 90 to 180 days, from the permanence period for foreign residents of Macao on multiple entries in the country. The measure includes permanent and non -permanent foreign residents of Macao that move “to the interior of China for short -term tourism, trade, visit to family members, visits and other activities”.
From July, the Chinese National Immigration Administration (NIA) had already allowed foreign permanent residents from Macao and Hong Kong to request authorization to enter the interior of China, valid for a maximum of five years.
The measure covers members of the Portuguese community who are permanent residents in Macao and, until then, were required to ask for a visa to travel to the other side of the border.
 
“Space oil” with tighter control
 
At the same session, Wong Sio Chak also announced that he will implement more strict controls for an anesthetic used in a new synthetic drug, known as 'Space Oil', linked to three deaths in Hong Kong.
In AL, the Secretary for Security revealed that the bill has already been sent to the Executive Board and will be discussed in this advisory body on May 2.
Wong said the new protocols could reach the Hemiciclo to be voted on urgent character in mid -May.
The secretary argued that the review will be "very complete" as it will include in a list of hazardous products targeted by restrictions not only the Ethomidate anesthetic, but also 20 other substances linked to 'spatial oil'.
Ethomidate, an intravenous short action anesthetic, is mainly used in emergency services, anesthesia units, operating rooms and intensive care units.
In February, Hong Kong implemented new protocols involving more rigorous control not only about drug storage but also on documentation and handling requirements in local hospitals.
Ethomidate was classified in the city as a controlled substance, so the sale or illegal possession could lead to a two -year prison sentence and a $ 100,000 fine of Hong Kong.
But the drug was included in a list of hazardous products targeted by restrictions, raising the maximum penalty for possession of "space oil" to seven years in prison and a fine of one million dollars from Hong Kong.
The trafficking or illegal importation of this substance has become a maximum period of life imprisonment and a fine of five million dollars from Hong Kong.
Wong Sio Chak stressed that, both in mainland China and Hong Kong, it is "relatively simple" to restrict ethomidate use and punish possession or trafficking in space oil as it is enough to publish the equivalent of an administrative regulation. In Macao, these measures require the approval of legislation by AL, said the secretary.
In early November, Hong Kong authorities confirmed that at least three deaths were related to 'space oil'.
It was also revealed in December that police have already detected four cases linked to this narcotic since the first case of 'space oil' found in a local school in October 2023.
This drug is known in Hong Kong as 'Zombie drug' because it can cause serious physical and mental damage, including dependence, memory loss, seizures, loss of consciousness and even death. Lusa
 
BOX
 
First case of attempted burla at the use of AI
 
Wong Sio Chak advanced at the Friday's plenary meeting that police authorities recently registered the first case of attempted Burla with Artificial Intelligence (AI) in the territory. According to the Secretary for Security, it was a fake investment scam. Wong indicated that this attempted slogan would not have made victims. In Hemiciclo, the Secretary for Security said that "it is very difficult" to precarious this type of crime, noting that the authorities will still reinforce combat work and dialogue with the services of the interior of China.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:48:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Baidu launches two new models of DeepSeek and ChatgPT rivals</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/baidu-lanca-dois-novos-modelos-d-rivais-da-deepseek-e-chatgpt/</link><description>Chinese Baidu has announced the launch of two new models of Artificial Intelligence (IA), Ernie 4.5 shift and Ernie X1 Turbo, in a conjuncture of intense competition from this technology after the impulse given by DeepSeek to the sector.
In an event for programmers of the Chinese company, the CEO (CEO), Robin Li, detailed the improvements introduced in Ernie 4.5 Turnbo, considered the base model of technology, and the X1 Turbo series, a platform presented in March, said the Official Journal of the People.
According to Li, the memory capacity of the model has been expanded and its inference engine is optimized to reinforce 'reasoning' capabilities and reduce the frequency of 'hallucinations' or out of context, one of the industry's problems.
In addition, Baidu stressed the ability of both systems to create and manage digital agents, autonomous programs that can be used in applications such as customer service, data analysis or automated information review processes.
This initiative responds to the Chinese technology plan to accelerate the development of its AI technologies, in the context of growing local competition from companies such as DeepSeek, Alibaba, Tencent and Bytedance.
Recent language models such as DeepSeek and others presented by Chinese Tencent, Alibaba or Bytedance have caused technology accelerated in recent months because they are able to compete in their capacities with US technological solutions at a lower price.
China has regulated AI services in 2023 to respect “the fundamental socialist values”, prohibiting these platforms from “generating content that threatens national security, territorial unity and social stability”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:52:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Former President of South Korea Moon Jae-In considers "unjust" accusation of corruption</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/ex-presidente-da-coreia-do-sul-moon-jae-in-considera-injusta-acusacao-de-corrupcao/</link><description>The former president of South Korea Moon Jae-in considered his accusation of corruption “unjust”, claiming that prosecutors abused his power and had political motivations. "Not only was the accusation unfair, but I also had the feeling that prosecutors had a well-determined direction, regardless of what happened," said the former 72-year-old president at a meeting with National Assembly leader Woo Won-Shik.
The former Centro Legal President (2017-2022) was “accused of corruption for receiving 217 million Won (132,200 euros) after facilitating the hiring of his son-in-law in an airline,” according to the Office of Jeonju district attorney.
For Moon Jae-in, this case "is a very clear example of politicization and abuse of power by the prosecution." "I will do everything in my power to clarify the public and inform you about the abuse of power of the prosecution and its politicization, as well as proving my personal innocence," he said.
According to the prosecution, Moon's son-in-law was appointed director general of the Thai Eastar Jet airline, "despite the absence of any relevant experience or qualification in the air transport sector."
The company, who is controlled by a former Moon party deputy Jae-in, will have appointed the president's son-in-law to obtain favors from the head of state.
All remuneration and other financial benefits paid by the airline to Moon son -in -law between 2018 and 2020 were confirmed as not being legitimate salary payments, but bribes to the president, ”the prosecutors explained.
Moon Jae-in became known for promoting the approach between Korea and, in particular, for organizing talks between North Korean leader Kim Jong Un and US President Donald Trump during his first term.
On Thursday, his party, the Democratic Party, which controls Parliament, described the accusation of the former president as an "abuse of uncontrolled judicial power."
The South Korean political scene has been shaken in the last months after former President Yoon Seok Yeol's failed attempt to introduce martial law in December, which resulted in its dismissal.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:55:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Consumer prices rise again in March after falling in February</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/precos-no-consumidor-voltam-a-subir-em-marco-apos-queda-em-fevereiro/</link><description>Consumer prices in Macao rose again in March, especially due to the cost of meals acquired away from home, after they retreated in February.
The Consumer Price Index (IPC) rose 0.04% in March, in annual terms, reversing a 0.16% retreat in February, according to official data released by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC).
February was the first month Macau fell on deflation (annual fall in consumer prices) since June 2021, when the city lived the last 10 consecutive months of price fall in the peak of the economic crisis caused by the Covid-19 pandemic.
Deflation reflects weakness in domestic consumption and investment and is particularly severe, as a drop in asset price, as a lawsuit under credit, generates an imbalance between the value of loans and bank guarantees. Still, the index went down 0.08% compared to February, a month that included part of the Lunar New Year, a high time for tourism in Macao.
In a statement, DSEC justified the increase in the rate in March with the cost of meals acquired away from home, which rose 1.52%, while the price of sports and recreational services increased 3.37%.
Lace costs and apartment mortgage spending rose 0.42% and 0.85% respectively. This although the housing prices rate fell 11.7% last year and Macau's monetary authority approved three interest rates in the last three months of 2024.
The Legislative Assembly approved, in April last year, the end of several taxes on the acquisition of housing, to “increase liquidity” in the real estate market, defended the secretary for the economy and finance, law wai nong.
With the increase in the number of visitors, the region recorded a 23.9% increase in the price of jewelry, watches and products made of gold.
Official data also show that health services were 1% more expensive, the price of newspapers, books and stationery increased 3.35% and education costs rose 1.16%.
In the neighboring Hong Kong region, inflation remained unchanged at 1.4% in March. In mainland China, by far the largest commercial partner in Macao, the IPC fell 0.1% annually in March, with the country suffering deflation for the second consecutive month.
In early March, after the announcement that China had fallen into deflation, the Council of State announced measures to revitalize domestic consumption. The plan will focus on increasing income, stabilization of the real estate sector and the scholarship market and the improvement of medical and pension services.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:55:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Surplus of public accounts until March has already supplanted forecast for 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/excedente-das-contas-publicas-ate-marco-ja-suplantou-previsao-para-2025/</link><description>Macao ended March with a surplus in public accounts that is already higher than the government forecast for the year 2025.
In the first three months, the surplus reached 9.25 billion patacas, 11.8% more than in the same period of 2024, according to published "online" data by territory finance services. Authorities had foreseen a surplus of only 6.83 billion this year.
Macao closed 2024 with an surplus of 15.8 billion patacas, more than twice the one recorded the previous year.
The year 2024 was the first since 2020, at the beginning of the Covid-19 pandemic, that the territory was able to keep the accounts on positive ground, something required by the basic law, without making transfers from the financial reserve. Still, on April 15, the new leader of the Macao government, Sam Hou Fai, admitted to fear a budget deficit in 2025, due to the slowdown in the game's recipes.
Official data reveals a growth of 0.15% to 22.2 billion patacas, in tax revenues over the game until March, which still represented 88.4% of the total.
The six city game operators pay a 35% direct tax on game revenues, 2.4% for the Macao Social Security Fund and urban and tourist development and 1.6% delivered to the Macao Foundation for cultural, educational, scientific, academics and philanthropic purposes.
Macao casinos registered total revenues of almost 57.7 billion patacas, more 0.6% than in the same period of 2024. Despite the growth in tax revenues, Macao's current revenue fell by 5.38% in the first three months of 2025, in annual terms, to 25.1 billion patacas.
The main reason for the decrease was financial revenues, which went from billion in the first quarter of 2024 to just two thousand patacas this year.
This heading corresponds to the results of the Macao monetary authority, the region's financial regulator, including investment and interest and dividend revenues.
In the first three months, Macau collected 22.3% of the projected current revenue for 2025 in the region's budget, which is 112.6 billion patacas. The increased surplus of the territory was mainly due to public expense that descended 13.8% between January and March, to 15.9 billion patacas, mainly due to a cut of 21.4% in social support and subsidies given to the population.
The government spent 4.52 billion patacas under the administration's investment and expenses plan, less 13.2% compared to the first three months of 2024.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:55:29</pubDate></item><item><title>STD foresees at least 4.1% on tourists during holidays of May 1</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/dst-preve-subida-de-pelo-menos-41-nos-turistas-durante-feriados-de-1-de-maio/</link><description>Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes believes in a climb of at least 4.1% in the number of visitors during the holidays of Labor Day. The director of tourism services, however, considers it to be “a bit early” to lower expectations for the total number of visitors during the year, which had been set at 39 million.
 
The Director of Tourism Services (STD), Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, provides for at least 4.1% on the number of visitors during the holidays of Labor Day. Senna Fernandes said she expects a daily average of between 127 thousand and 140,000 tourists between May 1 and 5, a period of holidays in mainland China, known as the "Golden Week".
To Portuguese -speaking journalists, the leader added that Macau could receive between 630,000 and 700,000 visitors during these five days, one of the high seasons for tourism in the territory.
The most conservative forecast would mean an increase of 4.1% compared to the same “golden week” of 2024, while the most optimistic forecast would be a 15.7% rise.
On Thursday, the Macau International Airport Management Company admitted that it could fail the passenger and load goals set to 2025, due to the “geopolitical situation and world economic instability”. But the STD's director said that “it is still a little early” to lower expectations to the total number of visitors during the year, which had been fixed by 39 million. This is because “really policies are changing every day (…) we don't have a global view yet what will happen, maybe in two weeks,” admitted Senna Fernandes. "We are very careful, we are observing what is happening worldwide," added the manager. “We have to have optimism and do our work, but also prepare for what can happen,” said Senna Fernandes.
The STD director spoke after the opening ceremony of the 13th International Tourism Expo (Industry) of Macao, which ended yesterday.
On April 10, Senna Fernandes said the region is aware of the potential impact on the trust of Chinese tourists from the United States imposed on imports from China. On April 15, the new leader of the Macao government, Sam Hou Fai, admitted a budget deficit in 2025, due to the deceleration in the game's recipes.
The previous Chief Executive, Ho Iat Seng, had predicted game revenues of 240 billion patacas by 2025, or 20 billion per month. But in the first three months of the year, Macao casinos registered total revenues of 57.7 billion patacas, below the Government's goal. “We have to have a feeling of risk,” warned Sam Hou Fai.
The government leader recalled that mainland China - from afar the main source of tourists to Macao - fell into deflation (annual consumer prices) in March for the second consecutive month, "but savings increased." Sam Hou Fai argued that these data show that the Chinese population also has "a feeling of risk." Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:54:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Wong Sio Chak denies legislative “failures” in the accusation and condemnation of cases of domestic violence</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/wong-sio-chak-desmente-falhas-legislativas-na-acusacao-e-condenacao-dos-casos-de-violencia-domestica/</link><description>The Secretary for Security dismissed the revision of the Domestic Violence Prevention and Fighting Law, rejecting that there are gaps in the legislation. The position of Wong Sio Chak came after criticism of Mrs Lo Choi In about the low charge of prosecution and conviction of cases of domestic violence, with only 12 cases, including 133 lawsuits, were charged with that crime. On the other hand, Wong Sio Chak said the situation has to do with the “definition and concept” of domestic violence.
 
Wong Sio Chak denies “failures” or “insufficiency” in the law of prevention and combating domestic violence, an accusation that Deputy Lo Choi in pointed to the secretary for security during the debate of the governance action lines in the Legislative Assembly, taking into account the low charge of prosecution and conviction of these types of cases.
According to official statistics last year, 133 cases on domestic violence were preliminarily and, after investigation, only 12 were considered as crimes of domestic violence. Already in 2023, there were 129 cases preliminarily filed and 15 cases accused of crimes of domestic violence. The Secretary for Security assured that the remaining cases were accompanied as offenses to physical integrity or other crimes.
In the plenary of the Legislative Assembly on Friday, Deputy Lo Choi In argued that the current low rate of accused and condemned cases “is attributable to the defects of the legislation” on domestic violence, considering that the execution of the law is violating the principle of protection for children and women. The legislator suggested that a review of the “obsolete law” on domestic violence and the Penal Code be started.
The secretary, however, disagreed with Lo Choi In accusation of "failures" at the law level. "I think the deputy does not know the law well," said the ruler, adding that there is no need at this time to change the legislation.
Wong Sio Chak understands that the processes of the crime of domestic violence arrest with the application of the law and the concept and definition of crime is at stake. Under current law, domestic violence is considered to be any physical, psychic or sexual abuse that are committed under a family or equivalent relationship, which is punished with a prison sentence of one to five years.
“Os actos de violência doméstica de grau leve ou moderado que possam constituir maus tratos ou ofensas corporais graves, são crimes públicos e serão tratados como crimes de violência doméstica, acusação que implica uma maior severidade; E se se tratar de um acto isolado de ofensas físicas graves, por exemplo homicídio ou ofensa à integridade física grave, cuja possível pena ultrapassa um a cinco anos, então será tratado ao abrigo de uma lei penal, ou Be more severe than the crime of domestic violence, ”he explained. "This is because some cases were not judged as domestic violence," he said.
In this case, Wong Sio Chak pointed out that the low rate of condemnation for domestic violence is also related to the definition of crimes of domestic violence, whose behaviors "must be repetitive, continuous, usual and serious."
He also stressed that the purpose of the Domestic Violence Prevention and Fighting Law is to promote family harmony rather than “destroying families”. Wong Sio Chak also assured that all cases were closely monitored by the Social Action Institute (IAS)
The secretary added that IAS has already gathered the competent services to discuss the revision of the Domestic Violence Prevention and Fighting Law, and the result of the analysis indicates that there is no need to change it. "As for the Penal Code, one of the main codes, cannot be altered easily and whenever you want. If criminal law is unstable, it will not be good for society," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:52:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Government wants to complete four important infrastructure projects in ten years</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/governo-quer-concluir-quatro-projectos-de-infra-estruturas-importantes-em-dez-anos/</link><description>The government is planning to launch four “iconic and important” works projects, which will be completed in eight to ten years, according to the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai. In an exclusive event for certain social communication bodies held yesterday, the government leader revealed that he has already started the construction of the Macao and Hengqin University City of International Education, with an investment estimated at 20 billion patacas.
 
One of the priorities of the government's government action for this year is to start four “iconic and important” works projects. Sam Hou Fai, head of the executive, presented yesterday the plan of infrastructure works and said he hoped the projects could be completed in eight to ten years.
According to the recent report of the Government Action Lines, the four projects include the construction of the city (university) of Macao and Hengqin International Education, an Integrated Integrated Tourist and Cultural neighborhood of Macau, a Hub (Porto) of Macao International Air Transport on the western bank of Rio das Pérolas, as well as an industrial park for macao science and technology development.
Sam Hou Fai spoke yesterday at a press conference entitled “Opportunities in the Great Bay; Opportunities in Hong Kong; Opportunities in Macao”, where journalists from certain social communication agencies were invited exclusively.
Quoted by Radio Macao in Chinese language, the government leader said that he has already begun the construction of the city (university) of International Education of Macao and Hengqin, which will be made in phases, with an estimated investment of about 20 billion patacas, hoping to “form high quality qualified pictures” for the development of tourism and leisure in the country and Macau.
It is expected that the enclosure will have the pedagogical activities of the University of Macau from 2028, followed by the University of Tourism of Macau, which will later extend its operation to Hengqin.
Regarding the proposal of the so -called Macao Integrated International and Cultural Bairro, Sam Hou Fai stressed that it will “enjoy” the space between the Macau Peninsula and the mud, and the Macao National Culture Museum, the Macao International Arts Center and the International Museum of Contemporary Art will be built.
The chief executive advanced a budget estimate of about 12 billion patacas for the venture in question, and public tenders will be launched from the second half of this year, lasting two to three years. "The project is expected to become an emblematic cultural base in the Asia Pacific region, as well as worldwide, highlighting the distinctive characteristics of Macao in terms of the fusion of Chinese and Western cultures and the promotion of Chinese culture and history," he said.
Sam Hou Fai, moreover, recalled that the landfill project to expand Macau International Airport was approved by the state, with an estimated investment of about six billion Patacas, to make Macau in a port of international air transport on the west of Rio das Perolas. He also said he hoped that the future industrial park of research and development of macao science and technologies could be a place to welcome the headquarters and research bases of large national and foreign companies.
At the time, André Cheong, Secretary for Administration and Justice, highlighted the progress of integration between Macau and Hengqin. He appealed to “bold innovations and advances in terms of convergence of mechanisms and rules” between the two places, as Macau and Hengqin present differences in governance that affect their integrated development.
LAM, secretary of social affairs and culture, in turn, believes that Macau still needs to make more efforts throughout the cultural industry and the construction of his brand, in order to create “cultural symbols of the unique city” of Macao. LAM also revealed that it will cooperate with the State Ministry of Culture and Tourism to establish a China Cultural Center in Lisbon, Portugal.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:55:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau sends five doctors to help prevent outbreaks after earthquake</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/macau-envia-cinco-medicos-para-ajudar-a-prevenir-surtos-apos-sismo/</link><description>Macau sent a team of five doctors to help Myanmar, namely in the prevention of contagious disease outbreaks after the March 28 earthquake, which caused more than 3,700 dead.
In a statement, Macao health services (SSM) said the territory team should work at Myanmar for at least 14 days in some of the areas most affected by the earthquake.
According to Macau, the team leader, the Leong, said the mission could be extended according to the needs of Myanmar's authorities. Macao doctors “will establish a coordination mechanism in coordination with Myanmar's Department of Health, will help to analyze medical needs in the area of ​​disaster and will provide technical support in the treatment of trauma and the prevention and control of infectious diseases,” SSM said.
One of the team elements, formed at the request of the World Health Organization, is Chan Soi Fan, consultant at the Prevention Center and Infectious Diseases and Surveillance of the SSM Disease Prevention and Disease Control Center. The SSM recalled that the first time Macau sent a team abroad was in May 2020, when five local doctors were supporting Algeria and Sudan in combating Covid-19 pandemic.
The magnitude 7.7 earthquake on the Richter scale that hit Myanmar on March 28 caused more than 3,700 dead in the country, as well as 22 in neighboring Thailand, leading the military junta in power to declare a temporary ceasefire until April 2.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:49:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Unemployment rate registered climbing in the first quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/taxa-de-desemprego-registou-subida-no-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>Macau's global unemployment rate rose 0.2 percentage points in the first quarter of this year, compared to the last three months of 2024, now being 1.9%. The specific unemployment rate of local residents also grew 0.2 percentage points to 2.5%.
 
In the first quarter of this year, the region of global unemployment in the region registered a quarterly growth of 0.2 percentage points for 1.9%. The exclusive unemployment rate of local residents also rose 0.2 percentage points compared to the last quarter of last year and is now in 2.5%.
The data were released on Friday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), which also show that the global sub-Camping Rate (1.2%) and the residents' underemployment rate (1.6%) lowered both 0.3 percentage points in quarterly terms.
According to DSEC, between January and March, the global number of employees (371,800) and that of residents employed (280,200) descended 6,500 and 5,800 people, respectively, compared to the fourth quarter of 2024. DSEC stresses that the number of residents employed in the game sector (65,100) fell 2,200 and the residents of the construction industry employees. (14,000) lowered 2,000 people, while residents of retail business (29,900) rose 2,200 people.
For its turn, the average monthly income of the employment of the employed population was 18,800 patacas, growing 800 Patacas quarterly. The average monthly resident employment income was 21,500 patacas, plus 1,000 patacas compared to the last quarter of 2024. DSEC explains this because some branches of economic activity attributed the 13th month of salary and profit sharing during the first quarter of this year.
Compared to the period between December last year and February this year, the global unemployment rate is now higher at 0.1 percentage points and that of residents at 0.2 percentage points. This is mainly due to the “large number of people sought jobs after the holidays,” explains DSEC. The global sub -unemployment rate (1.2%) and the sub -unemployment rate of residents (1.6%) also rose 0.1 and 0.2 percentage points, respectively, compared to those of the past period.
The number of employees (371,800) and residents employed (280,200) decreased 3,100 and 3,500 people, respectively, compared to the preceding period. The number of unemployed residents (7,300) rose 500 people in relation to the previous period.
DSEC also says that from unemployed residents looking for a new employment, most previously worked in the economic activity of restaurants and the like and in the field of construction. In addition to these, the number of unemployed residents looking for first employment represented 10.2% of unemployed residents, less percentage points, compared to the preceding period.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:51:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections with 37 voting locations</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/eleicoes-com-37-locais-de-votacao/</link><description>In the elections of September 14, 37 voting places will be made available with a total of 38 voting assemblies for direct suffrage and five more for the indirect suffrage, the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) said, not, however, where these voting places will be. The body has only indicated that "some places used in previous elections will be replaced by more appropriate places in the same zone and easier for voters."
In this year's elections, the indirect suffrage will be performed for the first time in two distinct voting places, "with the aim of deflecting the flow of voters and reducing the waiting time for voting," the body said.
Regarding the Constitution of Candidacy Committee, Seng Ioi Man, president of Caeal, stressed that, for now, he has not received any request for recognition, warning those interested in constituting the candidacy committee they must submit to Caeal the bulletin duly filled, until June 6, to recognize their legal existence.
In addition, Caeal appeals to voters who have changed residence, but have not yet made their alteration in the electoral census, to make the update until May 31, so that Caeal can assign to the voting meeting closest to its current residence.
Finally, Seng Ioi Man mentioned that the Public Prosecution Service received a complaint filed by officials from various local associations with the Judicial Police, claiming that a particular individual had published in social networks content that impaired the honor of associations. He added that, according to the information, the defendant is suspected of the crime of advertising and slander, noting that his conduct may also constitute the crime of coercion and fraudulent devices about the candidacy committee. Finally, the official appealed to everyone to abstain from conduct that may impair the normal and adequate development of electoral activities during the period of proposal of candidates such as the elections.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:52:01</pubDate></item><item><title>China decement Trump about commercial negotiations with the United States</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/china-desmente-trump-sobre-negociacoes-comerciais-com-estados-unidos/</link><description>China has again denied being in negotiations with the United States about the tariffs, denying the comments of US President Donald Trump. The leadership of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) announced on Friday new measures to stabilize and streamline the country's economy in an attempt to alleviate the effects of trade war with the United States.
 
"There have been no consultations or negotiations between China and the United States on tariff issues, let alone an agreement," the Chinese embassy in Washington said in a statement published on the Wechat messaging platform.
The US statements that a dialogue about the fares "are misleading," the Chinese diplomatic representation is underway. "If the United States really want to solve the problem through dialogue, they must first correct their mistakes, stop threatening and press others, and completely abolish all unilateral tariff measures taken against China," he reads in the statement.
In an interview published on Friday by Time magazine, the US president said discussions between the two countries were underway to try to reach an agreement and suggested that the process could be completed in the coming weeks.
He said, moreover, he spoke on the phone with Chinese counterpart, Xi Jinping, without specifying when or what the conversation content. "He called. And I don't think this is a sign of weakness," said the American leader.
The Chinese Ministry of Commerce had already denied on Thursday it was carrying out economic or commercial negotiations with Washington.
The US President decided to impose 145% overflows on certain products imported from China. In response, Beijing imposed 125% surcharge on products from the United States.
The leadership of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) announced on Friday new measures to stabilize and streamline the country's economy in an attempt to alleviate the effects of trade war with the United States.
Following a meeting dedicated to the analysis of the economic conjuncture, the CCP Central Committee Politburo acknowledged that, in the face of “increasing the impact of external shocks,” the Chinese government will “coordinate internal economy efforts with the challenges of international trade”.
Although not directly mentioning the United States, China's highest political decision-making agency referred to recent commercial tensions with Washington, which resulted in the mutual imposition of 100%tariffs.
Politburo highlighted the need to “further consolidate the foundations for a sustained economic recovery” and stressed the importance of promoting service consumption, reinforcing the role of domestic consumption as an engine of economic growth, according to a statement issued by the official news agency Xinhua.
Since the beginning of the trade war triggered by US President Donald Trump, many Chinese companies have returned to the domestic market in an attempt to mitigate the effects of US tariffs. However, doubts persist about the feasibility of this strategy, in the face of weak internal demand - one of the main obstacles to the resuming of the second largest economy world.
In this context, the political organ promised, although without advancement, an increase in income from the middle and low income groups.
In recent years, Beijing has avoided resorting to more aggressive stimulus packages, seeking not to repeat the levels of inflation recorded in the western economies after the pandemic. This containment is justified by the high public debt and the resistance of China President Xi Jinping, to which he considers it to be a model of “welfare”.
Politburo, consisting of 24 members and chaired by Xi, has ensured that he will “firmly manage national issues”, deepen a “high -level opening” and reinforce the implementation of “more proactive and effective” macroeconomic policies.
Advanced measures include support for scientific and technological innovation, stimulation of consumption and stabilization of foreign trade. For this, an active fiscal policy and a “moderately accommodating” monetary policy will be applied.
Already by the end of 2024, the authorities had signaled a change to “moderately flexible” monetary orientation, breaking with 14 years of “prudent” posture.
At the same time, it has been announced that there will be a reduction in interest rates “at the right time”. The most recent occurred in October, when the Popular Bank of China cut off the reference interest rate at 25 base points, from 3.35% to 3.1%.
The Politburo meeting comes at a time when Donald Trump was optimistic about the possibility of a new trade agreement between the United States and China.
However, Beijing has again demanded that Washington “stops pushing” and showing “respect” if he really wants to resolve commercial conflicts through dialogue. Chinese authorities have denied, however, that formal negotiations are currently between the two powers.
Still, Chinese and international communication agencies have reported possible exemptions and suspensions of tariffs on certain American products from China-signs that may indict possible relief in tensions.
 
He asks China to avoid flooding market with products that cannot go to the USA
 
The European Economy Commissioner said he asked China to "not flood" other markets with products he cannot put in the United States following the tariff war started by Donald Trump.
Commissioner Valdis Dombrovskis spoke at a press conference in Washington, where he is on an official visit on the spring meetings of the International Monetary Fund (IMF), a meeting that is taking the opportunity to meet with United States and China authorities to approach the trade war. "My message to Chinese counterparts is that it is important for China to show some moderation and does not start flooding other markets with these products, which can create possible contracted and trigger a domino effect," he said.
For the EU, he added, "it is important to preserve the rules based on the multilateral trade system because, at the end of the day, it is what works best for everyone." "On the side of China, they showed us understanding of our concern," he said.
 
China creates exemptions for chips industry
 
Several Chinese technology companies that import US chips have been informed that certain products related to semiconductors and integrated circuits are exempt from the rates imposed by Beijing on US goods, the Cailian newspaper said. Quoting business sources in the sector, the agency has revealed that a total of eight categories of chips related to taxes applied to all United States products, which Beijing has implemented as contracted to the rates on Chinese products imposed by US leader Donald Trump. A source from a Shanghai-based semiconductor company explained to the newspaper that authorities held an informative meeting to communicate the measure to companies in the sector. During this meeting, it was indicated that importers of exempt custom customs codes will be subject only to the 13%added value tax (VAT), and that memory chips are not part of the exemption list. It was also established that, for products imported between April 10 and 24 and that they have been subject to taxes during this period, importers may request the reimbursement of previously paid additional taxes.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:52:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Myanmar records about 200,000 out of place after the land of late March</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/myanmar-regista-cerca-de-200-mil-deslocados-apos-terramoto-do-final-de-marco/</link><description>About 200,000 people had to leave their homes at Myanmar after the 7.7 Richter scale, on March 28, which caused more than 3,700 dead.
 
The 7.7 earthquake on the Richter scale, recorded on March 28 at Myanmar and caused more than 3,700 dead, led about 200,000 people to have to abound their homes.
According to the International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crossing Societies (FICV), at least 198,600 people are displaced, with total or partial damage to 52,000 houses, 640 health facilities and 2,661 schools in the six downtown and northern country that have been declared emergency by the Military Board that leads Myanmar since the February coup d'état 2021.
The UN Humanitarian Coordination Office (OCHA) told the Spanish agency EFE that about four weeks later “the population is still recovering from the persistent impacts” of the earthquake.
"Many people do not have a safe place where they return and sleep in the open in improvised shelters, exposed to the weather. This situation aggravates travel in a country where more than 3.5 million people had already been forced to flee their homes," said O OCHA.
In the same response to EFE, the UN reiterated that drinking water and sanitation measures can scarce in affected areas, "which increases the health risks of already vulnerable populations," which also need "emergency shelters, economic aid, food and health care."
The multilateral organism also points out that, together with local organizations, it has been able to deliver humanitarian aid in areas that are difficult to access Mandalay and Sagaing, the cities most affected by earthquake, although acknowledging that "the magnitude and urgency of the catastrophe require much larger action, resources and access."
In this context, OCHA has again appealed to the international community to “intensify their support during this difficult period” as it is estimated that a third of residents in the country, about 21 million people, has urgent needs, some aggravated by the earthquake.
The data updated on Friday by the military junta indicate that the earthquake caused the death of 3,763 people, and there is still 5,107 injured and 110 missing.
The earthquake was registered at 06:20 (Lisbon time) on March 28, with a depth of 10 kilometers (km), with epicenter about 17 km from Mandalay, the second city of Burma, with 1.2 million, and 270 km north of the capital Naypyidaw. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:56:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Travel agencies want new government to promote more flights with China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/agencias-de-viagens-querem-que-novo-governo-promova-mais-voos-com-a-china/</link><description>The president of the Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies (APAVT) told Lusa to expect the new government to promote more direct flights with China. "We will see if, when we recover political stability in Portugal, there will be space and time to begin to develop more aerial connections [with China]," said Pedro Costa Ferreira.
Pedro Costa Ferreira said he had no doubt that direct flights between Portugal and China "will always be a success" and that the current problem "will never be economic." "It is the question of finding a space at the airport and the [operators] interested in flying. (…) It will eventually be [a problem] logistics and we hope it can be solved," he added.
There is currently only one direct connection between China and Portugal, with a frequency of four flights per week from Lisbon, bound for Hangzhou, the capital of Zhejiang Province (East), one of the most prosperous in China. "We are very far from what we want and far from what are, of course, the ambitions on both sides," said the president of APAVT.
Also the leader of the European Block of Tour and Tour Operators, Eric Drésin, said the lack of flights to China is the main challenge to attract more visitors in Europe. "The main problem (…) is connectivity. Flying is expensive," lamented the secretary general of the European Confederation of Travel Agency and Tour Operators (ECTAA) "European airlines cannot reach China overwitting Russia because of war in Ukraine, so they reduced the number of flights to continental china" Drésin.
The European Union closed airspace to Russian aircraft after the invasion of Ukraine, and Moscow retaliated with similar prohibitions, making the links between Asia and Europe more expensive. “Thus, we depend a lot on non -European airlines to bring travelers” to the Asian continent, Drésin explained, including companies from Singapore, Japan and South Korea.
In the case of China, "it is not very common for European travelers to travel with Chinese airlines. They need to better establish their mark in Europe," said the Frenchman.
Chinese airlines are still resuming routes that connected China to the rest of the world before Covid-19 pandemic after the Asian country limited international air traffic to less than 2% of the existing in 2019. Drissin spoke during the first day of the 13th International Expo of Macao (industry), which ended yesterday.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:55:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Francisco approached Santa See and Beijing without stepped on China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/francisco-aproximou-santa-se-e-pequim-sem-ter-pisado-a-china/</link><description>In Beijing's largest convent, China's Catholic seminary, a royal figure of Pope Francis, printed on a card, welcomes the entrance of each building, with a gesture of blessing.
 
"We would like it to come to China," a 28 -year -old Chinese seminarian, who identifies himself as Joseph, noted to China. "As it could not, we have brought it symbolically so far."
Despite not visiting the country, Francisco's 12th anniversary were marked by an unprecedented rapprochement between the Vatican and the Popular Republic of China, which resulted in a historic agreement on the appointment of Chinese Catholic bishops.
The communist regime retained the authority to propose the names of bishops candidates, but it is now the Pope who has the final word and may approve or refuse the appointment.
"He [Papa Francisco] played a key role in the redefinition of dialogue with Beijing," said Michel Chambon, a Christianity expert in Asia at the National University of Singapore, quoted by France Presse. "For the first time, the Chinese government acknowledged that the Pope could have a word to say in the management of Chinese Catholics," he said.
It is not a little thing: the Chinese Communist Party (PPC) suspects any organization that may threaten its authority and even more involving a foreign state, such as the Vatican.
Speaking to the Lusa agency, a European priest based in Beijing explained that “one of the Chinese government's struggles is exactly 'to be attached' many of the concepts and logic of non-Asian religions” and ensure that “patriotism” prevails between believers and priests.
China's Catholic Seminary Architecture reflects this process. Built in 2000, the church has a circular shape in red bricks with a triple roof of blue tiles. A kind of miniature of the prayer room for good harvests, one of the main temples of Beijing.
Only the stained glass and a discreet cross at the top distinguish this construction from any Taoist temple; Inside, the altar, raised only by a step, is adorned with a traditional Chinese wooden table. A small and discreet crucifix is ​​the only religious image exposed here. But there is more beyond what you see on the surface.
Walking through the stairs behind the altar and a long corridor comes to the church basement, where in the almost total darkness there are figures of kneeling believers, around an image of Christ about one and a half meters, erected behind a stone altar. "The death of Pope Francis is a sadness for all who seek a fairer world," a believer told Lusa. "Despite political barriers, many Chinese Catholics felt a deep bond with him," another.
Signed in 2018 between Beijing and the Holy See, the agreement provided for Biennial Renewals. However, in a sign of increasingly cordial relations, the two parts announced last October the extension of their validity for a period of four years. The exact content, which was never made public, raised contrasting reactions.
Some see the agreement as an increase in Beijing control over the role of the church in China, while others welcome it as a step towards greater understanding.
For Joseph, the approach between both sides "can only be good news." Your dream is one day to visit the Vatican. And when it is suggested that, perhaps in the future, the Pope becomes Chinese, his eyes shine. "You never know, the world goes around," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:52:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Consul “very annoyed” by the only air connection between Macao and Europe is not for Portugal</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/consul-muito-irritado-por-unica-ligacao-aerea-entre-macau-e-a-europa-nao-ser-para-portugal/</link><description>Alexandre Leitão, Portugal's consul-general in Macau and Hong Kong, was frustrated due to the fact that the only direct air connection between Macao and Europe does not go to Portugal but to Madrid. The official indicated, at the Macao International Tourism Fair, that he has been insisting with the Portuguese authorities for this connection to be made to Lisbon or Porto.
 
Portugal's Consul General in Macao and Hong Kong lamented that the only direct airline connection between Macao and Europe is made for Madrid and not to Lisbon or to Porto. This connection, by Ethiopian Airlines, was inaugurated two weeks ago and is part of a triangular route with Adis Ababa, the capital of that African country.
In a presentation at the Portugal Tourism Pavilion at the Macao International Tourism Fair, Alexandre Leitão stated: “I wrote it [a letter] to Lisbon, very angry, when Ethiopian Airlines opened its triangular load flight Adis Ababa-Macau and has created Macau's first direct connection to Europe”.
Quoted by the Diário de Notícias, Alexandre Leitão said at the time that he has been insisting with the Portuguese authorities over the past two years so that this connection was made by a Portuguese company, with a national airport as a European platform. Consul-general justified the position by saying that in Macau there are 153,000 Portuguese, inserted in a region that in a radius of 200 kilometers has two urban centers such as Shenzhen, Canton and Hong Kong.
"Here there are more than a hundred restaurants that complain Portuguese; there are dealers, there are commerce and this year will open two more Portuguese restaurants," he said, adding: "I repeat, do not convince me that a flight that makes a dual function of transportation and goods transportation is not feasible."
“Explain me there why is Lisbon not an Atlantic and also European plate, besides being Lusophone for markets like Brazil, which are served like no other? Or why the African, Lusophone capitals, are not also instruments, distribution platforms of goods and services to other countries in Africa who want to come here?”
Except not to be a specialist in aviation affairs, Alexandre Leitão asked for explanations from the Portuguese government and TAP. “Until I explain to me for the most B that makes no sense at all, I will continue to insist on it,” he said, concluding: “All people interested in Portugal, [look to] this potential before Ethiopia or another company even decides to make the flight of direct passengers to Madrid or Paris, wherever it is. So the task becomes more difficult.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:52:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump: the main measures in the first 100 days of term</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/trump-as-principais-medidas-nos-primeiros-100-dias-de-mandato/</link><description>Donald Trump's return to power has been marked by unexpected measures and movements, with critics to argue that the president forward the United States to "an autocracy" or an "imperial presidency."
 
Analysts have compared Donald Trump's first term in 2017 and the Return to the White House this year, evaluating the Republican as more prepared and willing to take more drastic measures in virtually all areas.
Here are some essential points about the main measures and actions taken by Trump during the first 100 days of the second term:
 
Diplomacy
 
The United States helped found the UN after World War II to prevent future global conflicts and promote international peace and security.  However, this did not prevent Trump from removing the country from the World Health Organization (WHO) or the Human Rights Council.
It also suspended all funding to the UN agency for Palestinian refugees (Unrwa) and indicated that it was going to review the UN organization for education, science and culture (UNESCO), and abandoned or cutting funding to multilateral agreements on health to human rights.
Still in the universe of diplomacy, Trump caused international shock by renking the Gulf of Mexico as "Gulf of America", promising to take control of the Panama Canal or by admitting the possibility of resorting to military force or economic coercion to assume control of Grolândia.
He insisted with the intention of attaching Canada, referring to former Canadian Prime Minister Justin Trudeau as governor and the country as “the 51st state”.
Still in terms of unexpected diplomatic movements, Trump hastened himself to normalize relations with Russia, despite the war against Ukraine still ongoing.
 
Conflict
 
In early February, Trump suggested that the US should take control of the Gaza Strip - Enclave destroyed by the war between Israel and the Palestinian Islamite movement Hamas - to rebuild and transform into the "riviera of the Middle East."
Since then, for shock from the international community, it has insisted that the inhabitants of Gaza should be permanently transferred to countries such as Egypt and Jordan.
Regarding war in Ukraine, Trump's difficulties have been evident in fulfilling the promise of a rapid resolution of the conflict.
According to analysts, Trump - unlike predecessor Joe Biden - has delineated a solution that widely favors Russia, anticipating the possibility of assignment to the Moscow of Ukrainian territories or rejecting the adhesion of Ukraine to the NATO.
While the new US administration has been focused on personal relationships and isolated events to try to end this war, the tense meeting in the White House will be met between Trump and Ukrainian leader Volodymyr Zelensky in late February.
At the time, the US head of state and the vice-president, JD Vance, severely criticized Zelensky and accuses him of not contributing to a peace plan with Russian President Vladimir Putin.
 
Justice
 
Several experts in constitutional law have considered that Trump is performing an “unprecedented attack” to the country's judicial system, endangering the rule of law.
Federal Courts are currently judging more than a hundred lawsuits against the president's measures, many of them related to immigration.
Since Trump's policies began facing legal barriers, the president's advisors and supporters have entered a crusade against lawyers and law firms, questioning the legitimacy of the US judicial system daily.
In March, the president threatened to take action against lawyers and legal teams that present lawsuits against government migratory measures, resulting in a climate of intimidation.
In addition to attacks on the judicial system, Trump has fostered rumors of a possible candidacy for a third presidential term, which would be a violation of the Constitution, which provides a maximum of two.
 
Education, Culture and Science
 
The Trump administration “cut the investigation financing and interrupted large areas of science funded by the federal government as part of an expense initiative led by billionaire Elon Musk,” said the scientific journal Nature, indicating that 75% of US scientists have now considered abandoning the country.
The White House intends to reduce the space agency's budget by 2026 to 2026 by nearly 50% and announced the cutting of thousands of millions of dollars in financing for universities across the country that did not align with the broad government reforms required by the executive.
In addition, a number of books that promote diversity, equity and inclusion, including works on holocaust, feminism, civic rights and racism, as well as the famous autobiography of US writer and poet Maya Angelou.
The measure marks one more step in the broad effort of the Trump administration to eliminate the so -called 'Dei' content (diversity, equity and inclusion) of federal agencies.
 
Immigration
 
Trump promised the biggest mass deportation in American history.
Since taking office, this plan has been placed in march, but not at the pace that the current executive anticipated.
The Immigration and Customs Service (ICE) deported just over 12,300 immigrants between March 1 and 28, just below 12,700 people deported in the same period last year, according to data obtained by the NBC News chain.
In this sense, the government has increased pressure on immigrants to voluntarily leave the United States and have reached an agreement with El Salvador President Nayib Bukele to send detained immigrants in the US to this Central American country.
The US has also revoked a view to hundreds of college students for protests against war in Gaza. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:52:03</pubDate></item><item><title>13th Mite record record of participation with 755 companies from 70 countries and regions</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/13-a-mite-regista-recorde-de-participacao-com-755-empresas-de-70-paises-e-regioes/</link><description>The 13th Macao International Tourism Expo (Mite), held from 25 to 27 April, brought a record of participation with 755 companies from 70 countries and regions. During the opening ceremony, the “East Asia Culture City - Macao Culture, China” Pavilion was inaugurated, promoting local culture and tourist exchanges. The event stands out as an important platform for business and partnerships in the sector, attracting heavy, local and international companies.
 
The 13th International Expo of Macao ended yesterday, after the opening ceremony was held on April 25, marking a new record in both exhibitors and business opportunities for the sector. Organized by the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), Expo, which took place at COTAI Expo Pavilions A, B and C in Venetian, attracted the participation of 755 tourism -related companies, as well as official entities from 70 countries and regions, consolidating their position as an international international platform.
With the motto “Explore Mite, try the world”, this year's edition presented a total of 1,502 stands, which includes 316 in the interior of China's exhibition zone, 411 in the Macao area and 343 in the area of ​​international exhibitors. This significant increase, 50% over the previous year, has a growing relevance of the Expo in the global tourist scenario.
The opening ceremony was attended by the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, who highlighted the importance of the event for the development of tourism in the region in a speech, besides promoting cultural exchange between nations. Among the speakers, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, director of STD, emphasized the Expo as a vital bridge that connects Macao's tour operators with international markets.
One of the main highlights of the opening was the inauguration of the “Culture of East Culture - Macau, China” Pavilion, which represents a significant initiative under the Macao Cultural Development Program. This pavilion projects the city as a center of cultural creation and creativity by 2025. With an area of ​​162 square meters, the space is presented under the theme “East -Kid Meeting, Asia in Harmony”, symbolizing the cultural intersection that happens in Macao, according to STD.
Through a detailed curatorship, the pavilion represented the history and local traditions, serving as a platform for emerging artists and content creators who wanted to share their contemporary views, highlighting the cultural plurality of the region. The space was divided into several sections that addressed different aspects of eastern Asian culture, in a combination between the visual arts, music, gastronomy and literature, allowing visitors a deep immersion in the cultural diversity of the region. In addition, the pavilion received live demonstrations, workshops and presentations. The “Cidade de Cultura East Culture” Pavilion intended to position the city of Macao as a prominent promoter of cultural exchanges in a global scenario, contributing to the construction of a more “cohesive and inclusive” international community.
This year's Expo also introduced significant innovations in its programming, with a wide offer of activities that included more than 70 forums and thematic events. The events aimed to enrich participants' knowledge of local tourist resources and foster the exchange of ideas between tourist operators from different continents. The exhibitions approached several areas, such as “Coffee Station”, a space for the promotion of quality coffees, and the “Halal Culture Products Pavilion”, which seeks to expand penetration in the region's halal market.
During the three days of the event, Expo was also the scene of specially promotions and promotions, which encouraged the active participation of the public.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:55:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Largo da Sé will be the target of renewal</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/28/largo-da-se-sera-alvo-de-renovacao/</link><description>The source and the beds in Largo da Sé will be the target of renewal works, the Institute said for municipal affairs (AMI). According to the body, these facilities, built in 2004, are aged and deteriorated.
Thus, from May 7, AMI will remodel the source and surrounding facilities in Largo da Sé, “with a view to providing residents and visitors a beautiful and clean leisure space”. The work is expected to be completed, in its entirety, at the beginning of the fourth quarter of this year.
"Due to their use over 20 years, the facilities are aged and damaged. A part of the source water supply pipes is clogged due to rust, which prevents water sprinkling," says AMI, adding that "the source wall is damaged and with leaks to different degrees, making it difficult to repair."
At the same time, “the lining of the beds and stone seats around the Largo da Cé are aged and some stones have cracks and peeling, resulting in an ineffective waterproofing”, which gives rise to “dirt and visible spots on the walls of the wall, discoloration and detachment of wall painting, fissures and damage of the tile wall, etc.”.
The work will be divided into three phases, depending on the area and the working method, including repair of the cracks in the central source of the Sé and the source wall around the Travessa do Meio, the replacement of the pumps and water pipes, the reconstruction of the waterproof waterproofs, the replacement of beds and stone benches on both sides. From the Travessa do Meio, the general cleaning of the stone walls, the renewal of the walls, the replacement of deteriorated tiles and murals, etc.
As this place belongs to the World Heritage Protection Zone, and is also an area with a large flow of people in the city center and adjacent to schools and the Cathedral, AMI has already consulted the opinions of the Soil and Urban Construction Services and the Cultural Institute and visited the Diocese of Macao and the Civic Associations of the Community neighborhood, to present their respective reparation and remodeling arrangements, aiming, optimize the details of the work.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 01:48:33</pubDate></item></channel></rss>