<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/elementos-de-instituicoes-de-ensino-superior-de-macau-foram-a-pequim/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>IAS wants to know the relationship of young people with fortune or bad luck</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/ias-quer-saber-qual-a-relacao-dos-jovens-com-os-jogos-de-fortuna-ou-azar/</link><description>The Institute of Social Action (IAS), through the Coordinating Office of Social Services Sheng Kung Hui, is carried out an inquiry to the young population about their participation in gambling or unlucky games. The inquiry began on Wednesday last week and ends on October 17.
This inquiry is intended for young people aged 13 to 35, aiming to “systematically collect the necessary information about the young people of MSAR to perform a study of the game's disorder,” says IAS. The data collected will also serve as a reference for the analysis of the needs of prevention and treatment of the game disorder for youth, as well as for the definition of the course to follow the development of services.
The Coordinating Office of Social Services Sheng Kung Hui Macau has invited young people from primary and secondary schools, higher education establishments, public services, companies and institutions and others in our community, to participate in the questionnaire. After completing the questionnaire, participants will have the opportunity to win a prize through a draw.
IAS calls for the participation of all the city's young people in the inquiry. All personal data collected will be kept confidential and used exclusively for analysis purposes.
When participating in the inquiry, young people qualify to gain awards through a draw, whose results will be released on November 30.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 08:26:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Risk of dengue fever propagation is “very high”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/risco-de-propagacao-de-febre-de-dengue-e-muito-elevado/</link><description>Health services say that, due to the frequent circulation of people among the various regions, the risk of cases imported from dengue fever in Macau or local propagation from imported cases is “very high”.
In a statement, the authorities point out that, in May, the Mosquito Propagation Index (Ovitrap) in Macao was 52.1%, which demonstrates that the activity of mosquitoes Aedes albopictus is active. In addition, in neighboring regions, such as the city of Zhongshan, local dengue fever cases have been reported this year.
Health services stress that "for the prevention and treatment of mosquitoes it is necessary to take integrated treatment measures, of which, the elimination of mosquito proliferation sources is the most effective." For this purpose, health services say they have reinforced the inspection and cleaning of mosquito proliferation sources in high -risk locations in the community, including vacant land, having made 6,289 inspections until May.
According to the authorities, the chemical elimination of mosquitoes in about 140 black points of hygiene in Macao was also reinforced, increasing the frequency of elimination of mosquitoes from once to twice a month. "Health services will continue to evaluate the risk of dengue fever transmission, adjusting the frequency of mosquito elimination according to the situation," reads the authorities' press release, which adds that at the same time, "they will pay close attention to the epidemiological situation of dengue fever in the surrounding regions and in Southeast Asia and perform the various preparatory work, with a view to protecting the population's health."</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 08:26:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai Downstairs to Portugal for the fall</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/sam-hou-fai-adia-visita-a-portugal-para-o-outono/</link><description>The chief executive decided to postpone the visit to Portugal to the fall due to the transition from the new Portuguese government and also because "there are several important matters in Macao," said Sam Hou Fai. Initially, the visit to Portugal was scheduled for the first half of this year.
 
Sam Hou Fai's visit to Portugal was postponed to the fall, said the executive head of the executive on the fringes of a visit to the Fai Chi Kei area, Canidrom and Ilha Verde. Initially, the government had pointed out to Portugal for the first half of this year, but then, with the Portuguese legislative elections, the chief's possibility of going to Portugal in summer was awarded. Now Sam points to the visit to the fall and justified the decision with the transition from the new Portuguese government and also because "there are several important matters in Macau".
In the fall, the Government of the Government should also go to Spain and Brussels, said the executive leader, adding that the program is currently being “approached and coordinated”.
The statements were made by Sam Hou Fai on Saturday, after visiting some surrounding neighborhoods and zones, such as the Patane Market, the Ilha Verde neighborhood and the Fai Chi Kei neighborhood, where he intended to find out about the business exploration environment. The boss also visited the former Yat Yuen canhydrome to alert the construction plan of the population's sports park.
 
Sam Hou Fai sees vitality in the economy of community neighborhoods
 
About this visit, Sam Hou Fai said he felt “the success” of stores with “their own characteristics” in social neighborhoods to attract residents and tourists. The government leader stressed that authorities will “continue to take action in various dimensions to improve the business exploration environment in social neighborhoods, reinforce the vitality, attractiveness and competitiveness of the community economy, as well as improve social infrastructure and equipment”.
Sam began by visiting the Patane Mercado Municipal Complex and took the opportunity to speak with the market vendins. He then moved to the Patane Food Center, where he talked to some residents and tourists, “encouraging food operators to constantly implement news to explore characteristics that attract more visitors,” cites a government note.
Sam Hou Fai then went to the Ilha Verde neighborhood, the Fai Chi Kei neighborhood and the adjacent areas, having visited several trade establishments. In addition, the Chief Executive also took the opportunity to visit the great social themed activity to boost the development of the community economy - the “Sanrio Character Dream Garden”, and the Feliz of Love Pavilion for the Fatherland of the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ). Finally, the boss visited the land of the former Yat Yuen Canidrome where the construction of a sports park is planned for the population.
After the visit, to journalists, Sam Hou Fai said that the Patane Food Center "is a very good example of market characteristic transformation", stressing that "the executive and the different sectors of society should reflect and consonant the situation of social neighborhoods, so that with mutual efforts and collaboration, they can improve the business exploration environment and raise the attractiveness to consumers."
Tai Kin IP, secretary for the economy and finance, stated that the project of the “Sanrio Character Dream Garden” was able to divert more than 240,000 visitors to that neighborhood, arguing that this “reflects the effectiveness of the measure”. The secretary explained that "the various services of his tutelage are preparing more projects to direct visitors to social neighborhoods, in order to activate the community economy and to commit more support to small and medium -sized businesses in the city's North Zone to proceed to a digital transformation."
Regarding the terrain of the former Yat Yuen Canid, Sam Hou Fai stated that the government has activated the plan that will turn this space into a sports park for the population, and the public contest of works for the first zone is scheduled to soon, he said. In parallel, the ruler assured that the works of the first zone will be considered so that they do not affect the functioning of the sports field and the Lin Fong Sports Center.
 
Government ponders take a slight meter to fai chi kei
 
Sam Hou Fai also revealed that the works for the east line of the light meter that connects the northern zone of the city to the mud steam "the good rhythm". The boss has advanced that the government is studying the possibility of extending the line of the light meter from Qingmao's border post to Fai Chi Kei neighborhood, as well as the future sports park of the population.
Raymond Tam, Secretary for Transport and Public Works, added that, in the underground part of the Sports Park, a parking lot will be built with more than 400 places for automotive vehicles, and the adjacent road network will be adjusted according to the access to the parking lot. However, to correspond to the use of the Sports Park, the works of the first zone and the second zone will cover the construction of superior passages for other crossings for existing pedestrians, on the opposite side of the Sports Park, and will be perfected the accessibility facilities without barriers.
Sam Hou Fai stressed that the government's orientation consists of “fully perceiving the economic environment and the general conjuncture of society, increasing interactivity with the population and listening to public opinion in a thorough manner”, and for this, the authorities will program more visits to other social neighborhoods.
 
Head of the Executive to visit the Great Bay until tomorrow
 
Sam Hou Fai began yesterday, with a delegation of the Government of MSA, a visit to six cities in the Great Bay: Shenzhen, Huizhou, Dongguan, Canton, Zhaoqing and Foshan. The chief executive returns to Macau tomorrow. During his stay, the Chief Executive will have meetings with managers of the six cities, “where they will exchange ideas in a deepening way on the continuous boost's development, the reinforcement of cooperation with mutual benefits, among other topics”, reads a press release released by the government. In addition, the delegation program also includes visits to developments under development and their companies in the areas of technological innovation, energy resources, among others, “in order to know the development situation of the important industries of those cities”. Elements of the MSAR government delegation include Tai Kin IP, Secretary for Economics and Finance, Chan Kak, Chief Executive's Office Chief, and Cheong Chok Man, Director of Regional Policy and Development Study Services, for example. During the absence of Sam Hou Fai, André Cheong, Secretary for Administration and Justice, acts interimly the duties of Chief Executive.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 08:29:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Middle East: UE urges all parts to step back</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/medio-oriente-ue-insta-todas-as-partes-a-darem-passo-atras/</link><description>European Union (EU) high representative Kaja Kallas yesterday called “all parts” to a step back to avoid a new climb in the Middle East. "I appeal to all parties to step back, return to the negotiating table and avoid a new climb," Kallas said, after the US bombardment against the main nuclear facilities of Iran. "Iran should not be allowed to develop a nuclear weapon, as this would constitute a threat to international security," Kallas said, adding that the ministers of European foreign affairs will debate the situation on Monday on Monday on Monday Brussels. The Iranian Foreign Ministry said yesterday that the United States launched a "dangerous war" against Iran following US attacks on three Iranian nuclear facilities.
The United States entered the Israeli war against Iran, bombarding the three main locations of the Iranian nuclear program, while President Donald Trump threatened Temerão's regime with more attacks if "peace does not arrive quickly." In a message to the nation, two hours later, Trump urged Tehor not to respond militarily and opt for peace. "Iran, the Middle East bully, must now make peace. If they do not, the future attacks will be much larger and much easier." For their part, some of the main ministers of the Israeli government have congratulated the US President "for his historic decision" after joining the offensive against Iran. Nato is also following the situation "closely," an Atlantic Alliance spokesman for EFE, while the allies negotiate a new goal of military expense before the 24th and 25th June.
EU foreign ministers gather on Monday to discuss, among other matters, recent developments after Israelite attacks on Iran and the climb of tensions in the region. In addition, the ministers will evaluate the options on the table to review the UE-Israel Association Agreement to verify if Israel is fulfilling their obligations on human rights regarding their military action in Gaza and the West Bank, although no decision is not foreseen.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 08:26:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Industrial and financial weakness is still barrier for a greater mozambican presence in Macao, analysts say</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/fraqueza-industrial-e-financeira-ainda-e-entrave-para-maior-presenca-mocambicana-em-macau-dizem-analistas/</link><description>Experts consider that Mozambican bet in Macau is kept conditioned by the lack of industry and financial resources, and that new partnerships, including in the new Chinese regional project, can project Mozambique on MSAR.
 
By visiting the Macao Forum Product Exhibition Center last year, the Academic Fatima Papolo, which studies Sino-Mozambican relations, has realized the existence of few Mozambique products on site, where articles from various Portuguese-speaking countries are exposed.
"There are many more Brazilian products, but it is, to some extent, a reflection of the Mozambican economic structure. I believe that, through the Macao Forum, we can also think about how to transform this economic structure positively and that will result in the existence of more Mozambican products to be sold in Macao," she has now told Lusa.
The territory imported from Mozambique last year, goods worth about 12 million patacas. In the case of Brazil, the value exceeded a billion million patacas. In this sense, paper refers to the need to create “more events” that put agents of the Macao and Mozambique trade “to discuss and explore possibilities for deepening these relationships”. "It is also necessary to put other individuals linked to industry, because only a developed industry can check out products that will be changed. Mozambique still needs to work hard on this development of the industry and this is how it will turn their products into manufactured, put them in the Macao market and, perhaps, from all over China," he says.
It constitutes "a differential" in the relationship between Mozambique and China, says papers, arguing, however, that "there has been a long time that it is not yet done." "It is important to look like a space of exchanges. In this case, investments should come to Mozambique, but Mozambican investments should also go to Macau. This second sense needs to be worked," he says.
Although China was one of the first countries to recognize Mozambique as a sovereign state, on the day it declared independence on June 25, 1975, the “fortification of ties” with Macau, then under Portuguese administration, will only take place after 1999. Much more alive, much more present, ”he says.
Historian Wu Zhiliang considers the creation of the Macao Forum “a recognition” of the role of the territory as a bridge between China and Lusophone partners.
Assuming that the region “has a lot to do to fulfill this mission well”, also president of the Macau Foundation refers to Lusa that the Forum should “expand its action, as well as the promotion of economic and commercial exchange, to the areas of teaching, culture and scientific research”.
Higher education, for example, was one of the areas of cooperation that gained encouragement in the post-transition. Of the 60 Mozambicans residing in Macao, more than half are students, estimates the president of the Friends of Mozambique Association.
Ângelo Patrício Rafael, also a professor at the University of São José, arrived in the territory in 2012 for a master's degree in international trade law, the result of a protocol between Eduardo Mondlane University and the University of Macao. But here, there is difficulties. "Universities, especially private, do not have financial capacity, for example, to assign complete scholarships to international students coming from Portuguese -speaking countries. On the other hand, it can be very expensive for these students to leave these countries," he says.
Rafael believes that "the challenge often goes through the right partners who believe in this role of Macao, who are willing to finance or somehow help in this process."
Regarding the reinforcement of sino-mozambican ties, “the hardest part”, reflects the official, is probably “the narrowing of these relationships beyond the institutional level”: “There is also a lot of culturally done, but I think [it is necessary] to enhance this interaction among peoples”.
An opportunity for Mozambique in the Chinese region constitutes, according to Fatima Papolo, the Great Bay, where they inhabit more than 86 million, and that Maputo should “enjoy and explore”. “I see a space in which Mozambique can promote their potential, can also seek services that will allow their economic development in various areas, from energy, industry, transportation, communication, because there is a lot of technological development in the area of ​​transport, to public policy formulation,” he proposes. And the Portuguese language, he says, will be “always advantage”: “It is necessary that Mozambique realizes this special place that has and makes good use of it, in the positive sense”. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 08:26:57</pubDate></item><item><title>New Zealand bet on cooperation despite differences</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/nova-zelandia-apostam-na-cooperacao-apesar-das-diferencas/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping and New Zealand Prime Minister Christopher Luxon highlighted in Beijing the solidity of bilateral relations and bet on deepening cooperation, despite the divergences of the approach between Beijing and the Cook Islands.
During the meeting, held at the Great Palace of the People, next to Tiananmen Square, XI pointed out that China and New Zealand “advance hand in hand” half a century ago, in a relationship that “was at the forefront” of Beijing's bonds with developed countries.
The Chinese leader said that both parties should “deepen economic and commercial cooperation”, explore new spaces in areas such as technological innovation and the fight against climate change, and “adequately manage differences”, preserving the principle of “mutual respect” and “pursuit of consensus”. Xi also noted that the two nations "have no historical conflicts or fundamental interests in dispute", which, he added, "must facilitate a constructive and stable relationship."
According to CCTV state television, Luxon reiterated that his country "maintains a commitment to the" one China "policy and expressed its intention to" reinforce high level dialogue ", while defending the expansion of cooperation in sectors such as agriculture, dairy and tourism. "The world is going through a period of uncertainty, and China is expected to play a relevant role," said the New Zealand Prime Minister, who was willing to collaborate with Beijing in the defense of the Multilateral Trade System and the preparation of the Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation Forum (APEC) that China will welcome by 2026.
The visit occurs in a context of diplomatic tensions between New Zealand and the Cook Islands, after signing an agreement between the South Pacific and China, which led Wellington to freeze part of his help to development. Beijing rejected Wellington's criticism and stressed that his cooperation with the Cook Islands "is not directed against third parties, nor should it be interfered or restricted by third parties."
China has argued that its agreements with the archipelago are based on “equality and mutual respect” and aim to “boost economic development and improve living conditions” in these territories of the Pacific.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 08:26:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Tesla will build electricity storage factory in China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/tesla-vai-construir-fabrica-de-armazenamento-de-electricidade-na-china/</link><description>Elon Musk's Tesla has announced that she has signed a contract in China to build her first large -scale storage factory for the Chinese power grid. "Tesla has officially signed its first project of a power storage factory for the mains in mainland China," said the group specializing in electric vehicles and also manufactures solar batteries and panels on his Chinese social network account.
The company said the installation, which should be "the largest" of its type in China, "will allow the adjustment of power grid resources and will effectively address urban energy supply pressures."
According to the Chinese financial newspaper Yicai, the contract signed by Tesla Shanghai, the city authorities of Shanghai China and China Kangfu International Leasing, provides an investment of four billion Yuan, ie almost 485 million euros.
Tesla installed a vehicle assembly line in Shanghai, which also produced more than 100 megapacks in the first quarter of 2025 for export, namely to Europe.
A megapack is a giant battery that can store more than 3.9 megawatt hours of electricity, equivalent to consumption of 3,600 homes on average for one hour, according to Tesla's 'website'.
The group stresses that these blocks, which resemble white containers, can be connected to each other to infinity, each with its own connectivity device.
At this stage, the American group claims to have installed the equivalent of more than 10 gigawatts hours (GWh), namely in several states such as Texas (81 units) and Alaska (37 units), as well as Australia (212 units).
The signing of this contract happens at a time of tense relations between Washington and Beijing, with the background of the trade war began by the President of the United States, Donald Trump.
Tesla's boss, billionaire Elon Musk, was a close advisor and financier of Donald Trump during his White House campaign and, by the end of May, headed the Government Efficiency Department (Doge, in the English acronym), whose mission was to drastically reduce federal expenses). More recently the relationship between Musk and Trump has determined in such a way that it led to an open war between them in their respective social networks.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 08:26:58</pubDate></item><item><title>New faces in the elections for indirect suffrage with exit from Kou Hoi In and Chui Sa Cheong</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/caras-novas-nas-eleicoes-por-sufragio-indirecto-com-saida-de-kou-hoi-in-e-chui-sai-cheong/</link><description>Kou Hoi In and Chui Sai Cheong, current president and vice-president of the Legislative Assembly, are out of the electoral race for indirect suffrage for the next legislature. Also counting on the absence of current deputies Vong Hin Fai, Chan Iek Lap and Wong Sai Man, the list of professional and industrial, commercial and financial sectors presented new guys to indirect elections, including Kevin Ho, businessman and nephew of Edmund Ho.
 
The unique lists of the indirect elections by industrial, commercial and financial sectors and the professional sector have already revealed candidates for this year's legislatures, with some new elements, as well as the departure of Kou Hoi In and Chui Sai Cheong, who are currently president and vice president of the Legislative Assembly. The two deputies since the first Legislature of the MSAR, which turn 71 and 72, respectively, can reform and leave the Hemiciclo.
The union of the business interests of Macao presented on Friday the list of four candidates, with two new faces and two deputies due. José Chui Sai Peng, the list leader, and IP Sio Kai remain on the list as in the last elections. Si Ka Lon, now deputy for direct suffrage, joins the team, and also enters the list also the businessman Kevin Ho. They are then off the list Kou Hoi In and Wong Sai Man.
The list was able to bring the proposal of 103 legal persons, totaling 108, so it should elect the four candidates. Quoted by All About Macau, José Chui Sai Peng, also Macao representative at the National People's Assembly (APN), said the team will hear opinions to make Macau's business environment more “attractive and profitable”.
José Chui Sai Peng refused to comment on the possibility of trying to be the new president of Hemiciclo, and in the last legislatures, this position has been held by number one on the list of industrial, commercial and financial sectors, such as Ho Iat Seng and Kou Hoi In.
IP Sio Kai, member of the Chinese people's Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC) and president of the Macao Banks Association, defends patriotism and expects to promote the development of the economy “in the presupposition of safeguarding national security, the country's interests and the harmony and stability of Macao”. In turn, Si Ka Lon, who is also part of APN, wants the government to provide more support for small and medium enterprises.
In his debut in legislative elections, Kevin Ho said he will promote a more harmonious and balanced relationship among workers and employers, creating a more favorable business environment.
Kevin Ho, who has been a member of APN since 2019 and now presides over the Macao Industrial and Commercial Association, is the nephew of Edmund Ho, the first head of the Mashely Executive, and grandson of Ho Yin, a known leader of the Chinese community in Macao.
 
Complete reformulation
 
The union of the interests of Professional Professionals, from the professional sector, proposed this year a completely new list, being absent from the Chui Sai Cheong list, as well as Vong Hin Fai, president of the Macao Lawyers Association, and Chan Iek Lap, doctor and president of the General Association of Macao Medicine Sector. As previously advanced the final point, Chan Iek Lap will not compete for elections for retirement reasons.
The three are replaced by Iau Teng Pio, current deputy named and lawyer, Vong Hou Piu and Wong Chon Kit. The two new candidates are members of the executive's head of the chief.
Vong Hou Piu, accountant and president of the Union of Macao Accounting Professionals Associations, also performs the functions of Macau Urban Renewal Fiscal Council, S.A. and the Cultural Development Fund, while Jerry Wong Chon Kit is a dentist and president of the Macao Stomatology Association, as well as member of the Community Services Advisory Board.
To the media, Iau Teng Pio stated that the team's political program “takes as guidance” the spirit of Xi Jinping's speeches about the development of Macao, focusing on the development of the rule of law and the defense of the rights and interests of professionals.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 08:26:56</pubDate></item><item><title>TSI maintains a sentence suspended from five months in prison to tourist who has sexually employed</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/tsi-mantem-pena-suspensa-de-cinco-meses-de-prisao-a-turista-que-importunou-sexualmente-empregada/</link><description>The Court of Second Instance (TSI) has decided to keep the penalty to a tourist who sexually harassed a hotel maid where he was housed. The Base Judicial Court (TJB) had sentenced the man to a five -month prison sentence, suspended for a two -year period.
The case dates back to July 21, 2023. That day, the tourist, housed in a mud hotel, called the hotel meal delivery service. Around 11:27 am, the man opened the bedroom door and let the maid enter the meal. According to the court, after entering the room, the tourist suddenly caressed the woman's arm with his hands. Although the woman tried to dodge, the man persisted in her acts, touching her over her back in the brain area of ​​the bra, trying to let go unsuccessfully. At this point, he implied that he wanted to have sex with her, but the maid refused. The woman left the room crying and a colleague, noticing the situation, asked the manager to help the police.
After the TJB sentenced the man to a penalty of five months in prison, suspended for a period of two years for the practice, in material, in the intentional and consummated form, of a crime of sexual harassment, the defendant appealed the decision claiming that the Court incurred a notorious error in the consideration of the evidence.
The TSI disagreed and pointed out that the appellant and the offended did not know or evidence in the file showing that the offended person has some reason to slander the appellant. The second instance concluded that there was no indication that the TJB rendered the conviction in doubt and, therefore, kept the penalty.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 08:26:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Floods in the south and downtown China leave tens of thousands of displaced</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/inundacoes-no-sul-e-centro-da-china-deixam-dezenas-de-milhares-de-desalojados/</link><description>The intense rains that have been reaching several southern and downtown China regions affected at least 300,000 people and forced tens of thousands of residents. About 60 million Yuan were channeled just to support emergency and reconstruction work in Guangdong, where about 70,000 people were redoled.
 
The intense rains that plague various southern and downtown China regions since the beginning of last week have affected at least 300,000 people and forced tens of thousands of residents, especially in Guangdong province.
In the village of Huaiji, one of the most affected areas, the rains caused flooding of up to three meters deep, leaving half of the local roads.
Images released on state television show muddy and neighbors and volunteers streets working in their cleaning.
The National Development and Reform Commission last week allocated 60 million Yuan to support the emergency and reconstruction work in Guangdong, where about 70,000 people were resolved, the Xinhua official news agency said. The situation is also critical in other provinces of the center and eastern of the country, such as Hunan, where the Lishui River has registered its largest flood since 1998.
In the village of Longshan, four people remain missing after being trapped in a flooded underground garage. In the neighboring province of Hubei, the authorities have removed hundreds of people in municipalities such as Hefeng and Laifeng. In the latter, a day care center was completely flooded and it was necessary to transport 500 children in rafts, said The Paper newspaper.
Chinese authorities keep an emergency response of level IV - the lowest of a four -level system - in at least nine regions.
The Ministry of Water Resources sent technical teams to high -risk zones and asked local governments to reinforce surveillance and preventive evacuation of vulnerable areas.
In the last summers, extreme climate events have caused damage in the Asian country: the summer months of 2023 were marked by flooding in Beijing, which left more than 30 dead and forced to resolve thousands of people.
In 2022, several extreme and dry heat waves hit the country and the east of the country, causing problems in supplying electricity to some hydraulic -dependent industries.
A year earlier, severe flooding in the central province of Henan, caused by unprecedented rainfall since there are records, caused the death of more than 300 people.
Local experts have warned in recent years that climate change may increase the frequency of extreme weather phenomena in the Asian country. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 08:26:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan cancels meeting with USA after Trump requires increases in military expenses</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/japao-cancela-reuniao-com-eua-apos-trump-exigir-aumentos-das-despesas-militares/</link><description>Japan canceled a high -level meeting with the United States scheduled for July, after Donald Trump's administration asks Tokyo to increase military expenses to 3.5% of GDP, the Financial Times reported.
 
Tokyo and Washington had scheduled the meeting of the respective foreign and defense ministers in the so -called “2+2” format in Washington to July 1, in which Marco Rubio and Pete Hegseth would participate respectively and Takeshi Iwayaya and Gen Nakatani on the Japanese side.
According to British Daily, the request for increased Japanese expenses with the defense was recently submitted to the Japanese government by the Pentagon's main political counselor Elbridge Colby.
The United States had already urged Japan to increase defense expenses to 3% of GDP, and the request for a new increase bothered the Japanese government, which decided to cancel the meeting, even though it had not yet been formally announced, according to Financial Times.
Another factor that led Tokyo to suspend the meeting in early July is the proximity of elections for the Japanese Parliament High Chamber, scheduled for July 20.
In 2022, after Trump's first term, Japan decided to double the annual defense budget to 2% of GDP by 2027, which represented a drastic change in the Post-War Japanese security policy, framed in a pacifist constitution that equalized the level of military expenses of NATO member countries.
The second administration Trump has criticized the security treaty between the United States and Japan, considering it unilateral, and indicated that Tokyo should pay more to host US troops parked in the Japanese archipelago, when bilateral Brazilian negotiations advance.
Japanese Prime Minister Shigero Ishiba made clear Tokyo's distance from Washington's demands, stating that decisions on defense expenses are the competence of the national government and not the requests of other countries.
The disagreement between Japan and the United States emerges shortly before NATO summit in The Hague next week, where the United States expects to approve the increase in military expenditure from member countries to 5% of GDP, a measure that Spain opposes and the United States themselves, by Trump's voice, say they are not required to accompany.
 
Inflation in Japan accelerates to Novo Máximo in two years
 
The main measure of Japanese consumer inflation accelerated for a new maximum of two years, when Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba prepares for summer elections and Banco do Japan is aware of price evolution.
Consumer prices, excluding fresh foods, accelerated for a third month to 3.7% over the previous year in May, according to a statement from the Ministry of Internal Affairs released.
This is the fastest pace since January 2023 and higher than the average estimate of 3.6% of Bloomberg economists.
Inflation in the food sector was again one of the main drivers, with the price of rice - the basic food of the country - to increase 102% over the previous year.
Service prices, an indicator closely observed by Banco do Japan (Boj), rose 1.4% over the previous year, slightly more than 1.3% in April.
The report comes at a time when the minority government led by Ishiba and opposition parties discuss the way to reduce repercussions with the population of increasing living costs, which contributed to the party's largest electoral setback since 2009.
The high pricing growth also supports Boj's predisposition to increase rates, at a time when the institution is awaiting clarity on US tariff measures and its economic impact on the fourth largest economy in the world.
Japanese inflation has been evolving at the fastest pace between the nations of the seven group in recent times and has been kept inside or above the goal of 2% of Boj for over three years.
With the elections for the Japanese Parliament High Chamber scheduled for July 20, Ishiba promised to give families money, and opposition parties require the first Always Sales Tax (VAT) reduction in Japan.
To calm the discontent of public opinion by rising rice prices, the government has taken a number of measures to lower the cost of cereal, helping to increase its popularity, which recently reached a historic minimum in a local media poll. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 08:27:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal point 2025.06.23</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/ponto-fatal-2025-06-23/</link><description>Japan canceled a high -level meeting with the United States scheduled for July, after Donald Trump's administration asks Tokyo to increase military expenses to 3.5% of GDP, the Financial Times reported.
 
Tokyo and Washington had scheduled the meeting of the respective foreign and defense ministers in the so -called “2+2” format in Washington to July 1, in which Marco Rubio and Pete Hegseth would participate respectively and Takeshi Iwayaya and Gen Nakatani on the Japanese side.
According to British Daily, the request for increased Japanese expenses with the defense was recently submitted to the Japanese government by the Pentagon's main political counselor Elbridge Colby.
The United States had already urged Japan to increase defense expenses to 3% of GDP, and the request for a new increase bothered the Japanese government, which decided to cancel the meeting, even though it had not yet been formally announced, according to Financial Times.
Another factor that led Tokyo to suspend the meeting in early July is the proximity of elections for the Japanese Parliament High Chamber, scheduled for July 20.
In 2022, after Trump's first term, Japan decided to double the annual defense budget to 2% of GDP by 2027, which represented a drastic change in the Post-War Japanese security policy, framed in a pacifist constitution that equalized the level of military expenses of NATO member countries.
The second administration Trump has criticized the security treaty between the United States and Japan, considering it unilateral, and indicated that Tokyo should pay more to host US troops parked in the Japanese archipelago, when bilateral Brazilian negotiations advance.
Japanese Prime Minister Shigero Ishiba made clear Tokyo's distance from Washington's demands, stating that decisions on defense expenses are the competence of the national government and not the requests of other countries.
The disagreement between Japan and the United States emerges shortly before NATO summit in The Hague next week, where the United States expects to approve the increase in military expenditure from member countries to 5% of GDP, a measure that Spain opposes and the United States themselves, by Trump's voice, say they are not required to accompany.
 
Inflation in Japan accelerates to Novo Máximo in two years
 
The main measure of Japanese consumer inflation accelerated for a new maximum of two years, when Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba prepares for summer elections and Banco do Japan is aware of price evolution.
Consumer prices, excluding fresh foods, accelerated for a third month to 3.7% over the previous year in May, according to a statement from the Ministry of Internal Affairs released.
This is the fastest pace since January 2023 and higher than the average estimate of 3.6% of Bloomberg economists.
Inflation in the food sector was again one of the main drivers, with the price of rice - the basic food of the country - to increase 102% over the previous year.
Service prices, an indicator closely observed by Banco do Japan (Boj), rose 1.4% over the previous year, slightly more than 1.3% in April.
The report comes at a time when the minority government led by Ishiba and opposition parties discuss the way to reduce repercussions with the population of increasing living costs, which contributed to the party's largest electoral setback since 2009.
The high pricing growth also supports Boj's predisposition to increase rates, at a time when the institution is awaiting clarity on US tariff measures and its economic impact on the fourth largest economy in the world.
Japanese inflation has been evolving at the fastest pace between the nations of the seven group in recent times and has been kept inside or above the goal of 2% of Boj for over three years.
With the elections for the Japanese Parliament High Chamber scheduled for July 20, Ishiba promised to give families money, and opposition parties require the first Always Sales Tax (VAT) reduction in Japan.
To calm the discontent of public opinion by rising rice prices, the government has taken a number of measures to lower the cost of cereal, helping to increase its popularity, which recently reached a historic minimum in a local media poll. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 08:26:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese support was “crucial” to Frelimo during and after independence, says an investigator</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/apoio-chines-foi-crucial-para-a-frelimo-durante-e-apos-guerra-de-independencia-diz-investigador/</link><description>Researcher Pedro Seabra considered that China played a “crucial role” in military and ideological support at the Front of Liberation of Mozambique (Frelimo), during and after the fight against the Portuguese Administration.
 
"Chinese influence, through Maoism, eventually helped unlock some of the internal debates and prevail over other options," said Seabra, deputy director of the Center for International Studies of the University Institute of Lisbon (ISCTE).
At stake was the need to incorporate “goals, agendas” and government solutions for post-independence, adapted to the specificities of armed struggle in Mozambique, in a context of ideological competition between China and the Soviet Union, whose models of political and military organization were distinct.
The ideology of Mao Zedong, founder of Communist China, promoted the mobilization of rural masses, the guerrilla war and self -sufficiency - principles that Frelimo would adopt in the struggle for independence, Seabra pointed out. "We are talking about an armed struggle with a very similar component, or very close, what was also the Chinese revolution itself," he said. "The support of peasants, the use of guerrilla tactics, the construction of popular armies. All of this did, from the outset, more sense from the point of view of maoism than of bolchevism," predominantly urban character, added the researcher.
The mobilization of the peasants for the armed struggle culminated with the victory in the civil war against the nationalist forces of Chiang Kai-Shek and the founding of the Popular Republic of China in 1949.
Mozambique's struggle for independence would begin 15 years later, with Frelimo's first attack against a Portuguese colonial administrative post in Chai, in the province of Cabo Delgado, in the north of the country.
Two years later, Mao would launch the Cultural Revolution, a mass political campaign to “deepen the class struggle under the proletarian dictatorship,” which for a decade plunged to China into chaos and isolation.
Still, the Asian country welcomed dozens of Frelimo combatants in military training fields, where they received training in rural guerrilla tactics, sabotage, explosive handling and Maoist political-military doctrine. Also influential Frelimo figures were received by Beijing, including Samora Machel.
The leader of the Mozambique Independence War and the country's first president from 1975 to his death in 1986 visited China four times - two of which before Independence in 1971 and February 1975.
China would become one of the first countries to establish diplomatic relations with Mozambique, as early as Independence Day, June 25, 1975.
Relations remain close: Mozambique is today one of the few countries to keep China a global strategic partnership and cooperation agreement - one of the highest levels of Chinese diplomacy - which reinforces not only political dialogue, but also “active cooperation” in areas such as “safety, energy, infrastructure, defense and technology”.
In addition to the African country, only Russia, Pakistan, Cambodia, Laos, Myanmar, Thailand and Vietname - all neighboring countries or in China - celebrated the same kind of agreement with Beijing.
In Maputo, the connection to the Chinese revolutionary past was also marked in toponymy: Massano de Amorim Avenue, located in one of the city's noble neighborhoods, was renamed Mao Tsé-Tung Avenue.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 08:26:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Deputies of the workers' and Fujian lists seek reelection in direct suffrage</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/deputados-das-listas-dos-operarios-e-de-fujian-procuram-reeleicao-no-sufragio-directo/</link><description>The lists linked to the Fujian community and the workers were the two who already presented the candidates for legislative elections for direct suffrage. Song Pek Kei replaced Si Ka Lon and is now a list of the Macao United Citizens Association, which has the current deputy Nick Lei. Ella Lei again leads the union for development and Leong Sun Iok remains like number two on the list.
 
Deputies Song Pek Kei and Nick Lei, Ella Lei and Leong Sun Iok are back in this year's legislative elections for direct suffrage. The two teams presented the list and the political program last Friday to the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal), having been the first to formalize the candidacy.
The Macao United Citizens Association, a list linked to the Fujian community, is headed by Song Pek Kei, who replaced Si Ka Lon, a deputy who moved this year for the indirect race with a guaranteed seat at the Assembly Table.
It is recalled that Fujian's list was the most voted in the 2021 legislatures with 26,599 votes obtained and three elected deputies-the reelection of Si Ka Lon and Song Pek Kei and the entrance to Nick Law's hemiciclo.
The list of candidates consists of ten people, the current deputy Nick Lei is number two on the list. The third is represented by Chan Lei Kei, who holds positions in various social organizations, as a member of the Youth Council and vice president of the Fukien Youth Federation of Macao, while the fourth is Loi Si Weng, member of the North Zone Community Services Advisory Board.
Accompanied by the charter of the Chan Meng Kam list, Song Pek Kei spoke on Friday and admitted that the team is “under greater pressure” and feel that the competition will be “the largest ever”, defining the goal of winning at least two places in the Legislative Assembly.
"Since the number of voters has increased more than 10,000 and reached 330,000, we have to work hard and face many challenges to get support," the deputy acknowledged, in statements to the newspaper Cheng Pou. Song Pek Kei did not give a firm answer about the confidence of the list to be the most voted again.
On the margin of presentation of the political program, quoted by All About Macau, Song stressed that the team's average age is 33 years and the group will give priority to six areas, namely national security, economic diversification, population welfare, employment protection, administrative efficiency and urban renewal.
Song Pek Kei was also questioned about overlapping the position of deputy and member of the Executive Board, but the official dismissed a possible conflict of the two functions. "The executive and the legislature coordinate development, although their functions and requirements are different, the essence of both positions is to promote the development of Macao and contribute to it," he said.
 
Faom lists
 
The Union for Development, a list associated with the Federation of Macao Workers' Associations (Faom), presented the team of 12 people led by current deputy Ella Lei, along with Deputy Leong Sun Iok. Lawyer Cheng Ka Man and the vowel of the Central Zone Community Services Advisory Board, Wu Hang San, debuted in the elections as number two and three on the list.
The Fan's list was the second most voted in the last elections, having obtained 23,761 votes and reelected two legislators.
Ella Law, in statements to the newspaper or Mun, said the team is mostly composed of young people, professionals and workers from different sectors, continuing to pay attention to resident requests.
Speaking about the political program, the deputy said that she will focus on improving the use of residents and life assistance measures, also hoping to promote the economy and expand the business environment.
"We are concerned with optimizing the affectation of educational resources, improving the health system, strengthening care and support for the elderly, children, disadvantaged groups and women, as well as improving transport infrastructure and facilitating citizens' mobility," said Ella Law, while Leong Sun IOK advocates the priority of employment for residents and better work protection and work protection.
Leong also intends to boost the reform of public administration and increase enclosure for sports and recreational activities and green spaces, improving the quality of life of residents.
Already Cheng Ka Man, also a member of the Youth Council and director of the Faom Youth Commission, said that work will focus on the development of education, employment and entrepreneurship by young people, "so that competent young people can have diverse career opportunities and options," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 08:27:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Artyzen Grand Lapa celebrates International Yoga Day with Collective Session</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/artyzen-grand-lapa-celebra-dia-internacional-do-ioga-com-sessao-colectiva/</link><description>International Yoga Day is celebrated on June 21, a day that marks the summer solstice in the northern hemisphere. Artyzen Grand Lapa pointed out the occasion yesterday morning at the hotel atrium, with a collective yoga session that brought together more than 120 participants.
O evento, subordinado ao tema global deste ano “Yoga for One Earth, One Health” (traduzível como “Ioga para uma Terra, Uma Saúde”), foi orientado por mestres e instrutores do instituto Yoga Light e da Associação Geral Desportiva de Ioga de Macau. Ao longo de 70 minutos, os participantes praticaram as poses clássicas do ioga de estilo Hatha, caracterizado por movimentos mais suaves e adequados tanto a iniciantes como a entusiastas da modalidade.
According to an Artyzen statement, the session began with "fundamental stretches, followed by several sun -greeting rounds [a sequence of twelve positions] and a fluid series of filed, seated, lying and supinement postures." As they practiced the exercises, participants were invited to pay attention to posture, breathing and body movements, in a "approach designed to improve flexibility, concentration and inner peace."
At the ceremony preceding the event, Artyzen Grand Lapa Human Resources Director Kent Chow reinforced the resort's commitment to “helping the community to nourish the body and spirit through cultural experiences and well-being” as well as to create “enriching moments for the Macao community and our guests”.
In his speeches, the representatives of Yoga Light, Rahul Hande and Yulia Tikhonova, focused on the beneficial properties of yoga. "More than physical movement, it is a way of life. Regardless of age, sex or physical condition, yoga teaches us to move consciously and live with intention," said the master of yoga. Yulia Tikhonova continued this line of thought, noting that "yoga increases flexibility, strengthens our immune system and helps to think more positively."
The representative of the local Indian community, Kavi Khemlani, expanded the reflection on the objectives of this millennial practice originating from India. "It is not just to twist the members or to sustain breathing. It is the exploitation of the mechanics of life; an experience in which everything becomes one. At a time when the world is moving rapidly in terms of technology, the yoga reminds us that we must develop an inner consciousness. It is more than physical-binds us to the universe of true consciousness."
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Macau received more than 3.3 million visitors in May</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/macau-recebeu-mais-de-33-milhoes-de-visitantes-em-maio/</link><description>Last May, Macau received 3,372,081 visitors, an increase of 25.3% compared to last year. The number of international tourists accounted for only 6.9% of this number, widely dominated by visitors from the interior of China.
 
In May, 3,372,081 visitors arrived in Macau, ie 25.3% more than in the same period last year. In total, in the first five months of the year, 16,327,537 visitors entered region, the highest number since 2019. Data were released by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) last Friday.
Despite this significant increase, the average period of permanence of the visitors was 1.1 days, less 0.1 days compared to the same period of 2024, while tourists and tourists maintained the respective 0.2 days and 2.3 days. Although the number of tourist entrances grew 9.4% in annual terms, it was the number of tour who observed the largest increase, with an increase in the order of 39.2%.
This is a trend that has been found since the beginning of the year: in the first five months of 2025, the number of entrances of tour and tourists increased by 26.4% and 2.4%, respectively, compared to 2024. The justification for the growth of short-term visitors may relate to several measures that have been implemented since last year to attract visitors from the interior of China.
It is recalled that the policy of individual visas for Hong Kong and Macau currently covers 59 cities of the continent, and the increase in the tax exemption limit of own use acquired by these visitors has been determined. In addition, since the beginning of this year that Zhuhai residents can visit the MSAR once a week, without limitations as to the number of times the visa can be requested.
DSEC data prove the effectiveness of these measures. In May, the number of visitors in the interior of China was set at 2,439,936, 31.4% in annual terms. Within this number, more than half (1,329,383) corresponded to visitors from the nine cities of the Greater Bay River Delta, with a 42.5% growth over last year. Zhuhai visitors specifically rose 66.1%. Also the entry of visitors from the regions of Hong Kong (621.106) and Taiwan (78,828) increased, respectively, 6.7% and 14.3%.
 
Philippines and South Korea dominated international tourist market
 
Among the 3.4 million visitors who arrived in Macau last month, only 232,211 were international tourists, which is just 6.9% of the total. Still, May's numbers represent a 25.6% increase over the same month last year.
The Philippines were the international tourist market with the highest representation (57,018) and also the one with a higher rise in annual terms, growing 59%. Still in Southeast Asia, the number of visitor entries from Indonesia (16,149) and Thailand (15,024) increased by 11.3% and 43.1%. On the contrary, the number of visitors of Malaysia (14,567) and Singapore (8,455) decreased 3.5% and 9.8% in the month in question.
In southern Asia, there were 14,774 visitors from India, less 7.4%. In Northeast Asia, the number of entries from South Korea (41,765) rose 22.8% and those of Japan (13,500) 36%. The number of visitors in the United States of America (11,241) had a homologous increase of 12.1%.
The DSEC also says that, as for the entrance route in Macao, 2,780,906 people entered Macao terrestrial (82.5% of the total), plus 32.4% in annual terms. The number of visitors to the Hengqin border post rose more than 70%, while maritime entries (10.3%of the total) and by air (7.2%) registered up 4.5%and 5.9%, respectively.
From January to April, 16,327,537 visitors entered the region, the highest number of the last six years. In the same period of 2019, the last year before the Covid-19 pandemic, 17,188,780 visitors entering Macao.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 08:28:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong and Macau Visual Arts Biennial Patent in Beijing</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/bienal-de-artes-visuais-de-hong-kong-e-macau-patente-em-pequim/</link><description>The Hong Kong and Macau Visual Arts Biennial is being shown at the Western Gallery of the National Center for Performative Arts in Beijing until July 13. The opening ceremony of the Hong Kong and Macau 2024 visual arts Biennial in Beijing took place last Tuesday, with the presence of Ho Hong Pan, substitute vice president of the Cultural Institute, along with eight of the artists participating in Macau.
Dedicated to the theme “Integration and Dialogue”, this year's Biennial covers visual arts, intangible cultural heritage and design, technological innovation, social design, among others. The Macao section has the theme "Not Macau, but it's called Macau". The means used vary between oil painting on canvas, acrylic combinations on screen, photography, multimedia, video, dynamic digital images, installations and immersive experience spaces.
The ten local artists include Cai Guo Jie, Ieong Wan Si, IM Fong, Lam im Peng, Lo Hio Ieng, Lou Kam Ieng, Ng Sang Kei, Ricardo Filipe dos Santos Meireles, Sit Ka Kit and Xie Yun. The 30 pieces/sets of contemporary art on display “reveal the ties and emotional links of artists with Macau - distant but intimate; strange but indispensable”, describes the Cultural Institute (IC).
At the inauguration ceremony, Hong Pan highlighted “the role of Beijing as a national cultural hub and a fundamental platform for artistic development”, noting that this exhibition “is a crucial window for Macao artists to present their works to a wider audience, with the aim of providing visitors of the capital a glimpse of the contemporary context of the Macao arts and the city's multicultural dynamism”. Ho Hong Pan also stressed the “Fruit and Longtime Cooperation between Macao and Beijing in various areas, including museums, cultural heritage, performative arts and artistic education”.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Government presents measures to encourage economy in ZAP</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/governo-apresentou-medidas-para-estimular-economia-no-zape/</link><description>The government held on Friday a meeting with Hotels of Zape to present to the sector measures to promote the tourism and the economy of that zone compared to the closure of the satellite casinos.
Helena de Senna Fernandes, director of Tourism Services (STD), presided over to the meeting and said that the government “assigns great importance to the development of Zape, and hopes that, through this meeting, ideas can be gathered and collecting opinions before implementing their work, in order to match the needs of the hotel sector, in order to join efforts to attract more visitor flows and improve the business environment”.
During the meeting, the authorities presented to the sector representatives preliminary measures in four directions, including the introduction of international intellectual property elements, the extent of the economic benefits of concerts, the proper use of spaces for the performance of activities and the optimization of the zone environment, among others. In addition, STD has encouraged hotel operators to explore new sources of visitors, launch complementary tourist products or accommodation promotions, "to create a rich and diverse tourism and consumption experience for visitors and residents."
According to the government's statement, “representatives of the tourist industry have generally agreed with preliminary measures” and, given the current situation of operation, “presented constructive opinions, working together to raise the vitality and attractiveness of Zape, boosting the transformation and development of trade between Zape and peripheral zones”.
In the press release, STD stresses that Zape has good tourist and commercial value facilities. The area has more than 20 hotel establishments of different types and categories, offering visitors a variety of accommodation options.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 08:26:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Ochoa revisits historical moment of sovereignty transfer with exhibition at Casino Estoril</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/rui-ochoa-revisita-momento-historico-da-transferencia-de-soberania-com-exposicao-no-casino-estoril/</link><description>Among the flashes of history and memory, Casino Estoril becomes a temporal portal from this Thursday. The exhibition ‘Macau: The Last Days of the Portuguese Administration’ reveals, through the lens of the renowned photojournalist Rui Ochoa, the decisive moments of December 1999. More than a journalistic record, these 50 photographs capture the poetic of political ephemeral. Gestures, looks and symbols that marked the transition from Macau to Chinese sovereignty.
 
The Estoril Casino Art Gallery hosts, from Thursday, the exhibition “Macau: The Last Days of the Portuguese Administration”, a collection of about 50 photographs captured by the prestigious photojournalist Rui Ochoa in December 1999, during the transition from territory to Chinese sovereignty. The show, organized by the Jorge Álvares Foundation in partnership with Estoril Sol, will be patent until July 27, with free admission.
The images, mostly unpublished, document the decisive moments that marked the end of almost five centuries of Portuguese administration in Macao. Among the most emblematic records are the signing of the Sino-Portuguese Joint Declaration (1987), the last Portuguese government meeting of the territory, the final session of the Legislative Assembly and the symbolic ceremony of the Portuguese flag slay, on December 19, 1999.
Rui Ochoa, then a photojournalist of Expresso, closely followed the days before the transfer of sovereignty, capturing not only official events, but also the daily life of a transitional city. His photographs transcend the documentary value, proving to be an artistic and emotional testimony of a period that marked the Lusophone history.  "The images captured witness not only the end of a cycle of nearly five centuries, but also the beginning of a new chapter in the history of Macao," says the administration of the Jorge Álvares Foundation in a statement.
Born in Porto in 1948, Rui Hernâni Ochoa is one of the most prominent figures of Portuguese photojournalism. He began his career at Jornal de Notícias and, from 1980, joined the Expresso team, where he ascended the editor and director of photography. Over the course of more than four decades, it has documented political and social events in Portugal and worldwide, publishing books such as “The Great Fire of Chiado” (2013) and “AFFECTS” (2016), the latter dedicated to Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa's presidential campaign, from those who have been an official photographer since 2016.
Primary with awards such as the Gazette of Journalism (1985) and the Society for News Design (USA, 1998), Ochoa was also awarded the degree of Commander of the Order of Merit in March this year.
The exhibition at Estoril coincides with the participation of Ochoa at the PhotoEspaña Festival in Madrid, where he presents “74-99”, a retrospective on the first 25 years of Portuguese democracy, as part of the 50th anniversary of April 25th. The show, which includes a selection of images originally displayed at the National Society of Fine Arts in 2023, will later travel to Zamora, continuing its itinerance within the same event. In recent statements, the photographer also mentioned plans for an exhibition on Mario Soares, scheduled for December at the Montepio Gallery in Lisbon, complementing the book “Mário Soares, 100 years”, published late last year in collaboration with Alfredo Cunha and Clara Ferreira Alves.
The exhibition “Macau: The Last Days of the Portuguese Administration” can be visited daily at the Estoril Casino Art Gallery. Admission is free, but reserved for over 18 years.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Elements of Macao Higher Education Institutions went to Beijing</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/23/elementos-de-instituicoes-de-ensino-superior-de-macau-foram-a-pequim/</link><description>The Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) has organized a delegation of 28 elements of the middle and higher level personnel, teachers and main investigators from Macao, foreigners or whose mother tongue is not Chinese, for a study visit in Beijing, which took place last week.
Classes began on June 17 at Beijing Language and Culture University. Prior to the opening ceremony, DSEDJ Director Kong Chi Meng, the head of the Department of Education and Youth Affairs at the Central Government Cabinet in the MSAR, Li Xuefei, and the international qualified staff of Macao Higher Education Institutions performed an exchange.
Kong Chi Meng said that “the Government of MSA continues to promote internationalization and the development of high quality higher education in Macao, to strive to attract and concentrate more international qualified frames in Macau” to the “construction of Macau as a place of aggregation of qualified frames around the world, as well as to take advantage of internal and external connection, in profoundly integrating the uniqueness of cultures miscegenation. Chinese and Western in the educational system ”.
In the press release released by DSEDJ, the body guarantees that “it will continue to travel to China from international qualified staff of Macao Higher Education Institutions to study and know the development of specialties and scientific research in the interior of China, reinforcing the knowledge of teaching and non -teaching staff of higher education institutions and educational development, forming qualified staff in needs in need. national and macao strengths ”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 08:26:55</pubDate></item></channel></rss>