<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/do-purpura-real-ao-cinza-da-penitencia/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>“It is not essential to have talent in art, but initiative”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/nao-e-essencial-ter-talento-na-arte-mas-sim-iniciativa/</link><description>Joana Merlini is an thought -provoking creator who synthesizes her multicultural identity in urban interventions. Known as Jojo Stickers, he was born in Macau and uses the streets as screens to spread messages of “love and connection” through murals and stickers. He believes in the power of initiative as the essence of art, leading his experiences and visions to communities around the world through art collectives, such as the solidarity project "You Are Not Alone". This year participates in HKWALLS, renowned “street art” festival in the great neighboring metropolis. In an interview with the final point, Joana Merlini leaves a glimpse of a learning life around the world.
 
"Art is love and I want to spread love." This is how the conversation with Joana Merlini started. A life story surrounded by creativity and the search for new places that would welcome a curious and desire to share an incessant desire to create, forever accompanied by a pride in saying, "I'm from Macao."
"If something doesn't exist, I feel that I need to create it." Thus a multifaceted artist works, which stands out for its involvement in projects that cross borders and cultures. Born in Macao in 1986, he graduated from multimedia from the Lusíadas University of Lisbon, returning to Macao to start his artistic journey in 2016. It was this year that he joined his Gantz5 Urban Art Group mentor to explore the creative possibilities of murals painting, also known as “Graffiti”. Since then, it has become a remarkable presence on the streets and walls of various cities, including Hong Kong, Czech Republic, England, Portugal and the USA.
Known artistically in the world of street art as Jojo Stickers, he discovered a passion for the creation and distribution of small -shaped stickers, another way to express this desire to intervene in the city and expose their ideas to the inhabitants of urban space. This practice that led her to know other artists anonymously through 'stickers' who emerged around their own.
One of its projects consists of three pieces of art in paste-up, an urban art style that consists of pastening paper or images printed on public surfaces using different types of adhesive. The works were inspired by the correspondence between Virginia Woolf and Vita Sackville-West, to the Royal Academy of Arts in Bristol. This immersion in literature reflects its understanding that art can capture profound emotions and stories, but it was the practice of past-up that has now brought it to the HKWALLS urban art festival.
The initiative that has been taking place for 10 years will take place between March 22 and 30 and coincides with the month of Hong Kong art. HKWALLS is a non -profit artistic organization that aims to promote street art and urban culture in Hong Kong. It focuses on connecting artists, both local and international. The event serves as a platform for the exhibition of various talents, while seeking to increase awareness of the importance of urban art in the community. In addition, HKWALLS offers programs aimed at professional development and artist workshops, one of which will be presented by Merlini, on the theme of the art of Pasture-Up, with the support of Macao CollexTives.
His contagious conversative energy and avid dedication makes Joana Merlini a creator who believes in the transforming power of art, using her platform to promote messages of hope, connection and resilience in communities.
 
How did your artistic course culminate in participation in a festival like HK Walls?
My artistic route began in Macao, influenced by my mother who is an architect and my father, engineer, responsible for several buildings in Macau. I started from a little girl to draw and paint. By the way, my mother's greatest pride is still when I won a drawing competition as a child and kept that flame on the drawing and always painted. At age 20 I met Pat Lam, also known as PIBG2038, the largest in Graffiti here in Macau. It was my mentor and helped me enrich this curiosity for art in murals. But I wanted to create more impact on people's lives, because I am so much to spread love. After spending time in Lisbon, where the urban art scene was not so developed, I realized that I needed to expand my horizons. I moved to the Czech Republic, where I had the opportunity to teach at the University of Prague and dive into the city's art scene through “Art Jam Sessions” (joint art sessions) and workshops with the local community in partnership with Molotow Prague. It was a very authentic experience, where art was inserted around every corner and had time, because of Covid, to observe this artistic side more. Then I went to London, where I first participated in the Paste Up Festival, which helped me connect with artists from around the world and start my adventure through the various conferences. I now actually part of five, Art House Project in London, London Paste Up Festival, Bristol Mural Collective, Suicide Prevention Project “You Are Not Alone Murals” and Lisbon Walls Collective. I also involved with social causes such as “Yes You Can Spray” in Lisbon and “Urban Pictus” in Prague. Now, back to Hong Kong I'm going again to be organizing an 'Paste-Up' Art Jam at HKWALLS and I feel like I'm here to give Macao artists a voice and represent the culture we have. Because some say that Portuguese born in Macau are not Macanese. But I always feel macanese.
 
What is the main objective of the 2025 HKWALLS Festival and how does this edition celebrate its 10th anniversary in a special way?
The HKWALLS Festival is a celebration of urban art, but is fundamentally about community and inclusion. For the 10th anniversary, they highlight the importance of art as a universal language that connects people. Therefore, I think the main objective is to give a platform for local and international artists to join, share their narratives and create. As Jason Dembski, the festival co -founder said: “The diversity of selected artists helps to highlight the possibilities of the variety of projects presented to the public, and we hope to inspire young artists. We are also organizing workshops, such as what will be done with Pat Lam and the Macau Outloud team, and we launch a new program called H.K. Rooms Walls for Exhibitions. This year's edition will be special with interactive events and exhibitions that emphasize the diversity of artistic voices, creating a space where everyone has the opportunity to express themselves and be heard. The graffiti scene is growing, but is still small compared to European cities. Hong Kong's audience has become more welcoming compared to street art, and we are helping with initiatives as a mentoring program for young artists. ” The intention of my Pasture-Up project at HKWALLS fits well with this attempt to interact with Hong Kong's audience and anyone who wants to come from Macau participates.
 
What would be the 'paste up'? How do you integrate inside HKWALLS?
Paste Up is a street art technique that transforms the urban environment through the collage of paper -printed works. It is light, accessible and, above all, creative. Within HKWALLS, Paste Up takes a central role, not just as a form of art, but as a means of social interaction. We planned to create a space where the walls serve as screens for artists of various styles, allowing a mix of ideas. The idea is to create an evolutionary mural, where artists can interact, and every piece of art will tell a new story.
 
How does your experience and artistic background in Macau and Portugal contribute to the creative vision that now brings to the festival?
My experience in Macau has brought a profound understanding of its traditions and the cultural fusion that happens here. At the same time in Europe, especially Lisbon and then Bristol, it provided me with a view of contemporary urban art and how it can be a engine of social change. This combination of influences shaped my creative view for HKWALLS. I want this festival not just an artistic event, but a platform that creates significant dialogues and demonstrates the evolution of urban art. I am here to bridge between local and international artists, bringing unique experiences of various cultures, including Macao, based on my experience in event organization as well. Sometimes I feel that I am very lucky to know these people and places, but as my family always said, "Luck is looking for!"
 
What are the biggest challenges you faced when balancing your own artwork with the organization of events and art collectives?
One of the most significant challenges has been to motivate and engage other artists, especially when my work is voluntary. Sometimes I feel that it is a lonely effort, where I am the only one to pull through the group. It is exhausting when so many talented people are around me, but there is not always the same willingness to get involved. It is not essential to have talent in art, but initiative. This makes me reflect on the importance of the community and how we can support each other. Despite the challenges, I'm here for passion. I speak to the artists, I send messages, confirm if they sent, look for more artists and try to give more space for each one. Art is my life and my purpose, and even if obstacles arise, I will never cease to believe that we can create something amazing together.
 
In your opinion, how is Macao developing in urban art?
I confess that as I have been out of Macau for some time I don't know which specific entities talk about, but I try to know. But I would like some connection, for example, with the Hong Kong festival. But create these cultural collectives I find it super important, especially in a macau-Portuguese connection. I believe that Macau has great potential to develop urban art through cultural collectives and collaborations. It is crucial to establish connections between artists from Macao and abroad, such as the Outload Festival group, especially in such an interconnected world. There are international prominent artists, who can even be invited to the events, but what about us, the places? We should have greater support, more appealing support on the legal walls of Macao. I would like to create more ties and make this past-up "pet" for people to start doing more. Right now being talking to the newspaper and leaving this message here, that it is possible to do, and maybe while I am not in Macau I can try to propose at a distance and create a paste-up festival by the end of the year. Who knows?
 
Any artist or urban art group that would like to highlight as an influence or for their work?
An artist who has always inspired me is the PIBG2038, has been a kind of mentor for me. Another highlight would be the duo AAFK, a couple I admire a lot. My collaboration with the collective Bristol Mural, a group that is dedicated to social causes through art can also be another example. I am not much of choosing an influence or talking about others. But I recently met a young artist named Nespoon, by Hong Kong, who has a unique style, mixing embroidery elements, such as those lace that grandparents have, in their works, which is a creative and very inviting approach. In the scenario of urban art, each one brings its own narrative, and this is what makes the community unique.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Timorese NGO condemns cases of sexual harassment in schools in the country</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/ong-timorense-condena-casos-de-assedio-sexual-nas-escolas-do-pais/</link><description>The Non-Governmental Organization forum of Communication of Women of Timor-Leste (Fokupers) yesterday sentenced cases of sexual harassment in schools in the country and demanded the “urgent attention” of society and the Timorese State.
"Schools and universities should be safe spaces for learning and the development of new generations, guided by the spirit of wisdom, not places of violence," Filomena Barros dos Reis, spokesman for Fokupers, said at a press conference held at the headquarters of that non-governmental organization in Dili.
Last week the Ministry of Education publicly reported two cases of sexual harassment in two schools in the country, perpetrated allegedly by the principals of those educational establishments. "There are cases of abuse and sexual harassment in two secondary schools, Nicolau Lobato Secondary School and the 5th Secondary School, which requires a firm condemnation on our part," he said.
Fokupers has condemned those crimes and said it will continue to develop law actions to combat all forms of violence against women and girls, requiring government entities to take concrete measures to guarantee justice to victims.
The non-governmental organization has appealed to the Ministry of Education so that, in addition to the application of disciplinary sanctions, it reinforces research processes. If the results of the investigations indicate criminal evidence, cases should be referred “quickly” to the judicial system, in order to ensure just and effective justice to the victims, he noted.
To prevent sexual harassment situations, the spokesman also appealed to the Minister of Education for the recruitment of principals and teachers to be performed with the maximum rigor, ensuring that workers in the field of education perform functions with professionalism, dedication and respect for the principles and values ​​of human rights.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:31:14+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sporting leader with demanding visit to Casa Pia in Ronda de SP.Braga-FC Porto</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/lider-sporting-com-visita-exigente-ao-casa-pia-em-ronda-de-sp-braga-fc-porto/</link><description>Sporting visits Casa Pia, in matchday 25 of the First Football League that the Lions seek to win and avoid disagreement similar to that of rival Benfica, defeated on the visit to Rio Maior.
 
Sporting has this journey a complicated challenge against Casa Pia in which the 'lions' seek to win and avoid a disagreement similar to that of rival Benfica, defeated on the visit to Rio Maior.
The leader, title champion, only enters the field only on Sunday, a day after Benfica, who is behind in the classification, three points, but with less a meeting played, playing at Estádio da Luz with Nacional.
The 'eagles' will end this journey still with this difference from a game for Sporting, regarding matchday 24, given that the visit to Gil Vicente is scheduled only for March 28.
In Ronda 25, Benfica has theoretically accessible commitment to the National, and, in case of victory, can put some pressure on Sporting, which will have an opponent who will be able to create greater problems at the outset. Still, the incarnates arrive at the round after a difficult test in the Champions League, at home with FC Barcelona.
Sporting, outside the millionaire test, continues to try to manage several physical problems on the squad, but with the very positive note to be able to rely on the midfielder Morita and have Viktor Gyökeres in the best moments.
The Swedish scorer, who had to be physically managed in recent times, seems to return to goals and has again made damage on the last day, with a 'bis' to Estoril Praia and the ability to stretch the Leonino game, frightening the contrary defenses.
Casa Pia, sixth, can still be demanding test to national champions, at a time when the team has not lost at home for the championship since late August, with four draws and six wins, one of which with Benfica (3-1).
Sporting de Braga and FC Porto, fourth and third, respectively, face Braga on Saturday, in a "big" game that can be crucial in future accounts and when the "dragons" are six points of leadership and with only three more than the "arsenalists".
For FC Porto the fight is made on two fronts, in its still candidacy for the title, but also in the third place and the proximity of Sporting de Braga, which in the last day was a little behind, losing on the visit to Rio Ave.
The 25th match opens on Friday, with the star of Amadora, in danger zone, located on 16th (of the maintenance play-off), to receive Gil Vicente, 15th and with less one game, and when both teams have the same 22 points.
The round of the round is scheduled for four days later, on Monday, also between two emblems practically 'glued', with Famalicão (ninth, 31 points) to receive Rio Ave (10th, 20). Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:31:20+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China highlights “jump” in the “strategic” domestic robotics industry</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/china-destaca-salto-na-estrategica-industria-de-robotica-domestica/</link><description>China's robotics technology gave a “jump”, and the difference with international developments and standards “decreased significantly”, yesterday defended an expert, on the sidelines of the plenary session of the country's maximum legislative agency.
 
At a press conference, Qiao Hong, a robot industry expert at the Chinese Science Academy, highlighted the rapid progress made by China and the strategic importance of robotics for the country's economic future.
Until about a decade ago, China imported almost all the industrial robots used in its factories. In 2024, internal production increased by 14.2%, in homologous terms, to 556,000 units, according to data cited by Qiao.
A robot is any machine capable of automatically performing a number of tasks, and includes robotic arms, autonomous cars or non -manned air vehicles (“drones”). But Qiao also highlighted the country's advances in the humanoid robot segment, which can use tools and operate in human environments such as homes, hospitals or homes of elderly.
The use of these robots, with head, trunk, arms and legs, in factories and warehouses, converges with the development of artificial intelligence systems, such as the Chinese deepseek platform, and can compensate for the rapid aging of China's population, which is assumed as a country of "non -imigration". “Humanoid robots are expected to become the next revolutionary innovation to follow computers, mobile phones and new energy vehicles, profoundly transforming production, human lifestyles and global industrial landscape,” reads a recent direction by the Ministry of Industry and Information Technologies of China (MIIT).
The humanoid robot market in China reached approximately 2.76 billion yuan in 2024, according to Qiao Hong.
The expert highlighted the “comprehensive industrial system” and the “robust supply chain”, which allows the country to effectively produce the components and complete equipment of the machines needed for the robots.
Qiao also pointed to the scale of the domestic market. “China has a huge demand for robot applications in sectors such as transformative industry, logistics and services. This vast dimension of the market and the diversity of application scenarios in China offer a continuous impulse for the iterative update of robot technology, ”he said.
MIIT guidelines include objectives and calendars for the sector, with emphasis on movement control and man-machine interaction. The ministry indicated that by 2027 humanoid robots must be integrated into the production chains “on a large scale” and their wide use to “whole society”. “Progress should be achieved in developing hands, arms and robotic feet, as well as the integration of artificial intelligence,” reads the document.
The approximately 3,000 delegates to APN, including a representation of the Armed Forces, are not, however, elected by direct suffrage, and the "leading role" of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) is "a heart principle." Delegates include the political elite, business, technological, media and artistic leaders of the Asian country.
This week, the delegates will pass new laws, political appointments and government reports, which detail the progress of various departments and ministries. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:31:16+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong Court nullifies convictions of former Tiananmen vigil organizers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/tribunal-de-hong-kong-anula-condenacoes-de-antigos-organizadores-de-vigilias-de-tiananmen/</link><description>The Hong Kong Superior Court annulled yesterday the condemnation of three former vigil organizers in memory of the victims of student repression in Tiananmen, in a victory for the pro-democracy activists of the former British colony.
 
Chow Hang-Tung, Tang Ngok-Kwan and Tsui Hon-Kwong, members of the Hong Kong Alliance to support China's Democratic Patriotic Movements, had made a request to the court to nullify the conviction. The three were sentenced to four and a half months in prison for refusing to cooperate with the police authorities, having already served the penalty.
The alliance was long known for organizing candlelies in the city on June 4th every year, when the anniversary of the repression of pro-democracy protests of 1989 in the Chinese capital is marked. However, the group decided to dissolve in 2021, following the imposition by Beijing of the National Security Law in that territory.
Critics claim that the closure of the alliance and this case is a sign of “that western -style civil liberties in the city are decreasing, despite promises that they would be kept intact when the former British colony returned to Chinese dominance,” which happened on July 1, 1997, wrote the Associated Press news agency.
Prior to the dissolution of the alliance, police tried to obtain detailed information about the group's operations and finance, allegedly due to alleged connections to pro-democracy groups abroad, accusing him of being a foreign agent. The group denied the accusation and refused to cooperate.
Yesterday, the Judges of the Hong Kong Superior Court decided unanimously in favor of the trio. The President of the Court, Andrew Cheung, announced the decision in court.
During a previous hearing in January, Chow Hang-Tung, who was represented to herself, said the case showed what a police state is. “A police state is created by the court's complicity in supporting such abuses. This kind of complicity should end now, ”said the activist, also a lawyer.
Since the Security Act came into force in 2020, several non -permanent foreign judges abandoned the Superior Court, raising questions about trust in the city's judicial system. In 2024, magistrate Jonathan Summption abandoned office and said the rule of law was deeply compromised. Cheung declared in January that the premature exits of the judges did not mean that the independence of the judicial system was diminished.
The annual vigil at Parque Victoria de Hong Kong was for decades one of the rare public ceremonies related to June 4's memory on Chinese soil, with thousands of people attended it annually, until the authorities banned the event by 2020, invoking anti-standing measures.
After surveying the restrictions imposed by Covid-19, the park was occupied on June 4 of this year by a carnival organized by pro-peak groups. Those who tried to mark Tiananmen were arrested. Chow and two other ancient alliance leaders, Lee Cheuk-Yan and Albert Ho, were accused of subversion in a separate process under the security law. They remain detained, awaiting the beginning of the trial. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:31:16+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>South and US Korea start annual military exercises next week</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/coreia-do-sul-e-eua-iniciam-exercicios-militares-anuais-na-proxima-semana/</link><description>South Korean and American troops start annual military exercises next week. The South Korean and American forces will participate in Freedom Shield, a computer-simulated control of computer, with military exercises on the ground, from Monday to 20 March.
 
South Korean and American troops start set-up annual military exercises next week, announced yesterday, days after North Korea threatens with high-level demonstrations against what he called the US-led aggression.
The South Korean and American forces will participate in Freedom Shield, a computer-simulated command training training, with military exercises on the ground, from Monday to 20 March, the South Korean joint is jointly a statement in a statement.
According to the statement, the exercise “Shield of Freedom” will imply answers to evolving challenges, such as the growing military partnership of North Korea with Russia.
North Korea considers large -scale military training between South Korea and the United States as an invasion test and often responds to missile tests and inflamed rhetoric.
North Korea did not respond to the announcement, but earlier this week Kim Yo Jong, the influential sister of North Korean leader Kim Jong Un, accused the United States of intensifying confrontation actions and threatened to increase measures "that threaten the safety of the enemy at the strategic level."
Kim Yo Jong cited the recent temporary detachment of US strategic means, such as a Long-range aircraft carrier and bombers in South Korea and other military activities with the participation of the United States.
According to observers, North Korea will be able to test powerful, nuclear missiles designed to reach the US continental territory and US military bases in the region.
United States President Donald Trump has already stated that he will contact Kim Jong Un again to print a new diplomatic dynamics between the two countries.
North Korea did not respond directly to Trump's approach, arguing that United States hostilities against the country has deepened since Trump's inauguration on January 20.
Kim Jong Un and Trump gathered three times in 2018 and 2019 to discuss the economic and political benefits that North Korea would receive in exchange for poisoning through nuclear disarmament.
This diplomatic impulse eventually collapsed after Trump rejected Kim's offering to dismantle his main nuclear complex, a limited step of denuclearization, in exchange for ample relief from sanctions. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:31:22+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Panda diplomacy</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/a-diplomacia-do-panda/</link><description>Considered one of the symbols of the Popular Republic of China, the giant panda is associated with peace, innocence and treated as a national treasure. Its natural habitat is in the mountainous regions of the provinces of Sichuan, Shanxi and Gansu in downtown China. In Chinese culture, due to its white and black coat, the animal is regarded as a perfect balance of Yin Yang, representing the balance of energies.
In the 1950s the pandas began to be used by China as a diplomatic gift, in a gesture of courtesy, recognition and friendship. Panda's “diplomacy” is the name given to the gesture in which the Popular Republic of China presents another country with one of its pandes, within the scope of foreign policy. Recently, after Panda was recognized as an extinct species, China eventually reviewed the act of giving the animals, being borrowed for ten years, for the value of one million US dollars per year, by copy. If reproduction exists, each child will have the cost of four hundred thousand US dollars per year, all pandas owned by China. However, the fact that animals have a price does not mean that any country can acquire a copy. China establishes its loan gesture only to selected countries, with which it maintains strong political or economic relations.
At the time of the celebrations of the 10th anniversary (2009) of the transfer of powers from the territory of Macao de Portugal to China, the mother mother presented Macau with a couple of panda. Unfortunately, a few years later, the female would eventually die due to kidney problems and the Popular Republic of China offered a new couple with the same name: “Sam Sam” and Hoi Hoi ”, which in Cantonese mean joy and happiness, respectively, and who dwell in the Macao Giant Panda Pavilion in Seac Pai Van Park. In the summer of 2016 Macau was blessed with the birth of male twins. After the population vote the selected names were “Jian Jian” and “Kang Kang” which, when pronounced together, means health.
Peculiar how only Macau knows how to be, in this bamboo scaffolding jungle, when when I'm not flying agile motorcycles I am suffocating with the light pollution of the casinos, I feel privileged and blessed by my auspicious front neighborhood, the panda couple and their two children.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:31:14+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Caeal “respects freedom of the press” and asks for impartiality in the elections</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/caeal-respeita-a-liberdade-de-imprensa-e-pede-imparcialidade-nas-eleicoes/</link><description>The Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) yesterday gave a lecture for the communication agencies, to prepare the legislative elections that will be held on September 14. At the time, Seng Ioi Man, president of the body, said that Caeal "respects freedom of the press", asking the media to safeguard impartiality. "
 
Yesterday afternoon a lecture was held by the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) addressed to the media to prepare the legislative elections that are scheduled for September 14. Seng Ioi Man, chairman of the commission, highlighted the role of the media and left requests for impartiality.
Seng Ioi Man began to say, in the discourse he gave at the time, that "the media plays the role of bridge and platform that connects all sectors of society, whose reports are an important means for the public to obtain information."
Thus, the media are "an indispensable element in elections," since their work is "an important means for the public to get information." The media are "an indispensable element in the elections, and their supervisory function is essential for elections to result in the law and in an environment of impartiality, justice and integrity."
"Caeal attributes great importance to the role of the media and respects freedom of the press, safeguarded by the basic law of masters and the electoral law to the Legislative Assembly," said the judge of the court of second instance.
Noting that the media “has always always performed its functions with professionalism, objectivity and impartiality,” Seng Ioi Man pointed out that both the press and Caeal itself have the same end: “to ensure impartiality in elections and to treat all definitely admitted application lists equally”.
The official said he hoped that the media will be able to distinguish the concept of news report and electoral propaganda. Noting that in the legislative elections of 2021, journalists “demonstrated impartiality and proved [their] professionalism,” Seng Ioi Man said they were convinced that, in the elections of September 14, the media “will continue to perform their role with professionalism, namely in the dissemination of information about the elections”.
"Social communication must objectively report the electoral campaign activities of the candidacies, according to the rules that regulate the media and the right to inform the public, and should be considered a news and non -electoral reporting, so it is not subject to the content of the instructions," said Seng Ioi Man, adding that Caeal expects to "safeguard impartiality in these elections with the media."
The organism's manager recalled that the media can maintain all reports on the election campaign online, and it is advised to be headline or highlight these reports during the period of reflection and election day. On the other hand, the sharing of news about online platform elections during the period of reflection and the day of elections "may constitute electoral propaganda, and responsibility lies with the person who performs the sharing and not in the media themselves."
The leader of Caeal left another “good faith” alert: “During the period of the election campaign, if the media want to conduct exclusive interviews with the candidates, they should treat all lists equality. Outside the election campaign period, bodies may interview candidates with relevant positions or social identities on social matters or welfare issues, but they must remain away from electoral matters. ”
Caeal wants to “continue to maintain good interaction with the media”, hoping that the work inherent in the elections will be done “quietly”, encouraging an “active participation of more voters in these elections for the Legislative Assembly”.
These are the first elections held after the entry into force of the new electoral law to the Legislative Assembly. The diploma stipulates that the State Security Defense Commission analyze the applications, being excluded the candidates considered non -patriotic. Deleted candidates will not be able to claim or file a litigation. In addition, it provides for the criminalization of incitement to abstention.
In the 2021 elections, even before the approval of this new law, Caeal excluded dozens of candidates from the Democratic wing, including, for example, NG Kuok Cheong - deputy for over 30 years -, as they do not allegedly defend the basic law or not faithful to MSAR. In these elections, there was a historical abstention rate of almost 58%.
 
 
BOX:
 
All About Macau again barred by press conference
 
All About Macau, local media, was again refused to enter a press conference, which took place yesterday in the next legislative elections. According to an article, the informative portal was again excluded in the invitation list and was prevented from participating in the press conference with the justification of lack of space in the event room, which was in the multipurpose room of the Public Service Workers Training Center at Cheng Feng Shopping Center, Nape. The event was organized by the Electoral Affairs Commission of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal), being a lecture for representatives of the media, whose agenda note, however, specified that “only journalists and daily and weekly newspapers, TV stations, radio stations and news agencies are invited, due to limited space”. All About Macau has questioned the authorities about the stipulation, but Caeal has reiterated that it will maintain the same willingness in the future for official activities related to legislative elections. ” It is recalled that the information agency had already been excluded from the news coverage of various government events, including the Legislative Assembly Spring Lunch. All About Macau journalists tried to question Kou Hoi In, President of Hemiciclo, about the impediment of entry into the event, but received no response. The situation has already motivated several complaints from the Macao Journalists Association.
 
C.c.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:29:37+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China advances with a project to bring samples from Mars, scheduled for “about 2030”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/china-avanca-com-projecto-para-trazer-amostras-de-marte-previsto-para-cerca-de-2030/</link><description>China continues to make progress in its plan to bring samples from Mars, expected to “about 2030,” said China's Aerospace Science and Aerospace Corporation (CASC), Sun Zezhou.
In statements released yesterday by the state press, Sun-also delegate of the National Popular Assembly (Maximus Legislative Body), which currently holds his annual session in Beijing, said the mission, nicknamed Tianwen-3, and harness the launch windows between 2028 and 2030, will adjust their design to optimize the collection and return of samples, taking into the atmospheric and geological conditions. From the red planet.
Among the news, the expert pointed out that the window for landing will coincide with the autumn-winter Martian, which will require technical adjustments in the selection of the orbit and the duration of the surface permanence. The expert recalled that the Chinese space program has already managed to bring samples from the moon and put a probe on Mars, experiences that “launched the foundations” for the collection of samples from the neighboring planet.
However, Sun Zezhou warned that the mission on Mars puts unique challenges, especially "due to its distance from Earth" and "great differences from the moon."
Unlike the moon - with a severity equivalent to one sixth of Earth's gravity - Mars has a third of the gravity of our planet, which requires "more energy to boost the surface load to the orbit." "Mars is the most similar planet to Earth, so the world wants to explore it, which will enrich our knowledge of Earth-like planets and help to understand the formation and evolution of the solar system," said the expert.
Tianwen-3 will aim to land and collect samples in a single point on the red planet, giving priority to various geological regions such as Chryse Planitia and Utopia Planitia, out of a total of 86 possible locations, recently said those responsible for the Chinese space program.
These areas, which include coastal lines, deltas and old lakes, are considered candidates for possible life forms preserved in their sediments.
China has invested strongly in its space program in recent years, having reached Marcos as the landing of the Chang'e 4 probe on the farthest side of the moon, the landing on Mars and the construction of the Tiangong space station, which will work for about ten years.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:31:15+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>March pairing sessions will make available 608 vacancies</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/sessoes-de-emparelhamento-de-marco-vao-disponibilizar-608-vagas/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) will again organize at least six job pairing this month, providing a total of 608 vacancies. The registration period begins today and takes place until March 24, and interested parties can apply through the DSAL website.
This time, there are 608 job openings available for pairing, available by various front line departments and behind the scenes of hotel and restoration establishments belonging to the portfolio of integrated resort and leisure companies. Vacancies are mainly part of the restoration, rooms and cleaning groups and front line operations, which account for about 70% of the total vacancies.
The vacancies offered in the present pairing sessions also cover some management positions and specialized technical posts, such as senior manager for development abroad, management manager and customer raising, Assistant Executive Housekeeper, auxiliary manager of the technology department, shift engineer, as well as chiefs and cooks from various cuisines, among others.
Initial pairing sessions for companies will take place on March 17 (SJM Resorts), March 18 (MGM and Melco), March 20 (Wynn and Sands China) and March 21 (Galaxy Entertainment Group). In addition to these, companies will be able to mark other depending on the number of participants. The exact place, date and time of interviews will be communicated by companies by phone or SMS message.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:31:18+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Critical reflections on the Zelensky-Trump-Vance meeting</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/reflexoes-criticas-sobre-a-reuniao-zelensky-trump-vance/</link><description>The short but unhappy dialogue between Ukrainian President Zelensky, on the one hand, and US President Donald Trump and Vice President Jd Vance in the Oval Room was seen worldwide, with tremendous implications for world politics, changing American foreign policy and Trumpian Americanism.
Firstly, it is impressive how the new US administration is trying to use commercial transactions to deal with their external policies, from the use of tariffs to the requirement to reach an agreement with Ukraine about their minerals and rich resources. If support for human rights and democracy was the US foreign policy pillar after World War II, what we are attending is a drastic change of human and pro-democracy pro-heading values ​​for business values. The point is that if US leaders treat equal commercial transactions as an indispensable element of American foreign policy, then their soft power of human rights and democracy defender has been severely undermined. Ukraine, as Western-style democracy, and President Zelensky, who was elected by the people of Ukraine, were treated very badly by President Trump and Vice President Vance. Although President Trump was convincing when he argued that Zelensky had no negotiating letters, the American side may have convinced Zelensky of what Ukraine would gain from an agreement that seems to put Ukraine in a highly unfavorable position.
Secondly, when Vice President Vance challenged President Zelensky to adopt diplomacy and thanking US military support, the former criticized the Biden administration for his foreign policy to deal with the Russian invasion of Ukraine. President Trump also criticized Biden in the dialogue with Zelensky. Interestingly, when Zelensky mentioned the fact that Russia ignored previous agreements with Ukraine and invaded Crimea in 2014 without US intervention, Vance and Trump did not respond. It seems that both President Trump and Vice President Vance could not capture the main argument articulated by Zelensky, who was given little opportunity to articulate his point of view in the dialogue.
Thirdly, if Russia has a “breach” history of agreements, as Zelensky argued, such as its cherry invasion from 1994 to 1996, its invasion and subsequent annexation of Crimea in 2014, is the drastic turn of the US foreign policy in relation to Russia not only an inversion of the previous US containment policy in relation to the former Soviet Union, but also an appealament policy that Risk to make the Trump-Vance leadership parallel to British Prime Minister Neville Chamberlain's appeasement policy over Hitler during the Munich Conference in September 1938? President Trump told Americans that he likes Russian President Putin. Interestingly, if Russia is looking forward to creating its great Russia, swallowing not only Crimea but also at least the eastern part of Ukraine, will the expansion of Greater Russia represent a danger to at least some small Baltic states in central Europe? President Putin once said that Ukraine belonged to the Soviet Ukraine and had never existed a Ukraine "in the history of humanity." Russia's territorial ambition to swallow Ukraine in the orbit of Greater Russia is obvious. Is there any guarantee that Russia, if the US under the new Trump administration can reach an agreement with Putin, will not transgress to any other territories of other independent European countries? If Putin Russia is imbued with the ideal of restoring the previous borders of the former Soviet Union, will this desire stimulate a third world war? If so, it will be Zelensky to really push the world to World War II, how did Trump question him twice at the heated meeting? If the US is now adopting an appeasement policy in relation to Russia, instead of its traditional containment policy, would this new deriva lead to the Third World War to begin again in Europe, perhaps perhaps originated in the ideal of restoring the great Russia instead of the territories of Greater Germany under Hitler?
Fourthly, what was surprising was that President Zelensky had kept persistent and honest at the meeting with Trump and Vance, fully demonstrating his Ukrainian nationalism that defends Ukraine sovereignty and territorial integrity. Although Vance argued that Zelensky was "disrespectful," it seemed that the leading US leaders questioned and discussed with Zelensky in a dominant way, from an objective perspective. As a Ukrainian nationalist, Zelensky made no concession during the meeting. In fact, Zelensky was already quite calm and smooth in the dialogue, questioning the meaning of diplomacy, as referred to by Vance.
Fifth, after the Zelensky-Trump-Vance meeting, European countries, such as France, Germany and the United Kingdom, continue to support Ukraine-an illustration of a continuity in the geopolitics of Europe where NATO has consistently adopted a control of control and balance of the power of the former Soviet and, currently Russian union. In fact, from an objective point of view, before Ukraine's Russian invasion in February 2022, Ukraine's intention to join NATO was an important step that triggered Greater Russia's national security concern, leading to the Russian invasion of Ukraine. If the US, under the new Trump administration, are eager to turn Ukraine a buffer area between Russia and other European countries, then President Trump and Vice President Vance should perhaps adopt a meeting to the closed door with President Zelensky. Openly discussing Zelensky was by no means leading to effective US diplomacy to get peace in the Russian war with Ukraine. As such, Trump's national security counselors should carefully rethink how the US should bring Ukraine back to the negotiation table and how Ukrainian interests should actually be considered and protected. Diplomacy has to do with the way to balance the conflicting interests of stakeholders rather than imposing a certain view of the world on another country with an image of US economic imperialism.
In sixth place, the turnaround in US foreign policy has a huge implication for American democracy. When US voters voted for the US presidential election that led Trump to power again, most of them saw internal issues, such as the encouragement of the economy, as a priority about US external relations. As such, Trump and his republican party were seen as the “Savior” of America from the perspective of the voters who voted for the Republicans. However, these voters seemed to ignore the impacts that the new Trump administration would have on world politics. Thus, if a democracy is based on the assumption that voters are rational, then it can be argued that American voters who voted again in Trump for presidential power were only partially rational, as they seemed to focus more on domestic interests than on US foreign policy implications. Likewise, when Trump's opponent, Kamala Harris, applied for presidential elections, his campaign counselors missed a golden opportunity to enhance their differences in terms of foreign policy regarding Trump and to underline as another Trump administration would have “harmful” impacts on world politics. In short, democracy, judging by US presidential elections and its aftermath, can be highly problematic because a new leader who is voted for power has huge powers to change internal and external policies through presidential directives and diplomatic transactions of business type, respectively. US voters who voted for US presidential elections in 2024 will not be able to fully understand the way the previous US leadership and image would become so quickly and shockingly.
President Putin once said that Ukraine belonged to the Soviet Ukraine and had never existed a Ukraine "in the history of humanity." Russia's territorial ambition to swallow Ukraine in the orbit of Greater Russia is obvious. Is there any guarantee that Russia, if the US under the new Trump administration can reach an agreement with Putin, will not transgress to any other territories of other independent European countries? If Putin Russia is imbued with the ideal of restoring the previous borders of the former Soviet Union, will this desire stimulate a third world war? If so, it will be Zelensky to really push the world to World War II, how did Trump question him twice at the heated meeting? If the US is now adopting an appeasement policy in relation to Russia, instead of its traditional containment policy, would this new deriva lead to the Third World War to begin again in Europe, perhaps perhaps originated in the ideal of restoring the great Russia instead of the territories of Greater Germany under Hitler? Fourthly, what was surprising was that President Zelensky had kept persistent and honest at the meeting with Trump and Vance, fully demonstrating his Ukrainian nationalism that defends Ukraine sovereignty and territorial integrity. Although Vance argued that Zelensky was "disrespectful," it seemed that the leading US leaders questioned and discussed with Zelensky in a dominant way, from an objective perspective. As a Ukrainian nationalist, Zelensky made no concession during the meeting.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:25:37+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Military plane launches eight bombs and hurts seven civilians in South Korea</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/aviao-militar-lanca-por-engano-oito-bombas-e-fere-sete-civis-na-coreia-do-sul/</link><description>The South Korea Air Force said yesterday that a combat plane launched by mistake eight bombs, which exploded in the wrong place during a military exercise, injuring seven civilians. "Eight MK-82 bombs were launched anomalously by an Air Force KF-16 plane, exploding outside the expected perimeter," the Air Force said in a statement.
The incident occurred yesterday morning around 10:00 am, in Pocheon (North), about 25 kilometers south of the wrap line with North Korea, which has nuclear weapons.
According to the same source, the fighter participated in a "joint exercise with real ammunition, organized with the Air Force and the Army." According to South Korean news agency Yonhap, South Korea was performing "exercises with the United States in Pocheon." "The bombs will probably fallen into a village during an exercise between the United States and South Korea," said the South Korean Civil Protection National Agency.
The incident caused four serious injuries, three light and “material damage” in a church and two houses, according to the same agency.
By the end of this month, the United States and South Korea are expected to begin traditional annual military exercises “Freedom Shield”, which include maneuvers to contain North Korea's nuclear threat.
Washington is the main ally of Seoul in security, having parked about 28,500 soldiers in South Korea. "We deeply regret the wrong launch of these bombs, which hit civilians, and wished a quick recovery to injured," the Air Force said in the note.
South Korea claimed to have created a committee to investigate the succeeded and committed to "compensate for damage."
Diplomatic relations between North Korea and South Korea, which remain technically at war since the 1950-1953 armed conflict, have been at the lowest point of recent decades.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:31:20+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>About 300,000 residents registered the iris in the border passage</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/cerca-de-300-mil-residentes-registaram-a-iris-na-passagem-fronteirica/</link><description>About 300,000 residents have registered Iris in the border passage, the Public Security Police (CPSP) has reported yesterday, adding that, from June 2023 so far, the automatic passage service at the appeal of the iris has been used 7.8 million times last year.
 
 
The automatic border passage service through the iris recognition began to be implemented in June 2023 and since then about 300,000 residents have registered the system. In total, iris recognition for border passage has been used 7.8 million times over the past year. The information was given by the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) in a statement published in the corporation's account on Wechat.
At the siege gates border post, the first to adopt the iris recognition system, the percentage of residents who choose this system already exceeded 40%, indicated that CPSP, noting that, both at the siege doors and at the Qingmao or Hengqin post, corridors reserved for students to facilitate crossing by transfronting students and parents who accompany them, with, with the parents who accompany them, with them, with the parents who accompany them, with the parents who accompany them A daily average of 3,500 students using these corridors.
The average daily number of QR code users to circulate between Hong Kong and Macau is about 3,600. Since the entry into force of this system so far, the QR code to circulate between the two regions has been used in total by 210,000 Macao residents and 43,000 from Hong Kong.
According to CPSP, the automatic channels for bordering vehicle passage was used by 77.7% of total cars, and at the Hengqin border post, 88.7% of traffic passed the quick roads to do the disalfanding.
In the context of combating illegal immigration, CPSP applied sanctions to 14,554 people who exceeded the permanence period in Macau, which represents a decrease of 1.5% over the previous year; expelling 249 illegal immigrants, which represents a 31% decrease over the previous year; and establishing lawsuits related to 36 cases of false marriage, and 78 people were detected; and 51 cases of false employment, having been detected 156 people.
With regard to immigration authorization services, the number of new and renewal requests made on the “Single Input Authorization” platform for foreign domestic workers ascended to about 17,000, representing more than half of the total number of orders and an annual increase of about 34%.
Making the balance of traffic work last year, CPSP said that the three main causes of the 15,510 traffic accidents that occurred last year were the lack of safety distance (3,169 cases), speeding (2,050 cases) and careless driving (1,829 cases).
In total, 1,648 traffic cases were investigated during the year, of which 849 cases of leakage to liability, 720 cases of negligence injuries and 79 cases of other offenses.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:28:33+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Suggested creation of a SINO-LUSOPHONE LOGISTICS to CCPPC</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/sugerida-criacao-de-uma-base-logistica-sino-lusofona-a-ccppc/</link><description>The reinforcement of the commercial connection between Macao and the Lusophone countries is among the proposals submitted by the members of Macao in the National Committee of the Chinese Political Advisory Conference. Businessman Francisco Ho Ka Lon proposed the construction of a Sino-Lusophone Logistics Center in Hengqin to extend the trade exchange between the territory, the interior of China and the Portuguese-speaking countries.
 
Macao authorities must study the creation of a sino-Portuguese international logistics in Hengqin, in order to expand the bulk import and export scale between the region, the interior of China and the Portuguese-speaking countries, defends Francisco Ho Ka in a proposal sent to the National Committee of the Chinese Policy Conference (CCPPC).
Macao's representative in the Chinese government's political advisory body argued that to transform Mountain Island into a sino-Portuguese trade center, the role of Macau must be used as a bridge with the Lusophone world. "Macao can take advantage of the construction of the Sino-Portuguese Logistics in Hengqin and expand the bulk import and export scale, including electronic components, airplanes, automobiles and high-range and high range goods," he said.
Francisco Ho, therefore, stressed that Macau can thus plan the construction of a series of import bases, as well as supervision places designated for imports, with the aim of “promoting the high quality development of relevant local industries in terms of production, transformation and commerce”.
In the document, according to the entrepreneur, the data indicate that, by 2023, imports of macao from food products from Lusophone countries reached about 1.25 billion patacas, representing more than 87% of the total value of imports by the region. The three types of food products with higher import value were, in order, magnesium, frozen pork and frozen cow meat.
Macao exports to Portuguese -speaking countries, according to the official, consisted mainly of organic medical and chemical products, cars and printed material. "Thus, the construction of a center of commerce and distribution of products and food can effectively support the innovative development of the transformation trade, encouraging the extension of the industrial chain business," said the entrepreneur.
In turn, Leonel Alves and Chen Ji Min suggested the creation of a university park in Hengqin to welcome all Macao university institutions. The two members of the CCPPC recalled that the planning of land in the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin provides for the reservation of a portion of 1.2 square kilometers for a university campus. They indicated that the space “can be used to allow Macao universities to work independently in this venue and share resources such as academic buildings, sports fields, libraries and canteens”.
Leonel Alves and Chen Ji Min intend to establish a regional center for the Integrated Development of International Science and Technology and Human Resources Teaching. The ambition revealed in their proposal also includes constructions of scientific research and technology laboratories at national level.
 
Ding Xuexiang wants to increase the confidence of the population of Macau
 
Ding Xuexiang, vice-prime minister, said he hoped that the confidence of the population of Macau in the future could be increased after understanding the country's main policies and development opportunities. In this case, the politician asked the members of Macao at CCPPC to learn and reinforce the dissemination of the “important spirit” of the “two sessions” to the public of the masters.
Ding Xuexiang's statement was given at a meeting held yesterday with CCPPC Macao representatives. Speaking to Macau Radio in Chinese language, Ho Ion Sang said Ding Xuexiang gave great importance to the economic growth of the territory. According to the official, the deputy minister also expects Macao members at CCPPC to fully support the new government and “more often visit the community to know the needs of the population, and reinforce international exchanges and cooperation,” he said.
At the same time, Edmund Ho, Vice President of CCPPC, stressed that Ding Xuexiang's visit to Macao members “reflects affectionate attention” to the region. In addition, he praised the work report of the CCPPC National Committee, describing it as a “pragmatic and advisor” report and “reinforces confidence and inspires the morale of people”. The former chief executive, who chaired the joint meeting of Hong Kong and Macao delegates at CCPPC, revealed that the meeting focused on promoting the accelerated national integration of Hong Kong and Macao.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:26:33+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New Army attacks on Myanmar cause 12 dead and 30 injured</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/novos-ataques-do-exercito-no-myanmar-causam-12-mortos-e-30-feridos/</link><description>Burmese forces killed 12 civilians yesterday and wounded 30 in new attacks in the cities of Myaing and Pauk, in the western state of Magway, denounced a local news portal.
 
Members of rebel groups operating in the area told the Portal Mizzima that one of the attacks targeted a oil field in Latpanto, near the Border between Myaing and Pauk. The attacks occurred at night, according to the same sources cited by the Spanish agency Europa Press.
"At this stage, we cannot confirm whether there are children among the deadly victims," ​​said a rebel forces spokesman fighting the Military Junta in Power in Myanmar since the 2021 coup. "Four of the dead are resident in Baung Bin and Myaing, while others are workers in oil fields," the same source added.
The spokesman also said that the army used fighters to launch several bombs, which also reached a rice field and a monastery.
The injured were taken to medical facilities, where they were identified by family members. Rebel groups began to isolate the area and warned of the presence of seriously amputated victims. Residents have expressed the fear that such attacks can be repeated in the near future, according to Europe Press.
The ancient Burma has been plunged into a severe crisis since the coup that has allowed the military to return to power. The government of national unity declared in September 2021, from exile, "a defensive war" against the military junta. He also appealed to citizens “from all corners of the country” to revive each other against the military who had taken power, which led to a civil war.
A humanitarian organization reported yesterday that the combat between the Army and the groups of rebels with Chinese projects in the Western Zanmar Zone caused 4,000 more displaced.
New combat hatching in late February around the city of Kyaukphyu, where China promised to build a deep water port in an estimated investment of nine billion dollars.
Isolated in the international scene, generals in power are deeply dependent on China, which also intends to build oil centers and transport connections in the western region. According to the United Nations, more than 3.5 million people are displaced in Myanmar.
The military coup of February 1, 2021 overthrew the Government of the National League for Democracy Party of the Nobel Peace Prize Aung Sang Suu Kyii, which has been in prison ever since. The military had already been in power between 1962 and 2011, and the 2021 coup interrupted the process of democratic transition in the country. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:31:20+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>In 2024, almost 15,000 residents got employment through government support</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/em-2024-quase-15-mil-residentes-conseguiram-emprego-atraves-do-apoio-do-governo/</link><description>Over the past year, 14,699 candidates have obtained professional placement through the support measures of the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL). Of these, more than 60% were under 35 years old.
 
In 2024, a total of 14,699 residents obtained professional placement through various measures to support the management of services for labor affairs (DSAL). The information contains a response to a written interpellation of Deputy Nick Law, where authorities also say that more than 60% were young people under 35 years.
In the written interplies, the deputy pointed to the data from the Board of Statistics and Census Services, which show that about 66% of the unemployed is in the age group from 16 to 44 years, “situation that is nothing optimistic”, noted Nick Lei, asking details about the plans of the authorities to support young people in search of employment.
In response, Dsal says it has “provides diverse employment pair -pairing measures according to the needs of employment and professional development of young people”, for example, having launched the internship plan “Create better work perspectives”, which provides jobs in tourism and leisure sectors, finance, technology, big health, public utility services, social services, construction, aviation and retail. On the other hand, youth employment fairs have also provided several vacancies and interview opportunities to higher education, states DSal.
In questioning, Nick Law also criticized the increase of non -specialized non -resident workers in Macao. "DSSA should globally review the import situation of workers not resident by large companies, including integrated tourism and leisure companies, namely the number of jobs suitable for residents, with a view to releasing these jobs and thus increasing the employment space of local residents," said the deputy in the interpelation.
DSAL replied that "the main premise of the government's labor import policy is to ensure that resident workers have priority in access to employment and that their rights and labor interests are not injured." On the other hand, in the treatment of non -resident workers' requests, “DSSA has taken into account the needs of Macao's socioeconomic development and consists of various factors, such as the supply and demand for human resources in the general labor market, the characteristics of the sectors, the size of companies and the exploration situation, dynamically proceeding to the adjustment and proper control of the number of TNR, promoting development sustainable socioeconomic of the masters ”.
In conclusion, the government guarantees that it will “guarantee, rigorously and in accordance with the law, the rights and labor interests of residents, closely monitoring the evolution of the labor market and the situation of human resources supply, continuously and dynamically adjusting the number of TNR and launching various employment support measures, in order to help young people expand job opportunities, towards a more diverse professional development”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:27:18+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Three artistic groups of Portugal participate in the Macao International Parade</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/tres-grupos-artisticos-de-portugal-participam-no-desfile-internacional-de-macau/</link><description>Three artistic groups from Portugal will participate in the 11th edition of the Macao International Parade, which leaves the streets of the 23rd of March, was announced yesterday. The president of the Cultural Institute (IC), Leong Wai Man, highlighted the “Young Percussion Group” Porbatuka and the Portugal Artfusion project, which “Mix Fado, Contemporary Portuguese Music and Dance” in the Saudade show. At a press conference, the IC revealed that the program also includes the Portuguese Company Theater Só, which will present the show Sorriso.
The parade will have about 1,800 artists, including 23 invited groups from 15 countries and regions, including Italy, Egypt, Polynesia, Morocco, Spain, India, France, Continental China and Hong Kong.
The IC highlighted the show 'The Gipsy Marionettist' (The Gypsy puppet) by Rašid Nikolić, a Gypsy artist born in Bosnia-Herzegovina, the Argentine Folk Dance Group Argentina and a German circus group.
The event will also have 60 local groups, chosen from 90 candidates, including several of Lusófona matrix, such as the Macao Capoeira Sports and Cultural Association, the Portuguese Dance and Singing Association ‘Macau na Coração’ and Casa do Brasil in Macau.
Leong highlighted one of the local groups, Casa de Portugal in Macao, which will present a show inspired by the Podence Carets, which were in the Chinese semi -autonomous region for the fifth edition of the parade in 2015.
The event begins in the ruins of São Paulo and, over three and a half hours, will go through several buildings in the historic center of Macao, considered a world heritage by UNESCO in 2005, including the São Domingos Church and Senate Largo. Before the parade, between March 16 and 22, the groups will participate in a series of eight street and community art activities.
Leong refused to reveal the budget for this year, claiming that it is "confidential information," as it will be funded by the six casino dealers in Macao. The budget last year was about seven million patacas, less than a third than in the last edition, in 2019 (23.3 million patacas).</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:25:33+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese economy faces external uncertainty and low internal demand</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/economia-chinesa-enfrenta-incerteza-externa-e-baixa-procura-interna/</link><description>China's economy faces uncertainties due to the volatile international environment and insufficient internal demand, a high in charge of the Asian country's economic policy said yesterday.
Zheng Shanjie, chairman of the country's National Development and Reform Commission, the country's top economic planning agency, has admitted at a press conference that “uncertainty in the external environment continues to increase” and that the country “faces problems such as insufficient internal demand and production and operation difficulties in certain sectors and companies”.
However, the official stressed that Beijing is “fully confident” of reaching the official target of economic growth this year, about 5%, and promised to make internal demand on the main economic engine.
China has “the guarantees necessary to achieve this year's growth objective,” said the employee, on the sidelines of the annual session of the National Popular Assembly, China's maximum legislative body.
Zheng's statements appear in a period of aggravation of the trade war between China and the United States, which threatens to a hard blow to Chinese exports, one of the engines of the world's second largest economy growth.
Faced with the internal and external challenges, Chinese Finance Minister Lan Fo'an announced at the same press conference that China will “increase further” its budgetary expenses by 2025.
The growth objective announced by the Prime Minister, Li Qiang, at the opening of the legislative session is in accordance with analysts' predictions. However, many experts consider it too ambitious, taking into account the size of the economic challenges that China faces.
Since the pandemic, the Asian country has been struggling to put its economic recovery into practice, due to the real estate crisis, weak consumption and high unemployment among young people.
This joins the obstacles placed by US President Donald Trump, who this week imposed new rates on Chinese imports.
These rates should affect hundreds of thousands of millions of dollars in trade between the world's two largest economies.
China announced on Tuesday measures in response and promised to retaliate "until the end." From March 10, Beijing will impose rates of up to 15% on a series of US agricultural products, including soy, pork and wheat.</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:31:15+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>From the real purple to the gray of penance</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/07/do-purpura-real-ao-cinza-da-penitencia/</link><description>On Wednesday began the religious period that traditionally in Portugal and in Christian countries is called Lent. The Portuguese word Quaresma derives from the Latin Ordinal Numeral Quadragesima, as part of the quadragesima dies phrase, that is, 'daylight day', referring to the forty days that the hard Lent. Although there is some confusion today in the way of calculating these forty days, as many think that Lent goes to Easter, in fact, the forty days rang from Gray Wednesday to the early eve of Ramos Sunday, when Holy Week officially begins. It is this, by the way, who affirm the rules of the Breviary of the Missal Romanos prior to the 1969-70 reform.
Lent as a time of preparation for Easter evokes the forty days that Jesus spent in the desert in prayer and fasting (Matt. 4: 1-2), before starting his public life and after being baptized by John Baptista on the Jordan River, according to tradition, at the age of thirty. These forty days are prefigured in the Old Testament for the forty years that the Hebrew people will have wandered through the Sinai Desert before finally entering the Promised Land (Num 32:13).
The custom of cyclically celebrating key events in religious history is inherited from the Judaism of the second temple. In fact, according to the Old Testament is God Himself (Ex 12: 1-3; 17-18), who establishes the way the Hebrews had to celebrate the Jewish Easter every year, which celebrated the liberation of the captivity of Egypt. Jesus Himself, who followed the religious calendar of the Jews (Matt. 26: 17-18), also celebrated these festivities every year as, by the way, is referred to in the Gospels. The last supper, for example, was the ritual meal of the Jews on Easter Thursday, which, according to the biblical tradition, was the day when God's hand passed by decimating the firstborn of the Egyptians, including the son of Pharaoh himself.
 
The origins of Lent
Lent, whose origins are lost in time, in its hodierna form, is understood as a period of preparation for Holy Week and Easter. The first explicit mention of Lent appears in the Council of Niceia, which was celebrated under the auspices of Emperor Constantine, the Great, in 325 of our age, in order to clarify once and for all the question of Jesus' nature in relation to God. Jerónimo de Estrredão (c. 347 - 420) and Pope Leo Magno (c. 400 - 461) in the West and Cyril of Alexandria (c. 376 - 444) in the East claim that Lent was instituted in the time of the apostles. Already Ireneu de Lião (c. 130 - c. 202), which Eusébio de Cesarea (c.260 - c.340) cites in his ecclesiastical history, says that in his time, the preparatory fast for Easter lasted only three days, instead of the forty that would later become the norm.
Nowadays different theories are about the origins of Lent, one of the most credible is that it will have started because it is a period of preparation for catechumens to be baptized in the Easter Vigil.
In the East, Greek orthodox call the Lent of great fast. The Orientals, save the Melquitas and the Maronites, two groups of oriental Christians linked to Rome, do not celebrate ash Wednesday. For most Orthodox is the cleaning or purification Monday that marks the entry into Lenten Time. During this first week of Orthodox Lent, people perform deep cleaning of the house while being encouraged to confess. This tradition of cleaning the house by this time derives from the Jewish custom of cleaning the house before Easter, so as to make sure no rest of yeast was behind, because the Jewish Easter is the Feast of Azimos, ie non-fermented. Confession would represent the spiritual equivalent of this cleaning in order to make sure that there are no remains of sin that prevent the celebration of Easter.
As in the West during the Middle Ages, orthodox gives great importance to fasting during this period and have very strict abstinence rules of certain foods, namely the meat, which cannot be touched for the forty days that lasts the great fast. In addition, immediately before the Lent itself, orthodox has a period of three weeks of fasting to prepare the great fast of Lent. This means that before Easter, orthodox have to fast for about ten weeks. The result of this, of course, is that very few people obey these precepts.
The Roman Church has never had such a long period of fasting and abstinence, even though until the liturgical reform of 1969-70, and still present in the extraordinary use of the Roman rite, the Latinos celebrated the weeks of the sexagentieth, the Sexay and the fifteen, thirty days that liturgically preambled the Lent.
With the changes of Vatican II, fasting and abstinence were put almost completely in the drawer. More recently, however, many of the things that have been lost have been reevaluated and even recovered. In this context, in 2011, the bishops of England and Wales reintroduced mandatory fasting every Friday of the year, an act that was described by many at the time as historical. The letter from the English bishops describes penance on Friday, not as a more or less masochistic exercise, but as a clear and distinct sign of Catholic identity [through which] Catholics identify with Christ at the time of their death on the cross. '
 
The Lent Purple
The liturgical color of religious ceremonies during Lent is purple, commonly called purple. [There are several shades in the purple spectrum, such as violet, lilac, etc. In Portuguese, purple is usually the generic name given to the colors of this spectrum. Although for many people, purple and purple do not represent the same color in this text by pure convenience, purple and purple will be treated as synonym, as if they were the same color. This is because, when we talk about purple in the context of royalty, we call it purple, while in religious language purple is called purple. In English, in both contexts, the word is the same, Purple.]
Liturgical colors are symbolic and serve to express the spirit of the occasion. They are white, red, green, pink, blue and purple. White, for example, usually embroidered with gold, is used in larger festivities concerning Jesus Christ such as Christmas or Easter. White can also be used at the Virgin Mary festivities, where it can be replaced by blue, color associated with the Immaculate Conception, which is why the Portuguese flag before the 1910 revolution was blue and white, as we had the opportunity to see here.
The liturgical color of advent and Lent is purple, but on the third Sunday of Advent and the room of Lent, called Gaudete, Latin to 'Regozijijai', and Laetare, Latin to 'rejoice, respectively, use the pink instead of the purple to express the gagens suggested by the entrance antiphon.
Prior to the liturgical reform of 1969-70, following Vatican II, there was even more color, the black, which was used in the suffrage masses for the dead. After the renovation, black was replaced by the purple at the mass masses. This change caused some confusion in the meaning of purple color in liturgical celebrations, as it came to be understood as a sign of mourning. It is not at all truth that the purple of advent and Lent represents sadness; In the special case of Advent, which precedes Christmas, this period could never be considered sad. What the purple intends to express in these two seasons of the religious year is solemnity.
In antiquity, as they mention Homer's Iliad and Virgil's Aeneid, the purple was a color reserved for kings and, in some cases, even reserved only to the gods. Clitemnestra, Agamémenon's wife, when she wanted to avenge her daughter Efigenia's death that her father, the same Agamémenon, had sacrificed Poseidon in order to go to Troy, deceives her husband by setting a purple rug, something reserved for the gods. Agamémenon knows what he is doing, he himself says that this is an honor reserved only to the gods, but Clitemnestra plays with his vanity and can convince her husband that he is also worthy of such an honor. By setting the purple rug, Agamémbenon commits an act of insolence and, having incurred Hybris, has to die. This is how Clitetenestra finds a justification to be able to kill her husband and avenge her daughter's death.
What raised the purple color to its real -colored status in the Mediterranean basin was its rarity. In antiquity, this color was achieved through the mollusk or mollusk called Murex, or, in adapted Portuguese, modern (which can be seen in the image that accompanies this article). It is, by the way, then the walled Spanish word comes to refer to the purple. For the production of pigment to dye purple fabrics it was necessary hundreds of these small mollusks that had to be opened and, after being removed from their shell, stimulated to produce the drool. This process was difficult, very slow and very expensive. Moreover, until the synthesis of ammonia at the end of the eighteenth century, the purple was a very difficult color to maintain as it tended to pass out with sun exposure and was disappearing with washing. Thus, the purple tissues had to be frequently retired, which made them even more expensive. As such, this color was accessible solely to the wealthier classes and in antiquity it was considered real color. This is exactly why the soldiers to make the joke of Jesus, accused of passing through the king of the Jews, dress him with a purple cloak and a crown of thorns (John 19: 2).
The purple of shooting, so called because it originated from the city of Tire, in Lebanon, was the most famous and most expensive purple color of antiquity.
From the Middle Ages to the mid -Century, in certain regions of Portugal, the purple was extracted from onion shells and fixed to goat urine tissues.
In view of its noble character, the intention of purple cannot be representing neither mourning nor sadness, but to express dignity and solemnity. Moreover, in the good way of the Romans, for whom the gravites and the solemnity expressed outwardly for sobriety to emphasize the content more than to form, the purple expresses the solemn and the noble in a discreet way. It was, by the way, to mark the content of the season and to avoid distractions that formerly covered with purple cloths all images within the church during the last week of Lent, called Passion Week, and during Holy Week. Upon entering a church where all the decoration is hidden under purple cloths we would be immediately warned that something very serious, in the Roman sense of the word, takes place there.
 
The ashes, solemn form of penance
Lent begins on Ash Wednesday, so-called because during mass of this gray day are placed on the head of the faithful, or on the cross-shaped forehead, accompanied by the phrase 'Remember, man, who are dust and that you will return to dust.' This act aims to remember the ephemeral and transitory character of man's passage through this world. The symbolic value of this small but solemn gesture marks the exordium of Lent, period of introspection and reflection, fortified, whenever possible, by the most frequent personal prayer, sharing with the most needy and the renunciation of pleasurable things and not only, as a way of trying to increase control over one's own body.
This Wednesday, the author of this text, Yours Trulary, went to Mass in one of the churches of our city. The Mass was said in a Portuguese where the conjunctive seemed to have gone on vacation, but, given that the priest in question was not a native speaker, until he was quite well; At least the sermon was opportune and made sense, it was not the usual standard of illogical absurdities and irrational fideism that is sometimes heard. Credulices and faith are not the same thing, St. Thomas said in the shorts that as grace presupposes nature (human nature is understood), faith presupposes reason.
Before the Council, the organ could not be sang, the organ could play, but there was no song because communion deserves and requires reflection. On the way to communion will be reflected in what will be done and after communion it will be reflected in what represents what has just done. It's not time for songs! But much worse than singing during communion is singing nonsense. There are a number of Portuguese religious songs of the sixties and seventy whose texts or do not make sense, or are not recommended by virtue of their colorado content. It was one of these texts chosen for communion on this solemn day of the religious calendar.
Thus, on the way to communion we would sing things like ‘We seek, Lord, your word | But we don't find it. ' Such a statement in line for communion is, at the very least, strange, since Jesus Christ is the Word of God incarnate - I am not the one who says it, but St. John in the prologue of his Gospel - that is, what are directed to the line to commune. How is the idea of ​​not being able to find God's Word with the fact that he is in the church and, on top, in line for communion? Continues the song: ‘No one talks about you, | No one can teach us | We want prophets that point paths, | To guide us'. Don't you talk about God in the church? What is the priest for? What was the priest to do during the sermon? And what the readings were about what? And the ceremony is about? You don't realize! This song makes no sense to those who practice religion, for those who go to church, for their letter suggests that the people are abandoned and drifting; To do the church then?
And, as it could not miss, it also brings a moderate dose of the Marxist grudge from that time when, words like ‘while many drag themselves, | In hunger and suffering, | There are others who live in their well-being, | As owners of the world, 'probably even sang with their fist closed in the air. Words of this nature should not take place within a temple during a religious ceremony; It seems more appropriate to sing or recite at the Avante party!
During the ceremony of the imposition of the ashes, a photographer was in the space of the altar that, as the priest drew with his finger the sign of the cross on the forehead of the faithful in front of the altar, he followed the priest and photographed the penitents, as the ashes were imposed, as if he had peeling altem in the zological garden, as they tried, as they If they were a tourist attraction to make postcards, or as if instead of being in a church they were at any television festival, never asking people if they wanted or allowed them to be photographed, thus disrespecting the right to the very image that each of us has and, above all, the right that people have to exercise their faith and practice their religion without photographic chambers around! This behavior during a penitential act of this level reveals a serious lack of sense of opportunity and understanding the true meaning of things.
Thank God, when it came to the author of this text, the photographer became the huge objective of his camera towards someone else, because this Yours Trury was already prepared to send a scream or two to the saying whose photographer, despite being inside the church. Some of us prefer to be photographed because we don't know well who even when we go to the church to pray. Is it me the only one who thinks like this?</description><pubDate>2025-03-07T03:31:14+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>