<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/19/ponto-fatal-20-outubro-2025/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Cambodia deports 64 South Koreans accused of involvement in organized crime</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/19/camboja-deporta-64-sul-coreanos-acusados-de-envolvimento-em-crime-organizado/</link><description>South Korean police confirmed Saturday that Cambodia deported 64 South Korean citizens accused of involvement in centers that practice internet fraud.

South Korea sent a team to Cambodia on Wednesday, where it believes around a thousand South Koreans are working in these centers, to discuss dozens of cases of abductions through fraudulent job offers.
Seoul then announced, on Friday night, that it was chartering a flight to bring back around 60 citizens, “voluntary and non-voluntary participants” in the fraud schemes, who were detained by the Cambodian police.
The group landed on Saturday morning at Incheon Airport, a South Korean police official told the France-Presse news agency.
Police authorities were seen preparing to transport them in black security vans.
Most of the South Korean returnees were detained in Cambodia during crackdowns on fraud centers and will face police investigations at home, Seoul's national security director Wi Sung-lac said.
On Friday, the South Korean government banned South Koreans from traveling to Cambodia, amid an increase in the number of people allegedly abducted by human trafficking networks and organized crime groups based in Cambodia.
Criminal groups forced South Korean citizens to commit fraud involving cryptocurrencies via the Internet, in an environment similar to that of a prison.
According to diplomatic sources in Seoul and the UN, South Korean citizens are held as slaves and have been subjected to acts of torture by organized crime groups.
Seoul's warning also recommends South Korean citizens to leave certain areas of Cambodia.
The warning was issued on the day that South Korean Vice Minister of Foreign Affairs Kim Jina met with Cambodian Prime Minister Hun Manet in Phnom Penh.
The meeting in Cambodia's capital took place after the death of a South Korean student who was allegedly forced to work in a fraud center in Cambodia.
Phnom Penh said on Thursday that in recent months it has deported 180 South Korean citizens involved in cybercrime and another 60 are awaiting repatriation.
According to a United Nations report, at least 200,000 people are currently held in fraud centers in Cambodia, while in Myanmar (formerly Burma, another epicenter of this phenomenon, the number amounts to around 120,000.
Seoul's decision came in the same week that the UK and US governments announced joint sanctions against Cambodia-based conglomerate Prince Group.
The president of the group of companies, Chen Zhi, is accused of setting up a cybercrime and human trafficking network. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:07:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan's ruling party close to securing new coalition agreement</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/19/partido-no-poder-no-japao-perto-de-garantir-novo-acordo-de-coligacao/</link><description>The Liberal Democratic Party (PLD), in power in Japan, is close to forming a government coalition, which would leave leader Sanae Takaichi just two deputies away from securing election as prime minister.
The main Japanese media reported that the agreement with the Innovation Party of Japan (Ishin) could be closed this Monday, the day before parliament meets to choose Shigeru Ishiba's successor.
The outgoing prime minister resigned in September from the leadership of the Government and the PLD, which, in primaries held at the beginning of October, chose the conservative and nationalist Takaichi as the candidate to be the first woman to lead Japan.
According to the Japanese news agency Kyodo, the PLD and Ishin have agreed to form a coalition without the opposition party guaranteeing seats in the new Government. In return, the PLD would commit to complying with a series of proposals, including reducing the number of deputies, eliminating the tax on food consumption and eliminating political donations from companies and organizations.
The Japanese newspaper Mainichi details that Ishin leaders presented the proposed agreement to their party on Saturday, after which a final meeting with the PLD is expected on Monday.
The newspaper reported that the opposition party is reluctant to occupy positions in Takaichi's possible government and prefers to first ensure that the new PLD leader complies with the terms of the agreement.
If elected, the conservative would lead one of the weakest governments in Japan's political history, with a clear minority in both chambers of parliament, which would force her to cooperate with the opposition to pass any law.
Ishin's support is essential for Takaichi, especially after the Buddhist party Komeito, with which the PLD was allied for 26 years, abandoned the ruling coalition.
The centrist Komeito withdrew from the alliance due to published news about alleged secret PLD funds, having also criticized Sanae Takaichi due to supposed changes in the leader's stance regarding visits to Yasukuni.
Takaichi, known for her hard-line stance towards China, has visited the Shinto shrine numerous times in the past, especially when she was minister, considered a symbol of the country's militaristic past. But, on Friday, on the first day of the Yasukuni autumn festival, 64 years old, he was absent and sent only one offering, because, according to Japanese media, he feared that a visit could upset neighboring countries.
Previous visits by senior Japanese officials to the shrine have angered Beijing and Seoul. China and the Korean peninsula were the scene of atrocities committed by the Japanese military in the first half of the 20th century. No sitting Japanese prime minister has visited the shrine in Tokyo since 2013, when Shinzo Abe's visit sparked fury among neighboring countries and rebukes from the United States.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:07:03</pubDate></item><item><title>University of Macau joins the UNESCO Chair dedicated to Portuguese heritage</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/19/universidade-de-macau-junta-se-a-catedra-unesco-dedicada-ao-patrimonio-portugues/</link><description>The University of Macau (UM) announced its membership of the UNESCO Chair in Intercultural Dialogue on Heritage of Portuguese Influence, a project launched by the University of Coimbra (UC).
In a statement released on Friday night, UM argued that joining the project “imposes a new dynamic in the development of research on cultural heritage” in the semi-autonomous Chinese region.
The collaboration with UC will promote “international academic exchange in Macau”, as well as strengthen “ties” with higher education institutions in Portuguese-speaking countries, UM added.
The institution's formal accession to the UNESCO Chair took place in a ceremony organized by the two institutions in Macau, on Wednesday, with the presence of Rui Martins, vice-rector of UM, and João Nuno Calvão da Silva, vice-rector of UC.
Rui Martins argued that UM's entry “will further enrich the academic resources and cultural perspective” of the already “wide network of partners” established by the UNESCO Chair.
The UC created the project in 2018, to explore “the multicultural results resulting from the influence of Portuguese-speaking culture”, such as architecture, arts, language, literature, landscape and urbanism, said the statement.
At the time, the UNESCO Chair already involved fifty teachers and researchers in a partnership with several European, Brazilian and African institutions.
The list included the University of Bologna Studies (Italy), the Universidade Federal Fluminense (Brazil), the universities Eduardo Mondlane and Lúrio (Mozambique), the University Paris Nanterre (France) and MEIA – Mindelo Escola Internacional de Arte (Cape Verde).
Rui Martins, a Portuguese academic who has long lived in Macau, highlighted that the UNESCO Chair is an international project “that integrates research, training and cooperation for development”.
In the case of UM, the Department of Integrated Resorts and Tourism Management of the Faculty of Business Management will “actively demonstrate its professional competence” in research into cultural heritage, guaranteed Martins.
The UNESCO Chair is coordinated by researcher Walter Rossa, who on Wednesday spoke about “the political significance” of research on cultural heritage within the organization's policies.
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO) was created in 1945 to promote world security and peace through international cooperation.
On the same occasion, the two universities agreed to support the joint development of the Camões Digital Library, a UC project dedicated to Luís Vaz de Camões, a 16th century Portuguese poet.
The project aims to create “a comprehensive digital platform”, as an “authoritative” reference source for research and resources on Camões worldwide, preserving and promoting the poet's works, UM said. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:14:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Government has already received more than 3,500 opinions on the LAG for 2026</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/19/governo-ja-recebeu-mais-de-3-500-opinioes-sobre-as-lag-para-2026/</link><description>The Chief Executive revealed on Saturday that 3,548 opinions and suggestions have already been collected on next year's Lines of Government Action (LAG), more than in previous years.
Sam Hou Fai spoke to journalists at the opening of the Government Headquarters to the public. The Chief explained that the Government is collecting opinions and suggestions through various channels, having received active support from residents, expressing their sincere thanks. Sam guaranteed that the Government gives “high attention to each of the opinions and suggestions collected, which will be analyzed seriously and included appropriately, developing the best possible lines of government action for the next year, constantly responding to residents' demands”.
This weekend, the Government Headquarters was opened to the public, which is now customary to happen every year. According to information from the Executive, on Saturday 6,226 residents visited the space and on Sunday at 12:30 pm more than 3,200 had already visited the Headquarters.
The Government Headquarters had floral arrangements dedicated to the 15th edition of the National Games on display. The exhibition was divided into four thematic zones. In the first, visitors are welcomed by the mascots “Xiyangyang” and “Lerongrong” and the collection of chrysanthemums. In the lawn area, cooperation between the three participating regions is highlighted through the use of the colors of the National Games emblem (red, purple and green) and a “gigantic floral installation” made up of flowers representing Guangzhou, Hong Kong and Macau.
On each side of the exhibition, event logos from the Guangdong and Hong Kong Competition Zones were displayed through the combination of green walls and themed floral arrangements. Finally, the exhibition area inside the Protocol Building uses the flowers of Guangzhou's kapok tree, Hong Kong's bauhinia and Macao's lotus as the main bouquet, accompanied by “animated mascots”.
Over the weekend, there were also performances by the Music Band of the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) and students from the School of Music and the School of Dance of the Macau Conservatory.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:10:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Fringe Festival attracted around 9,000 participants</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/19/festival-fringe-atraiu-cerca-de-9-000-participantes/</link><description>The Fringe Festival, which concluded at the end of September, attracted 9,000 participants this year. The Cultural Institute's (IC) initiative once again brought a multiplicity of performing arts, forms of expression and interactive activities to Macau, focusing on the cultural heritage of community neighborhoods and the city's unique characteristics.

The 23rd edition of the Fringe Festival welcomed almost nine thousand participants, attracted by more than a hundred artistic and cultural events spread across the city of Macau. During the festival's duration, between the 5th and 28th of September, 18 shows and 13 activities were presented under the theme “Urban Tour”, an ode to the connection between culture and community development.
In a statement, the organization recognizes that this year's edition used “unconventional locations” – from food establishments to the streets and alleys of the Parish of Santo António – to infuse “artistic creativity within the community” and make Macau's cultural heritage known to residents and visitors.
The festival was divided into 13 different thematic categories, encompassing artistic forms as diverse as theater or multimedia and also special programs such as the recurring series “Crème de la Fringe”, sub-divided into two events focused on theatrical and circus arts. The first, “TOMATO: Interactive Digital Theater Exhibition”, expanded the boundaries of traditional theater by fusing it with technology, allowing participants to explore Macau’s community neighborhoods and discover “fragments of memory” using digital platforms as an anchor.
The second sub-event, “Clowns for the Complicité Festival”, sparked laughter and “pure and genuine joy” in the audience, made up of kids and adults, with interactive demonstrations of juggling, martial arts and the physical comedy very typical of the performing art of clowning.
Among the highlights of this 23rd edition, the organization also mentions the play “Orquídeas à Velha Casa”, which conveyed the forgotten story of the trafficking of Chinese workers in Macau with a mix of music and narrative; “Chow T. II”, a message about intangible cultural heritage, family memories and personal growth presented through the traditional art of puppetry; “Oscillating Deck”, a fantasy journey through Porto Inner using augmented reality (AR) technology; and “A Meeting in Solitude”, a solo performance staged in an old Chinese tea room.
The public was also able to take on the role of artist by holding several creative workshops, in which different age groups exercised their artistic flair using materials such as paper, glass or ceramics. The works resulting from these sessions were then exhibited in the subsequent exhibition “Art Exhibition for All”, organized in the community areas of Ilha Verde and Jardim da Cidade das Flores. Amateur artists who did not participate in the workshops were also able to bring or spontaneously create their works on site, without restrictions regarding theme or format.
Geographical boundaries were blurred with the section “Fringe Exchange: Contact with other Festivals”, which took place at Doca dos Pescadores. In this session, the three guest curators – Jeff Khan, Jack Wong and Fan Xing – represented the performing arts from their native cities in Australia, Malaysia and Beijing, respectively, and shared their perspectives on festival planning, arts management and selection criteria.
It is worth remembering that the month of September was marked by the passage of several typhoons through the territory of Macau. Tropical cyclone Tapah, in particular, forced changes to the Fringe Festival's agenda, including the cancellation of “Máquina Sem Sonhos, Classe Inútil” and the postponement of “Orquídeas à Velha Casa” from the 7th to the 9th of September.
Once this year's program has concluded, the Cultural Institute (IC) guarantees that it “will continue to create platforms for local artists and groups and expand their development space, in order to present a varied range of artistic and cultural programs to the public”.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>President of the Supreme Court available to send more Portuguese judges to Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/19/presidente-do-supremo-disponivel-para-enviar-mais-juizes-portugueses-para-macau/</link><description>The president of the Supreme Court of Justice (STJ) said that Portugal is available, if Macau shows interest, in sending new judges, with a Portuguese magistrate about to leave the Macao SAR.
Judge Rui Ribeiro, of the Court of Second Instance, confirmed to Lusa, on the sidelines of a public event, that he will leave Macau at the end of October, bringing forward the end of the commission, which ended in May 2026.
The magistrate stressed that the Macau judicial authorities “did everything” to make him change his mind, but explained that he preferred to return to Portugal now given the uncertainty regarding a possible renewal of the special license by the Superior Council of Judiciary (CSM).
With Rui Ribeiro's announced departure, only one Portuguese judge remains in the Macau courts: Jerónimo Alberto Gonçalves Santos, president of a collective court at the Base Judicial Court (TJB).
The leader of the STJ, João Cura Mariano, who inherently also presides over the CSM, told journalists that, during a visit to Macau, he wanted to find out if the territory was interested in having Portuguese magistrates. “We are going to try to see what they can really convey that is useful and whether they are necessary, because if they are necessary, new judges will come”, he assured the journalists.
João Cura Mariano said that this “is certainly a subject to discuss” in meetings with the president of the Court of Final Instance (TUI), Song Man Lei, and with Sam Hou Fai, leader of the Macau Government and former president of the TUI. “I think it is very useful, because, being a former president of the court [Sam Hou Fai] he will be aware of the needs that exist”, said the Portuguese judge advisor.
But the president of the STJ highlighted that Portuguese justice is having “some difficulty in contributing judges”, due to the lack of qualified and experienced human resources. “Just now we removed a judge who had been here for many years and we needed him”, recalled João Cura Mariano.
In 2024, the CSM rejected the stay of Portuguese TJB judge Carlos Carvalho, who had been in Macau for 16 years and had been invited by the Independent Commission for the Nomination of Judges in the territory to continue for another two years.
The council did not authorize the renewal of Carlos Carvalho's special license and promoted him to judge, with placement at the Court of Appeal. Even so, João Cura Mariano assured that he was willing to help, “despite the difficulties that currently exist in Portugal in recruiting judges”.
The president of the STJ highlighted the example of Timor-Leste, where there are currently “many Portuguese judges collaborating in the Timorese judicial system”, because “they are very necessary”.
The judge is in Macau to participate in the 13th edition of the forum that brings together presidents of the Supreme Courts of Justice of Portuguese-speaking countries and territories.
Apathy in court reform
The president of the Supreme Court of Justice lamented what he said was “a very great apathy” in the reform of the courts and argued that “justice could be much better”. "The main problem with the functioning of the courts in Portugal is that there has been no reform for a long time. There was a view that it was better not to change than to ruin it", explained João Cura Mariano, who has led the STJ since June 2024. "Since I was elected, I launched this challenge of reform. I have maintained a continuous dialogue with the political power and everyone is in agreement", said the judge advisor. "Just the day before yesterday [Thursday] I was at the Assembly of the Republic and all parties expressed support for the necessary measures. I feel like asking why nothing happens afterwards", added the magistrate.
João Cura Mariano admitted that administrative and fiscal justice is a challenge “that has been going on for many years”, with processes whose final decision “often takes 20, 25 years”. However, the president of the STJ defended that justice is not as slow as it seems and lamented the negative impact on the “public perception” of mega-processes, which “always have setbacks and give the impression that the system does not work well”.
Even so, the advisory judge said he believed that, by investing in technological means and procedural reforms, including removing “formalities that no longer make sense”, “it was possible to greatly speed up the time of a process”. “There are those who say that waiting a year or two for a sentence is not much, but real life has sped up a lot”, said João Cura Mariano.
On the contrary, the president of the STJ argued that “major reforms, such as plea bargaining, which involve political options, are not as urgent and probably need to be more mature”.
The plea bargain, serving the sentence before the final judgment and the creation of a court specializing in highly complex cases are some of the suggestions of a working group, created in October 2023 by the Superior Council of the Judiciary (CSM) and coordinated by judge Helena Susano.
Some of the proposals have been discussed over the years, but never came to fruition, mainly because doubts were raised regarding their constitutionality.
As president of the STJ, João Cura Mariano also presides over the Superior Council of Judiciary.
“Gross negligence” when using AI
The president of the Supreme Court of Justice said, in Macau, that there have already been disciplinary proceedings against judges for using artificial intelligence (AI) in preparing decisions, but only in “cases of serious negligence”.
João Cura Mariano highlighted that sentences were detected with references to “articles that did not correspond to the correct content and to rulings that simply did not exist”.
The leader of the STJ of Portugal, who inherently also presides over the Superior Council of the Judiciary, recalled that “it is not prohibited” for judges to use AI, but that “there is an obligation to control the material it provides”.
João Cura Mariano warned of the risk of judges becoming not only “lazy”, but even having “a cognitive deficit” if they abuse the use of technology. The judge even expressed optimism about the greater use of AI tools in justice and predicted that “it will completely revolutionize the life of the courts”. For example, the president of the STJ said that technology could reduce the workforce needed to process processes: “any artificial intelligence system would do this without any problem”.
However, João Cura Mariano stressed that “there have to be limits” to ensure that “decisions continue to have a human component” and that judges will not be “replaced by mechanisms”. “When one day man gives up judging his fellow man, he will probably no longer be the prevailing species in the world”, predicted the judge. João Cura Mariano was speaking during a public event in Macau, where he will participate, on Sunday, in the 13th edition of the forum that brings together presidents of the Supreme Courts of Justice from Portuguese-speaking countries and territories. “These are very useful meetings, in which we share experiences, but in practice they are not very effective”, lamented the judge, who defended greater cooperation.
The president of the STJ gave as an example the training of magistrates, which could include “experiences in other countries”, studies of comparative rights and sharing of technological advances.
On the sidelines of the event, João Cura Mariano told journalists that, among Portuguese-speaking jurisdictions, Brazil is the pioneer, being “very advanced” in the use of AI. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:17:31</pubDate></item><item><title>First artificial heart implant surgery performed in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/19/realizada-primeira-cirurgia-de-implante-cardiaco-artificial-em-macau/</link><description>The first surgical procedure to implant an artificial heart in Macau was successfully carried out at the Centro Hospitalar Conde de São Januário (CHCSJ), in collaboration with the cardiothoracic surgery team of the First Affiliated Hospital of the University of Jinan.
In a statement, the Health Services said that the surgery “symbolizes significant progress in cardiac surgery in Macau, constituting the first implantation in Macau of a fully magnetically levitated artificial heart, developed autonomously in mainland China”.
The surgical intervention was performed on a 68-year-old patient with terminal heart failure. According to authorities, the condition presented was complex and the surgical intervention challenging. In the pre-operative period, the medical teams from the two hospital establishments carried out a multidisciplinary collegiate consultation with the purpose of comprehensively assessing the patient's condition.
In a statement, the Health Services explain that, during the surgical procedure, the patient underwent a left ventricular perforation and the implantation of a completely magnetically levitated artificial heart, under general anesthesia and with assisted extracorporeal circulation. Afterwards, the power cable was connected to an external device. After activating the artificial heart, using magnetic levitation technology, blood was pumped into the ascending aorta, establishing a parallel circulation state between the patient's heart and the artificial heart. The fully magnetically levitated artificial heart used in surgery was developed independently in the interior of China, featuring low hemolysis and high durability.
Its technical performance complies with international standards, effectively reducing blood damage and thrombosis, thus improving the patient's survival rate and quality of life. In the postoperative period, the patient made a satisfactory recovery, with resolution of heart failure symptoms and restoration of her usual mobility.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:10:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump confirms meeting with Xi Jinping in South Korea</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/19/trump-confirma-encontro-com-xi-jinping-na-coreia-do-sul/</link><description>The President of the United States, Donald Trump, confirmed that he will meet his Chinese counterpart, Xi Jinping, in South Korea, in “about two weeks”, on the sidelines of the Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC) summit.

“We will meet in about two weeks (…) in South Korea, with President Xi”, on the sidelines of APEC, said Trump, according to excerpts from the interview given to the “Fox Sunday Morning Futures” program that was broadcast on Sunday. The Republican leader is expected to arrive in South Korea on October 29th for a two-day visit and the summit will run until November 1st.
Trump's statements confirm the meeting between the leaders of the two main world economies, after the North American president threatened to cancel the meeting. The reason for the tension was due to the controls announced by Beijing on the export of rare earths, as well as machines and technologies that allow their refinement and transformation.
These raw materials are particularly sought after in the digital, renewable energy and defense industries, and Beijing controls an essential part of the value chain for almost all rare minerals.
Donald Trump classified this decision as “extremely aggressive”, threatening China with 100% additional customs duties and even considering canceling the meeting scheduled for two weeks from now with Xi Jinping.
However, the Republican acknowledged that the 100% increase in customs duties he threatened China with is “unsustainable” and said Beijing “forced” him to do so by imposing restrictions on the export of rare earths.
Asked by Fox News about the sustainability of that number and its consequences for the United States economy, the President replied: “It is not sustainable, but that is the number”. "I was forced to do it (…). I think we will get along well with China, but we have to have a fair agreement. It has to be fair", he said in another excerpt from the interview broadcast yesterday.
He also insisted that China “is a very strong opponent” and added that it will be necessary to wait for the meeting with the Chinese counterpart. "I raised our tariffs to 100%, on top of what they are already paying, which is much, much worse. We'll see what happens with China. I've always had an excellent relationship with Xi, but they are always looking for an advantage, they stole our country for years", he highlighted.
China announced that, in November, it will impose controls on the export of rare earths and the retaliation announced shortly afterwards by Trump marks the biggest disagreement with Beijing since the two powers agreed a tariff truce to negotiate a reduction in rates, which Washington raised to 145% during the trade war driven by the North American leader.
Trump and Xi held a telephone conversation on September 18, in which they approved a preliminary agreement to allow the TikTok platform to continue operating in the United States and agreed to meet in late October in South Korea, during the APEC leaders' summit.

China accuses US of cyber attack against center that manages its official timetable

The Chinese Ministry of State Security (MSS) yesterday accused the United States of carrying out a cyber attack against the National Time Service Center, the institution responsible for maintaining the accuracy of the country's official time.
In an article published in a messaging application, the MSS, which is China's main intelligence agency, claims to have recently discovered “irrefutable evidence” of a “major cyber attack” orchestrated by the US National Security Agency (NSA) against the aforementioned institution to “steal secrets, infiltrate and sabotage”.
The ministry explains that the National Time Service Center (NTSC) provides essential services for sectors such as energy, transport and defense, and that a cyberattack could result in network failures, problems for the financial system, blackouts, transport interruptions or space launch failures.
According to China, the US' “systematic and long-planned” attack against the NTSC began in 2022 through a vulnerability in the SMS service (short messages) of a “foreign brand” of cell phones, which allowed it to “covertly attack and gain control of the cell phones of several NTSC employees and steal confidential data stored on them”.
A year later, the NSA used stolen credentials to access the NTSC computer network and spy and, in June 2024, launched “high-intensity cyber attacks against several internal network systems” at the institution, the Chinese secret services claim. “National security authorities responded to the attacks by gathering evidence of U.S. cyberattacks, ordering the NTSC to conduct an investigation, interrupting the chain of attacks, and improving prevention capabilities to eliminate potential threats,” the article states.
In recent years, China and the US have accused each other of numerous cyber attacks, and the MSS reiterated this accusation yesterday: “Spy agencies, led by the NSA, have acted recklessly, carrying out continuous cyber attacks against China, Southeast Asia, Europe and South America.”
In this case, the accusation comes days before a new round of face-to-face negotiations between Beijing and Washington to try to ease renewed trade tensions between the world's two main economic powers. Lusa
 
China and the US will hold a new round of trade negotiations this week

China has confirmed that Chinese Vice Premier He Lifeng will meet this week with US Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent to discuss escalating trade tensions. In a statement, China's Ministry of Commerce said that Bessent and He, head of the Asian country's negotiating team, spoke via videoconference, also highlighting the participation of the US trade representative, Jamieson Greer. “Both sides had frank, in-depth and constructive conversations on important issues of bilateral economic and trade ties,” the Ministry said. The statement highlighted talks on how to implement the consensus reached in contacts between the leaders of the two countries, Donald Trump and Xi Jinping. Beijing also indicated that both powers “agreed to hold a new round of negotiations (…) as soon as possible”, but did not specify the date or location of this meeting. "Vice Prime Minister He Lifeng and I have shared frank and detailed discussions on trade between the United States and China. We will meet in person next week to continue our discussions," confirmed Scott Bessent.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:08:20</pubDate></item><item><title>DST was in Frankfurt and London to promote the Greater Bay Area</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/19/dst-esteve-em-frankfurt-e-londres-para-promover-a-grande-baia/</link><description>A Direcção dos Serviços de Turismo (DST), juntamente com o Departamento de Cultura e Turismo da Província de Guangdong e a Administração do Turismo de Hong Kong (Hong Kong Tourism Board – HKTB), visitaram na semana passada Frankfurt e Londres para a promoção “Greater Bay Area: Connecting Great Experiences”.
A iniciativa serviu para promover junto dos operadores e comunicação social as últimas ofertas dos três destinos com vista a promover produtos de viagens “multi-destinos” e a imagem de marca turística da região na Europa, para expandir em conjunto o mercado de visitantes internacionais.
This promotion was attended by a total of more than 200 tour operators. The program included presentations on tourism in the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area, discussion on cooperation opportunities for the development of tourism products, among others, “to lay a foundation for exploring the European visitor market”, says MGTO in a statement.
Jennifer Si Tou, deputy director of DST, was present in Frankfurt and London. The official highlighted that this promotional action allowed “one more step to be taken to reinforce the influence of Greater Bay Area’s tourist brand image on the international market”. Jennifer Si Tou also pointed out that, under the “multi-destination” travel model, “the three regions integrate their tourist resources and offer European travelers a rich and diverse travel experience”. The official also said that, “in the future, the three regions will continue to strengthen regional cooperation, jointly expand the long-haul visitor market and promote the development of the Greater Bay Area as a world-class tourist destination”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:09:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Macanese restaurant in Scotland wins “Heritage Kitchen of the Year” award</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/19/restaurante-macaense-na-escocia-vence-premio-de-cozinha-patrimonial-do-ano/</link><description>Macanese cuisine has once again been distinguished at an international level, this time with the award of the “Heritage Cuisine of the Year” award to Macau Kitchen. The team at the Edinburgh restaurant – the only one to serve this type of cuisine in the entire United Kingdom – says it is “deeply honored and pleasantly surprised” by the decision of the Asian Restaurant Awards 2025 jury and speaks of a “collective achievement” for the entire Macanese community.
 
The Macanese cuisine restaurant Macau Kitchen, located in the Scottish capital of Edinburgh, was the winner in the “Heritage Cuisine of the Year” category of the Asian Restaurant Awards 2025, aimed at rewarding the best Asian restaurants in Scotland.
This is the first time that a Macanese or Portuguese-Asian food restaurant has been distinguished at the gastronomic event, which this year marks its ninth edition. The nomination process took place at the beginning of the year, through a public vote in which customers and lovers of Asian cuisine were invited to nominate their favorite restaurants in the country. A panel of judges was then responsible for filtering the names suggested by the public to just 24 restaurants, using as evaluation criteria “culinary excellence, innovation, creativity and efforts undertaken over the last year”.
In addition to being the first Macanese gastronomy restaurant to win any category of the Asian Restaurant Awards 2025, Macau Kitchen enters the history of the gastronomic competition as the first ever winner of the “Heritage Cuisine of the Year” category, introduced for the first time this year.
In a note sent to PONTO FINAL, the Macau Kitchen team confesses to being “deeply honored and pleasantly surprised” with the award, highlighting its importance for the Macanese community around the world. “This award represents not only recognition for Macau Kitchen, but also a significant achievement for the Macanese community (…) and all Macanese and Eurasian restaurants around the world.”
Reinforcing this idea, the restaurant emphasizes the role of some of Macau's most prominent female chefs, as well as new talent emerging in the region, in the continued promotion of Macanese fusion cuisine, one of the oldest in the world. "This award recognizes the invaluable contributions of all Macau chefs and restaurants, especially those who laid the foundations for us. We are immensely grateful for the knowledge transmitted by culinary pioneers", recognizes the Macau Kitchen team, citing the names of well-known chefs in the territory such as Aida de Jesus, Neta, Florita Alves, Ana Manhão and Manuela Ferreira.
On the other hand, the restaurant also thanks Macau's “emerging talents” – such as chefs Sandra Barros and Ana Costa or even the team responsible for the Educational Restaurant of the Macau Tourist Training Institute (IFT), led by chef Hans Lee Rasmussen – for “paving the way for future Macanese chefs, allowing our cuisine to be appreciated from a new perspective by the guides gastronomic and restaurant award organizations”.
“This award is a collective achievement that belongs to the entire Macanese community and not just the restaurant”, emphasizes Macau Kitchen. More than a proof of the quality of the establishment, the award is also “a proof of the rich heritage and culinary excellence that we all strive to maintain by sharing our culture with the world”.
This year has been marked by consecutive recognition of Macau Kitchen's role in spreading Macanese gastronomy in the United Kingdom. In September, a month before the Asian Restaurant Awards 2025 ceremony, the restaurant had already received the award for “Best Customer Service” and was considered one of the “Best Chinese Restaurants of the Year” at The Spice Awards. The AA Rosette – culinary awards similar to the Michelin Guide, but limited to the United Kingdom and Ireland – also awarded Macau Kitchen another award for excellence in October, for the fourth consecutive year.
The Macau Kitchen restaurant, owned by the couple Kei de Freitas and Hoeyyn Ngu, opened its doors in 2019. To date, it is the only Macanese cuisine restaurant in the United Kingdom.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>André Cheong warns deputies not to limit themselves to “putting their stamp” on all diplomas</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/19/andre-cheong-alerta-deputados-a-nao-se-limitarem-a-colocar-o-seu-carimbo-em-todos-os-diplomas/</link><description>André Cheong argues that the role of deputies is not simply to “put their stamp on it”, but to “give practical opinions” to solve society’s problems. The new president of the Legislative Assembly said he hopes the hemicycle will be more efficient, intending to shorten the time for consideration of “important laws” that relate to public well-being, reinforcing communication between the hemicycle's advisory team and the Government.

The new president of the Legislative Assembly (AL), André Cheong, believes that deputies should not limit themselves to putting their “sign” on the bills presented by the Government, but rather commit to giving “constructive and practical suggestions”.
"Deputies should not limit themselves to raising their hands to approve the Government's bills, nor act as mere rubber stamps. Instead, through close communication with the Government, we will improve the bills, from their legislative intent to their technical aspects", warned André Cheong. In this way, says Cheong, laws, once enacted, can truly solve problems and promote social and economic development.
According to the former secretary for Administration and Justice, the role of deputies is not only to identify deficiencies in government administration and represent sectoral interests, but also to help the Government find the best solutions “within viable limitations” and collaborate with the Executive's governance.
André Cheong spoke to the Chinese press last Friday, the first day of work after assuming the role of president of the AL. At the time, Cheong admitted that he felt greater responsibility with the new position, but it was not a “drastic change”, as he had worked in the area of ​​justice for the last two decades, in the Public Administration.
In this sense, André Cheong assured that he will use past experience to improve communication with the Government in areas such as legislative planning, assessment of laws and political discussions, thus increasing legislative efficiency.
"Communication and coordination between the AL and the Government have improved significantly. In the experience of the last five years in terms of legislative coordination, all planned legislative projects were completed within the deadline, thanks to the regular communication mechanism between the parties", he praised.

MORE EFFICIENCY
 
Regarding the work of the new legislature, André Cheong said that he intends to further accelerate the legislation process, namely “important” draft laws and “those closely related to the well-being of the public”.
“We will promote preliminary communication between the AL advisory team and the departments responsible for the Government's proposals, facilitating the preparatory technical work for the subsequent presentation of bills to the AL for consideration, avoiding the exchange of technical correspondence that wastes time”, he defended.
André Cheong said he also intends to increase the quality of legislative work and, at the same time, encourage deputies to become more involved with local communities and understand residents' concerns.
He also warned that, when analyzing diplomas, it is imperative that opinions are based on the realities of society and are pragmatic. It also considers it necessary to move forward with the digitalization of parliamentary work to improve efficiency.
On the other hand, André Cheong recalled that 14 members of the hemicycle are first-time legislators, which is why he assumes that the AL must create conditions to help new members quickly improve their legislative and political debate skills. The AL president revealed that he will hold training sessions for new deputies this week, in order to familiarize them with the main legislative provisions and work procedures.
André Cheong concluded his term as secretary for Administration and Justice and member of the Executive Council last week, becoming the new president of the Legislative Assembly. In this sense, he has already ceased performing his duties in the Deep Cooperation Zone in Hengqin as Permanent Deputy Head of the Management Committee, according to the updated information in the deputies' profiles on the official portal of the Legislative Assembly.
In this case, the politician currently has only one position, in which he receives around 159 thousand patacas monthly, 80% of the Chief Executive's remuneration, a slightly higher amount compared to his former salary as secretary, of around 149 thousand patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:19:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan's main opposition party elects new leader</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/19/principal-partido-da-oposicao-de-taiwan-elege-nova-lider/</link><description>Taiwan's main opposition party, the Kuomingtang Nationalists (KMT), chose a former congresswoman as its new president, in an election marred by allegations of interference by China.

Cheng Li-wun — the only candidate in the race who positioned herself as a reformist — defeated former Taipei Mayor Hau Lung-bin and four other candidates for leadership of the pro-Beijing party by a large margin on Saturday.
At a press conference after the victory, Cheng said the nationalists would uphold the principles of equality, respect and mutual benefits in the conduct of foreign relations. "We must not let Taiwan become a troublemaker. Secondly, we must not let Taiwan be sacrificed to geopolitics," he said, adding that the KMT would also be a peacemaker.
Last week, Jaw Shaw-kong, a supporter of Hau Lung-bin, alleged that China was involved in an organized election interference campaign, giving as an example the publication on social media of videos attacking Hau and supporting Cheng. The head of Taiwan's Department of National Security, Tsai Ming-yen, said he found more than a thousand videos discussing the election on the short video platform TikTok, owned by Chinese company ByteDance. Tsai also mentioned the existence of 23 accounts publishing content related to the KMT vote on the video platform YouTube, with more than half of the accounts being registered outside Taiwan. The director did not say which candidates the videos supported nor did he reveal whether the accounts were registered in China, where YouTube is blocked.
Cheng Li-wun dismissed claims of China's influence on the party as "very cheap labels", urging politicians to return the island's politics to rationality.
Chen Binhua, spokesperson for China's Taiwan Affairs Office, said on Wednesday that the election was an internal KMT matter and that the views of some netizens did not represent the government's position.
The spokesman for the ruling Democratic Progressive Party (DPP), Wu Cheng, warned of Chinese interference and that the KMT should take careful precautions. Wu Cheng stated that the DPP expected the new Nationalist president to prioritize Taiwan's security over party interests.
Nationalists maintain strong political influence in Taiwan, despite losing three consecutive presidential elections to the DPP.
The KMT holds enough seats to form a majority bloc with its allies in parliament. The party survived two midterm elections a few months ago, called due to concerns about parliamentary decisions seen as a way of reducing the Government's power and favoring China.
With his inauguration scheduled for November, Cheng Li-wun will be able to influence how Taiwan deals with Beijing and other important national and international policies and political issues. Cheng will also be the party's leader in the 2026 local elections. The KMT must also prepare a candidate to challenge government leader William Lai's DPP in the 2028 elections. China has a tense relationship with William Lai, whom it accuses of being a separatist. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:08:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Cáritas Macau Food Bank received more than 3,500 requests by the end of September</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/19/banco-alimentar-da-caritas-macau-recebeu-mais-de-3-500-pedidos-ate-fim-de-setembro/</link><description>By the end of September, Cáritas Macau had received 3,509 requests for support for the Food Bank, said the organization's secretary-general, indicating that the final amount for the year should not deviate from that of 2024.

“We expect it [in 2025] to exceed four thousand, like last year”, Paul Pun noted to Lusa, pointing out that, in 2024, 4,936 requests reached the humanitarian organization, which, in turn, represents a drop of 2.5% compared to 2023 (5,065).
In an annual comparison, the first nine months of 2025 present values ​​similar to those recorded in the same period of 2023 and 2024: 3,589 and 3,596, respectively.
Even so, there has been a slight decline this year, which could be related to the “existence of other support resources” or “greater ease in applying for social housing”, noted Pun, implying that easier access to public housing could ease the bills at the end of the month.
The program, aimed at low-income people and financed by the authorities, foresees that the Bank's support will result in food aid for a period of ten weeks, with a second request being possible within 12 months.
Macau had, at the end of the first half of the year, 685,900 inhabitants, of which 182,583 were workers without residence status (TNR), according to official data. Among the TNR, Paul Pun highlighted, there is also a group that uses social assistance organizations. Last Saturday, he said, close to a thousand received support in the form of food baskets.
The minimum wage in Macau, a city with one of the highest Gross Domestic Products (GDP) per capita in the world, is 7,072 patacas per month or 34 patacas per hour, not covering domestic workers, the majority of whom are TNR.

Local Cáritas supports 2,100 people in Pakistan and Bangladesh

The secretary general of Cáritas Macau said that, as Macau does not face “very serious poverty” problems, the organization is supporting disadvantaged families in Bangladesh and Pakistan, providing aid to 2,100 people. “Since Macau does not face very, very serious problems of poverty, we also put our energy and work in other regions”, said Paul Pun Chi Meng, on the occasion of the International Day for the Eradication of Poverty.
Last week, Pun returned from Sylhet, a city in northeastern Bangladesh that he has visited several times since 2023, the year in which Cáritas Macau became involved in a program to “improve the health and nutrition of disadvantaged children”. With donations of around 15 thousand dollars per year, aid has already reached 400 people, said the person in charge. “We hope that, through training, in terms of care for newborns, mothers, they can achieve a better life”, pointed out the general secretary of Cáritas Macau, also noting that, on the table is the possibility of providing resources for the professional training of teenagers who dropped out of school.
A month ago, Paul Pun was also in Lahore, the second largest city in Pakistan, with around 14 million inhabitants and which has been affected, in recent years, by several floods.
Cáritas Macau's assistance to the “Informal education and development of young people and women” program, with the transfer of up to 35 thousand dollars per year, has already touched the lives of 1,200 children and 500 teenagers in Lahore, according to the leader of the humanitarian organization. "The children do not have schools [in these places]. They participate in this informal education program so that they have an opportunity to reach the standards and one day be able to enter school", he said.
In addition to supporting the education of teenagers – “especially boys” – in areas such as IT, the program also includes skills training “by young women”.
To Lusa, Paul Pun said that international assistance from Cáritas Macau arrives “via several channels”, namely through donations and the organization Good Fortune Charity Shop, the social enterprise of Cáritas Macau, which collects donated goods for charitable sale.
Cáritas Macau, founded in 1951, has 46 social service units and educational service units spread across the territory, serving more than 10,000 people per year, according to the organization's website. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:18:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Taxi drivers are increasingly committing irregularities</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/19/taxistas-praticam-cada-vez-mais-irregularidades/</link><description>Traffic infractions committed by taxi drivers have been growing exponentially in recent years. Between January and September 2022, the number of irregularities committed by taxi drivers was just 83; between January and September 2025, the number rose to 1,596 – almost 20 times more.
The number of irregularities committed by taxi drivers has skyrocketed in recent years. Between January and September this year, the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) registered 1,596. In the same period last year, the number of infractions was 600 and in the first nine months of 2023 it was 394. Between January and September 2022, only 83 irregularities committed by taxi drivers were recorded. This shows that, in the last four years, the number of infractions has increased almost 20 times.
According to data from the first nine months of this year, released on Friday by the CPSP, the vast majority of cases (933) had to do with customers not waiting in order of arrival at taxi ranks. This offense alone saw an increase of more than 500% compared to the same period last year. There were also 377 infractions related to refusal of transport, 86 of obvious route deviation and 40 of abusive charging, for example.
CPSP statistics also show that, in the first three quarters of 2025, there was a reduction in the number of road accidents compared to last year – 11,696 between January and September 2024 and 11,086 between January and September 2025.
During this period, there was one fatal accident, and in the same period of 2024 there were two. However, the number of deaths in road accidents increased from two a year ago to four. The number of injured remained stable at around 4,100.
In total, there were 533,877 violations of the road traffic law and the Highway Code regulations in this period, slightly less than the total for the same period last year (546,324). The total value of fines imposed for infractions also fell slightly by 4.5%, from around 147 million patacas to 140 million.
The number of pedestrians who crossed the roads without complying with traffic rules increased by 6%, now recording 6,546 irregularities of this kind.
Cases of speeding on public roads increased by more than 15% in this period, compared to last year. In the first nine months of the year, there were 10,274 cases and in the same period of 2024, 8,870 were recorded. There were also almost 4,000 red light overruns, whereas a year ago there had been only 3,358 such cases.
The CPSP also details that there were approximately 420 thousand cases of illegal parking on public roads, slightly less than last year. However, offenses related to illegal parking in charged or metered parking spaces increased significantly, from 31,979 last year to 50,744 this year.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:20:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal Point – 20 October 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/19/ponto-fatal-20-outubro-2025/</link><description>Traffic infractions committed by taxi drivers have been growing exponentially in recent years. Between January and September 2022, the number of irregularities committed by taxi drivers was just 83; between January and September 2025, the number rose to 1,596 – almost 20 times more.
The number of irregularities committed by taxi drivers has skyrocketed in recent years. Between January and September this year, the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) registered 1,596. In the same period last year, the number of infractions was 600 and in the first nine months of 2023 it was 394. Between January and September 2022, only 83 irregularities committed by taxi drivers were recorded. This shows that, in the last four years, the number of infractions has increased almost 20 times.
According to data from the first nine months of this year, released on Friday by the CPSP, the vast majority of cases (933) had to do with customers not waiting in order of arrival at taxi ranks. This offense alone saw an increase of more than 500% compared to the same period last year. There were also 377 infractions related to refusal of transport, 86 of obvious route deviation and 40 of abusive charging, for example.
CPSP statistics also show that, in the first three quarters of 2025, there was a reduction in the number of road accidents compared to last year – 11,696 between January and September 2024 and 11,086 between January and September 2025.
During this period, there was one fatal accident, and in the same period of 2024 there were two. However, the number of deaths in road accidents increased from two a year ago to four. The number of injured remained stable at around 4,100.
In total, there were 533,877 violations of the road traffic law and the Highway Code regulations in this period, slightly less than the total for the same period last year (546,324). The total value of fines imposed for infractions also fell slightly by 4.5%, from around 147 million patacas to 140 million.
The number of pedestrians who crossed the roads without complying with traffic rules increased by 6%, now recording 6,546 irregularities of this kind.
Cases of speeding on public roads increased by more than 15% in this period, compared to last year. In the first nine months of the year, there were 10,274 cases and in the same period of 2024, 8,870 were recorded. There were also almost 4,000 red light overruns, whereas a year ago there had been only 3,358 such cases.
The CPSP also details that there were approximately 420 thousand cases of illegal parking on public roads, slightly less than last year. However, offenses related to illegal parking in charged or metered parking spaces increased significantly, from 31,979 last year to 50,744 this year.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:06:21</pubDate></item></channel></rss>