<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/31/a-fonte-da-felicidade-esta-no-venetian-entre-personagens-infantis-e-mitologia-romana/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>The infinite world of Cristina Leiria</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/31/o-mundo-infinito-de-cristina-leiria/</link><description>Cristina Leiria, a Portuguese architect and sculptor who conceived the Ecumenical Center Kun iam, in Nape, made known some details about this “space of silence”, such as energy points, the representations of the “third vision” and the “infinite world”. During a guided tour, he suggested the conception of “a large cultural space”, linking the ecumenical center to the Science Center and the Cultural Center, lamenting that the government does not hear its proposals.
The Ecumenical Center Kun Iam, in Nape, was conceived, in the late 1990s, by Portuguese architect and sculptor Cristina Leiria. Inaugurated in March 1999, it aims to be a space of silence and meditation. Yesterday, Cristina Leiria organized a guided tour and drew attention to details that can go unnoticed to residents and tourists passing by.
The architect began to point out that the ecumenical center "was created for one purpose: to provide people from Macau and its visitors a space only for silence."
At 60 meters that connects Dr. Sun Yat-Sen Avenue to the artificial island where the statue of Kun Iam is, there is a lotus flower drawn on the stones of the Portuguese sidewalk, a gift left by Calceiro Zé Fernando to Cristina Leiria.
"Let's get into the infinite world, our mind, in our imagination," the sculptor warned before proceeding. "I found out with this work that my mission in this world was to find infinity," he said.
Among the various elements we find on the Portuguese sidewalk of the isthmus that leads to the center, there is a drawing of one eye. This is where we should "remember that what we are going to develop are capabilities that do not depend on our tact, is the third vision - is the big eye."
Ahead, there are “energy points calculated by a Feng-Shui teacher and confirmed by a sacred geometry master” and a symbol of infinity, for those facing the statue, or an “8”, for those who see it aside. When walking towards the statue of Kun Iam, we enter a “infinite world”; When, outside the space, people sit on the bench next to the symbol, they see the luck number, he explained.
On the way to the center, the architect also warned of details such as the representations of a sun and a moon drawn on the stone and the possible interpretations of the goddess moods with each step.
Already inside the space, we heard Kyao while Cristina Leiria was pointing to the panels with paintings, figures, symbols and texts related to Lao Tse, Confucius, Mencio and Buddha-all painted on rice paper. The architect also highlighted the entry of sunlight into space. Again from the outside of the ecumenical center but on the rear of the statue, Cristina Leiria pointed to an inscription on the goddess foot where she reads “Macao government” and her signature.
With a 20 meter high and a weight of 50 tons, the Kun Aíam statue is made up of about 50 bronze cast pieces. The base of the statue, in the form of lotus flower, consists of a contemplation room where you can rest, listen to music and read. The lower floor offers a multipurpose room with a capacity of 50 people, which is dedicated to concerts, conferences, movie viewing and other multicultural activities such as art exhibitions.
Cristina Leiria recalled that, in 2014, she presented several projects to the Government of MSAR to streamline that zone, connecting both the Cultural Center and the Science Center to the Ecumenical Center through superior passages, “linking everything in a large cultural space”. However, their proposals have not been heard by the authorities, complained.
The architect has been trying to schedule meetings with the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, the secretary for social affairs and culture, Lam, and the president of the Cultural Institute, Leong Wai Man: “I take big envelopes to take place since December, but they have not received me”. However, he is not ignored. "No, they have other priorities. I don't care that they call me boring, I have that goal."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Supports awarded by the Macau Foundation quadrupled in the first half</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/31/apoios-atribuidos-pela-fundacao-macau-quadruplicaram-no-primeiro-semestre/</link><description>The Macau Foundation granted nearly 1.6 billion financial supports between January and June this year, a significant increase of four times more compared to last year's same period. In addition to subsidies given to traditional associations, supports are highlighted for the University of Macao regarding the acquisition of land for the new Campus in Hengqin, involving a funds of more than 1,000 million patacas.

In the first six months of this year, the Macao Foundation has approved more than 1,000 financial support requests, whose funding amount reached 1.59 billion patacas. The total amount represents a sharp increase of 306% over the same period last year, when 391 million patacas were channeled.
The amount awarded in the first quarter of this year was 1.26 billion Patacas, equivalent to an annual increase of 556%, while the second quarter was 325 million patacas (+64%), according to the financial support list up to the entity on the public dissemination platform for supervision information and management services.
Analyzing the data, the difference in the total value granted by the Macau Foundation in the first half of the year was mainly due to two projects approved at the request of the University of Macau (one). The higher education institution was a beneficiary of a amount of 373.4 million Patacas in January, 659.8 million Patacas in February, and also 139.2 million Patacas in June, which totaled over 1.17 billion.
The Macau Foundation indicated that they were financial support for one of the acquisition of land for educational purposes in the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin. The three payments correspond to the “first installment” and “last installment” of the subsidy, the body advanced.
The Macau Foundation funded in January with 50 million Patacas, the Macao University of Science and Technology Foundation, under the “Macau Science Satellite-2” satellite project.
In this sense, unlike the usual, the traditional Macao associations are no longer the largest among the beneficiary entities. Of the traditional associations, the General Union of Macao residents' associations continues, as usual, to be the entity that received the most subsidies, with 36 million patacas, with the amount of 16.6 million and 19.3 million patacas in both quarters, respectively.
The Federation of Macao Workers' Associations follows, with a total of 28.7 million patacas of subsidy received by June. The General Association of Women was attributed with 27.6 million patacas, while the Macao Povo Alliance, an association linked to the Fujian community, received 14 million patacas.
Financial support was mainly for the operating expenses of the associations, as well as subsidies for the organization of community activities.
The Portuguese matrix entities are also among the beneficiaries. The Macao Portuguese School Foundation was granted with a financial support amount of 9.8 million Patacas in the first half of the year, in terms of subsidies for activities and expenses for the school year. Thus there was an increase of 20% in the financial support value obtained by this body compared to the same period last year.
In turn, Casa de Portugal in Macau received a financing of 7.5 million patacas, whose majority served for the association's operating expenses, as well as financial support for activities.
The Macao Foundation granted the Macanese Instruction Promoting Association a financial support of 765,000 Patacas. Already the Macanese Association received 2.1 million patacas, while the Association of Young Macanese raised 121 thousand patacas of subsidy for activities.</description><pubDate>2025-07-31 00:09:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Government promises greater control to atmospheric pollutants</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/31/governo-promete-maior-controlo-a-poluentes-atmosfericos/</link><description>The government is determined to implement more measures to reduce the emission of atmospheric pollutants. Authorities have revealed that they are studying more ozone restrictions and products with volatile organic compounds, indicating that monitoring of that substance in the air is underway inside Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau.

The Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) plans to reinforce control of the emission of atmospheric pollutants, namely ozone and volatile organic compounds (COV).
The executive “will study and elaborate more ozone control measures and COV products to reduce the emission of these pollutants,” he assumed, in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Ho Ion Sang.
In Macao, products containing high CoV content are already subject to control. The government has begun to regulate values that exceed the CoV limit since 2022. These policies and measures are currently seen by society as necessary to be reinforced to meet current environmental challenges.
In this case, according to the response of DSPA, weather and geophysical services have pointed out that the governments of Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau have been cooperating in the monitoring of CoV in recent years, having created a network of air quality monitoring of the Rio das Pearl region, in order to solve the problem of ozon pollution in the area.
CoV monitoring work also serves to provide scientific foundations for the analysis of the ozone formation mechanism and the elaboration of control measures, the government explained.
DSPA has stated that the measures of greatest restrictions on products with CoV will also be based on the results of this joint monitoring of the three regions.
It is recalled that the government has launched control measures that regulate architectural paints, oil paints, and vehicle repair varnishes used in civil construction and decoration works that exceed CoV's limitation values, respectively, 2022, 2023 and last year. "Ozone has been a major cause of impact on Macao air quality in recent years, with the control of COV emissions one of the crucial means to reduce ozone and photochemical pollution," said the executive.
In his question, Ho Ion Sang has criticized the impact on the air quality of Macao and the health of residents in recent years due to the ozone. "Last year, most estimates of atmospheric pollutant emissions in Macau registered an increase compared to the previous year, noting non-metanical volatile organic compounds (COVNM) from organic solvents, which had a significant growth of 68.3 percent, mainly due to increased importation of related products," he said.
The deputy, therefore, pointed out that in the face of the sharp growth of CoV emissions, the current measures are insufficient to contain, effectively, the worsening of pollution in the ozone, so it has requested more solutions to the situation.
In the replica, DSPA also said that it is promoting the work planning work of Macao for the next five years, where it will be into account all measures and objectives that can contribute to improve air quality.
In addition, it has pledged to resort to eco-schools, thematic lectures and activities, among other ways, to sensitize citizens to the impact of various pollution problems on the environment, encouraging them to create ecological consumption habits.</description><pubDate>2025-07-31 00:08:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Transform ideas into startups. Researcher of a sharing success experiences</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/31/transformar-ideias-em-startups-investigador-da-um-partilha-experiencias-de-sucesso/</link><description>Yesterday one of the morning meetings organized by the France Chamber of Commerce Macau (FMCC), this time under the theme “From the Laboratory to the Market: joining the gym and industry to the success of the startups”. Tang Yu Ming, the guest speaker of this session, shared some of the projects he helped realize at the University of Macao, from 100% craft beer made in Macau the ecological sand for cats, produced from the transformation of malt waste.

What do you have in common the malt used in beer production and cat sand? The July session of lectures and breakfasts organized monthly by the France Macau Chamber of Commerce (FMCC) at the Sofitel Hotel proposed to explore some of Macau's most creative ideas and find out how they gave rise to successful business.
The guest speaker of this session was Tang Yu Ming, a resident researcher at the University of Macau (one) and a lot of startups who triumphed in the region, such as the Funny Eye brewery and the mark of sustainable products for Biopetech pet. “Since 2018 I have helped students create their own companies,” he said yesterday morning.
The Funny Eye project was the first to gain life, catapulted from the UM UM Cheng Yu College for Macao's bars and supermarkets. It all started when Tang Yu Ming presented three of his students with interest in the art of craft beer - Alison Tam, Crystal Kwok and Lucas Lio - to another trio of former students who managed the Mak’s Brewery brewery in Hong Kong. While Lucas Lio refined his knowledge and produced beer in the neighboring region, Crystal and Alison sold the products ended in a banking set in the Hong Kung night market, on October 5th Street.
“One day Crystal called me and said a customer wanted to know where our brewery was,” said the employee of UM. "Beer was made in Hong Kong because in Macao we had several obstacles and it was hard to get all the requirements to open our own space. It was then that the customer told Crystal that he could help us with bureaucratic issues."
With the support of UM's Innovation and Entrepreneurship Center, a platform that supports the faculty and student body to create its own business and market research results, the only 100% brewery “Made in Macao” was born in the historic center of Macau. The flavors are diverse and based on the region's own culture, reconciling the classic taste of beer to more oriental brawings such as Lichia black tea or passion fruit green tea.
The investigator explained that during the breeding process of beer, a huge amount of malt residue was wasted. How to recycle these by -products? What use could they have? The solution emerged unexpectedly when a gray cat was abandoned on one in May 2020 during the Covid-19 pandemic. Tang and his wife decided to host the cat "for a night", which eventually led to many more. "My wife loved him and asked us to try to create. I had to buy a lot of things: food, toys ... and many sand packaging." It was then that these two materials without apparent connection came together in an unusual idea: manufacturing cat sand through the malt bagasse.
The initiative started with a mysterious poster in the corridors of UM, accounting for a “reading club” about “The Science of Cats”. "Many students saw the poster and wanted to join the activity, thinking that the goal would be to study the language of cats or the meaning of their behaviors. It was not the case," the researcher smiled. Velted by the image of the plump cat on the poster, the students eventually stayed and dedicated to numerous hours of research and experiences-some failed, some successful-from preparation to execution. One of the main problems to overcome was the odor: when waste was not processed correctly, the smell became "unbearable."
The formula was worked and improved throughout a long and intense process - so intense that of the 20 initial participants, only four remained, according to a statement from UM. The effort eventually compensated and culminated in the creation of Biopetech, a pioneering initiative in Macao that has already been distinguished in several business contests in the Great Bay area and even deserved a cooperation agreement with a company in Nansha district in Canton. In addition to being sustainable and biodegradable, unlike clay -composed traditional sands, it also has advantages over other plant -based products such as tofu sand. "Ours is better because grains have many small holes that make it easier for odors to absorb."
The cat that motivated the idea, Hans, passed away a month after being adopted, victim of feline infectious peritonitis (PIF). Despite its short life, its impact was not girded by biodegradable sand. Like Hans, a lot of cats often wanders one: "Students want to feed cats, but they ultimately neglect hygiene and leave the food on the floor, which has generated several complaints ...".
After about “ten or 15 cats” were collected by the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMIs), the university now seeks a solution to ensure that all cats that have passed a home, as happened with Hans. On the weekend of August 23 and 24, the animals will be available for adoption on the first floor of UM, at an event where everyone in Macau-teachers, students or only animal lovers-are invited to participate.</description><pubDate>2025-07-31 00:07:14</pubDate></item><item><title>The source of happiness is in Venetian, between children's characters and Roman mythology</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/31/a-fonte-da-felicidade-esta-no-venetian-entre-personagens-infantis-e-mitologia-romana/</link><description>Sands China brought together nine contemporary artists from different continents for a fusion between two apparently distinct worlds: the classic beauty of Roman mythology with the characters in the children's series “Rua Sesamo”. Titled “Dopamine: Source of Happiness”, the project proposes to discover the pure and infiltrated happiness formula, acting as a dose of dopamine at the audience that visits it.

The exhibition “Dopamine: Source of Happiness” was inaugurated Tuesday at Venetian, where it will continue to patent until October 15. The show is part of this year's edition of the cultural event “Arte Macau: Macau International Art Biennial 2025”, subordinate to the central question “Hello, what do you do here?”.
Dopamine, the neurotransmitter associated with the feeling of pleasure, gives title to an exhibition whose purpose is to “rekindle the happiness” of Macau's audience, through the combination of “vivid colors, unlimited imagination and the expression of positive emotions”. As a final touch of childish innocence, the artists participating in the project were invited to reinterpret the iconic characters of the children's program “Rua Sesamo” and cover them with a brightly colored pallet.
Craig &amp; Karl, Bibi Law, Grafflex, Hei Lok, Ilya Milstein, Jun Oson, Jonni Cheatwood and Song Zhou are the “nine notable artists” who sign the unpublished works of art, created exclusively for Macao, which now complement the resort's Venezian atmosphere. In addition to the childish elements, artistic works drink from the aesthetics of Roman mythology to create simultaneously contemporary and classic works, on a “multimedia, timeless and intercultural” journey that feeds “the emotional resonance of joy and happiness that the arts at Venetian Macau offer”.
Speaking at the inauguration ceremony, Leong Wai Man, president of the Cultural Institute (IC), praised “The Passion and Professionalism” of the Sands concessionaire, the curatorial team and the international artists who joined this project, infusing “a lasting impulse in the cultural landscape of Macau”.
Wilfred Wong, vice president of Sands China, expressed hope that the exhibition "can create a happiness factor for all-dopamine." "For this special exhibition, international artists collaborated with Sesame Street to intertwine their characters with ancient Roman mythology, creating large -scale unique art works for Macao," he said.
The co-founder and director of the curatorial team, Articross, said that collaboration with nine international artists “transcends the barriers of culture, language and style, to create a colorful and imaginative artistic dialogue in the multicultural city of Macau”. Ken Wong also added that participation in Macau 2025 art "is a very challenging but also immensely honorable artistic journey."
In a statement, Sands China said that collaboration with the artistic duo Craig &amp; Karl is not limited to “dopamine: source of happiness”. In parallel to this exhibition, it was created “an exclusive limited edition of the“ Jenga ”block stacking game for Macau 2025 art, especially designed to honor the spirit of the city - diverse, dynamic and living with cultural rhythm and creativity”. The pieces of art - with six unique patterns, “impregnated from the vibrant aesthetics characteristic of artists” - are exclusively available in the area of the outer Lagoon of Venetian.
Also noteworthy is the collateral exhibition “Beyond the Frame: International Contemporary Masterpieces”, which results from the main exhibition. Several of the artists who participated in “dopamine” (Bibi Law, Song Zhou, Jun Oson, Grafflex, Ilya Milstein and Jonni Cheatwood) return to present more than 60 works that “break conventional paintings through distinct visual languages”, collectively exploring the way “artistic borders are being redefined in the current global context”. While inviting public participation and forging “new artistic borders”, the works of the six artists also build “deeply personal creative kingdoms”, concludes Sands in a statement.</description><pubDate /></item></channel></rss>