<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/chamadas-fraudulentas-que-simulam-alipay-e-wechat-provocaram-46-vitimas-em-macau/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Brazilian soybean wins quota in the Chinese market in the face of tension with the US</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/soja-brasileira-ganha-quota-no-mercado-chines-face-a-tensao-com-os-eua/</link><description>China is turning to Brazil to compensate for the breaking of US agricultural product purchases in the context of Donald Trump's trade war, according to local press.
A total of 40 ships discharged this month 700,000 tons of soy from Brazil in the port of Ningbo, eastern China, an increase of 32% compared to the same period of 2024, according to Chinese state television CCTV. “After China reduced purchases to the US, Brazilian soy ships began to arrive one after each other,” wrote the channel, in a Weibo social network account.
The operation is another sign that China is reducing the dependence on US agricultural imports after canceling last week orders of 12,030 US pork metrics-the largest cancellation since May 2020.
Brazilian Minister of Agriculture and Livestock, Carlos Fávaro, assured that Brazil will take advantage of all the opportunities generated by the trade war between Beijing and Washington. "I do not like to celebrate crises, to celebrate any instability, which is the case. The United States begins to take action that brutally destabilize world business relations and we should not celebrate it. Now, in seizures are opportunities. And Brazil is aware of opportunities and will expand," he said.
Brazil has benefited from commercial disputes among the two largest economies in the world since the First Trade War, which began during Donald Trump's first presidential term (2017-2021). Since then, China has increased soy purchases to the country to reduce US dependence.
In 2024, China imported a total of 105 million tons of soy, of which 22.14 million came from the US, representing 21.1% of the total - a fall of 13.3% compared to 2018. During the same period, Chinese soy imports reached 74.65 million tons, representing 71.1% of the total, according to data from Chinese cans.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 05:11:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Association tried to organize demonstration of May 1, but eventually gave up</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/associacao-tentou-organizar-manifestacao-de-1-de-maio-mas-acabou-por-desistir/</link><description>For the sixth consecutive year, no manifestation will be held on the occasion of Labor Day. The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) indicated to the end that it received a prior notice for a demonstration on May 1st, but the prosecutor eventually gave up the idea “on his own initiative”.
 
The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) told the end that it received a prior notice for a demonstration on the occasion of May 1st, the Labor Day, however, the promoter of the initiative eventually canceled the intention “at its own initiative”. The CPSP was no further details about this marching request not even revealed which entity was trying to perform. Thus, for the sixth consecutive year, the date will not be marked with a demonstration that, by 2019, was usual at this time.
From 2020, the various associations that previously organized May 1st marches ceased to do so, initially due to the Covid-19 pandemic. Last year, CPSP received no request for the organization of the march. In 2023, Wong Wai Man presented the notice, but eventually gave up the initiative. First, Wong Wai Man claimed that he had been the target of pressure from the authorities not to realize the initiative, but then denied the initial version and said he had given up to preserve the "stability" of the territory.
The Federation of Macao Workers 'Associations, the Association of Game Workers' Rights and the Power of the People's Association, for example, which traditionally promoted marches by workers, have also disinterested the initiative in recent years.
In 2017, for example, the labor marches took about 2,600 people to the street. According to it was reported at the time, in 2006 and 2007, the number of protesters will have exceeded 3,000.
Regarding the end of the May 1 demonstrations in Macao, the Secretary for Security said in 2023 that this is not a sign of weakening the vigor of freedoms in the territory. By the way, Wong Sio Chak said the marches themselves are not a mandatory requirement to mark Labor Day.
It is recalled that, according to the law that regulates the right of meeting and manifestation in public places, the persons or entities wishing to hold meetings or demonstrations using the public road, public places or open to the public must notify, in writing, the CPSP commander, at least three business days in advance and the maximum of 15. anterior is reduced to two business days.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 05:14:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai wants to reinforce cooperation with Zhongshan and Jiangmen</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/sam-hou-fai-quer-reforcar-a-cooperacao-com-zhongshan-e-jiangmen/</link><description>This Monday, the 28th, the Chief Executive visited various points of interest in the cities of Zhongshan in the morning, and Jiangmen in the afternoon. Although with specific focuses in different industries, from Biomedical to cultural tourism, Sam Hou Fai's intention was similar in both cities visited: promoting bilateral cooperation, with a view to building a large more united and cohesive bay.
 
Executive Chief Sam Hou Fai visited the cities of Zhongshan and Jiangmen on Monday in Guangdong province, with the aim of deepening exchange and cooperation between Macao and both regions.
The visit to the interior of China began with Zhongshang in the morning with the biomedical industry and the sectors of medicine and health to occupy the main points of the program. In this regard, Sam Hou Fai visited the Zhongshan Pharmaceutical Innovation Institute of the Chinese Academy of Sciences, where he attended a presentation on the development of “innovative” medicines, according to a statement issued by the Communication Office (GCS). The chief executive expressed interest in the creation of a cooperation base between both regions regarding the medical and health industries, recalling that the current government of MSAR has encouraged and “strongly” the progress of traditional Chinese medicine.
The Great Bay's Future Technology Center was the next stop at the itinerary, where the MSAR representative witnessed a presentation on the synergistic development of the Great Bay area, highlighting the efforts to approach Shenzhen. It is recalled that the Shenzhen-ZhongShan connection was inaugurated in June last year, reducing travel time between the two two-hour destinations to just 30 minutes. On this topic, Sam Hou Fai stressed that the new bridge had come to strengthen the connection between the main cities of the Great Bay and was expected to be expected to the “multiple positive factors” that this novelty could provide, for example, in the area of ​​cultural tourism.
As for the technological scene of Zhongshan, the head of the Executive of MSA praised the “good platform in the formation and retention of high -tech qualified pictures” and recalled that Macau also has high -expense laboratories abroad, thus exploiting the possibility of future cooperation between the regions.
 
Once the visits to the Biomedical and Technological Centers, Sam Hou Fai met with the Secretary of the Zhongshan Municipal Committee of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) and president of the Permanent Committee of the Zhongshan Municipal Popular Assembly, Gou Wenhai. At the meeting, the ruler of Macao recalled the “deep connection in historical terms” of the two regions and praised the rapid “development” of the city of Zhongshan, ensuring that the government of MSar will “advance stable” with cooperation projects to “increase efficiency between the two regions in various domains, such as economy and commerce, biomedicine, cutting -edge technology and higher education”.
 
Jiangmen and Macau join the “cultural richness”
 
In the afternoon of the same day, the chief executive went west to the city of Jiangmen. Before meeting with the city's political representatives, Sam Hou Fai visited a food company with Macao investment, noting that the two cities “built a good cooperation base” in both food industry and in the cultural tourism sector. As the ruler noticed, the two zones are known for their historical heritage and cultural richness, paving the way for the joint development of their tourist sectors. This idea was corroborated on the next visit, this time to the Chinese overseas city museum.
Following the visits, Sam Hou Fai met with the secretary of the Jiangmen Municipal Committee of the CCP and president of the Municipal Popular Assembly, Chen Anming, as well as the mayor of Jiangmen, Wu Xiaohui. The chief executive began by expressing “a great satisfaction for his first visit to the city after the inauguration,” describes the GCS press release.
In addition to the convergence points between the two parts, the ruler of Macau also praised the “rich land resources” and the “good transport network” of Jiangmen, which enable an effective connection to various “advantageous” industrial sectors in the great bay. Thus, he stressed, the exchange of resources and the use of the “nucleum advantages” of each city may result in a “new chapter of highly qualified development for both”.
After the visits to Zhongshan and Jiangmen, Sam Hou Fai returned to Macau at the end of his own, April 28.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 05:11:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese exports to Lusophone countries reach a new record by March</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/exportacoes-chinesas-para-os-paises-lusofonos-atingem-novo-recorde-ate-marco/</link><description>Chinese exports to Portuguese -speaking countries had the best starter of the year, increasing 2.3% in the first three months, compared to the same period of 2024, according to official data.
 
According to information from China's customs services, released on Monday, goods sold to Lusophone markets until March reached $ 19.7 billion (17.3 billion euros).
This is the highest value for a first trimester since the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries (Macao Forum) began presenting this data in 2013.
The data released reveal that the main reason for the new record was Angola, whose imports from China more than doubled, to $ 1.58 billion (1.39 billion euros).
Still, and despite a 2%homologous decrease, Brazil remains the largest buyer in the Lusophone bloc, with Chinese China goods to reach $ 15.8 billion (13.9 billion euros).
Third on the list, now behind Angola, comes Portugal, who bought China products worth $ 1.48 billion (1.3 billion euros), 1.3% more than in the first three months of 2024.
In the opposite direction, exports from Portuguese -speaking countries to China fell 30.1% in the first quarter of 2025, compared to the same period last year.
Between January and March the Lusófono Block sold goods worth $ 24.5 billion (21.5 billion euros) to the Chinese market. This is the lowest value for the first three months of a year since 2020, at the beginning of the Covid - 19 pandemic.
The descent was mainly due to the largest Lusophone supplier in the Chinese market, Brazil, whose sales fell more than one third (34.1%) to $ 19.3 billion (16.9 billion euros).
In addition, also the second largest Chinese commercial partner in the Lusophone block, Angola, saw exports decrease $ 10.6% to $ 3.87 billion (3.42 billion euros). Similarly, Portugal's sales of goods to China decreased by 14.4% to $ 635.3 million (557.5 million euros).
On the contrary, Mozambique exports rose 18.5% to $ 484.5 million (425.2 million euros).
Equatorial Guinea exports to the Chinese market dropped almost a third (32.1%) to $ 204 million (179 million euros).
Also sales of Timor-Leste and Sao Tome and Principe shrank 97.4% and 53.2%, respectively, although neither has exported more than 3,000 dollars (about 2,600 euros) in goods to China. Cape Verde and Guinea-Bissau did not sell any products to the Chinese market in the first three months of 2025.
China registered a commercial deficit of $ 4.79 billion (4.21 billion euros) with the Lusophone bloc between January and March. In all, trade between Portuguese -speaking countries and China reached $ 44.2 billion (38.8 billion euros), less 18.6% than in the same period last year. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 05:16:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Police provides for the rise of burlas using artificial intelligence</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/policia-preve-subida-de-burlas-com-recurso-a-inteligencia-artificial/</link><description>The Judiciary Police warned of the possible increase in cases of scams using artificial intelligence in Macao, after the first case was detected in the territory last week. The authorities indicate, however, that they have already completed the updating of the Forensic Computer System, ensuring having made relevant response preparations.
 
The number of artificially intelligence -made cases may increase in the territory as technology and modus operandi evolve in computer fraud, admitted the Judiciary Police (PJ). Macau registered last week the first case of Burla using artificial intelligence, and the authorities estimate that “more cases” of identical fraud in the region in the future arise.
I am Sio Keong, a PJ subdirector, said he has reinforced the international exchange of information and will warmly warn the public if new crimes appear in neighboring regions. “We have also improved the relevant forensic computer system in recent years and we launched a special research project that analyzes the 'Deepfake' technology,” he said. Speaking to the Macau Forum Program of the Radio Macau Chinese channel, the official added that the PJ made the necessary preparations in terms of the execution of the law and the computer configuration.
Macao police received the first case of attempted mockery at the use of artificial intelligence using the Deepfake technology. According to the body, the portrait of an elderly resident was used to make a video to attract people to an investment project. So far, no victim has been registered with this scam.
PJ indicated that after clicking on the publication of the video produced by Artificial Intelligence, the user was sent to a fake site of a local newspaper that also contained a video generated through the use of Deepfake technology that falsifies the face and voice, pretending to be the complainant that was interviewed by the media, recommending some investment projects.
Before the case was detected, the scam made with the help of artificial intelligence had already raised the concern of society. At the end of last year, several Macao deputies were the target of a blackmail scheme with manipulated photos, with faces exchanged in a context of nudity. Wong Sio Chak, secretary for security, had recognized that “it is difficult to detect” online crimes of extortion with pornographic photos with face exchange, and it is also “very difficult” to caution the frauds that use artificial intelligence. "It is necessary to rely on more awareness actions so that the community knows that this is a scheme," he assumed.
I am Sio Keong reiterated yesterday that the prevention of telephone and online fraud has been one of the main priorities of the police authorities in recent years, hoping that the public will continue to maintain a high degree of surveillance against fraudulent cases. The PJ will take a series of measures against the scam, according to Si Sio Keong, including the expansion of the structure of the Coordination Center to combat the anti -fiprude application.
Regarding the work of preventing and combating drug trafficking and consuming, the PJ spokesman stressed that five cases related to ethomyidate, commonly known as 'spatial oil', have been detected to date.
The government plans to accelerate the legislative review to implement more strict controls to that drug. I am Sio Keong has advanced that PJ is acquiring test equipment and relevant reagents, so that the application of the law is faster and accurate after the entry into force of the change of legislation.
On the other hand, the Unit Police services revealed, on the same occasion, that they will organize in the third quarter of this year an interdepartmental joint exercise for emergencies in casinos, being coordinating with inspection direction and coordination of games about the choice of site and the details of the simulacrum.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 05:15:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Asia should look for new business partners</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/asia-deve-procurar-novos-parceiros-comerciais/</link><description>The President of the Asian Development Bank (BAD), Masato Kanda, said yesterday that Asian countries should diversify business partners and boost internal demand to overcome the trade war triggered by Washington.
"There is no room for complacency, as the United States persists in its high tariff application strategy," he said in an interview with Bad's Bad President Bloomberg, based in Manila. "This is the time for Asia to boost internal demand, follow solid economic policies and diversify industries and business partners," he added.
Asia-Pacific countries-BAD's area of ​​influence-especially China and Southeast Asia nations, were the most affected by the so-called “reciprocal tariffs” by US President Donald Trump.
Cambodia is the second country most affected by rates, with 49%. Countries like Vietname and Thailand were reached at 46% and 36% rates, respectively.
These nations serve as Chinese product transhipment points abroad, especially for the United States, a way used by Chinese exporters to circumvent the imposed rates already during Trump's first term (2017-2021).
The US leader granted a 90-day truce in his world-scale trade war except China, who saw tariffs about his products increase to 145%. Beijing retaliated with additional customs of 125% on US products.
In mid-April, Bad warned that China's decision to respond to US tariffs would have a "dragging effect" throughout Asia, given the dependence on many countries of the second largest economy world economy, and appealed to the region to deepen their economic ties. "What we can do is protect regional economies from external shocks and reinforce their ability to resist future crises," said Kanda.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 05:16:27</pubDate></item><item><title>China advances the return of astronauts due to weather conditions</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/china-adia-regresso-de-astronautas-devido-as-condicoes-climatericas/</link><description>China postponed the return to the land of three Chinese astronauts that remain six months ago at the space station due to climacteric conditions, local press advanced yesterday. Astronauts, Cai Xuzhe, Song Lingdong and Wang Haoze, should have terrified yesterday in Dongfeng, in the region of Mongolia Inner, northern China, after being half a year in space. The landing was postponed to “ensure the health and safety of astronauts” because the meteorological conditions were not the best, according to the official news agency Xinhua.
The three were sent to the Chinese space station Tiangong in October last year, and a new crew of astronauts recently arrived to replace them.
During their time on board, the three Chinese astronauts performed experiences and improvements in the space station.
Two of the astronauts, Cai and Song, took a nine -hour space walk, the longest ever, during their mission, said the agency responsible for China's crew space missions.
The Asian country built its own space station after being excluded from the International Space Station for concerns about the National Security of the United States.
The Chinese space program has grown rapidly in recent years. The Chinese space agency has already landed an explorer on Mars and a robot across the moon. Your goal is to put a person on the moon before 2030.
Last year, two US astronauts eventually got stuck in the space for nine months after a test flight with Boeing had problems and NASA determined that it was too risky for astronauts to return to Earth in the same capsule.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 05:16:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao presents its hybrid architecture at the Venice Architecture Biennial</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/macau-apresenta-a-sua-arquitectura-hibrida-na-bienal-de-arquitectura-de-veneza/</link><description>The exhibition “Mundos Paralelos”, organized by the Macao Art Museum, is present among the 11 events selected for the Parallel Program of the 19th Venice Architecture Biennial. Curated by architects Wang Shu and Lu Wenyu, the show explores Macao's unique identity through four “parallel worlds” that reveal the coexistence between historical heritage and modernity. With photographs by Iwan Baan and interdisciplinary installations, the dialogue exhibition with the central theme of the Biennial - “intelligent, natural, artificial, collective”. Patent in the Arsenale de Venice from May 10 to November 23rd.
 
The 19th International Architecture Exhibition - La Biennale di Venezia, which runs from May to November 2025 with Carlo Ratti's General Curator, presents a diverse program with 66 national representations and various parallel events spread across the city. These include “parallel worlds”, the latest exhibition organized by the Macao Museum of Art under the scope of the Cultural Institute, which throughout the biennial period will present studies on the urban fabric of Macao through improved photographic angles. This selection places Macau on the map of the main contemporary architectural reflections, along with projects that address from ecosocial architecture to projections on the future of cultural heritage.
The curatorship of the project is headed by a couple of renowned architects, both from the interior of China. Lu Wenyu, Xinjiang's architect who formed Amateur Architecture Studio in Hangzhou, and through the projects held with his team arrived at the Schelling award in 2010. His partner Wang Shu, also architect of Xinjiang, was laureated with the Pritzker Prize, being the first Chinese citizen to receive the prize in 2012 edition. The name of the office, where they work, was chosen to refer to the problems of “professional” architecture that has been demolishing many of China's urban cultural heritage, in favor of the country's rapid modernization.
The duo has a vast experience, both national and international, and works mostly on topics that reinterpret local traditions, proposing a poetic reading about Macao through four distinct but complementary thematic axes. Photographer Iwan Baan, winner of the Golden Award of the Venice Biennial herself, known for her humanist approach to architecture, captured scenes from everyday Macaense who dialogue with facilities created by students of the Academy of Arts of China and the University of São José de Macau.
This representation of Macao contrasts and complements other notable participation, such as Portuguese “Paradise. Today”, installed at Palazzo Fondaco, which explores the relationship between architecture and natural landscape. According to Portuguese curators Catarina Raposo and Nuno Cara, the project aims to “create awareness about the relationship between human action and nature”, showing the ecological diversity of Portugal. The project arises from a collaboration between architects Paula Melânea, Pedro Bandeira and Luca Martinucci. Interestingly, the palace with the Greater Canal has already welcomed Portuguese official representations between 2007 and 2012, now being the stage of the Portuguese presence after the participation of 2023, “future fertile”, which attracted more than 34,000 visitors.
Through an unprecedented partnership between three big names in architecture, the exhibition “Parallels” celebrates Macau's unique heritage through photography and several facilities scattered throughout the Arsenale space in Campo Della Tana, as well as positions the territory in the global debate on the future of cities, presenting the visible hybrid architecture of Macau, where contemporary spaces adapt to the compact urban mesh Peninsula and its occasional constructions of colonial influence.
The show will be patent from May 10 to November 23, with opening scheduled for May 9, at 13h00.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Hotel occupancy rate above 90% in the first quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/taxa-de-ocupacao-hoteleira-acima-dos-90-no-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>The occupancy rate of the hotel rooms was 90.1% in the first quarter of this year, representing a rise of 5.2 percentage points compared to the same period last year. According to the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), in the first three months of the year, Macao hotels received more than 3.5 million guests.
 
In the first quarter of this year, the occupancy rate of Macau Hotel Units was 90.1%, ie 5.2 more percentage points compared to the same period of 2024. The data were released yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). The body also says that in the first three months of this year, the average period of stay of guests was 1.7 nights, equal to last year.
Highlight for the occupancy rate of 5 -star hotels (93.2%), 4 -star hotels (84.5%) and 3 -star hotels (86.6%), which increased 6.1; 3.4 and 5.5 percentage points, respectively.
However, the number of guests fell annually. In the first quarter of this year, hotel establishments hosted 3,574,000 individuals, less 5.4% than in the first three months of last year. The DSEC details that the number of guests in the interior of China (2,721,000) fell 3.4%compared to the first trimester of 2024. However, the number of international guests (292,000) increased by 8.1%, highlighting that South Korea (92,000), Japan (26,000), Malaysia (22,000) and Indonia (17,000) 16.1%, 9.8%, 14.7%and 31.2%, respectively, while from Thailand (17,000), India (13,000) and the United States of America (13,000) descended 9.2%, 5%and 0.9%, respectively.
On the other hand, at the end of the first quarter of this year, there were 147 hotel establishments that provided public accommodation services, six more than last year, although the total offer of rooms dropped 5.8% in annual terms to about 44,000.
Between January and March, the number of visitors from visitors who arrived at excursions to Macau was 550,000 (plus 9.1%, in annual terms), of which 477,000 were from visitors from excursions from the interior of China (another 6.3%) and 60,000 were international visitors in excursions (plus 19.8%). It is noteworthy that the number of visitor entries in South Korea excursions (33,000) ascended 43.5%.
The DSEC also says that the number of Macao residents exits who acquired travel agencies for traveling abroad corresponded to 124,000 in the quarter under analysis, plus 8.7%, in annual terms. It is noteworthy that 31,000 exits of residents were on excursions (over 21%, in relation to the first quarter of 2024), of which 27,000 intended in the interior of China.
Observing only the figures related to March, the hotel occupancy rate was 88.8%, 5.1 points percentage than in March 2024. Last month, hotel establishments hosted 1,203,000 individuals, less than March 2024, and the average period of stay of guests remained at 1.6 nights.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 05:13:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Per month, Dsal treats 56 processes related to bosses that do not pay workers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/por-mes-dsal-trata-56-processos-relativos-a-patroes-que-nao-pagam-aos-trabalhadores/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) dealt with, in the first quarter since year, 170 cases of labor conflicts due to debt salaries, which makes an average of about 56 per month. The data given by DSAL to the end also show that since 2018, the body has already instituted 5,761 processes for bosses that have failed payment to its workers.
 
In the first three months of this year, the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) has already dealt with 170 cases of work conflicts due to debt salaries, ie about 56 per month.
The 170 cases instituted in the first quarter involve 242 workers. 154 cases were resolved, 16 of which needed to be referred to the judicial organs for trial.
The data were provided by DSAL to the end and also show that the monthly average has been falling in recent years. In 2024, 855 cases were dealt with, which made a monthly average of about 71. In 2023, the record of recent years was beaten, with a total of 1,050, ie a monthly average of 87.5.
Between 2018 and 2022, the number of cases of debt salary treated by DSAL annually ranged from 616 in 2020 and 795 in 2019. In total, from 2018 until now, DSSA has completed 5,761 such processes.
DSSA now details that in 2021, the follow -up of 785 cases of labor salary conflicts involving 1,495 workers were completed. After the investigation, 665 cases (85%) were resolved and 120 cases (15%) were referred to the judicial agencies. In 2022, 737 cases of labor -related labor conflicts were treated, involving 1,275 workers. After the investigation, 567 cases (77%) were resolved by DSAL, and 170 cases (23%) were eventually referred to the judicial bodies. In 2023, 1,050 cases of labor -related work conflicts were completed, involving 2,553 workers. After the investigation, 726 cases (69%) were resolved by DSAL, and 324 cases (31%) needed to be referred to judicial organs for trial. Last year, the follow -up of 855 cases of the genre was completed, involving 1,959 workers. After the investigation, 666 cases (78%) were resolved by DSAL, and 189 cases (22%) had to be referred to judicial organs for trial.
In the response, Dsal also says that, "as a competent service for the supervision of the work, it will accompany and proceed with the investigation, according to the law, of any complaint filed by workers." Then, if it is confirmed that the employer owes the salary to the worker, the payment of the debt is requested. If the amount is paid by the employer on the date indicated by DSAL, it is exempt from the payment of the fine applied to the offense. If this does not happen, the case is referred to the court.
It is recalled that, according to the Labor Relations Law, the basic remuneration must be paid within nine business days from the date of the obligation of the obligation. Bosses who violate this arrangement can be punished with fines between 20,000 and 50 thousand patacas by each worker in relation to which this offense is the DSSA.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 05:12:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao seeks “high -level” visitors at the largest tourism fair in the Middle East</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/macau-procura-visitantes-de-alto-nivel-na-maior-feira-de-turismo-do-medio-oriente/</link><description>The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) inaugurated an exhibitor alluding to Macau's tourist attractions at Arabian Travel Market 2025, currently taking place in Dubai until May 1st. This initiative is part of the current government's efforts to expand the offerings related to religious tourism, with a specific emphasis on the reception of Muslim travelers.
The layer of Muslim tourists from the Middle East, specifically, is made up of “with high purchasing power”, as the STD in a statement stresses. In order to attract this “high -level” tourist market, the stand “Feeling Macao” presents the region as a destination prepared to welcome Muslim tourism, bringing together suggestions for food options and travel itineraries in the “Macau for Muslim Travelers - Halal Travel Guide”, in distribution at the event. In addition to STD, are also present at Arabian Travel Market - the largest international tourism fair in the Middle East - six travel agencies and hotels in Macau, in order to conduct contact bags with partners of this geographical area.
According to the STD note, the next initiatives aimed at the Middle East audiences include familiarization visits to tour operators in June and for social communication agencies in September. At the same time, promotion actions will continue to be developed in Arabic through social networks and other platforms.
The director of tourism services, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, has been reiterated since last year that one of the government's main objectives involves promoting religious tourism, highlighting the Muslim market as “a new area to develop in the future”.
In late February, STD held promotion seminars in Riade, Saudi Arabia, and Dubai, in the United Arab Emirates, about the latest “Tourism + Conventions” and Macao exhibitions. In a statement issued at the time, the body stressed that the seminars allowed “more tourist operators and visitors from the Middle East to know the Macao Unique Charm”.
More recently, in April, this year's edition of the Macao International Expo in Macau (Mite) included the “Halal Culture Products Pavilion”. In addition to food and well-being products, the space also featured a simulated prayer room according to Islamic standards.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 05:16:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Four Hong Kong political activists released after their prison sentence</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/quatro-activistas-politicos-de-hong-kong-libertados-apos-cumprirem-pena-de-prisao/</link><description>Four pro-democracy activists were PMTE, released in Hong Kong, after meeting four-year and two months, for participating in unofficial primary elections for the opposition in 2020. Former parliamentarians Claudia Mo, Kwok Ka, Jeremy Tam and Gary Fan were released during the dawn of three different arrests.
The safety operation was significant, with nearby police patrols and access restrictions on several roads before the operation.
The release of the dissidents occurred after the court discounted the time since they were detained since the end of February 2021, waiting for trial.
After attending in court in March 2021, they were denied their request to leave on bail while awaiting trial for “conspiracy to subvert the power of the State”, according to the National Security Act.
According to a new law, passed a year ago, prisoners convicted of national security crimes have to meet more rigorous requirements to ensure early release, which makes their release unlikely.
This is the liberation of the first group of 45 Democrats convicted in the largest national security trial in the former British colony, completed in November.
In an initial decision issued on May 30, the Court of first instance considered the 14 culprits after a long case, which began after Beijing imposed the National Security Act in June 2020, ignoring the local parliament, following the largest anti -government protests in the city's history. Two other defendants were acquitted, while 31 admitted the accusations.
In total, 47 people were involved in the case, which began after the pro-democracy field had a non-official primary election in 2020, in which more than 600,000 voters chose candidates for legislative elections.
In March 2021, the block was jointly accused of “conspiracy to commit subversion” to connection with these unofficial primaries.
The defendants were accused of trying, if they had obtained the majority in the local parliament, veto projects of budgetary bills, paralyze the government and, finally, force the then chief executive, Carrie Lam, to dismiss.
Three Judges of the Superior Court, all chosen by the city's new leader John Lee, to judge national security cases, decided that the votes were part of a larger plan to “undermine, destroy or overthrow” the city's government and trigger a constitutional crisis.
According to the court, the conspiracy, if it had been successful, would have severely interfered, interrupted or impaired the functioning of the government due to the substantial damages that would have caused the "power and authority of the government and the chief executive."</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 05:16:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Candidates started choosing residence apartments for the elderly</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/candidatos-comecaram-a-escolher-apartamentos-da-residencia-para-idosos/</link><description>This round of apartment selection from residence for the elderly began on Monday and, according to the Institute of Social Action (IAS), the first day has already been completed the selection of apartments by 75 applications, of which 38 were presented by one person and 37 were presented by two people, involving a total of 112 candidates. In this round, more than 400 qualified candidacies were received, which covered a total of more than 550 candidates.
To “reduce the time of online or face -to -face residential apartments”, IAS advises candidates to access the electronic government application system for the elderly (www.olderpersonsapart.ias.gov.mo), prior to the beginning of the stipulated selection period, “in order to get out of the steps of online apartments, from the informative breadth of the apartments. residential, unlocked apartments and values ​​of use rates, etc. ”.
On the other hand, IAS also recommends that candidates "consult the dates and hours available in advance for signing the use agreement in that system, so that they can schedule the signing of the agreement within the stipulated deadline." If the candidates do not appoint, the respective dates and hours will be fixed by the IAS.
The qualified candidates must select the residential apartment online or in person within the notified selection period. If they are unable to complete their formalities within this period, they must communicate the matter to IAS, also within the established period, so that a new selection period is scheduled. Otherwise, the application will be filed. If the candidates intend to be placed on the waiting list, they must submit their request at IAS headquarters or in the social action centers within the stipulated period.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 05:16:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese mne says Ceder will make Washington "want to take more party"</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/mne-chines-diz-que-ceder-fara-com-que-washington-queira-tirar-mais-partido/</link><description>Chinese foreign minister Wang Yi warned in Rio de Janeiro that "being silent, giving in and backwards" will only make "Rufia want to take more party," referring to the United States.
 
Wang Yi said on Monday during a meeting among the heads of diplomacy from the member countries of the BRICS Emerging Block, which "the United States has benefited a lot with free trade for a long time, but are now using tariffs as a bargaining currency to demand exorbitant prices to other countries," according to the Chinese foreign affairs.
The diplomat stressed the “urgency to defend the rules of multilateral trade”, explaining that “the essence of trade is the mutual benefit” for both parties.
Wang argued that commerce "should not be a tool for individual gains" and lamented that the US "commits unilateralism, put their own interests first and put them above international public interests." "BRICS Countries should be jointly opposed to all forms of protectionism, firmly protecting the rules-based multilateral trade system, with the World Trade Organization at its core, defending its fundamental values ​​and basic principles and promoting the facilitation of commerce," added the Chinese minister.
Since the beginning of this month, China and the United States have been more than 100% tariffs on each other's products. Although US authorities said negotiations with their Chinese counterparts are underway to reach a trade agreement, Beijing repeatedly denied it, ensuring that “not afraid” of a trade war.
The BRICS Foreign Ministers debate in Rio de Janeiro the role of the Global South in promoting multilateralism, given the policies of US leader Donald Trump.
Discussions will serve to write a statement that will, in principle, will be filed on Monday and approved at the Brics's Heads Summit, a forum of ten emerging countries, which will also take place in Rio de Janeiro, on July 6 and 7.
 
Chinese diplomacy publishes video entitled “We don't kneel”
 
China's Ministry of Foreign Affairs published yesterday a video entitled “No Kneeling” (“We don't kneel ourselves”), which reaffirms the refusal to give in to the pressures resulting from the trade war with the United States.
In the video, published in the Ministry's official account on Wechat social network-similar to WhatsApp-Chinese diplomacy argues that giving in to what he describes as an American “hegemony” would not lead to resolution of tensions, but to its aggravation.
The ministry accused the US of triggering a global “tariff storm” and criticized the fact that Washington did not concession to China, such as the 90-day suspension of tariffs decreed by US President Donald Trump for other countries.
The authorities compared this dynamic to the "eye of a hurricane", warning that the apparent calm is actually a "deadly trap" that precedes new turbulence. "Historical registration shows that concessions do not guarantee a disagreement in commercial disputes and, instead, end up feeding the increase in pressure," said the country's diplomacy. "Giving in to the aggressor is like drinking poison when thirsty," he described.
With a musical background of increasing intensity, the video states that "China does not kneel" and argues that "fighting for cooperation allows cooperation to exist while looking for it through concessions leads to its disappearance." The video also adds that an assertive attitude would allow the smaller countries to be heard, would have potential abuses of power and defend international principles.
The video also describes opponents to this position as “paper tigers” and points out that US trade represents less than one fifth of world trade, so Washington could be isolated if other countries adhere to China's position.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 05:16:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Timorese Anti -Corruption Commission calls for application of the Witness Protection Law</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/comissao-anticorrupcao-timorense-pede-aplicacao-da-lei-de-proteccao-de-testemunhas/</link><description>The Anti-Corruption Commission (CAC) of Timor-Leste yesterday recommended the application of the Witness Protection Act in criminal proceedings to reduce the difficulties of criminal investigation work.
 
"With regard to the Witness Protection Act, it is not yet effective. Over the past few times, CAC has presented recommendations to the competent authorities to implement this law. Criminal investigation activity has faced major challenges," CAC commissioner Rui dos Santos said.
According to the commissioner, there is always concern about the protection of witnesses, especially in cases of corruption, where people are scared and without the courage to collaborate.
The official spoke in Parliament during the presentation of the 2024 report of the institution, created in 2009 by the Timorese Parliament to combat and prevent corruption.
Another difficulty for investigators, pointed out by CAC Commissioner, is the lack of files in state institutions. "One of the great difficulties we face, especially in criminal investigation, is the collection of documents in state institutions. We recognize that file management is not yet adequate. Governance changes often result in the elimination of files in digital format, with many files to be erased from computers. This is a CAC concern," he said.
Rui dos Santos stated that when investigating cases involving political figures CAC has greater difficulty finding documents. "Some documents are even destroyed. This makes it extremely difficult for us, as an institution, to be able to present documentary and witness evidence necessary to support the accusations," he said.
The CAC Commissioner also regretted the lack of financial resources that compromise the fulfillment of that institution's mission in preventing and combating corruption and that an asset recovery regime is established to detect deposited or transferred assets. "We ask the National Parliament to take advantage of a reasonable budget for CAC, in order to reinforce the efforts and actions to prevent corruption more appropriately and effectively," suggested Rui dos Santos.
The official needed that in 2024, CAC conducted 28 cases of investigation based on public complaints or initiated directly by the institution. Of those cases, eight were sent to the prosecutor.
The Public Prosecution Service, on the other hand, sent to CAC 17 cases, of which six have already been completed, and 11 continue to be investigated.
Regarding the State's leaders' heritage declaration, the report states that fines were applied to 439 offenders. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 05:11:11</pubDate></item><item><title>XI utters Banco dos Brics to assume greater role in the face of weak international order</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/xi-insta-banco-dos-brics-a-assumir-maior-papel-face-a-ordem-internacional-debil/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping yesterday urged the BRICS Bank to reinforce its support for developing countries and to assume a more important role in a global scenario marked by geopolitical tensions and trade war.
 
Xi visited the headquarters of the Novo Development Bank (NDB) during a trip to the eastern metropolis of Shanghai, where he also met with the leader of the institution and former Brazilian president, Dilma Rousseff, said Chinese state press.
The New Development Bank - founded by Brazil, Russia, India, China and South Africa - should, according to Xi, direct their efforts to a new phase of growth centered on sustainability, technology and energy transition without moving away from their original mission of supporting the global southern countries.
The institution “should align with real development needs and offer high quality and low cost financing,” said Xi, who also advocated the improvement of the bank's internal management and the expansion of his presence in areas, such as digital infrastructure and green projects.
The Chinese leader considered that the Bloc of Emerging Economies represents a growing part of the world economy and stressed that developing countries should have greater participation in the reform of the international financial system. However, it avoided referring directly to specific geopolitical tensions or to institutions such as the IMF or the World Bank.
Dilma Rousseff has assured that the World Bank will continue to focus on supporting strategic projects in emerging economies and warned against “unilateralism and protectionism”, which has accused “eroding the authority of international law” and “undermining the stability of industrial and supply chains”.
In his speech, Dilma also highlighted Beijing's role in a “turbulent” global context, in which “China firmly defends the interests of the global south” and is “an example” in the defense of “multilateralism, equity and international justice”.
The former Brazilian president, reelected in March for a five -year term at the head of the organization, thanked the support of member countries and defended the role of the bank as an instrument of multilateral cooperation. His candidacy was proposed by Russia and approved by consensus.
The Novo Development Bank, also known as Banco dos Brics, was created in 2014 and began operating a year later, with the aim of offering a funding alternative to developing countries.
In recent months, he has extended the number of members with the incorporation of Egypt, Iran, United Arab Emirates, Ethiopia and Indonesia, which formalized his entry in March, after a visit by Rousseff to Jakarta.
Bank expansion occurs at a time when the BRICS Group plays a more prominent role in multilateral forums, in the midst of debates on the reconfiguration of the world economic order. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 05:16:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Fraudulent calls that simulate Alipay and Wechat caused 46 victims in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/30/chamadas-fraudulentas-que-simulam-alipay-e-wechat-provocaram-46-vitimas-em-macau/</link><description>At least 46 residents will have been victims of telephone burla after receiving calls from individuals who were going through customer service employees from Alipay or Wechat. The complaints will have been a total loss of more than 2.61 million patacas, with amounts from each case ranging from 1,000 to 500,000 patacas. The Judicial Police (PJ) learned that the fraudulent scheme emerged in the territory earlier this month. According to the newspaper or Mun, among the victims, 16 are young, 25 are residents of middle age and five elderly. During the police police investigation, more than 330 residents denounced the situation and provided fraudulent cops related to the police.
The police authorities yesterday carried out a police operation and dismantled the headquarters of the network in question, located near the doors of the siege, having detained a non-resident worker couple. Eight Goip equipment were seized on site, which helped disguise the continent's calls as macao numbers to make fraud. Police are still looking for more escape elements. According to the PJ, the recipients of this scheme received calls with supposed origin in the companies Alipay or Wechat, where the Burlão claims, in Mandarin, that the back safety insurance or the victim's balance had won and that would be charged a large amount of money. By proposing help to cancel the insurance plan, the call is transferred to the alleged customer support service from other financial institutions, which requires personal data from the recipients of the scheme to verify the identity and to deal with administrative procedures “intended to defraud their money,” said the police statement. Authorities also indicate that the scam is made in many ways, including: Asking the victim to make a video -tamper through WhatsApp and activate the “Share screen” function and then fool the victim to start his bank account in order to steal his personal data; Ask the victim to make several shipments to verify the state of the account.
According to police, the burns also ask for information about the victim's credit card, or starting session on a phishing site from a false financial institution, as well as buying virtual currency to transfer money to a virtual currency wallet they designated. In response to the situation, PJ has already confirmed with Alipay and Wechat that relevant insurance services are provided automatic and free of charge to users and that there is no need to request renewal or pay any additional fees for this purpose.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 05:11:07</pubDate></item></channel></rss>