<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/05/vietname-pronto-para-ultrapassar-pib-da-tailandia-em-2026/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Ruben Amorim fired by Manchester United</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/05/ruben-amorim-despedido-pelo-manchester-united/</link><description>Portuguese coach Ruben Amorim was fired by Manchester United, one day after the draw at home to Leeds (1-1), the English Football League club announced yesterday. "Ruben Amorim has stepped down from his role as head coach of Manchester United. […] With Manchester United in sixth place in the English League, the club's leadership reluctantly made the decision that the time was right to make a change. This will give the team the best opportunity to finish as high as possible in the English League", reads a statement.
The Manchester club thanked Ruben Amorim for his work over 14 months and revealed that it will be Darren Fletcher, from the under-18 team, who will lead the team against Burnley, on Wednesday, in an English League game.
Amorim, 40 years old, arrived at the Red Devils at the beginning of November 2024 and had signed until the end of the 2026/27 season, after just over four seasons with Sporting, in which he won three championships – in the last season, Rui Borges ended up in charge after the departure of the former midfielder. Previously, Amorim had coached Casa Pia and Sporting de Braga, with whom he won the first of his three League Cups.
At Manchester United, the Portuguese coach had just 24 wins in 63 matches, leaving the club in sixth place in the English League, with the same points as Chelsea and three behind Liverpool, in the last position to access the Champions League, in addition to having reached the final of the Europa League last season.</description><pubDate>2026-01-05 23:23:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Alice Costa presents first solo exhibition of abstract painting at Creative Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/05/alice-costa-apresenta-primeira-exposicao-individual-de-pintura-abstracta-na-creative-macau/</link><description>From Law to Art. Macau's Alice Costa will open her first solo exhibition, entitled “FLOW”, on January 8th at the Creative Macau gallery, on the ground floor of the Macau Cultural Center. The exhibition, which will run until January 31st, presents a series of abstract paintings inspired by nature and its organic forms, and all net proceeds from the sale of works will be donated to ORBIS Macau.

The professional journey of Macanese Alice Costa (also known as Lili) went through a remarkable transformation, from the magistracy to the fine arts. The artist, who graduated in Law from the University of Macau in 1994 and was a judge at the Court of First Instance between 1997 and 2023, will now present her first solo exhibition, “FLOW”, in a new stage dedicated entirely to abstract painting. The exhibition opens on January 8th, at 6:30 pm, at the Creative Macau gallery, located on the ground floor of the Macau Cultural Center, and will be open to the public until January 31st.
The “FLOW” series explores the essence of nature through shapes, textures and emotions, without representing visual reality in a literal way. As the artist herself explains, “abstract art does not attempt to represent visual reality, but uses shapes, colors and gestural marks to achieve its effect”. His paintings are characterized by organic shapes, fluid lines and dynamic transitions, in an intense and impactful chromatic palette, which evoke shapes that bring to mind forests, tides, mountain ranges, storms or even the surfaces of planets, inviting the observer to “feel” rather than “recognize”.
The technique used by Costa is deeply tactile, employing methods such as impasto (thick application of paint), splashes, the famous Jackson Pollock technique, as well as overlapping layers to build textured surfaces that stimulate both vision and touch. This material approach gives a physical and spontaneous energy to the works, reflecting what the artist describes as “organic movement, fluidity, perfect transitions and dynamic energy”.
Costa's return to painting, an old passion that initially served to relax from his work in the judiciary, took place three years ago, through classes and workshops in Hong Kong. Her multicultural journey, being the daughter of a Portuguese father and a Chinese mother, and the experiences of her travels are fundamental sources of inspiration.
The exhibition also has a charitable purpose. The artist decided to donate all net income from sales of works to the non-governmental organization ORBIS Macau. ORBIS is an international nonprofit dedicated to building strong, sustainable eye care systems globally, with the goal of making treatment and prevention accessible to everyone. The organization operates across the entire chain of care, from eye health education to treatment and follow-up services.
“FLOW” thus marks an interesting debut, not only in the Macau artistic circuit, but also in the new life of Alice Costa, who has changed from the toga to the palette, now offering the public a unique sensorial experience and a gesture of generosity towards the community.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Japanese singer cancels event in Macau at a time of tension between China and Japan</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/05/cantora-niponica-cancela-evento-em-macau-num-momento-de-tensao-entre-china-e-japao/</link><description>Japanese singer Mika Nakashima announced the cancellation, “due to unavoidable circumstances”, of a concert scheduled for March 14 in Macau, at a time of tensions between Beijing and Tokyo.
In a statement published on Nakashima's official website, the artist highlighted that she is “in negotiations to reschedule the concert”, which was scheduled for the Londoner Macau hotel-casino, and thanks her fans for their understanding.
The concert in Macau would be the first of an Asian tour by the 42-year-old singer and actress, which continues to include visits to Bangkok (Thailand), Taipei (Taiwan), Kuala Lumpur (Malaysia), Seoul (South Korea) and Osaka and Tokyo (Japan).
On December 12, the Macau Government denied any interference in the cancellation of at least three concerts with Japanese artists scheduled for the region and assured that these were solely commercial decisions by the organizers. "I think that different parties have their own considerations", said the president of the Macau Cultural Heritage Council, Leong Wai Man, at a press conference. "It is normal to have adjustments regarding concerts or different events. Situations of cancellation due to force majeure are common", added the leader of the Macau Cultural Institute.
On December 9, the Venetian Macau hotel-casino announced the cancellation of a concert by Japanese pop singer Ayumi Hamasaki, on January 10. This is after the Hamasaki show in Shanghai, on November 29, was cancelled. A day earlier, a Christmas show, scheduled for December 25th, at another hotel-casino, Studio City, which included the female band Say My Name, which includes the Japanese Hitomi Honda, had also been cancelled. On the same day, a third show was cancelled, this time by the band Hi-Fi Un!corn, a group that includes Japanese artists, scheduled for December 21st at a third hotel-casino, Galaxy Macau.
On November 15, Macau followed Beijing's example and advised against traveling to Japan, “given that since the middle of this year, the trend of attacks in Japan against Chinese citizens has been increasing”. Days earlier, the Japanese prime minister spoke about a possible Japanese military intervention in a conflict between mainland China and Taiwan. Sanae Takaichi stated in parliament that if an emergency situation in Taiwan involved “the deployment of warships and the use of force, this could constitute a threat to Japan’s survival.”</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Grandes de Lisboa and Minho discuss title without winter “champion”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/05/grandes-de-lisboa-e-do-minho-discutem-titulo-sem-campeao-de-inverno/</link><description>Sporting and Benfica face Vitória de Guimarães and Sporting de Braga in the semi-finals of the Football League Cup, in the dispute for the most recent national trophy, without FC Porto, leader of the championship and true winter champion.

A 19.ª edição da prova volta a reunir pela terceira vez seguida o ‘exclusivo’ grupo de Sporting, Benfica e Sporting de Braga, em Leiria, onde, pela sexta vez seguida, é decidida a competição, hoje e amanhã, com as meias-finais, e no sábado, com a final.
Benfica, with eight titles in nine finals, continues to defend the trophy against Sporting de Braga, on Wednesday, at the Estádio Dr. Magalhães Pessoa, in a duel between teams that need stimulation for the second round of the I League.
The Reds are looking for 'spirit' to face the decisive phase of the championship with ten points behind the undefeated leader FC Porto, heading into the final 17 games in third place, still three points behind two-time champion Sporting, second placed.
Sporting de Braga is also below initial expectations, in an unusual fifth place, with 27 points, behind neighbors Gil Vicente, aiming for a fourth League Cup trophy, a competition in which they have 11 semi-finals and five finals.
Tomorrow's meeting repeats the last duel between Benfica fans and Braga fans in 2025, with a 2-2 draw at 'Pedreira', where José Mourinho left with the certainty of having achieved a victory.
Benfica's renowned coach will certainly not hesitate to add a different trophy to his trophy cabinet – in his debut in the League Cup.
Sporting, eight times finalists and four times winners, seeks to regain a scepter that has escaped them in the last three editions – with two appearances in the finals in those years –, facing the 'intruder' Vitória de Guimarães, the exception in the correspondence between the semi-finalists and the top four placed in the last eight editions of the championship.
After 'slipping' in Barcelos in a match in which the 'lions' heavily criticized the refereeing, and without the suspended Gonçalo Inácio, today they meet one of the last rivals from last year, who beat Minho 4-1, in the Guimarães' third appearance in the semi-finals of the League Cup, after 2008/09 and 2019/20, still looking for their first appearance in a final.
Vitória de Guimarães, whose last national trophy dates back to 2012/13, with the victory of the Taça de Portugal, is also having an irregular season, with a modest seventh place, rivaling the also Minho teams Famalicão and Moreirense.
The 'big ones' have always benefited from the League Cup formats, which, since last season, had the participants reduced to the top six in the I League and the top two in the II League. Vitória de Setúbal, in the inaugural edition, in 2007/08, and Moreirense, in 2016/17, continue to be the exceptions in history to the usual winners of national trophies. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-05 23:24:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Fewer restrictions suggested for carrying out works at night</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/05/sugeridas-menos-restricoes-para-a-execucao-de-obras-durante-a-noite/</link><description>Deputy Leong Hong Sai says that the environmental noise prevention and control law is limiting the execution of works at night. Therefore, it suggests that the Government relax the restrictions imposed by law so that less noisy works can be carried out even at night.

The environmental noise prevention and control law, which limits the noise produced by civil construction work between 8pm and 8am, must be amended so that “lower noise works” can be carried out at night. This is what deputy Leong Hong Sai defends in a written statement sent to the Government.
The deputy linked to Residents even says that “people in the construction sector want to change the law on the prevention and control of environmental noise, mainly because the current law limits the execution of works during the night, which affects the progress of works, particularly works that need to be carried out continuously, such as paving public roads, laying piles and concreting”.
Remember that the law stipulates that civil construction work involving the use of mechanical equipment is not permitted less than 200 meters away from residential buildings or hospitals, on Sundays and public holidays, as well as in the period between 8pm and 8am the following day on other weekdays. Modification, conservation and repair works in residential buildings are prohibited from 7pm to 9am.
“In order to reduce the work execution time, costs and impact on residents and stores, the Government should consider relaxing restrictions on carrying out works at night and carry out a scientific measurement of noise pollution, allowing lower noise works to continue after eight o'clock at night”, asks the parliamentarian.
Leong admits that the “rigid limitations imposed by current legislation on the execution of works at night” “effectively” safeguard the “tranquility of the night”, however, “put the construction sector in a difficult situation”. “Paving, pile driving, concreting and other special techniques that need to be carried out continuously cannot be completed within the time limits, therefore, the procedures are always interrupted, which not only extends the execution time of the works and increases costs, but also affects the stability of the quality of the works”, laments the deputy.
In the written interpellation, the deputy suggests that the Executive implement incentive measures to “control noise from the source”, making the construction sector “willing to invest more resources in the use of ecological noise reduction equipment”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-05 23:33:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Primeiro-ministro irlandês defende “livre comércio” em encontro com Xi Jinping em Pequim</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/05/primeiro-ministro-irlandes-defende-livre-comercio-em-encontro-com-xi-jinping-em-pequim/</link><description>Irish Prime Minister Micheál Martin yesterday defended “free trade” during a meeting with Chinese President Xi Jinping, at a time of growing trade tensions between Beijing and the European Union. “We believe in free trade, in good relations, and, with regard to trade in particular, we believe that it is essential that we work together to promote it,” said Martin, in a meeting with Xi at the Great Hall of the People, in Beijing.
The five-day visit to China is the first by an Irish head of government since 2012 and aims to strengthen bilateral ties, at a time when Dublin is preparing to assume, in July, the rotating presidency of the Council of the European Union.
Xi Jinping welcomed the evolution of Sino-Irish relations and highlighted that the volume of bilateral trade has “quadrupled” since 2012, when the two countries established a mutually beneficial strategic partnership. “China wishes to strengthen strategic communication with Ireland, deepen mutual political trust and expand concrete cooperation, for the benefit of both peoples and to boost Sino-European relations,” declared the Chinese head of state. Martin is also expected to meet with Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang before traveling to Shanghai, China's financial center.
According to data from the Irish Government, China is Ireland's main trading partner in Asia and the fifth largest globally. A Irlanda exporta sobretudo equipamentos médicos, produtos farmacêuticos, bens agroalimentares e serviços informáticos e financeiros para o mercado chinês.
The meeting takes place in a context of growing alarm on the part of the EU regarding the trade imbalance with China, with Brussels accusing Beijing of hindering access to its internal market.</description><pubDate>2026-01-05 23:27:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Leong Sun Iok calls for extension of water and electricity subsidies to Macau residents in Hengqin</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/05/leong-sun-iok-pede-extensao-de-subsidios-de-agua-e-luz-a-residentes-de-macau-em-hengqin/</link><description>With the increase in the number of Macau residents working or living in Hengqin, pressure is increasing on the transport network, border posts and local health services. In a written question sent to the Government, deputy Leong Sun Iok warns about the limited timetables and insufficient bus routes, the deficient health services and the lack of social support in the New Neighborhood of Macau.

Deputy Leong Sun Iok sent a written question to the Government about the need to reinforce the transport offer between Hengqin and Macau, as well as the efficiency of managing the flow of passengers at the border post between the two regions.
According to data presented by the deputy, in September last year there were 29,714 Macau residents employed or residing in the Deep Cooperation Zone, which represents an increase of 18.4% in annual terms. As a consequence, the Hengqin border post has also been receiving more and more passengers, totaling around 5.43 million arrivals and departures of Macau residents in the first nine months of 2025 alone – a marked increase of 52.4% compared to the same period of the previous year.
Approximately two years after the first apartments in the New Macau Neighborhood in Hengqin were made available for sale, Leong Sun Iok confesses to being “concerned” about the pressure on local infrastructure and services and the consequent impact on the quality of life of Macau residents who live in this residential area.
The first point of the question relates to the public transport system, limited by insufficient routes and paradoxical schedules. Although the border post operates 24 hours a day, the bus network only operates between 6:30 am and 11:15 pm and does not cover the travel needs of night shift workers.
To overcome this period of inactivity, the deputy proposes the introduction of “additional night bus routes between the urban areas of Macau and the Hengqin station”, while “extending or adjusting” the light metro schedules to allow better coordination between different means of transport.
In addition to difficult accessibility during night hours, border control crossings to Hengqin are also characterized by long queues during rush hours. The deputy's suggestion for this problem involves the creation of express buses that cross directly between Hengqin and the “main areas” of the Peninsula, Taipa and Coloane, coinciding with peak worker movements.
Looking at the arrivals and departures of Macau residents between January and September 2025, which more than doubled compared to the previous year, it is equally relevant to consider the overload of existing channels. Leong Sun Iok reveals that several Macau residents have lamented “congestion and long waiting times” both at the border post and in the lanes for single-registration vehicles – including the allegedly “abusive” use of the inspection area for vehicle passengers.
The solution proposed by the deputy involves the creation of exclusive channels for Macau residents, as well as increasing the number of manual channels in operation during rush hours. “At the same time, monitoring and management of the flow in the inspection hall for vehicle passengers must be reinforced, in order to ensure that border crossing resources can serve residents with real needs to the maximum”, he highlights.

REINFORCEMENT IN HEALTH AND GOVERNMENT SUPPORT

Mobility is not the only topic highlighted in Leong Sun Iok's interpellation. The Macau New Neighborhood Health Post is equipped with pharmacies and consultation rooms that allow it to meet some of the residents' needs, although its offer is still limited and unable to compete with hospitals in Macau or inland China.
As the deputy denounces, basic services such as vaccination, blood collection, specialty services or consultations outside office hours are unavailable, with emphasis on a bureaucratic problem: medical certificates issued by medical institutions in Hengqin are not recognized in Macau, forcing residents to resort to the Centro Hospitalar Conde de São Januário (CHCSJ) or the Hospital das Ilhas.
Cross-border ambulance service is another critical aspect. Although this medical emergency option came into operation in August 2025, the deputy argues that both hospitals and residents “are not very familiar” with the process and require a more comprehensive and detailed information campaign, in order to ensure that the service operates flawlessly.
Finally, the last point of the interpellation addresses equal rights and government support for residents of the New Neighborhood. Since this project was conceived as an extension of the territory of Macau, Leong Sun Iok proposes that current policies to support citizens – such as the granting of water and electricity subsidies – be extended to residents of the aforementioned Hengqin neighborhood, arguing that this is a fundamental condition to strengthen the attractiveness and development of the Integrated Cooperation Zone.</description><pubDate>2026-01-05 23:34:38</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 766 thousand visitors to Macau during the New Year holidays</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/05/mais-de-766-mil-visitantes-em-macau-nos-feriados-de-ano-novo/</link><description>Macau welcomed 766,240 visitors during the New Year holiday season, corresponding to the period between December 31st and January 4th. In total, 3,807,706 border movements were recorded during these five days, 1,551,610 of which related to entry and exit of visitors.
Among the 1,906,023 entries registered at the nine border posts accessing Macau, 686,720 (36%) were residents. Visitors from mainland China made up 53.88% (1,026,946) of total arrivals, followed by visitors from Hong Kong (112,058, or 5.88%), Taiwan (15,316, or 0.80%) and other points of origin (64,983, or 3.4%). The influx of visitors from Hong Kong could be justified by the absence of fireworks shows in the neighboring region, a decision justified by the tragedy that occurred in Tai Po.
Portas do Cerco received 353,788 visitors during the holidays and New Year weekends. The Hengqin border post came in second on the list, with 139,285 entries and an even higher number of exits: 151,394. Remember that, as reported by PONTO FINAL, many visitors from the interior of China chose to leave Macau on New Year's Day through the Hengqin passage channels, in order to avoid the crowds at Portas do Cerco. Also noteworthy is the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau sea bridge, which received 126,236 passengers, and the 45,625 tourists who landed at Macau International Airport.
The peak of visitors occurred on January 2nd, last Friday, when 188,561 people arrived in Macau. On the other hand, on January 4th, Sunday, the border posts received only 99,631 visitors.</description><pubDate>2026-01-05 23:30:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Residents’ deposits decreased by 0.7% in November</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/05/depositos-dos-residentes-decresceram-07-em-novembro/</link><description>The Macau Monetary Authority revealed that the money supply decreased in November, as did resident deposits and loans. In terms of currency composition, the Hong Kong dollar maintained a dominant position with 43.9% of the total.
 
Statistics released yesterday by the Macau Monetary Authority (AMCM) reveal that the money supply decreased in November, as did resident deposits and loans. From October to November last year, monetary circulation grew by 0.4%, while current deposits decreased by 2.3%. M1 fell by 1.5% and quasi-monetary liabilities fell by 0.6%. The sum of these two elements, M2 (or broad money supply), fell by 0.6% in this period, reaching 831.7 billion patacas.
In terms of currency composition, the Hong Kong dollar maintained a dominant position with 43.9% of the total, followed by the pataca, with 32.2%, the US dollar, with 15.3%, and the renminbi, with 6.3%.
Regarding deposits from banking activity, it is observed that deposits from residents decreased by 0.7% compared to the previous month, totaling 349.4 billion patacas, while deposits from non-residents grew by 2.6% and reached 349.4 billion patacas.
On the other hand, public sector deposits in banking activity decreased to 232.9 billion patacas, a decrease of 0.1%. All in all, total banking deposits grew by 0.2%, reaching 1,392.4 billion patacas. The proportion of Hong Kong dollar, US dollar, pataca and renminbi was 44.7%, 26.4%, 19.2% and 7.8%, respectively.
AMCM analysis reveals that domestic loans to the private sector decreased by 0.5% in monthly terms, reaching 495.5 billion patacas. Loans abroad fell even further by 3.2%, to 505.9 billion. As a result, the total value of loans from banking activity fell by 1.9% and totaled 1,1001.4 billion. The “weights” achieved by the Hong Kong dollar, the pataca, the US dollar and the renminbi were, respectively, 43.7%, 22.3%, 18.7% and 11.3%.
The entity adds that, at the end of November, the resident loans/deposits ratio remained fixed at 47.5%. Even so, the volume that included the non-resident loans/deposits ratio decreased from the level of 73.5% to the level of 71.9%. Current assets to be calculated based on periods of one month and three months against liabilities stood at 67.4% and 58.8%, respectively. Furthermore, the non-performing credit ratio grew from the level of 5.4% recorded at the end of October to the level of 5.5%, mainly due to the decrease in total loans compared to the previous month.</description><pubDate>2026-01-05 23:31:14</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 150 people evacuated from housing estate in Hong Kong after new fire</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/05/mais-de-150-pessoas-retiradas-de-bairro-social-em-hong-kong-apos-novo-incendio/</link><description>More than 150 residents had to be evacuated yesterday from a public housing complex in Hong Kong, due to the second fire to hit a social neighborhood in two days.

According to the South China Morning Post (SCMP), the alert was given at around 2:20 am, about thick smoke coming from an apartment on the 33rd floor in the Tai Yuan building, in the Tsuen Wan area, in the New Territories.
Firefighters broke down the apartment door and saved the 63-year-old resident, surnamed Chan, who had taken refuge in the bathroom. The elderly woman was taken to Princess Margaret Hospital.
A police source, cited by the SCMP, said that the elderly woman lit a candle before falling asleep and that the flame spread to other objects in the house.
The fire was extinguished while more than 150 residents were advised by firefighters to wait on the ground floor of the social neighborhood until the situation was under control. This is the second fire to hit public housing in Hong Kong in two days.
On Sunday, at least one person died and eight were injured in a fire that broke out in the Mei Yue building, in the Shek Kip Mei neighborhood, in Kowloon, in the center of the region.
According to the local press, firefighters believe that an electrical short circuit may have caused the flames, which forced the evacuation of more than 270 residents of the social neighborhood.
Fire Services department acting deputy chief Yip Kam-kong said flame-fighting equipment was working properly in the building, denying reports of a faulty fire hose on the 21st floor. Yip added that firefighters did not find any irregularities with fire safety equipment.
On November 26, a fire in the Wang Fuk Court housing estate in Tai Po, northern Hong Kong, killed 161 people and left thousands homeless.

The fire in Wang Fuk Court started when the net covering the bamboo structures in one of the buildings, as part of renovation work, caught fire. The fire spread quickly to the rest of the complex, reaching six other towers.
Taking into account the magnitude of the tragedy, the local government created an independent commission of inquiry, chaired by a magistrate, with the aim of clarifying the causes of the start and rapid spread of the fire.
At the same time, the Hong Kong Independent Anti-Corruption Commission detained the current president of the Wang Fuk Court residents' association, as well as his predecessor, as part of the investigation into the catastrophe.
The Public Prosecutor's Office is investigating more than a dozen people linked to the fire, under the presumption of having committed negligent homicide, including the directors and an engineering consultant of the construction company responsible for the works. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-05 23:27:40</pubDate></item><item><title>World order is “more unpredictable” and similar to “19th century imperialism”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/05/ordem-mundial-esta-mais-imprevisivel-e-semelhante-ao-imperialismo-do-seculo-xix/</link><description>The intervention of the United States in Venezuela leaves the world “more unpredictable”, “chaotic” and similar to “19th century imperialism”, consider analysts from Macau and Hong Kong interviewed by PONTO FINAL. Among the opinions, there are those who argue that this operation by the Trump Administration gives China the strength to advance towards Taiwan.
After the military action of the United States of America on Venezuelan soil and the arrest of Nicolás Maduro, the world order is even more unstable, agree analysts on this side of the globe interviewed by PONTO FINAL.
Jianwei Wang, professor emeritus of the Department of Government and Public Administration at the University of Macau and an expert on relations between the United States and China, began by describing the US intervention in Venezuela as “a major violation of the international order and the basic principles of international relations”. “We must have the minimum respect for the sovereignty of nations”, he pointed out.
In the university professor's opinion, “the world order is returning to the colonialism and imperialism of the 19th century, in which one could invade and attack other sovereign states under any pretext just because one had more power”. “If the international community does nothing, it will probably happen again with Greenland and Cuba,” he warned.
“The world order is increasingly unpredictable, chaotic and marked by the interests of each State”, argues Sonny Lo. The author and professor of Political Science in Hong Kong recalled the US military operation in Panama in 1989, which culminated in the arrest of that country's leader, Manuel Noriega, for drug trafficking – an accusation identical to that now made against Maduro and his wife. This “shows the US stance, which treats Latin America and Central America as its backyard”, considered Sonny Lo.
Michael Share sees this intervention by the Trump Administration as “an unprovoked act of aggression”. The Hong Kong-based American university professor says Maduro's detention constitutes yet another blow to the rules-based international order established after World War II." "The world is entering a new era of unilateral actions, in which an authoritarian leader can do whatever he wants without fear of consequences," said Share.
CHINA ATTENTIVE
Michael Share believes that the world is entering a phase in which there are three powers exerting influence in their areas of the globe: China in Asia, the USA in the Western Hemisphere and Russia in Europe. “Donald Trump’s action against Venezuela allows Putin to say: ‘Others do the same, why are they punishing me with sanctions and isolation?’”. Furthermore, “it allows Xi Jinping to put pressure on, and perhaps even take control of, Taiwan, without fear of reprisals”.
Beijing, which had a close relationship with Caracas, “will have to reevaluate its relationship with Venezuela carefully because Venezuela will get closer to the US economically and politically”, said Sonny Lo, adding that China will be “studying the situation carefully”.
Jiangwei Wang commented that “many people in China support” the idea of ​​Beijing moving towards Taiwan. "If the US can attack a sovereign country without any reason, why can't China reunify a part of its own country? There is no reason for the international community to say anything." Furthermore, this action also gives Russia more reasons to continue the war in Ukraine.</description><pubDate>2026-01-05 23:35:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Oath ceremony formalizes new direction of the DSF</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/05/cerimonia-de-juramento-oficializa-nova-direccao-da-dsf/</link><description>Ho In Mui and Kuok Iat Hoi assumed their respective roles as director and deputy director of the Directorate of Financial Services (DSF) yesterday. The oath-taking and inauguration ceremony was presided over by the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, and witnessed by the head of the Office of the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Lo Chi Fai.
Speaking on the occasion, Tai Kin Ip stressed that work in the area of ​​public finances is inseparable from the economic development and social stability of the Macao SAR. The mission that the two responsible undertake is “large-scale”, meaning they must strive to “accurately examine social dynamics” and cultivate “a pragmatic spirit and a professional style in overcoming adversities”, with the ultimate objective of leading the team towards “modernizing public financial management and improving Macau’s fiscal governance”.
Director Ho In Mui, in her speech, expressed “heartfelt gratitude for the trust” placed in her by the Government and committed herself to “guide her actions by the spirit of prudence, pragmatism and innovation”, to “foster stability and order in the sphere of public finances and in the fiscal sphere” and to contribute “to the adequate diversification of Macau’s economy”.
According to a biographical note published by the DSF, Ho In Mui has been working in this organization since 1995, having held successive positions as head of the Public Expenditure Division, the Public Accounting Department, the Financial Studies and Planning Department and, finally, the position of deputy director.
In turn, Kuok Iat Hoi joined the organization in 2002 and served as head of the Tax Inspection and Supervision Division, head of the Audit, Inspection and Tax Justice Department. Between August 2021 and June 2025, he assumed duties as deputy director of the Financial Services Bureau in the Deep Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin, before returning to the DSF to serve as deputy director.</description><pubDate>2026-01-05 23:30:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy hosts Macau's first international yoga competition</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/05/galaxy-recebe-primeira-competicao-internacional-de-yoga-de-macau/</link><description>Yoga in competition. Macau will host its first professional yoga competition, the “1st International Yogasana Championship”, organized by the Macau Professional Yoga Association. The event is scheduled for the 14th and 15th of January, at the Galaxy Macau Oasis, and promises to bring together local and international practitioners on a stage that will test the technique, stability and artistic expression of yoga postures.
The city will welcome a new chapter in its offer of events with the holding of the first professional yoga competition in its history. The Macau Professional Yoga Association (MYPA) announced the organization of the “Inaugural Macau Yoga Asana Competition”, an event that will take place on the 14th and 15th of January at Galaxy Macau.
The competition, described by the organizers as a “milestone”, aims to promote the culture of competitive yoga, raise the level of practice and encourage exchanges between local and international enthusiasts. To this end, a high-level competition platform will be made available, where participants will be challenged to refine their techniques and demonstrate the depth, strength and “beauty” of yoga practice.
The event will follow internationally recognized competition rules and will be supervised by a panel of judges made up of renowned instructors and internationally certified judges, thus ensuring authority and a fair evaluation process. Scoring will be based on multiple criteria, including precise execution of postures, stability, breath control, fluidity of movement and overall expression.
According to the information released, the competition will be divided into several categories, including divisions by gender and age groups. Competitors will have to complete, within a stipulated time, sequences of mandatory and optional postures with precision and fluidity.
In addition to the traditional categories, the program includes Artistic Yoga and Rhythmic Yoga tests, both individual and in pairs. These modalities, which combine sequences of postures with choreography and music, have time limits of 3 minutes and are evaluated for grace, diversity of positions and synchronization. The event is structured into several rounds, culminating in a “Champion of Champions” final, which includes a practical test and an oral test on yoga theory.
STRICT REGULATIONS
The competition applies strict technical and conduct regulations. Participants were grouped into six age categories by gender, from 8 years old to participants over 49 years old. The latter will all receive a trophy and certificate. Participants must perform specific series of postures in different rounds, with a defined maintenance time. The scoring system, detailed in a table of 10 points, evaluates the perfection, stability, elegance and compliance with the timing of each posture.
In terms of prizes, the total amount up for grabs exceeds 6,000 US dollars (approximately 48,000 Hong Kong dollars). The overall winner of the “Champion of Champions” title will receive a cash prize of 2,500 US dollars (around 20,000 Hong Kong dollars). The first, second and third places in each main category will also be awarded medals, certificates and monetary prizes in US dollars. All participants will receive a certificate of participation and a yoga kit.
Registration has been open since December 31, 2025, and requires a “participation fee” of 350 US dollars (or 2,800 Hong Kong dollars) per person and the submission of a medical certificate. The event provides free accommodation during the competition.
The president of the Macau Professional Yoga Association highlighted that the event is not only “a test of skill, but also a celebration of harmony between mind and body”. The association hopes that, through the competition, more people can appreciate “the power, balance and tranquility inherent in yoga postures”, while promoting the professional development of Macau’s yoga community and strengthening its connection with the global yoga culture.
The Macau Professional Yoga Association, organizer of the event, is a non-profit entity whose mission is to promote yoga and improve the physical fitness of Macau residents. The association also offers professional training services, trains instructors and issues relevant certifications.
Registration for the competition is open to all practitioners who meet the requirements of the defined categories, and it is necessary to prove their age through an official document. Interested parties should consult the regulations and register through the association's official website.</description><pubDate>2026-01-05 23:31:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Vietnam set to overtake Thailand's GDP by 2026</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/05/vietname-pronto-para-ultrapassar-pib-da-tailandia-em-2026/</link><description>Vietnam could overtake Thailand in nominal GDP this year, driven by public investment, as Thailand faces sluggish growth, debt and border tensions.

Vietnam is on track to overtake Thailand in economic capacity, measured by nominal GDP, later this year, helped by a major state-led infrastructure investment push that is accelerating growth, Nikkei Asia reported. ASEAN's economic landscape is changing as domestic political uncertainty and border tensions with Cambodia weigh on Thailand's economy and slow its growth.
Vietnam's real GDP in 2025 is expected to expand by about 8%, and Hanoi has set a growth target of more than 10% in 2026 and beyond. Although some consider the target overly ambitious, Prime Minister Pham Minh Chinh has insisted that double-digit growth is achievable.
If growth accelerates as planned, Vietnam's nominal GDP could reach the $500 billion range by 2026 or 2027, overtaking Thailand and potentially becoming the third largest economy in Southeast Asia, behind Indonesia. GDP per capita would also rise above $5,000, approaching Indonesia's level.
The main driver is the development of infrastructure across the country. Public investment plans for 2026 are expected to increase by about 26%, which could raise economic growth by 1.6 percentage points, according to Can Van Luc, chief economist at the Investment and Development Bank of Vietnam (BIDV). This is reflected in projects such as a new airport near Ho Chi Minh City, scheduled to open in 2026, while a Chinese-backed railway project in the north has already begun construction. Even so, legal reforms and reducing bureaucracy are still considered crucial to sustain investment in the next phase.
The Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) predicts that Thailand's real GDP will grow just 1.5% in 2026, a drop of 0.5 percentage points from the previous year. High household debt is also weighing on domestic consumption, tourism has been slow to recover and US import tariffs are increasing pressure on the manufacturing industry. In recent years, Suzuki Motor has abandoned the production of four-wheel vehicles in Thailand, while Honda Motor has reduced its production.
Southeast Asia, home to around 700 million people, has long been considered a key engine for global growth. But since May, tensions on the border between Thailand and Cambodia have intensified and degenerated into violent fighting in December, slowing bilateral trade and affecting tourism.</description><pubDate>2026-01-05 23:25:26</pubDate></item></channel></rss>