<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/da-grande-baia-aos-paises-lusofonos-fundacao-rui-cunha-discute-sandboxes-regulatorias/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Museum of the Grand Prix with free admission on the fourth birthday</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/museu-do-grande-premio-com-entrada-gratuita-no-quarto-aniversario/</link><description>The Macao Grand Prix Museum (MGPM) will mark its fourth birthday on June 1 with free admission to the public and a series of special activities.
Driven by the “Tourism + Sport” program of the Tourism Services Directorate (STD), the MGPM organization decided to streamline, on the first Sunday of June, an experience program that includes, in addition to free admission, playful study activities, magic shows and discounts at the souvenir store.
One of the events consists of a workshop called “Creative Running and Mosaic Camp”, where participants are entitled to a 45 -minute guided tour of the history of the Macao Grand Prix and then an experimentation session for the theme “Triumph Tr2” (the winning car of the first edition of the motorized sports event) under the guidance of professional instructors. The activity is free and has a total duration of 1:30, with sessions available at 11:00, 14:00 and 16:30. Interested parties can pre-register between May 15 and 21 on the STD Eservice page, and only 15 pairs will be selected.
Three spectacles of magic are also planned at 10:30, at 13:30 and 4:00 pm, where professional magicians will present shows and distribute balloons alluding to the public award to the public until the Stock exhausted. On the same day of the museum's birthday - which coincides with Children's Day - exclusive and limited discounts will also be available at the souvenir store.
The MGPM opened to the public on June 1, 2021, after remodeling works that introduced new elements and deepened the educational and interactive component of the exhibitions. The space is open between 10:00 and 18:00, ending on Tuesdays.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>LAM promises to reinforce teaching in the area of ​​artificial intelligence</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/o-lam-promete-reforco-do-ensino-na-area-da-inteligencia-artificial/</link><description>At yesterday's plenary meeting of the Legislative Assembly (AL), the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture indicated that the government will strengthen education in the areas of Science and Technology, namely Artificial Intelligence (IA). LAM has specified that AI teaching will integrate the curricula of primary and secondary schools, teachers will have training in this domain and the classrooms will include this type of technology.
 
LAM said yesterday that the government will reinforce education in the areas of science and technology, namely artificial intelligence (IA), through, for example, the formation of teachers in this domain and the integration of subjects related to the theme in the curricula of primary and secondary schools.
At yesterday's plenary meeting of the Legislative Assembly (AL), the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture responded to Deputy Lam Lon Wai, who asked Macao to articulate with the scientific and technological development of the interior of China.
The secretary pointed out that the review of the framework of the curriculum organization of regular education of the local school regime and the requirements of basic academic competences of regular education of the local school regime, to allow the programming and teaching of AI to integrate the curricula of primary and secondary schools. AI contents are now integrated into the curriculum guidelines of information technology classes.
Regarding the elaboration of teaching materials and the training for teaching staff, LAM highlighted the introduction of various teaching materials in the interior of China for adoption in the schools of Macao. The secretary also recalled that last year the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) and South China Normal University established a learning base and exchange with an AI teaching focus, which provides teaching materials on this institution and invites the interior of China experts and academics to teach teaching staff in the development of teaching activities on AI.
On the other hand, throughout this academic year, DSEDJ “intends to provide, in various ways, AI content or related to science and technology, with an average duration of 10 hours per year, computer teachers and six hours to teachers from other subjects,” said Lam.
The ruler also indicated that the launch of specific financing will be studied for schools to create AI classrooms, as well as support them in the organization of different types of extracurricular activities and specific training actions on the development of potentialities. This year, it is recalled, the Intelligent Education Pilot Project, which already has the participation of 25 schools, was launched, and LAM wants all Macao secondary schools to be included in this project in the school year 2026/27.
In the context of permanent learning, an AI popularization program has already been launched by the Macao Science Center that offers advanced courses for individuals seeking their professional skills, general intermediate courses for residents and basic courses, designed especially for the elderly, with the aim of transmitting knowledge about AI recognition and application.
In the context of higher education, the government “encourages higher education institutions to create academic courses related to AI and to expand the pedagogical contents of the same area in other courses”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 02:25:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Instated AMCM to ensure financial system stability</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/amcm-instada-a-garantir-estabilidade-do-sistema-financeiro/</link><description>The Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM) was instated by the Inspection Commission to take “necessary measures” to ensure the stability of the Macao financial system. In an opinion on the AMCM report and accounts, the committee warned of “uncertainties” in the local financial system because of the railway of the rally railway last year to 5.5%.
 
The high level of Malporado credit is concerning the Macao Monetary Authority Supervisory Committee (AMCM). The body has recently “solemnly request” to AMCM to take the necessary measures to ensure the stability of the Macao financial system.
According to the Inspection Committee, currently led by Leonel Alves, the appeal to AMCM was made considering that the rally credit ratio grew from 3.9% to 5.5% for 12 consecutive months last year, “which brought uncertainties to the stability of Macau's financial system”, can be read on an opinion on the AMCM 2024 exercise accounts.
The opinion was published yesterday in an official bulletin, attached to an AMCM report, where the authorities justify that, last year, the banking system of the banking system has increased "due to the joint influence of internal and external factors."
However, according to the body, the capital suitability ratio, composed mainly of tier 1 capital, remained a high level of 15.5%. "In addition, the banking system had sufficient liquidity, demonstrating the stability of the Macao bank sector," he insisted.
The AMCM report showed that by the end of last year, deposits and current bank accounts decreased by 13.6% over the balance at the end of 2023, having risen to 135.3 billion patacas, including mainly deposits in foreign currencies, particularly in Hong Kong dollars and US dollars, with 84.2% and 15.7%.
"In 2024, global geopolitical tensions remained at a high level, creating numerous significant uncertainties in external economic and financial markets," the authorities said.
They indicated, however, that Macau's economy recorded a “stable recovery” through the support of “a series of measures favorable to Macao introduced by the central government”, the “development of the diversification of the economy and the guarantee of the population's welfare”. "At the same time, Macao banks strictly fulfilled the prudent management principle, ensuring sufficient capital to stabilize the ability to resist risk resistance," read the document.
AMCM also ensured adhesion to a careful licensing system, continuous supervision measures and the fight against illegal financial activities, in order to preserve the safety and solidity of the local financial system.
 
Financial results fell 4.8%
 
The results of AMCM exercise were 6.7 billion patacas, with a drop of 4.8% compared to the previous year. However, a 5.8% and 24.4% increase in total and costs, respectively, compared to 2023, was recorded by 2024.
The level of AMCM's general risks, in turn, remained 5.3 billion patacas, which reflects "the continuation of prudential policy followed by AMCM in previous years." "In addition to responding to the volatility of the international financial market, a reasonable level of reserves has been established to avoid eventual financial losses induced by unforeseen turmoil in the market," he explained.
Regarding the total profit, AMCM registered an annual increase in interest revenue of 1.3 billion patacas. The body indicated that the increase was due to the rate of reduction of interest rates, adopted by the world's major central banks, being relatively slow compared to market expectations, and Hong Kong dollar interest rates have remained at a relatively high level.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 02:25:54</pubDate></item><item><title>A dialogue between leather and time</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/um-dialogo-entre-o-couro-e-o-tempo/</link><description>Upon entering Leather Angel, the aroma the leather soil hits us immediately. Italy cow-skinned and lamb skin piles fill all corners, while the walls display bags and key holders in various shapes, including owls and revoked with rainbow colors.
 
Leather Angel owner KK Chen is leaning over her workbench, carefully trimming a piece of core-beaded leather with a cutting knife.  His course with leather began with only scissors in his childhood. “When I was a girl, I loved to dismantle old clothes to do new things,” he recalls.
Years later, he began working in retail, but the daily routine wear it out. "Fulfilling sales objectives every day was exhausting to the soul."
Then the pandemic forced the world to stop and it opened an opportunity for KK to return to his passion. “I decided to take my handicraft books and bought my first tanned skin to the vegetable to make a wallet. I just wanted something different. I never thought that first cut would change my life,” he says.
The difficulties of self-learning helped her improve her abilities and patience, but she admits that it can be a little “obsessive”-once two months has been redoing a white skin box just because of a 1mm dislocation. “There are no shortcuts in handicrafts,” he says, pointing to the leather remains. "Time is your best teacher."
After publishing their work online, unexpected orders began to arrive. When a client told him, "His designs stand out with better details than mass-produced articles," KK decided to lease a small space over a coffee to become a true skin artisan in 2021.
Personalization is the main service of the kk atelier. Customers bring you different personal stories-recreate folders, offer their mates gifts or record their children's names on products. “I love to transform abstract ideas into real drawings,” he explains.
While many buyers want things ready quickly, KK was intentionally in the other direction, updating his store last year to focus more on personalization. Even simple card holders receive custom standards.
“Hurry can ruin the touch of leather,” he insists. “It's a lack of respect for the material. Each piece needs a 'massage' first, like a spa skin treatment,” he demonstrates, straightening a stubborn skin.
KK also organizes DIY workshops that have become very popular, and also focus on the art of being patient. Principles usually need to spend four hours to sew a skin product, and kk helps them to cut into pieces of skin until the edges are perfectly straight.
“Nowadays, people expect immediate results, but handicrafts, on the contrary, forces us to slow down,” says KK. "Many customers say they forget the mobile phones and deadlines while focusing on crafts. This is the magic of the thing - it is not perfection, but accepting the confusing learning process."
Next to KK's workbench is a Cítaara Guzheng - his "inspirational station." The artisan, dressed in a punk way and with bulky silver necklaces, surprises with her graceful skills in the CI. “People say I'm full of contrasts,” smiles, brushing her short hair. "Like the leather - the rough and the delicate can coexist."
As we talked, it demonstrates border dyeing techniques that recently learned in Shanghai-placing pigments on the edges of the lamb skin and polishing them until they are bright.
"The machines can finish the edges in seconds, but manual dyeing is like paint with Chinese paint - we need to wait for each layer to dry," he explains. "The real challenge has nothing to do with the skill, but with the desire to spend two hours in a thing."
This “philosophy of going slow” also affects your material choices. It loves Italian leather, which “ages as an old friend”, and the French lamb skin, which needs extra care. “It's soft like the skin, but it requires twice the patience,” he says.
Looking around the KK store, it is evident that there are no viral success products, but customers liked to be there, enjoying the beauty and originality of their craft work. Kk takes a suitcase that uses every day - a three -year -old black leather bag, with a well -kept shine at the expense. “They are not defects,” he says. "These are memories that grow with me," he concluded.
In this world of instant satisfaction, true luxury is not perfection, but the inaccurate and time consuming imperfections that result from true human effort.
 
Macau Closer</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Government will do a new study on demand for qualified paintings</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/governo-vai-fazer-novo-estudo-sobre-procura-de-quadros-qualificados/</link><description>The Development Committee for Qualified Quadros (CDQQ) will conduct a new study on the search for qualified frameworks, in order to “provide residents, sectors and society at large a predictable tendency to search for short, medium and long term qualified frames,” LAM said at the Legislative Assembly Plenary Meeting (AL) yesterday.
In response to the oral interpellation of Deputy Zheng Anting, the secretary for social affairs and culture recalled that last March CDQQ created the qualified frame data registration service through the single account, “widening the scope of the recipients of the system and encouraging more residents to register and to update their personal data”.
A joint mechanism was also developed to invite students from Macau who attend higher education institutions around the world to register their data and keep it up to date, using the system dissemination, which allows you to provide more updated information on stages and employment supports, among other aspects, “facilitating the planning and development of their careers”.
LAM also talked about the platform for the return of Macao residents, which provides information on professional accreditation, the policies of the large bay and the dynamics of the market to the registered abroad, through the qualified table database. "In the future, with the development of professional qualification regimes in various domains, studies can be performed, involving all parties, to create better conditions for the return of qualified paintings," said the secretary.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 02:25:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Suggested creation of careers of exclusive buses for tourists</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/sugerida-criacao-de-carreiras-de-autocarros-exclusivas-para-turistas/</link><description>Traffic Advisory Board Member Ku Heng Cheong proposed the creation of new exclusive bus careers. The measure aims to avoid the “competition for resources” of public transport between residents and visitors. The counselor said he was aware of pressure on public transport during the high times of tourist activities and suggested daily tickets for tourists to catch the special careers that undergo tourist attractions.
 
The government must study the creation of special trustee careers for tourist passengers that go through tourist attractions in Macau, argues Ku Heng Cheong, a vowel of the Traffic Advisory Board, justifying that the measure will help alleviate the load of public buses and optimize their frequency.
Ku Heng Cheong indicated that the idea came to the past week of May 1, when there were five days of holidays in the interior of China and many Chinese citizens chose to travel. During this period, Macau registered 850,000 visitors, a value that “was higher than expectations” and “further aggravated traffic pressure on the various migration stations and the main tourist attractions”, although the government coordinated with public transport operators in terms of passenger deviation measures and increased frequency of buses.
In the Macao Macao Forum program of Macau's Chinese channel, Ku Heng Cheong said it is possible to add buses to tourists while building the light metro network is not complete.
"Residents often catch buses, and tourists will also catch. Taking the example of career 17, tourists catch the bus to explore homes, but residents also need this career to go to work. Therefore, there is an overlap and a competition for resources," he explained.
Ku Heng Cheong pointed out that if the tourist route can be completed, the government should also consider the installation of stops at sights, as well as the creation of a daily ticket for visitors. "With the ticket, passengers can catch and leave the bus at any time at any stop within a day," he said. In this case, the operation model of this special bus career is similar to the Hop-On Hop-Off Bus trip, which is already common in many countries and regions.
It is recalled that, according to the Tourism Services Directorate, Macau also provides buses for tourists, and with the “Open Bus Tourist Circuit”, passengers can enjoy attractions with a day of this transportation, with rise and free descent at various points of interest. The service, which is also available at night time, is provided by the Limited Travel and Tourism Company. However, the service of the “Open Bus Tourist Circuit” was suspended on the 1 “due to the public holiday”, said the official portal of the company.
In the same radio program, the member of the North Zone Community Services Advisory Board, Wong Chio U, was concerned about traffic pressure in the North Zone, as tourists often enter the territory through the siege doors. "However, the means of transport could not divert the flow of people in a timely manner, thus increasing the pressure on the district," he said.
Wong Chio U, in this sense, has stressed the need to make transport services available through online orders, "which should at the same time focus on resident travel needs." "The online transportation service should aim to facilitate the displacement of residents. And casinos and hotels operators should increase the frequencies of direct buses to satisfy the need for tourists," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 02:23:50</pubDate></item><item><title>BNU profits fall 18.4% in the first quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/lucros-do-bnu-caem-184-no-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>The profits of the National Overseas Bank registered an 18.4% homologous decrease in the first quarter of the year, minus 30 million patacas than between January and March 2024. The main reason for falling profits was a 11.8% reduction in the net financial margin, coupled with impairment losses of 5.4 million patacas.
 
The National Bank Overseas (BNU) released its financial results regarding the first quarter of 2025. During this period, BNU registered a non -audited net profit of 133.2 million patacas, which represents a decrease of 30 million, or 18.4%, compared to the same period last year.
According to the bank detailed in a press release, between January and March there was a reduction of 31.2 million patacas on the net financial margin (ie, less 11.8% in annual terms) due to changes in the composition of deposits and the evolution of reference interest rates. This reduction was partially offset by an increase of 3.8 million patacas in net commissions (more 18.1%) resulting from greater economic activity.
Although impairment losses related to credit exhibitions and financial investments increased from 1.3 million to 5.4 million patacas, BNU ensures that the quality of assets remains “solid” and supported by “conservative credit practices and a robust level of provisions to respond to ongoing macroeconomic uncertainties”.
In turn, operating expenses registered a slight increase of 1.1%, which is justified with “the effectiveness of cost optimization measures”. In this regard, the Bank highlights the efforts employed in the simplification of processes, optimizing the client experience, integrating ESG (environmental, social and governance) principles in its operations, promoting sustainable growth and adaptation to digitization.
Also noteworthy is the “strategic” role of the branch in Hengqin in serving individual and business investors of Macau and Hong Kong, acting as a transfronic economic integration platform that connects the large bay zone to Lusophone countries, through the offer of personalized financial support and the development of a diverse economy.
Finally, the institution refers to the reinforcement of the total capital ratio to 25.2% in the first quarter of the year, after an increase of 1.9 percentage points compared to the same period. Globality, it is underlined, the results of 2024 reflect the resilience and ability of the bank to maintain a “disciplined financial management and a solid risk control frame”, enabling successful navigation in “complex economic contexts”.
It is recalled that by 2024 Macao banks made a profit of only 4.01 billion patacas, the lowest value of the last 14 years. According to a statement from the Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM), released in February this year, the main reason for reducing profits was a 18.3% drop in interest margin.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 02:22:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Babel and Macau Pioneer celebrate museums day with visits to Guangdong museums</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/babel-e-macau-pioneer-celebram-dia-dos-museus-com-visitas-a-museus-de-guangdong/</link><description>Two institutions based in Macau, Macau Pioneer and Babel will mark International Museum Day with visits to three Guangdong Museums on the 17th and 18th of this month. In addition to the artistic and cultural components, the program also provides a gastronomic aspect with the opportunity to taste authentic dishes from the regions.
 
Macao Pioneer and Babel - Cultural Organization designed a joint program regarding International Museum Day, celebrated this Sunday, consisting of exclusive visits to three Guangdong museums.
Visits take place on the weekend of 17 and 18 May and, according to a statement from Babel, aim to provide participants “free visits to the most emblematic museums [of Guangdong], where they will have the opportunity to meet their architectures, museographs, programming and collections in detail”.
The first institution selected for the activity is the GBA Art Center, an architectural work designed by the renowned he Jingtang architect that unites the Guangdong Museum of Fine Arts, the Intangible Cultural Heritage Museum and the Guangdong Literature Museum. Apart from the innovative design abroad, which resembles a swan to rest in the Rio Berma, the interior brings together numerous works that explore culture, art, literature and the architecture of the Lingnan area.
Following is the King Nanyue Museum, an archaeological site with more than a thousand artifacts whose name derives precisely from the location: it is built around the mausoleum of King Nanyue Zhao Mo, who ruled between 137 BC and 122 BC .. Between the thousands of patent cultural relics in space, the Golden Administrative Seal, which belonged to emperor Wendi, highlight Han Dynasty, and the Jade container, the only piece of clothing in the world where Jade ornamental stones are bound by silk and not gold, silver or copper, as traditionally happens.
Finally, participants will visit the Chen Academy, an academic temple built during the Qing Dynasty that currently welcomes the Guangdong Popular Arts Museum. Composed of 19 buildings built in a symmetrical pattern, the temple is world famous for the rich decoration and the engravings inscribed in different materials, such as wood, brick or iron - the latter, unusual in Cantonese architecture - that combine tradition with popular art.
The trip will be accompanied by gastronomic experiences “carefully integrated to taste and depth the cultural journey”, reads in Babel's statement. Each visit will be accompanied by the opportunity to taste authentic dishes that “tell stories and reflect local customs and traditions, transforming each meal into a celebration of regional culture and identity”.
Those interested in participating in the activity should consult the official channels of Macau Pioneer and Babel - cultural organization or contact the institutions by electronic message.
Babel is a non -profit cultural association that has the mission of promoting learning and research opportunities in the domains of art, architecture and environment.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Sporting with hand in the I Liga and Benfica title waiting for a slip</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/sporting-com-mao-no-titulo-da-i-liga-e-benfica-a-espera-de-um-deslize/</link><description>Sporting enters the last matchday of the First Football League depending on themselves to win the title of champion, equally with Benfica, who has to expect a slide from the 'lions' to be able to celebrate.
 
After equality to a goal in the 33rd and penultimate journey in Luz, the 'lions' and 'eagles' enter the last round with the same 79 points, but with Sporting having the advantage in direct confrontation.
Thus, to get the first two -time championship since reaching the tetra in 1953/54, Sporting, which hosts Vitória de Guimarães, has only the same result as Benfica, who visits Sporting de Braga.
Only one Sporting slip against the Vimaranenses can allow Benfica to be champion, always having to do a better result than the 'lions'.
For the last game of the time, scheduled for 6:00 pm on Saturday, such as Benfica, Sporting coach Rui Borges will not be able to count on Captain Morten Hjulmand, who completed a series of yellows, nor with Ricardo Esgaio, expelled after the end of the light meeting.
However, both Sporting and Benfica will find teams still with important objectives for realizing this season, with Sporting Braga to have more complicated accounts to reach third place than Vitória de Guimarães to reach fifth post and the last European seat.
The Braga have a lot of hopes to reach the podium, as they are three points from FC Porto, which also receives, also on Saturday, the already quiet national, without Nehuén Pérez, expelled in the triumph at Boavista's house.
Even in case of defeat, the dragons will hardly lose third place, which gives direct access to the Europa League League phase, as the 'arsenalists' would have to hit Benfica and recover from a difference of seven goals compared to FC Porto.
In the struggle for the presence in the League Conference, Vitória de Guimarães (fifth) and Santa Clara (sixth) join the last matchday on equality, with the same 54 points, although with advantage in direct confrontation to the Vimaranenses, who only need to make the same result as the Azoreans.
However, Santa Clara has, in theory, a more affordable meeting, as they visit the Farense 'distressed', although the representative Algarve in the I Liga is to force to score to try to escape the dispromotion.
The places of dispromotion will also be decided on the last day, with the certainty that the red flashlight Boavista needs a 'miracle' to reach the play-off, with direct maintenance already mathematically.
At the entrance to the last day, the Amadora Star (15th), with 29 points, is the first team in maintenance zone, but has only two points of advancement on AVS (16th) and Farense (17th), with the 'axadrity' to five points.
Apart from Farense, who plays with Santa Clara, the other teams face teams without clear objectives on the last day: Estoril Praia da Amadora, Arouca-Boavista and AVS-Moreirense.
For Boavista, the accounts are easy to do, but difficult to realize, as they have to earn your meeting and expect AVS and Farense to be defeated, thereby guaranteeing 16th place, access to the maintenance play-off, as with the three tied teams, the 'axadrity' have the advantage in direct confrontation.
For the star of Amadora, a victory guarantees maintenance, with any other result to leave the Lisbon club depending on the results of AVS and Farense, with which it has a disadvantage in direct confrontation.
A draw from the 'tricolor' and a victory for AVs and Farense left the three clubs tied with 30 points, with the Vila das Aves team ensuring maintenance, the Algarve the Play-off and the star to be dismissed, the same as the Amadorenses lose and the other two win.
There is an equality between AVS, which in case of Triunfo always ensures at least the play-off, and Farense, the advantage in direct confrontation will also be of the North team.
The only meetings of the last day that is not played Saturday are Famalicão-Casa Pia and Rio Ave-Gil Vicente, scheduled for this Friday. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 02:25:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing Fractions Income grew 4.5% in the first quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/rendas-das-fraccoes-habitacionais-cresceram-45-no-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>The Board of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) released yesterday the lace statistics of the first quarter of 2025, with a homologous increase in the average income of housing autonomous fractions.
Between January and March, the average income per square meter (service area) of autonomous fractions intended for stores was 485 patacas, a slight decrease of 0.9% compared to the last quarter of 2024. Also the average incomes of autonomous fractions for offices and industrial autonomous fractions registered descents of 1.3% and 0.2%, respectively, to 290 and 123. Patacas. On the other hand, housing autonomous fractions grew 0.4% in quarterly terms to 138 patacas.
Analyzing by zones, the rental rents of Macao downtown were the ones that diminished the most (3.7%reduction to 665 patacas), followed by black sand and iao Hon (2.4%, 452 patacas) and the barge zone (2.3%, 344 patacas). Commercial fractions at NAPE and landfills of Praia Grande Bay recorded evolutions towards the opposite direction, with a thin risen from 0.4% to 623 patacas.
As for housing autonomous fractions, the lace by square meters that rose most in quarterly terms were those of Baixa da Taipa (1.1%, to 140 patacas), Zape (0.8%, 120 patacas) and Nape and landfills of Praia Grande Bay (0.7%, 144 patacas). Only in the new landfills of the black sand there was a decrease of 1.5%for 163 patacas.
Regarding the useful area of ​​autonomous fractions, the average level of the level from 50 to 99.9 square meters increased to 138 patacas, more 0.5% than in the previous quarter. The opposite happened with the level of less than 50 square meters, which descended 0.9% to 166 patacas.
Establishing a comparison with the 2024 homologous quarter, it appears that the average income per square meter of offices, stores and industrial fractions descended 3.2%, 1.3%and 0.9%, respectively, while those of Macau's housing autonomous fractions rose 4.5%.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 02:25:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Wong Sio Chak warns “words and actions that destroy, defam and disturb Macao”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/wong-sio-chak-alerta-para-palavras-e-accoes-que-destroem-difamam-e-perturbam-macau/</link><description>Following the visit to Macao de Xia Baolong, members of the Government of the MSAR expressed support for the director pointed out by the Hong Kong Work Office Director and Macao from the China Communist Party Central Committee and the Hong Kong and Macao affairs director with the Council of State. Wong Sio Chak, Secretary for Security, warned of the "hegemonic acts of the US and Western countries" and the "words and actions that destroy, defam and disturb Macao."
 
Xia Baolong returned to Beijing on Tuesday after a six-day visit to Macao. Following the inspection by the Hong Kong and Macao Work Office director of the China Communist Party Central Committee and the Hong Kong and Macau's Office Director with the Council of State, several secretaries expressed support for the director's guidelines.
In a statement released yesterday by his office, Wong Sio Chak, Secretary for Security, said that the speeches given by Xia Baolong in the territory were "an important guiding meaning in the context of governing governing actions."
The secretary said that "currently, in the face of the rapid evolution of centenary changes in the world and the most intense strategic competition between China and the United States of America, the risks that affect Macao's national security and social stability become increasingly serious," in particular due to the "hegemonic acts of the US and Western countries, as well as the words and actions that destroy, defam and disturb Macao ”. Therefore, “the society of Macao must identify the situation, maintain the position firmly, cultivate the spirit of struggle, and cannot give in,” urged Wong Sio Chak.
"All residents of Macao are the beneficiaries and guardians of national security, no one is left out," said the secretary for security, adding that "Macao society should value the current favorable situation of stability and prosperity, should be aware of the crises, giving high importance to the problems we face within the development and security of Macau, supporting the government's development of the development of the system, adequately resolving the risks. Prevent and resolve the interference and destruction of hostile and criminals. ”
 
Lam, André Cheong and Raymond Tam manifest “total agreement”
 
Raymond Tam also issued a statement after Xia Baolong's departure, expressing “total agreement” with the guidelines of the Cabinet director for Hong Kong and Macau affairs. The Secretary for Transport and Public Works has pointed out that his guardianship has implemented "the spirit consecrated in President XI Jinping's important speeches, as well as learning profoundly the opinions of director Xia's guidance."
Tam argued that his team has adopted "effective measures in the domains of maritime planning, infrastructure construction and regional cooperation, with the aim of promoting the city's ordered development and consolidating social stability by improving the life conditions of the population."
The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture stressed that Xia Baolong's demands are intended for the entire population of Macao and "it would be very important to study seriously and understand them deeply so that the advancement of all work can be further guided." LAM stressed that its guardianship is “entirely dedicated to implementing Xi Jinping's guidelines”, when his visit to Macao in December last year.
LAM has also stated that its team will “seek to promote the spirit of 'daring to fight', will keep confidence in the country's development, firmly support the country's position and actions, consolidate national security awareness, will maintain a firm and clear position in the face of crucial issues, always keeping the responsibility of 'loving the homeland, an obligation and mission'.
"The patriotic education of young people will continue to be consolidated, reinforced and deepened," reiterated Lam, adding that "forms of education will be the target of innovation, through the use of new media, in order to bring patriotic education closer to residents' lives." “The cohesion of the citizens of Macao with the homeland will be continuously reinforced, and an imposing force of love for the country and Macau, the history of China and Macao, will be streamlined, as well as the institutional advantages of the principle 'one country, two systems' to the world,” promised the secretary.
André Cheong began to say that, “in the face of the complexity of the current international scenario, director Xia's important discourse contributed to the confidence of the industrial and commercial sector to take practical actions to love the homeland and defend Macau”, as well as “maximize their own advantages to achieve improvements in terms of development, and the same discourse also encourages in all sectors of the field of the field”.
The Secretary for Administration and Justice stated that the government must “follow the work requirements presented by the Xia Director, be fully aware of the eventuality of crises, and lead the various sectors of society in a total commitment to promoting the economy and improvement of development, remaining firm in defense of sovereignty, security and interests of the country's development and stability of Macao”. "The area of ​​administration and justice will assume and fulfill its responsibilities, promoting solidly the various governance actions," said the ruler.
 
“Being with the homeland in each breath”
 
Kou Hoi In, President of the Legislative Assembly (AL), also issued a statement to ensure loyalty in the face of Xia Baolong's guidelines, noting that it is necessary to “consolidate and promote the tradition of 'love for the homeland and Macau' and have the homeland in each breath, in good and bad times”.
The president of AL warned to "the resurgence of commercial protectionism, unilateralism and hegemonic coercion," noting that it is necessary to "effectively implement the" Macao Macao governed by patriots "principle. Kou Hoi in is eventually saying that "the Chinese nation is a resilient, resilient peace -loving people and that he knows and knows how to fight, never giving in any external pressure."
Leong Man Cheong, Commander General of Unit Police Services (SPU), also stressed the "importance" of Xia Baolong's visit to the territory, "which translates into an inspiration and in a deep guiding meaning for the stable development of the Society of Macao." "Given an international conjuncture marked by change and instability, the risks and challenges that Macao faces are complex," said Leong Man Cheong, adding that "a large country should always prioritize security, so no one should be alien with matters regarding national security defense."
Finally, Adriano Marques Ho, Director General of Customs Services (SA), stressed that the body he directs will remain “aligned with the homeland” and strive to “advance the modernization of customs services, the improvement of facilitation of border passage, the deepening of interdepartal and interregional cooperation, as well as the reinforcement of maritime security”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 02:24:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Opposition at Myanmar calls for international support after attack on a school</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/oposicao-no-myanmar-pede-apoio-internacional-apos-ataque-a-uma-escola/</link><description>The government of national unity that opposes the Military Junta in Power in Myanmar, yesterday asked the international community to take "decisive measures" after the bombing of a school, which killed 20 children and two teachers. In a statement, the government of national unit described the impact of Monday's air strike, which targeted a school in Tabayin, in the northern region of Sagaing, epicenter of the 7.7 magnitude earthquake of March 28, which made more than 3,700 dead. "After the air strike, approximately 500 residents of the neighboring village of OE Htein were displaced," the statement says, adding that 102 people also suffered wounds of varied severity in the Burmese army air strike. The government of national unity has classified the attack as a war crime and urged the international community, especially the United Nations (UN), "taking decisive measures and pressuring the military junta to finish their continuous civil attacks."
The executive stressed that, despite the announcement of the ceasefire extension until May 31 to facilitate humanitarian aid after the earthquake, "attacks against civilians intensified, with increasing attacks on religious buildings, schools and hospitals." According to opposition data, from January 1, 2023 until Monday, the Military Junta launched 2,679 air attacks, damaging 240 schools.
The opposition movement - composed in part by deputies without the military coup of 2021 - ensured that it will continue its efforts “to hold the Board responsible for these crimes before the international and national courts”. The Sagaing region is a rebel bastion of Myanmar, where pro-democracy guerrillas have gained ground against the army since the 2021 military revolt.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 02:25:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Assessment of constitutionality of the law of the Timorese Judiciary System is up to the Court of Appeal</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/apreciacao-de-constitucionalidade-da-lei-do-sistema-judiciario-timorense-cabe-ao-tribunal-de-recurso/</link><description>The Timorese President, José Ramos-Horta, said that the competence to consider the request for supervision to the constitutionality of the amendment to the law of the organization of the judiciary, submitted by the parliamentary opposition, it is up to the court of appeal.
 
"It is the Court of Appeal that must analyze the issue and its members know that there can be no conflict of interest. It was FRETILIN that presented the request and some of those within the Court of Appeal are already aware of it. There are those who say that the court is not independent, but no one knows for sure or not," said Ramos-Horta, when questioned by journalists on the subject.
The Revolutionary Front of Independent Timor-Leste (Fretilin) ​​and the Popular Liberation Party (PLP) delivered last week to the Court of Appeal an abstract verification of constitutionality after changes to the law of the organization of the country's judiciary.
The Timorese Parliamentary majority (National Council for the Reconstruction of Timor and Democratic Party, in Power), approved in April amendments to the law of the organization of the judiciary, namely the appointment of the President of the Court of Appeal, who in Timor-Leste also assumes the duties of Supreme Court and, consequently, an administrative, fiscal and accounts.
Prior to the amendment, the President of the Court of Appeal was appointed by the Head of State among the judges who made up that body of sovereignty. With the amendment, the Timorese head of state began to appoint any judge directly to the president of that court with at least 20 years of experience.
The request for inspection was added a legal opinion of the professor at the Faculty of Law of the Portuguese Catholic University Rui Medeiros, who considers the unconstitutional change. "The issue of law is not only known for one party. In Timor-Leste, I still do not know any element that can withdraw the competencies attributed to him by the Constitution," explained José Ramos-Horta. "I have not departed political and no one presses me to go to one side or the other. I will act only by law and my conscience. For example, if I wanted to favor any party after being elected in 2022, I would immediately dissolve the National Parliament and summoned early elections. But I did not.
Asked about decisions his allegedly contrary to the principles of the Constitution, Ramos-Horta replied that the Constitution cannot be interpreted in the taste of convenience, and that, according to the Constitution itself, it is the competence of the head of state to appoint the President of the Court of Appeal and the Attorney General, and that there is nothing more than that. "I have an excellent relationship with the judges of the Court of Appeal," he concluded.
 
Named First Ambassador of Timor-Leste in India
 
José Ramos-Hort announced yesterday the appointment of the first Timor-Leste ambassador in India, as part of the reinforcement of diplomatic relations and cooperation between the two countries. "Ambassador Karlito Nunes's appointment represents an important milestone in our diplomatic relations with India," said the head of state, cited in a press release by the Timorese Presidency.
According to José Ramos-Horta, as Timor-Leste advances in his course of regional integration and economic development, partnership with India is one of the “most promising diplomatic relations”.
Karlito Nunes, former Timor-Leste ambassador in the United Nations, currently held the position of advisor at the International Relations Unit in the Presidency of the Republic. The Timorese President received, on the other hand, in April the credential letters of the new India Ambassador in the country, Madan Kumar Ghildiyal.
Timor-Leste and India have established diplomatic relations in 2003 and have been cooperating in the domains of defense, education, agriculture and health.
Early last year, relationships had a new momentum with a visit by President Timorese to India, during which cooperation was discussed in the areas of oil, gas, digitization and exchange in the education sector. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 02:25:53</pubDate></item><item><title>China and Brazil positively evaluate signs of dialogue between Putin and Zelensky</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/china-e-brasil-avaliam-positivamente-sinais-de-dialogo-entre-putin-e-zelensky/</link><description>The governments of Brazil and China have positively evaluated the recent signs of willingness of Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky, and his Russian homologist Vladimir Putin to start negotiations for peace in Ukraine.
 
In a joint statement, Brazil and China stated that "they welcome the proposal made by President Vladimir Putin on May 10 to open negotiations for peace, as well as the positive manifestation of Volodymyr Zelensky in the same direction."
"Brazil and China positively evaluate the recent signs of disposition to dialogue and express their expectation that the parties can achieve an understanding that will be able to start fruitful negotiations, which contemplate legitimate concerns from all over," he added.
The governments of Brazil and China have added to expect, in the shortest possible time, a direct dialogue between the parties to end the conflict, and stressed that it is necessary to “find a political solution” for the crisis in Ukraine, with a view to a lasting and fair peace agreement for all parts.
In the note, they also remember that in May 2024, Brazil and China made a joint appeal for all parties involved to create the conditions for the resumption of dialogue and, months later, in September last year, created the group of friends for peace in the United Nations, bringing together global southern countries committed to the mediation of conflict in Ukraine. "Brazil and China continue to be available, along with the Global South, to continue supporting efforts to end the conflict," they said.
Brazilian President Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva, and Chinese President Xi Jinping, participated in the celebrations of the 80th anniversary of the Soviet Army victory day against the Nazi government in World War II, celebrated last Friday, in Moscow, where they had bilateral meetings with Putin.
The Brazilian president is in Beijing where he has fulfilled agendas related to the attraction of Chinese investments to the South American country. Yesterday, the Brazilian president attended the opening of the 11th Ministerial Meeting of the China-Celac Forum and will meet with his Chinese counterpart, Xi Jinping, with whom he will also sign agreements to expand bilateral cooperation.
At the global level, in addition to being members of the G20, which held their annual summit in November 2024 in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, China and Russia, along with South India and Africa, they are founders of the BRICS Forum, which they joined last year Iran, Egypt, United Arab Emirates and Ethiopia.
Brazil occupies the annual presidency of BRICS in 2025 and will host the next summit of the group, so it is expected that Xi Jinping visit the country in the coming months. Putin did not give signs that he will appear at the BRICS Cimeira due to arrest warrants that were issued against him by the International Criminal Court (ICC) for war crimes. Brazil is a signatory to the agreement, which provides for compliance with warrants issued by the Court. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 02:25:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Colombia confirms signature of memo adhesion to the Chinese initiative track and route</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/colombia-confirma-assinatura-de-memorando-de-adesao-a-iniciativa-chinesa-faixa-e-rota/</link><description>China and Colombia yesterday signed in Beijing a cooperation plan for the Latin American country to join the Chinese track and route initiative, the Colombian presidency confirmed through the X social network.
 
The memorandum, signed in Beijing by the leaders of the two countries, Xi Jinping and Gustavo Petro, brings together Colombia to an initiative with which the Asian giant intends to generate an international trade network and widen its world -level influence through the construction of infrastructure, and which have joined more than twenty Latin America and Caribbean countries.
“Under this meeting, Colombia has signed an important economic cooperation agreement for the adhesion of our country to the [initiative] track and route,” says the Colombian presidency.
Xi and Petro gathered yesterday to reinforce bilateral ties by signing new agreements, including this, among all the most emblematic.
Before traveling to China, Petro revealed that on his previous voyage to the Asian country in October 2023, he intended to sign this memorandum, but at the time it was not possible due to an alleged mistake of his previous Foreign Minister, Álvaro Leyva. "This is what I am going to do now, an agreement of intent; future governments will see if the intention comes true, and must come true," the Colombian president said.
Petro was with Xi on Tuesday at the opening of the China-Celac Forum (Latin American and Caribbean Community) in the Chinese capital, where he appealed to a dialogue between civilizations “free from authoritarianism and imperialism”.
The trade scale between Colombia and China is particularly unfavorable to the Latin American country, whose annual deficit is about $ 14 billion (12.5 billion euros).
By 2024, Colombia exported $ 2.38 billion (2.12 billion euros) of goods to China and imported $ 15.9 billion (14.2 billion euros) of Chinese products.
In addition, between 1994 and 2023, China invested $ 813.3 million (726.5 million euros) in Colombia -yet a value far lower than the United States and Spain -concentrated in sectors such as infrastructure, mining exploration, energy and transport.
In addition to trade, Colombia is trying to reinforce technological cooperation with China.
On Tuesday, Petro visited the headquarters of the Huawei 'giant' in Beijing telecommunications, where, according to Colombian Minister of Information and Communications Technology, Julián Molina, eventual initiatives for cooperation in the domains of artificial intelligence, data infrastructure and connectivity were discussed.
Petro's government's interest in strengthening commercial ties with China during the visit has caused internal controversy, due to the fear of any negative repercussions on the relationship with the United States, Colombia's largest commercial partner. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 02:25:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan approves amendment to extend Nuclear Centers Operation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/taiwan-aprova-emenda-para-prolongar-operacao-de-centrais-nucleares/</link><description>The Taiwan Parliament has approved an amendment that will allow nuclear central operators to extend the validity of current 40 years to 60 years, despite the government's criticism.
The measure approved on Tuesday was presented by deputies of the main opposition party, Kuomintang (KMT), and the Taiwan Popular Party (TPP).
The final vote ended with 60 votes in favor and 51 against, the latter of the Progressive Democratic Party (DPP), currently in power, said the Taiwanese public news agency CNA.
DPP opposition focused on nuclear waste management, while amendment proponents argued that it does not automatically expand operations, but introduces regulatory flexibility.
Taiwan's last active nuclear center, located in Pingtung County, was scheduled to close completely next weekend.
The head of the economy portfolio, Kuo Jyh-Hiei, quoted by the CNA, recently explained that the central should cease operations on 17 May, according to the legislation in force, although energy supply may continue until the end of the month. Kuo Jyh-Hiei also noted that, in case of extent of the operation of the reactor, it would be necessary between 16 and 18 months to reactivate and replenish the structure.
The nuclear power plants of Chinshan and Kuosheng, in Nova Taipei (North), began to be dismantled in July 2019 and March 2023, respectively, after license expiration.
For decades, DPP has defended the need to gradually eliminate nuclear energy on the island, but the growing demand for electricity by the technological industry and the lack of renewable energy development has increased fear of future energy shortages.
According to data from the Department of Energy, nuclear power represented 6.3% of Taiwan's energy matrix in 2023.
The approved amendment Tuesday fits into a broader political struggle between the government and the Taiwanese opposition, which has used most to, among other things, reject the budget presented by the executive.
In March, Taiwan's main opposition party announced the holding of two referendums on the abolition of the death penalty and the martial law and accused the government of instrumentalizing China's threat. KMT President Eric Chu Li-Luan explained that the objective of referendums is that the population "manifests and express their will", opposing the "abolition of fact" of capital penalty and demanding that the government does not provoke "risks of war or the imposition of martial law."</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 02:25:53</pubDate></item><item><title>That gives 'green light' to 17th Package of Sanctions to Russia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/ue-da-luz-verde-a-17-o-pacote-de-sancoes-a-russia/</link><description>Member States Ambassadors to the European Union (EU) approved yesterday the 17th Package of Community Sanctions to Russia by the invasion of Ukraine, three months after another, aiming to weaken the Russian economy and the funding of the war. European sources advanced to the Lusa agency that the 'green light' was at the meeting of this EU ambassadors morning in Brussels, and an official approval was scheduled at the meeting of the European foreign business ministers next Tuesday. This new set of restrictive measures comes three months after 16th Package of Sanctions - which was approved at the third anniversary of the Ukraine War - and again encompasses ships of the Ghost Fleet, with which the Russian regime was trying to circumvent Western restrictions on oil trade, reinforcing the fight against evasion to the embargo applied to Russia. New restrictions on more individuals and entities have emerged, the European sources advanced to Lusa.
Since the beginning of the Russian invasion of Ukraine on February 24, 2022, the EU has advanced with heavy sanctions against Russia, namely economic or diplomatic, aiming at 2,400 people and entities, including Russian President Vladimir Putin and the country's foreign business minister, Sergey Lavrov. At issue is the prohibition of traveling to the EU, the freezing of goods and the unavailability of access to funds that come from the community space. It was also advanced for the freezing of goods, a total of 24.9 billion euros of frozen private goods in the community space and 210 billion euros from the Central Bank of Russia blocked. At the commercial level, European restrictive measures aim for 48 billion euros in exports prohibited to Russia and 91.2 billion euros in prohibited imports from Russia. Ukraine has also counted on financial help and in the weapons of Western allies. Kiev's allies have also decreed sanctions on key key sectors of the Russian economy to try to reduce Moscow's ability to fund Ukraine's war effort. The three -year conflict caused the destruction of important infrastructures in various areas in Ukraine, as well as a number for determining civil and military victims.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 02:25:54</pubDate></item><item><title>China and Cambodia begin the largest joint military exercises of their history</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/china-e-camboja-iniciam-os-maiores-exercicios-militares-conjuntos-da-sua-historia/</link><description>China and Cambodia began yesterday the largest joint military maneuvers ever between the two countries, involving state -of -the -art Chinese military equipment, including artillery, war ships and robotic combat dogs.
About 900 Chinese soldiers and more than 1,300 Cambojan soldiers participate in the exercises, which will extend until May 28, according to a statement from the Khmer Royal Forces (RCAF, Cambodia).
According to the statement, will be presented state -of -the -art Chinese military equipment, including armored vehicles, helicopters, war ships, recognition drones and robotic combat dogs.
The objective is to “develop narrower ties and cooperation” between the two armies. "The exercises are larger than last year in terms of personnel and equipment," RCAF spokesman Thong Solimo told AFP, adding that a Chinese war ship, Chanbai Shan, attracted Ream Cambodian naval base with the equipment.
The ream base in southwest of Cambodia was renewed by China and inaugurated on April 2 by Prime Minister Cambodian Hun Manet and a Chinese military delegation. “China wants to show its muscles” and send the message that “it is a superpower”, through these exercises, nicknamed “Golden Dragon,” argued or Virak, a Cambodian political expert, quoted by the French news agency.
In addition to this demonstration of strength, China must also “give confidence to its partners, telling them that China is growing, developing and becoming stronger, both in terms of dimension and technological progress and military power,” he added or Virak. Cambodia should also receive two China war ships.
Relations between Phnom Penh and Washington have deteriorated in recent years as Beijing's influence has grown through millions of millions of dollars of infrastructure investment.
The first joint military exercises, called “Golden Dragon”, took place in 2016 and, in early 2017, Cambodia ended the “Angkor Sentinel”, a similar joint exercise that had been organized in the previous seven years with US forces.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 02:25:53</pubDate></item><item><title>From the great bay to the Lusophone countries: Rui Cunha Foundation discusses regulatory 'sandboxes'</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/15/da-grande-baia-aos-paises-lusofonos-fundacao-rui-cunha-discute-sandboxes-regulatorias/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation presents today, at 6:30 pm, an open class entitled “Creative Regulatory Environments: Steering the‘ Evolving Sandbox Economy ’From the Greater Bay to the Portuguese-Speaking Geographies”. The session will be conducted in English by guest speaker Sandro Mendonça, a full professor in Macau, Portugal and Italy.
The lecture proposes to explore the concept of “sandbox” or “sandboxes”-that is, controlled experimental innovation zones where new products and technologies are tested in a delimited and safe space, as if it were a children's recreational space. Through this system, it is possible to determine the mode of operation of a particular concept in a regulated and easily adjustable environment, according to different needs and objectives, without implementing it in reality.
As the name of the session indicates, the focus of the conversation extends from the Great Bay area-a region of large pioneering metropolises in techno-institutional innovation-to the Lusophone countries, which only recently begins to take their first steps in these experimental models, especially in the sectors of telecommunications and energy.
The guest speaker, Sandro Mendonça, is a professor at Macao City University and a recurring presence at the Rui Cunha Foundation lectures, and has already discussed topics such as 5G, Artificial Intelligence, and the future of the Big Tech (ie the five world giants Apple, Amazon, Facebook, Google and Microsoft)) and the Chinese Alibaba and Tencent.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 02:25:50</pubDate></item></channel></rss>