<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/03/filipinas-pede-investigacao-ao-desaparecimento-de-34-apostadores-de-lutas-de-galos/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Hospital das Islands attended 10,000 external specialty consultations</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/03/hospital-das-ilhas-atendeu-10-mil-consultas-externas-de-especialidade/</link><description>Law Wai Seng, a subdirector of Hospital das Ilhas, has revealed that the medical institution has provided more than 10,000 care for external specialty consultations, most of which were referred by health services. The hospital is preparing the creation of an assisted procreation center, a dialysis center and an oncology center, and will expand the service of its international medical center with distance learning in the second semester.
 
The Ilhas Hospital is available 47 external consultation services specialized and, since its official entry in operation in September last year, has already accumulated 10,000 calls to the specialties.
According to the hospital, 90% of these attendances were free medical services referred by the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center (CHCSJ), which “helped to divert the patients from CHCSJ,” said Law Wai Seng, the Deputy Care Complex - Macao Medical Center of the Peking Union Medical Hospital.
Law Wai Seng was yesterday at the “Macau Forum”, a morning program of the Chinese channel of Rádio Macau, where he said that the number of care in the specialties of the islands hospital in May increased more than three times compared to January.
The official cited health services information by indicating that, currently, the average waiting time for external consultations in most specialties is less than three weeks, while "only in some specialties can take five to six weeks", "a significant improvement in the waiting time."
For the hospital's short -term development plan, Law Wai Seng admitted that the service of its international medical center in the second half of the year will be expanded. In this case, hospital hospitalization services and special consultation services and distance consultations will be opened through cooperation reinforced with “renowned doctors or renowned hospitals, including Peking Union Medical College”.
This International Medical Center has already established external general consultations, vaccines and neurology, gradually providing medical aesthetic and day -to -day casterscopy.
 
Procreation services
 
Law Wai Seng also said that the institution is working on the creation of an assisted procreation center, a dialysis center and an oncology center.
According to Ku Sio Kuan, head of the medical group of the Assisted Procreation Center, the Islands Hospital began to provide external infertility consultation services in February this year, having attended to 230 couples so far.
Also the obstetrics and gynecology doctor explained that diagnoses and evaluations were made to patients and, for those who do not need to undergo in vitro fertilization, drugs were prescribed and services to monitor ovulation. "Some couples have successfully pregnant and the service got some results," he said.
According to Ku, the couples attended by the hospital have an average age of 37 years and 30% of them over 40 years. "Most have infertility problems due to endometriosis, which can affect the success rate of in vitro fertilization in the future," said the doctor, revealing that the hospital has adjusted the equipment and will start providing artificial insemination services this month. In addition, it expects to make available the in vitro fertilization service and assisted procreation from September this year, and it is also possible to provide egg freezing services in the future.
 
Hired 35 local general doctors
 
Regarding human resources, the hospital has already launched three general physician recruitment rounds, and 35 local professionals were hired, to whom the corresponding training in service will be provided, including clinical teaching by the union medical hospital peking union experts, and further studies at the Union Medical College Hospital in Beijing.
The hospital will also send certain doctors, nurses and clinical technicians to Beijing or other places to receive training. Thus, Law Wai Seng reiterated that the formation of qualified paintings is one of the objectives of the development of the hospital, which is planning to be a “high -level training institution” in Macao.
Regarding the training of medical experts, the hospital has just launched the first edition of the Medical Residency Program, which will form 28 young doctors residents of Macao. The official said that another edition of the program will be opened next year to cultivate a local specialized medical team. The recruitment of nine medical assistants was also opened to absorb local medicine graduates.
 
Operate emergencies
 
The Islands Hospital is also preparing to assume the operation of the Islands Emergency Post from the fourth quarter of this year. The Islands Emergency Post was installed at the University Hospital in Taipa and started to operate on the ground floor of the General Hospital Building of the Island Health Care Complex in late 2023, being operated by the CHCSJ.
Law Wai Seng, however, recalled that emergency services are different from first aid support, stressing that they are not prepared for first aid services as the necessary equipment, personal and systems must be introduced first for a service that requires high conditions.
"However, in case of bad weather and inconvenience of transport between the Macao Peninsula and the islands, the hospital can coordinate with firefighters and medical team sent by CHCSJ to provide limited first aid care," he said.
Law Wai Seng also stressed that, although there are means of transport such as the light meter that can arrive at the hospital, he intended added direct connection transportation services to the needy public, through cooperation with services to traffic matters and non-governmental organizations, in order to respond to increased demand for medical services.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 04:07:30</pubDate></item><item><title>International Art Biennial returns to Macao with a question: “Hello, what do you do here?”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/03/bienal-internacional-de-arte-regressa-a-macau-com-uma-questao-ola-o-que-fazes-aqui/</link><description>Local and international artists again converge in Macau for another edition of “Art Macau”, with the curated by Feng Boyi. Divided into six sections, the “International Cultural and Artistic Mega Event”-as described by the Cultural Institute (IC)-raises questions about the meaning of community concepts, globalization and identity in times of isolation and disunity. The main exhibition will be inaugurated on July 19, extending until October.
 
The “Macao Art: Macau International Art Biennial 2025” was presented yesterday in the conference room of the Macao Cultural Center. From the question “Hello, what do you do here?”, This year's edition aims to start a transfronic aesthetic dialogue, using artistic creation as a connection bridge between different cultures, civilizations and geographical points in an era marked by unknowns and challenges.
From July 19, the public will be able to contemplate about thirty exhibitions from artists from more than a dozen countries and regions, divided into six thematic sections: the main exhibition, the public art exhibition, the city's pavilion, the special exhibition, the local curator project and the collateral exhibition. "Between summer and fall, Macau will become a city of inspiration where life and art are in line," says the Cultural Institute (IC), describing the event as "an emotional aesthetic trip through the city's urban landscape."
At the local level, the local curatorship exhibition - for which six proposals of indigenous artists were selected, two more than usual - and the collateral exhibition - composed of works related to the city's creative panorama - will continue to “show the world the vibrant creativity of Macao artists,” as Leon Wai Man, the President of the IC, said at yesterday's press conference. In total, the number of local artists is about 27%, a number “comparatively higher than previous editions”.
On the other hand, Macao Statute as East Asia Cultural City in 2025 - a title acquired last June, during the 15th Conference of Ministers of Culture of China, Japan and South Korea - requires greater contact with the “Global Art Network” and greater inclusion of foreign works of art. Leon Wai Man gives as an example the installation of public art “The Tower of Time”, established together by three artists from the interior of China, Japan and South Korea, which will remain in the square of the Macao Cultural Center until December. "[This installation] wants to leave a friendship in the cultural cities of East Asia in Macao and further promote the city as a base of exchange and cooperation for the promotion of multicultural coexistence."
The initiative will cost 4.5 million patacas for the government, also with the participation of the six game dealers. "Its verified and exquisite artistic sense and generous investment of resources fully demonstrate their corporate social responsibility, making this year's event even more stunning and glamorous," emphasizes the president of the IC.
 
“Hello, what do you do here?”: A question as a starting point
 
Feng Boyi is the main curator of “Art Macau 2025”, which also has the co-cursor of Liu Gang and Wu Wei. Making use of the word, Beijing's researcher and art critic justified yesterday morning the relevance of the question that gives the project.
Although it has never been so accessible to travel to distant land, the geopolitical changes that take place globally, such as the “advance of conservatism, nationalism and populism”, promote a limited and “stagnant” perspective of the world. Artificial intelligence and trade war between the United States of America and China were others mentioned by Feng Boyi to regret “segregation and alienation” of societies and, by extension, the art they produce.
“Contemporary art is also stranded in unprecedented double challenges and dilemmas, making the need for new discoveries and new ways shared for even more urgent development,” reads IC informative yesterday at the press conference. "This concept of curatorship centered on issues is therefore a way of exploring issues in a proactive and artistic manner, manifesting self-criticism, choices and expressions in the exploitation of meaning, value and responsibility of life."
 
Local and international art, spread throughout the city
 
The Biennial starts on July 19 with the first of the six sections defined by the IC: the main exhibition, which will be on display for three months at the Macao Art Museum. In this module, the public is invited to apply the “great interactive question” to themselves and to embark on a self-discovery trip through the questions: “Who am I? Where do I come from? Where do I go?”.
The main exhibition brings together works elaborated with varied techniques, from painting to photography, signed by 46 artists from 13 countries: Germany, China (including Macau, Hong Kong and Taiwan), South Korea, the United States, India, Iran, Japan, Mexico, the Netherlands, Poland, Portugal and Singapore. "The exhibition will present a perspective of global visual art, allowing visitors to feel and experience various cultures of the world, and from Macao, in the various spaces of the exhibition," describes the CI.
“Space Management” is one of the great highlights this year, as Feng Boyi highlighted in the program's presentation. The exhibition of public art “waves of paths” comes to demonstrate how art is embarrassed in the mosaic of the daily life of the city and the circular movements of passers-by and coming, becoming collectively into physical, emotional and spiritual “tides” that, in their cyclic and interconnected pace, symbolizes “the symbiotic relationship constantly intertwined between public art, the public and the communities.”
According to the IC description, interactive and multi-sensory facilities allow works of art to become “bridges of connection between people and between people and the city, arousing the resonance and dialogue of life” and “remodeling the connotations and limits of public space”. In this section, works by international artists such as James Binning (United Kingdom), Ann Hamilton (United States) and Jason Ho (Australia) will be presented.
In this year's edition of the usual category “Pavilion of the City”, Macao Art presents only two pavilions: one relative to Portugal and one relative to the city of Jinan, curated by the general consulate of Portugal in Macao and the Jinan Museum of Art, respectively.
The exhibitions, which will be patent in the Tap Seac Art Gallery, have obvious differentiating points, due to the idiosyncratic history of each country: the Jinan Pavilion focuses on Qi-L-Lu Cultural Heritage, with 2,700 years of history, while Portugal's shows how a small town can close in its modest borders a huge history and vitality. Still, the IC highlights the similarities between the two projects: “[both focus] in the tension between tradition and innovation and the humanistic charm shown in the multiple cultures dialogue, reflecting Macao's platform value as the 'Center for Cultural Exchange between China and Portugal'”.
The local curatorship project and collateral exposure are totally centered on Macau, although they have differences that individualize them. The first makes known the “local artistic achievements” through six works carefully selected by the relevance and quality of the themes. Following the presentation at “Art Macau 2025”, the artists will be directly qualified for the preliminary selection for the 61st International Art Exhibition La Biennale di Venezia - Macao collateral event, China. The IC will then create a new jury with the task of selecting a single job to represent Macau in Italy in 2026.
The collateral exposure results from an invitation by IC to local individuals and organizations connected to the arts, "with the aim of making known the creative contemporary landscape of the city and raising the image of local arts at the international level." The nine projects chosen will be distributed to various parts of the city, from artistic spaces to universities.
 
Six dealers, six artistic projects
 
As part of the special exhibition, each of the six game dealers will present - and welcome in its facilities - a specific artistic project. Galaxy Macau chose to mark the career of interior designer Bruno Moard, presenting a collection of over 300 paintings, sketches and design manuscripts signed by the French. In this exhibition, there are a series of concepts created by Parisian company Moinard Betaille to the Hotel Capella, integrated in Galaxy, scheduled for this year.
Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, in turn, will collaborate with the Haas brothers in the “Clair de Lune” series, inspired by the artists 'Moontowers' Moonontowers in Texas. Guided by this nostalgic evocation, the artists “reinterpret the moonlight as a medium” and form a space where “the heart overflows with innocence and“ humanity coexists harmoniously with time and space ”.
MGM opts for a more futuristic approach, with the exhibition “Cai ™ ​​Lab 2.0 - is your look that finds mine, or mine that looks for yours?”. The artist falls Guo-Qiang-whose project Cai ™: Soul Scan was recently on display in Macau-returns to the territory with the Artificial Intelligence (AI) model that has been developing since 2017, where interaction with the public is essential for the creation of artwork. According to the IC, "the exhibition combines state -of -the -art technology with spirituality, presenting a constantly evolving multidimensional artistic world, similar to a laboratory."
Sands brings together eight “prestigious contemporary artists” from Asia, Europe and America for an unusual fusion of two seemingly distinct worlds: “the eternal beauty of Roman mythology” with the characters in the children's series “Rua Sesamo”. Titled “dopamine: source of happiness”, the project thus proposes to discover the “formula of happiness” pure and infiltrated, acting as a dose of dopamine at the audience that visits it.
This is followed by SJM Resorts with “Picasso: Beauty and Drama”, a world debut that brings together 143 engravings, ceramics and illustrations from Casa Natal Picasso Museo. From childhood in Malaga to inscription on the annals of world art history, the exhibition "explores revolutionary art and evolution" of the work of one of the most unquestionable names of the twentieth century, "through the forms, figures and images that define it."
Finally, Wynn Resorts Macao presents “The Odyssey of the Jingdezen Porcelain: a Macao's heritage trip to the world,” reconciling innovation and tradition by resorting to 4K Ultra HD projections to bring the Chinese porcelain of the Qing dynasty. "By creating new structures for intercultural understanding through digital mediation, the exhibition reaffirms the lasting role of Macao as a cultural bridge, while providing the global audience a new perspective on the tradition of Chinese porcelain."
“Arte Macau” is a cultural and artistic event that aims to promote the development of contemporary art in Macau, as well as the presentation of artistic creations from the territory to the international community. The event is organized by the IC and co-organized by the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), under the patronage of the Secretariat for Social Affairs and Culture of the Government of MSAR. The full schedule can be consulted on the official page at https://www.artmacao.mo/2025/en.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Transfers from Portugal to Macau grew 21% last year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/03/transferencias-de-portugal-para-macau-cresceram-21-no-ano-passado/</link><description>In 2024, 336 million euros from Portugal to Macau were transferred, representing a 21% jump compared to the previous year. Macau is currently in fourth place in the ranking of jurisdictions where they follow more flows of Portuguese capital. The data were released yesterday by the Portugal Tax Authority in the report on transfers to 'offshores' and tax havens.
 
Last year, the transfers from Portugal to Macau ascended at 336 million euros, 21% more than the 294 million recorded in 2023.
The updated data on transfers to offshores and tax havens were made available yesterday on the Portuguese Tax Authority page.
Of the total transfers Portugal-Macau made last year, 46 million came from accounts of non-residents in Portuguese territory. The remaining 309 million euros came from residents in Portugal.
For Portugal, Macao is part of the list of territories considered tax havens, ie territories and regions with privileged and clearly more favorable tax regimes, which comprising more than 80 jurisdictions that have financial centers where taxation of IRS or IRC is especially low or null, or that are considered non -cooperative countries for tax purposes.
Hong Kong is also part of this list. The neighboring region is, by the way, the second jurisdiction where it followed the largest amount from Portugal: almost 1.6 billion euros. In 2023, Raehk received about 1.2 billion euros from Portugal.
Switzerland remains in the first place on the list, having received in 2024 transfers from Portugal in the amount of 3.2 billion euros. The United Arab Emirates are third with 762 million.
In all, 131,000 transfers were held last year by 17,289 customers with bank accounts in financial institutions in Portugal. According to data from the Tax Authority, on average, each ordinant sent 467,300 euros to a privileged financial tax center.
The amount of transfers realized over 2024 is higher than in any of the previous four years. In 2021, the amount transferred was 6,698.9 million euros, by 2022 increased to 7,409.7 million euros, by 2023 dropped to 6,925.5 million and now grew again to 8,078.6 million euros. Both the number of customers and the number of operations have been the highest since 2021.
It is recalled that banks are required to communicate to the Tax Authority every year how much each client transfers to financial centers with a privileged tax regime when the amount sent annually is greater than 12,500 euros, and from these communications that the Tax Authority compiles these amounts for the purpose of combating fraud and tax evasion.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 04:09:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Vincent U on FDCT and Che Weng Keong on Ipim</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/03/vincent-u-no-fdct-e-che-weng-keong-no-ipim/</link><description>Vincent U, so far responsible for the Institute for Commerce and Investment Promotion (IPIM), and Che Weng Keong, who held the position of Chairman of the Board of Directors of the Fund for the Development of Sciences and Technology (FDCT), exchanged stations. Vincent U took office yesterday as president of the FDCT Administrative Board, while Che Weng Keong took office as chairman of the IPIM Administrative Board.
Tai Kin IP, Secretary for Economics and Finance, stated, at the inauguration ceremony, that the area that protects “proactively promotes works in a multifaceted manner, stressing that technology, as a nuclear element of economic development, is an essential dynamic for socioeconomic development”.
Quoted in the statement, the secretary stated that “reinforcing the articulation between technological innovation and emerging industries allows to foster the improvement of the quality of the sector”, adding that this change should enable “the promotion of the effects of converction in the in-depth integration between scientific-technological development and the capture of investments, enhancing the vast experience and professional competence of the two leaders to generate a synergistic effect, and Adopting innovative ideas to promote scientific-technological development and investment capture to reinforce the benefits to society. ”
At the time, Che Weng Keong promised to "enhance his professional experience to lead all IPIM colleagues to work together and cooperate closely with the organisms of the economy and finance." Vincent U has ensured that it will “combine experience in investment capture, conventions and exhibitions and the Sino-Delusophone platform, promoting the connection between research and technological development and commercial application”.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 04:10:34</pubDate></item><item><title>IMF predicts 3.9% economic growth for this year in Timor-Leste</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/03/fmi-preve-crescimento-economico-de-39-para-este-ano-em-timor-leste/</link><description>The International Monetary Fund (IMF) said yesterday that it provides for an economic growth of 3.9% for this year in Timor-Leste and insisted that the government should give priority to quality expenses in the infrastructure, health and education sectors.
 
"Growth is expected to remain robust, being 3.9% in 2025, supported by fiscal expansion and strong credit growth, with a slowdown to 3.3% in 2026," Carrière-Swallow said, who led the IMF team, which ended a visit to the country yesterday.
The team arrived in the country on June 19 to make discussions under Article IV of 2025. "Inflation, which had fallen sharply last year due to the descent of global food and energy prices, should moderately increase by rising international food prices," said Carrière-Swallow.
The IMF predicts that inflation is 0.9% this year and increases to 1.8% in 2026.
The financial organization, which held meetings with the Timorese authorities, private sector, development partners and civil society, also considers that the state budget for 2026 should give priority to “quality expenses in the areas of physical infrastructure and human capital, including health and education, while controlling recurring spending”. "The government is rightly focused on identifying measures to contain the public sector salary, which has grown markedly in recent years, and the implementation of an added value tax (VAT) from January 2027," says Carrière-Swallow.
The IMF recommends structural and budgetary reforms for 10 years to allow the Timorese government to support the development of the private sector through the gradual reduction of budgetary deficits to preserve debt sustainability. "By 2026, the reforms we propose would be compatible with an expense envelope of about $ 1.85 billion [about $ 1.5 billion] to the central government," read the statement.
In the statement, the IMF congratulates the government for “continuous progress in financial sector reforms” at the level of legislation, “whose implementation will support the development of the private sector”. "We also recommend accelerating the issuance of ownership securities and establishing a national digital identification system, crucial reforms to improve access to credit, diversify the private sector and increase the efficiency of public expense," adds the IMF.
The Timorese Government set this week the expense for the general budget of the state of 2026 by $ 1.85 billion (about 1.58 billion euros), a significant reduction compared to that of 2025. Lusa.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 04:10:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Economists advocate for use of stablecoins by China to reinforce Yuan's global role</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/03/economistas-defendem-uso-de-stablecoins-pela-china-para-reforcar-papel-global-do-yuan/</link><description>Economists and political counselors in China have been advocating the use of stable cryptocurrencies indexed to fiduciary currencies in cross -border payments, at a time when the United States seeks to reinforce dollar supremacy through this technology.
 
Despite maintaining a general prohibition on activities with cryptocurrencies, responsible from Banco Popular da China (Central Bank) have recently recognized the potential of stablecoins - digital active indexed to traditional currencies - in the global financial system, reviving the debate around its adoption.
During a Financial Forum in Shanghai in June, Central Bank governor Pan Gongsheng stated that stablecoins can revolutionize international finances, especially in a context of growing geopolitical tensions that show the vulnerability of traditional payment systems, often used as sanction instruments.
At the same time, former Governor Zhou Xiaochuan warned that 'Stablecoins' indexed to the dollar may foster dependence on the US currency, while other officials from Chinese continent and Hong Kong financial institutions suggested that Yuan versions could reinforce China's efforts to internationalize their coin.
Although Beijing continues to face cryptocurrencies as a threat to financial stability and capital control, several economists consider that there is now a strategic opportunity.
Quoted by Bloomberg news agency, investment bank chief economist Morgan Stanley in China, Robin Xing, argued that “Stablecoins' are not new currencies but new distribution channels, appealing to Yuan's indexing to a cryptocurrency as a way to maintain digital competitiveness.
The Senate of the United States has already passed legislation to regulate the stablecoins, in a victory for the crypto sector and for the US President Donald Trump's digital asset agenda. US Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent said the stablecoins may reinforce-not threaten-the dominant position of the dollar.
Morgan Stanley and other analysts suggest that China could resort to Hong Kong to develop 'stablecoins' on Yuan outside the continental territory, surrounding internal restrictions. Companies such as JD.com and ANT Group have already expressed intent on requesting licenses in the new regulatory table released by Hong Kong, which allows stablecoins emissions referenced in fiduciary currencies.
JD.com estimates that using these currencies can reduce international payment costs by 90% and settlement deadlines to less than 10 seconds. Zhejiang China Commodities City Group, operator of the world's largest grou's market, also plans to get license to issue 'Stablecoins'.
Analysts point out that these digital currencies can help Beijing capitalize the growing global discomfort with the dominance of the dollar, especially after the sanctions and freezing of actives imposed on Moscow following the Russian invasion of Ukraine.
In February, more than 30% of China's trade was settled in Yuan - the highest value of the last decade.
For Li Yang, president of the National Institute of Finance and Development, China should adopt an “two -front” approach: maintaining Yuan's traditional internationalization efforts - such as the Cambial Swap agreements and the CIPS liquidation system - and explore 'StableCoins' in Yuan through Hong Kong.
However, analysts warn that these initiatives may face limitations if they are not accompanied by broader economic reforms. According to Eswar Prasad, professor at Cornell University, the effectiveness of Chinese 'stablecoins' will depend on the unification of internal and external foreign exchange markets. Still, its adoption can serve as an incentive for advances towards financial liberalization. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 04:10:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Intangible Cultural Heritage: Public Consultation approves Folk Dance and Making Care</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/03/patrimonio-cultural-intangivel-consulta-publica-aprova-danca-folclorica-e-confeccao-de-pasteis-de-nata/</link><description>In November last year, the Cultural Institute (IC) presented a list of 12 items recommended to be integrated into the list of intangible cultural heritage, which included, for example, the Portuguese folk dance and the making of cream pastels. This list was subject to a public consultation, whose results, revealed now, show that the large majority of participants support the integration of these cultural manifestations into the list.
 
The public consultation for the 12 cultural manifestations proposed by the Cultural Institute (IC) to be integrated into the list of intangible cultural heritage gathered the approval of the generality of the participants. The list of items included demonstrations such as the Portuguese folk dance and the making of cream pastels, for example.
The public consultation was held between December 4, 2024 and January 2 this year, with 931 opinions. In the analysis of the opinions collected, released on Tuesday night, it appears that all 12 recommended items obtained more than 70% agreement, “indicating broad social support”, points out the IC.
Among the cultural manifestations recommended by the authorities, those who gathered the most favorable opinions were the belief and customs of Tou Tei, with a 94.5%approval rate, the dragon dance, with 93%, and the lion dance, also 93%. The lowest acceptance rate was the making of traditional Chinese wedding cakes, with 68.4% of favorable opinions.
The Portuguese folk dance achieved 83.8% of votes in favor and 16.2% against. The making of cream pastries obtained green light with 72.1% of favorable votes and 27.9% against.
The other approved cultural manifestations were the Spring Festival, the Dragon Boat Festival, the Tai Chi martial arts race, the making of almond cookies and the making of Jook-Sing pasta.
In the public consultation report, the IC also says that the public "provided many valuable additional opinions about the preservation work of intangible cultural heritage in Macao." These opinions also reflect comments and suggestions on the protection work of intangible heritage, hoping to attract more young people to the group of transmitters of this type of heritage, suggesting the promotion of Macao's traditional culture projects through multiple channels and ways to increase their notoriety and influence. ”
It is expected to be possible to include more characteristic and cultural content with intangible heritage and pay more attention to the criteria of recognition and issues of the transmission of traditional techniques of the transmitting groups of intangible cultural heritage projects ”, reads in the consultation report.
Now, the IC will advance with the work to register the 12 cultural manifestations in the list of intangible cultural heritage.
 
 
The 12 approved cultural manifestations:
 
 
 
TOUS BEET AND CUSTOMS
 
This belief is based on the “faith of the ancient Chinese that all things have spirit, as well as in their dependence, proximity and reverence for the earth,” explains the IC. In Macao, these customs have a large number of followers and are currently about ten temples dedicated exclusively to the god of the earth in the territory.
 
 
Dragon Dance
 
Dragon dance “has become an important activity performed during fairs related to traditional temples and festivals, especially in order to ask for protection and safety, as well as to provide an environment of good augurium and joy”, details the IC.
 
 
Lion dance
 
The Lion Dance is “a performative art that integrates martial arts, dance and music”. The Lion Dance has been transmitted and developed by civil sports associations, being held classes of interest on the art of lion dance among the community, to promote knowledge and culture on this dance, especially among young people, notes the IC.
 
 
Portuguese folk dance
 
The IC says that in the early 1970s and 80s of the last century, Portuguese folk dance became more popular and also developed in activities from other local communities. The dance “continually acquired Macao characteristics, and currently involves artists from the Portuguese, Macanese, Chinese communities, among others”, stress the authorities, who add that this manifestation “reflects the value of Macao multiculturality”.
 
 
Spring Festival
 
The Spring Festival representatively concentrates “the essence of traditional Chinese culture”. The CI adds that "the Spring Festival, being the most grand, significant and important festival of the year in Macao, is an important manifestation of the permanence and development of traditional Chinese culture in Macao."
 
 
Dragon boat festival
 
Tung NG, a dragon boat festival, is “a folkloric festival whose function is to bring reverence to ancestors, perform the worship of deities to ward off evil spirits and diseases, as well as to make prayers of blessing and protection against evil spirits”. These celebrations have “a long history” in Macao, continuing to be transmitted and taught.
 
 
Dragon boat tank top
 
The dragon boat tank top is a practice that is part of the festival with the same name. “As one of Macao's sporting events with a relatively significant scale and with an especially relevant social impact, the dragon boat tank top is an important representation of the transmission and continuity of traditional Chinese culture in the territory,” says the IC.
 
 
Tai chi
 
Tai Chi martial arts are a traditional martial art characterized by circular movements performed in a relaxed way. Tai Chi arrived in Macau in the early twentieth century and, according to the IC, since the 1980s that interest in this martial art in the region has increased significantly.
 
 
Cream pastels
 
The IC also wants to include in the list of intangible cultural heritage to make local cream pastries, which evolved from the Portuguese. "Macao cream pastels are very popular, having become emblematic sweet. Currently, the stores and restaurants that make and sell cream pastels are spread throughout the city," the body points out, adding that "this local intangible heritage manifestation can be considered as an important bridge of macao gastronomic culture to the world, having great cultural reference."
 
 
Almond cookies
 
Almond cookies are "an emblematic delicacy of Macao and an appreciated memory," which makes them "increasingly popular, both in Macao and internationally." "In recent years, the combination of traditional methods with modern techniques, both in quantity and quality and in variety of flavors, has consolidated almond cookies as a symbol of the gastronomic culture of Macao."
 
 
Wedding cakes
 
Chinese traditional wedding cakes maintain the components of traditional Chinese marriage and remain well preserved, and traditional Chinese wedding cakes remain one of the most sophisticated elements of the essential and basic marriages of the population of Macao. ”
 
 
Jook-Sing pasta
 
The Jook-Sing masses “are a characteristic mass food of Macau and a gastronomic element much appreciated by tourists, whose confection technique is its essence and represents the traditional mode of making masses of Macao, being of an important historical, cultural and significant economic value for the study of mass consumption culture and guangdong culinary culture, Hong Kong and Macao”.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 04:08:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Launched public tender for the start of the construction of the Jardim Sports in the Canidrome</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/03/lancado-concurso-publico-para-inicio-da-construcao-do-jardim-desportivo-no-canidromo/</link><description>The government published yesterday in the official bulletin, the announcement related to the opening of the public tender for the construction of the Sports Garden for citizens in the lot of the former Galgos Company - Zone 1. The contest stipulates that this first phase of the project will have a maximum global deadline for the execution of the work of 1,014 days, ie, near four years.
The contest does not stipulate a base price, even if the companies interested in the competition have to pay a provisional deposit of 28.5 million patacas.
The most important criterion in the assessment of proposals is the price of the contract, with a 50% weight in the decision, then the execution period and the experience and quality in society, with 20% each, and finally the execution program, with 10%.
The project was presented by the government in May last year and includes the construction of four pavilions, one of which at the center of the lot, with four floors, with two pools, including one for children, a basketball field, a running track and children's bike path, among others.
Pavilion No. 2 will be in the north of the lot and has six floors tall, with a skatepark and table tennis fields, wall climbing, volleyball and Badminton, among others. Pavilion No. 3 located next to Pavilion No. 2 is 5 floors tall, and is expected to be equipped with a soccer field for 5 people, two-story multipurpose room, multi-functional activities and outdoor activities.
The future sports garden for citizens also has a children's pavilion, where an outdoor activities zone for children, children's playground, creative classroom and reading zone is planned, among others. The respective basement will be intended for the activities room and storage space, among other spaces with more reinforced functionality.
In addition to the pavilions, there will also be an outdoor athletics field, which is located in the east of Pavilion No. 1, and the basement will be for a public parking park on a floor, with about 490 parking spaces for light vehicles and motorcycles.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 04:06:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong Central Bank intervenes to defend local currency parity over the dollar</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/03/banco-central-de-hong-kong-intervem-para-defender-paridade-da-moeda-local-face-ao-dolar/</link><description>Hong Kong's monetary authority (HKMA), the territory's factory central bank, intensified the market interventions to defend the currency parity of the Hong Kong dollar compared to the US dollar at a time of strong volatility. HKMA bought $ 20.02 billion from Hong Kong (about 2.2 billion euros) from the local currency, after signs that it had touched the lower limit of the allowed trading band during transactions in New York. This is more than double the amount purchased the previous week ($ 9.42 billion from Hong Kong).
The Hong Kong coin has recorded strong fluctuations in recent months, moving among the extremes of its negotiating band. For the first time since the implementation of the current currency regime in 2005, the authorities were forced to intervene to defend both the band's limits in the same year. These fluctuations renew the debate on the sustainability of the currency parity regime, although there is no immediate evidence of changes. Analysts have discussed the possibility of widening the negotiation band through Hong Kong (HKD) dollar indexing to Yuan or even allowing their free float.
In May, a strong devaluation of the US dollar led to a marked demand for the Hong Kong dollar, forcing HKMA to inject liquidity into the financial system to lock the coin appreciation, which threatened the band's upper limit (7.75 per dollar). The operation eventually caused a sharp reverse movement, pushing the currency to the lower limit of the band (7.85 per dollar).
Despite the new intervention this week, the aggregate balance of the financial system - one of the main components of the Hong Kong monetary base - is expected to fall only to 144.2 billion HKD (15.5 billion euros), maintaining widely market liquidity and reduced local financing costs. This also makes the so-called Carry Trade strategy, where investors contract cheap Hong Kong loans to invest in US dollars' assets with higher income. Analysts warn that the local currency may therefore soon test the lower limit of the band. "It may take time until liquidity conditions are normalized. The intervention will continue as long as high levels of liquidity persist," said Andy Ji, Stratega of Intouch Capital Markets, quoted by Bloomberg.
All attention is now focused on Hong Kong's interbank rates, known as Hibor, which remain low despite HKMA liquidity drainage. The difference between the Hibor rate to one month and its US equivalent remained close to historical maxims earlier this week. The Hong Kong dollar registered little variation yesterday, being negotiated at 7,8497 per US dollar. The Macao Pataca (MOP) is officially indexed to the dollar of Hong Kong. The exchange rate is 103.2mop to 100hkd, with a fluctuation band that can go to 10%.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 04:10:33</pubDate></item><item><title>The theater of the body in the images of Maria João Pereira on display at Creative Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/03/o-teatro-do-corpo-nas-imagens-de-maria-joao-pereira-em-exposicao-na-creative-macau/</link><description>In a world where the body becomes the scene of multiple stories and memories, Maria João Pereira invites us to look inside through her imagery, which transforms the private public. The exhibition “My Body” debuts next Thursday, July 10, at Creative Macao space, featuring 42 photographs created between 2019 and 2024. With an approach that mixes fiction and reality, the show invites the public to reflect on identity, memory and relationship with body, in an innovative and affordable artistic experience until August 2.
 
Next Thursday, July 10, the Creative Macau gallery hosts the inauguration of a show that proposes an unconventional perspective on the body and the memory it carries. This is the “My Body” photography exhibition, a creation of artist and actress Maria João Pereira, organized by the Cultural Association of Enga Macau in partnership with Creative Macau-Center for Creative Industries. With a selection of 42 images captured between 2019 and 2024, the exhibition presents an intimate and deep reflection on the representation of the body in the private space of the home, exploring the multiple facets of the self through a photographic language that mixes some fiction and reality through self -portraits.
The photographs, held with a Samsung Galaxy S20 Ultra mobile phone, constitute a visual narrative proposal that questions the present, memory and identity. The artist invites the audience to a performative trip between the four lines of an image. An introspective exploration where photographs act as an imagined stage, a kind of body theater through the lens. The author herself will be present at the inauguration, where she will perform a live action. A performance entitled “After 5 O'Clock Tea”, directed by Ricardo Moura, who aims to reinforce the project's performance and experimental dimension. This artistic encounter aims to create a liaison bridge between what is seen in the exhibition and what is lived in real time, in an engaging experience for those present during the opening.
Maria João Pereira, with a vast experience in theatrical representation, graduated from Chapitô-School of Arts and Crafts in Lisbon, having collaborated with several relief staff in the Portuguese scenario, such as José Wallenstein and João Brites. Since 1999, which is part of Companhia d'As Endas, participating in multiple shows that cross theater, performance and multidisciplinary arts. Its artistic practice is marked by an approach that crosses different artistic languages, one of them being photography, where it has also presented another exhibition entitled “My Phone Took a Picture”.
Its multidisciplinarity is reflected in this new show, which combines visual and performative elements in a proposal of self-reflection and questioning of the body in contemporary times. At a time when the boundaries between fiction and reality become increasingly diffuse, the “My Body” exhibition is therefore an opportunity for Macau visitors to explore new languages ​​and confront issues that touch the essence of being, in a space of dialogue and artistic discovery. The curatorship of the project was in charge of Vera Paz, director of the Cultural Association of As Endas Macau, responsible for the recent theatrical project “Home Sweet Home”, a play presented at the Cultural Center in partnership with Ricardo Moura.
The exhibition “My Body” will be open to the public until August 2, at Creative Macao space, where it can be visited from Monday to Saturday, between 14h and 19h, with free admission. The initiative is part of the program of the Macao Cultural Center, with the support of the Culture Development Fund.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Leong Weng In, former DSAJ leader, took office as director of SAFP</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/03/leong-weng-in-antiga-lider-da-dsaj-tomou-posse-como-directora-dos-safp/</link><description>Leong Weng In, who was so far the head of the Director of Justice Affairs Services (DSAJ), took office yesterday as director of administration and public service services (SAFP). Chan Sok Cheng also took office as a subdirector of the body. The order of the appointment, published yesterday in an official bulletin, is valid for a period of two years.
The inauguration ceremony was chaired by André Cheong, secretary for administration and justice, who said at the time that, in recent years, SAFP have done “numerous works in promoting the development of electronic governance and the reform of public administration, a result that depended on the joint efforts of all colleagues”. The ruler asked the new SAFP directors to continue "committed to uniting colleagues and better realize the work of the governmental action."
Leong Weng In highlighted in his speech that SAFPs assume a “fundamental responsibility in the reform of the Public Administration of the MSAR” and, in the face of the new position, will “make the most of their experience gained during the professional exercise in the legal area, working together with the team with a pragmatic spirit and meaning of responsibility, and striving to perform all tasks inherent in the deepening of public administration reform”.
Leong Weng In is a law degree from the University of Macao and has the bachelor's degree in Chinese-Portuguese translation and interpretation at the Macao Polytechnic Institute. He entered the civil service in 2005 and performed his duties as a higher technique of the legal area, head of the 2nd Division of Legislative Production, Head of the Department of Study of the Legal System and Legislative Coordination, as well as the position of subdirector of DSAJ. Since May 2023 has been holding the position of director of DSAJ.
Chan Sok Cheng has a degree and master in social sciences from the University of Macao and joined the civil service in 2003, having performed as a higher technique, head of the division of organizational performance and head of the Department of ORGANIZATIONAL PERFORMANCE AND OPERATION OF SAFP. Since February 2025, he has been holding the position of subdirect, SAFP substitute.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 04:10:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Pr Timorense devalues ​​Myanmar's position against Timor-Leste's adhesion to Asean</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/03/pr-timorense-desvaloriza-posicao-do-myanmar-contra-adesao-de-timor-leste-a-asean/</link><description>Timor-Leste President José Ramos-Horta yesterday devalued the position of Myanmar, who claimed to be against the full adhesion of Timor-Leste to the Association of Southeast Asia Nations (Asean), scheduled for October.
"A decision [was] made in summit by heads of state, there will be no other than to change that decision. (…) Myanmar participates in the level of chief of head of state, nor at the ministerial level, as a sanction applied by Asean herself following the 2021 coup," said the president. “It doesn't make the slightest difference,” added José Ramos-Horta in a meeting with journalists in the Timorese Presidency in Dili, when asked about Myanmar's position.
News yesterday released in various Asian media organs indicate that Myanmar sent a letter to the Malaysian presidency of the organization to manifest that does not support the adhesion of Timor-Leste, because "it does not adhere to the principle of non-interference in internal matters enshrined in the Asean letter."
Following the coup d'état of February 1, 2021, Myanmar was sanctioned and does not participate in the summits of heads of state and government, nor in ministerial meetings.
ASEAN leaders approved in April 2021 a five -point consensus for the Military Junta in Power in Myanmar to apply, but to this day has not been realized.
The full adhesion of Timor-Leste to Asean will take place at the headquarters of heads and government to be held in October in Malaysia, which assumes the rotating presidency of the Asian organization.
The Member States of ASEAN arrived at an agreement of principle in November 2022 to integrate Timor-Leste in the regional organization, becoming the country to have the status of observer and being able to attend all meetings, including in the summits.
ASEAN was created in 1967 by Indonesia, Singapore, Thailand, Malaysia and Philippines and aims to promote cooperation between Member States to ensure peace, stability and economic, social and cultural development of the region. Brunei Darussalam, Cambodia, Laos, Myanmar and Vietnam are also part of ASEAN.</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 04:10:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines asks for investigation to the disappearance of 34 roin fight gammers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/03/filipinas-pede-investigacao-ao-desaparecimento-de-34-apostadores-de-lutas-de-galos/</link><description>The Philippine Authorities want an “exhaustive investigation” to the disappearance in 2021 of 34 men linked to bets on rooster fights after a witness claimed to have been murdered. The case of the "sabunges", as the enthusiasts of the galle struggles in the Philippines are known, dates back to 2021.
 
The Philippine Authorities yesterday requested an “exhaustive investigation” from the disappearance in 2021 of 34 men linked to bets on rooster struggles, after a witness claimed to have been murdered with police complicity. "A complete investigation should be done to find out who is really involved in this and blame them," said Presidential spokesman Claire Castro at a press conference yesterday.
The appeal made through the office of Filipino President Ferdinand Marcos Jr. joins other recent statements by Asian country officials about the controversial case.
Police spokesman Jean Fajardo stated a week ago that investigators will "save no one" who find out that he has been involved in disappearances, "whether civilian, high-level authorities or even our colleagues."
The case of the "sabunges", as the enthusiasts of the galle struggles in the Philippines are known, dates back to 2021.
In just one year, at least 34 people linked to rooster fights and profitable online bets on combat, very popular in the Philippines.
These bets, known as 'E-Sabong', grew substantially at the time of COVID-19, but then President Rodrigo Duterte banned them in 2022, following various accusations of rooster manipulation and concerns about addiction and debt.
Family members and activists have claimed, for years, that the 'sabunges' have been kidnapped and killed because of rivalries, in a world that moves millions of Philippine weights, and have repeatedly expressed frustration with the lack of progress of the investigation authorities.
These disappearances were again at the center of attention last month, after a man identified only as Totoy told Radio Filipina GMA that the 34 men were murdered and later thrown into the lake surrounding the Taal volcano with the complicity of the police. “How can they be alive if they were thrown into Taal Lake?” Asked Totoy, identified by GMA as one of those investigated by the disappearances.
These accusations show the magnitude of the problem around this lucrative and now illegal online business: in 2021 alone, the state raised about 8 billion Philippines (144.42 million euros) thanks to bets on rooster fights. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-03 04:10:36</pubDate></item></channel></rss>