<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/14/tufao-podul-obriga-ao-cancelamento-de-varios-voos/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Cinemateca Paixão transforms the movie theater into a “sensory amusement park”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/14/cinemateca-paixao-transforma-a-sala-de-cinema-num-parque-de-diversoes-sensoriais/</link><description>Taking as a reference the multiple senses and sensations of the human being, Cinematic Passion presents a new program that aims to turn the movie theater “into a sensory amusement park”. The works chosen for "Daydreams &amp; Labirintos-Fantastic Film Festival" contemplate from timeless classics, such as "The Texas Chain Saw Massacre", to short films and feature films released this year, of which is the recent "Dangerous Animals".
 
Cinemateca Paixão will present a new theme program between August 16 and September 7, entitled “Daydreams &amp; Labirintos - Fantastic Film Festival”. According to the organization, the initiative aims to transform the space “into a sensory amusement park for the public during the summer holidays”, bringing together more than 20 productions of various genres with one common point: the study of the diversity of human desires and emotions.
The programming is divided into six main sections, regarding each of the five senses-and an additional “sixth sense”, defined as thought.
VISION
The first section, "Desire of Vision", begins this Saturday, the 16th, with a 4K version of "The Fall", a 2006 movie made by Tarsem Singh that combines elements of fantasy and adventure, with the backdrop of the early twentieth century in Los Angeles.
The next session included in this category is scheduled for the 24th and consists, more specifically, in three short films: “Romu-Mattila and a Beautiful Woman” (2012), “The Moonshiners” (2017) and “A Planet Far Away” (2023). Known as a whole as “the silent trilogy”, the works written and carried out by Finnish Juho Kuosmanen act as a tribute to silent cinema, where the absence of sound is offset by vivid expressions and visual symbolism.
The 26th is totally dedicated to eight short films that together last approximately 97 minutes. The Cinematic Passion Choices are the Scottish movie “Matta and Matto” (2023), the Hungarian “Children of the Bird” (2023), the South Korean “Glasses” (2025), the Slovenian and Croatian “Beyond The Face” (2024); The Japanese “Light, Noise, Smoke and Light, Noise, Smoke” (2023), Spanish “Portals” (2024), Iraqi “Beneath Which Rivers Flow” (2025) and Spanish “Where There Is No Light” (2025).
The last entry in this category is “Ravens”, a biographical film made by Mark Gill that explores the life and work of Japanese photographer Masahisa Fukase, eternalized in the artistic world for the daily photographs he captured from the second woman, Yōko Wanibe, and the collection of black-and-white photographs about “Ravens Solitude”. After a session on August 28, the event will be repeated on September 9, this time with a post-film discussion about the photographer's career and personal experiences.
HEARING
We headed for the sound domain with a documentary about the British Blur, aired on 17 August. Named “Blur: Until the End”, some of the most striking moments of the four members of the band are exalted here over 30 years, including the action at Wembley stadium in London. At the end of the session, a moment of reflection and sharing with the presence of the DJ and music critic Chor Chung Wong will be boosted. A second projection of the documentary is scheduled for September 7th.
Also on August 17, the Japanese “Let’s Go Karaoke!” Will be shown, an adaptation of the homonymous manga series featuring at least unusual plot: a member of Yakuza whose sole purpose is to win the group's leader's annual karaoke competition.
The celebration of the song continues on August 23, this time with a documentary about the Scottish band Mogwai. Regarding the celebration of 25 years of career, the film has a retrospective from the group's formation in the 1990s to the quarantine times in 2020, when the recording of the last LP.
SMELL
The programming for the third section, “the desire of aroma”, is not as romantic as the title could suggest. This Saturday (and later, on September 6) is the time to see "Dangerous Animals", a 2025 movie about a surfer kidnapped by a serial killer obsessed with sharks.
On the 27th, the featured film in the sensory world of Cinematheque is “Ghost Killer”, a 2024 Japanese production that tells the story of a university student possessed by the ghost of a revenge -based killer.
The section closes on the 30th with the original movie of “The Texas Chain Saw Massacre”, signed by director Tobe Hooper in 1974. Here, the reference to smell may be associated with different stimuli: blood, sweat… and even putrid meat.
Palate
For this category, Cinemateca has prepared two sessions full of flavor.
In the gastronomic film “Master Cheng”, scheduled for the 24th, a professional chef presents the flavors of Chinese cuisine to a remote village in Finland, demonstrating how culinary art can unite different crops around the same table. "Gifts from the Kitchen", on the 31st, tells in documentary form the story of the Chinese food restaurant "Fumin" in Tokyo, revealing the secrets behind each of the dishes made by chef Fumi Sai.
Tactic
The tact category comes on the form of human contact, medical procedures and radical self-acceptance of the physical aspect.
“Different Man”, with sessions on August 19th and 29th, follows the journey of a man with neurofibromatosis who undergoes experimental surgery to alter his face but eventually undergoes unexpected consequences.
On August 20 and September 3, follows "April", about an obstetrician who is accused of medical negligence when a newborn dies under his supervision and sees his entire life-professional and personal-scrutinated in the following police investigation.
The category closes with “The Girl With The Needle”, a 2024 movie. Ranked as a psychological horror movie with Gothic strings, the story unveils the secrets that hide in a children's adoption agency in the 1919 Copenhagen. There are two sessions: one on the 22nd and another on September 7.
THOUGHT
The sixth sense that spectators can acquire in Cinemateca is this: thought.
In three different sessions (August 30 and September 2 and 9), the protagonist of the movie “Exit 8” will have to use the logic and critical ability to discover the exit of one meter infinite and labyrinthine corridors in Japan and find out 8.
On September 9, the puzzle is more futuristic and dystopian with the French animation movie “Mars Express”. In the not too distant future, private detective Aline Ruby and her android partner are challenged to find a hacker in a world marked by corruption, evil robots and "brain factories."
Tickets for all sessions have a usual price of 60 patacas, although elderly, students and members of Cinemateca Paixão are entitled to 50% off. Those who buy ten or more tickets at one time can still benefit from a 20%discount. The full schedule is available on the Cinemateca Electronic page, where there is also an online box office.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Macao receives historical donation that revives friendship bell-cazaque through the musician Xian Xinghai</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/14/macau-recebe-doacao-historica-que-reaviva-amizade-sino-cazaque-atraves-do-musico-xian-xinghai/</link><description>In a gesture that reinforces the cultural ties between China and Kazakhstan, Macau yesterday received a donation of documents, sheet music and photographs that belonged to the famous composer Xian Xinghai, known as the “musician of the people”. The materials, delivered by Baldyrgan Baikadamova, daughter of the Kazakh musician who welcomed Xian Xinghai during exile in the 1940s, were donated to the composer's memorial museum. The ceremony coincided with the celebrations of the 120th anniversary of the birth of the artist and the 80th anniversary of the Chinese victory in the War of Resistance against Japan.

Macao once again served a diplomatic stage, this time in the cultural field, by hosting yesterday a meeting that accentuated the friendship between China and Kazakhstan. It was at the Xian Xinghai Memorial Museum that the donation ceremony of historical materials belonging to the celebrated Chinese composer - born in Macau - took place. Baldyrgan Baikadamova, daughter of Cazaque musician Bakhytzhan Baikadamov, delivered documents, sheet music and photographs that witness the period in which Xian Xinghai lived in Kazakhstan during the 1940s in Exile. A music bridge between two regions, which only occurred 80 years later. The donation assumes special symbolism this year in which the 80th anniversary of the victory in the War of Resistance of the Chinese people against Japanese aggression and the 120th anniversary of the birth of the composer.
Born in Macao on June 13, 1905, Xian Xinghai is celebrated as the “musician of the people”, author of emblematic works such as the Yellow River Cantata and Army March and the People, who became hymns of resistance during the war. Forced to exile in the Soviet Union in the 1940s, he found refuge in Almaty, Kazakhstan, where he was welcomed by the Baikadamov family. It was during this period that he composed pieces such as Symphony of Popular and Amangeldy Liberation, the latter a tribute to a Cazaque national hero, consolidating a cultural bridge between the two countries.
Choi Kin Long, substitute president of the Cultural Institute, highlighted the historical and educational importance of materials, which not only enrich the museum's collection but also reinforce the patriotic narrative of the region. He underlined the role of Xian Xinghai as a unifying figure during one of the most turbulent periods of the twentieth century. Present at the ceremony were also representatives of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of China, the Directorate of Education and Development Services of Youth and the Macao Museum, as well as members of the Baikadamova family.
After the ceremony, Baldyrgan Baikadamova shared with the young people present, stories about the friendship between his father and Xian Xinghai, recalling the difficulties faced during the war and the composer's commitment to the distant homeland. "These materials keep the memory of the friendship between my father and Xian Xinghai, who in the adversity of war created a musical bridge among our peoples. Despite exile, his soul never left China," he said, highlighting the legacy of "resilience and patriotism" that Xian Xinghai left to future generations.
Inaugurated in 2019, the Xian Xinghai Memorial Museum in Macao aims to preserve the composer's memory, whose connection to Macau is a pertinent historical framework of relevance to the region. New materials donated not only fill historical gaps, but say Macao once again as a "intercultural dialogue platform."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Government promises measures to relieve traffic pressure during a large prize and national games</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/14/governo-promete-medidas-para-aliviar-pressao-do-transito-durante-grande-premio-e-jogos-nacionais/</link><description>The big prize and national games will be held in the same period and the authorities ensure that they have prepared measures to reduce their impact on Macao traffic.

Authorities devalue the traffic concerns that Macau could face in November, when the Grand Prix and the National Games are held in the city simultaneously. According to Luís Gomes, president of the Institute of Sport (ID), the organizing authorities of these events and traffic services have been in “narrow communication and coordination”, with a view to reducing the impact on traffic during the respective period.
Luís Gomes has assured that the competent services will adopt various coordination measures to relieve the pressure of traffic in general, facing the challenges placed to the traffic of Macao by the high number of visitors.
In response to a written interpellation presented by Deputy Lei Chan U, Luís Gomes reiterated to give great importance to traffic needs, so it has already been coordinated to solve the overlay problem of some of the dates with the tests.
"The sports venues of the national games are mainly distributed in the Cotai area, in order to reduce the overlapping of traffic with the big prize on the Macao Peninsula," he said. According to the official, during the period of the Grand Prix, only one of the modalities of the national games will be played on the Macao Peninsula, which will further relieve traffic traffic jam.
It is recalled that the 72nd Macao Grand Prix will take place between November 13 and 16 this year, with the organization of seven events. In this edition will be held for the first time the FIA Formula 4 World Cup, which the authorities say it will "consolidate the International Motorized Sport Statute in Macao." Already the 15th edition of the National Games will be held in Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau between November 9th and 21st. Macau will welcome five modalities in competition.
In questioning, law chan u complained the pressure on traffic caused by the large amount of tourists coming to Macao on holidays.
"During the holidays, public transport is always overcrowded and bus stops are full of passengers," the legislator lamented, being concerned about the ability to flow traffic on public roads in November.
Quoted in the replica, the preparatory office for the organization of the Macao Competition Zone of the National Games, led Pun Weng Kun, said that the frequency of public transport will be adjusted and measures will be implemented to facilitate the flow of visitors through the wrapping roads, given that the sports facilities are concentrated in the Cotai zone.
Already the organizing committee of the Grand Prix, according to its representative Luís Gomes, will coordinate with other departments to make a “comprehensive evaluation” of the flow of visitors, the impact of traffic conditions and the demand for public transport, in order to define traffic plans in advance for both competitions.
"Based on the experience gained in the organization of large shows and sports events previously held, the area of closing of roads and their times will be dynamically adjusted, seeking to minimize the impact on the main arteries and residential areas," he said.
Luís Gomes also stressed that he will be coordinated in conjunction with the two operators of managing temporary careers, reinforcing the frequency of services, ensuring the effective flow of passengers.
The government will also highlight more personal for the order in waiting lines, being, moreover, coordinating the reinforcement of the operation of the light meter and the Hotiles Shuttle buses and the game concessionaires with a special focus on the deviation of flow in the immediate vicinity of competition enclosures and border posts.</description><pubDate>2025-08-14 01:43:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Former South Korean first lady detained on suspicions of fraud and corruption</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/14/ex-primeira-dama-sul-coreana-detida-por-suspeitas-de-fraude-e-corrupcao/</link><description>Former South Korean first lady Kim Keon-He, a wife of the detainee former president, was arrested preventively, in cases involving fraud, corruption and violation of electoral laws, authorities said. Kim Keon-Hee's arrest on Tuesday occurred hours after prosecutors announced the issuance of a detention warrant against former President Yoon Suk-Yeol's wife. The warrant was issued due to the risk of destroying evidence, according to South Korean news agency Yonhap.
Kim, 52, is accused of artificially inflating the value of the actions of a car trade company between 2009 and 2012 and accepting luxury gifts while being first lady in violation of anti-corruption laws. Last week, Kim Keon-Hee was interrogated by the prosecutors, having excused and promised to cooperate with the investigation. The former first lady is still accused of violating electoral laws by interfering with the process of appointing parliamentarians from her husband's former party, the Popular Power Party (PPP). Preventive arrest means that both members of the previous presidential couple are now detained, an unprecedented situation in South Korea.
Former Conservative President Yoon Suk-Youol, contested in April, is detained for briefly imposed the martial law in December and plunging the country in prolonged political chaos. Use of insurrection, was replaced in June by the center-left rival, Lee Jae-Myung.</description><pubDate>2025-08-14 01:39:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Only 40% of Mozambicans can save due to lack of resources</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/14/apenas-40-dos-mocambicanos-conseguem-poupar-devido-a-falta-de-recursos/</link><description>Only 40% of Mozambicans make some kind of savings, due to lack of income, with the government recognizing the need to increase this adhesion in the National Strategy of Financial Inclusion (Enif), to implement by 2031.

“There is a crucial need to educate Mozambicans about the benefits of savings, encouraging them to start saving and investing for their future, regardless of the formal or informal system,” reads the report by that Ministry of Finance, consulted by Lusa.
The proportion of adults that save, it is added, “it is low, both rural and urban”, since on the side of the demand “only 38.3% of adults spared by 2022”, according to the latest data, used in the study.
In the document it is added that "lack of planning and savings for the future puts individuals at risk of financial challenges, poverty and dependence on others or the state during the reduced working capacity phase."
As “to savings access barriers”, it is also pointed out in the document, “the lack of income is the main reason that competes for it”, describing even 72.0% of the non-saving Mozambicans that they do so for “lack of income”, 25.3% because they “do not consider a priority” and 16.7% because they make “unqualified expenses”.
The document recalls that the savings system in Mozambique “offers a variety of institutions capturing” of these resources, including banks, microbancies, credit cooperatives, electronic currency institutions, as well as savings and rotary credit groups.
"Much of the population that spared did not do so in a formal financial institution," he stresses in the document, pointing out that 36.4%of adults saved the bank, followed by the option of saving money at home (31.9%) and then through community associations (17.7%).
Expand access to financial products and services, increase the use of accessible and quality financial products and services, promoting financial literacy and reinforcing consumer protection and confidence in financial services are the four central pillars of the new financial inclusion strategy.
In the document with strategy 2025 - 2031 it is underlined that “financial inclusion serves as a catalyst to achieve the broader development objectives” in the country and “is not limited to providing greater access to financial products and services, but also aims to enable individuals and companies to improve their subsistence means, develop resistance and fully participate in the economy”.
"In addition to promoting entrepreneurship, financial inclusion facilitates savings and investment, contributing to economic and social well-being," it is also said that the strategy "results from extensive consultation and collaboration between the government, financial institutions, public and private sector, as well as development partners."
"Reflects the joint commitment to position financial inclusion as a central pillar of social and economic development of Mozambique," he concludes. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-08-14 01:36:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Planned “View to the City” next to Lake Nam Van</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/14/planeada-vista-para-a-cidade-junto-ao-lago-nam-van/</link><description>The Board of Public Works (DSOP) said yesterday that it will take advantage of the three lots of land A3, A4 and A9 from Lake Nam Van for the creation of provisional public spaces, namely a construction of “city views,” as the authorities call it.
This work, “besides meeting the reasonable expectations of residents regarding the best use of land, also allows you to raise the urban landscape in the city center, thus enriching Macau's experience as a tourist city,” says DSOP in the press release.
DSOP has recently begun the respective preliminary work, and the extraction and drainage of stagnant water and cleaning in lots A3 and A4 has been practically completed, and the topographic registration was underway. Authorities say that, as the situation of the structure of existing buildings in lot A9 is relatively complex, stagnant water extraction and drainage work is still underway, but weeds have already been removed and various materials stagnated to the pavement to prevent mosquito proliferation.
Regarding the structures of the cellars already built on the three terrain, the government will include an entity responsible for the quality control of proceeding to inspect the structure of the original constructions, in order to obtain the respective information to promote conception work.
DSOP will start the provisional works that include the construction of a provisional tour along the lake in the A9 lot, which will connect with the arches of surrounding buildings, landfill to soil level in lot A4, to interconnect with the A3 lot, for the construction of the provisional space, and it is planned again that the Cave is intended for the public parking lot.
"The measures can effectively improve the hygienic situation of the environment on the three land, in order to respond to the requirements related to the beautification of the physiognomy of the areas," says DSOP, noting that this zone is with some of the most sought after sights, being also a commercial zone. "Through the reuse of the three land recovered in the city center, this can not only relieve pressure on the flow of people in the surrounding areas, but also raise the image of the tourist city of Macao, realizing the rational use of soil resources," says the authorities.</description><pubDate>2025-08-14 01:38:01</pubDate></item><item><title>BNU net profit retreated 24% in the first half</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/14/lucro-liquido-do-bnu-recuou-24-no-primeiro-semestre/</link><description>The National Bank Overseas (BNU) reported yesterday that, in the first half of this year, made unhealthy net profits of 228.2 million patacas, minus 24.1% compared to the first half of last year. The financial margin also registered a drop.

The National Bank Overseas (BNU) reported, in the first half of this year, unused net profits of 228.2 million patacas, which reveals a 24.1% drop compared to the same period last year. The results of the first semester were released yesterday by the institution.
During this period, the bank's net financial margin registered a reduction of 75.3 million patacas, ie 14.9% in homologous terms, “mainly due to changes in the composition of deposits and the evolution of the interest rates context as well as the decrease in credit demand and the decrease in the margin of non -credit investments”, explains the bank in the statement released yesterday, stressing that this decrease was partially compensated by one Increase of 2.4 million patacas (+5.6%) in liquid commissions, “reflecting greater economic activity and greater customer involvement”.
The bank also recorded impairment losses related to credit exhibitions and financial investments in the amount of 14.7 million patacas. In the first half of 2024, the value had been 16.3 million, which, according to the BNU, reflects “the bank's prudent approach to risk provisioning”. "The quality of BNU's assets remains solid, supported by conservative credit practices and a strong level of provisions to face the ongoing macroeconomic uncertainties," says the institution.
Operating expenses registered a slight increase of 0.6% in homologous terms, which, according to the BNU, shows “the effectiveness of bank cost optimization initiatives”. On the other hand, “efficiency gains resulting from process simplification and strategic service review have helped compensate for increased digital investments, talent development and brand reinforcement,” says the press release, adding that “these investments are aligned with BNU's strategic priorities to improve client experience, reinforce operational agility and respond to rapid digital panorama changes”.
The bank states that it also continues to integrate ex -ex was included (environmental, social and corporate governance) principles in all its operations, “promoting the creation of long -term sustainable value for communities and the environment”.
Hengqin's bank branch “continues to play a strategic role in serving Macau and Hong Kong investors, including individuals and companies, as the Great Bay (GBA) and the Guangdong-Macau deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin deepen integration”. "Acting as a transfronted financial hub, the branch supports economic collaboration between mainland China, Macao and Portuguese -speaking countries through the provision of adapted financial solutions and the promotion of a diversified business ecosystem in the large bay."
In conclusion, the bank says that "BNU's capital and liquidity position remains strong, supported by disciplined financial management and a solid risk control framework" and "these pillars allow BNU to navigate complex market conditions, continuing to support its customers, communities and stakeholders."</description><pubDate>2025-08-14 01:44:14</pubDate></item><item><title>China says he has expelled a US fresher for invading disputed waters</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/14/china-diz-ter-expulsado-um-contratorpedeiro-dos-eua-por-invadir-aguas-disputadas/</link><description>The command of the Southern Theater of the Popular Liberation Army (ELP) yesterday indicated that US Fatherpeaker USS Higgins was expelled after invading waters adjacent to Huangyan Island in the Southern Sea of China. According to the ELP, the ship entered those waters "without authorization from the Chinese government."

The Chinese army said yesterday that US Fatherpeaker USS Higgins "enhanced" in the waters adjacent to the island of Huangyan, in the Southern Sea of China, having been "expelled according to the law."
In a statement issued on the Chinese social network Wechat, the command of the Southern Theater of the Popular Liberation Army (ELP) indicated that the ship entered those "without authorization from the Chinese government", having been "followed, warned and expelled."
Huangyan is the Chinese designation for Atol Scarborough (Bajo de Mansiloc), located in the Southern Sea of China and whose Beijing Sovereignty disputes with the Philippines.
According to spokesman He Tiecheng, the actions of the American ship "severely violated China's sovereignty and security, seriously impaired peace and stability in the Southern Sea of China and infringed international law and the basic rules governing international relations."
The spokesman added that the command troops “remain at full alert at all times to firmly defend China's sovereignty and security”, as well as regional “peace and stability”.
The area has often recorded incidents between Chinese and Philippines.
On Monday, the Chinese Coast Guard said several Philippine vessels "entered" in adjacent waters to Huangyan, having been "expelled."
The Philippine Coast Guard accused Chinese ships of performing “dangerous maneuvers” in the area, which caused the clash between a Chinese coastal ship and one from the ELP navy while chasing a Philippine vessel.
Manila also accused Chinese vessels of blocking access and using water cannons against their coastal guards.
China and Philippines maintain a prolonged dispute for the sovereignty of various islands and reefs in a strategic region, where about 30% of world maritime trade, which houses 12% of global fishing and potential oil and gas reserves.
Beijing, which has the largest sea fleet in the world, claims almost all of these waters for historical reasons. The tensions intensified since the arrival of power in 2022 of Filipino President Ferdinand Marcos Jr., whose government reinforced the alliance with the United States and adopted a firmer posture in the face of Chinese claims.</description><pubDate>2025-08-14 01:37:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Typhoon Podul obliges the cancellation of multiple flights</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/14/tufao-podul-obriga-ao-cancelamento-de-varios-voos/</link><description>More than 30 flights were canceled due to the approximation of the podul typhoon, according to Macao International Airport. The tropical storm passed yesterday through Taiwan and went to the south coast of Fujian and the east coast of Guangdong. Signal No..1 was issued in Macau yesterday at noon. Meteorological and geophysical services warn of flooding in low zones due to heavy rain between today and tomorrow.

Typhoon's approach yesterday led to the issuance of Signal No..1 of Tropical Storm in Macao, as well as the cancellation of at least 30 flights at Macao International Airport, and most of the affected airlines originated and destined for cities of Taiwan and Fujian province.
According to the information updated by Macau airport until 6 pm yesterday, a total of 35 flights was suspended, including 15 matches and 20 arrivals, which had initially scheduled for yesterday and today. However, the number may also vary depending on the evolution of the meteorological situation in the territory and in the regions involved.
The affected flights connected mainly to Taipei, Kaohsiung and Taichung in Taiwan; Xiamen and Jinjiang, in the province of Fujian; Beijing; Changzhou; Tawau, Malaysia; Hanoi, in Vietname; and Bangkok in Thailand.
Macao International Airport, in a note, asked passengers to contact the relevant airline to obtain more recent flight information, appealing to the verification of the state of flights and the conditions of the roads before traveling to the airport.
Typhoon Podul yesterday made his passage through Taiwan and moved to the west-new, towards the southern coast of Fujian and the eastern coast of Guangdong province. Upon entering the area of 800 kilometers from Macao, signal No. 1 of Tropical Storm was lifted in Macau yesterday at noon and remains in force during the day.
According to the analysis of the Directorate of Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG), Typhoon Podul reaches land from the interior of China today at dawn and gradually weakens. "However, its further intensity and trajectory are still uncertain, and there is a possibility to follow a southern trajectory," SMG estimated yesterday.
The probability of emitting the tropical storm signal No. 3 is “relatively low to moderate,” they said.
It is expected that the time between today and tomorrow, under the influence of the outer circulation of the tropical storm system, is “unstable” with occasional, sometimes strong, and accompanied by thunderstorms.
The SMG also state that the probability of flooding caused by “Storm Surge” is low, since the next two days are not from Maré Alta Astronomic. But flooding in low areas may occur due to heavy short rain.
Authorities recommend to the population to pay attention to the latest weather information and take appropriate precautions.
According to SMG forecasts in rainfall, the rainfall volume for today can reach 50 mm, and exceed 20 mm tomorrow.
It is recalled that “Podul” is part of the list of tropical storm names to be used in the Pacific Northwest and the South Sea of China, and was provided by North Korea, referring to the “tree normally found in cities and in the countryside”. "In the stuffy mood, people rest and talk to the shadow of the podul, that is, willow," according to the Hong Kong Observatory.</description><pubDate>2025-08-14 01:44:59</pubDate></item></channel></rss>