<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/25/china-promete-resultados-beneficos-em-forum-com-investidores-estrangeiros/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Coutinho criticizes social security regime and calls for greater protection for elderly people with disabilities</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/25/coutinho-critica-regime-de-seguranca-social-e-pede-maior-proteccao-para-idosos-com-deficiencia/</link><description>Representative José Pereira Coutinho defended, in a written interplies sent yesterday to the government, the updating of the Social Security regime, in order to give greater protection to the most vulnerable layers of society, namely the elderly with disabilities.
"As the population ages, it is essential to ensure that those facing additional challenges, such as physical, mental or sensory disabilities, have access to rights that promote their quality of life," says Coutinho, stressing that "access to elderly pensions, compatible with their condition, is not only a matter of social justice, but also of recognition of their continuous contribution to society mainly during their youth."
The president of the Macao Public Function Association (ATFPM) states that "protecting these citizens is an ethical imperative that reflects the commitment of an inclusive and solidary society, where everyone can live with dignity and security, regardless of their circumstances."
Coutinho warns that residents with disabilities, when they reach the old age, are faced with a "significant reduction in their income." This is because the Social Security regime says that "the pension for the elderly, disability pension, unemployment allowance and disease subsidy are not cumulative with each other."
Thus, Coutinho asks the government to “update and modernize the current regime of social security, which is manifestly disabled”, so that there is an integral cumulation and partial cumulation of the various pensions and subsidies. "A citizen who, since youth, receives a disability allowance and affects the elderly should have the right to accumulate the pension of the elderly," says Coutinho in his interpellation, stressing that the regime should "ensure greater equity and social protection for vulnerable citizens."
“What specific strategies does the Macau government intend to adopt to ensure that the disabled elderly have access to health care appropriate and adapted to their needs?”, The deputy questions.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:44:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Friendship Bridge was the place with the largest number of road accidents</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/25/ponte-da-amizade-foi-o-local-com-o-maior-numero-de-acidentes-de-viacao/</link><description>Last year, the place with the most traffic accidents was the Friendship Bridge, where 476 cases were reported, followed by Doctor Rodrigo Rodrigues Avenue and Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Avenida Sul Avenue. According to the Public Security Police, among the black points of road accidents, Avenida Dr. Sun Yat-Sen was the place where more accidents involving pedestrians were recorded. Authorities guarantee that they will analyze the data to improve the road facilities.
 
The Friendship Bridge was the place in Macao where more road accidents occurred over the past year, with a total of 476 cases registered, ie at least one accident a day. The number was advanced by the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP), also revealing that Doctor Rodrigo Rodrigues Avenue and Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau South Avenue were the places with the second and third largest number of road accidents in 2024, with 389 cases and 303 cases respectively.
In January this year there were 37 road accidents at the Friendship Bridge, which was also the place where more accidents appeared in the territory, and at the same time, Doctor Rodrigo Rodrigues Avenue continued to occupy second place with 35 accidents.
Quoted by Radio Macao in Chinese language last year, in addition to the three places mentioned, the list are also present the Road of Isthmus (254), Avenida da Friendship (249), Avenida Dr. Sun Yat-Sen (246), Wai Long Avenue (231), Rotunda do Isthmus (206), Avenida da Ponte da Friendship (204).
Data on traffic issues for 2024 also recall that the Friendship Bridge had the largest daily traffic flow, with 68,118 vehicles a day, and the Sai Van Bridge was used by 62,000 vehicles per day. The circulation of car on the Friendship Bridge, in this sense, exceeded for the first time, since they began to make records (2015), that of Ponte de Sai Van. In addition, 15,000 vehicles passed daily through the Noble Carvalho Governor Bridge.
The number of road accidents last year reached 15,510 cases, a number that represents an annual rise of 14% and record value of the last nine years. Accidents involving pedestrians increased 6.69%to 510 cases. Among the ten places with the highest number of road accidents last year, Dr. Sun Yat-Sen Avenue was the one that recorded the largest number of accidents involving pedestrians, with a total of six accidents, followed by the Road of ISTMO (4) and Friendship Avenue (4).
In this sense, CPSP stressed that it will conduct an analysis of the data related to road accidents and take stock of the places where accidents occur most frequently, to examine, later, the situation of the site and present to the competent services suggestions of optimization of travel facilities, hoping to eliminate potential risks to road safety.
Authorities also guarantee that they perform inspections and operations at times and irregular places to combat driving offenses in order to increase the determination effect and protect safety from pedestrians and drivers.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:44:59</pubDate></item><item><title>São Januário had more than 5,000 childhood and adolescence psychiatry consultations in 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/25/sao-januario-teve-mais-de-5-mil-consultas-de-psiquiatria-da-infancia-e-adolescencia-em-2024/</link><description>An exchange meeting organized by health services drew attention to the increasing challenges that Macau young people face. Authorities stress that the factors responsible for mental health problems in youth are multiple and that the whole community-including family, schools and medical institutions-must join the prevention and alert work.
 
The Department of Children and Adolescent Psychiatry at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center received more than 5,000 patients over the past year. The information was revealed on Monday by health services, in a statement published following the exchange meeting “overcoming borders: models of psychological services for young people”, where representatives of various government departments, medical institutions and social services participated.
Speaking at the event, Tai Wa Hou, a doctor in the direction of São Januário, acknowledged that young people face increasing pressures and challenges at the level of mental health, as a result of a world in permanent social and technological evolution. It stressed, in this regard, that the Psychiatry Service of the Hospital Center has an outpatient clinic of childhood and adolescence centered psychiatry, with professional psychotherapists in nine health centers and a team of community psychiatric services to accompany higher risk patients.
However, and as the causes of psychological and psychiatric disorders are multiple and varied, Tai Wa has argued that support and prevention work should not be bound to health professionals, being a joint responsibility of the various strata of society. The whole community, including family and school, should mobilize to protect the mental health of young people, namely through the referral and sharing of information relevant to competent medical services.
In an next intervention, Jiang Wen, head of the National Center for Mental Health Prevention and Control, stressed that the country “gives great importance” to the psychologists and psychiatric problems of youth, which attributes to family, social and environmental factors. It also echoed the need to build a cooperation model in preventing and intervention of these issues, involving schools, communities, families, means of communications and medical institutions.
In the health services statement, some of the government's directives and goals are listed to promote a healthy lifestyle, both in physical and psychological aspects, such as the “Healthy Community” program or “healthy companies” and “healthy schools” initiatives. Health authorities have also collaborated with the Directorate of Education and Youth Services (DSEDJ) and the Institute of Social Action (IAS) in the application of joint prevention and action mechanisms. In 2021, the creation of the “Working Group to monitor the physical and mental health of young people”, in which the Government of Mashes and Health Services, DSEDJ and IAS have jointly developed 85 actions for prevention, control, practices and dissemination to ensure the physical and mental health of Macao students.
Completing the statement, health services ensure that they will “continue to support non -profit institutions in providing psychological consultation services and provide clinical supervision and knowledge training to local psychotherapists, so that services can penetrate more professionally in the community, increasing the accessibility of services” and promoting the construction of a “happy macau”.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:45:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Constitutional Court rejects dismissal of interim president in South Korea</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/25/tribunal-constitucional-rejeita-destituicao-de-presidente-interino-na-coreia-do-sul/</link><description>The South Korea Constitutional Court yesterday rejected a request for dismissal of the Prime Minister, Han Duck-Soo, making him again interim until the sentence of the holder of the position, subject to the same process, is known. "Han's dismissal process was rejected by five votes against one by the eight judges of the Court," said South Korean news agency Yonhap. Han had been suspended by the deputies in December after a short initial transition period. Yesterday, the Constitutional Court has commented on its favor. The decision by the same court is now expected to dismiss President Yoon Suk-Youol.
The decision on Han is the first time the court has commented on a case related to Yoon's short -term martial decree, which plunged South Korea to the worst constitutional crisis in recent history. Political uncertainty has profoundly divided the nation, with thousands of protesters gather in Seoul, while the country awaits the court's decision on the maintenance or rejection of Yoon's dismissal. Han himself was suspended by the deputies at the end of December as an interim president, for resisting opposition pressures to appoint new judges to the Constitutional Court - a measure that would have increased the hypotheses of Parliament to take the process of Yoon's dismissal - and for allegedly helped Yoon to declare the martial law, accusations that Han denied. With yesterday's decision of the Constitutional Court, Finance Minister Choi Sang-Mok leaves the position of interim president.
Last week, opposition parties, which have a dominant majority in the National Assembly, presented a motion for the dismissal of Choi for delaying the appointment of a judge approved by the Assembly.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:47:15</pubDate></item><item><title>RPC Constitution and Basic Law? There are two separate orders, says Vitalino Canas</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/25/constituicao-da-rpc-e-a-lei-basica-sao-dois-ordenamentos-separados-diz-vitalino-canas/</link><description>In the case of the Constitution of the Popular Republic of China and the basic law of two multilevel legal orders of separation, it is not established that the rules of one have to submit to the rules of the other, says the Portuguese constitutionalist, Vitalino Canas.
 
The Legal Order of the Misheries and the Popular Republic of China have “a multilevel relationship of separation,” said the professor of the Lisbon Law School, Vitalino Canas, in a presentation that took place on March 17 during the Spring 2025 conferences at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center in Lisbon. Without “communicating ties”, in case of incompatibility, it is not possible to generate “the possibility of potential applicability of two standards with different content”.
The constitutionalist explains what multilevel orders are separation. "They are those who structurally imply that a legal relationship applies one and one legal norm," he says. "There are no communicating vessels between the two legal orders that establish that one rules have to conform to the rules of another, contrary to what happens in the case of multilevel cooperation orders," he adds.
 
And the normative superiority?
 
Looking at the constitution of the RPC, the expert states that "his normative supremacy is, from the outset, stated in the preamble himself, where it can be read that it is the fundamental law of the state and has supreme legal authority." But in which this normative supremacy is translated, in relation to all other rules that have no constitutional value? "It is ensured especially because the constitution is approved only by the national popular assembly and by a majority of two thirds according to article 64 of the constitution of the RPC," he says.
However, as the modern constitutionalism argues, the constitution of the RPC is omitted in some of the points that “are inherent or confirmed of this normative superiority. For example, the“ supervision of constitutionality by independent entities of public agencies ”is still expected to be an“ independent institution, in the style of the Constitutional Court in Portugal ”, nor was the competencies of constitutionality inspection by courts. In addition, the instances. The Superior Courts of the Territory are “on the dependence of the National Popular Assembly”, only providing for the political supervision of constitutionality by the National Popular Assembly.
However, Vitalino Canas asks: “How is the normative superiority of the Constitution, which then has little possibilities to be imposed beyond what the national popular assembly understands, expresses in relation to basic law?” With the constitution of the RPC to be “mere in relation to the legal nature of the basic law and totally changes in its normative relationship with the constitution”, there is room for many doubts.
According to article 31 of the constitution of the RPC, it is possible to create special administrative regions by law, emanating from the National Popular Assembly. The basic law of the MSAR was issued under these precepts, and its approval is to be approved by the National Popular Assembly. Going a little further into the interpretation of the article and systematic, it could be concluded that, on the one hand, “the laws of creation of special administrative regions have to be subordinated to some constitutional principle” and “can be overseeed with material parameters fixed in the Constitution”. In addition, “they are subjected to a special procedure for elaboration and training”, and there is also a “different position of the normative hierarchy implicitly fixed in the Constitution, for example, superior to other laws.” Still, the constitutionalist points out, it is only a possible interpretation, and these points are not manifested nowhere in the Constitution.
 
The value of the basic law
 
Considering all this, says the constitutionalist, "although it can be said that the basic law fulfills the function that a constitution normally performs, as it establishes a current normative system and burns rights, it cannot be considered to be in the face of a fully formal constitution in the formal and full term, as the ideology of constitutionalism advocates." This is because, according to this doctrine, the Constitution “is a normative set, preferably written, adopted by the people, who submits to him in the exercise of his free sovereign power, assisted of superior rigidity to the ordinary law, with adequate normative force to limit the exercise of power, which should be subjected, including the derived constituent power, and, as well as the legislator Thus, looking at the basic law, at least “the adoption for the people of Macau, who is not a sovereign people in independent territory”.
It can be concluded, therefore, that the basic law is “a reinforced law as to the function performed, although not as to the process and form, because the Constitution did not differentiate them from those required for other laws, insofar as the constitution itself establishes that the systems to be instituted in the laws of special administrative regions are defined by law, that is, the basic laws of RAE, 31 and 62,” he says. In the teacher's understanding, this means that "the constitution itself derogates or dispenses with the constitution reserve with regard to RAE, which are created in its context."
Therefore, concludes Vitalino Canas, it can be said that “the best way to characterize the multilevel region of the Constitution and the Basic Law is that of separation by the will and determination of the Chinese Constitution”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:45:01</pubDate></item><item><title>More protection required for workers on their own</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/25/exigida-mais-proteccao-para-os-trabalhadores-por-conta-propria/</link><description>Deputy Leong Sun IOK expects the government to reinforce workers' professional guarantees on their own. In written interpellation, the parliamentarian warns that there are many employers to hire workers through service contract even when it is not justified.
 
Leong Sun Iok wants the government to better protect workers' rights on their own. In a written interpellation sent to the government, the deputy linked to the Federation of Macao Workers 'Associations (Faom) denounces that several companies are adopting the workers' hiring model through service contracts, even if the workload and work are similar to those of normal labor relations.
"Being Macau a microeconomic, the market is limited and many people can only work this way, so, in this context, it is important to verify that employers are resorting to this possibility as a means to run away from the responsibilities and duties of the employment relationship," says Leong Sun Iok in interpellation.
Thus, the deputy says that "the government must study how to ensure the professional guarantees of workers on their own and professionals", encouraging, for example, employers to acquire work insurance for their workers with service contracts, "in order to improve labor guarantees in Macao."
Since this type of hiring is being most used by employers, Leong Sun Iok notes that other places are being studied mechanisms to protect these workers. For example, at national level, a regime for protecting the rights and labor interests will be created for new employment modalities and explicitly defined the responsibilities of platforms and companies in labor protection.
Therefore, the deputy reiterates that "the government must, in timely, have studied studies to optimize the rules of labor relations and the protection of relevant rights and interests under the Labor Relations Law and other legislation, as well as to improve the social security regime, complementary measures and legal diplomas."
Leong Sun Iok even says that this new type of hiring represents a potential “escape to employers' responsibility, suggesting to the government to perform an inquiry into the number and types of workers on their own and existing liberal professionals.
On the other hand, the workers' deputy points out that, under the law of labor relations and judicial decisions in the past, it is considered that there is a working relationship whenever “availability” is concerned. “To avoid non -compliance with employers and safeguard workers' rights and interests, will the government issue clear instructions and strengthen publicity actions and guidelines?”, Interrogates Leong Sun Iok.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:45:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Ipim will promote more than 350 Lusophone products</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/25/ipim-vai-promover-mais-de-350-produtos-lusofonos/</link><description>During next Friday and Saturday, the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment (IPIM) will organize the initiative “Meeting”, which aims to “provide the public opportunities to closely try the unique charm of products and culture of Portuguese-speaking countries”. The IPIM will present more than 350 products from Lusofonia and a dozen workshops and courses.
 
Hundreds of products from Portuguese-speaking countries will be exposed, between Friday and Saturday, in the complex of the commercial cooperation platform between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, as part of a promotional activity organized by the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM).
“Meetings” is the name of the initiative that will present and put for sale more than 350 quality products from Portuguese -speaking countries at more affordable prices. The products to be presented range from Café do Brasil and Timor-Leste to wines and objects in Cortiça de Portugal, for example.
The purpose of the initiative is, Ipim says, “providing the public opportunities to closely experience the unique charm of the products and culture of Portuguese -speaking countries,” says the IPIM press release.
The complex of the commercial cooperation platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries will be transformed into a “space that combines purchases and entertainment, offering a variety of products at promotional prices and a rich range of promotional activities,” Ipim points out in the press release yesterday. Consumers who make purchases of a certain amount on site can get a memory, or exchange a wine classified for only one level, until the stock is over.
The event will also include activities focused on the culture of Lusophone countries and their characteristic products. On Friday, there will be a promotion of Lusophony wines, focusing on commercial negotiations; A culinary demonstration of Portuguese dishes will be held, with the participation of cooking chiefs of Macao who will cook on site Portuguese dishes.
On Saturday, the activities will be oriented to interactive experiences, as IPIM collaborates with the Macau Technology Productivity and Transfer Center to launch the Lusophone Alcoholic Beverage Workshop, with wine specialists to share their knowledge about wine tasting; There will also be workshops open to the public, such as painting and collage of Portuguese ceramic, sardine rope braid and tile manual painting.
The public will also be able to visit the exhibition pavilion of the service platform for commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries “to know the results of Macau's work as a sino-Portuguese platform through guided tours, as well as know food and beverage products, agricultural products and handicrafts of nine Portuguese-speaking countries”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:43:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Proposal for a public hiring law: slow to approve, but on the way to transparency</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/25/proposta-de-lei-de-contratacao-publica-demorado-a-aprovar-mas-a-caminho-da-transparencia/</link><description>With the Government's acquisition regime currently being governed by legislation above all the 1980s, the proposed public hiring bill, which aims to amend these diplomas, resulted from a public consultation process started in 2018 and is still under discussion in the specialty in the Legislative Assembly of Macao. Marco Caldeira, professor at the Lisbon Law School, states that, although time consuming, it seems to go on the “good way”.
 
The proposal for the public hiring law, approved in general and in discussion in the specialty, since the beginning of last year, in the Legislative Assembly, will change the legislation that exists today, dated from the 1980s, and seems to be on the “good way”, seeking to “combat the lack of transparency”, preventing “conflicts of interest” and avoiding “direct direct adjustments”, says Marco Caldeira, a presentation of the Lisbon Faculty of Lisbon. On March 17, it took place on the occasion of the conferences of Spring 2025 that are now underway at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center in Lisbon.
For the administrativist, underlying this desire to revise public hiring, are, on the one hand, “eternal problems of public contracts” and, on the other hand, “the lack of consecration of the fundamental legal principles, which is marked with a gap in the 80s regime”. But it's not just. "There is a lack of regulation of public hiring policies - a very vogue theme that is in the European Union with sustainable public hiring, the circular economy and the prospect of pursuing the social and environmental purposes of public contracts," he adds.
There is also the need to “promote the transparency of public hiring procedures and the protection of loyal competition, a timeless theme as always”, as well as “more specific aspects, such as the qualifications of competitors and candidates, the formation of staff that integrates the proposals evaluation committees and the regulation of adjudication criteria”.
Looking at the public consultation that took place in the territory, many of these issues were addressed. "In addition to these aspects, the population and the economic operators consulted also highlighted points such as the need to treat the evasion of applicable hiring procedures, artificial fractionation of the object of the contract and expenses, explicit regulation of the security, very relevant problem for economic operators," he says. Then, he adds, the community, within the scope of public consultation, also mentioned the need to “create a computerized database and walk for the digitization and computerization of public hiring, the walk for electronic public hiring”, as well as the creation of “databases for the future and a competent public hiring service”.
Highlighting that the law proposal is very “in the sense” of the proposals made during the public consultation, Marco Caldeira states that, in general, the diploma proposes “a more detailed regulation of the criteria of choice of each of the procedures, but there is this idea of ​​combating the lack of transparency and ensuring transparency”.
The objective seems to be “preventing conflicts of interest to persons who participate in public hiring procedures, but also in an objective perspective, namely, the book of charges cannot be established to favor certain economic operators,” he says.
 
Necessary changes
 
Currently, the government's acquisition regime is essentially in three diplomas: Decree-Law 122/84/M (reviewed by Law 5/2021), regarding expenses, works and maintenance of services; DL 63/85, on the acquisition of goods and services; And, more recently, DL 74/99m that deals with public works contracts. "Political power found it convenient to heare with the population and the relevant stakeholders to promote an integrated review of the public hiring regime from the perspective of the two 80's diplomas - not 99 of the endeavors, as it should remain in force, but at least the other two of the 1980s are reviewed and unified in a single future law of public hiring," the teacher explains.
In the case of a slow process, as the public consultation began in 2018 and the diploma continues to approve, Marco Caldeira praised the review process. "It is healthy that it is realized that diplomas from the 80s, as good as they were at the time, will necessarily have to be reviewed and public hiring has a huge public relevance and is a matter that, even from a legal point of view, has been growing in complexity," he says. On the other hand, Marco Caldeira also praises the auscultation of the community in this process. "Not only was the public consultation very well done, but had good results," he says, specifying: "The working group signaled a set of problems and formulated 19 proposals in the public consultation report and the public consultation, besides these, also added other aspects that the experts had not considered."
In the case of a diploma that still continues to approve in the specialty, Marco Caldeira states that it is important to “ensure that the text is correct”, noting in its content “reminiscences of the current Portuguese public contract code”.
It is recalled that one of the diplomas regulating the expenses with works and acquisition of goods and services, DL No. 122/84/m, had already undergone a change in 2021, in order to increase the limitation value for the procedures inherent to public acquisition.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:45:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CK Hutchison's actions shot with the son of Li Ka-Shing in forum in China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/25/accoes-da-ck-hutchison-disparam-com-presenca-de-filho-de-li-ka-shing-em-forum-na-china/</link><description>The actions of CK Hutchison, by billionaire Li Ka-Shing, took up after one of their children was invited to a forum with high Chinese employees in Beijing, despite the sale of the company's ports in Panama.
 
Richard Li was invited, as founder of Pacific Century Group, to the China Development Forum of the State Council, according to a list of participants, quoted by the Bloomberg news agency.
Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang and vice-prime minister He Lifeng participate in the two-day event that brings together executives from some of the world's largest multinationals, including Tim Cook of Apple, Pfizer Albert Bourla, or Aimin Nasser, from Saudi Aramco.
Although Richard Li supervises his own business group and not playing any role in CK Hutchison, investors seem to have interpreted their presence as a positive sign for the LI family.
CK Hutchison actions rose 5.2% on Monday morning, the largest climb in more than two weeks.
Li Ka-Shing's main conglomerate of the global business empire was criticized in a commentary by a Hong Kong newspaper and later republished in the official portals of the Chinese administration in the region and in the neighboring city Macau.
The TA Kung Pao newspaper considered that the deal it transferred to a consortium, which includes the US active manager Blackrock, a 80% stake in a group subsidiaries, which generate 43 ports in 23 countries, including ports in both ends of the Panama Canal in Balboa and Cristobal, "not a normal commercial practice." "Many [Chinese] netizens strongly criticized this agreement and CK Hutchison Holdings, considering it as a spineless assignment, aiming only at profit and forgetting justice, ignoring national interests and major national principles, betraying and selling all the Chinese people. These emotional expressions are completely understandable," he reads.
A Chinese analyst denied the Lusa agency, however, that the comment represents Beijing's official position. "The business is a purely private agreement" and "by no means the comment represents the official position of China," said Gao Zhikai, who served as an interpreter of former Chinese leader Deng Xiaoping and is currently one of the best known commentators of Chinese television. "The company concluded that the price the US buyer has offered is a good price, or even undeniable, and that is the main reason behind the agreement. The Chinese government has nothing to do with this business," he added.
Bloomberg has, however, said that Chinese authorities are investigating the business for potential violations of national security and anti -monopoly legislation. CK Hutchison is expected to sign the agreement on the sale of its two ports in Panama until April 2. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:45:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Outdoor installations of Alameda da Harmonia in Seac Pai Van opened the public yesterday</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/25/instalacoes-ao-ar-livre-da-alameda-da-harmonia-em-seac-pai-van-abriram-ontem-ao-publico/</link><description>Yesterday opened a new leisure zone yesterday at Alameda da Harmonia, in Seac Pai Van, which features outdoor facilities suitable for different age groups, creating a richer and diversified leisure environment for the Seac Pai Van community neighborhood.
The Alameda da Harmonia leisure zone, located on both sides of Alameda da Harmonia (between the Lok Kuan building and the IP HENG building), in Seac Pai Van, has a total area of ​​about 2,730 square meters, and covers a children's fun space with separate areas depending on the ages of large equipment, with elements of climbing and adequate challenges, for the children They can increase the sense of coordination and balance during their games, and reinforce their physical fitness, ”describes the Institute's press release for Municipal Affairs (AMI), which adds that“ the adult's physical maintenance zone also takes into account the needs of young people, adults and elderly, with different age groups, with rich and diverse facilities ”.
The opening hours of the children's fun zone is from 7am to 10pm, while the physical maintenance zone for adults remains operating 24 hours. "AMI hopes that, through the use and reordering of existing public spaces, a rich and diverse leisure environment can be created, responding to the needs of residents of this zone in terms of leisure facilities," the statement stresses.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:44:57</pubDate></item><item><title>271 units of economic housing in zone A</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/25/vendidas-271-unidades-da-habitacao-economica-na-zona-a/</link><description>271 economic housing fractions have already been sold in 2019, three weeks after the process of choosing houses. The Housing Institute revealed that, among those sold, most correspond to T3 units and, for now, no one acquired T1 apartments. So far there are 2,632 household aggregates to wait for the choice of fraction.
 
The Housing Institute (IH) said that 271 units were chosen by the eligible candidates of the opened economic housing contest in 2019 and have already been sold. The statistics were updated until yesterday, in the three weeks since the beginning of the process of choosing the fractions, which started earlier this month, on the 4th.
The 2019 Economic Housing Competition provides a total of 3,017 fractions in the new landfills. According to IH information, among the 271 apartments sold, 191 are T3 units, 80 are T2 fractions, and there were no household aggregate to choose 1 bedroom apartments. There are therefore 2,746 remaining fractions waiting to be selected. Regarding the situation of household aggregates who chose economic housing, 105 are families with three people (39%), followed by 74 families with two elements (27%) and 71 families with elements (26%).
It is recalled that the economic housing available for acquisition in this contest are located in the Tong Seng Building (Lot B4), Tong Chong Building (Lot B9) and Tong Kai Building (Lot B10), in Zone A of new landfills, totaling 3,017 fractions, including 760 T1, 1,000 T2 and 1,257 T3 typology.
Data on the assessment of the 2019 Economic Housing Competition also show that more than 35,000 applications were admitted, with 18,029 nuclear household applications, 1,677 non -nuclear household aggregates and 16,061 individual candidates.
Until yesterday, 4,211 applications passed substantial appreciation. In this case, in addition to 271 who have already chosen the fractions, 2,632, who have fulfilled the requirements after the appreciation, are awaiting the selection of fraction. A total of 29 applications is still in legal procedure and 35 are under substantial assessment, including those who need to present complementary documents and suspension. 881 applications were registered that completed the legal procedure for not fulfilling the requirements, 186 proceeded to change group and ordering. In addition, 177 households presented withdrawal to the candidacy.
The Economic Housing Competition opened in 2019 is the last competition held under the former “Economic Housing Law”, which provides that the fixation of the sales price of the fractions must, in particular, to the purchase of the possible beneficiaries of this type of housing, the location of buildings, the year of construction, the orientation and location of fractions in the global structure of the building, the area and typology of the fractions. According to an order published last year, for the three residential buildings of Economic Housing, the price of T1 apartments ranges from 1.18 million patacas and 1.46 million patacas. T2 houses cost between 1.55 million patacas and 1.82 million patacas, while the price of T3 units is set from 1.93 million patacas at 2.37 million patacas. All values ​​enjoy a bonus ratio greater than 64%.
Once the period of 16 -year inalienability of 16 years, counted from the date of issuance of the license of use, if the acquirer intends to dispose of the fraction, must make the payment of compensation to IH according to the bonus ratio.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:42:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau has a holistic refuge where everyone is welcome (including animals)</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/25/macau-tem-um-refugio-holistico-onde-todos-sao-bem-vindos-incluindo-animais/</link><description>Ganaa Ávila founded Soul Healing Macau in 2023, with the aim of encouraging self-love and connection with the metaphysical plane through Reiki and Sound Baths sessions. Year and a half after the opening, it also offered treatments of water, acupressure and even energy cleaning to animals, creatures that it considers as “alive” and sentients as the human. In conversation with the final point, he explains what his work consists of and emphasizes the importance of positive thinking for a balanced life.
 
From the beginning of civilization that there is a record of beliefs in a universal energy, nicknamed “Qi”, “prana” or “reiki” according to societies of origin. Ganaa Ávila, holistic therapist at Mongolia and based in Macau for over 20 years, chooses to call her Reiki at Espaço Soul Healing Macao, opened about a year and a half ago in the Si Toi building in Praia Grande. Still, it explains to the end point that it does not fully identify with the title of "Master."
"This strength does not belong to me, nor am I who have the power of healing. I only work with energy and help clean the chakras of customers," he explains, reiterating that "anyone can learn to use this force if they want." The purpose of Soul Healing Macau is precisely this: empowering customers and encouraging them to take care of themselves, both physical and spiritually, through a holistic and natural perspective.
When he embarked on this career, he did not think of it as an economic investment. The main focus was to recover his mental and emotional health, weakened by a car accident that left scars so complex that modern medicine did not know how to heal with medicines. Disabled by mourning, he made himself think, "Why do I still get stuck with sadness? If I can't change the past or control the future, why not just enjoy the moment, love me and live a life with meaning?"
The next step was to extend this epiphany as many people as possible. The therapist gives as an example a metaphorical comparison between negative emotions and a rotting fruit piece. Like a boluto strawberry is infecting the others in a fruit bowl, the low frequency energies are contagious to those around us. But beware: the opposite also happens. By helping a patient relieve symptoms of insomnia or anxiety, Ganaa is not just helping a single person - her family and friends also benefit from this energy lightness.
 
Beyond Reiki and Tibetan Cups
 
When he opened the holistic space in the heart of Macao, the experiences that offered mainly in Reiki-by far, the technique most sought after by customers-and in the sound bath, or "sound healing", where the patient is induced in a meditative state while the different sounds emitted by tibetan cups resonate through space.
Since then, it has expanded its areas of knowledge with a traditional Chinese medical course, where it has learned new physical therapies (such as suction cups or moxibustion) and metaphysical (such as the meridian points and the energies of Yin and Yang). Today, it incorporates in its space an intentional mix of oriental philosophies, from Buddhists to Hindus, where all coexist and none impose themselves. What truly matters is believing in the self-esteem and life force of the universe, regardless of the name attributed to it.
“It all comes down to having a belief system. Believe in something positive attracts positivity to our lives,” explains Ganaa. The belief in the power of positive thinking popularized in 2004 with Rhonda Byrne's book “The Secret”; For the Tiktok generation, this technique will be better known for the term Manifesting. "When we imagine something and simulate the feeling of receiving it, our subconscious aligns us with this frequency and transposes what we imagine to reality."
Although perhaps it seems that the world has never been as chaotic as in contemporary times, the holistic therapist believes that, in fact, it has never been so easy to reach inner peace: "Just get it to youtube to learn to" manifest "or meditate." And the biggest advantage of these natural therapies? Have no side effects.
“People are increasingly looking for natural alternatives to pills, especially after pandemic. They want to maintain harmony between the physical and the spiritual,” he notes. In response to the first aspect, Soul Healing Macao recently introduced Gua SHA treatments and acupressive facial massages to the list of experiences it offers. With so many holistic rejuvenation treatments available, "Why opt for surgeries or the application of fillers that require retouching every six months?"
The therapist emphasizes it is impossible to take care of the body and disregard mental health, or vice versa-emotional wounds are accumulating and reflecting in the physical plane in the form of indispositions or diseases. "When we have too many emotions, our energy flows block and excessive anger, sadness, enthusiasm - whatever it may be - is stuck somewhere in the tissues of our body. Often people do not know how to unlock these sensations, and this is where holistic therapies enter."
 
Humans, animals and plants: we are all energy
 
The vast majority of customers are women, “biologically” programmed for a greater connection with the metaphysical. Men, less open to spiritual experiences, will represent “5% to 1%” of the total people seeking Ganaa Ávila services. But not all customers are human: an even tinned percentage consists of pets.
It all started when a friend proposed to resort to Reiki's energy to appease a group of cats that constantly fighting. “My reaction was: why not?” Spells the therapist. "Humans, animals or plants, aren't we all living creatures?" It was enough “one or two sessions” so that changes in five cats become evident, he says. "These were extraordinary results. The most problematic cat again eating, was more satisfied, started to get along with the others…."
The treatments of Soul Healing Macao - including animals - can be consulted and reserved through homonymous social networks by the end of the year. In 2026, Ganaa will move with her family to Portugal and start a new stage of her life. "I needed to reflect a lot, because it's a huge change." It was not long before it found comfort in the Alentejo wander and realize that, there, both the connection with nature and your business would flourish. "The Portuguese are already very interested in spirituality. It is the opposite of Macau, where many people do not yet know what are sound baths."
At the end of the interview, we invite us to sit in the center of the room and to know this therapy empirically. Ask us, first, let us close our eyes, put our hands on our hearts-where the respective chakra is located-and that we inhale and exhibit deeply.
Ganaa warns that these sessions lead to energy liberation in various forms: Some people cry, others are plagued by childhood memories. But in this space there is something for everyone. After an immersive bath of glasses, gongs, wind bells and Buddhist cymbals, even skeptics will return the house with a lighter step. For Ganaa Ávila, that is enough: the client took an hour from his routine to connect with the sensory world and practice the art of self-love, whether or not he believes in the magical forces of the universe. The purpose of your work has been fulfilled.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Approved professional accreditation records of 118 local veterinarians</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/25/aprovados-registos-de-acreditacao-profissional-de-118-medicos-veterinarios-locais/</link><description>By the end of February, 118 Macau veterinarians obtained the certificate of professional accreditation of veterinarian, after being approved in the examination performed by the Council of Veterinary Medicine Professionals (CPMV).
The process of registering professional veterinary accreditation is provided for in the new “Veterinary Clinical Care Law and Commercial Animal Activity”, which came into force on April 1 last year. The legislation, according to the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMIs), aims to better promote the healthy development of the Veterinary Clinical Care sector in Macao since the demand for service has been growing at an accelerated pace in recent years.
The CPMV has ensured that, with the implementation of the professional accreditation, registration and discipline registration regime of veterinarians in Macau, will work with AMI to supervise and coordinate works related to the activities of the sector, raising the professional level of veterinarians, promoting the healthy development of the sector of animal clinical care and protecting the health and welfare of animals.
This board organized two weeks ago the participation of Macao Veterinary Medicine professionals in the 2nd edition of the Great Bay Veterinarians Conference, which took place between 11 and 13 of this month in Guangdong.
At the conference that also featured the presence of AMI representatives, topics such as the development of the medical industry for pets, state -of -the -art technologies, and the interconnection of scientific research results, with the aim of promoting technological innovation, resource sharing and the training of clinical care sector for pet technology and the model technology and the model sector sector sector sector and model sector. management.
According to CPMV President Wu Sau Fong, cited by an AMI statement, the present event included on -site visits to the Clinical Skill Training Center, the Veterinary Hospital and the drug research and development companies, which helps to promote knowledge about industry and teaching integration practices.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:44:36</pubDate></item><item><title>DSAL and SJM launch Employment and Training Plan</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/25/dsal-e-sjm-lancam-plano-de-emprego-e-formacao/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) and SJM will launch a professional development plan in a guided tour of the operator's activities in hiring and then training, providing formations in all aspects and opportunities for professional development to residents that are dedicated in cultural and artistic industries.
Registration for this plan is open today and end on April 1. Registrations can be made on the DSAL Electronic page. Then there will be a lecture and the interviews on April 9.
The plan offers a total of 30 job openings for the guided tour category of the activities. Candidates admitted will receive a vocational training lasting 18 months, respectively, nine months in the Department of Hotel Operations and nine months in the Department of Activities Planning, and the training program covers initial training in the Cambridge Linguaskills, Practical English - English Conversation Training Course for the service sector, Forbes Travel Guide - Basic Excellence Training in Excellence Service, guided tour course, etc. In addition, they will also be provided by SJM to workers, opportunities for participation in various guided tours, study visits and cultural exchange sessions, among others.
According to the press release, workers who show good performance will continue to develop their professional career in the Hotel Operations Department or the Activities Planning Department.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:45:51</pubDate></item><item><title>China promises “beneficial results” in forum with foreign investors</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/25/china-promete-resultados-beneficos-em-forum-com-investidores-estrangeiros/</link><description>Chinese vice-master-master, he Lifeng, told executives of several multinationals present in a Asian country forum that China will “continue to open”, with “advantageous results for all”.
 
On the sidelines of the China Development Forum, He met with executive directors from companies such as Apple, Mercedes-Benz or Samsung, stressing that Beijing will take steps to “further improve the business environment,” the Chinese Ministry of Commerce said in a statement.
"China will host more investments from multinational companies, sharing development opportunities," said the minister, on the sidelines of the Forum, that Beijing presents as a dialogue platform between senior Chinese government leaders, multinational and academic executives.
The forum comes at a time when Beijing is trying to recover foreign investment, which has reached a record negative flows in 2024, and promote the development of the private sector, with confidence among investors near historical minimums. He Lifeng described the Chinese economy as "very resistant" and "full of vitality."
Some of the executives participating in the event, which ended yesterday, should meet this week with Chinese President Xi Jinping, according to Bloomberg news agency.
According to the Chinese government, the meeting is an opportunity to maintain direct contact with the leadership of the Asian country, being usually frequented by academics who sympathize with Beijing.
This year's theme, according to CGTN state television, is to “free all the potential for development”, with symposiums on macropolitics, scientific and technological innovation, environment or demographic challenges.
The forum has as its backdrop the slowdown of China's economy, in a period when facing the impact of the trade war launched by US leader Donald Trump.
At the opening ceremony, Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang said Beijing is "prepared" for "unexpected shocks from abroad," referring to the trade war triggered by the US tycoon, and promised that China will open more sectors of its economy to foreign investment. The Chinese executive chief urged international companies to “resist” to “protectionism”.
Li also met on Sunday with US Senator Steve Daines of the Republican Party, whom Beijing seeks “dialogue and cooperation with the United States”, and stressed that economic and commercial ties are “fundamental to bilateral relations”, according to an order issued by the official news agency Xinhua.
Li appealed to the United States to join the "principles of mutual respect and peaceful coexistence" and called for a "frank communication" to "deepen trust."
Daines also met with vice-prime minister He, whom he transmitted Trump's appeal to "stop the flow of Fentanil precursors," and said he expected "more high level dialogue."
These were the first meetings of an American politician with senior Chinese officials since Trump's return to the Oval Room.
The visit comes at a time when tensions between the world's two largest economies increase due to the mutual imposition of customs rates. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:45:49</pubDate></item></channel></rss>