<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/fundacao-rui-cunha-celebra-dia-mundial-da-poesia-com-sessao-especial-de-vida-a-um-poema/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Reopens in April Porto Cambojano whose expansion was funded by China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/reabre-em-abril-porto-cambojano-cuja-expansao-foi-financiada-pela-china/</link><description>The naval port in Cambodia whose expansion was funded by China and raised concerns about Beijing's growing military reach in the region will resume operations next month, the Cambodian authorities announced yesterday.
 
Porto will receive a Japanese ship as the first foreign vessel to pay a visit to the site, according to Major General Thong Solimo, spokesman for Cambodia's Armed Forces.
The Ream naval base-with a new quay to accommodate much larger ships, a dry dock for repairs and other infrastructures-will be inaugurated on April 2 by Prime Minister Hun Manet, according to Thong Solimo. "Giving priority to Japanese war ships is a tribute to the high level of openness in cooperation, relationships and mutual trust," he said.
China and Cambodia started the Porto project in 2022, which led the United States to express concerns that it could become a strategic post for the Chinese navy in the Gulf of Thailand.
The gulf is adjacent to the Southern Sea of ​​China, an essential wrap that China complains almost in its entirety. The United States refuses to recognize China's wide claim and regularly perform military maneuvers to reinforce sea status as international waters.
Initial concerns increased last year, after Chinese war ships gone to the newly settled pier for months, and two Japanese counterpiers, who made a visit to Cambodia, were diverted to a different installation nearby.
With the announcement of Japan's planned visit, Cambodia is probably trying to project the idea that it is open to countries besides China, the Australian Strategic Policy Institute said, Uni Graham, said Uni Graham. "It seems to be a conscious demonstration of Cambodia that Ream is not exclusively for China," he said, quoted by the Associated Press.
Japan's sea self-defense force confirmed Cambodia's invitation to Japanese ships, but refused to detail, citing operational safety regulations.
China is Cambodia's largest investor and its nearest political partner. In recent years, it has quickly expanded its navy and has become increasingly assertive in defending its vast maritime claims.
Concerns about China's activity on the ream base emerged in 2019, when the Wall Street Journal reported that a preliminary draft of an agreement, seen by US responsible, would allow China to use the base for 30 years, where it could put military personnel, store weapons and attract war ships.
The Government of Cambodia has denied such an agreement or any intention of granting China special privileges at the base, although Beijing has financed its expansion and attracted its war ships there for consecutive months.
In September, the Cambodian Ministry of Defense stated that China would give Navy Cambodian two ships of the type that were moved at the base while the expansion project was still underway.
The Ministry of Defense spokesman, General Chhum Socheat, said yesterday that Cambodia wants the installation to be open to the US and other countries. "All war ships from friendly countries can dock on the new quay, but they should first fulfill our conditions," he said, without specifying what these conditions would be. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 03:07:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Number of kindergarten students for each teacher fell to 11.7</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/numero-de-alunos-do-ensino-infantil-para-cada-professor-caiu-para-117/</link><description>The ratio between teachers and students of kindergarten was, in the academic year of 2011/2012, of 1: 16.7; In this school year, this ratio decreased to 1: 11.7. The figures were revealed by the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ), in response to a written interpellation presented by Deputy Ho Ion Sang.
 
The Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) says that the ratio between teachers and kindergartens has been falling over the last school years. According to official data, released in response to a written interpellation presented by Deputy Ho Ion Sang, in the academic year of 2011/2012, the teacher/student rat was 1: 16.7; In this school year, this ratio decreased to 1: 11.7. On the other hand, the class/kindergarten teacher in Macau increased from 1: 1.6, in the academic year 2011/2012, to 1: 2.3 in the school year 2024/2025.
In response, the DSEDJ also says that it has been encouraging schools to hire teachers to optimize ratios to “increase interaction between teachers and students and the care of teachers to the latter”. The authorities also point out that "currently, the kindergarten of most schools provides different types of services to education and students with different needs, such as supplementary classes, post-class care, school transportation and lunch service, among others."
In questioning, Ho Ion Sang said that the low birth rate of the region is causing significant damage to education, with some schools facing “survival crises” due to the lack of students, which can also do, from the perspective of the deputy, with which the quality of sector professionals decrease.
The DSEDJ replied that it has encouraged schools to elaborate their development plan, “in order to raise the educational quality of Macau”, including the application of global school evaluation, to encourage them to “optimize and development of management, curriculum and teaching, student support, among other aspects”. The Financing Plan for the Development of Educational Fund Schools provides the Intelligent Education Pilot Plan, “to support schools to apply intelligent technologies and thus provide personalized and accurate teaching,” says DSEDJ, adding that this academic year were held about 900 training courses. Interescolar pedagogical research work has also been promoted, “so that teachers from different schools can learn from each other regarding pedagogical results, with a view to raising the effectiveness of teaching and learning”.
Authorities also stressed that they have been aware of changes in the area caused by the fall in the birth rate and the school -age population, and therefore the subsidy for the promotion of school development was created, which attributes additional resources to schools that bring together the necessary conditions, “to support them in optimization or change, raise pedagogical quality and develop their pedagogical characteristics”.
DSEDJ also promises to organize professional team visits to schools and provide financial support, to support them to improve their teaching environment, as well as sensitize those in charge of education to better know the characteristics of different schools.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 03:04:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Caeal follows cases of alleged pressure to voters in the formation of candidacies</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/caeal-acompanha-casos-de-alegada-pressao-aos-eleitores-na-formacao-de-candidaturas/</link><description>The Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly is following any pressure or coercion of voters in signing the proposal bulletin of candidates to the September elections this year. Seng Ioi Man, chairman of the commission, revealed that he received reports from a resident who suffered pressure from an association to collect a certain number of signatures.
 
After the complaints in social networks about the eventual irregularity in the formation of the candidacy committees to this year's legislative elections, the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) yesterday left the guarantee of already following the possible cases of pressure or coercion of voters to sign the proposition bulletin.
Seng Ioi Man, president of Caeal, assured that he is aware of comments on online platforms on requests for support for the constitution of application committees. "We received the account of a citizen to say that he was pressured to deliver a certain number of voter signatures," the official said, in statements to journalists on the sidelines of a committee meeting.
Noting that he is accompanying and collecting information from the case, Seng Ioi Man reported, however, that no “official complaint” was received from that situation, although a citizen addressed the commission to report that he was the subject of pressures.
The spokesman also indicated that he does not currently have much information about the case. Already the citizen did not reveal if he is an employee of the association concerned, "but said it is part of the association," he said. "We appeal to all people, if someone is forced or the target of fraud to sign [an application], must immediately file a complaint to Caeal or the Commissioner against corruption, and deliver all information and data," he said.
The judge of the Second Instance Court assured that the Electoral Commission will “follow the cases rigorously”, as well as “all the opinions of citizens”. "We intend to carry out an impartial and full election, so we stress that interested parties must comply with the law and assume the responsibility of maintaining the order of election," he said.
 
Macau Pass Exchange
 
Regarding the situation in which some seniors were required to sign the proposal of applications when they asked for help from associations to exchange the new version of Macau Pass, in the context of participating in the government consumption stimulus program, Caeal pointed out to have learned of the case, but details to follow the case.
Seng Ioi Man admitted that Caeal, for now, “failed to get more information” from the case, despite trying to collect it through the various existing channels. "In fact, this is difficult for us, which does not mean that we will not follow the cases. "The entity, during the card replacement operation, cannot perform other tasks that do not have to do with the replacement of the card," he said.
The elections for the 8th Legislative Assembly are scheduled for September 14 and the electoral work is currently in the constitution phase of the candidacy committee. Until yesterday at noon, nine people requested with Caeal the request for recognition of the constitution of the candidacy committee, but, so far, no candidacy has been formalized.
At yesterday's press conference, Seng Ioi Man ruled out the impact on the formation of the candidacy due to the inequality of resources between traditional and small associations. According to Man, although associations are not prevented from collecting more than 500 signatures, "there are over 300,000 voters registered in Macao and groups can do their best to request public support," he said.
 
Without access to those excluded in the past
 
Thus will be the first scrutiny for the hemicicle after the revision of the electoral law to the Legislative Assembly last year, which provides for the exclusion of candidates considered non -patriotic. However, already before the amendment of law, in the legislative elections of direct suffrage by 2021 the candidacy of five lists and 21 candidates, 15 of which pro-democracy, “not defending the basic law” and not being “faithful to mashes” was excluded.
Seng Ioi Man, in this context, ruled out the possibility of admitting the re -candidacy to the present elections by the people who were disqualified in the elections for the 7th Legislative Assembly. "People who are not faithful to the Basic Law cannot participate in the election. The entity responsible for the assessment of the state security is the decision of the State, whose decision is liable and does not provide for an appeal.
On the other hand, under the Electoral Law for the Legislative Assembly, concessionaire companies for the exploitation of fortune games or bad luck must maintain neutrality and impartiality during the elections. Its workers observe, in the exercise of their duties, rigorous neutrality in the face of the various candidacies, being prohibited the display of elements of electoral propaganda by them.
Thus, Caeal met yesterday with the Directorate of Game Inspection and Coordination (DICJ) to co-organize, early next month, a meeting with representatives of the game companies to explain the relevant requirements.
CAEAL will also hold a clarification session on electoral procedures next Wednesday, whose registration is open until Friday at 18h. The sensitization work on legislative elections also had an information session in schools, scheduled for April 7, in order to promote students the knowledge of the holding of fair and full elections.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 03:05:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Criticisms the sale of ports of Panama do not reflect Beijing's position</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/criticas-a-venda-de-portos-do-panama-nao-refletem-posicao-de-pequim/</link><description>A Chinese analyst yesterday denied that the comment published by a Hong Kong newspaper about the sale of Panama ports by US conglomerate Blackrock representing the official position of Beijing.
 
"CK Hutchison's business is a purely private deal" and "by no means the comment represents China's official position," Lusa Gao Zhikai told Lusa Gao, who served as an interpreter of former Chinese leader Deng Xiaoping and is currently one of the best -known commentators of Chinese television.
The official portals of the Chinese administration in Macao and Hong Kong released on Friday the comment, widespread by the newspaper Ta Kung Pao, a publication of the former British colony seen as close to Beijing.
The newspaper considered that the deal it transferred to a consortium that includes Blackrock and the Investment Limited Terminal a 80% stake in a set of port subsidiaries, which generate 43 ports in 23 countries, including ports at both ends of the Panama and Cristobal channel, "is not a normal commercial practice."
"Many [Chinese] Internet users have strongly criticized this agreement and CK Hutchison Holdings, considering it as a spineless assignment, aiming only at profit and forgetting justice, ignoring national interests and major national principles, betraying and selling all the Chinese people.
Remembering that Hong Kong "enjoys freedom of the press" and "can write whatever they want," Gao Zhikai said the publication is "probably to exaggerate."
The analyst pointed out one of the maxims of the owner of CK Hutchison Holdings, the billionaire Li Ka-Shing, to justify the deal: "Everything can be sold. "Well, the company concluded that the price the US buyer has offered is a good price, or even undeniable, and that is the main reason behind the agreement," he said. "The Chinese government has nothing to do with this business," he added.
The agreement, announced on March 4, is valued at $ 22.8 billion.
Completed under the auspices of the United States in 1914, the Panama Channel, which crosses Central America, became one of the targets of US President Donald Trump, as soon as he returned to the White House on January 20. Trump accused China of mastering operations on the channel and promised to "take it back."
The comment published by TA Kung Pao also stressed that the news of the deal was known after the visit of the US Secretary of State, Marco Rubio, to Panama, and "on the eve of Trump's first speech to Congress." “It was just a coincidence? What was the nature of the agreement?”, He questioned.
The publication warned of the "Americanization and Policization" of Panama Channel: "China's maritime trade will definitely be subject to the United States."
On that possibility, Gao Zhikai was emphatic: "Someone who believes that two -part control in the Panama or Cabaz channel of ports involved in this particular transaction will affect China's leadership in transporting or naval construction is fantasizing."
In the last decade, the Asian country has built from the root or bought majority stakes on a vast network of fundamental ports for world trade, from Pireu, Greece, Gwadar, in Pakistan.
In 2024, he inaugurated a giant Porto in Peru, which aims to serve as a logistics center in the region and a crucial connection point between South America and Indo-Pacific.
According to the co cancil on Foreign Relations Reflection Group, Chinese state -owned companies hold participations in about 100 ports in 64 countries, in all oceans and continents, except Antarctica. China itself houses eight of the ten largest containers in the world. The Asian country has also modernized its naval forces and now has the largest navy on the planet.
 
BOX
 
Beijing avoids commenting on ports in Panama and criticizes economic coercion
 
China yesterday avoided commenting on the deal reached by the Hong Kong Ck Hutchison conglomerate to sell its participation in the ports of the Panama channel to the Blackrock US fund, merely rejecting “economic coercion” on the international scene. Chinese Foreign Ministry spokeswoman Mao Ning has called for “consultation of the competent Chinese authorities” to obtain specific business details without directly referring to the transaction or reports of a possible Beijing interference to prevent the sale. But he added that China rejects “economic coercion, hegemony and intimidation” at the international scene.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 03:04:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Wang Zhengping: The Magic of Photography in the Realism of Mongol Praedaries</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/wang-zhengping-a-magia-da-fotografia-no-realismo-das-pradarias-mongois/</link><description>The fantastic realism in photography. Within the 14th Macao Literary Festival - Rota das Letras, the TAP Seac Gallery will open its doors to the photography exhibition “The wind blows in the prairie”, by Chinese photographer Wang Zhengping. This exposure is not only limited to the visual aesthetics of the horses of the inner Mongolia, but also inserts itself in an important ethnographic context, where the culture and traditions of the region are eternalized through its lens.
 
The TAP Seac Gallery will be the stage of the official opening ceremony of Wang Zhengping's photography exhibition, entitled “The Wind Blows on the Pralada”, tomorrow, March 20, at 6:30 pm. This initiative is part of the XIV Macao Literary Festival Program-Rota das Letras and promises to transport visitors to a world where reality and fantasy intertwine through photographic art.
Wang Zhengping, photographer and ethnographer, has been acclaimed as one of the main exponents of artistic photography in the contemporary era of China. Since 2015, it has received international recognition, being considered one of the top ten pioneers of Asian photography in the ranking of the Pixel photographic magazine. His work, which includes award -winning photographic series and publications, reflects a deep connection with the horses that inhabit the vast landscape of the Autonomous Region of Mongolia Inner, a region that shaped his life and art.
Wang's approach to magical realism is especially remarkable. The elements that capture, from the majestic elegance of the horses to the vast horizon of the prairies, are not only visual representations, but reveal stories and feelings that capture the essence of life in Mongolia. As João Miguel Barros, the curator of the exhibition states, "The project on the northern horses of Wang Zhengping Mongolia is very close to perfection and sometimes seems to transport us to the world of enchantment and magical realism." This ability to transform everyday life into something extraordinary, as the curator pointed out, is a witness to Wang's mastery as a photographer and storyteller.
Magic realism is a literary, artistic and pictorial current that transforms the daily life into poetry and where the lines between the banal and the extraordinary irresistibly outline. Originating in Latin America, this approach challenges logic and celebrates local traditions, giving voice to stories that dance between real and fantastic. Authors such as Gabriel García Márquez and Adolfo Bioy Casares are examples of these narratives that reveal a world where the wonderful is part of everyday life. Wang Zhengping introduces this fantastic realism in the unique framing of your visual work.
The exhibition is not limited to the aesthetic beauty of horses, as well as deepens in the ethnographic dimension, where Wang Zhengping acts as a defender of cultural diversity and an archivist of human experiences. Registering the people, places and traditions of the territory, the artist promotes a richer and more complex understanding of the lives that inhabit the inner Mongolia. João Miguel Barros emphasizes that “in this other dimension, Wang Zhengping becomes a storyteller and a defender of cultural diversity”, thus highlighting the relevance of the photographer not only as an artist, but as a humanist who uses his camera to document human experience.
Also within the scope of photography, Rota das Letras enters hard in the culture of this year's edition image record and, in addition to introducing renowned photographer Chris Stowers during the prelude to the festival, now follows another collection of works by one of the biggest names in Portuguese photojournalism, with the inauguration of Alfredo Cunha's “New Independences” exhibition, scheduled for Friday, at 17h00, in the old slaughterhouse da Barra, in tune with the official opening of the festival. In addition, in the same place, the audience will have the opportunity to dive into the practice of photography with the workshop “New Nomadic Time - Observing Uniquely” by Jessie Rao, scheduled for Sunday, at 6:30 pm.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Timor-Leste first integrates Asean's internship program</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/timor-leste-integra-pela-primeira-vez-programa-de-estagios-da-asean/</link><description>Timor-Leste will first integrate the internship program of the initiative for the integration of the Association of Southeast Asia Nations (Asean), announced yesterday that organization, to which the country should join fully this year.
The program, which lasts for a year, aims to give practical experience in various Asean departments, namely the economic and socio -cultural policy and security to reduce development disparities in the region, and also include Cambodia, Laos, Myanmar and Vietnam.
"It has always been an honor to welcome employees for this important initiative and we are particularly pleased to welcome Timor-Leste's historic first participation in the program," Asean secretary Kao Kim Hourn said at the program opening ceremony, which began Monday.
According to Kao Kim Hourn, the internship program is "conceived to strengthen human capital and reinforce the institutional capacity of countries and now in Timor-Leste."
Timor-Leste President José Ramos-Horta said at the end of February that Asean heads of state should decide in May the full adhesion of Timor-Leste to the organization.
The Member States of ASEAN arrived at an agreement of principle in November 2022 to integrate Timor-Leste in the regional organization, becoming the country to have the status of observer and being able to attend all meetings, including in the summits.
ASEAN was created in 1967 by Indonesia, Singapore, Thailand, Malaysia and Philippines and aims to promote cooperation between Member States to ensure peace, stability and economic, social and cultural development of the region. They also integrate Asean, Brunei Darussalam, Cambodia, Laos, Myanmar and Vietnam.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 03:03:04</pubDate></item><item><title>UM Students were second in the Huawei ICT Contest Asia Pacific regional final</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/alunos-da-um-ficaram-em-segundo-na-final-regional-asia-pacifico-do-concurso-huawei-ict/</link><description>A team of students from the University of Macau Faculty of Science and Technology (one) participated in the Asia-Pacific regional final of the Huawei ICT 2024-2025 contest and won the second award in the computer area. This was the first time a team of UM has won an award in the computer area at the Asia-Pacific Regional final of the contest. UM student's team will continue to represent Macau at the global final in Shenzhen in May, where he will compete with top teams from around the world.
The competition attracted more than 8,000 students from over 20 countries and regions around the world. After competition rounds, more than 110 students from 12 countries and regions advanced to the Asia-Pacific Regional final.
The team consisted of Tan Hongye, Law Wai Hong and Ho Ka Meng, students of the Department of Informatics and Information Sciences at the Faculty of Science and Technology at UM. According to a statement issued by the higher education institution, the team received “great compliments” from the jurors for their “exceptional team work, solid professional knowledge and strategic planning”.
The Faculty of Science and Technology of a “is committed to providing students with state-of-the-art academic knowledge and practical opportunities, encouraging them to participate in international competitions to increase their global competitiveness,” says the institution.
The Huawei ICT contest, jointly organized by Huawei and the Asean Foundation, aims to improve students' practical knowledge and competencies on information and communication technologies, as well as develop their innovation and creativity in the use of new technologies and platforms.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 03:00:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Rotary Clubs of Macao appeal to the blood donation of the young population</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/clubes-rotary-de-macau-apelam-a-doacao-de-sangue-da-populacao-jovem/</link><description>The eight Rotary clubs of Macao and the blood transfusion services of Macao health services again co-organize Rotary's blood gift day, which will take place on Saturday afternoon, March 22, at Nova Mall Shopping Center in Taipa. Blood donation campaigns are regular practices of the Macao Rotary Club and aim to motivate the residents of Macao - especially the younger ones - to donate blood and ensure continuous blood supplies in the region.
In a statement, the organization thanks the collaboration of Nova Mall and underlines the importance of conducting the initiative in a commercial area conceived and frequented by the local Macao community. “Conducting the event will help us reach important demographic groups, including young people and middle-aged residents of various cultural and ethnic origins, which are potential blood donors,” he says in the note sent to the press. The appeal is especially directed to students of secondary and university teachings, as blood donation by these age groups has been decreasing from year to year.
According to data provided by Blood Transfusion Service, and cited in the statement, the percentage of new blood donors descended 13.6% in homologous terms, being 21.1% in 2024. In total, only 13,740 people donated blood last year, which represents a decline of 13.6% compared to 2023. Macao in the blood gift, as the statistics explain: by 2024, the number of donors attending university education decreased 3.5% compared to the same period, while the percentage of donors in secondary education went from 9% in 2019, for the 2% checked last year.
The Rotary de Macao club warns that "the decrease in the participation of young people in blood donation can lead to future shortages in blood reserves in Macao." Thus, this year's campaign focuses especially on younger populations, with a “special appeal to actively participate in the blood gift, contributing to a sustainable blood supply to the needy patients”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 03:00:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Hélder Beja is the new director of Doclisboa</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/helder-beja-e-o-novo-director-do-doclisboa/</link><description>Helder Beja was elected by the Directorate of APORDOC - Association for the documentary as the new director of Doclisboa - International Film Festival, succeeding the Mexican producer Paula Astorga. The former journalist performed the role of co-founder and director of the Macao Literary Festival during seven editions, between 2012 and 2018, and is currently one of the organizers of the Asia Pacific Writers &amp; Translators Biennial Conference.
Apart from the activity developed in Asia and, above all, in China - where he lived for almost a decade - the editor and the screenwriter joined the Doclisboa team in the last two editions, before taking over the new position. The 2025 edition also renewed the position of co-chief of programming, now occupied by Boris Nelepo, programmer and critic of Russian origin, and kept Cíntia Gil as an associated programmer, a function he has been performing since 2015.
Speaking to the observer newspaper, Hélder Beja assumes the challenge “with great enthusiasm and dedication”, noting the “unique place” of Doclisboa as the oldest film festival in Portugal dedicated exclusively to the documentary. “It is a festival that knew how to build its relevance in the international context through a unique and rigorous program,” he says, quoted by the Portuguese newspaper. "As a cultural and artistic project, it is a space that privileges time as opposed to immediacy, the deepening of opposition to superficiality. It is a festival with a very rich past and file, which always exceeded for the quality and risk in its programming line, without ever forgetting the public."
As a new director, Helder Beja maintains the mission of promoting the festival as a “project that supports the Portuguese film community”, not only through the promotion of national production films, “but also creating spaces for fundamental discussions about public policy for film”.
Doclisboa was founded in 2004 and takes place in Lisbon every year, always in October. The 23rd edition will take place between October 16 and 26, and is open the film entries until May 31st.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 03:06:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Miguel de Senna Fernandes appointed representative of China's intangible cultural heritage</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/miguel-de-senna-fernandes-nomeado-representante-do-patrimonio-cultural-intangivel-da-china/</link><description>The Ministry of Culture and Tourism of the Popular Republic of China announced yesterday the appointment of Miguel de Senna Fernandes as representative of the country's intangible cultural heritage, as promoter of the theater in Patuá. At the end, the director and director of the Dóci Papiaçám Di Macau is pleased by the distinction attributed by the interior of China and raises the veil over the show prepared for this year.
 
Miguel de Senna Fernandes was appointed by the Ministry of Culture and Tourism of the Popular Republic of China as a representative of the country's intangible cultural heritage, as a promoter of the theater in Patuá. This appointment arises after, in June 2023, the theater in Patuá was officially recognized as intangible cultural heritage in the country.
In addition to Macaense, LO Seng Chung, president of the Cheok Chai Un Fok Tak Chi Tou Mio Chek Lei Wui of Macau, was appointed representative of China's intangible cultural heritage, as a festivities dynamic in the name of the God Tou Tei.
In the case of Patuá, the theater has been the main vehicle of disclosure, justifies Miguel de Senna Fernandes. Speaking to the end, the director and director of the Dóci Papiaçá Di Macau says that the distinction "is a guarantee that Patuá theater will last in Macao." “Being recognized by the continent is very important,” he says, noting that this distinction must also be shared with the other elements of the Dóci Papiaçá di Macau.
 
This year's shows scheduled for May 30 and 31
 
This year's Dóci Papiaçá Di Macau show, included in the program of the Macao Arts Festival, is scheduled for May 30 and 31, at the large auditorium of the Macao Cultural Center. “Cuza is Rene? (What's up?)” Is the title of the play to be presented this year.
Miguel de Senna Fernandes raises the veil of the show and says that the narrative will have as a scenario a center of explanations and will touch topics such as the integration of Macao in the great bay and the connection with the Lusophone countries. References to Macao's current will be present, as always, being "to the interpretation of each one."
The group is already rehearsing, and the number of participants will be identical to last year's edition. As in the last edition, the musical component will be very present in this year's play, as well as the participation of younger actors. The part of the videos will also continue to be part of the show.
Miguel de Senna Fernandes wants to take the theater in Patuá to Portugal and the interior of China. This is one of the group's objectives for 2026, he confesses. What has been delaying the move from Dóci to Portugal is the logistics part, but there are already contacts with Portuguese entities and the group's guardian says that next year they will focus on this objective. Last year, it is recalled, Miguel de Senna Fernandes managed to take the Choir of the Choir of Dóci Papiaçám to act in Lisbon</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>WHO praises “excellence” of health care in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/oms-elogia-excelencia-dos-cuidados-de-saude-em-macau/</link><description>The director of the region for the Pacific-West World Health Organization (WHO) visited several hospital institutions in Macau and recognized the quality of the medical services of the territory, as well as the efforts to promote residents' physical and psychological health. 
 
Ma'u Piukala Skirt, director of the region for the Pacific-West World Health Organization (WHO), visited the medical institutions subordinate to the health services of Macao and praised the quality of services provided to users.
The WHO official was accompanied by Liu Yue, executive director of the Department of Planning and Management, and by Alvis Lo, Director of Health Services, in the visits made to some of the health facilities or representative of health promotion efforts in the territory. These include the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center (CHCSJ), the Green Island Health Center and a secondary school where the “Healthy School” project was implemented.
The delegation headed by the director of the region to the Pacific-Width of the WHO began by visiting Hospitals and Emergency Services: the emergency services of CHCSJ, Via Verde de stroke, the Endoscopy Center and the public health specialty building, according to the itinerary shared by health services in a statement. The WHO official recognized ChCSJ's “excellence of management”, highlighting the quality of the facilities and medical equipment available at the hospital, in addition to the efficiency of work and the level of technique of emergency medical personnel. He also considered that the waiting time for the provision of public health care was “shorter” in the MSAR than in other regions, being able to respond to the “great demand” by residents.
This was followed by a visit to the Ilha Verde Health Center, representing the areas of community health services and treatment of chronic diseases or caused by addiction (for example, alcoholic beverages or tobacco). In this regard, health services highlight that “the number of community medical services already represents more than 60% of the total number of services”, in a demonstration of the concept of “universal health coverage” that the WHO director also recognized and praised. He also stressed “three prominent points” in the context of community health care in Macao: the “remarkable results” and “international leadership” in the management of chronic diseases; the “exemplary value” of the diagnostic and treatment model by levels; And thirdly, the successful control of per capita alcohol consumption and the efforts to alleviate the problems caused by smoking. As for this point, he left the suggestion of "adopting as soon as possible, the total prohibition of the electronic cigarette."
Finally, the delegation visited one of 76 schools in Macao where the “Healthy School” project has already been adopted, which currently covers about 90,000 students. The WHO official visited several spaces of the secondary school selected for the visit - such as the bar, the fitness room and the health room - and praised the integration of various health promoting elements in the educational establishment, such as the availability of healthy meals or sports facilities. At the same time, it praised the concern with the psychological health of children and youth, through the provision of psychological counseling services, the promotion of group activities between teachers, students and in charge of education and the transmission of periodic “health messages” digitally. Health services highlight that these health and psychological health promotion measures have obtained “impressive” results.
MA'U Piukala Skirt had already found themselves last Thursday, with Lam, secretary for social affairs and culture. According to a statement issued by health services at the time, the WHO official considered that "Macao has done a good job of carrying out the objective of 'universal health coverage', with a relatively high level of health protection for residents."
Quoted in a press release of the Government of MSAR, Skirt Ma'u Piukala also said that vaccination work in the territory "has obtained remarkable results, having been established a comprehensive vaccination program that includes several common diseases, which significantly reduced the incidence of transmitted diseases, thus protecting the health of residents."
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 03:03:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says Chinese president visits Washington in a “not too distant future”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/trump-diz-que-presidente-chines-visita-washington-num-futuro-nao-muito-distante/</link><description>US President Donald Trump has said that his Chinese counterpart Xi Jinping will visit Washington in a “not too distant future” to the growing commercial tensions between the world's two largest economies due to the imposition of tariffs.
 
"This will happen in the not too distant future," Trump said to journalists during a meeting of the new Kennedy Center board, a famous cultural center of the capital Washington.
The US head of state also noted that senior Chinese government officials, “below” XI, will soon visit the US capital, although it has not advanced names or details about possible dates.
Trump mentioned Xi's visit when he said he received visits from foreign leaders in the White House in recent weeks and asked them how Washington was. The Republican stressed that he is “cleaning Washington”, including trying to clean tents used by homeless and graphitis.
Last week the US media had reported that Washington and Beijing began discussions about a summit between the leaders of both countries in June.
The Chinese press had already suggested the possibility of a meeting in April.
Also the Hong Kong South China Morning Post newspaper has advanced that Trump could move to China in April to meet Chinese homologist Xi Jinping.
Since the Republican's victory in US presidentials in November that Trump and Xi have expressed interest in holding a summit.
Since Trump's inauguration in January, US administration has threatened, and then suspended customs rates about Mexico and Canada, while committing to punish Europe and other business partners as well. So far, China is the only country that has effectively faced widespread increases in Trump's rates decided.
 
The White House imposed additional 20% rates on all goods from China, citing the role of the Asian country in the US Fentanil crisis. Beijing retaliated quickly at his own rates, adapting the answer to avoid climbing the tensions.
Other actions that are being considered by the Trump business team include restricting Chinese investment in the US and US investment in China, aiming at China-dominated industries such as shipbuilding, and further limiting the sale of high-tech products to Chinese companies.
Trump and Xi had already talked by telephone in January, days before the inauguration of the American for his second term, in a conversation in which they discussed business relations and the future in the United States of the Chinese company by the company bytedance. Donald Trump said he was open to negotiating a new trade agreement with China and praised Xi repeatedly.
The two leaders reached an agreement in 2020 to end the trade war that harmed both economies. However, bilateral relations deteriorated with the covid-19 pandemic, which Trump attributed to China. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 03:04:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Inaugurated Transfrontic Ambulance Service between Macau and Zhuhai</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/inaugurado-servico-de-ambulancias-transfronteiricas-entre-macau-e-zhuhai/</link><description>The transionic ambulance service between Macau and Zhuhai officially entered service, allowing the needy patients to be transported “point to point” among the designated public hospitals. Authorities predict that there is an increase in the demand for transionic health care in the future, highlighting that the inauguration of the new service has reinforced health cooperation in the Great Bay.
 
Macao and Zhuhai authorities have announced the launch of the transionic ambulance service since last Monday, after the parties signed, on January 9 of this year, the memorandum on the transfrontic transfer service point to “hospital-hospital” between the two sides of the border.
According to the Fire Department at the beginning of the year, five transionic ambulances will be available with double enrollment that can circulate to Guangdong.
According to a statement issued by the Unit Police Services (SPU), the competent departments of Macao and Zhuhai have held several meetings in recent months and have defined their traffic procedures and the facilitation mechanism of the border passage, stating that “the conditions are gathered” now to start the transmitting transport service of sick between Zhuhai and Macau.
"With the increase in the displacements of the residents of the Great Bay, it is expected that there is an increase in the demand for transionic health care," he said. The body stressed that the operating operating of the service is articulated with the requirements of the general line of planning for the development of the large bay, which stipulate that the public services of the various regions “should study the development of transfronting land transport services of people who do not suffer from serious or critical diseases” and “launch pilot projects of cooperation in the transfers transference of sick sick designated public hospitals ”.
The government explained that, to activate the transfrontic ambulance mechanism, it is necessary to exist a prior agreement between the issuing hospital and the receptor hospital. The availability of the service must also consider the needs, security and interests of patients. At the same time, a mechanism that foresees abusive situations was established.
The new mechanism will work in parallel with the old “Ambulance Ambulance” model, that is, patients need to change ambulance in border-controlled areas. “Certain patients who do not gather the conditions for direct transfringe transportation of ambulance still need to use the old model” with ambulance exchange, warned the body.
The present service between Zhuhai and Macau was launched four months later in relation to Hong Kong, whose transfronic ambulance pilot plan was inaugurated in late November last year, with three ambulances. For now, there was no case of use of this service.
The SPU stressed in a statement issued on Monday that the service between Zhuhai and Macao not only symbolizes “a realization of deepening health cooperation in the Great Bay”, but also “a new step” in health cooperation between Zhuhai and Macau. In addition, “has injected a new dynamic in the integrated development of regional health services” and is a solid basis for transfronist rescue work between Zhuhai and Macao, it can be read in the note.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 03:02:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Chan Un Tong promises to improve labor legislation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/chan-un-tong-promete-aperfeicoar-legislacao-laboral/</link><description>Chan Un Tong yesterday took office as director of the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL). Chan Tze Wai also took office as a subdirector of the body.
In the speech given at the time, Chan Un Tong said he felt the "weight of responsibility" and stated that "according to the spirit of President Xi Jinping's important speech, he will persist in the effective resolution of the population -based employment problem and reinforce training resources to form high quality qualified frames for Macao." The new director of Dsal also said that it will “improve labor legislation, promote the creation of harmonious labor relations, as well as to provide services in a sincere and pragmatic way to the entire population and to make efforts to support the development of micro, small and medium enterprises”.
Tai Kin IP, secretary for the economy and finance, said he hoped both Chan Un Tong and Chan Tze Wai lead Dsal's colleagues "to perform, pragmatically, work within their functions." On the other hand, the secretary also wished that the new leaders "further promote the global development of the Macao labor market, protect work rights and interests under the law and build, with new ideas, a harmonious society between employers and workers, thus continuing to make more efforts to Macao's prosperity and stability."
Chan Un Tong began working in Public Administration in 2002, and from May 2014 to May 2016, the position of Deputy Coordinator of the Human Resources Cabinet, and from May 2016 to the present date, the position of Subdirector of Dsal. Chan Un Tong has a degree in Economic Law at the Faculty of Economics of the University of Jinan in Canton.
Chan Tze Wai entered the civil service in 1991, having performed the positions of head of the Intellectual Property Department of the Directorate of Economics Services from 2006 to 2011, subdirecting the Directorate of Economics Services from 2011 to 2021 and the Deputy Directorate of the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development from 2021 to date. Chan Tze Wai is a degree in Economics from the University of Jinan in Canton.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 03:00:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Pequim diz que movimentos militares junto a Taiwan são castigo para líder da ilha</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/pequim-diz-que-movimentos-militares-junto-a-taiwan-sao-castigo-para-lider-da-ilha/</link><description>The China government has stated that the recent Chinese military activity with Taiwan is a "firm punishment" against the Taiwanese leader after William Lai ranked Beijing as a "hostile foreign force." On Monday night, the Taiwan Cabinet Office spokesman for the State Council (the Chinese executive) accused William Lai of "aggravating the confrontation" in Taiwan's Strait.
According to Chinese official news agency Xinhua, Chen Binhua described the Chinese military maneuvers as necessary, justified and "a powerful impediment against separatist forces."
At least 59 Chinese combat aircraft have flew over Taiwan in recent days, the highest number since October, the island's Ministry of National Defense announced yesterday in a statement. Of these aircraft, 54 participated in “joint combat” patrols with Chinese military ships on Monday, the ministry said, which also detected nine ships and two balloons.
In a statement issued Monday night, Taiwan's authorities expressed “strong conviction” by China's military actions and denounced the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) as “constantly” expands its presence in the region, challenges the status quo and “resorts to coercion in the gray area” to undermine stability.
“The CCP cannot, on the one hand, publicly declare that it wants stability, while, on the other hand, continuing to tease actions that undermine regional and even global peace and stability. As a responsible member of the international community, Taiwan will continue to fight for peace, stability and prosperity in the region,” said Lin Chia-Lung, quoted in the statement.
Military activity also served as “a solemn warning to the external forces that interfere” on the Taiwan issue, Chen Binhua said, referring to the United States, the island's main arms supplier. "Taiwan's independence is incompatible with peace in the Taiwan Strait," the spokesman reiterated, adding that Lai "has stubbornly adhered to the separatist position" and "has been pressured by dissociation between the two sides of the Strait." Lai's behavior, said Chen, "has continually pushed Taiwan into a dangerous military situation."
If the Taiwanese authorities “dare to provoke and play with the fire, they will only get their own ruin and be crushed,” he added. William Lai, considered a "Combatant for Independence" and a Beijing Agitator, classified China as a "hostile foreign force" on March 13, during one of his hardest speeches since taking office.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 03:03:14</pubDate></item><item><title>China wants to integrate exporters in the domestic market compared to protectionism</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/china-quer-integrar-exportadores-no-mercado-interno-face-a-proteccionismo/</link><description>China is studying measures to help export-dependent companies expand in the domestic market at a time when it seeks to compensate for the impact of protectionist measures on the United States and other markets.
 
The Chinese Ministry of Commerce is currently exploring the most effective ways to help exporters reorient themselves to the domestic market.
Minister Wang Wenta visited a Wide Textile Commerce Company this weekend, according to Yuyuan Tantian, an account on the Chinese social network affiliated with state television CCTV.
For Chinese exporters, a change of focus to the domestic market brings a number of challenges, including adapting to different preferences of consumers, payment systems and regulatory regimes. "Integrating domestic and external trade and supporting exporting companies in expanding their local sales will be a long-term strategy rather than a temporary response to external shocks," reads Yuyuan Tantian.
The measure arises after US President Donald Trump has an additional 20% customs tax rates on all Chinese products. Washington will also be preparing to launch a broader reciprocal tariff regime next month.
Beijing retaliated with the imposition of customs rates on a series of US agricultural products and restricted the export of various essential minerals. But the trade war is already felt throughout the Chinese economy.
China exports grew by 2.3%, in homologous terms, during the first two months of 2025, a significant slowdown compared to the 10.7% growth in December.
Beijing also summoned Walmart executives for conversations last week, after being reported that the US retailer giant pressed Chinese suppliers to lower prices to compensate for the impact of increasing customs rates. But Chinese companies face protectionist measures in other markets as well, including Europe and developing countries.
Indonesia, for example, imposed up to 200% rates on Chinese textile products in order to protect the country's small and medium -sized companies against what it considers to be unfair competition.
The US is also an important market for China's textile and clothing industry. About 17% of Chinese textile exports and clothing went to that country last year, according to Yuyuan Tantian.
To support the transition to domestic sales, the Ministry of Commerce plans to organize a series of exhibitions across the country to advise exporters to adapt their sales channels and product standards to the domestic market.
"The expansion of domestic sales to foreign trade companies is not about the flow of exports not sold - it has to do with the introduction of high quality foreign trade products in the domestic market," said CCTV -affiliated account.
The strategy fits the growing efforts of Beijing to increase domestic demand. On Monday, the government revealed a vast plan to stimulate consumption, which includes from reducing the costs of child care to stabilization of real estate markets and scholarships.
Signs of improvement are gradually emerging. Data released on Monday showed that retail sales in China increased 4%in homologous terms in the first two months of 2025, exceeding analysts' expectations. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 03:04:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Cunha Foundation celebrates World Poetry Day with Special Session “Give Life to a Poem”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/03/19/fundacao-rui-cunha-celebra-dia-mundial-da-poesia-com-sessao-especial-de-vida-a-um-poema/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation presents this Friday, March 21, at 6:30 pm, a tertulia entitled “Give Life to a Poem”, regarding World Poetry Day. The session, co-organized by the Book Friends Association in Macao and the Poetry of Friends of Jardim da Flora, will be held in Portuguese and Chinese languages ​​and has free admission.
The event will be led by the doctor and writer Shee Va, who will encourage those present to reveal poems with special meaning in their lives. Any interested party can participate this cultural afternoon, just bringing a poem of their choice, written in Portuguese or Chinese, and sharing it with the other participants gathered in the Rui Cunha Foundation gallery.
In a statement, the institution explains that the purpose of activity is to “enrich the common experience” through the sharing of poetry, one of the “pillars of literary art” that transcends centuries and civilizations “with its ability to thrill, provoke reflections and convey feelings”. In addition to serving as a tribute to poetic and literary creation, Tertulia also aims to support and preserve the linguistic diversity present in the territory of Macao, both in the written and spoken word.
“More than a simple set of verses, poetry is a manifestation of the human soul, which can be lyrical, epic, social, philosophical or experimental, adapting to the different eras and styles. From Camões's sonnets and the classic poems of Liu Yong, to the free verses of contemporary poetry, this literary genre has been a powerful means of communication and resistance,” released by the Foundation.
World Poetry Day was instituted by UNESCO in 1999 at the 30th General Conference in Paris. Celebrated annually on March 21, the date aims to emphasize the importance of poetry as a common artistic heritage to all humanity and as a tool promoting the creative expression and linguistic richness and plurality.</description><pubDate /></item></channel></rss>