<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/30/plataforma-chinesa-de-ia-manus-vai-integrar-grupo-meta-apos-acordo-de-aquisicao/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>The year 2025 in review</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/30/o-ano-de-2025-em-revista/</link><description>2025 ends in an international situation of confrontation and international division. Europe was the scene of this worsening, putting into question the virtualities of international law and the institutional meaning of the United Nations and its Security Council.


NATO

Reading the evolution of two years of war in Ukraine, NATO decided at its summit in June 2025 that its member states will have to increase their defense spending to 5% of GDP by 2035. The division has become sharper between those who invest in the purchase of military equipment to prevent the worsening of international tension and those who prioritize technological innovation in the development of internal capabilities. Of all the members of the Alliance, France emphasized its divergent line regarding a common Atlantic thought on the functioning of the continent's defense.
The Alliance reinforced its willingness to support aid to Ukraine in the face of the continued Russian invasion with the seizure of important areas of Dombass. In terms of equipment, air defense instruments and the promotion of joint initiatives, such as the development of a new generation of drones.


Ukraine and impossible peace

In March, the Summit on Ukraine took place in London, which brought together 16 allied and EU countries. The objective is to seek to develop a peace plan for Ukraine to complement North American initiatives. At the end of 2025, American diplomacy presented its own peace proposal. This met with numerous reservations from European partners and naturally from Ukraine. The proposal contained the following points: Ukraine's sovereignty would be formally recognized; Ukraine should give up accessing NATO by removing this reference from its Constitution; there would under no circumstances be NATO troops stationed on its territory.
On the other hand, the country would commit to reducing its military equipment in terms of internal resources. The plan ensured security guarantees for Ukraine under the commitment of the United States and European allies in the event of new military action by Russia. Finally, the US would cooperate with Ukraine in rebuilding destroyed areas and providing a financial reconstruction assistance package.
In the final weeks of 2025, Europe proposed a counterproposal aimed at guaranteeing Ukrainian sovereignty, including a non-aggression agreement from Russia. The changes to the American proposal are significant. Zelensky reinforced his diplomatic action through visits to European countries and meetings with their leaders. He sought two things: the provision of urgent military equipment for the country's defense; the use of Russian financial funds frozen in European banks to support Ukraine.
Despite the convergence of positions, European promises have been confronted with disagreement from the member states closest to Moscow: Hungary, Slovakia and Cyprus. These reservations, taking into account the principle of unanimity established by treaties for deliberation on foreign policy issues, weaken the European position. They reinforce Valdimir Putin's conviction that he can win the war.


The sunset of transatlantic relations

The Trump administration's new “National Security Strategy” redefines the role of the United States at a global level and adds reservations to the traditional conception of the transatlantic relationship. Europe is designated as a strategic risk (“civilizational erasure”) and the NSS document develops severe criticisms of the continent's immigration policies. The document states "immigration policies are transforming the continent and creating conflicts, censorship of freedom of expression and repression of opposition have grown, birth rates have collapsed and the loss of national identities and self-confidence has worsened. If current trends continue, the continent will be unrecognizable in twenty years, or less."
The document emphasizes the purpose of reducing American commitment to European defense. It pressures European states to reinforce their endogenous military capacity by accelerating self-defense efforts and adding capabilities to their defense industries. The document created a huge uproar among European governments, due to fear of a reduction in traditional US financial support, especially at a serious time of war in Ukraine. Added to this are Russian provocations in the North Sea and drone overflights over military infrastructures in European countries. These events were attributed to Russia.


Geopolitical realignments

The war in Ukraine has been causing the redefinition of alliances, military assistance, energy and security chains. It makes it urgent to review the logic of the post-Cold War blocs, not only with regard to NATO, but also with Mercosur and the West's complex relationship with China. The NSS strategic document qualifies China as “the supreme ideological enemy” and economic rival. It sets the objective for the United States to rebalance the economic relationship with Beijing, prioritizing reciprocity and fairness in commercial exchanges and reducing cooperation in sectors it calls “sensitive”. The document reveals the intensification of security concerns in the Indo-Pacific and refers to maintaining the status quo regarding Taiwan as essential.
The NSS states that military deterrence against China remains a priority, but depends on greater involvement of regional allies (such as Japan and South Korea) in defensive and deterrence efforts. It leads the development of regional partnerships with traditional US allies but this time includes India and other countries in the region within the “QUAD” framework to contain China's influence. QUAD is a cooperation platform between the United States, Japan, India and Australia. It aims to promote security and stability in the Indo-Pacific, in areas such as maritime security, supply chains, cutting-edge technology (5G and semi-conductors), infrastructure and humanitarian aid and response to natural disasters.
China has responded to this geostrategic challenge by deepening its strategic partnership with Russia, which it avoids calling itself an alliance although it brings together most of its characteristics by associating between great powers. It wants to reduce the US military, economic and regulatory presence in the Indo-Pacific region. This bilateral cooperation is developed along three axes: security and defense, economy and energy and regional diplomacy.
Russia and China carry out joint military exercises in the Pacific and maritime areas close to Japan and South Korea, participate in coordinated air and sea patrols, and collaborate on military technologies. On the economic axis, Russia supplies China with energy and raw materials. In return, it receives Chinese investment in infrastructure and the purchase of Russian energy at favorable prices. Russia actively participates in China's One Belt One Road initiative after previously resisting participation in it.
In terms of strategic orientation, both countries defend – at least in rhetoric – a multipolar order. They oppose what they call exclusive alliances such as QUAD and AUKUS. They align strategies in regional “foras”, such as the Shanghai Cooperation Organization. Their main objective is to limit the United States' ability to influence regional normative rules. This ideological and political consortium faces several risks: Russia fears becoming excessively dependent on China; China fears being drawn into conflicts involving Russia; Russia views its zone of influence in the Far East as an area in which Chinese economic participation is necessary. In the medium term, it is seen as a threat to Russian geopolitical interests in East Asia, but also in its relationship with North Korea.
In short, the year 2025 consolidated several trends that were outlined with Russia's invasion of Ukraine in 2022. On the one hand, the reinforcement of European and NATO defense commitments with very ambitious targets, in terms of military expenditure and operational readiness. On the other, the emergence of a new diplomatic and geopolitical race between the old transatlantic consensus and the Russia-China alliance.
On the other hand, the perception that peace in Ukraine and European security depend on political decisions where Americans, Europeans and Ukraine itself have different views. In how to guarantee peace on the continent. A complementary unknown is how the alliance in the East can help calm a tense and tumultuous international environment. Or on the contrary, worsen it with the increase in incidents in the South China Sea and the arms race in the Indo-Pacific.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 22:06:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Hotel occupancy rate exceeds 90% in November</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/30/taxa-de-ocupacao-hoteleira-supera-os-90-em-novembro/</link><description>The hotel occupancy rate increased slightly to 90.2% in November, although the rate for four and three star hotels decreased slightly in annual terms. According to data revealed yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), hotels in the region received more than 1.19 million people in the month in question, with emphasis on the growth in the number of guests from Japan (52.3% more) and Thailand (47%).

In November, the average occupancy rate of Macau hotel rooms stood at 90.2%, a slight increase of 0.7 percentage points compared to the same period of the previous year. This increase is due to the growth in the occupancy rate of five-star hotels, which increased by 2.5 percentage points to 94%, while the rate of four- and three-star hotels decreased by 1.2 and 3.1 percentage points to 84.6% and 84.3%, respectively.
According to data revealed yesterday by the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC), at the end of November there were 147 hotel establishments providing accommodation services to the public (1 more, in annual terms), providing a total of 45,000 guest rooms (3.5% more). During the month under review, Macau hotels hosted 1,193,000 individuals, which represents an increase of 1.9% compared to the same period last year.
Looking at the geographic origin of visitors who stayed overnight in Macau, the interior of China continues to lead the table with 859,000 guests – 72% of the total, although there is a slight reduction of 0.7 percentage points compared to the previous November. The number of guests arriving from Hong Kong rose 8.2% to 141,000 people.
The 125,000 international guests represented 10.5% of the total, an increase of 12.7% compared to last year's data. Within this group, guests from South Korea (34,000), Japan (11,000), Thailand and Singapore (8,000) stand out, with respective growth of 11.7%, 52.3%, 47% and 0.5%. In turn, the number of guests from Malaysia (10,000) fell by 5.1%. The average length of stay for guests corresponded to 1.7 nights, just 0.1 nights more compared to last year.
DSEC also counted 191,000 visitors entering the territory, a decline of 12.5% ​​in annual terms. Even so, compared to the previous month of October, there was an increase of 29.1%. While the number of tour visitors from mainland China (148,000) fell by 23.7% year on year, the number of international tour visitors (28,000) grew by 33.8%.
Taking stock of the first eleven months of the year, the hotel occupancy rate stands at 89.3%, 3.2 percentage points more than the same month last year. Hotel establishments also accommodated 0.6% more guests, totaling 13,313,000 individuals, for an average stay of 1.7 nights.
From January to November, the number of visitors arriving on tours to Macau corresponded to 1,716,000 people, a year-on-year drop of 10.3%. Conversely, the number of visitors on tours rose 17.7% to 215,000.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 22:14:48</pubDate></item><item><title>New annual award from the Jorge Álvares Foundation honors friendship between Portugal and China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/30/novo-premio-anual-da-fundacao-jorge-alvares-homenageia-a-amizade-entre-portugal-e-china/</link><description>The Jorge Álvares Foundation announced the creation of the “Jorge Álvares Foundation Award – General Vasco Rocha Vieira – Portugal-China Friendship”, an annual distinction worth 25 thousand euros. The award, which honors the last Governor of Macau, aims to encourage studies and actions that strengthen the relationship between Portugal, China and Macau, alternating annually between recognizing institutions and research work.

The Jorge Álvares Foundation has established a new annual award with the aim of promoting friendship and knowledge between Portugal, the People's Republic of China and Macau. Entitled “Jorge Álvares Foundation Award – General Vasco Rocha Vieira – Portugal-China Friendship”, the distinction, worth 25 thousand euros, pays tribute to General Vasco Rocha Vieira, last Governor of Macau, who was also founder and curator of the foundation itself.
The award will have two categories that will alternate in consecutive years. In even years, from 2026 onwards, it will be awarded in the “Institutions” category, open to any entity, national or foreign, that has developed relevant actions to deepen the relationship between the Portuguese, Chinese and Macau communities. These actions can cover areas such as culture, language (including Patuá), science, education and philanthropy.
In odd-numbered years, from 2027 onwards, the prize will be awarded in the “Research Works” category. This aspect is open to anyone, without academic or nationality restrictions, and rewards the quality of studies written on a specific topic, within the scope of Portuguese-Chinese relations, with a particular focus on Macau.
To provide preparation time for potential candidates, the organization announced in advance the theme of the first edition of the research category, which will be awarded in 2027. Under the title “From the signing of the Joint Declaration to the transfer of the Portuguese Administration of Macau”. This theme focuses on the historical period between the 1987 Sino-Portuguese agreement and the transition of sovereignty in 1999.
Applications for the first edition of the award, in the “Institutions” category for the year 2026, already have a defined calendar. The submission period will run from January 1st to June 30th, 2026, through an online form available on the award's official website. The jury's decision is scheduled for October 2026, with the delivery ceremony scheduled for December of the same year.
According to the regulations, available online, applications for works or initiatives that have been sponsored by the Jorge Álvares Foundation, or for institutional actions completed more than two years ago at the time of each edition's announcement, will not be accepted. Members of the foundation's governing bodies or its partner institutions also cannot compete in the “Research Work” category.
The Jorge Álvares Foundation, established in Lisbon in 1999 and recognized as a non-profit, public utility entity, has as its fundamental objective, within the framework of the Portuguese-Chinese Joint Declaration, to promote cooperation between Portugal and the Special Administrative Region of Macau. Its activity is carried out in the cultural, educational, scientific, artistic and social areas, with a particular focus on supporting the study and dissemination of Macau and promoting better knowledge of its reality and future projection, maintaining a privileged relationship with the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 22:12:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Creative economy is a “golden key” for Macau, says Tai Kin Ip</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/30/economia-criativa-e-uma-chave-de-ouro-para-macau-diz-tai-kin-ip/</link><description>Tai Kin Ip yesterday defended the importance of the creative economy for the development and opening of Macau to the outside world. In a speech given at the inauguration session of two events that took place, for the first time, in Macau, the Secretary for Economy and Finance also assured that the Government is promoting initiatives to attract creative talent and establish companies and large projects related to the sector.

Tai Kin Ip participated yesterday in the opening ceremony of the International Conference on Creative Economy and Commercial Development and the 6th Forum of Cultural and Creative Industries of China and Central and Eastern European Countries, events organized for the first time in Macau. Speaking on the occasion, the Secretary for Economy and Finance considered that the creative economy is a “golden key” for economic transformation, industrial development and Macau's cooperation with other cultures and civilizations.
The official began by pointing out that “the panorama of global development is changing” markedly in recent times, bringing new challenges and opportunities that must be managed through cooperation and dialogue with other countries and cultures. The creative economy – based on industries such as arts, technology or design – is understood as a “golden key” that allows connection and mutual understanding between Macau and the rest of the world, in addition to being a “new engine” for the recovery and economic transformation of the territory.
In this regard, Tai Kin Ip recalled that the proposals in the 15th National Five-Year Plan reinforce the role of culture as an essential pillar of society and defend its use for the country's economic and social development – ​​namely, by deepening “exchange and mutual learning between civilizations and broadly promoting international cultural cooperation”, he said.

FORUM IS A “SIGNIFICANT STEP” FOR MACAU

Speaking before an audience of experts and academics, the secretary highlighted the importance of the Forum for Cultural and Creative Industries of China and Central and Eastern European Countries as a connecting force for Eurasian countries and regions, which find space here for sharing “wisdom” and “resources”.
“The first holding of this event in Macau represents a significant step in realizing the spirit of the Silk Road, promoting a significant practice in the joint construction of high-quality development, as well as the recognition of Macau's role as a platform for international exchange”, he highlighted. The unique characteristics of the region – such as more than four centuries of Portuguese influence, the fusion between different cultures and the rich material and immaterial heritage – allow it to enjoy a position conducive to “innovative inspiration” and economic and commercial cooperation with the outside world.
The government official highlighted that the Macao SAR Executive has made efforts to promote an increasingly deeper and successful integration between culture, tourism and commerce, in order to inject new dynamism into the diversification of the economy and attract intellectual resources and highly qualified international staff.
In a new reference to creative industries, Tai Kin Ip also assured that the Government “is continually improving the political environment to attract creative talents and the installation of companies”, including the construction of “cutting-edge projects” such as the Macau International Integrated Tourism and Culture Zone and the Macau Science and Technology Research and Development Industrial Park.
The Secretary for Economy and Finance also mentioned the “imminent” launch of Silk Road Television, a new television channel that this year received a license to operate in Macau for the next 15 years. In an order signed by the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, and published in the Official Bulletin on September 1st, it is stated that “the primary objective” of the broadcaster “is to effectively communicate the Chinese narrative, spread the voice of China and present to the world an authentic, three-dimensional and complete image of the country”.
According to Secretary Tai Kin Ip, the channel also appears as an opportunity to provide “a new international media platform” that disseminates the Forum's results and promotes creative economic cooperation and cultural exchange between Asia and Europe. According to information released by the Government, the initial broadcast will cover more than a dozen countries, and is expected to reach an estimated audience of 50 million viewers.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 22:13:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Myanmar military junta accuses rebels of launching attacks during elections</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/30/junta-militar-do-myanmar-acusa-rebeldes-de-lancarem-ataques-durante-eleicoes/</link><description>Myanmar's ruling military junta yesterday accused rebel groups of drone, rocket and bomb attacks on election day and the day before, injuring at least five civilians.

Between Saturday and Sunday night, “malicious and brutal” attacks were carried out in 11 of the 102 municipalities where the first phase of elections organized by the military took place, state press reported.
The junta-controlled Global New Light of Myanmar newspaper listed rebel attacks ranging from “long-range fire with heavy weapons and homemade rockets” to “drone bombings.” “While the Government and the people chose the democratic path, terrorist groups continued their violent extremism,” the newspaper wrote.
The junta also accused the rebel groups of “sending threatening letters”, “spreading disinformation” and preventing people from going to the polls.
Myanmar's main pro-military party on Monday claimed victory in the first phase of legislative elections. “We won 82 seats in the lower house, in the constituencies where the count has already been completed, out of a total of 102,” said the representative of the Union, Solidarity and Development Party (USDP), who asked not to be identified, to the France-Presse news agency.
The official results of the first phase of voting, held on Sunday in just a few constituencies, have not yet been released by Myanmar's electoral commission.
Without any real opposition, the military junta presented the elections as a step towards reconciliation, almost five years after taking power on February 1, 2021, in a coup that overthrew the elected government, led by Nobel Peace Prize winner Aung San Suu Kyi.
Sunday's elections only took place in 102 of the country's 330 municipalities and, even after the next two phases, on January 11 and 25, 65 municipalities will be prevented from voting due to fighting between the army, ethnic guerrilla groups and resistance forces.
Human rights and opposition groups said the elections were neither free nor fair and that power should remain in the hands of military leader General Min Aung Hlaing. Critics said they doubted a transition to civilian rule.
Analysts considered that the decision to hold elections serves mainly so that neighbors such as China, India and Thailand maintain support for the military regime, which, according to the army, promotes stability in the nation.
Former leader Aung San Suu Kyi, 80, and the National League for Democracy did not participate in Sunday's vote. The Nobel Peace Prize winner is serving a 27-year prison sentence and the party was dissolved. Other parties also boycotted the vote or refused to run under conditions they consider unfair. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 22:07:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan records record number of Chinese incursions in waters near the Senkaku Islands</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/30/japao-regista-recorde-de-incursoes-chinesas-nas-aguas-proximas-das-ilhas-senkaku/</link><description>The Japanese Coast Guard detected Chinese ships in the vicinity of the Senkaku Islands for 356 days throughout 2025, setting a new annual record, the Japanese newspaper Asahi reported yesterday, citing official data. The vessels were observed in the so-called “zone contiguous” to Japanese territorial waters, according to monthly records released by the Japan Coast Guard. The mark exceeds the previous record, recorded in 2024, by one day, according to the Kyodo news agency.
The news comes at a time of diplomatic tension between Tokyo and Beijing over the issue of Taiwan. In November, Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi stated in parliament that a possible Chinese attack on the self-governed island could justify the intervention of the Japanese Self-Defense Forces, in support of the United States. The statements provoked a negative reaction from Beijing, which called on Chinese citizens to avoid traveling to the Japanese archipelago and imposed restrictions on imports of seafood from Japan.
According to Asahi, in addition to their constant presence in the contiguous area, Chinese ships entered Japanese territorial waters on several occasions.
In March, a Chinese Coast Guard ship spent 92 hours in these waters, setting a new record for stay. In May, a Chinese helicopter violated Japanese airspace after taking off from a ship located within Japanese maritime territory, in the first recorded incident of its kind.
In early December, the Chinese Coast Guard also expelled a Japanese fishing boat that allegedly illegally entered waters close to the disputed islands.
The Senkaku Islands – known as Diaoyu in China – have been administered by Japan since 2012, but claimed by Beijing and Taipei. The dispute intensified after Tokyo's nationalization of three of the islands in September 2012. Located in the East China Sea, the archipelago is not inhabited, but has great geostrategic importance and it is believed that there may be significant reserves of gas and oil in its waters. The Senkaku are located around 150 kilometers northeast of Taiwan, which also claims sovereignty over the islands.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 22:06:48</pubDate></item><item><title>2025 summarized in 20 moments</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/30/2025-sintetizado-em-20-momentos/</link><description>The year is coming to an end and PONTO FINAL summarizes some of the issues that have been most in focus in the last 12 months – from changes in the Government and the AL to the first arrest under the national security law.

PONTO FINAL now recalls 20 of the themes that most marked the year 2025 in the Macao SAR, a year fertile in changes. In the last 12 months, there have been changes in the Government, in the Legislative Assembly, in the rules on cash checks, in the number of visitors, in casinos and even in the application of the State security law.

DEATH OF ROCHA VIEIRA
PHOTOGRAPHY GONÇALO LOBO PINHEIRO
Vasco Rocha Vieira, the last Portuguese governor of Macau and former Army Chief of Staff, died in the early hours of January 22, at the age of 85. Rocha Vieira served as governor of Macau until 1999, when the territory was transferred to China. For history, the image of the emotion with which he held the Portuguese flag close to his chest in the last moments of the Portuguese administration remains.

EXPLOSION IN TAIWAN VICTIMATES MACAU FAMILY

An explosion at a shopping center in Taichung, Taiwan, killed a total of five people, including three Macau residents belonging to the same family. The grandfather died instantly and the grandmother died a few hours after the explosion, while the two-year-old child died days later in Macau. The child's mother, father, uncle and great-grandmother also suffered some injuries. The explosion, which occurred following a gas leak, took place on 13 February.

MEGA-PROJECTS

In the Governing Action Lines (LAG) for 2025, which were presented in April, the Executive announced plans for the construction of four mega-projects with the aim of leveraging the economic development of the Macao SAR: the Macau and Hengqin International Education (University) City; an integrated international tourist and cultural district of Macau, a Macau International Air Transport Hub (Port) on the west bank of the Pearl River and an industrial park for research and development of science and technology in Macau.

JOURNALISTS ARRESTED

Two journalists from All About Macau were detained, on April 17, by the police, when they tried to enter the Legislative Assembly hall to attend the presentation of the Lines of Government Action for 2025. The detention led to several criticisms from international institutions, warning of the deterioration of press freedom in the region. All About Macau ended up announcing the end of operations due to increased “risks and pressures”.

CHANGES TO CASH CHECKS

In May, the Government announced changes in the attribution of the cash contribution plan: with a few exceptions, anyone outside Macau 183 days a year will be left without a cash check. André Cheong, who at the time was secretary for Administration and Justice and also spokesperson for the Executive Council, indicated that the changes in the distribution of checks aimed to “optimize the use of public resources”. The measure came into force in 2025.

RETURN OF “HOUSE OF DANCING WATER”
ELOI CARVALHO PHOTOGRAPHY
“House of Dancing Water”, one of Macau’s most iconic shows, was presented again, five years after its hiatus. The City of Dreams show, by Melco, did not take place during the pandemic years and was resumed in May 2025, maintaining its original line, with only slight circumstantial changes. This, which is considered the biggest water circus show on the planet, now has technological elements.

END OF SATELLITE CASINOS

It was in June that the Executive and gaming operators announced that, by the end of this year, satellite casinos would cease to operate. Furthermore, most of the Mocha gaming machine rooms will close by the end of the year. The basis for these decisions by gaming concessionaires is the review of the gaming law carried out in 2022, which stipulates that, after the end of a transitional period of three years – which ends on December 31, 2025 –, if the concessionaires intended to continue operating satellite casinos, this exploration can only be done by hiring a management company.

FIRST LARGE-SCALE SHOW IN THE OUTDOOR PREVENTION

Norwegian DJ and music producer Alan Walker performed in Macau on June 15th at the Macau Open-Air Performance Venue, in Cotai. This was the first large-scale concert to take place in this new performance area after the opening event. This is a new outdoor entertainment area created by the Government with an area of ​​94 thousand square meters and capacity for more than 50 thousand spectators.

DISQUALIFIED ELECTION CANDIDATES

In July, the Legislative Assembly's Electoral Affairs Committee (CAEAL) announced the disqualification of 12 candidates for the September 14 elections. Among them Ron Lam, who in the 2021 elections had passed the scrutiny of the authorities and is now a deputy. CAEAL was based on the opinion of the State Security Defense Commission and simply said that the excluded candidates “do not defend the Basic Law” or “are not faithful to the Macao SAR”, without explaining the specific facts that led to the disqualification of these candidates.

AU KAM SAN ARRESTED

Former deputy Au Kam San was arrested at the end of July, in what is the first case of suspected violation of the Law on the Defense of State Security in the Macao SAR. The Judicial Police said in a statement that it had “strong indications” that the individual it detained was in collusion with an “Anti-China organization”. The arrest of the former Democratic deputy, who was in the Legislative Assembly for more than two decades, prompted criticism from international organizations, including the European Union, which warned that this case heightened concerns regarding the erosion of political pluralism and freedom of expression in the region.

PREMIERED SUBSIDY PLAN FOR CHILDREN

The new child care subsidy plan was launched in July, which provides for a subsidy of 18,000 patacas, in annual installments, for children up to 3 years of age. It is estimated that a total of 15,000 children will benefit this year and the budget for this year's plan is 270 million patacas. The measure aims to encourage the birth rate, which has been falling sharply in recent years.

SERIOUS ROAD ACCIDENT LEAVES FOUR DEATH

A serious road accident occurred at the beginning of August, on Avenida da Amizade, causing four deaths and three injuries, all of whom were in a light vehicle. Among the fatal victims are the driver, a 20-year-old resident, and three other male passengers, all of them young. The car skidded and ended up crashing into the iron barriers and road signs near the Grand Prix Building.

ELECTIONS WITH MANY NULL AND BLANK VOTES. COUTINHO ENDED UP WINNER
ELOI CARVALHO PHOTOGRAPHY
The legislative elections in the Macao SAR took place on 14 September and, despite efforts to get the population to participate in the vote, the participation rate (53.35%) was the third lowest participation rate in legislative elections in the Macao SAR. After counting, there was also an exponential increase in blank and invalid votes. It should be remembered that only candidates previously approved by the authorities were able to participate in these elections, with two lists and a total of 12 candidates being disqualified. The big winner of the ballot was José Pereira Coutinho, whose list received the most votes, winning three seats in the Legislative Assembly. The list led by Song Pek Kei also elected three deputies, while the remaining four lists each placed two deputies in the hemicycle.

MONTENEGRO IN MACAU
ELOI CARVALHO PHOTOGRAPHY
Also in September, Luís Montenegro, Portuguese Prime Minister, visited Macau, a visit that lasted less than five hours in total. After meetings with representatives of the Macau Government, Montenegro said he wanted to “take further” the cooperative relationship between Portugal and Macau, at an economic, social, cultural and historical level. The Portuguese Prime Minister indicated, after the meeting with Sam Hou Fai, that there will be a more agile regime for granting residence to Portuguese citizens. Au Kam San's detention was not discussed with local authorities because “there are matters that deserve some modesty”, he said.

SUPER TYPHOON RAGASA SHAKES MACAU
PHOTOGRAPHY PEDRO ANDRÉ SANTOS
Super typhoon Ragasa, which passed through Macau on September 23, left eight people injured and the Civil Protection Operations Center recorded 252 incidents, mostly falling trees and lamps. The maximum tropical storm signal was in effect for more than ten hours. In Porto Interior, flooding exceeded 1.5 meters. The floods caused fish to appear swimming in the streets of Porto Interior and several people tried to catch them. Videos of the moment went viral on social media.

GOVERNMENT REMODELING

At the end of September, Sam Hou Fai decided to remodel the Government: André Cheong, who until then was Secretary for Administration and Justice, was seconded by the Chief Executive to the Legislative Assembly as a nominated deputy – and was later chosen as president of the legislative body; to replace him in the Administration and Justice portfolio, the Chief chose Wong Sio Chak, who was the Secretary for Security; Chan Tsz King, who was a Public Prosecutor, took over as Secretary for Security.

GAME REVENUES FOR A MAXIMUM OF SIX YEARS

The gaming industry's gross revenues reached a six-year high in October. Macau's casinos recorded gross revenue of around 24.09 billion patacas that month, an amount that sets a record since the start of the Covid-19 pandemic. Revenue from casinos represents more than 80% of the Macao SAR's tax revenue.

NATIONAL GAMES

In November, the 15th edition of the National Games took place, hosted for the first time in Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau. Macau hosted five sports in this edition of the National Games, namely table tennis, three-a-side basketball, five-a-side basketball, volleyball and karate. The 13 days of games in various disciplines resulted in three gold medals and two bronze medals for Macau – the region's best performance ever in the sporting competition.

DEATH OF JOSÉ MANEIRAS
ELOI CARVALHO PHOTOGRAPHY
The architect José Maneiras died on November 24th, aged 90, leaving an architectural and social legacy. Maneiras not only inscribed his name in the urban landscape that he helped to rehabilitate and redesign, but also in the political life of the city, having been president of the Leal Senado between 1989 and 1993, and in mentoring the young artists who succeeded him. From start to finish, it was a life entirely dedicated to Macau.

NUMBER OF VISITORS HAS HIT HISTORICAL RECORD

Macau has already received more visitors this year than in 2019, a year that held the all-time record for the number of tourists. According to figures from the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP), from the first day of January 2025 until the 26th of December, 39 million and 411 thousand visitors entered the territory. The record that was broken was 39 million and 406 thousand. Until December 31st, the number of tourists is expected to still grow slightly.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 22:23:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Police intensify security operations for New Year's Eve</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/30/policia-intensifica-operacoes-de-seguranca-para-a-passagem-de-ano/</link><description>In anticipation of a large influx of people during New Year's Eve celebrations, the general commander of the Unitary Police Services (SPU), Leong Man Cheong, led a comprehensive inspection of the main event venues this Monday. The inspection, which was attended by several figures from the local security body, aims to ensure that public order, traffic control and crowd management devices are ready to operate effectively during the festivities.
The police delegation traveled to critical points in the city, including the areas of Ruins of São Paulo, the Macau Tower, Rua do Cunha and the Cotai area. In these locations, the general commander received detailed explanations about operational planning and instructed all police units to reinforce monitoring of people flows, improve emergency plans and intensify interdepartmental coordination.
The security operation also extended to the Hengqin Border Post. There, Commander Leong was informed about the special measures for the screening and flow of passengers during the festive period and held working meetings with officials from the Zhuhai border authorities, reinforcing cross-border coordination. During the visits, the commander-general extended greetings and words of recognition to the police personnel deployed to the front line, thanking them for their dedication during the festive season.
In the statement shared yesterday, the police also appealed to residents and tourists to, when participating in the celebrations, plan their routes in advance, consulting traffic information, and preferably opt for public transport. You are also asked to follow the instructions of agents on the ground, remain patient in situations of large concentrations of people and take care of your safety and your belongings.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 22:11:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Electric vehicles accounted for 36.6% of new registrations in November</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/30/veiculos-electricos-corresponderam-a-366-das-novas-matriculas-em-novembro/</link><description>At the end of November, there were 254,055 vehicles registered in Macau, 0.5% more than in the same month of 2024. The number of vehicles with new registrations was 864, 33.3% less in annual terms, with 316 (or 36.6% of the total) being electric.
The data was revealed yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), which also showed the occurrence of 1,215 road accidents, 14.2% less in annual terms, resulting in 395 injuries.
The movement of cars at border posts stood at 958,605 in the month under analysis, an increase of 15.1% in annual terms, highlighting DSEC that the movement of light cars was equivalent to 908,653, an increase of 16.3%.
According to data released by the organization, 223 thousand entries and exits were of cars with a unique Hengqin registration plate and 134 thousand entries and exits were of cars under the “Macao Vehicle Circulation in Guangdong Province” program, with year-on-year increases of 45.3% and 5.2%, respectively.
In the same month, the movement of passenger vessels (6,284) fell by 1.5%, although the number of commercial flights at Macau International Airport (4,645) increased by 0.7%.
Regarding the volume of cross-border cargo, the gross weight of containerized cargo entering and leaving Macau by land was 6,577 tons in November, 14.2% less year-on-year. The gross weight of air cargo also fell 9.1% to 10,807 tonnes, although the weight of containerized cargo entering and leaving ports rose 5.6% to 16,359 tonnes.
At the end of last month there were 1,494,421 mobile phone users, 3.4% more year-on-year, with respective increases of 4.1% and 1.6% in the number of users of postpaid services (1,085,251) and users with prepaid cards (409,170).
There were also 76,930 fixed-network telephone users, down 6.2%, and 785,108 subscribers registered for internet services, up 1.5% in annual terms. In total, users used 142 million hours of these services throughout the month, 4.1% less compared to the previous year.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 22:11:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Real estate crisis leaves consumers pessimistic despite Chinese growth</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/30/crise-imobiliaria-deixa-consumidores-pessimistas-apesar-do-crescimento-chines/</link><description>The Chinese economy is expected to reach the official growth target of around 5% this year, driven by exports and advances in artificial intelligence and electric vehicles, while many Chinese live in uncertainty about jobs and salaries.

The divergence between macroeconomic indicators and the population's daily lives raises doubts about the robustness of the economic recovery, despite the trade truce between Beijing and Washington, sealed after a meeting between the leaders of China and the United States, Xi Jinping and Donald Trump.
“Business is very difficult,” said Xiao Feng, owner of a billiard room in Beijing. "The rich don't have time and the people don't have money. At the end of the month, I'm left with nothing", he observed.
Xiao's wife, a nurse, is currently the family's main source of income. The businessman cut the number of employees and says he has not made any profit in the last six months.
The sentiment is shared by Zhang Xiaoze, a real estate agent specializing in commercial properties, who saw his annual income fall from three million yuan (around 364 thousand euros) to just 100 thousand yuan (12 thousand euros). "Many companies are leaving Beijing. The problem is that people don't have money," he explained.
Between January and November, Chinese exports reached a new record of 3.4 billion dollars (almost 2.9 billion euros), but domestic consumption shows signs of weakness. Retail sales rose just 1.3% in November, a slowdown compared to the previous month, while investment in fixed assets fell 2.6%.
The real estate sector remains a hot spot: housing prices have fallen by more than 20% since their peak in 2021. Sales of new homes fell by 11.2% and investment in the sector fell by almost 16% in the first 11 months of the year.
Xiao bought the apartment he lives in for more than three million yuan in 2019. "Now it's worth about 2.4 million. If it hadn't depreciated so much, I might have already changed my car. But I still have the same one as ten years ago," he said.
To reduce expenses, Xiao stopped paying tutoring fees to his 10-year-old son. "Now we teach at home. The future is uncertain."
Zhou, a tutor in Tianjin, has seen the number of students drop as parents stop investing in supplementary education. "Many prefer large classes instead of individual classes. Business is 50% worse than during the pandemic," he said.
Analysts such as Zichun Huang, from Capital Economics, consider that China's real growth could be below the officially estimated 5%. The think tank Rhodium Group points to a rate of just 2.5% to 3%.
The stagnation in the real estate sector directly affects consumer confidence, in a country where housing represents the main investment vehicle for families. Disposable income growth has also been lower than the pre-pandemic pace. “It’s a difficult transition,” said ING chief China economist Lynn Song, referring to Beijing’s attempt to reorient the economy towards domestic consumption and high-tech sectors. “The official rhetoric does not correspond to the reality experienced by many Chinese,” he explained.
Excess capacity in sectors such as automobiles, steel and consumer goods keeps prices and profits under pressure. According to HSBC bank, Chinese export prices have fallen by more than 20% since 2022.
The owner of a budget hotel in Shijiazhuang, northern China, who gave his name only as Zhai, says he sees no signs of recovery. “If things don’t improve by May or June, when the lease ends, I will close the doors,” he assured. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 22:09:26</pubDate></item><item><title>A special zone within the HKSAR</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/30/uma-zona-especial-dentro-da-raehk/</link><description>On December 22, 2025, when the opening ceremony of the Hong Kong side of the Hetao Shenzhen-Hong Kong Scientific and Technological Innovation Cooperation Zone was held, this cross-border innovation center represents a special and unprecedented development zone within the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region (HKSAR). The zone marks the establishment of a unique scientific and technological center within the HKSAR, utilizing the mainland's talents and companies across borders and strengthening innovative exchanges between Hong Kong and Shenzhen.
During the inauguration ceremony, Chief Executive John Lee said the Cooperation Zone would open up the area's transportation network, promote the exchange of mainland scientific and technological talents with their Hong Kong counterparts, and consolidate innovative links between the HKSAR and Shenzhen.
Construction has begun on a bridge that will connect the technology parks of Hong Kong and Shenzhen. It will serve, according to John Lee, as “a striking symbol of the ‘one zone, two parks’ vision, connecting the pulse of Greater Bay Area innovation” (South China Morning Post, December 23, 2025, p. A1). The bridge is significant from a technological, social and economic point of view, as it will connect the Shenzhen Technology Park to the Hong Kong Science and Technology Innovation Park (HKITP), known as the Hong Kong park.
The cost of the bridge will be shared between Hong Kong and Shenzhen, and its completion is scheduled for 2027.
The opening ceremony was attended by the deputy director of the Hong Kong and Macau Affairs Office, Xu Qifang, and the director of the Hong Kong Liaison Office, Zhou Ji. Shenzhen City Vice President Luo Huanghao also participated in this landmark event.
Shortly after John Lee's official visit to Beijing, where President Xi Jinping called on the HKSAR to align its development plan with the nation's 15th Five-Year Plan, the inauguration of the Innovation Cooperation Zone on the Hong Kong side is politically significant as it represents how the HKSAR's scientific and technological development is capitalizing on the advantages of Shenzhen's scientific and technological experience and knowledge, and how Hong Kong's scientific and technological policy is facilitating Hong Kong's joint research efforts and Shenzhen. In fact, Xu Qifang stated at the inauguration ceremony that the development of the park is part of the national development strategy promoted by President Xi.
During President Xi's visit to Guangdong in November, when he inaugurated the National Games, the president also mentioned the need for Greater Bay Area cities to cooperate in the areas of technological innovation, infrastructure networks, market integration and "soft connectivity" of rules and mechanisms.
Xu Qifang echoed the Chinese president's remarks, emphasizing the importance of Hong Kong in strengthening "soft" and "hard" connectivity. He also noted that Hong Kong should consolidate relations with other mainland zones such as Qianhai and Nansha to boost the development of the industrial supply chain and enhance the competitiveness of scientific and technological innovation, creating a win-win scenario in the Greater Bay Area.
The Innovation Cooperation Zone attracted foreign companies. More than sixty foreign, mainland and Hong Kong companies have signed leases for the two wet laboratory complexes located in the Hong Kong park, increasing the occupancy rate to nearly eighty percent. The remaining five building blocks will be completed in 2027, which falls within the first phase of scientific and technological development. The planning for the second phase has just been finalized. The total area covering the two phases of development would occupy two million square meters – a seventy percent expansion over the Hong Kong government's initial plan.
The Hong Kong park is expected to encompass the development of technologies related to life and health, artificial intelligence and data science. John Lee revealed that the objective of the park is to boost orderly development, consolidate the innovation and technology value chain, and promote cross-border and/or cross-border synergy between upstream, downstream and intermediary sectors.
In addition to the development of the Hong Kong park and its connectivity with Shenzhen, the San Tin Technopole is expected to be developed in a much faster space, with the aim of attracting more business investment and providing additional support for Hetao.
At a time when mainland authorities are emphasizing the importance of developing "new quality productive forces", Hong Kong's leadership has begun to explore how these "new quality productive forces" can be further promoted by adopting a new science and technology innovation policy, cooperating with Shenzhen more intensively and leveraging the immense experience and potential of the mainland's science and technology enterprises.
In fact, it took eight years for the Hong Kong park to come to fruition since an agreement was signed with Shenzhen in 2017 to develop the joint science and technology park. Critics stated that the HKSAR took too long to develop its science and technology policy (see Editorial, Ming Pao, December 23, 2025, p. A2). The Shenzhen side of Hetao has had faster development, but the Hong Kong side has been developing slowly.
In September 2025, the Hetao Institute of Interdisciplinary Mathematics and Science was opened, founded by renowned Chinese-American mathematician Yau Shing-tung (Hong Kong Standard, September 10, 2025). The Institute is located in Shenzhen Park and specializes in applied mathematics research. Yau highlighted that the Institute has already recruited 17 top talents and plans to expand the research team to 50 or 60 members by the end of 2025.
Despite the construction of the bridge connecting the two sides of the science and technology parks, some details still need to be resolved, including whether immigration and customs will adopt a single checkpoint or two different customs checkpoints (Ming Pao, December 23, 2025, p. A2). It was reported that a new idea of ​​adopting a "white list" will be adopted, which means that science and technology experts from the mainland will have their names registered and will be able to cross the bridge and easily enter the Hong Kong park.
Sun Dong, Secretary for Innovation, Technology and Industry, said that the flows of talent, goods and scientific data are now making good progress and that both Hong Kong and Shenzhen have reached a "basic consensus" on the logistical arrangements regarding cross-border biological samples from the mainland to Hong Kong. Obviously, the details of technical, scientific and technological operations will have to be meticulously formulated and implemented to ensure the fluidity and success of cross-border scientific and technological innovation and collaboration.
Other details will need to be discussed, including the number of researchers and postdoctoral scientists who will work at the Hong Kong park and the related issue of intellectual property rights for innovative products. In other words, both Hong Kong and Shenzhen will have to fully utilize the comparative advantages of “one park, two districts”.
Sun Dong told the press that a more pressing issue is to ensure that the development of the first phase of the Hong Kong park has sufficient financial resources (Oriental Daily, December 21, 2025). He revealed that HK$200 billion will be needed to complete the rest of the Hong Kong park and that the government cannot sustain such a large investment. Therefore, investment from the private sector will be necessary. The government received 27 proposals from the private sector, meaning a public-private partnership will be required for the smooth completion of the first phase of Hong Kong's park development.
As early as June 2025, Sun Dong had told the press that software and hardware would have to work together for the technology zone to be successful. He said: "By software, I mean how we can create a conducive environment for business, scientific research and exchange, so that the best talents and companies are willing to move to Hetao" (Hong Kong Standard, June 26, 2025).
Some foreign companies have expressed great interest in investing in the Hong Kong park. An executive from Swiss company Spirecut, Frederic Schuind, said he hoped to use the base at the Hong Kong park to enter the large Asian market (Ming Pao, December 23, 2025, p. A2). It has been reported that a quarter of the sixty companies in the Hong Kong park are from foreign countries and that they are deeply interested in entering not only the mainland but also the Asian market.
The Hong Kong park is expected to provide enormous and valuable research opportunities for doctoral and postdoctoral researchers who have been and are trained by local universities. They will have immense opportunities to work with and learn from the mainland's science and technology experts, creating a win-win situation in the exchange of high-tech talents from Hong Kong and the mainland. They will also learn a lot from the experience and international knowledge of foreign companies that have investments and operations in the Hong Kong park.
The talent dormitory in the Hong Kong park has already hosted some talents and employees from science and technology companies. Some restaurants were opened in one of the residential buildings. It can be predicted that when the Hong Kong park is further developed, more mainland, overseas and Hong Kong residents will be seen.
In November 2025, Kevin Choi Kit-ming, Permanent Secretary for Innovation, Technology and Industry, referred to the Hong Kong park as a “special zone within the special administrative region” of Hong Kong (Hong Kong Standard, November 10, 2025). He revealed that a German pharmaceutical company would establish its company in the Greater Bay Area, leveraging Hong Kong's international medical standards, while a Beijing-based AI company was using Hong Kong's blockchain technology to connect with the market in Australia. Choi revealed that the Hong Kong government had already allocated HK$24 billion for the initial phase of the park's infrastructure and public facilities, as well as an indirect investment of HK$14.3 billion for the road and infrastructure network connecting the Hong Kong park to Hetao.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 22:05:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese AI platform Manus will join Meta group after acquisition agreement</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/30/plataforma-chinesa-de-ia-manus-vai-integrar-grupo-meta-apos-acordo-de-aquisicao/</link><description>The Chinese company Manus announced yesterday that it will join the North American group Meta, maintaining its operation in Singapore, to reinforce the technological development and global expansion of the artificial intelligence (AI) agent platform.
In a statement published on its portal, the company indicated that it was “about to join Meta”, maintaining the offer of products and subscriptions through the application, as well as the operational headquarters in Singapore, where it moved in recent years.
Manus develops AI agents – systems capable of planning, deciding and executing chained actions based on general instructions from the user – in an approach different from traditional 'chatbots', which react to each interaction in isolation.
These agents are capable of analyzing information, browsing the Internet, using digital tools and completing tasks autonomously, without continuous human intervention.
According to the company, since its launch, the platform has processed more than 147 billion 'tokens' and created more than 80 million “virtual computers”, allowing agents to perform tasks in simulated environments.
Manus maintained that integration into Meta will reinforce the platform's position in the so-called “application layer” of AI, by transforming advanced capabilities into scalable systems applicable in real-world scenarios.
Manus' executive director, Xiao Hong, stated that the agreement will allow it to grow “on a more solid and sustainable basis”, without changing the company's operating model or decision-making processes, with a focus on continuous product improvement and service expansion.
Meta, owner of Facebook, Instagram and WhatsApp, said that it will integrate Manus technology into its own products, while maintaining the external marketing of the service, without disclosing the financial values ​​of the operation.
According to the Chinese newspaper The Paper, Liu Yuan, partner at ZhenFund – one of the Chinese venture capital firms investing in Manus – considered it to be “Meta's third largest acquisition since its founding”, only surpassed by the purchases of WhatsApp and Scale AI.
Founded in the USA by Mark Zuckerberg, Meta has invested heavily in AI as a pillar of its growth strategy.
Manus was initially developed by the company Butterfly Effect, created in China and later transferred to Singapore.
The platform gained notoriety in March with a preliminary version of its assistant – presented as a general-purpose AI agent – ​​whose invitation access generated strong demand and placed the company in the spotlight of the technology sector.
The operation is part of Meta's strategy of strengthening AI capabilities, in a context of intense global competition, at the same time that China continues to promote the development of its own technologies in this area, despite existing restrictions and regulatory controls.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 22:08:36</pubDate></item></channel></rss>