<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/jovens-de-macau-recebem-cinco-distincoes-em-competicao-de-guangdong/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Mandarin Oriental celebrates 15 years of presence in the city with honor of art and innovation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/mandarin-oriental-celebra-15-anos-de-presenca-na-cidade-com-homenagem-a-arte-e-a-inovacao/</link><description>Mandarin East Macau celebrated its 15th anniversary at a ceremony that was attended by over 250 guests, including representatives of the hotel sector, cultural institutions and local authorities.
The theme of the celebration was “Macao Redefinida” and presented the evolution of the city, combining “tradition and contemporary”. During the event, guests watched performances of giant fan performances - hotel logo symbols - as well as a live artistic installation by local artist Tsang Tseng Tseng, known for painting about fans and integrated the contemporary art exhibition “Modern Vision, Timeless Technique”, which is patent until August 31, presenting works by Tsang and Tsang and Leong Kit Man, another artist from Macau.
The hotel's director general, Franck Droin, highlighted the team's dedication and continuous commitment to improve services, noting that the celebration also served to recognize the resilience and innovation that have sustained the hotel's success over the years. Greg Liddell, vice president of Operations and Director General of the East Hong Kong Mandarin, also declared his appreciation for the service of the satellite hotel in Macao.
The night was marked by commemorative video projections, musical performances that combined traditional Chinese elements with contemporary styles, as well as dances that symbolized the history and modernity of the city. Curator Alice Kok stressed the importance of the interaction between tradition and innovation, technique and emotion, present in the artistic programming of the event.
In addition, to mark its birthday, Mandarin East has launched a special accommodation proposal - the “Discover Macau” package - valid until December 31. Priced from 6,388 dollars of Hong Kong a night, which includes one night in a welcome drinks, breakfast in the bedroom, a 500 dollars voucher of Hong Kong for purchases at One Central Macau, unlimited spa in private suite, butler service and an exploration experience of the city, including Macau Tower visits to the ruins of Sao Paulo, to the ruins of Sao Paulo, To the village of Taipa and the Lord Stow's Bakery in Coloane.
Internationally recognized, East Mandarin is responsible for a wallet of 43 hotels, 12 homes and 26 exclusive residences in 26 countries.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:37:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau hired more than three thousand migrant workers in one year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/macau-contratou-mais-de-tres-mil-trabalhadores-migrantes-em-um-ano/</link><description>Macao companies and families have hired more than three thousand migrant workers in the last 12 months, it was released yesterday.
According to data from the Public Security Police Corps, in late May, Macau had 183,783 workers without resident status, more 3.006 than in the same month of 2024.
The labor coming from abroad, including from mainland China, reached the highest value since June 2020 at the beginning of the Covid-19 pandemic.
Since the maximum peak of 196,538, hit in late 2019, before the pandemic, and until January 2023, the city lost almost 45,000 non-residents, which corresponded to 11.3% of the active population.
In January 2023, when the "Zero Covid" policy ended, which was in force in Macao and mainland China for almost more than three years, Macau had less than 152,000 migrants, the lowest number since April 2014.
The statistics, released by the Directorate of Services for Laboral Affairs, reveal that, since the end of the Zero Covid policy, the number of non-resident workers increased on 31.905.
The hotel and restoration sector was the one that has hired the most in the last 12 months, earning 3,379 non-resident workers, followed by domestic employees (another 1,553).
The hotel area and the restoration had been precisely the most affected by loss of labor during the pandemic, having faced more than 17,600 non-resident employees since December 2019.
Macao, which as China followed the Zero Covid policy, reopened the borders to all foreigners, including non-resident workers, from January 8, 2023, after nearly three years of strict restrictions.
The city received in 2024 34.9 million visitors, 23.8% more than the previous year, but still far from the record, 39.4 million, set in 2019, before the pandemic, and hotel establishments welcomed more than 14.4 million guests, a new historical record.
The economic crisis created by the pandemic led the unemployment rate to reach 4% in the third quarter of 2022, the highest since 2006.
Despite the number of non-resident workers, the unemployment rate remained 1.9% in the period between February and April. Still, several deputies have asked the government to force the six game dealers to say goodbye to the labor coming from abroad to ensure the use of the 5,600 places working in the 11 casinos that will end by the end of 2025.
Three of the six dealers-SJM, Galaxy and Melco-communicated to the authorities on June 9, which will end by December 31 the exploration of the 11 existing satellite casinos in the territory.
Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:53:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Filipino Court nullifies a former accountant mandate and concludes that he is a Chinese citizen</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/tribunal-filipino-anula-mandato-de-ex-autarca-e-conclui-que-e-cidada-chinesa/</link><description>A Philippine Court has invalid the mandate of a former mayor of the northern chamber of the country, identifying it as a Chinese citizen and considering that he illegally held the position between 2022 and 2024.
Publicly known as Alice Guo, the former mayor of the city of Bamban, in the province of Tarlac, was identified by the regional court of first instance of Manila as “undoubtedly a Chinese citizen” with the real name Guo Hua Ping.
The sentence, signed last Friday and released yesterday by the local diary Philstar, considers that Guo "usurped and illegally held the position of Mayor," invalidating all his term from the inauguration in 2022 until his suspension in 2024.
The case gained notoriety in the country about a year ago, when Guo fled the Philippines to avoid responding to the courts, ending up being detained in Indonesia in September 2024 and deported to Manila under police escort.
The former supply is the target of dozens of lawsuits that include accusations of trafficking in persons, malpractice, falsification of documents and, more recently, 62 capital laundering crimes, according to the Philippine Ministry of Justice.
The revelation of its alleged Chinese nationality has fueled suspicions of espionage in favor of Beijing, in a context of growing tension between the two countries due to the territorial dispute in the Southern Sea of ​​China - a strategic zone where about 30% of world maritime trade, which concentrates 12% of global fishing zones and important potential oil and gas reserves.
Guo began to be associated with organized crime when police philipine it linked operations of illegal casinos managed by Chinese mobster networks in Bamban.
Authorities rescued hundreds of Filipine and Foreign Citizens allegedly kept against their will in a center of that locality, where they would be forced to participate in online burla schemes.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:34:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau refuses to adjust prohibition of food imports from certain districts of Japan</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/macau-recusa-ajustar-proibicao-da-importacao-de-alimentos-de-determinados-distritos-do-japao/</link><description>Local authorities reiterate the continuity of restrictions on the importation of foods in Japan, especially ten Japanese municipalities. The measure was imposed in August 2023 in response to the release of nuclear wastewater of Fukushima, Japan. The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) issued a statement yesterday justifying the maintenance of policy to “ensure food safety and citizens' health”.
The AMI announcement arises in a reaction to the recent decision of the Chinese government about the survey of the total prohibition of Import of Seafood from Japan by the interior of China. China's General Customs Administration published a warning on Sunday that it has verified the “conditions” to restore the importation of some aquatic products of Japanese origin, but does not cover ten Japanese municipalities, including Fukushima.
It is recalled that since the beginning of the discharge of nuclear wastewater in Japan, mainland China has banned the entry of Japanese aquatic products and the government of Macao eventually introduced a measure to prohibit imports, as well as water and derivatives, fresh and living food products, food products of animal origin, sea salt and marine algae, including fruits, milk and milk Dairy, meat and derivatives and poultry eggs, which come from ten municipalities in Japan - Fukushima, Chiba, Tochigi, Ibaraki, Gunma, Miyagi, Niigata, Nagano, Saitama and Tokyo metropolis.
AMI has stated that it has been “strictly implementing” the measure and continues to reinforce radionuclide inspections at imported Japanese foods, as well as monitoring of Japanese food retail and verification of imports and imports of imports from food products.
However, AMI admitted that “no anomaly was detected” in all tests to food products over time. From August 2023 to June 22, 2025, the body has been made, with portable radiation detector, at about 193,000 imported Japanese food samples, and about 3,700 samples for radionuclide tests were also collected.
The Hong Kong government has reacted to the new measure of the interior of China and has also announced that it will maintain restrictions on importing water products, including fish, seafood and algae, of the ten municipalities considered "high -risk".
The neighboring region's executive reiterated the need to "act with prudence", since the duration and scale of water dump from Fukushima Daichi "are unprecedented." John Lee's government said it had maintained communication with the Japanese authorities to provide scientific evidence and updated information in the situation, in order to evaluate the eventual survey of restrictions.
 
SEM ANOMALIAS NA MONITORIZAÇÃO
Similar to the territory, China's general customs administration reported that samples collected in the international monitoring, and independent sampling by China, in the long-term water contaminated in Fukushima, "revealed no anomalies."
"In the premise that the Japanese government has pledged to safeguard the quality and safety of exported aquatic products to China […], in order to safeguard consumers' legitimate rights and interests, China has decided to resume, under certain conditions," Imports of seafood from certain areas of Japan, can be read in the "warning on the conditional resumption of water products in some regions of Japan." of the Chinese government.
"Japan considers this announcement from China as positive," Japanese government deputy spokesman Kazhiko Aoki said yesterday at a press conference. "The Japanese government continues to work with China to remove the remaining import controls on ten other Japanese municipalities and also over beef," he added.
On May 30, Japan Minister of Agriculture, Shinjiro Koizumi, said China would resume imports of Japanese seafood after the two countries reached an agreement.
The agreement provides that Beijing can participate, within the scope of the International Atomic Energy Agency, in the collection of samples of the wastewater of Fukushima, which began to be discharged at sea in August 2023.
At the time China blocked the imports of Japanese sea products because it considered that the release of waste could endanger the fishing industry and the coastal communities in East China.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:54:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Occupational accidents caused 1,130 victims in the first quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/acidentes-de-trabalho-provocaram-1-130-vitimas-no-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) released the data related to occupational accidents that occurred in the first quarter, revealing that 1,130 people were victims, a slight decrease of 6.6% compared to the same period last year.
According to the report, of the total, 1,128 people were injured with temporary disability, of which 122 were able to return to service on the same day as the accident. None suffered permanent disability, but there were two people who lost their lives due to work accidents, Dsal said. In fatal cases, according to the body, no offenses were detected to occupational safety and health standards, however, data on deadly accidents may be reviewed according to the judgments given by the court.
The authorities analyzed the causes of accidents and point out that by March 281 victims suffered falls, and the cause dominated the cases of occupational accidents, representing 24.8% of the total. Among these, 53 cases were “falling people at height” and 228 were “falling people on flat ground”.
The following main causes include the “raising in one or between objects”, which corresponded to 18.3% (207 cases) of all incidents; “Excessive efforts or false movements”, with 16.6% (188 cases); and the “gear or shock in objects”, which is equivalent to 16.5% (187 cases).
It is also noteworthy that “exposure or contact with extreme temperatures” affected 48 people, while “exposure or contact with harmful substances or radiation” injured eight people. There were also 98 workers who suffered injuries caused by means of transport, either during the execution of work and during the use of the transport means provided by the employer on their way to work or outflow.
The report finds that men aged 25 to 44 are the group, according to age and sexes, with a greater tendency to be the target of occupational accidents, with 334 (29.5%) registered injured.
 
More cases in the game and entertainment sector
 
Regarding the numbers of occupational accidents taking into account the economic activity, it appears that they dominate “cultural and recreational activities, lottery and other services”, ie game and entertainment, which had 350 victims (30.9%), followed by the sector “Hotels, Restaurants and the like”, with 285 victims (25.2%).
Analyzing according to the profession, “unqualified workers” were the most affected by occupational accidents in the first three months of this year, with 290 cases. The “staff of services, sellers and similar workers” and the “administrative employees” recorded 271 and 255 cases, respectively.
The document adds, on the other hand, that there was more than three thousand days of work lost between January and March, due to work accidents, one third happened in the game and entertainment sector, almost 900 days in the hotel and restoration industry and 162 day in the construction sector.
 
Fines applied last year
Regarding the monitoring of occupational accidents last year, when 5,095 cases were registered, the DSAL imposed fines to 45 entities for infringement of the legislation. In 2024 fines were applied to two entities for infringement of occupational safety and health legislation, involving two victims, totaling 4,000 patacas.
Fines to 43 employer entities for infringement of the legal regime for reparation for emerging damage to occupational accidents and occupational diseases were also imposed, which involved 303 workers, totaling 327,000 patacas. The number of fined people increased by 65.4% compared to the previous year. In total, 16 employers' entities did not comply with the duty to notify DSal the cases of occupational accidents and occupational diseases, and 27 did not comply with the duty to acquire occupational accident insurance policy in favor of the worker.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:53:46</pubDate></item><item><title>“I exceeded the limits to offer a more dynamic and engaging show”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/ultrapassei-os-limites-para-oferecer-um-espectaculo-mais-dinamico-e-envolvente/</link><description>How did you approach the process of reimaginating the spike and what are some of the new elements that were introduced?
Reimaginating the "House of Dancing Water" gave me an incredible opportunity to write for the first time a complete story to the show and give life to my creative and artistic vision without limitations. One of the main focuses of the reimagination process was to deepen the emotional depth, individuality and personality of each character. I wanted each character to look more human, more attractive and more emotionally engaging for the public. Their actions now have clearer motivations and their relationships are more tiny and significant. For example, Princess Aani evolved from a symbolic figure to a fully fulfilled heroin, moved by love, courage and a sense of destiny. Your journey is now marked by emotional growth and personal sacrifice, which gives your nature much more weight and relevance. Jean, the stranger, also gained more depth. It is not just an ordinary survivor by chance, their internal conflicts, courage and transformation are more visible and emotionally grounded. One of the most exciting additions is Salvador, the sailor. It brings a completely different energy to history. It is playful, unpredictable and charmingly unreliable. Its presence not only adds humor and exuberance, but also introduces a new dynamic to the narrative. The relationship between Jean and Salvador is particularly significant. Instead of a lonely hero journey, Jean now shares important moments with Salvador, creating a surprising and sincere friendship. Salvador becomes a kind of reluctant companion, sometimes unreliable, often charming, but ultimately loyal. Its evolution connection adds emotional texture and fun to history, showing how even the most unlikely individuals can form a pair through shared confrontations. This creative freedom has also become my artistic key to unlock new South Worlds and experiences never before seen. "The Magic Garden", "Aqua Cage" and "City of the Future" are striking examples that illustrate a narrative driven by timeless themes of love, fate, heroism and spectacular adventures. Other significant additions include symbolic elements such as Poetic and Precious Anni Stone "Heart of Water", the mystical "Sword of Water" and the immersive "World of the Waters." The show also features a new extravagant choreography, dynamic end, lighting and laser effects, video projections and a completely reorganized soundtrack, creating an experience that looks more like cinematic than ever. Last but not least, visually, the show underwent a complete transformation. We introduced new costume designs for a total of 300 costumes, along with renewed hairstyles and makeup with bold, dramatic and expressive touches, ensuring that each artist looks as stunning as the presentation itself.
 
How did the changes improve the public experience?
Improving public experience begins by plunging him into a rich and emotional story that seems timeless and plays with his imagination. By reimaging the House of Dancing Water, I focused on creating a more cinematic and emotionally engaging trip, where all the elements, from the look to the sound, function in harmony to attract viewers to the world I created. By introducing new scenes, environments and characters that surprise and captivates, such as those mentioned earlier, such as the "Magic Garden", "Aqua Cage" and "City of the Future", these scenarios are not only spectacular to see, but also essential for the narrative and to deepen the emotional resonance of the show. Technically, I exceeded the limits to offer a more dynamic and engaging show. This includes an impressive reorganized symphonic soundtrack that surrounds the audience with powerful sound landscapes, intensifying emotional moments and boosting the story. Aerial performances, including the updated “human chandelier”, now have improved and visual breathtaking movements that make the audience feel part of the presentation. The layer approach to the development of the characters allows the audience to connect more deeply, not just with the show, but with people in the center of the adventure. They are not just artists on stage; They are living and sensitive characters, whose relationships reflect real human emotions: love, trust, hatred, conflict, redemption. This is what really raises the experience. Finally, redesigned costumes, hairstyles and makeup create a more evocative and theatrical visual identity. Each character seems as extraordinary as their role in history, ensuring that the audience is continually surprised, inspired and emotionally connected from the first to the last moment of the journey.
 
How challenging was these new elements to integrate into existing history?
Integrating new elements in an iconic original production such as “House of Dancing Water” was a creative challenge and great artistic responsibility. The original show had its DNA and was worshiped by the public around the world, so the task was to evolve it without losing his soul and respecting this DNA. The biggest challenge was to find the right balance by introducing new and significant layers of narrative and meaning, characters and environments. Each new element, whether a character like Salvador, the sailor, or a scenario like the “city of the future”, had to seem organically integrated into the narrative, not added. Approaching this rethinking the plot from the beginning really guided me and helped me to ensure that the emotional journey remained coherent and engaging. The goal was not just to add a show alone, but to deepen emotions, raise the narrative and increase the sense of admiration and the unique experience of the public. Technically, integrating new South Elements such as flying chandeliers, immersive projections and dynamic water effects required reengineering of parts of the stage and the flow of the show. This required a close collaboration between creative, technical and performance teams to ensure that these innovations seem natural within the show world. In the end, these challenges became opportunities to innovate, reimaginate, and expand the boundaries than "House of Dancing Water" could be. The result is a production that seems new and familiar at the same time, offering the public a deeper, immersive and emotionally powerful experience.
 
What were some of the main challenges faced when bringing the show back to life?
Bringing the House of Dancing Water was a monumental task, full of creative, technical and logistics challenges. After a few years of absence, we were not just reviving a show and awakening a world, but also facing the first reimaginating challenge and then rebuilding everything from the inside out, based on my new artistic view. One of the biggest challenges was gathering and training a global team of artists, technicians and creative professionals. Some had worked in the original production, while others were totally new in this world. Align all around a renewed view, maintaining the accuracy and safety necessary for such a technically complex show, required immense coordination, patience and dedication. Team formation and joint work were fundamental. Another major challenge was to reinvent the show to meet the expectations of the current audience in a global digital world. Spectators now seek more immersive and emotionally engaging experiences, so we had to rethink the rhythm, narrative, scenic transitions and the visual impact of each scene. This meant reorganizing music, redesigning costumes, introducing cutting -edge technology and reformulating choreography, all preserving the emotional essence of the show. From a technical point of view, revitalizing a huge theater, built for this purpose, after a long interruption was no easy task. For example, we had to perform extensive tests and adjustments on the water stage, elevators and flight systems, among other key elements, to ensure that everything met the highest safety and performance standards. Finally, reintroducing the rethought show in a postpandey world brought its own set of challenges, from changes in public behavior to changes in expectations in relation to live entertainment. But in many ways, this has also become a source of inspiration: an opportunity to offer something cheerful, breathless and deeply human at a time when people need it most. By overcoming these challenges, all teams have come together with incredible passion and resilience, proving that this show, such as water and the gemstone in your heart, is always evolving and always full of life.
 
What is more proud of in this new version of the show?
What is most proud is to have reimaginating the housewash creatively and artistic, respecting its original DNA. I was never afraid of surprising, being innovative and taking the show to a new era. I took something iconic and loved and took it to a new level through a deep narrative, artistic risks and technical innovation. This gives the show, from my point of view, a new life and new meaning, and has always aimed to offer the viewer an unique and unique experience. I have a special pride of the emotional depth we added to the show. Characters like Princess Aani, Jean, The Strange, Lilith, The Black Queen, and Salvador, the sailor, among others, now have clearer motivations and papers. In addition, symbolic elements such as the “heart of water” gemstone or the “water sword” and “the world of water” add poetic and spectacular layers that connect more powerfully with the public. All decisions, from choreography to costume, from music to scenery, were taken with the intention of telling a more complete and resonant story. I am also incredibly grateful for the collaborative spirit that made it all possible. The passion, resilience and dedication of the teams of artists, technicians, designers and teams were extraordinary. Together we created a show that is not only visually spectacular, but also emotionally unforgettable and of which everyone can be proud. Ultimately, what fills me most proudly is hearing from the public who feel transported, moved and inspired. This is the magic of live performance and this is the soul of this "House of Dancing Water".</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Dalai-Lama reaffirms continuity of his institution on the edge of 90 years</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/dalai-lama-reafirma-continuidade-da-sua-instituicao-a-beira-dos-90-anos/</link><description>Tibetan spiritual leader Dalai-Lama reaffirmed yesterday the continuity of his institution, in one of the clearest statements to the date on the intention to secure a successor, six days of his 90th birthday.
Before hundreds of faithful and monks gathered at the McLeod Ganj's main temple in northern India, the Tibetan spiritual leader and the Nobel Prize for Peace has committed to “serving humanity” not only personally, but through the entity that represents, in a beam veiled to the continuity of spiritual lineage.
The Tibetan leader's statement took place during a Tenshug, an elaborate long -life offering ceremony organized this year by the Dhomey Province community. Using the traditional Pandita ceremonial yellow hat, Dalai Lama received, for about two hours, offerings from a long procession of devotees praying for their longevity.
At 89, Dalai Lama has lived in India since 1959, the year he fled from Tibet. Yesterday's message comes after the publication of his latest book, Voice for The Voiceless, in which the spiritual leader states that his reincarnation will take place outside Chinese territory. This statement precedes a key meeting of High Lamas, scheduled for this week in Dharamshala, precisely to discuss the institution's future.
Dalai Lama's position collides with Beijing's plans, which considers the Tibetan leader a separatist. The Chinese government seeks to control succession and, in 1995, detained Panchen Lama, a central figure in the recognition of reincarnation, with the aim of appointing a successor aligned with the interests of the Chinese Communist Party.
The ceremony marks the beginning of a decisive week for the future of Tibet, which will culminate on July 6 with the official celebrations of the 90th anniversary of Dalai Lama, an event that the world follows with expectation regarding the definition of eventual succession.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:40:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Greek gods benefit Hyundai and Tänak</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/deuses-gregos-beneficiam-hyundai-e-tanak/</link><description>Ott Tänak won the acropolis's rally and ended the Hyundai victory fasting in the WRC. The stoned pilot, navigated by Martin Järveoja, has always been very fast over the three days of proof and can thank the Greek gods for not having registered major damage in his i20 n rally1. It ended with an advantage of 32.8 seconds for the Toyota of Frenchman Sébastien Ogier and left teammate Adrien Fourmaux, who closed the podium, for more than three minutes.
"It was a fantastic but also incredibly demanding weekend. Road temperatures and conditions were big obstacles, but we were able to keep our tires alive and demonstrate our progress," said Tänak, who confessed a problem in his Hyundai's gearbox in the ultimate rally. "I was very worried. I lost the third speed, the others made noise. And even when we crossed the goal line we still had 50 kilometers to the Assistance Park. It was a big scare, but it went well."
The high temperatures - which even reached the 70 degrees centigrade in the habitules - and the rocky surface of Greece made many victims. There is not even memory of so many holes at a World Cup, with some riders to be disruption of bad luck more than once in the same classificative. "We avoided the holes by forcing the progress in the sections where the risk was lower. And we raised the foot in the hardest places, where the risk was potentially higher. That was the key to victory," the Estonium confessed.
Ott Tänak again starred in an intense battle with Sébastien Ogier (Toyota Gr Yaris Rally1) - it had been so in Portugal and Sardinia. This time Estonium took the best and reinforced the race to the World Cup. He left Greece with 30 points, three more than Ogier (the Gaul won Wolf Power Stage) and 13 more than Elfyn Evans. Toyota's Welsh, the championship leader, finished the acropolis's rally in fourth position, a result that was not even bad at the time of the ungrateful task of opening the road on Friday.
Evans now adds 150 points. Sébastien Ogier, eight times world champion, has 141, but keeps the idea of ​​failing some of the next rounds to spend more time with the family. It is recalled that last year the Frenchman reconsidered by opening the possibility of a ninth title. Tänak is in third place in the championship with 138 points.
"There was no big thing to do before OTT's elevated pace. I congratulate him because he deserved the victory. And we can be happy that we got 27 points. I think it was the best we could reach this weekend," said Ogier.
Who also showed service on Hellenic soil was Adrien Fourmaux. The Hyundai Frenchman came from a set of bad results, leaving Portugal and the Sardinia shaking. Fourmaux, navigated by compatriot Alexandre Coria, won several classifications and closed the rally in third place on the podium.
"It was for me one of the most difficult rally ever. The temperatures are very high and the soil is extremely abrasive, full of loose stones. I still tried to reach second place but it was impossible after the problem on the rear axle. It was so important to hold third place," the Frenchman confessed, referring to the impact on PEC10 that damaged the suspension of Hyundai, having lost a lot of time.
 
Neuville in Maré de Lezar
Thierry Neuville was below expectations. The current world champion even led but two holes on the first day of the race 'stole' about three minutes. There was no shortage of criticism of Hankook's tires. Hyundai's Belgian, who doubles with compatriot Martijn Wydaeghe, continues without winning in 2025 and will hardly enter the race for the title. At this time the fifth place in the championship, 54 points of Elfyn Evans.
"It was not the weekend we expected. We had several holes and other problems. Let us now concentrate on a large set of points in the Rally of Estonia," he said.
The bad luck knocked on the door of a hand full of Rally1 riders-only five of the main category cars ended in the Top-10 ′. Greegoire Munster (Ford) was forced to abandon when he was sixth place with problems in the fuel system. The same happened with Martins Sesks (Ford) and Sami Pajari (Toyota). The FIA ​​has revealed that it is investigating the issue.
Japanese Takamoto Katsuta and Finnish Kalle Rovanperä also disappointed. The two Toyota pilots were already in trouble when they both came out on the road at PEC11. “I tried to do my best, but it's a great disappointment this weekend, not at the level I should be. I apologize to the team, I'm going to work for Estonia,” promised Rovanperä.
Still, the Japanese builder maintains a comfortable advantage in the accounts of the World Cup, having benefited from a major championship starting with wins in the first five stages. Toyota now adds 358 points, Hyundai has 293 while M-Sport Ford adds only 97.
 
Solberg assumes WRC2 leadership
Oliver Solberg finished the acropolis's rally in an impressive sixth place in the overall classification, despite being in the commands of a Toyota Gr Yaris Rally2. The Swedish left Gus Greensmith's Skoda Fabia RS Rally2 at 53.8 seconds. Yohan Rossel (Citroën C3 Rally2) closed the podium. Solberg is now the WRC2 leader with a five -point advantage for Yohan Rossel.
The World Cup is returned from July 17 to 20 with the Rally of Estonia.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:39:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Research evaluates all theories for airplane fall from Air India, including sabotage</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/investigacao-avalia-todas-as-teorias-para-queda-de-aviao-da-air-india-incluindo-sabotagem/</link><description>The investigation into the fall of the Air India Boeing 787 on June 12 by raising Ahmedabad's flight in the northwest of the country is examining all theories, including sabotage, said the executive of Nova Delhi.
"All angles are being examined," said Minister of State for Civil Aviation, Murlidhar Mohol, in response to a question about a possible sabotage made on the NDTV news channel.
The air disaster, the deadliest in the world since 2014, made at least 279 dead, according to a provisional police report released two days after the accident.
A single passenger, sitting close to an emergency exit on the front of the plane, survived the crash when the device crashed into a residential area of ​​the city shortly after taking off. At least 38 people died on the ground, according to the same police report.
The pilot made an emergency warning shortly after raising flight, said the Ministry of Civil Aviation of India, without revealing further details about the cause of the accident so far.
Video images released after the accident showed the Boeing Dreamliner unable to gain altitude and then fall to the ground between an orange fireball.
In his interview with NDTV, Mohol mentioned, among other factors, the scenario of a simultaneous failure of both engines, in "this never happened," he said. "The (investigation) report will allow us to determine if the engines had a problem, if it was a fuel supply problem and why both engines stopped running," the minister added.
Murlidhar Mohol said that "it is too early to say," but whatever the cause of the accident, "it will be known," the release of a first report within three months.
The two black boxes of the aircraft, the flight data recorder (FDR) and the Cabin Voice Recorder (CVR) are being analyzed in India, the Indian Department of Civil Aviation Accidents (AAIB) said on Wednesday.
Air India Flight 171 fall, bound for London, was the first involving a B-787, which entered the service in 2011.
The civil aviation authority ordered an inspection to the other 33 B-787 in service of Air India the day after the fall, but Mohol reiterated on Sunday that this operation did not reveal "any problem."
To date, forensic experts were able to identify 260 victims through DNA. The identification process is still underway.
Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:35:01</pubDate></item><item><title>China's industrial activity retreats for the third consecutive month</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/actividade-industrial-da-china-recua-pelo-terceiro-mes-consecutivo/</link><description>The Purchasing Managers Index (PMI), the main indicator of the sector, was set at 49.7 points, above the 49.5 recorded in May, in line with the predictions of most analysts.
A value below 50 points represents an activity contraction compared to the previous month, while values ​​above signal growth.
Of the five subsidies that make up the PMI of the transforming industry, those related to production, new orders-key indicator of demand-and delivery times remained above the growth line, unlike raw material and employment inventories, which continued in contraction zone.
The GNE Zhao Qinghe statistical precisely highlighted the recovery “either of production and demand”, with reference to sectors such as food and special machinery, although it underlined “insufficient market activity” in other areas, such as non -metallic minerals or foundry metal and lamination.
In a report, British consultant Capital Economics noted that June data suggest that the Chinese economy "has gaining some impetus again." The subindex of new export orders rose from 47.5 to 47.7 points, the third consecutive monthly increase, although still in negative territory.
This performance “probably reflects an increase in US demand after the 90 -day commercial truce” began between the two countries in mid -May, analyst Zichun Huang pointed out.
Huang warned, however, with “persistent deflationist pressure” in the Chinese economy, with production prices accelerating in June, but remaining “at low levels”.
The GNE also released the PMI of non -manufacturing sectors - Services and Construction - which rose from 50.3 in May to 50.5 points in June, exceeding analysts' expectations.
Construction led growth, with the indicator advanced from 51 to 52.8 points, while the services practically stagnated, retreating slightly from 50.2 to 50.1. "Activity in areas such as restoration, tourism, hotel and logistics has fallen this month, but was more than compensated for the construction of the construction PMI, which reached the highest value of the last three months," said Huang.
The increase is explained by “continuous fiscal support for infrastructure expense” and signs of relief in the collapse of real estate, due to government efforts to help promoters accelerate ongoing projects.
The compound PMI, which adds data from the transforming and non -transforming sectors, rose from 50.4 in May to 50.7 points in June.
Despite positive signs, the capital Economics maintains a “cautious” view of the evolution of the Chinese economy, anticipating an export slowdown and a weakening of tax stimuli in the second half of the year, factors that “will probably lock activity” in the country.
Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:42:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Minimum age for low colo-recrectal cancer screening for 50 years</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/idade-minima-para-o-rastreio-do-cancro-colo-rectal-baixa-para-os-50-anos/</link><description>The minimum age for the tracking of colo-rectal cancer will be reduced from 55 to 50 from today, thus encompassing residents born between 1956 and 1975. The announcement was made yesterday by a press conference where the importance of early diagnosis was reinforced for detecting and treatment of the second most common-and more lethal-in the Macau region.
NG Ka Kai, a doctor of the health services gastroenterology service, began by admitting that “the number of patients with colo-rectal cancer should continue to increase” in the coming years, as a result of population aging and risk factors such as an unbalanced diet, excessive alcohol intake or a sedentary lifestyle. Early detection of the disease and increased survival rate therefore depend on the adoption of healthy habits and the proactive screening of the disease through stool or colonoposcopy harvests.
According to the data presented by the doctor, more than 31,000 appearances were registered in the Cancer Cancer Tracking Program since the launch of the program in 2016, which represents about 17% of the target audience. Over the past ten years, 2,999 participants have been subjected to colonoscopy due to the presence of blood in the stool-among them, 312 had high-risk polyps and 168 were diagnosed with colo-recctal cancer.
Early screening allowed half of the malignant tumors to be detected in the early stages, between stages 0 and II, while one third of the patients had carcinoma in situ (ie, stage 0). Ng Ka Kai pointed out that, if detected and treated in time, this type of cancer has a “high” survival rate, which can reach 95% in stage 0 and 93% and 80% in stages I and II, respectively.
Data collected by the Macau cancer registration system also show that, between 2018 and 2022, the mortality rate of colo-recctal cancer in the territory decreased 12.6% compared to the previous period, between 2013 and 2017. At the same time, the survival rate has risen about 8% in recent years, proving “the success” of the program implemented nine years ago by health services.
 
Proactive screening is the key to prevention
Colo-recrectal cancer often manifests symptoms such as stool bleeding, weight loss without apparent reason or constant fatigue, being more frequent in people with personal or cancer family backgrounds. SAO KUAN LAW, Family Medicine Assistant in the Community Health Care Area, has warned, however, that the disease may develop even in asymptomatic individuals who do not have known risk factors.
Marking for screening can be done in person or electronically, in the “My Health” tab of the Macao Single Account. After performing the hidden blood test in the stool, participants who accuse a positive result will be notified and only then referred to a colonoscopy exam - which, as NG Kai recalls, is a “simple” process and performed only in case of need. "People are afraid of being immediately redirected for colonoscopy examination, which is not true. We want to make it clear to all citizens belonging to this age range that first have the examination to the feces, and only then that the invasive examination - colonoscopy - is considered."
Wu Ya Ting, a public health assistant doctor at the Center for Prevention and Control of Health Services Diseases, added the panel with an overview of the disease evolution, as well as prevention measures to adopt. The expert explained that, in most cases, cancer originates from benign growth in the internal coating of the colon, called polyps. Although this medical condition may initially be benign, “it is possible that a small percentage of these polyps slowly transforms extremely evil tumors,” a process that can drag for years or even decades.
Risk factors are divided into unchanging factors-those related to age or hereditary genetic mutations, for example-and changeable factors that can be changed through awareness campaigns and lifestyle changes. "Reducing cancer risk begins precisely with the adoption of healthy everyday behaviors. Maintaining a healthy diet, eating fresh and natural foods, consuming less red meats, doing sports ... This lifestyle is not only beneficial for preventing colo-rectal cancer, but also for the prevention of cardiovascular or metabolic disease." Wu Ya Ting concludes: "Waiting for the emergence of obvious symptoms can mean missing the best treatment opportunity, so the proactive screening is the key to prevention."</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:53:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese mne starts for a ride for Europe to strengthen ties to disputes with Washington</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/mne-chines-inicia-periplo-pela-europa-para-estreitar-lacos-face-a-disputas-com-washington/</link><description>The prominent figure of Chinese diplomacy, Wang Yi, 71, has been planning to move to Brussels, headquarters of the EU, as well as France and Germany.
The visit takes place at a time when China seeks to strengthen ties with the European continent, before the growing tension with the United States, led by Donald Trump, who repeatedly classifies Beijing as a strategic rival.
Despite the approach, divergences persist between Brussels and Beijing, namely in the economic domain: the EU massive commercial deficit of China (304 billion euros), the partnership between Beijing and Moscow Despite the war in Ukraine, the additional European tariffs on Chinese electric vehicles, and Chinese retaliation aimed at the French brandy. "Sino-European relations face important opportunities, at a time when the world is going through rapid historical transformations, with the unsettling growth of hegemonic unilateralism, protectionism and behaviors," Chinese diplomacy spokesman Guo Jiakun said on Friday in an implicit critique of the US and trade war.
In this context, China and EU should “jointly preserve global peace and stability, defend multilateralism and free trade, safeguard international rules, equity and justice, and affirm itself as stabilizing and constructive forces in a turbulent world,” he added.
In Brussels, Wang Yi is expected to meet with the new head of European diplomacy, Kaja Kallas, for a “high-level strategic dialogue,” according to Chinese authorities.
In Germany, the minister will meet the homologist, Johann Wadephul, to address diplomacy and security topics. This will be Wang Yi's first visit since the formation of a new conservative government in Berlin last May.
In France, Wang will meet with Foreign Minister Jean-Noël Barrot, who visited China in March.
The war in Ukraine should master part of the conversations. China has been appealed to peace negotiations and respect for the territorial integrity of states - alluding to Ukraine - but avoids condemning Russia and deepened Moscow ties since the invasion in February 2022 in the commercial, diplomatic and military areas. Such a position has been valid to Beijing criticism from Europeans, who accuse China to offer essential economic support to the Russian war effort.
Business relations between China and EU have deteriorated in recent years, with Brussels to denounce unfair economic practices by Beijing.
The tension intensified last year with the imposition by the EU of additional tariffs on Chinese electric cars. In retaliation, China aimed at the French brandy.
The European Commission decided two weeks ago to exclude Chinese public tenders in the area of ​​medical equipment more than five million euros, invoking similar restrictions on European firms in China. Beijing reacted, accusing Brussels of applying a system of "two weights, two measures."
Another point of friction is the so -called "rare lands". Since April, Chinese authorities have required licenses to export these strategic metals, used in products such as mobile phones or electric car batteries. The issuance of these authorizations has been, according to the European, limited and slow auto industry.
In response, Beijing proposed in June that the creation of a “green channel” that allows priority access to rare land to the European market.
Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:40:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese communist party exceeds 100 million members</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/partido-comunista-chines-ultrapassa-os-100-milhoes-de-membros/</link><description>The Chinese Communist Party (CCP) exceeded the 100 million members in late 2024, according to a report yesterday released, in a context marked by more than a decade of campaign against corruption between their paintings.
The number of affiliates rises to 100.27 million -in a country with about 1,400 million inhabitants -an increase of 2.13 million compared to the end of 2023, indicated the organization department of the CCP Central Committee, on the 104th anniversary of the party's foundation, which is marked on Tuesday. "CCP affiliation has continuously increased, while its structure continues to improve and base organizations - currently at 5.2 million - reinforce," says the report, quoted by the state press.
The educational profile of the members has also evolved: almost 57% have college or higher education, the document revealed.
The number of women continues to grow, totaling 31 million affiliates (30.9%), and the average age of new members has decreased, with 83.7% of adhesions in 2024 to correspond to people 35 or less.
The report also indicates that the proportion of members from ethnic minorities remained in the 7.7% recorded in the previous year.
The party stressed that it maintains a focus on internal supervision and self -government, applying “the spirit of reform and strict standards”, and increased by 16.5% in the number of tables that received specific training in 2024.
Founded in clandestinity, the CCP is now considered the largest party in the world and exerts a transverse influence on China's political, economic and social life, with patriotic content linked to its history to emerge even in national university access exams.
China's party general secretary and president, Xi Jinping, yesterday chaired a meeting of the Central Committee Politburo, in which new rules were discussed to “improve” the functioning of deliberation, coordination and decision-making organisms. "At the meeting, the importance of avoiding formalism and bureaucratization was underlined, with a view to achieving concrete results," said the official news agency Xinhua
These principles join the repeated appeals to austerity by the party leadership, as part of the 2012 anti-corruption campaign in 2012, which has already resulted in the condemnation of dozens of corruption, including former ministers and leaders of companies and state organizations.
In January, Xi again asked for a "resolute victory in the hard and prolonged battle against corruption", which he classified as "the biggest threat" to the party.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:40:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong promotes in Portugal technology in the construction of public housing</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/hong-kong-promove-em-portugal-tecnologia-na-construcao-de-habitacao-publica/</link><description>The Hong Kong government announced yesterday that it will promote in Portugal the use of technology in the construction of public housing. According to a statement, Hong Kong authorities will organize in Portugal on Thursday a business lunch entitled “Unraveling New Horizons: accessible housing and opportunities in Hong Kong and the Great Bay”. The Commissioner for the Development of the Great Bay, Maisie Chan Kit Ling, will make a speech about “the huge business opportunities” that the regional project offers to Portuguese entrepreneurs. At the event will “share Hong Kong's experiences in increasing quantity, speed, efficiency and quality of public housing construction through the adoption of various innovative rapid and robotic construction technologies”.
Hong Kong's secretary for housing, Winnie Ho Wing Yin, invited more than 20 representatives of the region's construction sector and mainland China to participate in the event. These companies will talk about technologies such as prefabricated modules, the integration of mechanical, electrical and channeling facilities, and the use of robots in construction. The event can serve “to strengthen links between the Hong Kong and Portugal sectors and explore business opportunities”, it underlines in the statement. Also Maisie Chan and Winnie Ho will still participate in the 17th International Forum on Urbanism, which will take place between July 1 and 4, in the renewed Pavilion of Portugal, which, after the works carried out by architect Siza Vieira, was transferred to the University of Lisbon.
The political program of the new Portuguese government, led by Luís Montenegro, provides for the construction of 59,000 public houses by 2030 and financing for more housing, including public-private partnerships in the State Real estate. On June 17, the prime minister admitted to Parliament that the previous goal, to build 26,000 public houses by 2026, had "a difficult execution," but refused to be "defeatist and pessimistic." "I think we still have the ability to stimulate construction in the public sector," said Montenegro, noting that "the execution rate is now increasing." "We have an execution rate in the universe of these 26 thousand houses of 27% and, according to the information that the municipalities have transmitted us by the end of June, 13,429 housing will be ready in this program," he said. The prime minister also considered that it was necessary to exceed “administrative and bureaucratic blocks” that delayed the construction of new houses.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:40:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Radio Asia Livre stops publishing news in Cantonese due to Trump cuts</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/radio-asia-livre-deixa-de-publicar-noticias-em-cantones-devido-a-cortes-de-trump/</link><description>US broadcaster Radio Asia Livre announced yesterday that he will no longer publish news in Cantonese, a dominant language in Hong Kong and Macau, due to the financing cuts imposed by President Donald Trump's US government. "After US government's government's funding cuts, the size of the Radio Asia Livre team [RFA in the acronym in English] continued to decrease," the station lamented, in a statement published on the Portal in Cantonese on the Internet. “Our service in Cantonese (…) will no longer update news from tomorrow [Tuesday],” said RFA, referring to the day the 28th anniversary of the Hong Kong administration transition from the United Kingdom to China. "The news on our portal will become history and will remain there indefinitely," said the station. The statement also revealed that they had been drawn plans since 2024 to change the name of the service in RFA Cantonese to RFA HK, after registering a huge increase in popularity, after the wave of old manifestations and pro-democracy of 2019.
The protests led the Chinese central government to impose Hong Kong a national security law, which stripped a campaign for the repression of political dissent and the critical press of the Communist Party (Single Party). "After the disappearance of Apple Daily, Stand News, and Hong Kong Citizen News, with self-censorship in Hong Kong's main media, becoming increasingly common, the Cantonese service of Radio Asia Free became one of the media in which Hong Kong citizens trusted," said the station. Hong Kong is ranked 140th among 180 territories in the world's press release without borders for 2025, when it was 80th in 2021 and 18th in 2002. In March 2024, RFA had closed the delegation in Hong Kong after being accused of being “antichina” by Wen Wei Pao, two newspapers, two newspapers, territory detained by the Chinese authorities. Three months later, Hong Kong Security Secretary Chris Tang Ping-Kung accused the RFA of threatening China's national security "by using inaccurate information and inventing ways to incite people to distrust or hate the government." On June 20, the US government announced the resignation of more than 600 United States agency employees for global media (Usagm), a federal organization that generates broadcasters such as Radio Asia Livre and Radio Europa Livre. This measure completed the 85% reduction in the agency's workforce, resulting in 1,400 discharge since Donald Trump ordered the Usagm dismantling in March.
Radio Asia Livre, created in 1996, had already ceased to publish news in Tibetan and Uiguur (language of a Muslim mostly ethnic minority) in May, also due to cuts in financing.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:39:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Unemployment rate is set at 2.5%</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/taxa-de-desemprego-fixa-se-nos-25/</link><description>Macau's global unemployment rate was 2.5% between March and May, equal to the period between February and April. The rate related to the unemployment of local residents also remained at 1.9%. Unemployment continues at the same level compared to the same period last year, however, compared to 2023, there was a slight decrease.
Data released yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) show that between March and May, the active population living in Macau was 380,200 and the population employed was 373,000, or 400 and 200 people, respectively, compared to the previous period. The number of residents employed (282,200) rose 300 people.
DSEC points out that the number of residents employed in the construction industry has grown, and, on the contrary, that of residents employed in the financial activities branch decreased.
The number of unemployed residents was 7,200, most of those looking for a new employment previously worked in the field of economic activity of retail trade, in the field of construction and in the game, says DSEC. In addition to these, the number of unemployed residents looking for first employment accounted for 8.4% of unemployed residents, less percentage points, compared to the preceding period.
The global sub -unemployment rate rose 0.2 percentage points to 1.6% and the residents' subfather rate increased 0.3 points to 2.1%. The number of subjects in a sub -unemployment situation (6,000) rose 800 people, in relation to the previous period. It is noteworthy that most underemployed residents belonged to the economic activity of the construction and the business of real estate activities and services provided to the companies.
Compared to the period from March to May 2024, the global activity rate (66.6%) and the resident's activity rate (61.3%) lowered 0.8 and 0.7 percentage points, respectively.
DSEC also says that, according to preliminary estimates of migration records, the average number of Macao residents and non-resident workers who worked in Macao but lived abroad, was estimated at about 106,400 in the reference period, including these individuals, the total labor was approximately 486,500 people, compared to the past period.
Recently, several deputies were apprehensive about the employment situation in the region, namely due to the news of the closing of the satellite casinos until the end of this year, which could directly affect 5,600 local workers and other small businesses that operate with those spaces.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:53:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau youth receive five distinctions in Guangdong competition</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/01/jovens-de-macau-recebem-cinco-distincoes-em-competicao-de-guangdong/</link><description>Macao raised three silver medals and two excellence prizes at the 4th Professional Activity Competition of Guangdong Province, which took place in April. This year's edition had as its theme “Technical Skills illuminate the future, qualified pictures enhance industries” and brought together more than 1,300 young people from all over the province.
Ten competitors and nine macau referees competed in nine of the 101 existing modalities, under the organization of the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL): Commercial Product Exposure Techniques, Fashion Techniques, Network System Management, Website Techniques, Hotel Reception, Hairdresser, Autonomous Mobile Robot, Floral Art and Distribution of Information Net Line. In a statement released yesterday, Dsal reveals that young people raised a total of five medals in five different modalities.
The three silver medals were won by Luo Iao Seng, in the 'Website' technology, the duo Lyu Jin and Feng Ka Wai, in the Autonomous Mobile Robot mode, and Chan Chi Lek, in the hotel reception mode. The two prizes of excellence, in turn, were attributed to Chi Si Long, in the mode of commercial product exposure techniques, and Leong Weng Lam, in the mode of fashion techniques.
Macao first participated in the professional skills of Guangdong province in 2023, in the 3rd edition, having achieved a silver and one bronze medal. In the same statement, DSAL states that "it continuously organizes young people in Macao to participate in competitions for professional and regional professional skills, in order to encourage younger people in Macao to acquire technical skills and to follow this path to professional success."
At the same time, “the province of Guangdong and Macau will continue to deepen cooperation in the area of ​​qualified framework”, “to take advantage of the complementarity of mutual advantages and develop the spirit of benefits and mutual gains”, in order to transform “the large bay into a level of high -level qualified frames”.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:42:53</pubDate></item></channel></rss>