<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/22/comunidade-lusofona-mobiliza-se-em-campanha-de-solidariedade-para-apoiar-vitimas-das-cheias-em-portugal/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Government expects more than three thousand newborns in 2026</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/22/governo-espera-mais-de-tres-mil-recem-nascidos-em-2026/</link><description>After recording the lowest number of newborns in the last five decades in 2025, the Health Services say they expect young local couples to have more children in this Lunar Year of the Horse and for births in Macau to rise again to more than three thousand.
The Health Services are concerned about the continued decline in the birth rate and expect the number of newborns to increase again and surpass the three thousand level. The issue was addressed after Macau registered just 2,871 babies born last year, the lowest number since 1978.
Tai Wa Hou, deputy director of Centro Hospitalar Conde de São Januário, admitted that the birth rate is difficult to predict, but he hopes that young couples in Macau “will have more children”, taking into account that this Year of the Horse “is considered auspicious”.
It is recalled that the number of newborns in 2025 was 2,871, which represents a decrease of more than 20%, or 735, compared to the 3,606 registered in 2024. It was also the first time that this number fell below 3,000 for almost five decades, according to the Statistics and Census Services.
The Macao SAR's fertility rate, according to the United Nations' 2024 World Fertility Report, stands at just 0.68, the lowest in the world. This rate implies that, on average, each woman in Macau gives birth to less than one child during her lifetime, falling far short of the 2.1 level for replacing generations or maintaining a stable population.
Speaking to Radio Macau in Chinese, on the sidelines of a visit to the first babies born during the Lunar New Year, Tai Wa Hou highlights that the authorities have launched “high quality” services that cover the entire pregnancy cycle, being measures to promote births and favor child development.
According to the deputy director of Health Services, free Non-Invasive Prenatal Testing (NIPT) services have been launched since January 1st of this year for pregnant women residents of Macau, in all age groups, with the aim of protecting the health of pregnant women and their fetuses.
NIPT, as a non-invasive chromosomal screening tool that requires a blood sample from the pregnant woman, allows the identification of fetal deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) and early detection of chromosomal abnormalities and genetic diseases, such as Down syndrome, Edwards syndrome or Patau syndrome.
“Compared to traditional invasive diagnostic methods, such as amniocentesis, this test has the advantages of high precision, safety and no risk of miscarriage”, he guaranteed.
Tai Wa Hou added that the Government also launched the Health Management Platform for pregnant and postpartum women, an initiative that “supports prenatal care and safeguards the health of pregnant women and newborns”, said the doctor.
Low birth rates have been a recurring theme in society. In July last year, the Government launched the “child care subsidy” measure, of a provisional nature, to reinforce financial support for parents of newborns, with a total value of 54 thousand patacas for children up to three years old. The Executive also launched a public consultation on the increase, in the private sector, of maternity leave, from 70 to 90 days, and annual leave, from six to 12 days, so that workers can “obtain a better balance between work and family life”.
ELEVEN COLLECTIVE CASES OF GASTROENTERITIS
 
Macau authorities have received reports of eleven incidents of food poisoning since the beginning of this year, six of which were linked to the consumption of raw oysters. Tai Wai Hou revealed that most cases involved mild symptoms such as diarrhea caused by norovirus infection.
In light of the detection of several cases of gastroenteritis associated with the consumption of raw oysters in Macau and Hong Kong, Tai Wa Hou reminded the public to pay attention to food safety, and individuals with weakened immune systems and the elderly should avoid consuming raw oysters whenever possible.
The official also spoke about the flu situation in Macau, revealing that, since the start of flu vaccination in September last year, more than 200,000 doses of vaccines have been administered. According to Tai Wa Hou, the current positivity rate for the influenza virus monitored in laboratories and in the Emergency Department is approximately 6%, remaining below the alert threshold and not constituting an active period of influenza.
However, Tai warns of increased risks of flu infection due to the number of visitors during the Lunar New Year period, calling for unvaccinated residents to be vaccinated and for the public to avoid visiting crowded places.</description><pubDate>2026-02-22 23:32:58</pubDate></item><item><title>“Macau has a charming side”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/22/macau-tem-um-lado-encantador/</link><description>Rodrigo Leão has already passed through the territory with Sétima Legião and Madredeus, bands of which he is a co-founder, as well as twice solo. This time, he will join the program of the Macau Literary Festival and perform on March 11th, at the Macau Cultural Center, with a group of several musicians, to present his latest work O Rapaz da Montanha. In an interview with PONTO FINAL, he spoke about the Portugueseness that is visible in his songs, his love for cinema and music, in addition to his time in the East and the international recognition, which has taken him across borders.
 
It is the third time solo, in Macau, but the fifth time, in total, if we include the concerts with Sétima Legião and Madredeus. What are the expectations for this return?
I've been to Macau many times. In the East, I was in Japan, in North Korea with Madredeus and in South Korea, with my group, solo, twice, 15 years ago.
 
It is not common to be able to perform in North Korea. How was that concert?
I was in Pyongyang and it was one of the most incredible trips we took with the Madredeus, almost 40 years ago. When I went to play in South Korea, of course no one believed that I had been playing in North Korea.
 
What are your impressions of the Macau public?
It is, perhaps, a more spiritual audience and I suppose there are still some Portuguese. We have been doing this show [The Boy from the Mountain], essentially, in Portugal. We already presented it in Spain last year, in three or four places. We were also in Switzerland and Buenos Aires last year. It's the concert we've been doing for a year now. The album came out on April 25th last year and we always hope to attract a warm audience. We go with the band and we are eight musicians. I play piano and synthesizers and I also sing on five or six songs, almost for the first time, but we sing them all. We have the string trio, Celina da Piedade, who plays the accordion and also sings, Frederico Assis on drums, João Eleutério on bass and Ana Vieira on vocals. The concert is very focused on O Rapaz da Montanha, but we also play songs from other albums, such as Cinema or Mãe. We play old songs. Despite using many different languages ​​on my albums, from English to French to Spanish, this album is essentially in Portuguese. Maybe there is a theme that I will play, Pássion, which is in Castilian. In Macau, we will have a Chinese musician [Yueru Zhang] playing ehru with us. It's a concert where we had a lot of fun, because we played percussions, tambourines and drums. We sing together on many songs and there are calmer parts and happier parts.
 
His latest work, O Rapaz da Montanha, has sold out concert halls. Were you expecting this success?
We are happy with the public's acceptance. We have already done the Coliseu de Lisboa, the Coliseu do Porto, the Centro Cultural de Belém twice, a Casa da Música and then we gave concerts in some theaters. We also presented in Madrid and a few other places in Spain and we are happy. I don't have that concern that things live are exactly like they are on the records, but in this work, and especially these songs from O Rapaz da Montanha, they are quite faithful to the versions on the record. We also use some technology. There are songs in which we throw in some rhythms and voices to help our own voices sound more in tune.
 
É, atualmente, um dos músicos portugueses com maior projeção internacional. Considering the difficulty many people have in crossing borders, what do you think helps them achieve this?
I have had some luck, over the years, in being able to record the songs I want and play concerts. Often, it's luck or opportunity, but there are people who work with musicians, who are very important, like agencies. I have been lucky enough to work with António Cunha, who has been a long-time friend, for almost 30 years, and that part is very important: someone who sends records and videos of concerts. Now, above all, I don't like to create too many expectations when a record comes out and think: oh, this is going to be really good and we're going to play it all over the world. I prefer to think almost the opposite. There is no trick. A group that sings in English has more competition with other groups that exist outside Portugal. Although this album, in particular, is entirely in Portuguese, I have a lot of instrumental music and many songs sung in other languages, but there is some Portugueseness in the music I have made. There is some melancholy that exists in Portugal, which doesn't necessarily have to be sad. It can even convey hope or longing. There is still a connection to Portugal with the music I try to make, also through all the trips we make in Portugal, through the places and people we meet.
 
Is this Portugueseness intentional?
It's unconscious. This album, interestingly enough, was made from a song with my wife, Ana Carolina, who wrote most of the lyrics for this work and had already written lyrics on other albums. It was from a song called Cadeira Preta. The day after making it, I had a very clear idea of ​​the album I could make. At the time, I immediately felt a connection to some music I heard when I was a teenager, from the musical universe in Portugal, from composers like José Mário Branco, Zeca Afonso, Fausto and Sérgio Godinho — geniuses! — and, in fact, it is an influence that is present on this album. It can also be seen in the use of the choirs and in the themes in which we all sing together, the percussions are also traditional Portuguese and the fact that I invited José Peixoto, a musician with whom I shared the Madredeus stages for two years, many years ago. One of Jorge Palma's sons, Francisco [Palma], sings a song called Andava Eu. We have an accordionist, who I really like, who is Carlos Poeiras, who lives in Avis, where we have a house, two kilometers from the village, in the middle of the olive trees — where, in fact, most of these songs were composed. Gabriel Gomes, with whom I have played for over 40 years, in Sétima Legião, Madredeus and Os Poetas, also collaborates.
 
Throughout his career, he has also produced a lot of music for theater and cinema. Is it an environment where you navigate at ease?
I have always been passionate about cinema, even more than theater. We were kids and we were 13 or 14 years old. On Avenida de Roma, there was the Quarteto cinema, where we went to watch films on Fridays, from midnight to 5am. We went from room to room, but the truth is that my first projects, Sétima Legião and then Madredeus, also had an instrumental music component, which, in a way, was very cinematic. I always showed that I was interested in making music for films and, if in the first ten years, there were practically no invitations, from about 15 or 20 years ago, I had the opportunity to make music for films, such as The Butler or The Golden Cage, and for documentaries by Petra Costa, a Brazilian director. That gives me a lot of pleasure.
PHOTOGRAPHY Alfredo Cunha
Is the creation process different?
It's different at first, because we have an image and text, but then it ends up being very similar to the normal process. For this album, I knew the path I wanted to find and the album ended up being composed during 2024, when we celebrated 50 years of the freedom we achieved in Portugal, but, in many of the other works, I start by looking for melodies and harmonies. I have no idea where that album will go and if there are songs that will be sung. Often, the songs sung, almost all of them, start out as a sketch of an instrumental song. When I start working, mostly with João Eleutério or Pedro Oliveira, long-time friends, everyone participates. Carlos Tony Gomes plays the cello and ends up helping a lot with the string arrangements. There is teamwork. We go to the studio to record ideas, models and experiment with voices. This is very important.
Do these works start with an idea, but then the rest is improvisation?
Yes… I am self-taught. I started playing alone when I was 12/13 years old, a classical guitar and then a synthesizer. I learned to play with friends. Of course you will gain some experience. With the help of the computer, I can write a piano part, a cello part. It's a universe in which you can build layers of instruments.
The first two projects, Sétima Legião and Madredeus, are very different solo records by Rodrigo Leão. How important were these in your career?
Without these projects, I wouldn't have made these albums that I made later, even when I left Sétima Legião and Madredeus. Sétima Legião are a group of friends from childhood, from Bairro das Estacas [Alvalade], at the time, and we were living in the early 80s. We listened to a lot of groups like New Order, Echo and the Bunnymen, Joy Division, but we mixed that with some traditional percussion, like bagpipes. There was also this more cinematic and instrumental side. Madredeus was a project that Pedro Ayres Magalhães and I started. Pedro played in Heróis do Mar and I played in Sétima Legião. We wanted it to be different from the projects we were playing in at the time, more acoustic, without drums or electric guitars. The success that the group had later, a few years later, was a huge surprise. When our first album came out, it was 1987, and Madredeus took a huge leap forward. This project was more Portuguese than the Sétima Legião. Without being fado, with Pedro Ayres' lyrics and his direction, it was a great learning experience to do things that didn't fit into one project or another. So I started making my songs.
Meanwhile, Sétima Legião returned to giving concerts. Why stop and then return to the stage?
We didn't play for a while, but we celebrated our 30th birthday 14 years ago and played nine or ten concerts. Then we stopped. Unfortunately, Ricardo Camacho died and we marked 40 years at Culturgest, with two concerts dedicated to him. There was some kind of click there, which made us want to continue. In the last three years — we are now entering the fourth year — we have been doing seven, eight or nine concerts a year. We have a lot of ideas, the concerts have gone very well and we have been very good friends for many years. We are even thinking about recording a new album.
 
He worked in Macau in different decades. Do you notice a big difference in the territory, from the first concert to the last?
Yes, the last time I went there, there were already those casinos with seven floors. but there is that atmosphere that I like. That humidity, that smell of food on the streets. Macau has a charming side. I remember a street with some tailors with some suits that I liked. I remember buying a suit there for the concerts. The last time I was there was about 14 years ago, and it will definitely be different, but I'm excited.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Hong Kong airport looks at new routes after meeting with Alexandre Leitão</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/22/aeroporto-de-hong-kong-espreita-novas-rotas-apos-reuniao-com-alexandre-leitao/</link><description>Hong Kong airport confirmed to Lusa that it wants to launch new routes, a week after a meeting between infrastructure leadership and the consul general of Portugal in Macau.
On February 9, Alexandre Leitão met with the executive director of the Hong Kong Airport Authority (AAHK), Vivian Cheung Kar-fay, and with the person responsible for developing new routes.
“[The meeting in Hong Kong was an] opportunity to address issues of mutual interest,” said the consulate, in a message published on the social network Facebook.
Asked by the Macau press about whether the two parties had spoken about potential direct passenger flights between Hong Kong and Portugal, Alexandre Leitão did not reveal details about the meeting.
In a written response to questions from Lusa, AAHK said it has sought to “establish contacts with airlines and commercial partners in the global sector, including government authorities and airport operators”.
The aim is to “foster cooperative relationships in route development”, added a spokesperson for the Hong Kong airport operator.
AAHK also said that it has been working with the HKSAR Government to “establish new air service agreements or expand existing ones”.
Hong Kong does not currently have any air services agreement with Portugal, unlike neighboring Spain, which signed a pact in 2018.
Após lançar voos para 30 novos destinos em 2025, a AAHK garantiu que “continuará a expandir a sua ampla rede aérea”.
On April 3, 2025, the first long-haul cargo route between Macau and Madrid began, operated by Ethiopian airline Ethiopian Airlines.
At the time, the national director for China of Ethiopian Airlines, Aman Wole Gurmu, highlighted that Macau is “an important platform” for economic and commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries.</description><pubDate>2026-02-22 23:28:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan introduces electronic travel authorizations for 74 countries</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/22/japao-introduz-autorizacoes-electronicas-de-viagem-para-74-paises/</link><description>Japan will implement an electronic travel authorization system for citizens of countries that currently do not require a visa for short stays, including Portugal and Brazil, Nikkei reported.

According to an immigration reform bill, consulted by the financial newspaper, the Government will require airlines to deny boarding to travelers who do not have an electronic authorization.
The system, inspired by the Electronic System for Travel Authorization in the United States, will have a fee to pay and will be applied to visitors and tourists from 74 countries exempt from short-term visas.
The list includes Portugal, Brazil and the Chinese regions of Hong Kong and Macau, as well as some of the biggest tourist markets for Japan: South Korea, Taiwan and the United States.
People visiting Japan for less than 90 days will be asked to provide personal information online, as well as the purpose of the trip and place of accommodation.
The new system is expected to be implemented in fiscal year 2028, which starts in April 2028 and runs until May 2029.
The objective of the Japanese authorities is to prevent the entry of “undesirable foreigners” into the country, Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi declared on Friday, in her first speech to parliament after the recent electoral victory.
Takaichi justified the measure, called “JESTA”, as a way of filtering foreigners entering the country, which is experiencing an increase in tourism, and “facilitating the entry of visitors who do not represent a problem”.
In her speech, the first woman to lead the Asian nation also outlined other priorities for future policies towards foreigners, such as reviewing the rules governing land purchases.
The Conservative Government had already proposed a package of measures at the end of January to tighten immigration laws, including stricter requirements for obtaining Japanese citizenship. “We must take into account the fact that illegal activities and violations of rules by some foreigners have created a situation in which the population feels uncomfortable and unfairly treated,” Takaichi said on Friday.
In addition to receiving a record number of 42.6 million tourists in 2025, Japan had almost four million foreign residents.
The largest foreign community came from China, while Brazilians represented the sixth largest.
Sectors of Japanese society criticized what they consider to be excessive permissiveness on the part of the authorities, which translated into electoral gains for openly xenophobic parties.
The February 8 elections saw the right-wing anti-immigration movement Sanseito increase the number of seats in Japan's lower house of parliament, from two to 15. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-22 23:26:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Vietnam claims to have guaranteed greater access to US technology</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/22/vietname-afirma-ter-garantido-maior-acesso-a-tecnologia-dos-estados-unidos/</link><description>The Government of Vietnam announced that it has received a promise from the US President that Hanoi will soon be removed from the list of countries with restricted access to advanced technologies from the United States (US).

The general secretary of the Communist Party of Vietnam, To Lam, met with Donald Trump for the first time on Friday, after participating in the inaugural session of the American leader's Peace Council in Washington.
“Donald Trump said he will instruct the relevant agencies to soon remove Vietnam from the strategic export control list,” said the Vietnamese Government, on the official website.
The two countries continue to be involved in trade negotiations to finalize an agreement since Donald Trump began a global tariff offensive in April 2025.
On Friday, Donald Trump imposed a new 10% global customs tariff on “all countries”, after the US Supreme Court overturned the duties he had imposed.
Vietnam had the third largest bilateral trade surplus with the United States at the time of Donald Trump's tariff announcements in April, and was the target of one of the highest tariffs.
Something that Hanoi avoided in July by opening the market to North American products, which led the United States to reduce the tariff on Vietnamese products from more than 40% to 20%.
Three of Vietnam's airlines this week announced contracts worth almost $37 billion (€31.4 billion) with North American aerospace companies.
The US Supreme Court's decision concerns the so-called “reciprocal tariffs” applied in April to most countries, as well as other fees enacted based on a 1977 law that allows the President to regulate imports in a situation of national emergency.
The majority of judges considered that the law does not grant the head of the Executive the authority to impose taxes on imports, a competence that the Constitution attributes to parliament.
The case represents the first major dossier on Trump's agenda to reach the Supreme Court directly, which the President helped shape with the appointment of three conservative justices during his first term.
The new 10% rate will be in addition to “normal customs tariffs already in place”, said Donald Trump, suggesting that most trade agreements with the United States remain in place.
Customs duties charged by US authorities and targeted by the Supreme Court's decision exceeded 130 billion dollars in 2025 (around 110 billion euros at current exchange rates), according to analysts.
Since April 2025, the Trump administration has been negotiating agreements with its main trading partners, often reducing tariffs in exchange for increased purchases of North American products and industrial investments in the country. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-22 23:25:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau points to Portugal as a priority to attract more foreign tourists</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/22/macau-aponta-portugal-como-prioridade-para-atrair-mais-turistas-estrangeiros/</link><description>The director of Tourism Services, Helena de Senna Fernandes, said that Portugal will be one of the region's priorities when it comes to attracting more foreign visitors.
In a message broadcast by TDM – Macau Television, regarding the Lunar Year of the Fire Horse, Senna Fernandes pointed out among the targets for this year “European markets, such as Portugal and Spain”. The director also mentioned Southeast Asia, Northeast Asia – a region that includes Japan, Mongolia and the Far East of Russia – and “the emerging tourist markets in the Middle East and Central Asia”.
Senna Fernandes predicted that Macau will receive 41 million visitors in 2026, after reaching close to 40.1 million visitors last year, a new historic high. The majority (90.6%) of tourists came from mainland China or Hong Kong. The territory received 2.76 million visitors from abroad, an increase of 13.7% compared to 2024, but below the target, more than three million, which had been set in August by the leader.
The director of Tourism Services recalled the extension of the 10-day transit visa exemption policy to the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macao Bridge and the neighboring Hengqin special economic zone. The leader promised to “make the most of” this change to create tourist packages, together with Hong Kong and other cities in mainland China, to attract more international visitors.
On January 28, the Macau Tourism Board (DST) announced that the region will once again be present on the Lisbon Tourism Exchange (BTL), between February 25 and March 1, after a year of absence. DST also mentioned that it will participate, in February, in Portugal, in a promotion campaign for travel agencies.
Macau was not present at the previous edition of BTL, which took place between March 12 and 16, 2025, but at the time DST assured, in a written response to Lusa, that Portugal continued to be “a priority market”.</description><pubDate>2026-02-22 23:28:05</pubDate></item><item><title>German Chancellor visits China this week</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/22/chanceler-alemao-visita-a-china-esta-semana/</link><description>The German Chancellor, Friedrich Merz, will carry out a state visit to the People's Republic of China this week and until February 26, the Government announced.
Merz leaves Berlin on Tuesday and arrives in Beijing on Wednesday, being received by the Chinese Prime Minister, Li Qiang, and is also scheduled to meet the President, Xi Jinping, said a spokesperson for the German Government.
The visit will take place at a time when Beijing authorities are striving to present themselves as a reliable partner for Europeans, especially in contrast to the United States.
This is the first visit to the People's Republic of China since Friedrich Merz took office as chancellor in May 2025, and takes place just a few days after the end of the Lunar New Year celebrations.
The German Government spokesperson added that discussions will focus on bilateral relations, as well as issues of economic and security policy, highlighting Berlin's desire to maintain “fair relations” with Beijing in commercial terms.
On Thursday, the German Chancellor will visit the Forbidden City, in Beijing, before a meeting with a delegation from the German automobile group Mercedes-Benz, where new vehicles are expected to be presented.
The official agenda includes a visit to Hangzhou, a city on the east coast of China, as well as two business trips: one to the company Unity, a robotics group, and to the German energy company Siemens Energy.
The two countries have strong trade ties, which are currently strained due to accusations of unfair competition and protectionism leveled at Beijing. Even so, Berlin and Beijing have demonstrated a willingness to overcome differences, particularly in the context of the world order imposed by the current United States Administration.
In mid-February, on the sidelines of the Munich Security Conference, Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi told Merz that he viewed Berlin as a “driving force” in cooperation between the EU and China.
Economically, the relationship between Berlin and Beijing has changed drastically in the last decade, with China going from the best customer of German export industries to the main competitor.
The German economy is experiencing difficulties and Chinese competition is causing concern for some German companies, particularly in the automotive sector.</description><pubDate>2026-02-22 23:26:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Year of the Horse will bring “splendid new successes”, says Sam Hou Fai</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/22/ano-do-cavalo-trara-novos-exitos-esplendidos-diz-sam-hou-fai/</link><description>The Chief Executive is optimistic about the Year of the Horse. In his Chinese New Year message, Sam Hou Fai said he hoped Macau would reach “new horizons of development” and “new splendid successes”.
The Year of the Horse will be good for the Macao SAR, predicted the region's Chief Executive in the usual message left at this time. Sam Hou Fai took the opportunity to wish a good Chinese New Year to everyone who supports the development of Macau.
Sam pointed out that, according to traditional Chinese culture, “the horse symbolizes loyalty, courage, an exploratory spirit and freedom”, “qualities that must be promoted to face the future”. The Chief then asked for “courage and perseverance” to “promote the development of Macau in all aspects in the best possible way”. “We must, with persistence and dedication, continue to adequately carry out work to improve the lives of the population for their well-being”, he highlighted.
The Government leader also took the opportunity to say that he is “convinced that, under the firm leadership of President Xi Jinping and the Central Government, counting on the great country as unwavering support, as long as we have the courage to reform and innovate, better leveraging the institutional advantages of the ‘one country, two systems’ principle, we will certainly be able to achieve success, opening new horizons of development and creating new splendid successes”.
“I wish peace and prosperity to the great country; to the MSAR, I wish stability and prosperous development; to all the residents of Macau, I wish you happiness and good health”, he said, thanking the Public Administration workers and all the workers from the various sectors of society who were on duty during this festive season.
CHIEF EXECUTIVE ON TOUR
Over the last few days, the Chief Executive has traveled to various parts of the city. On the afternoon of February 16th, Sam went to the Tap Seac Chinese New Year flower and product fair, as well as the panchão burning area in Taipa.
At Tap Seac, sellers presented their products and, according to a Government statement, the Chief Executive praised their “creativity and proactive approach to sales”, adding that “the key to business success lies in bold innovation and the importance of advertising and brand building”. The Chief also encouraged young people to “persist in an entrepreneurial spirit, to have the courage to try new things and to contribute to the future of Macau”.
On the morning of the 17th, the Chief Executive visited the Conde de S. Januário Hospital Center, public service entities, Security facilities and the Hengqin Border Post.
Accompanied by the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, and the Director of Health Services, Alvis Lo, the Chief visited the public hospital. Sam went to the Emergency Department and the ambulance area to find out about the service provision situation and operations during the festive period, as well as to greet frontline healthcare professionals.
On that day, the Chief Executive also went to the dispatch center of the Macau Electricity Company substation in Porto Exterior to find out about the electricity supply, and to the headquarters of Transmac to find out about the provision of public transport services and other contingency plans. Later, Sam Hou Fai also visited the Fire Department's Areia Preta Operational Post, the Cybersecurity Incident Alert and Response Center and the Judiciary Police's Anti-Scam Coordination Center. Finally, Sam Hou Fai visited the departures wing and vehicle corridors of the Hengqin Border Post.
On Friday, Sam passed through some community neighborhoods, such as Rua de S. Paulo, Rua da Palha, Rua de S. Domingos, the Largo do Senado area, Mercado da Taipa, Taipa Velha, the village of Coloane and the Lai Chi Vun Shipyards, for example. During this visit, he highlighted that the Macao SAR Government is “committed to ensuring public order, protecting the assets and safety of the population and tourists, and at the same time supporting Small and Medium-Sized Enterprises to raise their quality and modernize themselves, as times change, jointly boosting the stable growth of the community economy”.</description><pubDate>2026-02-22 23:33:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Revision of the road traffic law returns to the Government's legislative agenda</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/22/revisao-da-lei-do-transito-rodoviario-volta-a-agenda-legislativa-do-governo/</link><description>O Governo pretende reiniciar a alteração da lei do trânsito rodoviário, diploma que não chegou a ser aprovado na especialidade na última legislatura. Chiang Ngoc Vai, director dos Serviços para os Assuntos de Tráfego, garante que continuará a auscultar as opiniões do público sobre a revisão da lei, e dará especial atenção às disposições que levantaram maiores polémicas.

The road traffic law, which came into force almost twenty years ago without being able to be changed twice, despite the Executive's proposals, will return to the Government's legislative plan for review. Preparatory work to resume the review of the law is already underway, according to Chiang Ngoc Vai, director of Traffic Affairs Services (DSAT).
The official, speaking to the Chinese channel Radio Macau, assured that the Government will continuously listen and collect the opinions of the public and various sectors, particularly on the “most controversial” provisions of the previous diploma. “We hope to formulate a more rigorous and comprehensive legal system in traffic matters, which takes into account a balance between maintaining order in road traffic and protecting the safety of public road users,” he stated.
Chiang Ngoc Vai, without advancing the legislative calendar for the presentation of the diploma or the expected date for approving the new law, said only that he will resubmit the proposal to the legislative process “at an opportune moment”.
It should be remembered that the road traffic law was subject to a review most recently in 2023, when the Government presented a proposal that intended to “strengthen the fight against infractions that compromise road safety or cause traffic disruption”.
This diploma was approved in general by the Legislative Assembly in April 2024 and was considered within the Permanent Committee, but was never voted on in detail in the plenary, thus remaining in the drawer as it progressed towards the end of the previous legislature.
At the time, this proposed law caused controversy in society since the proponent, in this case the Government, suggested introducing a “points system” applicable to all drivers. Initially with a form of deduction of points, and then it became the recording of accumulation of points, and the Government proposed that infractions be categorized into three levels with the attribution of different points, and each driver started with 0 points and would have their driving license canceled if they reached 18. The points could be eliminated by attending driving courses.
In addition to the points system on the driving license, another proposed change was the increase in fines, especially for misdemeanors of driving under the influence of alcohol and speeding.
The Government, before this proposal, had already presented a diploma amending the road traffic law in 2018, which was withdrawn due to strong criticism even before moving forward to public consultation.

NEW BUS CONTRACTS
 
Regarding bus contracts that will expire at the end of this year, Chiang Ngoc Vai said that the Government has already hired a third professional research entity to carry out a comprehensive assessment of existing public bus services, and then present recommendations for improving the service.
The Executive is also negotiating with the two bus operators, with the expectation of, with the new contracts, adjusting the routes and location of stops. “We will rationally allocate resources based on actual development and demographic changes in each area, to ensure that bus services meet the needs of society,” he assured.
Chiang Ngoc Vai also highlighted that he will study a transfer discount program between buses and the Light Rail, also giving priority to improving connections between bus stops and Light Rail stations.</description><pubDate>2026-02-22 23:30:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Asian Countries Respond to Trump Tariff Repeal and New Global Tariff</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/22/paises-asiaticos-respondem-a-anulacao-das-tarifas-de-trump-e-a-nova-taxa-global/</link><description>Several countries and regions in Asia reacted to the US Supreme Court decision that annulled the tariffs imposed by the President, as well as the new 10% global tax that Donald Trump instituted after the court decision.

Tokyo rules out that the invalidation of the rates will affect previously agreed investments, according to the economic newspaper Nikkei, while Taiwan and Hong Kong predict a “limited” effect of the new global tariff. China has not yet commented.
The reactions come after the United States Supreme Court determined on Friday, by six votes to three, that Donald Trump's government exceeded the powers it invoked to impose a large part of its taxes on its commercial partners.
In response to the resolution, which invalidates the so-called “reciprocal tariffs” and other widespread taxes applied by Trump, with a minimum rate of 10%, the President signed a global tariff of 10% on all countries.
The law that supports this new executive order only allows tariffs to be increased up to 15% and for periods of 150 days, so it is not clear how it will be articulated in the long term, writes the EFE news agency.
Japan indicated that the Supreme Court's decision will not affect the first investments foreseen in the trade agreement reached in July between Tokyo and Washington, which includes commitments valued at around 550 billion dollars (around 466.5 billion euros) and the reduction from 25% to 15% of tariffs on Japanese products, including automobiles.
The information was released by the economic newspaper Nikkei, citing a government source, whose identity was not revealed, adding that the first projects announced this week, valued at 36 billion dollars (around 30.5 billion euros), will be maintained as they are “necessary for Japan's growth and economic security”.
South Korea stated that the trade agreement with Washington, which provides for commitments such as a South Korean investment of 350 billion dollars (around 300 billion euros) and 15% tariffs from Washington, remains intact.
According to Yonhap news agency, South Korean authorities called an emergency meeting to assess the impact of invalidating the tariffs.
The governments of Taiwan and Hong Kong consider that the 10% global tariff announced by Trump will have a “limited impact” on their economies.
The spokesperson for the Taiwanese Executive, Michelle Lee, stated that Taipei, which this month signed a trade agreement with Washington that reduces tariffs for the island from 20% to 15%, will “closely” monitor the evolution of United States tariff policy.
Hong Kong's Treasury and Financial Services Secretary Christopher Hui said the financial center's economic structure, heavily centered on the services sector, significantly reduces its direct exposure to international trade tensions.
Indonesia, which on Thursday signed a trade agreement with the US, indicated that it will hold “new talks” with Washington in light of the “dynamics that are occurring”.
The spokesman for the Ministry of Economic Affairs of Southeast Asia's main economy, Haryo Limanseto, said that the continuity of the pact, which maintains tariffs from Washington to Jakarta at 19%, except for certain tax-exempt textile and agricultural products, including palm oil, “continues to depend on the decision of both parties”.
The agreement also includes purchases of North American products worth US$33 billion by Indonesia and cooperation in critical minerals and rare earths, in a context marked by global efforts to reduce dependence on China in this matter.
Malaysia assured that it “will continue to diversify its trade relations and strengthen regional and multilateral economic cooperation”, despite the decision that invalidates a large part of Trump's tariffs. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-22 23:25:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong demands Japan protect residents after Sapporo attack</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/22/hong-kong-exige-que-japao-proteja-residentes-apos-ataque-em-sapporo/</link><description>The Hong Kong government said it has demanded Tokyo protect residents of the region who visit Japan, after a resident was targeted in an attack in Sapporo.

The Hong Kong executive “expressed concern” to the Japanese consul general in the territory, Jun Miura, and urged Japanese authorities to “guarantee the personal safety” of Hong Kong travelers in Japan.
In a statement released on Thursday night, the territory's authorities said they are collaborating with Beijing's diplomatic representation in Hong Kong and the Chinese consulate in Sapporo, in northern Japan.
The objective, explained the Hong Kong Government, is to “understand the situation, follow up on the case and provide practical assistance in accordance with the wishes” of the resident targeted by the attack.
The Chinese consulate in Sapporo said the man was hit in the head with a beer bottle at a restaurant in the early hours of Wednesday, and that Japanese police had already detained a suspect.
China's diplomatic representation once again recommended that tourists not travel to Japan, because “the trend of attacks in Japan against Chinese citizens has been increasing”.
However, Hong Kong tour operators told the South China Morning Post that the attack was likely an isolated incident that would not affect residents' interest in visiting Japan.
In November, mainland China, Hong Kong and Macau advised against travel to Japan and urged residents and tourists in the country to be cautious. The warnings came after Japan's new prime minister, Sanae Takaichi, suggested that the country could intervene militarily in the event of an attack on Taiwan. The statements immediately provoked the anger of China, which retaliated by tightening controls on trade with Japan and carrying out joint aerial exercises with Russia.
Sanae Takaichi, the first woman to lead the Government of Japan, accused China of wanting to “change the status quo by force or coercion” in the maritime areas over which it disputes sovereignty with its neighbors.
Beijing “is intensifying its attempts to unilaterally change the status quo through force or coercion in the East China Sea and the South China Sea, while at the same time expanding and strengthening its military activities in the areas surrounding our country”, said the ultraconservative leader, in parliament. "Our government's consistent policy is to promote a mutually beneficial relationship with China, based on shared strategic interests, and build a constructive and stable relationship," Takaichi said. "Given China's important role as a neighbor and the many outstanding issues and challenges, we will continue our dialogue and respond calmly and thoughtfully in accordance with our national interests," he added. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-02-22 23:27:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau received more than 1.5 million visitors last week</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/22/macau-recebeu-mais-de-15-milhoes-de-visitantes-na-ultima-semana/</link><description>Over the last nine days, the number of visitors to Macau was more than 1.5 million. In other words, per day, around 170 thousand tourists visited the region, on average. These numbers slightly exceed the Government's forecasts. During this period of Chinese New Year, the daily visitor record was broken.

Macau received, between February 14th and 5pm yesterday, more than 1.5 million visitors, totaling a daily average of around 170 thousand visitors. Yesterday alone, until 5pm, almost 163 thousand visitors entered.
According to preliminary data from the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP), the day with the most visitors was Thursday, February 19th, with close to 228 thousand entries, thus setting a new historic high. The previous daily record was 221,968, recorded in May's Golden Week last year.
This Chinese New Year's figures slightly exceed the authorities' forecasts. The Directorate of Tourism Services (DST) expected that, in the nine days between 15 and 23 February, between 1.4 and 1.5 million visitors would enter Macau, that is, between 158 thousand and 175 thousand per day, on average. In the same period last year, the daily average number of tourists was 163 thousand. The CPSP had predicted an average of 670,000 daily border crossings, and more than six million entries and exits during the Lunar New Year period, between 15 and 23 February.
CPSP data also shows that, as usual, the Portas do Cerco border post is preferred by visitors. Around 40% of all visitors choose to enter or leave Macau through Portas do Cerco. The second most used border post is the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge, followed by Hengqin.
Despite the number of visitors, authorities indicated that the pedestrian zones installed in some of the city's main tourist attractions have worked well. “The operation of the pedestrian zones during the Chinese New Year installed in the old quarter of Taipa and Rua de Nossa Senhora do Amparo de Macau, between the 17th and 22nd of February, has been running smoothly and in good order”, indicates a statement released by the Government, adding that, from this year onwards, in addition to the Chinese New Year holidays, pedestrian zones in the old quarter of Macau will be implemented on a regular basis, also on the 1st of May and National Day holidays. Taipa and Rua de Nossa Senhora do Amparo.
DST emphasizes that it informed travel agencies in advance so that they are aware of changes to traffic and the places where tourists buses stop and pick up and drop off in pedestrian areas. In parallel, DST provides tourist information posts during the operation of the pedestrian zones to provide visitors with information about the characteristic activities, tourism and traffic in the areas.
For its part, the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) supervises the implementation of changes to bus routes and coordinates with bus companies to provide information on changes to bus routes in the areas, the placement of staff to guide passengers and the timely increase in the frequency of routes.
The CPSP mobilized more police officers to carry out patrols within and around the areas, ensuring the orderly flow of people and vehicles, directing traffic, directing the orderly and safe movement of pedestrians and drivers, as well as providing immediate support in resolving various emergency situations that occurred suddenly in the areas and surrounding areas.</description><pubDate>2026-02-22 23:35:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Lusophone community mobilizes in solidarity campaign to support flood victims in Portugal</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/02/22/comunidade-lusofona-mobiliza-se-em-campanha-de-solidariedade-para-apoiar-vitimas-das-cheias-em-portugal/</link><description>The storm passed, left a trail of destruction and solidarity crossed continents. In Macau, six Portuguese entities came together to launch a fundraising campaign in support of the victims of the floods that devastated Portugal. The tragedy, caused by the Kristin, Leonardo and Marta depressions, left 18 people dead and hundreds of people homeless, with particular incidence in the Centre, Lisbon and Vale do Tejo and Alentejo regions, where the water is only now beginning to recede, revealing the extent of the damage.

Faced with the serious situation that hit Portugal, where strong storms and floods caused widespread destruction, resulting in the loss of 18 human lives, homes, goods and livelihoods of hundreds of families, a group of institutions representing the Portuguese-speaking community in Macau and the Greater Bay Area decided to join forces to launch a public call for mobilization. In a joint statement issued on February 20th, the signatory entities invoked the “best tradition of fraternity and solidarity that unites Portuguese-speaking peoples” to join forces in raising and channeling donations that can mitigate the suffering of the affected populations.
The campaign, entitled “Macau in Solidarity”, is promoted by the Council of Portuguese Communities of the China Circle, the Casa de Portugal in Macau, the Club Lusitano of Hong Kong, the Lusophone Scout Group of Macau and has the institutional support of the Consulate General of Portugal in Macau and the participation of Banco Nacional Ultramarino (BNU). Monetary donations can be made through two solidarity bank accounts, opened for this purpose at BNU in Macau, in patacas (MOP account 9021818628) or in Hong Kong dollars (HKD account 9021818645), the holder being the “Support Fund for Flood Victims in Portugal”. According to the released note, the funds will subsequently be redirected, by agreement between the promoting institutions, to one or more Portuguese social solidarity institutions operating on the ground, which will be designated at an opportune moment, ensuring transparency and traceability of the entire process.
In addition to this joint campaign, other solidarity initiatives have emerged from Macau. On February 10, the Catholic organization Cáritas Macau launched a three-month fundraising campaign to help those affected by the storms in the Iberian Peninsula. The general secretary of Cáritas Macau, Paul Pun, justified the initiative by the “special connection” between Portugal and the Chinese region, recalling that “Macau residents include Portuguese citizens” and that this proximity naturally generates an impulse of solidarity. The União das Misericórdias Portuguesas revealed that it had received a donation worth 300 thousand euros from Misericórdia de Macau to support its counterparts who suffered significant damage caused by the Kristin depression.
The tragedy that motivated these campaigns had an extensive impact on Portugal. Eighteen people died following the passage of depressions Kristin, Leonardo and Marta, which also caused many hundreds of injuries and displacement. The total or partial destruction of houses, businesses and equipment, the fall of trees and structures, the closure of roads, schools and transport services, and the cut of energy, water and communications, floods and floods are the main material consequences of the storm, which affected the Central, Lisbon and Tagus Valley and Alentejo regions with particular severity.
The process of returning to normality has been gradual. The Santarém District Civil Protection Commission lowered the Special Emergency Plan for Floods in the Tagus Basin to blue level on February 21st, due to the decrease in flows released by the dams and the drop in the river's hydrometric height. The sub-regional commander of civil protection for Médio Tejo, David Lobato, explained that this level means that monitoring and warnings to the population will now be carried out within 24-hour periods. Although the river has returned to its normal bed in the Middle Tagus, some flooded areas remain in Lezíria and constraints remain on more than a hundred roads distributed across almost all 21 municipalities in the district of Santarém, including submergences, road collapses and slope collapses.
In parallel with recovery efforts, new issues are emerging in the public debate on resource and disaster management. The environmental association Quercus defended that companies that produce energy in dams should contribute to the disaster support fund announced by the Portuguese Government with a percentage of the extraordinary profits resulting from the water accumulation provided by intense rains.
Meanwhile, the conclusion of the independent expert opinion ordered by the Portalegre Chamber to investigate the causes of the flood of water, mud and stones that occurred on February 5th in that city, originating from the São Mamede mountain range, was announced. The study, developed by experts in hydrology and agricultural engineering, concluded that the situation had a “natural cause”, resulting from the saturation of the soil, caused by precipitation and runoff. The event caused damage to at least 10 houses, 52 cars and left three people homeless.</description><pubDate>2026-02-22 23:30:18</pubDate></item></channel></rss>