<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/29/china-asean-e-estados-do-golfo-prometem-solidariedade-economica-em-cimeira-tripartida/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Voices, Transport and Nature: USJ study identified 147 Sound categories in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/29/vozes-transportes-e-natureza-estudo-da-usj-identificou-147-categorias-de-som-em-macau/</link><description>The immersive sound and the sound landscape were the topics under one of the morning encounters organized by the France Macau Chamber of Commerce (FMCC). The guest speaker, Gérald Estadieu, a professor at the University of São José (USJ), presented the pioneering experiences that have already been implemented in Macao and unveiled some of the plans for the future, which may even include sound therapies in medical treatments.
 
 
Sound is one of the five senses fundamental to human experience, allowing a deeper understanding of the sensory and even artistic world that surrounds us. But what will be the importance of sound in the sector of technological innovation? This question was the starting point for the May session of lectures and breakfasts organized monthly by the France Macao Chamber of Commerce (FMCC), at the Sofitel Hotel, under the theme “Immersive Sound Landscapes: redefining experiences through space audio”. This time, the guest speaker was Gérald Estadieu, assistant professor at the Faculty of Arts and Humanities of the University of São José (USJ), whose research work focuses on the sound landscape and space audio.
Gérald Estadieu began by contextualizing the specificities of hearing and the way the mere action of listening can stimulate creativity. It is important to highlight, at this point, that the types of sounds recorded by the human ear are multiple and varied, highlighting three for their constant presence in everyday life: voice, music and environmental noise. While vision results from a process of brain interpretation, sound has a more specific “physicality” when transporting “air molecules” from the source of the sound to the ear of the receiver. Vision limitations are also evident: with open eyes, we can glimpse only what is before us; With eyes closed, the ability to see temporarily disappears. Hearing, in turn, allows sound processing in a 360 degree range, in permanent warning until we sleep.
This is where the concept of spatial audio interconnects with technology, as the speaker clarified. Mobile altifalals allow us to listen to music or dialogue, but not in the immersive and three-dimensional way we are used to. "Only with headphones can we have the total experience of sound. We need to hear the way our ears were made to listen, and this is what the industry is trying to implement and make it accessible to everyone." Some mobile phones, overlooked those with the latest operating systems, are already part of space sound formats that provide the user with the feeling that the audio of series, movies or music is being emitted from various directions.
"Sound has a creative power that I consider much more powerful than images, which greatly limit our imagination," said the university professor. It was based on this idea that the Soundscape (or sound landscape) project came to Estadieu in 2020 at USJ, with funding from the Fund for the Development of Science and Technology (FDCT). In the early months of Covid-19 pandemic, a team of researchers proposed to draw the Macao's sound landscape-that is, the different sounds that make up a particular environment.
"We have established a microphone and a recorder at various points of Macao over several days. We tried to collect sounds from different environments, including forest areas," Estadieu explained, noting that the most hard work came later: "We heard the recordings and manually identified all the sounds we recognized." In total, there were 147 identified sound categories, which ranged from human voices and music to the city of city transport and construction.
This was followed by the creative part of the project, in which the collected audios were presented in exhibitions in South Korea, Vietnam and Thailand before an audience that could only use the meaning of hearing to decipher the meaning of this sound landscape. "It was very interesting to note that some people interpreted the sounds totally differently, depending on their cultural context. For example, some people have associated the sound notices of public bus with 7-Eleven stores in China, because they are similar."
To this initial study, there were other sound experiences in casinos with ‘Ambisonic’ spatialization systems, a recreation of the 1874 “Great Typhoon” at a university in Vietname and a piece of puppet theater with immersive sound at the Caixa Preta Theater of the Macao Cultural Center. More recently, the USJ Library inaugurated the exhibition “The 1568 Bishop's Bible”, where the public can return to 16th century England and listen to the narration of archaic English texts until June 20.
The investigator's future plans now undergo an even more deepened investigation from the Macao region, the bubbling of recurring and idiosyncratic sounds that allow residents to recognize the even -eyed streets. "I don't know people's sound yet to play Mahjong or the Sound Landscape around the Sun, for example. And why do you mind gathering these sounds? It matters because it is the real experience we have in everyday life. We want to recreate the sound as if our brain is hearing the normal experience and not mere reproduction."
At the end of the presentation, a member of the audience recalled that Macau is - increasingly - one of the main medical tourism destinations in Asia, launching a question about the possible beneficial role of sound in medical treatments conducted in the region. Although stressing not being “expert” in the area, Estadieu admitted that this has been a frequently debated topic among USJ psychology and neuroscience professionals.
“A few years ago, sound waves were used to erase fireworks - it was a case that I gave as an example in my classes, to show how the sound is something physical; it is the movement of the air molecules around us. In the same way, we can research the effect of different sound frequencies such as meditation or Tibetan cups… We have not had the opportunity to research and verify if, in fact, there can be some cure process through these sounds, but we are open to these sounds, but we are open to these sounds, but we are open This hypothesis, ”he said.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 05:53:56</pubDate></item><item><title>European companies reduce investments in China in the face of economic slowdown</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/29/empresas-europeias-reduzem-investimentos-na-china-face-a-abrandamento-economico/</link><description>European companies are reducing investments in China due to the slowdown of the economy and competition, indicate the results of an inquiry carried out by the European Union Chamber of Commerce in China.
 
 
European companies are cutting costs and reducing investment plans in China as the economy slows down and fierce competition drops prices, according to an annual survey released yesterday.
"Many companies continue to reassess their involvement with the Chinese market, with a large number to cut costs, reduce expansion plans, transfer investments to other regions and take steps to isolate their supply chains in China and the rest of the world," reads the results of the European Union Trade Chamber in China.
"Confronted with a series of challenges-including the persistence of regulatory barriers and market access, increased geopolitical tensions, price deflation, low internal consumption and margin reduction-the optimism of chamber members in relation to short and medium term perspectives is now historically low level," he added.
The challenges faced by European companies reflect broader problems of the world's second largest economy, affected by a prolonged real estate crisis, which has contained consumer spending. Beijing also faces protectionist measures from the United States and Europe, in response to China's persistent commercial surpluses.
"The scenario has deteriorated in many key indicators," the European Union Chamber of Commerce in China said, in the introduction of its business confidence survey 2025.
The same forces that are boosting Chinese exports are penalizing business in the domestic market. Chinese companies, often supported by state subsidies, have intensively invested in specific sectors, such as electric vehicles, leading to the installed capacity of factories to overcome demand widely.
This excess of capacity has given rise to fierce price wars, which reduced profits and led companies to drain the excess production abroad, raising accusations of 'dumping' - a sale below production cost.
In Europe, this situation has generated fears that Chinese imports could harm local industries and their workers. Last year, the European Union has increased customs rates on electric vehicles from China, claiming that the country unfairly subsidized the sector.
"I think there is a clear perception that the benefits of bilateral trade and investment relationships are not being distributed equitably," said the EU Mayor in China, Jens Eskelund, during the presentation of the survey.
Eskelund greeted China's efforts to stimulate consumption, but argued that the government should also take steps to ensure that the growth of supply does not exceed demand.
Inquiry results indicate that the downward pressure on profits has increased over the past year and that the drop in business confidence has not yet reached its lowest point, he said.
About 500 associated companies responded to the inquiry between mid -January and mid -February.
"It's very difficult for everyone at this time, in a decline margin environment," he added.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 05:49:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Hotels won more than 4,000 workers in the first quarter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/29/hoteis-ganharam-mais-de-4-000-trabalhadores-no-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>The number of workers in the hotel industry at the end of the first quarter of this year was 60,482, which reflects an increase of more than 4,000 compared to the end of the homologous quarter of 2024.
Data regarding labor and remuneration needs, released yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), also show that at the end of the first quarter, 1,493 elderly services and 1,088 workers in the production and distribution of electricity, gas and water, which reflects an increase of 68 and 11, respectively.
On the contrary, the number of full -time workers of the restaurants and the like was 23,381 and the transformative industries of 7,402, ie less 624 and 437, respectively.
DSEC also points out that in March this year, the average remuneration of full -time workers in the transforming industries was 12,690 patacas, the elderly services of 17,050 patacas and the production and distribution of electricity, gas and water 31.140 patacas. These three areas recorded slight increases. However, the average remuneration of full -time workers in the branches of hotels (20,090 patacas) and restaurants (10,540 patacas) registered decreases of 1.9% and 0.7%, respectively.
At the end of the quarter-on-analysis the vacancies of the hotel branch (1.4%) and that of restaurants and the like (4.6%) lowered 1.1 and 1.4 percentage points, respectively, compared to the end of the identical quarter of 2024, as the vacancies of these branches were filled and the search for labor gradually again stabilized.
The number of hotels and the restaurants of restaurants and the like was 839 and 1,124, respectively. In addition, the turnover rate of hotel workers (3%) and restaurants (4.8%) also lowered 0.3 and 0.6 percentage points, respectively, “this reflects that the loss of human resources in these branches has slightly improved,” says DSEC.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 05:49:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Crime descended, but cases related to game fired</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/29/criminalidade-desceu-mas-casos-relacionados-com-jogo-dispararam/</link><description>Crime in Macao during the first quarter of this year dropped 7.3% in annual terms, which is the first drop since 2023. However, game -related crimes rose significantly, 61.5%, which was due to increased illicit exchange rate cases, said Secretary for Security, Wong Sio Chak. The statistics also highlighted the low level of incidence of violent crimes, drugs and theft, but also light growth of cases of sexual abuse of children and domestic violence.
 
 
Wong Sio Chak, Secretary for Security, presented yesterday the crime statistics between January and March this year, according to which the number of cases registered an annual decrease of 7.3%, with a total of 3,289 criminal inquiries.
"Crimes of severe violence register a continuous reduction, the criminal situation in general is under control and the social order remains stable and good," Wong Sio Chak said at a press conference. According to the authorities, Macau reported 56 cases of violent crime between January and March, minus 21 cases, ie 27.3%, compared to the same period last year.
The crime of kidnapping had a 42.9% break in the first three months, while the number of theft fell 16.7% and a set fire reduced 23.1%. Ten cases of violation were also registered, a decrease of four cases compared to the homologous period of 2024. “Half of the victims were residents of the interior of China, the cases occurred in hotel rooms and in some cases there were monetary conflicts between the victims and the suspects, not to dismiss the case that the cases occurred in a context of sexual transactions,” said the executive, who added that, in the executive, who added that in the executive, which added that Cases where the victims were residents, most occurred after alcohol consumption in bars when the victims "was in a state of deep drunkenness."
Cases of sexual abuse of children, however, increased and went from four cases to five, involving "mainly the practice of voluntary acts between people of the same age and the diffusion of photographs and pornographic images."
Youth delinquency witnessed a 6.1% decrease in the first quarter, with the record of 31 cases, while in the first three months of last year were 33, of which 26 have not yet been sent to the prosecutor and five cases are being dealt with by the judicial body. Less cases, but younger ones were involved. In the 31 cases were involved 54 young people, which, compared to the same period of 2024, reflects an increase of eight young people, ie 17.4%.
 
Condemnations for domestic violence remain low
 
Regarding domestic violence, 26 suspected cases were recorded in the first quarter, two more than at the same time last year. According to Wong Sio Chak, until the 12th of this month, among the 26 cases only four were classified as crimes of domestic violence. That is, the remaining 12 cases were considered as offenses to physical integrity, two such as other crimes and eight cases remain in the investigation phase.
Wong Sio Chak, during the previous debate on the lines of government action, had denied the existence of “insufficiencies” in the execution of the Domestic Violence Prevention and Fighting Law, despite the low accusation rate and condemnation of cases. In 2024, there were 133 cases on domestic violence and only 12 cases were considered corresponding to that crime.
The crime report also made known the decrease in drug-related crimes from 15 to 12 cases in the first three months, "there is a trend of low occurrence rate," he said.
In this context, the secretary stressed that the executive board has already completed the discussion about the legislative project, which provides to add to the table attached to Law 20 new substances regulated by the United Nations, as well as four other types of substances that are not yet subject to control, including ethomyidate, ie “spatial oil”. Wong Sio Chak expects the diploma to be analyzed and considered in June by the Legislative Assembly.
 
Illegal exchange rate increased gambling crimes
 
Police authorities settled in the first quarter 567 inquiries for game -related crimes, which represents an increase of 216 cases, or 61.5%, compared to the same period last year. Regarding this sharp rise, explained Wong Sio Chak, the main cause will have to see the entry into force of the illicit game crimes in October last year, which established the criminalization of illicit exchange exploration for game.
"In the first quarter of this year, police opened 132 illicit exchange exploration processes, occupying more than 60% of the number of increase in cases related to the game, which is the main reason for the increase," he said.
The secretary stressed that the authorities of Guangdong and Macau dismantled several criminal networks that were involved in several cases related to the game, thus resulting in the increase in cases, he said.
"The number of tourists who enter Macao increased by 11.1% over last year's same period, which brings to the most uncertain society that affect security," warned Wong Sio Chak.
 
Diminishing
 
On the other hand, as the Judiciary Police had advanced on Tuesday, the crimes of slopping and computer crimes in Macao began to record a decrease trend. The data updated yesterday by the Secretary for Security show a 15% decrease in fraud in general. In this case, 74 cases of telephone burla were reported, less 22 cases regarding the identical period of last year, of which about 40% of cases respect the “simulation of public service personnel”, and 20% were from “guesses who I am”.
Cyber ​​burla has led to 145 cases, ie, a reduction of 47 cases in annual terms, with the burles through online investment, ticket sales and online shopping the most frequent forms of the practice of this type of crimes.
There were also 141 cases of online payment fraud through credit cards, as well as 14 cases of online extortion through nude chat.
 
Less pedestrians cross streets without complying with the rules
 
With regard to road safety, Wong Sio Chak said yesterday that the number of traffic offenses committed by pedestrians had recorded a significant increase, but "the situation has already signaled progressive improvement" due to the "reinforcement of the inspection, dissemination and awareness actions" by police.
The ruler pointed out that, in the first quarter, 2,398 cases of people were illegally crossing the lanes, less 607 cases than in the same year's same year period, which represents a decrease of 20.2%.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 05:55:58</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM and University of Coimbra launch AI laboratory on nutrition</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/29/upm-e-universidade-de-coimbra-lancam-laboratorio-de-ia-sobre-nutricao/</link><description>Macao Polytechnic University (UPM) has announced the creation of a joint laboratory with the University of Coimbra that will use Artificial Intelligence (AI) to study the connection between nutrition and “healthy longevity”. In a statement, the UPM said the laboratory dedicated to the nutraceutical will focus on applying AI in “health care, precision nutrition, chronic diseases prevention and health management”.
The nutraceutical is a combination of nutrition and pharmaceutical and studies the potential positive effects for the health of components present in food. The new laboratory will “make the most of the advantages of the two universities in the areas of Artificial Intelligence, Health Sciences and Nutrition Technology,” said the UPM.
The agreement provides for interdisciplinary investigation with specialists from both universities to transform results into “state -of -the -art technical solutions” and “innovative applications”, he stresses in the statement. The Macao Higher Education Institution also assured that the laboratory will “train high -level talents for the Macao health industry [and] promote technology development through cooperation with industry”. The area of ​​health and well-being was pointed out as one of the four sectors in which the Macao government wants to bet to diversify the economy of the MSAR.
On the other hand, the UPM argued that the creation of the laboratory represents “a new milestone in educational cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”. The new institution will promote “scientific research and innovation in the area of ​​intelligent health in Macau and Portugal and support scientific and technological cooperation between China and Portugal,” he said.
The agreement for the creation of the laboratory was signed in Macao, by UPM Rector Marcus im Sio Kei, and by the Rector of the University of Coimbra, Amílcar Falcão. In June 2024, Falcão told Lusa on a visit to Macau that the Portuguese institution and the Polytechnic had launched a double doctorate in information technologies. The PhD was born in the previous school year and "is starting to give the first results", with 18 students, "divided between Portuguese and Chinese," said the rector of the University of Coimbra.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 05:49:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Consulate starts the month of Portugal with exhibition and display of the documentary “Heritople”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/29/consulado-da-inicio-ao-mes-de-portugal-com-exposicao-e-exibicao-do-documentario-heritople/</link><description>The month of Portugal officially starts today with the exhibition “Portuguese Art - Creative Dialogue”, at Galeria Amagao, following until the last day of June with the full agenda. The Consulate General, in turn, will host two simultaneous activities this weekend, which are part of the June event calendar, the exhibition “Macao Cultural Heritage” and the documentary “Heritople”.
 
 
The Portuguese Consulate-General in Macao and Hong Kong will be the scene of another cultural initiative that anticipates the month of activities to come, with the inauguration of the Macao Cultural Heritage exhibition and the exhibition of the documentary “Heritople”. The event, organized by the International Institute of Macau (IIM), highlights the richness of the historical, cultural and architectural heritage of the territory, valuing mainly preservation. The opening is scheduled for 5 pm on Saturday, at the consulate general headquarters.
The photographic collection, which has been continuously enriched over more than a decade through the “to discovery of Macao and Hengqin” contest, celebrates the 20th anniversary of the Macao Historic Center as a World Heritage Center by UNESCO, in 2005. The 2025 edition of the contest that gives rise to this exhibition is currently open to any photographer who wants to contribute to the historical archive of the region's heritage. The time to deliver photographs for the contest ends on September 26th.
Complementarily in the Consulate General, the documentary “Heritople” will be displayed, a production of the IIM, sponsored by the Macau Foundation and directed by António Sanmarful. The film, produced in three languages, features interviews with local residents, including figures such as IP Tat, President of the TCA Temple, and Jorge Rangel, president of IIM, among others, who share testimonies about the experience of cultural heritage in Macao. This project aims to involve especially young people in understanding the cultural legacy of the territory, promoting a greater connection between communities and local history.
These two events are part of a June cultural program, which celebrates the “June, Portugal Month in the MSAR”, with about 30 activities throughout the month, from art exhibitions and photography, to cinema shows, concerts and gastronomic initiatives.
The celebration of heritage will be one of the highlights of the June calendar, which also includes the inauguration of Portuguese contemporary art exhibitions, such as the exhibition “Portuguese Art - Creativity Dialogue” which opens today at 18:30, between traditional music activities, puppet workshops and book launches that highlight Lusophone culture.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Metro Light Dupidated Ticket Recipes</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/29/metro-ligeiro-duplicou-receitas-de-bilheteira/</link><description>By 2024, the mild meter of Macao obtained box office revenues of 27.7 million patacas, or more than twice the 13.5 million recorded in 2023.
Last year's balance sheet published yesterday in an official bulletin also shows that last year, the light meter provided approximately 129,000 circulation frequencies, with a total of more than 5.37 million passengers, which reveals a growth of 117% over 2023.
Last year, the Metro Ligeiro company employed about 550 workers. The percentage of local workers throughout the operating team exceeded 95%, says the Metro Ligeiro society.
The document, signed by Ho Cheong Kei, chairman of the Board of Directors of the Macao Metro Society, also points out that the opening of the SEAC Line Line of Metro Ligeiro, on November 1, 2024, marks the expansion of the Light Metro service to the Seac Pai Van community, allowing “faster and more efficient displacement of residents of this area and the bar and the bar region and the region offering a new option for transportation to citizens and tourists who move to Seac Pai Van ”. Subsequently, the Hengqin line went into operation on December 2, 2024, “offering Macao residents and tourists a new transport option to access that border post and contributing to a more active macao integration over the perimeter of a large Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau bay”.
During 2024, the company sought to explore alternative recipes for ticket sales, including revenue sources not coming from the sale of developed tickets, such as the lease of spaces for the placement of telecommunications service equipment, banking services and automatic sales machines, charging tariffs for the use of parking parks and rental carriages of the light meters for the light meters for Filming, marks the report.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 05:49:59</pubDate></item><item><title>The "very own" satire of the Dóci Papiaçám returns to Macau on Friday</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/29/a-satira-muito-propria-dos-doci-papiacam-regressa-a-macau-na-sexta-feira/</link><description>The Dóci Papiaçá di Macau are back with the show “Cuza is Renenia?” (“What is going on?”), A satirical exploitation of the relations between Macao, the Great Bay and the Lusophone world. In conversation with the final point, director Miguel de Senna Fernandes reveals what the public can expect from the 31st presentation of the group, more centered on the plot and with less emphasis on the musical component, and is said to be "carefree" regarding the request of the Cultual Institute to read the script in advance: "So far we have not received any note."
 
 
The Dóci Papiaçá Di Macau will return to the stage of the Great Auditorium of the Macao Cultural Center on May 30 and 31, Friday and Saturday, with the play “Cuza Tá Reni?” (or “what's going on?” In the Portuguese translation). It is the 31st time that the group of amateur actors perform before Macao, as highlighted by Miguel de Senna Fernandes in a humorous tone: "The theater in Patuá is part of the intangible cultural heritage of the People's Republic of China, so it is now an obligation to have to put up with another year."
The 2025 production is in a center of explanation, where a new leader has just arrived from the great bay with “big dreams and great ambitions”. The new scenario was chosen by the almost ubiquitous character of these institutions in the region, attended by students of all socioeconomic levels. The chosen scenario may seem simple, but it does not limit creativity and the scathing satire to which the Dóci shows have used the audience: “Let's address various issues about the great bay and Lusophony and play a little around these themes,” reconciling social comment and humor to an artistic show that includes even a musical component.
“There is still this musical side, yes, but this time with less weight,” clarifies Senna Fernandes. "When there is a lot to say, there is not so much room for music. This year we have another dynamic, another plot, and it was not possible to work this aspect the way I would like." Still, the play will feature at least one song interpreted by the children of the cast, composed and produced by the director himself. The humorous 'sketches', another characteristic element of the Dóci shows, will remain present in the same format. "Videos will be displayed before and after the break. Many times, right after the piece, we also present anything. It's a very own way to present the show, which may not be usual in Portugal…”
Despite cultural and artistic differences like this, the plans to bring the theater in Patuá to the European continent continue to be focused on the group's objectives for next year. "It would have to be a special piece, given that the public in Portugal does not understand Patuá. We also thought about taking the theater to the continent, but there too Patuá is not spoken ... There are several points to take into account before taking the show to other places. What matters now, is that the audience in Macau likes this new piece that goes to the scene."
In Macao, moreover, the Doric dispenses with presentations. Senna Fernandes stresses that, besides being the only artistic group “that makes social satire about what is happening in Macao”, the mixture of Patuá, Chinese and Portuguese attracts a varied audience of different nationalities, cultures and maternal languages, reflecting the diversity present in the backstage themselves. In total, there are “about 40 or 50 people” to contribute to the annual presentations, including actors and technical personnel.
Like what happened last year, the Cultural Institute (IC) again asked to analyze the script of the play before the official presentation at the Arts Festival. Miguel de Senna Fernandes devalues: "It is not so much to evaluate the script and to classify it, as there is a Show Classification Committee. We have naturally delivered the script, for the sake of compliance with the law, and so far we have not received any note." The director highlights, in conclusion, that the satirical nature of the show is incompatible with any attempts to censor. "The cultural institute itself, when it makes the theater publicity, expressly says that it is satirical and a way to make comedy based on everyday situations. Therefore, in this regard, I am not concerned."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Moody’s keeps sins with long -term credit notation “AA3”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/29/moodys-mantem-raem-com-notacao-de-credito-de-longo-prazo-aa3/</link><description>International Financial Notation Agency Moody's has decided to maintain MSAR long -term credit notation at AA3 level. On the basis of the decision was the “stable situation of public finances” in the region as well as external payments. In a statement, Macau's monetary authority says that "despite complex challenges," the region's economy has shown a "solid recovery trend."
 
 
International Financial Notation Agency Moody's has decided to maintain long -term credit notation at AA3 level assigned to the MSAR. This level is part of the fourth higher level and means that "the risk of credit default is extremely low."
Moody’s justifies the maintenance of MSAR long -term credit notation level with the “stable situation of public finances” and “external payments of MSAR”. "In addition, the absence of charges with debt by the Government of MSAR continues to confer a strong ability to resistance to potential external shocks," says the monetary authority of Macao (AMCM), citing the report of the international agency.
"Despite the complex challenges and multiple uncertainties that the global economy currently faces, the MSAR economy has shown a solid recovery trend," AMCM says in the press release, adding that in the first quarter of this year, the dimension of the local economy reached 85.2% of the level recorded in the same period of 2019.
In addition, local authorities say, "with the support of the central government, the Government of MSAR is orderly to promote the development of the proper diversification of the economy and regional cooperation, further reinforcing the sustainability of MSAR economic growth."
Still, the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) has recently confirmed a 1.3% drop in Macao's economy in the first quarter of this year. The retreat, according to the authorities, was due to the “change in the consumption pattern of visitors”.
At the end of April, the International Monetary Fund (IMF) has half reduced forecasts for Macao's growth for this year, warning of a global economic growth.
On the other hand, the government has been shown little optimistic about this year's public revenues. The Chief Executive has already warned that the MSar will face many economic challenges this year and the Secretary for Economics and Finance said that “this year's financial income may not be as optimistic as expected,” there is a need to “seriously study the future economic situation” and “persist in the management of financial resources with caution” based on the principle of maintenance of expenses within revenue limits.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 05:52:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Wong Sio Chak denies that police pressure to cancel demonstrations</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/29/wong-sio-chak-nega-que-policia-faca-pressao-para-que-se-cancelem-manifestacoes/</link><description>The Secretary for Security stated that the right to demonstration and the meeting of residents “is guaranteed”, but argued that protests “cannot have an impact on the public interest” or national security. Wong Sio Chak has assured police never pressure to cancel protests scheduled in Macao. As for the detention of two journalists last month, the ruler assured that the authorities acted "according to the law."
 
Police authorities “never pressured” associations to cancel demonstrations and have only had “normal negotiations” with them, said Wong Sio Chak, secretary for safety, in response to the cancellation of this year's labor on the day of the worker, as well as the fact that no demonstrations in Macao has not been organized since 2020.
"The right of meeting and manifestation is a legitimate civic right that must be protected but should not endanger the public interest," he said. The official assured that citizens are entitled to manifestation, however, the organization must take into account national security, public security and social order.
"This has to do with the general interest and the interest of the state. We cannot, due to a person's interest, damage the general public interest," he said.
At the Crime Balance Press Conference, Wong Sio Chak, admitted to receiving this year a prior notice for demonstration on May 1, but stressed that the police "communicated normal" with the prosecutor.
It is recalled that the promoting association of the march, power of the people, denounced to have suffered pressures, so he gave up “on his own initiative” of the initiative. The group said several details were required on the intentions of the march, and was warned by police about the consequences of a possible violation of the National Security Law.
"We had a negotiation of public order, as earlier, because a demonstration has to occupy a public space and can also have many people participating," said the secretary. Wong Sio Chak pointed out that the social order's concern about the organization of demonstrations is universal, giving the example of a case in Spain, where "the police banned a demonstration involving two religious groups that could lead to a conflict and disorder," whose decision "was also confirmed by justice."
 
Journalists are no exception to the law
 
Em relação à detenção de jornalistas durante uma cobertura noticiosa que aconteceu no mês passado, Wong Sio Chak veio justificar que o incidente está a cumprir a lei, uma vez que a polícia “exerceu a função de acordo com a lei” e o seu trabalho “é fiscalizado pelo órgão judicial”.
Wong Sio Chak, in this sense, indicated that journalists “are no exception” to the duty to comply with the law. "Everyone has a duty to comply with the law, no person may be above the law for their profession. All professions are subject to comply with the law," he said.
It is recalled that two journalists from All About Macau, online news portal, were arrested on April 17, while trying to enter the Legislative Assembly hall to attend the presentation of the political program in the area of ​​Administration and Justice to 2025. Wong Sio Chak refused to make more comments on the case, which the situation is now being investigated by the prosecutor.
 
Support to the driver who assaulted the police “may be a crime”
 
Wong Sio Chak also spoke about the case where a driver will have attacked a police officer with a metal bar, condemning behavior as "misconduct" and a "very serious case." The secretary warned that comments that are recently on social networks supporting the driver may constitute a crime.
"To express support for aggressors, crimes, it is a crime. [This act] is inappropriate," said the secretary, recalling an article in the Penal Code on the public apology of a crime.
The secretary stressed that “there was no problem” with how the police officer applied the law in this case. "All citizens must cooperate with the police. If the police have violated the law during law enforcement, the public may file a complaint, but cannot retaliate against the police regarding their personal security," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 05:54:57</pubDate></item><item><title>China, Asean and Gulf States promise economic solidarity in tripartite summit</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/05/29/china-asean-e-estados-do-golfo-prometem-solidariedade-economica-em-cimeira-tripartida/</link><description>In the context of the trade war launched by Washington, China, Southeast Asia countries and six Gulf states promised to promote narrower cooperation, with a strong emphasis on economic integration and energy collaboration.
 
 
 
China, Southeast Asian countries and six Gulf states pledged to promote narrow cooperation yesterday, with a strong emphasis on economic integration and energy collaboration, in a context of the trade war launched by Washington.
In a joint statement, the leaders of the Southeast Asian Nations Association (Asean), the Gulf Cooperation Council (CCG) and China reaffirmed their commitment to a multilateral commercial system based on rules and economic globalization, manifesting simultaneously “serious concerns” with the situation in Gaza.
Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang considered the tripartite summit, which took place in Kuala Lumpur, “an innovative initiative” in transregional cooperation, in an international “volatile” and weak global growth.
Malaysian Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim praised the joint statement issued at the end of the meeting, considering it “detailed and elaborate” and a strong message of solidarity and trilateral cooperation.
Based on an Asean summit with the CCG in 2023, the meeting was seen as an effort to diversify commercial bonds and counteract the tariffs launched by US President Donald Trump.
The declaration of 4,200 words did not directly mention the United States, nor touched sensitive issues such as territorial disputes in the Southern Sea of ​​China or the deepening of the crisis in Myanmar (former Burma).
Malaysia is Asean's current rotary president, which also includes Brunei, Cambodia, Indonesia, Laos, Myanmar, the Philippines, Singapore, Thailand and Vietnam. The CCG includes the Barorian oil producing nations, Kuwait, Saudi Arabia, Oman, Qatar and United Arab Emirates.
In their joint statement, the parties recognized the “fundamental role of China in the promotion of peace, stability, prosperity and sustainable development at regional and world level”, as well as the centrality of ASEAN in regional affairs and the “central role” of the CCG in the Middle East.
Highlighting mutual respect, international law, multilateralism, and its common commitment to regional stability, economic integration and sustainable development, the declaration outlined a broad trilateral cooperation framework, in close consonance with the Chinese track and route initiative and its impulse to expand world economic ties.
The parties said they have recognized the need to reinforce trust in a rules -based multilateral commercial system, with the World Trade Organization at its core, and reaffirmed its determination to make economic globalization more open, inclusive, balanced and beneficial to their peoples and future generations.
With regard to the Middle East, the leaders of China, the CCG and the Asean expressed "serious concerns" and condemned all attacks against civilians, simultaneously appealing to a lasting ceasefire in Gaza and the "most effective and affordable distribution of humanitarian aid."
The support for the implementation of the “two -state solution” was also reiterated, recognizing the international mediation efforts developed by China, Qatar and Saudi Arabia.
Participants also pledged to seek narrow cooperation to prevent and combat transnational crime, cybercriminality, terrorism and extremism.
In his opening speech by the Trilateral summit on Tuesday, I read Qiang to "firmly take this historical opportunity to enrich trilateral cooperation."
China and Asean are the main trading partners with each other, while the CCG provides more than one third of China's gross oil imports. ASEAN, CCG and China have a joint GDP of almost 25 billion dollars and a market of over 2 billion people.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 05:49:58</pubDate></item></channel></rss>