<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/coreia-do-norte-revela-proxima-etapa-de-programa-nuclear-em-congresso/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Former South Korean first lady sentenced to 20 months in prison for corruption</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/ex-primeira-dama-sul-coreana-condenada-a-20-meses-de-prisao-por-corrupcao/</link><description>South Korean justice sentenced the country's former first lady Kim Keon-hee to 20 months in prison for corruption, following her husband's arrest for acts related to the declaration of martial law in 2024. The prosecution had requested 15 years in prison for Kim for corruption and fraud.

A South Korean court yesterday sentenced the country's former first lady Kim Keon-hee to 20 months in prison for corruption, following her husband's arrest for acts related to the declaration of martial law in 2024. “The defendant is sentenced to one year and eight months in prison” for this first crime, declared Judge Woo In-sung, of the Seoul Central District Court.
Kim Keon-hee was, however, acquitted of charges of stock market manipulation and violating election campaign finance laws. The prosecution had asked for 15 years in prison for Kim for corruption and fraud.
The scandals surrounding Kim, 53, have strongly marked the presidency of her husband, conservative Yoon Suk-yeol, ousted after a brief declaration of martial law at the end of 2024, who is awaiting the conclusion of several trials in prison, one of which could end with a death sentence.
Kim Keon-hee, also detained, was accused of manipulating the stock market, electoral interference, accepting luxurious gifts from the Unification Church, better known as the Moon sect, and around 170,000 euros in bribes from businessmen and politicians.
During the arguments in December, the prosecution stated that Kim “placed himself above the law”, that he committed “abuses of power” and that he had collaborated with the sect, violating “the constitutional principle of the separation of religion and state”.
The former first lady claimed innocence and considered the accusations “profoundly unfair”, although she also apologized for “having caused problems, despite being an unimportant person”. “When I reflect on my role and the responsibilities entrusted to me, it seems obvious to me that I made many mistakes,” he acknowledged at the end of the trial.
Yoon Suk-yeol vetoed three attempts by the South Korean Parliament to open an investigation against his wife, the last of which was in November 2024, a week before declaring martial law.
The epilogue of Kim Keon-hee's trial comes a week after Yoon's former prime minister Han Duck-soo was sentenced to 23 years in prison, eight more than the prosecution requested, for complicity in the martial law case.
Investigations related to Kim also resulted in the arrest of Han Hak-ja, leader of the Unification Church, which claims to have millions of followers around the world and an immense economic empire. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-29 01:16:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Orchestra takes “Pedro and the Wolf” to 13 schools in an educational cycle</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/orquestra-de-macau-leva-pedro-e-o-lobo-a-13-escolas-em-ciclo-educativo/</link><description>The Macau Orchestra concluded the second phase of the educational cycle “Music for the Future – Music on Campus” for the 2025-2026 Season, bringing the symphonic story “Peter and the Wolf” to around 3,000 primary school students. At the same time, the orchestra is preparing for a series of large-scale symphonic and sacred concerts in the first quarter of 2026, including a concert with conductor and violinist Julian Rachlin and a performance of Bach's “Passion According to Saint John” with the Hong Kong Philharmonic Choir.

The educational project “Music for the Future – Music on Campus”, a cultural venture initiated jointly by the Cultural Institute and the Macau Orchestra Society, has just completed its second round of concerts this season. Under the direction of Resident Conductor Tony Cheng-Te Yeh, the Macau Orchestra toured 13 schools between December 2025 and January 2026, presenting the work “Peter and the Wolf”, by Sergei Prokofiev, to a total audience of approximately three thousand primary school students.
The school tour included institutions such as the Luso-Chinese School of Taipa, the Luso-Chinese Secondary School of Luís Gonzaga Gomes, the Colégio Diocesano de São José (No. 1 and No. 2) and the Official Luso-Chinese Primary School “Sir Robert Ho Tung”, among others. The central objective was to “plant musical seeds in the minds of young people”, using a playful and relaxed format that combined an engaging narration of the story with live interpretation by the orchestra.
“Peter and the Wolf”, a children's symphony composed in 1936, serves as an ideal pedagogical tool by associating each character and animal in the story with a specific musical instrument in the orchestra. This feature allows a clear and memorable introduction to the sound and role of instruments such as the oboe, bassoon, horns or violins, facilitating understanding and engagement for young audiences.
The “Music for the Future” cycle is one of the Macau Orchestra’s main educational projects, being designed specifically for different age groups. Through a carefully selected repertoire and adapted orchestral formations, the program promotes direct interaction with students, seeking not only to deepen their musical knowledge, but also to broaden cultural horizons and refine their artistic temperament.
The “Music for the Future – Music on Campus” initiative has been “very well received by teachers and students” over the years, according to the organization. Schools interested in hosting future editions of the cycle can obtain more information and register by contacting the Macau Orchestra by email.
In addition to educational work, the Macau Orchestra's agenda for the first quarter of 2026 includes two notable public concerts. On March 14th, at 8pm, in the Grand Auditorium of the Macau Cultural Center, the orchestra will be led by renowned conductor and violinist Julian Rachlin, who will also take on the role of soloist. The program includes Beethoven's “Coriolanus” Overture, Mozart's Sinfonia Concertante for violin and viola, K. 364, with Sarah McElravy on viola, and Mendelssohn's “Scottish” Symphony No. 3.
Later, on March 28, also at 8pm, the Macau Orchestra joins the Hong Kong Philharmonic Choir for a performance of the “Passion According to Saint John”, BWV 245, by Johann Sebastian Bach, at the Sé Church. This monumental work, which depicts the crucifixion of Christ, is traditionally performed during the Easter period and promises an experience of great spiritual and musical impact, lasting approximately two hours and fifteen minutes.
The Macau Orchestra's 2025-2026 Concert Season is co-organized by the Cultural Institute and the Macau Orchestra Society, with the sponsorship of several entities in the entertainment sector and the support of BOC Macau.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>CCP announces forum in Beijing with Taiwan's largest opposition party</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/pcc-anuncia-forum-em-pequim-com-o-maior-partido-da-oposicao-de-taiwan/</link><description>The Chinese Communist Party (CCP) and the Kuomintang (KMT), the main opposition force in Taiwan, will jointly hold a think tank forum in Beijing on February 3, official sources reported yesterday.

At a press conference, the spokesperson for the Taiwan Affairs Office of the State Council (Chinese Executive), Zhang Han, indicated that the event will be co-sponsored by “research institutes affiliated with both parties”, according to statements published by the official Xinhua news agency.
The vice-president of the KMT, Hsiao Hsu-tsen, also assured yesterday that he will visit Beijing between the 2nd and 4th of February “on the instructions” of the party president, Cheng Li-wen, who took office in November, and defends closer relations between the self-governed island and Beijing.
Hsiao will visit mainland China accompanied by the vice-president of the National Policy Foundation – the KMT's think tank –, Lee Hong-yuan, along with 40 experts and academics, Hsiao said in statements released by the CNA agency.
According to the KMT vice-president, the forum will focus on three major themes: tourist exchange, industrial cooperation and sustainable environmental development, jointly exploring aspects such as tourism, air routes, artificial intelligence, disaster prevention and mitigation and new energy.
Hsiao visited China in late November to meet with Song Tao, head of the State Council's Taiwan Affairs Office, who called for "joint efforts" to uphold the "one-China principle" and oppose "Taiwan separatism and independence."
The holding of this forum, which is limited to the academic scope and has a limited political scope, comes after weeks of speculation about a possible meeting between Chinese President Xi Jinping and Cheng Li-wen, a possibility that the vice president of the KMT did not rule out. "Cheng Li-wen has repeatedly emphasized that the KMT's mission is to restore cross-strait communication and exchanges. Therefore, Lee Hong-yuan leading this delegation is just the beginning; the aim is to gradually restore exchanges in various areas and directions," he said.
The harmony between the PCC and the KMT contrasts with the tone between the Chinese Government and the Taiwanese Executive, led since 2016 by the Democratic Progressive Party (PDP), a formation with a sovereignist tendency that opposes “reunification” with China and argues that only the 23 million Taiwanese have the right to decide their political future.
Taiwanese government leader and PDP leader William Lai, labeled an “independent” and “agitator” by Beijing authorities, announced in November a special defense budget of 1.25 billion Taiwan dollars (around 33 billion euros) to improve the island's defensive capabilities in the face of growing military pressure from Beijing.
However, the processing of this budget was blocked in Parliament by the KMT and the minority Taiwan People's Party (PPT), which together hold the majority of seats in the Chamber. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-29 01:18:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Government will create a system designed to assess the psychological health of residents</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/governo-vai-criar-um-sistema-destinado-a-avaliacao-da-saude-psicologica-dos-residentes/</link><description>The Health Services accept the creation of a new system for assessing the psychological well-being of residents and its respective database. The mechanism, which will also feature a “scientific measuring instrument” that assesses psychological disturbance, will serve to understand the physical and mental state of the population and define relevant policies. 

A new mechanism to assess and monitor the mental health of the Macau population is in the Government's work planning. The Health Services reveal that a system for evaluating indicators on physical and mental health and a database will be created, as a measure to improve services.
The new system will be established based on the results of two existing similar surveys, including the “physical condition assessment” of the Sports Institute and the “health assessment” of the Health Services, the organization said in response to a written question from deputy Ho Ion Sang.
According to Alvis Lo, director of Health Services, in this system, the psychological well-being of residents will be assessed based on five physical and mental health indicators from the World Health Organization (WHO), and a “scientific measuring instrument” will also be used to understand the state of psychological disturbance of residents. The objective of the service, indicated the leader, is “to understand the physical and mental state of the population in different aspects”, serving to support the definition and correct improvement of subsequent policies.
The five indicators of physical and mental health established by the WHO, commonly known as “WHO-5”, serve as an instrument for self-assessment of current psychological well-being, consisting of five statements related to the state of the respondents in the last two weeks.
Questions include how often they felt happiness, tranquility, energy, invigoration, and viewing life as interesting. According to the WHO, each statement is rated on a 6-point scale, with higher scores indicating better mental well-being. The instrument has already been translated into more than 30 languages.
The Health Services reiterate their commitment to improving services related to mental and physical health, after deputy Ho Ion Sang defended the regular carrying out, every five years, of the epidemiological survey on the mental health of the population, carried out by the Government. The legislator highlights, in this case, the need to systematically collect data on the prevalence of mental illnesses, the incidence rate and risk factors.
In his interpellation, the vice-president of the Legislative Assembly warns of the pressing demand for outpatient psychiatric consultation services in recent years in Macau. "With the fast pace of society and the constant increase in life pressure, the demand for mental health services by residents has been continuously increasing. In 2024, the number of users of outpatient psychiatric consultation services reached 50,597", he emphasized. He therefore insisted on the systematic optimization of services to increase their overall effectiveness.

COLLECTION OF CONSULTATION DATA
 
In his response, Alvis Lo assured that the Health Services had defined phased strategies and objectives to be achieved by 2030 in the field of mental health, meaning that the organization will progressively promote and monitor the execution of these works, to “increase the physical and mental health of residents”.
The authorities moved away from carrying out the survey every five years, as proposed by Ho Ion Sang, and pointed out, in this case, that they conduct the “Macau Health Survey” every ten years, in which data on the psychological state of residents is collected, which can serve as a reference for policy development.
Furthermore, the Health Services ensured that they systematically collected data on outpatient psychiatric consultations, number of hospitalized patients, patient diagnostic categories, rate of use of services and waiting time, among others. The data is intended to “provide scientific foundations for defining policies, managing resources and optimizing services, through the integration and analysis of this data”, they added.</description><pubDate>2026-01-29 01:26:32</pubDate></item><item><title>China closer to the United States as a global power, says Durão Barroso</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/china-mais-perto-dos-estados-unidos-como-potencia-global-diz-durao-barroso/</link><description>Former Prime Minister and President of the European Commission José Manuel Durão Barroso said that China is approaching the United States (USA) in terms of global power, including economic capacity.
Washington continues to be the “most important global power”, said Durão Barroso, 69, in Hong Kong, pointing to North American leadership in technology and finance. But “China is getting closer and closer, from my point of view”, added the Portuguese, in a speech given at the Asian Financial Forum, an annual event that, according to the organization, attracted 3,600 people to Hong Kong. “China is the country that has scored the most points recently,” said the president of the General Assembly of the Portuguese Diaspora Council, quoted by the Hong Kong newspaper South China Morning Post. “It is very important to observe not only the growth of the Chinese economy, but also the diplomatic victories that China has been achieving as a result of recent events”, highlighted Durão Barroso.
The Portuguese described the current international situation as more volatile, unpredictable and dangerous, with increasing “competition between the great powers”. Despite not mentioning the USA, Durão Barroso argued that China's diplomatic stance has caught the attention of analysts and political leaders.
On January 15, Durão Barroso became president of the board of directors and executive board of the Luso-American Development Foundation, replacing Nuno Morais Sarmento, who resigned for health reasons.
During the forum, which ended on Tuesday, the president of the European Commission also highlighted Europe's role as an essential player in the global order, alongside the US and China.
Durão Barroso recalled that the European bloc concluded, on Tuesday, a trade agreement with India, after 18 years of negotiations, ten days after signing a free trade pact with Mercosur, after almost three decades of negotiations.
Europe should not be underestimated and, in the face of global uncertainties, alliances, cooperation and trade openness are fundamental, said the former non-executive president of Goldman Sachs bank.
Durão Barroso argued that strengthening partnerships and maintaining a commitment to multilateralism is essential for international stability. A university professor, Durão Barroso was president of the European Commission for 10 years, between 2004 and 2014, having served as Prime Minister of Portugal between April 2002 and July 2004.
Durão Barroso was appointed in 2004, then aged 57, to the presidency of the community executive, becoming the 11th president of the Commission, and the first Portuguese to hold the position, to which he was reappointed in 2009, for a new term that ended on October 31, 2014.</description><pubDate>2026-01-29 01:17:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Number of labor conflicts falling</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/numero-de-conflitos-laborais-em-queda/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) reported yesterday that, between January and November last year, 1,223 cases related to labor disputes were opened, which means a drop of 18% compared to the same period in 2024. The majority of cases of labor disputes are due to the payment of wages, compensation for overtime work and compensation.

Between January and November last year, the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) opened a total of 1,223 cases relating to labor disputes, which reflects an 18% drop compared to the same period in 2024.
In a press release released yesterday, the organization also states that the majority of cases of conflict were due to salary payment, compensation for overtime work and severance pay.
During this period, the labor conflicts registered by DSAL involved a total of 1,936 workers, 832 of whom were local residents and 1,104 non-resident workers. The number of workers involved in labor conflicts in the first 11 months of last year decreased by 32% compared to the same period in 2024, DSAL also indicates.
In the statement, DSAL takes the opportunity to point out that it “continues, in conjunction with prevention and inspection measures, to strive to promote laws and diplomas in the area of ​​labor among sectors of society through diverse forms and in various languages, continually reinforcing the awareness of labor and employer parties regarding compliance with the law”.
Between January and November 2025, DSAL organized more than 50 information sessions on legal disclosure, whose content covers labor rights and interests, with the participation of a total of 3,351 people, “in order to effectively increase the understanding of the law by employers and workers”.
Regarding prevention and inspection, DSAL carried out, in the same period, 148 work inspection visits to 114 large construction sites and promoted the dissemination of legislation to 664 commercial establishments, “in order to identify and actively support the resolution of potential controversies”.
DSAL also says that it “will continue to firmly fulfill its legal duties, ensuring the rights and legitimate interests of workers”. Furthermore, “it will continue to reinforce legal dissemination through holding clarification sessions, producing infographics and videos, among other means and forms, striving to raise the knowledge and awareness of all sectors of society about labor legislation and compliance with the law, in order to jointly create a harmonious and stable working environment”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-29 01:24:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Relations between China and the United Kingdom must be seen from a global perspective</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/relacoes-entre-china-e-reino-unido-devem-ser-vistas-na-perspectiva-global/</link><description>A Chinese Communist Party newspaper argued yesterday that relations between China and the United Kingdom should be seen from a global perspective, in addition to the bilateral view, at the beginning of British Prime Minister Keir Starmer's visit to Beijing.

“The strengthening of a stable and predictable relationship between the two countries could contribute not only to the national interests of both parties, but also to the promotion of peace, stability and development at a global level”, pointed out the Global Times, in an editorial.
The newspaper cited recent statements by Chinese President Xi Jinping, made during a meeting with the Prime Minister of Finland, Petteri Orpo, in which the Chinese head of state highlighted that, faced with an international environment marked by geopolitical tensions, regional conflicts and economic uncertainty, the international community must strengthen coordination.
According to Xi, major countries must assume a responsible leadership role, promoting equality between states, respect for international order, cooperation and integrity in international relations.
According to the Global Times, these principles are equally applicable to relations between China and the United Kingdom, arguing that, despite existing political, ideological and strategic differences, both countries have solid foundations to deepen cooperation.
The newspaper maintained that the recognition of differences, combined with adequate management of disagreements and the reinforcement of dialogue, is essential to guarantee a “healthy and stable” development of bilateral relations.
The editorial highlighted that China and the United Kingdom maintain common interests in several areas, including trade, investment, finance, science and technology, education and combating climate change, and stressed that a constructive relationship between Beijing and London could play a broader positive role in the international system. “Cooperation between large economies is an important factor in facing common global challenges, such as the energy transition, food security, public health and sustainable development”, he pointed out.
The newspaper considered that confrontation and the logic of blocs do not offer effective solutions to current global problems and expressed the expectation that British delegations visiting China could convey to the United Kingdom and other Western societies a more direct perception of the Chinese reality.
According to the Global Times, visitors will have contact with an “open, inclusive and dynamic” country, arguing that this experience “could contribute to reducing misunderstandings and perceptions considered distorted about China in the West”.
Starmer's visit comes at a time of readjustment of British foreign policy towards China, after years of distancing under conservative governments, with London seeking to relaunch economic ties with Beijing, a strategy that coincides with the cooling of its relations with Washington after Donald Trump came to power.
In recent years, the United Kingdom has expressed concerns regarding issues such as human rights, Hong Kong or Taiwan, positions that have been rejected by Beijing as interference in its internal affairs. “The stability of Sino-British relations depends on the ability of both parties to avoid excessive politicization of economic relations and to resist external pressures that could compromise bilateral cooperation,” stated the editorial.
The visit to China, the first by a British head of government in eight years, runs until Saturday. During the visit, Starmer will be received by Xi and will hold meetings with Chinese Premier Li Qiang and the chairman of the Standing Committee of the National People's Congress, Zhao Leji. In addition to Beijing, the British leader will travel to Shanghai. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-29 01:18:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Violations of alcohol consumption and tobacco control laws increased by 27.9% in 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/infraccoes-as-leis-do-consumo-de-alcool-e-do-controlo-do-tabagismo-aumentaram-279-em-2025/</link><description>In 2025, authorities recorded a total of 5,474 violations of tobacco control and alcohol consumption laws. This is an increase of 27.9% compared to 2024.

Last year, authorities recorded a total of 5,474 violations of smoking and alcohol control laws, which translates into an increase of 27.9% compared to 2024.
Looking only at violations of the smoking law, the Health Services, the Public Security Police Corps, the Institute for Municipal Affairs, the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate, the Customs Service, detected 5,008 cases of illegal smoking, which represents an increase of 27%. 316 cases of transporting electronic cigarettes into and out of Macau were also detected, more than double compared to 2024.
134 suspected cases of violation of other provisions of the smoking prevention and control regime were also recorded, namely, failure to display signs prohibiting smoking, and failure to display a notice prohibiting the sale of tobacco products to minors under 18 years of age in sales outlets.
Casinos were where the highest number of cases of people smoking in prohibited places were recorded, in total, 1,111 cases. This was followed by catering establishments, 780 cases, gardens and leisure areas, 414 cases and, among others.
Authorities say that “the increase in cases of illegal smoking was compounded by several factors”, including “the continuous optimization of inspection methods, with an increase in their frequency (more than 240,700 inspections were carried out by inspection agents in 2025), the increase in the number of visitors to Macau (the number of cases of illegal smoking among tourists increased from 2,063 in 2024 to 3,050 in 2025, a increase of approximately 48%) and the failure of some establishments to dynamically fulfill their responsibilities in relation to the smoking prevention and control regime, or the concealment of smokers”.
Regarding alcohol, in 2025, there were 16 suspected cases of violation of the regime for preventing and controlling the consumption of alcoholic beverages by minors, six cases of which involved the sale or provision of alcoholic beverages to minors.
Other infractions had to do, for example, with establishments selling or providing alcoholic beverages that did not display signs prohibiting the sale or providing of alcoholic beverages to minors; Commercial establishments that provide self-service services do not clearly define or indicate areas for displaying alcoholic beverages and non-alcoholic beverages or advertising alcoholic beverages without displaying warnings in Chinese, Portuguese and English. Authorities say that the respective cases have already been instructed for appropriate follow-up.
The press release also notes that, during inspections carried out by alcoholic beverages and tobacco inspection agents, situations were detected in which several minors were consuming alcohol in a food establishment, and the workers did not stop them, and a case was initiated against the suspected violation of this law. According to the Health Services, “parents and schools of minors have already been notified so that they are reminded of the health risks associated with alcohol consumption and made aware of the harms of drinking alcoholic beverages to their health, and their behavior must comply with the law”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-29 01:25:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Authorities lower travel alert levels for Egypt and Indonesia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/autoridades-baixam-niveis-de-alerta-de-viagens-para-o-egipto-e-a-indonesia/</link><description>The list of countries covered by the Macao SAR Travel Alert System, created in 2017 to disseminate information about potential threats when traveling abroad, was updated yesterday. On the website of the Directorate of Tourism Services (DST), it is noted that Egypt has dropped from alert level 2 to level 1, the lowest on the scale, while the warning signals for Indonesia have been cancelled.

The Tourism Services Directorate (DST) yesterday updated the alert level of two countries covered by the Macao SAR Travel Alert System. The destinations affected by the changes were Egypt, which moved from level 2 to level 1, and Indonesia, which no longer had warning signs in place.
Macau authorities frequently issue warning signals to passengers intending to travel to Indonesia, depending on the country's political and meteorological situation. At the end of last December, remember, the island of Sumatra was devastated by floods that caused more than eight hundred deaths.
On the other hand, Egypt was raised to alert level 2 in August 2024, like Turkey, while Israel rose to level 3. According to the most recent update, of this trio, only Egypt went down to level 1. Turkey remains at level 2, while several areas of Israel – north of Nahariya and Safed, north and east of Lake Galilee, south of Ashkelon and west of Netivot – remain at level 3. The remaining Israeli territory is under alert level 2.
Based on the classification published on the DST website, alert level 3 advises against traveling to destinations that may pose “extreme threats” to personal safety. “Macau residents who plan to travel or are at the destination should be aware of the seriousness of the situation and the official assistance that can be provided”, write the authorities. In addition to Israel, this alert level includes several countries in the Middle East such as Iran, Syria and Lebanon.
Level 2 asks to “reconsider” non-essential travel to the destinations covered, due to the intensification of a danger scenario. This definition encompasses countries such as Turkey and Pakistan.
Finally, level 1 indicates the “emergence of a threat” and urges residents to remain alert to “developing events”. This is the alert level that covers most countries: Bangladesh, the Philippines (more specifically, the island of Mindanao), India, Japan (the Fukushima region), Myanmar, Nepal, Peru, the United Kingdom, Russia, Sri Lanka and Tunisia.
Although only Fukushima appears on the list, it is important to remember that both the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the People's Republic of China and the DST advised Chinese citizens against traveling to Japan. The warning appeared in November, following statements by Japanese Prime Minister, Sanae Takaichi, about possible military intervention by Tokyo in the event of a conflict between Beijing and the island of Taiwan.
In addition to the 110 countries covered by the Macao SAR Travel Alert System, authorities advise residents to “carefully” plan their itineraries to another 88 countries and destinations. This includes destinations such as Afghanistan, Colombia or Venezuela.
On the DST page, it is highlighted that the system is not prohibitive in nature – it is, rather, a set of relevant guidelines so that residents can adjust their travel plans according to the information provided. The risk level of the trip is assessed according to the possible threats faced by Macau residents in different destinations, which can range from natural disasters or terrorist attacks to public health incidents.</description><pubDate>2026-01-29 01:24:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau's financial reserve value rose 7.6% until November</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/valor-da-reserva-financeira-de-macau-subiu-76-ate-novembro/</link><description>Macau's financial reserve assets appreciated by 7.6% in the first 11 months of last year and are close to setting a new record high. According to the Macau Monetary Authority, the reserve was worth 663.2 billion patacas at the end of November, 47 billion patacas more than at the end of 2024.

Macau's financial reserve assets appreciated by 7.6% in the first 11 months of last year and are close to setting a new record high, it was announced yesterday.
According to the Macau Monetary Authority (AMCM), the reserve was worth 663.2 billion patacas at the end of November, 47 billion patacas more than at the end of 2024.
A balance published in the region's Official Bulletin shows that the reserve has already appreciated more than in 2024, the year in which assets rose by 35.7 billion patacas.
The best year ever for the financial reserve was 2019, before the start of the pandemic, when assets appreciated by 70.6 billion patacas.
The value reached at the end of November is the second highest ever, just below the record of 663.6 billion patacas, set in February 2021, despite the territory then being in the midst of a pandemic.
Even so, according to AMCM, the appreciation of the reserve slowed down in November, the month in which it gained 2.15 billion patacas, 198.3 million patacas less than the increase in October.
The value of the extraordinary reserve at the end of November was 456.5 billion patacas and the basic reserve, equivalent to 150% of Macau's public budget, was 167.3 billion patacas.
The territory's initial budget for 2025 predicted a 7% increase in total expenditure, to 109.4 billion patacas. But the Legislative Assembly (AL) approved in July a proposal presented by the Government for a new budget, which includes an extra increase of 2.86 billion patacas in expenses.
In November, the AL also unanimously gave the green light to the budget for 2026, which foresees public expenditure of 113.5 billion patacas.
Subcontracted investments represent the largest share of Macau's financial reserve, 283.2 billion patacas, which also includes deposits and current accounts worth 272 billion patacas and even credit securities worth 104.4 billion patacas.
In 2024, investments yielded almost 31 billion patacas to the financial reserve, corresponding to a profitability rate of 5.3%, said AMCM, at the end of February 2025. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-29 01:22:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Storm Kristin destroyed and caused at least 5 deaths in Portugal</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/tempestade-kristin-destruiu-e-causou-pelo-menos-5-mortos-em-portugal/</link><description>The passage of Depression Kristin across the Portuguese mainland caused four deaths yesterday, indicated the National Emergency and Civil Protection Authority (ANEPC), in a clarification note. At stake are one fatal victim in the municipality of Vila Franca de Xira, in the district of Lisbon, and four in the municipality of Leiria. The clarification comes after the municipality of Leiria indicated the record of two deaths directly related to the impact of bad weather and reported the existence of two more fatalities in the municipality due to cardiorespiratory arrests. The connection between these two cases and bad weather was still being investigated and, if confirmed, the total number of deaths in the country would reach five.
In the ANEPC note, received by Lusa, it is explained that “so far” there are three fatalities resulting from bad weather in the municipality of Leiria: two in Carvide (one “struck by a metal plate” and the other for being “trapped in the structure of the house”) and one in Fonte Oleiro, “found in cardiorespiratory arrest (PCR) on a construction site”. As had already been announced early yesterday morning, the death in Vila Franca de Xira was due to a tree falling on a light vehicle.
The passage of the Kristin depression through Portuguese territory left a trail of destruction, causing, in addition to the four deaths, several people to be displaced. The most affected districts were Leiria (where the depression entered the mainland), Coimbra, Santarém and Lisbon. Falling trees and structures, cutting or conditioning of roads and transport services, especially railway lines, closing schools and power, water and communications cuts, were the main consequences of the storm. Civil Protection yesterday placed a state of special readiness at level 4, the maximum, along the entire coastline between Viana do Castelo and Setúbal, and there were red meteorological warnings (the most serious level) along the entire coast of the continent.</description><pubDate>2026-01-29 01:16:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Sector defends “diversified businesses” for the Tamagnini Barbosa Market</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/sector-defende-negocios-diversificados-para-o-mercado-tamagnini-barbosa/</link><description>The Tamagnini Barbosa Market will undergo revitalization works starting this year, a project in which the sector calls for an expansion of the operational area and diversification of the types of business operated by the stalls, in order to attract more consumption.
Cheng Wong, president of the Macau Sellers Mutual Aid Association, revealed that the Tamagnini Barbosa Market currently has around 30 stalls in operation, a “significant reduction” compared to the pre-pandemic level.
Yesterday on the Forum Macau program on the Chinese channel Radio Macau, Cheng Wong highlighted that the market is facing challenges such as a decrease in visitors and consumers and an increase in vacant stalls, due to changes in consumption patterns and increased business competition in neighboring areas.
The sector representative hopes that the Tamagnini Barbosa Market, with the revitalization works, will have an expanded operational area in the future. He also suggested the introduction of an innovative management method, diversification of restaurant options to attract customers, focusing particularly on meal services for students studying in schools in that area.
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) had announced that it is preparing works to optimize the Tamagnini Barbosa Market, with the adjustment of the layout and design of public spaces and stalls, optimization of existing facilities and the creation of a food center.
Wong Chio U, member of the North Zone Community Services Advisory Council who also addressed the issue on the radio program, agrees with the need to renovate the Tamagnini Barbosa Market, an installation that represents local cultural sentiment. The official also pointed out that residents' consumption patterns have changed, with the public preferring market promotion through digital means, such as online video. Therefore, he suggested that, in the future, authorities open opportunities for collaborative management of municipal markets with private companies and community organizations.</description><pubDate>2026-01-29 01:21:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Wind will return to Macau – and improve air quality</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/vento-vai-regressar-a-macau-e-melhorar-a-qualidade-do-ar/</link><description>After a few days of clear skies and mild temperatures in the afternoon, the weather will cool down again. In an informative note published on its website, the Directorate of Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) says that the wind in the region will intensify in the coming days and provide “a cooler thermal sensation”, in addition to contributing to improving air quality.
The authorities explain that the “weak wind intensity has created unfavorable conditions for the dispersion” of pollutants and thus resulted in poor air quality. Over the last week, the SMG have activated the “unhealthy” air alert almost daily, calculated from data obtained from automatic monitoring stations. This means that the concentration of some pollutants in Macau has been higher than the reference values ​​stipulated by the “Ambient Air Quality Standards”.
This scenario should change from today onwards, with the influence of an air current from the eastern quadrant. Along with the wind, the clear sky will also give way to periods of cloudiness and rain during the weekend. The intensification of wind and precipitation will contribute to lower temperatures and the circulation of stagnant air, authorities say.
Sunday, the first day of February, will be the one on which thermometers will reach their lowest temperatures, with minimums of 13 and maximums of 17 degrees Celsius. The phenomenon is due to the influence of a northeast monsoon, which is expected to reach the southern coast of China on Saturday night. The SMG warn, however, that “there are still significant differences between the various forecast models”, which is why they appeal to the population to remain attentive to the most recent forecasts.
It is worth remembering that the city of Macau was ranked 52nd in the latest World Air Quality Report by the Swiss company IQAir. The 2024 report, the most recent, indicated that the territory “exceeds three to five times” the World Health Organization (WHO) guidelines. Macau appears between Sri Lanka (51st) and Guyana (53rd), in a higher position than Taiwan (54th) and Hong Kong (63rd). Mainland China, in turn, comes in 21st place. According to the report, the five most polluted countries and regions in the world are Chad, Bangladesh, Pakistan, the Democratic Republic of Congo and India.</description><pubDate>2026-01-29 01:20:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Timor-Leste and Australia want quick joint venture proposal to develop Greater Sunrise</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/timor-leste-e-australia-querem-rapida-proposta-de-joint-venture-para-desenvolver-greater-sunrise/</link><description>Timor-Leste and Australia yesterday asked the joint venture that will explore the Greater Sunrise gas field to present, as quickly as possible, to governments a development concept proposal, based on the study carried out.

The request is contained in the joint declaration on the establishment of a New Partnership for a New Era, signed yesterday by the Timorese Prime Ministers, Xanana Gusmão, and Australian Prime Ministers, Anthony Albanese, as part of a 24-hour visit that the head of the Australian Government is carrying out in Dili.
“Taking into account the conceptual study and the importance of Timor-Leste’s economic resilience, Australia and Timor-Leste encourage the ‘Sunrise Joint Venture’ to use this study and present to the states, as quickly as possible, a proposed Development Concept for Greater Sunrise, which meets the requirements of the Maritime Boundary Treaty”, can be read in the statement, distributed to the press.
The consortium is made up of the Timorese company Timor Gap (56.56%), the operator Woodside Energy (33.44%) and Osaca Gás (10.00%).
The two heads of government also committed to supporting the joint venture so that the “project can move forward quickly, after approval by the states of a single development concept”, and to develop a schedule for the completion of the Petroleum Mining Code, the Greater Sunrise Production Sharing Contract and the fiscal regime required by the Maritime Boundary Treaty.
The declaration also establishes that “Australia recognizes Timor-Leste’s commitment to onshore processing and the Tasi Mane project on the south coast” and support for “any commercially viable solution for the development of Greater Sunrise”, proposed by the joint venture.
Located 150 kilometers from Timor-Leste and 450 kilometers from Darwin, the Greater Sunrise project has been involved in an impasse, with Dili defending the construction of a gas pipeline to the south of the country and Woodside, the consortium's second largest partner, leaning towards a connection to the existing unit in Darwin.
The impasse led the joint venture to request a conceptual study, which was prepared by the British company Wood, which confirmed the feasibility of developing Greater Sunrise in Timor-Leste. “The Timor-Leste Liquefied Natural Gas (TLNG) option stands out for providing lower operating costs and, by allowing better general direct and indirect returns for Timor-Leste, will create a great socioeconomic impact in the country”, says the Timorese Government.
The permanent maritime border agreement between Timor-Leste and Australia determines that Greater Sunrise, a shared resource, will have to be shared, with 70% of revenues going to Timor-Leste, if the gas pipeline is built southwards, or 80%, if processing is in Darwin. Lusa</description><pubDate>2026-01-29 01:17:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Artistic training leads to a multifaceted exhibition in Barra</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/formacao-artistica-desemboca-em-exposicao-multifacetada-na-barra/</link><description>The project “Talent Training for Cultural and Creative Design of the Maritime Silk Road”, supported by the 2025 National Arts Fund of China and organized by MGM, reaches a public stage after a year of work. The final exhibition of the program, which presents the achievements of the 30 trained participants, opens on Thursday, February 5th, at the former Matadouro da Barra, with an afternoon sharing session at the POLY MGM MUSEUM.
This MGM Grande Paradise initiative was one of ten projects from Macau selected in 2025 to receive financial support from the National Arts Fund of China, marking the fourth consecutive time that artistic and cultural projects from the territory have obtained this national recognition. The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture considered that this type of support provides “a broader space for development, fostering a new situation of prosperity for the cultural and artistic development of Macau”, in addition to offering more resources and platforms to the sector.
The exhibition will bring together a selection of original works created by participants, coming from various parts of the country. The collection is diverse, including cultural and creative products, clothing design, painting, sculpture and multimedia installations, serving as a “living practice of the innovative transformation of the culture of the historic Maritime Silk Road”. The official inauguration, between 11:00 am and 12:30 pm, will feature institutional speeches, presentation by graduates, delivery of certificates and a guided tour.
To promote a deeper dialogue about the future of design inspired by this historical legacy, the POLY MGM MUSEUM, which served as the program's training base, will host a special sharing session on the same day, starting at 5pm. The event will feature two prominent speakers. The first presented by Chu Yan, Professor at the Beijing Institute of Fashion Technology and Dean of the Institute of Chinese Aesthetics in the New Era, and the second by Lou Jie, Researcher at the Dunhuang Academy. The session aims to deepen discussions and explore opportunities for intersectoral cooperation for the sustainable development of the local cultural and creative industry.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Health Services call for vaccination before Lunar New Year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/servicos-de-saude-apelam-a-vacinacao-antes-do-ano-novo-lunar/</link><description>The Health Services yesterday warned of the increased risk of contracting respiratory infections, such as flu and pneumococcus, during the Lunar New Year holidays, calling on residents to get vaccinated as soon as possible.
According to data presented yesterday in a statement, the positivity rate for the influenza virus in Macau is around 9%, which represents a “moderate” prevalence level. This risk is expected to increase around the Lunar New Year period, when trips abroad and gatherings between family and friends are common.
Vaccination against influenza is the most effective measure for its prevention, in addition to reducing the risk of developing complications or death after infection. The process of producing sufficient antibodies takes at least two weeks after administration, so residents are advised to get the vaccine “as soon as possible before the Lunar New Year”. Although the alert is given to the entire population, it is particularly important for “high-risk” people, such as pregnant women, children, the elderly and chronically ill people.
The vaccination schedule was extended until January 31st, to allow residents to be vaccinated at night and on Sunday mornings. Appointments can be made through the “My Health” tab of the “Macau Single Account” or through the Health Services vaccination appointment system – with the exception of high-risk groups, which do not need to schedule vaccination.
The authorities also add that the elderly and people with chronic illnesses should reinforce the flu vaccine with a dose of the 13-valent or 15-valent pneumonic conjugate vaccine, in order to prevent invasive pneumococcal disease. Both vaccines can be administered simultaneously, without the need for prior appointment.</description><pubDate>2026-01-29 01:20:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Matching sessions at the beginning of February will provide 274 places</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/sessoes-de-emparelhamento-do-inicio-de-fevereiro-vao-proporcionar-274-vagas/</link><description>The Labor Affairs Bureau (DSAL) and the Federation of Macau Workers' Association (FAOM) will organize four more job matching sessions in the first week of February, providing 274 more vacancies. Registration for these pairing sessions starts today and ends on February 3rd.
The first session takes place on the morning of February 4th at “Wan Tung Pharmacy”, providing a total of 20 job openings for salespeople.
On the afternoon of that same day, the pairing session for the restaurant sector will be held, with participating companies being the “Jin Yue Xuan Restaurant/Hip Seng Seafood Stew Restaurant”, the “Fu Ying Cantonese Restaurant” and the “Ut Cheong Private Kitchen Food Establishment”, with a total of 198 job vacancies, involving jobs such as head waiter, cook, F&amp;B service employee, fish tank manager, cook assistant and servant, among others.
On the morning of February 5th, a matching session for the hotel sector will be held, with “Hotel Four Seasons Macau” and “Hotel W – Studio City” as participating companies, with a total of 29 job vacancies, involving jobs such as receptionist, room service waiter, customer contact center agent, chef, cook and F&amp;B service employee, among others.
Throughout February 6th, the matching session will be held for “SJM Resorts, S.A.”, with a total of 27 job openings, involving positions such as assistant restaurant manager (Chinese cuisine/Japanese cuisine/casino meals), assistant concierge chef, public areas supervisor, receptionist, concierge ambassador and F&amp;B services employee, among others.
The sessions on the 4th and 5th of February will take place at the FAOM building, in Patane. The session on the 6th is at the Grand Lisboa Palace hotel.</description><pubDate>2026-01-29 01:19:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau is present at Spanish tourism fair</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/macau-marca-presenca-em-feira-de-turismo-espanhola/</link><description>The Spanish International Tourism Fair (FITUR) once again had a pavilion dedicated to Macau in its most recent edition, which took place between the 21st and 25th of January. For the first time, the Tourism Services Bureau (DST) also cooperated with the China pavilion in organizing tourism promotion activities and experiences.
The Macau delegation was represented by the deputy director of DST, Cheng Wai Tong, together with representatives from the tourism industry and integrated tourism and leisure companies. In a statement, the organization said it promoted “the connection between Macau operators and their European counterparts” and helped “expand markets abroad”.
This year's pavilion highlighted “the richest elements” of Macau's identity, characterized by the fusion of Chinese and Western cultures. The activities organized by DST focused mainly on Macau's intangible heritage, including Portuguese folk dances, tai chi and wing chun martial arts, Portuguese tile painting and tasting typical Macanese snacks. The objective was to enable European operators to experience the “cultural diversity and tourist resources of Macau”, making the city more attractive for tourist packages and “multi-destination” itineraries.
At the same event, MGTO held a seminar to promote Macau tourism in cooperation with the China pavilion, with a view to further disseminating Macau's tourism potential among the European public. Outside the context of the fair, DST also organized a series of promotional initiatives in the country, including a partnership with the Spanish group Ávoris.
The authorities inform that this year they will launch the third edition of the Online Training Course in Portuguese Language, which will also extend to Germany, Finland and the Netherlands, in order to help European tour operators to learn more in depth about the content of Macau's “tourism +” range. In the same statement, DST informs that it is still collecting data to analyze the preferences of European visitors and better plan the market development strategy.
Last year, the number of visitors from Spain and Portugal, as well as from Europe in general, registered “double-digit growth” compared to 2024. DST's tourist campaigns on the European continent will continue in the coming months, starting with the organization's participation in the “The Specialists” roadshow in February, in Portugal.</description><pubDate>2026-01-29 01:19:32</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea reveals “next stage” of nuclear program at congress</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2026/01/29/coreia-do-norte-revela-proxima-etapa-de-programa-nuclear-em-congresso/</link><description>North Korea declared that it will present “the next stage” of the nuclear deterrence plan at the next single party congress, the official North Korean press reported yesterday.
The congress “will clarify plans for the next step aimed at strengthening the country's nuclear deterrence force,” leader Kim Jong-un said on Tuesday during a ballistic missile launch, according to the KCNA news agency.
Accompanied by other North Korean officials, Kim was present during the test of a large-caliber multiple rocket launcher, during which four missiles were fired, KCNA reported.
While acknowledging that the development of the rocket launcher system has faced difficulties, Kim considered Tuesday's test to be "of great importance in improving the effectiveness" of "strategic deterrence."
The four rockets fired hit a target located more than 358 kilometers away, according to the North Korean leader.
The ballistic missiles were fired towards the Sea of ​​Japan, and two of them landed outside the country's exclusive economic zone, Japanese news agency Jiji Press reported, citing sources from the Japanese Ministry of Defense. “The outcome and scope of this trial will be a source of deep moral suffering and a serious threat to forces that attempt to provoke a military confrontation with us,” Kim said.
This is the second test of the month for Pyongyang, following a volley of missiles fired just hours before the South Korean leader's departure for an official visit to China. It also occurred the day after a trip to Seoul by the number three at the United States War Department, Elbridge Colby, who hailed South Korea as a “model ally”.
North Korea has stepped up missile testing in recent years. Analysts indicate that the campaign aims to improve precision strike capabilities, challenge the United States and South Korea and test weapons, before eventually exporting them to Russia.
Pyongyang is preparing to hold the first congress in five years of the Workers' Party of Korea, the single party, in the coming weeks. In anticipation, Kim Jong-un ordered the expansion and modernization of the country's missile production.</description><pubDate>2026-01-29 01:17:21</pubDate></item></channel></rss>