<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/governo-timorense-cancela-licencas-dadas-para-exploracao-de-jogos-e-apostas-online/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Chinese electric cars challenge Japanese rule in Southeast Asia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/carros-electricos-chineses-desafiam-dominio-japones-no-sudeste-asiatico/</link><description>Increasing sales of low -cost Chinese electric cars are shaking the domain of decades of Japanese brands in Southeast Asia, according to a study released by the PWC consulting and audit firm.

The market share of Japanese manufacturers - led by Toyota, Honda and Nissan - fell to 62% of sales in the first half of 2025 in the region's six largest markets, against an average of 77% in the past decade. Chinese producers increased their slice of almost null to more than 5% of 3.3 million units sold.
The Chinese offensive is explained by the price war that the sector faces in China, which led manufacturers to look for nearby external markets, benefiting from a regional trade agreement that guarantees access without tariffs. "The entry of Chinese electric vehicle manufacturers marks the end of a Japanese dominion era in Southeast Asia," said Patrick Ziechmann, PWC analyst in Malaysia.
In Indonesia, the largest consumer market in the region, Toyota's sales fell 12% between January and August, to 161,079 units, while Chinese Byd tripled to 18,989.
Affordable prices are seen as a determining factor: Some Chinese models start at $ 12,000 (over 10,000 euros). "The price is the decisive factor. The Japanese have to react, otherwise they will continue to lose market share," said the Vice President of the Indonesian Association of Automobile Manufacturers, Jongkie Sugiarto, quoted by the British newspaper Financial Times.
The Chinese presence in the country is not limited to sales. At least 15 brands are already active and another five are expected to come in soon.
Some have installed their own factories, while others produce in partnership with local companies, benefiting temporary exemptions for import rates for electric vehicles. However, starting next year, manufacturers will have to produce locally to continue to access subsidies, which could lock the advance of smaller brands.
In Singapore, the transformation is even more evident: BYD became the best-selling brand this year, surpassing Toyota, which in 2023 led 25% of sales.
Government incentives for electric vehicles and aggressive entry of various Chinese brands, with innovative marketing strategies, have helped change consumer preferences.
China is also betting on technology, seeking to take advantage of the advantage in the automotive software. The Xpeng manufacturer began this year to export models equipped with functions such as mobile -controlled parking to the region. “We see Southeast Asia as a potential market,” said company president Brian Gu. Reconfiguration is already transforming the regional industry. Subaru ended the factory in Thailand in 2024, while Suzuki plans to close its facilities by the end of 2025. On the other hand, BYD sent the first vehicle produced in Thailand to Europe in September, signaling global ambitions.
According to Jessada ThongPak, analyst at S&amp;P Global Mobility, Chinese penetration in Southeast Asia is just the beginning of a process that should replicate in other regions. The consultant provides that Chinese brands can represent 20% of car sales in Thailand by 2032.
Despite the positive economic impact that Japanese brands have had for decades in the region, consumers will “decide who will be the end winners,” BYD's director of Sales to Asia Pacific, Liu Xuelung, quoted by FT. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-02 22:45:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan leads Russia's world naphtha purchases despite supporting Kiev</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/taiwan-lidera-compras-mundiais-de-nafta-da-russia-apesar-de-apoiar-kiev/</link><description>Taiwan became the world's largest importer of Russian naphtha, a petroleum derivative used in the manufacture of chemicals needed to the semiconductor industry, according to an independent reflection group.

According to a report released on Wednesday, in the first half of 2025, Taiwan bought $ 1.3 billion in Russian NAFTA.
The monthly average of imports of this component reached a level almost six times higher than that recorded in 2022, according to the Energy and Air Research Center (CREA), a Finnish organization that collaborated with Russian and Taiwanese entities in this project.
Imports of this product through the island generated $ 1.7 billion in tax extraction to Kremlin, "enough to finance 170,000 Gerbera drones, each capable of causing damage in Ukraine," the document stressed.
Since the beginning of the Ukraine Russian invasion in February 2022, and by the end of June 2025, Taiwan imported approximately 6.8 million tons of Russian naphtha, worth $ 4.9 billion. This value is equivalent to 20% of the total NAFTA Russian exports, making Taiwan the third largest buyer of this product since the beginning of the conflict.
The Formosa Petrochemical Corporation Company Mailiao Refinery, located in Yunlin County in the west of the island, accounted for 96% of Russian naphtha purchases bound for Taiwan, increasing a 9% dependence before the invasion to 90% in the first half of 2025, according to Crea.
The semiconductor and electronic industries, which constitute the backbone of the Taiwanese economy, depend on naphtha derivatives, such as propylene, benzene and toluene, which serve as essential raw materials for petrochemicals used in chips and electronic components. "Excessive dependence on Russian naphtha potentially affects the availability of essential materials for semiconductor manufacturers such as TSMC, Nvidia, AMD and Intel," the report said. "This makes Taiwan vulnerable to geopolitical disturbances, secondary sanctions or strategic manipulation by Russia and its allies," the document warned.
Despite joining international sanctions against Russia, Taiwan - highly dependent on energy imports - did not restrict the purchase of Russian fossil fuels.
Since the beginning of the Ukraine invasion, the island has imported $ 11.2 billion in Russian fuel, according to CREA estimates.
The publication of the report occurred a few days after the head of the Taiwanese Foreign Pasta, Lin Chia-Lung, witnessed the signing of an agreement between Taiwan and Ukraine in Poland to help needed children in the Kiev region, particularly those who lost their parents during the conflict.
British reflection group Royal United Services Institute published another study based on contracts and documents obtained by a group of computer activists, which shows how Russia is supporting China for a possible Taiwan attack. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-02 22:46:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau receives more than 276,000 visitors in less than two days</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/macau-recebe-mais-de-276-mil-visitantes-em-menos-de-dois-dias/</link><description>Between Wednesday and 5 pm yesterday, the border stations of Macau registered the entry of 276,383 visitors. The second day of the golden week was the busiest, with a growth of about 20% compared to the data from the previous day.
 
In the first two days of the golden week of October, between Wednesday and 5 pm yesterday, 276,383 visitors entered Macao, according to data released by the Public Security Police (CPSP). In total, 1,108,506 border movements were registered during this period, almost half (461,422 movements, ie 41.6% of globality) concerned the entry and exit of visitors.
On the day the 76th anniversary of the Foundation of the Popular Republic of China (RPC) was celebrated, Wednesday, 673,778 entries and exits at Macao border posts were counted. Within this number, a slice of 265,646 corresponded to visitor transionous movements, shared between 139,854 inputs and 125,792 exits.
Among the nine borders of access to the territory, the doors of the right, the Hengqin border post and the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau bridge stood out as the election passages to the continent visitors. On October 1, 63,548 people entered Macao through the doors of Right and another 28,047 by Hengqin, with 20,796 visitors chose to get into the car territory through the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau bridge.

Second day with more visitors

Yesterday, until 17h, CPSP registered 434,728 border movements, 45% of them attributed to visitors (ie, 195,776 people).
Comparing the data compiled until 5 pm on the days under analysis, October 1 and 2, it is found that the second day of the golden week was the one with the highest movement at Macao borders and also the one with the highest flow of visitors. While Day 1 signaled the entry of 113,599 tourists from the interior of China until 5pm, the next day, at the same time, this number already ascended to 136,529 people.
Once again, the Borders of Election of the Visitors who entered Macao yesterday were the doors of the siege (69,439), the Hengqin Border Post (26,986) and the Maritime Bridge between Macau, Hong Kong and Zhuhai (16,746).
The data provided by CPSP allow you to calculate that the number of visitors' entries until 5 pm has grown around 20% between day 1 and day 2. If this 20% advantage is held until midnight, the day can end with a total of 167,824 visitors in Macao. The data for yesterday will be released during the early hours of today, after the closing time of this edition.
If this scenario is confirmed, the daily average of visitors in the first two days should be 154 thousand. This means an increase of about 9.2% compared to the same period of the same period last year and even a more positive result than the latest STD projections, which pointed to a daily average of 150,000 tourist entries. Multiplying the body's estimate by eight days of holidays in the interior of China, it is found that the total number of arrivals over this prolonged golden week may reach-or overcome-the 1.2 million.</description><pubDate>2025-10-02 22:58:08</pubDate></item><item><title>"There were boats that shattered before it arrived in Macau"</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/havia-barcos-que-se-despedacavam-antes-de-chegar-a-macau/</link><description>In the nineteenth century, four elements of the Mission Congregation came from the Portuguese capital and arrived in the territory seven months later, on the Vasco da Gama ship, leaving everything recorded in a manuscript. And although it is a very risky crossing, says Anabela Leal de Barros, a linguist, in an interview with the final point, which is particularly interesting in this kind of reports are the detailed descriptions that these missionaries make of what is spoken locally, besides the fauna, flora, cooking and religion. Authored by the researcher and former professor at the University of Macao, the book “Travel from Lisbon to Macau - 1825” is based on the Diary of Father José Joaquim de Miranda and Oliveira and is launched on October 8, at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center in Lisbon.

How did your interest in this 1825 trip arise?
It was not exactly this trip, but the interest I have in the study of grammatical and lexicographic works in Chinese and Portuguese made by the Jesuits and the Lazarists and, above all, by the work of Father Joaquim Afonso Gonçalves, the greatest Portuguese synologist. Since Father Joaquim Afonso Gonçalves, also Lazarista, departed from Lisbon in 1812, and I already have some articles about him and some books published about his manuscript, wanted to know what would be contained in this trip, which is a manuscript from the Braga District Archive. I went to visit the file and realized that it is a later trip, because it is from 1825, but I was interested in it, because it would be the same kind of experience that Joaquim Afonso Gonçalves had. It was curious, because, in fact, these priests would somehow replace Joaquim Afonso Gonçalves and another Lazarist priest, who came out, more or less exiled for a while, to Manila, due to misunderstandings with the bishop of Macao - at the time, Friar Francisco de Nossa Senhora da Luz Chacim - due to liberal struggles and liberal movements. The Jesuits had already been expelled from the College of St. Joseph and Macau and also from Brazil. The Lazarists had replaced us at the College of St. Joseph, but it was necessary to see more these priests (four)-in fact, they would be a priest, José Joaquim de Miranda and Oliveira, two minorists, Jerónimo José da Mata and João de Castro and Moura, and the coadjutor José Ferreira da Silva. And there is also a later trip, from 1831, which, in fact, brings other Lazarists who will, more or less, replace some of these, because the person who makes this report of this trip - José Joaquim de Miranda and Oliveira - arrives in Macao at 28, but at 31, had already died in Nanjing.
I was interested in the trip not only for this, but also for the experience that the priests had in these trips, for the curiosity to know what was going on when we were crossing the world, even in the nineteenth century, because it was not easy. It is interesting the view of Father José Joaquim de Miranda and Oliveira for the main stop points, Cape Verde, Indonesia de Java, Manila and La Laguna, in the Philippines, reporting agricultural, sociocultural, administrative, religious and linguistic aspects, among others.
 
Did your curiosity also bear the risk that involved a trip like 1825?
What interested me was not exactly the issue of risk and conditions. It was more because the priests had a spirit of linguists. Missionary strategy involved knowing local languages ​​soon - the first to arrive described the languages, besides fauna, flora, cooking and religion. They described and sent grammars and dictionaries to Portugal. Already during the trip these priests always show curiosity about the names of certain birds they have never seen and are no longer the current. There are interesting names like Frade beans or the mangallions. According to the places, the priests tell what is happening in cultural terms and the habits of the peoples. They talk about mascar (tobacco), smoking, clothing and use local terms for the weather facts.

But was this also a risky trip or not?
Everyone knows that they may not see your family again and may not see your country and your kingdom again. In the case of this trip, there were, above all, storms. There were downs or downs, there were the chains. Since they were sailing vessels, they could only navigate when there was wind, so the wind was the protagonist. The essential was to be alone in the face of all this. Even Father José Joaquim de Miranda and Oliveira said that, at one point, they helped the vessel that accompanied them, the war ship, to look for a man who had fallen into the sea but could not save. He said, God forbids us of a danger to which we are all so subject. They were all these dangers: that of falling into the sea, having a disease that cannot be healed in the middle of the sea without great support or there is a naval war. It is spoken in the pirates. It is in the nineteenth century: the question is above all piracy, misunderstandings in the middle of the sea, maritime wars and are, more or less, without the protection of their home, their brothers, their confreres.
There are other similar trips from some navigators who were alone to Macao and said there were boats that fell off before they arrived, because they didn't go at the right time to avoid bad weather.
Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro Photography
What kind of information do you contain the reports of Father José Joaquim de Miranda and Oliveira?
Father José Joaquim de Miranda and Oliveira's manuscript is relatively short - it is a long trip, from seven months, to Macau, but the report is still relatively brief, in relation to what is happening every day. But it was still seven months to arrive in Macau, there was two years, and then it was almost five months on a trip to Nanjing. The trips were not fast, not only by the means of transport, but also for the situation in relation to Christians. Chinese Christians were afraid of receiving priests because they were persecuted at that time. During the larger trip in Lisbon, the priest tells, in an unpretentious way, what happened. For example, he finds in Manila a Chinese Christian and says "as a persecuted." This information is interesting. Just as, when he arrives in Macao, he says that the bishop was hostile. It is already seen what the situation was and, even reports as simple and small as this, have a lot of linguistic, socio-cultural, historical and interest information to the current.

Is this story totally true or contains some details of fiction?
Yes, it's true. This priest is named Nanjing Vicar General and is there a short time because, on November 1, 1828, he dies with a disease. While this priest, who was the only one who was a priest at the beginning of the trip [of 1825], died, the other two who accompanied him, who survived him, were much more lucky and ended up being both bishops - one from Porto and one from Macao. We know that religious orders had this habit that was thoroughly reporting travel to their religious orders and the king, because it was part of the evangelization strategy. In 1831, other Lazarists came to Macau of Lisbon-one of them was replacing this one, José Joaquim de Miranda and Oliveira, in Nanjing-and this trip again includes some spiritual sayings of the other, some descriptions of one storm, also in the same way, in which benches and cutlery are also in a round wheel. There are some similar references, which show that priests read very carefully everything that had happened before, everything their confreres had already reported and integrated this information, not to copy what they had already said, but for everyone to know and share the information.

This episode that reports here in this book ends up in the course of its widest interest in the grammatical and lexicographic works in Chinese and Portuguese. Do you have other projects in hand right now?
It was a "detail", but it was a curious "detail", because, increasingly, I see that almost all are from priests, almost all have an ecclesiastical source. And this is because, in Portugal, we owe most of the heritage to the ecclesiastical class, the clergy, even the copy of baroque poetry manuscripts, for example. The kitchen cookbooks I have already edited are also from ecclesiastical source - I have published the second oldest kitchen book, so far, which is the Braga District Archive, anonymous, but is certainly a member of the Távora family, under the title “The Kitchen Recipes of a 16th century Portuguese friar”. I edited the work of Joaquim Gonçalves too. I edited the “Book of Properties of the Archbispal Braga table”, which has not yet left - will be four large volumes of the early seventeenth century. It is interesting because Braga's archbishops held land from practically the north of the country to the bishopric of Porto, Santarém and to Galicia. There were so many lands that, when they described the north-south confrontations, this west, we also knew who had the others on all sides. These lands are described in detail, the houses are also described in detail, so that we got to know thousands of names of people of the time, professions, nicknames, which was produced on each earth, because then a forum and pension was given. They were the Bogas of the Pinhão River, the dry and fresh lampreys of Minho. At this point, I am ending a dictionary of Portuguese-Chinese, who say it is from the eighteenth century-may bring material that was from XVI and 17th-of the study of the Portuguese language in historical terms. He is anonymous, but they were certainly the Jesuits and then the Lazarists, between Macau and Beijing, who did. Another dictionary I have already started, but the pandemic later prevented it from completing, is very precious and is in the Library of Old Beijing Books: the seventeenth-century Chinese-Portuguese dictionary. I just started, but let's also edit it. Then I also need to publish, from the kitchen manuscript I said (published the kitchen part, published the medicines) and will now publish the agriculture part and some of the veterinarian, as well as a large glossary of medicine and agriculture.

Are the sources of these works, even the dictionaries to which it refers, are all ecclesiastical?
Yes, dictionaries were made by priests in that strategy of writing their language so that others can learn it next, and also to teach in Macao in the formation of other ecclesiastics for evangelization. They had a structure much more like a glossary, they were not as structured as the current, but they are dictionaries. The only work that is not an ecclesiastical source, and will be published later this year, is the correspondence of the twentieth century pianist, but well known, Eurico Thomaz de Lima, which involves many Portuguese intellectuals, Brazilian, many music figures, but also of literature, painting, fine arts. Then there is the Timorese Oral Tradition literature and I will also publish another collection book, the last time I was in Timor in 2024.

These dictionaries to be referred to, made by priests, are somehow documents that turn out to be little objective and more religious?
Not in that respect. Even Joaquim Afonso Gonçalves, who wrote over 5000 pages in Portuguese and Chinese, made numerous dictionaries and included in them very much information. What happens is that it only chooses examples in which Christian ideology conveys, but in most cases, the examples are from Chinese sources, they are from classic, Confucian and Taoist sources. Ideas such as love for the brother, not killing, respecting his father and mother, will seek the examples not with the Portuguese side, but to the Chinese. The question that asks me has more to do with the entrances - the entrances of dictionaries, which develop a motto or word and sometimes are already religious words, even Christian, which cost to translate into Chinese. Ideas like angel or God have caused great controversy because they are difficult to translate, but they would always be difficult and always require a more or less creative solution by the priests to translate that idea into a different culture with different religions.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Typhoon Matmo obliges the issuance of signal No. 1 between today and Saturday</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/tufao-matmo-obriga-a-emissao-do-sinal-n-o-1-entre-hoje-e-sabado/</link><description>A tropical storm originated from the Philippines, baptized by math, should lead to the emission of the Tropical Storm signal No. 1 in Macao between tonight and early Saturday morning.
According to forecasts published on the website of the Meteorological and Geophysical Services Directorate (SMG), the system is expected to move “relatively fast” towards the island of Hainão and the West Coast of Guangdong. The most close moment in the territory should take place on Sunday, when the system has already evolved from “severe tropical cyclone” to the intensity of “typhoon” and find a distance of less than 300 kilometers.
According to the latest forecasts, the wind in the region should begin to identify itself “significantly” between Saturday night and Sunday, accompanied by strong and occasional showers. Authorities also warn that "some low areas" are particularly affected on Sunday, due to the combination of precipitation with the astronomical tide, although they warn of possible "changes in the trajectory and intensity of the tropical storm."
Regarding temperatures, a slight descent is expected to be minimal and maximum for 24 and 29 degrees Celsius, respectively, on Sunday. The next day, the weather should be “very hot” again in the region, with the thermometer reaching temperatures equal to or greater than 33 degrees Celsius.
Considering the current trajectory of the system, it is expected to lose intensity after reaching the Guangdong coast and end up dissipating in Yunnan province early next week.
The SMG had already warned of the probable passage of one or two tropical storms in the first half of October, after the impact of Super Typhoon Ragasa in late September. This is the fourth tropical storm since 2008 to receive the name MATM, which means “heavy rain” in Chamorro, an Austronesia spoken in Guam and other nearby islands.</description><pubDate>2025-10-02 22:50:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Earthquake that hit the Philippines has already caused 72 dead</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/sismo-que-atingiu-as-filipinas-ja-causou-72-mortos/</link><description>The death toll in the earthquake that hit the Philippines on Tuesday rose to 72, yesterday announced emergency services, which now focus on helping hundreds of injured and thousands of displaced.
Firefighters and rescue teams said they had removed the bodies of a woman and a child from the rubble of a hotel that collapsed in the city of Bogo, near the epicenter of the magnitude 6.9 earthquake on the Richter scale.
Another woman's body was also found at the scene on Wednesday, journalists from the France-Presse news agency advanced. The previous balance pointed to 69 deadly victims.
The epicenter of the earthquake was located at sea, near the island of Cebu, in the central part of the archipelago, on Tuesday at 21:59, at local time, according to the United States geological service.
More than 300 secondary tremors have already reached the region, according to the Filipino Institute of Vulcanology and Seismology, slowing rescue efforts.
The government reported that 294 people were injured and about 20,000 fled home, and almost 600 dwellings were destroyed in the north of Cebu Island, forcing many residents to sleep in the open.
Cebu province governor Pamela Baricuatro launched yesterday an appeal for help for thousands of families needing drinking water, food, clothing and shelter. “Many houses have been destroyed and many families need help to recover… they need our help, our prayers and our support,” Baricuatro wrote on Facebook social network.
President Filipino, Ferdinand Marcos Jr., visited Cebu yesterday to inspect the damage and coordinate help efforts. The head of state presented “sincere condolences to bereaved families” and promised quick help to the affected.
According to CEBU's civil protection, more than 110,000 people in 42 communities affected by the earthquake need assistance, especially to rebuild houses and recover subsistence means.
The recent passage of the Bualoi and Typhoon Ragasa storm had already caused about 40 dead in recent days in the Philippine archipelago.</description><pubDate>2025-10-02 22:44:33</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea's search for a strong and nuclear state: implications for the safety of Northeast Asia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/a-busca-da-coreia-do-norte-por-um-estado-forte-e-nuclear-implicacoes-para-a-seguranca-do-nordeste-asiatico/</link><description>Analyzing the speech given by Kim Jong Un at the 13th Session of the 14th Supreme Popular Assembly and judging by the recent development of Pyongyang's Nuclear Weapons Program, the search for North Korea not only strong, but also nuclear has huge implications for safety relations in Northeastern Northeast between the ideological coalition between North Korea and China and China and Alliance between the US, Japan and South Korea, on the one hand, and the military pact between North Korea and Russia and the US military coalition, Japan and South Korea, on the other.

Kim's speech is marked by the perceived success of Byungjin policy (economic and nuclear development), saying, first of all, North Korea progressed in complying with its five -year economic plan. Agricultural production is expected to reach the national cereal production target, followed by reforms such as the seed revolution, duo harvesting, scientific agriculture and mechanized agriculture. Construction and industrial production were driven, with the rapid development of the skills of heavy and light industries. Megaprojects such as the Tanchon Electric Center and the Ryongsong Industrial Complex were accelerated and renewed.

According to Kim, the life of the population improved with the construction of 50 000 apartments in the capital Pyongyang, accompanied by the construction of Wonsan Kalma's coastal tourist area. Pyongyang General Hospital is almost completed and about to be inaugurated, while public health facilities have been improved in several cities and countless. Kim claimed great successes in the areas of science, education, public health, arts and sports development, making the North Korean state stronger than ever.

His speech then went into the area of ​​defense capabilities of the North Korean state, adding that the country must defend its maritime sovereignty and reinforce its maritime power. Kim stated that "we have new secret weapons and have achieved many made in the science of defense, which will greatly contribute to reinforcing our military forces more radically (KCNA, September 23, 2025: Speech by the respected comrade Kim Jong Un at the 13th Supreme Popular Assembly of the RPDC (Oananews.org).

Economic growth and increased military force, according to Kim, are of enormous importance because they illustrate "the spiritual strength of the people, the driving force and the preparation of political-ideological force." In Kim's mind, North Korea can solve all its problems “through ideology and political offensive”, using strong leadership and defending patriotism and heroism expressed by the North Korean soldiers who sacrificed their lives in the war between Russia and Ukraine.
Kim emphasized the role of the people in the construction of North Korean socialism and criticized those who took the quotas of farmers under the pretext of marketing cereals through illegal channels. He praised the revolutionary spirit and the loyalty of the masses, but criticized the economic employees who are "working subjectively, acting on impulse, egocentrism, pursuit of fame, irresponsibility and incompetence." Kim's goals are to purge and eliminate these selfish and incompetent staff, while releasing the full potential of masses and elites, thus serving the North Korean state in a sincere and effective way. Their demands on North Korean bureaucrats are high and clear, especially when he criticized the "low quality of housing construction" in Songchon in 2024 during an inspection visit to the city. Adopting a style of government -oriented government, Kim developed a convention to make inspection visits to different cities and counties, verifying the performance of government officials in the implementation of several megaprojects.

For Kim, compulsory 12-year education is essential to prepare students to be more advanced in their knowledge and contribute to the North Korean state, as well as teachers, who need continuous training and socialization. At the same time, the socialist legal system aims to improve the role of law in state and social life, making all sectors more agile in its functioning and placing them 'under rigorous control'. Law application bodies should make a better strategy by adopting "an aggressive, comprehensive and rigorous approach" in order to "frustrate the enemy's actions to undermine our citizens and combat all kinds of crimes that disturb social and political stability". In short, the law is a tool for social control, while law agencies should prevent perceived enemies from destabilizing North Korea.

Kim then went on to the important theme of the use of military reinforcement as "powerful war dissuator." He praised the martyrs who died and who were "setting out" Kursk and appreciated the enthusiasm of young people and middle-aged people to voluntarily enlist in the army. All these sacrifices have shown a "growing and positive tendency to participate in the patriotic struggle, betting on the dignity of Koreans and the reputation of Korea." He said the Workers Party and the State assume full responsibility for taking care of the life of martyrs, returning the donations of ordinary people who expressed their patriotism to build the Memorial Museum and the Memorial Monument.

The most interesting part of Kim's speech is his detailed discussion about the US, South Korea and Japan, which have "a decisive impact on the safety of our state and on the situation in the region." He sees the security situation around the Korean peninsula as "a worse record after another." This perception is attributable to the US and its "vassal states", implying both South Korea and Japan without named them, because they "have" regularly committed provocative actions to exacerbate tension. " Kim referred here to the US Indo-Pacific strategy, the US Military Alliances of South and USA-Japan, the US-Japan-Japan-South Corea Military Cooperation System, and the various US and South Korea exercises in March and August of each year. Kim considers large -scale joint war exercises such as Ulji Freedom Shield, such as South Korea and North Korea activities. He criticized the US and South Korea nuclear war plans, stating that they enter a phase of "more practical and concrete implementation." The recent 'nuclear war rehearsal', called Iron Mace, between the US and South Korea was considered by Kim as 'a way to familiarize themselves with the procedures and the way of attacking our state with nuclear weapons'. Multirregional joint military exercise with the participation of Japan was also perceived by Kim as a hostile act directed to North Korea. At the same time, Japan witnessed "lightning implantation of the medium -range missile system based on the land of US forces for the first time in its history." This poses a risk to North Korea's safety, according to Kim.

Kim used all these measures taken by the US, South Korea and Japan to portray a 'more serious' situation, with the increase in the 'war prevention index'. Thus, the North Korean nuclear forces are "fully and perfectly performing their deterrent function" in response to the challenges and provocative actions of the abroad. The rapid development of North Korea's nuclear deterrent is a necessity, according to Kim, to defend its territorial integrity, national sovereignty and the life and security of the people.

As a politically cunning leader, Kim said North Korea needs to prepare for "both dialogue and confrontation." He recalled his good relations with US President Trump, but Kim stated that the appeal to "denuclearization" has already lost its meaning. The reason is that North Korea has already become "a nuclear state." After all, the "supreme law" of North Korea enshrines "our nuclear possession." Asking North Korea to accept 'denuclearization' is to go against its constitution, according to Kim. He said, "We will never resign our nuclear weapons," while the sanctions imposed by "hostile forces" taught North Korea to become stronger militarily. Kim believes that time is on the side of North Korea, which has already strengthened its economy along with the development policy of its nuclear weapons program.

Kim noted that North Korea and South Korea are two "completely" different states, with South Korea's historical "hostility" in relation to Pyongyang dating back to Syngman Rhee regime in 1948, which saw the northern neighbor as an enemy. Kim Jong Un added that North Korea defined the Republic of Korea (Rok) as "a foreign country and the most hostile state." For Kim, Rok is "an entity deformed to hemiplegia and a colonial tributary whose fields were all Americanized." Although recently formed Lee Jae Myung's government, he talked about dialogue and peace with North Korea, Kim said that behind the scenes, the Lee regime is "building an even louder confrontation wall, expanding and strengthening warmths for aggression, such as nuclear operations exercises and joint militarial exercises in various domains." Instead of pursuing 'unification by absorption', South Korea recently mentioned its peaceful coexistence with North Korea, Kim noted. He criticized the so -called denuclearization theory in three stages of Lee - suspension, reduction and denuclearization. Kim maintained that reunification cannot be reached less than one of two states ceases to exist. As such, he saw the reunification between the two Korea as a zero sum game.

Kim Jong Un's important speech can be analyzed from the perspective of the complex relations between the North Russian Korea Military Alliance and the US-Japan-South Coreia Alliance, on the one hand, and between North Kina Korea and the US-Japan-Japan ideological alliance, on the other.

Firstly, Kim's conviction that denuclearization should be abandoned by both the US and South Korea means that he sees North Korea as a de facto nuclear state. According to reports, North Korea has 2,000 kg (about 4,400 pounds) of highly enriched uranium with a 90%purity, and the uranium centrifuges in operation in four locations would be able to produce about 47 nuclear pumps, considering that 42 kg of highly enriched uranium is required for a nuclear weapon (Aljazeera, September 25, 2025). No wonder Kim expects US President Trump to leave the appeal to denuclearization as he believes North Korea has already become a nuclear power.
Secondly, North Korea's negotiation power is therefore reinforced to deal with any dialogue with the US and/or South Korea. Unlike the situation in 2018, when Trump met Kim in Singapore to forge a short approach between the two countries, North Korea in 2025 is a much stronger state with almost total capacity to produce nuclear weapons. Seeing how the US Air Force bombarded and attacked three nuclear facilities in Iran in June 2025 and how the US prevented the development of the capacity of Iran from building a nuclear weapon, North Korea is now increasing its ability to produce nuclear weapons to such an extent that Trump is probably or later, will start a dialogue with Kim. Such dialogue will not be easy, because North Korea is increasing its negotiation power by reinforcing its military capabilities.

Thirdly, Kim repeatedly warns his speech on military exercises between the US, Japan and South Korea, which means such "war rehearsals" will probably cause North Korea further. The implication here is that any US dialogue with North Korea would have to discuss the issue of reducing tensions by reducing military exercises between the US, Japan and South Korea. However, reducing the number of these exercises will probably lead to the risk of a poor response to the rapid and successful North Korean military strengthening, without mentioning any sudden conflict between North Korea and the alliance USA-Japan-South Corea.

Fourthly, the ideological perception of Japan and South Korea as US "vassal" states and Seoul as an "Americanized" regime tends to solidify the military preparation of North Korea. South Korea is seen as a "hostile" state under American hegemony and "colonialism". Such a perception will probably prevent any discussion about the interactions between peoples, not to mention bilateral trade, between North Korea and South Korea in the long run. As Kim sees North Korea and South Korea as two "completely different" states, both sides will not easily notice their relationships due to deep ideological differences and serious gaps of perception.

Fifth, Kim's recent participation in China's military chart on September 3, along with Russian President Putin, showed that North Korea has adopted double diplomacy to deal with the Military Alliance between the US, Japan and South Korea. Kursk Region, North Korea is committed to training its armed forces through royal battlefield experiences, to learn the most advanced technology of Russian and war missiles and drones, and to improve Pyongyang's military preparation in case of any military conflict with the US -led military alliance with South Korea and Japan. For North Korea economically, while the military pact with Russia can bring huge Pyongyang recipes through its military weapon exports to help Russia in its war with Ukraine. The mutually advantageous military pact between North Korea and Russia and economically beneficial relations between North Korea and China will be able to consolidate the parallel development of the Nuclear Weapons Program and Economic Modernization, thus leading to the success of North Korea's Byungjin policy. The success of Kim's byungjin politics consolidates the legitimacy of its regime internally and externally, in view of the perceived military threats of the US-Japan-Japan-South Coreia alliance.

In sixth place, although Lee Jae Myung's South Korean government is committed to improving bilateral relations with North Korea, the rapid development of the North Korea Nuclear Weapons Program and its increasingly strong, which has dealt with the economy and subsistence of the population in an assertive and successful manner, point to a difficult relationship between North and South. The reunification is now seen as a zero sum, which means that the two Koreas will have quite different ways of development from the previous reunification of East Germany and West Germany in October 1990.

Seventh, an improvement in relations between North Korea and the US-Japan-Japan-Japan Alliance will still depend on the initiatives taken by the current Trump administration. However, “denuclearization”, which was a theme in the 2018 summit between Kim and Trump, was a thing from the past to Kim. The South Korean idea of ​​suspension-reduction-disqualification is also not viable in Kim Jong Un. Since Kim emphasized military exercises between the US, Japan, and South Korea in their speech, these 'war rehearsals' will probably be an important issue to negotiate if Trump meets Kim for a security dialogue.
In eighth place, the sending of the North Korean army to the Kursk region seems to have multiple objectives. It was a military diplomacy adopted by Kim to conquer Russia's military friendship, to obtain advanced Russian missile and drone technology, and train the North Korean military with a high conscience of always being prepared for war. This awareness of crisis in the North Korean armed psyche is necessary because, in the event of sudden military conflicts between Pyongyang and Seoul, Pyongyang would probably have a strong performance, even if Seoul is and continues to be supported militarily by Washington.

Ninth, North Korea's relationships with Japan tend to be difficult and potentially conflicting. The two countries are involved in disputes, such as the alleged kidnapping of Japanese citizens by North Korea, the frequent North Korean missile tests that alarmed the Japanese side and the recent allegation that North Korean hackers stole cryptocurrency of the Japanese Bitcoin bag in 2024. Kim, in his speech, expressed his concern about the implementation of the implementation of the implementation of US medium -range missile system in Japan - a theme that will probably be another negotiable issue in the case of a summit between Trump and Kim. However, to protect its own sovereignty and security, Japan must have the US missile system as a defensive act. If US missile parking in Japan is seen as a zero -summed game by stakeholders, it will probably be a difficult theme in any dialogue between Trump and Kim.

Sometheres, if North Korea is now much stronger military and economically stronger than during the 2018 summit between Kim and Trump, US diplomacy in Asian northeast faces huge trial. Blaming Biden administration for its 'weakness' regarding the safety of the Asian Northeast is useless. Instead, proactive US diplomacy in the Asian Northeast should consider a gradual process of reduction of tensions, followed by how the International Atomic Energy Agency can be involved in the complex board for inspection and monitoring of North Korea's nuclear development activities.

In conclusion, Kim Jong Un has said that North Korea is now a de facto nuclear state. With a growing ability to produce nuclear weapons and improved economy, in a context of emphasis on improving the population's living conditions, North Korea's influence on the US has been significantly reinforced in any dialogue and negotiation between Kim Jong Un and Donald Trump. Seeing the military exercises and the implementation of missiles in the US-Japan-South Coreia Alliance as a serious threat to the safety of North Korean state survival, Kim Jong united North Korean military potential through the north-Korean military to the war between Russia and Ukraine and through the exchange of military technology and experiences of war between Pyongyang and the exchange of war experiences and Moscow. The military pact between North Korea and Russia reinforced Pyongyang's military weapons exports to Moscow, improved its military preparation for conflicts and wars on the Korean Peninsula and urged a permanent crisis awareness in the North Korean Armed Forces psyche. If so, early dialogue between Donald Trump and Kim Jong un will be diplomatically imperative and politically desirable if all stakeholders are eager to maintain peace and security in the Korean peninsula in a mutually beneficial way rather than a zero -sum perceived way.</description><pubDate>2025-10-02 22:39:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao and Poland artists present a project on linguistic diversity in Berlin</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/artistas-de-macau-e-polonia-apresentam-projecto-sobre-diversidade-linguistica-em-berlim/</link><description>Old Tempelhof Airport, a history of the Cold War in Berlin, will be the scene next Sunday, October 5, of an artistic collaboration that wanders on the theme of linguistic diversity that characterizes the German capital. Artist duo Marta Stanisława Sala and Cheong Kin Man, both with connections to Macau, Poland, Portugal and Germany, presents “Neukölln trans-lingual”, an initiative that seeks to dismantle linguistic barriers and reimaginate “translingism” as a shared cultural good.
Neukölln district, whose name literally means “new colony” in German, forged its identity through decades of migration and today welcomes more than 100 languages. Many of them were studied and practiced by Cheong Kin Man in Berlin, making the city's multilingual panorama part of the pair's artistic process.
From 12h00 to 18h00 on the 5th and October, the public is invited to participate in the “Translingue Game”, “Poetry Workshop” and “Final Happening” at the main entrance of Tempelof Airport, at Herrfurth Street. Through gesture, sound imitation and transcultural symbols, participants will improvise a shared translingual experience - not to establish a universal language, but to discover the intersections of intercultural communication, according to artists. The event culminates at 6.30 pm with a pop-up exhibition of 12 textile work at Mayer Pavilion, on Kienitz Street.
This project represents the latest incarnation of a collaboration that began within the collective of artists “Arbeitspause” in Berlin. Since 2021, the duo have developed linguistic experiments through various initiatives, including “The Ideograms of Berlin” and “Orthopedic House of Language”.
Cheong Kin Man's international trajectory also includes the presentation of his short film “A Useless Fiction-The Answer” at the 3rd Contemporary Film Show in Portuguese in Maputo, Mozambique, next October 8th. The film, which integrates materials from Portuguese photographer Jorge Veiga Alves with images from the Macao sovereignty transfer period, represents a new phase of collaborative work between Cheong and Marta Sala.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Hotel occupancy rate rose in August</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/taxa-de-ocupacao-hoteleira-subiu-em-agosto/</link><description>The average occupancy rate of hotel stations in the hotel establishments in August set at 92.9% (+1.5 percentage points in annual terms) and hotel establishments hosted 1,303,000 individuals (+3.0%). According to the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), the number of entries of visitors who arrived on excursions to Macau was 162,000, with variations of -18.8%, compared to August 2024, and +7.4%, compared to July 2025, adds DSEC.
At the end of August 2025 there were 147 hotel establishments that provided public accommodation services (+3, in annual terms), providing a total of 45,000 guest rooms (+1.3%). In the reference month, the average occupancy rate of guest rooms was 92.9%, plus 1.5 percentage points, in annual terms. It should also be noted that the occupancy rate of 5 -star hotels (95.7%) and 4 -star hotels (88.2%) rose 2.2 and 1.6 percentage points, respectively, while that of 3 -star hotels (89.9%) decreased 0.9 percentage points.
During August, hotel establishments hosted 1,303,000 individuals, plus 3.0%in annual terms. The number of guests in the interior of China (991,000) rose 2.4% in relation to August of the previous year, and that of international guests (87,000) increased by 20.3%. It is noteworthy that the number of guests from Thailand (8,000) registered a homologation of 157.7%. The number of South Korean guests (28,000), Japan (10,000), Singapore (5,000) and Malaysia (5,000) grew 6.0%, 58.2%, 36.2%and 29.2%, respectively, compared to August 2024, however, the number of guests from India (5,000) decreased 5.7%. In the month under analysis the average permanence period of guests remained at 1.6 nights, refers to DSEC.
The number of visitors from visitors who arrived at excursions to MSAR in August was 162,000, 18.8%less in annual terms. It should also be noted that the number of visitors from visitors at excursions from the interior of China (142,000) descended 24%, while international visitors in excursions (14,000) grew 30.2%.
In the first eight months of this year, the average occupancy rate of hotel -stained guest rooms corresponded to 89.8%, plus 4.3 percentage points, compared to the identical period of the previous year. Hotel establishments hosted 9,791,000 individuals (plus 0.1%) and the average permanence period of guests remained at 1.7 nights. For its turn, the number of visitors from visitors who arrived on excursions to Macao equivalent to 1,280,000 in the first eight months of this year, observing a homologous drop of 6.1%. However, the number of international visitors entries in excursions (143,000) grew 11.7%, compared to the same period of 2024, the DSEC concludes.</description><pubDate>2025-10-02 22:48:13</pubDate></item><item><title>André Cheong promises commitment to alive regardless of office</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/andre-cheong-promete-empenho-na-al-independentemente-do-cargo/</link><description>André Cheong, current secretary for administration and justice and appointed deputy, promised to dedicate his political experience in the future work of Hemiciclo. Without giving a direct response to the possible position of president of the Legislative Assembly, André Cheong emphasized that he would do his best in any function within the legislature. Two other secretaries and the nominated prosecutor are also confident of taking on new responsibilities.

The current Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, spoke for the first time after his appointment as a deputy to the new legislature of the Legislative Assembly, leaving his thanks to the confidence of the central government and the chief executive, as well as the civil servants and the general public.
André Cheong, who will take office as deputy of the Legislative Assembly on 16 of this month, guaranteed his commitment and commitment to the work of the legislative body, taking advantage of his experience in public administration and in court to promote a more positive interaction between the executive and legislative powers ”.
On the sidelines of the reception of the anniversary celebration of the Implementation of the RPC, André Cheong said that he is doing the transfer of work with the secretary to the administration and justice, Wong Sio Chak, to ensure a quiet transition in the protection of administration and justice.
André Cheong's passage from the Executive to the Hemiciclo has raised speculation that he eventually becomes the next president of the Legislative Assembly, succeeding the position of Kou Hoi In, who is leaving the legislative body for retirement reasons.
Asked by journalists about the possibility of aspiring to the presidency of the Legislative Assembly, André Cheong did not give a direct response, merely stating that, according to the Legislative Assembly Regiment, the president is elected by all deputies. "Regardless of my position in the Legislative Assembly, I will dedicate myself totally to the fulfillment of my duties in the hemiciclo," he noted.
It is recalled that André Cheong currently holds the position of secretary, in addition to working simultaneously the duties of member and spokesman for the Executive Board and permanent deputy chief of the Management Committee of the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin. In this sense, he confessed that his functions “will be consequent changes” when he begins to be a deputy from October 16 this month.
At the same time, other holders of the main positions and the newly appointed prosecutor also expressed gratitude to the confidence of the central government and the chief executive, stating that they will continue to fulfill their duty with competence and responsibility in new positions.
Wong Sio Chak, the current secretary for security that will replace André Cheong in the leadership of the Administration and Justice folder, said that work in the next four years will be prioritized by the reform of public administration, the best management of municipal affairs and national integration.
Already Chan Tsz King, current prosecutor and future secretary for security, said he was confident that he could quickly adapt to his new position. He has ensured that he will “follow the nuclear spirit of 'a country' that is the assumption for 'two systems', placing above all the defense of sovereignty, security and interests of national development,” he said.
The current president of the Second Instance Court and the upcoming prosecutor, Tong Hio Fong, in turn assured that he will place a greater requirement to the team of magistrates regarding compliance with the law, respect for disciplinary rules and integrity. It also revealed that more than twenty bailiffs will complete the training course in September next year, whose entry to service may relieve the overload of current workers, as well as increase judicial effectiveness.</description><pubDate>2025-10-02 22:56:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Government advances with projects of sino-slyphone cooperation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/governo-avanca-com-projectos-de-cooperacao-sino-lusofona/</link><description>The government plans to further advance cooperation with Lusophone countries through various business projects. The Chief Executive revealed that he is working to create the Center for Economic and Commercial Services between China and Portuguese -speaking (and Spanish -speaking) countries, as well as the establishment of a China -PORTUGUESE ECONOMIC AND COMMERCIAL DEVELOPMENT FUND, with an initial amount of billion of Renminbis.
The projects were presented by Sam Hou Fai in his speech given at the reception of the celebration of the 76th anniversary of the Implementation of the Popular Republic of China, last Wednesday, which was attended by 1,320 guests. The government leader has assumed that Macau will thus play the role of “precision interlocutor” in the context of cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries.
The plan to create the Syno-Lusophone Economic Services Center was started by the government in March this year, in order to start operations by the end of the year, offering training, internal and external resources correspondence, consulting, linguistic translation, legal services and financial audit. The center will be managed together by Macau and Hengqin.
In addition to projects related to sino-illusophone cooperation, Sam Hou Fai said this quarter was expected to operate in full facial recognition automatic channels, which do not require the display of identification document in the port of Hengqin, facilitating the development synergy between Macao and Hengqin.
In his speech about RPC National Day, Sam Hou Fai was quite optimistic to the national and Macao development, stressing that China presents this year a stability and an innovative vitality of the economy and society and the “national power is increasingly strong”.
"Macau will take advantage of the opportunities for national development to continue to achieve a new conjuncture of high quality development in the" country, two systems "principle, and commit to commitment to the desired perspective of a macao based on the rule of law, dynamic, cultural and happy," he said.
At the same time, Sam Hou Fai did not forget the compliments to Macao's current situation, saying that Macao's socioeconomic development presents a “stable and positive evolution” and moves to a new phase of high quality development recovery, “managing to safeguard its harmony and global stability”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-02 22:49:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Government remodeling aims to reinforce executive-legislative cooperation, says Sam Hou Fai</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/remodelacao-governamental-visa-reforcar-cooperacao-executivo-legislativo-diz-sam-hou-fai/</link><description>The chief executive said that the remodeling of the government aims to reinforce interaction and cooperation between the executive and legislative powers, responding to “unprecedented changes” of internal and external circumstances. Sam Hou Fai said he believed that the transfer of the current Secretary to Justice, André Cheong, to the Legislative Assembly will allow to “better coordinate the legislative work” of the region. On the other hand, the local government leader predicts that the official visit to Portugal and Spain can be completed in the first half of next year.

The series of changes in holders of the main positions of the recently announced government aims to “strengthen executive-legislative cooperation”, argues the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, who even explained André Cheong's transfer to the Legislative Assembly as appointed deputy and the nominations of new secretaries.
The government revealed on Monday the remodeling of the governing team, as well as the appointment of seven deputies for the hemiciclo, which provides for the departure of the current secretary for administration and justice, André Cheong, of the executive. It was the first time in the history of Macao that a secretary passes to deputy, and is dismissed without having made a serious mistake or other exceptional circumstances.
Sam Hou Fai, who presented the proposal for dismissal and appointment to the State Council, ensured that he made the decision “having as consideration the future development of the territory”. The government leader said he hopes "continuously reinforce executive-legislative cooperation and promote better interaction, boosting Macao's growth."
The chief executive approached the matter for the first time on the occasion of National Day, celebrated on Wednesday, adding that he invited the secretary to Administration and Justice to perform the functions of deputy in the new legislature.
"[Your] vast experience will bring in the future, during the process of elaboration of policies and even debates in the Legislative Assembly, greater positive interaction and narrow communication between the executive and legislative powers, in order to better coordinate the legislative work and respond to the expectations of the various sectors of society," he said.
He also highlighted the need for the Government and the Legislative Assembly to continue to reinforce “communication, coordination and positive interaction” as they perform their functions according to their legal responsibilities.
Sam Hou Fai, by the way, reiterated that Macau is undergoing a "drastic acceleration of unprecedented centenary changes" to internal and external levels, so the new adjustment and positioning of administration are considered as "pragmatic responses" with "the innovative approach and the reformist determination" for Macau to enter the next phase of transformation.
Already the decision to appoint deputies to the Hemiciclo, especially that of André Cheong, implies changes in some holders of the main positions, pointed out the ruler. Sam Hou Fai stressed that, therefore, the current Secretary for Security, Wong Sio Chak, will become a secretary for Administration and Justice, while the position of Secretary for Security will be performed by the current prosecutor, Chan Tsz King, whose position will be assumed by the current president of the second instance court, Tong Hio Fong.
In addition, the chief executive recalled that the new legislature of the Legislative Assembly is now complete with a total of 33 elected deputies, by direct and indirect roads, and appointed.
He argued that the appointment of seven deputies has “greater representativeness”, since they come from the areas of Administration, Legal, Science and Technology, Culture, Teaching, among other areas, which will “better promote diversified and adequate growth of the local economy, reinforce the management of public function, strengthen the creation of the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin, and promote the science and technology industry in Macau”, he said.

Travel to Portugal
 
Regarding the trip to Portugal, which was postponed several times, Sam Hou Fai has now advanced that he is “confident” that he can visit Portugal in the first half of next year.
The plan of this official visit, with destinations scheduled for Portugal and Spain, was announced in April this year, when Sam Hou Fai said the trip was scheduled for the first half of this year. The government later marked the visit to last September, with certain dates, however, was canceled without a new date.
"Due to various matters of the Government of MSAR, it was not possible to realize this visit yet," said Sam, adding that he was busy with the presentation of the first lines of governing action (LAG) and the legislative elections, and is now preparing the preparation of LAG for 2026. The official also recalled that the elections in Portugal imply changes in the sovereign organs of that country, which implies a difficult coordination of marking marking visit ”.
To journalists, Sam Hou Fai assured that Portugal has always been the first destination that pondered to visit abroad and that the visit "was always being prepared and coordinated." The government leader added that he also expressed this will to Luis Montenegro, Prime Minister of Portugal, during his visit to Macau last month, and the contacts and programming work “were always maintained”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-02 22:58:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Moon Festival</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/festival-da-lua/</link><description>The Moon Festival (in Chinese 中秋節), also known as the Fall Middle Festival, Lunar Cake Party or Lantern Party is the second most relevant celebration for Chinese culture after the Chinese New Year. As with the holidays of most Chinese festivities, the date of the Moon Festival is determined using the lunar calendar, celebrated on the 15th day of the 8th month of that calendar (mid -September or early October in the Gregorian calendar).
Despite its introduction as an official holiday in China to date back to the Tang Dynasty, it was in the Song dynasty that its celebration gained prominence in the local culture. More recently, in 2006, the Moon Festival was declared intangible cultural heritage by the Chinese government.
The lunar cake is the delicacy that characterizes the festival. Although the traditional lunar cake fits in the palm, with a rounded shape and about 10 centimeters diameter, as a rule its tasting is made in thin slices. With a dense mass, your filling usually consists of a thick paste of lotus or bean seeds, and may contain inside a duck egg yolk (remembering the full moon). On the shelves of Macau bakeries we can see hundreds of lunar cake boxes, which are the most popular cards. Others with an exclusive design, using noble materials such as metal or wood, ornate with thorough engravings alluding to the occasion, many worthy of artwork. Inside the lunar cakes, with the traditional filling or, for the boldest, exotic fillings such as ice cream, chocolate, dried fruit paste,…
Macao… always party. This time, the streets and alleys of the region are filled with colorful and luminous lanterns. On the night's eve of the holiday, families gather to the traditional Agape and later, when the moon is already high, heading for strategic moon contemplation points in scenarios such as the beach, mountain, lakes or gardens.
The atmosphere is of joy, with the family together, children run and play the ferry flashlights, grandparents and children share the cake between laughs and the moon loud, in its heyday, round and shining illuminates this party, because she is the queen of the night. It's the moon party.</description><pubDate>2025-10-02 22:40:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Casinos recipes go down in September</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/receitas-dos-casinos-descem-em-setembro/</link><description>After the record revenues recorded in August, September closes with 18.3 billion Patacas, reveals the Directorate of Inspection and Coordination of Games (DICJ). September thus becomes the second less profitable month for Macao casinos in 2025, despite a slight 6% recovery in homologous terms. In the first nine months of the year, the game industry has already faced 181.34 billion Patacas.

Macao casinos ended September with gross revenues of 18.3 billion patacas - the second lowest value of the year, exceeded only by April. Data were the day before yesterday provided by the Directorate of Inspection and Game Coordination (DICJ).
The September figure represents a decrease of about 17.5% compared to the previous month of August, when casinos made 22.15 billion of patacas and hit the postpandeia record. This monthly decline was already expected by Deutsche Bank Securities Inc analysts, who in early September anticipated a 11.2% decrease between two months.
For its part, Seaport Research Partners consultant warned of the possible interference of weather phenomena in the region, similar to what happened in September 2024 with the passage of Super Typhoon Yagi. This less optimistic perspective eventually came to fruition with Super Tufão Ragasa, the worst registered storm in the world this year, which passed through Macao on September 24 and forced the issue of signal 10 for a record 10.5 hours.
Still, analysts estimated that September's results were to record an increase in the order of 13% compared to last year's same period-which, it is recalled, was the least that made the least throughout 2024. According to the data provided by DICJ, growth was more modest than initially predicted, being 6%.
Looking for the last 15 years, and excluding the atypical years of the pandemic, it appears that it is usual to verify a slight decrease between August and September-month marked by the end of summer and the return to class. On the other hand, October is often highlighted by a significant recovery compared to September, a phenomenon that is justified with the “golden week” of the holidays of National Day of China and the end of the typhoons.
Last year, gross October game revenues hit the pre-pound records with a figure of 20.8 billion patacas-a nearly 21% climb over the previous month of September. This record was declined by May, June, July and August 2025.
This year, the game industry could benefit from the arrival of 1.2 million visitors from the interior of China between October 1 and 8, according to the latest forecasts of the Tourism Services Directorate (STD).

59 billion passes left to achieve government objectives

In terms of accumulated revenue, between January and September this year the casinos got about 181.34 billion patacas, ie 7.1% more compared to what they had raised in the same period last year.
The base budget prepared by the previous MSAR government to 2025 estimated that game revenues this year reach 240 billion patacas. After an beginning of the year below expectations, the current government presented a budget review with the forecast of 228 billion Patacas, which casinos should reach before the end of the year if the current pace are kept.
Consultant Seport Research Partners predicts, by the way, that the growth of gross game recipes intensify in the second half of the year, a period marked by more holidays and a vast program of concerts and sports events (such as national games).
Last year, gross game revenues rose to 226.7 billion patacas, an increase of about 24% compared to the 183 billion 2023. These values, although significant, continue short of the revenues prior to pandemic: in 2018, for example, the game sector obtained revenues of 302.8 billion patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-10-02 22:55:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Government discusses future lines of action in combating cybercrime</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/governo-discute-futuras-linhas-de-accao-no-combate-ao-cibercrime/</link><description>The Cybersecurity Commission gathered this Monday at the Government headquarters to analyze the 2024 Activities Report and outline the lines of action in the face of the increase in cybership in the territory. The meeting was attended by the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, who emphasized the need to adopt “concrete measures” to prevent risks, especially with the approach of national games. The Judicial Police had already pointed out in September that cyber security is increasingly “complex”, involving data violations, cyber extortion and online fraud.

The government is intensifying its cybersecurity strategy in the face of increased digital threats in the territory. At the Plenary Meeting of the Commission for Cybersecurity, held Monday at the Government headquarters, the next steps were discussed to combat the current situation, after being revealed that the average number of cyberatocations directed to essential systems increased 8.6% in 2024 to 6,300 daily attempts.
The chairman of the commission, the chief executive Sam Hou Fai, warned of nature “increasingly complicated” of the cybersecurity landscape, stressing that this is “a fundamental guarantee to safeguard national security, the harmony and stability of society and the welfare of the general public”. The statements arise in a context of growing concern for cyber crimes, including data violations, extortion and online fraud.
One of the focal points of the meeting was the preparation for the 15th edition of the National Games and Special Olympic Games for Disabled, scheduled for the end of the year. The Chief Executive instructed the services to “firmly implement cybersecurity safeguarding measures” to ensure the safe operation of competition systems and essential services to the population.
The government's strategy involves reinforcing regional cooperation, with the Judicial Police revealing plans to intensify collaboration with Guangdong and Hong Kong in the exchange of qualified frames and technological innovation. This tripartite approach aims to promote data transfrance of data and strengthen joint defenses against cyber threats.
The chief executive also emphasized the need for all services to persist in “thinking based on more unfavorable situations”, taking concrete measures to prevent and proactively resolve various risks of cybersecurity. This preventive approach aims to ensure the long -term sustainable development of computer technology at MSAR.
At the plenary meeting, the members of the Commission appreciated the “General Cyberrseness Report of the Year 2024” and discussed various topics about the work of cybersecurity, having negotiated and defined the objectives and concrete plans of the following tasks. The secretaries present spoke about the situation of the work linked to cybersecurity in their respective areas and the guidance of the work to be developed in the future.
The committee's vice-president, the Secretary for Security Wong Sio Chak, presented the balance of 2024 activities, while the cybersecurity alert and response center detailed the annual report, which included alert notifications to critical infrastructure operators and 38 incident reports, of which 12 were classified as cybers.
The Substitute Director of the Judicial Police, Lai Man Vai, had already warned of a recent forum that the territory should adopt a “worse scenario preparation mentality”, considering cybersecurity as a “life force” of the digital age that involves not only technical safeguards, but also “national security, economic development and social stability”.
The Cyberrsecurity Law came into force in 2019, establishing a preventive governance. The Cybersecurity Incident Alert and Response Center operates under the aegis of the Judicial Police, coordinating the responses to digital threats in the territory. Monday's meeting was attended by all secretaries, as well as representatives of the central government connection office, including Huang Liuquan, technical advisor to national security issues.</description><pubDate>2025-10-02 22:51:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Eighth Round of I Liga Promises Frantic Sunday in Dragon and Alvalade</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/oitava-ronda-da-i-liga-promete-domingo-frenetico-no-dragao-e-em-alvalade/</link><description>FC Porto seeks on Sunday to keep the perfect start at the First Football League and reinforce the lead in the classic with Benfica, with Sporting lurking at the Sporting Braga reception on the eighth journey.

Ronda promises to be one of the most frantic of the 2025/26 edition of the championship, gathering on Sunday and just hours apart FC Porto and Benfica at Dragão stadium, after Sporting and Sporting de Braga measuring forces in Alvalade.
One hundred percent victorious with coach Francesco Farioli, the dragons go on the lead journey, with three points of advantage over Sporting, classified, and have early on the new test of 'fire', now at the unstable reception of Benfica, after having passed '20 values' through the 'Leonino', when they defeated the two-time champion 2-1.
FC Porto has gone into force in the I Liga, while the incarnates, which follow four points of first place, live a complicated moment, with elections at the door, divided fans and already with a change in the technical team, with José Mourinho to yield the bad beloved Bruno Lage.
After the return to Stamford Bridge, in the 1-0 loss with Chelsea for the Champions League, Mourinho continues to revisit his past, this time visiting the dragons, for which he won a Champions League, a UEFA Cup, and two national championships.
In addition to the usual accounts for the I Liga, if you win, Farioli equals FC Porto's second best starter in the competition, the best in the 21st century, imitating the eight straight wins of Jesualdo Ferreira in 2007/08.
All factors point to FC Porto's favoritism, including the record of eight goals scored and none conceded at home, although the Lisbon enters the field with two more days of rest due to the portist's commitment to the Red Star in the Europa League League phase.
On Benfica's side, a Desaire promises to warm up on the sides of the light, while a dragon triumph may be the antidote that Mourinho needs to calm the hosts and renew the confidence of the incarnated players.
FC Porto-Benfica closes the round, shortly after Sporting and Sporting de Braga measuring forces in Alvalade, with national champions trying the fourth straight victory in the I Liga to a Minhota team in crisis and Spaniard Carlos Vicens trying to escape dismissal.
Rui Borges's team arrives in Alvalade after a Desaire in Naples (2-1), for the Championship, in a match where he took the 'luxury' to save Francisco Trincão, his best unit at this stage, all over the second half, and also other important figures such as Luís Suarez and Pedro Gonçalves, the two best markers, who also only played half of the match.
With a day of rest because of the Europa League, the seventh-ranked Minho, with nine points, arrive in Lisbon with a record of five in a row without winning at the I Liga, including two homemade defeats, the last before Nacional (1-0).
Vicens, former deputy of Pep Guardiola at Manchester City, even plays in Alvalade the 'Everything or Nothing', with a Desaire announcing a premature goodbye to Portuguese football, while a triumph has everything to give him a new breath in office.
The round starts this Friday with Casa Pia-Estoril Praia and, on Saturday, will be João Nuno's turn to live his first experience as a coach at the I Liga in charge of the Amadora Estrela, in a difficult visit to Campo do Gil Vicente, fifth classified.
Also on Saturday, the surprising Moreirense, who follows in fourth position, with 15 points, only below the three "big", goes to Madeira to face the national, and in the event of triumph, can even end the round in the last place of the podium, if Benfica leaves the Dragão stadium. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-02 22:41:56</pubDate></item><item><title>China foresees 2.4 billion trips during holidays of National Day</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/china-preve-24-mil-milhoes-de-viagens-durante-feriados-do-dia-nacional/</link><description>China's Ministry of Transport predicted more than 2.4 billion trips across the country during the so-called 'Golden Week' that began on Wednesday with Chinese National Day.

The Ministry of Transport estimated a daily average of 295 million trips, an increase of 3.2% compared to 2024, during the holidays, which ends with the lunar cake festival, on the night of October 6.
The cars are consolidating the position as the main means of transport, with 1.87 billion planned road trips, almost 80% of the total.
Authorities warned of intense congestion at the entrances of major cities and major tourist routes.
Chinese state railway operator reported that more than 110 million tickets were sold for trips between September 29 and October 10.
The company reinforced operations with the introduction of more than two thousand additional trains on the end days.
The operator foresees having transported 23 million passengers on the first day, after registering 18.4 million passengers on Tuesday, according to official data.
The civil aviation authority expects to transport 19.2 million passengers during the eight days of holidays, which would mark a record for this 'golden week', with the Beijing and Shanghai airports among the busiest.
The regulator also estimates that approximately 139,000 flights will operate in the country between Wednesday and 8 October, with an increase of 4.9% on domestic flights and 11.9% on international flights compared to 2024, according to data cited by Chinese state television CCTV.
The high tourist season has brought an increase, sometimes up to ten times, in hotel tariffs, according to Chinese social networks.
Lawyer Wang Duo, quoted by CCTV, has asked “companies that commit violations, such as malicious price increases, to be publicly reported” to “effectively dissuade price raising companies”.
According to the National Immigration Administration, the flow of people crossing China's borders will exceed two million a day during the vacation, with peaks on Wednesday and October 6.
Data from the reserve platforms cited by local media show that Japan, Hong Kong, Thailand, Malaysia, South Korea, Vietnam, Indonesia, Singapore, United States and Australia are among the main destinations for mainland tourists.
In Southeast Asia, Vietnam, Malaysia and Indonesia stand out for their strong increase in reserves, while in Japan, interest in cities like Kobe and Fukuoka is growing in relation to traditional Tokyo or Osaka.
In places such as Nang (Vietname) and Kota Kinabalu (Malaysia), hotel reservations by Chinese visitors more than quadrupled compared to last year, according to local press.
The coincidence of this year's national holiday with the lunar cake festival - which varies with the lunar calendar and in 2025 is celebrated on October 6 - widened the 'golden week' to eight days. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-02 22:47:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Partnership between STD and Pop Mart attracted more than 720 thousand people</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/parceria-entre-dst-e-pop-mart-atraiu-mais-de-720-mil-pessoas/</link><description>The initiative created by the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) in conjunction with Pop Mart - “Pop Mart Ride in Macao” attracted more than 723,000 people to the four facilities in the community and the area where the base was situated. The event, recall, took place between June 6 and September 21.
A total accumulated of about 45,000 people obtained a limited edition postcards, and the four phases of macao consumer draw, through six electronic wallets, recorded a total of 1.63 million users qualified by consumption. According to STD, the total number of qualified transactions was 3.64 billion patacas and the actual number of draws made was 2.77 million times.
The large -scale facilities of the Baby Molly, Crybaby, Dimoo and Labubu characters were on the sidewalk of São Lázaro Church, Luís de Camões Square, Santo Agostinho Largo and the leisure zone of Pai Kok da Taipa, “attracting the attention of fans from all over the intellectual ownership (PI), and making a large number of residents and visitors with visitors to residents and visitors to visitors and visitors Stroll and take photographs in community neighborhoods, streamlining tourism and consumption ”, can be read in a statement in the STD.
The body has promoted the event through various channels, including through its official social networking accounts (Wechat, Weibo, Douyin, XiaohongShu, Tiktok, Facebook and Instagram) and in collaboration with the official Pop Mart platform. At the same time, partnerships were carried out with influentors from the interior of China to create content, including an accumulated number of over 450 live broadcasts and publications with short images and videos. In total, they had an online exhibition of over 90 million times, “generating viral discussion on social networks about Macao tourism, which allowed to expand the reach to markets from visitors from other countries and regions,” the STD adds.
Since September 22, the winners of limited edition memories can travel to the Pop Mart store at the Yoho Hotel Treasury Island Resorts World to get the articles earned. The prize title is valid within 30 days from the date of the attribution in a draw, expiring late, warns the STD.</description><pubDate>2025-10-02 22:48:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Timorese government cancels licenses given for exploration of games and online bets</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/10/02/governo-timorense-cancela-licencas-dadas-para-exploracao-de-jogos-e-apostas-online/</link><description>The government of Timor-Leste approved, at a meeting of the Council of Ministers, a resolution to cancel licenses granted for online games and bets due to risks to security and social stability.

The resolution, presented by the Minister of Presidency of the Council of Ministers, Agio Pereira, also determines the “cancellation of procedures in course of granting new licenses and the prohibition of attribution of new licenses” for that type of activity, reads in the statement of the Council of Ministers.
The resolution was approved following “risks identified for safety, social stability, economic integrity and international reputation of the country,” the statement.
The resolution also determines that the Minister of Guardianship, together with the security forces, will oversee the implementation of the measures approved by the Government Resolution.
The United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime (UNODC) warned on September 11 for the proliferation of criminal networks in Oecussi, Timorese Enclave on the Indonesian side of Timor Island, noting that recent investigations show contamination of the region. “Oedusi's special administrative region seems to have been the target of criminal networks,” reads a report on Timor-Leste, which shows that there are all signs of digital criminal activity in this area, including the performance of people who have already been convicted of similar crimes in other Asian countries.
The UNODC document was released after an investigation by the Timorese authorities that resulted in the detention of 10 people on suspicion of involvement in illicit games and computing gaming in Oecussi.
"The expansion of the Southeast Asian fraud centers industry to Timor-Leste is a sign of its general growth," says the experts, noting that the case of Timor-Leste has "glaring similarities" with other troubled illegal digital game centers such as Macau, Cambodia, Laos, Philippines or Malaysian.
The problem, they warn, may worsen with the adhesion of Timor-Leste to the Association of Southeast Asia Nations (Asean) in October.
In the same report, Unodc states that a person “who holds a position in the Timor-Leste government” is one of the owners of a hotel that “seems to welcome companies” with criminal activity. "Hotel A is managed by several people, including one who holds a position in the government of Timor-Leste; [the hotel] seems to welcome companies that operate from their facilities and has been associated, through common commercial interests, with another hotel establishment in Dili linked to the recently devoid of Raeaa [Special Administrative Region of Oedusi]," reads a report on new criminal networks that are operating in Timorese enclave. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-02 22:43:28</pubDate></item></channel></rss>