<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/banco-norte-americano-citigroup-despede-3-500-funcionarios-na-china/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Chronic</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/cronica-15/</link><description>Paul French
 
           Ernest K Gann's sad Macao - Soldier of Fortune (1954)
 
 
Ernest K Gann's novel, Soldier of Fortune (1954), is now more remembered by his film version (1955), partially filmed in Hong Kong and starring Clark Gable and Rita Hayworth. Hayworth's refusal to leave America is known, which created some problems in editing the movie. Hayward's character Jane Hoyt looks for her husband, a photo-jornalist trapped in China as a spy. In Hong Kong, he cannot avoid falling in love with the marine transportation and smuggler Hank Lee (Gable). Lee does what is decent and eventually heads to Guangzhou to rescue Jane's husband. Then he is withdrawn chivalrously to allow them to resume their stagnant marriage. Along the way, Jane receives a tip from a man in Macao who can know about her husband's whereabouts. He then addresses the Portuguese colony-in the film, a scenario of Hollywood, with actor Mel Welles playing the player and “white slave trafficker” Rocha.
Although the film remains well known, the 300 pages of Gann's novel have not been reprinted since the 1980s, which is a pity, because it is a good reading, with much more detail than the movie (to which Gann also wrote the argument).
Ernest Kellogg Gann was born in Lincoln, Nebraska. His father worked in the field of the phones and, as a young man, got a job in Hong Kong to install telephone lines. On weekends, he visited Macau and thought he should leave the call business and devote himself to the writing of novels, writing something that took place in Hong Kong and Macau. Life, however, overlaps with his dreams. He spent some time doing news for the cine-jornals and then worked as a plane pilot, having crossed the Himalayas to China during World War II. Post-war, he rented a boat and sailed through the southern seas of China, writing Soldier of Fortune.
 
*
Jane catches the four-hour ferry Fat Shan to arrive in Macao after hiring the help of former nationalist General Po-Lin, who claims to know the territory well. Your mission is to find Fernando Rocha, “a worthless Portuguese,” but a man who can know something about her husband's fate. General Po-Lin suggests to Jane to tourism: “Macao will surprise her pleasantly. Time stops there… as for centuries… I always feel quiet when I'm in Macao.” She, however, insists on finding rock.
Fat Shan briefly enters Chinese waters and is still halfway between Hong Kong and Macau, with the Chinese navy boarding and leading General Po-lin to death. Shaken by the loss of his guide, Jane rides a taxi around the city - “the flowers fell from the walls that flanked the streets and the forged iron gates only partially obscured the gardens in front of the houses” - and is staying at Riviera Hotel, which used to be at the wooded intersection of Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro with Praia Grande, but unfortunately to give way to the Nam Tung commercial building.
Rocha directs a school of facade languages, the home tongue, on the famous street of happiness. Your "school" is just an empty office with filthy curtains. He says he knows the whereabouts of Joana's husband and tries to extort a "discovery rate." Jane pays you several hundred US dollars for the information. Tagging her in her poor accommodation, he immediately heads to the Central Hotel casino, right after Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro. The central is degraded, its heyday has long been overcome from before the war-"here, Macao workers could play Fantan and Chuck-a-Luck, or sit at long data tables where only one wheel was missing to duplicate the Rocha tables that Rocha remembered his youth in Estoril." On the top floors live girls, there is a dance floor and a Chinese band playing American jazz. Still above, "a sordid ballroom spectacle and an overbundance of hosts who harassed any man who ventured to pass the door with stuffed curtains."
Back to Hong Kong, Hank Lee learns that Jane blindly trusts in Rocha and is paying her. In Macao, Hank confronts Rocha, collects Jane and accepts the task of saving her husband.
 
*
In Soldier of Fortune, Ernest Gann offers us a night visit to Macao-from the exquisite suites from Riviera to the faded and mocking interior of the degraded Central Hotel, through the dubious endeavors and the inhabitants of Rua da Felicidade. Macao is a scenario of Hollywood, even with Portuguese traffic signs and fado guitarist.
Gann's Macao is a dark place, an economically impoverished colony full of secrets and hidden addictions. As with so many American portraits of the territory, Gann contrasts this reality with the busy and dynamic neighboring Hong Kong colony. Still, with all his weekend casinos, bars and hotels, Macau is invariably portrayed as sinful but romantic - we recall the weekend ride that the ill -fated lovers of Love is a Many Splendored Thing, from Han Suyin (filmed more or less at the same time as Soldier of Fortune in 1955) make (invented) Havana Hotel. The Macao of the Romance of Gann, although equally exotic and oriented, is ultimately a sad and desolate place.
On the internet, you can find second -hand copies of Soldier of Fortune. The film version is available on YouTube.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 06:01:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Chronic</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/cronica-16/</link><description>Dora Gago
 
           Suicide
 
I reach the scene of the occurrence at five and seven minutes of the afternoon. I see the body of Leong Fu, anticipated statue of meat made marble, my head covered with a plastic bag. All clean and tidy around. Official version already previously announced: suicide.
My boss gives orders in Cantonese and watches the scenario relaxedly, starting to light a cigarette. But suddenly, he remembers the anti-tabaco law, gives up the idea. Take a deep breath, take off an elastic pocket tablet, after putting on the gloves, picks the trimmed victim's suitcase on the floor, next to the toilet. Open it. It is meticulously organized and tidy: a box with tranquilizers, a slightly dirty razor, the lipstick, mirror, paper scarves, a ballpoint, a small notebook, the mobile phone, document cards, platinum credit cards, sunglasses stored in the corresponding box. The victim's wrists have mild cuts made perhaps by the razor, which later will have been cleaned and arranged inside the suitcase. A planned and organized death at least detail. Is this coldness and calculism possible in the last moments? Which will make someone out of the suitcase in the suitcase, some tranquilizers to, hours later, be found lifeless in the bathroom of a building, asphyxiated by a plastic bag placed in the head… This, when it was supposed to be in an important work meeting.
Such a tidy suitcase! Getting in death what Leong Fu never was in life, especially in the personal sphere: organized! According to the maid Filipina, who was cleaning the house, the feeling that he had when entering his apartment was that a level eight typhoon had just left at that time. Everything always spread everywhere, without even the notion of the need to keep the same things in the same places. It seemed that the objects each day found new places in that house, as if they were thinking creatures wanting to break free from routine slavery: the shoes in the desk, the toilet paper on the fridge, pens, or markers in the fruit basket… the strangest things in the most unimaginable sites.
The suicide thesis was, from the beginning, established by my police colleagues as absolute truth. Leong Fu had arrived seven years ago, from China Inner. Her husband and children continued to live on the continent, but they visited her some often. He had come to work for CCAC (Commissioner against Corruption), where he seemed to have a career in a meteoric rise, rapidly hit a leadership post. In a land where everything is as transparent and crystalline as the polluted sludge of the Pearl River, who could wish the end of Leong Fu? Interestingly, shortly before, in your apartment there was a small fire - a common event in the land of incense, panchões and where offerings are often burned to the gods and ancestors. But Leong Fu has always been coldly rational, distanced from beliefs and rituals. It is said to have been strange lately, perhaps too nervous. But from work I didn't talk to anyone. It took all the issues of professional secrecy very seriously.
Her colleagues stated that, professionally, everything would go too well: always on the rise, good relationships with superiors, influential friends-which seemed to inflate her more quickly. Personally, maybe there was any story of betrayal… Maybe she had discovered that her husband had a Indonesian lover, a spa masseuse he was very attending when Macao came… May the girl was pregnant… but no one knew for sure. Another version was that the husband had become pregnant the Filippine maid. Things that were said. There were also those who said that Leong Fu investigated a case of very serious corruption, involving owners of large casinos… a lot of powerful people to whom the magnetism of money catapult to Olympus above any law. But no, it could only be rumor, or "fake news," as it is said now, besides, here, on land of such crystal clear honestrity. And that Leong Fu received some threatening phone calls weeks after the entry into the territory of a mysterious container - finally, perhaps a joke of idle people, who failed Netflix, or forgot the password of social networks and was suddenly vacant.
Officially, it was concluded that Leong Fu, tired of living, depressed or disappointed, perhaps chose the public bathroom of a condominium to say goodbye to life: self-affixia with a plastic bag. To these and other mysteries, no one will ever answer, not even your body, now merely almost undefined ways under a grimy white sheet, pushed into a stretcher, after my boss ended up with the box of elastic tablets. After all what can life be?  With what lines is death with? Secrets unanswered buried in the delta of all doubts.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 06:01:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/breves-25/</link><description>Writers and illustrators ask for ceasefire in Palestine
 
A petition that brings together about two hundred names of Portuguese-speaking writers and writers appeals to the ceasefire in Palestine and to comply with international humanitarian aid rules. The document, promoted by the José Saramago Foundation, has names such as Chico Buarque, Djaimilia Pereira de Almeida, Itamar Vieira Júnior, Mia Couto and Lídia Jorge, among many others, and appeals "by ceasing immediate fourteen in Palestine, the urgent entry of humanitarian aid in the occupied territories, the liberation of all hostages and the political resolution of this occupation in the United Nations." The subscription is still open and it is expected that, in the coming days, more authors come together. The initiative follows the collective gesture assumed by Anglophone and Francophone authors who, in similar petitions, give voice to names like Ian Mcewan, Irvine Welsh, Zadie Smith, Annie Ernaux, Jean-Marie Gustave Le Clézio or Leo Slimani.
In the same vein, it is circulating another below signed, this time bringing together several professionals who create and work for childhood, namely in the editorial area. The document, which features the signatures of André Letria, António Jorge Gonçalves, Yara Kono or Luísa Ducla Soares, says: “We created and work for childhood. Before the massacre of thousands of children and other Palestinians in Gaza, we will not be accomplices for silence. We denounce and repudiate genocide. A world of peace is possible. This is the world we want. »
 
STD Prize for Luísa Costa Gomes
 
On June 28, Portuguese writer Luísa Costa Gomes will take the stage of the Theater Circo in Braga, to receive the Great Prize for Literature STD 2025. The distinction was attributed to him by the book Visit Friends and Other Tales (published by D. Quixote) and the jury, chaired by José Manuel Mendes, from the Portuguese Writers Association, and also composed by Lídia Jorge and Carlos Mendes de SousiFi The unanimity of the choice, stressing that the author's tales "surprise by narrative energy", revealing "powerful characters in their sociological and affective diversity", with a "refusal of existential inertia" and a "formal construction that enriches the reading experience", as read in the statement distributed by STD, the company responsible for the prize.
 
NGUGI WA THIONG'O (1938-2025)
 
Kenyan writer Ngugi Wa Thiong'o, the greatest name of African lyrics and permanent candidate for the Nobel Prize for Literature, died in late May, leaving an extensive work that includes soap operas, novels, dramaturgy, short stories and rehearsals, and ranging from social criticism to literature to the young. In addition to being a writer, he was also a professor of comparative literature at the University of California, taught at Yale University for a few years and at the University of New York, having lived in the UK and US exile decades after an intense involvement in the liberation struggles of his home country, Quenia, who was under British colonial rule to independence in 1963.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 06:01:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Jong-un promises “Unconditional Support” from North Korea to Russia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/kim-jong-un-promete-apoio-incondicional-da-coreia-do-norte-a-russia/</link><description>North Korean leader promised Russia “unconditional support” in the war against Ukraine, which has been going on for over three years. Kim expressed "his conviction that Russia, as always, will reach victory in its sacred cause of seeking justice."
 
North Korean leader Kim Jong-un promised Russia “unconditional support” in the war against Ukraine, which has been going on for over three years, advanced the North Korean state press yesterday.
Kim spoke at a meeting with Russian Security Council secretary Sergei Shoigu, who visited the North Korean capital for the second time in less than three months, the official KCNA news agency said.
At the meeting, held on Wednesday, the North Korean leader assured that Pyongyang will "support Russia's position and foreign policy unconditionally in all crucial international issues, including the Ukrainian issue." Kim expressed "his conviction that Russia, as always, will reach victory in its sacred cause of seeking justice," the agency added. Both parties agreed to “continue to gradually strengthen” relationships, according to KCNA.
The Russian embassy in Pyongyang referred on the telegram messaging platform that the two leaders "exchanged opinions about the situation around the Ukrainian crisis and the Korean peninsula."
The visit to North Korea of ​​Sergei Shoigu, former Minister of Defense, illustrates the growing approach between the two countries.
Moscow and Pyongyang have reinforced military cooperation in recent years with North Korea to provide weapons and troops to support the Russian war against Ukraine. The two countries signed a mutual defense agreement during Russian President Vladimir Putin's visit to North Korea in 2024.
A contingent of North Korean soldiers participated, alongside the Russian army, in the fighting in the Russian region of Kursk, situated by the border with Ukraine. Kiev's troops had occupied part of the region in a surprise offensive in the summer of 2024.
The Russian Security Council, an important advisory body that regularly gathers with Putin, had previously announced that discussions led by the Russian leader would focus on the “implementation of certain clauses” of the partnership between Moscow and Pyongyang, as well as in honor of the “Korean combatants who participated in the release of the Kursk region”.
In April, North Korea confirmed for the first time that it had sent troops to the Ukrainian front next to the Russian army.
On May 29, the United States and ten allies stated that military cooperation between Russia and North Korea violates the UN sanctions and has helped Moscow intensify attacks with missiles against Ukrainian cities.
The accusations have been in the first report since 11 countries - US, Australia, Canada, France, Germany, Italy, Japan, the Netherlands, New Zealand, South Korea and the United Kingdom - have come together to supervise sanctions against Pyongyang. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 05:43:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia refuses to sign “at any price” free trade with the EU</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/australia-recusa-assinar-a-qualquer-preco-tratado-de-comercio-livre-com-a-ue/</link><description>The Prime Minister of Australia yesterday ruled out the signature “at any price” of a free trade treaty with the European Union, after both sides resumed, in April, conversations about the agreement that negotiate since 2018. “We will look for a good enough agreement for Australia. If we will participate. parliamentary, according to public broadcaster ABC.
The labor leader stated that changes in the global business environment - alluding to the tariff war triggered by the United States - forced both parties to return to the negotiating table.
At the end of April, Albanese expressed his intention to enjoy the trip to the Vatican on the occasion of Pope Francis' funeral to resume talks with the EU about the bilateral free trade treaty.
These negotiations began in 2018, but stagnated in 2023 due to divergences around the original denominations of some products and the entry of Australian agricultural goods in the European market.
Australian Minister Don Farrell and European Commerce Commissioner, Maros Sefcovic, gathered on Wednesday, on the sidelines of the OECD Annual Ministerial Meeting in Paris, but few details are known to this meeting. Farrell said Camberra and Brussels are "working on pending issues to try to finish the agreement" and that this year can be achieved "substantial progress."
Among the differences that suspended more than a year and a half the negotiations of a bilateral free trade agreement are Australia's requirement to continue to call “Prosecco” and “feta”, respectively, to a white wine and a type of cheese produced in the ocean country, although it is denominations of protected European origin.
The controversy between the two territories also focused on the access of Australian agricultural products, such as sugar, to the European market, which covers more than 445 million potential consumers.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 05:43:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Editorial #94</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/editorial-94/</link><description>In 1995, a group of artists residing at Beijing East Village, a community dedicated to the arts in their multiple languages ​​and based on Beijing, decided to perform a performance. The collective gesture sought to intervene in the landscape, perhaps exploring the contradiction between the idea of ​​a permanent brand and the ephemerality that characterizes any performance work, and was recorded by different people, in photography and video. It is very likely that none of those involved had thirty years ago that to add one to have an anonymous mountain would take on a winging role in Chinese contemporary art and the world history of performance arts, but that is exactly what happened. Like almost all relevant stories, this is not linear, starting long before the day of performance-May 11, 1995-and extending far beyond it, in a ball of debates, conflicts and, above all, various inheritances and echoes that continue to show the importance of this work. It is this ballot that photographer and curator João Miguel Barros has been to deliver, starting by showing off in Lisbon at the Ochre Space Gallery, the one that will be the most detailed and complete exposure on performance and preparing at the same time a book that will gather important documentation (some of her dispersed or unpublished), interviews, images and a thick reflection on what was to anonymous Mountain, as he spread around the world, contrary to the curse of performing ephemerality and Echoes continues to produce in the present. We talked to João Miguel Barros about all this, right after we see the exhibition that will remain patent at Ochre Space until near the end of this month.
In this number, there is also a highlight for the two editions of the work Lin Tchi Fá-Flor de Lotus, by Maria Anna Acciaioli Tamagnini, in Portuguese-Frog and Portuguese-Chinese (published by Prail Editions, in translations of Lian Zimo and Ian Watts). Lin Tchi Fá was the author's only poetry book, who lived in Macao for two periods, between the first and third decades of the twentieth century, accompanying her husband, Governor Artur Tamagnini Barbosa. Its reception extended beyond cultural borders and those of the territory, achieving great prestige between the Portuguese, but also Chinese community, and being pointed out by Natália Correia, many years later, as a very relevant work in the context of the Portuguese language, something that the Azorean poet attributed to the 'literary talent with which [Maria Anna Acciaioli] sowed for newspapers and magazines in collaboration in collaboration Verse and prose, he still wants his commitment to social works and protection with which he encouraged the arts and letters ».  Lin Tchi Fá - Lotus Flower is back on bookstores and continues to raise dialogues and new readings, despite the inevitable passing of time.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 06:02:38</pubDate></item><item><title>EMPHASIS</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/destaque-4/</link><description>Unlike Efémeus: to add One Letter to Anonymous Mountain
 
In Lisbon, the Ochre Space Gallery has patented an exhibition that marks the 30th anniversary of the performance to add One Meter to Anonymous Mountain, one of the most striking events of contemporary Chinese art, and is just a first step towards the publication of a book about this performance signed by João Miguel Barros.
 
In 1995, a group of Chinese artists performed a performance that quickly turned into a milestone in contemporary Chinese art and international performance history. The story is made of many wires, in a plot that starts a few years earlier and extends to the present, but it is worth starting with the perfomance itself.
The ephemerality is the nature of performance, although records of different types that help maintain their memory in the future can be made, which also happened here. Still, what is astonishing in to add oneter to an anonymous Mountain is the impact that continues to be thirty years old, the many echoes, not just in the art market
Let's try, then, to summarize a long story and requires some context. In the early 1990s, in the village of Dashanzhuang, outskirts of Beijing, a heterogeneous group of artists settle in an area where the incomes were more affordable and then begins an artistic community known as Beijing East Village. Then they lived and worked together artists dedicated to painting, photography, music and other practices and languages, including performance, which turned out to be the great inheritance of this community.
In May 1995, already after several works created and exhibitions in different sites, the community is outlining. Some of its resident artists were detained following the performative work they performed, almost always having their body naked and confrontation with the elements as the central line, and the first abandonments of the community began to verify. Still, it is in this year that ten resident artists decide to perform the performance to add one meter to an anonymous mountain, a kind of final act and celebratory of this experience of a few years in community.
The performance can describe themselves in a summary way: artists Zhu Ming, Zhang Binbin, Duan Yingmei, Zhang Huan, Ma Liuming, Ma Zhoggren, Zuoxia Zuzhou, Wang Shihua, Cang Xin and Gao Yang, accompanied by curator Kong BU and some more people, headed for myofeng, one of the close mountains, one of the nearby mountains, one of the nearby mountains, one of the nearby mountains from Beijing East Village. Upstairs, at the top of the mountain, they are stripped and were weighed one by one, with the weight announced aloud by Kong Bu. Then they went on to the floor, with a face facing down, forming a kind of five-layer pyramid, organized by weight (leaving people heavier below, naturally). The pyramid formed by these ten bodies added one meter to the mountain, in an intervention capable of altering the landscape, giving it a new relief. An official meter, especially hired for the purpose, took the intervention measures and certified them. The event was recorded in different ways by some people, including Bagena (which was the only one to get a complete record of all the steps of performance, from the arrival of the artists to the top of myofeng to the formation of the pyramid that made the mountain grow one meter). In addition to him, photographer Lu Nan also registered the end result, as was Robin Beck, journalist of the international news agency France-Presse. It was the photographs taken by these three people who eternalized to add One Meter to an Anonymous Mountain, stubbornly contradicting the supposed ephemerality of the performative arts.
 
A book to honor the story of a performance
One of the many echoes left by this performance came to the photographer, curator and also lawyer João Miguel Barros, responsible for Gallery Ochre, Lisbon, and for a series of photography exhibitions, especially the work of Chinese photographers. It is in the ochre gallery that it is evident, until the 21st of this month, the one that will be the most complete exhibition on the performance to add one to be anonymous Mountain, which joins a core titled Rongrong's East Village, bringing together a series of Rongrong photographs taken in Beijing East Village. The exhibition, however, is just one step in a longer project that João Miguel Barros has realized the paragraph: “In fact this is not the end, it is the intermediate point of a much broader thing that will culminate in a book. The exhibition is a part of this path, but my final goal was always to make a book. When I planned everything to celebrate the 30th anniversary of performance, the idea was to open the exhibition and release the book, but it was not possible, time did not arrive. » It will come, however, are confirmed, and this book will certainly be a milestone for understanding what happened in that mountain from the outskirts of Beijing, but especially the lines that led there and the different impacts that this event has produced on Chinese art and worldwide.
The interest of João Miguel Barros in the performance to add One Meter to Anonymous Mountain began about a decade ago, long before imagining that he would make an exhibition and a book from it: «When I saw this photograph of the ten bodies lying down, I was fascinated, and at the time I did not know that there were ten bodies, nor who had taken the photography, not even what was behind it. It was a kind of magnetic attraction to the image, which stood out in a gigantic shoplifter of a Beijing gallery. ' The photograph was the one that did on the day of performance. «In fact, Lu Nan's image is perfect, the layers, the various gradations of the mountain range where that mountain is inserted… None of the other images shows this. Moreover, in the image of Lu Nan it is clear that the ten bodies are all aligned, lying down, and there is a particularity compared to other photographs: all heads are aligned down and all ten people, the ten bodies, are also anonymous, while in other photographs there is an individualization of people. This photograph became a presence, every once in a while I remembered her… Later, I realized that the photograph was from Lu Nan, that I had the opportunity to meet in the meantime, and he always dodged photography, without me realizing why.
About three years ago, the OCHRE Gallery official realized that a round date was approaching 2025, when they would spend three decades on the day of performance. At that time, he intensified his research on the subject, finding the work of a Chinese curator who, on the twentieth anniversary of the event, had conducted interviews with the ten artists involved and Kong Bu, the curator of performance. These interviews are available online, in Chinese language, but they seemed not profound to João Miguel Barros, increasingly embarrassed in serious reflection on the subject: “I began to think that there is a very Chinese view of this performance, condensed in this celebration of the twentieth anniversary, but was able to have a set of interviews in which people talked about performance, there is also a framework, there is also a framework, counting that passed, how was it all. And that's when I started thinking about doing this work, and about two years ago I started seriously. With the help of Duan Yingmei, one of the artists involved, currently living in Germany, managed to record the name of all the people who participated in the process in some way, not just the artists. It is at this moment that interviews Kong Bu, the curator, whose name appeared rarely in the various references to performance. He also interviewed all the artists, except one, Zuzhou, currently one of the big names in Chinese pop and rock music, which declined to be interviewed. It is at this time that João Miguel Barros gains a deeper conscience of the complexity of telling the story of to add One Meter to Anonymous Mountain, as he told the paragraph: “When I start talking to artists, I realize that I am in a dead end, because if I was expecting to establish a truth for the facts, that was impossible; They all had a different truth. It's not that everyone is lying, it's not that… For now, it has passed thirty years and I think that, as significantly it was an event in my life so long, with false and induced memories in the middle, things will build each other differently. On the other hand, this also had a traumatizing one side in people's lives. There is one thing that is certain: when they perform this performance, they do it from a very pure perspective, without any embarrassment, and none of them had the ability to predict that this would have this degree of world projection and of importance. I would say that the only person who had this capacity, in a way, was Lu Nan, who, when she makes the photographs she delivers a negative to each of those involved so that they could use it in the future. Lu Nan was already known when they invite him to join the project to take photographs, and what he says is that he received no instructions from anyone, it was not that process from an artist who invites a photographer to photograph about his direction, so the copyright of photography would always be his. He made sense, the conception, as photography was taken, and so I consider Lu Nan the official photographer of the final act of performance.
 
Fame and authorship
Two days after the performance, the first images of to add One Meter to an Anonymous Mountain appear published in the press of Hong Kong and Taiwan by Robin Beck's hand. After that, the images gain notoriety and some photographs begin to be sold, appear in galleries and some museums. Zhang Huan moves to the United States of America begins to work with galleryist Max Protetch, one of the interveners with great power in the US and international arts market. In 1998, the Exide Out exhibition, promoted by Gao Mingu, Robin Beck's photograph comes up with the name of Zhang Huan. As the Venice Biennial approaches in 1999, things are complicated and a stae a war between the artists and the various involved because of the perpetrator, with a below signed, an investigation that takes place in China and several other episodes that João Miguel Barros has properly documented and that will be present in the book: “My position is very simple, I will not make a book with a kind of conclusion, I want people to judge for themselves. What I want is to tell this whole story, let people judge, but create a paradigm for the future, if possible, that is, that the photographs will have a correct cataloging based on the idea that they have to have a caption where the author of photography must always be mentioned, deep down, as I do here. The way I classified the photographs here at the exhibition should be followed, from my perspective, everywhere, and the names of the artists should also appear in all the photographs. We can never say that it is the photograph of an artist and not mentioning who took the photograph and not mentioning, too, the names of all artists. In the background, this is my great thesis, so to say, in relation to this research work, which contradicts a bit to the policy of the museums when they classify photographs like these. Legal issues around copyright and copyright are complex and vary between countries and continents, but as João Miguel Barros explained, the authorship here is not confused: “When an artist hires a photographer to record his performance, then the photographer does not exist, but in this case it is completely different, because who photographed did not receive instructions, of course, or it is, of course, it is, of course, it is, of course Discuss image law and other issues that are complicated and that is why I have a chapter in the book on performance and copyright, because it is a complicated matter. See the case of Lu Nan, who did what he did was allow others to use the assets of the work, can sell it, enjoying his work, but can never remove his authorship. And that makes perfect sense, because authorship, the author's moral law, is his. And what I think is wrong is that often does not appear his name in the image of his, even if others have the right to sell it.
Thirty years after the performance that was the beginning of the end of Beijing East Village, there is still much to count, record and explain. The exhibition with the same name as the performative piece, which joins the core with Rongrong photographs made in the community, an important contribution to perceiving the origins and context of to add one to anonymous mountain, is, as its curator says, "a passage to say, the final act, and this is the book." We can count on him after summer, illuminating one of the most striking events of contemporary Chinese art.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 06:01:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Navigating</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/navegar-e-preciso-26/</link><description>https://fumaca.pt/
 
In 2016, a group of young journalists created a podcast that quickly asserted itself in the Portuguese journalistic landscape. Strict, transparent and focusing on topics that are often not deeply explored by most media, smoke has worked independently, struggling to reach a financing totally ensured by its listeners. On the site, the team is likely: «We are dissidents. We advocate the need to go beyond the current media agenda, to create alternatives to traditional journalistic structures in financing, editorial and work practices, and organization models. Smoke is legally detained by Verdes Memories - Association, a non -profit association composed exclusively by the people of the newsroom. We seek to appropriately remunerate the work of each person who is part of the collective, ensuring fair payments and decent work conditions. We aim for the editorial and operational radical transparency. We do not believe in the existence of neutral journalism: instead of affirming the exemption, we clearly assume our subjectivities and conflicts of interest.
In this line, smoke has already produced seven long series, which can be heard from its website or one of the many podcast platforms, on topics such as Palestine, gas exploration, mental health, European Union and its borders with regard to migrations, private security companies or climate crisis, as well as various reports and other smaller work. The most recent series, almost family, is about women who clean and take care of the world and put it to move, made in partnership with the Cassandra artistic creation structure. The idea came from the play of theater about housework “Monologue of a woman named Maria with her boss”, a creation of Sara Barros Leitão with the Cassandra structure, and the result follows the stories of many women (some, still children when they started working) who lived and live from housework, as well as the context in which this work develops, the total absence of rules prior to April 25 to the first union domestic and the many processes of awareness that marks the life of these people.
Known for harsh journalism, but also for having all its publicly available accounts for consultation, smoke currently has 45% of its operation ensured by the regular contributions of its listeners community and a series of scholarships and support from different origins, all properly explicit on the site.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 06:01:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong appoints first foreign judge in one year after several layoffs</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/hong-kong-nomeia-primeiro-juiz-estrangeiro-em-um-ano-apos-varias-demissoes/</link><description>The Hong Kong Parliament approved the first appointment of a foreign judge to the British Old Colonial Court within a year after a series of layoffs.
 
The Hong Kong Legislative Council voted on Wednesday in favor of a government proposal to appoint William Young to Hong Kong's last court for a three-year term, which is expected to begin in June.
Hong Kong's number two number two, chief secretary Eric Chan Kwok-Ki stressed to the deputies that the judge led a commission of inquiry into the March 2019 attack on two Mosques in Christchurs.
In August 2020, a white supremacist was sentenced to perpetual penalty without right to parole - the first sentence of this type in New Zealand - for having killed 51 Muslims.
The appointment of judges of other jurisdictions that share the system known as 'Common Law' inherited from the UK “contributed to the maintenance of a high level of confidence in the judicial system” of Hong Kong, defended Eric Chan.
The chief secretary also said that the coming of foreign judges "demonstrates that the basic law guarantees the independent exercise of judicial power."
After reforming herself from the Supreme Court of New Zealand in 2022, William Young, 73, served as a judge in the seychelles higher courts, Samoa and the Fiji Islands.
In July 2022, the New Zealand was appointed to the courts of the Dubai International Financial Center in the United Arab Emirates, but fired less than a month later.
At the time, Young gave the risk of “adverse perceptions” after the Human Rights Defense Organization Amnesty International accused the country of appointing foreign judges to try to legitimize the political regime.
Five non -permanent foreign judges (two from the United Kingdom and three from Australia) currently perform functions in the Hong Kong Superior Court, which also has Lusodescendent Roberto Ribeiro.
Several foreign magistrates, including from the United Kingdom and Canada, have abandoned the territory of the last 12 months.
In June 2024, one of them, British judge Jonathan Sumptio warned that the rule of law is “endangered” in Hong Kong due to pressure from the Chinese central government.
In an opinion article published in the Financial Journal Times, the 75 -year -old magistrate argued that “it was no longer realistic” that foreign judges remained in the city's Superior Court. "Hong Kong, who was once a vibrant and politically diverse community, is slowly becoming in a totalitarian state," said Summption.
In June 2024, the Hong Kong Watch Human Rights Defense Group told Lusa that the region has seen "a growing number of political prisoners, the decrease in judicial independence and the violation of international legal obligations." Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 05:43:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Criticism</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/critica-14/</link><description>Continuous gift
 
Chico Buarque
Bambino to Rome
Companhia das Letras
 
Fictional memory, like all memories, Bambino to Rome returns to the end of the end of Chico Buarque's childhood and the city that served as a refuge, themselves and their family, in this way out of a little recommended Brazil for those who enjoyed breathing some freedom.
It is the crossing by sea, between Rio de Janeiro and Genoa, which opens this prose, a fully Romanesque record where the fictional pact leads us to accept part of what we read as autobiographical. Narrated by the adult who now recalls the Roman years, the book is full of these little memories that give structure to a life: childhood friendships and feelings of injustice, the disturbed discovery of sexuality and loves, the projects for a future that imagined infinitely distant, small accidents. In a way, Bambino to Roma cartographs these moments with the same intention of rigor with which he is cartographicing the streets, squares and alleys of a Rome that has its past scatter, but has above all the mark of places that only gain full form in memory and writing. This awareness that it is the memory, a place of pitfalls and uncertainties, which builds us through the whole book, manipulated by a narrator who wants to remember, but also wants - and thus - create what he remembers, knowing that there are no immaculate records, as the children's project of writing a diary: «(…) I could not honestly describe what was happening to my day, even the most recent memories, even the recent memories they would be retouched as they were written. I thought it best to leave the idea of ​​a diary and let forget your work. In the future the imagination would cover the gaps of memory and real events would take turns what could have happened. ' (pg.88)
Upon arrival in Rome, after the sea, the permanent nausea and the train trip, Chico gradually becomes the Brazilian, as his friend Amadeo calls him, with whom he shares the love for football (and with whom he will learn new words in Italian, not all particularly recommended, as is an impression of any learning, also linguistic). American school, long tours of the city, colleagues from another social stratum, the people who are knowing in their journeys and a permanent feeling of strangeness. Somehow it is a double life that Chico seems to value, rarely letting the two worlds contaminate and never challenge their borders - even when he meets a colleague's mother, a famous Italian actress with whom she will dance at a party (before feeding various fantasies with the memory of this moment).
The characteristics of the author's prose are confirmed in this fictional memory, from the rhythm well measured to the short point of humor, from attention to tiny gestures that define an emotional state to colloquialism that never loves care language work. Still, this is a text with particularities that distinguish it from the author's novels, not only because matter is admittedly autobiographical, but especially because the assumption of this is one of the engines of the narrative. Already very close to the end of the book, it reads: «Path under rain by Via del Corso and I enter to take a grap in a cafe where I remember drunk with Brazilian refugees at the time of the dictatorship. It should go from eight in the evening, three in the afternoon, and if I were there at this time I would take a dip in Ipanema. Or maybe I would be secluded in a smoky room to advance my book, in which I would simulate being in Rome taking a grap in a sinister cafe that I attended at the time of the dictatorship. (pg.162) The tone that the narrator uses to shred his memories is that of a boy to discover the world, and to discover himself in the world, but is also that of an adult man, conscious of aging, who retreats to the past to permanently confirm it. This is the great prestigning gesture of Bambino to Rome, the illusion that the past is tidy followed by the shrewd revelation of being a continuous gift that we redo the years pass.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 06:01:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Tai Kin IP highlights Macau potential in the convention and exhibition sector</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/tai-kin-ip-destaca-potencial-de-macau-no-sector-das-convencoes-e-exposicoes/</link><description>The Secretary for Economics and Finance spoke yesterday at the Galaxy Macao International Convention Center, at World Exhibition Day celebrations, an event organized by the Global Association of the Exhibition Industry (UFI). At the time, Tai Kin IP highlighted the “continuous development potential” of the region in this area.
 
"In recent years, Macau's convention and exhibition industry has shown continuous development potential," said Tai Kin IP at World Exhibition Day celebrations, organized by the Global Association of the Exhibition Industry (UFI) at the Galaxy Macao International Convention Center.
The Secretary for Economics and Finance recalled the data of the report recently published by the International Association of Congresses and Conventions (ICCA), which says that last year, the territory was in 14th place in the ranking of the cities of the Asia Pacific region for international conventions, rising six places compared to 2023. At the world, the classification of Macau rose 31 positions, reaching 76th in the ranking of cities. worldwide for international conventions. In the first quarter of this year, 413 exhibition events were held in Macao, which represents a 23% increase over the previous same year.
Tai Kin IP pointed out that Macau also faces “problems and challenges”, including “the growing regional competition, the accompanied transformation, the technological adaptation and the ecological transformation, among other challenges”. "The convention and exhibition industry faces opportunities and challenges, and the formation of qualified paintings is an essential core for their development," he said.
The ruler also recalled that, in recent years, the local executive "has continually cooperated with international institutions, the MICE sector and higher education institutions to promote the formation of qualified frames in the area of ​​convention and exhibitions."
This year, Macau plans to hold 19 training sessions in the area of ​​Convention and Exhibitions, of which 11 will take place in the second half, including seven professional certification courses in cooperation with international convention and exhibition organizations.
"In the future, we will add training content, such as multimedia and digital applications, according to the evolution of the market, to promote the staggered training of qualified framework of the convention and exhibition industry in Macao, while providing training and internship opportunities for young people interested in entering this industry," said the secretary.
Tai ended his intervention by pointing out that this sector plays “an important role in promoting industrial diversification”. “Looking to the future, I hope that Macao convention and exhibition operators will continue to keep the spirit of 'focusing on the present tasks and planning long-term development', joining efforts to improve international competitiveness and create a new chapter for Macao's convention and exhibition industry,” he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 05:43:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Fifteen Hong Kong students suspected of dying this year by suicide</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/quinze-estudantes-de-hong-kong-suspeitos-de-morrerem-este-ano-por-suicidio/</link><description>At least 15 students in Hong Kong may have committed suicide in the first five months of this year, local newspaper South China Morning Post (SCMP) said yesterday. The number, compiled by SCMP, is equivalent to about half of the total recorded in 2024.
Numbers by education authorities, primary and secondary schools point to 11 suspected suicide cases between January and April.
The English language newspaper also accounted for four more cases in May, based on local "media", raising the total to at least 15 known incidents, an average of three per month.
Hong Kong's Department of Education has previously stated that an observed standard in the last five years suggests that the number of suicides is generally higher during the periods from May to July and September to November.
The territory totaled 28 suicide student deaths in 2024, a decrease compared to 32 in 2023. The numbers for 2022 and 2021 were 25 each year.
Also according to the newspaper, the secretary for education, Christine Choi Yuk-Lin, is expected to discuss the mental health of students and support measures at a meeting in Parliament on Friday.
Also in Macao, the number of suicides among the youngest has increased. In May, in a session of the Assembly, Deputy Ron Lam, noting that the suicide between the young layer deserves attention, took the following figures to the plenary: the registration, in 2024, of four cases aged 5 to 14 years - the first time there was more than one case in this group, in the last ten years - and nine cases between 15 and 24 years, “the largest number in the last ten years”.
The values ​​of the suicide attempt also remain high, said the parliamentarian, indicating that they arrived at 249 cases last year, a number that represents “an increase of 1.5 times compared” with 2015.
Also here, the deputy drew attention to what is happening to the younger ones, revealing that suicide attempts in the ages between 5 and 24 years, in the last five years, represent “on average”, 40% of the total cases, when between 2015 and 2019, the average was 20%. Lam, who belongs to the group of deputies elected by direct suffrage, stressed that, in order for society to study and analyze suicide causes and trends, greater transparency in the information released by the authorities is necessary. This, he said, is limited.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 05:43:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Readers under construction</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/leitores-em-construcao-13/</link><description>Paula Rego's example
The latest volume of the Heroines of the Arts is dedicated to Paula Rego, in a work where Catarina Sobral maintains the structure of previous books, without skidding to any monotony. Paula Rego's life is narrated here from what we know of her work, crossing biographical facts with the construction of this visual imagination that would cross the artist's paintings. We got to know the homemade environment of your childhood, the influence of parents, the stories told by an aunt, from the beach to the beach. At the same time, the social and political context of the time is also presented, justifying the trip to London, to study, and anticipating the political aspect of the works that would emerge later (as Paula Rego's father says in one of the images, "you will study for England. Portugal is not a place for women!", Referring to the absence of freedom in the country and the general disregard of women).
The chronology properly organized at the end of the book gives us well-groomed biographical data, creations, awards, but it is in the body of narrative that everything is played and, there, Catarina Sobral is excellent in creating strong ties between image and text, sometimes using speech balloons and drawing band sequences, in a work that makes it an extraordinary example, an extraordinary example, an extraordinary example Didactic that at no time do you dispense with the copyrighted brand and that gives us, critically, exciting and full of good examples, the history of the life of one of the great Portuguese artists ever.
Catarina Sobral
Turn the fear on the contrary as Paula Rego
China/F ink. Calouste Gulbenkian
A bear on the rug
In his books, regardless of whether they are thought to older or younger readers, David Machado knows how to take advantage of the gears of fiction to tell a story without giving in to the expected plots. In this book, these gears are themselves narrative elements that the story - the text, but also the images created by David Painter, full of movement and details - manipulates, misleading and stretches in various directions, creating different levels of likelihoods and opening the ever valuable possibility of what we call reality, after all, composed of much fiction.
In the history of the sister who tells stories to her younger brother, the narrative game depends on the credulity of those who hear the bear who entered the house, the pirates who appear in the meantime or the space ship ready to abduct everyone, and the contrast between the sister, who says it is all imaginary, and the brother, a believer in everything he listens (and somehow ends up seeing). Above all, it depends on the doubt that it is installed, especially when the bear enters the house and ends up falling asleep on the sofa of the bedroom, without the parents dropping the screens with which they enter and without the two children to give up their certainties: the oldest, the oldest of all being invented, the youngest, satisfied by the lived adventures, the two well accompanied by the huge animal beside the bed.
David Machado and David Pintor
A serious story
Path
Other books
Philip Ball Bernardo P. Carvalho
Three great questions
Tangerine Planet
Amanda Gorman &amp; Christian Robinson
Little by little
Black orphew
Translation by Alice Neto de Sousa
Susana Moreira Marques and Inês Viegas Oliveira
The bedroom
Association for the Cultural Promotion of the Child
Philip Bunting
Questions and more questions!
Booksmile
Marta Nazaré</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 06:01:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Books Montra</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/montra-livros-8/</link><description>MADELINE PEREIRA
Butterfly
Path
Translation by Alice Pereira and Hélio Pereira
Born in France, Madeleine is being remembered the Portuguese origins through the xenophobic comments of her schoolmates. Despite the discrimination, curiosity about its origins leads it to interrogate the father and discover, in an admittedly autobiographical comic band, the stories, context and life course of those who preceded it in a dictatorship dominated and reached democracy.
 
Nuno Duarte
Clay -feet
Leya
Romance winner of the latest edition of the Leya Prize, Barro feet has its narrative located in the early 1960s in Lisbon and the construction of the 25 de Abril Bridge (then, Ponte Salazar) as a scenario. As the bridge rises, framing the trail of ships that depart to the colonized and war, Victor Tirapicos, locksmith and resident in one of Alcântara's courtyards, who guides the narrative, between loves and disagreements, dreams that are undone.
 
Fernanda Melchor
This is not Miami
Elsinore
Translation by Cristina Rodriguez and Artur Guerra
With the stories he collected over a decade, Fernanda Melchor makes up these reports, taking advantage of the diffuse border between what we call reality and what we like to imagine as fiction. From the emptied Mexican prison to a Hollywood movie to the group of clandestine migrants who confuses Veracruz with Miami, Melchor proves all the reasons that criticized it as one of the most extraordinary voices in Latin American literature.
 
Ailton Krenak
Ideas to postpone the end of the world
Antigon
Ailton Krenak is one of the voices to take into account when it comes to Brazilian indigenous movement and in this book discusses the way we live globally, contrasting the predatory mode of infinite economic production and growth and the precariousness to which this mode condemns much of humanity. In this title it is added ancestral future, also has just published, where this global view of living beings and its belonging to nature is explained in detail.
 
George Ernest Morrison
AN Australian in China
LETTEL BOOKS
Originally published in 1911, this book reports the experiences of Australian journalist and adventurer George Ernest Morrison, who traveled through China in the early twentieth century, traveling cities, villages and many landscapes without human presence. In this crossing, registered here, it is intensely reflected on culture, identity and political and social changes that shaken China of that time.
 
Alexandra Lucas Coelho
Gaza is everywhere
Path
Writer and journalist Alexandra Lucas Coelho returns to a territory that has marked her writing, gathering reports, chronicles, some texts never published and 148 color photographs, almost all unpublished. The first report is prior to October 7, 2023 and the Hamas attack on Israel, but all other works are later, focusing on the present (without ignoring the so many antecedents) and denouncing the genocide that continues to take place in Gaza.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 06:01:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Employment pairing sessions will provide 686 vacancies</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/sessoes-de-emparelhamento-de-emprego-vao-proporcionar-686-vagas/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), together with the six integrated tourism and leisure companies, will hold this month six job pairing sessions, providing a total of 686 job openings. Registration starts today and ending June 24.
The 686 job vacancies are distributed through several departments of the front line and the logistics of hotels and restoration establishments of integrated tourism and leisure companies, namely in restoration, rooms and cleaning and front line operations, representing about 75% of the total vacancies.
In addition, these pairing sessions also involve some management and professional technique stations, such as purchasing manager, customer development manager, sales manager, shift engineer, safety supervisor and food hygiene, cooking chief and chief cooks from different cooking, among others.
The first pairing sessions for companies are scheduled for: June 17 (Melco), June 20 (Galaxy and SJM), June 24 (MGM), June 26 (Sands China), June 30 (Wynn). Alongside this, there is a likely to be scheduled by the companies more pairing sessions on other dates depending on the number of registered in pairing, and information about the place, date and time of these interviews will be communicated by telephone or by SMS messages, and the candidates should keep their mobile phone linked so they can attend the interview at the time.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 05:43:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Extreme climate phenomena and greenhouse gas emissions increased by 2024</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/fenomenos-climaticos-extremos-e-emissoes-de-gases-de-efeito-de-estufa-aumentaram-em-2024/</link><description>The Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) released yesterday the Macao 2024 state report, regarding the celebration of World Environment Day. The body reveals that, while the flow of tourists and the region's economic development continue to grow, some environmental indicators - such as greenhouse gas emissions, water consumption and electricity and the amount of urban solid waste - have worsened. Climate change also play a relevant role in extreme weather phenomena that occurred in Macao in 2024, the year the city reached a maximum temperature record.
 
Yesterday, on World Environment Day, the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) published the Macao State Report on 2024. According to the document, the growth of the economy and the number of tourists to visit the region resulted in higher resource consumption and a pressure increased in several environmental indicators, which increased the previous year of 2023. Electric and the area of ​​green spaces increased in annual terms.
In an opening note, Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Tam Vai Man, acknowledges that “the path to the green transition with low carbon emissions is long and challenging”, but ensures that the government will continue to contribute “to the construction of the large bay (…) as a pioneering zone in the development of a beautiful and sustainable China”. "Green development is currently a global trend and the way to follow to the progress of contemporary society," he said.
The report is divided into seven chapters that focus on various data collected in Macau last year, from the socioeconomic evolution of the territory to the investment of entities and companies in the environmental area.
 
Increased tourism has environmental impact
 
If the year 2023 was a period of socioeconomic standardization, after the government-imposed border restrictions by the end of 2022, the year 2024 was marked by the almost total recovery of pre-pound tourist levels. Over the past year, the number of visitors increased 23.8% in annual terms to 35 million, and the local Gross Domestic Product (GDP) registered an increase of 8.8%.
With the improvement of the economy and the recovery of the tourist sector, estimated local emissions of greenhouse gases (GHG), volume of invoiced water, electricity consumption and urban solid waste. All of these environmental indicators recorded increases between 5.1% and 5.6% compared to the previous year of 2023.
"Given that the growth of the economy has pressure on various environmental indicators, it should be taken into account the effective use of resources and the protection of the environment during the development" of economic and tourist sectors, stresses the DSPA report, suggesting the "promotion of the development of green economy, the circular economy and innovative technologies" as strategies for "accelerating green transition and to form a new driving force to urban development."
 
2024 was the second hottest year ever
 
The occurrence of extreme meteorological phenomena in Macao reached a record level in 2024-the warmer year since it is registered, in pairs with 2019. The average temperature of the region (23.6 degrees Celsius) and the number of very hot days (42) were above the climate average, while there was a light increase in total rainfall and annual average of sea level rise. The report also points out that of the seven tropical storms hitting Macao last year, three occurred in November, establishing a new record of late tufts in the region.
Also the air quality worsened compared to 2023. The number of days when the average air quality recorded in the six Macau monitoring stations was classified as “good” or “moderate” descended three percentage points, being 88%. In the opposite direction, they accounted for between 15 and 35 days when the air was described as "unhealthy" (against seven to 32 days last year), while the number of days with the classification of "very unhealthy" rose for two days. The average ozone (O3) concentrations even have exceeded the standard values ​​in a few days, in a trend contrary to that of the other pollutants, which have a descent trajectory.
Exhaust gases emitted by transport are one of Macao's leading atmospheric pollutants, a problem that the Government of MSAR has sought to minimize policies related to the promotion of the use of electric vehicles. Last year, this type of vehicles grew by almost 50%, and the proportion of electricity consumption - mainly from the interior of China - already represents 70.4% of the total energy of Macao.
Towards the objectives of the “double carbon target”, the report also points to the importance of “promoting the development of renewable energy, progressively installing photovoltaic electricity production systems in public buildings that meet the necessary conditions, and studying the development of hydrogen technology and its applicability in Macao”.
 
Commercial sector is what consumes the most water
 
As for the quality of water resources, the DSPA report indicates that water salinity remained in the green index - that is, low in salinity - in 2024, proving the trend of the last ten years. Also the annual average value of chloride content decreased almost 19% in homologous terms, remaining “far below” the maximum limits established.
Last year, the volume of invoiced water increased by 5.6% compared to 2023 - mainly driven by tourism and entertainment sectors, as it is possible to verify by the range of increase in Cotai landfills. The increase was transverse to all categories, observing the highest climbs in public use groups and industry. DSPA also highlights the significant increase in the volume of water consumed by the commercial sector, which has already surpassed the consumption of the domestic sector.
Regarding the quality of water from maritime areas, it is emphasized that by 2024 the overall water quality assessment index and the non-metallic exposure evaluation index throughout Macao maritime area rose about 21% compared to 2023. The total daily volume of wastewater treated in Macao showed an equal increasing trend, with an increase of 4.2% compared to 2023.
 
“Under pressure” waste treatment
 
In the report, it appears that by 2024 the amount of discarded urban solid waste and its per capita amount increased by 5.1% and 4%, respectively. DSPA explains that factors such as “population growth, urban construction and tourism industry development, among others, aggravated pressure on the treatment of urban waste from Macao” and justify the slight descent registered in the rate of recyclable waste collection, fixed at 21.7%.
In this chapter, it is read that the amount of construction materials was increased by 13.5% compared to 2023, while the number of special and dangerous waste dropped of 0.9%.
The body recalls that the government has completed the construction of the third phase of the Macao Solid Waste Incineration Center and is currently advancing with the construction work of the organic waste recovery center, "in order to transform even more energy into energy." In parallel, efforts continue to “optimize the recycling network, available more recycling facilities in the community”.
 
More green spaces, but less protected birds
 
The Dsal report reveals an increase in the number of urban green spaces under the management of the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMIs), especially those created on road roads. This growth was particularly expressive on the University of Macao campus, Hengqin Island and Cotai landfills.
Last year, 33 BLA-Black harvesters were sighted in Cotai ecological areas, described as “one of Macau's most precious wet zones, which offer habitats for numerous species of zooplankton, bentonic organisms, fish, insects and birds”. In the previous year of 2023, 19 animals of this species had been spotted, subject to special protection in China.
Both the number of import and re -export certificates of endangered species and the number of processes instituted by violation of the convention on international trade and endangered wildflores (citize) wildlife and wild flora increased 14.6% and 22.2%, respectively.
 
Environmental noise decreases
 
With regard to noise levels, the report shows that the values ​​have been stable over the last few years. Still, last year, there was a slight decrease in environmental noise, while ecological areas presented a growing tendency due to the development of the surrounding area - for example, the beginning of the regular operation of the light meter.
DSPA has six environmental noise monitoring stations - Avenida de Horta e Costa, Cidade de Braga Street, Correia da Silva Street, Ecological Zones, Seac Pai Van and Areia Preta - and the average values ​​registered last year was 65.78 decibels (DB (A)). In 2023, the average of the six monitoring stations was 66.41 dB (A).
The complaints received by public services about excessive noise increased slightly from the 2023 number, continuing to predominate the categories “Conversation and Screams”, “Music and Karaoke” and “Construction Works”.
 
Expenses with environmental protection fell 5.3%
 
Finally, the report made accounts to the public government's public expenses related to environmental protection. According to DSPA, the government spent last year close to 1.9 million patacas, representing 2% of the total expenses and a decrease of 5.3% compared to the same period of the previous year.
"Expenses were mainly intended for the construction and modernization works of recycling and treatment of wastewater and solid waste, construction works for recyclable materials treatment, the operation and maintenance of current environmental infrastructures and the launch of studies and projects related to environmental protection, among others," it reads in the document.
The promotion of environmental management with the companies is another priority focus of DSPA, guarantees the entity, noting that 17 more hotels were rewarded in the 18th edition of the “Hotel Verde Macau Award”. In the same year, there were three more institutions in Macao to obtain the certification of the ISO14001 environmental management system, a norm that ensures companies' commitment to environmental performance and sustainability.
A word is also dedicated to the activities of environmental awareness and dissemination organized by DSPA and AMI, whose number of participants and co-organizers has increased by 2023, while expenses with activities decreased.
Removing themselves on regional cooperation in the environment, the report says that “Macao will continue to develop its advantages, to actively integrate into national development, to participate in the construction of the large Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau Bay, to deepen cooperation and exchange with other cities in the large bay and to promote the development of regional environmental management, jointly building a natural city and a better quality ecological environment”.
 
C.B.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 05:44:22</pubDate></item><item><title>In focus</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/lin-tchi-fa-a-flor-de-lotus-desabrochou-em-chines-e-ingles/</link><description>Lin Tchi Fá: The Lotus Flower blurred in Chinese and English

Lin Tchi Fá-Lotus Flower now has two bilingual versions, in Portuguese-English and Portuguese-chinas, edited by Prail Editions. Maria Anna Acciaioli Tamagnini, originally published in 1925, has a translation of Lian Zimo and Ian Watts.
 
Lin Tchi Fá - Lotus Flower, the work of Maria Anna de Magalhães Colaço Acciaioli Tamagnini, originally published in 1925, is now available not only in Portuguese but in English and Chinese. Prail Editions launched these bilingual editions, with translations of Lian Zimo and Ian Watts and Preface by Sara Augusto. After 1925, the book was in the Shadow, having been published again in 1991 by the Cultural Institute and later in 2006 by Tágide.
Daughter of Judge Manuel de Barros da Fonseca Acciaioli Coutinho and Lia Magalhães Colaço, the author of Lin Tchi Fa was born on July 3, 1900, in Torres Vedras, Portugal. At 16 he began his studies at the Faculty of Letters, in Lisbon, where he met Artur Tamagnini, his teacher, whom he married in 1916.
Artur Tamagnini Barbosa was appointed governor of Macau two years later and Maria Anna accompanied him in her first two missions, in a total of seven years: the first between 1918 and 1919, the second lasted from December 1926 to March 1931. In Macau, Maria Anna Tamagnini greatly prestigious. Natália Correia wrote in 1991 that this was due to the "radiation of her spirit that shone at the flower of the delicate beauty that her portraits show us" and also by the "literary talent with which she sown by newspapers and magazines an remarkable collaboration in verse and prose, also wants to commit social works and protection with which she encouraged arts and letters."
This prestige was not only among the Portuguese community, but also Chinese. In Macao, Maria Anna Acciaioli Tamagnini was a teacher of French and the history of French literature, speaking Portuguese, English, Castilian, Italian and even could be expressed in Cantonese.
In addition to writing, Maria Anna painted, with the East as a frequent theme of her works. As a reader, he opted for Florbela Espanca, Junqueiro War, Eça de Queiroz, Antero de Quental, Fernando Pessoa, Camilo Pessanha and Wenceslau de Morais.
He then published Lin Tchi Fa in 1925, when he was 25 years old. Although it was well received, this was his only book of poems. At 32 he died at the birth of his fifth son.
 
Collection of 32 poems of eastern influence
Lin Tchi Fá - Lotus Flower, which in the first edition had as title poetry of the Far East, together 32 East -themed poems, with Chinese and Japanese influence. The work was well received by critics, recalls Sara Augusto in the preface to this bilingual edition.
"Who was this surprising poet that at the far East, in Macao, hid from the wanton of fame the exotic species of his singular poetry?" Wrote Natália Correia in the preface to the 1991 edition. Natália Correia refers to the symbiosis established between her Portuguese soul, made of "emotion and brown", and the images of the East, made of mystery. It also states that the Parnassian feature of Maria Anna's poetry, visible in concern for the form and elegance of the verses, with the refinement of images and scenarios, is combined with symbolism, "markedly in the precious exotic range of the East that the symbolist imagery was brought down."
In this publication of Prail Editions, Sara Augusto points out that, in addition to the images and scenarios, the Assiduous reading of Camilo Pessanha by Maria Anna reveals itself in orientalism that is not 'decorative, but inner and subtle'. Regarding the possibilities of artistic affiliation, Seabra Pereira, in his Macao Literary Delta, considers that Lin Tchi Fa «is so plausibly tax of this Parnassian tradition as in inherited tendencies of finissecular (decadentist and symbolist) aestheticisms from twentieth century, to a lenifier assimilation by parts of reaction. neo-romantic ».
 
Translation: What challenges?
Ian Watts and Lian Zimo have now made the translation of the lotus flower into English and Chinese, respectively. Watts has its roots in the Portuguese communities of California and HAVAI and graduated in Anthropology and US government at the University of Virginia, and later obtained PhD in Philosophy in Portuguese and Brazilian Studies at the University of Brown. Lian Zimo, for his part, has a bachelor's degree in Portuguese from the University of International Studies of Sichuan, currently pursues the master's degree in Chinese-Portuguese translation at the University of Macau.
The work was presented in the last edition of the Macau Literary Festival - Rota das Letras. In a moderate session by Vera Borges, an associate professor at the Faculty of Humanities and Social Sciences at the City of Macau University, the two translators and Sara Augusto talked about the work. The author of the preface to this edition said that, upon discovering this work of Maria Anna Acciaioli Tamagnini, she was "absolutely amazed by the quality of poetry." "It is not an egocentric literature, it is a poetry that has a narrative aspect, in which the characters evolve as if there was a distance," said the teacher also from the Faculty of Humanities and Social Sciences of the City of Macao, adding that "does not undo the feelings and emotions of the poetic self, it is more than that."
Ian Watts crossed Maria Anna's poetry while investigating the Opium War in Macao. The translator found a text by Artur Tamagnini Barbosa in which the governor defended the opium trade and then came across another text by Maria Anna in which she said it was "the degradation of the human soul," which, the academic supplies, would have brought discussions between the two. That's when the interest in the author began, who led to this English translation.
Already the responsible for translation of the Chinese language spoke about the challenges she found during the process, the main of which was the evolution of the Portuguese language over the 100 years since the original publication of the poems. For Lian Zimo, another of the difficulties of translating the work had to do with the transcripts of the names, which forced her to cross references and to consult various documents. Finally, the cultural context and aesthetics of poetry, for example the translation of the rhymes, also posed challenges to the translator.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 06:01:36</pubDate></item><item><title>COMMA</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/virgula-8/</link><description>José Luís Peixoto
Return to Mozambique
 
Mia Couto is known, perhaps few news I have to give about his work. The pages of Mia Couto are born from Mozambique, but inhabit whole worlds, cross borders. In his hands, this language we speak and wrote becomes an even more living matter, like one of those huge African trees, like a embondeiro, for example. The tongue used by Mia Couto feeds on the earth itself. There is an ancient force in it, as if the words carry echoes of many tongues of many times. Their stories do not close in the real; Mix what you imagine with what you remember. Mia Couto's writing is born from the cross between the human and the invisible. Its narrators often do not know everything, but they present much more than it is accessible to knowledge itself. The characters are people in transformation, there is what they were and there are not yet. Many of them live in injured territories, but are not reduced to it, they are always armed with dignity that does not need to be said, it is evident. What happens in Mia Couto's books is not just a succession of facts: it's a way of looking, listening to what has no name.
All this is recently, over a few days, to have returned to the pages of Flamingo's last flight, more than twenty years after the first reading.
In Mozambique, in the early years of the postwar, Tizangara could have been a vulgar village if the UN soldiers had not started exploding. Without explanation and without leaving any trace beyond their characteristic blue caps and their genitals, the soldiers involved in the peace process "simply began to explode." This is the mystery that the narrator, a translator who does not translate, proposes to us in the text that begins the romance. A mystery that runs through the whole book and remains even after several possible explanations are given. It is up to the reader to decide which one seems to be the right one or which one prefers to believe, because "after all, everything is belief."
Between stories, legends, myths and parables, Mia Couto is building characters, where extreme realism intersects with an extreme fantasy. This is the case of timer, a woman whose face was sentenced to old age only for, during youth, having refused all suitors; Or Sulplício, the narrator's father, who “says” and extends his own bones in a tree before bed, because only invertebrate can really rest. Among many others, there is also the administrator Estêvão Jonas, former combatant of liberation and author of letters to the governor, “comrade excellence”, which constitute some of the most hilarious chapters and where the work of language is evident.
Writing intends to imitate orality, but does not hide a committed search around literary saying. Mia Couto writes badly to write well. That is, it uses grammatical and syntactic “errors” in order to gain more expressiveness. With this writing, with its neologisms and metaphors, Mia Couto is suggesting the huge Mozambique.
Massimo Risi, the United Nations Italian military man who has the arduous task of ascertaining the bizarre mystery of the explosions, is lost in this country, incomprehensible to the eyes of a European. The one that could have been a simple mission with a simple solution turns out to be a trip where the world of the living and the dead, the prosaic and the fantastic, jealousy and love is crossed. With Massimo Risi, we are taken on this trip, where we intersect with the denunciation of racism, social differences, confrontation, veiled or open, between foreigners and nationals or the remnants of colonialism.
That is, absolutely current reflections.
Rereading a novel twenty years later is a curious gesture. The memory of the first reading does not remain intact, dissolved in time, turned into another thing. It was a general impression, a vague atmosphere, perhaps the name of a character, a plot fragment. But all this has already moved away from the book itself. The ideas that resisted evolved, are not exactly the same. However, by advancing the rereading, something happens. The pages are not absolutely new. There are descriptions that light a spark: there is something recognizable there, an old taste. It can be a sentence, the rhythm of the words aligned in a certain order. And you can't be sure if it's a true memory or just the illusion of having been there before.
It is a return and at the same time a debut. The reader of now has not been the same as twenty years, and the book, despite maintaining the same words, has also changed. The rereading is a double meeting: with the work and the memory of the reader who knew her before. It is like following the divisions of an old house, where you lived briefly, recognize shadows, sounds and silences. There is being there, but there is also mystery, there is "this is happening", but there is also "this has happened". Between the past and the present, the world of the book, as a country.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 06:01:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Gwong Dung Waa? Yes, I'm a foreigner… And I speak singer!</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/gwong-dung-waa-sim-sou-estrangeiro-e-falo-cantones/</link><description>Guillaume Leclerc, Álvaro Rodrigues, Mário Tomé, Miguel Lemos and Augusto Fernandes have a common point: they are all outside the territory and learned Cantonese (or Cantonense). Still, they admit: it is no easy task and there are many who give up.
 
 
Anyone who went to Macao without any connection to the earth is often seen in the arms with a difficulty: learning the singing. Children, if they are in a more Chinese environment, are easier. But for adults, the difficulty is added. The end point was to know some stories.
We started with Guillaume Leclerc, the 44 -year -old, born in Lunéville, France, who stopped in Macao for the first time in 2006. “It was only passing, on a great trip through Asia,” he recalls. He returned again to the territory, but only remained here a few days ago, until he decided to settle in 2008. “I was looking for stable sites to settle and had an job offer from the former inter-university institute [current University of St. Joseph] in Macao,” says the computer programmer.
Alone, I wanted to see something "different from the West" and, of course, "learn local culture as well as language." In his workplace, there were Mandarin classes and that's how Guillaume began his way. Still, what he really wanted was to communicate with people in the territory. "Foreigners who do not speak Chinese always say that Mandarin is easier and there are more people to fail, but in my case, considering that they came to live in Macau and the people here did not speak mandarin, I thought it would be better to learn first Cantonese," he says. In fact, he adds, would have several free lessons. “Each time I went to the market or the supermarket, I would be having a free singing class,” he says.
In the Mandarin course, which was attending, he met another foreigner, like him, who gave him some suggestions. “I met Miguel [Lemos], I'm with him and he talks to the lady in Cantonese, I was immediately surprised,” he recalls. The former professor of law at the University of Macao advised him three books and this pointed out the beginning of Guillaume's journey in Cantonese. “These are the best language books I've ever seen,” he says. He followed the model of romanization of Yale Cantonese, as he was in the manuals, and sought, from that moment, to complete one of the 25 lessons a day. “You do one a day, take you half an hour, you will apply what you have learned and work,” he says.
Just practicing with these books, without the support of a teacher, Guillaume kept focus and discipline. “I lived deliberately in the area around Tap Seac Square, in a Chinese environment, I went to the local supermarket, where no one noticed English, and did my lesson of the day,” he says, explaining that this was how he eventually learned. “Speak as much as possible and use the book.”
Arrived in Macao in January 2008, in August went to Taiwan and, when he returned, he realized that something had changed. “I started to realize a lot of what was going on,” he says, adding: “It's like learning to play an instrument: you're trying there and a day when it works.”
Summing up to you now that you think about it, the trick was “to put yourself in uncomfortable situations”, in which she was forced to communicate in Cantonese.
The years have passed and Guillaume still today has with him, every day, two notebooks: one to write down new words, every day, in Cantonese, and another dedicated to Mandarin. In fact, you are now trying to expand your knowledge to Mandarin. “I'm taking classes and I go to hengqin once a week to talk to people,” he reveals.
 
A Portuguese who never gave up
 
Guillaume speaks, nowadays, better than Miguel Lemos, but it was the latter who encouraged him to start. The former professor of law at the 46-year-old University of Macao, who lived in the territory for 15 years and has been in Portugal for a year and a half, remembers his arrival in the territory. In 2006, he soon began learning Cantonese. “I had some classes and then joined someone during the week and we talked,” he recalls.
But what motivated you? It was what was said locally, and in his head it made no sense to "go to a place and make no effort to speak." He then used Guillaume's same books and practiced regularly. Still, with some penalty, it does not consider itself fluent. “I could communicate and have a more complicated conversation using many English terms, without mixing it was impossible,” says the current law professor at the University of Coimbra.
After a year of this process, he felt that, to grow, he also needed to learn Mandarin. “I started taking Mandarin classes and today my Mandarin is better than my singing,” he says. But that's when he began to learn to read that he truly felt to evolve.
The jump to the Mandarin was also due to the lack of offer of courses in Cantonese. "From what I realized, serious courses to learn Chinese were only in Mandarin, at least I don't remember finding anything but those basic classes to say things, some more complicated things than these and stayed right there," he says.
Nowadays, it admits with some penalty, both in Cantonese and Mandarim only feels that "it is enough to communicate and unravel."
 
Communicate at work
 
Mário Tomé, 49, an employee of an electronic systems installation company, has a slightly different story. He was born in Germany, grew in Portugal and decided to go to Macau at the age of 18 to go to some family members. "At the time there was still some disciplines in the 12th grade and, at the same time, working in 'part-time' in a Portuguese restaurant," he says.
When he arrived, he had a "great curiosity" through the territory and thought that if he wanted to stay longer, he would have to learn Cantonese. He also felt motivated because he had some family members they knew. “If they can talk, I will be able to learn,” he says.
At first, the process was difficult, but gradually it became less. “At work, I was trying to learn Cantonese talking to his Chinese colleagues - at first, just a few words, and little by little, he was learning more,” he recalls. By the end of a year, he spoke only "some basic songs," but after three, "I could have more complex conversations." Working in Chinese environments forced him to daily communication, helping him learn faster.
The hardest, he admits, are the shades. "The same word said in another tone has another meaning, and only hearing a complete sentence was that I could see (guess) what they were saying," he recalls. Sometimes I realized "the wrong words" and, on the other hand, also sometimes "tried to speak using direct translation from Portuguese to Chinese and gave grammatical and structural errors." Often, in his efforts to speak Cantonese, he was not realized. And even after several years, he still has a difficulty: "Realizing what is formally spoken, such as a news, because I'm only used to talking informally to people in Macao."
Considering that Cantonese is "enough" in the territory, he has never learned a lot of mandarin. “Even nowadays, when they talk to me in Mandarin, I only understand a few things, it is not enough to have a conversation as I have in Cantonese,” says the Portuguese who resides in the territory.
 
Professional motivation
 
The lawyer Álvaro Rodrigues, 56, learned Cantonese to survive at work. A native of Cape Verde, he was part of the first group of students from Portuguese -speaking African countries to be contemplated with a Macau Foundation scholarship. He arrived in the territory in 1990, to take the course at the University of Macau, and eventually felt that it would be necessary to learn what was spoken in the territory, especially when he arranged a job that implied service to the public. “Being in college, I had a job at the Building Registry Office,” he recalls. “The audience was all Chinese and I spoke very little [Cantonese],” he says. I needed to learn with some speed and therefore hired a private teacher to accelerate the process. "I had in my school curriculum the Cantonese course, but it was not enough, so I had to take private classes to learn more and better Cantonese, so that I could exercise my professional activity," he explains.
I had classes almost every day, because I needed to survive, but adopted a strategy. “I made a selection of what I needed to learn and focused on it,” he recalls.
Nowadays, it is fluent in Cantonese and considers it very useful, even in the exercise of its current professional activity. As a lawyer, when communicating with most of his clients, he feels that he conveys “confidence”, facilitating the work relationship. “I insist on practicing, it makes a lot of difference [at work],” he says.
 
Is learning as a child easier?
 
Augusto Fernandes, 41, was born in Angola and left the country when he was five years old. Roller hockey coach, founded the first skating school in the territory and speaks Portuguese, English and Cantonese to his students.
But let us go back in time. Augusto was five years old when he arrived in Macao and was a little lonely. "There was no one of my color," he recalls, adding, "They also thought I didn't have a good Portuguese accent and, at that time, if I didn't speak Chinese, there was a barrier between me and them."
Therefore, he decided to “pull for himself” and learn from his colleagues. “I walked at Don Bosco College, most of Don Bosco's colleagues were Macanese, that is, they spoke Portuguese and Cantonese,” he says. In these years, he has been learning at school, but also at home. “I saw a lot of Chinese television in my free time,” he says, adding that he was also his mother's private “translator” when she went to the market. “I walked a lot with my mother, she doesn't speak Chinese and I always translated,” he says, highlighting that he gave her pleasure to help her. Then it was also "a bit boring," because he insisted and asked, whenever he tried to communicate and "not realizing a word." Without realizing it, at the age of 8, was already fluent in Cantonese.
Augusto has grown and today has two children, who do not speak Cantonese. “I grew up at Don Bosco, the Portuguese School and the Commercial and the Chinese was always spoken,” he recalls. Nowadays, however, it says that Macau is different. After all, when you leave your children at the Portuguese school, you only hear English. "To learn Chinese, if you are not studying in a Portuguese-chinese school, it will be a little difficult," he says.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 05:43:21</pubDate></item><item><title>US Bank Citigroup dismisses 3,500 employees in China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/06/banco-norte-americano-citigroup-despede-3-500-funcionarios-na-china/</link><description>The US bank citigrigoup fired about 3,500 technology division employees in mainland China, as part of a global cost reduction strategy and operational restructuring, Jornal Financial Times said yesterday.
 
The cuts affect a division based in the cities of Shanghai and Dalian, responsible for the provision of computer services to Citigroup operations in more than 20 countries.
According to the bank, some of the jobs will be relocated to other countries, "to be closer to the business and products they support," without, however, revealing numbers or concrete destinations.
The financial institution also indicated that the process should be completed "at the beginning of the fourth quarter." "Although there is still work to do, many of our efforts have enabled the efficiency of our way of operating, our workforce and the global presence in infrastructure," said Marc Luet, Citi's head to Japan, North Asia and Australia, quoted by the Financial Times.
The bank, which has been present in mainland China since 1902, has ensured that the decision will not have an impact on the banking operations of its Chinese subsidiary, headquartered in Shanghai, nor the Canton -based technology team that continues to provide services to mainland China and Hong Kong.
Third largest United States Bank in terms of assets, Citigroup has sought to resolve persistent operational and profitability challenges through deep restructuring, which included the dismissal of thousands of workers and a simplification of the management structure.
Marc Luet also stressed that Citi "is still committed to moving forward with the creation of a securities and future company company fully detained by the group in China." In recent years, several foreign financial institutions have been trying to obtain full control of their operations in the country, despite the unfavorable economic and geopolitical context.
This cut represents one of the largest discharges registered between foreign financial groups in China in recent years, and reflects a growing trend of frame reduction in the technological area.
In October, Fidelity International cut about 500 jobs in Dalian. IBM announced last summer the elimination of over a thousand positions in the Chinese market.
These discharges are also inserted in a wider context of staff reduction, motivated by the weak dynamic in mergers and acquisition operations and the slowdown of the Chinese economy. According to data compiled by Financial Times, based on the annual reports of local subsidiaries, Western banks reduced their workforce in China by 13% by 2023. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 05:43:15</pubDate></item></channel></rss>