<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/aprovadas-alteracoes-orcamentais-para-este-ano/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Five missing after lands in the center of China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/cinco-desaparecidos-apos-deslizamento-de-terras-no-centro-da-china/</link><description>Five people remain missing following a landslide that buried a residential building in the province of Sichuan, downtown China, where yesterday was registered rainfall. The landslide took place on Tuesday at 10:09 pm local village, in the village of Xuyong, Luzhou City, the China News Service news agency said. According to local weather services, the villages of Hejiang, Xuyong and Gulin were hit by torrential rain between Tuesday afternoon and yesterday dawn, and up to 150 mm of precipitation in just three hours were recorded. The authorities removed 24 residents of the immediate vicinity of the building, which were transferred to a secure zone. Search and rescue operations continue to locate the missing. On Saturday, at least three people died in another landslide in the same province, which hit a highway, dragging several vehicles or leaving them buried. In the latest summers, extreme weather phenomena have caused damage to China, with thousands of affected people and large damage due to heavy rainfall and flooding in various regions of the country.</description><pubDate>2025-07-10 03:33:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ukraine and Russia ask the Pope for help in war -related issues</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/ucrania-e-russia-pedem-ajuda-ao-papa-em-questoes-relacionadas-com-a-guerra/</link><description>Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky, who was received yesterday by Pope Leo XIV at his summer residence, said he has the Vatican to organize a "high level" meeting that end the war. "Of course we want peace, we want this war to end, and we have the Vatican and his holiness to help us find a place for a high -level meeting with the leaders in order to end this war," said Ukraine president when he departs from the audience with the Pope. Zelensky was received by the Pope at his summer residence in Castel Gandolfo, on the outskirts of Rome, where Leo XIV is spending a few days of rest. This was the second official meeting between both since the inaugural mass of its pontificate on 18 May. "I am very grateful for his holiness for this meeting, for receiving us and, of course, for his help and that of the Vatican in relation to our children," said Zelensky, who seeks the help of the Holy See to facilitate the return of "kidnapped" children by Russia during the war. "This is a very important question that the Pope has highlighted, at a very significant moment and that we want deeply," he stressed. In turn, Leo XIV has reported Zelensky the Vatican's availability to host negotiations with Russia, according to a brief statement from the Holy See. “The Holy Father reaffirmed his willingness to receive representatives from Russia and Ukraine at the Vatican for negotiations” of peace, ”the statement says. During this half -hour “cordial meeting”, the two leaders discussed “the ongoing conflict and the urgency of just and lasting peace processes”. In addition, the Vatican added, defended "the importance of dialogue as a privileged path to end hostilities." The Pope "expressed his grief for the victims and renewed his prayer and proximity to the Ukrainian people, encouraging all efforts aimed at liberation from prisoners and demanding shared solutions," he concluded.
Russian court provider Tatiana Moskalkova announced yesterday she sent a letter to Pope Leo XIV to ask for help in the return of Russian citizens in Ukraine. “I went to the Holy See at the Vatican on this subject and sent a letter to Leo XIV to request assistance for the return of our citizens, as this contradicts norms and morals,” Moskalkova said at a press conference in Bismkek, the capital of Kyrguistan. The Russian provider clarified that the letter was sent about three weeks ago through the Apostolic Nuncio and that "has arrived" to the recipient, the Russian news agency Tass said. “I also headed to the UNTO HUMAN RIGHTS of the United Nations [Volker Turk] and the Secretary-General of the Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe [Feridun Sinirlioglu] to ask them to help repatria civilians,” he added. Moskalkova's request is related to 30 people in the Ukrainian region of Sumy and originating from the Kursk Border Russian region, where Ukrainian troops made an incursion in August 2024 and where they were expelled in this year's spring.</description><pubDate>2025-07-10 03:32:56</pubDate></item><item><title>“We don't just sell bread, we sell a meeting with the Philippine Culture”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/nao-vendemos-apenas-paes-vendemos-um-encontro-com-a-cultura-filipina/</link><description>A bakery of culture. Founded by Olinto Oliveira and João de Guzman (JRD), the brand seeks to redesign the experience of a Philippine Bakery, where tradition intersects with a new perspective in every detail. Mano Bakery is a tribute to the cultural roots of the Philippines. The name reflects the spirit of respect for the elders, a philosophy that permeates the whole experience, which aims to create community, promote culture and emancipate creativity. In an interview with the end point, creators show their passion for the Philippine inheritance in an innovative business while facing authenticity challenges and plan a future that unites the past and present in each delicacy.
 
In a busy corner of the mud, the irresistible aroma of fresh bread involves the continuous good mood of a dedicated team. This is where Man Bakery, inaugurated on May 18, is redefining what a Philippine bakery means. Founded by Olinto Oliveira and João de Guzman (known by Nickname JRD), Mano is not just a place to buy bread - it is a cultural experience, a tribute to the roots and a flavors laboratory where the past and the present merge.
The name “Mano” comes from the Philippine Gesture of Respect, in which the youngest leads the hand of an elder to the forehead to receive a blessing. And it is this same spirit that guides the bakery: honor traditions as modern creativity embraces. “We are not a common bakery. We are a platform for sharing culture, creating community, but serving amazing breads,” explains Olinto, while arranging a tray of newly outshed in the oven.
The two founders reveal how they turned a passion for the Philippine inheritance into a prosperous business, the challenges of innovating without losing authenticity and ambitious plans for the future.
 
Where did the idea of ​​creating the bakery “bro” from?
João de Guzman (J.R.D.): One of Mano's main missions is to innovate, but at the same time preserving the Philippine inheritance. There are two parts of the Philippine Community; The older generations, who want to keep things as always, and young people who want to push the boundaries and make their own brand. The idea arose, therefore, in the objective of union: maintaining the tradition of how these sweets and breads are made, but also to try to innovate and move forward. So the name 'Mano' comes from the gesture of asking for blessings from the elders, an expression of respect in Philippine culture. It is a symbol of reverence to our grandparents and parents, to which our ancestors have done, but also to move on and make our own history. When we were thinking of names, this idea really resonated with us. And so it was.
 
Olinto Oliveira (O.O.): For me, as Brazilian, it was interesting because we have something similar in our culture, regarding respect for the elders. This idea of ​​honoring culture, art and heritage, while seeking to raise them, is something we are both in love with. So when John introduced me to the idea, it was easy to accept. And, to top it off, I mean that, although we have no bakery formation, the focus was never just bread. We always wanted to share culture, promote artistic expressions, create a community and a platform where creativity and art can happen.
 
How does the bakery mix the traditional philipine flavors with modern bakery techniques?
O.O.: We have a team of bakers who are in love with what they do. We took a long time to choose a team that was dedicated, to understand their craft and also creative. Our work is divided into two large product groups: a set of products say more “traditional”, such as Pandesal and Coco Pan, which follow the traditional method with great attention to quality and preparation; And another group of products we call “Premium Line”, like Essaymada, which is our best selling product. The traditional test is a very humble recipe, made only with bread, margarine and sugar - for the heart for sure! (laughter). But delicious, very simple and not sophisticated. We thought 'why not raise this?' So we decided to use three different cheeses and a 'cream cheese' stuffing, creating a more creamy, sweet and salty version at the same time. It is a recipe that has an amazing flavor that everyone loves. We still took this to another level with special editions, punctual releases, such as the “Oreo”, UBE or Canela version, which are very popular and that, in our knowledge, no one else in Macau is doing. We also have a diverse team, with some places, others of Philippine and even Indonesia, but many were born and grown here in Macao, which brings a unique view. Our “Poster Head”, JRD, has a very special perspective, as it has grown here and is Filipino, and this further enriches our approach.
J.R.D.: Tests are an example of innovation that also brings affective memories. The older people who were born in the Philippines say they remind her childhood, even with our modern version. We changed the recipe, but we kept the essence that causes these memories. We also create products that mix traditional flavors with innovative ideas, such as the 'Yema Babies' - “YEMA” threads, which is traditionally a sweet Filipino made with milk, but we turn into a cream topping inside the thread. Another example is 'Leche Flan Bao', a bread stuffed with flavors of Flan and Calamansi, which mixes a Philippine recipe based on a Taiwan delicacy, the Bao, which was created by one of our bakers.
 
How is the cultural part of brand experience and online communication integrated? How has the public reception been?
O.O.: Our focus is that the bakery is more than just a place that sells bread and sweets; It is a cultural expression platform! When we make our posts social networks, we are not just selling products, we also tell stories. We want people to understand the Philippine culture behind each delicacy, the story it carries. This approach is a two -way road: it's a conversation, not a message from one direction. For example, our 'Surprise Drops' - Limited Special Products - Many of the ideas come from our own bakers or even public opinions. People may suggest, vote, ask if we can do something specific. We recently made a community vote to decide which product would be in the menu longer. We also have Proofing Room, a monthly series where we highlight local artists, musicians or dancers, using the bakery as a creativity space. Thus bread becomes a universal language, a means of promoting art, music and culture. As for the public opinion, we see that customers are very fond of this interaction. Even with only six weeks of operation we already have loyal clients and a diversity of audience - Philippines, Chinese, expats. Traditional products, such as Pandesal, are popular among the Chinese community, as they appreciate the softer and less sweet flavors.
 
J.R.D.: As Olinto said, we are not just selling bread, we are offering a meeting with the “Pinoy” culture. Our goal is to show that Philippine Culture can be modern, trendy and desirable, even for those who do not know its origin deeply. Despite the short time of operation, the reception has been very positive. The Philippines find it cool and 'Trendy'; The elders feel nostalgia and the places find it interesting to try different flavors, which they may not risk experimenting with a traditional Philippine restaurant. Even though it is a recent operation, we have already sold about 2,000 units per day. We have just started and we are still growing, gradually making adjustments, but our goal is to maintain quality and authenticity while we expand the production scale in a sustainable way.
 
How do they look at the local market and competition, especially with the presence of other cultures and business growth in China?
O.O.: It is an interesting question. Macau is a challenging market, especially with business competition in China, where many people are migrating to start companies or consume. However, because it is a small place, bread is a daily necessity, so there is greater resistance to “cannibalization” between business. Our advantage is that, because they are daily consumer products, they have a constant demand. In addition, we are aware that the Macao bakery market often offers many options with a wide range of products - there are often dozens available in conventional bakeries. We adopted a more similar approach to a Michelin restaurant, with a small menu of 5 to 10 delicacies, well made, focused on quality. Thus, our customers know that they can count on these high quality products always available, but they can also be surprised by news from time to time. The public acceptance has been very good, including among other communities other than Philippine. Authenticity is critical to us, and JRD, which leads communication, ensures that our products are faithful to the roots. This helps transform traditional Philippine flavors into something modern, desirable, which is unique here in Macao.
 
How does a normal working day take place at “Mano”?
J.R.D.: We have a part of the team that works very early, they arrive shortly after midnight, to prepare the mass of the day. Depending on the climate, the fermentation time varies - if it is hot, breads grow faster, if it is raining or colder, it takes longer. That way, around 7am, we already have fresh breads coming out of the oven. Essential products, such as Pandesal and Coco, are made by these “night” bakers, who also train bakery assistants, who now also know how to make the simplest products and start working at 7:30 am when we open the store. Our total team is about 10 people, including the main bakers and assistants. We greatly value the feeling of participation and pride in the team, encouraging them to get involved as they help in preparing all products and are free from creating new delicacies. Our production flow is focused on peak times: in the morning, with the breakfast movement, and at night, with the end of the day of work. We are also developing salty products that serve as breakfast, such as the 'Canned Beef Brekkie'-bread with meat and Calamansi sauce-to diversify the menu. Our goal is that the whole team knows how to make all products so that we can maintain quality and gradually climb the production.
 
What are the future plans of the brand?
O.O.: The plan is that the opening of the bakery is just the beginning. Phase two is already underway, with the launch of 'Proofing Room', a monthly initiative where we invite local artists - musicians, dancers, visual artists - to expose their work. We are also thinking of developing gift sets, with personalized products and special packages, to create a single memory. We want to turn the brand into a platform that is not just about the bakery itself, but into a creative community. Food will always be a catalyst to unite people, and our idea is to expand this connection with events, workshops, gift products and collaborations with local artists. There are still plans to expand besides Macao, carrying this Philippine culture in an innovative way, with cafes of Philippine origin, cultural events, and more activities that promote local creativity. The idea behind this initiative, as we advanced on this journey and, as we conceived bakery, was to create something that, when experienced by customers, could make your day a little better. Whether for the pleasure of enjoying good bakery products, or simply contacting a friendly and welcoming team, the goal was to provide a positive experience. As entrepreneurs, I can say that it has been a very rewarding experience, as it not only allows us to create something of value, but also offers us a sense of personal fulfillment.
 
JRD: Exactly. For the future, we want to consolidate our presence, create a community of faithful clients and also collaborate with other local artists and creative. The idea is that the bakery is a meeting space, where culture, art, music and gastronomy complement each other. We are planning to launch cultural events and be present on special occasions such as birth parties or birthdays. In addition, we want to continue to innovate in flavors and techniques, always with authenticity and a modern "footprint". Our goal is that the brand will be recognized as a symbol of culture, creativity and local community.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>ALS President says that meetings at the closed door avoid “unnecessary controversy in society”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/presidente-da-al-diz-que-reunioes-a-porta-fechada-evitam-controversia-desnecessaria-na-sociedade/</link><description>Yesterday the new rules of the Legislative Assembly (AL) were approved. Some of the changes have generated discord, in particular the fact that the deputies are prohibited to publicly reveal the content of the committees' meetings, except the president and the secretary of the respective commission. Coutinho and Ron Lam criticized this point, but the generality of other deputies defended the measure. Kou Hoi In, president of AL, even said that confidentiality in relation to the meetings serves to protect the confidentiality of the opinions of the deputies and "so that they can speak at ease."
 
The new Legislative Assembly (AL) Regiment, approved yesterday, foresees, for example, that the deputies are prohibited to reveal the content of the committees' meetings, with the exception of the president and secretary of the same commissions. This point generated discord in yesterday's debate, with Ron Lam and Pereira Coutinho claiming that the measure will make these meetings even more opaque.
The diploma, presented by the deputies who are part of the AL Regiment and Mandates Commission, now states that “the deputies cannot reveal, in any case, the content of the commission meetings that take place at the closed door”, except for the President and the Secretary of the said commission.
Coutinho and Ron Lam have asked for transparency, but Ho Ion Sang, one of the proponent deputies of the bill, reiterated that the tribunes “have to fulfill the duty of secrecy”, and at the end of the meetings, journalists can already ask questions to the president and the secretary. "This formula has achieved good results," said Ho Ion Sang. Iau Teng Pio, another of the proponents, said that the purpose of this norm is that government representatives, advisory and deputies "can discuss at will."
Kou Hoi In, president of AL, defended the change to regiment, stating that the new standard "prevents there is unnecessary controversy in society." Moreover, "the opinions of deputies must be protected," Kou justified, adding that "the reserve character is so that they can speak at ease during the meeting." "We have to protect the deputies. We have to ensure confidentiality," he concluded.
Song Pek Kei also came out in defense of the new regiment and said it is sufficient that only the president and the secretary of each commission can comment publicly what was said inside the room. Chui Sai Peng stated that the change was "necessary and appropriate." Pang Chuan, in turn, recalled that the norm can prevent deputies from publicly publicizing the content of social networks meetings, as happened in the past, according to themselves.
After the discussion, this point was eventually approved with the votes against Pereira Coutinho and Ron Lam. All other deputies voted in favor.
In the chapter of the duties of the deputies, a paragraph is added that obliges parliamentarians to attend plenary meetings and the committees to which they belong and present “committed opinions and suggestions”. This point also generated some tension of the hemicycle. Coutinho asked the al coordinate the schedules so that the deputies can also go to the committee meetings to which they do not belong. Chan Chak Mo, president of the 2nd Alternate Commission of AL, said it is difficult to coordinate the times between the commissions and said that, despite the request, Coutinho rarely attended the committee meetings to which he does not belong. To this provocation, Coutinho responded with another and said that the lack of available schedules could be resolved with weekend meetings, noting that it would be availability, unlike “businessmen”, in reference to businessman Chan Chak Mo.
In addition, this alteration to AL regiment also prohibits that during meetings, deputies wear clothes or signs, banners, signs or other objects with “offensive content or political provocation, or to undermine the dignity of the AL”.</description><pubDate>2025-07-10 03:35:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Lo Choi in asks for the return of electronic consumer valleys</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/lo-choi-in-pede-regresso-dos-vales-de-consumo-electronico/</link><description>Representative Lo Choi in warned yesterday to the poor strength of the region's economy, which is leading to breakage in the purchasing power of residents and the decrease in the shopkeepers' turnover. Therefore, Lo Choi in suggested that the government stimulates consumption through, for example, the assignment of electronic valleys to residents.
 
Lo Choi in suggested the return of the electronic consumption valleys yesterday. At the plenary meeting of the Legislative Assembly (AL), the deputy was pessimistic about the future of the region's economy, demanding measures to the government.
In his intervention before the agenda, Lo Choi In noted that, "when GDP returned to grow, the rate of default on real estate mortgage loans reached the highest historical level." On the other hand, "when the unemployment rate remained at 2.5%, the underemployment rate was multiple times higher than the pre-pound period" and "when the number of visitors reached a new record, per capita consumption gradually decreased." These factors show that "the benefits brought by visitors, besides not covering all community neighborhoods and sectors, gradually decreases other marginal benefits, beyond the game taxes," he said.
Lo Choi in said that when the government speaks of "stimulating consumption," this "already demonstrates that our economic environment is very weak." "The yields of the citizens have diminished a lot and the tenants are suffering a lot," said the deputy.
Thus, the deputy suggested that the government give priority to the implementation of a regular plan of awards and incentives for consumption and not so much to the promotion of "check-in" points and the intellectual property economy. This is because, the deputy said, the effectiveness of this type of initiative is not consensual.
“I urge the government that, while the engine of economic diversification does not yet work, at this difficult and crucial time for the integration of both regions, take advantage of the public purse to again distribute the electronic consumption valleys, even if only two or three thousand patacas, in order to support families from the lowest social strata, the people in disappearance, the elderly, etc. The public purse constituted "a healthy internal circle in the community economy."
The deputy elected by the way he asked the executive not to replace “the policies for activities”, since, “in addition to long -term integration between Hengqin and Macau, it is necessary to find a way to the local economy, namely, to take advantage of the dismissed lands, advance with active investment and exploit more economic sectors”.
Lo Choi also asked for the reinforcement of support for social and education institutions, so that young people have more professional exits and job opportunities, "widening the social security network and reducing the occurrence of tragedies."</description><pubDate>2025-07-10 03:34:56</pubDate></item><item><title>China discovers deposit with 490 million tons of lithium and other minerals</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/china-descobre-deposito-com-490-milhoes-de-toneladas-de-litio-e-outros-minerais/</link><description>China, the second country in the world with largest identified lithium reserves, discovered a new deposit with about 490 million tons of this and other minerals, the state press yesterday. According to the Provincial Department of Natural Resources, the deposit was located in the Jijiaoshan Minas Gerais zone, in the municipality of Linwu, in the central province of Hunan, and contains approximately 1.31 million tons of lithium oxide, as well as rubidio, tungsten and tin. The discovery resulted from years of prospecting and the application of new geological exploration technologies, said the Hunan Mineral Resources Measurement Institute, quoted by the Chinese Official News Agency Xinhua. According to Xu Yiming, a professor at the Institute, the resources found should support the development of the new energy industry in the city of Chenzhou, also located in Hunan. According to data from the Chinese Ministry of Natural Resources, China recently exceeded the United States and became the second country in the world with largest identified lithium reserves, behind Bolivia, with an increase of 16.5% compared to 2024. The discovery occurs at a time when China intensifies efforts to explore domestic resources, with the aim of reinforcing energy security and access to strategic raw materials Global competition for minerals such as lithium, crucial for the production of batteries used in electric vehicles.</description><pubDate>2025-07-10 03:32:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Teams look for 19 missing after floods that killed nine in Nepal</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/equipas-procuram-19-desaparecidos-apos-enchentes-que-mataram-nove-no-nepal/</link><description>Nepal authorities continued yesterday the search operations for missing, after flooding caused by heavy rainfall destroyed the main bridge with China and caused at least nine dead.
According to the Rasuwa District Administration, the floods of the Bhotekoshi River in the north of the country dragged the Friendship Bridge in Rasuwagadi, about 120 kilometers from the capital, Katmandu.
Nine bodies have already been recovered from Rio, while 55 people were rescued alive, including four Indian and one Chinese citizens.
Authorities reported 19 missing, including 13 Nepalese and six Chinese citizens.
According to the China Embassy in Nepal, cited by the state press, the Chinese and eight of the Nepalese worked in a construction project supported by Beijing, on the Nepalese side of the border.
The floods occurred at dawn on Tuesday and also destroyed several houses, as well as trucks awaiting customs inspection by the border, including hundreds of electric vehicles imported from China.
Nepal Prime Minister Khadga Prasad Oli went to the scene, accompanied by several ministers and high employees, after convening an emergency meeting on the day before rescue and assistance efforts.
The destruction of the bridge completely interrupted the trade between Nepal and China through that road. The nearest alternative now implies the transport of goods by ship from China to India and then terrestrial to Nepal.
The monsoons, which take place between June and September, often cause severe flooding in Nepal, with damage to infrastructure and risk to populations.</description><pubDate>2025-07-10 03:33:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Wu Zhiliang continues in the lead of the Macau Foundation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/wu-zhiliang-continua-na-lideranca-da-fundacao-macau/</link><description>Wu Zhiliang will continue to lead the Macau Foundation. According to an order published yesterday in an official bulletin, signed by the chief executive Sam Hou Fai, the appointment of Wu Zhiliang was renewed as chairman of the Macao Foundation Board of Directors, with a period of one year.
Wu Zhiliang joined the Macau Foundation in 1988, and began the leadership of this public institution in 2010, and was also president of the Federation of Macao Cultural Sectors and member of the Chinese people's Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC).
With this mandate renewal, Wu Zhiliang will earn the monthly remuneration corresponding to index 1,100 of the Public Official Indicion Table, which corresponds to about 103,000 patacas per month.
In the same order is also the renewed appointment of Zhong Yi Seabra de Mascarenhas as vice president of the Macau Foundation Board of Directors, for a period of one year, being assigned the monthly remuneration corresponding to index 960 of the civil service evidence, corresponding to about 90 thousand patacas per month.
The Chief Executive also renewed the nominations for the Macau Foundation Fiscal Council, with Vong Hin Fai to continue to hold the position of President, and Ho Mei and Lau Veng Lin to remain as members of the Fiscal Council.
In an official bulletin, another order from Sam Hou Fai announced the appointment of four new members to the Macau Foundation's curators council, including
André Duarte Xavier Sales Ritchie, architect, former deputy coordinator of the defunct Cabinet for Transport Infrastructure and current member of the Advisory Board for Municipal Affairs; Cheang Hong Kuong, professor and leader of the Macao Education Association; Lok Wai Kin, Professor of Law at the University of Macao; and Choi Chi Tou, editor-in-chief of the newspaper or Mun and member of CCPPC.
The appointment of the members of this body was also renewed, including Iong Weng Ian, Carlos Marreiros, Chan Meng Kam, Leong on Kei, Lao Ion Fai, Chan Hong, Ng Siu Lai, Mok Chi Wai, Cristina Neto Valente, Chan Wa Keong, MA Chi Wa, Liu Ca Seng.
In this sense, from the Macau Foundation's curators board are Anabela Sales Ritchie, Pui Lam and Lok Po.</description><pubDate>2025-07-10 03:33:28</pubDate></item><item><title>China rejects EU criticism and states that its development is an opportunity</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/china-rejeita-criticas-da-ue-e-afirma-que-o-seu-desenvolvimento-e-oportunidade/</link><description>The Chinese government said yesterday that the country's development represents "an opportunity for the European Union (EU), not a challenge," rejecting criticism from the president of the European Commission, Ursula von der Leyen.
 
"China's industrial subsidy policies are in full compliance with the World Trade Organization (WTO) rules and are open and transparent," Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Mao Ning said. Mao appealed to the EU to “not amplify specific problems” and defended a “bidirectional opening” relationship between Brussels and Beijing.
The spokeswoman also criticized the existence of “invisible barriers” for Chinese companies in the European market and pointed out as an example the recent decision to exclude Chinese firms from public tenders in the area of ​​medical devices, considering that it is a measure “far from fair and open”.
On Tuesday, Ursula Von Der Leyen warned that Europe faces "real risks" of a "strategic and systemic" nature for its safety and competitiveness, resulting from the fact that China operates with a completely different system and unique instruments to play the margin of the rules "commercial rules.
Beijing and Brussels have registered some reconnament in recent months, in a context marked by the trade war between China and the United States, driven by US President Donald Trump. Nevertheless, divergences persist between EU and China, both in the commercial and geopolitical level, especially with regard to war in Ukraine, in the face of which Beijing has kept an ambiguous position.
The Chinese government also rejected the interference in its relations with Russia, after Ursula Von der Leyen appealed to Beijing to end his “unshakable support” to Moscow in the war against Ukraine. "Normal cooperation between China and Russia does not admit interference from third parties," Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Mao Ning said at a press conference. Mao assured that the ties between Beijing and Moscow "are not directed against any third part."
The statements arise in response to criticism from von der Leyen, who said the day before, during a debate in the European parliament, that "the unshakable support of China to Russia is creating great instability and insecurity for Europe." "We can say that, in practice, China is allowing Russia's war economy - and this is not acceptable," said the leader of the community executive, stressing that the way Beijing continues to interact with the Vladimir Putin war will be determining for the future of relations between the European Union (EU) and China.
Von der Leyen is expected to visit Beijing in late July, accompanied by European Council Chairman António Costa for a summit who will mark the 50 years of diplomatic relations between the two parties.
Since the beginning of the Ukraine large -scale Russian invasion in February 2022, China has deepened its ties with Moscow, which has generated concern in Brussels.
Beijing has maintained an ambiguous position in relation to the conflict, appealing to “respect for the territorial integrity of all countries, including Ukraine”, but also the consideration of “legitimate security concerns from all parties” in reference to Russia. Several Western countries have accused China of supporting the Russian war effort, something Beijing has been repeatedly denied.
 
China denies having pointed to laser the German plane in the Red Sea
 
China yesterday refused Berlin's accusation that he pointed to a laser to a German plane in the Red Sea, considering these allegations "completely incompatible with the facts." "Both parties should adopt a pragmatic attitude, reinforce communication in a timely manner and avoid misunderstandings and calculation errors," Chinese Foreign Ministry spokeswoman Mao Ning said.
Germany said on Tuesday that an aircraft plane was shot July 2 by a Chinese laser in the Red Sea. China's ambassador to Berlin was summoned by the German Ministry of Foreign Affairs.
The plane was participating in Operation Aspides from the European Union to protect maritime traffic against the attacks of the Houthis rebels in Yemen.
The German plane was targeted by the laser “for no reason or prior contact” by a Chinese war ship during a routine surveillance flight, according to a German Ministry of Defense spokesman.
Using the laser, the Chinese ship “risked people and equipment in danger,” he added, without specifying the nature of the used laser. Mao Ning indicated that Chinese ships perform escort missions in the Gulf of Aden and Somalis waters, "thus contributing to the safety of international maritime routes."
China has been accused several times of maritime intimidation with lasers. In February 2023, a ship from his navy was accused of using a “military laser” against a Philippine Coast Guard ship in the Southern Sea of ​​China. In 2022, Australia accused the Chinese army of pointed out a military laser to one of its planes in northern Australia.
Since 2017, China has been a Djibuti military base, with access to the Gulf of Aden, at the Red Sea Foz, allowing Beijing to protect its huge geopolitical and economic interests (transport, industry, energy) in the region. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-10 03:33:29</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korea delivers to Pyongyang six North Koreans rescued at sea</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/coreia-do-sul-entrega-a-pyongyang-seis-norte-coreanos-resgatados-no-mar/</link><description>South Korea handed over to Pyongyang six North Koreans who had been rescued at sea several months ago and had asked to return to their country. The rescued had apparently crossed the sea border accidentally and asked to be returned to North Korea.
 
The South Korean Unification Ministry announced yesterday the delivery to Pyongyang of six North Koreans who had been rescued at sea several months ago and had asked to return to their country.
"The South Korean government today repatrized six North Koreans through the East Sea," Korean name for the Japan Sea, the ministry said in a statement. "With the full consent of all involved, the six North Koreans were repatriated together," he said.
In early June, South Korea announced that it rescued four North Koreans in May, whose boat was alleged to drift in territorial waters in the Japan Sea.
The South Korean navy “detected a small North Korean wooden boat about 100 kilometers from the coast of Goseong”, on the east coast of South Korea, a military spokesman said.
According to South Korean news agency Yonhap, the rescued had apparently crossed the sea border accidentally and asked to be returned to North Korea. The four were delivered "to the competent [South Korean authorities]," the military said.
North Korean deserters are usually subject to interrogation by South Korean security services.
Seoul stated at the time that he was still awaiting a response from Pyongyang about the repatriation of two North Koreans found in similar circumstances three months ago in the Yellow Sea, located between China, North Korea and South Korea. North Koreans returned to the north "on his own," said the South Korean unification ministry.
The ministry has assured that "worked in cooperation with relevant agencies to ensure the fast and safe return of the North Koreans from a humanitarian perspective."
Last week, a North Korean crossed the land border with South Korea in the demilitarized zone, then intercepted and detained.
In early June, in the inaugural speech, the new South Korean Center President Lee Jae-Myung said he wanted to approach North Korea in a speech that contrasts with the hard line of the deposed predecessor, Yoon Suk-Yeol.
North Korea suspended, in practice, almost all diplomacy and direct communication with the south after the collapse of nuclear negotiations with the United States in 2019. Lusa.</description><pubDate>2025-07-10 03:33:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Open Renewal of Quotas for the Circulation of Macao Private Vehicles in Hong Kong</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/aberta-renovacao-de-quotas-para-circulacao-de-veiculos-particulares-de-macau-em-hong-kong/</link><description>The government is already accepting requests for regular quota renewal for the circulation of Macao private vehicles between Macau and Hong Kong, on the Delta Bridge, by the quota holders for the years 2018 and 2019. Opening of requests was announced yesterday by the Directorate of Service for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) and the renewal in question is valid for a period of three years.
Holders of the interested quotas that meet the necessary requirements may, within 90 days prior to the date of the term of the quota or to the date of the expiration term, access the DSAT Electronic System to comply with formalities, making the payment of the respective rate, in the amount of 1,000 patacas online. The amounts paid will not be, in any case, reimbursed. The quota will be canceled and redistributed, if the holder has not submitted the request for renewal until the term of validity of the quota.
According to the DSAT note, the holders of the quotas covered by this renewal do not need to maintain their qualification related to Hong Kong, as required when obtaining the quota.
Thus, the holder of quota for a private entity does not need to do paid work in Hong Kong, or to constitute a company registered in Hong Kong, or to have houses/shops/land in Hong Kong. Already the holder of quota for commercial entity does not need to stop more than 50% of the actions of a subsidiary company in Hong Kong, nor to be a company registered in Macao and Hong Kong, nor to be linked to another company registered in Hong Kong.
DSAT, however, points out that the holders of commercial entity shares shall comply with the provisions of point 3 of the remarks contained in the announcement of renewal, that is, within the validity period of the quota, it will be the same canceled if one or more, more than 50% of the corporate capital of the company of Macau, except for transfer by succession.
The authorities say that they will perform periodic or random inspection of the situation of the share capital of quota companies, and the appropriate measures are taken in case of verification of violation.</description><pubDate>2025-07-10 03:33:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Consumer prices rise 0.1% in China in June after four months of falls</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/precos-no-consumidor-sobem-01-na-china-em-junho-apos-quatro-meses-de-quedas/</link><description>ECONOMY
 
China's consumer price index rose 0.1% in June, in homologous terms, the first increase after four consecutive months of descents, the country's statistical agency yesterday indicated. The data surprised the analysts, who predicted a new price contraction, after a 0.1% drop in May.
According to Dong Lijuan, statistic of the National Statistics Office, the measures adopted by the government to stimulate internal demand and encourage consumption “continued to have an effect” in June.
The second largest world economy remains under deflationary pressure due to the combination of poor internal demand and excessive industrial capacity, aggravated by trade war with the United States, which has hindered the flow of inventories accumulated by companies.
Deflation (annual drop in consumer prices) reflects weakness in domestic consumption and investment and is particularly severe, as a drop in the price of assets, as a rule, generates an imbalance between the value of loans and bank guarantees.
Chinese authorities have reiterated that reinforcement of internal demand will be one of the central economic priorities for 2025.
The same source also released the price index in the producer, which measures the prices to exit the factory, which accentuated the 3.3% drop in May to 3.6% in June, the lowest value since July 2023.
The descent was greater than the forecasts of the market, which pointed to a lower contraction.
Dong Lijuan warned that some export -oriented industries are “under pressure” in terms of price and “uncertainty in global trade has affected the expectations of exporting companies”.
In May, Beijing and Washington agreed a temporary 90-day pact, for which China would reduce US products from 125% to 10%, while the US would decrease its rates on Chinese goods from 145% to 30%.</description><pubDate>2025-07-10 03:33:27</pubDate></item><item><title>DSEDT and Local Trade Sector look at Portugal and France to expand business</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/dsedt-e-sector-local-do-comercio-online-olham-para-portugal-e-franca-para-expandir-os-negocios/</link><description>A delegation composed of representatives of economics and technological development services and the Macao Electronic Trade sector made a visit to Portugal and France this month. Authorities emphasize that the initiative reinforced the exchange and transfrontic cooperation in the commercial area and helped extend the parties' international business.
 
The Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) again took the sector of Macao Transfronic Electronic trade to a visit abroad, but this time was, for the first time, Europe, namely Portugal and France.
Authorities have organized a delegation composed of representatives of the e-commerce industry for a visit to Portugal and France this month, with the aim of "looking for new opportunities for transfronical cooperation in the field of e-commerce."
According to the body, the delegation participated in various activities, such as exchanges with local commercial associations and sectors, stores visits and live tracking live transmission, ie a live transmission that presents the products of their manufacture and processing to packaging.
The DSEDT thus hopes to promote the development of the Macao Transfronic Electronic Trade sector, reinforcing exchange and international cooperation, as well as “valuing the role of internal and external connection” played by the territory.
Regarding the visit to Lisbon, according to a statement from DSEDT, the delegation made a series of promotional actions, visiting Portuguese neighborhoods and a wine cellar where a live broadcast was made to the interior market of China, during which the Chinese consumers were presented to the wines and soaps of Portugal, and the essential oils and food and 'Big Health' of Macao.
Online promotion got about 6,000 transactions with a turnover of over 1.1 million patacas, "demonstrating the potential of real -time electronic trade," he said.
The delegation also had meetings with the Luso-Chinese Association of Traders and Industrialists, the Luso-Chinese Chamber of Commerce and Industry and the representatives of local companies, under the expansion of markets in the interior of China and Macau by the companies based in Portugal.
In addition, in its passage in Paris, the delegation visited Bonjour Brand, Printemps and Galeries Lafayette, in order to take knowledge of the new trends in the local consumer market and discuss with those responsible events eventual opportunities for cooperation with the brands of French SMPs.
Representatives of the DSEDT and the Macao Live Transmission Association moved to the Government Agency of Trade Choose Paris Region, having met with the heads responsible for the Asia-Pacific region, hoping to promote economic and commercial cooperation between the two parties through the transfringing electronic commerce.
In the statement, the government ensures that it has been encouraging the reconversion of traditional industries and promoting the use of transionic electronic trade and live transmission by SMEs to explore markets, and has also provided support for the formation of qualified frames in this field.
According to the authorities, the initiative "reinforced the ties and interactions between Macao and Portugal and France in the transionic electronic trade sector, helping the products of Portuguese -speaking countries to develop the interior market of China," said DSEDT, stating that the trip "has made room for the interior of the interior of China to develop their international business."</description><pubDate>2025-07-10 03:33:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Coutinho praises Raehk's government for the opening of the Cristiano Ronaldo Museum</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/coutinho-elogia-governo-da-raehk-pela-abertura-do-museu-de-cristiano-ronaldo/</link><description>José Pereira Coutinho used his intervention before the agenda, at the plenary meeting of the Legislative Assembly yesterday, to leave praise to the Hong Kong authorities for the opening of the Cristiano Ronaldo Museum in the neighboring region.
Without referring to Macau, the deputy listed the various factors that Hong Kong could benefit from the opening of the CR7 Museum: "The CR7 Museum in Hong Kong will not only boost tourism and the local economy, but also reinforce the city's image as a dynamic and diverse global destination."
In addition, Coutinho defended the museum dedicated to the Portuguese footballer in Hong Kong will bring “various economic benefits” to the neighboring region, such as “direct recipes with entry tickets, merchandising stores and interactive experiences (such as soccer simulators)”. It will also “benefit restaurants, hotels, transport and logistics due to the increase of visitors”.
The museum will also reinforce “the image of Hong Kong, as a cultural and sports destination, and not only, a financial center, but also a hub of culture, entertainment and sports, and can attract other sports events or similar exhibitions in the future,” said the president of the Macao Public Function Workers Association (ATFPM).
"There is no doubt that Raehk rulers are more pragmatic in foreign investment attraction, acting with dexterity and speed in approval initiatives that bring quick economic return on policies and strategies focused on economic growth, where a pragmatic mindset, well -delineated plans and concrete results oriented," concluded Coutinho.
The CR7 Life Museum opened to the public last Monday, at K11, in Tsim Sha Tsui, and it can be known a little more about the career of the Portuguese star, from the origins in Madeira to the present, in the Saudi Arabia al-Nassr.</description><pubDate>2025-07-10 03:32:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Photographic dialogues without borders in the new edition of Halftone</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/dialogos-fotograficos-sem-fronteiras-na-nova-edicao-da-halftone/</link><description>Photography is the art that captures time and at the same time releases it. Today, the Rui Cunha Foundation opens the doors to the launch of Halftone #12 magazine, an edition that brings together six distinct visual projects, between black and white and the chromatic explosion. The publication consolidates itself once again as a space for contemporary photography, where female intimacy and vastness of Alentejo, Macaense tradition and urban modernity is evidenced. A late afternoon to see the world through multiple lenses, which starts at 6.30 pm. 
 
A magazine that portrays the world from six perspectives. Today, at 6.30 pm, the Rui Cunha Foundation features the launch of Halftone #12, the latest issue of Halftone's Quarter -Right Magazine - Macau Photography Association. The session, conducted in English by Francisco Ricarte and Sara Augusto, will present the publication and diversity of contemporary photography through the work of six artists.
The publication, which has already stated as a reference in promoting photography in the region, maintains its inclusive character, welcoming both professionals and enthusiasts. As in preceding paragraphs, the National Bank Overseas (BNU) ensures sponsorship, reinforcing its commitment to non -profit culture and art.
Edition #12 opens and closes with two black and white projects, which explore different contrasts and narratives, between intimacy and visual poetry. Jane Xu, with “Black Enlivened by Colors”, plunges into female intimacy, continuing her thematic research on identity and representation. Already João Palla ends the magazine with the second part of "White Gold whispers", a poetic sequence where the game of light and shadow transcends the mere aesthetic, inviting a deeper reflection, among geometric shapes on the earth.
The four central projects of Halftone #12 explore color in all its expressiveness, from its form as language, memory and tradition it carries. Jorge Veiga Alves transports the public to “Memories of Macau”, capturing traditional spaces, especially of religious nature, in an approach that evokes nostalgia and spiritual contemplation.
José Luís de Sales Marques stands out again, this time with an essay dedicated to the procession of Senhor dos Passos, an emblematic event of Macao. Their images not only document tradition, but also underline the integration of this cultural manifestation in the urban fabric of the city, in the mix of Portuguese and Chinese inheritances.
António Duarte Mil-Homens takes us to Alentejo with “Sunset, Moonrise”, a visual meditation on the passage of time and the immensity of the plain. The succession of shades - from the golden twilight to the blue of moonlight - transforms the landscape into a sensory experience.
In the penultimate project, Tang Kuok has challenges urban perception with “photosynthesis”, a work that reinterprets Macao through a polychromatic palette. The city emerges as a photographic laboratory, where color not only defines spaces, but also emotions and experiences. An expressive experience in photography.
Since its inception, Halftone has been affirmed as an innovative editorial project, becoming a platform without borders for experimentation in Macau, promoting photography as a form of art and document. Open to all interested parties, regardless of experience, the association continues to foster a dialogue between different looks and techniques.
The launch of Halftone #12 will therefore be another testimony of the dedicated work of the Association team. It is not limited to the mere presentation of a new magazine, being a meeting of perspectives, a celebration of photography as a universal language. For image lovers, today it will be a night to see, feel and, above all, dialogue with the world through the lens of six artists.  The entrance is free.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Beijing announces issuance of national obligations in Macao worth six billion RMB</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/pequim-anuncia-emissao-de-obrigacoes-nacionais-em-macau-no-valor-de-seis-mil-milhoes-de-rmb/</link><description>This is already the fourth consecutive year in which the Chinese government launches national obligations in Macao. The central government has confirmed that it will issue debt securities on 16 July, in a amount of 6 billion Renminbi, the highest amount compared to previous editions. This issue “will help attract international investors to participate in the obligation of the territory”, defend local authorities.
 
The central government will issue national obligations in Macao worth six billion Renminbi, and the emission will take place next Wednesday, 16 of this month, intended for professional investors.
The information was advanced yesterday by the authorities, in citing the announcement jointly from the Ministry of Finance of the Government of the Popular Republic of China and the Government of MSAR, highlighting the objective of "supporting the development of the obligation" market "from the territory.
"The continuous emission of national obligations in Macao demonstrates the importance and support of the central government regarding the cultivation of new areas of financial activities in Macau, such as the obligationary market, and the promotion of diversified development of the economy of Macao," says the executive. The government greeted the finance decision in Beijing and expressed its "sincere thanks" to the central government.
In addition, the emission “will help attract international investors to participate in the Macao's obligationary market, will promote the development of the‘ offshore ’market [Renminbi] in Macao and will deepen financial cooperation between the interior of China and Macao”, can be read in the note.
According to information released, this emission represents the fourth consecutive year in which the central government issues national obligations in Renminbi in Macao, and the fifth time of the issue.
The government applauded Beijing's approach considering that “it contributes to reinforcing the improvement of the regular emission mechanism”, in addition to providing “investors in secure and stable investment options, and playing a positive role in improving Macao's obligation to further infrastructures, further optimizing the structure of the investor base and accelerating the progress of connection to the international market,” he defended.
Authorities have added that a constant increase in terms of the amount of emission has been verified over the last few years. It is recalled that in October last year, the Chinese Ministry of Finance issued debt titles in the amount of five billion Renminbi, amount equal to the previous edition dated September 2023.
In 2022 national obligations were issued by three billion Renminbi and in 2019 worth two billion Renminbi.
The Macao government has mentioned the possible creation of a 'offshore' stock market, called Renminbi, linked to the role that the region has taken as a platform for commercial and financial services between China and Portuguese -speaking countries.
In January, Macau's financial regulator said the central banks of Angola and Timor -Leste are interested in issuing a public debt to the territory to attract mainland China investors.
Henrietta Lau Hang Kun, a member of the Board of the Monetary Authority of Macao, said the institution has been trying to promote the territory as "a financial service platform with Lusophone countries." "For now, we are still negotiating with Lusophone countries" so that the debt issuance "passes here, through Macao, to the [China] market," added Henrietta Lau.
In May 2019, Portugal became the first country in the eurozone to issue debt in Chinese currency, worth two million Renminbi.</description><pubDate>2025-07-10 03:32:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Approved budgetary changes for this year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/10/aprovadas-alteracoes-orcamentais-para-este-ano/</link><description>The deputies to the Legislative Assembly (AL) approved yesterday, in the specialty, the budgetary scrambles proposed by the government to meet the game revenues of the beginning of the year that were below expectations.
The debate took place without start -up and the deputies had no substantial doubts, however, Ron Lam again insisted that the government should have made a public consultation before moving forward to the awards to the attribution of the pecuniary check, which from now on are only for residents who are 183 days a year in Macao, taking some exceptions.
In this budgetary review for 2025, the government predicts that casinos gross revenues are located at 228 billion patacas, instead of the 240 billion that were registered in the budget presented in December last year. Tax revenues from the game industry represent more than 80% of all of the FIE tax revenues. Thus, the total amount of revenues enrolled in this new budget becomes 116.5 billion patacas, while the previous budget referred to revenues of 121 billion.
This budget review also provides for an increase in expenses throughout this year. Previously, the expenses registered had 113 billion patacas and now they are 116.2 billion. This increase, according to the government, is due to the construction of the Campus of the University of Macao in Hengqin and the investment in research and scientific and technological development. The new UM HENGQIN campus will cost 1.75 billion to MSAR coffers throughout this year. The six -year project has a global budget of 8.4 billion. With the new amounts of revenues and expenses, the budget balance shrinks significantly from 7.7 billion to about 300 million patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-07-10 03:32:54</pubDate></item></channel></rss>