<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/oposicao-timorense-quer-investigar-procedimentos-de-deportacao-de-ex-deputado-filipino/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Hong Kong calls for caution to residents visiting United States in the face of confrontations</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/hong-kong-pede-cautela-a-residentes-que-visitem-estados-unidos-face-a-confrontos/</link><description>The Hong Kong government has called for caution to residents in the United States or want to visit the country due to clashes in the city of Los Angeles, California.
 
A spokesman for Hong Kong authorities said residents should "track the local situation, be careful, take care of personal security, avoid large agglomerations and pay attention to local communications."
The warning, justified with “recent protests and riots in the United States”, still ongoing in that state, emerged in a statement released Monday night.
The clashes in the largest city in the state of California led the Hong Kong Security Department to update, also on Monday, travel alerts to the United States. "Since early June 2025, protests and riots have occurred in various cities, including Los Angeles, resulting in violent and injured clashes," the alert.
Also on Monday, China advised the Chinese living in Los Angeles to “remain extremely vigilant, reinforce precautions (…) and avoid crowding places, crowded areas or poor public safety”.
The Chinese consulate in Los Angeles also advised against "going out at night or traveling alone."
United States President Donald Trump sent two thousand another thousand California National Guard soldiers and 700 Marines to Los Angeles, raising to nearly 5,000 the total number of military personnel mobilized in that metropolitan area.
The information was communicated by California State Democratic Governor Gavin Newsom after allegedly reported by the White House.
Trump began to announce last Saturday the sending of two thousand members of the National Guard of California, without the approval of the governor, who is the chief commander of these troops in the state, the first time in 60 years that the US executive imposes himself in this way.
California prosecutor Rob Bonta presented a judicial action against the Trump administration, claiming that the measure taken by the White House constitutes "abuse of the authority of the federal government and violated the tenth amendment" of the Constitution.
Los Angeles City Council Democratic President Karen Bass assured that the confrontation perimeter is confined to “some streets” in the city center, but according to Trump, the Californian metropolis would have been “swept from the map” if he had not decided to send the National Guard.
The president's statement was denied by Los Angeles district prosecutor Nathan Hochman. "We have not watched any large -scale civil agitation that required two thousand national guards and 500 or 700 additional soldiers," he said to the NewsNation channel. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 02:51:41</pubDate></item><item><title>STD announces 52 vacancies for the new edition of the International Festival of Cities of Gastronomy</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/dst-anuncia-52-vagas-para-a-nova-edicao-da-festa-internacional-das-cidades-de-gastronomia/</link><description>The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) announced the opening of 52 vacancies for exhibitors of gastronomy, joining the second edition of the event “International Festival of Cities of Gastronomy, Macao”.
The recruitment process will end on June 18, being subject to preferred criteria that include the license and certification of establishments, the experience of participation in events of large wingspan and the characteristics of business.
Interested parties can consult the manual and registration on the STD thematic electronics page (https://www.macaotourism.gov.mo/pticle/events/gastronomy-fest-2025) and clarify doubts through the Wechat platform (Honcholo01), telephone contact (62140059) or e-mail (*Proteced Email*).
The three prominent activities for this year are the “demonstrations of the cities of gastronomy”, the “International Forum of Macao Gastronomy” and the “Avenida da Gastronomia Internacional”. As in the previous edition, this last activity will consist of a hundred stands with macao gastronomy samples and inland China: 25 belonging to companies on the continent, 23 from abroad, and the 52 exhibitors to define.
The new edition of the event will take place between July 11 and 20, at Doca dos Fishermen. In addition to the initiatives already mentioned, the event will feature "stands" for six integrated tourism and leisure companies, meal zones, game zones, coastal bar and occasional shows, "STD states in a statement.
The main objective of the initiative is to promote synergy between tourism and gastronomy, as well as strengthen the position of Macau as a city of highlighting tourism, leisure and gastronomy. Last year, in its first edition, the party lasted ten days and attracted the participation of 107 thousand people. On social networks, the various publications and live broadcasts boosted by over 20 digital influencers have reached about 28.4 million cybernauts.</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 02:51:47</pubDate></item><item><title>China prolongs until December anti -dumping inquiry on European pork meat</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/china-prolonga-ate-dezembro-inquerito-antidumping-sobre-carne-de-porco-europeia/</link><description>The China Ministry of Commerce announced yesterday that it will last until December the investigation for unfair competition to imports of certain pig meat products from the European Union (EU), which began in June 2024.
In a statement published on its official portal, the ministry justified the extent of the investigation “meeting the complexity of the case”, setting as a new deadline December 16.
The inquiry, launched on June 17, 2024, initially had a one -year duration, with the possibility of extension “in special circumstances”, as it had already been signaled at the time.
The investigation focuses on pork and offal, both refrigerated and frozen, as well as fat and derivatives, originating in the EU.
Beijing began this measure as retaliation of customs imposed by Brussels on electric vehicles manufactured in China, claiming that state subsidies received by this sector create distortions in competition from European brands.
Despite tensions, in recent months there was a slight approximation between China and the EU, namely after the impact of the trade war began by US President Donald Trump.
In April, Beijing had already extended until July his investigation for unfair competition to EU Brandy imports-another measure of retaliation for rates on Chinese electric vehicles-and also continues with anti-dumping processes to dairy products from 27 Member States.
European Commerce Commissioner Maros Sefcovic, who visited China in March, recently said that Brussels and Beijing "share significant mutual interests in resolving bilateral and global challenges" and stressed that it is "equally important to face differences."
According to the European official, the two parties are “working hard” to achieve advances before the bilateral summit scheduled for July, China, when the 50th anniversary of the establishment of diplomatic relations between Beijing and Brussels will be celebrated.</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 02:51:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Paragraph #93</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/paragrafo-93/</link><description /><pubDate /></item><item><title>SJM may be the most affected concessionaire for the closing of the satellite casinos, says JP Morgan</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/sjm-podera-ser-a-concessionaria-mais-afectada-pelo-encerramento-dos-casinos-satelite-diz-jp-morgan/</link><description>The closing of the satellite casinos in Macao by the end of this year should have little impact on Melco and Galaxy dealers. But SJM, which is operating nine satellite casinos, could face a “complex situation,” said the JP Morgan investment bank, due to increased wage charges after the “proper placement” of workers.
 
A recent analysis by the JP Morgan Investment Bank warned of the “complex” situation to the SJM game concessionaire regarding the closing of the satellite casinos that currently operate in Macao.
The end of the local satellite casinos, scheduled for the end of this year, was revealed on Monday by the government, with 11 satellite casinos, nine of which belonging to SJM Resorts, S.A., while Melco Resorts (Macau) S.A. and that of the Galaxy Casino, S.A., respectively, a casino satellite.
Quoted by the GGR Asia Portal, JP Morgan acknowledged that the decision made by the concessionaires about the closing of the enclosures was a “negative surprise” for the industry. In the case of SJM, according to the report, the satellite casinos represented 4% of profits before taxes (EBITDA) of the company's last 12 months.
The eventual impact on EBITDA should be “controllable” by SJM, but JP Morgan indicated that the absorption of workers of these satellite casinos may cause financial pressure at the concessionaire. "The relocation of about 440 tables on the part of the satellite casinos business would probably put thousands of employees on the SJM direct payroll," he noticed. JP Morgan added that the situation can "result in wage charges unless SJM can gain a significant quota with these additional tables."
Operators have committed to absorb workers who run out of employment following the end of the satellite casinos, and the government has ensured that it will oversee the process.
It is recalled that, according to the data revealed, the nine SJM satellite casinos closed the year 2024 with revenues of 10.5 billion patacas, representing 4.5% of Macao game revenues. Casino Landmark and Casino Fortuna were the two most profitable, with annual revenues, respectively, 2.7 billion patacas (1.1% of Macao game revenues) and 1.8 billion patacas (0.7% of game revenues).
Despite significant recipes, SJM decided to let Landmark and fortune close, but chose to try to explore the casinos on bridge 16 and L'ARC. SJM Resorts has advanced that it will consider the acquisition of the ownership of the hotels where the Casino Ponte 16 are located and Casino Le Royal ARC, requiring the government to direct the casinos in these two facilities.
The investment bank's analysis, on the other hand, stated that the impact of cessation of satellite casinos operations would be “negligible” for Galaxy Entertainment and Melco Resorts, unlike SJM. “Its satellite properties contributed only 0% [E] 1% to 2%” for the ebitda of the last 12 months of Galaxy Entertainment and Melco Resorts, he noted.
 
Looking for new paths
 
Some casinos-satellite operators issued communications yesterday to react to the announced closing of the spaces by the end of the year, especially three companies that cooperate with SJM, which revealed that they received the notification of the SJM decision just last Monday.
Paradise Entertainment Limited, which explores the Kam Pek Paradise casino, admitted that a “significant reduction” of revenues and profit attributable to the shareholders from next year is expected, since “revenue from the rendering of Hong Kong casino management services in December 31, 2024, which represented 66.2% of the total revenue from Group ”.
However, the company plans to change business focus on developing, selling and renting electronic gaming equipment and systems in macao and international markets, as well as “exploring alternative business opportunities” to diversify their operations and mitigate risks.
In turn, Emperor Entertainment Hotel Limited and Macau Legend Development Limited share the idea of ​​diversifying and expanding your business, namely in your hotel facilities, to enable other sources of recipes.</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 02:53:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Arraial de São João again held at the Tower of Macau on June 21 and 22</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/arraial-de-sao-joao-volta-a-realizar-se-na-torre-de-macau-nos-dias-21-e-22-de-junho/</link><description>The Arraial de São João, one of the most prominent popular festivities among the macanese and Portuguese communities of the territory, is returning to the Macao Tower on the 21st and 22nd of this month. Miguel de Senna Fernandes, the president of the Organizing Association, recognizes embarrassment at budgetary and labor level, but guarantees to the end: "The party has to continue".
 
The Arraial de São João returns to Macao on the 21st and 22nd of this month, from 14:30 to 22:00, in an outdoor area next to the Tower of Macao. As in the previous edition, the event has live action of local music groups and the usual food, handicraft and games tents.
In a statement, the Macanese Association (ADM) explains that the festivity goes beyond the religious dimension of “tribute to a popular saint” - more concretely, the patron saint St. John the Baptist - and that represents a whole “community effort to maintain the tradition of celebrating the historical date of June 24, 1622”, in which the Portuguese forces defeated the Dutch and ensured the preservation of “own characteristics” of Macao. Celebrated as the day of the city of Macau until the transfer of sovereignty of the region, the date is still celebrated annually by the Portuguese and Macanese communities.
Speaking to the end point, Miguel de Senna Fernandes admits that this year's camp, inserted in June to overflow activities and events related to Lusophony, lacks “human resources” and schedule availability by the members involved. "This year, we could not organize the conference we usually do. We have been a little on the time to put [the Arraial] standing, but even if it is a little on time, the party has to continue. It depends a lot on people's availability and good foster."
The village will take place in an outer area of ​​the Tower of Macau for the second year in a row, after a four-year break motivated by the Covid-19 pandemic and, later, by traffic restrictions in the São Lázaro neighborhood, where the festivities had place since 2007. “Open the sidewalk of São Lazaro would mean cutting the party in borders, and that would not be possible. Senna Fernandes, recognizing the logistical support of the Macau Tower as essential to the continuity of tradition.
"Only then has it even been possible to imagine a celebration of the genre. There is no other solution, because we have to rule with the thin budget subsidized by the Macau Foundation ... Good thing we continued to rely on the support of the Tower, which very promptly agreed to grant the same space. Otherwise, this would be absolutely unrealizable," says the president of ADM.
The preservation of the cultural habits of the region's macanese and Portuguese communities is the priority of the organization, regardless of logistical or restriction issues. The guardian reiterates, "The key is not to let this die or fall into oblivion."
The ADM initiative has the collaboration of associations such as the Association of Young Macanese (AJM), the Macanese Instruction Promoting Association (APIM), the House of Portugal in Macau (CPM) and the Macao International Institute (IIM).</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Seminar addressed cooperation between startups of Portugal and Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/seminario-abordou-a-cooperacao-entre-startups-de-portugal-e-macau/</link><description>Last Saturday was held a seminar subordinate to the theme “Innovation and Partnership: Cooperation between Startups of Portugal and Macau”, which was organized by the Macao Public Workers Association (ATFPM), together with the Portuguese Communities Council of the China Circle (Macao, Hong Kong, Continental China, Tokyo, Seoul, Bangkok and Singapore), the Association for Promotion of Exchange Economic, commercial and cultural between China and Lusophone countries and the Association of Naturals of the Dongguan District of Macao.
This seminar was attended by more than 120 participants, mostly businessmen from Macau, Dongguan, Hong Kong and other Chinese cities.
The seminar had as speakers Bernardo Pinho, deputy consul for commercial affairs and investment and delegate of AICEP/Macau, and Stella Ho NGA Sze, representative of the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services of MSAR.
According to a statement released yesterday by ATFPM, Bernardo Pinho presented the dynamic ecosystem of 'startups' in Portugal, referring initiatives such as Web Summit and the support of AICEP to investors. Already Stella Ho NGA Sze detailed Macau's policies for young entrepreneurs, including the youth entrepreneurship support plan and the integration with 23 great bay incubation centers.
Rita Santos, president of the Atfpm General Assembly, also spoke to highlight the "crucial role of Macau as the economic bridge between China and Lusophone countries." "It is essential to take advantage of the position of Macau as" a center, a platform, a base "to attract Chinese investors to Portugal and promote the export of Portuguese services to the large bay," he said. Rui Marcelo, president of the Asia Regional Council and Oceania of the Portuguese communities, pointed out that, despite the challenges, “innovative cooperation between Portugal and Macao transcends borders, with startups playing a key role as engines of creativity and development”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 02:51:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau rises 31 positions in the international ranking for ICCA conventions</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/macau-sobe-31-posicoes-no-ranking-internacional-para-convencoes-da-icca/</link><description>The World Convention and Exhibition Industry Institution - International Association of Congresses and Conventions (ICCA, in the English acronym) - recently published the “ICCA annual report on the 2024 International Congress Market”, where Macau had a bright performance, according to local authorities, with a total of 33 international convention events recognized by ICCA in 2024. This number represents a 50% increase over the 22 events recognized 2023.
According to the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment (IPIM), among these, 26 events (79%) are related to the key industries of the proper diversification plan of the “1+4” economy, highlighting the growth of modern finance-related conferences and tourism. "This demonstrates the constant development of the Macao Convention and Exhibition industry in the course of promoting industrial diversification, further reinforcing the effect of synergy between industries," says IPIM.
In the ranking of the cities of the Asia Pacific region, Macau ranks 14th, rising six positions compared to last year. In the ranking of the world cities, Macau positions himself in 76th place, rising 31 positions, drawing with Beijing, in mainland China, and Doha, in Qatar. This is, since 2019, the first return of Macau to the top 100 of the world cities. In the ranking of world countries and regions, Macao also climbed 10 positions, reaching 57th place.
"This series of data, along with the international awards that Macau has received in recent years, prove the growing power of Macau as an international destination for conventions and exhibitions. This not only recognizes the comprehensive strength of the local convention and exhibition industry, but also strengthens Macau's competitiveness in the world convention and exhibition market, bringing positive meaning to attract more high quality international conferences in Macau." IPIM statement.</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 02:52:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Culture Magazine recalls Macau in world historical narratives</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/revista-de-cultura-recorda-macau-nas-narrativas-historicas-mundiais/</link><description>The latest number of the Cultural Institute's Culture Magazine will focus on issues of maritime conflict, diaóporic heritage and cultural hybridism, positioning Macao in global historical narratives, says a statement from the IC.
According to the organism, it begins with a study of the maritime history of Canton in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, "which analyzes the behavior often disorder and undisciplined of foreign sailors, which generated tensions with the local population and hindered sino -cental relations." In another topic, a study highlights an export painting, a rediscovery of the eighteenth century, which, according to the IC, “captures the urban vitality of Macao and maritime trade, revealing its socio-artistic importance in the mid-Qing dynasty”. In the scope of anthropology, Macau's migration to the Mascarenhas archipelago was investigated, based on archival sources and ethnographic studies, through which the Chinese heritage in Creole identity was analyzed.
Regarding the Macao Studies section, "religious syncretism is deepened through deities whose hybrid worship reflects processes of cultural fusion." “Reports on the daily lives of foreigners in Macao in the nineteenth century are enriched by the unprecedented diary of an American merchant's woman, providing a rare approach to the routines of expatriates,” says the IC. Finally, there are two recens, one falling into a fiction novel on a Macao-related political scandal and the other describing the class dynamics in the Macanese society.
The IC also claim that the invitation to present contributions centered on historical and cultural research related to the theme “Culture of East Asia 2025” - Macao, China ”, including, although not exclusively, the historical and cultural links between Macao and the Macao Role and the Contribution of Cultural Interacts in the region, as well as the Eastern Asia Contribution, is maintained. intrinsically present in the Macao multicultural heritage.
The magazine is for sale at the RAME Services Center, at the Macau Archive, at Macau Plaza Cultural Bookstore, among others.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Completed evaluation of the performance of 13 public capital companies, all approved</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/concluida-avaliacao-do-desempenho-de-13-empresas-de-capitais-publicos-todas-aprovadas/</link><description>The government assessed the exploitation and operation of 13 local public capital companies. According to the results released by the services of supervision and management of public assets, the International Airport Society and the Society for the Development of Industrial Parks obtained the highest classifications among all companies. The executive stressed that the evaluation this time focused on management performance, rather than economic and social responsibility.
 
A total of 13 public capital companies were submitted to the annual evaluation of their exploration and operation performance. The Macao International Airport Society (CAM) and the Society for the Development of Macao Industrial Parks were the companies that had the highest classification of “A-” class, with 80 to 85 values ​​on a scoring scale up to 100.
The Directorate of Services of Supervision and Management of Public Assets (DSGAP) published yesterday the results of the evaluation of the year 2024. The companies evaluated are divided into two types, and eight are commercial industry companies and five social enterprise companies.
Consulting the information available on the body's electronic portal, all public capital companies scored equal to or greater than 70 values, exceeding the goal of 50 that may lead to the execution of measures provided for by law, including the obligation of companies to submit reform proposals, meet with DSGAP or deliver the written justification, as well as submit to specific audit or investigation into their operation.
In addition to the two companies with “A-” classification, mentioned above, the results of the assessment show that from commercial industry companies, Macau Urban Renewal, Umacert Research and Limited Engineering Tests, the Macao Unipessoal Securities Settlement Center and Macau Investment and Development were class “B+” (with a score of 75 values, but less than 80 values). Already UmTec, limited and the Macao World Trade Center were located in class “B” (equal to or greater than 70 values, but less than 75 values).
As for social enterprise companies, they all obtained “B+”, including the Macao Science Center, the Macao Orchestra Society, the Macau Slaughterhouse, the Macao Metro Society and the TDM - Macao teledifusion.
DSGAP explained that the indicators were defined for the evaluation and performed the evaluation with different guidelines and outbreaks, taking into account the characteristics of companies of different types, as well as the actual situation of each company.
According to the regulation of the exploitation and operation performance assessment of public capital companies, issued by DSGAP in March 2024, the evaluation is performed with standards of economic indicators, such as revenue and budget execution; management; social responsibility, including the formation of qualified staff and the provision of support to the public interest and charity; mission, in relation to the fulfillment of the tasks designated by the government; and reform, such as the situation of innovation of activities.
However, among the evaluation indicators for the last year, “the essential indicator for all companies was management performance,” said DSGAP, noting that the evaluation provides attention particularly “to the rationality and regularity of the establishment of the governance structure, the completeness of the establishment of internal management regimes, the exploitation in accordance with the law, as well as the regularity of information disclosure”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 02:52:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Cunha Foundation inaugurates today Retrospective Exhibition of Lúcia Lemos</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/fundacao-rui-cunha-inaugura-hoje-exposicao-retrospectiva-de-lucia-lemos/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation presents today, at 18:00, the exhibition of art “Metamorphoses”, a project that brings together several works produced over the decades by artist Lúcia Lemos. The show will remain patent to the public until July 21, with free admission.
The event, inserted in the cultural program “June, Portugal's month”, brings together 44 pieces of different artistic and aesthetic branches - such as engraving, photography, installation, painting and ceramics - which the artist has elaborated along her professional career, in a reflection on the sense of belonging to Portugal after four decades living in Macau.
In a statement sent to the newsrooms, the Rui Cunha Foundation states that the founder of Creative Macau “uses organic materials to give body to ideas, and meanings to her art, in the different languages ​​and forms she has been experiencing and learning throughout life, now with greater freedom and time to explore” as long as she retired from the project about a year ago.
Quoted in the statement, Lúcia Lemos deepens the concept of metamorphosis that gives title to the exhibition, associating it with the “lived transformations and personal visual observations of physical space” where it lives, Macau, “never failing to practice portugality, as a sense of belonging from where [departed] four decades ago”.
The artistic retrospective symbolizes, therefore, “the symbiosis of construction and maturation of my identity, modeled by the changes in adaptation and adoption to the metamorphosis of the new place”, frames. "Art and the artistic process are looking for forms of integration and connection of the human being into the nature and the world around him."
In its extensive curriculum, we highlight the foundation of the Creative Macau project, which coordinated for over two decades, and the launch of the Macao International Short Festival. The artist also participated in more than 50 collective and individual exhibitions, both nationally and international, “with some award -winning works and varied artistic languages,” says the Foundation.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Chinese students face uncertainties about studying in the USA</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/estudantes-chineses-enfrentam-incertezas-sobre-estudar-nos-eua/</link><description>He Qixuan, a student of Shanghai, rejoiced with joy when last Friday answered Lusa's call and said that his visa to study in the United States had been approved.
 
“I'm going to celebrate! It's the first step to studying abroad!” The young candidate for the master's degree in emerging media studies at the University of Boston told Lusa after an interview at the US consulate in Shanghai, where, like her, in the same line, almost 200 candidates waiting for interviews were approved.
If the scene seems to illustrate the commitment made by the US President in the telephone conversation with Chinese counterparts, Xi Jinping last Thursday-and shape Donald Trump's statement that the US “loves to receive Chinese students”-Washington's signs on the subject are more than contradictory, from the perspective of several Chinese sources in statements to Lusa.
The Yi Si agency, headquartered in Guangzhou, specializing in the support of Chinese students who want to study abroad, accounts for the growing concern with the rejection of visas among candidates who resort to their services. "I have two students from the Macao University of Science and Technology to whom they have been denied visas to study in the United States three times," the agency director Christ Feng told Lusa, noting that the US Consulate "has not provided any reasons" for rejections. "During Trump's previous presidency, it was the computer students who faced the highest rejection rates, but now the candidates of all specialties risk being refused," Feng added.
Xiangning Wu, an associate professor at the University of Macao's Department of Government and Public Policies, told Lusa that, in recent years, their number of students studying in the United States "has been decreasing due to" increased bribes "and" safety reasons. "
Wu also mentioned that visa refusals have mostly targeted science and engineering students, which has made these students ended Hong Kong and Singapore.
Descriptions seem to find resonance in what US Secretary of State Marco Rubio announced in a statement on the eve of the call between Trump and Xi last week.
According to the state department's statement, the United States will begin to "aggressively revoke" the visas granted to Chinese students, and the measure will focus on students with calls to the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) and those in the United States to study in sensitive areas. "Under the leadership of President Trump, the State Department will work with the internal security department to aggressively revoke the visas granted to Chinese students, including those with calls to the Chinese Communist Party or studying in critical areas," Rubio said. "We will also review the visa grant criteria to increase the scrutiny of all future visa requests from the Popular Republic of China and Hong Kong," added the US Secretary of State.
This determination was heard with due attention in China. The direction of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) in Macau told Lusa that he is preparing to “watch” about 200 students from the Special Chinese administrative region to study in the United States, as well as others who want to continue their studies. "DSEDJ has communicated with third party institutions in Macao and asked them to be aware of the latest developments and provide the necessary facilitation and assistance to students in the United States, or who want to study in the United States, with the aim of transferring to other countries," the institution said in a statement sent to Lusa.
In the school year 2022/2023, the total number of Chinese students in the United States was 289,526, representing approximately 27.4 percent of the total number of US international students, and heading for the 14th consecutive year, according to the Open Doors report, funded by the US State Department. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 02:51:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Japanese government offers another 200,000 tons of rice to lock prices</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/governo-japones-disponibiliza-mais-200-mil-toneladas-de-arroz-para-travar-precos/</link><description>Japanese Minister of Agriculture, Shinjiro Koizumi, announced yesterday that another 200,000 tons of rice from the National Reserve will be available to sell at controlled prices and help lock the rise of its price due to speculation.
The rice that will hit the market was produced in 2021 and 2022 and comes from the 2020 harvest, marking the first time that the rice collected five years ago is made available, Koizumi announced yesterday at a press conference after the meeting of the Council of Ministers. "We will provide unlimited amounts of stored rice if there is search, so that companies that wish you can use. Therefore, we will sell 100,000 tons of the 2021 harvest and 100,000 tons of the 2020 harvest," said Koizumi, quoted by Japanese public broadcaster NHK.
Rice sales price will be about 1,700 yen (10.30 euros) for every five kilograms, he added.
Some consumers and restoration companies complained about the age of rice, stating that after several years of production, it has to be used for animal feed and no longer has the quality necessary for human consumption.
The price of national rice, a basic food of the Japanese diet, doubled last year, forcing restaurants and consumers to look for alternatives such as the importation of the cereal from other countries and forcing the government to release part of their national reserves to try to stabilize prices.
Prices have increased by 90% over the past year, a rise that was driven by factors such as increased demand in restaurants due to tourism growth, gross and intermediate speculation, and “panic purchases” after the government issued a possible earthquake alert last summer.
Given this situation, the Japanese government has decided to make tons of its rice reserves available to the general market from March, something unpublished, and at the end of last month began to sell rice through direct contracts with retailers at controlled prices.
Japan created its national rice reserves in 1995 after a serious scarcity of rice two years earlier due to an unusual summer. Every year, the government stores about 200,000 tons to ensure reserves in case of emergency.</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 02:53:04</pubDate></item><item><title>A reference that reinvents itself</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/uma-referencia-que-se-reinventa/</link><description>Forty years after the opening, the Portuguese bookstore continues to reinvent itself and adapt to the reality of the territory. Today, the space is not only made of books, it is a meeting point for the community and a showcase of Portuguese culture for tourists who arrive in Macao.

It is on the corner between Rua de São Domingos and Travessa do Bispo that, since 1985, the Portuguese Bookstore, owned by IPOR, which has been concessed since 2010 to Praia Grande Editions. Today has been 40 years that the Portuguese language serves as a meeting point of the Lusophone community, presenting it to the world.
Patrícia Ribeiro, director of IPOR, observes the mutations of the Portuguese bookstore over the years in reaction to changes in the territory. The strategic location makes it a mandatory stop for visitors and "of course the products we see for sale today have also changed to respond to this more touristy demand."
On the other hand, "there are more and more different products representative of culture and Portuguese language, while continuing to serve the local population with a variety of publications."
The reinvention of space has also been through products for children and youth and cultural collaborations with other entities that result in initiatives in the Gallery of the Livraria, highlights Patrícia Ribeiro.
Evaluating with positive note the development of the Portuguese bookstore over the years, the director of IPOR says it is optimistic about the future of space: "Of course there are always some questions we can improve and this are always reflections that must be made, but I still believe it remains a place of reference for Portuguese literature."
Jorge Rangel shares the optimism of Patrícia Ribeiro. The former Secretary for Education, Culture and Tourism, who, in 1985, had the idea of ​​creating a Portuguese matrix bookstore on this corner of the then called Rua das Mariazinhas, says that “the bookstore is an indispensable institution for the Portuguese community”, an “important milestone” and a space that does an “remarkable” work. Assuming himself as a book lover, the current president of the International Institute of Macao also highlights the cultural sessions in the Cave da Bookstore. Rangel leaves votes that the Portuguese bookstore "keep looking back, creating conditions for tomorrow."
The project of the Portuguese bookstore is “very expensive to the heart” of Anabela Ritchie, who was president of IPOR when the transfer of the management of the cultural institute to the Portuguese body, in 1990. At the time “the role that the bookstore could play was already able to guess. "We were aware of the importance that the Portuguese bookstore would have for Macao."
The former president of the Legislative Assembly of Macao describes the space as “a fundamental instrument of Portuguese language and culture in Macau, more fundamental than ever”. “Today, when I look at the bookstore, I think it has an absolutely unavoidable role in Macau,” he says.
The Portuguese bookstore “has to have” tools to subsist in the future, argues Amelia António. “It has to adapt to reality and maintain its fundamental role in serving the Portuguese Language community,” says the president of Casa de Portugal in Macau. Especially because space is "absolutely indispensable".
40 years ago, he recalls, “the bookstore was constituted with the clear objective of being a pole of diffusion of Portuguese language and culture” and, nowadays, “is one of the rare spaces in the service of the Portuguese Language community”. "It has not had a route without waves, but what is certain is that it is a milestone that has to always be defended," he concludes.
Miguel de Senna Fernandes looks at the development of the Portuguese bookstore in the last 40 years “with great satisfaction”. “It is important for these things to last in time,” even though the Portuguese community is shrinking, the lawyer and director of the Dóci Papiaçám di Macau points out.
University professor Lola Xavier describes the bookstore as “an irreplaceable institution of the Portuguese language in Macao”. Assuming as a frequent attendant of space, the teacher adds that it is “a fundamental space for the dissemination and sedimentation of Portuguese culture”, highlighting the preponderant role in the distribution of school books at the beginning of the school year. “I can't imagine Macau without the Portuguese bookstore,” he ends.
Sara Augusto, also she professor university professor at the bookstore, considers this “one of the most important spaces of the Portuguese language in Macau”. “It fulfills its goals well and in a way that does not close to the tourists visiting Macao,” he says. For Sara Augusto, this is also a “meeting point for teachers, students, artists, photographers, writers”. It is, in the background, "a space of encounters."
“The Portuguese bookstore has been the true territory of Portuguese in Macau,” says João Miguel Barros, noting that after the transfer of sovereignty of Macao, its importance has been accentuated. "The Portuguese community of Macao is not only linked through the pastry of cream, folklore, baked sardines and, occasionally, the deification of our Ronaldo," says the lawyer, photographer and healer, concluding: "It is the language and culture that can give us the sense of belonging that is usually precarious outside our land."</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 02:55:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Paragraph #94</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/paragrafo-94/</link><description /><pubDate /></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai thanks contribution from the Portuguese community to Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/sam-hou-fai-agradece-contributo-da-comunidade-portuguesa-para-macau/</link><description>At the reception at the time of Portugal, Camões and the Portuguese communities, Sam Hou Fai went to the Portuguese community and thanked his contribution to the development of the MSAR. The Chief Executive said the cooperation between Macao and Portugal will be reinforced.
 
“The contribution of Portuguese communities has been important to healthy development in multiple aspects of this region,” began to say Sam Hou Fai in the speech given at the reception of Portugal, Camões and Portuguese communities, which took place yesterday at the consular residence. "I take this opportunity, to thank, with sincerity, all the support, effort and cooperation that the Portuguese community has provided to the work of the Government of MSAR, as well as the undeniable contribution that has been making to the economic and social development of Macao," added the chief executive.
At the celebration of June 10, the leader of the local government pointed out that "the strong and deep historical ties between Portugal and Macau are already known to all," says Luís de Camões, who had passed by Macao, having been one of the "first moments of this historical meeting of two peoples".
Sam Hou Fai stressed that "it is because of this centenary meeting of cultures, in this" outdoor window "of China, which arises the" uniqueness "of Macao as the only place in the world whose official languages, the Portuguese and the Chinese," as indicated by Xi Jinping when his passage in December last year.
The chief executive also stated that cooperation between China and Portugal reveal "an exemplary model of collaboration and exchange between two countries, always prevailing respect and consideration for their social and cultural differences." In addition, macau-Portuguese cooperation in the domains of economics and commerce, scientific and technological innovation, human resources, medical and health, education and culture “have been continually reinforced and, convinced, they will continue to be deepened in the future, taking good advantage of the unique characteristics of Macao”.
Sam stressed the government's commitment to the “concentration of efforts to build a higher-level opening platform, reinforcing bilateral opening with Lusophony, and promoting comprehensive mutual benefit cooperation”, in order to widen “the role and functions of Macao as a sino-illusophone platform”.
The ruler also assured that the “Macao Multicultural Characteristics” will continue to be defended and the “development in all strands, thus trying to ensure and continually improve the well-being of all residents of Macao, including Portuguese communities in Macao”. “We hope to continue walking hand in hand to a bright future, with new opportunities and platforms for the narrowing of cooperation relations between Lusophony, China and Masters,” concluded Sam Hou Fai.</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 02:54:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing uses 11 billion state background of Yuan to attack crisis in the real estate market</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/pequim-utiliza-fundo-estatal-de-11-bilioes-de-yuan-para-atacar-crise-no-mercado-imobiliario/</link><description>China is resorting to a public housing fund worth 10.9 billion Yuan to support the real estate sector in crisis, offering an alternative to bank loans.
 
The state savings program created to help citizens acquire their own home has been gaining importance as a source of financing, at a time when banks are more cautious due to compression of profit margins.
By 2023, the fund exceeded banks in the volume of loans, reaching 8.1 billion Yuan in active mortgages. "It is one of the main measures to support the real estate market," said Chen Wenjing, research director in China Index Holdings, quoted by Bloomberg news agency. "The market is still under pressure, and many local governments have appealed to this mechanism to relieve loans," he said.
Inspired by the Singapore model, the fund has been implemented in China three decades ago and requires monthly contributions of workers and employers, then allowing housing credits, often at lower rates than those practiced by banks.
The growing importance of the fund arises in a context of difficulties in the banking sector, which has been called upon to support the economy, facing historically low profit margins, deceleration of profits and increased rally credit.
Facilitating access to credit remains crucial, at a time when the recovery of the Chinese real estate market remains fragile.
According to Bloomberg Intelligence, the country's 100 largest real estate promoters are expected to record at least 10% in sales in 2025 to about 3.4 billion Yuan - less than a third of the 2020 amount.
Residential sales fell again in May. Country Garden, one of the biggest promoters in trouble, recorded a 28% break in sales, reflecting the concern of buyers with the company's financial health and the sector.
In the past, the fund was underused due to various restrictions, such as boundaries in the amounts of the credits granted and the prohibition of money use as entry financing.
However, since 2023, at least 50 cities have relieved access criteria, increasing credit limits. Shenzhen, the most expensive city in China, began this week allowing the use of fund deposits to pay the entry for home purchase.
The fund to the fund has increased: in Beijing, it financed 33% of residential mortgages by 2023, compared to 29.4% in 2020.
Recently, the Central Bank has reduced the interest rate of credits granted through the fund, making them 0.9% cheaper than bank loans. Still, analysts warn that savings, about 3%, is “marginal” and unlikely to generate a significant increase in housing sales.
In 2024, the volume of fund loans grew 3.4%, while housing credits granted by commercial banks retreated 1.3%. Unlike banks, the fund has robust liquidity, resulting from regular contributions of about 180 million workers and employers, according to official data. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 02:51:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Indonesia revokes mining exploration permission after nickel extraction</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/indonesia-revoga-permissao-de-exploracao-mineira-apos-extracao-de-niquel/</link><description>Indonesia has announced that it has removed the permission to exploit Minas Gerais to four of five companies active in the Raja AMPAT archipelago, where environmental consequences for nickel extraction are causing high costs. Indonesian president Prabowo subsantic, "decided that the government would revoke the mining exploration permissions of four companies in the [islands] Raja AMPAT," the Minister of Secretary of State, PraSetyo Hadi, announced to journalists. According to Energy Minister Bahlil Lahadalia, these companies violated the regulations in force. "We think this region should be protected," he added. The Raja Ampat archipelago, located in the province of Papua Southwest, is part of the “coral triangle” and are considered from the most preserved reef zones in the world. They are celebrated by their crystal clear blue waters, making them a popular diving place.
Greenpeace Indonesia warned of the situation last week by posting videos that became viral about the environmental consequences of Nickel extraction programs on three islands of the archipelago. According to this Non-Governmental Organization (NGO), these exploration activities on the islands of Gag, Kaw and Manuran led to the destruction of more than 500 hectares of forest and vegetation. Environmental advocates have recalled that coral and marine life are threatened by extraction explorations, but Energy Minister Bahlil Lahadalia estimated that the surrounding areas have not been affected. "If people say that the coral reefs of the ocean have been damaged, come to realize. Have attention to distinguish what is real from what it is not," he said. Greenpeace Indonesia greeted the measure, but appealed to do more. "We appreciate this decision, but we must ensure that the decision will be implemented. We must be sure that they [companies] cease" their activity, "Greenpeace Indonesia reacted to the AFP agency. In response to the news agency, Greenpeace Indonesia called on the government to restore the areas where companies led to deforestation. He stated that the Indonesian government has allowed nickel extraction companies in the Maluku islands to commit environmental damage and illegalities against indigenous populations without anything being done.</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 02:52:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Portuguese Bookstore 40 years</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/livraria-portuguesa-40-anos/</link><description /><pubDate /></item><item><title>Opposition Timorese wants to investigate procedures for deportation of former deputy Filipino</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/11/oposicao-timorense-quer-investigar-procedimentos-de-deportacao-de-ex-deputado-filipino/</link><description>The Revolutionary Front of Independent Timor-Leste (Fretilin) ​​and the Popular Liberation Party (PLP), an opposition Timorese, presented yesterday a resolution project to investigate the procedures that led to the deportation of a former Filipino deputy.
 
In the resolution project, delivered to the table of Parliament, the Timorese opposition asks that the Human Rights and Justice provision, within 90 days, to verify that there were violations of human rights, violation of legal and administrative rights and whether there are indications of crimes on national and international laws.
The resolution also asks the Human Rights Provision to verify if there was abuse of power by the government and if there was a serious institutional setback that threatens the independence of the judicial system and the democratic balance between organs of sovereignty.
The Timorese government deported on 29 May the former deputy Filipino Arnolfo Teves Jr, accused by the Philippines of having allegedly murdered more than 10 people, who had been in Timor-Leste since April 2023, after the appeal court has refused his extradition.
The Timorese Appeal Court refused extradition, claiming that the Constitution does not allow extradition for crimes to which the requesting state law or life imprisonment or whenever the person to be extradite may be subject to torture.
The Timorese Government announced the deportation of Filipino by administrative decision of the Interior Ministry, being in the country with no valid visa, legal authorization of permanence and with the passport canceled by the authorities of his country.
The executive also reported that the Philippines authorities formally guaranteed Timor-Leste that Arnolfo Teves JR will not be subjected to inhuman torture or treatment and will not be sentenced to the death penalty.
The defense of the former deputy considered the deportation illegal. "It is not at question the person aimed at the decision. What is at stake is the respect for the constitutional order, the judicial system and the fundamental rights of anyone under Timorese jurisdiction," said Mrs Nurima Alkatiri of Fretilin in an intervention in Parliament.
According to the deputy, by “disobeying a definitive court decision, the highest instances of political power transgressed one of the most sacred principles of the state - the separation of powers”.
For the deputy, the “administrative action, taken by the default of the judicial pronouncement, raises substantiated doubts regarding the respect for the constitutional principles of separation of powers, the obligation to comply with judicial decisions and the legality of the applied procedures.
Nurima Alkatiri stressed that Fretilin does not defend people who may have committed serious crimes. "What is at stake is not the deported person. What is truly concerned is the fulfillment of the Constitution, the safeguarding of administrative legality and the credibility of our institutions," he added. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 02:53:06</pubDate></item></channel></rss>