<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/17/negociador-japones-nos-eua-com-esperanca-de-obter-beneficios-mutuos/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Chinese economy grows 5.4% in the first quarter of 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/17/economia-chinesa-cresce-54-no-primeiro-trimestre-de-2025/</link><description>The Chinese economy grew 5.4% in the first quarter of the year, according to official data spread yesterday, as manufacturers rushed orders, before customary rates rise in the United States.
 
Growth is in line with the rhythm of expansion achieved by the world's second largest economy in the fourth quarter and exceeds the goal of “about 5%” to the year 2025 set by Beijing.
The impulse comes at a time when US President Donald Trump has intensified the trade war against Beijing, threatening total dissociation between the world's two largest economies, at a time when China already faces a prolonged real estate crisis.
Fees on most Chinese products have increased to at least 145%, one level that could lead to exports in China to contraction this year and impair a crucial growth engine.
The data released by the National Statistics Office (GNE) exceeded the consensual estimate of 5.2% of economists inquired by Bloomberg news agency.
Industrial production expanded 7.7% in March, compared to the same period of the previous year, in faster growth since June 2021. Retail sales have increased by 5.9%, the best pace since December 2023.
"The most pleasant surprise is retail sales, which shows that consumption subsidies are working," said Michelle Lam, economist at French Bank Society Generale SA to China, quoted by the agency. "Industrial production was a surprise, but understandable after the strong export data. But this is now part of the past," he told Bloomberg.
Despite the positive data, the GNE recommended caution, stressing the need to give greater support to the economy. "We must be aware that the external environment is becoming more complex and severe. The impulse of internal demand for growth is insufficient and the basis for economic recovery and sustained growth is yet to consolidate," the office said in a statement. “We have to implement more pro - active and effective macroeconomic policies,” he said.
Investment in fixed assets increased by 4.2% in the first three months of 2025, while the real estate investment registered a contraction of 9.9%, prolonging the crisis that reached the sector in 2022.
The urban unemployment rate was 5.2% in March, descending 5.4% in the previous month.
China may have difficulty reaching its official growth goal this year without further stimuli. In recent weeks, several international banks, including UBS Group AG, Goldman Sachs Group Inc. and Citigroup Inc., have lowered their growth forecasts from China to about 4% or less, the result of the aggravation of commercial tensions with Washington.
Some economists expect China's Popular Bank to reduce interest rates or the amount of money banks should keep in reserve this month, while others provide for several Yuan billion in loans and additional tax expenses to fill the void left by falling exports.
China has to rapidly increase domestic consumption and investment to counteract the impact of tariffs. The weakness of the labor market continues to prevent consumers from spending more, even before US fees reach export -related jobs.
The impact of the trade war will probably speak on economic activity from April, after an increase of 12.4% of exports in March, as companies rushed to complete orders.
The possibility of an agreement between the US and China on commercial dispute seems reduced in the near future, as Beijing has adopted by retaliation of successive trump rounds imposed by Trump.
China's scholarship rates largely kept their losses after the disclosure of the data, with the Hang Seng China Enterprisses, which brings together the main Chinese Hong Kong companies, losing 2.4%, and the CSI 300, which replicates the performance of the 300 main actions traded in the Shanghai and Shenzhen pockets, to fall 0.8%. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 05:34:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Authorities waiting for high quality medical services with the creation of day hospitals</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/17/autoridades-a-espera-de-servicos-medicos-de-alta-qualidade-com-a-criacao-de-hospitais-de-dia/</link><description>The government intends to introduce a new law that enables the creation of day hospitals, whose public consultation starts today 30 days. According to the consultation document, the new category of the private medical institution will provide specific medical services with a shorter execution period, but without hospitalization. Its positioning of services is between Hospital and Clinic and the Executive hopes to boost the development of health care industry.
 
The government today launches public consultation on the legislation that provides for the creation of day hospitals - a new category of the private institution providing health care classified between hospitals and medical clinics.
The consultation document suggests that the day hospital will serve for some of the specific medical procedures originally performed in hospital, provided they have a shorter duration, and usually do not require hospitalization.
In this sense, specialized medical procedures with an expected duration of diagnosis or treatment not exceeding 12 hours, for example, advanced therapy, the use of medically assisted procreation techniques and surgeries with general or local anesthesia are medical services that can be provided in this new type of medical institution.
According to health services, hospitals, thus, continue to provide hospitalization services, emergency services and medical services of the specialty, while clinics operate activities for the provision of basic services of external consultations of Western Medicine of traditional Chinese medicine or small surgical operations without hospitalization service.
The creation of day hospitals aims to “extend the scope of development of the private health care market of Macau, attracting more investment and creating more employment opportunities for local health professionals,” said Alvis Lo, director of health services, at a press conference held yesterday.
With the new legal regime, the government also intends to accelerate the development of the 'Big Health' industry, create necessary conditions so that the sector can provide more diverse and high quality health services to citizens, as well as “attract more tourists who aim to resort to health care, maintain good health and well-being”.
 
Insert and fixation of number of beds
 
The consultation document for the “legal regime for the exercise of activity of private institutions providing health care” provides for a provision on the security, which does not exist in the current law, establishing the provision of a deposit of five million patacas to the hospital and one million and fifty thousand patacas for hospitals.
Health services explained that the secretion of security aims to ensure the ordered development of the sector, given that health care in hospitals and hospitals of the day involve the right of interest of users and the public interest. Clinics are excluded in this requirement due to the limited dimension of medical services.
Requirements relating to the minimum area of ​​hospitals and hospitals of the day are also planned, with a view to ensuring that private institutions provide enough space for basic facilities and medical equipment. The minimum useful area of ​​hospitals will be fixed at 900 square meters and the hospitals of the day is 500 square meters.
The proposal of law provides for the creation of a minimum number of hospitalization beds: 20 hospitalization beds in hospital establishments and at least five beds not intended for hospitalization in day hospitals, such as operative block recovery beds, hemodialysis units, chemotherapy beds, daytime nursing beds.
In addition to the revision of the registration and licensing regime, the director of health services revealed yesterday that technical guidelines will be defined to regulate operating procedures and have inspection mechanisms to day hospitals to ensure the quality and safety of services.
There are also provisions that regulate telemedicine, proximity medical services and advanced therapies. Alvis Lo considers these medical services constitute a general market trend, and the government also provides medical services to proximity to elderly with mobility difficulties and people with disabilities living in homes for the elderly. "It is expected that, through the legislation, the rights and interests of health services and residents providers can be better safeguarded and that the healthy development of the health care sector can be promoted," he concluded.
The public consultation period will take place until May 16 and the government will hold five public consultation sessions, including three destined for professional groups and two for the general public.</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 05:32:04</pubDate></item><item><title>The American presence in Macao and the artistic representations that ended up Salem</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/17/a-presenca-norte-americana-em-macau-e-as-representacoes-artisticas-que-foram-parar-a-salem/</link><description>Rogério Miguel Puga was yesterday at the Portuguese Bookstore, where he presented the work “Representations of Macau at Peabody Essex Museum (Salem)”. In the book, the academic explores the American presence in Macao in the nineteenth century and the artistic representations of the region that ended up in the city of Salem, in the United States. The “fascination” he feels for the history of Macao originates from the intercultural interaction that takes place in the region, namely the Anglo-Sano-Portuguese relations, the investigator said to the end.
 
“Representations of Macau at the Peabody Essex Museum (Salem)”, an investigation work by Academic Rogério Miguel Puga, launched in 2023 in Lisbon, was presented yesterday in Macau, in the Portuguese Bookstore. At the session, the academic recalled the research process for the book, which began in 2009, when he discovered in that museum a collection of parts related to Macao.
At the end, the professor of the Department of Languages, Cultures and Modern Literatures of the Faculty of Social and Human Sciences of the New University of Lisbon explained that the investigation accompanies the presence of a US community that established itself in Macao in the nineteenth century.
The work was supported by the Luso-Asian Studies Research Center (Ciela) of the University of Macao (one) and the investigation was subsidized by the Macau Foundation. The event at the Portuguese Bookstore was also attended by Joshua Ehrich, academic of the Department of History of UM. In Macao, Rogério Puga also presented a series of four lectures on UM, about intertextual relations between English literature and Portuguese literature regarding Macau and Anglo-Portuguese relations and the British presence in Macao in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, for example. The academic also today presents communication at the University of Sun Yat-Sen in Canton. Then, on Tuesday and Wednesday next week, he presents lectures at the UM UN Department of English.
This is a study of the American presence in Macao in the nineteenth century, which ends up explaining how several artistic representations, such as drawings, watercolors, real estate with macao landscapes, ended up to Peabody Essex Museum in Salem, near Boston, United States.
“Escolhi como forma representativa imagens de quadros, desenhos e mobiliário representativos da colecção do Peabody Essex Museum, que é o museu mais antigo dos Estados Unidos da América”, diz o investigador, salientando que este museu “tem um espólio enorme sobre Macau”. No livro de Rogério Miguel Puga são publicadas cerca de 200 imagens de representações artísticas de Macau presentes no museu norte-americano.
Each of the pieces, mostly produced by Western to consume other Westerners, was studied and grouped according to the theme in categories such as architecture, ethnographic landscapes, rituals, monuments, buildings, civil, military and religious architecture, for example.
And how did these pieces go to the United States? "These works were taken by American merchants coming to Macau in the nineteenth century to show the family." Some also ended up to the United States because there were merchants who bought them from the English painter George Chinnery, who lived several years in Macau, explains the Portuguese academic, adding that they later sold the wholesale pieces to pay debts.
The investigation was made based on the contextualization of descriptions that especially US women made each piece in their diaries. "I did this search for files and libraries from the United States and England." Rogério Puga conducted an interdisciplinary study on nineteenth -century Macao and the visual culture of English romantic painting, "especially because most works are by George Chinnery and there are works by Chinese painters imitating George Chinnery." "There are sewing tables with macao landscapes, there are also fans with Macao, Canton and some of Hong Kong painted on both faces, there are many portraits of merchants who were painting and family members," he enumerates. Part of the process was “contextualizing the production and circulation of these pieces worldwide and then studying the representation and importance of these pieces in the image of Macau in the American and English visual culture of the nineteenth century”.
Rogério Puga says that the "fascination" for the history of Macau is due to the "meeting and cohabitation between cultures". In particular, Anglo-Sino-Portuguese relations in Macau. And the book now presented in Macao is part of this scope, with the Anglophone part the United States. “I find it very interesting to see the cultures here in interaction and often in conflict,” he says. Rogério Puga says there is still “a lot to discover” about the story of Macau. In the cultural relationship of Anglophone communities, “American women's diaries are the most rich historical sources to study the history of Macao's daily life,” he concludes.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>XI tries to position China as a source of stability for Southeast Asia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/17/xi-tenta-posicionar-china-como-fonte-de-estabilidade-para-sudeste-asiatico/</link><description>The Chinese president is using a journey through Southeast Asia to defend free trade and position Beijing as a source of stability, at a time when the region is the main target of Washington's tariffs.
 
Xi Jinping was received on Monday in Hanoi with pomp and circumstance by Vietname President Luong Luong, and the next day he left for Kuala Lumpur, the capital of Malaysia, part of a three-day journey that ends in Cambodia.
In Hanoi, Xi told the Secretary General of the Vietnam Communist Party, to Lam, that the two countries "bring valuable stability and certainty" to a "turbulent world." "As beneficiaries of economic globalization, both China and Vietnam should reinforce strategic determination, jointly oppose unilateral acts of intimidation, defend the global free trade system and maintain global industrial chains," said Xi Jinping, according to a statement from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of China.
China and Vietnam signed a series of memorandum on cooperation in supply chains and a joint rail project. XI promised greater access to Vietnamese agricultural exports to China.
Vietnam is seen as the main beneficiary of the 'triangular trade' used by Chinese exporters to circumvent the rates imposed by US President Donald Trump about hundreds of millions of dollars of imports from China during his first term (2017–2021).
This system allowed products to be exported almost completed from China to the neighboring country to add a component or finish, aiming to change the manufacture place.
The US now absorbs almost 30% of Vietnamese exports, with Hanoi's surplus in bilateral trade setting up at $ 104 billion (101 billion euros), almost three times the value of $ 38 billion (37 billion euros) of 2017, when Trump took office.
Vietnam and Cambodia are thus the most punished countries with rates -46% and 49%, respectively -after China. However, Trump included both in a 90 -day truce, while increased rates on products from China to 145%.
Reacting to Xi's visit to Hanoi, the Republican said that China and Vietnam were trying to "find out how to sand the United States."
In Malaysia, Xi should discuss a free trade agreement between China and the 10 members of the Southeast Asian Nations Association (Asean), as Malaysia chairs the association this year.
Malaysia “is next to China” in the field of trade, Malaysian Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim said yesterday at the beginning of a visit by Chinese President Xi Jinping to Southeast Asia. "We are next to the Chinese government, for the well-being of our people and our national economic interests, as well as for the general development and stability of our country," Anwar told Chinese state television CGTN.
Quoted by the Chinese press, Asean's secretary-general Kao Kim Hourn said the deal will eliminate many of the customs between China and the block members. "We will reduce the rates to zero in many cases and then expand them to all areas," he said in an interview with China CGTN state television.
Malaysia is the headquarters of several projects of the Strip and Route initiative, including a Chinese rail project of $ 11.2 billion (9.9 billion euros). China is also the largest commercial partner and one of Malaysia's main foreign direct investment sources. "From the Chinese point of view, it is mainly about ensuring that the influence of China in the region remains strong and vibrant, and Southeast Asia is China's main commercial partner," said Oh EI Sun, researcher at the Singapore Institute of International Affairs, quoted by the Associated Press. "China can offer Vietname and other ASEAN countries a lot during this volatile period," said Nguyen Thanh Trung, Professor of Vietnamese Studies at Fulbright University of Vietnam. "I think China can be a leader," he said. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 05:33:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Store Cats: Between Rat Predators and Bairro Mascots</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/17/os-gatos-de-loja-entre-predadores-de-ratos-e-mascotes-de-bairro/</link><description>Photography Eloi Carvalho





Photography Eloi Carvalho





Photography Eloi Carvalho





Photography Eloi Carvalho


When we talk about cats in Macau, immediate thinking refers to pets. However, some typical stores resist the accelerated modernization of the region and continue to resort to felines to control pests and company in long hours of work. Some are more shy and alternate among hunting for rats and seaks in card boxes, away from customers; Others have conquered the heart of the neighborhood with their docile temperament and are even dismissed from the function of hunters. The end point was to know stories from three stores where cats exist in a limbo between freedom and domestication, without committing each other totally.
 
In the North Zone of Macao, far from the sparkling bullies of the historic center, the city's casinos and tourist flows, typical stores survive as a bubble of tradition and preservation of old rituals that are being forgotten in the outside world.
They are family businesses passed from generation to generation and mostly intended for an elderly audience, faithful to the same hairdressers, food establishments and convenience stores that frequented and aged with them. The shelves on the walls and boxes on the floor overflow with dry food, traditional Chinese medicine products and indecipherable labels, painting a amalgam of colors and textures that, from time to time, is interrupted by an unusual movement. Some pointed ears emerging behind the boxes. A sudden race behind the counter when customers get too close. Occasionally, a curious meow.
Cats of the typical Macau stores symbolize a slice of Chinese culture that still lasts in the region, despite the growing number of modern, large -scale shopping centers that only authorize human visitors. They are not totally wild; Some stroll through the neighborhood and refuse in puddles on the rides, but they know when and where to return to take the meals and spend a quiet night. Domesticated? Maybe it's a hyperbole. The most appropriate word to describe your function may be "collaborators."
Unlike apartment cats living a carefree routine between moist food dishes, comfortable beds and hundreds of patacas, local stores cats retain part of their wild nature by fulfilling their mission entrusted by store owners: pest control. Day and night, patrol the space with sniffer muzzles and look suspiciously, attentive to the passage of rats or other unwanted animals and then throw themselves over them and devour them. At least, this should be its function-but there are those who believe that even these semi-silvesters are being lazy.
“Nowadays, the cats get rats just to play with them, not to eat,” sighs the owner of a black electrodomers' repair store, looking from soslaio to a plump, white and black, that sleeps on a washing machine. "Even so, since I have the cat here, I have never seen rats in my store. There is a Chinese proverb that says all things have its enemy, that there is always one animal to subdue the other.
The owner, of Chinese origin, met Mao Mao - "cat cat" in Portuguese - "eight or ten years", when the cat of a store near the IAO Hon market had "a huge litter". Of the various felines who have already gone through their space, this is the only one who has not fled: “As it is sterilized, it is calmer and does not escape to find girlfriend,” smiles the owner of the establishment, leaning over the counter. "Unlike the other cats I had, it doesn't urine everywhere. It always uses the sandbox, and it didn't even have to teach it." It points to a corner of the store, where the belongings of Mao Mao are accumulated. In addition to the box with sand, it also has a hot, covered bed, and two bowls for water and food. "He likes feed, but sometimes I give him rice to eat more diverse foods."
When the question of taking the animal home and, therefore, of making it definitively, the shopkeeper adopts a more reticent speech: "No, no, there is a lot of hair; he can convey illness; if he went home the family would spend too much time with him." Still, the smiling comments that launches in the direction of Mao Mao denounce an attachment that has been consolidated over the last decade.
"It's very intelligent. During the day, go out alone to take a walk and sunbathe. Lies on the floor and exercise, rollers, jokes ... It's like a child. Then, go back to the store to spend the night sheltered from cold and wind." A couple enters and leaves a machine near the entrance, for repair, under the watchful look of Mao Mao. Those who approach it should do so with caution: only after the cat sniffs the strangers and the ears return to the relaxed position that their consent is implicit.
"It's a good cat, quiet. When you get back from the tours, you always come to me to stroke you. I never had any problem with him." Mao Mao seems to understand the owner's words and stretches proudly, before limming the claws in a paper box almost totally destroyed.
 
Four hunters (one reformed)
 
If the Electrodomestics store is reign by a single cat, a convenience store ten minutes away is an authentic matriarchal paradise.
The group consists of four cats, including two sisters who share an identical tricolor pattern. The oldest cat-of unusual orange coat, more common in male cats-has already sniffed the corners of the store since 2007 and now prefers to delegate the hunting to younger felines and stay in a hidden corner of the warehouse to enjoy the deserved rest.
“It is very normal to have cats in the typical stores of Macao,” says the owner. Chinese and Japanese superstitions associate the figure of little felines with prosperity, as the famous “Maneki-Neko” (or lucky cats) proves, but the store owner does not seem convinced that these magic properties extend to meat and bone cats. “In my opinion, I lose more money than I earn. You need to give food, take care of them, take them to the vet if they get sick… It's not easy to have animals,” he says.
One of the tricolor cats suddenly jumps to a strategic position, at the top of a closet, attentive to the group of clients that has just arrived. He is an ex -imy hunter, the owner reveals, although his intimidating presence is sufficient to "dissuade" the rats to approach space. When the prey can scarce, the cats enter the card boxes or to walk around. "Every day they are the same: they sleep in the morning and walk in the afternoon. They can recognize their way to the store and have been spending the night here," says the merchant. Packed by her voice, the cat goes back to her eyes at the highest point of the closet, ready for the morning nap.
 
The Mascot of the Neighborhood
 
The four cats of the convenience store, although they are “good company” and appreciated by the neighborhood, have no name. It is not necessary to call them: they do their work in the store, eat, walk, sleep, and interaction with the owner does not exceed this meticulously fulfilled routine. The case of Wong Dai, a cat-cat of an establishment that sells tape soups in the northern area of ​​Macao, has quite different contours.
On the scale between wild cat and home cat, Wong Dai-“yellow band”, literally, due to hair color-approaches the last category. Do not hunt rats-“Especially because there are no rats here”, rush to stress the owner, showing to the end the kitchen where she prepares the mass dishes-nor wanders abroad, vulnerable to the dangers of the road. Still, it is not a domestic cat in the strict sense of the word. Pass the mornings and afternoons outside the store, in a zone designed specifically so that nothing is missing. There is water, food, sand, toys, pills and two beds offered by the neighbors, one of them painted an even more vibrant orange than your hair.
“We got the cat when I was a baby to keep us company. It's more pet than store animal,” explains the owner, among the ribbons of tapes that is serving customers. Outside, Wong Dai delights with the caresses of the passing passersby and cannot resist touching their soft coat. Last year, the animal has become so popular among customers and neighbors that it may make sense to consider it a common pet to the whole neighborhood, united in a collective effort to ensure its comfort (and whims). It is often seeing children leaning under the chair where Wong Dai hides on the days of greatest movement, trying to attract him with pate sticks, or old man to deceive quench blankets or beds on colder days.
"Sometimes, during the day, let's go out to keep him company. At night, he sleeps inside the store to get hot and also for security reasons," confides the owner, sescribing her eyes to the curious who approach the cat. Since Wong Dai is not castrated yet (“Let's see; it is my son's wife who treats these things”) and, especially, due to the growing number of admirers, it is indispensable to put a leash during the day to ensure that he does not move away from the store that, after all, is his home. In a hand-added inscription in the breastplate, it reads the owner's contact number to ensure that the small “yellow band” returns to its place of comfort in the event of an escape.
According to the Food Hygiene Technical Instruction Document, issued by the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMIs), no pets are allowed in the area of ​​food handling or marketing, as they represent a “potential risk for food safety”. Asked by the final point, the body reveals that it has received 19 cases of “opinions on animal breeding in commercial establishments, mainly related to noise, feces and environmental hygiene” since 2023, and any violations of the animal protection law or food safety law ”after inspection in places.
The owner devalues ​​the subject. "The cat is always on the street, outside the area where it is touched by food. In addition, so far, we've never received any complaints. Everyone who passes here likes the cat a lot." Wong Dai also seems to like the attention. It even measures the level of enthusiasm that should employ the profile of those who approach. It patiently allows children and the elderly to caress him, but also knows how to run and throw themselves to the toys that the most enthusiastic customers use to captivate it.
It plays with mastery its intermediate role between an extinction cultural phenomenon, typical of the community neighborhoods and the street trade of the peripheries, and the contemporary society in which the animal company is increasingly valued. Judging by the toys that accumulate in the chair in front of the store, as if fan letters were dealt with, it is evident that even the most traditional areas of Macau are striding for the second scenario.
C.B.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>The real estate market will continue to fall by 2025, anticipate analysts</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/17/o-mercado-imobiliario-vai-continuar-a-cair-em-2025-antecipam-analistas/</link><description>The real estate market of the territory is in crisis. Although the number of transactions went up last year, prices descended significantly. Analysts and agents claim not to be a time -favorable height, which should continue to fall over this year.
 
It is true that the number of transactions has risen slightly, but “hides a larger collapse,” argues Ryan Choi, director-general of the Properties Environment: investors are selling the properties with great discounts. But, after all, what is happening? People in the territory are with little confidence in the local, national and international economy, and have avoided buying, in addition to waiting for a higher drop in prices, analysts and agents contacted by the end agree.
The figure services number numbers indicated that in the first quarter of the year, residential transactions corresponded to 651 (270 in January, 176 in February and 205 in March), equivalent to an increase of 21 percent compared to last year's homologous period. The average price in the first half of March came down to 69,343 patacas per square meter, which corresponds to 15 percent less, when compared to the same period of 2024. “It results from a flood of properties sold by investors with great discounts,” says Ryan Choi. As a result, "buyers are retracting, waiting for larger falls."
Also Mark Wong, the sénior director of Jones Lang Lang Lang, anticipates negative growth for 2025, even though he admits that this fall will be lighter in the residential sector than in others, in the order of 5 percent. "It has come down substantially three years ago and there are some prices already quite low, so we say it is a light forecast for residential units," he says. Given the volume of transactions, the representative of this agency states that these are “very low” numbers, compared, for example, with 1999, when the transfer of administration took place. “But the lowest point was two years ago, with the sale of only 3,000 units per year,” he says.
As for the reasons, Wong says residents already have a property and "the only reason that leads them to buy may be for the next generation or for investment purposes." Regarding this last reason, Wong says the height is not favorable. "I don't think the real estate market is good to invest now, not only in Macau, but globally, given the high interest rates," he says.
 
The local economy with some challenges
 
The flap is suffering, with empty stores, given “the high income that crushes business, losing to the continent's business, made through TAOBAO or crossing the border,” says Ryan Choi. In some cases, commercial rents “fell 30 percent”, with public services to change to public buildings and landlords to reduce values ​​to retain tenants.
In fact, residents' yields are decreasing. "The unbalanced recovery of the game and the removal of the junkets eliminated some jobs and the available performance, affecting the expenses in properties and luxury," he says. Then argues Choi, there is an excess of offer. "The new social housing units have increased excess, leading to increasingly lower prices," he justifies.
But there are still the obstacles of government policies. For example, earlier this year, the government decided to alleviate measures related to the real estate market to reduce speculation, descending from 80 to 70 percent the maximum limit of mortgage loans ratio for housing acquisition. With this measure, says Mark Wong, prices descended significantly. This is the limited number of people in Macao with a desire to buy a house in the territory and the public housing units, which are on the gutter in the future. "There is some competition between the private and residential market, although some of these fractions are in Hengqin, in the new neighborhood of Macau," he says, claiming that another government initiative, which is in competition with the Macao residential market.
 
Fluctuations in transactions
 
After the government raised demand control measures last April last year, the number of transactions increased slightly. But three months later, says economist Henry Lei, he went down again. And if, in January, the number was already higher, ascending 518, it is still low compared to the period prior to the pandemic. "Before we had 900 or sometimes more than 1000 transactions per month, not to mention 2018, when we had over 2000 transactions per month," he says. In short, for the analyst, people are not buying houses in Macau and, as a result, prices are also falling. “Overall, the price of properties in Macao descended to 2006 levels,” he says. "If at peak heights, the value of a property could exceed 11000 patacas per square meter, the values ​​are approximately 5000 patacas per square meter," he adds.
Among the factors, the analyst believes that the main one concerns the economic conditions of the population. "Many people receive less income compared to the pre-standard age," he says, noting that, according to official statistics, the median salary is only 17,000 patacas. “Imagine that you only receive the median and have a family of two: I don't believe a total yield of 40,000 patacas is enough to buy a two -bedroom apartment in Macao.”
Also, there is a lack of confidence from people. “With the price of houses coming down for three consecutive years, this may indicate that there will be more adjustments in the near future,” he says, “People are conservative to make their investments or even decide to have their home.”
Lastly, like all other respondents, Henry Law believes it is directly related to increased supply. “There are more units in mainland China, becoming more convenient to move to China, for example, in Hengqin,” he says, also highlighting the new Macao neighborhood, very appealing to prices. In addition, the bank sector itself squeezed control or requirements for bank loans.
When a potential foreign investment in the Macao real estate for Henry Law, such as the places are conservative, the international environment also does not favor major investments. "In recent days, global financial markets have suffered great oscillations, affecting the confidence of potential buyers," he says.
 
The impact of the Chinese economy
 
For analyst José Luís de Sales Marques, in this part of the world, there are some particularities. On the one hand, the Chinese economy is also at a stage when growth has been only moderate. At the same time, looking at the game's recipes, it is clear that there is some “uncertainty” announced by the government itself. "The executive said that the expectations of growth of game revenues will not arrive what had predicted and regarding which a budget was made," says the economist.
Afterwards, Macau had a “crazy increase between 2010 and 2014”, which corresponded, according to some analysts, to a “pricing of houses 14 times higher than the increase in inflation”, but in recent years there has been “a paradigm shift of the game model with the junkets and all related activities to a big break”, generating a chain effect also in real estate.
Overall, there are “various signs” that play in line to “the real estate market already has a look for the lower ones. For example, thinking of the 17,000 -patacas median salary and the current price per square meter,“ there is clearly a situation that is structural of a complete dissonance between the price of real estate and the income we have in Macao, although they are normally considered quite high. ”
In the economist's opinion, there will continue to be a progressive descent of the real estate price, as well as some government incentive to credit. "We see that because interest rates are high in the United States - we follow the tendency of the US monetary market - Prime Rate in Macau is very high," he says.
 
Should the government intervene?
 
Henry Law does not believe that the government should seek to stimulate the real estate market as it can result in "excessive risk to both buyers and the banking system." However, he continues Henry Lei, the government is now facing a dilemma related to regional territory integration in the Greater Bay region-whether national strategy is to encourage more residents of the territory to settle in hengqin or large bay, how can the places to buy home in the real estate market of Macao?
Ryan Choi disagrees, suggesting a series of measures that can be taken by the government. Among them, the aligning of mortgage rules. “They can again have the buyer support measure for the first time to improve their economic capacity,” he says. On the other hand, to attract foreign investment, such as neighboring Hong Kong, the territory can also eliminate the seal tax. To improve the sector of retail and small and medium enterprises, the executive can “provide support for income or subsidies to ensure employment and purchasing power”.
In turn, Mark Wong also believes the government can take some measures. It can, for example, have 80 percent as a maximum limit of the mortgage loans for housing, and also seek to attract foreigners to work in Macau. “We are a little back in this theme, compared to other countries. We still have some restrictions on the entry of foreigners,” he says.
Last week, the Centaline Real Estate Agency, in its report, predicted a global breakdown of housing prices of 10 to 20 percent throughout the year. "The real estate market entered the ice age, with housing prices and the volume of transactions falling," the agency also admitted.
In February, the Macao Building Commercial Association was not optimistic about the possibility of the real estate market recovering later this year, providing for the crisis to drag for another year and a half to two years before the effective resumption.</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 05:34:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Support for mental health and economic perspectives worry experts from a</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/17/apoio-a-saude-mental-e-perspectivas-economicas-preocupam-peritos-da-um/</link><description>A seminar held by the Macao Center of Studies of the University of Macao, gathered ten experts and academics to analyze the 2025 governive action lines. Paul Pun, Secretary General of Caritas, and Elvo Sou, teacher of psychology, defend measures to support mental and physical health of the population, especially young generation. Other researchers reported being aware of the problem of Macao's unit economic structure.
 
Mental health, youth development, and the region's financial situation are among the most worrying issues of experts and academics in relation to the government lines for next year. The Macao Center of Studies of the University of Macao (one), held on Tuesday a seminar and invited ten experts to present more suggestions to the work of the present government.
The seminar was chaired by Agnes Lam, director of the Macao Center of Studies, during which, according to the institution, the academics said they agreed with the political orientation presented, but requested practical actions to improve government capacity and effectiveness.
Paul Pun, Secretary General of Caritas Macau, advocates the introduction of more measures for the promotion of physical and mental health for all and for the sensitization of citizens for the value of life. He also suggested that policies are created to relieve the pressure of care for their parents and that private care institutions are created to release more vacancies in public organizations.
Asking for more attention to the development of young people, Paul Pun indicated that the number of international exchange vacancies for students should be increased, promoting the participation of young people in social affairs and reinforcing international exchanges in public welfare through universities.
The assistant professor in the Department of Psychology at UM, Elvo Sou Kuai Long, said he was also aware of the lack of multidimensional policies to deal with the lack of psychological support of young people. He proposed actions to “promote physical and mental health and improve the quality of mental health programs”, “increase the time dedicated to sport and reduce entertainment with resources to electronics of young people” and “solve the privacy problem of people seeking psychological help,” he said.
He asked for more support for the professional development of young people by improving the mechanism of internships and employment in the area of ​​the large bay and the creation of a system for evaluating and supporting employment.
Regarding economic performance, Henry Law, an associate professor at the Department of Finance and Business Economics at UM, said Macao's objective economic situation “is not optimistic”, taking into account the uncertainty of tax revenues, unit economic structure and the sole source of tax rate.
Henry Lei considers that the government should still study how to explore the way of increasing companies' investment in the territory and in Hengqin to create a model of government led investment promotion. It is also waiting for the announcement of specific operational details for assistance measures to small and medium enterprises.
At the time, Kaian Lam, assistant professor at the Department of Government and Public Administration, addressed the issue of the city's monolithic economic structure. "The government -action line report mentioned the need to develop international markets, however, in Spanish and African language markets, it is difficult [promotion] to have results in a short period of time," he warned.
The government must also work in the mechanism about the responsibility of civil servants, defended the academic, noting that it is necessary a legislative review to improve the efficiency and responsibility in the civil service, taking into account the lack of motivation of some public officials in Macao.
Alfred Wong Seng Fat, professor of electromechanical engineering, in turn, urged to promote data interoperability in the great bay to develop an intelligent city, as well as to improve the means of barriers without barriers in response to population aging.</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 05:33:05</pubDate></item><item><title>India Anti -Corruption Agency accuses leaders of capital bleaching</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/17/agencia-anticorrupcao-da-india-acusa-lideres-da-oposicao-de-branqueamento-de-capitais/</link><description>India's anti -corruption inspection agency accused opposition leaders Sonia and Rahul Gandhi of money laundering as part of “a criminal conspiracy”, along with other members of the Congress Party (INC).
The names of Sonia Gandhi, president of INC from 1998 to 2017 and from 2019 to 2022 and currently a member of Rajya Sabha, or High House of Parliament, and her son Rahul Gandhi, who acts as the opposition leader in the Baixa of Parliament, were cited in the process opened by the Supervisory Directorate (ED), according to The Indian Express.
This case dates back to a complaint filed in 2014, which accused several InC leaders of participating in a capital laundering scheme to acquire properties valued at more than $ 230 million. The investigation, however, only began in 2021, the EFE agency reported.
According to Ed, either Sonia and Rahul is the majority shareholders of Young Indian, a private company that acquired the properties in question for only $ 58,000, owned by AJL. They are still accused of more crimes through false donations and advances of false incomes.
Although the case was contested in several courts, he guaranteed that he was maintained "by both the Superior Court of Delhi and the Supreme Court of India, allowing the investigation to continue." The case will be tried by a special court on April 25, according to the newspaper.
None of the two affected leaders issued any statement about the prosecution so far, although another high employee of InC, Adhir Ranjan, denounced the accusation as an Indian Prime Minister's conspiracy, Narendra Modi, to destroy the opposition party, in statements to the Indian news agency Ani.
A Gujarat State Court sentenced Rahul Gandhi to two years in prison for defamation in March 2023 after the politician claimed during a rally in 2019 that “all thieves” have the nickname of Prime Minister Narendra Modi.
However, the Supreme Court immediately granted him bail while waiting for the result of his appeal.</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 05:36:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Prices of new houses in China fall for the 22nd consecutive month</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/17/precos-das-casas-novas-na-china-caem-pelo-22o-mes-consecutivo/</link><description>The prices of new houses in China fell for the 22nd consecutive month in March, despite the government's measures to wage the prolonged sector crisis. Prices in 70 selected cities fell 0.11%compared to the previous month, according to data released yesterday by the Asian National Statistics Office (GNE). The fall in February was the same percentage value.
Among the localities mentioned above, 41 registered descents in the prices of new houses compared to 45 in February. Among these, 24 - including some important such as Shanghai or Shenzhen - registered increases, more than the previous month (18).
GNE data also revealed a 0.2% drop in the price of secondhand houses in March, a more moderate pace than recorded in the previous month (0.3%).
In the case of this type of real estate, 56 of the 70 cities registered descents, four remained at the same level as in December and ten registered climbs.
In recent months, Chinese authorities have continued to announce measures to wrap the real estate market, an issue that worries Beijing due to their implications for social stability, as housing is one of the main investment vehicles of Chinese families.
One of the main causes of the recent softening of the Chinese economy is precisely the real estate crisis, whose weight in national GDP - adding the indirect factors - was estimated at about 30%, according to some analysts.</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 05:32:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Fight for the title 'warms' in Guimarães on the Easter journey</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/17/luta-pelo-titulo-aquece-em-guimaraes-na-jornada-de-pascoa/</link><description>Benfica's visit to Guimarães, already after Sporting hosted Moreirense, "warms up" the 30th round of the I Football League, which marks the start of the final sprint of the two "big" Lisbetas in search of the title.
 
On Easter weekend, Sporting hopes to have a "Santa" Friday in Alvalade, before Moreirense, although Moreira de Connegos team has already beaten the "lions" this season, then hope Benfica's "pilgrimage" to Minho is not quiet the next day.
Already the incarnates, still marked by the (2-2) unexpected draw with Arouca in Luz in the past journey, move to the always difficult home of Vitória de Guimarães and again have a new test outside the doors, after the '20 values' note obtained before FC Porto (4-1) at the Dragon Stadium.
Draw at the top of the I Liga, with 69 points, Sporting, which comes from a difficult victory in the Azores (1-0), is the first to enter the field against Moreirense. Now, at a time when it is forbidden to let out points, Sporting is required to beat the 10th classified of the I Liga and repeat what has done consecutively a decade ago. It is necessary to retreat until 2014/15 to find the last time the Moreirense did not leave defeated from Alvalade (1-1).
Expelled after the final whistle in Azores, Harder is low right, as is Morita, which remains an important absence at midfield. After a long absence (five months), Internacional Pedro Gonçalves returned to the pitch in the last round, but will hardly be in physical conditions to be a starter.
On Saturday, already aware of the result of rival Lisboeta, at the meeting that closes the journey, Benfica will face in Guimarães the fifth classified of the race, in the always 'scorching' environment of D. Afonso Henriques.
Bruno Lage's team, who will have the main squad figures at their disposal, wants to quickly forget the draw with Arouca and demonstrate that it can even reach the title and prevent Sporting's two -time championship. However, the task promises not to be easy, as Vitória de Guimarães comes from two straight triumphs in the I Liga and does not know what it is to lose to the championship since the end of January.
At home, the team now led by Luís Freire only once defeated in this edition, still in the ‘Era’ Rui Borges, when he fell before FC Porto (3-0), on the sixth round.
Ronda 30 also promises to write another chapter in the fight for third place, with Sporting de Braga, which adds 60 points, visiting on Saturday Estoril Praia. A day earlier, FC Porto, which adds 59, hosts Famalicão, a team in good form (three straight wins, four in the last five games), in a new exam for the continuity of Argentine coach Martín Anselmi next season. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 05:35:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism Transfronho: Hong Kong and Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/17/turismo-transfronteirico-hong-kong-e-macau/</link><description>If transfronted tourism encompasses the way the tourist authorities of Hong Kong and Macau interact with the continent's authorities about the ways of boosting the tourist industry of the two special administrative regions, the visit of the new secretary for culture, sports and tourism of Hong Kong, Rosanna Law Shuk-Pui, Beijing and also the visit of the new secretary for social affairs and macao culture, Lam, Beijing, in early April, deserve our attention.
Rosanna Law's first visit to Beijing was significant, as she and other subordinates went to the Cabinet director for Hong Kong and Macao affairs, Xia Baolong. According to Law, Xia was deeply interested in the way Hong Kong could develop his tourist sector, especially Xia's “special directive” to encourage Hong Kong to use his peripheral islands to innovate tourism by introducing cruise trips.
Xia's “Special Directive” was mentioned a long time ago when she met the former Secretary for Culture, Sport and Tourism, Kevin Yeung. As a successor of Yeung, Law naturally has to follow Xia's innovative idea.
Rosanna Law stressed the need for Hong Kong to take advantage of Hong Kong's central tourism government policies, maximizing the territory mark and producing new tourist products to attract visitors from the continent and abroad.
Law has also met with Gao Zhidan, director of the General Administration of State Sports, to discuss the way Hong Kong and the continent cooperate in the preparation of the 15th National Games, which will be co-organized by Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau, which will be an important event to mark the narrower collaboration between the two special administrative regions and Guangdong.
GAO expressed the continent's strong support for Hong Kong's sports development, including training, athlete training, and even funds on facilities - areas that Hong Kong sports need, as territory sports have been generally underdeveloped compared to the continent, although Hong Kong has impressive achievements in some sports areas, such as the world, such as Hong Kong. fencing.
Law visited China's film administration to discuss forms of cooperation and exchange between Hong Kong and mainland China-a vast cooperation area that can progress further, as Hong Kong films can be co-produced with mainland China, the huge, the huge, the huge rental costs of continental china, the huge facilities, the huge rental costs, the huge. resources and specialized knowledge of invaluable value. The reinforced economic partnership agreement has already allowed the Hong Kong film industry and its professionals and investors to move to the interior, aiming at the continent's audience and co-producing high quality films with profitable perspectives.
On April 1, the Secretary for Macao Social Affairs and Culture, LAM, went to Beijing to attend a meeting of the China's interior work committee on how to integrate tourism and culture in Macao. Among the interior authorities of China who attended the meeting, were the Deputy Minister of Culture and Tourism, Gao Zheng, and the deputy director of the connection office, Huang Liuquan.
The April 1 meeting has analyzed the progress of collaboration between the continent and Macao in the fields of culture and tourism since 2024, and both parties have reached an agreement on how the Macao's Ministry of Culture and Tourism will promote Chinese culture and tourism with foreign countries.
Under the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau and the Great Bay project, Macau is expected to play the role of a platform that uses Chinese culture as the main characteristic, simultaneously emphasizing its unique role as the base of multicultural exchange.
In response to this project in the Great Bay area, the Macao government presented its 2016-2020 Development Plan that aimed to develop Macao as a Chinese culture promotion center and, at the same time, emphasize its multicultural identity in the promotion of tourism. In May 2023, the continent's Ministry of Culture and Tourism signed an agreement to form a joint work committee to promote Macao as a base that emphasizes Chinese culture as the main characteristics and multiculturalism as another coexistence characteristics.
Thus, Lam's visit to Beijing was a follow -up action of the idea of ​​developing Macau as a "base" for Chinese culture such as main characteristics and multicultural coexistence.
Macao has had an impressive performance in the development of cultural tourism. In June 2024, Macau received the title of East Asia Cultural City 2025 (see: Macao distinguished as the cultural city of East Asia 2025 - Portal of the Government of MSAR (www.gov.mo)). The nomination of the city of East Asia Culture was a joint initiative by the governments of China, Japan and the Republic of Korea. The 2024 meeting was the first international cultural city nomination event in Asia and represents a transnational and transfronted event in which Macao's cultural tourism was highly praised.
In addition to this award, Macau has been able to obtain the awards from the China National Art Foundation in 2023 and 2024, and the city has produced many innovative local and young artists whose creative work gained eleven Foundation awards in 2023 and ten of the same foundation in 2024.
It is noteworthy that during the meeting with Lam, Gao Zheng mentioned the award awarded to Macau as an East Asia Cultural City and added that the central government expects narrow cooperation with Macau to promote Chinese culture through the city.
Transfrontic cooperation in the field of tourism is increasingly important between Hong Kong and Macau. On April 7, 2025, the Macao Tourism Services Directorate invited Hong Kong's Tourist Industry Council to visit Macau and hold a meeting. The 27 member delegation of the Hong Kong Tourist Industry Council was headed by President Tam Kwong-Shun. The interim director of the Macao Tourism Services Directorate, Cheng Wai Tong, discussed with Hong Kong some concrete questions, including the way to promote tourists visit to the Great Bay through the idea of ​​introducing “a multiple visits”, how to better use tourist resources for Hong Kong and Macau, and how to develop new tourism directions in both places.
In analytical terms, Hong Kong and Macau tourism authorities should reinforce dialogue and in -depth discussions about how they can and will promote the idea of ​​"a season, multiple visits." Tourists from the interior of China and abroad can take the opportunity to visit Macau first and then go to Hong Kong, or vice versa. They should be encouraged to visit Shenzhen, Zhuhai or other cities in the Great Bay to achieve an advantageous situation for the tourist development of Hong Kong, Macao and Continental China. A mutual investigation on the duration of tourists in Hong Kong and Macau must be carried out. If the short stay of the stay in Hong Kong and Macau is the standard, the tourist authorities of both cities should take advantage of this short stay to make Hong Kong and Macau visits interconnected in a single package.
Traditionally, Hong Kong has depended a lot on the individual visits of the inhabitants of mainland China since July 2003 and their collaboration with the mainland China tourism authorities can be reinforced. Hong Kong tour authorities have created Hong Kong's image as an international city, but Hong Kong's historic meeting as an oriental city with Western culture was not fully disclosed and enhanced in Hong Kong's tourist promotion. The central government also did not guide Hong Kong's tourism development to the recent observations of Xia Baolong on how Hong Kong must fully use his peripheral islands to expand tourist points and attractions.
Hong Kong and Macau tourism authorities should reinforce their collaboration. The recent meeting between the Macao Tourism Services Directorate and the Hong Kong Travel Industry Council is a good sign; However, the idea of ​​“a station, multiple visits” needs to be released not only in Macau but also in Hong Kong. It remains to be seen how Hong Kong's tourism authorities from both private and public sector will actually understand and implement this important idea in the coming years.
Traditionally, Hong Kong's tourist authorities have also emphasized mega events to attract foreign and continent tourists such as Ruby Sevens, the Hong Kong marathon and international boat tank top. Similarly, Macau has used the mega events to promote tourism, namely the Macao Grand Prix. In ideal terms, these megaevents in both cities can and should be connected in an innovative way, with a view to realizing the idea of ​​“a station, multiple visits”.
Sports tourism in Hong Kong and Macau has plenty of space for collaboration with the continent. Football, for example, is relatively underdeveloped in both Hong Kong and Macao. Whenever Hong Kong invite famous foreign football teams to visit Hong Kong, they can also be invited to play in Macau and the Great Bay (GBA).
Another innovative idea is the creation of a first league for the big bay, Hong Kong and Macao, with several top teams from the Hong Kong first league and its Macao First Division counterparts participating in an annual GBA football tournament with GBA's top teams. Desta forma, o nível do futebol pode e será melhorado através da injeção de mais competição e dos jogos em casa e no local. Os adeptos e seguidores de várias equipas podem visitar as cidades da GBA, estimulando um cenário em que todos ganham no turismo de futebol.
Many other sporting events can and should adopt the above model. Currently, sports development in Hong Kong and Macau is relatively limited only to two cities, without great collaboration between the two cities and the continent. The 15th national games are expected to stimulate various sports sectors to consider the way sport and tourism can be integrated and co-developed in the coming years.
Traditionally, Macau has integrated cultural heritage with tourism, while Hong Kong was created as an international city famous for its financial and monetary center. Both cities have emphasized their tourist image and adopted different strategies in the field of tourism: Macao as a casino center and a special Chinese cultural center with multicultural colors for continent and foreigners tourists, while Hong Kong as an international city in the eyes of the continent's tourists.
Hong Kong's tourist authorities may have to do more to preserve historical sites and enhance the way the city has historically played a crucial role in the interface between the East and the West. In this respect, Hong Kong museums may have to reflect more on the expansion of the theme of the East meeting with the West. The traditionally non-interventionist policy adopted by the Hong Kong government in tourism seems to be exceeded, as Xia Baolong's comments about Hong Kong tourism point to the need for better planning and a more coordinated and innovative strategy.
If cruise tourism is a way to follow Hong Kong and its peripheral islands, it can also be linked to Macau, where the renewal of casino concessions mentioned the need to develop cruise tourism on the Macao Peninsula and Taipa Island. If parts of Hengqin are now under the co-administration of Macau and Zhuhai, Hengqin can also develop cruise tourism, connecting it not only Macau but also Hong Kong in the long run.
In conclusion, Rosanna Law's visits and LAM to Beijing on tourism issues related to Hong Kong, Macau and their cooperation with mainland China have an important impact on tourism development in both cities. If innovative ideas for Hong Kong are required, they are needed and more collaborations between Hong Kong and Continental China, Macao and Continental China and Hong Kong and Macau. Better coordination, more dialogue, more innovative ideas and more mobilization of cultural and sports sectors in both special administrative regions are needed in order to maximize the enormous potential of Hong Kong and Macau as twins of cultural and sports tourism on the southern coast of China.</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 05:31:05</pubDate></item><item><title>The meaning of the word Easter</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/17/o-significado-da-palavra-pascoa/</link><description>The Easter celebrating this Sunday, the most important festivity of the Christian religious calendar, is a mobile festivity, that is, there is no fixed date on the calendar, such as Christmas, and its date is calculated according to the phases of the moon, thus following the custom of the ancient Hebrews. The date of Easter, according to the Computus Paschalis of Rome or Paschalion of the Greeks, falls on the first Sunday after the first Moon Moon following the spring equinox. Although the formula is the same for Catholics and Orthodox, the fact that orthodox still today follow the Julian calendar explains that Christmas, a party fixed on December 25, and the Easter mobile party do not coincide in the West and the East. However, in the particular case of Easter, from time to time, the dates coincide; Such is the case this year when it is celebrated by Catholics and Orthodox this Sunday, April 20.
In 2025, the spring equinox, according to the Julian calendar, was on April 3 (April 20 in the Gregorian calendar). Thus, the first cash moon after the spring equinox was, in both calendars, on April 13, falling Easter on both sides of the church on Sunday. This phenomenon occurs every three or four years.
The Easter calculation formula dates from around the century according to our age. Christian Easter celebrations are directly related to the Easter of Jews who use a lunar calendar to calculate their religious dates. The lack of coincidence between the lunar and solar division of time, causes followers of lunar calendars to be required to readjust their calendar from time to time so that the lunar year can be contained within the regular repetition of the year's stations, which is determined by the rotation of the earth around the sun. To resolve this mismatch the Jews add a thirteenth month, that is, the last month, the month, the month, the month, the month, the month, the month, the month, the month, the month, the month, the month, the month, the month, the month, the month, the month, the month, the month, the month, the month which happens seven times every 19 years.
The undoing between the Julian calendar used by Christians in the Roman Empire and the lunar calendar of the Jews, which, however, left Palestine, were scattered through different regions, began to create difficulties around the third century. For these heights, Hipólito of Rome (170–235) and Anatólio de Laodicea (? –283), began to create calculation tables for Easter.
Associated with this was also the desire to separate the Christian feast from the Jewish party. Thus, the Council of Niceia, in 325, establishes computus paschalis, or formula for calculating the date of the Christian Easter, as universally compulsory. The calculation formula remained the same since then, the only change was the introduction of the Gregorian calendar that came into force in 1582, as we had the opportunity to discuss here.
 
Jewish Easter
Jewish Easter or Pessach celebrates the liberation of the Jews from slavery in Egypt according to the biblical narrative.
The Jewish Torah says that Joseph, one of the twelve sons of Jacob, grandson of Abraham and also known as Israel, was sold by his brothers and taken as a slave to Egypt, where he would eventually become Pharaoh's advisor thanks to his ability to interpret dreams (Gen. 37-41). During a period of great hunger, Joseph's brothers went to Egypt to buy cereals and, once the peace with their brother, were invited to settle in Egypt under Joseph's protection (Gen. 42-47).
However, Joseph died and the new Pharaoh enslaved the Israelites because they, having grown in number, were seen by the Egyptians as a potential threat (eg 1: 8-10; 11–14).
Arrived to this point, Moses, an Israeli who according to the biblical tradition was created in the Egyptian court, who receives from God the mission of freeing the Israelites from slavery and taking them to a promised land where they could be free.
Faced with Pharaoh's refusal to let the Israelites leave, God throws the famous ten pests upon the land of Egypt, the last of which he is responsible for the death of the Pharaoh's son with all the firstborn of the other Egyptians (eg 12:29). The night that death passed through the land of Egypt, the Jews celebrated their first Easter as they prepare for the departure of Egypt.
‘The Ten Commandments, 1956, one of the greatest epics of American cinema directed by Cecil Demille and with Charlton Heston and Yul Brynner as leading protagonists, tells the story, albeit romanticated, how Moses freed the Israeli people from the Pharaoh yoke and how the Israelites crossed the Red Sea to pass the two to pass the two to pass Israelites.
 
The origin of the word 'pesach'
The biblical narrative that reports the escape of the Israelites of the land of Egypt is today considered by the vast majority of academics and theologians as a legendary story, probably removed from local folklore that has been elaborated and expanded until it became the saga of the Hebrew people today.
The reasons that lead to this conclusion have nothing to do with the belief or not in miracles, such as the Red Sea partition in two. The reasons for today this story to be considered non-factual are of a various, philological, archaeological, historical, etc., and some complexity, so that we cannot explain it here conveniently. Let's see only two.
The first has to do with the geopolitical structure of the time. Although we opted for a more flexible chronology, the escape of the ancient Hebrews to Palestine would represent an Egyptian escape to Egypt since at the time Palestine, the only access corridor of the Hittites to Egypt and vice versa, was under the Egyptian rule to control any attempt to raid the hitites over their territory.
A second reason equally easy to understand is the demographic issue. According to the book of Exodus (12:37), six hundred thousand men left on foot of Egypt, not to mention women and children, says the text literally. Let us then imagine that the Israelites, including women and children, would always be in accordance with the biblical narrative, about one million and two thousand people. The whole Egyptian population, calculated, would be, at the time-and Egypt was one of the region's most important and prosperous kingdoms-both and the three million people. Thus, the Israelites would represent, more or less, between half and one third of the population of Egypt. Such a demographic stampede would be enough to collapse the country, yet there are no records - and the Egyptians registered everything - of an emigration movement of this dimension or the economic consequences that such a population exodus would necessarily cause. Admittedly, the numbers and estimates that the Bible rarely offers are reliable, but still, the loss of the entire slave population of an Egyptian economy would inevitably have to leave noticeable marks in history.
Another problem related to Jewish Easter is the meaning of your name. In Hebrew the Passover of the Jews is said to be Pesach. This word derives from the PSch verbal root whose meaning is ambiguous. In fact, the first instance of this word in the Old Testament is exactly in the text that describes Pesach, as soon as we need to compare prior terms to this use of the word. According to the uses of this verb outside the context of the Pesach festivity, its meaning is something like passing by or wide, in the sense of not reaching the target, hence that in English Pesach is usually translated as Passover. In some contexts, this verb also means toxify.
The Hebrew noun Pesach, which may have begun its existence as a verbal form in the third person singular Niphal, wanting originally to say, he will refer to the episode, told in the book of Exodus, in which God's hand passed through the land of Egypt killed all the firstborn children, except those of the homes whose Unebrais were marked with the lamb's blood. This lamb, called Pascal Lamb, should be sacrificed and eaten that night, a custom that began to characterize the Jewish pesach until the destruction of the temple in our age and was part of Christ's last supper with his disciples.
In the houses where the blood of the lamb was painted in the umbra of the gates, the hand of God would pass off and the firstborn of this house would be spared. It is from here that the image of the Paschal Lamb is first derived whose blood avoids death and is a sign of life.
Although the Hebrew word Pesach means etymologically he has passed by, the word is often interpreted as wanting to say only passage in reference, not to the passage of God's hand over Egypt, but to the passage of Israelites out of Egypt, an interpretation that Christianity prefers. It should be noted that the interpretation of the Old Testament made by Jews and Christians differs significantly.
Hebrew pesach corresponds to the word Pascha in the septuagint, the ancient Greek translation of the Old Testament made for the Jews of the Diaspora. In fact, the word Pascha is not a Greek translation, but the transliteration of the Aramaic equivalent of the word Pesach, since it was Aramaic the common language of Palestine in Jesus' time.
Latin adopted the word Pascha as the Greeks had transliterated it from Aramaic. The Portuguese word Easter derives from the confusion made by the ordinary people between the Greek word Pascha and the Latin Pascua, which means pasture, from the same root of feeding. From this popular confusion, beyond the Portuguese word also the Castilian Pascua, the Italian and Catalan Pasqua, the Frenchman and Provencal Pascas.
 
Christian Easter
The Christian Easter derives and at the same time completes the Jewish festivity as, from the theological point of view, this is the culmination of Pesach.
At the time of his passion and death, Jesus was in Jerusalem to celebrate the Pesach and our Holy Thursday refers to the ritual meal that the Jews celebrated. In the pesach azimo bread was ate, ie non-fermented bread, lamb with bitter herbs and drank wine. The unhealthy bread was to remember the hurry with which the Jews ate their last meal before leaving Egypt, the bitter herbs served to remember the sufferings of slavery, and the lamb resembled the blood that had spared the ancient Hebrews of divine wrath.
After his last supper, Jesus was arrested and tried. Sentenced to death, he was crucified, died and was buried the next day, Friday. On the third day, our Sunday, when women who followed him and the disciples went to the grave, this was open and empty, Jesus had risen.
At first, Palestinian Christians, who were seen as just another faction within Judaism, continued to celebrate the religious festivals of the Jewish calendar. Christians outside Palestine, for the most part converts of paganism, had no attachment to Jewish traditions, and since relatively early, Easter for them had much more to do with the resurrection of Christ than with the liberation of the Hebrew people, which, by the way, continued to look at these pagan -coming Christians as second -class. Thus, Christians from outside the Palestine break ties with the Jewish tradition of Pesach and begin to celebrate the foundations on which their new religious identity was based. Nevertheless, the historical-genetic relationship between Pesach and the Christian Easter has not been lost, nor was the name of the festivity that remains the same, although in its Hellenized version.
In this context, the word Pascha, the Greek and Latin version of our word Easter, which represents no more than a transliteration of the Aramaic spoken by Jesus and the Jews, his contemporaries, acquires a new meaning. Christians outside Palestine, who know neither Hebrew nor Aramaic, do not know that the verb or that the word derives and as such the meaning depends on their understanding of the deeds described by this word which, at least, at first is something strange and to which it is necessary to attribute some meaning.
 
The meaning of the word Easter
The preface to the Paschal Vigil, the ceremony that marks the resurrection of Jesus Christ, says in the original Latin version ‘Vere Dignum et iustum est, aequum et salutare, te (…) in HAC power nocte gloriosius pascha nostrum immolatus est christus’, in Portuguese ‘is truly worthy, rational, and healthy, rational May we (…) bless you more gloriously at the night when Christ, our Easter, was immolated. '
The translation of Latin does not explain the meaning of the word Easter, only identifies Christ with Easter which can, in a way, until the confusion is increased. The English version says in ‘When Christ, our Passover, Has Been Sacrificed’. The text seems to suggest that the word Easter refers to the lamb that the Jews used to immolate or sacrifice at the time of Pesach to atone for their faults, which in the New Testament had been replaced by Jesus.
Among the Jews it was customary to sacrifice animals as a way of atonement, or to pay, for acts that they had committed against the Mosaic Law. The Jews did not have the concept of sin that we have, therefore, to the Jews of the second temple universal morality did not exist, to sin was to act contrary to what was prescribed by law, and nothing more. These animal sacrifices were individual and punctual as they would have to be repeated whenever a new foul was committed by the individual against the law. There were also community sacrifices, but they also had to be repeated every year.
Christ, being God,, in replacing Himself to the Paschal Lamb, would have made a perpetual and final sacrifice, that is, a sacrifice valid forever that it does not need to be repeated and eliminates, not the faults, not a particular individual, but of all human genre. That is why it is said that if by the action of one man sin entered the world, also by the sacrifice of one man the sin of the world was exposed.
In the Pesach of the ancient Hebrews, the hand of God, passing by Egypt, spared the lives of the firstborn whose doors were marked with the blood of the lamb sacrificed that night in the Christian Passover, also celebrates that those marked by the blood of the lamb are spared to death. This is the bond between the two Easter. The difference lies in the quality of the lamb. In the sacrifice of the Old Testament, the lamb was a mere animal while in Christian Easter the immolated victim is God himself in the person of his son who, incidentally, voluntarily offers himself. Necessarily also the result will be distinct. In the Old Testament, Jews in Egypt escape temporal death, while in the case of the sacrifice of Jesus Christ, which offers himself as a victim, the human genre escapes eternal death.
Egypt's escape, the historical-genetic origin of Easter, which today we know not to be factual, is the image or foreshadowing of the Passover of Christ. This is exactly why, the fact that the events described in the books of Genesis and the Exodus are not what we call truth, that is, factual reality, does not cause any importance to the religious meaning or the theological value of the text. Not everyone sees things in this way, and there are those, especially among American evangelicals, continue to believe that all that is told in these biblical myths has really happened. The Bible is not a history book, but of theology!
Christ is also considered the new Isaac. Abraham was asked to sacrifice his only son, Isaac. When he was about to do so, God allowed Isaac, at the time a boy, to be replaced by a lamb. Thus the sacrifice would have been incomplete. Here too this story is not to be taken to the letter. Perhaps an Abraham and Isaac existed in the history of the peoples who inhabited Palestine in ancient times. However, today it is believed that these characters, to have in fact existed, were not even related to each other and will have been the Bible compilers, especially after the Assyrian-Babylonian and Persian occupations, who tried to relate the heroes of local folklore to create coherent national narrative.
Again here is the theological-symbolic content of the text that matters. Contrary to Abraham, God in fact sacrificed His only Son and thus Christ's sacrifice is considered the perfect sacrifice and as such an eternal and without repetition. The Mass, which the Council of Trent defines, in its twenty -second session, as the same sacrifice that Christ offers on the cross, but in an incredent form, is not a repetition of sacrifice, but a material update of the metaphysical reality of the sacrifice of two thousand years ago. As a result of the general confusion that settled after Vatican II, most people, including priests who should know more, think that Mass is a reenance of the last supper - is a Protestant idea.
The Easter we celebrate this Sunday, in fact, to the Catholic faithful, at least for the most educated, is celebrated, that is, it becomes present, whenever Mass is said. (Yes, in Portuguese the expression is to say Mass, or sing Mass; celebrating mass is a linguistic modernism imposed by force in common language, which, as well as being right liturgically, is, at the very least, ridiculous when your lawyers do not even know what it really is!)
Happy Easter!</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 05:31:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong suspends sending orders to the United States</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/17/hong-kong-suspende-envio-de-encomendas-para-estados-unidos/</link><description>Hong Kong's post office yesterday announced the suspension of ordering orders to the United States in response to the imposition, "abusive", tariffs by US authorities. "The Hongkong Post will not definitely charge any customs rates on behalf of the US and will suspend the acceptance of postal shipments containing goods destined to the US," says a post office. For orders via maritime and terrestrial, the decision has an immediate effect “due to longer shipping”, and for air mail, enters into force on April 27, the note indicates. In the case of “surface mail with goods that have not yet been issued to the US,” the Hongkong Post will organize the return and reimbursement of sizes from April 22.
The United States “are not being reasonable, they are intimidating and imposing customs rights abusively,” says the statement. "To send articles to the US, Hong Kong audiences must be prepared to pay exorbitant and unreasonable exorbitant fees due to the Unreasible and aggressive acts of the US. The other postcards containing only documents, without commodities, will not be affected," concluded the Hongkong Post.
The Chinese Communist Party's main official for Hong Kong and Macao affairs and the leaders of the governments of both regions accused the United States of imposing tariffs to sabotage China. "The US has targeted our fares, they target our own survival," said Xia Baolong, director of the Hong Kong and Macau affairs, under the tutelage of the Council of State, the Chinese executive. "Although Hong Kong is the largest source of US commercial surplus, the United States still imposed high tariffs. This is extremely arrogant and blatant," said Xia. The US continued the leader, "cannot tolerate Hong Kong's prosperity and stability and are the biggest sinister manipulator that undermines human rights, freedom, rule of law, prosperity and stability in Hong Kong."</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 05:33:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Japanese negotiator in the US hoping to get “mutual benefits”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/04/17/negociador-japones-nos-eua-com-esperanca-de-obter-beneficios-mutuos/</link><description>Japan's chief negotiator appointed to negotiate with the US the customs tariffs traveled to Washington to meet with US counterparts, hoping to obtain “mutual benefits” for both countries.
 
"I will think carefully about what will best serve our national interests and what will be more effective, and we will conduct negotiations that firmly protect these interests," said Ryosi Akazawa before leaving for the United States to negotiate customs tariffs.
The official stressed that the end result depends on confidence, adding that there are “good commercial abilities” on the American side and that it considers feasible a “win-win” situation (advantageous for both sides).
Akazawa, minister responsible for economic revitalization and new capitalism, will be in the United States until Saturday, to negotiate various measures, in meetings scheduled with the US Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent, and US commercial representative Jamieson Greer.
The purpose of the trip is to “build a relationship of trust between responsible government representatives” and “request a review of the expected measures,” said Yoshimasa Hayashi, a government spokesman at a press conference on Tuesday.
The Japanese government has been asking Donald Trump's administration to be exempt from the new rate on the automotive industry, which is particularly harmful to Japan as it affects one of its main industries, which has the largest market in the United States, as well as other customs announced by Washington.
The new tax on passenger vehicles goes from 2.5% to 27.5% for Japanese imports.
Donald Trump has indicated that he could give some car manufacturers more time that are considering moving production facilities to the United States before imposing new measures. The head of state also announced, last week, a 90 -day break in the application of what it designates as “reciprocal tariffs”, which affect the main US business partners and ascending 24% in the case of Japan. Japan has had a priority in negotiations on these tariffs.
Trump administration has also launched national security investigations on imports of chips and pharmaceutical products, which, according to Americans 'media', will be used to impose new rates on these products.
 
Japanese regulator accuses Google of violating anti -monopoly laws
 
Japanese regulatory authorities accused US technology to violate anti-monopoly laws, referring to similar actions in the United States and Europe. Google Japan stated in a statement that it considered action “unfortunate” and the company said it has invested significantly in the country to promote innovation as a technological leader.
The “order of cessation and withdrawal” of Japan's Fair Trade Commission says Google has to stop the Google search engine preinstallation on Android smartphones, which, according to the commission, actually excludes the competition.
It is not known if Google, a subsidiary of Alphabet Inc., based in Silicone Valley, USA, will take legal action to combat the order.
In the US, a judge decided last year that Google's “omnipresent” search engine illegally explored his dominance to master the competition.
Google has denied the allegations, arguing that it is immensely popular because people like what it offers.
Japanese regulators began research on Google in 2023 and say they have consulted foreign authorities who dealt with similar cases.
European regulators also criticized what they consider to be Google's monopolistic domain.
The decision marks the first time that Japan's Fair Trade Commission takes action against a large world technological company. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 05:36:13</pubDate></item></channel></rss>