<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/03/obras-com-execucao-conjunta-aumentam-20-em-2025/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Bomb threat drill carried out at Macau International Airport</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/03/realizado-simulacro-de-ameaca-de-bomba-no-aeroporto-internacional-de-macau/</link><description>The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) carried out a simulation exercise at Macau International Airport in the early hours of yesterday, with the aim of testing the effectiveness of contingency plans and the response capacity of entities participating in air security incidents.
The exercise, which was given the title “Airport Security Exercise 2025 – Bomb Threat”, was carried out between 2am and 4am and included the cooperation of several entities, such as the Unitary Police Services (SPU), the Health Services (SS), the Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs Services (DSAMA) and the Civil Aviation Authority (AACM).
The starting point of the simulation was a man with “suspicious attitudes”, who fled after being approached by CPSP agents who were patrolling the passenger terminal building. Once again caught by authorities, the suspect ended up admitting to having placed explosives in the airport area.
Security guards and the airport's police division immediately took action, blocking the place and beginning the necessary searches. Meanwhile, the police managed to discover that the individual in question had parked his vehicle in the car park south of the airport, thus allowing them to discover the location of the bomb. Given the severity of the incident, the airport immediately activated the contingency plan, which included the evacuation of the space and the alert of all government departments and relevant operators.
Once on site, explosives personnel inspected the suspected trash bags and checked whether the objects contained in them were explosives, ensuring that their destruction was carried out safely. In turn, after interrogation, the Judiciary Police (PJ) confirmed that the man in question suffered from mental problems and that his intention was to “cause panic in society”. Once the absence of any further suspicious objects was confirmed, the emergency situation was canceled and Macau International Airport resumed normal operations.
In a statement released yesterday, the AACM stated that “the entire exercise went well and the expected results were achieved”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 23:40:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Death toll from floods in Indonesia now exceeds 800</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/03/numero-de-mortos-nas-cheias-na-indonesia-ja-ultrapassa-os-800/</link><description>The death toll caused by the floods that hit the large island of Sumatra, in Indonesia, exceeded 800, the Indonesian National Disaster Management Agency (BNPB) announced yesterday. Authorities previously indicated that 631 people had died.
According to BNPB, the latest toll is 804 dead, more than 650 people missing and hundreds of thousands of residents evacuated from their homes on the island of Sumatra, in western Indonesia.
Despite more than 800 deaths, thousands of injuries and massive destruction in Sumatra, the Indonesian government is resisting growing pressure to declare a state of emergency following the floods.
The country only took this measure three times, according to available records: during the 1992 earthquake and tsunami, the 2004 tsunami that killed tens of thousands of people and during the covid-19 pandemic.
Calls are growing for the Government to declare a state of emergency, with supporters arguing that such a measure would free up resources and improve the coordination of humanitarian aid.
The government of Indonesian President Prabowo Subianto has so far insisted that the country has the necessary resources to deal with the situation. This situation contrasts with that in Sri Lanka where a state of emergency was declared and help was requested from the international community to deal with the effects of the floods.
Amnesty International (AI) Indonesia believes the decision to declare a state of emergency is urgently needed “so that national and international forces can be mobilized to help the victims”.
Authorities warned that the destruction caused by the rains was due to the large amount of water that fell over a prolonged period, causing rivers to overflow.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 23:29:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong residents remember deaths a week after fire</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/03/residentes-de-hong-kong-recordam-mortos-uma-semana-apos-incendio/</link><description>Thousands of people yesterday left flowers at an improvised memorial next to the Hong Kong public housing complex where, a week ago, a fire broke out that left at least 159 dead.

Most people walking to the park located next to the Wang Fuk Court complex in Tai Po, New Territories, north of Hong Kong, carried bouquets of white and yellow flowers, colors associated with mourning in Chinese culture.
Ivy, 42, told Lusa that she had come from Taikoo, in the south of Hong Kong, 30 kilometers from Tai Po, to “pay condolences to those who died in this tragedy”. But the resident downplayed the distance: "I didn't do anything. It's very easy for me to get here. And spending some time here doesn't mean I did much for them [the victims]. Because they lost everything."
Others came from further away. Among the hundreds of branches left at the memorial were some with notes written by residents of the neighboring Macau region or across the border in the metropolis of Shenzhen.
For some, the fire left very close marks, as is the case of 21-year-old Aiden, who has an old high school classmate whose family lived in Wang Fuk Court. "Fortunately, he and his family are safe. During the incident, they were not at home. But that night he called me to ask for help. I could feel his pain", the young man told Lusa.
Aiden added that, like many other pets, his friend's two cats weren't so lucky: “The firefighters weren't able to save them.”
The streets around Wang Fuk Court are covered in posters put up by owners who have not yet given up hope of reuniting their pets, from dogs and cats to turtles and birds.
Next to the makeshift memorial to the people who died, there is also another, smaller memorial to the pets who were victims of the fire, where people are invited to make origami birds.
The atmosphere is heavy and some of those who stopped by to leave flowers refused to speak to Lusa, with a young woman pointing out the significant police presence: “It's not a good idea”. But Ivy holds no grudge against the Hong Kong Government. “I think they responded quite quickly because they arranged housing for the residents [of Wang Fuk Court]”, he highlighted.
On Tuesday, Chief Executive John Lee said that 2,500 of the complex's approximately 4,000 residents had been moved from temporary shelters to youth hostels, hotels or public housing.
On the other hand, said Ivy, “firefighters, police and government departments helped to find those missing in the buildings”.
On Tuesday, Hong Kong firefighters said 30 people were yet to be found or identified.
In the midst of the tragedy, John Malig, a Portuguese born in Hong Kong, told Lusa that “something I had never seen before” happened. “Everyone came together and was really worried,” he said. “Even the younger generation went to buy bottled water to help the residents [of Wang Fuk Court]. It touched me a little, seeing the people of Hong Kong really coming together,” said Malig. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 23:32:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau hotels expect occupancy to exceed 90% at Christmas</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/03/hoteis-de-macau-esperam-ocupacoes-a-superar-90-no-natal/</link><description>Macau hotels could register an occupancy rate of over 90% during the Christmas period this year. Jocelyn Wong, president of the Macau Hotel Association, indicates that more than 50% of rooms have already been booked, with the rate continuing to rise as Christmas approaches.

Jocelyn Wong, president of the Macau Hotel Association, is optimistic about the occupancy of local hotel establishments for Christmas, estimating that the hotel occupancy rate could exceed 90%.
Although the Christmas season has no holidays in mainland China, the main source of tourists for Macau, the territory may see more international visitors at that time. According to Jocelyn Wong, international tourists from Southeast Asia and other regions are showing “strong demand” for the Christmas holiday period, so the tourism sector “has been actively promoting” travel packages through online and in-person channels to attract even more visitors.
The executive director of Hotel Royal, speaking to Jornal do Cidadão, said that the current booking rate for Christmas in hotels has already exceeded 50% and will continue to increase as the date approaches.
It should be remembered that, last year, the Directorate of Tourism Services had also predicted a “positive performance” of tourist activities for the Christmas and New Year holidays, but tourist data for the season was not released after all. However, according to the Statistics and Census Services, in December 2024 the average occupancy rate of guest rooms in hotel establishments was 89.9%, an increase of 4.2 percentage points in annual terms.
Hotel establishments in Macau, on the other hand, had 89.3% of rooms occupied last month, the highest figure for October since before the pandemic, with the rate registering an increase of 0.9 percentage points compared to the same month in 2024.
Jocelyn Wong, in this sense, praised the Government's work in promoting tourism throughout this year through the organization of various activities, such as concerts and large-scale sporting events.
The official said she hopes that the events held by the Government during the Christmas period will continue to attract more and more visitors, suggesting that future activities be extended to historic areas, including Rua dos Ervanários, Praça do Tap Seac, Bairro de São Lázaro and the vicinity of Avenida do Conselheiro Ferreira de Almeida.
“Through initiatives such as markets, art fairs and concerts, we can help divert the flow of Cotai, stimulating the community economy”, understood Wong, highlighting that Cotai continues to be a place that brings together many tourists, with high hotel occupancy rates, while hotels in Macau are registering lower demand and a disparity in occupancy numbers, a phenomenon that also occurs for Christmas this year.
The president of the Macau Hotel Association said that prices generally increase during the festive season, but there is a significant difference between hotels in Cotai and the rest of the city.
He added that the sector is studying a collaborative initiative led by the Association, bringing together hotels in Macau's old neighborhoods to promote the development of community tourism.
Regarding the outlook for next year, Jocelyn Wong said that, in addition to the mainland China market, the industry should focus its efforts on consolidating sources of visitors from Southeast Asia, while developing other international markets. “The sector will actively collaborate [in tourism promotion], creating maps of World Heritage routes and integrating Portuguese cultural and historical experiences, to attract visitors to explore the old city”, he indicated.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 23:59:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Portugal says queues at Lisbon airport “are an embarrassment” that five ministers monitor</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/03/portugal-diz-que-filas-no-aeroporto-de-lisboa-sao-um-embaraco-que-cinco-ministros-monitorizam/</link><description>The Secretary of State for Infrastructure assured that the Government is monitoring the queues at Lisbon airport “very closely”, admitting that they are an embarrassment for the Government, which is expected to be resolved by the summer.

"The border situation is an embarrassment for the Government. It has no other name. We have to have an attitude of humility regarding what we do and, at this moment, it is an embarrassment and the only thing that could be done was to apologize", said Hugo Espírito Santo, in Macau, at the 50th congress of the Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies (APAVT).
The official said that the causes exist, have been identified and that solutions are being evaluated, praising the help that ANA – Aeroportos has given in the situation. "We currently have very close monitoring of this issue by the Government. We have five ministers directly involved, we are looking at the data day by day to see how long it takes to cross the border in Lisbon (…)", added the government official.
Hugo Espírito Santo recalled that “the root” of the problem “is clear” and relates to “the lack of PSP agents”, which adds “difficulty and instability from a technological point of view, especially in ‘egates'” and, thirdly, “a greater slowness of the system”.
Having identified the causes, says the government official, now it is time to try to resolve them. "One of the things we have already decided, together with Ana – who has done remarkable work with us to help us resolve this – is to redesign the entire departure and arrival area. We will increase the number of boxes and 'egates' by 30% at departures, we will increase the number of boxes by 30% at arrivals, and we will increase the number of 'egates' by 70%", he said.
The challenge, the government official assumes, is to have the situation resolved by June, “before summer”, the peak tourism season.
The tourism sector, namely the Confederation of Tourism of Portugal (CTP) and APAVT, have asked for urgent solutions to this constraint, which causes reputational damage to the destination of Portugal. “It is a very serious problem, which is not in our hands”, had stated earlier, also yesterday, the president of the Board of Directors of ANA – Aeroportos de Portugal, José Luís Arnaut.
The Secretary of State for Infrastructure considers that “nothing prevents” ANA – Aeroportos de Portugal from accelerating the deadline for the new Lisbon airport, in Alcochete, pointing to 2034-2035 as a viable deadline.
Hugo Espírito Santo addressed the topic, in Macau, after the president of the Board of Directors (‘chairman’) of ANA – Aeroportos de Portugal, José Luís Arnaut, admitted wanting to bring forward the deadline, but, even so, remembered that 2037 is what is defined in the initial proposal, “as a safety valve”. "The 2037 (deadline) is the exclusive responsibility of José Luís Arnaut [president of ANA]. Our 'timing' is 2034-2035. We have this discussion. José Luís Arnaut did the exercise here of counting all the deadlines, but if Ana came forward to the deadlines, we would be deeply recognized and it would be a sign that Ana is deeply committed to this partnership with the Portuguese State", stated Hugo Espírito Santo.
Governor and chairman of the national airport management company spoke at the 50th National Congress of the Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies. "Therefore, there is nothing stopping them from accelerating the deadline and we on our side will do everything we can. But, therefore, 2035", highlighted the government official, responding to a question from the president of APAVT, Pedro Costa Ferreira, who wanted to know if it was possible to design all the accessibility and infrastructure works "at the same time until 2037, so that the airport can happen".
Previously, the head of ANA had highlighted that the process is long, remembering that there is a set of legal requirements, procedures, European and national legislation until entering the construction phase. “The position of my shareholder and mine as president is ‘it’s been decided [Alcochete], let’s anticipate, let’s accelerate, and let’s have Alcochete up and running as quickly as possible.’ Because that’s in the country’s interest,” stated José Luís Arnaut.
Urged by the president of APAVT several times to define a probable date, the ANA chairman said he did not want to commit.
However, he added again that “there is a great desire”, especially because ANA’s interest “is the same as that of the Government and the tourism sector”, to “try to shorten as much as possible the steps that can be shortened (…) in order to start the work as quickly as possible”.
José Luís Arnaut recalled that at stake is a future airport that will be five times the size of Humberto Delgado airport. "Our desire is for it to be before [2036]. But let's see the final project, let's see what the construction companies are going to do (…) I would like it to be in 2035, but let's see… in 2035, 2036. (…) We are talking about the idyllic scenario", he reinforced. “The deadline in our proposal is 2037 – for a simple reason, because it was necessary to have some safety valves here –, but we are working with the Government to reduce the deadlines”, namely work that can progress without having to wait for others, he explained. “This coordination is being done in the national interest, which is common”, guaranteed José Luís Arnaut. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 23:24:53</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korean leader understands that he must “apologize” to Pyongyang for his predecessor’s actions</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/03/lider-sul-coreano-entende-que-deve-pedir-desculpas-a-pyongyang-por-actos-do-antecessor/</link><description>South Korean President Lee Jae-myung said yesterday that he owed North Korea an apology for the order given by his predecessor to send drones and propaganda leaflets across the border.

“I think I should apologize, but I hesitate to say it out loud,” said the head of state at a press conference marking the first anniversary of the short-lived declaration of martial law by former president Yoon Suk-yeol. “If I do, I'm afraid it could be used as an argument in ideological battles or to accuse me of being a supporter of the North,” he added.
Lee's statements are based on accusations that Yoon ordered the South Korean Army to fly drones over Pyongyang and launch hostile leaflets at North Korea, with the aim of provoking a military response.
A reaction from Pyongyang could have legitimized Yoon Suk-yeol's proclamation of martial law, providing him with the pretext for a national emergency.
The deposed former president was accused by the country's courts last month of, together with other people, “conspiring to create the conditions that would allow the declaration of emergency martial law, thus increasing the risk of an inter-Korean armed confrontation”, according to the Public Ministry.
North Korea declared last year that it had evidence that its neighbor sent drones to drop propaganda leaflets over its capital, an act that Seoul's army has not confirmed.

Seoul considers it “extremely difficult” to manufacture nuclear submarines in the US

The South Korean President declared yesterday that it will be “extremely difficult” to manufacture nuclear-powered submarines in the United States. “From our point of view, producing them there is extremely difficult, to be realistic,” said the head of state, at a press conference.
Seoul and Washington finalized an agreement in November on the construction of this type of submarine for the South Korean navy, but the construction site has not been determined. A joint note detailed that the two countries committed to “continuing collaboration in the field of shipbuilding through a specific working group”.
In October, after having given “yes” to an agreement in principle for the manufacture of a nuclear-powered submarine for the South Korean ally, North American President Donald Trump wrote on the social network X and on Truth Social, which he owns, that it would be built in Philadelphia, in the United States.
Yesterday, the South Korean President indicated that the issue “still requires discussion”. Lee Jae-myung stressed that Seoul's position has always been to produce the submarines domestically. “What we asked for was not ‘build them for us’ or ‘give us the technology,'” he said. “Our position was simply that we would build them with our own technology, so we just need to authorize the fuel supply,” he added.
Lee Jae Myung also stated that Seoul should not take sides between Japan and China, at a time when relations between the two countries are tense due to the Taiwan issue. “Japan and China are in conflict, and taking sides only worsens tensions,” Lee said at a press conference, which marked the first anniversary of the short-lived declaration of martial law in South Korea. “The ideal approach is to coexist, respect each other and cooperate as much as possible,” said the head of state.
The South Korean President also described Northeast Asia as “a very dangerous region in terms of military security”.
Relations between Beijing and Tokyo have been tense since the new Japanese Prime Minister, Sanae Takaichi, suggested last month in the Japanese Parliament that her country could intervene militarily in the event of an attack on Taiwan. Beijing strongly condemned Takaichi's statements, advised its citizens to avoid traveling to Japan and summoned the country's Japanese ambassador. Since then, diplomatic incidents have followed one another, the latest of which was on Tuesday, with Tokyo accusing the violation of its territorial waters by two Chinese ships off the Senkaku Islands, in the East China Sea.
The uninhabited islands, called Senkaku by Tokyo — which administers them — and Diaoyu by Beijing, are a constant point of tension, with both countries claiming sovereignty over this territory of economic and strategic interest. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 23:29:50</pubDate></item><item><title>CEM customers will be entitled to compensation for power outages</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/03/clientes-da-cem-vao-ter-direito-a-compensacao-por-falhas-de-energia/</link><description>The new Macau Electricity Company (CEM) contract reinforces consumer protection, with mandatory compensation on the bill whenever supply failures exceed the defined parameters: two annual interruptions or an accumulated duration of four hours. The contract, published in the Official Bulletin, also defines new measures for the company's green transition.

The new Macau Electricity Company (CEM) concession contract, which will be effective from January 1, 2026, introduces a compensation scheme for customers in the event of prolonged or repeated power outages. The measure appears in the extract from the contract published yesterday in the Official Gazette, which establishes the renewal of the concession for another 15 years.
According to the document, the concessionaire is obliged to compensate all affected consumers in the event of an interruption in the electricity supply for more than 15 minutes. If the energy supply is interrupted between three and five times a year, or exceeds a total accumulated duration of four hours, customers are entitled to a 3% deduction on the total value of the bill. The discount increases to 6% whenever there are more than six interruptions or an accumulated time of more than six hours. In more serious cases, where the interruption lasts for more than eight hours, the discount is 9%.
It is also added that, in the case of more than one interruption within a twenty-four hour interval, only the longest one will be considered. The maximum value of compensation for each customer corresponds to 20% of the monthly average of invoices from the previous year and cannot be combined with other forms of compensation. Furthermore, any interruption in the supply of electricity must be communicated to consumers at least thirty-six hours in advance, in order to allow them to “take appropriate measures to avoid or reduce losses resulting therefrom”.
The contract also stipulates a new limit for the company's profits. From 2026 onwards, CEM will be entitled to an annual remuneration of 8.2% on the value of its fixed assets. If the company generates profits greater than this value, the surplus is deposited in a “Provision for Tariff Stabilization” account; on the other hand, if profits are lower, the company can use the balance in this special account to cover the difference and reach the maximum profit allowed. Whenever the account balance exceeds 15% of annual sales revenue, one third of the excess amount will be returned to consumers in the form of a discount on the electricity bill.
In environmental matters, the contract reinforces CEM's role as an active agent in Macau's decarbonization policy. Starting next year, the company will have a contractual obligation to acquire, install and maintain renewable energy production facilities, such as solar panels. The electrical energy produced by these installations and respective rights reverts to the Government, which bears all costs, and can be used to offset the consumption of public lighting or other purposes defined by the authorities.
It is recalled that, last year, the Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) reported that it was monitoring the CEM contract renewal process, in order to ensure that the various environmental objectives for the region – such as the double carbon target or the introduction of environmentally friendly energies – were met.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 23:58:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Alibaba Subsidiary Platforms Help Promote Business on ZAPE and NAPE</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/03/plataformas-subsidiarias-da-alibaba-ajudam-a-promover-negocios-no-zape-e-nape/</link><description>The ZAPE and NAPE areas, which are facing the threat of becoming deserted due to the closure of several satellite casinos in the area, could receive a boost from the economy with the start of a promotional campaign yesterday.
Launched jointly by the ZAPE Industrial and Commercial Association of Macau and two subsidiary platforms of the Alibaba group, with support from the Economic and Technological Development Services, the initiative has, to date, had the participation of 60 traders, predominantly from the restaurant sector. It is expected to generate an additional revenue of MOP10 million for participating companies during the one-year program period.
The campaign is promoted in cooperation with Amap and Damai. Amap, a digital map and navigation service developed by Alibaba's AutoNavi, is now one of the main map services in mainland China, with Baidu Maps as its main competitor. Damai is a ticket sales platform for shows and sporting events, also belonging to the Alibaba Group, whose business is based on e-commerce.
According to Chinese-language Radio Macau, the campaign includes activities for cross-border consumption, which will allow tourists and customers to travel to the ZAPE and NAPE zones by offering promotions and discounts on consumption and services that facilitate route definition.
Wu Tat Chong, president of the ZAPE Industrial and Commercial Association, said that in the context of an era deeply integrated with the digital economy, merchants face challenges in using technology platforms to attract customers. The person responsible believes that local store owners must learn, through digital resources, to create “more precise connections” with potential customers and convert online traffic into in-person consumption.
“The campaign aims to take advantage of Amap’s navigation and localization technologies, as well as its strengths in attracting flow, to guide tourists from inland China away from traditional attractions to the NAPE district, where they can experience in-depth local commercial and cultural features,” he highlighted.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 23:36:09</pubDate></item><item><title>CURB project wants to involve the entire community in the construction of public space</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/03/projecto-do-curb-quer-envolver-toda-a-comunidade-na-construcao-do-espaco-publico/</link><description>The IN SITU Placemaking Biennale 2025 will recontextualize the streets of Macau next week, from the 11th to the 14th of December. Architect Nuno Soares, president of CURB, explains to PONTO FINAL the importance of the initiative for enhancing public space and calls for the participation of the entire Macau community in an event that, he guarantees, is not just aimed at artists.

A celebration of public space, built together by the entire Macau community. This is how Nuno Soares, president of CURB – Center for Architecture and Urbanism, describes the initiative that aims to give a new vision of Macau's streets and the role that everyone – from artists to passers-by – has in their development.
The project is as ambitious as it is ephemeral. The six winning installations will remain at the six designated sites for just four days, from December 11th to 14th, although the organization expects the impact on the community to be lasting and transformative.
“The main idea is to be able to transform the inner streets of the historic center into a performative space, which in these four days will be very different from what it is in everyday life”, explains the architect, in conversation with PONTO FINAL. Each of the installations promises to interact with visitors and the surrounding space “in a very peculiar way”, which will be translated to the public through guided tours and sharing sessions led by the artists themselves. Alternatively, it is also possible to independently visit and contemplate the installations that will make up this artistic network, without the need for a prior invitation.
This is the basic objective of the initiative: to transform Macau into an open-air artistic exhibition, which everyone can contemplate and in which everyone can participate. “Each citizen builds public space, and this public space also participates in the construction of each one of us”, points out Nuno Soares. "We want people to look at public space in a more active way and to interact with the installations in creative and unexpected ways. They are very welcome to use these installations in a way that makes sense to them."
The points of attraction are the intersection between Travessa do Aterro Novo and Rua dos Mercadores, Rua de São Lourenço, Largo do Lilau, Praça de Ponte e Horta, Largo do Aquino and Pátio da Claridade. The first three will feature installations by international artists, while the last three will house the works of local artists. And why six installations, specifically? "It's a very manageable number and allows you to have experiences that are very different from each other, but also relatively close. We want visitors to be able to complete the itinerary and see all six", explains the director of CURB, emphasizing the fact that this is a pioneering event in the city. "As this is the first edition, the city is not yet used to holding this type of event. We are all still learning."
In addition to the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM), which authorized the temporary occupation of the aforementioned spaces, the organization also had the responsibility of communicating directly with residents and traders – an experience that is described as “a great learning experience” for those involved. “We realized that residents also view these installations with some sympathy, because we are paying attention to the places where they live and temporarily transforming them and inviting them to participate. We had to learn how we could make sure it was good for the artists, the city, the residents and the merchants.” A commitment that, although delicate, has “gone very well”.
CURB continues to look for volunteers until Friday, the 5th, to help with tasks such as welcoming and managing participants, guiding visits and supporting activities and workshops. Interest in interacting with others is an essential requirement, but it is not the only one – it is also necessary to have a desire to learn so that, perhaps, today's volunteers will develop similar initiatives on their own in the future. "The issue of volunteers is also a question of training. We want them to learn how these interventions are carried out, so that they themselves, on their own initiative and in their contexts, are able to continue celebrating public space", concludes Nuno Soares.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 23:57:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong elections plunged into uncertainty after fire</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/03/eleicoes-em-hong-kong-mergulhadas-em-incerteza-apos-incendio/</link><description>Campaigning for Hong Kong's parliament resumed yesterday, a week after a fire that killed at least 159 people, but with greater uncertainty about the vote on Sunday. Debates between parliamentary candidates resumed after six days of interruption, although the remaining public activities of the electoral campaign remain suspended. Political commentator Sonny Lo told Lusa that the fire in the New Territories increased uncertainty surrounding Sunday's vote, which will be “a clearer indicator of the Government's credibility”. Residents unhappy with the executive's response to the tragedy have three possible choices, the analyst highlighted: “not voting, voting for centrist or independent candidates, or presenting an invalid vote”.
The leader of the Government of the special administrative region announced on Tuesday that the elections “will be held as scheduled” on Sunday. Maintaining the date for the elections for the Legislative Council (LegCo), which the executive considered postponing, “is respecting the constitutional order and the rule of law”, insisted John Lee. An announcement that did not reach everyone, including John Malig, a Portuguese born in Hong Kong: “Really? I thought they were going to postpone them”. Nothing that changes the singer's life: "I haven't voted since I was born here and I don't intend to vote [on Sunday]. Besides, my family never voted either, so it doesn't affect me much." Malig explained to Lusa that he never voted because, as a Eurasian, of Portuguese descent from the neighboring Macau region and of Filipinos, he always felt like an outsider in Hong Kong. But even for ethnic Chinese residents, the impact of the worst fire to hit the city since 1948 looms large over Sunday's legislative elections.
After a record low turnout of 30.2% in the 2021 vote – the first after an electoral reform that alienated Democrats – authorities had launched a campaign to attract voters. Sonny Lo admitted that it is impossible to predict voters' intentions, since the 2021 review made public incitement to boycott elections, blank or invalid votes, a crime punishable by a prison sentence of up to three years. However, the political commentator highlighted that, in addition to discontent, the fire could also lead to less mobilization of parties aligned with the Government and Beijing. Of the 90 seats in the LegCo, only 20 are elected (among 51 candidates) by direct universal suffrage in geographic constituencies, with 30 elected (among 60 candidates) by different sectors of activity and the remaining 40 (among 50 candidates) designated by an electoral college, whose 1,500 members are, in their majority, pro-Beijing.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 23:22:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Malaysia resumes search for Malaysia Airlines plane missing 11 years ago</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/03/malasia-retoma-buscas-por-aviao-da-malaysia-airlines-desparecido-ha-11-anos/</link><description>Malaysia yesterday announced the resumption of the search for Malaysia Airlines flight MH370, which disappeared with 239 people on board in March 2014, shortly after taking off from Kuala Lumpur en route to Beijing.
“[Company] Ocean Infinity and the Government of Malaysia confirm that they will begin [on December 30] search operations for a total of 55 days, intermittently”, announced the Malaysian Ministry of Transport, through a statement dated yesterday.
Ocean Infinity is a robotics and deep-sea exploration company based in the United States and the United Kingdom, which has been collaborating for years in the search for the plane, which disappeared on March 8, 2014, around 40 minutes after taking off from Kuala Lumpur en route to the Chinese capital.
The aircraft disappeared from radars after leaving Malaysian airspace and entering Vietnam, when, in principle, it deviated from the route to the south of the Indian Ocean, without the causes yet being known.
Aboard the Boeing 777 were 153 Chinese, 50 Malaysians (12 were part of the crew), seven Indonesians, six Australians, five Indians, four French, three North Americans, two New Zealanders, two Ukrainians, two Canadians, two Iranians, one Russian, one Dutchman and one Taiwanese.
Initially, Malaysia, China and Australia carried out a joint search of around 120,000 square kilometers in the Indian Ocean, but ended operations in January 2017, without finding the plane's wreckage.
Ocean Infinity also tried to locate the device in an area of ​​around 100,000 square kilometers between January and June 2018, without success.
Last April, the Malaysian Government stated that the search operation for the aircraft had been interrupted because it was “not the ideal time” for that purpose, but said that it would be resumed at the end of this year.
Yesterday's statement states that the search will be carried out in a “specific area with the highest probability of locating the aircraft”, and follows an agreement between Ocean Infinity and the Malaysian Government, without giving further details.
Last February, the company stated that the search is based on “reliable” information and will focus on an area that “was ignored” during previous missions.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 23:25:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Books reimagined in “UNFOLDING+” challenge the digital age with exhibition and workshops</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/03/livros-reimaginados-no-unfolding-desafiam-a-era-digital-com-exposicao-e-oficinas/</link><description>In a digital world, the act of “leafing through a book” approaches anachronism. On this premise, “UNFOLDING+” transforms Pin-to Livros &amp; Música into a laboratory for reinventing the book object. With an exhibition of the best Dutch designs, a sound installation and creative workshops, the event invites the public to rediscover the book not only as a vehicle of knowledge, but as a sensory and creative raw material. The project landed for the first time in Macau and runs until December 14th, from Tuesday to Sunday, on Rua Coelho do Amaral.

In a purposefully analogical gesture, the “UNFOLDING+” project opened its pages to the public at the Pin-to Livros &amp; Música bookstore, defying the era of “infinite scrolling” with a profound celebration of the book object. Organized by MyLand Culture and financed by the Fund for Cultural Development, the program, which runs until December 14, aims to “unfold, reveal and leaf through” the multiple dimensions – material, aesthetic and conceptual – of the printed book. It is curated by Pal Lok and Kathine Cheong Weng Lam, who conceived the event as a response to profound changes in reading habits and the evolution of the media.
The centerpiece of the inaugural edition in Macau is an exhibition of rare quality: the first local exhibition of works awarded in the 2022 and 2024 editions of “The Best Dutch Book Designs”. More than 50 books, selected by international juries, are on display, representing the most innovative work in editorial design in Europe. This award, organized by Stichting De Best Verzorgde Boeken, is the oldest of its kind in Europe, having been created in 1926 to raise the design standards of the Dutch edition. The exhibition allows visitors to explore each book in person. Turn the pages, discover the content and experience the beauty of the book object in a selection of award-winning titles. This collection offers local and international designers, publishers, and readers an unprecedented opportunity to closely examine the experimentations with materials, printing techniques, typography, and layout that define the cutting edge of book culture.
At the same time, the project unfolds into three interdisciplinary axes that explore the book as a sensorial medium. Local sound artist Kawai Ng presents “Sound Installation 03”, a work where sound, traveling invisible through the air, is materialized through paper, in a space remodeled by eight speakers that create a fluid field of time. With frequencies that intertwine, collide and overlap. The paper becomes the vessel where the sound finally takes shape. Kawai Ng, an Ambient and Experimental musician, is known for using Noise, Drone and patterns to build soundscapes, having presented his work at events such as TPAM, in Yokohama.
The “Right-to-Left, Left-to-Right” workshop, scheduled for December 6, from 3:00 pm to 5:30 pm, will be co-led by Hong Kong artist Katol and Macau designer Kun Lam. Katol, founder of Social Nerd and Coffee &amp; Laundry, is a prominent name in the Hong Kong graphics scene, with a unique style influenced by the city's cosmopolitan culture and a specialization in sign painting, which resembles graffiti, but specialized in the signage part seen on the facades of stores or small businesses. Kun Lam, co-founder of Indego Design, is an internationally award-winning designer, with distinctions such as the Young Guns 19 (USA), the D&amp;AD Yellow Pencil (UK) and the ADC Gold Cube (USA). The workshop, costing 150 patacas, starts from the culture of reading and the art of printing to a dialogue about the design cultures between the two cities, culminating in the creation of unique fanzines with materials printed using rhizography and collage techniques.
The “Reading Corner: The Past and Future Lives of the Paper Book”, or “Canto de Leitura: As Vidas Passadas e Futuras do Livro de Papel” in Portuguese, curated by Anson Ng, owner of Pin-to Livros &amp; Música, offers a specialized selection of books that explore book culture from multiple perspectives, from the historical, social, craft and aesthetic side of the book object. This reading “corner” invites visitors to rediscover the texture, weight and temporality of printed books, and to imagine possible futures for the paper book, considering how the materiality of printing shapes the production of knowledge and the preservation of cultural memory.
The project, which has the support of The Best Dutch Book Designs Foundation in Amsterdam and the Consulate General of the Netherlands in Shanghai, positions the book as an “open structure” that can be rewritten through sound, gesture, print and tactile experience. In a context where information comes to us in a fragmented and instantaneous way, the “UNFOLDING+” project questions how a “book” can continue to function as a material medium with sensorial and conceptual weight for contemporary creators.
The official opening took place on November 28th, and the exhibition remains open to the public, with free entry, until December 14th. Registration for the workshop, which takes place on December 6th, from 3:00 pm to 5:30 pm, is open via the QR code published on MyLand Culture's social media. The exhibition hours are from Tuesday to Sunday (but closed on Monday), from 1pm to 7pm.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Surreal artistic saga about the silk road and futurism ends with performance at Casa Garden</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/03/saga-artistica-surreal-sobre-a-rota-da-seda-e-futurismo-encerra-com-performance-na-casa-garden/</link><description>What happens when the ancient Silk Road meets the technological language of the 21st century? The exhibition-performance “Golden City of Seres” ends an almost two-month saga that merged the boundaries between dance, visual art and music, scheduled for this Saturday at the Fundação Oriente headquarters. The project, a collaboration between Macau and Antwerp, shows the public a reflection on desire, technology and cultural identity through an aesthetic that the creators call “Surrealist Chinoiserie”.

The artistic project “Golden City of Seres – Surrealistic Chinoiserie” reaches its culminating moment on December 6th, with a closing performance that promises to merge artistic languages ​​into a unique immersive experience. After an exhibition tour lasting almost two months at Fundação Oriente – Casa Garden, the initiative organized by the Art For All Association (AFA) ends with a presentation that summarizes the cultural relationship between Macau and the Belgian city of Antwerp, exploring the new meanings of the Silk Road in the contemporary context.
The project title deliberately evokes the Latin term “Sērēs”, used by Greco-Roman geographers to designate the people associated with silk production. A historical reference that serves as a starting point for a reflection on cultural transmission, material value and identity. The “Golden City” refers, in turn, to the transformation of Macau from a historic port to the current model of Cotai, creating fertile ground for a surreal dynamic about materiality and desire.
At the center of the exhibition was the work of visual artist Leong Chi Mou, who explores the concept of “new silk” through industrial materials such as brass, copper and metal mesh. In his series “Serica – Diamond Hill” and “Serica – Golden Landscape”, Leong reinterprets the Chinese tradition of landscape painting (shan shui), questioning structures of value and cultural heritage. His work “Serica – Auspicious Drone” confronts ancestral auspicious symbols, such as those in the “Scroll of Auspicious Cranes” by Emperor Huizong of the Song Dynasty, with contemporary technological omnipresence, represented by surveillance drones.
This visual investigation takes on a performative and corporeal dimension in the closing performance, co-directed and performed by dancers Jay Zheng, from Beijing, and Tina Kan, from Macau. The choreography merges influences from classical Chinese dance, namely the ethereal lightness of Dunhuang dance, with the language of contemporary ballet, creating a physical vocabulary that mirrors the concept of “Surrealist Chinoiserie”.
The visual dimension of the performance is amplified by the work of body painting artist and stylist Mandy Cheuk, who transforms the performers' bodies into human canvases. Inspired by the concept of “Diamond Hill” present in Leong Chi Mou’s paintings, Cheuk designed a futuristic image for dancer Tina Kan, a piece that evokes the image of a “cyborg”, a hybrid being between human and machine, and that questions the lines between the natural body and technological modifications.
The sound dimension is ensured by musical producer and arranger Faye Choi, known for her work with the electronic music band EVADE, with instrumental contributions from Iris Lo on the flute. The original composition combines an ethereal oriental aesthetic with the contemporary rhythm of electronic music, creating an auditory landscape that engages the viewer in the proposed cross-cultural dialogue.
 "'Golden City of Seres' is not just an exhibition or a performance, it is an experience. It is a journey through a reimagined cultural landscape, where the ornate history of Chinoiserie is filtered through a surrealist sensibility, and where the distinct but interconnected identities of Macau and Antwerp find new forms of expression", explains curator Alice Kok, who academically followed the project.
The initiative, which officially opened on October 24th, also featured opening creative workshops led by Belgian artistic director Dirk Decloedt, who brought to the table influences from Belgian surrealism, in particular from René Magritte. “Golden City of Beings” proposes itself as a profound reflection on the contemporary human condition, in a world where desire, technology and cultural codes intertwine in a complex way. Something pertinent not only for Macau, but for the current situation of contemporary art surviving in the progressing technological scenario.
The closing performance, with free entry, will take place on December 6th, at 6:30 pm, at Casa Garden. “Golden City of Seres – Surrealistic Chinoiserie” is organized by Art For All Society with support from the Cultural Development Fund.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Hong Kong again postpones sentence in case of shipwreck in 2012 that killed 39 people</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/03/hong-kong-volta-a-adiar-sentenca-em-caso-de-naufragio-em-2012-que-matou-39-pessoas/</link><description>A Hong Kong court has postponed the reading of the sentence in the case of the collision of the Lamma IV ferry, in 2012, with 39 deaths, when the investigation begins into the fire that broke out exactly a week ago in the territory.
The court postponed the reading of the verdict for the third time, after a long process that involved eighty-four witnesses. A court spokesman on Tuesday confirmed the suspension but declined to give a justification, while court sources cited by local newspapers said the decision was unlikely to be made before January 20.
On the night of October 1, 2012, China's National Day, the Hong Kong and Kowloon Ferry Company passenger boat Sea Smooth collided with the Lamma IV, which was carrying 124 Hong Kong Electric employees and their families on their way to the fireworks display in Victoria Harbor. The Lamma IV sank in just 100 seconds, in what was the most serious accident in the city since 1971.
An official commission in 2013 blamed the two captains and found a chain of construction-related failures and overhauls, although it did not clarify who removed a mandatory bulkhead or who approved a ten-millimeter steel plate on the Sea Smooth's bow that acted as a blade.
After winning an appeal in 2023, the victims' families managed to open a second case in court, focusing on structural safety and the responsibility of the maritime authority.
The complainants state that, thirteen years later, they still do not have a complete picture of what happened and denounce the “institutional negligence” that persists, despite the announced reforms.
Este novo adiamento da leitura da sentença no caso do Lamma IV ocorre uma semana após o incêndio que arrasou sete blocos do complexo residencial Wang Fuk Court, em Tai Po, norte de Hong Kong, deixando um balanço provisório de 156 mortos e cinco dezenas de desaparecidos.
Na quarta-feira, o chefe do Governo de Hong Kong, John Lee, anunciou o estabelecimento de uma comissão de inquérito independente, presidida por um juiz, para apurar as causas do incêndio.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 23:30:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Jointly executed works increase by 20% in 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/03/obras-com-execucao-conjunta-aumentam-20-em-2025/</link><description>By the end of November, around 360 road works had begun, a reduction of more than 30% compared to the same period last year. Of these, around 120 – approximately a third of the total – were executed jointly, reflecting an increase of around 20% compared to the same period last year.
The data were released following a meeting of the Working Group for the Optimization of the Coordination of Road Works, which met yesterday to take stock of the activities carried out in 2025. According to a statement issued by the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT), this year's figures demonstrate “the growing effectiveness of the coordination work carried out by the group” founded in March.
The pipeline reserve pilot project carried out on Rua dos Mercadores was also “successfully completed”, he says. The monitoring of the Working Group made it possible for the work to be completed within the deadline and with the required quality, establishing “solid foundations” for the implementation of the duct reserve in other works – as is the case with the drainage currently underway on Rua do Volong.
In relation to this project, the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, required the members of the Working Group to analyze the experiences acquired in the Rua dos Mercadores pipeline reservation project and the integration of provisions relating to coordination zones, as well as the approval process for works in the vicinity of gas pipelines. The group was also instructed to adopt measures to reduce the number of well covers on public roads, in order to guarantee the safety of drivers and motorcycles and mopeds.
At the meeting, road works plans for next year were also presented, integrated into 47 “coordination zones” defined according to areas and execution periods. This makes it possible to carry out several works in the same area together, avoiding repeated excavations on the roads.</description><pubDate>2025-12-03 23:41:27</pubDate></item></channel></rss>