<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/15/servicos-de-saude-alertam-para-risco-de-hipertermia/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Difficulties do not bring dreams of 'forced' Mozambican girls to be mothers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/15/dificuldades-nao-travam-sonhos-de-raparigas-mocambicanas-obrigadas-a-serem-maes/</link><description>At 17 Diana dreams of being a nurse and daily wakes up at 05:00 to cook what she sells at the door in Maputo, before going to school while trying to support her two -year -old son.
 
“When I had my son, it was a blessing, but then came the difficulties,” he says to Lusa, sitting at the door, with baby Kayon, the lap, in the neighborhood of Mafalala, downtown Mozambican capital and where the Eusébio football star was born.
A child who has not been planned since, like so many thousands of other Mozambican teenagers, contraceptives are not a priority: "It was a great lesson, I will never make this mistake in my life again."
Diana Manhiça's life is a reflection of a global United Nations report that points to Mozambique as the country with the fourth highest birth rate in adolescence, 15 to 19 -year -old girls worldwide, further anticipating the population in 25 years.
The report “Situation of the World Population 2025”, presenting a week ago in Maputo by the United Nations Fund for the population (FNUAP), says that the birth rate in adolescence, from 2001 to 2024, reached 158 out of each thousand Mozambican girls. "It was very difficult, especially at school. I had to face bullying, bad eye. That was a big challenge for me. But with the support of my parents I got there, at the end of the year," recalls the teenager, who deals with his son alone, with the support of his parents only in the same house, where six people live in a dozen square meters.
At very cost, the father of his son, then 23, took over the child, but "never took care as it should be." After birth they were not together and does not receive any pension. The only support comes from parents, despite the fear that was revealed the pregnancy, which tried to hide until the last one. “Challenge was to tell my father that I was pregnant. It took me about six months (…) Fortunately my father received the information as it should be, as I did not expect,” he says.
In the street, and at school, the reality was different, with the "eyes and criticism of the neighbors that increased with the growth of the belly." “My belly came out at seven months (…) my mother noticed, my father did not,” he recalls, admitting that he knew of family planning, but was “afraid” to put an contraceptive implant after hearing alleged difficulties experienced by other women. “I regretted myself,” he says, to quickly assume that three months after his son was born, he soon put the implant. Something that, assumes, should have done before: "I would do without thinking twice, not once."
The FNUAP report estimates that the Mozambican population is around 35.6 million people this year, 44% up to 14 years old and only 3% over 65 years. In Mozambique, the report points to 25 years as the deadline for duplication of the current population.
Alien to statistics, Diana feeds the desire to be a nurse and although her pregnancy has made a splash in 10th grade, she never left school, at her father's insistence, who also helped her set up a small tent. “A dream? Being a nurse, because I want to help a lot of people. Treating people well,” he says, “I want to be a good nurse”.
Every day it gets up at 5:00 am to cook Badjias (fried salty) that serves with bread, the backyard, the door of the house, and APAs (flat bread), which sells next to the school. At the end of the morning leaves his son at his father's barber shop. “Then I prepare and go to school at the Red Star. I enter 12:00,” he says, with his hands still full of dough, while looking at the clock, with the time to go to classes coming.
Despite the “very difficult” life that assumes to lead, and the full support of parents, expects the child that “does not make the same mistakes” in the family planning he did not. “I will tell you about contraceptive methods, so that he […] does not play bad, to suffer the consequences of having a child early,” says, as he assumes, fear, the desire to give him a brother. “I want to have him with time and time. So that he has no difficulty what the first has happened. It has to be everything with time,” he says.
The FNUAP study suggests that only one in three Mozambican women can make decisions about the number of children, because of the difficulty in accessing sexual and reproductive health services, and on average a child in each family results from unla's pregnancy. It also points to the high rate of premature unions, which affect almost half of girls (48%) and give birth to light for the first time before 18 years.
Hortênsia Zefanias, 21, also makes life in the Mafalala neighborhood and carries his two children with his lap. He got pregnant from the first to 17 and only told his mother, who lives in Inhambane, after childbirth: "It was not easy. I tried an abortion, it didn't work."
He interrupted the school in the 10th grade and today lives with his partner, who depends on Biscates in the works, the mother -in -law and the brother -in -law, in the same house. If before I never wanted to know of contraceptive methods, the difficulties for this forced it and two children later put an implant. "I have no children, now, I think I would be working. I would have completed the school," he laments, while guaranteeing: "We are happy, despite the difficulties."
Of children “okay” and back to school is objective, dreaming of being an “entrepreneur”, because I worked in a tent before getting pregnant. And about the children, still babies, assumes that he will have the conversation about family planning, when the time comes: "teach the good way, other than me ... go to school and work."
In the same yard of Hortênsia, in a house of plates equal to so many others, he lives Cíntia, 16, the oldest of three brothers. At the time I couldn't imagine, but it was a hortênsia, which treats by sister -in -law, who gave her the news: she was 14 years old and was pregnant. "There was no belly, it only appeared at four months. She found me. I was afraid to tell my mother," says nervously, with her daughter Anaya on her lap.
The 17 -year -old boyfriend denied that he was his father and shortly after Hortênsia left school. Contraceptive methods was something that did not think and quickly, as a child, life changed and jokes spent responsibility, such as laundry and cleaning, to have money for the trousseau.
Now try to end the 9th grade and assumes the goal of taking care of the daughter, without thinking about boyfriends or more children. The goal: “fight for my family”. The daughter is only two years old, but Cíntia thinks about the future and especially in "mistakes": "I will ask you to know how to do things with her partner."
In Mozambique, according to the study of FNUAP, the fertility rate is 4.6 children per woman, average that Emilia Rodrigues, or 'Maimuna', in the neighborhood of Mafalala, knows well.
He pregnant for the first time at 17, today he is 35 years old and four daughters from three different parents, which forced her to leave school in the 5th grade. The last one was about 10 years ago, no programmed, but always with the desire, already pregnant, to be born boy. “It was very playful,” he recalls, after using wooden remains to put the kettle spent on the heat, to make tea for the youngest. "It's just that to have these all, I wanted to have a boy." Every pregnancy was born a girl, "he says, recalling the warning he received from his brother, who helps her at home:" Girl, beyond born [get pregnant]. " “This belly is not mine,” was the answer that tired of hearing from his companions, forcing her to do for life. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-15 04:48:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Coutinho calls for review of the careers of civil servants of the front line</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/15/coutinho-pede-revisao-das-carreiras-dos-funcionarios-publicos-da-linha-da-frente/</link><description>José Pereira Coutinho defended yesterday the revision of the careers of workers from the front line of the public administration due to their contribution over the three years of pandemic, with “physical effort, total dedication and commitment to the service of citizens”.
“The problem of non-payment of overtime is also resolved through the electronic machines that register the entries, exits and intervals of employees to be paid all the overtime derived from overwork,” suggested the president of the Macao Public Workers Association (ATFPM).
According to Coutinho, hundreds or even thousands of civil service workers “are required to work beyond normal working hours, without paying overtime or hours compensation”. The deputy also said that "these workers do not dare to complain to the competent entities for fear of reprisals or not renewal of labor contracts."
In addition, Pereira Coutinho added, the government must solve the problem of “accumulation of the work of colleagues who retired or who have halted themselves from the civil service and all others who are on vacation or illness or were transferred temporarily or definitely to work in other public services or other locations”. “Here is also the non -payment of overtime,” warned the deputy.
In his intervention before the agenda, Coutinho concluded that the executive, “by dignifying the professional careers of front line workers, simultaneously raises his image of being a good employer because he creates a positive and productive work environment, valuing his employees and promoting their professional development”.</description><pubDate>2025-07-15 04:48:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Al approves law that aims to make public hiring fairer and more transparent</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/15/al-aprova-lei-que-pretende-tornar-contratacao-publica-mais-justa-e-transparente/</link><description>The deputies to the Legislative Assembly (AL) yesterday gave light green to the proposal of public hiring. The diploma renews the legislation that has been in force for over 30 years. The objective, according to the government, is to make public hiring clearer, fair, transparent, full and efficient.
 
Yesterday the proposal of public hiring was approved yesterday. The diploma will replace the three diplomas that regulated this type of procedures, which had been in force for more than three decades. The legislative process of the proposal now approved had started in 2018, with a public consultation that would be approved by the participants.
In the justification of the diploma, the government says that it is "essential to establish a set of clear, fair, transparent, righteous and efficient public hiring procedures." Thus, the proposal approved yesterday determines the principles that public services should observe in hiring, such as the principle of transparency and publicity, the principle of loyal competition, the principle of impartiality and the principle of stability.
The pleading defines the award criteria and determines the rules of conduct of workers and members of the opening and evaluation committees of proposals involved in the public hiring procedures.
The government also explains that the proposal also has as specific objectives to determine the inapplicability of the law proposal to certain contracts; Establish the fundamental principles that public services must observe in hiring; ensure that workers and members of the opening and evaluation committees of proposals involved in public hiring procedures perform their duties impartially and integrally; define types of clear and uniform hiring procedures, determining the requirements for your choice; Create an electronic page of public hiring, through which the informative elements related to public hiring procedures are adequately advertised in order to guarantee the right to information of the interveners and reinforce the monitoring of the population in relation to the hiring performed by the government; and explicitly define the sanctioning regime of infringements to any legal duties.
Recently, the new regime was applauded by Marco Caldeira, professor at the Lisbon Law School, at a conference that took place at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center in Lisbon. The academic stated, at the time, that this public hiring diploma seems to be on the “good way”, seeking to “combat the lack of transparency”, preventing “conflicts of interest” and avoiding “addressed direct adjustments”.</description><pubDate>2025-07-15 04:45:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Put up the appeal of 13 pro-democracy activists in Hong Kong</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/15/arranca-julgamento-de-recurso-de-13-activistas-pro-democracia-em-hong-kong/</link><description>Thirteen Pro-Democracy activists began yesterday to appeal the prison sentences to which they were sentenced in the largest trial under the National Security Law held to this day in the former British colony.
 
In all, 45 opposition figures were sentenced by the end of 2024 to effective arrest penalties for organizing an informal primary election in 2020, classified by the authorities as a conspiracy to subvert state power.
Among the defendants are former deputies, district, academic and trade union representatives, with positions ranging from moderate to radical. Many have been arrested in 2021 and has spent more than four years detained.
The repression against opposition was intensified after the imposition by Beijing of a rigorous national security law, following the pro-democracy mass protests that shook Hong Kong in 2019.
Old deputies Leung Kwok-Hung (known as 'Long Hair'), Lam Cheuk-Tre, Helena Wong and Raymond Chan are among the 13 activists who will contest the convictions at audiences scheduled for ten days. Owen Chow, 28, is the defendant with the heaviest penalty among those who now resort: seven years and nine months in prison.
"The only way to restore the image of the city as a place where rights are respected and people can freely express their opinions, without fear of being arrested, is to nullify these convictions," said the director of Amnesty International to China, Sarah Brooks.
The informal primary election organized by activists aimed to increase the probabilities of conquering a legislative majority in Hong Kong elections, with the aim of pressuring local government to accept claims such as the introduction of universal suffrage under threat of vetoing the budget.
Three judges, appointed by the authorities to judge lawsuits related to national security, considered that the plan was an attempt to provoke a “constitutional crisis”.
The United States, the European Union and the United Kingdom have already condemned the judicial process, considering it illustrates the erosion of fundamental freedoms and political opposition in the former British colony, transferred to Chinese sovereignty in 1997.
During the appeal phase, prosecutors will also contest the acquittal of lawyer Lawrence Lau, one of the only two defendants in the case of the so -called “47 of Hong Kong” to be declared innocent in the first instance.
The trial of Lau and other opponents have been seen as a symbol of the collapse of guarantees of freedom of expression and association in Hong Kong.
However, eight activists, including former journalist and lawyer Claudia Mo and the LGBT+ Jimmy Sham rights defender, have already served their penalties and have been released in recent weeks.
In parallel, one of the last opposition parties still active in Hong Kong, the Social Democrats League (LSD), announced dissolution in late June, invoking "immense political pressure." Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-15 04:48:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing provides for deepening the dialogue with the US after meeting with Rubio</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/15/pequim-preve-aprofundamento-do-dialogo-com-os-eua-apos-encontro-com-rubio/</link><description>Chinese diplomacy head Wang Yi said yesterday that the meeting with US homologous, Marco Rubio, held on Friday in Kuala Lumpur, created conditions to deepen bilateral contacts at a time of increasing commercial friction.
According to a statement from the Chinese Foreign Ministry, Wang considered that the meeting contributed to managing the differences between Beijing and Washington, recognizing that both sides represent “the most important bilateral relationship in the world,” with global impact.
"The meeting was constructive, with both parties involving a dialogue on an equal foot and a spirit of mutual respect," said Wang, quoted in the same note. "I believe it has allowed to improve the United States's understanding of China and prepared the land for the next phase of contacts between the diplomatic teams of both countries," he added.
The statement indicates that Wang spoke to journalists after attending ASEAN meetings and East Asian -related meetings held in the capital of Malaysia, without specifying the exact place of the conversation with Rubio.
According to Chinese diplomacy head, Friday's meeting served to reinforce dialogue, avoid misconceptions, managing divergences and expanding Sino-American cooperation.
The meeting took place in a context of renewed commercial tension between the two largest economies in the world.
Since Donald Trump has returned to the US presidency in January, US administration has hardened its economic policy against China, imposing new tariffs on Chinese strategic sectors such as electric vehicles, batteries, semiconductors and critical minerals.
Beijing reacted with retaliation measures, including controls to export metals essential to the global technological industry, such as gallium and Germanium, and new restrictions on rare land exports.
In parallel, both countries agreed in mid -May with a 90 -day commercial truce, which has allowed technical negotiations to try to avoid a generalized tariff climbing.</description><pubDate>2025-07-15 04:48:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing praises unparalleled “strategic value” of relations with Moscow</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/15/pequim-enaltece-valor-estrategico-inigualavel-das-relacoes-com-moscovo/</link><description>Chinese diplomacy chief Wang Yi said on Sunday that the relationship between Beijing and Moscow is the “richest of strategic value in the world” during a meeting with Russian homologous, Serguei Lavrov in Beijing.
Lavrov's visit to Beijing followed a trip to North Korea, where he received guarantees of support from Pyongyang regarding the conflict in Ukraine.
According to a statement from the Chinese Foreign Ministry, Wang Yi stated that among the great powers, the sino-Russian relationship is "currently the most stable, the most ripe and the richest of strategic value."
Chinese diplomacy chief underlined the “joint preparation of upcoming high -level exchanges,“ deepening global strategic cooperation ”and“ common response to the challenges of a change and turbulent world ”.
According to the same statement, the two ministers also addressed the situation in the Korean Peninsula, the crisis in Ukraine, the Iranian nuclear program and other international affairs. "The parties discussed relations with the United States and the possibility of resolving the Ukrainian crisis in accordance with the principles of the United Nations Charter (…), other 'warm' issues were discussed, including the Israelo-Roranda conflict and the situation on the Korean peninsula," reads in a statement distributed by the Russian Foreign Ministry.
The heads of the two diplomacy "expressed their satisfaction with the positive dynamics of Russian-Chinese global interaction and discussed the bilateral agenda in depth with the priorities defined for the May Summit in Moscow."
Foreign ministers of both countries "confirmed firm mutual support on matters regarding the main interests of each party, including the defense of sovereignty, territorial integrity and state unity based on its regional and ethnic diversity." "The conversations were constructive and based on the confidence inherent in Russian-Chinese relations," concluded Russian diplomacy.
China, Russia's diplomatic and economic ally, has claimed to maintain a position of neutrality as to the conflict in Ukraine. Beijing did not condemn the Russian invasion that began in 2022, nor explicitly appealed to the withdrawal of the Russian troops. However, Kiev's allied countries accuse China to provide significant support to Moscow, especially in the political and economic level.</description><pubDate>2025-07-15 04:48:15</pubDate></item><item><title>New service requirements in special taxis motivate drivers complaints</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/15/novas-exigencias-de-servico-nos-taxis-especiais-motivam-queixas-dos-condutores/</link><description>The Macau Taxi Radio Services Company is introducing several measures to adjust your service following the audit commissioner's criticism. However, drivers are dissatisfied with the adjustment and complain about the difficulties of operation, and even some who want to leave the job, denounced Ron Lam and Leong Sun Iok. The deputies asked for a revision of the number and taxi service methods.
 
The new demands imposed by the Macau Taxi Radio Services Company at their service motivated complaints from their drivers, leading some to get out of office. The situation was denounced by deputies Ron Lam and Leong Sun Iok, who said they had received reports from the taxi drivers involved, thus asking for solutions to the government.
According to the deputies, following the audit report on the supervision of the provision of special taxis services, presented by the Audit Commissioner, the direction of services to traffic matters (DSAT) required the concessionaire to proceed to the necessary corrections.
In detail, the company reestablished the mandatory waiting time for 30 -minute passengers for reservations, which was once 10 minutes, as well as the distribution of markings in which passengers are far from the taxi driver, instead of the limitation of vehicle reserve in a 1.5 km geographical radius.
Ron Lam, in a written interpellation presented to the executive, pointed out that the radio company Taxi did not pay the reasonable remuneration to taxi drivers despite prolonging the waiting time. "It came to demand that drivers would fulfill the contractual obligation to wait for the passengers 30 minutes in advance, but only a 3 -pataca subsidy was attributed to them," Ron Lam said, indicating that this has led drivers' yields dramatically. " "It is difficult for them to continue their activity by maintaining reasonable performance, even having decided to abandon their job," he lamented.
The deputy said he predicted that, in the future, the availability of taxis by calls becomes even lower and that it is even more difficult to satisfy the search for citizens and tourists.
Leong Sun IOK shares the same opinion that the extension of waiting time for passengers makes the taxi driver can only conclude a trip while taking longer, which reduces the number of reserves received and affects taxi driver's recipes.
"Special taxis drivers have to endure expenses such as rental and fuel. And if a passenger cancels his order, the driver will eventually receive anything. To earn his life, taxi drivers have to work more hours in exchange for income, which affects their job security," said the deputy in a press release mentioned by the newspaper or Mun.
 
Lack of taxis
 
On the other hand, the two legislators have again drawn attention to the problem of lack of taxis, whether of black taxis or special taxis, to respond to the search for the service. "The increase in the number of tourists and border posts in recent years have led to a serious taxi scarcity, coupled with the fact that the online taxi order mechanism is not yet ready, which makes taxi services unable to respond to community development needs, leading to the dissatisfaction of residents and tourists," said Leong Sun Iok.
Leong said the audit report revealed problems of surveillance and execution of the special taxi contract, but did not analyze the global planning of taxis, so the government must proceed to review the number of taxis and the mode of provision of the service.
 
Guarantee the interests of drivers
 
Ron Lam left another criticism of the “exploration” of workers by the Radio Taxi Services Company, which “got the concession at a low price, but oppresses drivers' performance”.
The deputy explained that the company is subject to an annual rate of only 6,000 patacas for each taxi license, which is significantly lower than the general taxis bidding price. Nevertheless, the company, instead of hiring drivers on a contractual basis, “subcontracted intermediaries to exploit the service, it offered no sufficiently low taxi rentals or a reasonable return,” Lam reported, noting that the company did not assume contractual obligations and reduced drivers' performance.
In this sense, remembering that “blue” and “red” special taxi licenses will expire on September 30 this year and May 31 in 2028, respectively, Ron Lam requested a review and improvement of the special taxi operating model, as well as accelerate the introduction of online transportation services in Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-07-15 04:44:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Government promotes teacher education in artificial intelligence to modernize teaching</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/15/governo-promove-formacao-de-professores-em-inteligencia-artificial-para-modernizar-o-ensino/</link><description>About 250 educators, experts and school leaders have gathered to launch the “teacher training action in artificial intelligence teaching”. The event, held at the Salesian Institute of Immaculate Conception, marked the beginning of an ambitious strategy: to equip teachers with tools to integrate artificial intelligence (AI) in primary and secondary education, aligning with China's national guidelines and global trends.
 
As part of the strategy of modernizing international education, the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) held, on July 11, the “inauguration ceremony of the teacher training action in Artificial Intelligence Teaching”, marking a significant step in the updating of the Macau Educational System. The event, which took place at the Salesian Institute of Immaculate Conception, brought together about 250 participants, including experts, academics, school leaders and teachers, with the aim of aligning the territory with global technological and educational trends.
The government has been part of the programming and artificial intelligence in the mandatory curricula of primary and secondary education, reviewing the framework of the curriculum and the requirements of basic academic skills. This measure aims not only to modernize teaching, but also to prepare students for an increasingly digital future and with the aid of intelligent machines. In line with China's “Popularization of Science and Technology Popularization Law and the General Planning Lines for the Construction of a Strong Nation in Education (2024-2035)” from the Central Government, the DSEDJ will begin this year an interchange of planning to “medium and long term of non-higher education”, with the aim of fostering a deeper integration between technology and education.
The DSEDJ training strategy is based on three fundamental axes. Firstly, it aims to update teachers about the latest advances in artificial intelligence, allowing them to accompany innovations in the area. Secondly, it focuses on six AI practical application scenarios, including assistance in teaching and evaluation, support for school research and management, and personalized learning tools. Finally, DSEDJ will provide financial support to schools so that they can promote internal training, with programs adapted to information technologies, lasting 10 hours, and teachers from other areas, with 6 hours of training.
The inaugural session served as a starting point for this training system, with experts to share knowledge of IA educational policies, global trends and practical cases of application in classrooms. The presentations and discussions were attended by director Fan Lianghuo, Director Ke Qingchao, Chai Ching-Sing subdirector and Lung Hsiang.
According to DSEDJ, this initiative intends not only to empower teachers, but also stimulate the critical and creative thinking of students, preparing them for the challenges of a rapidly adaptation to a constantly evolving technology. By fostering AI literacy, schools not only modernize teaching methodologies, but also promote transversal skills such as computational thinking and problem solving. This approach ensures that the territory maintains educational competitiveness, in line with international best practices, according to DSEDJ.</description><pubDate>2025-07-15 04:48:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Prime Minister of Timor-Leste in Singapore to reinforce cooperation</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/15/primeiro-ministro-de-timor-leste-em-singapura-para-reforcar-cooperacao/</link><description>Timor-Leste Prime Minister Xanana Gusmão began an official visit to Singapore to reinforce the bilateral relationship and cooperation between the two countries. Timor-Leste is developing its blue economy and within that policy aims to establish a marine education and research center on the island of Armaro, in front of Dili.
 
The Prime Minister of Timor-Leste, Xanana Gusmão, began yesterday an official visit to Singapore to reinforce the bilateral relationship and cooperation between the two countries.
On the first day of the visit, according to information to the press distributed by the Prime Minister's office, Xanana Gusmão met with his counterpart, Lawrence Wong, who also accumulates the position of Finance Minister, and Singapore President Tharman Shanmugaratnam.
The Timorese Delegation will also visit the Singapore Oceanarium to “better know approaches in the areas of Marine Education, Research and Institutional Development”, can be read in the information to the press.
Timor-Leste is developing its blue economy and within that policy aims to establish a marine education and research center on the island of Armaro, in front of Dili, on the north coast of the island.
This Tuesday, the head of the Timorese government has been visiting a visit to the Cora Environmental Energy Center, to realize how Singapore found solutions to solve waste-related problems by turning them into energy solutions.
Xanana Gusmão will also give a lecture at a school of international study dedicated to the theme “Timor-Leste and Asean [Southeast Asian Nations Association]: a new chapter in the history of the region” and plant a camellia in the Bay gardens.
Also under the visit, which ends Wednesday, the prime minister will visit the Singapore Housing and Development Council to “obtain information on public housing policy, financing models and urban planning with social dimension,” says the information. “Lessons learned from Singapore's successful public housing model will be able to contribute to the continuous efforts of Timor-Leste to develop quality housing and accessible to the Timorese people”, read the information released to the press.
Xanana Gusmão leads a delegation that includes the vice-prime minister and minister coordinating economic affairs and Minister of Tourism and Environment, Francisco Kalbuadi Lay, Foreign Minister Bendito Freitas, the Deputy Minister for Asean, Milena Rangel, and Secretary of State for Social Communication, Expedito Dias Ximenes. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-15 04:48:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Suggested direct flight macau-lisboa</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/15/sugerido-voo-directo-macau-lisboa/</link><description>IP Sio Kai suggested yesterday, at the Plenary Meeting of the Legislative Assembly (AL), to bet on direct flights between Macau and Lisbon in the name of the role of service platform for commercial cooperation between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries that the MSc should perform. The deputy proposed the creation of subsidies to support the high costs of exploiting air routes.
 
The IP deputy Sio Kai proposed yesterday, in the Legislative Assembly (AL), the bet on direct flights between Macau and Lisbon, in order to enhance the role of platform of MSAR. "As a service platform for commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, Macau has to consolidate the basic work of economic, commercial, cultural and personal exchange," he said.
"Portuguese -speaking countries are far from Macao, and trade exchange depends largely on air transport," said IP Sio Kai in his intervention before the agenda, noting that MSar has autonomy to enter into air traffic rights agreements with other countries or regions and have direct flights to several foreign cities from local airport.
In the opinion of the deputy, regular direct flights of medium and long course to Europe and Portuguese -speaking countries are lacking and this “compromises to some extent compromises Macau's connection role in the international network, and the contribution and influence of Macao, as a platform between these countries, for face -to -face interaction”.
To arrive in Lisbon, residents and visitors have to travel through Hong Kong, Dubai or Istanbul, for example, “which represents a long trip, having to change the airport or wait for connecting flights, which makes air traffic considerably inconvenient and does not favor the promotion of the normalization of SINO-Portuguese commercial and business activities to Macao ”.
"The opening of direct flights between Macao and Lisbon is the basis of a platform, which serves to connect, through the Portuguese airline, Brazil and Portuguese -speaking countries in Africa," said IP, justifying that this "will contribute to further promoting trade, tourism and the flow of people between Macao and European countries, reinforcing the substantive function of Macao as a link to the world."
IP Sio Kai acknowledged that these long-distance routes would have high operating costs, so "without initial subsidy or support for complementary administrative support or measures, airlines can hardly assume the high risks of exploitation of these routes."
Thus, the deputy elected by the indirect way asked the government to study the creation of a “specific allowance to support the high costs of the initial exploitation of air routes, for example, the expenses with traffic rights, airport rates, as well as the costs of staff and fuel, assigning phased financial subsidies”. "These subsidies can be attributed through a fixed amount according to the number of flights or, more flexible, through the gradual and phase reduction of an initially assigned amount of years of exploration of routes, in order to help airlines reduce initial risks and promote the entry into operation of these routes," he explained.
The deputy also suggested that the government reserve traffic rights and implements the rapid appreciation regime of the main routes for these “long -course strategic routes”, “simplifying the approval procedure, as well as taking measures such as reducing or exempting the departure and disembarkation rates and the use rates of terminals”.
IP Sio Kai also proposed that the government, through the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), the Office for Conventions and Exhibitions (GCET) and the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), define a “strategy of effective flight effectiveness”, through the launch of consumption promotions for accommodation, transportation, cultural activities, etc. for the passengers of these flights. Finally, he suggested that there is cooperation with game operators, in order to offer travel packages or subsidies to international visitors using these routes, “increasing the average number of days of stay and per capita consumption, materializing the general economic benefits of exploiting direct routes and the basis of their permanent operation”.
This was not the first time that the bet on direct flights between Macau and Portugal was suggested. Recently, in the presentation of the political program of the Nova Esperança list to the legislative elections of September 14, Pereira Coutinho defended the same measure.</description><pubDate>2025-07-15 04:42:12</pubDate></item><item><title>STD foresees a daily average of 110,000 tourists in July and August</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/15/dst-preve-media-diaria-de-110-mil-turistas-em-julho-e-agosto/</link><description>Helena de Senna Fernandes, the Director of Tourism Services (STD), has announced that the government's latest forecasts point to a daily entry of 110,000 tourists in Macao during the summer holidays. The number of international tourists should also increase from tomorrow due to a new measure of visa exemption to five Middle East countries.
 
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) expects Macau to receive 110,000 daily visitors in July and August, as a result of the various events and activities to take place in the territory throughout the summer.
Speaking yesterday to the newspaper or Mun, on the sidelines of the International Gastronomy Forum, Helena de Senna Fernandes said that, in addition to the Gastronomy Fair, another of the great highlights of the Veranil Season is the International Arts for Children of Macao, organized by the Cultural Institute (IC), which will last until the last day of August. Moreover, there will be several activities planned for these two months in hotels, urban areas or community sites distributed throughout the city, especially a “Zape area” that will combine “cultural and creative” elements with gastronomic offers.
Macao has exceeded 20 million tourist entries on July 8, almost a month earlier than last year. The daily average of tourists in the first half of the month was the 106,000 entries, a number still lower than the latest forecasts of the STD director for the second half. Speaking at the time to the newspaper or Mun, Helena de Senna Fernandes admitted that the registration of 20 million visitors was “very encouraging”, although she chose to maintain a “conservative” attitude due to the unpredictability of meteorological conditions such as typhoons.
 
On the other hand, Cheung Kin Chung, president of the Macao Hotelers Association, estimated that the hotel occupancy rate for summer should exceed 85%. "With the increase in visitors arrivals, and a favorable situation of supply and search hotel, it is expected that the total number of tourists will increase compared to the same period last year, with the month of August the highest time," he noted in an interview with Radio Macau in Chinese language.
 
Five Middle East countries dismissed from a visa
 
Another measure for strengthening the flow of tourists - especially international - overlooking the expansion of the number of countries with visa exemption and prior entry authorization, recently extended to include five Middle East countries. The measure officially comes into force tomorrow, the 16th, and covers the nationals of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, the state of Qatar, the state of Kuwait, the Kingdom of Barém and the Sultanate of Oman.
Asked about this new incentive to Muslim tourism, Helena de Senna Fernandes admitted to or Mun that, "in the past, the number of visitors from the Middle East countries was relatively low," a situation that was repeated in the first half of this year. However, the STD director notes that the profile of these visitors-with numerous families and a greater tendency to remain in the territory for long periods-makes them particularly attractive to the Macao tourism sector, which has been stressing efforts to reinforce the ability to welcome Muslim tourism.
Also the Public Security Police (CPSP) has commented on this topic, ensuring that the enlargement of the visa exemption will help to attract more international visitors to Macao and, consequently, boost the city's statute as an “important opening bridge abroad”. Quoted by Chinese TDM, CPSP says it “will actively complement the position of the Government of a center of a center, a platform and a base” by continually reviewing and optimizing the process of border passage.
According to TDM, the passport holders of these five countries are authorized, as of tomorrow, crossing the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau bridge without leaving vehicles with nine or less places. The same source adds that “eligible people” will also be able to use the self-service kiosks of the Macao border points.
This new measure arises at a time when the tourism sector seeks to reinforce measures for the capture of international visitors, focusing on Muslim markets. In February, in parallel to various promotion seminars in Saudi Arabia and Dubai, STD launched a sightly developed tour guide for Muslims, with halal options and itinerary recommendations.
Regarding the integration of an exhibitor of Macao in Arabian Travel Market 2025, between April and May this year, the STD stated in a statement released at the time that the Middle East Muslim tourist layer is made up of “with high purchasing power” visitors, constituting a “high level” tourist market.</description><pubDate>2025-07-15 04:41:19</pubDate></item><item><title>“Cantonense culture is an important cultural active of Macau”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/15/cultura-cantonense-e-um-activo-cultural-importante-de-macau/</link><description>Wang Sai Man defended yesterday that Macau should promote the Cantonense culture in order to attract language speaking tourists. In the opinion of the deputy, Macau must bet on the market of talk of Cantonese due to “cultural proximity and ease in travel”.
"Cantonense culture is an important cultural active of Macau and can be our basis of tourist attraction through language, so we can go to discovery and revitalize this cultural advantage that is fundamental to the construction of an image with identity and intimacy with tourists who speak it," Wang said in his intervention before the order of day at yesterday's plenary meeting of the Legislative Assembly (AL).
In 2024, there were about 24.5 million visitors from the interior of China, of which 54% came from Guangdong Province, "which demonstrates that these visitors are the main source of Macao tourism," said the deputy, adding that of the 120 million Cantonese speakers in the world, Guangdong province is about 67 million and the remaining 50 million are distributed by Singapore, Malaysia, Vietnam, Canada and San Francisco, in the United States of America. "These communities are very interested in and are attracted to the Tourist Regions of Cantonense Matrix, namely, local gastronomy, respective festivities, neighborhood culture and entertainment programs," said Wang.
However, "Products and disclosure strategies are still unable to fully develop our advantages for singing tourists," said the deputy elected by the Indirect Way, reinforcing that "guided tours at sights, tourist content and social networks lack a Cantonese -centered cultural representation."
"It is necessary to reinforce, more systematically, the position of the Cantonense Culture of Macau, because, in addition to consolidating the main source of tourists that comes from Guangdong, one should at the same time take the initiative to promote Macau through the communities around the world, as well as through English, with a view to increasing the irradiation of urban culture and capturing economic benefits from foreign visitors." Wang comes out Man.</description><pubDate>2025-07-15 04:48:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Exports of rare land in China rise 32% after licensing flexibility</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/15/exportacoes-de-terras-raras-da-china-sobem-32-apos-flexibilizacao-de-licencas/</link><description>Chinese rare land exports increased 32%between May and June, after Beijing promised to “review and approve” requests to sell abroad this group of critical minerals to industries such as semiconductors, aeronautics, automobiles and defense.
 
According to data released yesterday by China's General Customs Administration, the exported volume of rare land increased by 32.02% in June, compared to May, and grew 60.34%, in homologous terms.
In the first half of 2025, exports increased 11.9% compared to the same period of 2024, although the value of these sales retreated 24.4%, according to customs reports. Preliminary data released yesterday do not detail exports by element or indicate the destination countries, presenting only the total aggregate.
Since April 2, in the context of the trade war with the United States, China has implemented a new license regime that obliges foreign companies to request seven of the 17 minerals that make up the rare land group - namely Samário, Gadolinio, Terbius, Discipli, Lutecio, Scandamus and Itrio - as well as derived irans, invoking national security reasons.
The introduction of these restrictions caused a sharp drop in exports in April (-15.56%), but in May sales recovered with a monthly increase of 22.57%, even surpassing March levels.
Controls have a significant impact on highly dependent sectors of these materials, as China accounted for 99% of the global rare land processing in 2024 and has about 49% of world reserves.
The promise of accelerating licensing issuance is part of Beijing's commitments under the agreement achieved during the latest round of commercial negotiations with the United States, held just over a month in London.
At the time, the Chinese authorities were committed to “reviewing and approving” the export requests of restricted goods, in an apparent reference to the rare land-one of the main focuses of tension between the two powers and that threatened the continuity of the 90-day commercial truce started in mid-May.
 
Exports accelerate in June after a break in the trade war with the United States
 
China exports registered a strong acceleration in June, as manufacturers took advantage of the 90 -day truce in the Washington trade war to anticipate shipping, a performance that widely exceeded analysts' predictions.
The world's largest exporter saw their sales abroad increase 5.8%in homologous terms to $ 325.2 billion last month, China's general customs administration said.
The value represents an acceleration compared to the 4.8% growth recorded in May and far exceeds 3.6% foreseen in a poll performed by Wind, a Chinese financial data platform.
Imports also surprised positively, rising 1.1% in June, after a 3.4% drop in the previous month. The same wind poll pointed to a new contraction, estimated at 0.58%.
The surplus of the Chinese trade balance ascended to $ 114.8 billion in June.
Despite unprecedented commercial tensions with the United States, China's foreign trade remained solid in the first half of the year. Exports increased by 5.9% compared to the same period of 2024, totaling $ 1.8 billion, while imports retreated 3.9% to more than $ 1.2 billion. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-07-15 04:48:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Government studies extending visa period for Chinese spectators of the National Games</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/15/governo-estuda-alargar-periodo-de-visto-para-espectadores-chineses-dos-jogos-nacionais/</link><description>The Macao government is communicating and negotiating with the Chinese authorities, especially Guangdong, to widen visas to the China visitors with tickets to the National Games, with the aim of facilitating the trip of Chinese tourists to Macao to watch competitions.
It is recalled that the National Games, the National Games for People with Disabilities and the National Special Olympic Games will be held in November and December in Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau.
Pun Weng Kun, coordinator of the preparatory cabinet for the organization of the Macao competition competition zone, indicated yesterday that visa widening plans to cover the day of the competition, a day before and a day after the event, according to the ticket. According to the official, it is sufficient for visitors to present their tickets to the competent authorities in the interior of China when requesting the visa and the measure of facilitation are granted them.
Quoted by Radio Macao in Chinese language, Pun Weng Kun also revealed that the authorities of Guangdong province reported on the possibility of introducing, before the games, a border passage system without contact for tourists visiting Macao.
"It is believed that this measure will provide a new experience to sports supporters who visit Macao, encouraging them to stay in Macau and participate in the event, boosting the economy," said Pun Weng Kun.
On the other hand, the official said he had completed the test competitions of the five events organized by Macau for the National Games, while two Badminton competition tests at the Special Olympic Games for the disabled will be held in mid -month.
Pun Weng Kun stressed that the test competition process “took place in a quiet way”, having been “very well evaluated” by the continent experts participating in the tests. He added that local volunteers who completed the training for the games "had excellent performance." The coordinator expects the event tickets to be put for sale next month.</description><pubDate>2025-07-15 04:48:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Health services warn of hyperthermia risk</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/07/15/servicos-de-saude-alertam-para-risco-de-hipertermia/</link><description>The territory of Macau is on alert yellow due to the heat, which will extend (and intensify) by Friday. Authorities advise the population to adopt preventive against hyperthermia, highlighting that this condition can result in irreversible brain injuries or even death.
 
Health services yesterday issued a yellow alert for high temperatures, drawing attention to the risk of hyperthermia in the coming days and appealing so that citizens adopt preventive measures.
The authorities' electronic page explains that time in the region should remain “very hot” in the coming days, with maximum temperatures equal to or greater than 33 degrees Celsius. According to the meteorological forecast for the rest of the week, the maximum temperatures will reach 34 and 35 degrees Celsius on Thursday and Friday, respectively, while the minimums will remain at 28 degrees Celsius. Relative humidity will oscillate between 60% and 95%, with occasional deposits provided for Friday.
Temperatures will start to down gradually from Saturday until they set at a maximum temperature of 30 degrees Celsius on Monday. It is also expected that this weekend is marked by a very cloudy sky and periods of thunder and thunderstorms, which should intensify on Sunday.
 
Avoid hyperthermia
 
Health services explain that, in intense heat environments, the body activates thermoregulation mechanisms to decrease the internal temperature, which is an example perspiration and faster breathing. However, adverse conditions such as a very high environmental temperature, prolonged exposure to the sun, the use of waterproof clothing or a poorly ventilated or moist environment may make it difficult to adjust the body and eventually cause symptoms of hyperthermia.
This phenomenon can manifest in different ways, as the authorities clarify. Heat syncope - also known as heat fainting - is a condition that can occur when the body is exposed to high temperatures and skin vessels dilate, causing dizziness, moist and cold skin and weakening of the pulse. Hyperthermia can also manifest itself through cramps and muscle seizures or seizures caused by the loss of electrolytes through sweat.
Symptoms and possible complications are aggravated by heat exhaustion, a condition characterized by extreme thirst, fatigue, lack of strength, nausea, headache, dizziness or temporary unconsciousness. The most severe form of hyperthermia is, however, the internal one, most popular by the term “heat blow”. In this situation, the patient's perspiration decreases or may even cease after prolonged exposure to an environment with intense heat. If the victim is not rescued quickly, he may suffer irreversible brain injuries or even die.
Health services advise citizens to resort to the doctor “immediately” in case of indisposition, or to contact the body of firefighters through number 999 in more serious cases. Until the arrival of the ambulance, the victim's body temperature should be regulated with a wet towel, ice, or a fan. If the patient is conscious and has no vomiting, an electrolytic drink (such as mineral water or salt water) can be administered every ten or 15 minutes.
While the yellow warning is in force, health authorities recommend to the entire population to adapt preventive measures such as the use of hat and light colors, water intake and extra attention to obese, elderly or fragile health. On the other hand, direct and prolonged exposure to the sun should be avoided, “strenuous” activities in hot and humid environments and the permanence in outdoor parked vehicles.</description><pubDate>2025-07-15 04:43:08</pubDate></item></channel></rss>