<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/quase-700-vagas-na-industria-do-turismo-anunciadas-para-fevereiro/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Hong Kong considers the WTO against “excessive tariffs” from the United States</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/hong-kong-pondera-recorrer-a-omc-contra-tarifas-excessivas-dos-estados-unidos/</link><description>The Hong Kong government announced yesterday that it is considering submitting an appeal to the World Trade Organization (WTO) in response to the “excessive tariffs” imposed by the United States on the products of the former British colony.
Secretary for Economic Trade and Development, Algrenon Yau, ordered a radio program to impose an additional 10% rate on imports from the territory, classifying the irrational measure. "It is a disrespect for the region status as a member of the WTO and Autonomous Customs Territory," he said. "Washington made a significant mistake by imposing these tariffs," he warned, installing the White House to "approach the decision with prudence."
The secretary said that over the past decade, the United States have registered a commercial surplus of more than $ 270 billion with Hong Kong, underlining the benefits of bilateral trade. In addition, he said that exports from the former British colony to the country represent only 0.1% of the total, suggesting a limited impact of new customs rights.
Yau noted that in recent years, Hong Kong has diversified its markets, such as Middle East, Southeast Asia and Central Europe, to mitigate “the repercussions of geopolitics”, allowing local companies to adjust export strategies.
Finally, he highlighted the resilience of the business sector of the special administrative region, which has trading chambers prepared to face the challenges that arise in this context.
China has taken US Customs Rights to the WTO and both parties now have the possibility of resolving the dispute through bilateral negotiations within the next 60 days.
After this period, the parties have the right to request the WTO the formation of a panel to resolve the commercial dispute. However, the decision of this committee may take months or even years, if one party appeals to it.
On Tuesday, Beijing announced the application of customs rights of 10 to 15% over certain US products, in retaliation of customs rights imposed by the United States to import Chinese products.
China has also announced new essential mineral export controls and has launched an investigation into monopoly practices against the Google US technological giant.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07T05:05:01+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Xi Jinping asks Zardari more security for Chinese interests in Pakistan</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/xi-jinping-pede-a-zardari-mais-seguranca-para-interesses-chineses-no-paquistao/</link><description>The Chinese president asked yesterday from the Pakistani counterpart to reinforce security measures to protect China's interests in Pakistan, after several attacks on staff, projects and Chinese institutions. The two leaders were gathered in Beijing.
 
Chinese President Xi Jinping asked yesterday from the Pakistani counterpart, Asif Ali Zardari, who reinforces security measures to protect China's interests in Pakistan, after several attacks on staff, projects and Chinese institutions.
The two leaders gathered in Beijing on the occasion of an official visit by the Pakistani leader, during which Xi also urged him to “reinforce bilateral and multilateral cooperation” against terrorism, according to a statement from the Chinese Foreign Ministry of Foreign Affairs .
In October 2024, two Chinese citizens were killed and more than a dozen people were injured in a suicidal attack at Carachi city airport and, in March of the same year, another suicide bomber killed at least five Chinese and one Pakistani, all workers From the Dasu Hydroelectric Project, in the province of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, in the northwest of the country.
During the meeting, Xi highlighted “the strong” friendship and bilateral cooperation, which turns 75 in 2025, as well as the development of the China - Pakistan economic corridor, a project that said it was committed to deepening.
Beijing has pledged to invest $ 64 billion in Pakistan infrastructure projects under the China Economic Corridor-Pakistan (CPEC), part of the Chinese Strip and Route initiative, which aims to create new commercial roads along Eurasia.
Xi also assured that Beijing faces relations with Islamabade of “a strategic perspective” and will always support the country in “safeguarding its sovereignty and territorial integrity, in the fight against terrorism and in the pursuit of a way of development appropriate to its characteristics national ”. "China appreciates the active support of Pakistan to its three global initiatives and is ready to resist unilateralism and hegemonic practices, reinforce multilateral coordination and defend the common interests of developing countries," he added.
Zardari stressed - according to the Chinese official statement - that Pakistan will remain unconditionally alongside China "regardless of the evolution of the situation."
The Pakistani president greeted Beijing's assistance to Pakistan's socioeconomic development, supported the bilateral economic corridor reinforcement proposal and said that Islamabade is willing to work with China to "defend multilateralism and free trade."
Following the meeting, XI and Zardari presided over the signing of several cooperation agreements on trade, science, technology, audiovisual means and also on the China-Paquistan economic corridor. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-07T05:05:22+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>10.2% increase in international visitors during New Year's holidays</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/aumento-de-102-nos-visitantes-internacionais-durante-os-feriados-do-ano-novo-lunar/</link><description>During the Festivities of the Lunar New Year, which took place from January 28 to February 4, Macau received approximately 1.31 million visitors, with a daily average of 163,700 tourists. Although the number of visitors in the interior of China decreased by 3.2%, international visitors increased by 10.2%, totaling about 58,000. The hotel sector also stood out, with an occupancy rate of 95%.
 
As part of the Lunar New Year festivities, which extended from January 28 to February 4, Macau registered a considerable tourist movement, receiving about 1.31 million visitors. This figure represents a slight decrease of 3.5% over the same period of the previous year, but still indicates the relevance of Macau as a tourist destination during this traditional festive time for many families in the region. The daily average of visitors was about 163,700 people, a number that was below expectations of the Tourism Services Directorate (STD), which provided for a daily average of 185,000 tourists.
On the other hand, international visitors, although constituted a smaller portion of the total, showed a considerable growth of 10.2%, totaling about 58,000 people during the festive week, or about 7,300 people a day.
In terms of comparison, the numbers show that Hong Kong tourism, although it represented a significant percentage of 17.6% in total visitors, saw a decrease of 8.9% compared to last year. On the other hand, tourists from mainland China increased 5.9% and those of Taiwan, a remarkable growth of 14.7%. However, it is the rise of international visitors who really stand out. This 10.2% increase reveals Macau's potential to attract not yet fully explored market travelers, crucial to the future of the tourist sector.
January 31st was the day of the highest movement, with the arrival of 219,000 visitors, an increase of 9.1% compared to the same day of the previous year, establishing a record of arrival of tourists since 2019 and The second largest in the history of Macau.
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) took advantage of the occasion to invest in promotional campaigns and marketing initiatives focused on international visitors, where it launched varied ads on international social networking platforms such as Facebook, Instagram and Tiktok, encouraging digital influencers to share them their experiences with local culture and diversified gastronomy of the region. The festivities included cultural events and artistic performances.
Macau maintained an average hotel occupancy rate of 95%, with an average price per quarter of about 1,839.5 patacas, which shows that, despite competition, the quality of service and tourist experience remained at a high level, according to STD.
Under the tourist experience, STD highlighted the creation of temporary pedestrian zones in the Taipa area, where they provided a new experience for international visitors who were able to explore small streets, local handicrafts and typical cuisine.
In addition, during Lunar New Year's Golden Week, the Macau Grand Prix Museum attracted a total of 7,590 visitors, which represents a 2% growth over the same period last year. February 3, corresponding to the sixth day of the festivities, registered a peak of 1,314 visitors, becoming the busiest day of the holiday.
Authorities showed interest in further diversifying their sources of visitors, seeking to leverage the growth of international markets beyond the usual flow of travelers in Greater China. In the past, Macau has benefited from visitors mainly from the Asian region, but recent data suggest that there is an opportunity to be explored to attract tourists from Europe, America and the Middle East.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07T05:07:35+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Timorese Government announces test to teachers hired and dismissed in 2023</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/governo-timorense-anuncia-teste-a-professores-contratados-e-dispensados-em-2023/</link><description>The Ministry of Education of Timor-Leste announced yesterday that it will perform a special test for teachers hired and dismissed in 2023 and have been protesting to be integrated into the teaching system.
 
“This special test will be held this year. It will begin with general secondary and vocational technical education, followed by the test for the level of basic education, according to the needs, ”said the spokesman for the Timorese Ministry of Education Filipe Rodrigues Pereira, at a press conference, in response to teachers.
In late 2023, many Timorese teachers who worked on a contract with the Ministry of Education were dismissed, failing to integrate the public education system in the country.
According to the spokesman, this special test will be exclusive to the group of teachers hired in 2023.
The Ministry of Education will provide a matrix or study guide so that candidates can prepare for the exam. “The matrix will be a general reference material for the special test. It is expected that, with good preparation, former teachers can get good results in the exam, ”he said.
The official also explained that the Ministry of Education will analyze solutions, according to the rules, for former teachers hired in 2023 who do not comply with the criteria of the special test, because they have only the diploma of secondary education. "The resolution of the problems of former teachers hired in 2023 will be done with phases, starting with the special test, and later a solution will be found for those who have only the secondary education diploma," he added.
According to the spokesman, the Minister of Education has already directed the Director General of the Ministry of Education to prepare all the necessary procedures to advance with the publication of the registration process and participation in the special test.
The leader also stated that, in previous meetings, the former teachers hired agreed with the decision of the Ministry of Education and expressed availability to participate in the test.
Filipe Rodrigues Pereira recalled that, in recent years, two tests have been performed for teacher training scholarships, in which about 200 former teacher hired teachers have been approved.
For this reason, the Ministry of Education encourages former teachers hired in 2023 who have not yet participated in the previous tests to take this opportunity to contribute to quality education in the formation of future generations in the country. “I would like to say that the solution to former teachers hired in 2023 is at the Ministry of Education. This special test was discussed with Prime Minister Kay Rala Xanana Gusmão, who is aware of the process. We hope everyone can participate in the special test within a short time, ”he said. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-07T04:58:52+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>January 2025 was the hottest ever recorded in the world</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/mes-de-janeiro-de-2025-foi-o-mais-quente-ja-registado-no-mundo/</link><description>The month of January was the hottest ever recorded and the temperature exceeded 1.75 degrees Celsius (° C) the pre-industrial level, being the 18th month of the last 19 with an average temperature above 1.5 ° W. According to the European Land Observation Service, which released the data yesterday, nor the emergence of a 'la niña' - a cyclic natural meteorological phenomenon of decreased temperature in the Pacific Ocean, in contrast to the warming caused by 'El Niño ' - He prevented last month from being the hottest worldwide ever. According to the copernicus service report, the average global air temperature was 13.23 ° C, plus 0.79 ° C than the average of 1991-2020 for January. The copernicus service specifies that the last period of 12 months (February 2024-January 2025) was 0.73 ° C above the 1991-2020 average, and 1.61 ° C above the estimated average of 1850-1900, used to define the pre-industrial level.
In Europe, the average temperature in January was 2.51 ° C above the average of January 1991-2020, the hottest second after January 2020, which was 2.64 ° C above average. In eastern Europe, including eastern Russia, it was where temperatures were higher, with Iceland, the United Kingdom, Ireland and northern France, in contrast, temperatures below average. In the rest of the world, higher than average temperatures in Canada, Alaska and Siberia, southern South America, Africa and part of Australia and Antarctica. Lower than average were recorded in the United States, Arabica Peninsula and Southeast Asia. The average sea surface temperature in January registered the second highest amount ever registered for January (20.78 ° C) only exceeded by January last year.
In hydrological terms, January was more humid than the average in regions of Western Europe and parts of Italy, Scandinavia and the Baltic countries, and drier than the average in northern the United Kingdom and Ireland in East Spain and north of the Black Sea. Arctic marine ice reached the lowest monthly extension in January, 6% below average, practically tied with January 2018. The extension of marine ice in Antarctica was 5% lower than average.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07T05:00:14+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Spelling (4): writing and the law</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/ortografia-4-a-escrita-e-a-lei/</link><description>Since the mid -century twelve, as the 'pact of the parents', the news of guarantors', or that of the derision song' witnessed 'pact', sometimes host the lord of Navarre ', until 1911, the Portuguese wrote Portuguese without any need of legal protection, agreement or other law, which told them how to write their language.
The spelling of the Portuguese language, as we saw in the previous column, had two large phases, the phonetic phase during the Middle Ages and the etymological phase that begins to plant its roots with the Renaissance. The process of progressive maturation through which the writing of the Portuguese language has passed almost spontaneous as it cannot be glimpsed an external guiding line that predetermined the way to follow; The writing of Portuguese was accommodating, if not naturally, at least with relative naturalness to the historical circumstances it was crossing. This evolution, which goes from learning to represent the sounds of the language that the people speak on the street by wearing it with the colors of the classic culture from which they, after all, derive, gradually erect a modus scribendi, or a tradition Spelling that in the century of Eça, Camilo and Garrett was already solidly built. This does not mean that there was no variation in the way of writing, May or mother, father or PAE, Paulo or Paolo, among other examples, were more or less the will of the customer. This in no way represented the situation of chaos, or as it was written then, orthographic chaos that often reads there attributed to this time. He who wrote had a certain latitude within which they could employ their own criteria in the way they represented the language in writing. This to us today may seem strange, accustomed as we are to rigid spelling rules imposed by law. It is not that anything would then be accepted, in thisness or in -science would be immediately recognized as spelling errors, not because the state would determine it, but because the known orthographic tradition of all naturally led to this conclusion.
The rules of Portuguese spelling prior to 1911 were built through tradition and use. The trends that marked the spelling tradition were dictated by the way writers such as Eça, Garrett, Camilo, among many others, wrote Portuguese and who served as a model or example for their contemporary society. With the appearance of editorial houses and newspapers, they also influenced the way of writing. In addition, there were institutions, such as universities or academies, not to mention the state itself, which then communicated with its citizens exclusively through writing, although Facebook or Twitter did not exist yet, which They also served as an example with regard to which spelling trends to follow.
The existence of more or less rigid spelling rules obeys an objective necessity. As we have seen in this column, the whole living language has within it variation, dialopic or regional variation, diastratic or social variation, diaphasic or registration variation, not to mention style variations. Writing, like grammar, must be stable, congruent and logical so as not to compromise the communicative act; In a word, we cannot write as you give us real veneta. The question is who has protection about the national language? Who has the right to determine what is right or wrong in the way people write their language?
Between the need for a 'stable' writing and the question of whom it is necessary to fix this stability there is a conflict. In Portugal, this issue has never been raised, since since 1911 it has been assumed, at least implicitly, that it is up to the state to determine what is orthographically right or wrong. Such an attitude is, by the way, according to what, in general, happens in our country where they are fully accepted natural degrees of interference from the state in the lives of citizens who in other places would be considered absolutely intolerable.
 
The spelling reforms
The 1996 spelling reform was, in fact, contested, but the Portuguese State, in its interpretation of its powers, felt no need to explain itself, much less to correct the path by which it once again decided to embark. This path is, for someone as cynical as the author of this text, that of being subservient, not of his people, but almost everything that comes from outside. Outside it is good! The history of spelling agreements in Portugal seems to be led by wills lodged outside the borders of our little rectangle and who always find someone willing to please.
The very first spelling reform of Portuguese with official value was, not in Brazil, but in Portugal and was, in fact, quite contested on the other side of the Atlantic. However, the 1911 reform follows and follows the baton of the reform proposed by the Brazilian Academy of Letters of 1907 whose objective, clearly exposed in his declaration of intent, was to end the etymological writing and adopt the phonetic principle. The 1911 spelling reform, however, was not as far as the proposal by the Brazilian Academy and tried, as much as possible, to maintain a certain balance between the etymological origin of the language and its phonetic production in the standard variety. Thus, to give only one example, the p-mudo disappears in the word 'writing', because it has no function, but remains in 'baptism' because there points out the open production of vowel A in an unstressed position.
In the 1911 reform, were mainly words of Greek origin, such as Psychology, Physic Philosophia or Grammatica, the ones that suffered the most from the transatlantic modernist cravings associated with the ever-enthusiastic Republican Sanha of some of ours, compare with the post result post -Acorde Psychology, Physics, Philosophy and Grammar. This reform was, in its generality or at particular points, very contested at the time. Fernando Pessoa, who led to the disappearance of the ipsilon, under the heteronymy of Bernardo Soares, compares it, in the book of the restlessness, the "direct sputum that disgusts me regardless of whom the spit [a]."
It did not exist in 1995, or in the years prior to that date, at least, a cry of the Portuguese people who demanded, to shouts through the streets, a reform of their written language, nor did the Portuguese authors go on foot Indian line to Fatima beg for the orthographic miracle. It was once again something from outside that determined what we have to accept as right or wrong today. The excuse was that an alleged uniformity of the Portuguese written around the world would make our writers 'bestsellers' in the Brasis and other Lusitanian lands of language. As I mentioned here in the past, the Portuguese authors are known cannot yet lead the lives of Hollywood stars thanks to the dividends of the international star that the new spelling has yet provided them. They are still waiting!
Despite some sowing-the fire of the usual-the saying whose agreement has avenged there and the Portuguese in a mixture of their usual Laissez Faire and the very supine 'fired-the-ultimate', the two post-revolutionary versions of the old 'Um- Brand-killer people 'from Ti' António de Santa Comba, there swallowed the syrup all the harvested. And what a syrup!, There is no cough that can resist. Or maybe there is, by view, the Angolans have already begun to cough again.
In Macao the syrup was not prescribed, apart from scarce exceptions, here writes everything to cough. The problem of Portuguese in Macao is different, but the author of this text prefers to pass Silent about this matter, it will not be that someone will shoot him when he goes through the street guilty of injuring the sensibilities of others.
 
The German spelling reform of 1996
The Germans are less than taking syrups without proper recipe. In 1996, when Germany, Austria, Switzerland, and Liechtenstein signed an orthographic agreement that intended to simplify and make some rules of German spelling more logical, barely knew members of the working group for the elaboration of the new rules which 'Ràí vineyards!
The 1996 Orthographic Reform follows a discussion that has existed in German society since almost the end of the war. In 1980, when Germany was still divided into two, it was decided to form an international working group to discuss spelling reform. In 1992, this group published a first renovation proposal that, in 1993, was scrutinized by 43 working groups of the four nations involved in the process. After reviewing certain more controversial aspects, in 1994 the proposal for the revision of German spelling was ready to be adopted. In June 1996, the states (Bundesländer) of Germany, Austria, Switzerland and Liechtenstein decided that the new rules would come into force in August 1998, with a transition period until 2005.
Although some Länder's from Germany had decided to introduce the reform in the 1996-97 academic year, the reform found great opposition from the general public and many German institutions.
In the same year of the signing of the agreement, during the Frankfurt Book Fair, believed as the largest book fair in the world, a petition against the implementation of the reform was signed by hundreds of people, including some of the most sleepless names in the literary universe German, such as Günter Grass (1927-2015), which would win the Nobel Prize from Literature in 1999. Several initiatives against reform, both at national and training, in 1997, of the 'Association for The spelling and conservation of the German language 'that described itself with the epithet of' Initiative Gegen Die Rechtschtschreiberm), or even state level, as the popular referendum with which, in September 1998, rejected the reform in the state of Schleswig-Holstein. (The result of the referendum would be annulled later by vote in the local parliament).
Several newspapers and media also criticized the reform and some, including Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung, one of Germany's most influential newspapers, refused to use the new spelling.
As a result of all the commotion that the implementation of the Orthographic Agreement caused in the German society in June 1997, it was introduced in the German Federal Parliament (Bundestag), a multiparty motion (BTDrucks 13/7028) that led to a public hearing of linguists and jurists regarding the most controversial aspects of the agreement. In March 1998, on the recommendation of the Commission on Legal Affairs, the German Federal Parliament passed Resolution BT 13/224, p. 20567 in which it expresses its concern for the 'high degree of legal and linguistic uncertainty' that the reform had caused in society while claiming that 'the language used by citizens develops constantly, progressively and organic through an agreement between speakers'; The Federal Parliament concludes that, ultimately, 'language belongs to the people' (Die Sprache Gehört Dem Volk).
In fact, the German Parliament decided not to decide anything and, instead, the ministers responsible for implementing the agreement, taking into account the opinion of different quadrants of German society and working together with the various states of the federal state, seeking achieve a 'consensus within the speaker community' (Konsens in der sprachgemeinschaft).
Given the state's inction, in May 1998, 594 German language and literature teachers filed a complaint to the German Federal Constitutional Court (BundesverFuSungsGericht) since German law allows individuals to file complaints (VerfassungsBeschwerde) directly to the Constitutional Court whenever they consider that their constitutional rights have been violated. The reasoning for this complaint was based on the violation of both individual rights (Personlichkeitsrechts) of their children as well as the law of parents to actively participate in the educational process of their children, as provided by German law.
This complaint would be rejected on July 14, 1998, when the Constitutional Court issued sentence 1 BVR 1640/97, in which it declares that 'the State is not constitutionally prevented from regulating the correct spelling of the German language for teaching in schools . The Constitution (Grundgesetz) also does not contain a general prohibition of creative interventions in spelling. The sentence that appears in only four points that barely fill a page is followed by 34 pages with 169 paragraphs with the rations (Gründe) that underlie the rejection of the complaint.
Paragraph 122 of the grounds of the judgment that ‘the Constitution does not contain any prohibition that considers spelling as an object outside the regulatory scope of the State. Such a prohibition does not result from the fact that the State was not expressly authorized to regulate spelling. The Constitution is not based on the principle that each measure taken by the state should be based on a constitutional authorization. On the contrary, it is based on the general authority of the state to act on the common good, even if [the constitution] imposes certain restrictions on it, both formal and material. Under these circumstances, the prohibition of regulation [of spelling] cannot result from the lack of constitutional authorization, but only from constitutional limits to state decisions. ' In the same line, the next paragraph adds that ‘the nature of the language does not mean that there is an absolute prohibition of regulation. The assumption that the language 'belongs' to the people cannot justify such a prohibition because 'belonging' does not express an attribution in the legal sense, nor the underlying thesis to the assumption, if it had legal content, could prevent the involvement of the state. The fact that an object does not 'belong' to the state does not prevent the state from subjecting its use to certain rules. May language not emanate from the state and develop through social use, does not prevent its regulation by the State. 'These two paragraphs deal with the' right 'of the state to act on spelling; Paragraph 99, on the other hand, presents a justification for the interference of the State in the spelling of the language because it argues the resolution that, although the language preceded the existence of the state, spelling guidelines are necessary for 'teachers and students to know what they have to teach and learn '. The decision of the German Constitutional Court focuses mainly on problems related to teaching because these were the main concerns raised by the complaint of language and literature teachers who signed the petition.
These legal considerations could perhaps be extrapolated to the Portuguese case since the Portuguese Constitution also makes no mention of the state's powers in the regulation of language spelling. Article 9, in its paragraph f) only says that it is the fundamental task of the state to 'ensure permanent teaching and appreciation, defend the use and promote the international diffusion of the Portuguese language'.
What is here at stake is not, of course, any linguistic proximity between Portuguese and German, not even similarities or disparities in the process of spelling evolution of the two languages, but the fact that in Germany the German Constitutional Court was called to pronounce on the legitimacy of the State in this type of decisions and, consequently, their legality. The Portuguese situation is only comparable to the German as, as in the German case, the state was listed from a right that cousin could not be yours.
To what extent this example of the Jurisprudence of the German Court can be extended to the Portuguese case and, thus, justify the intervention of the state in the orthographic issue bumps into the problem of the disparate historical situation of the two languages ​​with regard to the development of their respective orthographics and to the relationship of this same development with the state itself.
Until the mid -eighteenth century, the spelling of German suffered from a great lack of uniformity. Part of this problem derived from the fact that the spoken language also varied from region to region. The regional variation of the German is very different from that of Portuguese as dialects, especially in the north, called low-alem (Plattdeutsch), can be considered languages ​​and are, in many chaos, closer to the Dutch than German and the German dialects, especially from southern Germany.
The translation of the Bible by Luther, the New Testament in 1522 and the old man in 1534, provided the first spelling model for a written standard German, but it was only in the late eighteen century that would appear a standard uniform spelling for the German language. It should be borne in mind that Germany, as a country, until the formation of the German Empire in 1871 had never been a unified state like Portugal since the Middle Ages. The formation of the German state in 1871 requires the constitution of standard German (Standardhochdeutsch) that serves as the state's official language and has a uniform spelling. Thus, in 1876, the Prussian Minister of Culture brings together the first spelling conference that, based on the proposals of Rudolf von Raumer (1815 to 1876), establishes for the first time the rules of the Prussian and Bavarian spelling of the German, which would be compiled , in 1880, by Konrad Duden (1829 to 1911) in its German language spelling dictionary.
But the question was not resolved! In 1901, a second conference had to be summoned because the results of the former did not please everyone and thus begins the history of the various interventions of the German state in the spelling of his language.
The differences between the Portuguese case and the German case are evident, the state intervention in the German spelling responds to an objective sociopolitical necessity. It could even be said that until state intervention in 1876 there was no German spelling. In the case of Portuguese, when in 1911, the state decided to intervene for the first time in the writing of the language, the Portuguese spelling was well established and of good health. Political intervention in the Portuguese spelling of the time was ideology in nature and not the answer to an evident social problem, even though the issue of high levels of literacy was evoked at the time. Like the 1996 reform no longer put into our writers' pockets, the 1911 reform did not diminish illiteracy rates, on the contrary, given the confusion that the First Republic brought with it, illiteracy even rose.
Another evident difference is that, since 1901, the German state paid attention to society and as a result of its stance, in 2004, its most controversial points of the 1996 reform were renovated.
 
The right to error?
The German Constitutional Court Resolution was, in a way, limited to the terms of the original complaint and, as such, most of its 169 paragraphs deals with the problems presented in the complaint. Notwithstanding this limitation, one of the interesting conclusions of the Court's resolution is the suggestion that only in teaching, and perhaps in state institutions, although the text does not refer to it, is that the use of new spelling is mandatory. Resolution never explicitly says it, but seems to suggest it; Paragraph 155 even says that 'the introduction of spelling reform in school classes does not affect the economic freedom of choosing companies to (…) to decide or against the conversion of their products and business processes to the new spelling.' What newspapers as important as Die Zeit, Neue Zürcher Zeitung, Süddeutsche Zeitung, and even Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung have decided to adopt their own spelling norms confirm this interpretation.
 
In the form of epilogue
The truth is that in the German case, the controversy and social pressure began since in 2004, even before the end of the transition period, the reform was revised and the most controversial issues resolved, if not all, almost all.
Here on earth, fado is another; The state gives, the people receive.
There was still out there to feed hope that the Grand National Commoner, which lives in that pink house in Belém, and that for the author of this text represents one of the best arguments in favor of Portugal's return to the monarchy, not Because, as D. Duarte says in his old age, God keep him!, he behaves like a king should behave but, considering that being a head of state should be something more than grandfather songs of the nation, do something, At least in relation to the most contentious parts of the agreement, but it did not serve. And now that it is busy with the choice of the new rental of the pink house, it does not seem to have time for these bagatels that only consume these unoccupied who are dedicated to writing or reading.
I don't know if they still remember the 1964 movie 'Mary Poppins', based on a series of Australian author Pamela Travers (1899-1996), which tells the story of a Dry AMA with magical powers capable of cheering rigid Victorian education . Its many lessons came in the form of songs - this was not a movie from the sixties and on top of Walt Disney - and among these was the famous Cantilena 'a spoonful of sugar makes the medicine go down', that is, something like that Like 'a sugar spoon makes the medicine easier to take.' Now, contrary to what we watched in Portugal, when it was not even necessary to get the spoon, the Germans needed much more than a spoon full of sugar to swallow the potion.
Oh, these mild customs…</description><pubDate>2025-02-07T04:57:03+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Association concerned with landscape impact of the viaduct between zones A and B</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/associacao-preocupada-com-impacto-paisagistico-do-viaduto-entre-as-zonas-a-e-b/</link><description>The construction of the viaduct between zone A and zone B of new landfills in NAPE is worrying about the association of Macau synergy due to a possible impact on the landscape of the Macao Historic Center. Heard by the association, architect André Liu was disillusioned with the future demolition of the upper passage attached to the Cultural Center, while urban planner Lam Iek Chit warned of the impact on the leisure zone of the Kun Iam statue. Urbanist Ferreira Manuel IOK PUI defends the proposal of a road tunnel instead of the viaduct.
 
The Macao Synergy Association alerts to the impacts of the viaduct construction between zone A and Zone B of the new landfills, namely in the Macao Historic Center landscape, as well as the spaces of the Cultural Center, Science Center and leisure zone of the marginal of the statue of Kun Iam.
The project has raised concerns since the government announced its plan, with the maximum height of the viaduct the most discussed theme. The association of synergy, currently led by Johnson Ian and Deputy Ron Lam, spoke to several experts in a video analysis, where they criticized the lack of consideration by the government before advancing the venture.
Architect André Liu expressed concern about the impact of the works on the Macao Cultural Center complex, showing opposition that the government demolishes the superior crossing of the Macao Cultural Center because of the works of the A and B viaduct. Cultural has in front of him facing the sea and his rear turned to the guide lighthouse, demonstrating continuity. The existing higher passage is part of the Cultural Center and is an extension of its axis, linking the sea, the city and the mountains, ”he said.
André Liu recalled that the Portuguese Administration of Macao launched a conception contest of the Cultural Center, being a first enclosure for cultural activities, requiring the construction to be representative and can be seen when people pass from the boat, bridge or helicopter and look to Macau. In this case, the viaduct could obstruct the landscape view of the Cultural Center and hinder the connection between the complex and the sea. He also mentioned the Sino-American architect Ieoh Ming Pei who “also took into account Eco between with the Cultural Center when he designed the Macao Science Center,” he said.
The construction work of the viaduct is now underway. According to the Directorate of Public Works Services (DSOP), the viaduct will be located between the Macau Peninsula and Zone A, will connect to the west with the roundabout of the Macao Science Center and Dr. Sun Yat-Sen Avenue, crossing, In the east, the Friendship Bridge, and will end in Zone A, interconnecting with the Macau Bridge.
The project is about 3.2km long, with the maximum altimetric quota of 25.8 meters. In this matter, DSOP had removed the possibility of the height exceeding the allowed provided for in the current law, justifying that this is not a project to build buildings, so it is not applicable to regulate the order of Chief Executive No. 83 /2008.
In turn, urban planner Lam Iek Chit emphasized that the city's positioning is a Tourism and Leisure Center, and the Center of Science, the Cultural Center, the Art Museum, the Kun Iam statue and the leisure zone “ They created a synergotic effect. ” “The access bridge of the Zona A and B viaduct will be next to the Kun Iam Statue Marginal Leisure Zone playground. Imagine that children who play there will have many vehicles in the future to pass and honk behind them, which is a very bad situation, ”he said.
Lam Iek Chit also fears that the viaduct will cause more traffic problems in the Nape area, namely in the time of peak traffic. The urban planner also warned of the future removal of more than 600 trees in the area, which harms the environment and is a “lack of respect for residents”.
Urbanist Ferreira Manuel IOK PUI condemned the adoption of the construction of a viaduct instead of a road tunnel, indicating that the government “did not fully evaluate and respected the architectural characteristics and the use of the surrounding land” when the project advanced. "It is unfortunate that the viaduct of zones A and B will completely harm the view of the important cultural facilities of the sea waterfront and cause more emissions and noise in the marginal of the statue of Kun Iam," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07T05:06:28+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese Astrology and Zodiac - Part I</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/astrologia-e-zodiaco-chines-parte-i/</link><description>Astrology plays a primordial role in Chinese culture. In their analyzes, in addition to making use of one of the oldest and most accurate Lunissolar calendars, considering both the movements of the sun and the moon, the main Chinese astrological schools present methods that are based on the relationship sky and earth, relating the 5 Qi movements, also known as the 5 elements (fire, earth, metal, water and wood) and their yin and yang energy cycles.
Unlike western astrology whose sole reference is the solar calendar and, consequently, the land translation movements, being the attribution of the signs based on the months of the year, Chinese astrology makes use of the Lunissolar calendar to define the beginning of the year and the respective sign, thus being an entire year governed by the energy of a single sign. Thus, and taking into account the combination of each of the 12 signs with the 5 elements, it will take 60 years to end a cycle (the current cycle began in 1984).
To add to that relationship with heaven and heavenly energy, the seasons also influence local beliefs. It should be noted the title of “Son of the Heavens”, attributed to the Chinese Emperor who, depending on the station station resided in the respective palace, built taking into account all the requirements and specificities (Spring, Summer, Autumn and Winter Palace).
Being the Chinese astrological calendar based on a cyclic energy calendar, it is quite common to consult past periods with the same energy combinations in order to predict the best moments for the success of certain events, such as marking wedding dates, records Building, job contracts or even a haircut. Among families it is quite common that special attention to the year and day of birth of the descendants be paid, as it directly influences their personality and prosperity.
It is undeniable the seduction that surrounds Chinese astrology, with millennial beliefs and traditions that bewitches and win even the largest of skeptics. You do not know Portuguese here that you do not know your Chinese sign and that, when visits to Portugal, do not clarify family and friends about their signs and meanings, unable to hide a certain pride. It is case to say that in macanese lands we become gullible for coexistence.
 
Francisca Beja
Interior design and architecture project manager</description><pubDate>2025-02-07T04:58:14+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Executive reinforces awareness work on youth crime</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/executivo-reforca-trabalho-de-sensibilizacao-a-criminalidade-juvenil/</link><description>Security tutelage said it was reinforcing the dissemination of information on the prevention of youth delinquency through online platforms, especially with advertising content that integrates “elements of interest to young people” such as music and short films. The Judiciary Police added that its Wechat anti-bullshit mini-program has obtained more than 50,000 visits by the end of last year, since its launch in April 2024.
 
Authorities are attributing “great importance” to the work of raising awareness of youth crime on social networking platforms, the Secretary's Office for Security said. In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Lam Lon Wai, the authorities pointed out that online platforms are an important channel of social life and information for young people, so they are used to publicize information about criminal prevention.
Police officials said they have created official accounts on social platforms such as Facebook, Instagram, Youtube, Wechat, Tiktok and The Little Red Note, among others, to publish information against crime. The publications “incorporate some of the advertising content with elements of interest to young people,” said the secretary's office for security, giving as an example a video of a rap -style song by the public security police body.
According to the body, in addition, the Judicial Police launched an anti-drug short film, having invited an Olympic champion, Chinese table tennis athlete, to film, as well as other short films on 'bullying' in schools and bets on the internet .
The Judicial Police, quoted in the answer, recalled that an anti-bullshit mini-program was launched at Wechat in April last year “which attracted comprehensive attention” of society. "The total number of visits was over 50,000 by the end of December last year," he said. It is recalled that the mini-program offers four functions, including 'survey at the scope of the scope', which has been used more than 23,000 times by users to perform risk assessments on the number of the received call, email, banks and doubtful accounts. Users, through the program, gave more than 1,400 clues about the police to the police.
Lam Lon Wai questioned the government about the prevention measures of the new youth crime through the new media used by young people in particular. In his questioning, the deputy warned of the tendency to increase drug transport crimes, telephone throws and cyber crimes committed by young people.
"According to the recently released data, in the first three quarters of 2024, there were 89 cases of juvenile delinquency, an increase of 14 cases (18.7%) compared to 2023," he said. The deputy also stressed that the 3rd quarter of the year coincides with the summer holidays, and “as free time young people are more exposed to crimes, there was an increase of 26 cases of youth delinquency compared to the 2nd quarter ”.
Wong Sio Chak's office, in response, said police launched more than 900 crime prevention activities aimed mainly at young people, parents or teaching staff, who had over 100,000 participants. "Given the growing tendency of youth delinquency during prolonged holidays or large events, police intensified prevention and control measures, including the youth toxicodependency prevention campaign during summer holidays," he said.
Authorities also assured that they have been working to raise awareness against phrauds with telecommunications and drug -related crimes targeting new students who arrive in Macao to study. Police also said they had worked closely with students' counseling services for “behavioral deviation prevention” and “positive behaviors”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07T05:08:09+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Tesla launches her biggest discounts in China and prolongs price war in the sector</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/tesla-lanca-os-seus-maiores-descontos-na-china-e-prolonga-guerra-de-precos-no-sector/</link><description>The American Tesla electric vehicle manufacturer announced yesterday the largest price reduction ever for his model 3 in China, part of a fierce price war among the main brands in the country.
From yesterday, Tesla is offering an insurance allowance equivalent to about $ 1,100 and a five -year payment plan without interest. This is the first time the two incentives are combined. The initial price of rear -wheel drive model 3 will be reduced in China to about $ 31,200.
Buyers will benefit special charging programs for vehicles and will be eligible for other public subsidies and Tesla offers worth up to $ 8,000.
In recent days, other brands, such as Xpeng, Nio and IM Motors, have also announced interest -free payment plans, entry payment reductions or price reductions in some of their models.
According to sources of the sector cited by the YICAI News Portal, sales of major brands in several dealers have fallen more than 40% in January, in homologous terms, affected by the approach of the high season of December and the usual softening during the Lunar New Year , the main festive season of the country.
The Secretary General of the CPCA Employers Association, Cui Dongshu, predicted that the price war among car manufacturers in China will continue throughout this year, in a context of “extremely fierce” competition, although it has also stated that sales could increase Thanks to the “renewal plan” multimillionaire promoted by the government, which provides for the assignment of subsidies in the exchange of old articles for new ones.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07T05:05:21+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Contemporary Reflections by Tsang Tseng Tseng about an millennial art</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/reflexoes-contemporaneas-de-tsang-tseng-tseng-sobre-uma-arte-milenar/</link><description>Tsang Tseng Tseng is an emerging macao artist who stands out for mixing Chinese traditions with contemporary practices. His works were recently in Goa, representing Macao at the 30th anniversary of the East Foundation delegation in India. Tsang seeks to explore new narratives with experiments on the culture of traditional Chinese painting. His work causes reflections on identity and preservation of art, consolidating it as a relevant voice in the current art scene. Speaking to the end, he discussed the importance of technique and artistic development for new generations.
 
Tsang Tseng Tseng is a rising artist in the contemporary artistic world of the territory, being recognized for his excellent technique and the reflections that accompany his work around art and culture. In a context where globalization and tradition often collide, Tsang can find a subtle balance that not only preserves cultural legacy, but also updates it, providing new interpretations that speak to the modern audience.
He recently inaugurated another solo exhibition, entitled “Rhythms of Chinese paint at the São Paulo Church in Macau”, with works on Macau at the Rui Cunha Foundation gallery. Then he took works to Goa, with the support of the Oriente Foundation (FO), after being prominent in his participation in the Fall Salon, to represent the territory community in the 30th anniversary of the FO in Goa delegation, with deeper work and others who present their most artistic side, with paintings about fans.
With a promising start in 2008, she was the winner of the New Talent Award at the 24th Collective Exhibition of Macao Artists, awarded by the Institute for Macao Municipal Affairs, where she first exposed in the prestigious space of the Macao Military Club.
Also known as San Zhan, the artist shared her perspectives on the fusion of the Chinese tradition with contemporary artistic approaches in statements to the end. “My inspiration comes from the history of Chinese education and culture. While studying tradition, I also carefully observe the environment that surrounds me in Macao, ”he said.
This duality is a constant present in his works, which incorporate the softness and elegance of the painting of the Jiangnan region, where he began his formation, while adapting to the vibrant and urban influences of the present.
Its approach, however, is not limited to the mere representation of the real. Tsang states that when he looks at nature, he is not only attached to what he sees at the moment. "My works are compositions that include small details and stories, almost as a 'collection' of my experiences and emotions."
This ability to capture the essence of moments and transform them into artistic expressions is one of the aspects that distinguishes their practice, offering the public a multifaceted but essentially intimate experience.
 
Technique as a pillar for creation
 
His formation at the Chinese Academy of Art in Hangzhou, under the direction of the master in landscape painting Lin Hai Zhong, is a fundamental pillar in his work, says Tsang. "The technique is an essential component that must be dominated so that emotions truly reflect through painting," he says.
An interesting aspect of its trajectory is its commitment to the formation of the new generations of artists as a professor at the University of Macau. Tsang has revealed that he often comes across students who focus too much on surface aesthetics. “Many art students focus only on creating something visually attractive at first, looking for perfection. I encourage them to focus on brush technique and control, which are essential for art narrative, ”he explains, demonstrating their genuine involvement with artistic education and professional development of other future artists.
By reflecting on the reception of his work by the artistic community, Tsang is expressed in an optimistic way. “The city offers several opportunities for artists. It is gratifying to know that my style is recognized, ”he said.
In addition to painting, Tsang is also open to interactions with other artistic forms. “When invitations arise for performances, I see this as an opportunity to expand my practice. These experiences bring a new dimension to my work and allow a more direct connection with the public, ”he reveals.
The willingness to experiment demonstrates its clear objective of presenting contemporary art as a space of continuous evolution, where new forms of expression can enrich artistic discourse. On certain occasions, the artist has made “live” paintings, where he uses traditional fans as a basis for small works of paint paint.
The dialogue between the past and the present is a constant in Tsang's work. Throughout his speech, he commented on the influence of the masters of painting that preceded it, specifically citing Wu Li, a painter of the Ming and Qing dynasties who was also in Macao. “Imagine how Wu Li would interpret the macau landscape today offers me a new perspective. This reflection leads me to think about the intersection between the history of art and my current practice, ”he explained, highlighting the importance of pondering cultural heritage as something new is created.
The challenges of the creative process are an undeniable reality that Tsang faces with a pragmatic look. “It is often difficult to maintain a connection with a work in which so much time and emotion has been invested. However, what really matters is the creative freedom that can be achieved, ”he said, recognizing the complexity that characterizes the life of an artist. This sincerity regarding the difficulties faced during the creative process is, in itself, an important lesson on the necessary resilience in artistic practice, the artist points out.
By approaching the future, Tsang expresses a clear desire to continue to explore and expand their practices. “I want to develop new series that contains different stories and reflect the evolution of my own perspective. Art must be a reflection of who we are and the time we live in, ”he concludes.
Tsang Tseng Tseng stands out for his approach that unites tradition and modernity, offering the viewer a vision of what contemporary painting can represent today. Your work is not simply an aesthetic appreciation; It is also a contribution to a broader debate on culture and identity, something that he himself makes very clear. In embracing its cultural roots while adapting to the new currents of the art world, Tsang offers a space, on screens, for the ending reflections of Chinese history and what currently represents, something that resonates not only in Macao, but also in artistic contexts global.
This balance between traditional and modern elements, coupled with its contemplative and technical approach worked, establishes Tsang as a relevant artist in the contemporary landscape. His art aims to continue to challenge norms and question the boundaries between what is considered traditional and what is innovative, making the artist an important voice in conversation about the future of art in the region.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Delegation of the East Foundation in Goa: 30 years to reinforce historical bonds</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/delegacao-da-fundacao-oriente-em-goa-30-anos-a-reforcar-os-vinculos-historicos/</link><description>In the year of celebrating the 50th anniversary of restoration of diplomatic relations between Portugal and India, the delegation of the Oriente Foundation in Goa celebrates three decades of activity. The objective has been to reinforce the historical ties that connect Portugal and India. At the end, Paulo Gomes, Delegate of the Oriente Foundation in Goa, highlights the role of the body in supporting the teaching of the Portuguese language, in the arts and the recovery of the territory, for example.
 
ANDRÉ VINAGRE
*Proteced Email*
 
They have now celebrated 30 years since the East Foundation established a delegation in Goa, India. This year, the 50th anniversary of the restoration of diplomatic relations between Portugal and India are also marked. Through initiatives linked to the arts, heritage and the Portuguese language, the Goa delegation of the Oriente Foundation aims to value the bonds between the two countries.
To mark the date, Carlos Monjardino, chairman of the East Foundation Board of Directors, as well as João Amorim, a vowel of the Board of Directors, were in Goa, between January 27 and February 2, also being present at the second annual meeting of the delegations of Goa, Macao and Timor-Leste. Under the celebrations, the delegation of Macao made known in Goa the works of an artist of the region, Tsang Tseng Tseng (see page 12); And the Mount Music Festival was also held, one of the most important events in Goa's cultural calendar, which featured the performance of Portuguese fadista Cuca Roseta. Also within the scope of the ephemeris, yesterday were performed concerts of violin and Portuguese guitar in the Indian Council for Cultural Relations (ICCR), in the Indian capital, Nova Deli.
“The Oriente Foundation is not only a bridge between East and West, but also between different parts of the East where Portuguese speaks and where there are delegations that collaborate with each other,” reads the official note about the commemorations of the ephemeris, which also highlights That, over the last 30 years, “the delegation of the East Foundation in India has supported Portuguese language teaching projects in Goa's secondary schools, but also contributed to the diffusion of culture, not only with support in the areas of music, theater , dance and literature, as well as through festivals, concerts, seminars, conferences, publications and exhibitions of Indian and Portuguese artists, with exchanges between the two countries. ”
 
A “determining role” in Portugal-India relations
 
Paulo Gomes is the delegate of the Oriente Foundation in Goa since June 2022. At the end, he highlights the “determining role” of the delegation in relations between the two countries.
The official begins by pointing out that the presence of three decades of the institution in Goa emerged "in a fundamental period to again establish ties between Portugal and India". After the restoration of diplomatic relations between India and Portugal, in 1975, “practically nothing existed, from a cultural point of view, in the relations between Portugal and Goa and Portugal and India”, and it was then that Carlos Monjardino, the suggestion of Mário Soares, decided to implement a delegation of the Oriente Foundation in Goa. After the Indian authorities realized that the intention was not political or religious, but cultural and educational, the Indian central government gave the project green light.
Paulo Gomes highlights, in the first place, the role of the delegation regarding the teaching of Portuguese language. The Foundation pays the fees to about 20 Goes teachers who teach Portuguese in 20 secondary schools in a universe of 1,100 students. “We replaced the government and paid the fees of these teachers, which is also a way to keep Portuguese alive in Goa,” says the official. Alongside this, Portuguese courses and workshops are organized for teachers.
In the Portuguese Language teaching, there is also a program of scholarships in which it is awarded every three or four scholarships for higher education students and researchers who want to go to India to do their studies, or, on the contrary, Indian researchers and teachers who want to go to Portugal.
Then there is also the area of ​​performing arts: “We have an art gallery with a permanent exhibition of a brilliant artist Goes, António Xavier Trindade, who has also been a good milestone even for Indians who visit us from other states and who They find the collection beautiful. ” There are also awards for visual arts projects and the aforementioned Mount Music Festival, for example.
Another area of ​​performance of the East Foundation delegation in Goa has to do with publication and literature. “We have our own annual publications about Goa, about India, an endless set of conferences, workshops that we also developed here at the Foundation, with writers, Portuguese, Brazilian, Indian authors,” says Paulo Gomes.
Another “essential” aspect has to do with the recovery of heritage, essentially heritage with connections to Portugal, such as churches and chapels, but also some Hindu heritage. Finally, highlighting the social action of the delegation in Goa. "We have had an important role here, either to support government organizations or to support the elderly or orphanages," says the delegate.
For Paulo Gomes, the biggest achievement of the delegation has been the preservation of the teaching of the Portuguese language: "The great achievement was the young people of today could be in schools to learn Portuguese, having contact with the Portuguese language." Another victory, he says, has to do with “the opening of the Foundation for Diversity”. "Having acceptance and recognition of government entities, civil society, entrepreneurs, is something that makes us very pleased and I believe it is the greatest achievement," he says.
Reinforcing that the relationship of the delegation with all the sectors of the Goa Society “is fantastic”, Paulo Gomes underlines: “We do not interest politics, we do not get involved in religion, we are here not to lose what was the almost 450 years of Portuguese presence here, the historical, religious, cultural and patrimonial heritage that exists between the two countries ”.
The foundation's delegate says that for the future, a new initiative is planned that will want to give new opportunities to abandoned girls who are in orphanages in the aspect of linguistic formation or the arts, for example.
 
 
BOX:
 
Delegation based in the emblematic neighborhood of Fontainhas
 
The delegation of the Oriente Foundation in Goa is headquartered in Panjim. The building is a Portuguese manorial house of Portuguese influence, located in the emblematic neighborhood of the Fontainhas. The headquarters has an art gallery with the permanent exhibition of artist Goes António Xavier Trindade. The building is “one of the central points of connection and contribution to Goa's vibrant cultural life,” says the Oriente Foundation.
 
 
BOX
 
Goa by Paulo Varela Gomes
 
Paulo Varela Gomes, a Portuguese writer deceased in 2016, was the delegate of the Oriente Foundation in Goa between 1996 and 1998 and then between 2007 and 2009. The author published several texts about his passages through India, namely “Once Upon a Goa”, Winner of the Great Romance and soap opera of the Portuguese Writers Association 2016. The book accompanies Graham Greene, a British citizen who arrives in 1963 with scarce resources and by little orthodox means, being systematically confused with a Portuguese infiltrate. In the work of Paulo Varela Gomes, the protagonist states: “This is what I will remember better in Goa: the voice in Concanim telling strange stories, the howl of wild dogs to go down the hills, the golden light of the rice, rice, The feeling of deep country peace. Industrialization will eventually arrive. ”</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>End of US exemptions for low value imports can subtract 0.2% to Chinese GDP</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/fim-de-isencoes-nos-eua-para-importacoes-de-baixo-valor-pode-subtrair-02-ao-pib-chines/</link><description>The end of tariff exemptions on Chinese products valued at less than $ 800 can reduce China's economic growth rate by 0.2% this year, according to estimates by the Japanese investment bank Nomura.
 
A report published yesterday by this entity places the value of packages sent by Chinese companies such as Temu or Shein to the US, taking advantage of the exemption that has been in force so far, about $ 46 billion (44.2 billion euros ), which represents 11% of total US imports from China.
In addition to this impact on GDP, 10% rates or other additional costs applied to this type of packets will also translate into a 1.3% reduction in the total export growth of the second largest economy in the world.
The measure announced by Trump could reduce China from 60% to the US of goods currently sent under a mechanism known as the minimis.
By 2024, Chinese "minimis" packaging exports sent directly to consumers around the world reached about $ 240 billion, representing 7% of total sales abroad and 1.3% of Chinese GDP.
The number of packaging of this type sent to the US increased almost ten times between 2015 and 2024, from 139 million to 1.365 billion units. Although the exemption has almost a decade of existence, has been scrutinized in recent years due to the explosion of Chinese e -commerce by companies such as Shein, Temu and Aliexpress, part of the giant Alibaba.
By 2024, China registered about $ 23 billion in exports through small orders sent to the United States, according to Bloomberg news agency, which considers that this amount could be underestimated, as there is information that companies are reported. Chinese are sending Grosso goods to Mexico and deliver them to small packaging for the neighboring country.
Chinese retailers have conducted massive digital marketing campaigns in the US, offering a vast inventory of clothing, homeless and electronic articles, placing them in direct competition with Amazon, Ebay or ETSY.
In response, Temu supported Chinese salespeople at warehouse opening in the US to allow them to send products locally and avoid import rates, while Shein opened distribution warehouses and supply chains in the US.
Local News Portal Yicai recalled that US retailers like Amazon and Walmart also benefited from this mechanism: for example, the group led by Jeff Bezos has launched a platform called Haul, through which sellers can send products-all with one Maximum price of $ 20-directly from China to US buyers.
 
Hong Kong Post Offices suspend the shipping of goods to the USA
 
Hong Kong Post Office suspended the sending of “postal articles with commodity” to the United States, hours after the US postal service stops accepting orders from China or Hong Kong. In a statement issued Wednesday night, the Post Office said they will only send packages or orders that customers have registered with Customs and Border Protection (CBP) of the United States. This record “requires the necessary import documents and the payment of fees made through a customs dispatcher,” said Hong Kong's post office. Shortly after taking office, the new president of the United States, Donald Trump, specifically eliminated a tariff exemption for low value products, purchased directly by consumers and sent through the postal service. This exemption encompassed articles of less than $ 800. All packages and orders that reach the United States without paying the fees “will be returned to Hong Kong,” the Post Office of the Territory stressed. "Postal shipping services containing only documents will not be affected," added the Hong Kong post office.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07T05:05:23+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SINO-TAILENDE POLICE COOPERATION IN FIGHTING BURLA UNIONS: Implications for Asia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/cooperacao-policial-sino-tailandesa-no-combate-aos-sindicatos-de-burla-implicacoes-para-a-asia/</link><description>On January 27, 2025, China's Deputy Minister of Public Security, Liu Zhongyi, headed a delegation to Thailand, where he met with the Thai Police Commissioner of the Cybercry Research Office, Trairong Phiwpan in Nonthaburi province. Liu's visit was significant as it pointed out a Sino-Tailandi police cooperation in combat together to the Burla unions that operate in the Myawaddy region of Myanmar, which borders the Thai province of Tak (Bangkok Post, January 28, 2025 ).
According to Liu, there are currently 36 large -scale burla unions operated by Chinese of Ethnicity in Myawaddy, who employ and control 100,000 people to dedicate themselves to cybercrime scam, deceiving victims' money and directly triggering the illegal traffic of victims of mainland China (Oriental Daily, January 30, 2025, p. A17).
Liu added that many Chinese citizens were enticed, deceived, and kidnapped to work in Myanmar; Some were beaten and others even died. Liu proposed several measures to the China and Thailand police to resolve the situation: (1) China would provide Thai police in detail about the capital flows of fraudulent unions, especially about money transfers involving the smuggling of humans; (2) China asks Thailand to help arrest gang chiefs hiding in Thai territory; (3) China will help Thailand to stop twenty suspects of involvement in the abduction of continental actor Wang Xing; (4) These twenty suspects will be extradited to China to be tried as soon as they are detained; and (5) China expresses its gratitude to Thailand for all the assistance provided in the pursuit of crime suspects.
In addition, Chinese police asked their Thai counterpart to use their information and technology services to confirm the identities of the Chinese detained in Mianmar's territory, to adopt measures to rescue them, that Thailand would end the supply of electricity to these Fraudulent unions (an action appreciated by the Chinese party) that reinforced the control of the routes involved in the smuggling of humans. In short, the space for the activities of the transfronic burla unions would have to be reduced. The Chinese and Thai police will create a joint coordination center in the fight against transfronist burla unions, with the participation of researchers from both parties, and increase the intensity of their joint operations. Under these circumstances, the anxiety of Chinese tourists is expected to be security when visiting Thailand to be appeased, thus increasing the confidence of international society in Thailand.
The Thai Police Cybercrime Investigation Office proposed several cooperation measures. These include a joint working group consisting of the Thai Cybercriminal Control Center and Chinese public safety. Both parties will share criminal information. Thai police will also ask China's help to dismantle Chinese ethnic gang chiefs and Thai collaborators. In addition, since the Burla Unions have used cryptocurrencies in the processes of capital transfer and laundering money from redemptions, both parties of the police will share criminals and capital flows and prevent money from the country's rescues from the country . Finally, Thai police suggested that Chinese police take the initiative to summon a regional police meeting with Myanmar, Laos, Cambodia and Thailand to discuss long -term measures and solutions to combat transfrontic cybercriminality and burla unions.
In response to the suggestions of Thai police, Liu Zhongyi has lived vividly praised the proposed measures and believed that, through joint cooperation between the Chinese and Thai police, a highly efficient model to combat cross -boring unions will be established and an example of combat will be given an example of an example of combat to the circumvents in the region and in the world.
Just a day before Liu's visit to Thailand, Thai police took quick steps to repress some corrupt elements of the Thai police force and to rescue seven Chinese that had been kidnapped.  On January 27, Thai police announced that four corrupt police, one soldier and three ordinary citizens (one of them Burmese) had been detained for being involved in the abduction of Chinese victims. The seven Chinese, who were rescued by Thai police, had their relatives intimidated to request a $ 460,000 rescue from Hong Kong to release each victim. The seven Chinese victims, aged between 22 and 25, were enticed with lucrative jobs, illegally crossing the Laos border to the northeastern territory of Thailand. The abductors asked the victims to call their families in the laos to ask for a ransom. According to Thai police, all corrupt elements of the local police will be the subject of administrative, disciplinary and criminal sanctions.
On January 17, it was reported that the Thai military sent a special service group to install inspection places over the main routes on the border between Thailand and Myanmar. Signs of warning were used in Thai, English, and Chinese to alert tourists to the danger of the existence of burns unions along the border zone. The Thai military has created inspection points to control the vehicles that cross the border with Myanmar, consolidating and intensifying the identity controls of foreign tourists and ending the passage of the border of people without justification.
Thanks to the close cooperation between Thai and Chinese police, one of the leading suspects of having participated in Wang Xing's abduction plan was arrested and sent back to mainland China on the night of January 25. The suspect used a high compensation to attract Wang Xing to participate in a "movie" in Thailand. Two Chinese from mainland China, which belonged to the same group of victims involving Wang Xing, remain missing (Ming Pao, January 28, 2025, A11).
The main suspect of being arrested in the Wang Xing case came from Jiangsu's province and used different names to deceive the victims. According to information from Hong Kong, the suspect previously worked in the continent's film industry and said he was coordinator of a film company in Thailand. He invited at least ten people from the continent to work in Thailand (Eastern Daily, January 28, 2025, A13). In response to Wang Xing's case and other cases of victims, mainland China police have called for Chinese citizens to increase their surveillance in relation to burla unions and distrust any malicious attempts to entitle them to work outside China with alleged highly paid jobs.
The Wang Xing case alarmed the Thai police, as the image of Thailand as a tourist center was questioned. Thai police took quick measures to repress the transmitted criminals. From January 20 to 24, the entry to Thailand was refused to ten visitors considered high risk. Forty -seven people were not allowed to stay in Tak province and ninety -two people who remained too long in Tak province were arrested and fined, including a Chinese and a Indonesian. In addition, twenty Burmese were arrested who were illegal immigrants. This cleaning measure contributed to the fight against transfronical trafficking of humans and the abduction. Thai police also reinforced border control and inspection of people who have housed in fields and inns near Myanmar, including tourists from China, South Korea, Laos, Vietnam and Ethiopia (Eastern Daily, January 28, 2025, A13).
In addition, since the Burla Unions have used cryptocurrencies in the processes of capital transfer and laundering money from redemptions, both parties of the police will share criminals and capital flows and prevent money from the country's rescues from the country . Finally, Thai police suggested that Chinese police take the initiative to summon a regional police meeting with Myanmar, Laos, Cambodia and Thailand to discuss long -term measures and solutions to combat transfrontic cybercriminality and burla unions. In response to the suggestions of Thai police, Liu Zhongyi has lived vividly praised the proposed measures and believed that, through joint cooperation between the Chinese and Thai police, a highly efficient model to combat cross -boring unions will be established and an example of combat will be given an example of an example of combat to the circumvents in the region and in the world. Just a day before Liu's visit to Thailand, Thai police took quick steps to repress some corrupt elements of the Thai police force and to rescue seven Chinese that had been kidnapped. On January 27, Thai police announced that four corrupt police, one soldier and three ordinary citizens (one of them Burmese) had been detained for being involved in the abduction of Chinese victims. The seven Chinese, who were rescued by Thai police, had their relatives intimidated to request a $ 460,000 rescue from Hong Kong to release each victim. The seven Chinese victims, aged between 22 and 25, were enticed with lucrative jobs, illegally crossing the Laos border to the northeastern territory of Thailand. The abductors asked the victims to call their families in the laos to ask for a ransom. According to Thai police, all corrupt elements of the local police will be the subject of administrative, disciplinary and criminal sanctions.
In conclusion, it is imperative that there is transfrontic police cooperation in combating transnational burla unions, involving China, Thailand, Myanmar, Cambodia, Laos, Singapore, South Korea, Japan, Malaysia, Philippines and Indonesia. Regional organizations, such as Interpol and Asean, will perhaps have more coordination and planning work, respectively, in addition to the ongoing intergovernmental police cooperation between these countries. With the rapid development of the media, cryptocurrencies and artificial intelligence, the transfronist criminal elements became much more active than ever in Asia, especially in the post-covid era, where many people in Asia were attracted by false Allegations of highly paid jobs in foreign countries. As such, in addition to intergovernmental police cooperation in the fight against transfronist burla unions through the sharing of information and joint operations, the internal combat to bureaucratic corruption, the strictest control of customs over borders, the internal education of citizens to Increasing its sensitivity to personal safety and individual surveillance against transfronist cybercriminals are necessary measures for a collective and more effective crime against transnational crimes in the Asia Pacific region.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07T04:58:34+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Monjardino takes a “very positive” balance of the presence of the Oriente Foundation in Goa</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/monjardino-faz-balanco-muito-positivo-da-presenca-da-fundacao-oriente-em-goa/</link><description>Regarding the 30th anniversary of the beginning of the activities of the Oriente Foundation in Goa, Carlos Monjardino takes a "very positive" balance of the role of the institution in India, namely in the cultural scene of Goa. Speaking to the end point, the president of the East Foundation Board of Directors also states that, after the initial distrust of Goa's official entities, the institution is now perfectly accepted.
 
Carlos Monjardino went to Goa earlier this month to mark the 30 years of activity of the East Foundation Indian delegation. At the end, the chairman of the East Foundation board recalled the process to establish a delegation there and highlighted the current role of the institution in India.
Monjardino recalled that the establishment of the delegation in Goa in 1995 was based on a suggestion of Mario Soares, President of the Republic of Portugal at the time. “He asked me to contemplate the hypothesis that the foundation had anything in Goa, because there was nothing Portuguese, neither consulate, nor Camões, nothing. We decided to open it, ”he said. This was the second delegation of the East Foundation, the first had been established in Macao in 1988, and that of Timor-Leste began its activity in 2002.
About the presence in Goa, the official of the East Foundation highlighted the subsidies granted for the teaching of the Portuguese language. Nowadays there are still about two dozen subsidized teachers. There are also scholarships for Goes students who want to attend higher education in Portugal.
In addition, “we also take on as creators of a certain kind of cultural manifestations with connections to Portugal, whether artists, painters, etc.,” he said, pointing to the Monte's Music Festival and the exhibition of painter Goês António Xavier Trindade which is evident on the ground floor of the Delegation Building, located in the Fontainhas neighborhood.
These aspects make Carlos Monjardino a “very positive balance” of the presence of the Foundation in Goa. "We remain a very important stone in all that are cultural events in Goa," he said.
Regarding the inclusion of the East Foundation in the local community, Monjardino recalled that, "at first, not on the part of the places but from the official part, there was some resistance because they still had the colonial part of the Portuguese." In the late 1990s, there were also obstacles by descendants of the entitled “Freedom Fighters”, a movement that in the nineteenth century struggled to end the domain of Portuguese colonization. However, “this has been disappearing over time and nowadays we are perfectly accepted, so much so that Goa's official entities go to our cultural manifestations and I just have to say well of this relationship,” he concludes.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Blocked access to DeepSeek in two ministries in South Korea</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/bloqueado-acesso-a-deepseek-em-dois-ministerios-na-coreia-do-sul/</link><description>The South Korean Defense and Trade Ministries announced yesterday the Deepseek blockade on the two departments computers, while waiting for the Chinese 'startup' explanations about the treatment given to users' information.
The regulatory entity responsible for protecting personal data announced last week that he asked DeepSeek to explain the processing of information provided by users, following the example of other countries, such as France and Ireland. “Deepseek blocking measures were implemented Specifically for the PC [computers] military-linked to the internet, ”the Ministry of Defense told France-Presse (AFP) news agency.
Already the Ministry of Commerce stated that access to DeepSeek was also temporarily restricted in all computers of the government department. "We temporarily blocked DeepSeek because it did not respond to the committee's investigation for personal information protection," an AFP official of the Ministry of Commerce told AFP.
South Korean technological giants, including Samsung Electronics and rival SK Hynix, are the main suppliers of advanced microprocessors used on DeepSek's artificial intelligence (AI) servers.
The appearance in January of the Chinese startup R1 conversation robot surprised the ability to match US rivals at a much lower cost, according to the company, in question the business model of the AI ​​industry.
DeepSeek also quickly began to raise concerns between authorities around the world. A day before the South Korean counterpart, the Italian authority for protecting personal data launched an investigation into the DeepSek conversation robot, to whom it prohibited from saving data from Italian users.
The Italian authority justified the decision that DeepSeek gave answers “totally inadequate” to questions about the use of personal data.
On Thursday, the Australian Interior Ministry issued a directive that removes Deepseek programs from “all the Australian government's fixed and furniture equipment,” in response to a safety risk he considered as unacceptable. China has denounced the decision, stressing that it is opposed to “politicization of economic, commercial and technological issues”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07T05:09:43+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Thailand and China promise to combat online fraud networks</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/tailandia-e-china-prometem-combater-as-redes-de-fraude-online/</link><description>Chinese leader Xi Jinping and Thai Prime Minister Paetongtarn Shinawatra yesterday fought the scams that plague Southeast Asia during a meeting in Beijing.
 
Myanmar, Cambodia and Laos, which are south of China and share borders with Thailand, have become the main 'online' fraud operations centers, where people attracted to false advertisements of well-paid jobs are kept in secret complexes and Forced to work for criminal groups that generate slips directed to people around the world.
This situation has affected Thailand's reputation, as there were several stories about Chinese that were attracted to work in Bangkok and then were trafficked to some of these complex in Myanmar, being Chinese actor Wang Xing the latest victim.
Thai and Chinese authorities took public measures to solve the problem of the mockery, including a visit by Liu Zhongyi, Chinese Public Security Deputy Minister, in the border region.
“China appreciates the strong measures adopted by Thailand to combat online fraud. Both parties should continue to reinforce law enforcement, security and judicial cooperation, ”said Xi, quoted by state television CCTV. "Thailand is willing to reinforce cooperation in law enforcement with China and other neighboring countries and to adopt resolute and effective measures to combat transionic crimes such as game and fraud," Paetongtarn said.
Prior to his visit, Thailand cut off electricity to some Myanmar areas by his border to try to disturb the operations of fraudulent groups. The effect of this measure is not clear, since complexes often have their own generators.
The visit to China was the first of Paetongtarn as Prime Minister and occurs at a time when the two countries celebrate 50 years since the establishment of diplomatic relations.
Regarding other bilateral issues, Xi said China is willing to work in a new rail project between the two countries. On Tuesday, Thailand approved a $ 10 billion railway connection that will connect Bangkok to the Laos-China high speed line. The Chinese president also stated that the two countries expect to deepen cooperation in the field of electric vehicles, as Thailand is an emerging market for Chinese car manufacturers.
China was once a significant part of the Thailand tourist segment, but by 2024, the number of visitors dropped to 6.7 million, well below the 11 million visitors in 2019, before the coronavirus pandemic, when Chinese visitors represented almost one third of all arrivals. Paetongtarn has shown that Thailand is willing to accommodate Chinese interests on fundamental issues.
In January, a group of Uigures, Chinese ethnic minority of Muslim origin, detained in Thailand, asked for help before being deported to China. Thailand's decision to deport the Uigures, who are persecution, occurred before the 50th anniversary of relations between the two countries. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-02-07T05:09:46+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump signs executive order that prohibits transgender athletes from practicing women's sports</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/trump-assina-ordem-executiva-que-proibe-atletas-transgenero-de-praticar-desportos-femininos/</link><description>United States President Donald Trump yesterday issued an executive order that prohibits transgender athletes from practicing women's sports, in another attack on the community that has been aimed at having returned to power. "With this executive order, the war against women's sport ended," the Republican promised to sign the text in a ceremony in the White House, under the applause of several dozens of female athletes. The order, entitled “Keeping men out of women's sports”, gives federal agencies, including the Departments of Justice and Education, wide latitude to ensure that entities that receive federal financing comply with Title IX in alignment with the Trump Vision View , who plays "sex" as the genre that someone was designated at birth. The 1972 Federal Law, known as Title IX, prohibits discrimination based on sex in sports programs that receive federal funding.
The moment of the order coincided with the National Day of Girls and Women in Sport and is the last of a series of Trump executive actions directed to transgender people. The Order authorizes, for example, the Department of Education to penalize schools that allow the competition of transgender athletes, invoking non -compliance with Title IX, which prohibits sexual discrimination in schools. Any educational establishment that is considered in violation may be potentially ineligible for federal financing. The order also requires that private sports bodies meet in the White House so that the president can hear personally “the stories of female athletes who have suffered lifelong injuries, who were silenced and forced to bathe with men and compete with men in fields of athletics across the country. ” The measure is the latest of Trump administration to limit the rights of the transgender population. It also opened the door to the exclusion of transgender members from military service, appealed to the end of federal health insurance and other gender affirmation financing for transgender people under 19 and restricted the way in which gender lessons can be taught in schools.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07T04:59:35+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Dsal and faom promote pairing sessions with 48 vacancies available</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/dsal-e-faom-promovem-sessoes-de-emparelhamento-com-48-vagas-disponiveis/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), in collaboration with the Federation of Macao Workers Associations (Faom), will organize three employment pairing sessions in mid -February, with the offer of 48 vacancies in specific sectors. According to organizing entities, this initiative aims to support Macao residents who need employment to quickly integrate into the job market, also relieving pressure on sectors looking for human resources. Registration opens today at 09h00, and end at noon of 12 February.
The sessions are scheduled to occur within two different days. First, on February 13, during the morning, there will be a pairing session of CDFG Macau, a limited unipessoal society, focused on the retail sales sector of pharmaceutical products, which offers 15 posts for the function of seller. In this day, in the afternoon, there will be a session for the Information Technology sector, with the participation of Limited Kingdee (Macau), and Boardware Limited Information System, which will offer 13 vacancies for positions such as project assistant and systems analyst . Already on February 14, the sessions held by SJM Resorts, S.A. will focus on the hotel sector, with 20 opportunities for functions that include heads of care service for VIPs and receptionists.
The pairing sessions will take place in different places, being the first in the multipurpose room of Dsal's headquarters and the second at Hotel Grand Lisboa Palace Macau. With the limited number of vacancies, interested parties are encouraged to register as soon as possible. DSAL and FAOM will notify the candidates enrolled through SMS. For more information, residents may contact the departments responsible for the numbers available during office hours, or through the DSSA online page.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07T05:05:32+08:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Almost 700 vacancies in the tourism industry announced for February</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/02/07/quase-700-vagas-na-industria-do-turismo-anunciadas-para-fevereiro/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) announced six employment pairing sessions in February, aimed at leisure companies. This initiative, which aims to serve the growing demand for labor in the tourism industry, provides a total of 691 vacancies in the areas of restoration, room cleaning and front line operations.
The registration process is already open and will continue until February 24, with interested parties to be able to access the “Local Employment Offers” Portal from the DSSA website, where they can consult the offers and make their application online. Upon delivery of the necessary documents, candidates may be summoned to interviews, which will take place on several dates throughout the month.
The initial sessions are scheduled for February 18, involving the companies Melco and MGM, followed by SJM Resorts on the 25th, Galaxy Entertainment Group on the 26th and Sands China with Wynn on the 27th. The exact place and time of the interviews will be communicated directly by companies to candidates.
In addition to vacancies in the most common areas, DSAL also offers opportunities in management positions and specialized technical posts, including positions such as strategic analysis manager and systems engineer for shows, reflecting the diversity of functions necessary for the operation of this sector in full expansion , according to Dsal.
Companies will also be able to schedule additional pairing sessions as required, demonstrating a flexibility in addressing the region's employment needs.
For more information, candidates can contact Dsal's Employment Department through the numbers available on the online page, ensuring that consultation about employment opportunities can be done efficiently.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07T05:05:28+08:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>