<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/04/seul-promete-esforcos-para-repatriar-seis-cidadaos-detidos-na-coreia-do-norte/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Ukraine and trade imbalances dominate meeting between Macron and Xi Jinping</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/04/ucrania-e-desequilibrios-comerciais-dominam-encontro-entre-macron-e-xi-jinping/</link><description>French President Emmanuel Macron yesterday appealed to the efforts of his Chinese counterpart, Xi Jinping, to end the war in Ukraine and correct trade imbalances, at the start of a state visit to China.

"We must continue to mobilize for peace and stability in the world. And from Ukraine to the different regions of the world affected by war, our ability to work together is decisive", said Macron after a restricted meeting with the Chinese head of state and before extended discussions.
“We know that we have many points in common, sometimes we have disagreements, but we have a responsibility to know how to overcome them, to find mechanisms for cooperation and dispute resolution for an effective multilateralism in which we believe,” added the French leader.
Xi assured, for his part, that China intends to cooperate with France to “eliminate any interference” and “make the overall strategic partnership between China and France more stable”.
Macron also called for the growth of “cross-investments” between the two countries, to rebalance the commercial relationship, and defended cooperation within the G7 towards economic governance based on “rules”.
The Chinese President, accompanied by his wife, Peng Liyuan, received Macron and his wife, Brigitte, at the People's Palace, where the two leaders listened to the national anthems and reviewed the troops, before being greeted by children.
The French head of state, who arrived in Beijing on Wednesday night, accompanied by 35 leaders of large business groups (including Airbus, EDF and Danone) and family companies, from the luxury to the agri-food sector, is expected to attend the signing of a series of contracts.
Macron intends to address Chinese trade practices that Paris considers unfair, from the automobile sector to steel.
The relationship between China and the European Union is characterized by a huge trade deficit ($357.1 billion) to the detriment of the EU.
Paris is also committed to pressuring China to invest more in France, and accept a sharing of technologies comparable to that practiced by Europeans, which has contributed to Beijing's economic growth.
Another sensitive issue is access to rare metals, whose global production and transformation is dominated by China, a lever that Beijing used in 2025, in the midst of a trade war with the United States, shaking up the planet's supply chains.
This is Emmanuel Macron's fourth state visit to China since being elected President in 2017. Xi Jinping was welcomed to France in 2024 and the Elysee presents the time Xi will spend with Macron until Friday, including private meetings, as a sign of the importance of the Sino-French relationship. “We have a constant expectation regarding China: It is that it will use its influence with Russia to get it to stop the war” in Ukraine, at the gates of the European Union, says Eliseu.
China has reiterated that it wants peace, but has never condemned Russia's invasion of Ukraine in February 2022. Russia's fundamental economic and political partner, the Asian giant is the world's largest buyer of Russian fossil fuels, including petroleum products, thus fueling the war machine. Europeans also accuse Beijing of supplying military components to Moscow.
During his previous trip to Beijing, in 2023, Macron called on Xi to “call Russia to reason”.
The Chinese President reserved privileged treatment for his Russian counterpart, Vladimir Putin, in September, inviting him, together with the North Korean leader, Kim Jong-un, to be present at the military parade commemorating the 80th anniversary of the end of the Second World War.
As in France in 2024, the two presidential couples will meet on Friday in a more informal setting in Chengdu, in the province of Sichuan (southwest), birthplace of the giant pandas that have become China's ambassadors around the world. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 23:02:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Feng Shui: nine fish and a dog with sneakers</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/04/feng-shui-nove-peixes-e-um-cao-com-tenis/</link><description>In Macau, as soon as we enter a traditional store or typical restaurant, we always come across an aquarium full of fish, very well maintained, as if it were the heart of the establishment. It's not just fashion, it's living, tangible Feng Shui.
Unlike Westerners who, when moving into a new house, rush to buy an entrance rug or a plant for the living room, the Chinese have a different priority: first of all there has to be an aquarium with fish or a cage with a bird.
The phonetic similarity of goldfish to the words “gold” and “abundance” drives the Chinese mantra of putting nine fish in an aquarium: eight red or orange and one black. Black fish absorb bad “Chi”, while warm-toned fish bring prosperity. When one dies, there is no drama, it is interpreted as a sign… A sign that the fish took bad luck with it.
Birds have another function. A canary on the balcony, singing in the morning, activates the “Chi” of success and recognition. Older people swear that singing opens new paths. When the bird dies, the cage is placed facing the wall for three days as a sign of respect and prevention of stagnant energy.
In mainland China, relationships with animals have always been more pragmatic. For centuries, in the coldest regions, on the winter solstice, dog meat was eaten as it was believed to warm the body and increase “yang”. The saying goes: “when winter comes, a dog is worth three fur coats”. It was seasonal, almost ritual. In Yulin, the dog meat festival continued until recently, but urban pressure, new generations, international values ​​and globalization caused the custom to retreat. Today, in almost all of urban China, the dog is treated as a member of the family, complete with fashionable grooming and branded clothing.
That is why in Macau it is often said, half jokingly and half seriously, almost always to justify the cultural shock felt in so many areas, that “we walk the dogs and eat the birds; they eat the dogs and walk the birds”. The local reality, however, belies the stereotype. In Macau, the dog has always been a guard or companion, never a pot. Maybe because of the intentional influence of the Portuguese, maybe because the money from the casinos arrived early and brought other luxuries or, maybe, because the region is blessed with short, sunny winters. In Macau, the most common barking is that of a micro poodle inside a baby stroller, with sneakers on so as not to burn their paws in the scorching tar of the summer months and an Instagram account with more followers than many humans.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 22:55:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau International Airport committed to contributing to the internationalization of the city</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/04/aeroporto-internacional-de-macau-comprometido-a-contribuir-para-internacionalizacao-da-cidade/</link><description>Macau International Airport celebrates its 30th anniversary this year. CAM – Sociedade do Aeroporto Internacional de Macau claims to have been optimizing its facilities and the quality of services and that, in the future, it will align itself with the Government's strategic plans to position Macau as a World Tourism and Leisure Center.
Ma Iao Hang, president of the Board of Directors of CAM, highlights that the airport will proactively participate in the development of the Greater Bay Area and in the “One Belt, One Route” initiative, promoting the economic diversification and internationalization of the city. “With continuous innovation and commitment to excellence, Macau International Airport will continue to grow, contributing to the economic diversification and internationalization of Macau”, highlighted Ma Iao Hang, in his speech during the reception commemorating the airport's 30th anniversary, held yesterday with the presence of around 400 guests.
The Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, in turn, highlighted the importance of the airport, as an “essential gateway for Macau’s integration in regional development and international cooperation”, as well as an “engine of socio-economic development” for the territory. Raymond Tam indicated that the Government is currently committed to the construction of a Macau International Air Transport Hub on the west bank of the Pearl River, the orderly development of the airport landfill and expansion project and the project relating to the “Upstream” cargo terminal in Hengqin.
According to the secretary, these facilities, in conjunction with the airport cooperation project between Zhuhai and Macau, will build a new logistics and mobility panorama, characterized by the “uninterrupted Macau–Zhuhai connection”, reinforcing Macau’s competitiveness as a regional air hub.
The deputy administrator of the Civil Aviation Administration of China, Ma Bing, emphasized that Macau's civil aviation sector has contributed to the creation of the cooperation and trade platform between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, ensuring continuous support for the development of the territory's industry.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 23:03:41</pubDate></item><item><title>CCAC studies review of the law to prevent corruption in the private sector</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/04/ccac-estuda-revisao-da-lei-de-prevencao-da-corrupcao-no-sector-privado/</link><description>The Commission against Corruption (CCAC) intends to review the law on the prevention and repression of corruption in the private sector, which has been in force since 2009. In the Lines of Government Action, the body admits “difficulties and challenges” in applying the law, taking into account the “profound changes” in Macau society and the differences to similar laws abroad. The CCAC will also examine the monitoring work of the last legislative elections to propose changes to the electoral law.

The review of the corruption prevention regime is on the work agenda of the Commissioner against Corruption (CCAC) for next year, with the plan to amend the Law on Prevention and Repression of Corruption in the Private Sector, which came into force more than 15 years ago.
“In 2026, the CCAC will promote a study on the Law for the Prevention and Repression of Corruption in the Private Sector and will present, in a timely manner and in accordance with the social environment and legal requirements of Macau, revision proposals considered relevant”, reveals the organization in the Lines of Government Action (LAG).
The CCAC, currently led by the Commissioner against Corruption, Ao Ieong Seong, explains in the report the need to update the legal framework, due to “profound changes” that Macau society has experienced since the law came into force.
Furthermore, he points out that the current law still presents major differences in comparison with similar laws in neighboring regions and with the provisions of international conventions applicable in Macau, “which means that, in the process of combating corruption in the private sector, many difficulties and challenges are encountered in its application”, he admitted.
Reiterating the priority of combating corruption, the CCAC stated that it will persist in combating corruption crimes in both the public and private sectors.
“The CCAC will study the characteristics of public services and high-risk sectors where more cases related to corruption occur and adopt specific measures, combining the fight against corruption with publicity and awareness”, guarantees the CCAC, assuming the defense of an “integrity environment” in Macau, “which has already been hard won”.
Therefore, according to the LAG, the organization, taking advantage of the practical experience of anti-corruption work over the last 20 years and in conjunction with the reflection and review of Macau's criminal legal system, will dedicate itself to improving the respective legal regimes, particularly with regard to criminal law and criminal procedural law.

152 PROCESSES UNTIL SEPTEMBER
 
With regard to the investigation of cases, the report states that, until September 30th of this year, 152 cases were investigated by the CCAC in the context of combating corruption, not including those related to elections, with 86 relating to the public sector and 66 to the private sector.
A total of 93 cases were concluded, including 56 related to the public sector and 37 to the private sector, of which 8 cases, with investigation completed, were forwarded to the Public Ministry for follow-up.
It should also be noted that cases related to the area of ​​security and the area of ​​social and cultural affairs dominated the processes relating to the public sector, while the processes involving the private sector continued to be mainly related to the repair and administration of buildings and the management of integrated tourism and leisure companies.
The CCAC assures that it has been paying attention and being alert to the different types of cases of fraud to obtain Government subsidies, “investigating all cases, seeking to suppress, at its root, the practice of these acts and prevent their recurrence, with a view to ensuring the good use of the Macao SAR's public funds”, can be read in the document.

EXAMINE ELECTIONS LAW
 
The Electoral Law for the Legislative Assembly may also be revised. The CCAC states that it will carry out a “serious” assessment of the work monitoring elections and the execution of the law on elections, in order to present opinions and suggestions to the Government to eventually amend this law.
According to an assessment in the context of this year's elections for the Legislative Assembly, the CCAC, until September 30, 2025, received a total of 146 complaints related to the elections, with 29 cases being processed, of which 3 were forwarded by the Legislative Assembly's Electoral Affairs Commission (CAEAL). In the same period, the organization unofficially forwarded 34 cases to CAEAL and 15 cases to the Judiciary Police.
“Through the investigation and treatment of some cases, some irregularities that emerged at the beginning of the election period were repressed, ensuring the integrity, justice, transparency and impartiality of the elections for the Legislative Assembly,” he stated.

PUBLIC GOVERNANCE SUPERVISION
 
Another highlight of the CCAC's LAGs is in the scope of the ombudsman's office. The organization says it will strengthen monitoring of the legality and reasonableness of acts of public governance, in addition to seeking more diversified means to increase the efficiency and quality of services provided by administrative entities.
It also aims to reinforce, at the same time, citizens' knowledge and trust in the inspection system in the context of promoting integrity, through “strengthening communication, from the initial phase, with complainants”.
The authorities also want to increase civic awareness of filing complaints with a sense of responsibility, while continuing to safeguard the principle of confidentiality. The organization also revealed that it intends to gradually create, next year, an automated program to increase efficiency in responding to complaints presented.
On the other hand, the CCAC emphasizes that it will reinforce communication with public services, during which it expresses its opinions in the course of handling ombudsman cases. It thus hopes to provide public services with more room for maneuver to carry out self-evaluation and self-improvement before issuing opinions or recommendations by the CCAC.
The body also plans to “integrate the matters that most concern society”, thus carrying out an informal intervention, discussing and defining with the competent services guidelines or measures that can be implemented, with the aim of helping to resolve social problems at their root and in a more comprehensive way, thus responding to citizens' requests, according to the report.
It is recalled that the CCAC initiated, until September 30 of this year, 135 new processes within the scope of the ombudsman's office. Combining the files carried over from last year, a total of 279 investigation files required follow-up, of which the total number of investigation files whose investigation was concluded and archived was 96.
And, for the purposes of monitoring the implementation, by public services, of the opinions or suggestions issued by the CCAC, 4 new cases were included in the “look back” list, while 5 cases were removed from the same list following the conclusion of subsequent inspection work.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 00:00:11</pubDate></item><item><title>“The Memory of the Smell of Things” brings a message about empathy to the Cinemateca</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/04/a-memoria-do-cheiro-das-coisas-traz-uma-mensagem-sobre-empatia-a-cinemateca/</link><description>The film “The Memory of the Smell of Things” is scheduled to premiere today, at 7:30 pm, at Cinemateca Paixão. After the cinema session, the public is invited to stay a little longer in the room to interact and ask questions to director António Ferreira and producer Tathiani Sacilotto. In conversation with PONTO FINAL, the Portuguese filmmaker explains that the work is more than a portrait of the racism that still persists in Portugal: it is a universal reflection on aging, vulnerability and the bonds of empathy that are born where least expected.

Arménio, an octogenarian shaped by the Colonial War, now has a nursing home as his permanent residence. It is Hermínia, a black woman, who takes care of him and accompanies him as his health declines. “The Memory of the Smell of Things” is a film that addresses themes such as racism and the legacy of colonialism in Portugal, but at its heart is a much more universal story. The inevitability of time, the violence of aging and the empathy that gives reason to human existence.
"That's the central theme, the issue of aging and the approaching end of life. We will then address the other themes in parallel, arising from this", admits director António Ferreira, in conversation with PONTO FINAL. The characters are easily recognizable in contemporary Portuguese society, with Arménio – played by actor José Martins – personifying an entire generation indoctrinated for war.
"It's the story of an ex-combatant who, as is customary for these types of men, grew up having to be strong and never needing help from anyone. Now, at the final stage of his life, he is forcibly admitted to a home due to health problems, and the person there to help him is a black woman", summarizes the Portuguese director, on the eve of the film's premiere in Macau. “That’s the film’s starting point: a man who grew up in the Salazar mentality, educated to look at black people as enemies, to see himself in a vulnerable situation”
Hermínia understands the discomfort: “She is a black woman who normally runs away from an ex-combatant, because she is used to being treated in a certain way, and would normally never talk to him”. The daily interactions that they are forced to maintain serve as seeds so that, on the screen, a message about empathy, humanity and the deconstruction of prejudices can flourish. More: an analysis of how these prejudices arise.
"These men are not like that by chance. Racists are not born racist; they are manufactured through society. It is important that we talk about this, because it is not such a distant story", highlights António Ferreira, remembering that Portugal is the only European country with a still living generation of war veterans. Now elderly men who, in their youth, were groomed for violence and death – and then discarded with open wounds that never healed.
"80% of young people at the time were mobilized for the Colonial War. Men were trained to hate, a rifle was put in their hands, “go there, kill”, and when the war ended no one gave them any explanation. No one asked them if they were okay. With the celebration of the end of the dictatorship and the war, a great silence was imposed on these men".
Meanwhile, Portugal's demographic and social landscape has changed radically. The black population integrated into Portuguese society and reached places formerly reserved for white people (“black people can be our family doctor, the teacher at school, our daughter's husband”), but a certain age group remained crystallized in the mentality of the past. “The film aims to reflect on this through this forced contact, without pointing fingers, with great affection for both characters, even with all their flaws.”
It is, in short, an exercise in empathy in times of “social media hysteria”, as the filmmaker notes. "Everyone is on their side of the trench pointing the finger at the other side. What I wanted to do with the film was to force two parties that normally don't talk at all to establish a link."
The performance of actor José Martins – openly anti-fascist and “the opposite” of the character he plays – received applause from specialized critics, including the “Best Actor” award at the Shanghai International Film Festival. “He really played an extraordinary role”, praises the director. “In addition to being an excellent actor, he is also a man with convictions, who had to put himself in the shoes of a person completely different from him.”
From Shanghai to Istanbul, passing through Morocco and São Paulo, the public reception was equally enthusiastic, marked by a palpable emotion towards an unexpectedly universal theme. "I thought that younger people might not care about the film, but the issue of the end of life is close to all of us. It reminds us of our grandfather, it reminds us of our father. It's transversal to any society." The audience's tears are probably the greatest recognition of all. "I often say that I am part of the affection cinema club. My films are narrative; I want to communicate with people. When I have that type of reaction, I feel that the objective has been accomplished."
As for the debut in Macau, António Ferreira admits he doesn't know exactly what to expect. “I don’t know if there will be more Portuguese, more people from Macau, if it’s mixed…”. Go to today's sharing session, taking place at the Cinemateca after the film's screening, with an “open and curious spirit, eager to know what people's reactions are like” and to answer any questions raised by the public.
“The Memory of the Smell of Things” closes this year's edition of the Film Festival between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries, which brought around 30 films to the Cinemateca Paixão. The film starts at 7:30 pm, followed by a question and answer session with the presence of director António Ferreira and producer Tathiani Sacilotto.
Remember that this edition of the festival has several additional discounts at the box office, in order to further encourage public participation. In addition to the “buy one, get two” discount option, upon presentation of concert tickets or proof of purchase at the Illustrated Book Exhibition, “Friend Tickets” are also available, where it is possible to buy a ticket for two people for just 60 patacas.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Gastronomy Festival combines health and cuisine with a record number of participants</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/04/festival-da-gastronomia-alia-saude-e-cozinha-com-registo-recorde-de-participantes/</link><description>The 25th edition of the Gastronomy Festival was the space for a pioneering activity that put health on the table. The Health Services, in partnership with the Union of Associations of Owners of Food and Beverage Establishments of Macau, took the “Restaurants – Healthy Eating” program to the center of the event, involving more than 3,000 people in interactive games and attracting a dozen participating restaurants. The aim was to promote conscious food choices without sacrificing the pleasure of good food.
In an event traditionally dedicated to the pleasures of the table, health took center stage. During the 25th edition of the Macau Gastronomy Festival, the Health Services (SS) transformed the promotion of a balanced diet into a participatory and accessible experience, managing to directly involve more than 3,000 people through an educational tent set up in the center of the venue.
The initiative, part of the “Healthy Community” program, proposed implementing the “paradigm change” and “decentralization of resources” policies of the “Action Plan for Healthy Macau”. In partnership with the Union of Associations of Owners of Restaurants and Beverage Establishments of Macau, the strategy involved taking the message of conscious nutrition directly to the public, in a relaxed and familiar atmosphere, already well known at the festival.
The practical pillar of the intervention was the focus on the “Restaurants – Healthy Food” program. During the festival, 12 establishments (around 10% of the total number of traders present) joined the initiative, displaying the program's logo and offering at least one healthy dish designed under the recommendation of nutritionists. This offer allowed residents and tourists to easily identify balanced options, promoting the culture that one can “enjoy gastronomy while practicing a healthy diet”. According to the SS, local traders reported an increasing demand from residents for this type of options in recent years, which has encouraged them to innovate in offering healthier dishes.
For the first time at the festival, the SS set up a dedicated tent, where knowledge about nutrition was transmitted through fun games. Activities such as reading tongue twisters, quick question and answer sessions and explanations about caloric balance through physical exercise captivated thousands of participants. At the same time, a 'check-ins' campaign on social media (Facebook, Instagram, Xiaohongshu and Douyin) recorded more than 1,000 shares, expanding the reach of the message beyond the event venue.
During the busiest times, namely Friday, Saturday and Sunday nights, the festival's main stage also hosted question and answer sessions with prizes, under the theme “Three portions of vegetables, two portions of fruit – a rainbow on the plate”. The objective was to clarify with greater emphasis one of the key messages of healthy eating, which is the recommendation to consume at least three portions of vegetables daily, equivalent to a bowl of raw vegetables or half a bowl of cooked ones and two portions of fruit, which is roughly equivalent to the size of two fists. Avid audience participation demonstrated a positive assimilation of the nutritional concepts conveyed, SS said.
Currently, the “Restaurants – Healthy Food” program already has the support of more than 300 establishments in the territory, covering a wide range of cuisines, from Chinese and Western to Japanese, Korean and Southeast Asian. From then on, these traders are committed to making at least five healthy dishes available daily, according to the organizers.
The SS renewed the call for more restaurants to join the initiative, highlighting the importance of tripartisan cooperation between “government promotion, sector support and resident participation” to create a truly healthy food environment in the community.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 23:07:08</pubDate></item><item><title>“In very urban cities, water is like a place of freedom”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/04/em-cidades-muito-urbanas-a-agua-e-como-um-lugar-de-liberdade/</link><description>The “Women From The Sea” project explores the deep connection between women and the ocean. After a first edition in the Azores, the initiative now lands in the South China Sea looking for 88 women from Macau and Hong Kong who want to share their stories of connection with the sea. Those responsible for the initiative spoke to PONTO FINAL about the origins and future prospects for the initiative, which already has the participation of almost a thousand women.

There are those who look at the sea and see it as an infinite source of inspiration and tranquility. Others fear the treacherous waves, which become stormy as soon as you turn your back on them, and the blue that drops to pitch black on dimly lit nights. The sea is peaceful, destructive, calming, terrifying – but, above all, it is a symbol of life.
It is also a symbol of femininity. Since ancient times, the female figure and temperament have been linked to the sea, whether through legends about mysterious mermaids or scientific theories about their role as a generating force for all life on planet Earth. It is this deep connection between women and the sea that “Women From The Sea” aims to explore, elevating voices that are often neglected in an industry still largely dominated by men.
The first edition of the project took place in the Azores and brought together hundreds of women of different origins, ages, professions and cultures, focused on a common passion. The next phase, which includes the production of documentaries, a mini-series and a communication campaign that extends to social media, now dives from the heart of the Atlantic to the South China Sea.
The organization's objective is to find 88 (intentionally chosen number) “sea women” living in Macau and Hong Kong by January next year, so that they can share with the world what makes them love, respect and fear the oceans. What worries them, in a world where human activity corrupts soil, skies and sea.
About a month before the scheduled start date of the initiative, PONTO FINAL spoke with the director and founder Raquel Martins and the environmental activist Tanja Wessels, responsible for international affairs. Macau women who feel a special connection with the sea – any type of connection, with no right or wrong answers – are invited to join this global community, just a click away.

How did this project come about and what is its mission?
Raquel Martins: The project started in 2021. At the time, I was looking for projects and they asked me to do something related to the ocean. It's something that I've always loved, that has always been part of me... It's my refuge, where I feel at home. At that time, I was starting to get involved with people, mainly from the “Escola Azul” [educational program coordinated by the Directorate-General for Maritime Policy], who told me about the state of the oceans. In a conversation with a friend, I mentioned that I would love to hear the voices of women who have an emotional connection to the ocean and he thought it would be a very powerful project. At the beginning, we thought: "Let's keep it in Portugal, but not just with Portuguese women. They can be of any age, professional background or culture, as long as they have an emotional connection with the sea." And these women started to appear. By the end of the first year, we had over 100 women eager to speak. This is what makes the project unique: bringing together women who have nothing in common, except the most important thing in their lives. The ocean. At the end of 2023, we ask for UNESCO's support to be a Decade of the Oceans project. We had some very good partners joining us: the UNESCO Intergovernmental Oceanographic Commission, the Canadian Ministry of Fisheries and the Ocean, the Government of the Azores…

The first project was in the Azores. Why film this next documentary on the other side of the world?
Tanja Wessels: In 2026, I will complete 20 years of my life in Asia, and it will also be the time to say goodbye and return to Portugal. Before that, I would love to pay tribute to two cities that meant a lot to me: Hong Kong and Macau. Taking this project to these cities would be a dream come true and also a way to honor all the extraordinary women I met in these cities when I lived there and was involved in sustainability projects. So even though “Women from the Sea” is a global project – and will always be a global project – I thought we could bring this part of Asia into the conversation. It's an interesting and valuable part of the world, but sometimes overlooked when it comes to these topics. That is my great wish. We have big dreams and we are just starting to put them into practice, but by January 2026 we hope to be on the right track.

They say they want to find 88 participants by January. Why this number?
Tanja Wessels: I've been in China for too long (laughs). Well, actually the goal is to get as many people as possible. We are cautious and thoughtful about who we bring into the team: we talk to people, we do interviews, we count on the trust of the people we already work with. But we are also very open, because this is not our project. We are just guardians of the concept. So, 88 seemed like a tangible goal to make us think about what the pace of work will be like. How many people do we need per week? What are the logistics? If we have more than 88 women, fantastic. It's not a race. It's a very organic process.

Looking at Macau, in recent decades there has been a major expansion of the territory through landfill projects. Will the documentary address the environmental impact of this practice? What kind of stories do you expect to hear here?
Tanja Wessels: We hope to reflect what women are thinking, and that can happen in different ways. When we think about ocean pollution or problems in the ocean, we think about beach cleanups, for example. But, as he pointed out, the reality is that there are many different layers that are not always visible to the public. If we can find someone who is campaigning to draw attention to the issue of land reclamation and the devastation it causes to the ecosystem, this issue will be addressed. Much of Hong Kong is also reclaimed land. We get used to thinking that this is normal and natural, but people don't necessarily think long term. With rising sea levels and uncertain weather patterns, floods and typhoons, what does this mean for Macau's future 50 or 100 years from now? What are the unintended consequences of moving the ocean floor and building on the water? We haven't met anyone from Macau yet, but I interviewed a young woman from Hong Kong who had just moved to Peng Chau island. It was the first time she lived near the sea and at night she liked to walk by the sea... She felt calm, at peace. This is someone who never grew up near water, and who now cannot imagine their life without it and the well-being they derive from this experience. Many people simply don't know what they're missing because they've never known what it's like to wake up and hear the sound of waves. How could they question him? In cities like this, very urban, stressful and with little time available, water influences everyday life in unexpected ways. People go to meditate, dive… it's like a place of freedom for them. For people who come from coastal countries it may seem normal, but for people who live in high-rise buildings it is a new idea.

Raquel Martins: Regarding the content of the documentary, we have a set of questions that we prepared and adapted locally. For example, when I was filming in the Azores, I asked what it was like to live on an island, to be surrounded by water every day. It's different from living on the mainland. But the set of questions, the basis of our questionnaire when we interview, is emotional. We don't have an agenda.

On your page, you describe women's connection with the sea as something almost spiritual. Do you think there is a biological predisposition for this connection?
Raquel Martins: We are often asked: "Why not men? Men also have an emotional connection with water...". I'm not a scientist, but I know we came from water. We were in the water in our mother's body – and even now, when I'm floating, especially if the sun is shining and the water isn't too cold, it's like I'm back in the womb. It's something I've felt forever, and then I started hearing women talk about it. We come from the water, we carry our babies in the water, in our bodies, and we take care of them… There are these two aspects, caring and carrying, that are related to water. Our role in Humanity is to create. Obviously there are men who also do this, but they have a different program in their bodies. When it comes to survival, they are more aggressive and we are more united. Of course these are all stereotypes, but talking to so many women over the last four years has shown me that this is common for women who have a connection to the ocean. They are naturally caregivers. That's why it's interesting to hear the voices of those who identify as women and have this feminine perspective on caring for others, because that's our motto.

Regarding financing, have you approached any local organizations?
Tanja: On January 31st we are going to Club Lusitano in Hong Kong, for the launch of the project, and the Portuguese consul general, Alexandre Leitão, will be present for the opening words. We were very honored and flattered. We have also been in contact with IPOR and [director] Patrícia Quaresma, but we are still at a very early stage. We hope that once we finish the pitch deck, we can get more feedback and engagement. In the Hong Kong group, we have two women who work with diving and sustainability and are helping us boost that side of the project. This is not a Portuguese project – it is international. We want to reach people who normally wouldn't take part in these types of initiatives, people who don't know how to swim, who don't speak English. We want to strengthen our ties with Chinese organizations and communities and with all the people we haven't met yet.

Raquel: We need someone on the ground to spread the message, to start talking to local people and organizations. This is normally how we do it, always by word of mouth. A woman is interviewed and meets a friend, who meets another friend… That's what I love about the project. It's always growing, growing, growing, and now there are more than 900 women.

What message do you give to the women of Macau who are reading this interview?
Tanja: The first step is to contact us – and there are so many ways to do that. We're on LinkedIn, Facebook, Instagram... just send a message and we'll take care of the rest. Raquel and I are in different time zones, so there is always someone awake to respond. We are starting from scratch and we appreciate all kind of support, even in terms of equipment and locations for filming, translation...

Raquel: You can also get in touch through our website, helpimages.org. The important thing is that they feel a connection with the sea. We are not going to define it, nor are there right or wrong answers. It's an emotional connection. It's taking care of what we love.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Children of tycoon Jimmy Lai worried about the health of their father detained in Hong Kong</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/04/filhos-do-magnata-jimmy-lai-preocupados-com-a-saude-do-pai-detido-em-hong-kong/</link><description>The children of Jimmy Lai, the Hong Kong tycoon who has been imprisoned for five years, expressed concern about their father's poor health during a meeting with journalists in Washington, the AFP news agency reported yesterday.
"He has lost a lot of weight and is much weaker than before. His nails are turning almost purple, gray and greenish before they fall out, and his teeth are rotting," the tycoon's daughter, Claire Lai, told journalists, including from AFP, who left Hong Kong after visiting her father a few months ago.
Claire Lai spoke to the media during a visit to Washington, where the family is seeking support to free her father.
Jimmy Lai, a major media businessman in Hong Kong, was accused by Beijing of sedition and collusion with foreign forces during the 2019 pro-democracy protests, in which he was a central figure.
The media mogul, who will turn 78 next Monday, has been in prison since December 2020. Diabetic, Jimmy Lai has been held in solitary confinement without air conditioning in a prison where summer temperatures reach 44°C, his children said.
The Hong Kong Government condemned what it called the “distortion” of Lai’s story in the press, including reports published by AFP. “These reports seek to defame [the Hong Kong Government] by attempting to deceive the public,” authorities in the Chinese territory said in a statement. According to Hong Kong authorities, Jimmy Lai is receiving “adequate and comprehensive” care in prison.
Jimmy Lai, founder of the banned pro-democracy newspaper Apple Daily, is accused of inciting Western governments to impose sanctions on China and the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region following the repression of the pro-democracy movement. He is also accused of producing seditious articles and content, including editorials published under his own name. These crimes are severely punished by law.
Jimmy Lai's son, Sebastian Lai, hopes that US President Donald Trump and British Prime Minister Keir Starmer will continue to raise his father's – who is a British citizen – issue with China. "It would only take two hours to put my father on a plane and send him to another place. It would be the human thing to do, it would be the right thing to do", said the businessman's son, adding that his father was "put through hell".</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 23:01:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Government reiterates support for emerging scientific and technological industries</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/04/governo-reitera-apoio-as-industrias-cientificas-e-tecnologicas-emergentes/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai reaffirmed the Government's support for Macau's technological development, with a determination to “optimize the technological innovation ecosystem” and promote the growth of emerging scientific and technological industries. At the opening of the first edition of the Global Exhibition of Artificial Intelligence Machines and Electronic Products, the Chief Executive admitted the implementation of the government fund for industries and the guidance fund.

The first edition of the Global Exhibition of Artificial Intelligence Machines and Electronic Products (AIE) opened yesterday, an initiative jointly organized by the authorities of Macau and Zhuhai with a program of three consecutive days, with the participation of professional buyers, exhibitors and technological leaders from more than 30 countries and regions.
The Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, once again valued Macau's technological development and assured, in his speech at the opening of the exhibition, the provision of support to emerging scientific and technological industries. “We will persistently optimize Macau’s technological innovation ecosystem, promoting synergies between the transformation of research results and their commercialization to catalyze new drivers of economic growth,” he said.
The Government leader highlighted that he will also promote the construction of four relevant projects, including the Macau Scientific and Technological Research and Development Industrial Park, whose plan is in the public opinion gathering phase, in addition to moving forward with work to implement the government fund for industries and the guidance fund.
The authorities will also take advantage of the development of the Hengqin Deep Cooperation Zone and the integration of the Greater Bay Area to promote the growth of emerging scientific and technological industries, “injecting new impetus into the high-quality development of the global electronic information sector”, said the official.
According to Sam Hou Fai, the exhibition, themed “Smart Manufacturing in the Greater Bay Area and Global Sharing”, adopts the innovative model of “one event, two locations”, taking place simultaneously in Macau and Zhuhai. The Macau exhibition area mainly focuses on intelligent electronics, while the Zhuhai exhibition area mainly focuses on intelligent machinery.
The event features the launch of new elements in existing and newly innovated products, and the latest achievements in the high-tech domain will be showcased.
“In addition, by articulating innovative policies, such as the separate line management system in the Deep Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin, an international electronics consumption platform will be jointly created that simultaneously integrates exhibition, incubation and contact exchange”, highlighted Sam.
Also in his speech, Sam Hou Fai recalled a speech by Chinese President Xi Jinping given during a visit to Guangdong last month, in which he “clearly indicated the direction for deepening cooperation between Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau”.
The Chief Executive understands the Greater Bay Area as a center for the global consumption of smart products, namely electronic products, smart household appliances, high-tech equipment and vehicles powered by new energy, thus having the advantages of bringing together smart electronics industries and industrial chains of scientific and technological innovation.
Finally, Sam Hou Fai highlighted that Macau, as an international city, has been facilitating the participation of foreign professionals from different sectors in exhibitions and conferences for investments and commercial negotiations in the city.
Durante a exposição, foi criado também o “Pavilhão de Inovação e Tecnologia de Macau”, onde serão apresentados os 4 Laboratórios de Referência do Estado em Macau, assim como os novos resultados inovadores gerados pela colaboração entre empresas tecnológicas e o conjunto tríplice da indústria-academia-investigação.
The initiatives “facilitate deep integration and efficient correspondence between technology and national and international industrial fabrics and a professional services portal for intelligent machines and electronic products in the Greater Bay Area and across the country will be established”, said Sam Hou Fai.
 
Government buildings will have photovoltaic solar energy installations
 
The photovoltaic solar energy generation equipment in the Macau Electricity Company (CEM) building will come into operation by the end of this month, and the relevant installations will be extended to Public Administration buildings in the future, revealed Benjamin Yue, main advisor to the CEM Executive Committee. According to CEM's new concession contract, which was renewed for 15 years and will come into force next year, the expansion and modernization of public renewable energy generation facilities are planned. Quoted by the newspaper Ou Mun, on the sidelines of the Global Exhibition of Artificial Intelligence Machines and Electronic Products, Benjamin Yue said yesterday that, in addition to the CEM building, the two thermal power plants in Macau are preparing to install a photovoltaic solar energy generation system, scheduled to start operating next year. A similar installation has already been completed at the thermal plant in Zone A of Novos Aterros. Regarding the forecast for Macau's electricity consumption, Benjamin Yue estimates that there will be a slight increase of 0.2% this year compared to last year. Furthermore, CEM has partnered with technology company Pachira to introduce 24-hour multilingual intelligent customer service services to reduce customers' waiting time and improve service experience and quality.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 23:09:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Walking continues to lead the way residents travel</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/04/andar-a-pe-continua-a-liderar-os-modos-de-deslocacao-dos-residentes/</link><description>Traveling on foot continues to be the form of transportation that residents adopt most in their daily trips, revealed a survey by the Traffic Affairs Services about the population's travel habits. Buses remain the main means of motorized transport used by residents.

Instead of using buses or private cars, Macau citizens travel more on foot in their daily lives and choose to walk in almost half of the trips made over the past year. This is the conclusion of the “Macau Origin-Destination Matrix Study” for 2024, a survey that takes place every five years and was released yesterday by the Traffic Affairs Services Department (DSAT).
The results of the survey reveal that, among the different modes of travel, walking continues to record the highest proportion, corresponding to 46.5% of total travel. The percentage choosing to walk remains stable compared to that recorded in the last survey carried out in 2019, when walking occupied 46.3% of public trips.
Walking has been the most used form of mobility in Macau according to the latest DSAT surveys dating back to 2009, when even more residents chose to walk, in around 49.7% of their trips.
Furthermore, according to the study, buses remain the main means of motorized transport used by residents, being the second most used method of travel in Macau. Although the proportion of bus use in 2024 registered a drop of one percentage point compared to 2019, it remains the main choice for around a fifth of residents' trips, at 20.9%. The proportion of use of private passenger cars increased by 0.8 percentage points last year compared to that recorded five years ago, rising from 14.7% to 15.5%.
DSAT's analysis also indicates that traveling by motorbike is among the preferred means of transport in the territory, but with increasingly less frequent use. The use of motorbikes stands at 11.3% between trips, having suffered a drop of 0.5 percentage points compared to 2019, and 4.2 percentage points compared to 2014, as well as a decrease of 5.5 percentage points compared to 2009.
Among other means of transport, the use of direct buses for workers or students represents 4.2% of total trips, followed by direct buses from casinos, taxis and Light Rail.
In trips made by residents using motorized vehicles, there is a continuous increase in the proportion of trips between the islands, as well as a gradual increase in the demand for trips on the islands. In 2024, the proportions of inter-island travel and intra-island travel increased by 0.3% and 2.8%, respectively, compared to 2019.
The report also analyzed the average travel time for trips with motorized vehicles. Last year, the average travel time overall was approximately 31 minutes, a reduction of 1 minute compared to 2019, with the decrease primarily attributable to public bus travel times. Travel by private car and motorbike remains the same as it was five years ago.
In general, over the last decade, travel times using motorized vehicles have shown a slight downward trend.
With regard to night parking spaces for private cars, parking in private car parks with monthly rentals predominates in the choice of resident drivers, with this trend showing an upward trend. Among other forms of driver preference are parking in public car parks (17.4%), in metered spaces (17.2%), in spaces with free parking for workers or students (15.3%) and in private car parks with hourly rentals (2.4%).
Motorcycles, however, are mainly parked in parking meter spaces, at 53.6%, although this practice is in continuous decline, from 71.7%, recorded in 2014, and 57.8%, in 2019.
According to DSAT, the Executive has carried out the survey every five years since 2009, with the aim of understanding the population's habits and opinions regarding their travel, in order to be able to “update and formulate transport policies and plans more precisely”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 23:10:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau wants to remain a platform for attracting tourists between Portugal and China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/04/macau-quer-manter-se-como-plataforma-de-captacao-de-turistas-entre-portugal-e-china/</link><description>Helena de Senna Fernandes wants the city to continue to be a platform for attracting tourists between Portugal and China. The Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies announced that it once again chose Macau – which hosted this congress for the sixth time – as the association's Preferred Destination in 2026, which will allow the partnership to be strengthened.

The director of the Directorate of Tourism Services (DST) wants the city to continue to be a platform for attracting tourists between Portugal and China. “The work developed in recent years in partnership with APAVT, to showcase Macau and to open doors to tour operators and boost tourist flows, must continue”, said Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes yesterday.
The person in charge was speaking at the closing of the 50th congress of the Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies (APAVT), which took place in Macau between Tuesday and yesterday. “Today we close [a cycle], but we will continue with other work, and the designation of Macau as a [APAVT international] Preferred Destination for 2026 provides the framework to keep this connection alive”, he recalled.
The director of DST added, in closing, that “another fundamental idea” of the region is that operators and travel agents bear in mind the advantage they have in “accessing the market in the interior of China, taking advantage of the platform provided by Macau to create itineraries and destinations”. Portuguese people do not need a prior visa to enter China for up to 30 days.
“The partnership with APAVT over the last three years has really been one of our management's main strategies to boost the Portuguese market, and there have been a series of joint initiatives, above all, to reconnect with Portuguese tour operators”, he had also stated on Wednesday.
Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes discussed the numbers obtained, which, she says, “show this path well”. “Until October, the number of visitors, both from Portugal and from Europe in general, registered an annual increase in the order of double digits, recovering to around 80% of the pre-pandemic period figures”, he said.
APAVT announced that it once again chose Macau – which hosted this congress for the sixth time – as the association's Preferred Destination in 2026, which will allow the partnership to be strengthened. APAVT's Preferred Destination is a program that includes the areas of communication and marketing, and thus helps the chosen destination to promote itself in other markets.
"Macau and APAVT have decided that they should not stop. That is why I convey to you with great joy that we have decided, Macau and APAVT, that Macau will be APAVT's preferred international destination throughout 2026", stated the president of APAVT, Pedro Costa Ferreira in the territory. "I can't be happier. You know my status in my last term. I'm fulfilling a dream, which is to return to Macau and work with Macau again. (…) The Congress has been, in my opinion, memorable from the point of view of the themes, but it has also been memorable from the point of view of the number, it is the biggest ever, and it has been memorable from the point of view of reception capacity", reinforced Pedro Costa Ferreira.
APAVT's Preferred Destination is a “very broad” program, which has two fundamental parts, communication and marketing, and which, in this way, helps the chosen destination to promote itself. "It means that in all our presences, we will have Macau with us and, therefore, we have this communication, added the president of the association, remembering that in this way there is a reinforcement of a relationship that has existed for many years. "The return of Congress to our city this year and the designation of Macau, along with China, Preferred Destination for 2026, paves the way for us to continue working well", said the director of the Macau Tourism Services Directorate, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes.
The main new feature in 2026 for Destino Preferido will be the launch of an 'e-learning' program about Macau for travel agents from Germany, Finland and the Netherlands, just like the program that was launched in Portugal in 2024.
The ‘e-learning’ will be developed by APAVT and Macau Tourism, in collaboration with the European Confederation of Travel Agents’ and Tour Operators’ Associations [ECTAA]).
Pedro Costa Ferreira also recalled that this congress has several “special meanings”, firstly “because it is the sixth” in Macau and because it was chosen “to complete the celebration of the 75th anniversary” of the association.
APAVT says it has accredited 1,039 congressmen from 172 different flights, congressmen who “will now visit several provinces in China in collaboration with Macau Tourism”.
The number of tourists passing through the territory was the highest for any month of October since the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) began compiling monthly data, in 1998, still during the Portuguese administration. The region had also recorded an all-time high for September the previous month: almost 3.8 million visitors, 9.8% more than in the same period in 2024.
On January 17, the director of Macau Tourism Services said she expected between 38 and 39 million visitors this year. In August, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes set a goal of more than three million international visitors by 2025.
In the first 10 months of the year, Macau received almost 2.97 million tourists from abroad, 14.9% more than in the same period in 2024. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 23:09:08</pubDate></item><item><title>China places yuan below expectations after reaching year highs against the dollar</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/04/china-situa-yuan-abaixo-do-esperado-depois-de-atingir-maximos-no-ano-face-ao-dolar/</link><description>China's central bank set its reference exchange rate for the yuan below what markets expected, in a sign that Beijing seeks to halt the currency's recovery against the dollar. The decision, considers the Bloomberg agency, represents the biggest difference between market expectations and the rate finally set by the BPC since February 2022.

China's central bank yesterday set its reference exchange rate for the yuan below what markets expected, in a sign that Beijing is seeking to halt the currency's recovery against the dollar.
According to information released by the People's Bank of China (PBOC, central bank) on its official website, the official exchange rate for yesterday was set at 7.0733 yuan per dollar, 164 'pips' (one hundredth of 1%, a measure used in exchange rate analyses) below the most widespread forecasts among investors and analysts.
The decision, highlights the Bloomberg agency, represents the biggest difference between market expectations and the rate finally set by the BPC since February 2022.
The exchange rate set by the BPC is fundamental for the quotation of the “onshore” rate — negotiated in national markets — of the yuan, as it can only deviate within a maximum daily range of 2%, both when it appreciates and when it depreciates.
Given the optimism that followed the trade truce between China and the United States, followed by the announcement of the possible visit of US President Donald Trump to the Asian country next year, the yuan has been approaching the psychological barrier of 7 units per dollar, and its value in the markets is on track to reach the highest levels since 2020.
Part of the appreciation of the yuan in relation to the dollar is also due to fears, reflected in the US currency, regarding the budgetary policy of the United States, as well as forecasts of a reduction in interest rates by the Federal Reserve (Fed). "The PBOC has been prioritizing exchange rate stability, so it is not surprising (…) that they are slowing down the pace of increases. We do not expect the level of 7 units [per dollar] to be put to the test for the rest of the year, but it will probably be surpassed at some point next year", said Lynn Song, ING's chief economist for China, cited by Bloomberg.
In turn, Khoon Goh, from Australia; New Zealand Banking Group, notes that the PBOC seeks to “manage the rhythms” of yuan growth, “but not stop them”. “Most likely, authorities want a smoother pace of appreciation for the currency, especially given the expected volatility in exchange rates,” he added.
At the beginning of the year, the Asian giant's currency was close to falling to its lowest levels since 2007, due to fears of the impact of the trade war with the United States, and some analysts pointed out that Beijing would try not to revalue itself, in order to support the competitiveness of Chinese exports. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 23:02:17</pubDate></item><item><title>The tragedy of the fire in Tai Po and its sociopolitical implications</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/04/a-tragedia-do-incendio-em-tai-po-e-as-suas-implicacoes-sociopoliticas/</link><description>The fire that engulfed Wang Fuk Court in Tai Po a few days ago is not only a great tragedy, but also an event with profound implications for the construction profession, society and politics in the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region (HKSAR).
The Fire Department and its officers are to be commended for their diligent efforts in fighting the fire, which broke out on the afternoon of November 26th. At night, the fire level was raised from level three to five, which made the firefighters' work in fighting the fire and rescuing the victims very difficult.
The government said the fire was apparently caused by the spread of flammable materials outside the eight building blocks at Wang Fuk Court, including especially the Styrofoam used to seal the windows, which is highly flammable. One building was miraculously intact, but the other seven were seriously damaged. It was reported that from July until the fire broke out, the Department of Labor conducted sixteen inspections, issued six notices of required improvements, and served three notices of legal action, most of which related to high-end renovation work. It is unclear whether inspections will have to require higher standards in the future — a question that is left to the conclusion and recommendations of the investigative working group created by Chief Executive John Lee.
Another agent suspected of having stimulated the spread of the fire was, in addition to the Styrofoam that sealed the windows to prevent them from being damaged by debris, the mesh that wrapped the external wall of the buildings. Whatever the reasons for the fire's rapid spread, the Independent Commission Against Corruption (ICAC) arrested eight people from the contractor and two other consultancy firms.
The government acted quickly, carrying out a citywide inspection to see if other buildings being renovated with scaffolding and protective nets could use Styrofoam sheets to cover windows. By November 29, two other cases of renewal were found and the companies involved were immediately forced to remove the materials. The Department of Buildings issued a directive requesting all registered construction companies and contractors to review and report their renovation projects using scaffolding and netting within a week. This swift action demanded by the Chief Executive and carried out by the government was appropriate and commendable.
Without a doubt, the practices of contractors responsible for renovation work will have to be rigorously reviewed, with much stricter guidelines to be used and heavier penalties to be applied in the near future, if another similar tragedy is to be avoided.
Additionally, some residents complained that the fire alarm systems in the Wang Fuk Court buildings did not work — a serious matter that will need to be investigated further. Some residents indignantly pointed out the unprofessional behavior of some workers, who smoked during renovation work and ignored residents' requests to stop smoking. If smoke is found to be the source of the fire tragedy, the ethical and professional standards of all workers under the supervision of contractors and those in charge must be reinforced and strictly observed.
Some experts maintained that bamboo scaffolding was not the main cause of the fire, while others called on the government to study the possibility of replacing the traditional use of bamboo scaffolding with steel scaffolding. This issue will be addressed by the working group created by John Lee, but it is clear that any transition from the use of bamboo scaffolding to steel scaffolding will take time, including the retraining of workers and contractors.
The fire tragedy was apparently stimulated and accelerated by a strong wind that suddenly arose and swirled around several buildings, as seen in videos on social media, while flammable materials outside the buildings caused the fire to quickly spread from the base to the top of the skyscraper in a very short period of time.
Some internet users questioned the equipment used by the Fire Department, but its chief explained that the helicopters could not be used due to concerns about the precision of the water dropped on the buildings and that the wind produced by the helicopters could have worsened the fire on top of the buildings. Internet users also raised the issue of using drones and using fire engines with much taller ladders. Fire officials explained that drones with lower water volumes could not handle many burning apartments simultaneously. Fire engineering experts have also noted that there are real limitations to using large fire engines in Hong Kong's narrow streets.
In Shenzhen, drones carrying extinguishing agents, robots and thermal imaging devices were used (South China Morning Post, November 20, 2025). Shenzhen also has tall fire escapes, reaching 101 meters or 33 floors. Soon, the Hong Kong Fire Department will have to modernize its advanced equipment and facilities after learning from the experiences of the Tai Po fire tragedy and its difficulties. Chief Executive John Lee mentioned that his government had drawn up a list of equipment for which the Fire Department would need more support from the mainland Chinese government.
There were media reports that the Shenzhen fire department was prepared to help Hong Kong on the night of November 26th. On November 27, Chief Executive John Lee said he thanked neighboring cities for their concerns, and the Fire Department confirmed that it had not requested help from the mainland (Hong Kong Standard, November 27, 2025). The Fire Department had enough personnel to deal with the fire at Wang Fuk Court. Thus, there was no need to request help from Shenzhen. Furthermore, allowing fire engines from Shenzhen to enter the HKSAR could create other problems, such as the issue of cross-border coordination and leadership and whether narrow streets would be able to accommodate fire engines from the mainland.
On the evening of November 26, President Xi Jinping expressed his condolences to the fatal victims of the Tai Po fire and the firefighter who sacrificed his life in the line of duty (Hong Kong Standard, November 26, 2025). He extended his condolences to the families of the deceased and asked that all efforts be made to fight the fire. He requested that the Hong Kong and Macao Affairs Office and the Liaison Office support the HKSAR government in doing everything possible to deal with the fire.
In response to President Xi's appeal, the Liaison Office created an emergency task force to assist the HKSAR government. On the other hand, two deputy directors of the Hong Kong and Macau Affairs Office (HKMAO), Xu Qifang and Nong Rong, led a working group that visited Hong Kong to help with relief efforts (TVB News, November 27, 2025). Zhou Ji, director of the Liaison Office, and Nong Rong went to visit the victims of the disaster on the morning of November 27, expressing the central government's deep concern for Hong Kong.
The deep concern expressed by central authorities shows the positive dynamics of central-local relations between Beijing and Hong Kong. On the one hand, the central government is supporting the HKSAR government in all matters related to disaster relief, including providing equipment to the fire department and logistical support to families affected by the fire. On the other hand, the HKMAO is observing how the HKSAR government is handling post-disaster relief work.
Traditionally, the chief executives of Hong Kong and Macau must present their annual reports to the central leadership in December. John Lee is expected to present a preliminary report on the fire tragedy to President Xi and Premier Li Qiang.
The fire tragedy has enormous sociopolitical implications for Hong Kong.
Firstly, the people of Hong Kong not only stood together, but also showed great solidarity and immense support for the victims of the fire. Donations and logistical supplies were sent to areas near Wang Fuk Court, prompting the government to announce on November 29 that any additional donations and supplies would have to be centralized. Groups and organizations also provided financial support to victims. The mourning for the victims of the fire tragedy began on November 29th and continued until December 1st.
Secondly, on the evening of November 29, the Office for Safeguarding National Security of the Central People's Government of the People's Republic of China in the HKSAR made a statement saying that during the fire tragedy, some people who are "anti-China and disruptive to Hong Kong" are still trying to act and create chaos (TVB News, November 29, 2025). According to the Cabinet, some people spread fake news to attack the HKSAR government's rescue work and used "public opinion" to try to create trouble. Social media reported that Hong Kong police observed a trend of some activists from the 2019 violence appearing to be active in donation work and logistics provision in Tai Po. If this news were true, it was natural for the Cabinet to issue a statement on the evening of November 29th.
Third, while netizens on social media became quite critical of the government's handling of the fire tragedy, some young activists distributed leaflets in Tai Po, asking more citizens to sign in support of four demands: (1) persistence in helping the victims and relocating them; (2) creation of an investigation committee to uncover any “hidden transfer of interests”; (3) renewal of scrutiny of building renovation works; and (4) persecution of government officials who may have been negligent and failed to supervise. Activists launched an online signing site, but this was quickly closed on the evening of November 29, with 10,262 supporters having already signed the petition.
It is unclear whether the activists who launched this petition and the online site were the potential “rioters” mentioned by the central government's Office for Safeguarding National Security in the HKSAR. On the night of November 29, social media claimed that one of the activists was being investigated by the police.
Fourth, at a time when HKSAR authorities have already mentioned the importance of public service accountability, especially after the water bottle scandal, the government is likely to be more politically cautious in dealing with the Tai Po fire tragedy. If the government tries to determine the responsibility of any department, it may give the impression that this would fit with the young activists' demands, especially the fourth demand, which called for holding the government accountable. However, without investigating how any department can do a better job, such action would unintentionally and curiously deviate from mainland China's practice of holding local officials accountable for their possible negligence, such as the period when the Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS) and Covid-19 outbreak witnessed some local cadres and officials being held accountable and being transferred, demoted or punished. The Tai Po fire perhaps focuses more on holding the construction industry and building renovation sector accountable to the government and members of the public.
Fifth, at the time of writing, it is unclear whether the Legislative Council elections will be postponed. Regardless, observers will have to closely monitor not only voter turnout but also how voters express their preferences, especially in the Tai Po district. Hong Kong's new political culture is characterized by three types of citizens: those who are politically active, those who are politically apathetic, and those who are online cynics who are quite critical of the government, as expressed in the opinions of netizens on social media. It remains to be seen how the fire tragedy will have a possible impact on registered voters.

Conclusion

The fire in Tai Po is an unprecedented event in the history of the HKSAR. The death toll far surpassed the tragedy of the Garley building fire in November 1996, which killed forty-one citizens. There is a need to learn from the Wang Fuk Court fire, including how the construction and building renovation sectors should improve their professional and ethical standards and conduct, how management companies can and should supervise their building renovation works, how government departments can strengthen their scrutiny and inspections of contractors, and how contractors who violate required professional standards should be severely penalized. At a time when the HKSAR has just strengthened its national security and is focusing on promoting economic prosperity, it is perhaps ironic that the Tai Po fire tragedy points to some crucial gaps and failures in protecting human security, which is an indispensable part of national security by global and mainland Chinese standards. The Tai Po fire disaster calls for more effective corrective actions in terms of strengthening relief work, relocating victims after the disaster, and psychological counseling for victims and their families. It also requires deeper reflection and study into how professional standards and conduct in the building construction and renovation industry should further improve. In response to the fire tragedy in Hong Kong, authorities in mainland China took swift action to require all construction companies and their related contractors to review the materials they use in building renovation works — a swift action that points to the efficiency and effectiveness of China's governance. As a Chinese and international city, Hong Kong must learn a bitter lesson from this tragic fire accident and prevent it from happening again in the future.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 22:55:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan bond yields rise to highest level since 2007</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/04/rendimento-dos-titulos-da-divida-do-japao-sobe-para-nivel-mais-alto-desde-2007/</link><description>The yield on Japanese 10-year debt reached 1.91% yesterday, the highest level since July 2007, due to expectations that the Bank of Japan (BoJ) will raise interest rates.
Japan's central bank governor, Kazuo Ueda, sparked speculation on Monday about a possible rate hike, when he suggested in a speech before business leaders that economic conditions are ripe for continuing with the normalization of monetary policy, which the organization suspended in January to assess the impact of new United States tariffs.
Without anticipating the outcome of the BoJ's next monetary policy meeting in the middle of this month, Ueda said that "appropriately adjusting the level of monetary easing, neither too late nor too early, is necessary to smoothly achieve the objective of price stability, while ensuring the stability of financial and capital markets." The words caused sharp falls on the Tokyo Stock Exchange and debt securities, which had already reached highs since the 2008 financial crisis due to concerns about the archipelago's fiscal health, soared.
They also happened after the announcement by the new Japanese Executive of Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi, last Thursday, of the project for the expected supplementary budget for 2025, valued at 18.3 billion yen (more than 100 billion euros), which will be financed largely with the issuance of State bonds, and intended above all for an ambitious stimulus package.
The BoJ is, by far, the largest investor in bonds of the most indebted country among the most advanced economies, whose yield is the barometer par excellence of long-term rates.
The central bank has kept benchmark interest rates at 0.5% for the past six monetary policy meetings, since a 25 basis point increase in January.
The last meeting of the year generated great expectations, after the change of government in Japan, in October, but the BoJ maintained a cautious stance, before knowing the financial position of the new prime minister – who was critical in relation to the rise in interest rates – and also taking a stabilized view on tariff negotiations with the United States, Japan's second largest trading partner, after China.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 23:00:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Seoul pledges efforts to repatriate six citizens detained in North Korea</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/12/04/seul-promete-esforcos-para-repatriar-seis-cidadaos-detidos-na-coreia-do-norte/</link><description>The South Korean government yesterday committed to seeking the repatriation of six citizens detained on espionage and other charges in North Korea between 2013 and 2016, even though Pyongyang refuses dialogue with Seoul. “We will resolve the problem by striving to quickly resume inter-Korean dialogue based on national consensus,” stated the presidential office, in a response that was pending on Wednesday at a press conference by South Korean President Lee Jae-myung, in which the head of state acknowledged that he was not aware of the matter.
The six citizens include three North Koreans who defected to South Korea. The other three are missionaries detained by North Korean authorities between 2013 and 2014, namely Kim Jung-wook, Kim Kook-kie and Choi Chun-gil.
The presidential office did not reveal the identity of the three North Korean defectors to protect the safety of their families in the North and prevent them from suffering sanctions by association, normally applied by Pyongyang. “As inter-Korean talks and exchanges have been suspended for a long time, the suffering of our people continues and the issue needs to be resolved urgently,” adds the statement, cited by The Korea Herald.
Seoul requested the release of the missionaries in March, still under the previous South Korean government, at the request of the Ministry of Unification, after a United Nations working group classified the detentions as illegal.
The last time the issue of detained South Koreans was openly discussed between the two parties was during the 2018 inter-Korean summit between then-South Korean President Moon Jae-in and North Korean leader Kim Jong-un, and in the high-level talks held in the same year. “As a result, a point was very close to the release [of the detainees]. Kim Jong-un even promised the then President Moon: “I will do everything in my power to [the release of the detainees]”, recalled yesterday deputy Yoon Geon-young, who at the time was director of the South Korean presidential Situation Room.
Kim explained that, after the failed Hanoi summit between Pyongyang and Washington in 2019, and the Covid-19 pandemic, inter-Korean relations deteriorated, “so it was not possible to obtain a result”. “The reason why we were unable to publicly inform citizens about this situation at that time was simple: in matters such as the release of detainees, if the process is made public, it could negatively affect the outcome depending on the case,” he added.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 23:01:20</pubDate></item></channel></rss>