<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/primeiro-ministro-indiano-ameaca-punir-o-paquistao-por-futuros-ataques/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Trump includes Jimmy Lai's release in commercial negotiations with China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/trump-inclui-libertacao-de-jimmy-lai-nas-negociacoes-comerciais-com-china/</link><description>The US president said he included the release of the tycoon Jimmy Lai, arrested since 2020 in Hong Kong, among the topics to be discussed in the current negotiations with China, focused on tariffs.
Donald Trump, who had previously stated that he was going to seek Lai's release before returning to power, indicated that he had already raised the issue with Beijing and insisted that he will do “everything he can to save” the former owner of the independent newspaper Apple Daily, to be tried in Hong Kong for accusations of collusion and sediction, for which he can be sentenced to perpetual imprisonment.
However, Trump acknowledged that "President XI [Jinping] will not be enthusiastic" to free Lai.
"That said, the name [of Lai] has entered the circle of questions we are talking about and we will see what we can do," added Trump, warning that Lai "is not a young man" and that his health "is not very good."
The US President signed an executive order this week to suspend another 90 days the punitive overcutions in imports of China, while a comprehensive agreement continues to be negotiated.
The suspension of tariff application is the expected result of the last round of negotiations between Americans and Chinese, held in Stockholm, Sweden at the end of last month.
The possible liberation of Jimmy Lai, accused of several crimes under the Hong Kong National Security Act, would be a demonstration of goodwill to advance to a commercial agreement with the US, according to analysts.
Lai and the three companies linked to the extinct Apple Daily newspaper face accusations under the rigorous legislation imposed by Hong Kong in 2020, which provides, along with the local decree of safeguarding national security, penalties that can go to life imprisonment for acts such as betrayal, insurrection, sabotage, external interference, section, state -of -the -art, and spying.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 06:34:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Employment dominates requests for help</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/emprego-domina-pedidos-de-ajuda/</link><description>Several deputies to the Legislative Assembly presented the balance of work carried out in the last session of this legislature and revealed that the employment and housing problem dominated requests for help from the local population.
Deputies linked to the Fujian community, including Si Ka Lon, Song Pek Kei and Nick Law, said they received 5,774 requests for help during the legislative session, on matters such as employment, social housing, repair of old buildings and environmental hygiene.
Manifesting concern about Macao's internal economic governance, the group called for more measures to stimulate the economy and improve the accountability mechanism of civil servants. The government also entered the situation of hiring non-resident workers by large companies, in order to ensure the priority of employment to local residents.
Deputies associated with the community of Jiangmen - Zheng Anting and Lo Choi In, received 2,343 requests for help related to economic development, housing, benefits for the elderly, employment and talent formation.
A melhoria das condições comerciais das pequenas e médias empresas foi um dos pedidos dos dois deputados para o Executivo, que solicitaram o reforço da cooperação interdepartamental na elaboração de políticas económicas. Esperam ainda que o Governo proteja melhor o emprego dos residentes e reforce o apoio aos idosos e aos grupos desfavorecidos, ajustando, por exemplo, as despesas da Residência para Idosos.
Por sua vez, para os deputados ligados à Federação das Associações dos Operários de Macau (FAOM), Ella Lei, Leong Sun Iok, Lam Lon Wai e Lei Chan U registaram seis mil pedidos de ajuda, cuja maioria diz respeito a questões de trabalho e práticas irregulares de recrutamento.
Legislators have complained about the situation where the places are unable to work full time and are part-time, appealing to the reduction in the number of non-resident workers especially in game companies and banks.
They also asked to reduce the repetition of works on public roads and improve the quality and durability of the roads. In addition, they raised questions about pressure on civil servants, requiring the government to implement better personnel management. They also suggested that the maternity leave to 90 days be increased and the Festival of the Dragon Boat is added as a mandatory holiday in Macao.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 06:38:37</pubDate></item><item><title>China will be restricting rare land accumulation by foreign companies</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/china-estara-a-restringir-acumulacao-de-terras-raras-por-empresas-estrangeiras/</link><description>Beijing asked foreign companies to avoid accumulating rare land reservations, at a time when the fear of export restrictions is increasing the demand for these metals, crucial to various strategic technologies, the Financial Times said yesterday.
According to sources cited by the newspaper, Beijing warned that excessive storage of rare lands and derived products, such as ways used on electric motors, could expose companies to higher risk of scarcity. Authorities would also be deliberately limited export volumes approved to wage the creation of large inventories abroad.
China processes about 90% of the worldwide supply of rare land and manufactures 94% of permanent iam, using this control as a pressure instrument during the commercial war with the United States. In April, he placed seven medium and heavy rare land categories on the export control list, which also encompassed permanent iam and other finished products, causing shortage in sectors such as the car.
Efforts to prevent companies from accumulating major inventories, which would give them more flexibility to respond to scarcity and price fluctuations, show Beijing's determination to maintain maximum influence on the sector, sources said.
In April, China placed seven medium-sized rare land categories on an export control list in response to the tariffs imposed by US President Donald Trump. The measure, which also encompassed permanent iam and other finished products, caused scarcity in various sectors, particularly in the automotive industry.
Although Washington and Beijing have woken up this week a new 90 -day length of trade war, Chinese control over rare land supplies remains an important part of negotiations.
Beijing controls the production of rare land through extraction and processing quotas. Last year, only two state -owned companies received quotas.
China exported 3,188 tons of permanent rare land in June, more than twice the May volume, but less than 38% than the same month as last year. From three months to June - since Beijing imposed commercial restrictions - the exports of the imm were about half of the volume recorded in the same period of the previous year.
A study by the US Business Council, conducted in July, indicated that half of the companies inquired saw their pending or rejected export requests, especially when the volume exceeded the historical average.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 06:35:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Portuguese knight bets on the formation of competition horses in China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/cavaleiro-portugues-aposta-na-formacao-de-cavalos-de-competicao-na-china/</link><description>João Ruas Trains six horses daily on a farm outside Beijing. The Portuguese arrived in China a year ago to create six horses and to form Dressage.

 Step, trot and gallop: On a farm outside Beijing, Portuguese João Ruas training six horses daily to the practice of Dressage, an equestrian Olympic discipline that seeks to expose the maximum of the animal's athletic capabilities.
“It's a very very relationship,” he described to Lusa the Knight, a native of Lisbon. "There are days when we are almost like a father to teach the son, others where it is the horse that teaches us to us. But there must always be mutual respect," he said.
Streets, 28, arrived in China a year ago to raise six horses and form Dressage on a farm in Shunyi, the district in northeastern Beijing where the villages and agricultural fields resemble the interior of China than the capital of 22 million.
Ten kilometers from the Huairou reservoir, a 12 -kilometer artificial lake that supplies Beijing and regulates the flow of local rivers, the fifth is surrounded by watercourses, tree -lined slopes, corn fields and natural reserves.
On the horizon, the mountainous chains that rise to the north of the Changing and Huairou districts complete a landscape that contrasts with the tangle of glazed torres and apartments blocks of Beijing's urban network.
“When I'm here I don't remember if I'm in China, Portugal or Germany,” explained João Ruas. "I'm in a bubble, let's say, and it's a good bubble."
Without previous experience in the country, the Portuguese was surprised by the sympathy of the Chinese and the reception of the local community. On the day he was interviewed by the Lusa agency, his cargo tricycle advocated on his way to the supermarket. Depressing the neighbors quickly sent to try to fix the vehicle.
“I am the only foreigner here. I communicate for gestures, I am still learning Chinese, but I have always been very well treated. The neighbors help in everything,” he said.
Despite the enthusiasm with life in the countryside, the coach admits difficulties in the exercise of the sport he has been practicing since he was nine years old. "There is a lot of amateurism, little technique, expensive and poorly frequency evidence. And everything that involves horses here is frankly more expensive than in Europe."
The horse “is not dominated by force: it requires patience, knowledge and sensitivity,” he said.
"It's like an athlete. There are good days and bad days. And don't talk. We have to know how to read the signs. A small reaction may indicate a serious problem," he noted.
In Portugal, João Ruas studied at the D. Dinis Agricultural Professional School, where he reconciled the classes with the weekends passed with the coach. Since then, it never left the horses. "I started with once a week, then two, then three, until I got to five. I had to insist a lot with my parents to start," he said.
In China, he works with European horses, brought on purpose to compete in Dressage evidence. The goal is to prepare animals since the age of three for competitions that normally start at four. "A tradition of creation with sports focus is still missing. Horses have been raised for many years, but not with selective criteria for sport," he said.
Shanghai, the country's economic “capital”, leads the practice of drassage in the country, with more proof and better infrastructure. In Beijing, there is a growing interest, but there is still a long way to go. “It can be good to start like this, almost from scratch. It allows you to do things well. Without addictions,” reflected streets.
With the arrival of another horse soon and the prospect of continuing work in China, João Ruas is said. "I see myself here for many more years. It only costs the distance. But with today's technology, we managed to shorten it," he said. "There are sacrifices that are good for the soul."</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 06:34:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai says that al “effectively safeguarded the constitutional order of masters”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/sam-hou-fai-diz-que-al-salvaguardou-efectivamente-a-ordem-constitucional-da-raem/</link><description>The chief executive joined the deputies at a dinner to mark the end of the legislative session and the legislature. At the time, Sam Hou Fai stated that the deputies of the 7th Legislature of the Legislative Assembly safeguard the constitutional order of the MSAR. This legislative session, defended the boss, "achieved extraordinary results overcoming challenges and difficulties."

After the 7th Legislative Assembly Legislature (AL), Sam Hou Fai decided to gather the deputies at a dinner. In the speech, the chief executive has left great compliments to the work performed by the organ over the last four years.
It is recalled that, at the end of each legislative session, the Chief Executive usually goes to Hemiciclo to answer questions from the deputies, but Sam Hou Fai did not fulfill the tradition and signaled the end of the works of AL with this dinner that took place on Friday.
With Ron Lam Present - Deputy prevented from applying for the elections of September 14 by, according to the authorities, to be unfaithful to MSA - Sam Hou Fai said that the 7th legislature of the AL “effectively safeguarded the constitutional order established by the Constitution and the Basic Law, ensured the effective and soft functioning of the structure with the predominance of the Executive Branch established by the basic law, always supported and supported and supported, and supported and supported and collaborated He supervised the government in governance under the law, effectively exercised the powers and functions attributed by the Basic Law, achieved extraordinary results overcoming challenges and difficulties. ”
Quoted in a press release released by the government, Sam Hou Fai stated in his speech that the "important successes" of this legislature provide "solid foundations" for the next, which begins in October. Thus, Sam thanked the work of "all deputies" for the "exceptional contribution to MSAR and for the support provided to the new government of MSAR."
The Chief Executive stressed that the latest legislature "constantly boosted the modernization of the Free Legal System and achieved fruitful results." 86 laws were passed “involving the improvement of the state security defense of the state security, the increase in the governing capacity of the MSAR, the development of the proper diversification of the economy, the important areas related to the well-being of the population, and the improvement of the operation of the Legislative Assembly and the rights and duties of deputies”, noted Sam.
In addition, the leader of the Government of MSAR said that the deputies of this legislature “actively performed the attributions of supervision conferred by the law, effectively fulfilling their inspection functions, as well as maintained close connection with all social sectors and residents in general, presented actively opinions and constructive suggestions, promoting an increasingly reinforced representativeness and professionalism in the Legislative Assembly”.
In the speech, Sam explicit the desire for the “firm implementation” of the “Macao Patriotas” principle, the fulfillment of the “soft functioning of the structure with the predominance of the executive branch” and the improvement of “legislative efficiency and quality to ensure the legal compliance of macao's environment and the prestige of the law in the rule of law”.
Sam Hou Fai also assured that the government will “reinforce close collaboration with the legislative and judiciary, unite and lead all social sectors, and will correctly identify properly, manage properly and actively seek changes, take full party out of the institutional advantages of the 'one country, two systems' principle.” "Having the country as support, it will be ordered in an orderly manner the various governing plans, and respond to the uncertainties of the external conjuncture with the certainty of development itself."</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 06:44:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Gastronomic Fair at Zap adds food, culture and interactive games</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/feira-gastronomica-no-zape-junta-comida-cultura-e-jogos-interactivos/</link><description>Inaugurated on the 15th, the “Zape with Flavors” fair will remain open to the public until Sunday with a diverse offer of local and Southeast Asia food. In addition to the gastronomic dimension, the joint initiative of the Directorate of Tourism Services and the General Association of the Overseas Macao Chinese presents a cultural and creative aspect with dance shows, theatrical performances and interactive games.

The “Zape com Flavors” fair was inaugurated in the outer port landfill zone (Zape), reconciling a diverse gastronomic offer with cultural shows starring local groups. The initiative will remain open to the public until Sunday, the 24th, between 15:30 and 22h.
The Director of Tourism Services (STD), Helena de Senna Fernandes, was present at the inauguration, where she highlighted the role of Macao as a “creative city of gastronomy” - a title awarded by UNESCO in 2017. Discant at the time, the responsible “combines diverse restoration elements, gastronomy and cultural and creative industries”, contributing to an “consumer atmosphere” that aims to promote the economy. Nocturnal in community neighborhoods and encourage tourist accommodation in surrounding hotels. STD projections point to about four thousand daily visitors, according to statements made to TDM.
Subordinate to the theme “Flavors of Street Food in Food Truck”, the Fair offers six rulots and 33 tents with a “Great Local Gastronomic Variety and Southeast Asian specialties”, as described on the event's official page. In addition to the culinary offer, the public can also enjoy drinks such as handcrafted coffees, 'cocktails' and wine, while entertaining with the various “interactive games (…), live music, dance and theatrical performances” planned for the event.
The space is divided into several sections, with a maximum capacity dining zone for a hundred people and facilities designed to take photographs. Over the ten days of the fair, participants who spend a minimum of 100 Patacas are entitled to play for free on a claw machine, enabling prizes that include discount coupons on hotels or offers of “cultural and creative products”.
In a statement, STD-the co-organizer of the event, in collaboration with the General Association of the Overseas Macau (Agcum)-points out that, more than a gastronomic fair, “Zape with flavors” is “a vibrant point for the dynamic community of Macao”, dynamizing the community economy and the tourist flow of the area.
In order to expand the range of the fair, STD has also promoted an advertising campaign in collaboration with digital influencers from Macau, Hong Kong and the interior of China, in which videos are published or live broadcasts that portray the “animated atmosphere” of the initiative.
“Following Zape with Flavors, DST will continue to maintain communication with the tourism industry, developing other promotional projects, encouraging the hotel sector to explore new sources of visitors, launching complementary tourist products or promotional accommodation activities, to jointly streamline the Zape community tourism economy,” says the body.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 06:39:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief Executive went to Hangzhou to observe state technology sector</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/chefe-do-executivo-foi-a-hangzhou-observar-sector-da-tecnologia-de-ponta/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai began a five -day visit on Saturday in the province of Zhejiang, in the city of Shanghai and Jiangsu province. In Hangzhou, in the province of Zhejiang, the chief executive analyzed the development situation of the state -of -the -art technology industry.
The Chief Executive visited the Hangzhou Global Center for Scientific and Technological Innovation at the University of Zhejiang, and said he hoped Macau's Center and Higher Education Institutions reinforce exchange and cooperation, conducting joint scientific research projects.
Sam Hou Fai has also met with several representatives of scientific and technological companies in Hangzhou, noting that, over several years, Hangzhou has actively promoted the development of scientific and technological innovation, and through the capture and formation of qualified paintings, promotes new dynamisms and creates advantages for industry, and thus effectively realizes high quality development in the area of scientific innovation. ”
The boss added that MSAR intends to diversify the economy and stressed that cutting-edge technology is one of the main development industries, with a special emphasis on the transformation and application of the university-in-plating industry results. "The cooperation basis between Macau and Hangzhou is good, and both parties should further further complement their advantages, deepen collaboration, especially in the area of scientific and technological innovation, further boost exchange and cooperation between companies in both territories, learn the successful experience of Hangzhou." Sam invited more scientific and technological companies in Hangzhou to expand their business in Macao.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 06:37:43</pubDate></item><item><title>DSAT says that quality of public bus service has improved</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/dsat-diz-que-qualidade-do-servico-dos-autocarros-publicos-melhorou/</link><description>The results of an evaluation to the two local public bus companies indicate that the quality of service has improved and that passengers are more satisfied with their performance. The degree of satisfaction of passengers obtained 28.5 points, from a scale from 0 to 40, plus 1.5 points in semi -annual terms. TCM's overall evaluation remains unchanged in “B-” and that of Transmac has risen to “B-” as well.

An assessment made at the service of the two public bus companies, for the second half of last year, shows that the two operators are classified as "B-".
This means that the TCM classification remained unchanged compared to the previous semester, while Transmac's rose from 'C+' to 'B-' and receiving the best since first half of 2021 reveals the results of the evaluation released by the Traffic Affairs Directorate (DSAT).
The authorities released the results of the evaluation regarding the period from July to December last year, and the “B-” level corresponds to a score scale between 80 and 83 points. As the body explained, the highest classification of “A+” equals 97 points or higher, and the lowest of “E” includes the score of less than 60 points.
According to DSAT, the assessment of the bus service includes a poll about the degree of satisfaction of passengers, through which passengers were collected from the passenger service with the stops, in order to “ensure public participation in the bus evaluation regime”. The score, in this case, is calculated on a scale of 0 to 40 points.
Passengers, as DSAT showed, rose the assessment and the degree of satisfaction in general was 28.5 points in the second half of last year, which represented an increase of 1.5 points over the previous semester. There was also a rise of 0.4 points compared to the same period of 2023.
In detail, TCM obtained 28.5 points, an increase of 1.1 points compared to 27.4 points of the first half; Transmac took 28.3 points, an increase of two points for the 26.3 points recorded in the previous semester.
DSAT says that the respective evaluation has been carried out since July 2013, in order to “reinforce the supervision of the bus service”, and the results serve as a reference to evaluate the quality of the service of bus operators.
The assessment consists of three indicators, which comprise the service and management indicator, the means of transportation and safety equipment and the degree of satisfaction of passengers, which have, respectively, 30%, 30% and 40% of their classification.
As a rule, the assessment is made every six months, and the result is published with the same periodicity.
"Through the score of the above indicators, you can supervise and incite bus operators to continue to raise the quality of service, making the level of service closer to public expectations," he said.
The DSAT document stressed, on the other hand, that bus operators take steps to increase drivers awareness of safety and service quality, including training, awards and suspension of service.
However, for the repetition of security problems or services, such as violation of driving safety rules, severe road accident that causes passenger injuries or unjustified absence, drivers may be fired or pressured to resign.
According to the data provided by the bus operators, 30 conductors were fired and 25 were pressured to dismiss.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 06:45:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Families face losses and prices to shoot after deadly storm on the island of São Vicente</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/familias-enfrentam-perdas-e-precos-a-disparar-apos-tempestade-mortal-na-ilha-de-sao-vicente/</link><description>After the storm that made nine deadly victims in São Vicente, the population is now doing damage to the damage and facing the escalation of prices.

Six days after the storm that caused nine dead on the Cape Verdean island of São Vicente, Jessica Lopes tries to assimilate the loss of belongings and the difficulty of ensuring food after having paid almost double the rice.
“We lost everything. Clothes, furniture, food. The mattress we have to sunbathe every day so we can sleep, but we have no bed cloths, no light, no water, and cooking became a big challenge,” Lusa Jessica Lopes, 32, sitting at the door, surrounded by mud, damaged furniture and plastics dragged by the flood.
With two children, 14 and 3 years old, Jessica, resident in Praça Estrela, states that "the hardest thing is to forget the event and move on after years of conquest."
“The rice that cost 100 shields already bought for 150 [0.91 and 1.36 euros]. We bought it because we had no choice. There may still be other products like oil. My husband works, but we have a basic salary and I'm unemployed,” he laments, adding the fear of disease due to the accumulating of rainwater.
“There are puddles of water on the door, mud everywhere. We, neighbors, have already cleared, but I can't sleep rested on all this,” he adds.
Erickson Colonel, 28, a taxi driver, also reports that prices have already begun to rise, such as 0.5 liter water, from 45 to 80 shields [0.41 and 0.73 euros].
“It's almost double, I could have bought two bottles, but I understand the situation and don't complain,” he explains, adding that vehicle circulation is also limited due to damaged roads.
In commerce, there is “a lot of demand for basic products”.
Leinira Dias, 34, owner of a mini -market, describes the race for beans, pasta, water and hygiene articles: “The challenge now is to supply and respond to demand,” he says, explaining that some products from other islands are already rising in price, such as cheese, potatoes and carrots.
Maitê Lima, 23, works in another mini-market and says that after reopening on Tuesday, sales are busier than usual, but still without any changes in prices.
"Water, bread and cookies are being bought in large quantities, especially by those who will distribute to people, also because some stores have not yet opened due to the damage," he explains.
Nilza Xalino, 49, who is responsible for a mini -market, says that despite having had “big losses” at home and at the product warehouse, the establishment has been intact and already records a high demand for basic products, but maintains the more affordable prices, aware of the situation of those who also lost everything.
Lusa tried to obtain clarification from the Well Chamber of Commerce about the rise of prices and the situation in commercial establishments, but has not received any response so far.
Fulls on Monday left flooded neighborhoods, destroyed roads and bridges and affected the energy supply and one person is yet to locate.
The Cape Verdean government declared a situation of calamity for six months in São Vicente, Porto Novo (Santo Antão) and in the two municipalities of São Nicolau.
In addition, a strategic response plan that includes emergency support for families has already been announced, but also to economic activities, with lines of credit with bonuses and lost funds, justifying the decision with the “exceptional dramatic framework”.
The government will use resources from the National Emergency Fund and the National Emergency Fund, created in 2019 precisely to respond to situations of natural disasters or impact of external economic shocks.
A Portuguese Navy ship attracted on Friday in São Vicente, with 56 military personnel, rubble removal equipment, a desalinizing hospital and drones to collect aerial images in hard-to-reach areas, as well as divers and teams prepared to support the population.
Countries such as Timor-Leste, Guinea-Bissau, Portugal and Sao Tome and Principe have already expressed solidarity. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 06:31:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ron Lam stops publishing an opinion column in the newspaper Son Pou</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/ron-lam-deixa-de-publicar-coluna-de-opiniao-no-jornal-son-pou/</link><description>Ron Lam announced the end of the opinion column in the Son Pou newspaper, where he wrote almost eight years ago, with over 350 articles that analyzed different policies and events in society.
The deputy's decision was revealed in his last article in this weekly newspaper, published last Friday-also the last day of the present legislature in which Ron Lam was present.
Less than a week ago the deputy and the association he directs also ended the last episode of the podcast they had eight years ago, where they discussed weekly about policies and social affairs with the public.
It is recalled that Ron Lam entered the hemiciclo in the 2021 elections and was recently one of 12 candidates disqualified for the next legislative elections. The removal of the race to the Legislative Assembly was due to the fact that the authorities considered that the list of Ron Lam did not defend the basic law and was not faithful to MSAR, based on an opinion of the State Security Defense Commission, which proceeded to an assessment of the “patriotism” of candidates to the legislatures, but without providing detailed justification.
In the last column published, Ron Lam said goodbye to Son Pou's readers and explained that he stops writing because he will "change his career."
“I apologize for not being able to continue to serve you all. I would like to sincerely thank my family and my colleagues for their support and follow-up along the way, and also to all readers for their support and encouragement over the years. But, as they say, everything has an end,” macao synergy Association lamented.
Ron Lam also made a retrospective of the last four years of his career as a deputy, as well as the 17 years of social work. “I am proud to have worked, served, given my best, and have been recognized and valued in a place where I grew up and I love. I have nothing to regret and I still believe that in Macau, the sun always shines after the rain!” He said.
It is recalled that Au Kam San, a former deputy now detained due to an alleged violation of the National Security Law, was no longer a columnist for the same weekly newspaper last year after a 35-year collaboration. Au indicated to have stopped the column for "political motives" and that his articles were "supervised" and censored.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 06:37:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Japanese Prime Minister speaks of remorse for crimes in World War II</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/primeiro-ministro-japones-fala-de-remorso-pelos-crimes-na-segunda-guerra-mundial/</link><description>Japanese Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba recalled the country's crimes in World War II. "We should never repeat the horrors of war again. We should never lose," he said.

Japanese Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba spoke in “remorse” to remember the country's crimes in World War II by marking the 80th anniversary of the end of the conflict.
"We should never repeat the horrors of war again. We should never lose," said Ishiba during the 80th anniversary ceremony of Japan surrender at the Nippon Budokan stadium in Tokyo.
"We must now, once again, keep the remorse in the background of our hearts as well as the lessons learned from that war," he added, using a term that no head of government had used in over a decade.
Emperor Naruhito, accompanied by Empress Masako, also expressed his "deep remorse" during the ceremony, as he had done in previous years, and wished "the damage of war never repeat."
"Our country today enjoys peace and prosperity thanks to the tireless efforts of the Japanese people," said the emperor.
Ishiba, however, did not go into detail about the role of Japan during conflict or crimes such as the use of tens of thousands of girls and women as sexual slaves during Japanese domain in Korea.
In this sense, the South Korean government vehemently protested Ishiba's decision to send a ritual offering to Yasukuni Shinto Sanctuary.
No prime minister visited the place in person since the former Japanese prime minister Shinzo Abe did so in 2013, which caused a diplomatic storm.
In place of the head of government, as this year, ministers often appear - to appeal to the conservative base of the Liberal Democratic Party. This year, it was the Minister of Agriculture, Shinjiro Koizumi, surrounded by supporters of the party of far right out.
After learning of the symbolic offer of Ishiba, South Korea's Ministry of Foreign Ministry spokesman Lee Jae Wong expressed “deep disappointment” on behalf of the government.
"We regret that Japanese leaders have sent offerings again and visited the place, and we once again install them to face history with frankness and demonstrate, through actions, humble reflection and a genuine desire to solve historical problems," he said in a statement released by South Korea's official news agency, Yonhap.
The confrontation also occurred less than two weeks before President Lee Jae Myung's scheduled visit to Tokyo on August 23 and 24 to talk to Ishiba before traveling to Washington to a summit with US President Donald Trump. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 06:33:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Government returns to issue licenses for terraces</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/governo-volta-a-emitir-licencas-para-esplanadas/</link><description>The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) once again accepted licensing requests for terraces on Friday after a 16-year suspension. The measure aims to “optimize the business environment of the small and medium -sized companies of Macao” and inject a new dynamism in the region's gastronomic experiences.
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) returned this Friday to accept requests for granting licenses for terrace and beverage, restaurants and bars of Macao. In a statement, the body emphasizes that the measure will operate in an experimental way and that its effectiveness will be “constantly” monitored to ensure that traders comply with licensing requirements and exploration rules of esplanades.
The resumption of emissions-which, it is recalled, had been suspended in 2009-has been accompanied by new criteria for the request and operation of the terraces, aiming at “the balance between the community environment and the life of the population”. The new terraces in the region must comply with a set of requirements distributed in various parameters, including “fire prevention, environmental protection and health, noise control and space for pedestrian circulation”.
Specifically contemplating the scope of “noise control”, AMI says that the new rules prohibit the operation of terraces between 9 pm and 9am and the use of altifalantes or sound equipment in the area in question. In addition, the space should be sanitized during and immediately after use, including cleaning any stains on the floor and the proper handling of garbage bags, and having safety instructions in bad weather situations such as tropical storms or 'Storm Surge'.
Owners wishing to request a license should go to the 2nd floor of China Plaza Shopping Center with relevant documents, and the approval period for “competent surveillance services” is about 30 business days. "After the authorized establishments are entry into operation, [AMI] will highlight more personnel for inspection, exhorting traders to meet the exploration requirements," the same statement is read.
Advantages for tourists and residents
The measure was announced just a day after Chan Chak MO, president of the Union of Associations of Macao Restoration and Beverages Owners, announced that the restoration sector and the government were in the discussion phase regarding the opening of the most terraces in Macao.
Speaking to the newspaper or Mun last Thursday, Chan Chak Mo stated that the growing number of visitors in the region longed for diverse gastronomic experiences and “outdoor meal sites with European characteristics”, particularly in the busy Cotai zone, creating conditions conducive to the reopening of the licensing process. The official also argued that, as the macao terraces have no restrictions on the presence of pets, the increase in the number of outdoor meal spaces would also appeal to a significant slice of local customers.
In Friday's statement, AMI explains that the decision came “in order to optimize the business environment of Macau's small and medium-sized companies,” weakened by the closing of the 11 satellite casinos operating in Macao. "The AMI has had colloquiums with the Advisory Board for Municipal Affairs, the Advisory Board of Community Services of Three Zones and with the industrial, commercial and restoration associations, with the purpose of auscultation opinions to define the new request requirements and operation rules," he reads.
There are currently about 20 commercial restoration establishments in Macao that have licenses to operate terraces.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 06:42:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Fatal Point - 18 August 2025</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/ponto-fatal-18-agosto-2025/</link><description>The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) once again accepted licensing requests for terraces on Friday after a 16-year suspension. The measure aims to “optimize the business environment of the small and medium -sized companies of Macao” and inject a new dynamism in the region's gastronomic experiences.
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) returned this Friday to accept requests for granting licenses for terrace and beverage, restaurants and bars of Macao. In a statement, the body emphasizes that the measure will operate in an experimental way and that its effectiveness will be “constantly” monitored to ensure that traders comply with licensing requirements and exploration rules of esplanades.
The resumption of emissions-which, it is recalled, had been suspended in 2009-has been accompanied by new criteria for the request and operation of the terraces, aiming at “the balance between the community environment and the life of the population”. The new terraces in the region must comply with a set of requirements distributed in various parameters, including “fire prevention, environmental protection and health, noise control and space for pedestrian circulation”.
Specifically contemplating the scope of “noise control”, AMI says that the new rules prohibit the operation of terraces between 9 pm and 9am and the use of altifalantes or sound equipment in the area in question. In addition, the space should be sanitized during and immediately after use, including cleaning any stains on the floor and the proper handling of garbage bags, and having safety instructions in bad weather situations such as tropical storms or 'Storm Surge'.
Owners wishing to request a license should go to the 2nd floor of China Plaza Shopping Center with relevant documents, and the approval period for “competent surveillance services” is about 30 business days. "After the authorized establishments are entry into operation, [AMI] will highlight more personnel for inspection, exhorting traders to meet the exploration requirements," the same statement is read.
Advantages for tourists and residents
The measure was announced just a day after Chan Chak MO, president of the Union of Associations of Macao Restoration and Beverages Owners, announced that the restoration sector and the government were in the discussion phase regarding the opening of the most terraces in Macao.
Speaking to the newspaper or Mun last Thursday, Chan Chak Mo stated that the growing number of visitors in the region longed for diverse gastronomic experiences and “outdoor meal sites with European characteristics”, particularly in the busy Cotai zone, creating conditions conducive to the reopening of the licensing process. The official also argued that, as the macao terraces have no restrictions on the presence of pets, the increase in the number of outdoor meal spaces would also appeal to a significant slice of local customers.
In Friday's statement, AMI explains that the decision came “in order to optimize the business environment of Macau's small and medium-sized companies,” weakened by the closing of the 11 satellite casinos operating in Macao. "The AMI has had colloquiums with the Advisory Board for Municipal Affairs, the Advisory Board of Community Services of Three Zones and with the industrial, commercial and restoration associations, with the purpose of auscultation opinions to define the new request requirements and operation rules," he reads.
There are currently about 20 commercial restoration establishments in Macao that have licenses to operate terraces.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 06:29:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Tropical depression in southern China forces the signal 3 in Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/depressao-tropical-no-sul-da-china-obriga-a-icar-sinal-3-em-macau/</link><description>Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) yesterday the Tropical Storm signal no. According to information published on the authorities' page, the probability that the alert signal evolves to paragraph 8 throughout today is “low”.
Signal No. 1 was issued at 9 pm on Saturday, when the meteorological phenomenon entered a radius of 800 kilometers from the Macao region. The SMG later raised the alert signal to paragraph 3 in the face of the gradual approach of the system, which at the time of closing the writing was 620 kilometers from Macao and about to reach the island of Hainão.
During yesterday, the intensity of the wind in Macao oscillated between 41km/h and 62km/h, with gusts of about 110 km/h. At an update at 5 pm, SMGs predicted that the signal remain in force during Sunday night and warned of “frequent heavy rains” earlier this week, which could give rise to flooding in the low areas.
The rain will only give respite on Thursday, although the sky remains "very cloudy" and there is the possibility of "scattered sweeteners". On the other hand, temperatures will remain high throughout the week, with maximums ranging from 28 degrees Celsius, today, to 32 degrees Celsius, scheduled for Thursday.
While signal No. 3, SMG appeals to the population to be aware of updated meteorological information and adopt precautionary measures, including verifying the safety of works and objects that can be dragged by wind.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 06:36:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Road Traffic Bill was in the drawer</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/proposta-de-lei-do-transito-rodoviario-ficou-na-gaveta/</link><description>The 7th legislature ended on Friday without the Legislative Assembly (AL) voted in the specialty the proposal of road traffic-was the only diploma that was approved in this session. Since bills cannot transit between legislatures, the government will have to present it again in the future.

It ended last Friday the 7th Legislature of the Legislative Assembly (AL) without the deputies having approved in the specialty the proposal of road traffic-the only diploma that was approved. Thus, and since the diplomas under consideration is not allowed to move between legislatures, the government will have to present this bill later.
The AL regiment says that "the projects and the law proposals not voted in the legislative session in which they were presented do not need to be renewed in the following legislative sessions, except in the occurrence of a legislature."  The Law of the Legislature and the Statute of Deputies to AL says that the next period of operation of the AL begins on October 16, with the new deputies resulting from the elections of 14 September.
The AL table released a deliberation on Friday. Since the deadlines for the discussion in the commission was exceeded, this body of AL says that the proposal of road traffic bill "does not gather the requirements for voting by the plenary", and "the government can renew the initiative when it understands timely."
Over time, the Alternate Committee of the AL that analyzed the proposal was raising several issues related, for example, with the viability of certain rules and the interpretation of certain points. The government indicated that it needed more time to "analyze, study and listen to more opinions." The ALS table stressed that, as the bill has an impact on society, "the government must continue to hear public opinion and seek to achieve greater consensus."
The deliberation points out that the diploma had a period of assessment until August 7, and then the deadline was postponed to last Friday. The ALS table says, in the deliberation, that, "given the complexity of follow -up and studies on the law, it is difficult to conclude and present, soon, the formal and conclusive alternative version." Al and government agreed that the document did not meet the requirements to be voted in the specialty in this legislature.
Some of the main points of this law proposal now withdrawn was the increase in fines and the introduction of a point system system, for example.
The government had already submitted a proposal to change the road traffic law in 2018. At the time, the direction of services for traffic affairs (DSAT) eventually removed proposals and their complementary diplomas because they were being the subject of strong criticism even before being subject to a public auscultation.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 06:43:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Combating smuggling has produced “remarkable results”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/combate-ao-contrabando-tem-produzido-resultados-notaveis/</link><description>The Secretary for Security was pleased with the work of combating parallel trade, arguing that “remarkable results” were obtained and illegal activities “continue to contract”. Wong Sio Chak indicated that the offenses in the four terrestrial border posts decreased by 21% in the first six months of the year. According to the secretary, Customs has technological resources to identify contraband practitioners.

The fight against parallel trade in Macau has been effective, obtaining “remarkable results,” said Wong Sio Chak. The Secretary for Security pointed out that the number of cases of parallel trade registered a descent and there was a “effective repression” of the main channels of the activities of the practitioners of this offense and, therefore, the illegal activities related to “continue to contract” in the territory.
In an article published on the electronic portal of his office, the secretary revealed that, in the first half year, compared to the same period last year, there was a reduction of 511 cases of offenses in the four terrestrial borders, ie a decrease of 21%. Customs posts include the doors of the siege, Qingmao, Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau and Hengqin bridge.
Cases of pedestrian transportation decreased 476 (20%) and those related to transfronheous vehicles re -educated 35 (41%).
Statistics also show that from January 2024 to June this year, customs services (SA) detected 13 cases at source, which involved goods of 2.53 million patacas. 392 cases were also detected within the city and 436 people assessed, being the value of the goods seized of about 37.01 million patacas. Already at the terrestrial border posts there were 6,526 offenses involving 6,533 people.
Wong Sio Chak, in the article, addressed society's concern about the problem of parallel trade activities.
"Due to the differences between the interior of China and Macau within the fiscal regime of goods, supply and price, there were practitioners of parallel trade, who take advantage of the facilities of border passage to transport goods to the interior of China through a reward," he explained. He stressed that the practice not only results in tax dropout, but also "seriously disturbs the economic order" of both locations and the normal trade of legitimate companies.
It is recalled that the smuggling continues to be very visible especially at the doors of the siege, with many “sale” points of products that serve to be delivered later to the continent, most of them alcoholic beverages such as Moutai and red wine, powdered milk, even shampoo or bath gel.

Evolved practices
 
The secretary stressed that the activities of parallel trade have been adjusted consistent with the execution of the law, namely moving from street stores in the siege gates to a covered operation in industrial buildings and mobile warehouses, even using vehicles.
The groups also use social networking platforms to organize work and attract the elderly and students to practice parallel trade, as well as enjoy transfrontic enrollment vehicles for smuggling, the government noticed.
In this case, Wong Sio Chak argues that SA always maintains a “firm and intense attitude” in combating parallel trade, having implemented a “innovative” management strategy through interregional cooperation and technological training.
According to the executive, the SAs installed in the border stations non -invasive scanner systems that allow rapid detection of the transport of bodied and hidden goods in the body, or concealed in compartments. In addition, there is a classification of risk levels at the entrance and exit of the territory of people and goods that, through the analysis of the Megados can identify and locate the possible practitioners of smuggling.
Wong Sio Chak said that through the CPSP collaboration mechanism, in the first half of the year and after risk screening, they were sent to the high risk SA 2,779 people, which helped "increase interception efficiency."
Security guardianship official also said that he created a connection with the direction of education and youth development services, in order to prevent young people from being deceived or enticed by evildoers to participate in parallel trade activities.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 06:41:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Indian Prime Minister threatens to punish Pakistan for future attacks</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/08/18/primeiro-ministro-indiano-ameaca-punir-o-paquistao-por-futuros-ataques/</link><description>Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi warned Pakistan that India will respond to any future attacks against its territory by marking the 78 years of independence in the face of British colonial domain.
Speaking from Fort Red, in Nova Delhi, Narendra Modi said that the country will not tolerate "nuclear blackmail" and established a "normal new" that does not distinguish between terrorists and who supports them.
The statements appear three months after four days of intense combat between India and Pakistan, the worst in decades, triggered by an attached attack in Caxemira under Indian control, which killed 26 people.
Nova Delhi responsible for Islamabade -supported militants, who denied any involvement.
The clashes, which almost led to a war, involved air strikes and bombing, causing dozens of dead on both sides, before a US mediated ceasefire in May.
Narendra Modi also said that India will maintain the suspension of the Indian water treaty, accusing the Pakistan of benefiting from irrigation, while Indian farmers face scarcity. Islamabade warned that any deviation of water will be considered "war act."
Not to mention directly the tariffs imposed by the United States, the Indian Prime Minister reaffirmed that he will not compromise agricultural interests, refusing to open the market to certain products.
The Indian leader also announced a “demographic mission” to combat illegal immigration, which his party, Hindu nationalist Bharatiya Janata Party, considers a threat to national security.</description><pubDate>2025-08-18 06:32:34</pubDate></item></channel></rss>