<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/18/dsedt-quer-atrair-visitantes-para-as-zonas-afectadas-pelo-encerramento-dos-casinos-satelite/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>USJ and Sun Yat-Sen university sign agreement to strengthen cooperation in law and philosophy</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/18/usj-e-universidade-sun-yat-sen-assinam-acordo-para-fortalecer-a-cooperacao-em-direito-e-filosofia/</link><description>The University of St. Joseph (USJ) and Sun Yat-Sen University signed, last Wednesday, a memorandum of understanding that aims to reinforce cooperation in the domains of law and philosophy. The ceremony took place at the university's main campus in Canton, and was attended by a USJ delegation led by rector Stephen Morgan.
Sun Yat-Sen University President Gao Song began by presenting the institution's academic achievements and development objectives. Rector Stephen Morgan followed the example and also stressed the importance of this collaboration in promoting academic exchange between Macao and the interior of China.
After both parties signed a memorandum of understanding at the institutional level, there was a signing of a specific memorandum for law cooperation, celebrated between the director of the Sun Yat-Sen University Faculty of Law, Zhang Liang, and USJ Department of Law and Public Policies Director Ansoune Douty Diakité. Preparations were also initiated for a memo between the Department of Philosophy of the University of Canton and the Faculty of Religious Studies and Philosophy of the USJ.
In a statement sent yesterday to the newsrooms, USJ reports that "both parties participated in in -depth debates on collaboration in law and philosophy," proposing reinforced cooperation in legal states related to the area of ​​the great bay and regarding "Chinese philosophy, western philosophy and ethics."
"The signing of these memorandos of understanding establishes a solid basis for future academic exchanges and talent development between the two institutions," reads the USJ press note. "Both parties plan to continue to promote cooperation in law and philosophy through student exchanges, joint investigation and academic activities."</description><pubDate>2025-06-18 02:28:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Erupted volcano in Indonesia launches ash cloud 10,000 meters high</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/18/vulcao-em-erupcao-na-indonesia-lanca-nuvem-de-cinzas-com-10-mil-metros-de-altura/</link><description>A volcano yesterday erupted on Flores Island in eastern Indonesia, and threw a 10,000 -meter -high gray column above the summit, the Indonesian authorities announced. Mount Lewotobi Laki-Laki, a 1,584-meter-high two-peak volcano on the Tourist Island of Flores, erupted at 5:35 pm, according to a statement from the Vulcanology Agency. "The height of the eruption column was observed about 10,000 meters above the summit. The gray column was gray and thick," the agency said. Authorities had no record of victims or damages, according to France-Presse (AFP) news agency. The volcanology agency has raised a warning level to the highest in a four -level system. The inhabitants and tourists should avoid any activity within at least seven kilometers around the volcano crater, said the head of the Geology Agency Muhammad Wafid. It also warned of the possibility of dangerous mud flows, known as 'Lahars', a type of volcanic material flow consisting of mud or debris, in case of heavy rain, particularly for communities near the rivers. Wafid also advised places to wear masks to protect themselves from volcanic ashes.
Mount Lewotobi Laki-Laki erupted several times in November 2024, which resulted in the death of nine people. Thousands of people had to be removed from near the volcano, which also caused the cancellation of many international flights to the island of Bali, about 800 kilometers to the Western, straight line. Indonesian authorities have not registered so far cancellation of flights due to yesterday's eruption. Laki-laki, which means "man" in Indonesian, is flanked by another volcano, Perempuan, which means "woman" and is higher, with 1,703 meters. Indonesia, a vast archipelago, often suffers from seismic and volcanic activity because it is situated in the so -called Pacific “Ring of Fire”, which extends through Southeast Asia and the Pacific Basin. This area, of great seismic and volcanic activity, records thousands of earthquakes per year, mostly weak to moderate magnitude, and has close to 120 atcivas volcanoes.</description><pubDate>2025-06-18 02:30:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Two people considered guilty for trying to help ABby's ex-husband Choi flee to Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/18/duas-pessoas-consideradas-culpadas-por-tentarem-ajudar-ex-marido-de-abby-choi-a-fugir-para-macau/</link><description>A man and a woman were accused of collaborating with Hong Kong's ex-husband Alex Kwong in the attempt to escape by Macao in February 2023. The pair has proposed to assist the alleged murderer to enter the neighboring region without being intercepted by the authorities, in exchange of 300,000 dollars of Hong Kong.
 
An agent from an yacht company and an influencer were convicted Monday for trying to help Alex Kwong, Abby Choi Tin-Fung's ex-husband, flee to Macau after the model's murder.
Hong Kong's Kowloon City Court determined that Lam Shun and Irene Pun Hau-Yin-44 and 31, respectively-had agreed to plan an illegal boat trip between Hong Kong and Macau to enable the alleged murderer to enter the territory without being intercepted by the authorities.
According to the South China Morning Post (SCMP) newspaper, the duo will have discussed the telephone plan with a Macao resident, identified as Ivy, who requested the rental of a boat on behalf of a "friend" named Alex. In the various telephone conversations that took place between February 24 and 25, 2023, Macau's intermediary stressed that money "was not a problem" and that his friend's priority was to leave Hong Kong "as soon as possible." In response, Lam Shun proposed a $ 300,000 rental rate of Hong Kong, justifying the value with the possibility of interception by the Navy officers.
During the trial, the defense indicated that the exchange of money never happened, thus making it impossible to conclude a formal contract. Influencer Irene Pun-who identified herself as unemployed in court-assured her that she has not yet associated the name “Alex” with Abby Choi's ex-husband, initially judging her boyfriend of another personality of the internet, and denied any knowledge of the illegal nature of the plan.
"I would say she was accidentally dragged to this incident," said Lydia Lau, the Pun lawyer, claiming that the defendant is currently under "huge stress" as a result of the insults published on cybernauts by accompanying the case.
In turn, the accusation argued that the mere intention of assisting Alex Kwong was sufficient reason to condemn the two suspects, even if the payment had not been completed. Magistrate Philip Chan Chee-Fai also devalued the theory that the duo would not know the contours of the case, contrasting: "The court has difficulty realizing why a person who has not committed any offenses and is not sought by the police has to urgently leave Hong Kong to Macau at all costs."
After reading the verdict, the two convicts are currently in pre-trial detention until the sentence, scheduled for June 27.
The case dates back to February 2023, when police discovered parts of the dismembered body of model Abby Choi in the kitchen of a house in the village of Tai Po, in the suburbs of Hong Kong. According to information released by the authorities, the reason for the crime will be related to the dissatisfaction of the ex-husband and his family as to how the young woman managed her fortune.
Alex Kwong will have conspired with his father and brother to murder and quarter his ex-wife, with whom he had two children. Also involved in the case are the mother of Kwong, accused of perverting the course of justice, and the father's lover, who will have leased the house to hide the alleged murderer.</description><pubDate>2025-06-18 02:26:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing criticizes Taipé's “ADULATION” to the US for restricting business with Huawei and SMIC</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/18/pequim-critica-adulacao-de-taipe-aos-eua-por-restringir-negocios-com-huawei-e-smic/</link><description>The Chinese government yesterday accused Taiwan authorities of Adulating Washington, after Taipe has included two Chinese companies on a black list of foreign entities with which commercial transactions cannot be made without express permission.
At a press conference, Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakun said that "China firmly opposes the politicization of science, technology and economic and commercial affairs by the United States."
The statements arise after, according to Beijing, under pressure from Washington, Taiwan added to his list of entities to Huawei technology and the main semiconductor manufacturer of China, the Manufacturing International Corporation (SMIC) semiconductor.
Guo criticized what he classified as “generalization of the concept of national security”, “abuse of export controls and extraterritorial jurisdiction” and “malicious repression against China”. "The behavior of the Taiwanese authorities will only harm and destroy Taiwan," added the spokesman.
In the latest update on the list of entities of the Taiwan International Trade Administration, published over the weekend, are now Huawei, SMIC and several subsidiaries of these companies, both Chinese and foreign.
The new rules require Taiwanese companies to obtain an express authorization from Taipei before they can sell products or technology to these companies.
According to Bloomberg agency, restrictions will limit, at least partially, Huawei and SMIC access to Taiwanese materials and technology related to the production of semiconductors for artificial intelligence (AI) and the construction of sector factories.
Taiwan houses TSMC, a global leader in semiconductor production, a technology considered critical to China's technological self -sufficiency strategy, which still depends on third parties to access the most advanced technologies.
Although Taipei has forbidden exports to China for essential equipment for the production of chips, such as lithography machines, this is the first time that includes large Chinese technological companies in the referred control regime.
TSMC - a key supplier of companies like Apple or Nvidia - had, moreover, suspended by 2020 supply to Huawei following the sanctions imposed by Washington.</description><pubDate>2025-06-18 02:29:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Support measures to commercial establishments at Zape</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/18/apresentadas-medidas-de-apoio-a-estabelecimentos-comerciais-na-zape/</link><description>The Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) has announced that it has made visits to commercial establishments in the surrounding satellite zones since June 10, in order to ascertain the possible economic impact of the closure of these casinos and publicizing the current measures to support Small and Medium Enterprises (SMEs).
The outer port landfills (Zape) - where nine of the 11 casinos to close by the end of the year - was one of the most visited by the representatives of DSEDT. Over the past week, in the zone in question, the body made known to the SMEs the current support measures they have and provided clarification to entrepreneurs who want to restructure or reconvert their business.
SME-directed support plans include the Small and Medium Enterprise Support Plan, the Bank Credit Interest Bonus Plan, Bank Credit Guarantee Plans and SME scan support services.
In a statement released yesterday, DSEDT reveals that “there were ZAPE entrepreneurs who asked for information (…) about the requirements and formalities for formulating the request of the Bank Credit Interest Bonus Plan for small and medium enterprises, and the DSEDT supported them in the submission of the order with the bank”.
The body ensures that it will continue to “closely monitor the situation of exploration of stores around the satellite casinos”, while “making all efforts to accelerate the appreciation and approval of requests” for SMEs.
Last week, the government announced that 11 satellite casinos that currently operate in Macau will end until December 31. At issue are 11 properties: the GrandView Casino, Casino Legend Palace, Casino Fortuna, Casino Landmark, Casino Ponte 16, Casino Le Royal Arc, Casino Emperor Palace, Kam Pek Paradise Casino and Casino Casa Real, which belong to SJM Resorts; Melco Resorts's Grand Dragon Casino; and Casino Waldo, from Galaxy Casino.
In addition, from the six Melco Mocha Clubs, three will be closed (Grand Dragon, Royal and Kuong Fat), while the other three will continue to be explored by the operator by hiring a management society (Golden Dragon, Porto and Sintra).</description><pubDate>2025-06-18 02:30:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Detected case of collective gastroenteritis infection at the São José International Nursery</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/18/detectado-caso-de-infeccao-colectiva-por-gastroenterite-na-creche-internacional-de-sao-jose/</link><description>Health services were notified for a case of collective gastroenteritis infection in a class of the São José International Nursery. In total, four children were infected: three male and one female.
Patients began to have symptoms such as abdominal pain and diarrhea from June 13, Friday. Although some students were undergoing treatment at health institutions, there was no record of cases or serious complications.
Sanitary authorities clarify that certain characteristics of the disease, such as symptoms and incubation period, exclude the possibility of food gastroenteritis and make the hypothesis more likely that the "pathogen agent is related to a viral infection." Health authorities ensure that they are following the case and guide the school in question regarding control and infection measures, such as the correct way to treat vomiting and excrement and the maintenance of good ventilation.
Norovirus and rotaviruses are frequent diseases of viral gastroenteritis and advert with ease. In a statement, health services warn that the transmission route includes the consumption of food or water eventually contaminated by viruses; contact with vomiting or waste of sick persons; contact with contaminated objects; or the transmission by saliva droplets.
Symptoms of both diseases are generally light and last between one to five days without complications. Still, health services call for the population to pay attention to personal, environmental and food hygiene. Health and restoration professionals are especially advised not to attend workplaces when they have symptoms such as nausea or diarrhea, and should seek immediate medical care.</description><pubDate>2025-06-18 02:25:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan and USA fail agreement due to persistent disagreements</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/18/japao-e-eua-falham-acordo-devido-a-divergencias-persistentes/</link><description>Japanese Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba and US President Donald Trump failed to ensure a bilateral trade agreement during a meeting in Kananaskis, Canada, on the sidelines of the G7, due to persistent persistent disagreements.
 
Speaking to the Japanese press, Ishiba emphasized the need for Tokyo to reach an agreement that protects Japanese interests, something the ruler considered not yet achieved, and refrained from specifying a concrete deadline for the adoption of a possible commercial agreement with Washington.
"So far, we have kept frank conversations, we have negotiated until the last moment to explore the possibility of an agreement. However, there are still points in which we disagreed, so there is no general agreement," explained the Japanese Prime Minister during the press conference.
"Negotiations are uncertain until the last moment. It all comes down to whether the national interests of each party are realized and, for Japan, for example, cars are a truly important national interest. It all comes down to making the utmost efforts to protect our national interests," Ishiba added to a key point of negotiations.
Tokyo has asked Washington to exempt Japan from all tariff increases implemented by the Trump administration and especially the 25% increase over vehicles, which raises the customs rate applied to Japanese vehicles to 27.5%.
Automobile exports are fundamental to the Japanese economy and have great weight in Asian trade with the United States, representing about 30% of the total. The US part has refused to review this tariff and Trump himself threatened to increase her even more.
During the meeting between Ishiba and Trump in Canada, which lasted half an hour, the main negotiators were present on both sides: Japanese minister responsible for economic revitalization, Ryosi Akazawa, and US Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent.
Japan is one of the countries to which the United States has given preferential treatment in these negotiations, which remain without results after six rounds of ministerial meetings and yesterday's summit.
Asked about the possibility of being extended for another 90 days the suspension of what Washington called “reciprocal tariffs”, imposed on most countries and territories and that, in the case of Japan, is 14%, the Japanese prime minister said he cannot confirm.
It is expected that the moratorium on the rates expire on July 9. If it comes into force, added to the general rate of 10% established for all US imports, products from Japan will be penalized 24% on arrival at US markets.
Ishiba also refused to reveal what are the other points in negotiations, which, according to local press, include topics such as shipbuilding, weaponry purchases, exchange issues or the cost of US troop parking lot in Japan. Lusa.</description><pubDate>2025-06-18 02:30:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Frank Law: A humanist legacy that transcends words through the image</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/18/frank-lei-um-legado-humanista-que-transcende-palavras-atraves-da-imagem/</link><description>Frank Law was a fundamental figure in the artistic scene of Macau, whose sensitivity, innovation and commitment shaped a cultural heritage of invaluable value. As a photographer, mentor, and driver of spaces of expression, Frank Law transcended borders and styles, capturing the essence of a society in transformation with a humanist and poetic look, without the need for many words. Its trajectory reflects a legacy of creativity, resistance and dedication to art, which continues to inspire generations and consolidate Macau as a vibrant center of contemporary culture, now forever remembered in the exhibition “When the Islands Cast Their Shadows”, at Casa Garden, which presents unpublished works of the artist as a form of memory and reflection.
 
Frank Law's trajectory is one of the most illustrative chapters of the Macao cultural scene, revealing itself as a narrative of dedication, creativity and a unique sensitivity that went through borders and artistic disciplines. Born in Beijing, in December 1962, and based in Macao since he was ten years old, law has consolidated itself as a central figure of the local artistic landscape, not only for his talent as a photographer, but also for his role as mentor, founder of cultural spaces and driving out of an innovative view of contemporary art.
His academic formation reflected a constant demand for knowledge and expression. Degree in Journalism from the University of Jinan, China, and later in Cinema and Video at the University of Paris III, Frank further deepened his training at the National Higher School of Decorative Arts (Conuded) in Paris, where he studied photography. This combination of experiences, crossing oriental and western culture, gave it a unique sensitivity, which was reflected in his work, marked by a poetic and humanist approach.
His passion for photography has revealed himself as a tool of understanding and interpretation of the world around him. From an early age, he demonstrated a natural talent to capture the essence of everyday life, turning simple moments into visual testimonies of a society in constant transformation. In 1991, he won the first prize in the International Street Photography Contest, organized by the European Museum of Photography, a recognition that highlighted him at the international level.
However, it was on his trip to Cuba in 1992 that Frank Lei revealed one of his most striking facets: documenting a society in crisis, but full of culture and hope. The photographs captured in this period, now subject to an exhibition at the Village Art Space Taipa, curated by Alan Ieong, offer a window to a resistance sul, marked by political tensions and a cultural richness that the photographer knew how to eternalize with sensitivity and rigor. This first tribute to Frank Law was the opening red carpet to a large -scale retrospective now inaugurated at Casa Garden.
 
Reflection islands in an unprecedented retrospective
 
Frank Law's new posthumous exhibition opened yesterday at Casa Garden and is evident until June 29, under the title "When the Islands Cast Their Shadows." It occupies the space of the gallery in its entirety with more than 60 photographs, without leaving a doubt about the work and quality of the organization. One of the curators of this new retrospective is Lam Sio Man, who shared details about the process of elaborating the show, highlighting the collective effort and the importance of the archives in the preservation of Frank Law's work. He stressed the collaboration with the artist's family, especially Sister Jane Lei, who is also one of the curators, and the impact that Frank had on her generation.
The assembly of the exhibition took over a year and involved the support of several elements that helped establish the bases of the project. With the help of files from Wind Box Association and his family, Frank Law's works and personal objects were well preserved, now presented in the new show. “It was a great honor to work with Jane Law and his family, who were very generous to open the collection and trust our work. We visited Frank Law's studio and saw his huge collection of music and books, choosing some for the exhibition,” Lam Sio Man, said.
Frank Law's influence extended to the creation of emblematic cultural spaces, which became true poles of creativity and experimentation. Founder of the 1996 Stone Commune, by Old Ladies House Art Space in 2001, later known as the Boi Warehouse in 2003, Frank Law was a driving force of Macao's artistic development, promoting coexistence, exchange and innovation. These spaces welcomed exhibitions of great influence, contributing to the city's affirmation as a culture center, especially in the area of ​​contemporary art.
"When I was younger, I had contact with Frank's work through the Boi Warehouse, which promoted contemporary art in Macao. I met his book 'The Walking and Watching', published at the time at Pin-To Bookstore. Even without meeting Frank personally, his work greatly influenced my generation," Lam Sio Man.
Frank Law was a citizen of the world, exposing in France, Cuba, Portugal, Hong Kong and now in Macao. His work, which includes series such as “City Sight”, “Sleeping City” and “Cuba Cuba”, reveals a constant concern with the city, the urban space and the people who inhabit it. His sensitive gaze allowed him to capture Macau's essence in times of change, reflecting a city that, although in transformation, maintains a deeply rooted human identity, the focus of many of the works exposed in the new retrospective.
 
A master of few words
 
In addition to his photographic production, Frank Law stood out as an exemplary mentor. His dedication to teaching, especially at the School of Arts of the Macao Polytechnic Institute, shaped generations of young artists, instilling in them a critical, sensitive and innovative view. The testimonies of his former students, such as Alice Kok and Bianca Law, reveal an educator who stimulated deep thinking, who promoted reflection through calm conversations and, above all, conveyed a genuine passion for art.
In the words of André Ritchie, architect of Macao who had a direct contact with the personality of Frank Law, the photographer was a silent master who transcended the words with the quality of a visual artist. "All of his students said he was a very pleasant person, but he said nothing about the work, did not take over the work of the students. He developed the work by the image, not so much for the words," he recalled.
According to André Ritchie, Frank Law was one of the first, if not the first, photographer in the local Chinese community to offer a space for experimentation and a new way of understanding photography. His stance, more guidance than prescription, allowed young photographers to realize that creative work was his own, and that photography could be much more than a pictorial representation of landscapes or objects.
Francisco Ricarte was another element of the Macao artistic community that recently left his comment as an introduction to one of Frank Law's publications, where he says that the artist can "emphasize his understanding of photography as a humanist act of seeing."
“Frank's visual sensitivity in terms of composition, scale and balance between light and shadow (sometimes transmitting deeply dramatic shadows) to portray Macau as a land of perpetual change and new times to come, allows us to better understand this city and its human identity. In Frank's photography, space is always transmitted through a human scale that enhances its meaning and role,” says Ricarte.
For Alan Ieong, curator of the recent exposure on Frank Law's work on Cuba, at the Taipa Village Gallery, the photographer is "an important but little known artist, since he has not published many of his work during his life and is so humble that most people outside of Macao do not know much about him." “Even though it was so humble that I would never admit it, Frank is, in fact, a reference when we talk about photography. So it is important that we all know more about it, since contemporary art is about the present and also about the past, and without knowing the past we are not able to understand where we are going. I think this is the most important idea that we can convey to the recent exposure and publication.
Frank Law's work was often unnoticed by the community. In what highlights Portuguese photographer António Mil-Homens, Frank Law still “continues to discover”. "Unfortunately, I think lovers of photography, and many others, have been on their backs for this artist's work. Frank has works that are very out of the Chinese community of photography. It has a more intimate work. It is very important to appear to see this recent collection that has so much love for the art of photography," said António Mil-Homens.
Frank Law's passage, unfortunately prolonged by a disease that led him to be in a coma for four years, left an indelible mark in the artistic community of Macau. His death, which occurred on May 18, 2022, aroused a wave of honors and recognition for its invaluable contribution. Artists, academics and institutions lamented the loss of a humble, generous and innovative artist whose work and action left a legacy that will continue to inspire new generations.
Today, the recognition of its journey manifests itself in exhibitions such as "When the Islands Cast Their Shadows" and the launch of posthumous works such as "Beyond The Gaze." Thus, his legacy lasts, inspired by a passion that illuminated the way to all those who believe in the transforming power of creativity, but also in the importance of valuing and conserving memory. Frank Law will be forever as an example of how art is a powerful tool for social, cultural and human testimony. "I was there and that's what I saw at that moment of my life"-Henri Carrier-Bresson.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>After renewal, Casa Garden wants to consolidate the past and look at the future</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/18/depois-da-renovacao-a-casa-garden-quer-consolidar-o-passado-e-olhar-para-o-futuro/</link><description>In all, five months of restoration work were in all. Casa Garden is now washed and yesterday started the cultural programming with a tribute to photographer Frank Law. Catarina Cottinelli, delegate of the Oriente Foundation in Macao, says that now we have to consolidate the story of Casa Garden, promoting it for the future.
 
Between December last year and May this year, Casa Garden was the target of deep renewal works. These are essential works, complex and executed in record time, says Catarina Cottinelli, delegate of the East Foundation, an organism that has occupied that space since 1989.
The process for renewal of the building began in October 2023, when the East Foundation exposed the situation to the Cultural Institute (IC), based on opinions from Cesl Asia engineers, for example. A month later, IC technicians made an assessment of the state of Casa Garden and in April 2024 the Macao East delegation received response from the local authorities in which they pledged to take over the space renewal process.
The works encompassed above all the structure of the main building. There were repairs to the roof structure to combat the infiltrations and the ported, the interior windows, isolation and the locks were also intervened, for example. The East Foundation took advantage and also renewed the air conditioning pipes and pipes.
The house was no longer the target of this wingspan for over ten years. “We hope that after these works it will be protected for another decade,” says Catarina Cottinelli.
Casa Garden's cultural programming was suspended, waiting for the works to be completed. The activities began to be suspended in August last year and the following month was all stopped. Nevertheless, the East Foundation's Macao delegation has also organized some events outside the Garden House, such as the Autumn Hall exhibition in Parisian.
The cultural program at Casa Garden was officially resumed yesterday, with the inauguration of the exhibition “When the island projects its shadows”, in honor of photographer Frank Law.
Acquired in 1989 by the East Foundation, with the purpose of installing its delegation in Macau, this white and pink palace was erected in 1770 by a Portuguese merchant named Manoel Pereira. The space was then rented to the Eastern Indian Company over 55 years. After that, that space served several destinations, one of which the creation of pigeons, having become known as the house of the pigeons-a name still used when translated into Chinese, "pak-kap-chau".
The 1885 was acquired by the Portuguese State and had several uses: since the direction of public works, deposit of war material, national press, the Central Archive of the Province and Macao Museum. From the 1960s to 1980s it was converted into a museum dedicated to Luís Vaz de Camões, and in 1989, was acquired by the East Foundation.
Part of the Macao Historic Center list, Casa Garden was recognized in 2005 as a UNESCO World Heritage Site - now 20 years ago.
At the end, architect Catarina Cottinelli said that the institution now wants to consolidate the story of Casa Garden, particularly regarding its architecture. In this context, a reissue magazine of the book “Casa Garden”, by Rogério Beltrão Coelho, is being thought out, adding another chapter on the history of the building's architecture. Through collaboration with IC, it is planned to create virtual guided tours through space, through a QR code, in collaboration with the IC.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Beijing's tariff exemption to Africa can redefine relationship with the continent, says consultant</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/18/isencao-tarifaria-de-pequim-a-africa-pode-redefinir-relacao-com-o-continente-diz-consultora/</link><description>Oxford Economics believes the tariff exemption offered by China to all African countries “is not just a commercial initiative, but a strategic maneuver” to redefine the relationship with the continent. Analysts believe that the deepest implication is a gradual decline in US influence in Africa, with Chinese leaders being more inclined to support the Chinese perspective on the world stage.
 
Consultant Oxford Economics considered yesterday that the tariff exemption offered by China to all African countries “is not just a commercial initiative, but a strategic maneuver” to redefine the relationship with the continent.
"Beijing zero tariff policy is not just a commercial initiative, it is a strategic maneuver for redefining its alliances with Africa, reducing the power of influence of the United States, and implementing China more deeply in the continent's political and economic future," says analysts from the African department of this British consultant.
In a commentary of Beijing's decision to exempt African exports to China, with the exception of Essuatini for recognizing Taiwan, analysts write that “the deepest implication is a gradual decline in American influence in Africa, with Chinese leaders to be more inclined to support the Chinese perspective on the world stage, thus reducing the influence of the Western”.
In addition, they also point out, attempts by western countries to impose sanctions or implement commercial regulations may lose effectiveness, as "African economies will be more integrated with supply chains and Chinese commercial networks."
Last week, during the China Africa Cooperation Forum (FOCAC), China announced total tariff exemptions for taxable products from 53 African countries with which it maintains diplomatic relations, as well as new measures to facilitate African products access to its market.
At the same time, Beijing reaffirmed his willingness to cooperate with Africa in sectors such as green industry, e -commerce, artificial intelligence, security and governance, in the context of an economic relationship that has gained weight.
According to data from the General Customs Administration, bilateral trade exceeded 2.1 Yuan trilions (255.7 billion euros) by 2024, while in the first five months of 2025 it grew 12.4% over the previous year, up to 963.21 billion yuans (117.29 billion euros).
According to Oxford Economics, the Democratic Republic of Congo and Angola were, in 2023, the largest African exporters to China, with the Lusophone country exporting almost half (46.4%) of total sales to the Asian giant, in a list where Mozambique also appears in a prominent place with almost 20%. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-18 02:29:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai wants reinforcement of cooperation with University of Beijing</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/18/sam-hou-fai-quer-reforco-da-cooperacao-com-universidade-de-pequim/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai met this Monday with Gong Qihuang, Rector of the University of Beijing, at the Government headquarters. During the meeting, topics such as the reinforcement of cooperation between Macao and the interior of China in the domains of higher education, academic investigation and the formation of qualified paintings were addressed.
According to a statement issued after the meeting, the head of the executive praised the University of Beijing as an institution of “excellence and top”, with international prestige and assiduous presence in the rankings of the best universities in the world. Noting that the number of students in Macao attending the University of Beijing has been growing in recent years, Sam Hou Fai thanked the institution “for the constant support in the formation of qualified pictures” in several aspects essential to the development of the local economy.
The ruler has assured that the Government of MSAR is “concentrating all efforts on the proper diversification of the local economy and the construction of the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin”, as indicated in the discourses of Xi Jinping when visiting Macao and, equally, in the first report of the Government Action Lines (LAG) since its inauguration.
Given these objectives, Sam Hou Fai expressed the hope that the university will continue, “as always”, to deepen the exchange with Macao higher education institutions and to produce high quality qualified pictures, essential to the transformation and diversification of the local economy.
From the Government of MSAR, were also present at the meeting the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM, and the chief of staff of the Chief Executive, Chan Kak. For its part, the Beijing delegation included the head of the Humanities and Social Sciences Office, Chu Xiabo, the Director of the Faculty of Law, Guo Li, the director of the Disciplinary Development Office, Xiao Yunfeng, and the director of Hong Kong, Macau and Taiwan, Li Yun, and the sub-director of the same cabinet, Zhou Jing.</description><pubDate>2025-06-18 02:29:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Xi Jinping in Astana to reaffirm China's influence in Central Asia</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/18/xi-jinping-em-astana-para-reafirmar-influencia-da-china-na-asia-central/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping gathered yesterday in Kazakhstan with the leaders of the five Soviet republics of Central Asia, where Beijing wants to state as the main power, to the expense of Russia and its historical influence.
 
The Central Asia-China summit runs in the capital of Kazakh, Astana, takes place two years after the first, held in China, and brings together Xi Jinping-which arrived on Monday to the country-with the leaders of Kazakhstan, Quirgistan, Uzbekistan, Tajiquistan and Turquemenistan.
A “Treaty of Good Neighborhood, Friendship and Eternal Cooperation” must be signed, according to Cazaque diplomacy. "The leaders of the different countries will draw a new script together for future cooperation," said Guo Jiakun, spokesman for Chinese diplomacy.
Under Russian influence between the mid -nineteenth century and the fall of the Soviet Union in 1991, Central Asia, whose geographical location between Asia and Europe is strategic and rich in natural resources, is coveted by the great powers trying to compete with Moscow.
Although central Asian leaders maintain strong ties with Russia, the decline in the influence of this country has been accentuated since the war in Ukraine.
The five Soviet Republics of the region are taking advantage of this growing external interest and coordinating their diplomacy, as shown by the multiplication of “5+1” summits.
Countries have gathered in this format with China and Russia, but also with the European Union (EU), the United States and even Turkey and other Western countries. "Central Asian countries oscillate between different power centers, wishing to protect themselves from excessive dependence on a single partner," said Narguiza Mouratalieva, a local foreign policy analyst, cited by France Presse.
On Monday, Kremlin spokesman Dmitri Peskov guaranteed “not fear” this approach between China, a “privileged strategic partner”, and the countries of Central Asia, “natural historical partners”.
Symbol of this competition, Kazakhstan announced on Saturday that the Russians will build the country's first nuclear center and the Chinese probably a second.
China is the largest commercial partner in Central Asia, with trade exchanges valued at $ 95 billion in 2024, according to Chinese customs, far ahead of the European Union and Russia.
On the other hand, Asia occupies, on the other hand, a prominent place in the Chinese track and route initiative - a gigantic investment plan in infrastructure that encompasses 65 countries, comprising approximately 62% of the planet's population and 30% of Gross Gross Domestic Product (GDP). "Neither Russia nor Western institutions are able to allocate financial resources for infrastructures so quickly and on such a scale, sometimes bypassing transparent procedures," explained Narguiza Mouratalieva.
Chinese companies are also multiplying agreements in the energy domain, seeking, for example, gas in Turquemenistan, uranium in Kazakhstan and rare lands in Tajiquistan. “Central Asia is rich in natural resources that the Chinese economy, in full growth, needs. For Beijing, to ensure uninterrupted supply of these resources, bypassing unstable maritime routes, is an important goal,” says the Polyologog Quirguiz.
China also presents itself as a supporter of the Central Asian regimes, mostly authoritarian.
In the 2023 summit, Xi Jinping appealed to “resistance to external interference”, likely to provoke “revolutions” that overthrow the instituted powers. "Central Asia borders the Autonomous Region Uiguur de Xinjiang (E) Beijing considers the stability of the Central Asian states as a guarantee of the security of borders in the west," Chinese, "explained Mouratalieva. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-18 02:29:57</pubDate></item><item><title>DSEDT wants to attract visitors to the zones affected by the end of the satellite casinos</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/18/dsedt-quer-atrair-visitantes-para-as-zonas-afectadas-pelo-encerramento-dos-casinos-satelite/</link><description>The Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) will soon launch measures to attract visitors to NAPE and ZAPE, with the aim of mitigating the effects of the closure of satellite casinos in those zones. The measures go through the streets of the streets and the launch of discounts to foster the consumption of tourists.
 
To alleviate the negative effects of the closure of the satellite casinos at NAPE and Zape, the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) will launch a number of initiatives to attract visitors to those zones. The news was advanced yesterday by Yau Yun Wah, director of DSEDT, on the sidelines of the Innovation and Entrepreneurship Contest for technology companies in Brazil and Portugal.
It is recalled that SJM, Melco and Galaxy have recently announced that by the end of the year they will fail to explore the 11 satellite casinos that operate currently. In addition, of the six Mocha, explored by Melco clubs, three will be closed. Satellite casinos currently employ 5,600 local workers and Mocha clubs employ about 300 residents. There are also several commercial and small and medium-sized surfaces that operate with the satellite casinos and that can be affected by closing, the government said.
Only in Nape and Zape zones there are about 160 stores that depend on most of the satellite casinos customers, now indicated DSEDT, adding that the idea of ​​the authorities is to allow these stores to change more easily.
The first measure to be implemented by the government is the streamlining of the streets of Nape and Zape with intellectual property elements, as happened in other areas of the city with characters such as Hello Kitty or Labubu. This project is expected to be launched in the second half of November, and next year there will be similar projects also in that area, Yau Yun Wah said.
Another measure to mitigate the effects of the closure of the satellite casinos on Nape and Zape is the offer of discounts and coupons for visitors to consume in that area. These coupons will be attributed to visitors who participate in concerts and shows in the territory, as well as those who are staying in hotels of three and four stars.
DSEDT also wants to collaborate with commercial associations and community services so that associations organize more activities and events in that area. The body also promised to improve the urban environment of Zape and Nape.
The closure of the satellite casinos does not worry the chief executive. On Monday afternoon, Sam Hou Fai pointed out, at a press conference, that these casinos have a little relevant weight in the GDP of the territory.</description><pubDate>2025-06-18 02:27:20</pubDate></item></channel></rss>