<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ponto_final EN</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/mocambique-superou-meta-ao-vacinar-mais-de-19-milhoes-de-criancas-contra-polio/</link><description>Ponto_final EN RSS</description><item><title>Wutip: Storm signal was in force 105 and a half hours, one of the longest periods ever</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/wutip-sinal-de-tempestade-esteve-em-vigor-105-horas-e-meia-um-dos-periodos-mais-longos-de-sempre/</link><description>Wutip, the first tropical storm to affect Macau this year, forced the authorities to alert signs for a total of 105 and a half hours. This period was the longest fourth since 1968, the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) indicated.
 
The Wutip Storm, which passed relatively close to Macao last weekend, forced the authorities to maintain the warning signs for a total of 105 and a half hours. This was the fourth largest period since 1968, yesterday indicated the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) in a summary of the storm released yesterday on the electronic page. Signal No. 3 was issued twice without signal 8 had been activated, yet the Wutip did not cause damage to the region.
The wind in the territory intensified at dawn on Thursday of last week. It was predicted that the wind would continue to persist for a while, which is why signal 3 in the dawn of that day was issued. During this period, the 10 -minute sustained winds recorded in the four bridges were between 46 and 55 km/h. Wutip was expected to continue to affect Macao, even with the weakening of the high pressure crest, leading to the emission of signal No. 1 of tropical storm in the afternoon of the same day.
Then, with the approach of the storm and the joint influence of a southwest air stream, it was expected that the wind in Macao would intensify significantly, so signal No. 3 of tropical storm was emitted again on Saturday morning. With the change of direction of the wind and the influence of a rain band, some urban and open areas have become more vulnerable and huge, with gusts of maximum wind that reached level 8 and whose time of influence was extended, SMG say.
In the press release published yesterday, the SMG also say that, "With the development of society, the number of buildings in the city has been increasing and, moreover, the influence of wind in different zones depends on the direction of the wind." "In general, the force of wind in urban areas is weak; in open areas and bridges, the influence of wind is generally more considerable," says the authorities' statement.
The SMG also take the opportunity to say that although Wutip has been away, it is predictable that today the weather is still unstable due to the "influence of a high altitude atmospheric disturbance." Thus, thunder and thunderstorms may occur, being sometimes strong. At the end of the week, temperatures should rise slightly and the showers may be more dispersed.
 The SMGs again appeal to the population to pay attention to the latest weather information, especially to the weather warnings, in due course adjusting travel and outdoor activities.</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:41:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Francisco Ricarte's exhibition reveals the continuity of time through images of the past and present</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/exposicao-de-francisco-ricarte-revela-a-continuidade-do-tempo-atraves-de-imagens-do-passado-e-presente/</link><description>The exhibition “Macao: Yesterday and Days” invites the public to a visual trip over time, where the past and the present are in a harmony of images that reveal the unique identity of the city. With an approach that goes beyond documentation, photographer Francisco Ricarte explores the essence and spirit of Macao, showing that despite the transformations, certain elements remain alive in memory and local culture. The show opens on June 24 at the headquarters of Casa de Portugal.
 
The headquarters of Casa de Portugal in Macau hosts, until September 30, a singular exhibition entitled “Macau: yesterday and today”, a photographic show by Francisco Ricarte. The inauguration begins at 7 pm, on June 24, in an initiative that aims to establish a visual dialogue between the past and the present of the city, highlighting its evolution and the preservation of its cultural identity.
The exhibition features 20 diptic: visual compositions composed of an old photograph of Macao, dated from the first half of the nineteenth century or from ancient postcards of the early twentieth century, in a comparative relation with a contemporary image of the same space or what remains of it in today. This “visual proposal” allows visitors not only to appreciate the physical changes in the city, but, above all, to understand the continuity of the social, human and cultural meaning of these spaces over time, according to artist Francisco Ricarte.
Unlike mere documentation or comparison of urban changes, Ricarte seeks to capture the “spirit” of these places, highlighting how constructed or natural elements remain relevant and how their presence remains a reference of identity for the community. The introduction of colors into current photographs reinforces this connection, in contrast to the usual black and white of old images, and brings new interpretations to the public as to the meaning of these places in their presence in the past and present. The color therefore works as a link of permanence and meaning. 
"The color, in this context, articulates the perpetuity and identity of the places and their meaning, evident in the days of yesterday, with the contemporary times of the same spaces, evidenced by their presence and identity in the" days ", thus making another interpretative reading of these photographic records," explains the photographer. 
Francisco Ricarte, of Portuguese nationality and born in 1955, is architect and affected by photography since 1976. His coming to Macao in 2006 aroused a new vision of his own history, leading him to explore themes such as identity, memory, visual culture, literature and poetry through his artistic work. As a founding member of the “Halftone” photographic association, since 2021, Ricarte is dedicated to reflecting on the impact of time on the city and its community, using photography as a tool for expression and research.
The exhibition “Macao: Yesterday and Days” is not limited to a simple recollection of the past, but proposes a new reading that values ​​the permanence of identity elements and their meaning in contemporary times. Thus, Ricarte invites visitors to rethink the city, recognizing in it a continuous narrative, where the old and the new coexist and complement themselves in their visual and cultural richness.
The initiative is inserted in the cultural agenda of “June, Portugal's month in the masters”, with the organization of Casa de Portugal and support from the Macau Foundation. It will be available to the public from Monday to Friday, from 1 pm to 7 pm, at the headquarters of Casa de Portugal in Macao, offering an artistic perspective that celebrates the collective memory and evolution of Macao, through the sensitive and reflective look of Francisco Ricarte.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Porto interior will have a water pollution control and monitoring plan later this year</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/porto-interior-tera-plano-de-controlo-e-monitorizacao-de-poluicao-hidrica-ainda-este-ano/</link><description>In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Leong Sun IOK, the Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs Services (DSAMA) assumes embarrassment in the management and cleaning work of watercourses - due to the geographical “complexity” of coastal spaces - and announced the elaboration of a water pollution control and monitoring plan in the interior port, to be released by the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) (DSPA) (DSPA) (DSPA). This year.
 
The Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs Services (DSAMA) has announced that a water pollution control and monitoring plan will be prepared in the interior port in 2025, with the aim of improving water quality in this area. The organism's statements are in a document of response to a written interpellation of Deputy Leong Sun Iok, in which he warned the growing sanitary concerns on the coastal borders and the need to implement an “efficient and ecological” marine cleaning plan.
The deputy's interpellation was beginning that, despite the frequent DSAMA inspection actions, residents of the inner port continue to denounce the accumulation of waste and “unpleasant odors” from coastal spaces. These situations are often associated with “weather conditions that facilitate the dragging of debris and waste along watercourses, as well as illegal discharges and inadequate disposal of waste from individuals,” said Leong Sun IOK, noting that the approach of the tufts - scheduled to begin the second of June - may exacerbate the problem.
In addition to the “sanitary concerns”, the deputy argued that the situation also affects the “physiognomy of the city” and compromises tourist and developmental ambitions in the area, noting that one of the objectives contemplated in the “Maritime Area Plan” was precisely to build a commercial range and a garden by the seaside in the area in question.
Based on the above, Leong Sun Iok questioned the government about any plans for the elaboration and implementation of efficient measures for the cleaning and removal of maritime waste, citing the neighboring region of Hong Kong - which resorted to autonomous robots to collect pollutants in rivers and lakes - as an example regarding the application of technological means.
Regarding this first point, Dsama Director Susana Wong stressed the particularities of Macau's location as a partial justification for growing pollution. "Macao is located on the west coast of the river estuary of the Pearls, and a large amount of garbage from the upstream of the river is constantly dragged by the chains to his coastal edge," he said. Despite the efforts stated by the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA)-which include the “daily patrol of maritime areas, the removal of waste in the sea, the placement of oil containment barriers and other anti-pollution equipment in appropriate places”-the “complexity” of geographical space requires that the removal of waste can only be done by vessels or manual.
In a second and last question, Deputy Leong Sun IOK also inquire about the results of Dsama's anti-pollution barriers in some coastal areas and questioned whether they would be extended to other places or allied to “other innovative measures for pollution prevention and control”.
On this topic, Susana Wong pointed out that the established oil containment barriers have contributed “to effectively reduce waste accumulation in hard -to -reach coastal areas”, but "" the conditions are not yet gathered to extend the placement area of ​​these barriers. " Nevertheless, the official pointed out that DSPA has been developing cleaning and improving work on the Western port quality of the peninsula, such as the reordering of wastewater drainage, which will join this year “a water pollution control and monitoring plan”.
Provisional wastewater treatment facilities of Avenida Marginal do Lam Mau are also in operation, and the construction works of provisional wastewater treatment facilities south of the interior port should be completed by 2026.</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:44:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Doctors graduated from the University of Macau will be able to exercise in Portugal</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/medicos-formados-pela-universidade-de-macau-vao-poder-exercer-em-portugal/</link><description>Doctors graduated from the future medical school of the University of Macau (one), from 2028, may also exercise in Portugal, a leader of the University of Lisbon told Lusa (Ulisboa).
 
Ulisboa Medical School is collaborating with one to create a curriculum with a structure “close to what is the structure” of the courses at the Portuguese institution, said the director.
Luís Graça explained that the courses will work in co-tutela, allowing doctors graduated in one to obtain “an equivalence and recognition” by the Ulisboa School of Medicine.
Among the advantages will be “thus allowing doctors trained there in the territory [Macau] can also exercise medicine in Portugal”, stressed the investigator.
In December, Uma Vice-Rector Rui Martins said Ulisboa will help create the first Macao Public Medicine School in the institution's new campus in neighboring Hengqin.
The University of Science and Technology of Macao, a private institution, has since 2008 a Faculty of Health Sciences, officially renamed as Medicine Faculty in 2019.
In an interview with the Portuguese Public Television Channel TDM, Martins said medicine will be one of the four new colleges to be born on the new UMA campus in Hengqin. "We will have a Faculty of Information Sciences, a Faculty of Engineering, with new types of engineering, as well as a design faculty and should include architecture," said the Portuguese academic. "The idea in this campus is terms 'dual degrees' [courses in co-tutela] with foreign universities. Medicine is already with Lisbon and now we are defining for other colleges," added Martins.
The new Campus in Hengqin, whose first stone was launched on December 9, will be inaugurated in 2028 and allows the current 15,000 to a maximum of 25,000 students, stressed the Vice Rector for global affairs.
Luís Graça, a transplant immunology expert, also demonstrated enthusiasm with potential collaborations between the two universities in the area of ​​scientific research. "If we think in terms of science, the reinforcement of the scientific potential of both institutions with a collaboration close to each other is something that will clearly benefit both sides of this partnership," said the leader.
Graça said the Ulisboa School of Medicine is organizing the first symposium to gather the institution's researchers and UM, with a view to promoting joint research projects.
The college has had “occasional collaborations of researchers with researchers from other Chinese universities” as “it is important to proximity to places where excellent science is made and teaching excellence,” said the director. But Graça said that collaboration with one is "more institutional ... and can allow even greater reinforcement of these partnerships." Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:42:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Five Middle East countries dismissed from a visa to enter Macau</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/cinco-paises-do-medio-oriente-dispensados-de-visto-para-entrar-em-macau/</link><description>National citizens of Saudi Arabia, Qatar, Kuwait, Barim and Oman are dismissed from a visa to enter Macau from mid -July, yesterday announced authorities, who are trying to attract more international visitors. “Visa and prior permission of entry into the Special Administrative Region of Macao are noted in the nationals of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, the state of Qatar, the state of Kuwait, the Kingdom of Barém and the Sultanato de Oman,” was published in an official bulletin.
The measure, which comes into force on July 16, comes at a time when the Macao government wants to attract more international visitors and after the territory's authorities and tour operators visited in February Saudi Arabia and Dubai to promote cooperation.
The Directorate of Tourism Services launched, on this occasion, “a Macao Tour Guide to Muslims, with dissemination of 'halal' options [namely in food, in accordance with Islamic law],” the STD said in a statement. “The guide presents the aspects to consider during the stay in Macau, gastronomic culture, itinerary recommendations, among other useful information for Muslim visitors,” reads the note.
In order to facilitate the entry of visitors from other geographies outside China, the Secretary for Macao Security announced in late April, plans to accelerate border control through the use of automatic electronic channels.
During the presentation of the political program for 2025, Wong Sio Chak stated that the territory will extend the use of automatic passage points to foreign citizens without resident or work authorization.
To facilitate “exterior exchanges”, authorities will expand autoservice equipment to the biometric data collection system, which will apply to all foreign visitors, the leader explained. To the deputies at the Legislative Assembly, the secretary added that the government will continue to optimize iris recognition technology in border controls and to study the extension to non -residents in 2025.
According to official data, Macau received, in 2024, 34.9 million visitors, 23.8% more than the previous year, but only 2.42 million (6.9%) were international tourists. The bulk of visitors - 70.1% - arrived from the interior of China, and another 20.6% are from Hong Kong and 2.4% of Taiwan.</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:40:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Annually, 20,000 teachers and students participate in patriotic visits on the continent</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/anualmente-20-mil-professores-e-alunos-participam-em-visitas-patrioticas-no-continente/</link><description>The Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) indicated that, every year, about 20,000 teachers and students participate in patriotic visits in the interior of China. On the other hand, in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Ho Ion Sang, the authorities indicated that the “Patriotic Education Camp” for students of the 1st year of secondary education, launched this academic year, was already attended by over 4,500 students.
 
Annually, there are about 20,000 teachers and students from Macao who make patriotic visits in the interior of China to “develop their learning itineraries,” said the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Ho Ion Sang.
On the other hand, as part of the reinforcement of patriotism among the young people of Macao, the government launched this year an activity of camping patriotic education for students of the 1st year of general secondary education. This camp aims to reinforce students' knowledge of “national history and defense and external relations” through accommodation and camping activities at the Pai Van Pousada, as well as visits to patriotic education facilities in Macao, Zhuhai and Hengqin. This activity was attended by more than 4,500 students from 33 schools until April, mentioned (DSEDJ).
Authorities have been conducting other activities to promote patriotism with young people, such as the Ecological Learning Excursion to Hengqin within the science and technological education plan for students, intended for 6th grade students; The Patriotic Education Day, for students of the 1st year of General Secondary Education; The National Defense Education Day, for students of the 2nd year of General Secondary Education; and study visits in the Hengqin cooperation zone, intended for 1st grade students of complementary secondary education; as well as the Military Summer Camp for young students from Macau for complementary and higher education students.
The DSEDJ also says that to commemorate the 80th anniversary of the end of World War II - or the “victory of the Chinese people's resistance war against Japanese aggression and world victory against fascism”, as the Macao authorities call it - a series of commemorative activities will be held, planning to take advantage of the “Patriotic Educational Resources of the Great Bay, Cultural Travels and Thematic Activities about the big bay, guiding students and young people to visit the historical ruins of the resistance war in South Zone of China ”.
Still in the context of the end of World War II, the DSEDJ will elaborate a didactic material with the theme “The War of Resistance and Macao”, “so that schools can perform pedagogical activities about the history of this war, in order to allow students to better know the history of solidarity between the residents of Macao and the people from all over the country during the war”.
“DSEDJ is striving to provide students with diverse and rich learning experiences about the education of love for the homeland and Macau,” says the body, adding that this year will be created a “Macao Patriotic Education Exhibition Pavilion”, which combines in loco visits and immersive experiences through artificial intelligence, for example.
According to the authorities, this initiative will serve for Macao students to know “the results obtained with patriotic education, the education of national defense, the development of didactic materials, diplomatic education and education on national security, from the return from Macau to the country”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:43:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Three areas of investigation of one among the 0.1% best in the world ranking</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/tres-areas-de-investigacao-da-um-entre-as-01-melhores-em-ranking-mundial/</link><description>The University of Macao (one) is located at the top 0.1% of the most cited institutions in the world in the areas of Engineering, Computer Sciences and Pharmacology and Toxicology, according to a ranking of Essential Science Indicators. Another 13 research fields, such as Geosciences and Mathematics, were in the top 1% of the same list.
 
The University of Macau (one) is positioned among the 0.1% best institutions in the world in three fields of research - Engineering, Computer Science and Pharmacology and Toxicology - in the latest ranking of Essential Science Indicators (ESI), a compilation of data that evaluates the scientific performance of international universities and research institutions based on their scientific articles.
ESI's database follows strict criteria, including only articles that are among the 1% most cited in the last decade. In addition to the three dimensions already mentioned, 13 other areas of research were included in the general ranking: Social Sciences, Material Science, Psychiatry and Psychology, Clinical Medicine, Chemistry, Agricultural Sciences, Biology and Biochemistry, Environment/Ecology, Molecular/Genetics Biology, Economics/Business, Geosciences and Mathematics.
In a press release published on the UM page, the institution attributes the distinction to its “oriented research strategy, which emphasizes key technological areas and has produced remarkable results in the collaboration between industry and the academic world”. In the field of engineering, it is read that the university has been establishing “a leadership position in cutting-edge domains”, such as microelectronics, artificial intelligence, robotics and ecological development, “over years of effort” and collaboration with the analog and mixed VLSI laboratory.
In the field of computer sciences, it refers that the university “has not only published numerous articles in first-rate newspapers and international conferences, but also successfully translates its research results into practical solutions”. The UM Communications Office cites the Internet of Things State Reference Laboratory and the Collaborative Innovation Institute, both under the university's protection, as essential pillars in the conquest of “advances and innovations in critical areas such as artificial intelligence, megasted and computer systems”.
Regarding pharmacology and toxicology, the university devotes special emphasis on the development of Chinese medicine - namely, through the integration of areas such as immunology, neuroscience, synthetic biology, material science and artificial intelligence in investigating this millennial therapeutic approach.
In this context, a recall has established “prominent pharmaceutical research platforms” with the Chinese Medical Sciences Institute and the State Reference Laboratory for Quality Research in Chinese Medicine. It also highlights the Cooperation Agreement signed with the Institute for Pharmaceutical Supervision and Administration (Isaf), responsible for managing pharmaceutical activities and medicines used in traditional Chinese medicine.
It is recalled that in April this year, one maintained 180th in the 2025 edition of the Times Higher Education ranking, which compares and evaluates the best universities in the world. This was the best one-ranking one on the British magazine list, confirming a growing trend that has been at all for a decade.</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:42:02</pubDate></item><item><title>New mortgage loans for housing rose 13.8% in April</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/novos-emprestimos-hipotecarios-para-habitacao-subiram-138-em-abril/</link><description>Statistics revealed yesterday by the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM) reveal that the new Housing Mortgage loans (EHHs) approved in April grew over the previous month, while new commercial (ecais) business loans approved. The same source accuses a decrease in the gross balance of EHHs and ECAI compared to the previous month of March.
In April this year, the new EHHs approved by Macao banks grew 13.8% compared to the last month, reaching a value of 883.28 million patacas. The new EHHs approved to local residents, which represented 92.7% of the total, grew 6.8% to 818.39 million, while the non-resident component grew to 64.89 million. From February to April, the average monthly number of the approved new EHHs reached 794.61 million patacas, corresponding to a decrease of 15.7% compared to the previous period from January to March.
AMCM statistics also indicate that the new approved ecals grew 133.2% of the previous month to 1.52 billion patacas. Of these, 66.9% were granted to local residents and decreased 45.6% to 1.01 billion patacas. This value corresponds to a significant increase of 67% compared to the previous period - that is, the first three months of the year.
At the end of April, the Gross EHH balance reached 214.39 billion patacas, which represents a 0.6% decrease compared to the previous month and 5.3% over the past year. AMCM details that of these loans 96.7% were granted to residents. Compared to the previous month, gross balances of EHHs intended for residents and non-residents decreased 0.5% and 2.5%, respectively.
On the other hand, the gross balance of the ecals reached the level of 148.08 billion patacas, a decrease of 0.3% in monthly terms and 5.2% in annual terms. 91.9%of the loans were granted to residents, with a decrease in gross ECAI balances for both residents (less 0.2%) and non-residents (0.4%).
At the end of April, the debt ratio not paid to EHHs remained constant at 3.6% in monthly terms, with a growth of only 0.1 percentage point. The non -paid debt ratio of the ecais also increased 0.1 percentage point to 5.5%, with a more significant climb of 2.1% compared to April 2024.</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:49:18</pubDate></item><item><title>China asks for conditions for dialogue between Iran and Israel to be created</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/china-pede-que-sejam-criadas-condicoes-para-dialogo-entre-irao-e-israel/</link><description>China defended yesterday that they are created “conditions to resume the right path of dialogue” between Iran and Israel, following last -day attacks, which caused more than 20 Israeli dead and more than 220 Iranians. "We are deeply concerned about Israeli attacks against Iran and the sudden escalation of the military conflict," Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakun said at a press conference.
Guo appealed to all parties to "take immediate measures to relieve tensions and prevent the region from plunging into even greater agitation," arguing that "strength cannot bring lasting peace." "The deepening or eventual spread of the conflict between Israel and Iran will have as first victims the countries of the Middle East," he warned, adding that China will continue to "maintain communication with relevant parts and promote peace and dialogue."
On Saturday, Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi maintained talks with his Iran and Israel counterparts, in which he ordered Israeli air strike into Iranian territory, which he classified as “violation of international law” with the potential to trigger “disastrous consequences”.
Wang reiterated, in both calls, China's opposition to the use of force, defended the diplomatic pathway as the only solution to the Iranian nuclear issue, and again offered Beijing mediation to prevent greater destabilization in the Middle East.
Among the dead on the Iranian side, there are at least eight higher officers, including the Chief of Staff of the Armed Forces, General Mohamad Hossein Baqari, Irani Revolutionary Guard commander, Hososin Salami, and Head of Revolutionary Guard Aerospace, General Amir Ali Hajizadeh.
The Israelite attacks, made by 200 aircraft against a hundred targets, reached mainly Tehran (North), the uranium enrichment centers of Fordow and Natanz (Center), Mehrabad National Airport and various military bases. Iran retaliated with hundreds of missiles directed to the cities of Telavive and Jerusalem. The conflict has already made dozens of dead and hundreds of injuries on both sides.</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:45:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Eight lists admitted to legislative elections and Wong Wai Man excluded from the race</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/oito-listas-admitidas-para-as-eleicoes-legislativas-e-wong-wai-man-excluido-da-corrida/</link><description>The Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) has announced that eight requests for the candidacy for direct suffrage of the legislatures were validated. “Mutual aid Grassroots, a list led by Wong Wai Man, was excluded for not having sufficient signatures on time. Seng Ioi Man, president of Caeal, refused to comment on the alleged detention and police investigation of Wong Wai Man, as well as the descent of almost half of the number of lists competing for the elections.
 
The Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) recognized as legal candidacy committees, by direct suffrage, for the next legislative elections. After the consideration of the constitution of the candidacy committees, Seng Ioi Man, president of Caeal, admitted yesterday that the legal existence of the candidacy of “Mutual Grassroots”, led by Wong Wai Man, was not being able to present sufficient signatures to formalize the application within the established deadline.
At a press conference held yesterday, when asked by journalists, Seng Ioi Man refused to reveal whether “mutual help grassroots” was involved in a recent case of alleged electoral corruption, as well as police arrest, cases that happened last week during the period the list needed to raise signatures and deliver them to Caeal.
"The investigation work is still ongoing. Due to the secret of justice, they did not disclose the identification of people. Therefore, if I now disclose the identification or mention the connection with [any] application committee, it would not be adequate. Since the investigation is still underway, the commission will not make comments," he said.
It is recalled that the Commissioner Against Corruption (CCAC) said he had received a case suspected of electoral corruption involving five people who will have provided benefits to receive signatures from the election proposition bulletin. 
According to All About Macau, the suspects of this case belong to the list of mutual grassroots, whose agent, Wong Wai Man, commonly known as “Captain Macau”, was also detained on Wednesday last week by the Judiciary Police (PJ) for allegedly being responsible for an illegal Mahjong House. At the same media, elements of the list warned that they could not submit the candidacy with Caeal because the person responsible was at CCAC.
 
Police power
 
Seng Ioi Man, in this case, reiterated that "one cannot make a connection between these cases with any list," but stressed that police bodies or research entities do the work "within their competences."
Regarding the eventual intervention of police power in the elections with the detention of persons on the list during the period to supply the deficiencies of the request for constitution of the candidacy committee, the president of Caeal again avoided a direct response. "Police bodies accompany, within their competences, about all the complaints they received. They only do the investigation work and we will not comment on their work," repeated the judge of the second instance court.
The Caeal spokesman also explained why the list "Aid Mutual Grassroots" was rejected, indicating that the commission delivered more than 300 signatures, "but after appreciation, most were not signed by voters who gather the conditions."
"There is also a repetition of the subscription or a person signs several times, or the signature does not correspond to that of BIR, which is not accepted according to the law," he said. He also added that in the symbol of the list there was determined content that did not correspond to public order.
Seng Ioi Man said Caeal notified the agent that within five days could make the respective corrections, but no longer received any information from the list. 
 
Love the homeland
 
In the balance of Caeal's work to date, Seng Ioi Man pointed out that the candidacy commissioners admitted to the CAEAL, by June 26, the application list and the political program. In addition, all candidates in the lists must sign the Defense of Defense of Basic Law and Faithfulness to MSAR. The commission said it will immediately carry out appreciation work after receiving the lists and programs.
"Regarding the eligibility of the candidates, namely regarding whether or not they defend the basic law, or whether they are faithful to MSAR, according to the legislation, it is up to the State Defense and Security Commission to appreciate," he said. CAEAL will disclose the late 15th of July the decision on the appreciation of the eligibility of the candidates.
The number of lists in direct suffrage to this year's elections is the lowest in history since the establishment of the MSAR. Seng Ioi Man was also questioned yesterday about a eventual concern of Caeal that the rate of abstention will be even higher than in the last elections in 2021. 
Seng Ioi Man has merely answered that Caeal will promote election work according to the law and that “better conditions” are being created, allowing voters to vote in a more convenient way, including “more barely and safer” voting places. The official thus appealed to the population to “unite all the forces to vote and elect” deputies who have the desire and ability to serve Macau.
According to Seng, 7,500 voters have already updated the address, whose number is the highest in the last three years, marking voters' collaboration.
For legislative elections scheduled for September 14, according to Caeal, the eight lists admitted to direct suffrage are: the union for development, the promoting union for progress, the Association of United Citizens of Macao, the strength of popular Liveliod in Macao, the power of synergy, the Good Home Alliance, the New Hope and the Union of Macau-Guangdong.
In the indirect suffrage, all sectors have a single list, except the work sector, in which two lists will compete.</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:45:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese industrial production slows back in May despite the truce with the United States</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/producao-industrial-chinesa-volta-a-desacelerar-em-maio-apesar-da-tregua-com-estados-unidos/</link><description>Industrial production in China grew 5.8%, in homologous terms, a lower value of 0.3% to the registered in April, indicating that the commercial truce reached with Washington was not sufficient to reverse the tendency to slow down.
 
The data, released yesterday by China's National Statistics Office (GNE), were slightly below the expectations of analysts, which provided for a slowdown up to 5.9%.
Zichun Huang, an analyst at Capital Economics consultant, pointed out in a report that the reduction in external demand “had some responsibility” in this evolution, adding that “despite the commercial truce, the contraction of industrial sales for export was aggravated last month”.
Among the three major sectors where the GNE divides this indicator, which increased production in May was that of the transforming industry (+6.2%), followed by the mining sector (+5.7%) and the production and supply of electricity, heating, gas and water (+2.2%). The entity also highlighted the growth in the production of specific goods, such as 3D (+40%) printers, industrial robots (+35.5%) and electric vehicles (+31.7%).
In accumulated of the year, Chinese industrial production has a growth of 6.3%.
The GNE also released data on retail sales, consumer key indicator, which surprised, accelerating from 5.1% in April to 6.4% in May, when experts expected a retreat to 5%.
For the capital Economics, consumption data was the "positive point" in May, driven not only by the ambitious plan for subsidies for the consumption of the Chinese government, but also by commercial truce with the United States, which "reduced families' anxiety about trade war and encouraged them to spend."
The official unemployment rate in urban areas also presented a positive result by retreating from 5.1% in April to 5% in May.
 
The growth in investment in fixed assets softened to 3.7% in the first five months of 2025, compared to 4% in the first three months. Analysts expected a lower slowdown to about 3.9%.
The GNE also indicated that commercial real estate sales, measured by the area sold, decreased by 2.9% in homologous terms until aaio.
 
New houses prices fall for the twenty -fourth consecutive month
 
The prices of new houses in China fell in May for the 24th consecutive month, aggravating the rhythm of descent against April, despite the measures of the Chinese government to wage the prolonged crisis in the real estate sector.
According to calculations based on data released yesterday by China's National Statistics Office (GNE), prices in 70 cities analyzed recorded an average of 0.22% compared to the previous month after a decrease of 0.12% in April.
Among the monitored cities, 53 registered decreases in the price of new housing, compared to 45 in April. Only 13 cities - including large urban centers such as Shanghai and Hangzhou - showed up, less than 22 registered in the previous month.
The price of secondhand houses also descended 0.5% in May, compared to the previous month, accelerating the fall trend observed in April (-0.41%).
In this category, 67 of the 70 cities registered price falls. The only exceptions were Wuxi (east), Luayang (Centro) and Nanchang (center), where prices climbed.
Chinese authorities have announced, in recent months, a set of measures designed to contain the fall of the real estate market, a sector that Beijing considers critical for social stability, given the weight of housing as the main form of investment for many families.
The crisis in the sector is pointed out as one of the main factors for the softening of the Chinese economy, with some analysts estimating that real estate - including indirect effects - represents about 30% of the country's Gross Domestic Product (GDP). Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:45:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao Forum went to Fuzhou attending fishing exhibition</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/forum-de-macau-foi-a-fuzhou-participar-em-exposicao-de-pesca/</link><description>A delegation of the Macao Forum Permanent Secretariat, between June 13 and 15, was fuzhou to participate in the 17th International Fishing Exhibition of China.
On the first day of the trip, Ji Xianzheng, Secretary-General of the Macao Forum, led the delegation on a visit to the Fishing Expo pavilions before the opening ceremony, and then took the opportunity to meet with Liang Dong, vice president of the Fuzhou City Council.
The delegation of Macau participated in the Forum on the Development of the Maritime and Fishing Economy, organized by the Directorate of the Sea and Fisas de Fuzhou. The event presented the situation of the development of the sea fishing sector from various countries, including China, Brazil, Ecuador, Chile, Australia, Thailand, among others, as well as the current state and the assessment of fisheries in Asia.
On the afternoon of the same day, the Macau Forum organized, in collaboration with the Fuzhou Municipal Popular Government and the Directorate of the Sea and Fisheries of Fujian Province, the presentation session on Maritime Fishing Cooperation between Fuzhou and Portuguese -speaking countries at the International Center for Fuzhou Strait Convention and Exhibitions. On this occasion, Ji Xianzheng pointed out that the Macao Forum is “committed to promoting the comprehensive cooperation of mutual benefits between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”. 
Liang Dong highlighted in his speech that "Fuzhou is following the glorious plan outlined by the X Jingping party secretary general, continues to advance the construction of the" maritime economy "of the city." Liang Dong expressed the desire that Fuzhou and Portuguese -speaking countries “work together to build industrial fishing bases to leverage fishing resources, explore international markets, promote the internationalization of Fuzhou companies and attract more cooperation and investment projects to the city”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:40:42</pubDate></item><item><title>China requires US to stop interfering in Latin American countries</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/china-exige-que-eua-deixem-de-interferir-nos-paises-da-america-latina/</link><description>Chinese authorities have asked the United States to stop interfering with internal affairs in other countries. ” The requirement arose after the American embassy in Panama announced that it will replace 13 telecommunications equipment from the Chinese company Huawei in that country.
 
China has demanded yesterday from the United States to stop “interfering with internal affairs in other countries,” after the US embassy in Panama announces that it will replace 13 Chinese telecommunications equipment Huawei in that country.
"The United States government has long been conducted surveillance and cybership in Latin America and Caribbean, which has had a negative impact on the western hemisphere and has had insecurity in the countries of the American continent," Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakun said at a press conference.
Guo stressed that "China has always supported the Latin American and Caribbean countries, including Panama, defends independence and opposes hegemony, intimidation and external interference." "Beijing has never sought spheres of influence, nor was he involved in geopolitical competitions, nor coerced other countries to take sides," he said, adding that Latin America "is not anyone's backyard."
The spokesman also asked Washington to "stop politicizing economic, commercial and technological affairs, to interfere with the internal affairs of other countries and to undermine their sovereignty and independence."
China's Ministry of Foreign Ministry statements come after Panama President José Raúl Mulino required last week to the United States and to refrain from dragging the country to the “geopolitical conflict” between Washington and Beijing.
The reaction of the Panamian head of state followed the announcement made by the US embassy in Panama, which stated that the government led by Donald Trump will replace, “with safe US technology”, 13 Huawei equipment under a campaign to “counteract China's evil influence” in the region.
According to the Panama Ministry of Public Security, the replacement is due to technological incompatibility in the context of an agreement with the United States to reactivate a public security program started in 2017.
Huawei has been the target of growing restrictions by Washington, which claims concerns about national security. The US has also expressed concern about an alleged Chinese influence on the Panama Canal, denied by the Panamian authorities. 
 
Taiwan adds Chinese companies Huawei and SMIC to a black list of exports
 
Taiwan put the Chinese giant of Huawei technology and his counterpart in the semiconductor sector, the Semiconductor Manufacturing International Corp (SMIC), in a black list of exports, further restricting Beijing access to advanced technologies. “Based on the prevention of weapons proliferation and other national security considerations, a total of 601 entities (…) were added to the list (…) including Chinese companies” such as Huawei and SMIC, the Taiwan Ministry of Economic Affairs said in a statement released on Sunday. The headquarters of other organizations in this “list of strategic entities in the sector of high-tech goods are in Russia, Pakistan, Iran and Myanmar, the same source added.
Taiwanese companies wishing to sell high -tech products to Huawei, SMIC or any other listed company will have to request authorization from the Taiwan government, the territory responsible for producing more than half of world semiconductors, including the most sophisticated semiconductors. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:45:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Bank of Japan gathers with focus on the State Obligations Purchase Program</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/banco-do-japao-reune-se-com-foco-no-programa-de-compra-de-obrigacoes-do-estado/</link><description>Banco do Japan (Boj) began a two -day meeting on monetary policy yesterday, in which most analysts foresee the maintenance of interest rates and a slowdown in reducing state obligations purchases.
 
The institution has been shown to be cautious about changes in monetary policy, at a time when uncertainty about the impact on the global economy of aggressive and erratic US tariff policy is growing.
This concern adds to the climb of attacks between Israel and Iran, a destabilizing factor in the Middle East that worries Japan, given its high dependence on the region's oil.
The consensus among analysts is that the Japanese Central Bank maintains the short -term reference rate and that discusses the possibility of reducing the rhythm of decreased purchases of government obligations, compared to recent abrupt long -term securities income.
These income fired in May, due to fear of the country's fiscal health, whose debt is more than double the Gross Domestic Product (GDP), and after some deputies proposed the reduction of consumption tax. 
Japanese Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba ponders new fiscal aid to families, pressured by inflation, which would lead to an increase in public spending.
Last July, Boj decided to reduce quarterly by 400 billion yen (about 2.4 billion euros at the current rate) the volume of state obligations purchases by March 2026 in an attempt to normalize monetary policy.
The entity is expected to continue to progressively reduce these purchases beyond next year, but the market wants to know if the central bank, the largest holder of Japanese government obligations, will take steps to avoid volatility compared to current economic and geopolitical uncertainty, including a possible reduction in the reduction pace.
In March last year, Banco do Japan ended the little orthodox monetary policy it maintained for a decade to combat deflation, realizing the first rise in rates in 17 years. In August, it also began a quantitative adjustment to reduce its high balance.
Kazuo Ueda, governor of the Japanese Central Bank, said the institution maintains the plan to continue to rise interest rates if the evolution of the economy and prices meet expectations, but it has made it clear that there are no short -term changes to current uncertainty.
The Japanese obligationist market, previously low oscillation, has recorded volatility peaks that are felt globally. Japan's debt securities, namely long -term those have recorded accentuated ups, which amplifies instability in debt markets around the world, especially due to fears about increasing global tax deficits.
Bloomberg analyzes indicate that US treasury titles are increasingly sensitive to Japanese titles movements, while Japanese debt market volatility-valued at about 7.8 billion dollars (6.7 billion euros)-reached the highest levels in more than two decades.
This phenomenon represents a significant change from recent years, during which Boj's income curve control has functioned as a global anchor for financing costs. With the loss of this control, the global debt market has been more exposed to volatility.
The deterioration of appetite by Japanese titles may lead to even higher income, increasing the weight of Japanese public debt, which is the highest among the main economies.
Experts point out that the rise in income from Japanese obligations has direct effects on other markets, reducing the relative attractiveness of sovereign debts in other countries and causing greater volatility and sales in these markets.
The increase in correlation between the Japanese and US, UK and Germany titles has been notorious, with recently recorded historical peaks. After an auction of Japanese obligations for 20 years had had little demand in May, the income of the 30 -year Treasury obligations in the US reached the highest value in 19 months. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:48:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Land sliding caused by Wutip leaves three dead in southern China</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/deslizamento-de-terra-causado-pelo-wutip-deixa-tres-mortos-no-sul-da-china/</link><description>At least three people died following a landslide caused by torrential rainfall associated with the Wutip Typhoon in the autonomous region of Guangxi, southern China, the local Yicai Local News Portal said yesterday. The incident occurred on Saturday, in Shapo, Vila de Luchuan, when the accumulation of water gave way to a mass of land, reaching various dwellings and causing deadly victims. Local authorities have mobilized emergency teams to assist affected populations and evaluate the damage, according to the portal.
Typhoon Wutip, the first of the season in China, played Earth on June 14, in Hainan's island province, as a severe tropical storm, reaching the continent over the weekend, with heavy rains and strong winds in various southern provinces.
In Guangdong province, where some rivers levels remain high, authorities reduced the emergency response level on Sunday night from grade II to grade III - on a scale where grade I is the highest - after stabilization of weather conditions.
Wutip is the first typhoon of the season in China, but its formation recorded a delay of more than two months compared to the usual beginning of the time, which usually occurs at the end of March.
According to experts, the delay was due to the presence of an abnormally strong subtropical high pressure system and the late arrival of the summer monsoon to the Southern Sea of ​​China, factors that inhibited the tropical convection needed for cyclone development.</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:42:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Diagnosed case of epidemic typhus</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/diagnosticado-caso-de-tifo-epidemico/</link><description>Health services diagnosed a suspected case of tsutsugamushi - epidemic typhus - in a 60 -year -old woman. This is the third suspected case of tsutsugamushi since the beginning of the year.
According to health services, on June 2, the woman had fever, dizziness and headaches, having resorted to a private clinic for medical treatment, however, symptoms did not improve. Last Thursday, the woman resorted to treatment at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center. During the medical examination, a painless scaram was detected, approximately the size of a greenish bean on the right side of the abdomen. According to vital symptoms and signs, the patient's clinical diagnosis is tsutsugamushi disease.
Currently the patient is in a clinical state considered stable, and is hospitalized for medical treatment. According to the health authorities, the patient periodically returns to their domicile in the interior of China, around which they are shrubs. In daily life, the patient performs activities in that area. He claimed to have been bitten by insects in that residence and have detected painless rashes in the right side of the abdomen before symptom manifestation.     
Tsutsugamushi disease is acute infectious infectious caused by the bite of larvae with orientia tsutsugamushi. The rodents that exist in the jungles with high temperatures and moisture covered with herbs constitute the natural habitat and multiplication of orientia tsutsugamushi. Its larvae can be infected when parasitizing rats, and if people are chopped by the larvae with orientia tsutsugamushi that exist in the jungles may become sick.
Symptoms include fever, headache, muscle pain, rash and have a special feature: the larva bite site forms a painless span with a hole in the center. If it is not treated immediately, a small number of patients can develop serious complications, including pneumonia, encephalitis and myocarditis, resulting in respiratory failure, shock and even death, with a mortality rate up to 60% of affected patients.</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:41:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Pr Timorense calls for the state's general budget to 2026 that reduces poverty</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/pr-timorense-pede-orcamento-de-geral-do-estado-para-2026-que-reduza-pobreza/</link><description>The Timorese President appealed to the Government to, in the state's General Budget proposal to 2026, to assign funds to reduce poverty in Timor-Leste. Ramos Horta also appealed to the government to make the proposal special attention to the areas of education, health and infrastructure.
 
The Timorese President, José Ramos-Horta, appealed yesterday to the government to, in the proposal of the State General Budget (OGE) to 2026, to attribute funds to reduce poverty in Timor-Leste. "As the prime minister knows, as the government knows, as everyone knows, the main concern of the presidency is the implementation of effective policies to reduce poverty in rural areas," Ramos-Gorta told journalists.
The president spoke on the sidelines of the ceremony of delivery of the renewal works of Cantina Matak, funded by the Australia Embassy, ​​in the Presidential Palace.
The Timorese Government started Budgetary Days for 2026, which mark the formal start of the state budget preparation process for next year.
In his speech, Prime Minister Xanana Gusmão stressed that the budget for 2026 should continue to reflect the determination to build a “prosperous, equitable and more resilient society”.
Ramos Horta also appealed to the Government so that the OGE 2026 proposal pay special attention to the areas of education, health and infrastructure. "It is necessary to prioritize the education sector. You need to see how schools are, if they have basic conditions such as bathrooms for girls and boys. It is necessary to reinforce the school lunch program and ensure the supply of drinking water in schools," he said.
According to the head of state, another important sector is health, stressing that health policies should not only focus on hospital treatment, but also in the prevention and promotion of public health. "I also ask the government to look at infrastructures, especially rural roads in the interior of the country," he said.
The Timorese Chief of Staff also asked the Government to continue to improve water supply services to the population, especially those communities that continue without access to drinking water.
Multidimensional poverty in Timor-Leste reaches about 48% of the country's population, which is about 1.3 million inhabitants, and poor nutrition affects about 47% of people, especially women of childbearing age and children.
The World Bank recently recommended Timor-Leste to increase investment to reduce hunger, malnutrition and delay in children's growth, thus contributing to the improvement of human capital and the country's economic development. Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:44:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau and Canton receive artistic residency “Next Step”</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/macau-e-cantao-recebem-residencia-artistica-next-step/</link><description>Between tomorrow and June 27, Canton and Macau receive an artistic residency “Next Step”, promoted by the Macau T theater, in collaboration with the Parasite Association of Lisbon.
Four creators were selected for the initiative in the field of contemporary dance and expanded choreography: Bibi Doria, Inês Zinho Pinheiro, Luísa Saraiva and Romain Beltrão Teu. The group will join resident artists in China for an intensive research and sharing experience.
The activities start in Canton, between tomorrow and next Monday, and then go to the T theater in Macau until the 27th of this month. The organization explains that residence proposes a space of dialogue between dance and diverse artistic practices, such as sound, theater, visual arts or cinema. Over these periods, the public will have access to a series of open events: workshops with each of the four artists. 
Each of the artists in the residence takes a focus of singular investigation. Bibi Doria, located between experimental cinema and performance, investigates body strategies for transmission and forgetting images. Inês Zinho Pinheiro proposes “forms of smeoring” - practices that relate olfactory memories and movement.
Luísa Saraiva explores folk work songs and resonance in the context of contemporary work and ecology. Romain Beltrão Teu investigates the translation as choreographic and spectral gesture, working with voice, vibration and ghostly presences.
According to the co-cure of the Guo Rui project, this edition of Next Step has as its starting point the notion of polysemia, inspired by the view of art historian James Cahill, who argued that a vital art resists fixed interpretations.
The organization explains that the residence "also aims to reflect on the role of difference as fertile matter in intercultural relations, creating space for emerging voices to develop critical approaches to their cultural and community identities and memories."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Mozambique exceeded goal by vaccinating more than 19 million children against polio</title><link>https://pontofinal-macau.com/2025/06/17/mocambique-superou-meta-ao-vacinar-mais-de-19-milhoes-de-criancas-contra-polio/</link><description>Mozambique vaccinated against polio more than 19 million children up to 10 years, from June 2 to 6, above the defined goal, the health authorities announced yesterday, providing for another phase of vaccination in July. "If the goal is 18.2 million, the achieved was over 19 million, the total coverage indicates above 100%. Therefore, we surpassed the goal that had been defined," said Quinhas Fernandes, national director of public health, at a press conference in Maputo, to present vaccination data against the type two variant of the disease, in a national campaign that took place from June 2 to 06.
The national administrative coverage was 107%, having varied 96% in the province of Maputo, south of the country, up to 111% in Nampula, northern Mozambique, said. According to Quinhas Fernandes, all polio vaccination campaigns are evaluated by teams independent to the sector, through quality evaluation in lots (LQAS).
Through this method, at the end of the campaign, in a random sample of 60 children per district, if there are more than three not vaccinated, it means that the district, from the epidemiological point of view, is not well covered.
The results of the LQAS, in this vaccination operation, indicate that 131 of the 159 districts passed in this evaluation, representing about 82%. Among the 28 districts that did not pass, 11 had four to six non -vaccinated children, six with seven to nine unvaccinated children and 11 with ten or more non -vaccinated children, Fernandes said. "These results of the LQS are considered good, however, for the second round, we must fight to improve this performance. This will be very important to control the outbreak of the type 2 polio variant. It will be even more important to ensure that districts that have not passed in this round have better performance in the second," he said.
The next phase of vaccination against the type 2 polio variant will be held from July 8 to 12, he said.
In May 2024, an independent team that evaluated the response to polio outbreak recommended to the World Health Organization (WHO) that the end of the disease outbreak in Mozambique and Maláui was declared. "After exhaustive evaluations in Maláui and Mozambique, an independent team of response to the response to polio outbreak recommended (…) to declare the end of the type 1 wild polyvirus outbreak [PVS1]" in both countries, "a significant milestone in the fight against African region," WHO said in a statement.</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:44:27</pubDate></item></channel></rss>